<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
   xml:id="VAC6129">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Over the Brink, or, The Peril of Beauty </title>
            <author>Colfax, Jasper</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6129</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0598A</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                  copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction
                  project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                  University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
                  to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                  contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                  educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                  inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University
                  Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
               Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Over the brink, or, The peril of beauty</title>
                  <author>Colfax, Jasper</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>100 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Lewiston Me. </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1869">[1869?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
               Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
               website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
               been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
               Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-03-31">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-10-03">Finished TEI
            conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-06-23">Converted document from SGML to TEI
            P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-06-23">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents
            and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (Titlepage) " xml:id="VAC6129-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>OVER THE BRINK;</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">OR THE PERIL OF BEAUTY.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">A Story of Life in a Factory Town.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>JASPER COLFAX,</docAuthor> Author of "The Medical Student," "The
               Royal Prize," "The Rival Sisters," "The Black Doctor," "The Recluse," etc.</byline>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>LEWISTON, MAINE.</pubPlace>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="7" xml:id="VAC6129-00000002"/>
         <div type="preface">

            <head>NOTE.</head>
            <p>The following story was originally published in 1866, in the "Once a Month" and
               "Yankee Blade," and was widely copied by other papers at the time. It is intended to
               portray certain phases of life in a factory town, its perils and pitfalls, and while
               endeavoring to avoid anything that could offend the most exacting sense of propriety,
               the writer has at the same time sought to truthfully present the facts as they exist,
               that those most deeply concerned may take heed, and thus add greater security to the
               sacred ties of the home and fireside.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JASPER COLFAX.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Over the brink, or, The peril of beauty</head>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6129-00000003"/>
               <head>OVER THE BRINK.</head>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                  <head type="sub">OUR HEROINE AT HOME.</head>
                  <p>Seated in a farmer's dwelling, her nimble fingers swiftly plying the needle,
                     was a girl of exceeding loveliness. From appearances it would seem that her age
                     could not be over sixteen years, while the merry air and happy laugh which
                     occasionally lit up her youthful features, indicated that her life had not as
                     yet been so affected by unfavorable contact with the world as to destroy that
                     most inestimable element in the female character—an amiable disposition. Nature
                     had indeed been lavish with her favors, and the maiden's form, shaped in her
                     fairest mould, would at once enlist the admiration of the beholder. Nor were
                     the artful devices of fashion requisite to enhance the symmetry of the work
                     which nature had already so faultlessly performed. Blessed with the full flush
                     of health, which lent its lustre to the clear hazel eye and roseate cheek,
                     endowed with a profusion of dark, wavy tresses, drawn back from the fair, full
                     forehead with an unstudied grace, our heroine was at once a fitting ideal for
                     the painter's brush, the sculptor's chisel, or the poet's pen. And all these
                     outward indications did not belie innate worth of Dora Vernon. A New England
                     girl, reared with the most rigid adherence to Puritan principles, she was now
                     the possessor of a mind wholly free of ostentation, and<pb n="10-11"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000004"/> altogether worthy in it's remotest tastes and
                     inclinations.</p>
                  <p>The room was one of those cheerful, sunny living rooms, of ample dimensions, so
                     common to our country homes. An ancient mahogany book-case, well filled with
                     choice volumes, both secular and religious, stood in a retired corner, while
                     near by, and more convenient of access, was a table laden with the current
                     magazines and newspapers of the day, evincing the intelligence and cultured
                     tastes of the occupants, as well as the prosperity with which they were
                     favored. Pictures adorned the walls, while from without the open windows, which
                     disclosed a broad expanse of fields rich with well-cultivated crops, were
                     wafted the notes of the uncaged songsters who reveled in the delights of the
                     midsummer scene.</p>
                  <p>Beside the girl, engaged in some household duty, sat an elderly lady, dressed
                     in neat but inexpensive attire, whose features readily betokened the
                     relationship that existed between them. As we enter the dwelling an earnest
                     conversation is going on.</p>
                  <p>"And so, mother," said the younger, in a gratified tone, "you will let me go. I
                     know it will be better for me. Only think, what a lot of money I can earn to
                     clothe me, saving you and father the trouble of doing so. I am not afraid to
                     work, and in the factories at Lewiston I am sure I can do quite as well as many
                     who have been there before me."</p>
                  <p>"Possibly you might, Dora; but you must know that you would be an entire
                     stranger at Lewiston, excepting in your uncle's family, with whom you can
                     associate but little, and will have to form new acquaintances, it may be those
                     of a dangerous character, in your ignorance of their antecedents, whose
                     influence may result in your injury."</p>
                  <p>"Never fear, dear mother. You scarcely give me credit for the good teaching you
                     have ever emplanted in my mind. Thoughts of you and dear father, if nothing
                     else, would deter me from going astray from your loving precepts. Be assured, I
                     shall make acquaintance with only those whom I have every reason to believe
                     worthy. Strong as may be the temptations to enter into the exciting allurements
                     which I understand encompass the factory girl at Lewiston, I trust I shall be
                     proof against them, and never do aught to reflect shame upon the name of
                     Vernon."</p>
                  <p>"I believe you will not, Dora; and if your father is willing, I will consent to
                     your leaving home, although I would much prefer to have you remain with us, and
                     am confident we would find no difficulty in affording you all the articles of
                     dress and comfort you might require."</p>
                  <p>"Thank you, dear mother. You have ever been kind to me, and wherever I am, or
                     whatever circumstances may attend me, the memory of your affectionate goodness
                     will ever be uppermost in my mind. With this as a talisman to protect me from
                     bad example or evil influence, I shall be able to withstand any
                     temptation."</p>
                  <p>"Be not too sure of that, Dora. You will need to watch yourself constantly,
                     that you may not yield an iota to the frivolities which will surround you. The
                     young have many perils to contend with in the larger cities. The daily papers
                     contain reports of occurrences in Lewiston and elsewhere which may well cause
                     the inexperienced to distrust their powers of resistance. Young men and young
                     women alike fall victims to the snares of Satan. But here comes your father,
                     and we will hear what he says to your proposition."</p>
                  <p>Mr.Vernon, a fine specimen of the New England<pb n="12-13"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000005"/> farmer, entered the dwelling, and, with a
                     cheerful word to his wife and daughter, seated himself for a brief perusal of
                     the agricultural paper, which had just arrived.</p>
                  <p>Dora awaited her opportunity, and when, at length, he laid the paper aside and
                     looked up for a short conversation, she broached the subject of her desire to
                     enter into service as a factory girl. It is perhaps needless to say that Mr.
                     Vernon opposed this idee of his child in the most marked terms, dwelling upon
                     the trials she would necessarily be subjected to, and the want of care, when
                     once beyond the reach of parental guardianship. His opposition did not avail,
                     however. The girl's mind had for some time been fixed upon the purpose, and,
                     contrary to the usually pliant and passive course she was wont to pursue, she
                     insisted upon the feasibility of her undertaking, and with such zeal and
                     enthusiasm, that her father finally acquiesced, and yielded a reluctant
                     consent.</p>
                  <p>This compliance with her wishes elicited a degree of gratitude from Dora, for
                     she loved her parents with a most sincere affection, and nothing but a
                     confirmed and long-meditated scheme could for a moment have caused her to
                     persist in a course that was at all objectionable to them. But she had heard of
                     Lewiston; of its advantages to the factory girl, and in her country home,
                     dressed, perhaps, in home-spun, at times, she may have dreamt of gorgeous
                     ladies in silken garments, sweeping the pavement with their regal attire.</p>
                  <p>Such is the tendency of life. Human nature is much the same the world over;
                     never satisfied; always grasping beyond its present sphere; always reaching
                     forward into the visionary world, building castles in fancy never to be reared
                     in reality. Was it to be thus with Dora Vernon?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
                  <head type="sub">LIFE IN A COTTON FACTORY.</head>
                  <p>Clang! clang! rang out the bell in the factory tower, as the hour arrived for
                     the operatives to gather to their daily tasks. Clang! clang! and the streets
                     that a few moments before were empty and silent, were now filled with a crowd
                     of hurrying human beings, all moving towards the immense, substantial
                     structures of brick and stone which stood just across the dark waters of the
                     canal. Clang! clang! How many a weary toiler had heard the tones so oft before
                     that their repetition fell like a dull pain upon their wretched hearts! Here
                     could one behold, as in nearly all other occupations, the varied conditions of
                     life, from the pale, tired mother upon whom devolves the entire support of a
                     family, to the thinly-clad child whose meagre pittance ekes out the scanty fare
                     of a household, the father being dead, or worse, perhaps, cursed with the
                     appetite for strong drink. Some greet the chiming of the bells as they would
                     the notes of a festal occasion, and trip to their work as though it were a
                     pleasant pastime; others, who see no rift in their future experience, plod on
                     with the moody countenances of persons condemned to a term of penal servitude.
                     Light and shade are blended in experience as well as in character; and amid the
                     hastening throng one skilled in reading the human face and mind, would find
                     ample material for study and reflection.</p>
                  <p>When Dora Vernon heard the ringing of the bells on the first morning after her
                     arrival in Lewiston, it possessed no disagreeable sound to her. The<pb
                        n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6129-00000006"/> quiet, staid, unbroken round of
                     country life had, in a measure, grown irksome, and the change, the novelty of
                     the new relation she was about entering, filled her with a degree of pleasant
                     anticipation. Had the task not been self-imposed", it is possible its
                     assumption would have been less cheerful. When she appeared at the
                     breakfast-table, many curious eyes were bent upon the fair features of the
                     newcomer, and mental comments and sidelong glances readily communicated the
                     impressions and opinions entertained of the youthful stranger. Dora did not
                     observe these, however, but modestly partaking her food, she quietly repaired
                     to the factory and reported herself ready for the task which had previously
                     been assigned her.</p>
                  <p>Those who have visited a cotton factory, and observed the activity that
                     prevails there, the din of the machinery, and the indifference of the
                     operatives to the seemingly dangerous contact of belt and pulley, can
                     appreciate, to some extent, the feelings of partial bewilderment which came
                     over Dora when she emerged upon this busy scene. But these feelings gradually
                     departed as she became engrossed in her newly-chosen vocation, under proper
                     instruction.</p>
                  <p>A few hours later two girls stood conversing together at their looms. That they
                     were on terms of closest intimacy was evident from the freedom which
                     characterized their conversation. Presently the eyes of one fell upon our
                     heroine.</p>
                  <p>"There is the girl I was telling you about, Pauline. Isn't she a beauty?"</p>
                  <p>The one addressed looked in the direction indicated, and, unobserved by her,
                     studied the features of Dora. So intent was she in this that she quite forgot
                     the other's interrogation.</p>
                  <p>"You do not reply," urged the first speaker, noticing ing rather curiously her
                     abstracted manner. "I asked you, if you did not think her beautiful?"</p>
                  <p>A tinge of red suffused the cheeks of the girl addressed, as she perceived that
                     her close scrutiny or admiration had been observed by her companion.</p>
                  <p>"Yes," she at length replied; "your statement seems fully confirmed by the
                     original of the picture."</p>
                  <p>"And you will have to look well to your laurels after this, I fancy. The girl
                     who has so long worn the enviable distinction of the Belle of the Corporation
                     is likely to be eclipsed by this fresh arrival from the country."</p>
                  <p>"Let your mind be at ease about my laurels. I don't think they will be
                     endangered by the advent of this verdant country girl."</p>
                  <p>"But she's not so verdant—at least, she will not be, long. A few months often
                     works wonderful transformations. Do you remember the day you first came to
                     Lewiston? You were from the country, I believe?"</p>
                  <p>"I was." And the red deepened in the girl's cheeks as she spoke, whether from
                     thought of her present or past life, it would be hard to tell.</p>
                  <p>"Queer things sometimes happen in this changeful, fickle world," continued the
                     other, reflectively. "I'll venture to predict that some of your admirers will
                     yet desert you for this same country girl whom you affect to regard so
                     lightly—Dick Bruce, for instance."</p>
                  <p>There was another interval of silence. Many strange thoughts seemed to be
                     coursing through the brain of the girl whom the other had sought to tease. The
                     first speaker had intimated that her companion was a being of unusual personal
                     appearance. This fact would at once become apparent to the most casual
                     observer. The girl addressed as Pauline had indeed been beautiful, and that
                        at<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6129-00000007"/> a time not long past. But other
                     lines than those of beauty were now revealed in her remarkable
                     face—dissipation, late hours, the ball-room, convivial—shall we say,
                     vicious?—companionship, had left their impress there. Not only had she
                     prepossessing features, but there were evidences of mental powers of no
                     ordinary degree. Whether those powers were elevated by her better or subverted
                     by her baser characteristics, we may in due time learn.</p>
                  <p>"Dick," she at length replied, a smile of peculiar meaning lighting up her
                     face; "I should be most happy to have him become acquainted with her. And yet,"
                     she mused to herself, in a tone that could not be heard by her companion above
                     the noise of the speed—"no, it would not do; it would be too cruel of me. Ah!
                     me! how short a time it seems since first I came to this place! What was I
                     then? what am I now? Before me I behold one as I was, but never, never can the
                     past be recalled! And what care I? Out upon these reflections that come rushing
                     in upon me! I have had to learn by experience; let others do the same I Do you
                     know," she continued, loud enough for the other to hear, "that I must become
                     acquainted with this new girl Dora, as you call her. You think my vanity will
                     cause me to be jealous. To convince you of the contrary, I am determined to
                     become her intimate companion, her chum, her crony, if you please."</p>
                  <p>"Perhaps you will succeed no better than in your attempt to become intimate
                     with the Bishop girls," replied the other, renewing her efforts to tease.</p>
                  <p>"I care not for the Bishop girls, so long as they do not run across my
                     purpose."</p>
                  <p>"And they will not be inclined to do that, I imagine agine, for they mind their
                     own affairs, and care little for the attentions of the other gender. Only one
                     of them has a suitor, I believe, and he is hardly up to her standard."</p>
                  <p>"You mean, Agnes?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes. Do you know I sometimes think she would make a splendid actress, with her
                     elegant manners and graceful carriage? The stage is her <foreign xml:lang="FRA"
                        >forte,</foreign> or I'm mistaken. Why, she's the very personification of
                     dignity and pride."</p>
                  <p>"Poor and proud!"</p>
                  <p>"Yes, poor and proud, and beautiful, too, you will admit. Belle and Agnes
                     Bishop were reared in luxury and refinement, one can easily see."</p>
                  <p>This aside allusion did not seem to be relished by the girl Pauline, and the
                     stopping of a loom which required the attention of the first speaker,
                     interrupted the conversation, and afforded her an excuse for leaving the alley.
                     Repairing to another part of the room, she resumed her own task.</p>
                  <p>For the remainder of the day Pauline Montville's mind was no less active than
                     her hands. Two elements in her nature seemed struggling for the ascendency; and
                     not until a severe mental conflict had been fought did one wholly usurp the
                     throne of action.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6129-00000008"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
                  <head type="sub">IN THE TOILS OF THE DESTROYER.</head>
                  <p>"Surely, Dora, you will not attempt to go home to-night; it is so late, and you
                     can hardly find your way to the corporation. You are not familiar with the
                     streets, and would be as likely to take the wrong one as otherwise. Besides, we
                     should be worried for your safety."</p>
                  <p>"Which would be a needless matter. Never fear, Julia. I am not afraid of
                     darkness, and as for the streets, they are regularly laid out, and I have
                     little doubt that I can find my way. Then, if I should remain over night,
                     obliging me to be late in the morning, the 'old man' would not like it. And you
                     know I want to get off all the work I can, in order to procure my new dress
                     this payment," replied Dora, laughing, as she used some expressions that had
                     fallen upon her ear several times during her brief operative experience.</p>
                  <p>"O pshaw! Don't fret about the 'old man' and the new dress to-night. Be
                     contented where you are. You certainly would be incurring great risk to venture
                     out alone, and there is no one at home to accompany you. It isn't always safe
                     for females to travel the streets even at an early hour of the evening, and
                     now, owing to our agreeable conversation, we have failed to note the flight of
                     time, till it has become quite late, and nobody but stragglers are. abroad;
                     that is, if I, may except the police, who are so few in numbers it would be
                     hardly reasonable to depend upon them for any protection. If you don't stay, I
                     fear you'll have occasion to regret your imprudence."</p>
                  <p>"Nonsense! cousin dear. You place a poor estimate upon my courage. I am not
                     frightened so easily, I assure you. Just dismiss your forebodeings, and imagine
                     me safe at my destination."</p>
                  <p>"If you insist upon going, then," said Julia, "I must go with you a portion of
                     the way."</p>
                  <p>"No, cousin, I cannot permit that"; for you would have to return alone, and
                     that would only increase the possibilities of the danger which you
                     suggest."</p>
                  <p>Perceiving how useless were her efforts at persuasion, Julia attended Dora to
                     the door, and, as she departed, bid, her good-night.</p>
                  <p>Once out in the darkness, and alone, however, the latter's spirits and courage
                     did not appear so buoyant. She was possessed of a good degree of self-reliance,
                     naturally, and while yet comfortably ensconced in the home of her cousin she
                     felt more like laughing at that worthy young lady's misgivings than like
                     viewing them with any sort of seriousness. Now, it must be confessed, something
                     of a revulsion took place in her feelings. Nothing but the uncertain light of
                     the stars, struggling amid the drifting clouds, afforded any aid for her
                     guidance. Had she not already committed herself so far as to make it seem
                     almost absurd for her to forgo her purpose, she would gladly have turned and
                     re-entered the house. But she felt too proud to do so now, arid passing without
                     the gate, she tripped lightly along, many dark thoughts and vague fears
                     flitting through her mind as she advanced, sometimes uncertain of her
                     whereabouts, and far from positive that she was pursuing the right course.</p>
                  <p>Under other circumstances, perhaps, Dora would have felt less concern for her
                     safety, but her conscience upbraided her for treating Julia's anxiety so
                     inconsiderately. Her cousin, she knew, would feel ill at ease till next she
                     heard from her, which,<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6129-00000009"/> in all
                     probability, would not be for several days. In the country, where her life had
                     thus far been spent, no more danger was anticipated in the highway at night
                     than in the broad light of noonday. Few tramps were abroad at any time, and
                     seldom could one be found after dark when a convenient barn or corn-crib
                     offered him a chance for undisturbed repose. But in the city, as Dora was not
                     aware, the night is the season of special activity on the part of certain
                     characters.</p>
                  <p>At length, she reached a section of more frequent habitations, and the rays of
                     an occasional street light, penetrating their darkened recesses, formed
                     fantastic figures which her excited imagination converted into living beings
                     about to spring forth and intercept her passage. Repressing a shudder, she
                     would continue on her way, chiding her weakness for yielding to such feelings
                     of timidity.</p>
                  <p>Some distance had been traveled, when she fancied she detected the sound of a
                     man's footsteps following her. Even if such were the case, she reasoned, that
                     fact alone need excite no apprehension. It might only be some one; who, like
                     herself, was belated from home. Still, at the swiftness with which she was
                     going, she thought the sound must at once increase if he designed to overtake
                     her. This impression was soon confirmed, for, though she pressed forward with
                     redoubled haste, her trepidation greatly accelerating her progress, she
                     perceived that her pursuer, as she now believed the person to be, was rapidly
                     nearing, till, at last, when nearly out of breath, a young man reached her
                     side, and accosted her:</p>
                  <p>"Excuse me, miss; this is a late hour for one of your sex to be out, and a dark
                     night. Can I be of service to you? I am a member of the force, and shall be
                     happy to render any assistance or escort desired. It would be unsafe for you to
                     go farther unattended."</p>
                  <p>"Thank you," replied Dora, timidly, pausing necessarily, for the individual had
                     almost confronted her—"thank you, sir; but may I know why it is that you are on
                     the street at such a time?"</p>
                  <p>"Ah! you do not understand. I am one of the force—a policeman,—and it is my
                     duty to attend any one whom circumstances compel to be out at a late hour."</p>
                  <p>"O, indeed!" returned Dora, with some confidence; "then you will direct me the
                     way to my boarding-house on the corporation." And she gave him the name and
                     number where she wished to go. "I assure you your services are most opportune.
                     I am almost a stranger in Lewiston, and should not have started out only for a
                     foolish whim."</p>
                  <p>"I dare say," was the reply, with a sinister leer that, could Dora have seen
                     it, would have driven the blood back to her heart in cold chills. "But come; I
                     have detained you. We must make haste, for you are doubtless anxious to get to
                     your boarding-place."</p>
                  <p>"Thank you for your kindness," said Dora.</p>
                  <p>And the two walked briskly along, turning into, a more sparsely-populated
                     thoroughfare presently, however, as the guide suggested they would thus lessen
                     the distance to be traversed.</p>
                  <p>Dora had been but a few weeks in Lewiston, and this was the first time she had
                     trusted herself to leave the corporation alone of an evening. She knew very
                     little of the various localities, yet this knowledge had been deemed sufficient
                     for her guidance when belated at the suburban home of her cousin, Julia
                     Cameron.</p>
                  <p>As they now passed from street to street she wondered at her recklessness in
                     attempting to find<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6129-00000010"/> her way. No objects
                     appeared in the least familiar to her, and soon they were once more where the
                     street lights did not shed their friendly rays. How fortunate that she were not
                     alone! And yet—could it be?—a faint suspicion passed through her mind which she
                     scarce dared entertain.</p>
                  <p>Still on they went, going a mile, it seemed to Dora, ere her companion again
                     spoke, and then he merely deigned a word of reply to her questions as to their
                     whereabouts. Something whispered, to her consciousness that all was not right.
                     Instead of approaching the dark, brick walls of the corporation, as they should
                     have done before this, she perceived, almost by instinct, that they were in a
                     section of fields and woodland, and must therefore be far away from her
                     destination. Completely alarmed, she ventured to expostulate at the route they
                     were pursuing.</p>
                  <p>"O, don't worry, don't worry!" said her escort, in a gruff voice, wholly unlike
                     that in which he had first addressed her. "This is the way; come along!"</p>
                  <p>"But, sir, I cannot. I fear I have done wrong to accompany you thus far."</p>
                  <p>"Ah! indeed! You've made that discovery, have you? I fancy it's a little too
                     late to be of service, however. Do you understand me?"</p>
                  <p>The poor girl was standing still, trembling with a deadly fear at the cruel,
                     insinuating tone of the stranger, whom she now knew to be a villain, while, the
                     designs he entertained were but too evident.</p>
                  <p>"Come, come, I say! You are already out of the reach of help. You must
                     come!"</p>
                  <p>"But, sir, I dare not!"</p>
                  <p>The villain had advanced several steps beyond Dora as she hesitated.</p>
                  <p>"As you choose, then," he said, in a determined tone, moving towards the
                     terrified girl."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
                  <head type="sub">SOMEWHAT DIGRESSIVE AND DESULTORY.</head>
                  <p>Let us digress at this point long enough to introduce two new characters, one
                     of whom, at least, will receive more or less attention in the following
                     chapters of our story.</p>
                  <p>"Well, Robert, we are nearing the close of our college life. One year more of
                     study and preparation, and then we shall go forth into the world to battle for
                     fame and fortune."</p>
                  <p>"So far as I am concerned that may be true. With you, however, it is quite a
                     different thing. The last condition is already met in having wealthy parents
                     who will supply all the needful, and as to the first, it is sure to come, as a
                     matter of course."</p>
                  <p>"How sanguine you are, Robert!"</p>
                  <p>"For you, yes. Your father is a prominent journalist and proprietor of one of
                     the leading newspapers of the West, and with your inherited literary tastes,
                     and the benefit of his long experience, I predict for you the fulfillment of
                     your most glowing anticipations in the fields of journalism."</p>
                  <p>"Thanks, my dear Robert. I shall endeavor not to disappoint you. And, in turn,
                     allow me to expect for you a career no less brilliant in the profession of
                     medicine."</p>
                  <p>"That profession does not admit of such extended reputation as that of
                     journalism. The pen is said to be mightier than the sword, and I presume it is
                     mightier than the scalpel, also. The physician's life is comparatively obscure
                     and commonplace, unless, perchance, he adopts some specialty and distinguishes
                     himself in it. On the other hand,<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6129-00000011"/>
                     journalism keeps one's name constantly before the public, and is ever open to
                     its commendation."</p>
                  <p>"Condemnation, you might have said, also, Robert. Unfortunately, all
                     journalists do not invariably espouse the cause of right. Selfish motives,
                     political aspirations, particular objects blind, too often, the editor's
                     vision, to write his honest convictions, if he has any, and society suffers in
                     consequence. The true reformers of our day are few and far between—men who have
                     nobly overcome their desire for personal aggrandizement or personal notoriety,
                     and entered the arena to combat with some pernicious doctrine or practice from
                     a love of principle, and nothing else."</p>
                  <p>"Still you will concede there are such."</p>
                  <p>"Yes, but conspicuously few. History occasionally mentions them, but where they
                     have stood out in their truest fidelity, and thrown their light with greatest
                     effect into the dark background of their day, may be found indications of
                     violence, oppression and wrong; of persecution on the one hand, and patient,
                     untiring forbearance on the other, in striking contrast with the obstacles and
                     surroundings of our modern reformers."</p>
                  <p>"In the West you will find plenty of room to distinguish yourself as the
                     champion of right," said Robert Converse, regarding his friend with an
                     approving smile.</p>
                  <p>"I trust so. It is truly sorrowful to contemplate the iniquity and folly which
                     exists in the West at the present time. A vast new country, open to immigration
                     from all parts of the world, how important it is that her leaders should be men
                     of principle as well as stamina, purity as well as vigor; that this great mass
                     which is accumlating there, and which must accumulate for generations to come,
                     from the remotest parts of the globe, should be properly directed, instructed
                     and nationalized at the beginning. And for this guiding power the West depends
                     to a great extent upon her press; no instrumentality is so potent for good or
                     evil in freedom-loving Columbia. Unfortunately, however, newspapers are too
                     often moulded by public sentiment rather than moulders of public sentiment. The
                     tide that has set westward for many years has contained an element that few
                     have dared to antagonize, while many have been only too ready to cater to its
                     abasing demands."</p>
                  <p>"But the West has improved in regard to her press, as in nearly everything
                     else, since the Rebellion closed," said Robert, interrupting his classmate in a
                     subject that evidently deeply interested him.</p>
                  <p>"Yes. Immediately on the opening of hostilities there sprang up a class of
                     free-lance journalists who run a-muck, as it were, in their reckless career.
                     There was no word too profane, no sentence too vulgar for their sheets. They
                     obtained a notoriety and a circulation by this, and this alone; encouraged
                     treason, multiplied the enemies of the government, and led the deluded Southern
                     people to believe that vulgarity was chivalry, and open defiance of law the
                     height of patriotism. Their monstrous calumniations of the best men of the
                     North were intended solely to satisfy the prejudice and conscience of the
                     rebellious faction, and keep alive the feelings of animosity, as revealed in
                     the diabolical doings of the Ku-Klux Klan. These papers were worthy the darkest
                     period of the world's history, fitting relics of a barbarous age, well
                     calculated to induce a reign of terror no less terrible than that of France in
                     its demoralizing results. For their proprietors the Guillotine were too easy a
                     mode of exit. They should have been<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6129-00000012"/>
                     made to feel, to appreciate more effectually the wrath of an injured
                     community."</p>
                  <p>"And they did feel it. The leading papers of the class you mention went down,
                     as they deserved to, and their owners are now remanded to the oblivion they so
                     richly merited. Time will effect a radical change in all these matters."</p>
                  <p>"Doubtless. The promises of the West are unlimited, in growth, in wealth, in
                     everything—but morals. Several of her leading cities are very maelstroms of
                     vice and crime, where the New England boy, fresh from the pure atmosphere of
                     his native hills, encounters all the baneful associations that are so inimical
                     to his better nature, and goes clown with the flood-tide of dissipation. The
                     restraining element, at best, is feeble, inadequate, and life and honor hold
                     little consideration where wealth is sought with hands imbued with human blood.
                     With a purified press this condition of affairs will be remedied; when the
                     unprincipled journalists who have taken advantage of the unorganized state of
                     society, to disseminate their erroneous ideas, are wiped out, extirpated, then
                     will society be founded on a basis of morality, Christianity and civil
                     liberty."</p>
                  <p>"Nobly spoken," responded Robert Converse, as his friend concluded and subsided
                     into a chair from which he had risen as he became warmed up with his
                     subject.</p>
                  <p>Norman Chester was a Western boy, whose father had experienced many trying
                     vicissitudes on the border during the early part of the civil war, and these
                     facts had so impressed themselves upon his mind that his one ambition was to
                     equip himself to assist and possibly eventually succeed the latter in the
                     publication of a journal whose staunch loyalty and outspoken advocacy of
                     justice had won for its publisher honorable distinction and generous
                     revenue.</p>
                  <p>"I was right, Norman," continued his companion, "in already according you a
                     brilliant success. I fancy you now wielding the editorial pen in the cause of
                     humanity, making for yourself a powerful constituency, and then going to
                     Congress, as the distinguished Congressman Chester."</p>
                  <p>"No, I thank you," returned Norman, laughing., "I haven't forgotten Wolsey's
                     advice to Cromwell. In adopting my profession I have endeavored to ignore
                     selfish ends."</p>
                  <p>"Which is the surest way to succeed. Those who aim only to accomplish their own
                     advancement are generally the last in securing it. Your victory is assured. In
                     a medical profession, however, I see no such triumphs for myself."</p>
                  <p>"You are too pessimistic, Robert. As the <foreign xml:lang="FRA"
                        >protege</foreign> of our kind tutor, Prof. Payson, you have enjoyed unusual
                     advantages, which you have not neglected to improve, by the way, and with such
                     a companion as Ella Payson to share your future lot, the prospect could
                     scarcely be more auspicious."</p>
                  <p>The color came slightly in Robert's face at the mention of the name which had
                     evidently touched a tender chord in the student's feelings.</p>
                  <p>Both young men were excellent specimens of mental and physical training. This
                     evening Norman Chester had called at the room of his friend and classmate,
                     which was at the residence of Professor Payson, in order that they might
                     mutually assist in their studies. These satisfactorily disposed of, they were
                     indulging in a glance at the future as we intrude upon their presence. However
                     irrelevant to our story may be the conversation to which we have listened, it
                     affords an inkling of<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6129-00000013"/> the hopes and
                     anticipations which each entertained.</p>
                  <p>The room, which was spacious and comfortably furnished, contained besides many
                     articles of luxury which gave evidence that a more than friendly hand had
                     arranged for its occupant. Choice plants, rare botanical specimens, and
                     fragrant flowers lent their cheerful influence to the apartment. Text books of
                     various kinds were within easy reach, while standing in a corner were a set of
                     Indian clubs, on the floor by which reposed a pair of dumb-bells of no trifling
                     weight.</p>
                  <p>"And now for a brief exercise with the gloves before I go," said Norman,
                     arising to leave.</p>
                  <p>The two students put on a set of gloves and, quietly engaged in the sport of
                     boxing.</p>
                  <p>Both were adroit in their manœuvres, but as the practice with them had been
                     mainly to promote a healthy muscular development, neither sought to display
                     superiority over his opponent.</p>
                  <p>After a few light passes, Norman stopped and looked at his watch.</p>
                  <p>"It's high time I was going," he said; "it's later than I supposed."</p>
                  <p>And hastily assuming his hat, he wished his friend a hearty good-night, and
                     started out in the darkness, taking the nearest way across the fields to his
                     own place of abode.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
                  <head type="sub">AN OBSTACLE IN THE WAY.</head>
                  <p>However cunningly devised, however carefully executed, the schemes of villainy
                     are not always permitted to succeed. And sometimes they are so permitted. When
                     one scans the daily record of crime in which the innocent so often suffer and
                     the guilty go unpunished, the question naturally arises and frequently
                     expresses itself, Why are such things allowed to be? If man's vision were not
                     finite, the question might never occur. That justice will be meted out somehow,
                     somewhere, we should not dare doubt. It is as certain as that there is a
                     Supreme Judge whose rulings are never wrong, and whose decisions no technical
                     evasions can annul.</p>
                  <p>But let us return to Dora Vernon, whom we so abruptly left under such critical
                     circumstances at the conclusion of a previous chapter.</p>
                  <p>Not many strides had the bogus policeman taken, when a young man, who in the
                     darkness and excitement had approached them unperceived, interposed himself
                     before Dora, and as the fellow advanced, gave him a stinging blow which sent
                     him to the ground. Only for a moment, however. Finding himself opposed by a
                     formidable assailant, for the blow he had received was no child's play, he
                     struggled to his feet, with curses on his lips, and commenced an onset. While
                     no mean foe to be met in a hand-to-hand encounter, he found one who, although
                     comparatively slight in figure, was yet able to render his efforts harmless,
                     and at the same time return sallies that were very<pb n="30-31"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000014"/> much out of his reckoning, and altogether too
                     severe for his corporeal system to withstand. Consequently, after vainly
                     endeavoring to reach his adversary till his strength was quite exhausted, he
                     received a <foreign xml:lang="FRA">coup de grace,</foreign> which wholly
                     unsettled his equilibrium and brought him to mother earth again. Thanks to that
                     blow, it furnished its recipient with enough quietus to keep him in an
                     unconscious state for some time.</p>
                  <p>No sooner had the villain fallen than the newcomer hurried to the side of Dora,
                     who had also fallen, but only in a swoon, from which she was fast reviving.
                     Placing his arm around her, he gently lifted her from her unseemly couch, and
                     succeeded in restoring her to entire consciousness. Slowly did her eyes open at
                     first with a dazed, bewildered expression, and then, as the tender words of
                     solicitude fell upon her ear, she became reassured and cognizant of her
                     position, a shudder passing over her, however, as she mentally recalled the
                     scenes through which she had just passed.</p>
                  <p>"Dear miss," said the young man, when she had become sufficiently composed, "I
                     have found you under the most embarrassing circumstances, and hope I have
                     rendered you a service."</p>
                  <p>"O, sir, you have, indeed—a service I can never forget, and which shall ever
                     receive my warmest gratitude." And she would have narrated the events we have
                     given the reader, but he urged her to wait till they reached his place of
                     residence, which was but a short distance away.</p>
                  <p>This she complied with, and escorted by the young man, Dora soon had the
                     pleasure of seeing a bright light beaming from the windows of an elegant
                     dwelling—the only one in the vicinity, to which the surrounding estate
                     belonged.</p>
                  <p>And here Norman Chester—for it was none other—was made acquainted with Dora's
                     adventure till he had encountered her in the toils of the destroyer.
                     Exceedingly wroth was he when he heard from those fair lips the story, told in
                     the sincere and pathetic manner peculiar to Dora; and he blamed himself that
                     his chastisement of the wretch had not been more severe. He had recognized his
                     antagonist as one Harland Banford, a fast young man of respectable family,
                     residing in another portion of the city. Perhaps he put a deal of emphasis on
                     his wish for the fellow's annihilation, but the fact was, he cared little
                     whether that individual was dead or alive, since he had been permitted the
                     pleasure of rescuing so fair a creature, and could hear from her own lips the
                     relation of his gallant achievement.</p>
                  <p>If Dora Vernon showed gratitude, Norman Chester revealed in his glowing eye
                     something warmer—attachment, it might have been love for the youthful stranger.
                     While assuming no credit for having rescued one who had thus unavoidably been
                     cast upon his protection, the exercise of that faculty had kindled a flame of
                     sympathy which had already attained a remarkable growth and threatened serious
                     havoc with his unpledged affections. That he had never met a girl coming quite
                     so near his ideal of true loveliness, he could but acknowledge, and fondly as
                     he had imagined himself invulnerable to the female graces, the young man was
                     compelled to cast down the gauntlet and recognize their potency.</p>
                  <p>That night Dora Vernon slept under a strange roof, but she did it willingly.
                     She felt that they were friends near her, people who cared for her welfare, and
                     who' would not allow aught of harm to come to her. All this she thought over
                     after she had retired—this coupled with her providential<pb n="32-33"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000015"/> deliverance from an untold fate; and of her
                     cousin she thought—her dear cousin, Julia Cameron, whose wishes, had she
                     complied with them, would have saved her so much trouble. Still continuing her
                     meditations, she came at last to the one who had rescued her, Norman Chester,
                     and, most credulous reader, will you believe it?—she took more pleasure in
                     dwelling upon thoughts of him than aught else that had entered her mind. Like
                     many another girl, she was susceptible to Cupid's influence, and he, the
                     embodiment of powers capable of protecting her from enemies, and of personal
                     advantages of no common order—well, well, who could blame her?</p>
                  <p>The next morning she partook breakfast with her newly-made friends, and after
                     receiving a cordial invitation to repeat her visit under more favorable
                     circumstances, she started for her boarding-house, accompanied by Norman, who
                     was especially delighted with the walk.</p>
                  <p>But we are not going to divulge all the conversation that transpired during
                     their slow stroll toward the corporation. The imaginative reader can conjecture
                     various topics that might have occupied their attention. He is assured,
                     however, that only one subject was indulged in—a subject agreeable to both.
                     More than this it is not, perhaps, necessary to disclose.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
                  <head type="sub">A FESTIVE OCCASION.</head>
                  <p>"Miss Montville, you're wanted at the door!" rang in shrill tones through the
                     hall of a certain Lewiston corporation boarding-house.</p>
                  <p>There was an inquisitive flutter at the head of the stairs, several doors
                     stealthily moved on their hinges, as the young lady, gaily attired in full
                     evening costume, appeared and recognized her caller. She had evidently expected
                     his coming, and with only a word of greeting, the two sallied forth upon the
                     street, their exit closely scrutinized by a dozen or more eyes curiously
                     peering from the block they had just left.</p>
                  <p>"Where to-night, Dick?" familiarly inquired the girl, the twain presently
                     emerging upon Lisbon street.</p>
                  <p>"To the theatre. The play is having a big run there. You will be pleased with
                     it."</p>
                  <p>"I shall be pleased with nothing of the kind!"</p>
                  <p>"How so, my beauty?"</p>
                  <p>"I have a play of my own to-night. We're going in another direction!"</p>
                  <p>"Just as you please. Where, then?"</p>
                  <p>"To the Park."</p>
                  <p>"What! to hear the band play?"</p>
                  <p>"No—not exactly—to see the crowd. The evening is splendid, the birds will be
                     out in full feather, and I want to see the styles."</p>
                  <p>"You! How about me?"</p>
                  <p>"Well, you can see them, too, if you'll agree not to become enamored with some
                     of the fair creatures, and desert me."</p>
                  <p>"Desert you! Never!"</p>
                  <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6129-00000016"/>
                  <p>"Until you find one that suits you better."</p>
                  <p>Both laughed at the badinage indulged in, as, thus conversing, they entered the
                     Park, and were soon mingling with the gay crowd that was promenading its
                     embowered avenues in time with the sweet strains of instrumental music which
                     floated on the evening air.</p>
                  <p>The younger population of Lewiston were here fairly represented, in their
                     happiest mood. Goldsmith's genial pen could have pictured a scene of no more
                     rational enjoyment. Merry throngs of boys and girls frolicked in the utmost
                     freedom upon the grassy lawn, the more sedate gathered in groups to discuss the
                     latest predictions of the weather bureau, while multitudes of belles and beaux,
                     engaged in pleasing converse, filed up and down the gauntlet of observing
                     loiterers, who commented on their appearance or exchanged a word or look of
                     recognition. This was a part of Lewiston life—this assembling on the Park of
                     Thursday evenings, to pass a brief season in agreeable diversion from the
                     exactions of routine labor.</p>
                  <p>"There they come," said Pauline Montville, to herself, as, seated with her
                     companion, she descried a couple approaching them in the moving throng. "The
                     country girl that she is, her beauty outvies all the lavish displays of dress
                     made here. It's evident she's captivated him—this young student of prospective
                     fortune. Perhaps she will win him; I doubt it, however. Pauline Montville has a
                     hand in this game. But I must avoid their seeing me."</p>
                  <p>She averted her head as the couple passed by—Dora Vernon and Norman Chester—for
                     the young student, having received her permission to call, had pressed his
                     advantage by soliciting her company on the Park for the evening. Feeling
                     confident that no ill could come of it, Dora had gladly complied.</p>
                  <p>"There goes a beauty for you," said the young man Dick to his companion, as the
                     couple disappeared in the moving crowd. "Who is she?"</p>
                  <p>"An acquaintance of mine."</p>
                  <p>"Of yours? You didn't recognize her."</p>
                  <p>"I was looking the other way."</p>
                  <p>"O, yes; of course. I see; you didn't care to be recognized in turn. You were
                     ashamed of your company, eh?"</p>
                  <p>"How excessively modest you are getting, Dick! A young man of your brilliancy
                     should hardly consider himself in that light."</p>
                  <p>"I consider myself in any light that suits you."</p>
                  <p>"That's good, Dick, and leads me to believe that our acquaintance has not been
                     in vain."</p>
                  <p>"Perhaps not."</p>
                  <p>"Dick!" She turned upon him so suddenly that he glanced at her in surprise. "We
                     are only friends, you know?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes."</p>
                  <p>"Well, suppose this was our last appearance in public together?"</p>
                  <p>"As you choose," he replied, with an indifference that showed his association
                     with the girl was only a matter of pastime.</p>
                  <p>"I have a proposition to make," she continued.</p>
                  <p>He inclined his head and listened. His eyes lit up with a strange fire. As she
                     proceeded he glanced inquiringly into her face, as if to read the thoughts that
                     remained unuttered.</p>
                  <p>"Well, you are a brick I" he exclaimed, when she had concluded. "You are the
                     devil's own child, and no mistake!"</p>
                  <p>The Androscoggin bell slowly struck the hour of nine, the music ceased in the
                     band stand, and the crowd gradually dispersed, leaving the Park a scene of
                     solitude and quiet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6129-00000017"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
                  <head type="sub">FROM NOONDAY TO MIDNIGHT.</head>
                  <p>Two months wore away in the factory experience of our heroine—not always
                     pleasant experience, nor yet altogether disagreeable—when a beautiful Sunday
                     was ushered in, with a clear sky and bland, exhilarating atmosphere. It was a
                     day fit to excite man's deepest gratitude for the blessings of life and inspire
                     him to the worship of its divine Author. Dora Vernon, adhering to the custom
                     which she had scrupulously observed at home, prepared herself for church, and,
                     attended by Norman Chester, with whom pledges of more than friendly fealty had
                     already been exchanged, was among those who listened to the expounding of the
                     holy scriptures. Rev. Mr. Candor, the popular preacher, much beloved for his
                     zeal and earnestness, chose for his text a passage particularly adapted to the
                     young, admonishing them against the treacherous enticements of sin, seeking
                     constantly to ensnare the unwary, and its consequent remorse and ruin. With
                     glowing colors did he picture the happiness which falls to the lot of those who
                     ever walk in the path of rectitude, while with sombre hues did he paint the
                     future of those who wander estray in the mountains and deserts of iniquity,
                     where the voice of the Good Shepherd calls in "vain-for their return. On Dora's
                     plastic mind, across whose camera no lasting lines of darkness lingered, the
                     words, fell with joyful impress, and as the congregation retired, she mentally
                     concurred in the general comment upon the excellence of the sermon and the
                     eloquence of the preacher. Alas! that the world stands ready to tear down the
                     noble structures of such worthy builders!</p>
                  <p>After dinner, anticipating a quiet afternoon, Dora went to her room, of which
                     she was the sole occupant, it being a small but pleasant one usually assigned
                     to the last arrival, intending to entertain herself with a choice volume which
                     she had obtained at the public library the evening previous. Lying upon the
                     book, probably placed there by the chambermaid in her absence, she found a
                     note, carefully sealed, bearing her address in a precise, feminine hand.
                     Breaking the seal, she read:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>DEAR DORA: Thinking you would not be engaged this afternoon, I have
                                 taken the liberty to make up a little party of friends in your
                                 honor, for the purpose of visiting one of the most interesting and
                                 picturesque spots on the Androscoggin, called West Pitch. During
                                 the short acquaintance I have been privileged to enjoy with you I
                                 have been impressed with your admiration of the beautiful in
                                 nature, and with due regard for the character of the day, I trust
                                 you will see no impropriety in accompanying us. I will call for you
                                 at two o'clock, Please be ready.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <salute>Your Friend,</salute>
                                 <signed>PAULINE MONTVILLE.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Dora regretted that the invitation had been extended. She would have preferred
                     to remain at home and read for the afternoon. Did the sermon of the forenoon
                     recur to her mind, warning her against the step she might take? But she
                     hesitated to decline. She had already received many tokens of kindness from the
                     writer of the note, and would it not be ungrateful and rude to refuse so
                     thoughtful a request, especially when the affair had been arranged in her own
                     behalf? Yes; she would be ready.</p>
                  <p>Pauline Montville, the leader of the expedition,<pb n="38-39"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000018"/> if we may call it such, had from the first
                     fastened herself upon the attention of Dora. What could. be her purpose in
                     seeking the association of one so unlike herself, the reader may need not be
                     informed. Certain it is that such association could bring only harm to the
                     latter. With her presuming manners and winning ways, with a ready wit for all
                     emergencies, Pauline Montville had thus far avoided any exposure of her real
                     character, and had succeeded in presenting herself only in the light of a good
                     and true friend. A friend! when from the depths of her heart she hated
                     Dora—hated her for the graces she possessed; hated her for the place she held
                     in the estimation of Norman Chester. And this hatred had grown to a deadly
                     malignity, warmed and stimulated by their daily intercourse, till now it only
                     sought some mode in which to vent itself. Under the golden coating of deceit
                     lurked the poisoned fangs of envy, ready and impatient for the opportunity to
                     fasten themselves into their prey. Pauline Montville had studied her part well;
                     her role was perfect as rehearsal could make it; and the curtain was rung up on
                     act the first when Dora Vernon yielded to her solicitations to visit the spot
                     we have mentioned. Was it to be comedy or tragedy? It could not he farce;
                     Pauline Montville never had part in such.</p>
                  <p>It was a perfect day, and the merry party of girls took every occasion to
                     express their delight at being free from the labor of the factory, indulging in
                     outbursts1 of jest and song which at times were repulsive to the sensitive and
                     untainted ear of Dora. But she forebore expressing displeasure, and at length,
                     when her companions chided her for a lack of cheerfulness, so fair entered into
                     the excitement and enthusiasm of the moment that they could illy conceal their
                     gratification at seeing her footsteps tending so naturally toward that greatest
                     of moral precipices, over which theirs, perhaps, had long before inadvertently
                     slipped. Many a girl with her coveted her superior qualities of mind and heart,
                     but at the same time would gladly have beheld them crushed, if only to satisfy
                     the baser tendency of their desires. Cunning prevented this being shown openly;
                     the heart's secrets were locked, that their silent workings might be the more
                     effectual.</p>
                  <p>West Pitch! scene of the tragic Indian romance! a beautiful specimen of
                     Nature's workmanship, perhaps, although the encroachments of civilization, with
                     its vandal touch, may have robbed it of some of its primeval attractions! here
                     do we find our heroine, amid her gay associates, all bent on enjoying
                     themselves as best they might.</p>
                  <p>Seated upon the projecting ledge, the girls recounted to each other the many
                     frailties which had attended their career in Lewiston; told of lovers' affairs
                     and flirtations generally; of balls, and rides, and evening promenades, when
                     Pleasure reigned, and Principle and Honor sank beneath her ghastly car.</p>
                  <p>Yet here Pauline Montville displayed the most remarkable trait in her
                     character—that of guarding her emotions and assuming stoical indifference to
                     the exciting incidents around her. She was too good an actress to be diverted
                     from her own imperturbable part by the witty sallies of the moment's jester.
                     With a calm exterior, she bided her time, studiously rehearsing to herself each
                     chosen passage, that, when her name should be called, her success might be the
                     more certain, her triumph the more complete.</p>
                  <p>At length a young man approached the party,<pb n="40-41"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000019"/> and being recognized by a majority of the girls,
                     was introduced by Pauline to Dora, as Richard Montville, her brother.</p>
                  <p>Prepossessing in appearance, pleasing in manners, and quite confident and
                     self-assured, he bespoke a person well accustomed to female society, and
                     received a deal of flattering attention from the group of girls. Little die} he
                     seem to care for this, however, for his eyes we fixed upon Dora, and in the
                     most familiar manner possible, he seated himself by her side and entered into
                     conversation.</p>
                  <p>"A fine day to enjoy the Pitch," said he to Dora,1 as the other girls seemed at
                     once to find something of new interest in another locality, thus leaving her,
                     somewhat against her own inclination, to engage the entire attention of the
                     new-comer. "Sister Paul informs me that you have but recently come to
                     Lewiston."</p>
                  <p>"I have been here but a brief period," replied Dora.</p>
                  <p>"And this is the first time you have visited the Pitch? It must be quite a
                     novelty to you."</p>
                  <p>"It is, indeed. I should hardly have ventured to come had the girls not
                     extolled its beauties to such an extent. And yet, its very terrors seem to
                     enhance its beauties."</p>
                  <p>"It would be a terrible thing for one to fall into the abyss of water dashing
                     amid the rocks below us," he continued, directing her attention to the "Pitch,"
                     which was greatly swollen by recent rains.</p>
                  <p>"An awful fate!" said Dora, shuddering. "One could scarcely conceive a more
                     certain death. There would be little hope of life after falling into such a
                     dreadful place. Its contemplation is enough to excite the deepest alarm. I fear
                     I am in peril now."</p>
                  <p>"O, there's no danger here," replied he, laughing ing. "Take my hand and we
                     will approach nearer the precipice."</p>
                  <p>She gazed at him a moment and then drew back. Turning to see what had become of
                     her companions, they were not in sight.</p>
                  <p>"What!" she exclaimed; "have they left me here alone?"</p>
                  <p>"No—not alone," said the young man; "I am here. Paul knew you would be well
                     cared for while I were with you, and so probably did not consider it a breach
                     of propriety to leave you. She is a thoughtful sister, is Paul."</p>
                  <p>"She has been very attentive to me," said Dora.</p>
                  <p>"And of course you will excuse her if she permits me to assume some of that
                     attention."</p>
                  <p>"But she will return?" queried Dora.</p>
                  <p>"It is scarcely probable. They are a party of wild girls, with her, and are
                     doubtless far away ere this. I trust my company will prove no less agreeable
                     than theirs."</p>
                  <p>An expert at words, an adept at deceit, and his faultless attire bespeaking a
                     person with scrupulous regard for externals, at least, he presented himself in
                     such glowing colors to the artless perceptions of the young girl that she
                     imagined him, both in purpose and appearance, a gentleman. It was but natural,
                     when we consider how little she had seen of life—how much of the sweet and how
                     little of the bitter she had drank. No drama on the stage had depicted to her
                     how transparent are many beings who drift about within the pale of
                     society—human vampyres, whose sole aim and object is to destroy. And how was it
                     with her companions? Well did they know into whose hands they had committed
                     her; 'twas all too well, arranged; and, if anything, their footsteps were more
                     buoyant homeward, gloating as they did over the prospect of another victim.</p>
                  <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6129-00000020"/>
                  <p>Withdrawing to a more remote point of observation, where the cataract afforded
                     a better perspective, and the interlacing branches spread their canopy of
                     leaves above their heads, the circumstances and surroundings seemed conspiring
                     to render Dora oblivious of the dangers that lurked in her pathway, her young
                     soul, meanwhile, unsuspectingly drinking in the enchanting beauties of the
                     scenery and entering with full zest into the sentimental strain which her
                     companion was pleased to indulge in. Many times had she had opportunity to
                     commune with Nature before, and always attuned to its inspiring influence, her
                     mind had ever kept above the carnal allurements of earth, and traveled in its
                     own chaste, poetic sphere, untrammeled and unclouded by the false, and crafty,
                     and subtle realities of life. Filled with this fervor, this admiration of the
                     good and beautiful, she noted naught but the finer sentiments of the young man
                     at her side, nor detected beneath the glittering surface, the sinister designs,
                     the gloomy pitfall so skillfully being laid for her unwary feet.</p>
                  <p>Thus did the hours glide, thus did the conversasation teem with glowing
                     expressions of appreciation and delight, till the shades of night began to grow
                     thick around them, and glimmers of light shot out from the windows of the
                     distant habitations. Then did the thought occur to Dora—how similar were the
                     circumstances to those in which she had recently been placed—yet how different!
                     Then she was with a stranger; now she was with the brother of her friend. Poor,
                     confiding, inexperienced girl! Little did she know what fiendish designs are
                     instigated to mislead the feet of innocence. Yet did she sorely blame herself
                     for so far overstepping the bounds of propriety as to have remained alone in
                     such a place and at such an hour with a comparative stranger, and in so doing,
                     committing herself to his honor.</p>
                  <p>But Richard Montville was too well up to his profession to let aught
                     successfully oppose his advances, and the wily, accomplished libertine bent all
                     his arts and well-tried schemes to effect his purpose.</p>
                  <p>Would that this chapter could be blotted from our story, but it cannot; it is
                     real-life, and must remain. It is the old recital—innocence yielding to false
                     representations and delusive sophistries—and is only what frequently occurs in
                     Lewiston and elsewhere. It is enough for us to add here, that when Dora Vernon
                     returned to her boarding-house, late that night, she was as her associates had
                     desired her—a despoiled, ruined girl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6129-00000021"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
                  <head type="sub">END OF ACT THE FIRST.</head>
                  <p>The next day Dora Vernon was not at her accustomed place in the factory. Word
                     went in that she was ill—and true, she was. The thought of what had transpired,
                     the reaction of her moral forces, with their blighting crimination, had
                     completely stunned, bewildered her; and her mind went into a semi-trance state,
                     from which it never emerged. Error once fastened upon her footsteps, she was
                     not one to repent and try life again; but remorse, hydra-headed and with
                     baleful eyes, confronted her at every avenue of thought, crushing out whatever
                     of good purpose or noble impulse might have remained, and plunged her into the
                     darkest abyss of despair.</p>
                  <p>Thus she remained. Norman Chester called upon her, but received word that she
                     had gone home. Julia Cameron also called, and received the same reply. Had they
                     known how deeply she suffered, how sadly it must all end, perhaps they would
                     have rushed to her side, and diverted the course of events, But could Norman
                     Chester ever forgive? No; his was a soul too noble to grant acquittal to such a
                     course; and yet he could pity—would pity—had not circumstances prevented.
                     Confined to her room under plea of indisposition, having her food brought to
                     her, seeing none of her companions—who as well avoided her,—Dora spent the time
                     in reflections of the most bitter character, and in meditating how she could
                     rid herself of that now intolerable curse—life. With each day that she remained
                     in this self-imposed immurement she became more morbidly sensitive, more keenly
                     alive to the infamy of her position, fancying as she did that every one knew
                     the story of her disgrace. Live she could not, with reproach constantly before
                     her, dragging her down and crushing her in the sight of mankind. And he—Norman
                     Chester, the one to whom she had given her best, her holiest affections—to meet
                     him were a far more deadly portion than that drawn from the poisoned chalice.
                     She felt that all this must have an end, and that soon. Repentance, the only
                     recourse left to her now, proffered its hand of mercy. The past was black and
                     forbidding, but the future, the unknown, the invisible, whatever might be its
                     mysteries, she gladly welcomed its opportunity for escape; and Dora Vernon, so
                     short a time-before happy with the most glowing anticipations that life could
                     afford, now committed herself to her God, preparatory to taking that step which
                     should set her free from the thralldom of her existence.</p>
                  <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/>
                  <p>There was a great stir one afternoon when it was proclaimed on the street and
                     throughout the factories, that a girl had drowned herself, and the body had
                     been taken from the river where the deed was done. The excitement was intense,
                     and the news, with all the startling details that imagination could suggest,
                     soon appeared in the latest edition of the daily paper. The suicide had chosen
                     a singular place at which to terminate her life—from the jagged rocks of West
                     Pitch had she hurled herself, and the body was recovered, shortly afterwards,
                     some distance below the falls. Tender hands at once bore her to her late
                     boarding-house. To this abode large multitudes flocked to obtain a view of the
                     unfortunate creature. Among the crowd was a young man, drawn by idle curiosity,
                        who<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6129-00000022"/> walked along, with thoughtful
                     countenance, toward the scene of attraction. As he entered the house he noticed
                     for the first time that it bore a familiar appearance, and with an excited,
                     tremulous step, he passed into the room where the drowned girl lay. Merciful
                     God! could human heart be proof against such a trying ordeal?—Norman Chester
                     standing there, petrified, crazed, gazing with blank, unutterable anguish upon
                     the dead, body of his betrothed—Dora Vernon! Such a scene would be remembered
                     for a lifetime, and excites the human compassion to its highest degree.</p>
                  <p>But strange events and coincidences were yet to occur. While the group stood
                     around the lifeless form of Dora Vernon, it was rumored that a man had been
                     killed by being caught in the shafting in the factory. In course of time this
                     was confirmed, and the name was made known. Reader, would you like to hear it?
                     It was Dick Bruce, the <emph>false</emph> Richard Montville! Mysterious indeed
                     are the dispensations an over-ruling Providence.</p>
                  <p>Then did the whole story leak out. The two tragedies, almost simultaneous, had
                     brought events to a climax, and the affair was too strange to be kept a secret
                     by those to whom it had been imparted in boastful jest. Among the articles
                     belonging to the unfortunate girl was found a long letter, directed to her
                     mother, containing her last sad chapter of experience. How must her grief have
                     been augmented as she recalled, the admonition, fresh in memory, of that loved
                     one!</p>
                  <p>Dora Vernon was carried home to be buried in the quiet country churchyard,
                     attended and mourned over by a stricken father and mother, and Julia Cameron
                     and Norman Chester, together with a large concourse of friends who had loved
                     and respected her in her halcyon days of innocence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
                  <head type="sub">OLD ACTORS IN NEW ROLES.</head>
                  <p>"There she goes, Harl!"</p>
                  <p>Two young men stood in the recess of a building on Lisbon street, of a Saturday
                     evening, watching the lively tide of human beings coursing down toward City
                     Hall, where an unusually brilliant affair in the character of a ball, was about
                     to come off.</p>
                  <p>The remark with which we opened this chapter was elicited by the appearance of
                     two young ladies, both dressed in the gayest apparel, and evidently bent on
                     making a night of it at the ball. As they passed, one of them bestowed an arch
                     look upon the young men we have noticed.</p>
                  <p>"Who?" said Harland Banford, turning to his companion at the observation.</p>
                  <p>The young man pointed to the girls, and inquired:</p>
                  <p>"Don't you know the one on the left?"</p>
                  <p>"Know her? certainly not. Why should I?"</p>
                  <p>"You've very good reason to. Though you may not be aware of it, she's a worthy
                     accomplice of yours."</p>
                  <p>"How so?"</p>
                  <p>"You haven't forgotten the girl who committed suicide the other day?"</p>
                  <p>"Hist! not so loud."</p>
                  <p>"Well, you remember the one who assisted her towards taking the step. You
                     recollect how you got euchred by the student, Norman Chester, who afterwards
                     became so sweet on the ill-fated girl. But that's all between you and me, for
                     it seems the fellow doesn't intend to blow on you, or else he didn't discover
                     who you was."</p>
                  <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6129-00000023"/>
                  <p>"Perhaps not; but what's that to do with this girl?"</p>
                  <p>"A good deal. She's the one who played the decoy for Dick Bruce, and helped him
                     to succeed with the part in which you failed. But Dick got knocked out in the
                     factory afterwards, poor devil!"</p>
                  <p>"The deuce, you say! Then this is none other than—"</p>
                  <p>"Pauline Montville."</p>
                  <p>"You're sure of it?"</p>
                  <p>"Positive. She's going to the ball to-night, and as we're on the same bill,
                     I'll introduce you."</p>
                  <p>"You know her, then?"</p>
                  <p>"Of course; and a more perfect trump was never dealt. It's very few she cares
                     to associate with, although I understand she was quietly snubbed by the Bishop
                     sisters when she tried to make their acquaintance. She's a speculating
                     character, and even in pleasure she always looks to business."</p>
                  <p>"A little above the average, I imagine."</p>
                  <p>"Decidedly so. They say it was all envy that made her seek Dora Vernon's
                     destruction. She'd an eye on Norman Chester, and, thought by effecting the poor
                     girl's ruin her own chances would be improved. But in this she counted without
                     her host. Norman Chester belongs to another class altogether; and yet, he's a
                     tiger when emergency requires—eh! Harl?"</p>
                  <p>"Hush!" replied Harland Banford, fiercely, his anger quickly rising, and
                     revealing itself in flashing eyes, the orbit of one unnaturally limited by a
                     slight swelling in its immediate vicinity.</p>
                  <p>"O, don't get excited, Harl," said the other, discreetly returning to his first
                     subject. "She's a good card, and as you become acquainted to-night, you can
                     make her your right bower."</p>
                  <p>"Suppose she doesn't condescend?"</p>
                  <p>"Depend upon if, she will. Your pater's got the stamps, and as for you, that's
                     a matter of little consideration; the means are nothing—the ends are all with
                     her. If you give her the slightest prospect of gratifying her foolish ambition,
                     you can make her your obedient slave, I'll assure you."</p>
                  <p>But in this the young man was over-confident He little knew the powerful will
                     that Pauline Montville exercised, and that once given the advantage, it seldom
                     failed to attain its object.</p>
                  <p>So they conversed for some time, still scanning the female faces passing by,
                     some modestly turned to the walk to avoid their intrusive gaze, and others
                     brazenly peering at them with expressions which it were an easy matter to
                     interpret But leaving them to this diversion, we will go back a short period in
                     the history of Harland Banford, and learn some of its passages that are
                     pertinent to our story.</p>
                  <p>When Stephen Banford obtained a position for his son with the firm of
                     Stringham, Belcher &amp; Co., New York city, he had hoped their old friendship
                     and former business relations would be productive of great advancement to the
                     young man; that Harland's ambition would be aroused by the advantageous
                     opportunities presented him, and that in business matters he would prove as
                     successful as had been his father years before. In this the anticipations of
                     the senior Banford were doomed to mortifying disappointment. Harland, once
                     planted in the broad and fertile fields of dissipation spread out in the great
                     metropolis, soon yielded to the natural bent of his disposition, and found no
                     difficulty in affiliating with the most deeply-schooled roughs of the town,
                     attending upon all the various resorts of a questionable character—the theatre
                     first, then the dance-hall, and finally the gambling<pb n="50-51"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000024"/> house, so that he soon came to enjoy their
                     associations with even more zest than those who had been reared in their midst
                     and always accustomed to their scenes. This course soon became known to his
                     employers, and, unable to tolerate the habits of dissipation which were daily
                     growing upon the young man, word was sent to Stephen Banford that it would be
                     for the welfare of his son, and for their interest, that Harland should be
                     immediately called home, for his presence was not desirable, but would prove a
                     serious misfortune if longer retained in the establishment. Deeply aggrieved,
                     the father at once directed his son's return; but whatever his business
                     relations, evil associations could not be severed so easily, and Harland
                     remained for several weeks a constant attendant at the gaming-table, where
                     luck, as is often the case, was for a time lavish with her favors. The change
                     came at length, however, and in one brief encounter with a skillful son of
                     Belial, his funds were entirely exhausted, and he was thrown penniless upon the
                     street. At this juncture, it was hinted, an affair of a desperate nature
                     occurred in which Harland participated, for he left the city in a hurry, and
                     returned to Lewiston, considerably sobered in deportment, and for a while
                     evidently oppressed with some well-defined apprehensions.</p>
                  <p>Stephen Banford was not aware what a depth of villainy existed in his son, nor
                     did he care to sound it, for young Banford's strong and violent passions would
                     not have hesitated at any step in retaliation for a father's reprimand.
                     Unchecked as his later life had been, he had grown to acknowledge no master but
                     his own wishes, and these, reckless and perverted as they were, led him into
                     all sorts of misdemeanors, and stamped his character indelibly with the
                     satanical imprint. And yet, with all his faults, there were those who readily
                     attached themselves to his company, and sought to encourage rather than
                     restrain his career of recklessness and profligacy. Not young men only, but
                     females—some claiming the highest respectability—were often in his society, so
                     that the clique of which his means soon gave him the acknowledged leadership,
                     was of no ordinary proportions. To become a favored one of this clique was now
                     Pauline Montville's greatest ambition. The fact of the bad character of Harland
                     was of trifling significance when weighed against the wealth which he some day
                     had the promise of possessing; and. she was quite giddy with delight when, that
                     Saturday evening, on the ball-room floor, she received an introduction to the
                     dissolute young man. Proud, selfish and vain, she at once began to build
                     castles for the future, when, as the wife of Harland Banford, she would take
                     position in a society to which her aspirations pointed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6129-00000025"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
                  <head type="sub">RECEIVING PAYMENT IN KIND.</head>
                  <p>Summer had passed, autumn had followed with its ripened glory, and close in its
                     footsteps, with less cheerful welcome, it may be, came the austere, frigid
                     tread of winter. The warm, enervating days, when humanity seems but a waif upon
                     the tide of time, drifting along in its passive course, had gone, and the
                     sharp, inspiring airs of the colder season brought stronger pulsations to the
                     heart and more practical views of life. Perhaps the effects were palpable upon
                     the moral nature—for the moral and physical are ever in sympathy,—and better
                     thoughts and nobler purposes were engendered by the more vigorous
                     atmosphere.</p>
                  <p>Two months had elapsed since Pauline Montville took up her abode at the stately
                     Banford residence as the wife of the only son and heir, Harland. And what
                     changes had those two months wrought upon them both! Harland, once the reckless
                     follower of pleasure, had wholly abandoned his former career, and adopted a
                     course of the most exemplary rectitude, while Pauline, but recently the cold,
                     cruel and ambitious girl, looking upon him only as the means of gratifying her
                     unscrupulous pride, had in that brief time undergone a most remarkable
                     transition. Instead of regarding him as such now, she had grown to consider him
                     as the very soul of her existence. By that strange power which lies hidden in
                     some natures, however depraved, he had drawn her to himself as by a mesmeric
                     influence, and her once peerless individuality was completely submerged beneath
                     the overpowering tide of her affections. And the sudden change in Harland's
                     character seemed to merit all this. A new life, as it were, had dawned upon
                     him, which gave promise of a course of usefulness and noble realization in the
                     future; so that Stephen Banford, reviewing the earlier career of his son,
                     gratefully thanked the better decrees of fate which had brought about such
                     happy results.</p>
                  <p>But all this proved to be only a link in the chain of retributive justice which
                     was to attend them. It was but the transient favors of a destiny which rears
                     the wicked to a higher degree of enjoyment, that, when the punishment is
                     administered, the pain shall be the more poignant, the chastisement the more
                     severe.</p>
                  <p>Day was slowly sinking away in the sombre shades of evening, and Harland sat in
                     the drawing-room with his wife, conning the daily paper.</p>
                  <p>"Do you know, Pauline," said he, at length, laying aside the paper, "that I
                     always look at the criminal record first?"</p>
                  <p>"Indeed!" replied she, nervously. "Why should you prefer that department,
                     Harland?"</p>
                  <p>"I can't say that I do prefer it, Pauline, but I find it impossible to avoid
                     it."</p>
                  <p>"Impossible?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes. A certain premonition tells me there is evil in store for me, and not
                     only for me, but I fear for you, too, on my account."</p>
                  <p>"I trust not," said Pauline. "I have tried to bury the' past out of sight. You
                     should do the same, Harland. Hark!"</p>
                  <p>There was a violent pull at the door-bell. Pauline quietly passed to the door,
                     and opening it, beheld two men, who inquired if Mr. Banford lived there. On
                     learning that Harland was within, they did not pause for ceremony, but ushered
                        themselves<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6129-00000026"/> selves at once into the
                     room where he sat, closely followed by the wife, now full of trepidation and
                     alarm. Her alarm was greatly increased when she beheld Harland seized by the
                     two men, and after a desperate struggle, thrown to the floor and handcuffed.
                     The truth flashed upon her in a moment—these were the officers of the law, and
                     Harland was about to suffer the penalty for some crime he had committed in
                     times past. The thought that he, her all, the very life and existence of her
                     being,, was about to be torn from her, so worked upon the agonized wife, that
                     the breath for a while forsook her, and she fell fainting beside her
                     husband.</p>
                  <p>Pauline Banford had thought rightly, and when at length her senses returned and
                     she was informed that Harland would be conveyed to New York to undergo trial
                     for his participation in an extensive burglary which had been fully brought to
                     light through the treachery of an accomplice, reason for a time wholly deserted
                     her, and the punishment grew more terrible in its effect For days she raved in
                     all the horrors of delirium, often pleading to some imaginary being for the
                     restoration of Harland. And in this delirium another form appeared to her—a
                     beautiful girl, cold in death, with garments wet and reeking, but with voice of
                     an unearthly tone, accusing her of an awful crime.</p>
                  <p>What she underwent in those few days of torture might far exceed the agony of
                     the Inquisition. There was no cessation of the dread infliction, till nature,
                     from sheer exhaustion, stopped its deranged action. Repose succeeded, and from
                     this she finally came forth with reason restored, but with a burden of guilt
                     oppressing her such as she had never felt before.</p>
                  <p>Stephen Banford, accompanied by Pauline, went to New York to do everything
                     possible for the release of Harland, but mightier powers were pitted against
                     them, and neither the money of the one nor the pleadings of the other availed
                     anything, towards his liberation. Justice and the interests of society had to
                     be satisfied, and Harland Banford was sentenced to Sing Sing for a period of
                     ten years.</p>
                  <p>Stephen Banford heard the sentence with a degree of composure, but to Pauline
                     it was as a death-knell. Her ambition, her hopes, her all, had perished, and
                     the persuasions of the old man for her to return home with him, were but bitter
                     mockery to her ears. He came back alone, leaving her broken in spirits,
                     stricken in conscience, and sinking beneath her guilt, an outcast in that
                     hot-bed of sin.</p>
                  <p>Why wonder we, then, that at such a time her remarkable face should attract the
                     attention of many an evil eye, and that cruel hands should be extended to her
                     in pretended sympathy for her condition? Alas! it has been the fell fate of
                     thousands far more deserving than she. Let once the pride be gone, hopes
                     blasted, and all that is noble In life becomes of indifferent value at best,
                     while the tinsel and glare of iniquity and folly for a time dazzle the senses
                     and bring transient relief to the mind in forgetfulness of the past. Pauline
                     Banford's was the course of many another, but it was not of long duration.</p>
                  <p>Reader, you have probably heard how the "Castle Glen" went down—we mean the
                     vessel, with its freight of abandoned women. Would it be too much to tell you
                     that Pauline Banford, under an assumed name, was among the number? Does your
                     sympathy bar you from desiring for her such an end? Turn back a few months, and
                     see another being, purer by far, sinking beneath the tide, and remember who it
                     was that plunged her there. Is it not payment in kind, and can you question its
                     justice?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6129-00000027"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
                  <head type="sub">PROSPECTIVE AND RETROSPECTIVE.</head>
                  <p>Let us return for a while to the scene of our opening chapter—the home of Dora
                     Vernon. More than a year has elapsed since our last visit. We then beheld her
                     there in all her loveliness and innocence—a child of nature's own purity,—just
                     ripening into those maidenly graces which bespeak the coming charm of
                     womanhood. Alas! that the cold, damp sod lies piled above her now, and decay
                     has already began to mould away the delicate fabric of that fair temple.</p>
                  <p>The room has changed but little since last we saw it—the same precise
                     appearance marks the general appointments of the place, while the picture of a
                     sweet, youthful face—the last sad token of her now gone—looks down upon the
                     scene she once made joyous with her presence.</p>
                  <p>There are four persons in the room—Mr. Vernon and his wife, and two visitors
                     who have come to sympathize with them in their affliction. As you may suspect,
                     the visitors are Norman Chester and one whom we have known as Julia Cameron,
                     but who now bears the name of Mrs. Chester—strange as may seem the fact to
                     those who have not been permitted to trace their history. Norman is now part
                     owner and associate editor of an enterprising journal in the West, and with his
                     young wife is passing a brief vacation at the East. His career is justifying
                     the most sanguine expectations of his former classmate, Robert Converse. But
                     there is a sad episode in his life which is painfully recalled by his present
                     visit to the parents of her who received ceived the tribute of his first love.
                     How heavily has the hand of sorrow laid upon them! What Christian resignation
                     did it require to pass unscathed the fiery blast that swept over that
                     household! And yet faith was not subdued, and affliction has done no more than
                     temper with a deeper hue the reliance in that power which is all-sustaining in
                     the hour of need. The clouds were dense, but the light of the spirit penetrated
                     even their density, and revealed the goodness of Him who never forsakes his
                     children. Instead of casting the Bible aside, and treating all its promises as
                     vain, it became a closer companion to the stricken ones, and the daily
                     devotions were of greater length and more fervent than of old.</p>
                  <p>Mr. Vernon and his gentle wife had grown to regard their visitors with as much
                     affection as if they had been their own children, and every few months prior to
                     their departure for the West, had insisted upon their coming to spend a season
                     with them in their quiet, country home. Nor did they see any impropriety when
                     the youthful couple, holding in the most sacred remembrance the relations of
                     the past, had, not long previous, united themselves in the bond of matrimony.
                     They looked upon it as a bond riveted and made holy by the memory of their own
                     dear Dora, and thanked Heaven for a union so fraught with promises of good to
                     noble lives, made happy and contented by morality and virtue.</p>
                  <p>When Norman Chester had stood by the bier of Dora Vernon, he had realized to
                     its fullest the strength of the ties that had been so ruthlessly sundered. She
                     had burst upon his quiet student life like the sudden flash of a meteor, had
                     revealed to himself the hidden recesses of his own heart as they had never been
                     revealed before, and had<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6129-00000028"/> then as
                     suddenly disappeared, leaving him dazed, bewildered at the experience. For a
                     while he knew not which way to turn for relief. The chosen profession of his
                     life had lost its inspiration, and nothing but the most dreary, aimless
                     existence seemed his portion. From this abstracted frame of mind his unselfish
                     nature was suddenly recalled at beholding the grief of another—one who had
                     shared the mutual acquaintanceship of himself and Dora for a brief season—Julia
                     Cameron,—and whose excellent qualities, kindly nature and congenial tastes had
                     already inspired his highest esteem. Scarcely less beautiful than her cousin
                     had been, but two years her senior, Julia Cameron might well deserve such. And
                     this was all that Norman Chester at first entertained for her; but as the weeks
                     rolled by and became months, till his student days were fast nearing their
                     close, he perceived that, while time could not entirely dispel the dream which
                     had so enchained his senses, the sober realities of the future claimed his
                     attention, and he must accept the situation that events had thrust upon him. No
                     one could ever fill the place left void by the loss of his first love. Would
                     Julia Cameron accept another? The question was simple, and she was too sensible
                     a girl not to comprehend its import. She did not start or feign surprise when
                     the proposal came, but recognizing the noble character of its author, and no
                     less dearly cherishing the memory of her lost cousin, she answered in a quiet,
                     unaffected affirmative.</p>
                  <p>"A year has gone since she was torn from us," said Mrs. Vernon, reverting to
                     the subject that was ever uppermost in her mind, "and it has been a year of
                     much darkness mingled with its sunshine. I sometimes feel to repine at her
                     sorrowful death, but a Voice is ever ready to rebuke me for the presumption
                     sumption. No; I trust it is all for the best, and her spirit is beyond the
                     reach of trouble. The stroke was severe, but it has chastened the soul, and
                     taught us to rely more fully on the inscrutable purposes of Him who doeth all
                     things well."</p>
                  <p>"We do not realize how much suffering there is in the world till a portion
                     falls to our own lot," said Norman, as Mrs. Vernon ceased speaking, from the
                     fullness of her feelings, and tears suffused her eyes. "I notice by the papers
                     that the Castle Glen," a vessel having a number of disreputable females aboard
                     as passengers, has been sunk at sea, and the poor creatures went down with
                     her."</p>
                  <p>"A sorrowful end, truly," said Mrs. Vernon, with a sigh of sympathy at the
                     intelligence. "Could we but go back to the home of their infancy, perhaps we
                     would find many a parent's heart wrung by the catastrophe; and yet, might they
                     not rather wish a daughter deep down in the sea, than leading a life of infamy?
                     Far worse a life whose only fruits are dishonor, than a death which severs the
                     earthly ties ere the soul is blighted! We little know what first led them to
                     adopt such a course. Some, perhaps, from nature lacked moral principle to
                     withstand the temptations of life, while others may have been the victims of
                     circumstance, as we call it. Too often the pressing hand of poverty performs
                     the fearful work—oppressive task-masters in large cities, who, for the paltry
                     gain of restricted wages, consign those in their charge to the troubled sea of
                     woe When I think of all this, my own affliction grows lighter, viewing, as I
                     must, the awful whirlpool of despair into which hundreds yearly sink. Many are
                     compelled to suffer deeper than we—bereaved parents whose children have passed
                     away in the darkest midnight of sin."</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Vernon's emotions so overcame her that<pb n="60-61"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000029"/> the tears sprang afresh to her eyes, while
                     Julia's arms stole gently around her neck, as she sought to console the dear,
                     good woman. Other arms had encircled her neck once—her own child's,—and yet she
                     did not refuse the tender office so kindly meant, but looking up through her
                     tears, she parted the rich tresses of hair from the pure, white brow bending
                     over her, and imprinted a kiss there—a kiss of motherly affection and
                     tenderness. Taking Julia's hand, she led her to the spot where Norman sat, and
                     placing it in his, a joyful smile lit up her face as she said:</p>
                  <p>"Heaven bless you, my dear children! You were the last friends she saw on
                     earth, and to you my heart must ever turn in the deepest gratitude. May
                     misfortune and sorrow never cast their gloom over your now happy lives. The
                     future is spread out in glowing fields of anticipation before you. May no storm
                     imperil the way, but a kind Hand ever guide you safely in the path of right, to
                     that eternal city whose walls are jasper and whose streets are gold!"</p>
                  <p>A fervent "Amen" from Mr. Vernon showed that he was far from being an unmoved
                     spectator of the scene. With hearts filled with religious fervor, they all
                     knelt down, and one united prayer found audible expression in his voice, while
                     an air of holiness seemed to pervade the room, imparting fresh tokens of grace
                     and peace by its sanctifying influence.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>THE PERIL OF BEAUTY.</head>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                  <head type="sub">THE ORPHAN SISTERS.</head>
                  <p>"I declare, Belle, I'm getting heartily sick and disgusted with this stupid
                     factory life. Day follows day with the same monotonous, unchanging routine of
                     labor and care, till one grows weary at heart, and indifferent to living, at
                     the slight prospect of ever obtaining anything better. 'Tis three years since
                     father died and left us alone in the world, to care for ourselves. And three
                     lonely, burdened years they have been, as you well know—drudgery, drudgery,
                     nothing but drudgery—no relief, no cessation, as if life itself would be
                     relinquished at the relaxation of toil. I long for a change—something better
                     than the experience of the past few years, and I will have it!"</p>
                  <p>The girl's cheeks flushed to a deeper glow while she spoke, her manner growing
                     more and more earnest as she continued, till her excitement reached such a
                     pitch that the calm, thoughtful face of Belle Bishop grew suddenly more serious
                     and thoughtful with concern.</p>
                  <p>"Hush! sister mine; don't let your feelings so get the better of you. How
                     childish, to think you must have nothing but the sweet, flowery side of life!
                     You have already seen too many comforts and luxuries to let you bear your
                     present lot with<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6129-00000030"/> becoming submission.
                     Don't complain. There is a future filled with happiness for us yet, I
                     trust."</p>
                  <p>"O, you can philosophize, if you will; as for my part, I don't believe I was
                     ever made to wear my life away in daily drudgery. More than one venturesome
                     admirer has told me I possess a beautiful face, and the mirror does not lack in
                     confirmation. When I was at school in our native town, you will remember, I
                     used to take a prominent part in the exhibitions, and it was then said I
                     displayed a talent the would be worth a fortune to another girl. But rather had
                     not received the fatal stroke of adversity then, and he laughed at the idea.
                     Things are changed now, however; I must use the means, the endowments which
                     nature has given me."</p>
                  <p>"How? What do you mean, Agnes?"</p>
                  <p>"The theatre plays here next week!"</p>
                  <p>"And you—"</p>
                  <p>"Mean to join it."</p>
                  <p>"What! and become—</p>
                  <p>"An actress. You have anticipated it. It is a free, easy life, full of pleasure
                     aud change; and I have no doubt that I shall succeed on the stage. I shall win
                     a name, a fortune, and can make for us both a home of plenty."</p>
                  <p>Belle Bishop covered her face with her hands, and tears of bitterness coursed
                     over her pale, wan cheeks. This was the darkest cloud that had ever threatened
                     her peace. Rendered almost stoic by the adversity which had robbed her of
                     parents and home, she had not yet schooled herself to abide the fate which
                     might thus rob her of a sister.</p>
                  <p>"O, Agnes," she sighed, "how can you think of such a thing? What foolish
                     ambition has taken possession of you? We are subject to peril enough now,
                     without courting the dangers which come with such an exposure to the heartless
                     world. You cannot not have forgotten the sad fate of Dora Vernon, who probably
                     thought herself as secure from harm as any one could be. With her dark history
                     fresh in memory, it behooves us to beware which path in life we pursue—the
                     right or the wrong."</p>
                  <p>"But she was unsophisticated and inexperienced."</p>
                  <p>"So are you, Agnes, in many things. Treachery and crime lay wait on every side
                     to assail honor and purity. 'Twas only last evening you were accosted by a
                     stranger, who seems to have taken an unwonted interest in your beauty. You
                     remember him—that dark-browed fellow, whose eyes were constantly upon you, and
                     who, at last, made bold to solicit your company from the hall. Think of him,
                     Agnes, and the many of his class who only await encouragement from those they
                     would destroy."</p>
                  <p>"Pshaw! Belle. He was presuming, certainly, but I gave him a reply that
                     satisfied him, I trust. Don't imagine I would associate with such as he; no,
                     not <unclear>so long</unclear> as I have a will, and can exercise it for
                     myself. But I must confess to a strange dread at the fellow's words. He appears
                     to be a newcomer in Lewiston."</p>
                  <p>"Yes, a strolling adventurer, probably, who goes from place to place only as
                     the law compels him. How know you but that you may encounter characacters like
                     his in the course you contemplate, and fall beneath the cunning arts of their
                     deceit? O, Agnes! I had rather see you buried beneath the cold earth, than on
                     the stage, with its gaudy, tinseled plumage. What would become of you; once
                     entered upon its questionable career—an outcast, a wreck in society, a wretched
                     sacrifice to a false ambition." And Belle Bishop buried her face in her hands
                     as if to shut out the terrible vision.</p>
                  <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6129-00000031"/>
                  <p>Agnes laughed a loud, careless laugh, which only augmented the grief of her
                     sister.</p>
                  <p>"Ah! Belle," she replied, you had better join with me. I am sure such acting as
                     this would make you a star at once. Really, I didn't imagine you had such a
                     talent for the stage. There, brush away your tears, and let's have a little
                     plain, common-sense talk about the matter, for it is already decided that I am
                     to become an actress."</p>
                  <p>"Don't mention it again, Agnes."</p>
                  <p>"Yes, I shall, Belle; and I'll make you one, too. So, come, let's have a little
                     performance right here, all by ourselves, just to see how we shall appear. I'm
                     fond of farces. Suppose we try our hands at a farce."</p>
                  <p>"A tragedy, more likely, for such it may end. You forget, Agnes, the duty you
                     owe one who has proved such a kind friend to us—yourself, especially."</p>
                  <p>"You mean Albert."</p>
                  <p>"Yes, Albert Heywood. You little think how he would suffer under such an
                     affliction—he who has given you his whole wealth of love."</p>
                  <p>"There, Belle, do not speak of him. What if he has seen fit to cast his heart
                     at my feet? It does not follow that I should accept it. Albert is a poor
                     machinist, depending upon his daily labor. We were born amid wealth, and though
                     I am a factory girl now, I don't feel bound to wed myself to poverty. No, no;
                     Albert may be very good, and while I may like him as a friend, I could never be
                     his. When the theatre leaves here I shall go with it, if I can make an
                     engagement."</p>
                  <p>The beautiful brunette surveyed herself in the mirror, as if studying her
                     chances of success when brought before the footlights. And while she thus
                     stands, let us glance over her shoulder and view the same reflection.
                     Certainly, no one would question the superior attractions of her person—the
                     full, almost voluptuous development of her form, the gently arched neck,
                     supporting a head rich in an abundance of raven tresses, which but now had been
                     thrown back in haughty contempt at the serious swords of her pale, blonde
                     sister. Agnes Bishop was far from being ignorant of her charms; to the
                     contrary, she knew the power of a beautiful face and form to elicit public
                     favor, but failed to reflect that the same beauty which in some cases might
                     prove a blessing, in others would prove a curse.</p>
                  <p>As she thus regarded herself before the mirror, the door bell sounded
                     familiarly, and while Belle proceeded through the hall to receive the visitor,
                     Agnes seated herself in a chair, and assumed a studied indifference that ill
                     became her.</p>
                  <p>It was Albert Heywood—good, generous Albert, a mechanic, to be sure, but with a
                     nobler heart and mind than usually falls to the endowment of man. Tall,
                     graceful, with an expression of firmness and gentleness which combine the
                     elements of true worth; a clear, full eye, beaming with candor and
                     intelligence, and a broad brow—this was Albert Heywood, whose tender regard
                     many a fair one would have given her soul to possess, yet whose love was held
                     in such light esteem by the ambitious Agnes.</p>
                  <p>The latter bowed coldly as he entered, deigning only a word of welcome, to
                     which the young man seemed only too well accustomed, however, for he took a
                     seat beside her, and talked with the two orphan sisters with the freedom of a
                     brother—free on his part and that of Belle, but Agnes restrained her language
                     to monosyllables and brief rejoinders. This had the effect to increase Belle's
                        entertaining<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6129-00000032"/> qualities, and the
                     conversation was warmly conducted till, at last, no longer able to keep back
                     the fearful subject, she fully divulged Agnes' intention to become an
                     actress.</p>
                  <p>The effect could not be told in words; neither could it be fully known save by
                     the party concerned. He did not prostrate himself before her, and plead with
                     her to desist from her purpose. He did not even reply for a while, but a
                     chained tongue and subdued heart showed deeper feelings than could have found
                     utterance. It needed no avowal now. The story had been told. His devotion was
                     as complete and apparent to its object as human speech could make it. What need
                     of further words? If these were naught, if declarations vain, then come the
                     dark reality of action, and faith in strength to meet it!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
                  <head type="sub">A VILLAINOUS PLOT.</head>
                  <p>The theatre had already played a week in Lewiston, with indifferent success,
                     perhaps, but sufficient to draw out most of the community who were accustomed
                     to patronize the drama. And this class is ever larger than it should be, where
                     the hard-earned wages are required to satisfy an unhealthy desire for
                     amusement, the effect generally being to degrade rather than elevate, to dwarf
                     rather than enlarge the moral comprehension.</p>
                  <p>It was dusk as a young man entered the reading room of the hotel where the
                     manager of the theatre sat conning the daily paper. At first he approached
                     cautiously, but as he neared, the latter looked up, his hand was extended, and
                     a mutual recognition took place.</p>
                  <p>"By Jove! Clarkson, is this you?" exclaimed the manager, in the brusque manner
                     of a Bowery sport, "and what the deuce brings you away down here in this little
                     city of Lewiston? Well, this is odd, I declare; and the last I saw of you, you
                     was among the careless boys of North end, or bearing a hand at Harry Flemings'.
                     But I'll bet high you left Boston for Boston's food."</p>
                  <p>"Ah! that I did," replied Clarkson, in an undertone—"a bit of a fracas in which
                     your humble servant was engaged."</p>
                  <p>"As I suspected."</p>
                  <p>"And may have learned?"</p>
                  <p>"No; we theatricals don't mind such things. We've too much business behind the
                     scenes to note events outside. You sly dog, you even feared<pb n="68-69"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000033"/> I would peach on you, and so kept shady till
                     now. But it's all right, Clarkson; you should know me too well for that, even
                     if I had been familiar with the circumstances. It's for our mutual good that
                     the past be kept a secret with us, eh?"</p>
                  <p>"Your memory serves you."</p>
                  <p>"Always. But we sha'n't be overheard. Suppose you give me the particulars of
                     your last, and then we'll go to the hall, for it wants only an hour of the time
                     to open."</p>
                  <p>These few words had been spoken in a low tone, yet not so low but that a young
                     man, who sat back to them, looking absently towards the window, caught their
                     import, and became singularly interested.</p>
                  <p>"Well, you recollect, a month ago I met you at Harry's, just before you started
                     on your trip down east?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes."</p>
                  <p>"A week later, the young owner of the Dudley Iron Works, while going over
                     Charlestown Bridge at night, was robbed of a cool thousand and this trinket,"
                     tapping a pocket evidently containing a watch.</p>
                  <p>"Ah! I see; and you—"</p>
                  <p>"Yes; you understand. But the beauty of the thing is, no clue has been
                     obtained, nor is likely to be; for I've kept in the background, and read the
                     papers, which only say the robber was not recognized, and his name is
                     unknown."</p>
                  <p>"Good! and you are down here, having a flash time on your thousand dollar
                     bounty. Ah! well—it's just like you, Clarkson, for all the world; and I'll
                     venture to say you've got some female or other on the string."</p>
                  <p>"Female? ha! ha! that reminds me, so I have—a devilish pretty girl, too; but
                     she doesn't seem inclined my way Do you believe it?—I strayed into a musical
                     affair, the other night, where she was, (and where I first saw her, in fact,)
                     and tried to force my attentions upon her; but, with all my polished North End
                     airs, the girl fairly disdained my overtures. Zounds! I half believe she knew
                     who I was, by the way she treated me. It seems another fellow escorted her and
                     her sister home, but she treated him deuced coolly, for all that."</p>
                  <p>"Of course you know her name?"</p>
                  <p>"I believe so; let me see; yes, I have it—Agnes Bishop."</p>
                  <p>"Agnes Bishop! Agnes Bishop! that's the name of the girl who applied to me
                     to-day for a chance to join my company, and I told her I would let her know
                     to-morrow."</p>
                  <p>"You don't tell me, Cool! By Jove! this is most fortunate. Now for a piece of
                     strategy that will discount your finest plays!"</p>
                  <p>"How so?"</p>
                  <p>"When she calls to-morrow, engage her—engage her for <emph>me!</emph> Do you
                     take? I am tired of this one-horse affair, and am going to make back tracks for
                     Boston, which way you are going, I believe."</p>
                  <p>"Yes; and I told her, if I secured her a place, it must be at one of the Boston
                     theatres, as this is my last night in Lewiston, and I shall disorganize on my
                     return. I rather fancied the girl myself."</p>
                  <p>"Well, let her go with you, and I'll go on the same, boat, unbeknown to her.
                     When we arrive in Boston, I'll furnish her with conveyance and see to her care
                     afterwards!"</p>
                  <p>"That's cool, Clarkson. You would play the game all your own way, I see. But
                     you're an old pal, and I don't mind humoring you, although you'll have to meet
                     the consequences, should anything turn up. If she has friends, and they learn
                     of her fate, just take care of yourself—that's all."</p>
                  <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6129-00000034"/>
                  <p>"Never fear for me, Cool. I can manage a little affair of this sort, you bet!
                     She's only a poor factory girl—an orphan—with only one sister, and a dingy
                     machinist—the one I saw her with that night. I believe his name is
                     Heywood—Albert Heywood—a good-looking fellow enough, but a down-east flat, for
                     all that. You see I have made this case a special study, and know well the
                     whereabouts of the parties. They all reside on B—— street. Don't be alarmed for
                     me, Cool."</p>
                  <p>"Well, I don't mind; it shall be as you say."</p>
                  <p>"Your hand for it."</p>
                  <p>"There it is."</p>
                  <p>And the two villains grasped each other's hand with all that peculiar
                     cordiality which is born of the deepest-dyed knavery.</p>
                  <p>"And now for the hall. Of course you will honor me with your presence
                     to-night?"</p>
                  <p>"Certainly; but we mustn't be seen out together where the light would reveal
                     us, for it might put an end to all our fine plotting."</p>
                  <p>"Just as you like," replied the other, as both locked arms and sallied
                     forth—the dignified manager of a vagabond strolling troupe, and his confederate
                     of the past in the crimes and crookedness about Boston.</p>
                  <p>As they departed, the young man who had feigned to be half asleep in his
                     retired corner, and had overheard the whole conversation, arose to his feet
                     with an excited countenance, and strode back and forth across the room, his
                     mind evidently stirred to its very depths with a strange agitation. Thus he
                     continued, now and then glancing at the clock upon the wall, till some half
                     hour must have elapsed, when, buttoning his coat snugly about him, he went
                     forth from his transient abode, into the evening air. That he was a stranger
                     soon became evident from his inquiry of a passer-by for the location of a
                     certain street, toward which he directed his steps.</p>
                  <p>Not far had he gone in the direction indicated, when, in crossing a street amid
                     the darkness, a runaway horse came suddenly upon him, and would probably have
                     killed him outright had not a young man, coming from the opposite direction, at
                     great risk of his own life, grappled the animal's bit just in time to retard
                     his progress in a degree, yet not sufficiently to prevent a blow which hurled
                     the first party to the stony earth, stunned and rendered senseless by the
                     concussion.</p>
                  <p>With the assistance of a policeman, his rescuer was enabled to bear him back to
                     the hotel, which was near at hand, and medical attendance was summoned.</p>
                  <p>The injury was not serious, the doctor remarked, although several days would
                     probably elapse before a full return of conscousness would transpire, as the
                     most dangerous blow received was upon the head in its coming in contact with
                     the earth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6129-00000035"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
                  <head type="sub">A SINGULAR INTERVIEW.</head>
                  <p>It was a week later, one evening, as Albert Heywood sat in his room at his
                     boarding-place, his head resting upon his hand in deep meditation, that a boy
                     rang the door-bell, and the following note was sent up to him:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>MR. HEYWOOD—Sir: I understand that to you I owe my deliverance from
                                 an impending death on the evening of the third. For this and your
                                 kind solicitude for my recovery, as I learn from the clerk, you
                                 have my heartfelt thanks. But I have something to tell you, and I
                                 was in search of you at the time of the accident which nearly
                                 deprived me of life. Come at once to my room, No.—, and perhaps I
                                 may be able, in a measure, to repay the deep debt I owe you. Do not
                                 delay a moment; time my prove more valuable than gold. Heaven help
                                 it be not too late.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <salute>Yours,</salute>
                                 <signed>HARRY DUDLEY.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Nervously Albert glanced at the note, read it, wondered at its remarkable
                     language, and with a feeling of concern set out to comply with its request. A
                     short, brisk walk, and he was ushered into the presence of Harry Dudley, who
                     was confined to his bed, unable, as yet, to arise from his injuries.</p>
                  <p>"Albert Heywood, I believe," said Dudley, giving his hand a cordial grasp, as
                     the former approached his bedside. "Would I could tell you in words the
                     gratitude I feel for the service you have rendered me. But I must not waste
                     time with such. I can better serve you, I trust, although it may be too late.
                     You had a very dear friend in this city, a week ago—a beautiful lady, who was
                     infatuated with the idea of becoming an actress, and contemplated joining the
                     theatre?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes! yes! I had."</p>
                  <p>"And she has gone with it?"</p>
                  <p>"She has!"</p>
                  <p>"My God! then it may be too late—too late to save her!"</p>
                  <p>"To save her! What do you mean?"</p>
                  <p>"That she is entrapped, and may ere this be the victim of a foul betrayer. Do
                     you know a fellow named Clarkson, who has been in Lewiston of late?"</p>
                  <p>"Clarkson? Ah! yes, I do—a person who has represented himself as a runner for a
                     large mercantile house in Boston, although no vestige of goods was ever seen
                     about him. He has tried to foist his attentions upon the lady you mentioned,
                     but she detested him for a villain, as she believed him to be."</p>
                  <p>"She was right. The night I received my injuries I was seated in the
                     reading-room below, and overheard a disclosure and a plot that almost congealed
                     my blood. This Clarkson chanced to be there, and a friend of his—one Cool
                     Graham, who has been the pretended manager of an affair they called a theatre,
                     so recently performing here. They conversed, and I listened; and well I might,
                     for I was an interested party. Some time ago, in crossing Charlestown Bridge,
                     from Boston, at night, I was robbed of a thousand dollars and a gold watch.
                     Clarkson was the criminal party, and he had thus far avoided detection by
                     coming east. He told this to his friend. But this was not all I overheard. The
                     rest concerns you. A plot was laid—a plot fit for fiends, and not men; for when
                     Agnes Bishop arrived in Boston, instead of joining the theatre,<pb n="74-75"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000036"/> as she expected to, she was to be given over to
                     the tender mercies of that blackleg, Clarkson!"</p>
                  <p>Albert Hey wood heard it as marble, as a corpse, if you will, so cold and
                     lifeless were his features; but as the last words were uttered, the volcano of
                     emotion slumbering within him could contain itself no longer, a cloud of
                     unconsciousness thickened o'er his senses, and he fell prostrate to the
                     floor.</p>
                  <p>The noise of Albert's fall drew several servants to the room, who chafed his
                     temples and hands till consciousness returned.</p>
                  <p>Harry Dudley, himself an invalid, had not counted on the effects his words
                     might produce, and now regretted his thoughtlessness in thus suddenly
                     disclosing the whole affair. As Albert revived, he bethought himself to at once
                     propose some plan to rescue the maiden, if possible, from him who probably now
                     held her in his power.</p>
                  <p>"You must start to-morrow for Boston," he said to Albert, as the latter, now
                     recovered, yet ghostly white, sat at the bedside. "There is a detective, a
                     friend of mine, shrewd and cunning as any of his craft, to whom I will send a
                     note by you, and if the girl is dead or alive he will find her. You must start
                     by the first train; find Trevelyn, the detective, as I shall give you
                     directions, and be assured he will ferret out the whereabouts of the parties. I
                     will have the note ready for you in the morning; and may God help that you find
                     Agnes Bishop undefiled by the crafty villain."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
                  <head type="sub">ALONE IN A STRANGE CITY.</head>
                  <p>What stranger has been through the by-ways of North End, Boston, and not seen
                     indications of depravity, crime and wrong from which he has turned in unfeigned
                     abhorrence? New York has her low slums, to be sure, reeking with poverty and
                     filth, and breathing of disease, corruption and death; but Boston, although
                     cleaner on the exterior, has crime-stained walls within, and black hearts
                     seething with their fullness of sin and woe. To many evils of the former, in
                     past years, may be attributed her unfortunate political management, the
                     treachery of office-holders, and encouragement given to frauds, swindles, and
                     all manner of low pursuits, by a clique groveling in the foulest mire of their
                     own streets, yet powerful enough to hold the reins of municipal control.
                     Ignorance and lack of principle combined have effected this, and the poor dupe
                     of misplaced confidence has found only a confederate of his victimizer in the
                     regulation blue. The support has been mutual; knavery knows its own; and the
                     result has been a daily catalogue of iniquities at which the heart has
                     sickened. But of all these Boston has had her portion. There is no need of
                     comparison. The metropolis of New England, populated in the main by descendants
                     of the good old Puritan stock, we will not attempt to erase the fact of her
                     many faults.</p>
                  <p>Bound for this city, the steamer which contained Agnes Bishop and the troupe of
                     players, left the rock-bound coast of Maine, on its usual passage—<pb n="76-77"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000037"/> left the high-reaching hills and lofty pines,
                     where good and true hearts beat with all the freedom, nobility and grandeur of
                     nature. With the other members of the party she refrained from associating, and
                     sought alone the aft deck, to watch the receding land where her life till now
                     had been spent, and enjoy the novelty of her first sail on the broad ocean.
                     Slowly did the landscape disappear from view, growing fainter and fainter as
                     darkness and distance intervened, till finally nothing remained but a seeming
                     wall of water. Thus shut in to herself, her thoughts turned to bright
                     anticipations of the future, which, ere long, became more glowing and animated
                     as strains of music issued from the cabin, and, with the moonbeams playing
                     antics upon the water's surface, suggested to her ardent imagination the
                     presence of mermaids, with pearl-studded hair, engaged in serenade. How more
                     enchanting than anything she had ever experienced—anything she had ever
                     dreamed! Of all the romantic conceptions of the past, the fevered fancies of
                     her girlhood and maturer years, none had so completely filled her with the
                     entrancing sensations of ecstacy and delight. To always live in such soul-born
                     rapture, with music's potent spell to hold the senses willing captive, to paint
                     the vision's canvass with its vivid hues, and set at naught the gloomy vagaries
                     of doubt—Agnes thought this must be happiness indeed—a foretaste of the
                     generous feast in store for her.</p>
                  <p>At length the music ceased, leaving her again to the quietude of her own
                     musings, and not till drowsiness admonished her of sleep, did she forsake the
                     spot, and descending to the ladies' cabin, seek a place of rest.</p>
                  <p>The next morning, having made a quick, pleasant trip, the steamer arrived at
                     India Wharf, Boston ton, at about five o'clock, while it was yet dark, and
                     gloom nestled down over the silent, sombre city.</p>
                  <p>There was a jar, as of something colliding with the boat, and Agnes startled
                     from her slumbers, a. little frightened at first, but once fully awake, and
                     hearing the commands of the captain to make fast to the wharf, she knew they
                     had arrived at their destination. As she hurriedly threw on her clothes, and
                     emerged into the cabin, for the first time a feeling of bitter desolation and
                     homesickness took possession of her. Sleep had, as it were, dispelled the false
                     beacons that had directed her course, and left nothing but the dreariest, most
                     forbidding darkness around her. Poor girl! She would have given all she
                     possessed at that moment to once more be permitted to perform her usual task in
                     the factory, and enjoy the society of her clear sister Belle and—yes, Albert
                     Heywood. Now she felt the love she could never fully realize before; now she
                     became aware how good it had been to see him, although treating him at the
                     time, perhaps, with scorn. These were but passing thoughts, however, and she
                     had not entered into the arena of action already being prepared for her. As she
                     mounted the stairs the clamorous tones of the hackmen in soliciting passengers
                     fell upon her ear with a disagreeable, repelling sound, and gave her a strange
                     impress of the little soul contained in the world of business.</p>
                  <p>Cool Graham, the manager, was the first person to greet her as she reached the
                     upper deck, and affectedly inquired after her rest during the night's
                     passage.</p>
                  <p>"You are looking charmingly this morning, Miss Bishop," he said, gazing upon
                     her with a look of wanton admiration. "You have made a lucky choice, and will
                     create a sensation when placed<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6129-00000038"/> upon
                     the boards. I anticipate a great success for you, and scores of lovers will
                     flock to throw themselves at your feet. You will have to bar your heart to the
                     flatteries of the rich young men who will offer their fortunes, or the stage
                     will be robbed of your light at the outset I am in hopes to see you engaged
                     without delay, and have already sent an agent forward to procure a place for
                     you."</p>
                  <p>"You are very kind," replied Agnes. "I hope to obtain a place where I shall not
                     be troubled with any suitors. I have chosen the theatre in hopes that I may
                     earn a competence, and place myself and sister beyond the necessity of
                     toil."</p>
                  <p>"Be assured you will that," rejoined Graham. "Never fear of ever again having
                     to soil your dainty hands with the dirt of labor. Your fine form was not made
                     for such a purpose. Let those who have no better means of obtaining a
                     livelihood use their hands, but one with charms such as yours need not feel
                     compelled to drudgery."</p>
                  <p>How strange! Even these few words seemed unlike what he had used before—their
                     tone, so changed, struck her as odd and unnatural.</p>
                  <p>"Wait a moment," he continued; "most of our party have left the boat, and I
                     don't know but that you may have to take a hack alone. I will speak with a
                     driver, and direct him where to carry you."</p>
                  <p>"But I shall see you ere long?" said Agnes, growing a little nervous.</p>
                  <p>"You will probably be called upon during the day," he replied, carelessly; and
                     went to consult a driver—an ill-looking fellow, more fit for a. guerilla than a
                     hackman, one would think—who was taken aside for a few moments, and the
                     directions given, but not such as would have done for Agnes' ear.</p>
                  <p>"See here, Bill," accosted Cool, in a guarded tone, "I've got a little extra
                     job for ye; nor it isn't for me exactly, either, as it happens, but for
                     Clarkson."</p>
                  <p>"Clarkson! Clarkson! Is he back to the city again? I haven't seen his face this
                     many a day. Where's he been?"</p>
                  <p>"Of on a wedding tour, I should say, for he's got a piece of calico aboard, and
                     has gone ahead to make ready for her reception."</p>
                  <p>"Is that so? Then Jake has done it at last," said the hackman with mock
                     gravity. "But where shall I take her?"</p>
                  <p>"To Moll Baxter's, on Billerica street, up three flights, in the rear."</p>
                  <p>The hackman put one finger to the side of his nose, and closing an eye,
                     ejaculated slowly, "O, yes, I see."</p>
                  <p>And the two went back with all the affability at their command, to assist our
                     heroine into the hack.</p>
                  <p>Their hands did not touch hers, however, for she drew them back as though in
                     fear of being stung by a serpent, and entered almost unassisted, which movement
                     had the effect to make the hackman shrug his shoulders, and cast a quizzical
                     look at Cool, as much as to. say, "A dainty piece, this."</p>
                  <p>A sharp cut of the horses, and away dashed the vehicle over the stony pavement,
                     which rattled strangely to Agnes' ear. Never in a city of any great magnitude
                     before, and Boston particularly, the frequent turning of short corners kept her
                     in a state of uneasiness during the ride, and she had little change for
                     reflection. If such she had had, with the premonition of evil which had come
                     over her while standing on the steamer's deck, it is possible she would have
                     thrown open the door, and flung herself out, if only to be dashed to pieces on
                     the cruel pavement.</p>
                  <p>At length the horses were reined up, the driver<pb n="80-81"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000039"/> opened the door, and Agnes alighted on the
                     sidewalk in front of a brick building, but more than this the darkness as yet
                     prevented her from observing. A quick pull at the bell by the hackman, and an
                     old woman appeared at the door, light in hand, to receive the new-comer.</p>
                  <p>"Come right in—come right in," she croaked, as Agnes hesitated, distrustful and
                     undecided at the sight of her repulsive countenance; "come right in," she
                     continued. "I've been expectin' ye, and everything's as nice as ye cud
                     wish,"</p>
                  <p>There was no alternative now, and trust that it was yet all right turning the
                     balance, Agnes entered her new abode.</p>
                  <p>No sooner was she inside than the door was bolted, the key turned, and a
                     rattling noise without told her the hack had gone, and she was now fully
                     consigned to the charge of those around her, whoever they might be. As she was
                     yet somewhat fatigued from her brief sleep on the steamer, she asked to be
                     shown to a room, with which request the old woman, with peculiar delight,
                     complied, leading the way up three long flights of stairs, into an apartment
                     with but one window, and that in the roof, yet spacious, and in other respects
                     quite comfortable.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto, Agnes had hoped she had not misplaced her confidence, but when the
                     old woman retired from the room, bowing herself out with mock civility, and
                     wishing "my dear lady good morning," then turning the key in the door after
                     her, hope left her as the thunderbolt leaves the cloud, and she sank down with
                     the conviction that she had been betrayed, entrapped!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
                  <head type="sub">GETTING THE TRAIL.</head>
                  <p>The next day after the visit of Albert Heywood to Harry Dudley, at the hotel,
                     found him speeding away on the train for Boston—at a rapid rate, perhaps, yet
                     not half so fast as he could have wished. Even had it placed his life in
                     jeopardy, he would have increased the speed, for what was living to him now but
                     a bitter void, a blank, indifferent experience?</p>
                  <p>It was afternoon when the cars arrived at Hay-market Square, Boston, and
                     without a moment's delay Albert started far the residence of the detective to
                     whom he had been directed. Having been in the city on several occasions before,
                     he found no difficulty in getting around, and in due time had the pleasure of
                     shaking hands with Spencer Trevelyn, whose grasp was all the more cordial from
                     his friendship with Harry Dudley. A few inquiries about the latter, a few words
                     of commiseration at his misfortune, and Albert then gave him the note Harry had
                     sent. The detective read it with marked interest.</p>
                  <p>"Ah, ha!" he broke forth, at last; "and so Clarkson was at the bottom of it
                     all. How thoughtless of me not to have noted his, absence from the city before!
                     A robbery, and now a—well, I must look to this. And you are interested, I see,"
                     he continued, turning to Albert.</p>
                  <p>"As interested as I am in my own life."</p>
                  <p>"Ah! yes; but keep up good courage, my friend. This Clarkson is a queer dog; it
                     is to be hoped we shall block his game yet. He is bad enough, certainly<pb
                        n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6129-00000040"/> tainly, but not so bad as many we have
                     to deal with; in fact, in some places he would readily pass for a gentleman. It
                     is now well along in the afternoon. Between this time and twelve o'clock is the
                     best period for work in the whole twenty-four hours. The sports are out in full
                     feather, and if a clue is to be obtained, then is the time to get it. Let me
                     see: Cool Graham's troupe arrived about a week ago, and Clarkson was aboard the
                     same steamer. I have it." The detective sat for few moments in deep study, and
                     when a course had evidently been decided upon, he arose, and assuming a slight
                     disguise, prepared to go forth.</p>
                  <p>"You will let me go with you," said Albert, not content to remain behind
                     inactive, when his presence might prove of the greatest value.</p>
                  <p>"I should be pleased at your company, young man," replied Trevelyn, kindly,
                     "but I think it will be as well for our plans that you remain here. I can work
                     to better advantage single-handed, and when necessity requires I am not at a
                     loss for assistance," he remarked, opening his coat and disclosing a pair of
                     light, richly-mounted revolvers. "At a close scratch I can call these to my
                     aid, and woe to the man that stands before them. We detectives don't use many
                     scruples when once in a close corner. But I must not tarry longer. As Harry
                     says, we should lose no time."</p>
                  <p>"If I must remain behind, then heaven help you in your undertaking," said
                     Albert.</p>
                  <p>Trevelyn tarried only long enough to introduce Albert to this family, seeing
                     him well disposed for the evening, when he started out on his singular and
                     dangerous business.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
                  <head type="sub">THE SPIDER AND THE FLY.</head>
                  <p>Sadly did the time drag along with Agnes Bishop. What wild imaginings coursed
                     through her busy brain! Only once was she disturbed the first day in her new
                     abode, and then it was by the old woman, who came with a waiter on which were
                     ample supplies of food to satisfy her appetite, which, however, had almost
                     forsaken her in her peril. At that time she questioned the hag as to the
                     purpose of her detention, but no word of reply could she obtain, save that "He
                     will come soon! he will come soon!" and then she disappeared, locking the door,
                     as before, and leaving Agnes more painfully agitated with conjecture.</p>
                  <p>The occurrences of the following day made the meaning of the old woman's words
                     too apparent to her. She was startled by a man's tread upon the stairs, coming
                     up, and, she doubted not, about to enter her apartment. Nor was she mistaken.
                     The key turned, the door swung back, and before her stood Clarkson—the man she
                     had met at Lewiston, the one she had scornfully repulsed when he had sought
                     favor at her hands. She started to her feet a moment in glad surprise, thinking
                     he might in this instance be a friend, and have come to her rescue; but she
                     settled back as his chilling words greeted her:</p>
                  <p>"O, ho! Miss Bishop; and so we've met once more, have we? You didn't think, in
                     your little country city, that we should meet again under so peculiar
                     circumstances. And you are to become an actress—well, well, that's rich; and so
                     you are<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6129-00000041"/> —an actress in high life—three
                     stories at that, with one window in the roof," and the arch villain, having
                     locked the door on the inside, seated himself on the bed which the room
                     contained, and laughed a fiendish laugh which sent terror to the very depths of
                     Agnes Bishop's heart.</p>
                  <p>"O, leave me, sir!" she cried in alarm. "What cruel fate has brought you
                     here?"</p>
                  <p>"The same that brought you, Miss Bishop; I was a passenger on the same steamer.
                     I heard that you aspired to the stage, and as I am something of an actor
                     myself, I propose to introduce you to life behind the scenes."</p>
                  <p>The villain chuckled as he said this.</p>
                  <p>"But I will expose you to the authorities," faltered Agnes, scarcely above her
                     breath, her terror depriving her of speech; "I will have you brought to
                     justice."</p>
                  <p>"That's fine, Miss Bishop. Your tone and manner are just suited to the stage.
                     As My Lady Clarkson your triumph is assured. Your audience will not be very
                     large, but it will be all the more select."</p>
                  <p>"What mean you, sir," said Agnes.</p>
                  <p>"That for the present you are to know only Jacob Clarkson and Moll Baxter, the
                     old woman who will attend to your wishes. It was a singular stroke of fortune
                     that led me to your down-east city, for I've brought back a prize that will pay
                     me well for my trouble. You are mine, wholly in my power, and at my pleasure.
                     Bear this in mind, and govern yourself accordingly. You are trembling and
                     scared now; I will give you time to compose yourself. A private enterprise
                     takes me out to Dorchester for several days, and when I return I hope to find
                     you in better spirits, and disposed to regard your lot more contentedly. So
                     good-day."</p>
                  <p>Again the key was turned on Agnes Bishop. This time it proved a source of
                     relief. She had feared the worst from the villain; but a respite was offered—a
                     few days only, yet might she not in those few days succeed in effecting her
                     escape?</p>
                  <p>As the sound of Clarkson's footsteps died away she fell to musing again upon
                     the singularity of events, the rapid changes, strange and unexpected, which had
                     flashed over her life like a cyclone. No longer did the mist of uncertainty
                     rest upon the past actions of her enemies. Her leaving the boat was recalled to
                     mind. Early as it had been, and she dressed and on deck at the first signal of
                     their arrival, yet Graham had told her the other ladies had preceded her. How
                     blind of her not to have seen at once that the statement must be false! No
                     other lady of the party had made her appearance above stairs, and might not
                     have risen, possibly, till an hour or more later. Graham's duplicity now became
                     more apparent. After these, other acts were noted; but the climax of her
                     realization was not reached till the fact of Clarkson's presence occurred to
                     her. What subtle power this man possessed that might thus place her in
                     captivity at his will, she could not conceive. It seemed to her that heaven had
                     indeed forsaken her, and thrown her life into the hands of wicked men. O, how
                     she wished that those who loved her could only know where she was, and fly to
                     her deliverance! Yet how could they know—how suspect? To the tearful entreaties
                     of Belle to write at the very first opportunity, she had given a careless,
                     indifferent reply; and now her means of communication were cut off had she felt
                     disposed to correspond. Bitter, bitter thought! that she had let her foolish
                     ambition so blind her for the time, and bid her choose a course so repulsive to
                     the deeper, better impulses<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6129-00000042"/> of her
                     nature; that should turn her feet from the paths of humble enjoyment, to seek
                     that flashy bauble which many clutch at, but few obtain. Untutored, as she had
                     been—unlearned in the ways of the world, its delusions and vagaries, its
                     falsehoods and deceptions, she was now taking her first dark, sad lesson of
                     experience. Might it not be her last? An orphan, in a great city reeking with
                     crime, no friends near, a prisoner without means of escape, and a fate
                     impending to which death were a blessing—Agnes Bishop felt so overcome at these
                     thoughts that she fell upon her knees and implored that divine favor which too
                     many forget till the dread hour of adversity and distress comes. Yet her prayer
                     was not altogether actuated by fear and peril. At heart pure, good and noble,
                     she had breathed true piety from those lips before, and now felt the same
                     relief from oppression which had answered her supplications in times past. The
                     clouds of her perversity were obstinate at first, but she implored more
                     fervently, and at length the sunlight broke through, and hope lighted up the
                     firmament of her life, till the glad hour of noonday beamed with all its wonted
                     glory. She arose. Could it be possible there was a chance of escape? or was all
                     this promise held out to her only to be withdrawn again to leave, her in the
                     darkest midnight? Was it the foretoken of something real, or the delusion of an
                     excited imagination? O, that it might prove substantial and abiding!</p>
                  <p>Going to the door, she examined the lock, the hinges, and exerted her powers to
                     test their strength. As well might she undertake to remove the house from its
                     foundation; not the least effect was perceptible. Then she viewed the window,
                     but that was up out of her reach, and she saw that it was securely fastened,
                     and in all likelihood could not be removed, if she were able to reach it. The
                     place was a prison indeed; and who could tell, thought Agnes, how many victims
                     had been there before her? how many an. one, like her, had been entrapped, and
                     perhaps set at liberty only when robbed of that which woman holds most dear,
                     or, slight difference, not permitted to leave alive? She had read of similar
                     cases—of bodies taken from the docks, cold and lifeless, whose identity no one
                     could prove. Might they not have been allured from dear New England homes, been
                     betrayed, and thus met a dreadful fate? The thought chilled her.</p>
                  <p>The room contained a light-stand. Moving this in position, and getting on top
                     of it with the aid of a chair, she could just reach the window. An iron rod
                     attached to it projected down a foot or more, and by this she tried to force
                     the sash upward, but all in vain.</p>
                  <p>While standing thus, a step was again heard on the stairs, and in her haste to
                     get down she lost her balance, falling to the floor, as the door opened and the
                     wicked phiz of Moll Baxter grinned upon her misfortune.</p>
                  <p>This was evidently a rich treat for the old hag, and she had to hold her
                     bloated sides with laughing. Beastly, coarse, depraved; what a contrast was
                     here between two of the same sex—one lost to all that was good and virtuous,
                     the other pure and spotless as the falling snow!</p>
                  <p>Agnes was not seriously hurt, and she arose to her feet without assistance,
                     disdaining the extended hand of the hag. They were in the middle of the room,
                     the door open; quick as thought, Agnes sprang towards it; but there was no lack
                     of watchfulness in those bleared eyes, for a brawny hand grasped her arm with a
                     vise-like grip, and she was forced back into the room—back, and hurled
                        violently<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6129-00000043"/> lently upon the bed. Moll
                     Baxter had been faithful to her trust.</p>
                  <p>"None o' that, none o' that, my dainty miss. I've jest caught ye tryin' to
                     'scape have I? Faix, and ye'd broken iv'ry bone in yer body if ye'd gone out by
                     the windy. Well, guess I'll lock the door now," and she turned the key in the
                     lock, and held it up before the girl in tantalizing defiance. "O, no, my lady,
                     ye can't get out o' here—not till he says, so—not till Clarkson takes ye out.
                     He's a fine gintleman, is Clarkson; has lots o' money, and says he's goin' ter
                     marry ye. What d'ye think o' that? A gintleman the likes o' him marry ye! Why,
                     ye ought ter be proud o' it, though I don't s'pose ye are. 'Tisn't iv'ry one a
                     gintleman like him would marry. Faix! but I'm thinkin' ye'll be glad enough ter
                     do it when he gits back with the nice bit o' money he's gone for. A fine
                     gintleman is Clarkson, and he pays me well for me trouble—so he does!"</p>
                  <p>The voluble old woman had brought up some victuals for Agnes, but had left them
                     outside the door as she heard the noise. These she now brought in.</p>
                  <p>"Look at this, will ye? See the nice dainties Clarkson gits for ye. Och! but
                     I've er mind ter taste 'em meself, if I'd think he wudn't know it."</p>
                  <p>"Take them if you wish," said Agnes; "take it all—only set me free from this
                     place, and once at liberty, I will see you well rewarded."</p>
                  <p>"That's kind, my lady; but I cudn't do it; Clarkson wud finish me if I did. No,
                     I wudn't dare ter do that, Ate yer vittels—ate yer vittels. I must have ye
                     lookin' nice an' hearty when he gits back."</p>
                  <p>And Moll Baxter, having executed Clarkson's latest orders, once more left the
                     apartment to its lonely occupant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
                  <head type="sub">A CHAPTER IN PARENTHESES.</head>
                  <p>The next evening after Albert Heywood's departure from Lewiston, Harry Dudley
                     had so far recovered that he was able to walk out, and he at once sought the
                     boarding-place of Belle Bishop, where he took the liberty of introducing
                     himself to her, and explaining the object of his visit, which was to allay, if
                     possible, her fears in regard to Agnes, of whose peril she had been partially
                     informed by Albert. Strange as it may seem, he found her outwardly quite
                     composed over the matter, exhibiting but very little alarm in her countenance,
                     and not disposed to give way to the force of her feelings. Did some Power
                     greater than her own sustain her? Doubtless. Although Belle Bishop's was a
                     peculiar nature, and discipline had developed within her such a remarkable
                     strength of will, that, however deep or poignant her emotions, she could
                     command and maintain composure.</p>
                  <p>Yet she did not refuse the proffered kindness of her visitor, who manifested
                     such heartfelt interest in the fate of Agnes. She at once saw the sympathetic
                     soul which prompted it, and thanked him with all the gratitude she felt. That
                     Harry Dudley was a gentleman in every sense of the word, she soon became aware,
                     and having been reared in refinement herself, the young man's company was, to
                     say the least, quite agreeable to her. Nor did hers seem less so to him.
                     Unforgetful of the events which had brought them together, these two persons
                     were not prevented from recognizing in each other the embodiment of congenial
                     natures, minds<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6129-00000044"/> running in similar
                     channels, and actuated by similar tastes and dispositions.</p>
                  <p>"There are certain characters that do not change with circumstances," said
                     Harry, at length, after the more important subject had been talked
                     over—"characters moulded with the very beings who possess them, and are not
                     dwarfed or inflated by the fickle tide of fortune. Such characters are rare,
                     but when found form the really true type of our humanity. Let adversity come,
                     and they are the same as when favored with prosperity; they are ever above the
                     reach of such accidents, and prove themselves rulers rather than serfs in the
                     world of chance."</p>
                  <p>"True, Mr. Dudley," replied Belle; "but poverty has its restrictions, and the
                     elements that might otherwise be of service are obliged to remain passive, and
                     so, we may say, rust and decay from lack of employment."</p>
                  <p>"To a degree, I acknowledge it; but so far as I have studied human nature in
                     this city of factories since my brief sojourn here, I find but little
                     indications of rust and decay. Action, action is observed on every hand, and
                     few deem it compulsory or falter at their places, however humble. Give me New
                     England for representatives of these traits of character, for she is their
                     nursery and abiding-place."</p>
                  <p>"You think New England superior, then?"</p>
                  <p>"I do; and thank the fates that I was reared upon her soil. My father was born
                     in England, and was a prominent iron-master there till some years ago, when he
                     came to Boston, and established his business in that city. His death, two years
                     ago, left everything in my hands; and it was upon business connected with the
                     factories that I came to Lewiston."</p>
                  <p>"You have visited the factories, then?" said Belle, blushing slightly, to think
                     she was herself an "operative," and might have been observed by him while at
                     work.</p>
                  <p>"I have; and have seen in them happier faces and more contented lives than one
                     can see in a large portion of the so-called first circles of our metropolis.
                     Many persons possessing millions would gladly give all their riches for the
                     cheerful hearts which abound so generally here. Of course, there are bright and
                     dark sides to nearly every phase of life. I find it true that happiness is not
                     always the attendant of wealth, although I have no doubt that wealth, when
                     properly disposed, may be made conducive to happiness."</p>
                  <p>"You philosophize well, Mr. Dudley," said Belle. "We are all apt to find
                     sunshine in the lot of those whose condition in life is unlike our own. Had
                     your words reached the ears of sister Agnes in season, they might have averted
                     the misfortune that has befallen her. Reared in the pride of wealth, she could
                     not bend her will to accept the situation which adversity had forced upon us.
                     Rejecting, as she did, the love of one who would have made her happy in a
                     humble sphere, her false ambition prompted her to seek retrieval of fortune
                     through the perilous medium of the stage."</p>
                  <p>"A mistaken idea, certainly," replied Harry. "Your allusion to Mr. Heywood
                     reminds me that he is a skillful workman in the iron department of one of the
                     factories."</p>
                  <p>"Ah! you know this, then," said Belle, wondering at his knowledge of Albert's
                     occupation.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, my business brings me in contact with men of his class, and I make it a
                     special object to learn more or less of the capacities of those who perform the
                     work in detail. This study has been<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6129-00000045"/>
                     both interesting and profitable. It has afforded me pleasure to learn that Mr.
                     Heywood is a superior mechanic, and is competent for a far better position than
                     that he now occupies. I became aware of this previous to our interview at the
                     hotel, and since that time the facts of his skill and acquirements have become
                     more favorably impressed upon my memory. He probaby has no knowledge of this,
                     however."</p>
                  <p>"As a friend, I most heartily thank you for the interest you have manifested in
                     him, Mr. Dudley."</p>
                  <p>"I might well feel an interest in him now," continued Harry, after he has saved
                     my life. But further than this, if you will pardon me, I must confess I have
                     conceived an unusual interest in the future of yourself and sister, and
                     whatever may be the sequel to this at present seemingly unfortunate affair, I
                     trust it will be the means of establishing an acquaintance which may tend to
                     our mutual good."</p>
                  <p>No school of deceit and artifice had educated Harry Dudley's tongue in the use
                     of unmeant expressions, but open candor and spontaneous sympathy for a
                     deserving object were the natural outgrowth of his feelings and impulses. When
                     he sauntered towards the hotel, shortly after, two minds were engrossed with
                     thoughts of a kindred nature. Who knows what will come of it?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
                  <head type="sub">FALSE HEARTS AND TRUE.</head>
                  <p>The evening Detective Trevelyn started forth in search of Agnes Bishop, or some
                     clue that might lead to her whereabouts, Clarkson returned from Dorchester,
                     where an adroit burglary had been committed by a league of desperadoes of which
                     he bore the leadership. The haul had been a rich one, and as he entered Moll
                     Baxter's, elated with his success and the wine he had imbibed on the strength
                     of it, he felt as good as one possibly could under such circumstances.</p>
                  <p>"The girl—how's the girl?" was his first inquiry of the old woman, who greeted
                     him with a grin of welcome.</p>
                  <p>"Ill, Mr. Clarkson, ill. She's been nearly sick these two days, and hasn't ate
                     enough to kape a rat alive."</p>
                  <p>"O, ho! she hasn't eh? Well, I reckon she'll revive when she sees me. I didn't
                     intend to be gone so long, but the job was exceedingly difficult to get at. You
                     know I have a fine job now and then, Moll, that requires my particular
                     attention."</p>
                  <p>"Ah! well I know that, Mr. Clarkson," replied Moll, who knew about as much of
                     his affairs outside of her domicil as the man in the moon—"ah! well I do, Mr.
                     Clarkson; and you're a gintleman, so ye are, to be sure."</p>
                  <p>"Yes; that'll do, Moll," replied Clarkson. "Now give me a light, while I visit
                     the bridal chamber, and see how the bride will receive me."</p>
                  <p>He took the light and mounted the stairs, to the room which contained Agnes
                     Bishop. As he opened<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6129-00000046"/> the door, she
                     started up from the bed on which she had thrown herself, her loosened hair
                     falling in wild disorder over her partly disrobed person, and with a
                     half-crazed air gazed at him.</p>
                  <p>"So you have returned," she murmured, just audibly. "I had prayed you would
                     never come back; but no, no!" and her head sank down again upon the pillow,
                     while tears coursed over her pallid cheeks.</p>
                  <p>"There! there! enough of that!" said Clarkson, fiercely; no whimpering here.
                     You are to be a bride to-night; so dry your tears; they ill become one in such
                     a relation."</p>
                  <p>"O, you will not, you will not kill me!" moaned Agnes, scarcely knowing what
                     she said. "Let me go free from this place, and you shall not be harmed. O,
                     spare me, spare me!"</p>
                  <p>"Stop your noise, or I'll smother you, you blubbering baby. Enough of it, I
                     say. You should know by this time that I am ruler here, if you did spurn me in
                     Lewiston."</p>
                  <p>Agnes was in a sort of stupor when Clarkson entered, but she soon became wholly
                     aroused to the impending peril of her situation.</p>
                  <p>The unchecked fires of licentious passion now flashed from the villain's eyes,
                     and he moved toward the bedside.</p>
                  <p>"Back, sir; come no nearer!" shrieked Agnes, with affright.</p>
                  <p>Clarkson's deep interest in his intended victim had prevented his catching a
                     slight sound which occurred in the hall below a moment before, and as the
                     girl's cry rang through the building, there was a cat-like tread upon the
                     stairs, a quick movement in the door-lock, and Detective Trevelyn stood face to
                     face with the would-be despoiler.</p>
                  <p>"Nabbed at last," he said, quietly, as the wretch glowed towards him; "nabbed
                     at last, Jake Clarkson, and in the midst of your villainy. I caught your trail
                     to-night, and have followed you. A highway robbery, a burglary, and now a—"</p>
                  <p>Clarkson whipped out a pistol and fired, but the detective's eye was upon him,
                     and his own revolver spoke at the same time. The result was that the former
                     only was wounded, though not dangerously, yet enough to render him senseless
                     till the handcuffs were placed upon his wrists. Then Trevelyn turned to Agnes,
                     but she was unconscious, having fainted away. From this she shortly recovered,
                     however, and at once became aware that her rescue had been effected, yet how
                     and by what means she could not conjecture.</p>
                  <p>When Clarkson found himself completely at the will of Trevelyn, whom he had
                     ever been careful to avoid, his prudence could hardly suppress his rage and
                     curses; while old Moll, who had always held him in such high esteem, now that a
                     revolution was likely to take place, adopted a little diplomacy in trying to
                     forstall it.</p>
                  <p>"The wicked skamer that he is, Mr. Officer! Bad cess ter him fur the
                     disturbince he's after causin' an inoffensive female like mesel', and all fur
                     his wicked dades, so it is. The poor, dear lady, too, what he made me b'lieve
                     was his wife, when I knowed she wasn't! O, worra! worra! that the likes er him
                     should pertind sich a thing!"</p>
                  <p>"Hold your jaw, you old witch!" growled Clarkson, striking her a blow with the
                     handcuffs that felled her to the floor, she having imprudently approached him
                     in her demonstrations. "Take that for your blabbing tongue."</p>
                  <p>The old woman doubled herself up in a ludicrous heap, and sent forth howls of
                     imprecation upon the head of her aggressor, who regarded her<pb n="96-97"
                        xml:id="VAC6129-00000047"/> with a look of mingled contempt and amusement at
                     the result of his blow. Both of them were now in a fit condition for
                     recrimination and exposure—he wounded in the arm and suffering with pain, and
                     she ornamented with a gash on the head from which the blood was freely
                     flowing.</p>
                  <p>Without loss of time, Clarkson and Moll Baxter were placed in the custody of
                     some faithful policemen, and sent to the station-house. This part of the
                     business off his hands, Trevelyn again directed his attention to Agnes, who had
                     hastily resumed the articles of clothing she had worn there, and bade her
                     accompany him from the place.</p>
                  <p>"But where shall we go?" she asked, innocently, yet now rid of all fear of
                     evil.</p>
                  <p>"To a good place, my dear girl. Don't be afraid when you are in the care of
                     Detective Trevelyn; there shall no harm reach you."</p>
                  <p>"O, you are very kind—you are very good," said Agnes, joyfully, as they wended
                     their way through the dimly-lighted streets. No one could tell the joy she felt
                     at her opportune deliverance. Now, indeed, had her petition been answered, and
                     Providence had interposed in her behalf. An unspoken thanksgiving rested upon
                     her lips during the remainder of their walk, unmindful of the bustling throngs
                     that they shortly encountered returning from the theatres, till at length they
                     turned up into a more quiet thoroughfare, and entered a house which the
                     gaslight opposite revealed as one of elegance and respectability.</p>
                  <p>"This is my residence," said Trevelyn; "we will go in here."</p>
                  <p>"As you wish,," replied Agnes, in tones of gratitude, following her companion
                     without hesitation up a short flight of stone steps, into the detective's
                     home.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
                  <head type="sub">JUST AS IT SHOULD BE.</head>
                  <p>Spencer Trevelyn ushered Agnes Bishop through the hall, and into a parlor where
                     sat a young man, who glanced up anxiously as they entered.</p>
                  <p>She recognized him at once, while he, with ready perception, read in her joyous
                     countenance the happy assurance that she was yet unharmed.</p>
                  <p>"Agnes!"</p>
                  <p>"Albert!"</p>
                  <p>There was an embrace, a—but the indulgent reader will pardon a slight omission
                     of details here. Suffice it to say, there were two most grateful hearts under
                     the detective's roof that night, and Agnes Bishop was satisfied in loving, and
                     being loved by, Albert Heywood.</p>
                  <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/>
                  <p>There are ordeals which must be borne in nearly every life to at length attain
                     any great and lasting good; trials, severe, perhaps, in themselves, yet
                     necessary to the development and exercise of a better nature which may have
                     remained dormant beneath the influence of less potent agencies. This had been
                     the case with our heroine, whose heart had ever been a mystery to herself till
                     the storm of adversity lowered its threatening clouds over her head; then the
                     truth burst upon her in its fullest effect, disclosing the hidden secrets she
                     had never before sought to fathom. Happily for her, the storm passed away, the
                     clouds disappeared, and she was permitted the fulfillment of those
                     affliction-wrought hopes—as will be observed in the closing scene of our
                     truthful story.</p>
                  <pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6129-00000048"/>
                  <p>A private sociable is being given at the elegant residence of Harry Dudley, on
                     one of the most aristocratic avenues in Boston; and, believe us, it is a
                     sociable affair, despite the exclusive character of the locality where it
                     occurs. Nor will one wonder at it when told who are the principal persons in
                     the gathering. To begin the list, there is Harry himself, and his bride, whom
                     we so recently knew as Belle Bishop, a factory girl; next comes Albert Heywood
                     and his bride, formerly Agnes Bishop; and then, though by no means an
                     unimportant personage in the assembly, is Detective Trevelyn, and with him his
                     wife and family.</p>
                  <p>Albert Heywood now has the oversight of the Dudley Iron Works, a position for
                     which his capacity and experience eminently qualify him. Harry and Albert
                     occupy a splendid brownstone, and an attachment exists between them which time
                     cannot sever, but which grows stronger and stronger in their brotherly
                     intercourse. Having everything. at hand to promote comfort and happiness, and
                     two sensible partners to share these with them, the prospect is that they will
                     partake to the fullest of the enjoyments of this world.</p>
                  <p>Do not wonder at this remarkable transition of our characters. When we remember
                     the worth of Belle Bishop, there is nothing strange that Harry Dudley, with his
                     quick faculties of observation, should have seen in her the realization of his
                     fondest wish, and extracted a promise from her that she would be his. This was
                     after Albert had returned to Lewiston with his rescued Agnes, and the hour was
                     so auspicious for such a consummation.</p>
                  <p>And the present gathering was more to talk over the affairs of the past,
                     perhaps, than anything else, an occasion where only intimate friends were
                     invited, where stilted formality was quietly dispensed with, while social chat
                     and intercourse engaged the hour. It was as pleasant as genial hearts and
                     smiling faces could make it.</p>
                  <p>Trevelyn, whose experience as a detective had furnished him with a fund of
                     material for story-telling, entertained the company with incidents in his
                     personal career while engaged in the dangerous and uncertain business of
                     searching out the more adroit class of criminals and bringing them to justice.
                     To these reminiscences all listened with interest, and especially Agnes, who
                     imagined the narrator must be little more than human from the part he had taken
                     in her own rescue.</p>
                  <p>"I have had many odd adventures in my day," he said, finally, "but never one
                     which has afforded me greater satisfaction than that to which an item in the
                     evening papers seems a proper conclusion. I have no doubt you all would like to
                     hear it."</p>
                  <p>He produced a paper, and read:</p>
                  <p>"'BOLD ASSAULT.—While officers were conveying Jacob Clarkson to the Charleston
                     prison, in irons, to-day, they were assailed by a party of roughs, evidently
                     bent on effecting his rescue. Several shots were fired on both sides. Of these
                     but one took effect, however, and that was from the assaulting party, aimed at
                     an officer, which, singularly enough, struck the prisoner in his custody,
                     inflicting a fatal wound. On beholding this, the assailants were filled with
                     consternation, and fled, though not till one of their number, Cool Graham by
                     name, and Bill Caffers, who had a hack in waiting for them, were captured. It
                     is now known that the party are a gang of burglars and midnight marauders, of
                     which Clarkson had been the leader until his arrest several months ago, and
                     their exploits have been numerous and daring. This Cool Graham, who so suddenly
                        changed<pb n="100" xml:id="VAC6129-00000049"/> places with Clarkson, will
                     probably have a chance to taste prison fare, as his complicity with the latter
                     can be easily proved.</p>
                  <p>"All of which is respectfully submitted," added the detective, turning to his
                     deeply-interested listeners.</p>
                  <p>"And goes to show that the play is a tragedy, after all," said Agnes, looking
                     askance at Belle.</p>
                  <p>"Yes; and you may congratulate yourself on being withdrawn from the boards at
                     the time you were; otherwise—but it is all over now, sister dear, and I have no
                     fear you will ever again have a desire to become an actress."</p>
                  <p>"No, Belle; be assured of that. I have too much regard for the heads of my
                     friends," laughed Agnes.</p>
                  <p>"A thoughtful ness worthy of commendation," said Harry, good-humoredly. "As for
                     me, I am satisfied with the result if Albert is. Broken heads may be very bad
                     in their way, but they don't begin to compare with broken hearts. Happily for
                     us all, our hearts and heads are safe, and it is hoped they may continue to
                     remain so."</p>
                  <p>"The prospect never seemed better," said Albert. With our good friend Trevelyn
                     near at hand, there is little to apprehend from the schemes of villainy."</p>
                  <p>"While to God we should render praise for the kindness He has shown us, and the
                     happiness we are now permitted to enjoy," remarked Agnes, with a sincerity of
                     feeling that bespoke the truthfulness of her character, and made the detective
                     inwardly rejoice that he had ever interposed a hand to rescue at <emph>the
                        peril of beauty.</emph>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
