<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
   xml:id="VAC6545">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Great "Trunk Mystery" of New York City </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6545</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1018</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                  copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction
                  project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                  University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
                  to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                  contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                  educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                  inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University
                  Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
               Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Great "Trunk Mystery" of New York City</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>104 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Barclay</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia Pa. </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1871">1871</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
               Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
               website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
               been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
               Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-03-21">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-08-25">Finished TEI
            conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Converted document from SGML to TEI
            P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents
            and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="Illustration" xml:id="VAC6545-00000001"/>
         <div type="frontis">
            
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>"HORRORS UPON HORRORS ACCUMULATE." DISCOVERING THE BODY AT THE DEPOT. THE
                     CURTAIN LIFTED ON THE TRAGEDY.</head>
                  <p>"Schrecken auf Schrecken verbreiten sich. Entdeckung der Leiche auf dem Depot.
                     Der Verhang der Tragödie wird aufgezogen.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6545-00000002"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE GREAT "TRUNK MYSTERY" OF NEW YORK CITY.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">MURDER OF THE BEAUTIFUL MISS ALICE A. BOWLSBY, OF PATERSON, N.
                  J.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">Her Body placed in a Trunk and Labelled for
                  Chicago.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">MANY STRANGE INCIDENTS MADE PUBLIC.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>BARCLAY &amp; CO., PUBLISHERS,
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>21 NORTH SEVENTH STREET,</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA, P. A.</pubPlace>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The Great "Trunk Mystery" of New York City</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6545-00000003"/>
                  <p>moved it out on the platform to have it placed in a baggage car, he noticed a
                     disagreeable odor arising from it. This aroused his suspicions, and he at once
                     informed Mr. Vandeward, the baggage master. That gentleman had the trunk
                     removed to an outer building, and ordered it to be opened. To the indescribable
                     horror of those who witnessed it, the object uncovered proved to be the body of
                     a</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>YOUNG AND BEAUTIFUL WOMAN.</head>
                  <p>The body was entirely nude, and had been shockingly distorted in the effort to
                     pack it in so small a space. In the top of the trunk and covering the body were
                     a comforter or heavy bed quilt, a piece of a blanket, a coarse chemise, and two
                     or three other articles of common material. All these things, much soiled,
                     emitted a very offensive odor.</p>
                  <p>Mr. Vandeward at once gave orders to close the trunk and summon officers Murphy
                     and McCullough of the Twentieth Ward Police, who took charge of it. Captain
                     McCaffrey was at once summoned, and messengers were dispatched in quest of a
                     coroner.</p>
                  <p>At 9 o'clock Coroner Herrman arrived and gave a permit for the removal of the
                     trunk and its ghastly contents to the Morgue, to await identification and
                     inquest.</p>
                  <p>The scene at the depot after the discovery was an exciting one. Railway
                     officials rushed up and down in the search for the woman who had brought the
                     trunk, and policemen were active in their efforts to find some clue by which
                     the persons engaged in what now seemed clearly a tragedy might be discovered.
                     But few saw the woman or had their attention particularly called to her or her
                     movements. One or two noticed that she exhibited nervousness when</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>HAVING THE TRUNK CHECKED</head>
                  <p>and this in a marked degree when the baggage-man told her that the lid of the
                     trunk was not secure, and advised her to buy a strap to go around it. Expense
                     did not seem to her any object at all, although she did not appear to be a
                     person likely to incur it heedlessly. This circumstance attracted one or two
                     pairs of eyes to her, but only momentarily. The boy who assisted the carman to
                     carry the trunk into the depot had a clearer recollection of the woman and her
                     movements than any other person who saw her. His story as told to our reporter
                     is as follows:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE STORY OF THE BOY.</head>
                  <p>My name is Alexander Potts; I am twelve years old, and live with my mother at
                     Thirty-seventh street and Eighth avenue. I am around the Hudson River Railroad
                     depot every day, where I sell candy and papers and carry light baggage from the
                     carriages. On Saturday I was standing in front of the depot on Thirtieth
                     street, about one o'clock, when I saw a <unclear>one-horse</unclear> cab coming
                     toward the depot from the direction of Ninth avenue. The cab stopped in front
                     of the ladies' entrance to the depot, and I ran and opened the door of the cab,
                     when a lady got out. She wore a common calico dress with a thin alpaca shawl,
                     and had on a small jockey hat without a veil. She wore no waterfall, but her
                     hair was tied up in a small knot behind and enclosed in a net. She seemed to be
                     about eighteen or nineteen years old, and her hands looked like those of a
                     working girl. As she got out of the cab she handed the cabman a one-dollar bill
                     and he drove off. She then turned to me and said, "Sonny, can you tell me where
                     the ticket office is?" I asked her how far she was going, and she said she
                     was</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>GOING TO CHICAGO.</head>
                  <p>I then told her that if she went inside and got her ticket she could then get
                     her baggage checked. She then went with me to the ticket office, and after
                     inquiring the price of a ticket, she handed the ticket clerk two twenty-dollar
                     bills, and he returned her the change, $18, and a ticket. The change he gave
                     her was three five dollar bills, a two-dollar bill, and a one-dollar bill. She
                     then stood talking with the ticket clerk about five minutes, but although I was
                     standing near, I did not hear what was said, because I paid no attention. When
                     she got through talking with the clerk, she turned to me and said that she had
                     not intended to go to Chicago, but had</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CHANGED HER MIND,</head>
                  <p>guessed she would on account of her baggage. I told her that unless she went
                     her baggage couldn't go. She then asked me what she should do about her
                     baggage, and said it would be there soon on Tripp's express wagon. We then went
                     outside, and while standing in front of the depot she saw a wagon coming down
                     the street from the direction of Ninth avenue. She then turned to me and said,
                     "Here comes my man," and then beckoned with her finger to him as if to hurry
                     him on. When the man with the wagon saw her beckon he seemed to drive faster.
                     She then asked me if I would mind helping him in with the trunk, and said that
                     she would pay me. When the wagon stopped in front of the baggage room, I
                     stepped up to help the man to place the trunk on the sidewalk, but he
                        <unclear>wouldn't</unclear> let me, saying he'd handle it himself. He</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>LIFTED IT CAREFULLY,</head>
                  <p>and set it flat on the sidewalk. I then took one handle and he the other and we
                     carried it into the baggage-room. I wanted to set the trunk of its end, as they
                     always do, when the woman and the man both stopped me, saying that the trunk
                     contained glass, and it mustn't be handled roughly. I stepped up to the counter
                     and told Frank, the baggage checker, that the lady wanted to get her baggage
                     checked to Chicago. The truckman and I then took hold of the trunk to place it
                     on the<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6545-00000004"/> counter, when the lady placed
                     her hands underneath the trunk and assisted us. She said that she would like to
                     have an extra strap around the trunk, and I told Frank what she said. Frank
                     then told her that the strap would cost her $1, and she answered, "I don't care
                     for a dollar if you strap it good." Frank then put the strap around the trunk
                     and drove three nails into it. She then gave Frank her ticket and $1. He
                     punched the ticket and handed it back to the woman with a baggage check. She
                     then turned to the truckman and said: "I'm much obliged to you for your
                     trouble." They then</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SHOOK HANDS,</head>
                  <p>and the truckman drove off, wishing her good-bye. The woman and I then went
                     into the street, and she handed me five cents. I told her that was not enough,
                     and she gave me five cents more, and asked me to show her a good restaurant
                     where she could get some dinner. I went with her to Keenan's saloon on Ninth
                     avenue, between Twenty-ninth and Thirtieth streets. When we got there she would
                     not go in, but said she guessed she would go to her friends, as she didn't have
                     much time and very little money. She then left me and walked down Ninth avenue,
                     and I went back to the depot.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>IN THE MORGUE.</head>
                  <p>The appearance of the body as it lay in the trunk was frightful. The trunk was
                     but two feet eight inches in length, yet the young woman was over five feet in
                     height, and had been literally crushed into it. Her head was forced over on her
                     breast, and her limbs were drawn up to the very fullest tension of the
                     ligatures in order to crowd the body into the narrowest compass possible. The
                     rags which covered the body had evidently been selected for the purpose because
                     of their worthlessness. Two pillow cases, which were among the number, had
                     pieces torn out of the open ends, evidently to remove the name which had
                     probably been written on them.</p>
                  <p>Our reporter viewed the remains as they lay in the dead-house at Bellevue. In
                     life the young woman was doubtless very beautiful, although now sadly
                     disfigured by death's terrible follower. She was apparently about twenty years
                     of age, of slight and delicate figure, and as ethereal in form as Guido's Io. A
                     tangled mass of the</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MOST BEAUTIFUL GOLDEN HAIR</head>
                  <p>fell in waves over her shoulders, which must have been as white as Parian
                     marble, and eyes of blue, that even death's horrors cannot pale, look out in
                     all their ghastliness from swollen and discolored lids. The limbs were white
                     and shapely, and the feet tiny and delicate. The arms and hands were faultless
                     in their symmetry, and every feature showed refinement and grace. The small
                     exquisitely cut face was terribly discolored and the mouth distorted by
                     suffering. The teeth regular in<pb n="24 (Illustration) -25"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000005"/>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Rosenzweig, assisted by the Truckman, removing the trunk containing
                           the body poor Alice Bowlsby.</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Rosenzweig, unterstüzt von dem Fuhrmann bei
                              Fortschaffung des Koffers, die Leiche der armen Alice Bowlsby
                              enthielt.</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure> form and pearly in their whiteness. One of the knees was much
                     bruised, and the skin had been peeled off. This shows what brutality the fiends
                     must have practised in their efforts to force the delicate form into its narrow
                     box. The trunk stood near the box enclosing the remains of the poor girl. In it
                     were the mute witnesses to the terrible deed—the rags which accompanied the
                     body. The trunk is an ordinary old shoe trunk. The hinges are loose, and the
                     lock not secure. The inside of it is discolored with blood, but not a spot
                     appears on the outside.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE POST MORTEM EXAMINATION.</head>
                  <p>Dr. Cushman, Deputy Coroner, went to the Morgue, and made a post mortem
                     examination of the body. He found it, as it lay in the coffin, decently covered
                     with a linen sheet. He says that the girl was about twenty years of age, and
                     had been dead three days. The body Dr. Cushman found very much decomposed: the
                     eyes were swollen and the mouth open. Decomposition had particularly far
                     advanced in the head, neck, and trunk. There were no external marks of
                     violence, but the lower part of the person was very much swollen and bloody. On
                     opening the body the abdominal cavity was found to contain a large amount of
                     fluid, and there were evidences of acute peritonitis. The examination of the
                     womb showed marks of laceration, and there were found evidences of intense
                     inflammation; also of the placenta; a small portion of the placenta still
                     adhered to the posterior surface. All the other organs, the liver, kidney,
                     heart, stomach, etc., were in a perfectly healthy condition. Dr. Cushman
                     thought that death was caused by metroperitonitis—the result of malpractice, or
                     criminal violation of nature's laws in the delivery of the unfortunate girl in
                     childbirth. But up to the time here referred to, mystery had as yet veiled the
                     whole.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE PHYSICIANS' THEORIES.</head>
                  <p>Physicians who examined the position of the body in the trunk were at a loss to
                     understand how it could have been so distorted after death. When <foreign
                        xml:lang="LAT">rigor mortis</foreign> exists, the joints become as
                     inflexible as iron bars, and this too five minutes after the breath leaves the
                     body. This gives rise to the <emph>dreadful suspicion</emph> that the fair
                     young victim was <emph>crushed into the trunk while yet alive,</emph> and
                     several medical gentlemen give it as their opinion that this was actually the
                     case. The joints were bent naturally, and when relieved from their confinement
                     the limbs remained as they were bent, and it required force to straighten them
                     out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE SEARCH BY THE POLICE.</head>
                  <p>The police continued indefatigable in their efforts to fathom the mystery. Soon
                     after the discovery, Captain Caffrey informed himself of all the facts that he
                     could get, and then went to the Central Office and conferred with Inspector
                     Walling. The result of the consultation was that<pb n="26-27"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000006"/> the finding of the man who drove the truck
                     should be the objective point. The boy Potts was sent for. He soon arrived at
                     the Central Office in charge of Sergeant James. The boy said he did not notice
                     the number of the truck, but was positive that the name of Tripp was painted on
                     it. One of the cart inspectors and Ward Detective Freeman of the City Hall were
                     then telegraphed for. Detectives Brice and McConnell soon arrive, from the
                     Thirty-seventh Street Station, and after a careful examination of the list of
                     carmen and truckmen, the detectives started off at midnight in search of any
                     truckman who might bear the name of Tripp. At about one o'clock, officers
                     Freeman and Carnoghan found, 231 Bowery, an old German carman, who gave his
                     name as Medert Trapp. Trapp was</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MARCHED IN TRIUMPH</head>
                  <p>to the Central Office and confronted with Inspector Walling. He admitted that
                     he had been applied to by a stranger to take a trunk for him from a house in
                     Bond street to the depot, but said that he did not take the job.</p>
                  <p>Inspector Walling winked at Detective Tilly, as much as to say, "We've got the
                     right man sure." Then it was suggested that the boy should see whether he could
                     identify Trapp as the man. Young Potts was then brought in, and without
                     hesitation he declared that Trapp was not the man. Trapp was thereupon allowed
                     to depart. He seemed indignant at his detention, and vowed that he would have
                     satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>The detectives were then started off with orders to search every part of the
                     city, and not stop until they found Tripp. The search for Tripp was kept up
                     unceasingly until about 8 o'clock on Tuesday morning, but no such man was
                     found. At about 9 o'clock Detectives McConnell and Brice learned that</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A MR. LEE BRADY, OF THIRD AVENUE,</head>
                  <p>owned a truck which corresponded with the description of that which carried the
                     trunk to the depot, and that he had taken some baggage in it to the depot. The
                     detectives hurried to Brady's house, taking the boy with them. On their arrival
                     the boy failed to identify either Brady or his truck. Brady then told the
                     detectives that a cabman by the name of Francis Cooper had driven a woman to
                     the Hudson River Railroad depot on Saturday. They then ascertained that the
                     cabman could be found at Seldon's livery stables, on Twenty-third street, near
                     Third avenue. Thither the detectives bent their steps, and found Cooper. The
                     boy recognized Cooper. He was the man. Cooper told the detectives that he was
                     just in the act of leaving the stable with the coupé when a lady went into the
                     office of the stable and told the clerk, a colored man, that she wanted to be
                     driven to the depot, and inquired the price. When she was told that the price
                     was $1.50, she said that she was poor and could not pay more than $1. The clerk
                     receded from his demand, and the woman entered the cab by herself. Cooper took
                     no particular notice of her, nor did he see her until they arrived at the
                     depot. There the boy opened the door of the coupé and she paid him the dollar.
                     He feels convinced, however, that he should know her if he ever saw her again.
                     The police continued persistently in working on other clews as fast as they
                     came up.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND DAY (MONDAY) AMID THE TRUNK MYSTERIES.</head>
               <p>Early in the day, by order of Inspector Walling, the boy
                     <unclear>Alexander</unclear> Potts was taken in a carriage with officers
                  Carnochan and Freeman, of the Twenty-sixth Precinct, to make a tour of the entire
                  city, visiting every place where trucks stand for hire, with the hope that at some
                  one of these he might identify the man or the vehicle concerned in the affair.
                  Hours passed away, during which nothing was heard from this party, and it was
                  presumed they were constantly engaged in carrying out the instructions they had
                  received. Meantime the curious called in great numbers upon Inspector Walling, who
                  remained at Police Headquarters, anxious to learn the latest developments. For all
                  of these he had but one answer, that he had nothing new; but to the members of the
                  Press he added that when he had the truckman, and that person had given him such
                  information as would lead to the detection of the murderer, and he was so close
                  upon the latter that escape would be impossible, he would give in full all the
                  facts, but until then he should not give any whatever.</p>
               <p>Not trusting to the inspection by the boy Potts, and anxious not to leave a single
                  chance neglected, Inspector Walling issued orders which practically put every
                  policeman in the force upon the case, and waited impatiently for something to turn
                  up.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE TRUCKMAN FOUND AT LAST.</head>
                  <p>At 3 o'clock a telegram was received from the Eighteenth Precinct that the
                     truckman had been found, and was then in charge at that station, and in a few
                     minutes Inspector Walling left Headquarters and went to the Eighteenth Precinct
                     Station-house, in Twenty-second street, near First avenue. He there found a
                     truckman named William Pickett, who lives at No. 471 First avenue, but who
                     stands for hire at the corner of Third avenue and Twenty-ninth street. With
                     Pickett was Warden Brennan, of Bellevue Hospital, and the statement of the
                     latter has priority in this narrative of the startling events by which the
                     abortionist was tracked to and dragged from his lair. He stated that he had
                     known Pickett intimately for a long time, and that shortly after noon he came
                     to the hospital greatly troubled to seek for advice. He had read the accounts
                     of the mystery in the morning papers, and thought that he was the man who had
                     taken the trunk to the depot. The Warden got Pickett to relate the
                     circumstances, on hearing which he was convinced of the<pb n="28-29"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000007"/> man's identity, and persuaded him to go around
                     to Captain Cameron of the Eighteenth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>PICKETT'S STORY.</head>
                  <p>When they arrived there, Pickett told the captain that about 1 o'clock, P. M.,
                     on Saturday, a woman came to his stand on the corner of Twenty-ninth street and
                     Third avenue, and asked him to go to the basement of No. 687 Second avenue and
                     get a trunk of hers, which he would obtain by ringing the bell and telling the
                     people what he wanted. Then he was to put it on his truck and bring it to the
                     Hudson River Railroad Depot, whither she was going in a coupé. She paid him in
                     advance, changing a five-dollar bill to do so, and they parted. He went to the
                     house, rang the bell, and, the door opening, was ushered into the basement
                     chamber. There was no hall. Here he observed several women and a tall man, whom
                     the carman described so accurately, as to enable Acting Police Sergeant Rooney
                     to identify him as Jacob Rosenzweig, whom he knew well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ROSENZWEIG'S ARREST EFFECTED.</head>
                  <p>Without more ado, Captain Cameron, having ordered Sergeant Rooney to put on
                     citizen's clothes, took the man to No. 687 Second avenue; went down the
                     basement, and applied for admission. The door was opened, but the doctor was
                     out. His wife and daughter only were in. The wife is in a delicate condition,
                     having been confined but four weeks previous. Things looking unsatisfactory,
                     Captain Cameron withdrew, taking care to put the house under strict
                     surveillance, so that nobody could enter or leave without being seen. Sergeant
                     Rooney, in his civilian disguise, watched for the doctor's arrival. He came at
                     last, and was seen to enter a liquor store near his house. Rooney followed, and
                     was about to arrest him, and Rosenzweig made a dash for liberty, because he
                     recognized his captor. He was too late to escape, and fell into the officer's
                     hands easily Seeing that there was a struggle between the men, the police who
                     had been quietly waiting on the other side of the way, dashed across, followed
                     by a number of persons who quickly scented the game, and would have lynched the
                     prisoner, but for the officers, some of whom were compelled to draw their
                     revolvers while Sergeant Rooney got his man into a Second avenue car, and took
                     him in safety to the Eighteenth Precinct.</p>
                  <p>When Captain Cameron returned with the truckman, earlier in the
                        <unclear>evening</unclear>, from their unsuccessful attempt to find the
                     doctor—or man who had given him the trunk—they brought with them to the
                     Station-house the servant girl from No. 687, and a Jew peddler boy, from whom
                     he hoped to obtain some information.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE TRUCKMAN MAKES A DETAILED STATEMENT.</head>
                  <p>Inspector Walling met the party, and immediately made the truckman recount the
                     circumstances of Saturday. He told in addition to the manner of his engagement,
                     as already described, and the delivery of the trunk, that he placed it on his
                     cart and proceeded to the Hudson River Railroad depot, where he found the woman
                     waiting for him, conversing with a boy whom she had engaged to help her with
                     the trunk. He, the truckman, took hold of one end of the box to lift it off the
                     wagon, and the boy attempted to raise the other end, and not being able to do
                     it alone, was assisted by the woman. He and the boy then carried the trunk
                        <unclear>into</unclear> the depot and put it on the counter to get it
                     checked. While Frank Dunning, the baggage-master, was thus engaged, a bystander
                     remarked that the lock was very weak. The woman asked for a rope to tie the lid
                     down more firmly. Frank Dunning said he had nothing but a strap. She replied
                     that it would do. "Do you know what it will cost you?" said he. "I don't care,"
                     she answered. "It is worth a dollar," the man remarked. She told him to put it
                     on, and paid the money. The truckman then left.</p>
                  <p>When he heard this story, the Inspector, learning that the boy had arrived,
                     called him in and made him relate his recollection of the facts in the man's
                     presence. The latter, at the conclusion, said that every word was true, except
                     the assertion that he shook hands with the woman when parting. This he strongly
                     denied. Here was the only point of difference between them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ROSENZWEIG INTERROGATED.</head>
                  <p>Rooney brought his prisoner in at this juncture, and the Inspector confronted
                     him with Pickett, and asked him if he knew anything about the trunk which he
                     had given the man on Saturday. Rosenzweig appeared perfectly amazed at the
                     question, and denied having ever before set eyes upon the truckman, and was
                     totally in the dark about the trunk. "What trunk?" said he. Pickett said that
                     he believed Rosenzweig to be the man who had given him the trunk, but he was
                     not sure that he had ever seen the girl before. The wife, he thought, was in
                     the basement at the time of its delivery, and asked him where he was going to
                     take it. However, he was not very clear on these points. The inspector ordered
                     the prisoner to be locked up, and the servant girl, truckman and Jew peddler to
                     be set at liberty.</p>
                  <p>On further examination it was found that Mrs. Rosenzweig, who at first denied
                     all knowledge of the trunk business, said very innocently that she was too
                     delicate to be down stairs on Saturday when the truckman called, but hastily
                     correcting herself, she again professed total ignorance of any such affair
                     having transpired. Inspector Walling found out afterward that the woman had
                     been down to the basement four or five times since her confinement. Around this
                     female's complicity in this affair, a great deal of doubt and uncertainty
                     exists, and no light at all thus far has been thrown upon the woman who engaged
                     the truck, went to the depot in the coupé, and was so diabolically cool in her
                     efforts to have the evidence<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6545-00000008"/> of the
                     crime removed to a far distant city. She has thus <unclear>far</unclear>
                     escaped: but not for long, if the fears of conviction are worth anything to
                     unlock prisoners' lips.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SEEKING TO IDENTIFY THE VICTIM.</head>
                  <p>Having disposed of these persons, Inspector Walling believing that some clue to
                     the poor victim's identity might still exist in the shape of a valuable trinket
                     or article of wearing apparel, which the oupidity of the wretches into whose
                     merciless hands she fell caused to keep, placed a close guard over the arrested
                     man's premises, and afterward issued an order that they be thoroughly searched.
                     He then returned to Police Headquarters. In brief then, although the task of
                     relating these events has occupied so little space, the unravelling and pursuit
                     of the matter. step by step, had to be carefully managed, not to alarm those
                     whose arrest was desired, and the whole afternoon and evening were consumed in
                     watching and investigating satisfactorily. No sooner had he reached his desk
                     than two persons called upon him in the belief that they had recognized in
                     deceased a friend whose fate and absence from home could not be accounted for.
                     Their testimony was too indistinct and vague to be considered worthy of serious
                     credence especially when heard in connection with that of several others, who
                     came to the Central Office during the early part of the day and claimed the
                     dead girl as their friend. Yet each person was from widely-separated parts of
                     the country and State. Late at night a gentleman waited upon Inspector Walling
                     with a photograph, in the hope that by it some one who had seen the victim
                     might relieve his anxious mind of the fear that she was the original of the
                     carte. He had to leave in a state of uncertainty, as no one felt able to hazard
                     anything like a just opinion.</p>
                  <p>About 10 o'clock Inspector Jameson, with several other officers, went to the
                     house in Amity place, South Fifth avenue, occupied by the prisoner as an
                     office, to find, if possible, the woman who had sent the trunk to the
                     depot.</p>
                  <p>Not having any evidence by which to identify the woman, should she be on the
                     premises, considerable caution was at first exercised to prevent alarming the
                     inmates, or making an excitement in the neighborhood. The house was closely
                     watched, and to the officers and the small band of reporters, it was for the
                     time-being an object of intense interest. Several females were sitting on the
                     stoop, apparently unconscious of the espionage on the house.</p>
                  <p>The rear window of a house on Amity street was taken as a place of observation
                     by some of the reporters, and the movements of those in the house were watched
                     with Argus eyes. A Saratoga trunk was seen on the porch looking out into the
                     garden, that was thought to be one of the trunks used in the business.</p>
                  <p>The police finally entered the house, and Mrs. Ascher, the woman in charge, who
                     is quite old, denied that the place was as it was represented<pb
                        n="32 (Illustration) -33" xml:id="VAC6545-00000009"/>
                     <figure>
                        <head>The "unknown" woman ordering the mysterious trunk to be lifted
                           carefully from the truck. (Evidence of the boy Potts)</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Die "unbekannte" Frau anordnend, den
                              geheimnißvollen Koffer behutsam vom Wagen zu heben. (Aussage des
                              Knaben Potts.)</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure> No proofs being at hand to show that it was, the police were obliged
                     to be satisfied with the statement that it was occupied by respectable people,
                     and that "Dr." Ascher only kept an office there. Subsequently Inspector Walling
                     sent the truckman and boy to Rosenzweig's, alias Ascher's house in Amity place
                     with an officer. They saw all the females in the building, but failed to
                     recognize among them the woman who was at the depot on Saturday.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SKETCH OF THE PRISONER ROSENZWEIG, ALIAS ASCHER.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>A.—Ladies in trouble guaranteed immediate relief, sure and safe; no fees
                        required until perfectly satisfied; elegant rooms and nursing provided. Dr.
                        Ascher, Amity place, etc.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>This advertisement was clipped from a late issue of the <title>Herald.</title>
                     The following is an accurate description of the man now arrested:</p>
                  <p>"Dr. Ascher," alias "Rosenzweig," of South Fifth avenue, below Amity street,
                     claims to be a Russian, but his voice has the twang of a German Jew. He is very
                     bulky in figure, about 40 years of age, and is said to know more of saloon
                     business than of medicine. His diploma is said to have cost $40. His house is a
                     large three-story and basement one, and is able to accommodate twelve patients.
                     He does a large business. When called upon he assures applicants, "These other
                     fellows are all humpugsh; they bromish to do something vot they don't do. I
                     poshitively do all operashunsh widout any danger, and as sheap as anybody." The
                     corpse like faces to be seen peering through the bed-room blinds are enough to
                     horrify the stoutest-hearted passers-by.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE PROFESSIONAL ABORTIONIST'S BUSINESS VARIETY.</head>
                  <p>"Dr." Rosenzweig, besides the house in Amity place, of which more hereafter,
                     has another at No. 687 Second avenue, where he resides with his family. How
                     many more of these horrible dens he keeps in other parts of the city may yet be
                     discovered. From this house the body was carried in the trunk to the depot.
                     Those who know Rosenzweig say that about two years ago he kept a lager beer
                     saloon in this city, but probably not finding it as profitable as he desired,
                     he turned his attention to the "practice" of medicine, which in his hands
                     became the practice of murder. Hanging in his "office" is a diploma which he
                     procured to give him a licence to pursue his murderous calling. This diploma
                     was obtained from an "institution" in Philadelphia, with eight principal
                     professors and eight adjuncts. He told an acquaintance that he had paid $40 for
                     that particular diploma, but, said he, I did not need it, for I have got three
                     or four of them. The "Dr." has a wife living, a daughter, fourteen years of
                     age, and a child of about a month old. He is a fat, coarse and sensual-looking
                     fellow, without any traces of refinement in person or manners, and does not
                     bear the faintest appearance of the educated physician. None but the wretched
                     creatures, who, driven to desperation by<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6545-00000010"
                     /> their condition and the fear of discovery by friends, would place any
                     confidence in his skill. Many of the misguided women that he has treated could
                     not fail to have misgivings when they have placed themselves under his
                     treatment, but probably preferred risking life rather than discovery in what
                     they regarded as a misfortune. One of the friends of this monster is "Dr."
                     Franklin, alias Jacoby.</p>
                  <p>Ronsenzweig is said to have boasted, some time ago, that he, with "Dr.
                     Franklin, was in partnership in an abortion case. This Jacoby, until three or
                     four years past, kept a barber-shop in Sixth avenue. Each of them, according to
                     Rosenzweig, received an equal share in that transaction, and a gold watch was a
                     part of the spoils.</p>
                  <p>Another case is related of a woman who was in excellent health when she first
                     went under Rosenzweig's treatment, and after a few weeks of his "practice," she
                     is described as being a piteous spectacle. The flesh hung to her bones, her
                     eyes had lost their lustre, and she became as weak and decrepid as though old
                     age had suddenly laid its hand upon her. She left him a complete wreck, and
                     with her health probably blasted for life. He told a medical acquaintance that
                     he produced a salivation by administering from fifteen to twenty grains of
                     calomel, and said the medical gentleman referred to, "I never use more than two
                     and one-half grains."</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>DEVELOPMENTS OF TUESDAY, THE THIRD DAY.</head>
               <p>Up to the period here suggested, all but one of the difficulties in the way of
                  solving the bloody mystery had been overcome. That difficulty consisted in the
                  identity of the outraged girl; a world of speculations were indulged in,
                  identifying her with really innocent and living parties. By this reckless and
                  merely sensational speculation much injustice was done, and we therefore suppress
                  all reference to names thus wrongly published. Thus far (Tuesday) the body
                  remained unidentified. In order, however, that no chance for identification might
                  be lost, the body was placed upon ice, where it was continued for several days
                  after.</p>
               <p>Although the condition of the body had been fully published, and the stench, even
                  outside the room where it was exposed in the dead-house of Bellevue Hospital, was
                  almost unendurable, hundreds were drawn on Tuesday by a prurient curiosity to look
                  upon the horrible mass. All of these made the pretence of desiring to see if they
                  could identify the remains, but very few claimed to have friends or relatives
                  missing, and none of these few saw anything that they could recognize. Warden
                  Brennan who still seemed, to put faith in the Kelly story, thought it might be
                  possible to recognize the body from the hair, the ears, and the forehead, which
                  remained intact, and therefore permitted every one desiring to see the body to
                  enter the room where it was exposed. The same was allowed on Wednesday, although
                  decomposition was rapidly progressing, and the remains were becoming dangerous to
                  the health of the hospital and vicinity.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>JUSTICE ON THE TRACK OF HER OWN</head>
                  <p>While the hope of ever identifying the murdered woman was almost dying out
                     during Tuesday, that of bringing the murderer to justice was greatly
                     strengthened. By order of Inspector Walling, Captain Cameron sent Sergeant
                     Randall to the house of Rosenzweig early in the day to make a thorough search
                     of the premises. It is a three-story and basement brick house, with a white
                     marble stoop, and is one of two standing upon one lot. This makes it very
                     narrow and causes the street doors to open directly into the rooms on the first
                     floor and basement instead of into halls, as in full width houses. There are
                     but two rooms on each floor making eight in all, and none of them are of large
                     size. The house is furnished comfortably, and even handsomely throughout,
                     showing that the infamous practices of Rosenzweig yielded him an income
                     sufficient to supply him with all the comforts of life. Sergeant Randall going
                     to this house, which has been in constant possession of the police ever since
                     it was pointed out by Pickett, made a systematic and thorough search of it with
                     some important results. In the upper rooms nothing suspicious was found, nor
                     was there any evidence anywhere that the house or any part of it had ever been
                     used as a lying-in hospital. But in one of the drawers of the desk used by
                     Rosenzweig were a number of papers, and in the cellar a most important
                     discovery was made. In one corner under a pile of rubbish were found some
                     bloody rags, portions of an old petticoat and the half of a chemise. This last
                     was seized as a most valuable atom of evidence. It was of fine quality, and a
                     determined effort had been made to destroy both its identity and the blood
                     stains upon it. The latter had been attempted by partial washing with the usual
                     result of spreading the stains evenly through the fabric, and the destruction
                     of the identity had been sought by tearing the chemise into parts, only one of
                     which had been left in this spot. This portion had been torn from the yoke, and
                     had one of the arm-holes, but the sleeve had been wrenched out, as the ragged
                     edges plainly showed, with sudden violence. With the bloody rags and petticoat,
                     the chemise was wrapped up and taken to the station-house.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A CRIMINAL ESTABLISHMENT AND ITS BRANCHES.</head>
                  <p>Nor did this bundle contain all the evidence carried away from the house. Among
                     the papers in the drawer was a scrap on which was written, "Ladies cured with
                     or without medicine, by Dr. Ascher, Amity Place," thus conclusively proving the
                     identity of Rosenzweig with the remorseless abortionist exposed lately in the
                     press. There was a certificate of death in the case of a still-born child,
                     filled up on the regular blanks of the Board of Health, signed Dr. Rosenzweig,
                     No. 15 Orchard street, and dated August 11, 1867, thus showing that he had
                     pretended to practice medicine four years ago at least. There were receipts
                        for<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6545-00000011"/> rent, showing that he has
                     rarely remained long in one place, and that he has lived or had an office at
                     No. 105 First avenue, No. 33 Wooster street, No. 138 East Broadway, No. 5 Essex
                     street, No. 79 Grand street, and at No. 15 Orchard street, as above stated.
                     There were a dozen scraps of paper, on which were scrawled, scarcely legible,
                     names and location which seemed to be memoranda of appointments in the practice
                     of the pretender, and of no bearing upon the case. They were retained, however,
                     and with the more valuable articles which had been secured, taken to the
                     station-house. Before leaving the premises of Rosenzweig, Sergeant Randall made
                     a discovery that for a time seemed to promise important results. This was in
                     the fact, that in the cellar wall between his house and that next door,
                     occupied by Dr. Sutlinski, there was a door, which was, how ever, closed, and
                     fastened on the side of Dr. Sutlinski. The fact was, how ever, noted and
                     reported to Inspector Walling.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>EVIDENCE OF AN UNDERTAKER.</head>
                  <p>While this search was being made, another and far more important link in the
                     chain of circumstantial evidence against Rosenzweig was found James F. Boyle,
                     an undertaker at No. 658 Second avenue, which is only a few doors from the
                     residence of Rosenzweig, called at the Eighteenth Precinct Station-house, and
                     asked to see the prisoner, as he thought he could throw some light upon the
                     case. He was taken out to the prison by Captain Cameron, and Rosenzweig having
                     been called to the door of his cell, Boyle looked at him steadily for a moment
                     and then said, "Yes, that's the man." His statement was then taken down by
                     Captain Cameron, and is as follows:</p>
                  <p>On the morning of Saturday, the 26th inst., a man whom I recognize as Dr.
                     Rosenzweig came to my store where I do business as an undertaker and asked me
                     how much it would cost to bury a woman, and then added that a servant girl of
                     his had died; that she was very poor and only had $10, and that it did not
                     matter to him how or when she was buried, so that it was done. I asked him what
                     sort of a funeral he wanted. He said he only wanted a hearse. He then asked if
                     I could take the body to the store, saying that it was not far off. I replied
                     that I could only do this if he would furnish me with a certificate from the
                     doctor who had attended her, and then I could get a permit from the Board of
                     Health <unclear>on</unclear> further conversation, he said that the doctor who
                     attended the deceased lived down town. He then went away.</p>
                  <p>In the afternoon the father of Boyle, who was present at the interview, called
                     at the station-house and also recognized the prisoner as the man who had
                     called.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE FELON'S CONFESSION.</head>
                  <p>Rosenzweig at last made his first confession, and without being asked to say
                     anything on the subject, he astonished every one present by saying, in a
                     quivering voice: "Yes, I wash dar, but I must makes fun." Having thus, in
                     police parlance, "given himself away," the grim countenance of Captain Cameron
                     was lighted with a smile as he locked the door on his prisoner, and said, "I
                     wonder if the fool knew what he was saying."</p>
                  <p>The next step in the case was to exhaust the possibility of the door in the
                     cellar, and, by order of Inspector Walling, a visit was made late in the day by
                     Captain Cameron and Sergeant Randall to the house of Dr. Sutlinski, and
                     thoroughly searched it. There was nothing found, how ever, to sustain the
                     suspicion that there might be a connection between the two houses and the two
                     doctors. Dr. Sutlinski was found to be, so far as the police could judge from
                     appearances, a regular practitioner, and there was nothing irregular whatever
                     about his house. There were several other failures during the day, among which
                     was the arrest of two women suspected of hiring the truckman, but upon the
                     truckman Pickett and the boy Potts being taken to the Sixth Precinct
                     Station-house and confronted with the women, they declared without the least
                     hesitation that neither bore any resemblance to the woman. Inspector Walling
                     has as yet no clue to this woman, and has now but little hope that she will be
                     found, but he considers that he has the principal in the case, and that he has
                     evidence enough to convict him without the testimony of the woman who was an
                     accessory to the crime. Enough has been done to thoroughly frighten the entire
                     community of abortionists, and some of the most prominent of them seem to have
                     fled from the city. Among these is Madame Van Buskirk, whose house at No. 8 St.
                     Mark's place, was last Tuesday night for the first time entirely deserted.</p>
                  <p>The case is now ready for the final action of the coroner and
                     district-attorney. Inspector Walling believes that all the evidence which it is
                     possible to obtain is now in hand, and that it is sufficient to send Rosenzweig
                     to Sing Sing. There are, of course, thousands of rumors floating about the
                     case, as there always are in such affairs, and as many crude theories of
                     amateur detectives as to the identity of the murdered woman, but they are
                     unworthy of mention. The prisoner, who Tuesday night was furnished with a
                     comfortable bed of blankets and pillows sent from his house, of course stoutly
                     denied all knowledge of the crime, and his servant, Jane Thompson, who was up
                     to this time still detained at the station-house, continued to profess entire
                     ignorance of the affair. But with these denials, and with the identity of the
                     girl yet unknown, the case is complete</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A REPORTER'S MARVELLOUS STORY ABOUT DR. ASCHER, ALIAS ROSENZWEIG</head>
                  <p>During the month of July last I was directed by the <title>Times</title> editor
                     to investigate thoroughly the entire business carried on so extensively in this
                     city by professional abortionists. In order to secure success, and to avoid
                     suspicion, I was instructed to take a lady with me. After a long, tedious, and
                     in many respects an unpleasant experience, we unearthed a<pb n="38-39"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000012"/> mass of evidence that, if available in a court
                     of law, would drive a score of villains to the refuge of the State prison.</p>
                  <p>Among others upon whom we called was "Dr. Ascher." at his office in South Fifth
                     avenue, as advertised daily in the <title>Herald</title> for months previously.
                     We rang the bell and were promptly ushered into the hall-way of an ordinary
                     first-class house of the former period. It was of the kind of dwellings that
                     would have been aristocratic ten years ago. A woman of, say, forty years of age
                     opened the door and led us into the parlor As we entered the room a young girl
                     emerged therefrom. She seemed to be about twenty years of age, a little more
                     than five feet in height, of slender build, having blue eyes, and a clear,
                     alabaster complexion. Long blonde curls, tinted with gold, drooped upon her
                     shoulders, and her face wore an expression of embarrassment at the presence of
                     strangers. She retreated to the end of the hall, and stood there for a moment,
                     and then went to another part of the house. In a few moments the doctor made
                     his appearance.</p>
                  <p>"Do you wish to see me?" he asked.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, sir. We have come to consult you professionally."</p>
                  <p>The room in which we were seated was nicely furnished. A fine tapestry carpet
                     covered the floor; at the window was an elegant mahogany desk, against the wall
                     was a long, easy sofa, in the centre of the room was a marble-top table covered
                     with books and pamphlets, and chairs were placed about in the usual manner.
                     Folding-doors seemed to separate the rooms, and adjacent thereto was what
                     seemed to be a piano, having a large cover of heavy damask. The man laid down
                     the pipe from his mouth, for he had been smoking, and wheeling and easy chair
                     in front of us, at once began the conversation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>INTERVIEW DIRECT.</head>
                  <p>"I suppose you called for medical services?" he asked.</p>
                  <p>"We called for medical information," was the answer.</p>
                  <p>"Exactly; we probably understand each other. You wish to release a lady from
                     difficulty."</p>
                  <p>"We came to inquire what you propose to do, and what your charges are for such
                     work."</p>
                  <p>"Well, what are the symptoms—tell me exactly."</p>
                  <p>"We tell you nothing; but suppose that a lady is ——, and that —— are the
                     symptoms. What can you do?"</p>
                  <p>"Well, you wish to save her and her family. I can do it without danger. I will
                     not fool you. You know what risk there is in this business.<unclear>I
                        want</unclear> $200 down. If there is no trouble, I will see the lady safely
                     through for that sum."</p>
                  <p>"But the <emph>result</emph>—what is to be done with that? Are we
                     responsible?"</p>
                  <p>"No, I will take care of the 'result'" (with a significant look and motion of
                     the hand to the lips). "You need not trouble yourself bout that</p>
                  <pb n="40 (Illustration) -41" xml:id="VAC6545-00000013"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>The "unknown woman" and the MYSTERIOUS TRUNK at the Depot.</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Die "unbekannte Frau" und der geheimnißvolle
                              Koffer auf dem Bahnhofe.</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>"But—a young lady and gentleman—what can they do to save their reputation?"</p>
                  <p>[Sotto voce.] "<emph>I will give you marriage or burial certificates. I have
                        facilities for both.</emph> Is this the lady?"</p>
                  <p>"No, sir."</p>
                  <p>"Well, I must see the lady," he said, and bowed us out.</p>
                  <p>Next week I called alone. He was again beclouded in smoke.</p>
                  <p>"Well, sir," he began, "you have not brought the lady?"</p>
                  <p>"No: I have not."</p>
                  <p>"I cannot tell you anything without I see her."</p>
                  <p>"You told me you could attend to any case; in the far West, for
                        <unclear>instance</unclear>."</p>
                  <p>"But I must know the person and her peculiarities."</p>
                  <p>"I want to know just what you could do in a certain case. Suppose it to be
                     this——"</p>
                  <p>[Here an imaginary case was put.]</p>
                  <p>"Well, that is serious, <unclear>too. I</unclear> have had lots of them. I can
                     do the worst safely. If the first means fail I must go to the extreme."</p>
                  <p>"Dare you use instruments, and is it safe?"</p>
                  <p>"I do nothing but what is safe. I can do more than all these humbugs that
                     pretend, yet cheat."</p>
                  <p>"But in case of the child's death, who is responsible in the eye of the law if
                     a discovery is made?"</p>
                  <p>"Don't worry about that, my dear sir. I will take care of the
                        <emph>result.</emph> A newspaper bundle, a basket, a pail, a resort to the
                     sewer or the river at night. Who is the wiser?"</p>
                  <p>"But, doctor, if the mother dies?"</p>
                  <p>"If that should happen, of course you would stand the expense. <emph>But you
                        need never fear. The lady can be disposed of without trouble. I can get
                        marriage or burial certificates without trouble. You know Madame Restell and
                        all the others. I have the same facilities they have.</emph> We can do the
                     thing up handsomely, and I can save you lots of expense. All these other
                     fellows are humbugs. But, why did you not bring the lady here?" he asked, with
                     an evident suspicion of the visitor, and then turning the key in the lock and
                     leaning his ponderous form against the door, he seemed to forbid our egress
                     from the place.</p>
                  <p>"<unclear>You seem</unclear> to hang off," he continued. "What do you
                     mean?"</p>
                  <p>"I don't bring you a case. I ask what would you do under the circumstances I
                     have named?"</p>
                  <p>"You are a —— sneak and a liar!" he exclaimed, with flashing eyes and an
                     excited manner. "You are a —— spy. I will split your head for you, you—you ——
                     —— ——!"</p>
                  <p>The piano, or table, stood between me and the only means of exit, which his
                     bulky form covered. The blinds, too, seemed to be fastened. He was<pb n="42-43"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000014"/> a muscular man, at least three times the weight
                     of myself, and appeared wrought up to the highest pitch of excitement.</p>
                  <p>"Let me see, sir," I exclaimed.</p>
                  <p>"You ——, I'll kill you——(advancing), I'll give you all you want; you spy, you
                     devil, you villain!"</p>
                  <p>Matters seemed desperate. I had not expected such a denouement. But I felt that
                     there was but one thing to do—either to be conquered or to conquer, and leave
                     the house I must, or else suffer violence at his hands.</p>
                  <p>Perceiving his desperation, I was at once upon my guard. A sudden movement of
                     his hand to his breast pocket, startled me into the belief that he was about to
                     draw forth a deadly weapon and possibly take my life as he had threatened. In
                     an instant I drew a revolver, the sight of which intimidated him, and in his
                     moment of terror and confusion I escaped.</p>
                  <p>"I will have you arrested," he screamed, as I slammed the door shut and hurried
                     to the street. As I passed through the hall-way I saw the same girl who left
                     the parlor when I made my first visit to the house. She was standing on the
                     stairs, and it was the same face I saw afterward at the Morgue. I positively
                     identify the features of the dead woman as those of the blonde beauty before
                     described, and will testify to the fact, if called upon to do so, before a
                     legal tribunal.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>AN IMPORTANT ITEM OF EVIDENCE.</head>
                  <p>Late Tuesday night, the servant of Rosenzweig, Jane Thompson, spoke to what may
                     prove good purpose in a conversation with Warden Brennan, to whom she said that
                     she had determined to tell everything she knew. With this preface, she again
                     declared that she knew nothing whatever of the corpse in the trunk, that no one
                     had died in the house within the past few days, and that she did not know of
                     the trunk being in the house. She then made the important admission, that on
                     the 7th of June a young woman died in the house just after her confinement, and
                     was buried under the name of Mary Carrol, which was not her true name. The
                     certificate gave dropsy as the cause of death, but the servant knew nothing as
                     to what was the real cause. Thomas Carey, undertaker, No 401 Third avenue, had
                     buried the woman, and after the funeral the servant and Mrs. Rosenzweig had
                     taken the child, which, of course, had been born alive, to the Sisters of
                     Charity at the Foundling <unclear>Hospital</unclear> and left it there.
                     Inspector Walling was determined to get at the whole truth of this matter, as
                     it is apparent only a part had been told.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>STARTLING ADDITIONAL DISCLOSURES—THE MURDERED GIRL'S IDENTITY
                     ESTABLISHED.</head>
                  <p>At 7 o'clock Wednesday evening Warden Brennan reached Police Headquarters in
                     great haste, and inquired for Inspector Walling. That officer was absent, as
                     was supposed, at supper, but in fact had gone to the Eighteenth Precinct
                     Station-house with a man who knew Ascher intimately, and by whom it was desired
                     to identify him as the same person as the prisoner. Warden Brennan intimated
                     that there had been important developments in the case, but he declined to
                     state what they were until he had officially reported them to Inspector
                     Walling. He, herefore, went at once with the three gentlemen who had
                     accompanied him to the Eighteenth Precinct Station-house, where a long private
                     consultation ensued between him, his companions and the Inspector. At it
                     conclusion the three gentlemen went away, and some time afterward Inspector
                     Walling stated that he was ready to give the important information that the
                     body had been fully identified as that of the lady mentioned. He then read an
                     official statement, made to him in writing, by Warden Brennan, saying that Dr.
                     Theodore G. Kinne, of 162 Main street, Paterson, and Dr. Joseph F. Parker, a
                     dentist, having his office in the same building, had identified the body.
                     Having stated in brief terms the means of identification, he concluded with
                     returning his thanks to the physician and dentist for the invaluable aid they
                     had rendered in reaching this vital consummation in the case.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE EVIDENCE IN DETAIL.</head>
                  <p>The facts connected with the identification are, however, entitled to be told
                     in more detail than in the concise official statement of Warden Brennan. It
                     appears that three days before, Dr. Kinne visited the dead-house, and, after
                     attentively examining the remains, sought Warden Brennan in his private office,
                     and told him that he thought he knew the identity of the deceased. The Warden
                     had been told the same thing dozens of times before by all sorts of people, and
                     paid at first no more attention to this statement than he had to the scores of
                     others of like character which he had heard. In his incisive hasty way, he
                     asked his visitor how he knew the identity. Dr. Kinne said briefly and calmly
                     that he recognised a scar on the left arm, below the elbow, where he had
                     vaccinated deceased. This was something more than the wild stories he had
                     heard, and Brennan listened more attentively. He knew there was nothing more
                     unusual than vaccination below the elbow, and that such a scar identified by
                     the physician who had caused it was most important. But he was most anxious to
                     have something more definite, and asked Dr. Kinne if he
                        <unclear>could</unclear> not bring something more positive. Dr. Kinne
                     reflected for a moment, and then saying decisively that he could, went away. It
                     does not appear that anything more was heard of him until last Wednesday
                     afternoon, and the hope raised by his first visit had nearly expired, when he
                     returned with Dr. Parker, and both gentlemen desired an opportunity to make the
                     fullest examination of the corpse possible under the circumstances.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6545-00000015"/>
                  <head>THE DEAD GIRL'S PHYSICIAN AND DENTIST.</head>
                  <p>Dr. Parker, before going to the dead-house, minutely described the work he had
                     done in the mouth of Miss Bowlsby, which consisted in the extraction of one of
                     the molars and the filling of two of the upper teeth, and stated that there was
                     a scar on one of the jaws from an ulcerated tooth for which he had been
                     consulted. The gentlemen then went to the dead-house with Warden Brennan, and
                     the latter proceeded to get the body after it had been taken from the coffin,
                     in a fit condition to handle, by drenching it with water from a hose. After
                     this had been done, Dr. Parker made a thorough examination of the teeth, mouth
                     and jaw of the deceased, and concluded by declaring his readiness to swear to
                     the identity of the body as that of Miss Bowlsby. He recognized his work beyond
                     the possibility of a mistake, and this ended the vexed question of identity. In
                     addition, the gentlemen gave Warden Brennan details of the movements of the
                     lady during the latter part of her life, and some facts which the Warden
                     promised not to divulge, and he has kept his word. All that he was at liberty
                     to say was, that Miss Bowlsby left the home of her aunt in Newark, to go to New
                     York by the 9.15 A. M. train, on Wednesday last, saying she was going to her
                     home in Paterson, and that since that time she has not been seen alive by any
                     of her friends</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE HANDKERCHIEF! AY, THE HANDKERCHIEF OF THE GIRL-VICTIM!</head>
                  <p>But Inspector Walling, having at last a name for the victim, again ordered a
                     search of the house of Rosenzweig, with the hope of finding somewhere about it
                     some article of clothing belonging to her. If any such thing had been left
                     about the premises it was certain that it was there yet, as a guard had been
                     constantly on the house, and no one except the officers permitted to leave it
                     since the arrest. By order of the inspector, Captain Cameron, with two of his
                     sergeants, went to the house and searched it thoroughly from top to bottom, but
                     no article belonging to the victim was found anywhere until they came to the
                     kitchen. In the wash-tubs were the clothes which the girl, Jane Johnson, was
                     engaged in washing, when she was arrested two days before. Picking these out,
                     one by one, and examining them attentively, Captain Cameron came finally to a
                     linen hem-stitched handkerchief, such as are usually carried by ladies Holding
                     it up to the gas-light, in one corner there seemed to be letters, but so faint,
                     that they were not distinguishable. The searching was continued until the
                     entire house was exhausted, but nothing further was found, and Captain Cameron
                     returned to the station-house, where the handkerchief was delivered to
                     Inspector Walling. That officer placed the letters upon the handkerchief under
                     a magnifying glass, and there in distinct characters, sentencing the monster
                     Rosenzweig to the full penalty of his crime, were the letters, A. A.
                     Bowlsby.</p>
                  <p>But this decisive culmination had been reached only after a day of great labor
                     upon the part of Inspector Walling and his able corps of assistants, and the
                     previous history of the day must now be given.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>POLICE OPERATIONS.</head>
                  <p>The work of tracing out the slender lines of evidence leading in every
                     direction from the case, as it stood in the hands of the police authorities on
                     Wednesday morning, was resumed with vigor. The house No. 687 was kept under
                     surveillance, as heretofore, and everything in the Eighteenth Precinct Station
                     stood just where the reports had left it the right before.</p>
                  <p>The prisoner had passed a bad night, and was very dejected in the morning. His
                     air of injured innocence and outraged professional dignity had given place to
                     the anxious, care-worn bearing of a man in serious difficulty. In this
                     condition he was found by his wife, who called upon him early. She had overcome
                     the struggles and outward semblance of fear, which had been so markedly visible
                     from the time her husband was arrested. Wednesday she looked nothing worse than
                     annoyed, or, as Sergeant Rooney graphically defined it, "as if she were used to
                     difficult situations." She did not remain very long; but took care to express a
                     wish that she might be relieved of the disagreeable presence of the officer
                     stationed at her house all the time. However, her request could not be granted
                     very consistently with the purposes of justice; but she was permitted to
                     remove, with her two children, to her mother's residence, No. 98 Bayard street.
                     In a conversation she had with Captain Cameron, she told him that although her
                     husband had a diploma from a Philadelphia college, she never knew of his having
                     resided or even lived there for a brief period.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CAMERON'S SECOND RAID.</head>
                  <p>After her departure, the chief of the "Eighteenth," aided by a few reporters,
                     systematically began to ransack Rosenzweig's desks and chest of drawers. Every
                     nook and cranny was searched, with very good results. Numerous documents were
                     found, tied up, and brought to the station-house for examination. They were
                     spread out on the table in the back room, and separated. They were nineteen
                     letters altogether, which were unintelligible to the examiners, because written
                     in Polish, Russian and German, in execrable chirography. There were, also, one
                     or two in Hebrew, which were as little understood. Cards of Rosenzweig's,
                     bearing the addresses of some of his other offices, such as Nos. 5 and 2 Essex
                     street, and the names of patients, and the hours at which they should call were
                     in the pile, and many of the envelopes were directed to "Dr. Rosenzweig, of
                     Nos. 114 Thompson, 304 Grand, 311 Fourth, and 138 East Broadway, and 203 North
                     Sixth street, Williamsburg. Besides these were a number of papers of little
                     value, except to prove his identity. Abortionist's instruments, evidently much
                     used were discovered, as also<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6545-00000016"/> a number
                     of blank certificates of the cause of death, and certificates of stillbirth,
                     such as are furnished by the Board of Health to practitioners of respectable
                     standing. Among the others was a Central Express envelope, bearing the
                     indorsement that John W. Thompson, of Pottsville, Pa., had transmitted $40 to
                     Dr. J. Rosenzweig, for services rendered. A bill of dues from Mordecai U. O. B.
                     B. Lodge, No. 57, showed him to have been a member. Here was another paper:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <opener>
                                 <dateline>NEW YORK, May 3d, 1867.</dateline>
                              </opener>
                              <p>This is to certify that I am acquainted with Dr. Rosenzweig, No. 15
                                 Orchard street, different years; that I had often consultations
                                 with him by sick people, and that I found Dr. Rosenzweig a
                                 practical man in medical knowledge.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>DR. LOLA NORDEMAN,</signed>
                                 <address>
                                    <addrLine>No. 157 Henry street.</addrLine>
                                 </address>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>The following slips were likewise brought to light: A letter from Dr. E.
                     Harris, of the Board of Health, dated September 5th, 1866, asking for a full
                     return of the death of David Harris, and addressed to Dr. Roseman; a bill to
                     Dr. Schinkowitz, for the use of a horse; an introduction from Dr. Kokensburger,
                     of No. 68 West Thirty-ninth street; a passport from Warsaw, dated November
                     21st, 1864; several addresses of John Gray, undertaker, of No. 549 Grand
                     street; and a policy of the Brooklyn Fire Insurance Company on No. 5 Essex
                     street, for $2000, and afterward transferred to No. 53 Wooster and No. 15
                     Orchard streets. There was an old copy of a diploma, similarly worded to that
                     heretofore noticed. It was made in a large school-boy hand, and been corrected
                     here and there. The question arose as to which of the copies had been first
                     made; the parchment-framed one, or the school-boy's. Is the first a
                     forgery?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A LIST OF DRUGS.</head>
                  <p>Now we come to the curiosities. Among the many papers found there was none that
                     gave rise to so much speculation as a large white sheet of foolscap, on which
                     were inscribed a list of "recipes," in cramped penciling, evidently extracts
                     from some evil monitor's fertile brain, or a medical work of practice. They
                     were numbered and catalogued as used for Mrs. Clark and Miss Cottek, who had
                     been either patients or midwives. The principal ingredients were nux vomica,
                     iodine, calomel, opium, <unclear>belladonna</unclear>, laurel-water aqua
                     phageda, aqua satur, emil canab, sulphuric acid, Fowler's solutions, and hyd.
                     mur. cor. These may be taken as specimens of the prescriptions, they were the
                     most legible:</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>1st. Unguentum kail, 4 scruples extr. opii and belladonna, equal ten grains:
                        2d Aqua saturnalia, 8 drachms; extr. opii, 1 oz; No. 3. Aqua phageda niger,
                        5 scruples</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MAKING A GOOD RECORD.</head>
                  <p>The following affidavit speaks for itself:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>"<hi rend="i"/>City and County of New York, ss.: Joseph Rosenzweig,
                                 of said city, being duly sworn, deposes and says that he is a
                                 regular practising physician of said city<pb
                                    n="48 (Illustration) -49" xml:id="VAC6545-00000017"/>
                                 <figure>
                                    <head>Opening of the MYSTERIOUS TRUNK, and horrible
                                       Discovery.</head>
                                    <p>
                                       <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Oeffnung des geheimnißvollen Koffers
                                          und schauderhafte Entdeckung.</foreign>
                                    </p>
                                 </figure> and has his office No. 687 Second avenue, in this city;
                                 that he has professionally treated James Muller for disease of the
                                 lungs, for some time past, and this deponent has advised him to
                                 leave the city during the summer months for Minnesota, as a
                                 residence in the city during the heated term would prove injurious
                                 to said Muller, and perhaps fatal in its results; that said
                                 deponent is informed that said Muller is now absent from the city
                                 for the benefit of his health, and will return in the fall.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>"J. ROSENZWEIG, M. D.,</signed>
                                 <address>
                                    <addrLine>"No. 687 Second avenue."</addrLine>
                                 </address>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>On the back of this attempt at whitewashing was the professional malpractice;
                     written in a feeble, straggling hand were these words:</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>"AGNETTA DUMAGU, East Henrietta, Monroe County, State of New York. This was
                        my birthplace—where I was born. and where once I was happy and free; but I
                        fell and now I am doomed to roam with Augur."</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>LEAF FROM ROSENZWEIG'S DIARY.</head>
                  <p>In an old diary of the doctor's were found the names of a number of patients
                     whom he had formally attended: Mrs. Johanna Piccon, No. 13 Bayard street, New
                     York; Mr. Grynberg, No. 74 Warren street, near Chambers; Mrs. Workman, No. 28
                     Chrystie street; Mrs Bernstein, of Poughkeepsie, N. Y., with directions in
                     Polish, written after name; Mrs. Smith, Seventh avenue, corner Forty-ninth
                     street; Mrs. Caufman, No. 203 Division, near Clinton street; Mrs. Samuel
                     Harris, Nashville, Tenn. Then followed a number of receipts for money from
                     gentlemen who payed for the relief extended to patients. Mr. Levy, No. 224
                     Greene street, $20, dated 1st January, 1866; Mr. Peck, No. 75 Hester street,
                     $25; Mr. Samue, No. 183 Clinton street, $20; Mr. Fischer, No. 41 Walker street,
                     $15. Here again we append the names and addresses of more female patients; Mrs.
                     Harper, No. 31 Chrystie street, May 1st, 1866; Mrs. Thon, No. 135 Sixth street;
                     Mrs. Dayment, No. 144 Seventh avenue, corner Twentieth street; Mrs. Jacobson,
                     No. 411 Houston street, store; another name, whether of male or female, it is
                     difficult to state; S. Ascher, No. 44 Allen street; and the names of the
                     families followed; Mrs. Graham, No. 213 Seventeenth street, Avenue A and First
                     avenue; Mrs. Morris, who appears in three different places as a patient; in
                     one, she requests the "doctor" to call at No. 115 Chatham street, second floor;
                     afterward, at No. 62 Orchard street, and No. 43 Norfolk street.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE DAY IN THE STATION-HOUSE.</head>
                  <p>Although Dr. Rosenzweig must have many acquaintances in this city, Scarcely any
                     paid him a visit of condolence last Wednesday. A few did call, but it would
                     have been better for Dr. Rosenzweig, alias Ascher, if they had never taken it
                     into their heads to see him at all. One person, a gentleman whose name was not
                     ascertained, recognized in him a person whom he had engaged to attend his wife,
                     then suffering from a feminine disorder. He almost killed the woman through
                     ignorance, and was kicked down stairs and outdoors for his rascally assurance.
                        Another<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6545-00000018"/> person, a Jew, who had
                     known the man formerly, waited on him in the hope of eliciting something like
                     the truth; but he was greeted with doleful looks and flat denial. "These
                     people," said Ascher, in whining tones, "know I am a Jew, and believe me to be
                     rich, and want to extract it from me by prosecution. That is why I have been
                     seized and incarcerated. I assure you, sir, I never met or saw the truckman in
                     my life before. I am, in fact, perfectly innocent." His only other visitor was
                     his counsel who administered what consolation he could. It was a dismal day for
                     the wretched man, who sat in his cell listening to the pelting rain with a
                     countenance as dark as the lowering heavens without. He was miserable and very
                     nervous. Not so Jane Johnson, the servant girl, with whom our reporter had a
                     very interesting conversation. She roamed about the station-house, and
                     conversed freely, feeling no alarm at her position.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>WAS JANE JOHNSON A PATIENT?</head>
                  <p>The servant girl is apparently about twenty-seven years old. She is a brunette,
                     and rather good looking. She entered the back room while the reporters were
                     examing the captive, when going to the cooler, she took a drink of water. At
                     this point a reporter called her and told her to sit down beside him. She did
                     so, and fixing her black eyes steadily upon him, waited.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Are you sure you told all you could remember of the transition in
                     Rosenzweig's house to Mr. Brennan?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I am, sir; perfectly sure.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—How long have you been there?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—A little over three months.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Where is your husband?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Dead.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—How long, Jane?</p>
                  <p>Jane (with downcast eyes).—Over six years.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Where did you live before you came to the doctor's?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Out West.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—What part of the West?</p>
                  <p>Jane (breaking down).—Oh! I would rather die than tell you, for, did you know
                     it, the newspapers would have the whole story of my shame, and my brother and
                     son would both hear of it. No! No! I would kill myself rather than tell
                     you.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Well, well, I won't press you. But surely you can say when and why
                     you left them?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I got into my present trouble about eight months ago, and when I could no
                     longer keep it a secret, I resolved to come to New York until all was over. My
                     folks did not know of my coming, nor did they hear from me since I came.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—How did you learn of Dr. Rosenzweig's existence, and how did you come
                     to enter his house?</p>
                  <p>Jane (embarrassed).—Oh! I heard—that is—I—ah—Mrs. Rosenzweig and I were
                     acquainted before I came to this city</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—For how long?</p>
                  <p>Jane (confusedly).—A month or two.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Had you met her anywhere?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Oh, no, sir. I heard from—of her.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—And came to New York to meet her, eh?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—No.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Where were you hired as Mrs. R's servant?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—At her house, of course.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Who brought you there?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I went myself.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Why to her?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Because I wanted to live in a doctor's house until my trouble was
                     over.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Wanted to get rid of it?</p>
                  <p>Jane (indignantly).—No, I didn't want to get rid of it; I only wished to be
                     with somebody who could take care of me while I was in a dangerous
                     condition.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Then you took service with this man because you desired his help?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Not help, care.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Oh! I see. He was good to have hired a person in your condition, care
                     for her, and give her wages too. Don't you think so?</p>
                  <p>Jane—It's the truth, if I was to die this minute.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Well to go back: where were you when the carman got the trunk from
                     the doctor on Saturday?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—He got no trunk from the doctor.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—How do you know?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Because he was out all day.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—And Mrs. Rosenzweig?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—She was not well.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Had she been confined lately?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I believe so.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—When was she out of doors first after that event?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Oh! three or four times. During the week before Saturday she went out for
                     a walk.</p>
                  <p>The remainder of the conversation would be uninteresting to the reader. Suffice
                     it to say that the girl, after crying a good deal, "weakened some what," to use
                     a police term, and acknowledged, in addition to the foregoing that "the trunk
                     might have been taken out," but she would not say positively that it had; she
                     never had observed anything wrong in the establishment and never knew of any
                     blonde having been there as a patient. The result of this interview might have
                     been summed up in a few words. Jane Johnson was a country girl, who, having
                     been seduced, left her brother<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6545-00000019"/> who,
                     she says, is worth some money, and came to New York, and to Rosenzweig's to
                     destroy the evidence of her folly. The manner of doing so can only be inferred.
                     Also she confessed that Mrs. Rosenzweig had been out much before the time she
                     confessed to the authorities she had, and then, despite her point-blank
                     assertions in the negative heretofore, she admits that a trunk may have been
                     given to a carman on Saturday. It is probable that Rosenzweig will be in Sing
                     Sing Prison ere many suns roll round, beginning the fullest term of service
                     allotted by the law to his crime, which is manslaughter in the second degree
                     under the law. There <unclear>are</unclear> several minor points yet to be
                     solved, but the case is now complete in legal proof, and Inspector Walling does
                     not consider it necessary to make any further effort.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>FINAL DISAPPEARANCE OF MISS ALICE BOWLSBY FROM HER NEWARK FRIENDS.</head>
                  <p>On Monday Miss Bowlsby was reported at Police Headquarters to have disappeared
                     from the house of her aunt in Newark the Wednesday before. No special
                     importance, however, was at first attached to this circumstance in connection
                     with the trunk mystery, and beyond the taking of an accurate description of the
                     girl at the time of her disappearance, as is done in the cases of all missing
                     persons who are reported at headquarters, no attention was paid to the matter.
                     But on the following Thursday, this description of the girl as she left the
                     residence of her aunt, Mrs. Harriet L. Williams, No. 80 Belmont avenue, Newark,
                     had not only a sad interest, but in some of its parts is vitally important to
                     the ends of justice.</p>
                  <p>She was a young girl whose life had apparently never been darkened, and upon
                     whom the breath of suspicion had never fallen. Moving in respectable society,
                     and having relatives in the highest circles, she was everywhere received as an
                     ornament and a delight. Having a most amiable character, elegant in her
                     manners, possessed of vivacity and good conversational powers, she was a
                     favorite everywhere and especially among her male friends. Her rare beauty
                     surrounded her with many devoted admirers. Her rarely regular features, clear
                     complexion, blue eyes, profusion of light auburn hair, little figure and
                     graceful carriage, made her marked among women for her personal attractions.
                     When she left the home of Mrs. Williams on Wednesday these charms were
                        <unclear>heightened</unclear> by the simple elegance of her costume. She had
                     on a white lawn dress, tucked and ruffled, a blue sash and ribbon around the
                     waist, a white straw hat trimmed with blue ribbons and flowers, a light shawl
                     striped brown and red, a brown parasol, a black satchel or hand bag, such as
                     ladies usually carry. She wore also a gold chain and locket, the latter
                     containing a miniature of her mother, and she had in her pocket a portmonnaie,
                     in which were several visiting cards. Saying to Mrs. Williams and her mother,
                     who was also visiting that lady, that she was going home to Paterson by the way
                     of New York she gayly tripped away, waving her adieu with her handkerchief
                     which was to be the chief means of fastening the clutches of the law upon her
                     murderer exactly one week later. She was never seen alive again by any of her
                     relatives, and for a time her fate was a profound mystery. But even the fact of
                     her disappearance was not known until after she had become the prey of the
                     abortionist and, packed in the narrow compass of that trunk, her remains had
                     been gazed upon by thousands. Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, and Saturday she was
                     not missed in the circle where she was so dearly prized. Her mother, who
                     remained with Mrs. Williams, supposed she was at home, and her relatives in
                     Paterson, who had not heard of her departure from Newark, believed that she was
                     still with her aunt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>LITTLE ROSA.</head>
                  <p>On Thursday Captain Cameron arrested Rosa, the daughter, hoping to elicit
                     something from her about the person who had transferred the trunk from the
                     house to the depot. Soon Rosa was brought in as a kind of prisoner at large,
                     and was permitted to occupy the captain's room, where she sat by the window
                     reading most of the morning. The doctor was not quite as comfortable as he had
                     been. He was much more irritable than he was the day before. He stared at
                     anybody who approached him with a desire to chat. The Jew peddler was also
                     among the unfortunates again. He had been released, but was rearrested on
                     Thursday, by order of the Inspector, and lodged with his friends at the
                     station-house all night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>DECEASED'S AUNT IDENTIFIES HER.</head>
                  <p>In the forenoon of Thursday, a lady drove up to the station-house in a close
                     carriage. She was shown into the captain's private room, and had a long talk
                     with him, in which she disclosed the fact that she was Mrs. Barriet L.
                     Williams, of No. 80 Bellmont avenue, Newark, N. J., and the aunt of Alice
                     Bowlsby, who had been staying at her house previous to her departure for New
                     York last Wednesday. She said that she believed that from what she had gleaned
                     concerning her niece's habits that Walter F. Conklin, of Paterson, was the
                     seducer. She then drove to the Morgue and identified her niece. Thence she
                     returned with a detective to the Central Office, and had an interview with the
                     Inspector, to whom she repeated her story.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>JANE JOHNSON'S CONFESSION AT LAST.</head>
                  <p>At last the ends of justice seemed to be nearly attained. The servant girl
                     confessed. She was removed to Bellevue Hospital on Wednesday night, as her
                     condition demanded it, and the kindly offices of Warden Brennan were calculated
                     to break down her obstinacy. On Thursday he was pre-eminently successful.
                     Calling on her during the day, he obtained the following statement from her: On
                     Wednesday, a young lady came in by the parlor door of No. 687 Second avenue,
                     and went into the<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6545-00000020"/> doctor's room. He
                     took her up stairs to a private room on the second floor. Before she entered,
                     the doctor had run in by the basement door, in a very great hurry, and met her
                     as she entered. Before taking her up to the other room, he came to the kitchen
                     and looked in at me. Then he retired, and shut the door after him. Immediately
                     I opened it a little, and peeped out. There I saw the pair—doctor and young
                     lady—going up the stairs. I remember the white lawn over-skirt looped up
                     behind. She remained above during the evening, so far as I can judge, for,
                     indeed, I never heard her go out. I asked Rosa, the doctor's daughter, who she
                     was, and she said it was a patient who had called to see her father. I wanted
                     to know if she had gone away the previous night, and Miss Rosa replied: "Oh!
                     yes, she went away last night." "What," said I, "in all the rain?" "Yes," said
                     Rosa, "her friends came with a coach, and, wrapping her up comfortably, took
                     her away." "I should have thought there was danger of her taking cold." "Not at
                     all," said Rosa. The first day that the lady was in the house Rosa went up
                     stairs and remained there a long time. Her mother went up afterward, and came
                     back to the kitchen in a short time to make a cup of tea, she said. This
                     draught, made by herself, she handed to Rosa, who took it to the upper chamber.
                     From what I could see, Miss Rosa and her mother waited on the lady. I did not
                     mistrust anything, and, indeed, believed all was right, when Miss Rosa told me
                     she had gone home with her friends. On Saturday Mrs. Rosenzweig told me to
                     hurry up with my work, as she wanted me to get through by noon and take the
                     children out to walk. This was such an unusual proceeding that I was delighted,
                     and did my best to get ready. Miss Rosa went out at noon, and was absent about
                     an hour and a half, returning at 1.30 o'clock. I remember nothing more of the
                     circumstances until I recognized the comforter and baby's diaper, which were
                     found in the trunk, as being the property of the Rosenzweig family. The other
                     articles I never saw before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE VICTIM'S PATERSON HOME AND HER PREVIOUS LIFE—SUICIDE OF HER ALLEGED
                     SEDUCER.</head>
                  <p>The city of Paterson was intensely exiced last Thursday, first by the
                     announcement in the morning papers that the victim was a Paterson girl, and
                     later in the day by the report that the young man who had kept company with her
                     before her disappearance had taken his own life, through fear of exposure and
                     punishment.</p>
                  <p>At about 7 o'clock the news of the identification of Miss Bowlsby's remains was
                     broken to her widowed mother by Drs. Parker and Kinne, who on the evening
                     preceding had identified the body at the Morgue. The grief of the mother and
                     the younger sisters was too terrible for words to express, a sense of disgrace
                     and shame mingling with their sorrow for the loss of one whom they had loved as
                     innocent and pure. For an entire<pb n="56 (Illustration) -57"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000021"/>
                     <figure>
                        <head>The Detectives enter Rosenzweig's house in search of the
                           "Doctor."</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Die Geheimpolizisten dringen in Rosenzweigs Haus,
                              als sie den "Doktor" suchten.</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure> week they had been in suspense, waiting for the news of Alice. Eight
                     days previous she had left the house of her aunt. Mrs. <unclear>Elizabeth
                        L.</unclear> Williams, in Newark, to return to her mother's house
                        <unclear>in Paterson.</unclear> She did not arrive home on the day fixed and
                     inquiries were sent to Newark, for information of her. Word was returned that
                     she had left Mrs. Williams' house, where she had been staying about three
                     weeks, and ought to have arrived home on the preceding day. Then the search for
                     the missing girl commenced. Her uncle Mr. Charles E. Sandford, of Broadway,
                     Paterson her cousins. Henry Sandford and John Williams, of Newark; and D. Kinne
                     the family physician gave nearly all their time for several days is endeavoring
                     to trace her. A visit by young Sandford to the Morgue gave the first faint hope
                     of success in finding her or learning her fate. He thought he recognized the
                     body of the then unknown murdered girl, and the subsequent identification by
                     Drs. Parker and Kinne, whom he <unclear>induced</unclear> to come to the
                     Morgue, proved the correctness of his supposition.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE BEREAVED FRIENDS AND HOME.</head>
                  <p>The information was unexpected to Mrs. Bowlsby on Thursday morning, when she
                     was informed of the identification of the body, for neither young Sandford nor
                     the doctors had hinted their suspicions regarding the body at the Morgue to the
                     bereaved mother. Friends and acquaintances dropped in to console her and the
                     two young daughters in their terrible affliction. Occasionally a small crowd
                     would gather in the street to look at the dwelling where the poor girl had
                     spent the last years of her life. It is a small, two-story brick house,
                     situated on West street, bearing the sign, "Mrs. Bowlsby, Dressmaking," in
                     small, gilt letters. To this house the family removed ten years ago from
                     Parsippany, upon the death of Mr. Bowlsby. Mrs. Bowlsby, with her three
                     daughters, worked at dressmaking, Alice having been employed recently in an
                     establishment at No. 163 Main street, over the office of Drs. Parker and Kinne.
                     Alice and her sisters were esteemed by all who knew them, and not only Alice's
                     mother, but all her acquaintances, believed her to be strictly virtuous. In
                     answer to inquiries made on Thursday morning, the friends of the family stated
                     that they could not say who was the seducer of Alice; they suspected a young
                     man whose name would not be given until the inquest should be held. Dr. Parker
                     was reluctant to give any information except that the murdered girl was well
                     known to him as a pure, high-minded girl, whom he would never have suspected
                     under any circumstances. He thought he could identify the man who had wronged
                     her, but he believed that she had gone there alone, and that the man whom he
                     suspected had nothing to do with the murder. The doctor exhibited a photograph
                     of the deceased, a well-formed and intelligent looking blonde, with bright
                     eyes, full lips and smiling face. The photograph agreed with the description
                     given of her by the doctor and other friends of the deceased, and would<pb
                        n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6545-00000022"/> indicate that she was what they
                     pronounced her to be—a joyous good-natured girl, free of manner and fond of
                     amusement, who had friends wherever she was known.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE GIRL'S DESTROYER.</head>
                  <p>Many stories were carried from one to another, giving the names of Miss
                     Bowlsby's male friends. But it was, however, learned, by the statements of Mrs.
                     Williams, of Newark, that Walter F. Conklin, the son of Alderman Conklin, had
                     been very much attached to her, and had visited her at Mrs. Williams' house in
                     Newark, three days before Alice left for New York. Mrs. Williams did not
                     hesitate to say that he was responsible for Alice's misfortune. At 1 o'clock
                     all the city was convinced that this supposition was correct. At that hour
                     young Conklin committed suicide in Dale's Silk Mill, where he was employed.
                     Conklin arrived at the mill early on Thursday morning, looking pale and
                     nervous. He remained at his desk during the forenoon, conversing but little,
                     and when spoken to concerning the absorbing sensation caused by the reports in
                     the morning papers, he spoke of it as a matter of no consequence to him. At
                     noon he did not go to dinner according to custom. While the other clerks were
                     at dinner, one of the men employed in the mill heard the report of a pistol. He
                     ran immediately to the office, but found no one, and continued his search,
                     going into the large fire-proof room, where the most valuable silks were
                     stored. On the floor he found Conklin's prostrate form. Blood was flowing from
                     a wound back of the left ear, where the bullet entered. A revolver was found on
                     the floor beside him. The man dragged the body out into the office and sent for
                     physicians, at the same time sending information also to Alderman Conklin. When
                     the physicians arrived they found that the wound was fatal, the ball having
                     passed through to the temple, where it lodged. The dying man did not move.
                     Within half an hour he was dead. Coroner Butterworth was immediately summoned
                     and viewed the body. In one of the pockets was found the following note in
                     young Conklin's handwriting:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>I have long had a morbid idea of the worthlessness of life, and now
                                 to be obliged to testify in this affair and cause unpleasantness in
                                 my family is more than life is worth. Good by, dear father, mother,
                                 brother and sister.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>WALT.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>In his pocket a card was found on which was written, in his own hand "115 E.
                     24th st."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>INQUEST ON THE SUICIDE.</head>
                  <p>Coroner Butterworth immediately impanelled a jury and commenced an inquest. The
                     testimony of the physician, the workmen at the mill, and others cognizant of
                     facts connected with the shooting, was taken, after which the jury rendered a
                     verdict that the deceased came to his death by his own hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>INTERVENING MOVEMENTS.</head>
                  <p>About Miss Bowlsby's movements, after she left Mrs. Williams' house in Newark,
                     but little can be learned. Her mother, who went to Newark with her, returned
                     home. She left Alice only money enough to pay her fare from Newark to Paterson.
                     When she left Mrs. Williams' house, at <unclear/> o'clock on Wednesday before
                     her death, she had only eighty cents. She could not therefore have paid Dr.
                     Rosenzweig the amount which he would be likely to have demanded. Somebody must
                     have accompanied her, <unclear>or</unclear> have gone before her and paid for
                     the doctor's services.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SHE WAS SEEN IN NEW YORK.</head>
                  <p>On Monday, the 21st inst., Miss Bowlsby was met in company with another
                     Paterson woman by Mr. Wm. J. Healey, of No. 82 Main street, Paterson. Mr.
                     Healey states that he met Alice twice in Broadway, near St. Paul's Church. The
                     woman who accompanied her he knew, but cannot remember her name. It is thought
                     probable that Miss Bowlsby went to New York without giving her aunt any
                     intimation of her movements on Monday, and that this woman helped to make the
                     arrangements with her. From the circumstances of the case, it is certain that
                     young Conklin furnished the money, but whether it was he who inquired in New
                     York on Saturday if the trunk had been sent up the river, cannot be known at
                     present. Conklin was known to have gone to New York on Saturday, returning in
                     the evening. He had money. His father is one of the owners of the Dale Silk
                     Mill where young Conklin worked, and the latter drew a good salary as
                     book-keeper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SAD COINCIDENCES AND CIRCUMSTANCES.</head>
                  <p>On Wednesday evening, while Drs. Parker and Kinne were looking at the remains
                     of Alice in New York, Mrs. Bowlsby and young Conklin were conversing about her
                     in Paterson. Conklin called to inquire if anything had been heard from her, and
                     appeared to be concerned for her safety Mrs. Bowlsby, who was almost crazy with
                     alarm for her daughter's safety suggested that the body found in the trunk
                     might be hers. Conklin said "Oh, no; that couldn't be Alice." Conklin was about
                     twenty years old—the same age as his victim. He had visited Miss Bowlsby for
                     over two years. He went to Europe last year, but returned in September,
                     resuming upon his return his intimacy with her. He was a young man of good
                     appearance, tall and well-proportioned, and dressed with scrupulous neatness.
                     In the mills where he worked no one knew of his acquaintance with Alice
                     Bowlsby, and with the sad news of the suicide came the first intimation to Mr.
                     Conklin, sr., of his son's intimacy with the murdered girl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6545-00000023"/>
                  <head>THE INQUEST AT BELLEVUE HOSPITAL.</head>
                  <p>The inquest <unclear>on</unclear> the body of Alice Augusta Bowlsby was held on
                     Friday by Coroner Schirmer at Bellevue Hospital. The following jury was
                     empanelled: Samuel W. Baldwin, No, 162 West Forty-fourth street; Charles
                     McLacklin, No. 11 Park Bow; Welcome Alexander, Bellevue Hospital; Adolph B.
                     George, No. 118 Third avenue; Duncan C. Lee, Bellevue Hospital; Thomas C.
                     Wilson, No. 107 King street; Peter G Standish, No. 853 Third avenue. At about
                     10 A. M. Rosenzweig was Brought in, accompanied by his counsel, Mr. Howe. He
                     was a little paler han usual, and somewhat nervous in his behaviour. A large
                     number of spectators were present, and others crowded around the doors to hear
                     the testimony. Before beginning to hear the examination, Coroner Schirmer took
                     out the jurors to view the body, which was then only a loathsome, putrid mass
                     of flesh. The first witness called was Dr. Theodore Y. Kinne, a practising
                     physician in Paterson, New Jersey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF DR. KINNE.</head>
                  <p>Q. Go on, doctor, and tell what you know-about this case. A. My attention was
                     first drawn to this case by seeing the reports in the Sunday and Monday papers
                     of this city, coupled with the fact that a young lady patient of mine had
                     mysteriously disappeared; the resemblance to this person in the account led me
                     to suspect that the two were identical; I consulted with Dr. Parker, a dentist
                     occupying rooms in the same building, No. 163 Main street, and, on Tuesday
                     morning, the 29th, I came to Bellevue Hospital to view the body; the warden
                     directed me to the room, where I found the corpse with only the face and head
                     exposed; I found two marks upon the face which seemed to justify my suspicion,
                     one being a scar upon the right side of the jaw, and the missing right eye
                     tooth; I think I had with me the photographs of the young lady for whom I was
                     searching, which I showed to the warden, to see if he could detect any
                     similarity between them and the body the day it was found; he was not satisfied
                     with the resemblance, and I returned to Paterson for further proof; in company
                     with Dr. Parker, I visited Mrs. Bowlsby, the mother of the girl, and obtained
                     other evidence which would be conclusive; Wednesday afternoon, the 30th, I
                     visited Bellevue Hospital with Dr. Parker and on presenting the proofs to
                     Warden Brennan we were permitted to view the body, and identified it fully as
                     Miss Alice Augusta Bowlsby.</p>
                  <p>Q. What proofs? A. The scar on the right side of the jaw, and a nole upon the
                     left side of the neck, and the vaccination mark below the elbow of the left
                     arm; the Warden, being satisfied, took us to Captain Cameron at the Eighteenth
                     Precinct Station-house, and from there to Police Headquarters; we then returned
                     to the Eighteenth Precinct, and went from there to No. 687 Second avenue, if
                     possible to identify the clothing worn by the young lady we found but one
                     article which we could positively identify: a cambric hem-stitched handkerchief
                     was found by Detective Larne, and identified by a mark placed upon it by him,
                     and by the name in the opposite corner, "A. A. Bowlsby;" there was also a blue
                     sash found, which corresponded with the article worn when she left; that was
                     all we could identify, and we returned to the station-house and went home to
                     Paterson; I have attended the family; attended the young lady for five years;
                     longer than the rest; for common diseases, such as intermittent fever and
                     inflammation of the lungs.</p>
                  <p>Q. Has she consulted you lately? A. I think she visited me on the
                        <unclear>1st</unclear> of June, and I gave her some medicine; I think it was
                     for menstrual derangements.</p>
                  <p>Q. Did you ever know her to be in the family way? A. No, sir.</p>
                  <p>Q. Had you any suspicion of it? A. No, sir, for the reason that } had treated
                     her so lately for difficulties arising in a manner that I knew she was not.</p>
                  <p>Q. This body that you have seen a little while ago is it the same body of Alice
                     Augusta Bowlsby? A. I think it is.</p>
                  <p>Q. (By a juror): Have you any doubt of it? A. None at all.</p>
                  <p>Q. (By a juror): Is it frequent to vaccinate persons under the elbow on the
                     left arm? A. I never saw but one other case, and that was of a lady who did it
                     herself; it is very rare.</p>
                  <p>Q. (By a juror): Did you vaccinate this young lady? A. No, sir, she was
                     vaccinated when an infant. Q. Do you know that she was vaccinated in the left
                     arm below the elbow? A. Yes, sir.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF DR. JOSEPH F. PARKER.</head>
                  <p>Witness.—I am a doctor in Paterson; I am not in business for myself; my
                     attention was first called to this affair by the murdered girls mother sending
                     to my house for me on Sunday; they informed me that their daughter had been
                     missing since Wednesday, when she left Newark for New York on the 9 o'clock
                     train; the mother was in great distress of mind; and wanted to know what was
                     best to do; I advised her to remain quiet for a few days, and see if we did not
                     hear from the girl, as she might possibly be detained on the road; when I heard
                     about the finding of a murdered girl in the trunk, I thought it a strange
                     coincidence, as the description of the body applied so nearly to the appearance
                     of Miss Bowlsby then Dr. Kinne asked me if I was willing to go with him the
                     following afternoon and view the body, and see if we could identify it; I was
                     omewhat familiar with the condition of her teeth, having operated on hem for
                     her two or three years ago; we went to Bellevue and saw the body, and
                     identified it from the filling of the upper teeth on the right upper jaw, and
                     also by the broken eye-tooth on the right side; she consulted me about three
                     months ago in regard to the removal of that eye-tooth; I examined the root of
                     it, and was of the opinion that it should be pulled, and I suggested putting
                     one in its place; the form of the eve-tooth as I<pb n="62-63"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000024"/> saw it the other day was the same as when I
                     viewed it three months ago, with no perceptible change in its appearance.</p>
                  <p>Q. Did you recognize the body by any other marks? A. I recognized it from a
                     cicatrized ulcer on the right lower jaw from inflammation caused by a bad
                     tooth, owing to its having been lanced on the side; it caused a slight
                     depression in the bone.</p>
                  <p>Q. What about identifying the articles of clothing? A. I can only corroborate
                     Dr. Kinne in the matter of the handkerchief and sash.</p>
                  <p>Q. Is the body you have just now seen the same that you identified? A. It
                     is.</p>
                  <p>Q. What is the reason that you did not mention to Mrs. Bowlsby your
                     apprehension that the victim of the murder and her daughter were identical? A.
                     From motives of delicacy, because I had never believed the young lady would do
                     as she did.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF WILLIAM PICKETT, THE CARMAN.</head>
                  <p>Witness.—I am a carman, and reside at No. 471 First avenue; my stand is at
                     Twenty-ninth street and First avenue; on Saturday afternoon, after 1 o'clock, I
                     was hired by a young woman, who came up to the stand and asked me how much I
                     would charge to take a trunk from Thirty-seventh street and Second avenue to
                     the Hudson River depot; I told her one dollar; she offered me half a dollar,
                     and I would not take it; she then asked me if I could change a $5 bill; I told
                     her no, and she went into a liquor store at the corner, and came out and told
                     me she could not get it changed; I told her I could; I took the bill and went
                     and changed it; I came right back and gave her $4, keeping the $1 myself; she
                     asked me if I would go right away for the trunk; she was going to Paterson, and
                     wanted the trunk taken away right off; she was going to hire a carriage and
                     would be to the depot before me and wanted me to go to No. 687 Second avenue; I
                     wrote the number down myself; she told me to go to the basement and ring the
                     bell and I would be given the trunk; I would not go on those terms without
                     getting her real name, because I was afraid I might not get the trunk at all;
                     she told me her name was Julia Sidney, and I wrote down her name on the same
                     card; I went then to this house, rang the basement bell, and a man opened the
                     door and stepped back while I stepped in; I told him that a girl named Julia
                     Sidney sent me after a trunk; there was a woman sitting in the inside who asked
                     me where I was going; I told her that Julia Sidney told me not to tell: I found
                     the trunk in the front basement, inside the door; the man inside assisted me to
                     put the trunk on my truck; then he went right in again; didn't speak to me at
                     all.</p>
                  <p>Q. Could you recognize the man? A. Yes, sir.</p>
                  <p>Q. Do you see him here now? A. Yes, sir; that is the man sitting right there,
                     only he looks paler now than he did then, to the best of my knowledge; (the
                     witness pointed to Rosenzweig, who muttered some inaudible words to his
                     counsel, Mr. Howe, and appeared considerably perturbed). I then took the trunk
                     to the depot and returned to my stand.</p>
                  <pb n="64 (Illustration) -65" xml:id="VAC6545-00000025"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>ARREST OF DR. JACOB ROSENZWEIG.</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Arretirung des Dr. Jacob Rosenzweig.</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. Did you perceive any smell from the trunk?</p>
                  <p>A. No, sir; I formed no suspicion, and didn't smell it; when I got to the depot
                     I saw this Julia Sidney standing there; Julia Sidney assisted me with it; then
                     the boy helped me in with the trunk; the boy and Julia Sidney took one end of
                     the trunk and I the other, and we put it upon the counter; she looked at the
                     lock and said the trunk was not strong enough, and she asked for a rope, and
                     they had no rope but had a strap; some body asked her if she know the price of
                     the strap, and she said she would pay $1 for it.</p>
                  <p>Q. Have you seen the trunk since? A. Yes, sir, in Warden Brennan's charge, and
                     I recognize it as the trunk I carried to the depot that day.</p>
                  <p>Q. Are you able to give a description of that young lady? A. No. sir.</p>
                  <p>Q. (By a juror): What was it that Julia Sidney requested you not to tell? A. If
                     any one asked me where I was taking the trunk not to tell them.</p>
                  <p>Several other witnesses were called directly after the foregoing, including the
                     boy, Alexander Potts, who met the strange woman with the trunk at the depot;
                     but nothing new or additional to that heretofore given was elicited from them.
                     We may add, however, from the</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>BOY POTTS</head>
                  <p>the following scrap:</p>
                  <p>Q. Was she dressed like a servant? A. Yes.</p>
                  <p>Q. Did you see the trunk again? A. I saw it before it was taken from the depot;
                     I saw the body in it.</p>
                  <p>Q. Did you hear her say anything in particular to the truckman? No, sir.</p>
                  <p>Q. Was there any stench coming from the trunk? A. No, sir, I didn't smell
                     anything.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF THE BAGGAGE-MASTER</head>
                  <p>Frank Dunning, the baggage-master at the Hudson River Railroad depot, testified
                     that the woman who checked the trunk stated to him that she must have a strap,
                     as the trunk was weak; I put a strap around it; and nailed it on; there was no
                     name or address on the trunk; I checked it for Chicago, and wrote "Chicago" on
                     it; I was present when the trunk was opened, and saw the body</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF ROSENZWEIG'S SERVANT GIRL</head>
                  <p>Jane Johnson testified that she had been living at "Dr." Rosenzweig's house,
                     No. 687 Second avenue, three months, doing general housework; am a widow; my
                     husband has been dead six years; I have received ten dollars a month wages.</p>
                  <p>Q. Do you remember about a certain young lady coming there on<pb n="66-67"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000026"/> Wednesday or Thursday of last week? A. I saw a
                     young woman there then in the afternoon; saw her going up stairs, and that is
                     all I saw of her; did not see her face at all, and don't know how she looks;
                     she had on a white dress. (The blue sash was shown to the witness, but she
                     stated that she never saw it.)</p>
                  <p>Q Have you seen anything here in the hospital that you can identify as being at
                     that house? A. Yes, sir; I have seen a comforter, a small piece of muslin, and
                     a diaper.</p>
                  <p>Q. Did the doctor sometimes have patients there? A. Yes, sir.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF DR. CUSHMAN.</head>
                  <p>Deputy Coroner Cushman testified that he had made a post-mortem examination of
                     the body; he found the womb large, and evidence that a fœtus had been expelled;
                     there was a laceration, which was probably produced by some sharp instrument;
                     death, in his opinion, had been caused by metro-peritonitis, the result of an
                     abortion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF WARDEN BRENNAN.</head>
                  <p>Warden Brennan corrobarated the testimony already given in regard to the carman
                     Pickett's story, and testified that he was present when the body of the girl
                     was identified, and also when the woman Johnson identified the comforter which
                     had been taken from the trunk.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF J. D. LARNE.</head>
                  <p>John D. Larne testified—I am a policeman of the Eighteenth Precinct; on
                     Wednesday evening last I went to No. 687 Second avenue with some keys for Capt.
                     Cameron; he met me at the door, and we began a search through the house for
                     some trace of the young lady; we went into the back basement, where there were
                     two wash-tubs; in one of these I found a handkerchief marked "A. A. Bowlsby."
                     (Witness then identified a handkerchief shown him by the coroner as the one he
                     found.)</p>
                  <p>Coroner Schirmer at this point asked the jury if they were prepared, with the
                     testimony they had heard, to bring in a verdict, or would they prefer to hear
                     further evidence. The jury replying through their foreman that the testimony
                     had been abundant to enable them to reach a decision, the room was cleared, and
                     they retired for consultation. After ten minutes' deliberation they returned to
                     their seats, and the foreman read the following:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE VERDICT.</head>
                  <p>We find that Alice Augusta Bowlsby came to her death by metro-peritonitis, the
                     result of an abortion produced, as we believe from the testimony, by Jacob
                     Rosenzweig, between the 23d and 26th of August, 1871, at No. 687 Second
                     avenue.</p>
                  <p>Coroner Schirmer (turning to the prisoner, who arose).—You will
                        <unclear>act</unclear> your pleasure in answering the questions I am about
                     to ask you.</p>
                  <p>Mr. Howe.—He will answer any question you may ask him.</p>
                  <p>Q. What is your name? A. Jacob Rosenzweig.</p>
                  <p>Q. How old are you? A. Thirty-nine years.</p>
                  <p>Q. Of what nationality are you? A. I am a Pole.</p>
                  <p>Q. Where do you live? A. At No. 687 Second avenue.</p>
                  <p>Q. What is your business? A. I am a physician.</p>
                  <p>Q. You have heard the verdict of the jury; have you any answer to make against
                     the charge?</p>
                  <p>Mr. Howe.—The prisoner has a perfect answer to the accusation, and believes
                     that before the calm deliberations of a legal tribunal he can make a perfect
                     defence. He believes that a great deal of the testimony admitted here has been
                     illegally admitted; but with that you have nothing to do. In regard to the
                     atrocities and to this abortion charged upon him, he gives an emphatic denial,
                     and declares that he is not guilty.</p>
                  <p>The prisoner was then committed to the Tombs to await the action of the Grand
                     Jury.</p>
                  <p>The writ of <foreign xml:lang="LAT">habeas corpus</foreign> in favor of
                     Rosenzweig was not served on Friday, inasmuch as it was merely designed to
                     procure his release on bail in case the coroner had seen fit to postpone the
                     inquest. Another writ was obtained from Judge Jones with a view to secure the
                     discharge of Rosa Rosenzweig, the doctor's daughter, but the coroner released
                     her at the close of the investigation.</p>
                  <p>The police authorities endeavored to accumulate further evidence on Friday, but
                     without material success. Professional pride dictated that the woman who so
                     daringly guarded the trunk at the depot should be traced and arrested, but
                     further effort in this direction was generally felt to be useless. Not a clue
                     remained of the many that had been perseveringly followed to a disappointing
                     conclusion. A long search was made among Rosenzweig's relatives, but none were
                     found to resemble the woman described by the boy Potts.</p>
                  <p>The efforts to arrest Mrs. Rosenzweig were discontinued, it being very well
                     determined that she would testify only in her husband's defence. The testimony
                     of other witnesses was found to be needless, and the Jew peddler, arrested in
                     the house, was therefore discharged from custody.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE DESOLATED PATERSON HOMES.</head>
                  <p>Both the Bowlsby and Conklin houses were closed on Friday, and few except
                     sympathizing friends called upon the families. Walter F. Conklin's body was
                     placed in a coffin and removed on Thursday evening to his father's house at
                     Water and North Main streets, after the remains had been viewed by a great
                     number of the inhabitants of Paterson.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>DISCOVERY OF FURTHER LINKS IN THE CHAIN OF EVIDENCE.</head>
                  <p>More evidence proving the identity of Alice Bowlsby, and establishing the guilt
                     of the monster Rosenzweig, was discovered on Saturday. Sergeant<pb n="68-69"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000027"/> geant Rooney, in searching the house of
                     Rosenzweig, at No. 687 Second avenue, found a false bosom, such as is used by
                     women. Taking it, with other female wearing apparel, to the servant girl, Jane
                     Johnson, now at Bellevue Hospital, he asked Jane if it belonged to her. Jane
                     said that it did not, and was not in the house before the strange young lady
                     came. The bosom was taken back to the Eighteenth Precinct Station-house, and
                     Captain Cameron sent an officer to Paterson, to the home of the murdered girl,
                     to ascertain if the bosom had been her property. Her mother, Mrs Bowlsby,
                     identified it at once as having been made in her house, and worn by her
                     daughter. It will be used as circumstantial evidence against Rosenzweig.
                     Captain Cameron also sent the boy Potts, and the truckman William Pickett, to
                     identify a fortune-teller, Mrs. Bailey, in Paterson who was suspected to have
                     been the one who accompanied the trunk to the depot, and exhibited so much
                     coolness about the horrible business. The suspected woman, however, could not
                     be identified, and she has so far baffled every attempt at discovery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE ABORTIONIST'S BAYARD STREET HOUSE.</head>
                  <p>The neighborhood of the house, at No. 98 Bayard street, was visited by a
                     reporter last Saturday, and it being the Jewish Sabbath, the windows of the
                     butcher were closed, though the door was open. About a dozen persons, male and
                     female, were in front of the house, and through the open door of the shop the
                     wife of Rosenzweig, his daughter Rosa, mother, and brothers, were seen moving
                     about. Mrs. Rosenzweig had her bonnet on, as though she might have just come
                     in; and the daughter Rosa was smiling and showing no outward signs of sorrow
                     for the present rather uncomfortable position of her father. The drug-clerk, in
                     the store opposite, told the reporter that "Dr." Rosenzweig had frequently got
                     medicine there, always coming himself for it, but his employer being absent, he
                     could not tell what he got when he came. He said, also, that owing to the large
                     number of Polish Jews living in the neighborhood, Rosenzweig did a large
                     business in that vicinity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>FUNERAL OF WALTER CONKLIN.</head>
                  <p>On Saturday the funeral of Walter Conklin took place at the residence of his
                     father, No. 8 North Main street, Paterson. Only a few of the friends of the
                     family were present. Rev. Dr. Banvard, pastor of the First Baptist Church, to
                     which the family belong, preached the funeral sermon. The remains were placed
                     in the receiving vault of Cedar Lawn Cemetery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ROSENZWEIG'S GUILT</head>
                  <p>The chain of circumstantial evidence against "Dr." Jacob Rosenzweig, alias
                     Ascher, is very strong, but the unfortunate failure of the police to secure the
                     woman who engaged the truckman, Pickett, will leave the prosecution without any
                     witness who can positively swear that the accused cused performed the operation
                     which resulted in Alice Bowlsby's death. The principal points thus far
                     established are as follows:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>First. The discovery of the dead body with unmistakable
                     indications that an abortion had been committed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Second. The removal of the trunk containing the remains from the
                     house of Rosenzweig, on Second avenue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Third. The identification of Rosenzweig by the truckman as his
                        <unclear>assistant</unclear> in transferring the trunk from the basement to
                     the truck.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Fourth. The identification of the remains by the Paterson
                     physicians.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Fifth. The discovery of the sash and marked handkerchief in
                     Rosenzweig's house.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Sixth. The identification of the clothes in the trunk by the
                     servant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Seventh. Rosenzweig's application to the undertaker on Saturday
                     morning to bury a servant girl.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Eighth. Rosenzweig's bad character, suspicious practice, and
                     numerous aliases.</p>
                  <p>The non-identification of the remains was to have been made the principal point
                     in Rosenzweig's favor, but the appearance of the Paterson physicians demolished
                     that defence.</p>
                  <p>It is expected that the defence will now be based upon the absence of witnesses
                     to the abortion. Rosenzweig must have been instructed upon this point by his
                     counsel, as whenever he is pressed he exclaims: "Who saw me kill her? no one
                     saw me operate on her."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE REMAINS OF ALICE AUGUSTA.</head>
                  <p>The body of Alice Augusta Bowlsby was quietly buried on Hart's Island at 5
                     o'clock Saturday morning. Her friends sent word during the day asking that her
                     remains be forwarded to Paterson for interment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE BOY POTTS.</head>
                  <p>President Smith and Superintendent Kelso, in consideration of the aid which the
                     boy Potts has given the police, have opened an account for him in one of the
                     savings banks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A LINK OF EVIDENCE.</head>
                  <p>A valuable link in the evidence against Rosenzweig came to light in Newark, N.
                     J. It may be stated, <foreign xml:lang="FRA">en passant,</foreign> that the
                     case of the unfortunate Alice Bowlsby excites as much attention in Newark as in
                     New York, from the fact that she was quite well known there, had for years
                     lived there, and has near relatives now living there. On Sunday two gentlemen
                     called on a New York reporter in Newark, and stated that two years ago a lady
                     of the latter city, who was suffering greatly from a breast cancer, consulted a
                     female physician in New York, who advertised in the leading German paper of New
                     York as Madame Schwartz, of Henry street. By the latter she was referred to
                     "Dr" Ascher, alias<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6545-00000028"/> Rosenzweig, who
                     "treated" her case. Instead of growing better, however, she grew worse under
                     his care, and, after paying Ascher, alias Rosenzweig, nearly $300, she died.
                     This Madame Schwartz is described as being the exact counterpart of the woman
                     who conveyed the boxed-up body to the Hudson River Depot, and shipped it to
                     Chicago.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A GENERAL RETROSPECTION OF THE CRIME!</head>
               <head>MISTAKEN IDENTITY! WHAT HAS BECOME OF FIGA?</head>
               <head type="sub">THE UNKNOWN WOMAN AND THE TRUNK!</head>
               <p>There is many a true word spoken in jest, and "many a true story culled from a
                  fleeting rumor." The reader should know that the exact accounts, as given in the
                  previous pages of this pamphlet, were not known for some time after the occurrence
                  of this tragedy, and that during the first days of the excitement all sorts of
                  rumors were circulated and believed by the great majority. Still, it is not our
                  purpose to give here any of those rumors which scarcely contained plausibility,
                  but to place before the reader those rumors and side events which were not noticed
                  at the time, but which may yet explain and bring to light many things connected
                  with this sad affair, now under a cloud of mystery. To do this, it is necessary
                  that we go back to the first, that we make general and comprehensive
                  retrospection, and we can do so in no better manner than by commencing with the
                  coroner's inquest on the body of young Walter Conklin, of Paterson, N. J.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE INQUEST.</head>
                  <p>Coroner Abram Butterworth having been summoned took charge of the body, and it
                     was removed to the undertaker shop of J. W. Ensign, No. 271 Main street, and
                     placed on ice in a patent ice coffin in the back room of the shop. A large
                     crowd of persons visited the place during the afternoon and looked upon the
                     dead man's face. A jury was quickly summoned, and subpœnas were sent out for
                     the necessary witnesses. At 7 o'clock they had all gathered in the undertaker's
                     shop.</p>
                  <p>The jury were John Buckley, foreman, Enoch Dobson, John E. More house, Peter G.
                     Hopper, John Pettigrew, Isaac Condit, Robert Morris, Charles E. Noble, and
                     Charles E. Atherton. After taking the oath, and viewing the body by the light
                     of two kerosene lamps, the jury adjourned at 7 o'clock to a room in the
                     Paterson Opera House, almost directly across the street. The windows were
                     darkened, and nobody was allowed in the room but the reporters and the
                     witnesses.</p>
                  <p>Oswald Warner M. D., was the first witness. He testified as follows<pb
                        n="72 (Illustration) -73" xml:id="VAC6545-00000029"/>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Rosenzweig's cellar searched. Startling circumstantial evidence
                           against the accused.</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Rosenzweig's Keller durchsucht.
                              Schreckenerregender zufälliger Beweis gegen den Angeklagten.</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Sucide of Walter Conklin, of Paterson, N. J., lover of Miss Alice
                           Bowlsby.</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Selbstmord von Walter Conklin aus Paterson, N.
                              J., Geliebter von Alice Bowlsby.</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure> I was called to see deceased about 1 o'clock. I was coming down
                     Willet street, near State, and was asked to go and see a young man who had
                     burst a blood vessel in his ear; he was alive when I got there; I was asked to
                     go to Dale's mill; I found the man lying on the floor with blood and brains
                     issuing from his ear, and from the wound behind the ear; also little fragments
                     of bone; I was then told that he had shot himself; the wound was plainly such a
                     one as would be produced by a pistol shot he was in a hopeless condition, with
                     no opportunity of anything being done to save his life; he lived probably about
                     ten minutes after my arrival; he was entirely insensible; didn't speak at all;
                     after his death I passed my finger into the wound as far as I could and found
                     it penetrated the scalp and went upward, forward and toward the opposite side;
                     there was a prominence on the upper portion of the temple, which probably was
                     caused by the ball breaking the bone, but not having been sent with sufficient
                     force to break through; the wound was</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SUFFICIENT TO CAUSE DEATH,</head>
                  <p>and was undoubtedly the cause of death; his brother told me the reason of his
                     suicide was on account of some scandal; a number of people were standing
                     around, among them Dr. Terberry and Dr. Quinn; when I saw him he was not in the
                     vault but in the room back of the main office; I didn't see any weapon.</p>
                  <p>Mr. John Waltham, superintendent of the raw silk department in the mill, was
                     next sworn. He said: I went to work about fifteen minutes to 1 this afternoon.
                     A girl came to my house and told my wife that Conklin had shot himself. This
                     was between the time I left the mill and returned.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE BODY WAS IN THE BACK OFFICE</head>
                  <p>when I arrived. I had a conversation with him before the shooting, at fifteen
                     minutes past 12. I asked him what he thought of the trunk affair; his reply was
                     that it was rather mixed up; I asked him how it was so; he replied that
                     unfortunately he had been a visitor at the young lady's house, and he expected
                     that a report would come naturally to the mill; he did not say what report; I
                     asked him if the report affected him in the least; his reply was that it had
                     not; I asked him if he knew anything about the affair, and he gave me an
                     evasive answer; I noticed he was rather pale about fifteen minutes after eight,
                     the time the papers usually come; I had no other conversation with him on the
                     subject; I did not know him to be absent any time last week; he could not be
                     absent from the mill half a day without my knowing it; his brother called to
                     see him between 9 and 10 o'clock; I spoke to him merely out of curiosity.</p>
                  <p>Mr. John L. Conklin, the dead man's brother, arrived at this moment, and took
                     the witness stand. He is a tall, thin young man, with an emaciated face, a thin
                     mustache and dark hair. He was dressed in black, and</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6545-00000030"/>
                  <head>WORE A LARGE DIAMOND PIN.</head>
                  <p>He testified as follows.—I last saw my brother alive between 1 and 2; he was
                     dying at the time; I saw him also about 9 o'clock in the front office of Dale's
                     mill; I have been in the habit of calling there very seldom; I had a letter to
                     deliver to him to-day, which he considered very important; he spoke about it
                     many times; it was from Russia, and was written in the Russian language; I had
                     but one letter, and that was from Russia; I had some conversation with him
                     about the trunk affair this morning; I asked my brother if he had seen the
                     morning paper yet; he said, "Yes, it is terrible, isn't it?" My brother was
                     sitting at a desk, when I entered, writing; I first handed him the letter; I
                     replied, "Yes; it was." I told him I was sorry he was in the habit of calling
                     at the lady's house; I told him I was afraid he would be brought up also; he
                     said, "Yes; but that there had been a great many in the habit of calling at the
                     house." I said, "Yes, I supposed everybody who called at the house for the last
                     year would be brought up also." I told him there was thirty-one cents due on
                     the letter. He said, "All right." That was all; I was not talking with him ten
                     minutes; I think the portrait in the locket is that of</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A YOUNG LADY IN RUSSIA.</head>
                  <p>I heard him say it was his wife, in a joking way. He was as cheerful as usual,
                     except a slight depression on account of the letter from Russia, after he had
                     read a part of it. He had been expecting to go back to Russia during the last
                     six months.</p>
                  <p>Frederick S. Dale, the son of the proprietor of the mill, a very young man, was
                     the next witness.—I was absent when the shooting took place. I know nothing
                     about it; I had a conversation with Mr. Conklin; I came to the mill this
                     morning about 10; as I entered my small office he handed me the paper, pointing
                     to the trunk affair, and remarked what a horrible thing it was. He wished that
                     he hadn't been a caller at the young lady's house, as he supposed he would be
                     called as a witness. He remarked that it was an unpleasant thing, but that he
                     would be willing to face the music; that was his expression. That was all that
                     passed between us then. I asked him if he would go to dinner, and he remarked
                     that he would; he then said that all callers at the house would</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MOST LIKELY BE BROUGHT UP.</head>
                  <p>That was all that passed between us. He was not absent last week to my
                     knowledge; it he had been absent I would have heard of it; I was out of town
                     myself last week; somebody told me about Mr. Conklin's being absent; I spoke to
                     him about it, and he said he was absent last Sunday and the Sunday before. His
                     position was that of time-keeper; I don't know whether the record of Saturday
                     was in his hand or not; about his absence on Sunday he remarked that he was at
                     his cousin's; he could prove it, and it would be unpleasant to bring them into
                     it. Mr. Hurst or Mr. Dale, my brother, would know if he was absent on Saturday
                     or not; the time marks are made in pencil going through the factory, and
                     afterward copied in ink; some one else could have taken the time, and Conklin
                     could have copied it afterward. I never saw him with a revolver. When I opened
                     the vault door for the coroner today I discovered the revolver (pistol shown).
                     It is the same; it belongs to the mill; the night watchman carries it; Mr.
                     Conklin carried <unclear>a</unclear> key to the stock safe (key shown); that is
                     the one.</p>
                  <p>John H. Waltham recalled.—I said to Conklin if he was implicated in the matter
                     I would like to know about it. He said that if the worst came to the worst he
                     would face the music; I never told any one that he had any conversation with me
                     relative to an abortion case. There was nothing further said.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CORONER'S CHARGE.</head>
                  <p>Coroner Butterworth then charged the jury in a ludicrously incoherent manner,
                     and at great length. It was with great difficulty that his listeners could
                     restrain their laughter, and several actually burst out into a loud guffaw two
                     or three times during its delivery. He named a great many different modes of
                     death of which they could find young Conklin guilty, and the room was cleared
                     to permit the Jurors to deliberate. But they could find no verdict on the
                     evidence. It had not been proved that Conklin had killed himself; his letter
                     had not been read at the inquest; no cause had been assigned for the act.
                     Indeed every effort had apparently been made to hide the true reason. So, after
                     a lengthy debate, a vote was taken to decide whether they should adjourn and
                     have the inquest reopened. The first result was a tie, but at 10 o'clock
                     another vote adjourned the inquest until the following afternoon at half-past 2
                     o'clock. The whole affair was a great farce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SECOND DAY.</head>
                  <p>Resumed at Paterson Opera House at 3 o'clock. There were many spectators.</p>
                  <p>Thomas H. Hurst testified: I am bookkeeper at the Dale mill. I knew Walter
                     Conklin. I did not see the shooting, not being there at that time. In the
                     morning (Thursday), about a quarter past 8, he came an and stated that the
                     trunk mystery had come to Paterson, and that the lady was a friend of his.
                     Nothing further on the subject passed at that time. I told him I was sorry the
                     matter had come to Paterson. I noticed</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CONKLIN WAS SOMEWHAT PALER THAN USUAL.</head>
                  <p>Did not attach any importance to this, as I had no suspicions relative to the
                     trunk matter. In a jocular manner I told him it would be a good thing now for
                     him to go to Russia again. It never occurred to me that<pb n="76-77"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000031"/> Conklin had anything to do with this matter
                     until I went to dinner. I heard of his implication, by rumors, during the
                     morning. Mr. Conklin was time-keeper. I have the record of the time of last
                     week with me. (Time book produced, but every day was filled out as usual, with
                     marks.) Conklin occupied the same room as I. He was not absent a full day last
                     week. Don't remember that he was absent an hour on any day last week. He could
                     not have been absent without my knowledge. I was in the office when John, his
                     brother, called. Did not see him destroy any letter. Never saw the scraps of
                     the Russian letter until the Coroner called to-day.</p>
                  <p>These letters are torn up in small scraps, and written in Russian. They were
                     found in the waste basket at Dale's mill.</p>
                  <p>I do not know that Conklin was out last Saturday. Could not say positively that
                     any one called to see deceased Thursday morning beside his brother. I do not
                     know positively myself that Conklin shot himself. The mill stops at 2.30 on
                     Saturday. Conklin left about 4 o'clock last Saturday. He usually left when his
                     work was done. Never saw a letter from Alice Bowlsby to Conklin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A MYSTERIOUS NOTE.</head>
                  <p>A note was brought into Conklin by a boy. It said: "Walter, come over; the
                     train has not started yet." It was on a scrap of paper. Do not remember what
                     day. The note was handed to me. Conklin was up stairs, and I sent the note to
                     him. Conklin went out on receiving the letter. Could not swear positively what
                     day it was. It was a lady's handwriting. It was not on Saturday, but can't say
                     what day. It was written in pencil, and was not signed by any name. Deceased
                     immediately went out. It was in the afternoon. He was out only five or ten
                     minutes. I saw him when he came in. Did not notice anything excited about him.
                     He came in and went right on to his desk as usual. Had no subsequent talk on
                     the subject. I cannot remember the date. Can't say whether Mr. Dale was absent
                     the same day.</p>
                  <p>One of the jurors here said the boy was a boot-black, and thought he could be
                     reached.</p>
                  <p>Hurst's evidence was then read and signed, but all present were certain that
                     much more important testimony could have been adduced from him had things been
                     rightly managed.</p>
                  <p>Marcus J. McKeon testified.—I am clerk at the Erie Railway Station in Paterson.
                     I heard there had been a note sent over to Dale's mill. Did not see it myself;
                     heard it was. Directly I heard Miss Bowlsby ask deceased if he had received a
                     note, and he said "Yes." It was on</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE 17TH OF AUGUST.</head>
                  <p>two weeks ago Thursday; it was about 9 o'clock in the morning. I heard the
                     boot-black had taken the note over; know of no subsequent note. I saw the two
                     (Alice and Conklin) together; have never seen Alice there at the depot since. I
                     have not seen Conklin at the depot since either, that I can remember; have seen
                     Alice since the 17th ultimo, but not at the depot.</p>
                  <p>Witness' testimony was thus ended abruptly.</p>
                  <p>The Coroner here read the note which was found in Conklin's pocket it was the
                     same as that previously mentioned. The handwriting was identified by Mr. Hurst,
                     the bookkeeper.</p>
                  <p>Coroner Butterworth then charged the jury again.</p>
                  <p>After a few minutes consultation the jury returned the following</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>VERDICT:</head>
                  <p>We, the undersigned jurors, empanelled in the case of Walter L. Conklin,
                     deceased, do find that he came to his death by means of a pistol shot either
                     from his own hand, or by some person or persons unknown to the jury. And we
                     also recommend that the Coroner be requested to have the letters, Russian and
                     English, placed together and translated for future reference if required.</p>
                  <p>This remarkable verdict was signed by all the jurors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CONKLIN'S ESCAPE FROM ARREST.</head>
                  <p>Mrs. Williams, of 80 Belmont avenue, Newark, the aunt of Alice Bowlsby, at
                     whose house the unfortunate girl had been visiting when she went to New York,
                     is a woman of respectability and refinement. When interviewed she spoke with
                     much emotion. She stated that she went to New York on Thursday to satisfy
                     herself that the mysterious occupant of the trunk was Alice Bowlsby, and if so,
                     to make such an affidavit as would insure the arrest of young Conklin. The
                     young couple had been very intimate, and it was understood by Alice's friends
                     that they were soon to be married. Therefore she had no doubt that Conklin was
                     Alice's seducer. She obtained a warrant for the arrest of Conklin, and although
                     Captain Cameron offered to send an officer with her, she proceeded alone to
                     Paterson to have Conklin arrested. Arriving in that city she learned that death
                     had served a warrant; that Conklin had died by his own hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MISS BOWLSBY'S DEPARTURE FROM NEWARK.</head>
                  <p>On Monday, the 21st of August, Alice and her mother arrived in Newark from
                     Paterson, on a visit to Mrs. Williams. On Wednesday, the 23d, Alice said she
                     had made an engagement with Conklin, and was to meet him in New York, from
                     which place they would proceed together to Paterson. She dressed herself,
                     taking more than ordinary pains in making her toilet, and left the house of her
                     aunt at 80 Belmont avenue,<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6545-00000032"/> saying she
                     was going to meet Conklin in New York. That was the last ever seen of Alice
                     Bowlsby alive by her aunt and mother.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MISSING.</head>
                  <p>On Saturday, the 26th, Mrs. Bowlsby returned to her home at Paterson, and was
                     surprised to find that Alice had not been seen since she left with her mother
                     on Monday for Newark. On Monday, the 28th, Mrs. Bowlsby again visited Newark,
                     for the purpose of tracing her daughter. Mrs. Williams said she then knew of
                     the terrible trunk tragedy, but did not for a moment suspect that Alice, who
                     always was a good girl, was the victim. If for a moment she associated Alice
                     with the girl found in the baggage-room, the idea was quickly dispelled, for
                     the newspapers stated that the victim in the trunk was of full figure, well
                     proportioned, and handsome, while Alice was delicate and frail, and was not
                     what might be termed good looking; and the girl found was represented to be
                     about 20, whereas Alice was 28<ref rend="super" target="#note_001"
                        xml:id="return_001">*</ref>
                      years old. Remembering that Alice had stated just before she left the
                     house that she was going to New York to keep an engagement with Conklin, Mrs.
                     Williams advised Mrs. Bowlsby to return to Paterson at once, and question
                     Conklin as to when and where he had last seen Alice; and threaten him with
                     arrest if he did not tell her whereabouts. Mrs. Bowlsby</p>
                  <note place="foot" xml:id="note_001">
                     
                     <p><ref target="#return_001">*</ref>The difficulty in arriving at the exact age of a lady will account for
                        these differences in stated age of the late Alice Bowlsby.</p>
                  </note>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>WOULD NOT LISTEN TO THE SUGGESTION</head>
                  <p>for a moment. She declared that Conklin was a gentleman; that she held him in
                     high esteem, and that she believed that it was impossible that he should know
                     of her absence. Mrs. Williams saw it was useless to further advise Mrs.
                     Bowlsby, and desisted. That evening Mrs. Bowlsby again returned to her home. On
                     Tuesday it was suggested to Mrs. Williams that Alice might possibly be the
                     unfortunate girl found in the baggage-room. "That was the first," said Mrs.
                     Williams, "that the thought struck me." On Thursday morning she learned that it
                     was indeed too true, and she immediately went to New York to take measures for
                     the arrest of Conklin. She states that Alice was always careful and discreet in
                     her actions, that her character had never been questioned, and that her friends
                     and relatives were very fond of her. Mrs. Williams stated that there was
                     nothing in the appearance or actions of Alice to indicate that she was in a
                     delicate state, and that the idea was never dreamed of by her friends.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A LETTER THAT MAY DISCLOSE SOMETHING.</head>
                  <p>The following was found among many other things in Rosenzweig's house. In a
                     fireplace in the doctor's room they found evidences of a recent fire, as if
                     papers and perhaps clothing had been burned. Some fragments<pb
                        n="80 (Illustration) -81" xml:id="VAC6545-00000033"/>
                     <figure>
                        <head>"DR." JACOB ROSENZWEIG, ALIAS "ASCHER," ETC.</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">"Dr." Jacob Rosenzweig, alias "Ascher,"
                              u.</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure> ments of letters were found that may possibly throw some light on the
                     absence of some other missing lady. One of these fragments is a half sheet of
                     large-sized note paper, closely written on both sides in a very neat lady's
                     hand, the sheet being mutilated at the bottom. It bears neither date nor
                     signature, but as far as legible reads as follows:</p>
                  <p>"<hi rend="i"/>Monday Evening.—I did not get to finish my letter last night,
                     and have not found time to touch it to-day until now. Katy was here this
                     morning to wash. Papa started away on the early train. Clayton Hunt came for
                     the bookcase, and beside I had to go up town. So you see I have been busy with
                     cooking and other work beside. I am getting my dress made this week, and I had
                     to go this morning to buy trimmings and give my measure. When I went up to the
                     store I saw a piece of black silk, with a little white stripe in it, and I
                     concluded that I liked it so much better than the brown that I exchanged.
                     Brown, you know, looks so old womanish. I will have it trimmed with black
                     satin. I got Ella a pretty white marseille, which she has made up. Mrs. Graves
                     made it, and a pretty calico which she is making herself. I will send you
                     scraps of our dresses when I write again. I shall be very busy with my sewing
                     for a while. Mrs. A.—— is making my dress. Now I ha —— thing very sad to write
                     to you —— —— will shock you very ——gic who Terre Haute at once which we did. By
                     solicitation of Dr. Waters, Mr. Washburn conducted the funeral services. O, it
                     was heart rending. I dare not think of it. It seems to me I have just had one
                     crash after another for the last two or three years, till my heart begins to
                     feel numb. Those poor little motherless children! My heart bleeds to see them.
                     Maggie wanted me to have the little girl, but I cannot take her now. She is a
                     sweet little dear. How cruel death seems, and yet as I looked at her dear face,
                     lying cold in death, I could not grieve altogether, for I thought of the sorrow
                     and woe she had escaped. Her pure spirit has gone where sin and sorrow are
                     unknown. But I did grieve that I had not seen her again in life. How I
                     regretted that I did not go over when she sent for me! But we can never
                     anticipate the future. What a comfort it is that I can feel that she never had
                     an unkind thought toward me. But I must close and send this to the office.
                     Beside if I write in this strain —— get so sad I cannot sleep; write ——
                     immediately, and tell me every —— seen Stoddard and —— clothes and ——"</p>
                  <p>The following detatched paragraphs are from a letter in the same handwriting,
                     which had been torn into fragments:</p>
                  <p>"I never said any thing harsh of Scott or any one now. I think for some time I
                     have known this life of trust. If I have not known it fully I pray God will
                     lead me into it. And you, Maggie, you must trust God in all things. He will be
                     your best friend.</p>
                  <p>"He will tell you what I said about your coming and staying with us a while. I
                     would like to have you, though I could offer you little besides a roof. But I
                     told him if you and he agreed upon terms, and you<pb n="82-83"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000034"/> wanted to stay with me a while, put my arms
                     lovingly about you and pray that He will take very gentle care of you in this
                     sinful world. I was not surprised at the scrap of a letter you sent to me. I
                     knew Thomas had written to —— I never saw any one so nervous when he found you
                     ——. You would have very little to do and would have much time for books. Do as
                     you think best. Mary and Amy Johnson have a school at Poughkeepsie, a boarding
                     school. Hannah was there the other day and asked me your address; said she
                     wanted to write, was sick; was well just two weeks, then was sick again. I
                     suffered unutterable pain. I don't think you ever saw me look so badly as I did
                     last week. I was very pale. Those Johnsons—tattling yet—Stoddard—"</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TWO MORE STRANGE WOMEN.</head>
                  <p>The mysterious young woman who engaged Pickett's trunk, and afterwards received
                     the trunk at the depot and had it checked for Chicago, after leaving Pickett to
                     go for the trunk, walked down Third avenue, and was joined by two others rather
                     better dressed than herself. The three turned into Twenty-third street. They
                     passed the livery stable of Jas. S. Selden, at 156 East Twenty-third street, on
                     the opposite side of the way, and scrutinized it so closely as to attract the
                     attention of some of the employés. The woman that had engaged the truck finally
                     crossed the street and entered the office of the stable, while her companions
                     passed on and have not since been seen. On entering the office the woman asked
                     for a coupé to take her to the Hudson River railroad station. After arranging
                     the terms, Frank Cooper, a driver, was called and ordered to hitch up his
                     coupé, which he did, when the woman got in and was driven to the depot. Her
                     subsequent operations in buying a ticket for Chicago, securing a check for the
                     trunk to the same destination, and then disappearing without attempting to take
                     the train, have already been told.</p>
                  <p>This mysterious woman nor her associates, nor the man who inquired of Kerwin,
                     the truckman, about her, have none of them since been seen, and the police have
                     been baffled in every attempt to track them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ACCOMPLICES IN VILLANY.</head>
                  <p>The identity of the corpse that Rosenzweig sought to have buried by Bayle &amp;
                     Boylston, and the one which was subsequently sent to the railroad station,
                     seems to be established beyond a doubt, and thus, at least, as accomplices in
                     the effort to conceal a monstrous crime, are inculpated at least six persons,
                     viz.: Dr. Rosenzweig and his wife, the mysterious woman who engaged the truck
                     and checked the trunk, and her two companions, and the unknown man who made
                     inquiries of Kerwin, the truckman, regarding the conveyance of the trunk. Of
                     these, as yet, only Dr. Rosenzweig has been arrested, though his wife is kept
                     under surveillance, and his servant girl and a lodger in his house are detained
                     as witnesses.<unclear>But</unclear> all the facts that had as yet been brought
                     to light pointed to Rosenzweig as the principal actor, and the rest as merely
                     assistants in the effort to get rid of the body of the victim.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MISTAKEN IDENTITY—STRANGE, VERY STRANGE.</head>
                  <p>One of the strangest cases of mistaken identity that has ever been known, was
                     the supposed recognition of the body of Miss Bowlsby as that of Figa
                     Rosenzweig, and another case as horrible may yet be developed. The
                     circumstances were as follows: An Israelitish merchant of Baxter street called
                     on Capt. Kennedy at the Franklin street station, and said that from certain
                     circumstances which had come to his knowledge he believed that the body of the
                     young woman which was found in the trunk was that of Figa Rosenzweig, a niece
                     of the doctor. The gentleman told Capt. Kennedy that the girl was well known to
                     most of the Israelites of Baxter and Bayard streets. He gave so accurate a
                     description of the girl that Capt. Kennedy became convinced that there was more
                     in his assertion than idle talk. Capt. Kennedy immediately conferred with
                     Inspector Walling, and Detective Eustis was detailed to assist in working up
                     the case. The Captain and Detective Eustis accompanied by Mr. Price of 56
                     Baxter street, Mr. Bernstein of 66 Bayard street, Bernstein's wife and two
                     daughters, Mr. Cohen of 73 Baxter, and Max Levy of 64 Baxter street, all of
                     whom were intimately acquainted with the girl Figa, went to Bellevue. After a
                     critical examination of8 the corpse, they all unhesitatingly declared it to be
                     that of Figa Rosenzweig, and said that they were willing to swear to it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE OLD, OLD STORY.</head>
                  <p>The story, as told by those who were acquainted with the family, is that about
                     one year ago Rosenzweig sent to Warsaw, Poland, money sufficient to pay the
                     girl's passage to this country. When she arrived she went to live with
                     Rosenzweig's mother in the basement of 98 Bayard street. At this place
                     Rosenzweig owns a butcher shop, which is attended by his mother, who lives in
                     rooms at the back of the shop. Some time ago the neighbors noticed that
                     Rosenzweig was assiduous in his attentions to Figa, and before long the girl
                     bore unmistakable signs of being <foreign xml:lang="FRA">encient.</foreign>
                     When questioned in relation to the matter, she said that Rosenzweig the father
                     of her unborn babe. Four weeks ago yesterday Rosenzw called at his mother's
                     house, and after conversing awhile, said that the basement was damp and
                     unhealthy, and as Figa's health was delicate, he intended to take her home to
                     his house, and keep her there until she was entirely recovered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>GOING TO HER DEATH.</head>
                  <p>Figa left the Bayard street house with him that same afternoon, and since that
                     time has not been seen by any of the neighbors. Captain Kennedy, having heard
                     that Hannah Goldwasser, an aunt of the girl, and<pb n="84-85"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000035"/> step sister of Dr. Rosenzweig, lived at 450
                     Pearl street, conjectured that sho was the woman who accompanied the trunk to
                     the depot, and bought the ticket for Chicago. Mrs. Goldwasser was arrested, and
                     taken to the station house. The boy Potts and the truckman Pickett were sent
                     for. On their arrival they both said that she was not the woman. Mrs.
                     Goldwasser was much agitated, and told several contradictory stories. She said
                     that four weeks ago Dr. Rosenzweig bought a ticket for Figa to return to
                     Poland; that she accompanied the doctor and the girl to Hoboken, and saw her
                     get on board a steamer, the name of which she does not know, and saw the
                     steamer sail with the girl on board.</p>
                  <p>The reader all this while must bear in mind that the detectives were working up
                     the wrong case, under the supposition that the body of Miss A. A. Bowlsby then
                     lying at the Morgue was that of Rosenzweig's niece, "Figa."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE HOUSE OF CRIME.</head>
                  <p>The house on Second avenue, in which it is probable this dark deed was
                     committed, and in which resides Dr. Rosenzweig and his family, is a three story
                     and basement marble front house, about twelve feet in width by thirty deep. The
                     main entrance is reached by a flight of ten marble steps leading from the
                     sidewalk, and which are common to this and the adjoining tenement. Annexed is a
                     diagram of the basement, in the front room of which, or dining-room, the trunk
                     containing the body was standing when the truckman called for it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>A—Door opened by Dr. Rosenzweig to admit the drayman. B—Trunk
                           containing the body. C—Servant's trunk. D—Lounge on which Mrs. Rosenzweig
                           sat when the truckman called for the trunk.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE UPPER FLOORS.</head>
                  <p>The main or parlor floor is divided into three equal-sized rooms. The front
                     door opens directly into the front room, which is furnished with imitation
                     rosewood furniture upholstered with crimson satan damask. All the pieces are
                     covered with crochetted tidies. The middle room is plainly and sparsely
                     furnished. It is a mere hall, from which stairways lead to the basement and
                     upper floors. The rear room is furnished with black walnut. A rosewood piano
                     also stands in this room. On the mantel also stands a bust of General Grant.
                     The rooms are separated by sliding doors with ground glass panels. The carpets
                     of all the rooms are uniform, bein a heavy light-colored Brussels. The second
                     floor is divided into two square rooms, front and rear, with a hallway, off of
                     which is a bathroom and water-closet. The front room is occupied as the family
                     dormitory, the Doctor, his wife, and the three younger children occupying it
                     together. The rear room is used by Rosina Rosenzweig, the doctor's daughter, a
                     girl of fourteen years. The third floor is divided the same as the second, save
                     that the small closet corresponding with the bathroom below is used as a
                     servant's sleeping room. Abram Seal, a peddler, of the some nationality as
                     Rosenzweig, and a boarder, occupied the front room. The rear room was vacant.
                     Seal is detained at the Twenty-second street station as a witness.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A WATCH ON THE PREMISES.</head>
                  <p>Two officers were placed in charge of the house on the Doctor's arrest, who
                     kept up a strict surveillance, allowing access to none but those connected with
                     the Police Department. Captain Cameron accompanied by Sergeants Frank Randall
                     and Rooney, and Roundsman Keating, went to the house and instituted a thorough
                     search, which brought to light evidence sufficient to prove, although the fact
                     is denied by the prisoner, that Dr. Jacob Rosenzweig of 687 Second avenue, and
                     Dr. Ascher of 3 Amity place, are one and the same person.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE UNDERTAKER'S STORY.</head>
                  <p>My name is James F. Boyle, and I do business as an undertaker at 658 Second
                     avenue. On the morning of Saturday the 26th, a man whom I now recognize as Dr.
                     Jacob Rosenzweig came to my store. I was at the time conversing with my father.
                     I turned and asked the doctor his business. He asked me how much it would cost
                     to bury a woman, and then added that a servant girl of his had died. He said
                     that she was very poor and only had $10, and that it did not matter to him how
                     or where she was buried so that she was buried. I asked him what sort of a
                     funeral he wanted. He said that he only wanted a hearse and coffin. He then
                     asked if I could not take the body to my store, saying that it was not far off.
                     I answered that I would only do this if he would furnish me with a certificate
                     from the doctor who had attended the girl, and then I could get a permit from
                     the Board of Health. In further conversation he said that the doctor who had
                     attended the girl lived down town. Nothing further transpired, and he went
                     away, as I supposed to get the doctor's certificate. He did not return, and I
                     never saw him from that<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6545-00000036"/> time until I
                     saw him to-day in the cell. I was induced to come here and make this statement
                     from what I read about the affair in the papers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>AN INTERVIEW WITH ROSENZWEIG.</head>
                  <p>Our reporter visited the prisoner Rosenzweig in his cell, and engaged him in a
                     protracted conversation. He strenuously denied any connection with or knowledge
                     of the crime of which he is charged, and attributes the truckman's recognition
                     of him and his house to a mistake. He admits <unclear>calling</unclear> on the
                     undertaker Boyle, but says he merely dropped in there by chance, and thought to
                     "make one hand tickle the other" by offering the undertaker work in return for
                     any chance practice that might be sent to him. He claims to have come to this
                     country from Europe in 1864, since which time he has lived in various parts of
                     the city. He says he was a regular allopathic physician in Poland, but on
                     coming to this country he turned his attention to the eclectic system of
                     medicine, and attended lectures for two years in that school of medicine in
                     Philadelphia, though retaining his residence here. He denies any intimate
                     acquaintance with Dr. Ascher, of Amity place, but claims that there is such a
                     man, and that he knows him casually. Dr. Ascher's specialty is cancers and
                     tumors, and he practises some in confidential cases. He does not judge Dr.
                     Ascher's standing or ability, and when pressed on this point becomes petulant
                     and refuses to answer. He is also easily irritated in regard to his diplomas,
                     and refuses to answer questions about them. He claims Dr. Willard Parker as his
                     friend, and boldly refers to him for his character and standing as a medical
                     man. "Dr. Parker," he said, "has frequently consulted with me, and he would not
                     meet me in consultation if I was not a competent and regular physician." The
                     doctor also denies that he has ever been engaged in any other business than the
                     practice of medicine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>WHAT DR. PARKER SAYS.</head>
                  <p>Our reporter then called on Dr. Willard Parker in regard to Rosenzweig's
                     claims. Dr. Parker said that some time last year this man called on him and
                     presented an official card, at the same time saying that his child was sick
                     with diphtheria, and requested him (Dr. Parker) to call and see it. Rosenzweig
                     was then living at 161 Thompson street. Dr. Parker called several times and
                     ministered to his child out of professional courtesy. Subsequently he was
                     called to see a patient in Macdougall street. On inquiring who the attending
                     physician was, he was told it was Dr. Rosenzweig. As he knew nothing against
                     Rosenzweig he obeyed the call. This is the extent of his professional or social
                     acquaintance with the man. He has an indistinct recollection that when he
                     called at Rosenzweig's house he saw Rosenzweig's professional card on the front
                     of the house, and also one that his remembrance makes sound something like
                     Ascher or Aker.</p>
                  <pb n="88 (Illustration) -89" xml:id="VAC6545-00000037"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>WALTER CONKLIN, Alice Bowlsby's lover, as he appeared in his
                           coffin.</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Walter Conklin, Alice Bowlsby's Geliebter, wie er
                              in seinem Sarge aussah.</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE MAID SERVANT'S STORY.</head>
                  <p>Warden Brennan had a long interview with Jane Johnson, the servant of Dr.
                     Rosenzweig, in the Twenty-second street police station. He represented to her
                     what trouble she would get herself into if she persisted in refusing to tell
                     what she knew about the death of the young lady, and he offered to procure her
                     immunity from punishment, to take the best of care of her during her illness
                     (she has been pregnant seven months) to admit her to the hospital, and to
                     provide for her afterward if she would make a clean breast of it. She was very
                     much affected, burst into tears, and seizing the Warden's hands, she said that
                     she would tell everything. She said she entered Rosenzweig's service on the
                     first of May last, and went on with a long story, differing in no point from
                     her former statements, except when she told of</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE DEATH OF A WOMAN</head>
                  <p>who came from Newburg, and entered Dr. Rosenzweig's house under the assumed
                     name of Mary Carrol. She died on June 7, after giving birth to a living child,
                     and was buried from the house at the expense of a man who used to visit her
                     occasionally under pretence of being her husband. Thomas Carey was the
                     undertaker (Carey afterward corroborated this story). The doctor certified that
                     Mary died of dropsy. Jane and Mrs. Rosenzweig carried the child to the Sisters
                     of Charity, where it is still. Jane positively denied that she knew anything
                     about the present case, and affirmed with many protestations that she had told
                     the truth. She appeared to be fully cognizant of what she was saying, and all
                     efforts to elicit anything further from her proved abortive.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>DON'T KNOW FIGA ROSENZWEIG.</head>
                  <p>Our reporter called upon Miss Johnson in the station-house, for the purpose of
                     questioning her in regard to the story about Figa Rosenzweig, but she doggedly
                     denied that the doctor ever had a niece. He was an only son, she said, and had
                     never had a brother. Nothing further could be got from her, notwithstanding
                     that the reporter represented her dangerous position in the strongest light,
                     and explained to her how she might save herself by a full confession.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>VICTIM RECOGNIZED AT LAST—NOT FIGA ROSENZWEIG, BUT ALICE BOWLSBY.</head>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <opener>
                                 <dateline>BELLEVUE HOSPITAL, NEW YORK, Aug. 30, 1871.</dateline>
                                 <salute>Geo. W. Walling, Esq., Inspector Police. City New
                                    York.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>SIR: I have the honor to report that after three days' searching
                                 for some <unclear>person to</unclear> recognize the body of the
                                 unknown woman found in a trunk, and brought to the morgue on last
                                 Saturday evening from the Hudson River Railroad depot. I am
                                    finally<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6545-00000038"/> rewarded by the
                                 remains being recognized by Dr. Theo. G. Kinne, of 163 Main
                                    <unclear>street</unclear> Paterson, N. J., and also by Dr.
                                 Joseph F. Parker, dentist, of the same number, as Miss Alice
                                 Bowlsby, of 43 West street, Paterson, N. J. She was visiting her
                                 aunt in Newark, N. J., in company with her mother, and left Newark
                                 on Wednesday on the 9.15 A.M. train for Paterson, by way of New
                                 York. Very respectfully yours,</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>THOS. S. BRENNAN. Warden.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>This solution of the mystery of identification only adds to the obscurity the
                     whole dark affair. How came this young woman in Dr. Rosenzweig's house? Who
                     enticed her there? An entire new field for investigation is hereby opened up.
                     And then, what has become of Figa Rosenzweig, the doctor's niece? How are the
                     contradictory statements in regard to her, given below, to be reconciled? Are
                     there other victims of this man's dark practices yet undiscovered? Who can
                     tell?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ESTABLISHED FACTS AGAINST ROSENZWEIG.</head>
                  <p>Two damaging facts against the doctor have been established beyond the
                     possibility of a doubt. The first is, that he called at the undertaker's shop
                     of Boyle &amp; Boylston, in Second avenue, at 9 o'clock in the morning of
                     Saturday last, and endeavored to negotiate for the burial of a young woman,
                     representing that she was his servant girl and poor. This transaction is
                     established by the evidence of three witnesses, the credibility of either of
                     whom cannot be assailed. The second fact is the employment of the truckman,
                     Pickett, to take a trunk from the doctor's residence, which trunk was delivered
                     to him from that residence by Rosenzweig in person, and was subsequently found
                     to contain the corpse of the young woman. And as if to establish this fact
                     beyond all peradventure, the truckman, on receiving the order to call for the
                     trunk, entered the address in his memorandum book, as follows: <q>
                        <p>687 Second avenue, JULIA SIDNEY.</p>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This entry was made when the order was received, and solely for the purpose of
                     guiding him to the place. No. 687 Second avenue was occupied only by the
                     household of Rosenzweig, and the truckman further identifies Rosenzweig as the
                     man who delivered the trunk to him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>PERSISTENT IGNORANCE OF THE ACCUSED.</head>
                  <p>Rosenzweig's household consisted of himself, his wife, his daughter Rosinetta,
                     and three small children, the Jew peddler, Abram Seal, and the servant girl,
                     Jane Johnson. Each and all of these parties strenuously deny any knowledge of
                     the trunk or its contents, or of its delivery to the truckman, or any
                     circumstance connected with it. The doctor, however, though at first disposed
                     to equivocate, finally admitted, as he could not deny that he called at the
                     undertaker's shop on Saturday morning, but persists in his denial of any
                     conversation of the specific tenor alleged by the three witnesses of the visit.
                     He maintains that he merely spoke of <unclear>burials</unclear> in a general
                     way, his idea being that by impressing upon the undertaker he could give him
                     employment from time to time, the <unclear>undertaker might</unclear> be led to
                     send him patients.</p>
                  <p>The doctor, who has hitherto most strenuously denied that any deaths had
                     occurred at his house, was yesterday forced to admit that the girl called Mary
                     Carrol, whom he had delivered of a child, did die there last June. He still
                     denied, however, that she died in childbirth, but maintains that her malady was
                     dropsy, as he certified at the time in order to secure a burial permit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ROSENZWEIG'S STORY OF HIS NIECE'S WHEREABOUTS.</head>
                  <p>In regard to the girl Figa Rosenzweig, his reported niece, whose identity with
                     the corpse was considered as established, the doctor told Capt. Cameron that he
                     had detected her stealing money at his mother's in Bayard street, and had sent
                     her to Poland several weeks since. He said that she was now in Poland, as he
                     knew from letters he had received from the police of that country. When asked
                     where these letters were, he said they were at his residence. Capt. Cameron
                     immediately sent to the residence and made diligent search for all letters and
                     papers it contained. Of these a great batch were found, but none of them
                     confirm the doctor's story. There are no letters among them, either from Figa,
                     from Polish police officers, or from any other source whatever alluding to the
                     girl's arrival in Poland, or referring in any way to her. It will be seen from
                     an interview with the doctor's wife and other female relatives, printed below,
                     that their stories about this girl do not in anywise agree, a circumstance that
                     tends to corroborate her alleged murder at the hands of these people.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>JANE JOHNSON'S CONTRADICTIONS.</head>
                  <p>The girl Jane Johnson, who was detained by Captain Cameron, is a mystery in
                     herself. She represents that she was born in Canada, of Catholic parents, but
                     is herself a Protestant. She has been married, but her husband died of cholera
                     in this city seven years ago. Since then she has lived at service. She is now,
                     according to her own story, <unclear>Seven</unclear> months advanced toward
                     maternity, but persistently refuses to same the father of her unborn child,
                     merely saying that he is out West. She is about 28 years old, of good form and
                     carriage, with remarkably soft, pleasing eyes, and attractive features. Her
                     complexion, however, is coarse, and betrays her station. Our reporter who
                     visited her understood her to say that she had lived with the Rosenzweig family
                     only about a month ago; but in this the reporter may have been mistaken. To
                     another reporter, however, she did positively say that she had lived there only
                     three months, whereas she now admits that she has been<pb n="92-93"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000039"/> there since May. After the disclosures were made
                     on Tuesday evening regarding Figa Rosenzweig, a reporter was sent up to the
                     stationhouse from this office expressly to interrogate her regarding Figa. To
                     that reporter she positively denied any knowledge of such a person, and
                     undertook to establish her assertion by a real or pretended knowledge of the
                     doctor's family history and connections. Yesterday she denied having had any
                     such conversation with the reporter, and admitted that</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SHE KNEW AND HAD OFTEN SEEN FIGA,</head>
                  <p>usually at the house in Bayard street, and occasionally at the doctor's house.
                     She would tell nothing more about her, insisting that she knew nothing, only
                     she persisted that Figa never stayed at the doctor's house only as she called
                     there from time to time.</p>
                  <p>From all the developments in this strange and mysterious case, it being so
                     evident that this girl, if at home last Saturday, must have had some knowledge
                     of the trunk transaction, our reporter urged her to tell all she knew. But she
                     persisted that she knew nothing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SEEKING LIGHT IN THE KITCHEN.</head>
                  <p>Reporter.—Were you not at home on Saturday?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Yes, sir; I was at home.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—All day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I might have been out half a dozen times of errands to the grocery, or
                     something like that.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—How long were you gone from the house at any one time?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I can't tell how long.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Were you gone an hour at any one time?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—No, sir, I don't think I was.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Were you gone half an hour</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I can't exactly say.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Where did you go that day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I might have gone to the grocer's opposite, where we usually bought
                     groceries, or sometimes I went around into Thirtieth street about the middle of
                     the block, between Second and Third avenues. I know I went after milk soon
                     after dinner to a place near First avenue on Thirty-ninth street.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Were these all the visits you made out of the house durin that
                     day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Yes, sir.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—What time do you dine?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Between 12 and 1 o'clock.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Then it must have been soon after 1 o'clock that you went for the
                     milk?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—About that time.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—What were you doing that day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Oh, I can't remember that.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Well, usually you wash on Mondays, don't you? and another day you
                     iron, and another day you have general sweeping, and so on; some particular
                     work for each day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Yes, sir.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Well, can't you remember what you were doing last Saturday?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—In the morning I made the beds.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—How many beds?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE FRIDAY NIGHT LODGERS AT ROSENZWEIG'S.</head>
                  <p>Jane.—Let me see. I made Rosie's in the back room; Mrs. Rosenzweig always made
                     her own in the front room; I made the bed in the front room on the top floor,
                     where the young man slept; and I had my bed in the little closet-room in the
                     middle of the house on the top floor. I used to sleep in the back room, but the
                     bugs were so thick there they drove me out.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did you make no bed in the back room that day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—No, sir.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Well, after you made the beds, what did you do?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I scrubbed the kitchen, and then I washed out the back yard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>AN UNCERTAIN DINNER.</head>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did you do this all before dinner?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I can't say about that. When I was busy, Rosie generally got the
                     dinner.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did Rosie get the dinner that day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I think so.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Can't you remember?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I don't think there was any dinner got that day. The doctor don't always
                     come home to dinner, and then we just fix something on the kitchen table.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Was the doctor home that day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I can't say for sure; no, I don't think he was.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—What makes you think he was not at home?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Well, he went out after breakfast. I remember, because I went to get a
                     handkerchief out of my trunk behind the door in the dining-room, and he came
                     through and pushed the door back against me. He said, "Excuse me; I didn't know
                     you were there." I remember this because he very seldom speaks to me. I don't
                     think he speaks to me once a week.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did he go out the basement door?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Yes, sir. He went right out after speaking to me.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—And he didn't come home to dinner?</p>
                  <pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6545-00000040"/>
                  <p>Jane.—No, sir. Mrs. Rosenzweig was sick up stairs, and Rosie took her dinner up
                     to her.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Then the dinner table was not set in the dining-room that day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—No, sir.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did the doctor usually go out and in through the basement her?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Usually, though he sometimes went up the steps, and went in front
                     door.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>WHAT THE GIRL MIGHT HAVE HEARD.</head>
                  <p>Reporter.—If he had come in the basement door you would have known it, wouldn't
                     you?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Not necessarily; he might have come in and I not heard him.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did he have a night key to that door?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—No, sir; the door was not fastened; it is never fastened. Sometimes it is
                     left unlocked all night.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—But, even then, you would have heard the door open and shut, wouldn't
                     you?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—Not if the kitchen door was shut. You know there is a hall leading from
                     the dining-room door to the kitchen door.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Yes. Were these doors shut that day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I don't remember.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—If they had been shut you couldn't hear what was going on in the
                     dining-room?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—No, sir.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Could you not hear people going up and down the basement stairs?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—I don't think I could.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Was Mrs. Rosenzweig down stairs that day?</p>
                  <p>Jane.—She might have been down just for a little while at a time, don't know
                     whether she was or not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>WHAT SHE MIGHT HAVE KNOWN.</head>
                  <p>Reporter.—Now, Jane, it is certain that a trunk, containing the dead body of a
                     young woman, was taken out of that front basement at about 2 o'clock on
                     Saturday afternoon. It is strange if you don't know anything about it. If you
                     do know about it, you ought to tell it at once, or your persistence in seeking
                     to conceal the fact may place you in a very bad predicament. Whether you know
                     it or not, the trunk did go out. Now tell me honestly, whether you know
                     anything about it or not.</p>
                  <p>Jane.—If I was to die for it this minute I could say no differently. I know
                     nothing about it.</p>
                  <p>The reporter, as he could get nothing further from the girl, left her. Soon
                     after, Warden Brennan called, and in consideration of her delicate<pb
                        n="96 (Illustration) -97" xml:id="VAC6545-00000041"/>
                     <figure>
                        <head>JANE JOHNSON, SERVANT TO "DR." JACOB ROSENZWEIG. A prominent witness,
                           with a "story of her own."</head>
                        <p>
                           <foreign xml:lang="DEU">Jane Johnson, Dienstmädchen des "Dr." Jacob
                              Rosenzweig. Eine wichtige Zeugin, nebst einer "eigenen
                              Erzählung."</foreign>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                     <unclear>attention</unclear>, Captain Cameron committed her to his care, and
                     she was removed to Bellevue Hospital, where she will be cared for.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A DISCOVERY THAT BELIES THE GIRL'S STORY.</head>
                  <p>But the measure of credibility that may be placed in her statements can be
                     judged from the fact that in the wash-tub at which she was engaged when
                     arrested, and which was left undisturbed for a few days, there was found a
                     lady's white lawn handkerchief, marked with indelible ink, "A. A. Bowlsby," the
                     name of the young lady from Paterson, showing that not only had the unfortunate
                     one been in the house, but that her soiled garments were given to this girl to
                     wash. Beside this fact, proving Miss Bowlsby's presence in the house with Kate
                     or Jane Johnson's knowledge, there was also found upon the promises a blue silk
                     scarf, which has been identified as one worn by Miss Bowlsby when she left
                     Newark. Thus, even though the servant may explain away her pretended ignorance,
                     there can no longer be a doubt that this young lady was made away with in that
                     house, and, of course, by Dr. Rosenzweig in the practice of his unholy
                     trade.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>HOW MANY MORE VICTIMS ARE THERE?</head>
                  <p>But, having found the identity of this particular corpse, the child-slayer is
                     not yet relieved from suspicion regarding his niece.</p>
                  <p>Our reporter, widely known in Philadelphia as "Quizzing Gus," and who was sent
                     by us to New York city expressly to "work up" this case visited Bayard street,
                     the residence of Rosenzweig's mother. Sitting in the underground meat shop, he
                     found Mrs. Leonora Rosenzweig, the doctor's wife, nursing her baby, five weeks
                     old, Miss Rosinetta, the doctor's eldest daughter, Mrs. Rosenzweig, the
                     doctor's mother, and another old Jewess. The doctor's three younger children
                     were playing on the greasy floor of the butcher shop. When the reporter entered
                     the place the elder members of the Rosenzweig family were engaged in an earnest
                     conversation, which was immediately hushed. Asking for Mrs. Rosenzweig, both of
                     the madams claimed that honor, and after making himself known, the following
                     conversation ensued between the doctor's mother and the reporter.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—I suppose that you have seen the statement that the girl found in the
                     trunk was Miss Figa Rosenzweig, a niece of the doctor, and that she formerly
                     lived at this place.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Rosenzweig (in imperfect English).—Yes, I see it all; but
                        (<unclear>excitedly</unclear>) it is all a lie</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE MOTHER'S ACCOUNT OF FIGA.</head>
                  <p>Reporter.—When did Figa come to this country?</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Rosenzweig.—Figa's father and mother died in Poland, and when my husband,
                     who is now dead, heard of it he sent for Figa's brother,<pb n="98-99"
                        xml:id="VAC6545-00000042"/> Hyman, to come here; that was about one year and
                     a half age. He came, and after he was here about six months he was taken sick
                     with the dropsy and we sent him to Mt. Sinai Hospital, where he died. My
                     husband then sent for Figa and she arrived here about the time of the "Feast of
                     Hannuccan;" that was about the latter part of last February.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did she live with you after her arrival?</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Rosenzweig.—Yes; she lived with me until about nine weeks ago when she
                     left and went to live with her aunt, Mrs. Goldwasser, at 450
                        <unclear>Pearl</unclear> street.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Why did she leave your house to live with Mrs. Goldwasser</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>IMPUGNING THE HONESTY OF THE MISSING ONE.</head>
                  <p>Mrs. Rosenzweig.—That is a family matter which I have never spoken about, but
                     I'll tell you the whole story, and you can then judge for yourself. When Figa
                     lived with me I had a man working for me about the shop. His name was Carish
                     Cohen, a countryman of mine. Well, about nine weeks ago, and just before Figa
                     left me, I was robbed of $426 in money and about $350 worth of jewelry. I
                     suspected that Carish Cohen was the thief, but he said he was innocent, and
                     finally proved that he knew nothing about the robbery. Just about this time,
                     Figa complained of being sick, and Mrs. Goldwasser came to my house one day and
                     said to me. "You know that Figa's brother died with the dropsy, Figa is sick,
                     and may be she'll die the same as her brother did. I am going to take her to my
                     house to live." Figa went with Mrs. Goldwasser the next day. Figa came to see
                     me every day until about four weeks ago.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>FIGA'S MYSTERIOUS DISAPPEARANCE.</head>
                  <p>Then her visits ceased entirely. I did not know what was the matter, and one
                     night I went to Mrs. Goldwasser's house and asked her where Figa was. She said,
                     "I haven't seen Figa for several days. She is at your son's house. He came and
                     took her away." I then went to my son's house in Second avenue; it was nearly
                     12 o'clock at night. I asked him for Figa. He told me he had not seen her for
                     three weeks</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Have you any idea where Figa is now?</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Rosenzweig.—Two days after this Mrs. Goldwasser called at my house, and
                     said that she had heard that Figa had gone to Poland. I asked her, "Where did
                     she get money to buy her ticket with?" Her answer was, "I don't know where she
                     got it, but Figa has got plenty of money."</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Do you think that Figa stole your money and jewels?</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Rosenzweig.—I didn't think so at first, but I am now certain, from her
                     actions, that she was the thief, and divided with Mrs. Goldwasser.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Was Figa <foreign xml:lang="FRA">enceinte</foreign> when she left
                     your house?</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Rosenzweig (emphatically)—No, sir; she had the dropsy</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—The neighbors say that your son was very attentive to Figa, and took
                     her to the theatres, to balls, and carriage riding. Is this true?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>COVERING THE TRAIL.</head>
                  <p>Mrs. Rosenzweig (smilingly).—No, sir; my son hated Figa because she made
                     trouble between him and his father. Why, sir, my son wouldn't
                        <unclear>be</unclear> seen on the street with Figa. You ought to see her;
                     she looks like regular "sheeny."</p>
                  <p>Just at this point in the conversation Miss Rosinetta addressed the reporter,
                     and volunteered the following description of Figa:</p>
                  <p>"She was short and very fat, with red hair a yard long, which she wore in two
                     large braids down her back. Her hair, in fact, was so very red that we all
                     called her 'Carrot.' She had black eyes, but one of them was much darker than
                     the other. Her neck was perfectly beautiful. Her hands were short, fat, and
                     very red. She had only half nails on her fingers. Her feet were very small—she
                     wore No. 3 shoes. She spoke very little English. She was so fat that she had no
                     figure; her shoulders and waist seemed to come together. As my grandmother has
                     told you, She looks like a regular sheeny.'"</p>
                  <p>To Mrs. Leonora Rosenzweig, the doctor's wife, our reporter addressed the
                     question, "Is it true that a woman died in child-bed in your husband's house
                     about three months ago?"</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>STILL ANOTHER VICTIM.</head>
                  <p>The doctor's wife (hesitatingly).—You mean the woman Mary—Hughes, I think her
                     name was. Yes, she died in my house about three months ago.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Was her husband with her when she died?</p>
                  <p>The doctor's wife.—I suppose you mean George; he was not her husband. His name
                     was Hughes, and he was Mary's brother-in-law.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did the baby live?</p>
                  <p>The doctor's wife—Oh, yes; I kept it two or three weeks after the mother's
                     death, and then my sevant girl, Jane Johnson, took it to the Sisters on
                     Waverley Place. The baby was sickly, because the mother died with dropsy. She
                     was in my house about three weeks, and was confined two weeks after she came
                     there. I was sick, and didn't ask her where she lived; but she told me that she
                     lived in the country. If you ask the undertaker who sent her body home you can
                     find out where she came from.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Did your husband attend her during her sickness?</p>
                  <p>The doctor's wife.—He did, and was assisted by Dr. Rosenthal.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Have you heard anything lately of the whereabouts of Figa?</p>
                  <pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6545-00000043"/>
                  <p>The doctor's wife.—No; my husband wrote to the Burgomeister of the town in
                     Poland as soon as he heard she had gone, and afterward telegraphed, but never
                     received an answer.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Are you acquainted with Dr. Cetlinski?</p>
                  <p>The doctor's wife.—Oh, yes; the doctor often called at our house to see my
                     husband.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—How long have you been married?</p>
                  <p>The doctor's wife.—I was married to Dr. Rosenzweig in Warsaw, Poland, fifteen
                     years ago. My parents are still living there; their name is Gefülhaus.</p>
                  <p>Letters are in possession of the police showing that Mrs. Rosenzweig's father's
                     name is Phillips, and that he lives in Birmingham, England. This throws doubts
                     on all her statements.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>FIGA'S NAME NOT ON THE PASSENGER LIST.</head>
                  <p>Inspector Walling, with his detectives, made most untiring efforts to discover
                     the whereabouts of the woman who accompanied the trunk to the depot, but thus
                     far he had been baffled. The strap which the baggage man had sold to the woman,
                     and which was placed around the trunk, has been resold by the baggage man,
                     although orders were left to preserve it as evidence. Inquiries were made at
                     the offices of the German steamships in this city and in Hoboken whether a
                     ticket had been sold to a woman of the name of Figa Rosenzweig. A careful
                     examination of the books for the past four months failed to reveal any such
                     name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>LAWYERS DISAGREE.</head>
                  <p>Ex-Judge Sydney H. Stuart stated that the evidence already accumulated against
                     Dr. Rosenzweig was sufficient to convict him, and that he would not assume the
                     case for the defence for any amount. On the contrary Counsellor Howe, who has
                     taken the case, yesterday told Rosenzweig that there was no case at all against
                     him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE CHILD-SLAYER'S PROFITS.</head>
                  <p>Among the effects found in Rosenzweig's house were several bank books, showing
                     deposits in different banks to the amount of several thousand dollars. Also,
                     three lady's gold watches, besides the one worn by the doctor's wife, and a
                     quantity of jewelry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE FIGA ROSENZWEIG MYSTERY.</head>
                  <p>The mystery attending the sudden disappearance of Miss Figa Rosenzweig is still
                     unravelled, and circumstances strongly point to the fiend Rosenzweig as the
                     person most intimately connected with the deep damnation of her taking off. The
                     contradictory stories told by the doctor and the female members of his family,
                     then the version of the affair as given by the servant girl, Jane Johnson, and
                     Figa's aunt, Mrs. Goldwasser, of 450 Pearl street, all point with unerring
                     finger towards Rosenzweig as the murderer of the girl Figa. Our reporter called
                     on Mrs. Goldwasser at her residence, and asked her if she still persisted in
                     the story should Capt. Kennedy, viz., that Figa had left for Poland four weeks
                     ago with a ticket purchased for her by Dr. Rosenzweig. Mrs. Goldwasser
                     said:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE AUNT'S VERSION.</head>
                  <p>"When Figa came to my house to live she was always complaining of being sick,
                     and I said she ought to go home to Poland. She said she had no money. I then
                     went to Dr. Rosenzweig and asked him to buy a ticket for her. He said he would
                     see her d—before he would give her one cent, and advised me to make her enter a
                     house of ill-fame, saying it was an easy way of making money, and that Figa was
                     a very pretty girl. I then went home and told Figa what he had said. She then
                     became very angry, and said, 'I'll show him something: I'll make him give me
                     money or anything else that I want. I've got a hold on him, and he dare not
                     refuse me.' She then dressed herself and started, as she said, for the doctor's
                     office. She returned in about an hour and showed me $50, which she said the
                     doctor had given her. The next day she went out again, and on her return she
                     showed me a ticket, which she said the doctor had bought for but."</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Was your husband present when Dr. Rosenzweig called at your house to
                     see Figa?</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Goldwasser (coloring).—My husband, about four years ago, got into bad
                     company. A burglary was committed in Brooklyn. My husband was arrested as the
                     guilty party, and sent to Sing Sing for ten years. I've got five children, and
                     support them by peddling dry goods through the country. My oldest boy helps me
                     by blacking boots and selling papers.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Were you acquainted with Dr. Rosenzweig's family in Poland?</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Goldwasser.—Oh yes, I knew them intimately.</p>
                  <p>Reporter.—Have you ever heard that the doctor had any other cases of
                     malpractice?</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Goldwasser.—Yes I heard that he was the cause of the death of a young
                     Jewess 17 years old, Miss Hester Tennelow, living with her mother in Pearl near
                     Chatham street. She died about three weeks ago, but as I am not positive about
                     the circumstances, you had better inquire of the neighbors, and they can tell
                     you more.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6545-00000044"/>
               <head>THE TRIAL OF ROSENZWEIG.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE SISTER AND MOTHER OF THE MURDERED GIRL IN COURT.—PRODUCTION OF
                  THE HORRIBLE TRUNK.</head>
               <p>THE trial of Jacob Rosenzweig, for causing the death of Alice Augusta Bowlsby, of
                  Paterson, N. J., by means of an abortion, was commenced October 26,
                     <unclear>in</unclear> the Court of General Sessions, before Recorder
                     <unclear>Hackett</unclear>. Mr. William F. Howe, the prisoner's counsel, was
                  early on hand. His junior associate sat beside him, while at the left hand side of
                  both, the principal in the trial,</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ROSENZWEIG,</head>
                  <p>surnamed the man with the colossal cranium, occupied a seat. District Attorney
                     Garvin was in attendance, and sat composedly interweaving his fingers, while
                     his able assistant, Algernon S. Sullivan, was leaning back on a chair,
                     reflecting the light of his brilliant orbs on the frontispiece of his
                     associate, Garvin.</p>
                  <p>Recorder Hackett surveyed the entire scene from the elevation of the bench, and
                     listened attentively as the District Attorney prepared to deliver his opening
                     address to the jury, who were in their places shortly after the Court room was
                     opened. The horrible trunk, in which was packed for transportation the remains
                     of the unfortunate Miss Bowlsby, was brought into Court, and kept to be put in
                     as evidence against the accused. It is an ordinary-sized trunk, and apparently
                     almost new. It was tied round with a rope, the same as when its contents were
                     inspected at the depot of the Hudson River Railroad.</p>
                  <p>At a quarter past ten, ex-Judge Garvin arose and proceeded to address the
                     twelve men sitting in judgment on the wretched prisoner. He briefly
                     recapitulated the enormity of the crime charged, and stated to the jury what he
                     expected to prove on the past of the people. The prosecution would prove that
                     the deceased left her aunt's house in Newark on the 23d of August, 1871, and
                     that she entered the dark, fearful den of the accused. They would also prove
                     that she was never seen alive after entering this den. Her body was afterwards
                     sent from the house in the trunk, then lying under the stenographer's desk, but
                     none of her clothing was found upon it. They would be able to show by the
                     medical testimony from what cause Miss Bowlsby died.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF MRS. BOWLSBY.</head>
                  <p>Mrs. Bowlsby, the mother of the unfortunate Alice, was called as the first
                     witness for the people. Witness briefly described the apparel of her daughter
                     on the day she left to come to this city. After which she continued:—She also
                     had a handkerchief with her, marked "A. Bowlsby," and a small basket containing
                     some little trinkets; I never heard anything from or of my child after she
                     left, until the body was <unclear>recognized</unclear> by Dr. Kenny at the
                     Morgue; the deceased had a mole on the left side of her neck, and a
                        <unclear>vaccination</unclear> on her left arm just above the elbow; on the
                     left side of her jaw there was a scar caused from an ulcerated tooth which had
                     broken off; there was also an eye tooth missing on the right side of her
                     mouth.</p>
                  <p>At the conclusion of this testimony, the counsel for Rosenzweig proceeded to
                     cross-examine</p>
                  <p>The Witness.—I did not see the handkerchief my daughter took away with her on
                     the 23d of August. I knew all her handkerchiefs from the mark of "A. Bowlsby;"
                     she wore a false bosom, or pads, at the time of leaving; the bosom was the same
                     as very many ladies wear; Alice was the eldest of my children; her age was
                     twenty-five.</p>
                  <p>In reply to the District Attorney.—There was a young gentleman who used to keep
                     company with my daughter; his name was Mr. Walter Conklin; he died on a
                     Thursday; I don't remember the date; he committed suicide by shooting himself;
                     he used to frequently visit the house; I do not know whether they were engaged
                     or not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MISS CARRIE BOWLSBY,</head>
                  <p>the sister of the deceased, generally corroborated the testimony given by her
                     mother. She recognized the pads shown as the ones made by her sister out of
                     material belonging to a dress.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>JANE JOHNSON, THE SERVANT GIRL OF THE PRISONER,</head>
                  <p>was placed next on the stand.—Have lived with Dr. Rosenzweig; I was doing
                     housework in the doctor's house; about the time of the trunk trouble, the
                     parties living in the house were, the prisoner and his wife, her four children
                     and myself; there was a young girl also; she was not living there, but she used
                     to be there a great deal; her name was Nettie; I don't know her last name; the
                     deceased came there with the prisoner on the 23d inst.; I saw her going up
                     stairs; the Doctor, I think, went up with her; I never saw her after; I know
                     that the woman called Nettie knew that the woman in white, the deceased was in
                     the house.</p>
                  <p>The trunk was here shown. The witness said she either saw that trunk, or one
                     like it, in the kitchen previous to the visit of the deceased. I heard that the
                     lady in white was a patient of the Doctor's I heard it from Rosie, the
                     prisoner's daughter; the trunk that looked like the one shown in Court belonged
                     to the woman Nettie, who so often visited the house.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>WILLIAM PICKETT,</head>
                  <p>of No. 471 First Avenue, the carman who was hired to carry the trunk to the
                     Hudson River depot, testified that on Saturday, the 26th of August, he took a
                     trunk from the house of the prisoner; a young woman came to his stand and
                     wanted him to take a trunk from Thirty-seventh street and Second Avenue to the
                     Hudson River depot; he took the trunk from 687 Second Avenue; this same woman,
                     accompanied by a boy, whose name the afterwards heard was Potts, met him at the
                     depot when he arrived there with the trunk; a man opened the door, and I told
                     him that I called for a trunk to take to Twenty-ninth street; the man then took
                     hold of one end and helped to lift the trunk on the cart; that is the trunk
                     (pointing to the one in court), and that man (pointing to the prisoner,
                     Rosenzweig) is the man that helped me carry the trunk; he is the man; he never
                     spoke word; when we arrived at the depot, the boy assisted me to set the trunk
                     on the counter to get it checked, afterwards the woman helped also; she looked
                     at the lock on the trunk, and said she was afraid it would not hold; a strap
                     was then put round it, for which the woman paid a dollar; I then went away. The
                     witness recognized a boy shown him in Court as the one who helped him with the
                     trunk at the depot.</p>
                  <p>The witness was cross-examined at considerable length, but it failed to shake
                     his evidence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ALEXANDER POTTS,</head>
                  <p>the boy who assisted in carrying the trunk into the depot, was placed on the
                     stand. He testified as fellows:—I live at 429 Eighth Avenue; I carry baggage
                     for a living, and remember being on Thirtieth street on Saturday, the 26th of
                     August; I met a woman man on that day; she came in a cab; I recognize the
                     carman; the woman asked me if I knew anything about the trains; she came ten
                     minutes before the man with the trunk; she bought a ticket for Chicago at
                     half-past four; I would know the trunk I helped to carry to the depot if saw
                     it.</p>
                  <p>Q. Is that the trunk? (the trunk in Court was here shown the witness.) A. Yes,
                     sir, that is the trunk I saw; the baggage man checked the trunk for Chicago,
                     and gave her a ticket for the same place; I afterwards saw the trunk opened,
                     and saw a naked dead body; the body was squeezed in the trunk; the body as
                     lying on its side and doubled up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>PETER MURPHY,</head>
                  <p>police officer, sworn:—The baggage master called my attention to the trunk
                     lying outside on the platform; we opened the trunk and found the body of a
                     woman wrapped in some blankets and other things; I reported at the station
                     house, and then delivered the body at Bellevue Hospital.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THOMAS S. BRENNAN.</head>
                  <p>Warden in Bellevue Hospital, identified the trunk as the one that was brought
                     to the dead house; Drs. Henry and Parker examined the body twice; they had a
                     photograph of the deceased.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>DR. JOSEPH F. PARKER</head>
                  <p>was the next witness. He said he was a dentist at Paterson, knew Mrs. Bowlsby,
                     and accompanied Dr. Kenny to the Morgue, when they identified the body as being
                     that of Miss Bowlsby; he saw the mark of vaccination, the mole and the cicatrix
                     formed by an ulcerated tooth on the right side of the lower jaw; he found the
                     eye tooth gone, broken off, which he had been about two months before in the
                     mouth of Miss Bowlsby, whose dentist the witness had been for five years.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>JAMES F. BOYD,</head>
                  <p>an undertaker, doing business at 336 East Thirty-fifth street, testified that
                     on the Saturday morning before the body was found at the depot, the prisoner,
                     Rosenzweig, came to him and said that a servant girl of his had died, and asked
                     how much it would cost to bury her; witness asked him where she was, and the
                     prisoner replied, "Not far away from here," but he did not state where; he said
                     she was very poor, and had about $10; the prisoner asked him if he could take
                     the body of this girl to his store, and he told him that he could not; that he
                     (the prisoner) would first have to get a certificate from the doctor; the
                     prisoner said the doctor lived away down town: he went out, and said he would
                     call again.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>OFFICER LARUE</head>
                  <p>testified that he went Pickett, the carman, to Rosenzweig's house in search of
                     the girl who had charge of the trunk at the depot, but could not find her; on
                     Wednesday, the 30th of August, the officer searched for clothing, and found in
                     a stationary wash-tub in the back basement of the prisoner's house a
                     handkerchief marked "A. A. Bowlsby," with a lot of children's clothing, and
                     ladies' wearing apparel; Sergeant Randall found a blue sash in a bureau drawer
                     up stairs, and also some jewelry—two ladies' watches, chains, breastpins, and
                     rings—which were returned to Mrs. Rosenzweig.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>OFFICER RANDALL</head>
                  <p>testified that he found a blue sash, and also the false bosom, which he marked
                     at the time; the bosom he found in a barrel of old clothing in the kitchen;
                     part of a bloody chemise and skirt were found in the cellar, covered over with
                     dirt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>DR. JOSEPH CUSHMAN</head>
                  <p>testified that he made a post-mortem examination of the body of Alice Augusta
                     Bowlsby, at the Morgue, on Sunday, the 27th of August; the body was 5 feet 3
                     inches long, and well developed; the hair was blonde and the eyes blue; there
                     were no external marks of violence. In the Doctor's opinion, death resulted
                     from metro-peritonitis, caused by abortion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE DEFENCE.</head>
                  <p>William F. Howe, the indefatigable counsel for Rosenzweig, then proceeded in an
                     able and exhaustive argument to open the case for the defence, and in an
                     argument of great length said that the crime imputed to the prisoner was
                     fiendish in the extreme, and might well be hurled back against those who had
                     charged him with a fiendish crime—a crime so full of revolting circumstances
                     that humanity must shrink at it aghast.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MEDICAL TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>Drs. Garrish and Parker were called for the defence, and gave testimony upon
                     more technical questions on obstetrics, that served very little to elucidate
                     the main point at issue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ANOTHER MRS. BOWLSBY.</head>
                  <p>The next witness called for the defence was a demure-looking female, aged about
                     thirty, who said her name was Mrs. Cornelia Bowlsby; she lived in Myrtle
                     avenue, Brooklyn; I am married and have six children; one of the my children is
                     named Anna Martini Bowlsby; she is now married; she is sick now and not here,
                     but was here on Monday; she had</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A POCKET HANDKERCHIEF</head>
                  <p>marked; I visited you (counsel) at your office recently, and afterwards went to
                     the Districts Attorney's office to see the handkerchief marked "A. M. Bowlsby;
                     "I would know that handkerchief.</p>
                  <p>The handkerchief was here shown the witness, who pronounced it the same as the
                     one she had seen in the District Attorney's office.</p>
                  <p>It is somewhat dirtier than when I first saw it; I should say that</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE LETTERS ON THE CORNER OF THAT HANDKERCHIEF</head>
                  <p>were A. M., with the M partially rubbed out, also a B, which is partially
                     obscured; I don't know how my daughter marked her handkerchiefs; we visited Dr.
                     Rosenzweig's on the 7th of August, the Thursday before my daughter was married;
                     we had some wine at the doctor's house; my daughter got some wine on her gloves
                     and took them off and wiped her hand with her handkerchief; we read of the
                     finding of the handkerchief in the newspapers, and my daughter then said</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SHE WOULD BET</head>
                  <p>the handkerchief spoken of was hers.</p>
                  <p>Cross-examined—My husband's given name is William Henry; we are not related to
                     the Bowlsbys of Jersey; we never heard of them previous to this trial; I did
                     not see my daughter marking her handkerchief; I did not make known what I knew
                     about</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THIS HANDKERCHIEF</head>
                  <p>until Mrs. Rosenzweig came to my house; that was, I think, about three weeks
                     ago; I did not give her any satisfaction; I did not notice particularly, what
                     kind of a handkerchief my daughter had at the Rosenweig's only, that it was a
                     very common one. (Several questions were asked of the witness, and the latter
                     endeavored to equivocate. In fact she<pb n="104" xml:id="VAC6545-00000045"/>
                     persistently, wilfully affected to misunderstand the queries pat to her.) A man
                     came to our house in Brooklyn just before my daughter got married, and wanted
                     to sell some stencil plates; he marked one handkerchief for my daughter—marked
                     it A. M. Bowlsby; he marked it in the hall; I was in the basement at the time;
                     I know he marked it; this was the only one that was marked.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TESTIMONY OF JACOB COHEN.</head>
                  <p>Mr. Cohen examined:—I was sick on the Saturday the trunk was found at the
                     railroad depot; I sent for Dr. Rosenzweig, who came to me at about half-past
                     twelve; he sat two or three hours with me, as I was very sick.</p>
                  <p>Cross examined:—I do not recollect what date it was, but I know two or three
                     days afterwards the doctor was arrested; I am a cigar and cigarette
                     manufacturer; I was sick at my house, which is some distance from Mr.
                     Rosenzweig's house; the doctor was with me nearly all the time he staid, with
                     the exception of going back and forth to the store in front.</p>
                  <p>After some unimportant testimony as to the reputation and character of the
                     prisoner,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ROSENZWEIG WAS PUT UPON THE STAND.</head>
                  <p>He testified as follows:—I am a physician; I reside at 687 Second avenue; I
                     graduated in Warsaw; I came to this country in 1865; I established my business
                     in this country at 33 Bayard street; I know the Bowlsbys of Brooklyn; I have
                     known them about six or seven months; I never did know the Bowlsbys of
                     Paterson; I have heard all the testimony that has been given in this Court; my
                     wife and daughter are in Court; never saw the girl Nellie Willis now in Court,
                     at No. 3 Amity place, within a year or two, and never performed an abortion
                     upon her; he also emphatically stated that the undertaker's testimony was all
                     false; that he never said anything about a servant girl being dead near by; he
                     did not know a woman named Nettie staying in his house on Friday or Saturday
                     nights, and when Jane Johnson swore to that she testified to what was not true.
                     Before he left the stand Rosenzweig said, he never performed an abortion at any
                     place in the city of New York, nor did he know of any woman being brought to
                     his house, dead or alive, during the week of the alleged occurrence who had any
                     operation performed upon her.</p>
                  <p>The counsel, at a quarter past ten, proceeded to address the jury on behalf of
                     the accused. He (the counsel) would show, when he came to direct the attention
                     of the jury to the evidence, that the District Attorney had failed completely
                     to prove anything against his client. They (the defence) contended, first,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE BODY TAKEN TO THE MORGUE</head>
                  <p>was not that of Alice Augusta Bowlsby. The jury must have in their minds some
                        <unclear>doubt</unclear> as to the identity of the body found in the trunk
                     with that of the missing girl, the murdered Alice A. Bowlsby. The jury must
                     have a doubt of this, because the mother of the deceased herself had. The
                     counsel continued at considerable length, endeavoring to interpret the
                     testimony in a favorable light for the wretched man who was his client, but the
                     effort was a total failure. He</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CONCLUDED</head>
                  <p>with a Tombs Police Court appeal to the jury to have pity on the wife and
                     children of the prisoner, whom the jury would deprive of a natural protector,
                     etc., if they concluded to convict. He concluded at a quarter to twelve, at
                     which time District Attorney Garvin arose to argue the case on behalf of the
                     people.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>AFTERNOON PROCEEDINGS.</head>
                  <p>District Attorney Garvin commenced his address by depicting in elegant language
                     the enormity of the crime with which the prisoner stood charged. After this he
                     ably recapitulated the bits of evidence the together made so conclusive the
                     guilt of Rosenzweig. He explained to the jury the temptations to which young
                     girls, who have an inheritance of beauty which is more</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>DANGEROUS TO THEIR PEACE OF MIND</head>
                  <p>afterward than anything else they may possess, <unclear>as</unclear> subjected
                     day by day until they arrive at woman hood, and after they arrive at that
                     period, they meet one whom they love. They are importuned, caressed and in a
                     moment of thoughtlessness they fall—then ruin is consummated. The vile seducer
                     has no responsibility, his victim</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>DARE NOT DENOUNCE HIM</head>
                  <p>because by so doing she lays herself open to the <unclear>cold</unclear>
                     criticism and sarcasm of an unsympathetic world. She dare not talk to her
                     father. She cannot to her mother. She will not divulge the secret grief that is
                     gnawing at her heart to her sister, and her brother if she has one, is not
                     approachable. Her seduce has forsaken her, and walks erect among his fellow men
                     in comparative security. What then is</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE POOR VICTIM</head>
                  <p>to do? To whom will she fly for relief? She take up a newspaper, runs her eyes
                     up one column an down another. The advertisements of such fiends to the
                     prisoner arrest her attention, stating that his business is the relieving girls
                     of their troubles in this way. She goes to him in a moment of desperation, and
                     is lost! Her cold corpse is the result. How many</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SLEEPLESS NIGHTS</head>
                  <p>testify to the agony of mind of the seduced <unclear>girl</unclear> previous to
                     taking the fatal determination of consulting these hell-hounds called
                     abortionists; when she knows and calculates with horror that every day brings
                     her nearer shame? O, what a fate is this How many unfortunate, erring women
                     have died lingering agonizing deaths at the hands of these Dr. Aschers, who
                     sticks a sign out in</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A DARK ALLEY,</head>
                  <p>and allures the miserable into his lair? This man practices abortions in Amity
                     place as Dr. Aschers he keeps a place in Second avenue as Dr. Rosenzweig for a
                     respectable business. If he is discovered in his vile doings, it is Dr. Ascher
                     that is arrested, and no Dr. Rosenzweig. Does not this speak for itself?</p>
                  <p>The learned gentleman then</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>WENT ON TO ANALYZE THE EVIDENCE,</head>
                  <p>and draw deductions applicable to the points of the case.</p>
                  <p>When Judge Garvin concluded, Recorder Hackett charged the jury. The counsel for
                     Rosenzweig read several points which he requested the Recorder to incorporate
                     in his charge, which was done with three exceptions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE CHARGE</head>
                  <p>of his Honor was an elaborte and lengthy one, and thoroughly exhaustive. The
                     case was given to the jury at precisely nine minutes after two o'clock, who
                     retired to deliberate, and did not return up to three o'clock.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE VERDICT.</head>
                  <p>The jury returned at twenty minutes to four, with a verdict of guilty of
                     manslaughter in the second degree. Recorder Hackett then sentenced him to the
                     State Prison at hard labor for seven years. He regretted that the penalty was
                     not death.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
