<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6062">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Happy Home, Woman's Rights, and Divorce </title>
            <author>Clark, S. W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6062</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0535</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Happy home, woman's rights, and divorce</title>
                  <author>Clark, S. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>45 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Chicago Ill. </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1875">1875</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-03-05">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-04-30">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (Cover) " xml:id="VAC6062-00000001"/>
         <div type="half_title">
            <bibl>
               <title>HAPPY HOME WOMAN'S RIGHTS AND DIVORCE</title>
            </bibl>
           
         </div>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6062-00000002"/>
         <titlePage>
            
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>HAPPY HOME, WOMAN'S RIGHTS, AND DIVORCE,</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>S. W. CLARK, MINNEAPOLIS, MINN.,</docAuthor> Author of "From the Sublime to the Ridiculous."</byline>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>CHICAGO, ILL.</pubPlace>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1875">1875.</docDate>
            </titlePage>
            <pb n="3" xml:id="VAC6062-00000003"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1875, BY S. W. CLARK, In the Office of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington.</edition>
            </bibl>
         </div>
            
       
         <div type="introduction">
            <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>Having spent a number of years in Colorado and the Rocky Mountains, and being with old hunters and trappers a part of the time, I gathered from them information which gave rise to the subject of this story. The life of Edward Gayloyd Farnham, (Buckskin Ned,) and Minnie C. Dunbar, (the heroine sheriff,) shows a striking instance of genuine true love and a happy home. Hoping that the moral contained within these pages may make a good and lasting impression upon the minds of the public, I leave the reader to judge of its merits.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6062-00000004"/>
         <div type="preface">
            
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>There is nothing so essential to mankind as a happy and loving home, a home of parental devotion and filial affection, where all of the family blend together in unison and harmony. But there is an epidemic in the land called "woman's rights," which has crept into many of our loving homes, and spoiled our doves, making hawks of them. Divorce steps in, cuts the bonded cord and leaves the home in ruins</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>AUTHOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Happy home, woman's rights, and divorce</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HAPPY HOME</head>
               <head type="sub">Woman's Rights and Divorce</head>
               <p>IT was during the year eighteen hundred and seventy, when women's rights were in full force in the Territory of Wyoming that a heroic woman was elected sheriff, and even wielded a sceptre of influence and power over a small railroad town on the Union Pacific, near six hundred miles west of Omaha. Before giving you a history of her daring deeds and wild adventures, I will describe that novel, embryo town which was named in honor, or rather after a blood-thirsty band of red-skins called Cheyennes, who roam from their reservations killing buffalo, elk, deer, antelope or pale faces indiscriminately. Uncle Sam donates them blankets, guns, ammunition, and provisions. The Government agent, or some one else, sells them poor whiskey, gets them drunk, takes advantage of their ignorance, then who gets the cream of the donation? Nothing is said and all goes lovely until we are reminded of these free gifts by some horrible,<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6062-00000005"/> bloodthirsty, Indian massacre; and even then some will say it was nothing but poor Lo, whose untutored mind snuffeth up the east wind.</p>
               <p>Cheyenne is situated on a high plateau or table land near the western verge of the great American desert. To the west and southwest your vision beholds a long line of snow-capped mountains with long peaks in their midst seemingly penetrating the very sky, as though she were keeping sentinel over a brood of lesser peaks around her.</p>
               <p>Towards the rising sun you can see nothing but a vast sea of naked plains, once the happy home of Indians, buffalo and prairie dogs.</p>
               <p>Cheyenne was laid out and built near its present size in 1867. During its early history it was a large trading point, being a focal centre for Idaho, Montana, Utah, Colorado and New Mexico. Long trains of mule and ox teams left daily, loaded with goods for the mines and various government posts. These trains were generally owned and propelled by dusky Mexicans, who massed together and moved in large trains as a protection against Indians and robbers. They were prepared at all times to fight the red skins or straggling highwaymen. While Cheyenne was yet in its infancy it was in full possession of armed banditti ditti, robbers and blacklegs. It was even dangerous to be safe, and not safe to be a man of principles. Law and order was unknown. Honest men were shot down in the streets, hung up to trees and their bones left to whiten and dangle in the midnight air.</p>
               <p>But time makes changes, there must be a law for the lawless, and a speedy execution of the law. Every dog must have his day, so this border town had had its day. Emigration began to pour in, vigilance committees were formed, outlaws were caught and hung, holes more black and damning than the infernal regions were closed up. Soon law and order reigned supreme, and this frontier town began to wear an aspect of civilization.</p>
               <p>Emigrants continued to pour in, and in a few years the surrounding hills and valleys were dotted with flocks of sheep and countless herds of cattle—the result of untiring industry and stern perseverance.</p>
               <p>But I must return to the principal actor in this story. The heroine sheriff, or as we will call her, Minnie C. Dunbar. During a certain session of the Legislature of the Territory women suffrage became a law. The gentler sex had a right to hold office, vote, hold the plough, drive mules, <emph>lick</emph> their husbands and wear the breeches generally if they saw proper<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6062-00000006"/> to do so. At a certain election held in Cheyenne for electing county officers, Miss Minnie was unanimously elected high sheriff. She was a large muscular woman, athletic in frame, well proportioned, auburn hair, intermingled with red and yellow, and hung in wavy tresses upon her shoulders. She had a dare-devil eye, but with-all rather a pleasing countenance and a determined look, as much as to say, "I can "catch a thief." She was well selected from her sex, and got an overwhelming vote in her favor. Her election was a great novelty among the boys, and on several occasions petty thefts were perpetrated and the woman sheriff sent in pursuit. The culprits were generally brought back in irons and duly punished for their supposed fun, but sport of that nature soon fell to zero. Minnie had a man of the male persuasion for a deputy, so all moved on safe and lovely.</p>
               <p>Her skill as an officer was tested almost daily. She soon became an adept in the business, and even a terror to law-breaking citizens. But the scene is soon to be changed, life is full of stirring events, especially among female sheriffs. Early one morning in July Minnie was informed that a store had been broken into and robbed, a horse also had been stolen and tracks in the soft sand were seen making off in a southerly direction towards Denver. She hurriedly buckled on her revolver and knife, took a pair of hand-cuffs, mounted her sure-footed horse and was off in pursuit with the fleetness of the wind.</p>
               <p>She had rode on several miles before the thought came into her mind that she was all alone. She had in her hurry forgotten to summons her deputy, and she would need his help in catching so formidable a thief. If she returned for the needed assistance the fugitive would be out of reach and past taking, for if he should get across the river he would be among low timber and underbrush, and have a much better chance of escape. So, on second thought, she put the spurs into fleetwing, resolving that she could and would take the thief alone. At the end of ten miles she rode up to a dilapidated stage station with her horse in a white foam of sweat. She inquired of the keeper if he had seen any one riding past on a dark bay horse. He said a man rode by on that description of a horse; had passed not more than thirty minutes before and enquired if the water was high at the ford. On, on she pursued with lightning rapidity. It was only ten miles to the river, and she must overtake him before he reaches the ford or he would dash over and make into the jungle.</p>
               <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6062-00000007"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Minnie capturing the thief at the ford of the Cache-a-la-poudre.—(WOMAN'S RIGHTS.)</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>On ascending a hill in the road and looking down towards the river she clearly saw the absconding thief not more than one-fourth of a mile in her advance. He was on the lookout and saw her about the same time that he was discovered. It was now only a trial of speed who should win, for he well knew if he could reach the ford first and get safely over to the opposite bank he could get into the thicket and soon hide himself from his pursuers, for he supposed her deputy was close in the rear and he would be an easy prey in the hand of two so well armed. He reaches the water's edge and dashes into the turbulent stream, but ere he reaches the middle of the foaming river she is at the water's edge calling out in a commanding voice, "Hold on, thief; "stop! or I'll shoot you down in the water!" He looked back to see from whom the command came, and, unfortunately for him, his foot slipped from the stirrup, his horse stumbled and threw him sprawling into the water. He caught hold of a snag and managed to get on his feet again just as Minnie rode up to him. His pistol had fallen from its scabbard into the stream, and she had no trouble in making him her prisoner. She put on a pair of handcuffs and marched him to the opposite bank where his horse had already gained the shore and was quietly grazing with the pack of stolen goods firmly lashed to the saddle.</p>
               <p>It was now nearly midsummer and extremely warm, not even a gentle zephyr moved the leaves of the adjacent thicket. But she must rest before returning with the prisoner, so she lariatted out both horses in a fine patch of buffalo grass and then marched the thief to the shade of a friendly oak and seated herself near by. Her captive was a large portly man,<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6062-00000008"/> he wore a full suit of buckskin from head to foot. His beard was unshorn, his hair long, and hung in ringlets or rather in a knotty mat upon his neck. One would have thought he had been beyond the border of civilization for a century. However, there was an expression of countenance which reminded her of some old friend; it looked familiar, yet strange. She now, with the dignity and face of a fairy queen and the power of a high sheriff, demanded his name. Calling her by name, he said, "Minnie C. Dunbar, my name is Edward Gayloyd Farnham; my old home was Charleston, South Carolina."</p>
               <p>On hearing these words she flew to his arms and there never was such rejoicing in the wilderness beyond the Mississippi. His shackles were thrown off and there, alone, twenty miles from civilized life, she had met the one she had long sought after. One whom she dearly loved; one with whom she had played in childhood and had gone to school with while in her teens.</p>
               <p>In his younger days Gayloyd was a noble-looking and promising young man. He had taken a collegiate course in a well known institution of the South, and was well off in this world's goods. He owned a large estate and had many slaves, but the rebellion came on, his slaves were set free and his large property confiscated, which left him a penniless pauper. But still his inmost soul was carried away with Minnie; he loved her fondly, and she returned it as in his brightest days of prosperity. They were finally engaged, and the day set for their marriage. Friends were invited, and all was in readiness for the happy union of two loving hearts. But a dark cloud had already begun to dim the horizon which was to send thunder-bolts on the coming event. Since Gayloyd was now poor, Minnie's parents took decided measures to break the intimacy and the coming wedding. They did not want her to marry a poor man while her own parents were reveling in luxury. But true love cannot die. He met Minnie one week after this, and they pledged their love until death. He said he was going to seek his fortune in the far West and when he had a fortune he would send for her, and they would yet realize many happy days. She agreed to the plan, and with sealed vows, a hearty shake of the hand, a kiss and a tear they reluctantly parted, promising a faithful correspondence.</p>
               <p>Gayloyd now left his old Charleston home, went to New Orleans, thence into Texas, where he meandered up the Brazos to the western part of the State. Here he bought a few head<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6062-00000009"/> of cattle and went to stock-raising. His herd increased, and in a few years he had cattle upon a thousand hills. He was now wealthy; dame fortune had smiled upon his labor and he longed to consummate that vow taken on that memorable eve when he and Minnie parted in Charleston. He wanted her to enjoy with him the fruits of his toil, for he was full of joy and overflowing with pleasurable emotions of thought. But when amidst our brightest hopes our excessive joy is often cooled down to zero. So it was with Gayloyd.</p>
               <p>As I have before said, he was far up the Brazos; he was also on the border of hostile Indian grounds. The Comanches and Arappahoes had often made raids on the frontier ranches and drove off their entire stock, killing the herdsmen and taking their horses.</p>
               <p>It was early one morning in July, while seated alone in his adobe cabin that he heard the wild whoop of Indians and the heavy tramp of horses. A large band of mounted Comanches had broken into his corralls, made a stampede and his entire stock of cattle were headed towards the open prairie followed, in a semi-circle by the yelling Indians, who were soon lost in clouds of dust. He watched the red skins until they descended from a high plateau and were lost behind the western hills.</p>
               <p>He returned to his cabin and was for the second time at poverty's door, dejected and thoroughly disheartened. He fastened his cabin door and made his way to a stage station some forty miles distant to see if there was not a sweet missive from his dear Minnie. A letter was handed him, but it was not backed with the usual familiar hand. He tore the wrapper asunder and drew forth a note which read thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>"CHARLESTON, S. C., June 24, 1865.</dateline>
                           </opener>
                           <p>"MR. GAYLOYD FARNHAM"—SIR.—Our dear Minnie has sickened and died; was ill but a short time. Was buried in the family yard.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <salute>"Yours truly,</salute>
                              <signed>"S. WENTWORTH DUNBAR."</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This sad news came like a death-knell to his already bleeding heart. It palsied his limbs, and he sank unconscious to the ground. Restoratives were given him, and in a few days he was around again. Finally he became calm and resigned, but concluded not to go back to his cabin, or even to Charleston, but left on the first westward bound coach for Santa Fe, firmly resolved that he would spend the rest of his days far from civilization in some lone retreat in the Rocky Mountains.</p>
               <p>He reached Santa Fe in safety. From there he went up a mountain valley northward to<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6062-00000010"/> Taos in New Mexico, where he fell in with old Kit Carson, the renowned hunter, trapper and guide.</p>
               <p>Kit told him of his many adventures and hair-breadth escapes from hostile Indians and wild beasts, but now he was too old to follow the chosen vocation of his younger days, and had come to this quaint old Spanish town to spend his last days in quietude. He had married a Spanish woman of some beauty and had a number of children.</p>
               <p>At this place Gayloyd joined a band of trappers, who had for several years trapped up and down the eastern slope of the Rocky Mountains from Las Animas north to South Pass. During these several years of mountain life they had encountered many hardships, privations and hunger. Had had many narrow escapes from hostile tribes of Indians and mountain grizzlies.</p>
               <p>Gayloyd was with these trappers for a year and a half, when they were finally disbanded and separated and left the country. But Gayloyd still chose to remain in the wilderness in solitude. For the last six months he had camped near the head-waters of the Cache-a-la Poudre (Cash la pou), on the very stream where he had been taken by the woman sheriff. He had built him a neat cabin, and seldom left its immediate neighborhood except to go to some remote outpost or stage station for ammunition and provisions; but now the great continental railway was completed to Cheyenne, which was not more than fifty miles from his cabin. So he had for some time done his trading at this important point.</p>
               <p>It was while on one of these trading trips to Cheyenne, while he was laying in a winter's supply and ammunition and flour that he saw the well-known female sheriff and at once recognized her as his old betrothed and loved Minnie. He did not make himself known, but took a small package of goods from a store so as to get her on his track, and when fifteen or twenty miles from Cheyenne and all alone he would make himself known, and the more would Minnie be surprised. And it was as I have before described that he made himself known to her.</p>
               <p>Five years had passed, and from the well-dressed Edward Gayloyd Farnham of Charleston, he was entirely changed to a mountaineer. Having assumed a buckskin suit his comrades called him Buckskin Ned, which name is yet familiar with old Rocky Mountain hunters.</p>
               <p>I have now been at some length in tracing the footsteps of Gayloyd from Charleston, S. C., to his cabin home on the Cache-a-la Poudre,<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6062-00000011"/> of his discovery of Minnie in Cheyenne and of his capture by her at the ford. I will now give you her history, her escape from home, and how she had meandered from Charleston, from civilization, crossed the Mississippi, entered the American desert and finally settled in Cheyenne at an early date of its history.</p>
               <p>After Gayloyd had left his old Carolina home Minnie received letters from him regularly for a number of years, but all at once the correspondence was dropped and she heard no more of him. Was he dead or had he forsaken her. She could not think of either. Minnie's father had done the mischief, as the sequel will show.</p>
               <p>Mr. Dunbar did not want his only daughter to marry a poor man; true worth had nothing to do in this case. Nothing but a consideration of greenbacks would do the old gentleman. So to throw Minnie off the track he wrote to Gayloyd that Minnie was dead; as a result, in after life it proved his own.</p>
               <p>Minnie was now cast down, gloomy and sad. She longed once more to see the one she loved so well. She sat one evening in her room all alone, and while thus meditating she made up her mind to roam, in hopes of once more seeing his familiar face. If he had died in the far West she wished to plant an evergreen and drop a friendly tear upon his grave.</p>
               <p>Minnie's father was a wealthy cotton planter, and she the only daughter, and at no distant day she would be sole possessor. If she wished for money all she had to do was to ask for it. She had free access to his safe, and when she wanted a few hundred dollars she only had to give the amount to the book-keeper so he could keep his cash account right. By this means of securing money she took one thousand dollars and told her parents she was going to Atlanta, Georgia, to visit some cousins. Instead of going cousining she made direct for New Orleans, and into Texas, in search of Gayloyd. She ascended the Brazos for five hundred miles, and after a long and weary search she found the ranche and the little adobe cabin where Gayloyd had spent three long years in accumulating his large stock of cattle.</p>
               <p>She broke into the cabin and found everything as he had left it. There stood his rude table and old chair where he had written many a line to his far-off Minnie. In one corner was his cot as he had left it; near by stood his stove, a perfect wreck; one would have thought it had come over with the pilgrims in the Mayflower, for its age was unmistakable. On a shelf she found a package of letters, all being backed by her own familiar hand.</p>
               <p>She left reluctantly, closing the door after her. The one she was seeking for had gone<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6062-00000012"/> she knew not where. She looked about her, but could see nothing but naked plains and herds of grazing cattle. The Brazos went bubbling by, and its smooth surface dazzled in the noon-day sun. She was told that the Comanches had run off his stock, and when last heard from he had gone to a stage station, taken a coach for Santa Fe; and from an old trapper she learned that he had joined a band of hunters and was many miles away to the northwest.</p>
               <p>It was useless for her to pursue him any further in this direction, for she would have to pass through hostile Indian tribes and be in danger of perpetual captivity among the savages. Her courage was yet good, and she resolved to tack in another direction. Retraceing her steps to the Mississippi she took a steamer for St. Louis, and from there up the Missouri to old Fort Leavenworth, in Kansas, resolving to trend her way either by wagon train or Union Pacific to some point near the mountains, and in this way she might accidentally hear of her long lost Gayloyd. As a trapper he would in all probability come out to some of those points to sell his furs and procure ammunition and provisions.</p>
               <p>At Leavenworth she joined an ox train going out to South Pass and Salt Lake. It was composed of sixty wagons, two hundred men, women and children. They were going there to settle, therefore took along their flocks and herds. She made an arrangement with a Mr. Raymond to take her to South Pass for fifty dollars. He had a wife, two daughters and a small boy; was from Eastern Tennessee and wanted to make himself a home somewhere in the great Salt Lake valley.</p>
               <p>The train was soon fitted up and in readiness, and the long line of prairie schooners moved westward. Day after day they plodded on, being constantly in clouds of dust. At night their wagons were drawn up so as to form a hollow circle, or artificial barricade, or it might be called a temporary fort, against the Indians. After the stock had grazed sufficiently they were driven within the enclosed wagon corrall for the night. At nine o'clock a guard was thrown out and the rest rolled themselves up in their blankets for the night.</p>
               <p>On the eleventh day out they reached what is now called South Platte city. Here the train remained over a few days to recruit themselves and stock. South Platte city is a genuine young America, an embryo rail road town, gotten up and thrown together in a hurry for speculative purposes. The city was composed of a few adobe huts, a temporary Hotel and a<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6062-00000013"/> Station house, although it was situated in the midst of a fertile prairie country and destined at no distant day to be a place of some importance.</p>
               <p>After a full rest the train moved on, following the windings of the Platte in a westerly direction, sometimes near the rail road and at other times remote from it.</p>
               <p>They were now nearing the Indian country, where blood-thirsty Cheyennes and Arapahoes might be encountered with at any time, on even a moments warning, But a few days before the rail road had been torn up and a car thrown off, and several of the passengers killed outright. The train now moved compactly, slow and cautious, corralling their stock early and making careful preparations for any intruding enemy.</p>
               <p>On the 13th day of June, as they were bringing in their stock for the night, a lone Indian rode by at full speed. This seemed to the wagon master as a premonition of coming danger. Every preparation necessary was made for an Indian raid. Minnie put her revolver in ship shape and buckeled it on carefully, putting her knife in the sheath of her belt, she was determined to sell her life as dear as possible. Her cartridge box was laid under her head, and she rolled up in her blanket for the night, but no sleep came to her eyelids, a sense of danger had taken full possession of her. Midnight came, and the long wakeful hours of night passed wearily. All was still as a death knell save the low moaning winds and occasionally the yell of a distant wolf. The second watch was now on and it was three o'clock, she had just fallen into a doze when the guard fired their guns. The Indians were upon them, and in an instant, every man was at his post. The yelling of the savages seemed as though Pandimonium was let loose, and all the combined tribes of North America were upon them. But as I have before said, they were well prepared for the redskins; their wagons were good baricades, and they returned the fire with deadly aim, causing many of the indians to kiss the dust. It was now day-light, and still the fight went on. The whites had the advantage of the ground, being on a slight eminence. But an unseen trouble threatened their doom. In the affray their stock had broken from the enclosure and were pouring out upon the plain, if the red devils should get their cattle they would in a measure be powerless. But an unseen providence was at hand, soldiers who were stationed on the railroad for its protection, had heard the firing and on this critical moment came dashing in upon the scene of action, almost unpreceived by friend or foe. The Cheyennes made instantaneous flight hotly pursued by our mounted cavalry, and in less<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6062-00000014"/> than ten minutes nothing could be seen but clouds of dust, on the distant prairie. They now ventured beyond their wagon barricade to view the battle ground, there lay their dead enemy in their gore. They had killed twenty-one Cheyennes and eleven ponies. Having no use for scalps their carcasses were left upon the ground for ravens, coyetts and wolves. The stock had not gone far, was soon collected together and the train moved on again as usual.</p>
               <p>As they moved farther west, the country became more sterile, barren and desolate, it was rather on the order of high table lands, interspersed with high cliffs, with now and then a lone tree. Game became more plenty, especially deer, antelope and buffalo. Prairie dogs became as numerous as bed bugs in a hotel, but were not so fierce and ravenous as some I have become acquainted with. By the way, I have a good bed bug story to relate which sadly came to my knowledge some years ago at a hotel in Denver, but I will not relate it in full for it might keep emigration out of Colorado. On my first night at this place, these little brutes followed me to the register, took my name, the number of my room, and were there <foreign xml:lang="FRA">en masse</foreign> when I entered the apartement, ready for active business, and they meant business too, for it was a long sad night. The number of regular pitched battles I will not relate, I shall keep that a profound secret, suffice it to say that I came off victorious, and left the enemy in their gore upon the field. Dear readers, I have solid information enough, on the habits of this animal to fill a large volume. It is the only carniverous little fool that inhabits the whole globe. Dr. Kane found him near the north pole on floating cakes of ice. Captain Cook was killed by Sandwich Islanders and afterwards eaten up by bed bugs. I was once in the Mammoth cave, and when at the extreme end of the cave, near ten miles from its entrance, what did I discover but a genuine bed bug moving gracefully along the dark cavern towards me. I was indignant, mad. I took up a boulder and spoiled his physiognomy, and that ended the life of one of the most ignominious salamanders that ever lived. I have somewhat strayed from the path of this story. I now proceed. It was on one beautiful evening in August when they arrived at Cheyenne, near six hundred miles from Leavenworth. It was then the western terminus of the Union Pacific road. They were informed here that it was very dangerous to cross the Laramie plains on account of hostile Indians; that the railroad surveyers had to keep armed cavalrymen for their protection. Minnie had had fortaste enough of Indian massacres, for a while at least, so she<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6062-00000015"/> choose to remain in Cheyenne as it was full of life and business at this time. The train however moved on, and made Salt Lake without any serious difficulty. A description of this place I have already given, suffice it to say, that Minnie remained here a number of of years, became well acquainted with her leading citizens, and took a deep interest in her education and politics. The question of woman's rights, and her inalienable right to vote became the leading topic of the day. It was talked of on street corners, in drawing rooms, in adobe cabins, in public halls, and on house tops. It became an epidemic throughout the Territory. Finally that august body (which composed the supreme rulers of Wyoming) had an attack of this pestilential scourge, and before the scab was entirely scratched off woman's suffrage became a law. It was a joyful day for Minnie, for she was now in her glory. Her prairie home was an earthly paradise. If she had wings she would have flown away to realms on high and told her sisters that had gone before that heaven was now established on one spot, in this mundane sphere. She was elected to several offices, and filled them with perfect satisfaction, and finally was elected to high sheriff, and by performing her duty led to that happy meeting of Gayloyd, under the friendly oaks in a far off wilderness.</p>
               <p>Five years had elapsed, and passed away, but time had not caused either to loose their untiring love, and true friendship, which was as fresh and green as ever.</p>
               <p>After a long and protracted conversation, their plans were completed for a second time, which was to proceed at once to Denver, and there be joined in the holy bonds of matrimony, then return and live in Gayloyd's cabin on the beautiful Cache-a-la-Poudre, for they both had learned to love a wild mountain life. The sun was fast sinking behind the western snow caps, and its lurid crimson lay upon the distant crags, when suddenly the rumbling stage started them to their feet. It was now getting late so they leaped into their saddles and rode off towards the Queen city of the plains, stopping for the night at the first stage station. The next morning when the coach came in bound for Cheyenne, they sent back the stolen goods without even an explanation, and the citizens of Cheyenne knew not the fate of their heroine sheriff, till more than a year afterwards. After breakfast they rode on towards the golden gem of the west. It was a delightful summers morning, and the sun shone forth her genial rays upon all animated nature. The birds gave them their sweetest songs. The surrounding country was one grand panorama of nature's loveliest scenes. To the right lay<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6062-00000016"/> a long chain of white capped mountains, seeming to kiss the very sky. To their left lay the great American desert, a treeless, dreary waste of sand, once the bed of a vast ocean. Towards their advance they could see nothing but the winding road and empty nothingness.</p>
               <p>They arrived in Denver the same afternoon, and in the evening were made one by the aid of a methodist parson, whose lengthy nose reminded them that he would be a profitable man to hire on a farm. He would be so handy to use in digging potatoes and gathering apples.</p>
               <p>The next day, by hard riding, they reached Gayloyd's cabin, late in the evening, nearly wearied out and ravenous hungry. A hasty meal was eaten, and they retired to their couch, to peaceful sleep, nature's sweet restorer. Morning came and the sun peeped into their happy abode ere they awoke. The cabin was built in a small grove of timber, on the river bank, at a point where it emerged from the mountains. One could see the water foaming and tumbling over jaded rocks far up the steep canion. Near by was a natural cave where Gayloyd had stored his amunition and provisions, it was also a safe retreat from the Indians, for one man could defend himself, against an attack of five hundred successfully in this cave.</p>
               <p>The Cache-a-la-Poudre was a beautiful stream, being formed by melting snows. It coursed eastwardly fifty miles, and empted into the river Platte. It was so named by a party of early French trappers, who, at a certain time, buried a quantity of powder on its bank. Catche, to bury, and a-la-Poudre, meaning powder, (buried powder); pronounced cash la pou. The happy pair were now fairly settled down, and had nothing to do but hunt, fish, and ramble at their leisure. In all of these excursions, Minnie took an active part, she was a dead-shot with the rifle, and many an antelope, deer and buffalo did she bring down with her trusty gun. She believed in woman's rights, and therefore took care of her own horse, and they both shared the work in the culinary department. She believed in voting, holding office, and taking the place of a man, fairly and squarely, if she choose to do so.</p>
               <p>Her liege lord could not see matters exactly in this light, but was willing for her to exercise her own judgment on that point, while with him in their forest home, so far from civilized life. But if they should go back to Charleston he would want a recognition of the sex, (or he might be taken for Mrs. Farnham.) Gayloyd could not agree with her exactly on the subject which led to a long debate on the question. Says he, I want to take a rational<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6062-00000017"/> view on the so called woman's rights, and if you will listen to me for a few hours; I will give you my views on the great topic of the day. In the first place, woman, noble woman, should have her inalienable rights and her whole and full claims in her own sphere. But what, and where is her sphere of action? Is it the same as that of man? verily not, it is far different. God specifically made the dividing line, and if you should split a hair into a thousand pieces, you could not persuade the Creator to change the variation. Adam was placed in the garden of Eden to till and dress it, that it might bring forth fruit in abundance for the sustainance of life. God saw he needed a help meet, so he caused a deep sleep to come over him while he took a rib from his side and formed woman, for a companion, for a help meet. She was taken from his side to be his equal, not to be trodden down, or to be above him, not equal in strength, and endurance, but socially. Man has a much larger and stronger physical frame and calculated to perform the rougher and harder work of every day life: such as cutting down our forests, tilling the soil, making rail roads, digging canals, building cities, forming governments and ruling nations. Woman could not do this, for she would be out of her sphere of action. She has not the bodily strength to do this if she wished to. Her mode of clothing is not suited for this class of labor. How would an intelligent and refined woman look, holding the plough, chopping down large oaks, building houses, digging in the canal by the side of Pat, Tim, or John, and as to holding office, she is not calculated or suited for that. No Lady of refinement would want to be a lawyer, justice, or judge. If she was a town constable she would capture more hearts than prisoners. There are exceptions to all rules, a few women of your own muscular strength, and dare-devil self confidence might fill an office with apparent satisfaction. You have had the suffrage law in Wyoming, but it soon will die out for want of public patronage. Whether the woman question or the Chinese question is greater, it makes no difference, both, like a mushroom, are of to-day, but may stay before us until settled. We may remember also that nothing is ever settled until settled aright. The embarrassments of the woman are peculiar, for if a man dones his armor and walks forth as woman's knight, he is exposed to the suspicion of letting his gallantry run away with his judgment. If he opposes the wild crusade he is quite sure to be accused of neglect or cruelty. Will it be endured if we mention this view taken of it, is the clearest proof that some women are not reasoning creatures. Her faculty<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6062-00000018"/> of reaching a conclusion is instinct, intuition, inspiration or whatever superior thing you may please, but it is not reason. If we are to reason upon a subject, the reasoning must be something better than merely saying because, etc. When women propose to discuss with society the great hobby of rights, which they claim are denied them, they must first be willing to put the matter upon its merits and give up all considerations before given them by virtue of their sex. It is not necessary to say that if woman desires to obtain rights to the full extent claimed, they must not expect distinctive privileges and courtesies also. If woman are to become equal with men, they cannot ask to be more so. The thousand and one ways, which men now yield to women as being weaker are inconsistant with the claimed inequality of the sexes. If woman deny that they are the weaker, they must not look for a continuance of favors given them. Decidedly, woman cannot unite in herself incomparable qualities. To be sure she may do some deeds of daring skill in the face of all the world, and win deserved admiration, but she cannot at the same time sustain the character of a modest shrinking creature. No, no, she may build a greater than a Pacific rail road, and do it all with the labor of her own hands, but then we cannot give her the place of a tender, gentle being. This seems plain, but the feminine advocates do not yet publicly admit it; or rather they will not, the sticking point is right here; some women are mad because God Almighty did not make men of them. 'As to society, religioa, art and literature,' woman rule in these fields as much as they deserve and dare, and how shall any direct reform help them. As to politics, a very little black paint will leaden a large quantity of white, and afterwards the addition of white seems powerless to whiten the mixture. The mire of politics would soil our doves, and make hawks and owls of them. In some things women are absolutely wronged; they should have control of their own property, and their person; they should not receive less pay for their work because they are women. But if women attempt to do men's work they will find nature made differences in the sexes, which no resolutions or revolutions can remove. Again, how would a man look as milliner and dress maker, a wet nurse, or how would a lady look as a lawyer in a court room filled with tobacco smoke and loafers, pleading a case of bigamy? it would simply be rediculous, no decent, refined women in the United States, except a Woodhull, could do it; and it would turn her stomach without it was lined with cast iron. All married woman are supposed to have a home and family<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6062-00000019"/> cares, and it is her imperative duty to preside over, and keep that home. It is the mother who guides the pratling feet of youth, and through her influence they are good or bad, of course it needs the hearty co-operation of the father, but still it is the mother in the main that makes the child the man. Washington, Franklin, Lincoln, John Webster and many others of our great men had noble mothers, and they never even had a sympton of the so called woman's rights. It was unknown in the days of Ben. Franklin. Woman's nature is more tender and she has a finer sense of feeling and generally more taste than her liege lord, therefore she is the more suitable and capable as a house keeper, and if the house is kept in a neat and tidy way, in an economical ship shape manner, she has done much towards the comforts and happiness of the home and family. Let a man take her place, and the house would soon look more like a sty than a human habitation; why, simply because he is out of his sphere of locomotion. If women are to take the place of man, hold office, go to congress, build railroads, climb trees, race horses, pump thunder and go to war, let them decorate the American stage and prate woman's rights and gable about her wrongs, it is getting contagious. These poor ill used creatures will lecture night after night, if she gets nothing but money for her trouble. If she should take a vote from her own sex, nine out of every ten would say I have my rights now, but the agitation must go on, and so long as the American stage is decorated with the roses of Sharon, so long will Stanton's, Brown's, and Woodhull's slash away at woman's rights. If she must come down to a level with man in all of the vocations of life let her go and join some savage or half civilized nation, such as the Chinese, Turks, Tartars, Hottentots or even our American Indians. Here she can have the privileges of taking the place of her husband or brother. Woman of these nations are trodden down and made slaves of by their husbands. In the Hartz Mountains woman carry heavy burdens upon their backs over precipitious mountain paths. The Circassian woman are sold to Turks as slaves. Squaws vote and do the drudgery, would you like to take her place? if so, wade in. But among civilization and civilized society, woman should have her inalienable rights, and that is to perform her whole duty in her own noble sphere, which God has given her to fill. Minnie had listened long and attentive to this confab on woman's rights, and readily fell in with the argument, saying that she hoped he would carry out the plan which he had represented if they ever got back to civilization and domestic life. But while<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6062-00000020"/> they were in that wild romantic region, she wished to act the part both of a man and woman, and sail in her own canoe. Gayloyd noded an assent, and suiting their words to immediate action they sprang into their saddles and dashed out upon the plain for a hunt. They had not gone far when they discovered a fresh Indian trail. Gayloyd got off to see in what direction they had gone. From all indications they were a band of Cheyennes on the war path, either with some tribe of Sioux or some frontier white settlement. They now quietly hastened back to their only safe retreat—the cave. No sooner had they reached the spot and made temporary preparations than they saw them coming around the bend of the river and directly towards the cabin, which they perceived was inhabited, by the barking of their dog, which they had neglected to take into the cave with them. The cabin was immediately surrounded and old <hi rend="i"/>pont was the first one to fall a victim from the hands of the red skins. This enraged Gayloyd, so he sent a death warrant to the same Indian, and he fell from his pony, stone-dead.</p>
               <p>The cave was now discovered and they surrounded them with terrible yells, and their war hoops died away in doleful echoes on the distant mountains. Gayloyd and Minnie poured a steady volley into the enemy's ranks, every<figure>
                     <head>(The Cabin and Cave, Gayloyd and Minnie's wilderness home.)</head>
                  </figure> time they came in front range of the cave. They had plenty of amunition and could stand a month's siege. Night came on, and the firing ceased. They kept up a continual watch, for they well knew Indian stratagem, which would be to dash in upon them at day break, and take them by surprise. Their predictions were true, for at the first peep of day the Cheyennes made a sudden dash upon them, yelling like very devils. But they were, as before, ready for them. They both had Remington rifles and Minnie could shoot with deadly aim, for in less than thirty minutes they<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6062-00000021"/> killed thirty-three of the noble red braves. The rest were terror stricken, run for their ponies and were soon seen making rapidly across the plain. They now ventured out cautiously, but none of the enemy were in sight. The ponies of the slain warriors were still picketed out as they had left them the night before. Gayloyd cut them loose and let them go, for he had no use for them. The dead Cheyennes were buried in one common grave, being thirty-five in all.</p>
               <p>Months passed by and they were unmolested in their cabin home on the Cache-a-la-Poudre. They hunted and fished as usual, and spent many a happy day in the sports of the chase. It was now Autumn, and the leaves were dry and rustling on the ground, and chilly winds went whistling by with low and pensive sound, yes, the yellow foliage told them of the coming winter. It was also the usual time of laying in a winter supply of provisions and amunition. Minnie had long thought of writing back to Charleston and learn if her parents were yet living, so one beautiful evening she penned her father a short note telling him of her whereabouts, and of her marriage to Gayloyd Farnham, stating that her address would be Cheyenne, Wyoming Territory. In due time they went to Cheyenne and found a letter in waiting for Minnie G. Farnham, from Char leston. It was opened with a trembling hand, and read thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>Charleston, S.C., Oct. 9. 1868.</dateline>
                           </opener>
                           <p>"Dear daughter Minnie, your letter came like a thunderbolt to me, for I long thought you dead. Your father died more than a year ago, and I am living all alone on the old homestead, the property shall be willed to you, when I am no more, come home, dear Minnie, and live with me. You and Gayloyd shall have a welcome home while I live, the past shall all be forgotten. Hoping to see you both soon, I remain, your affectionate</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>MOTHER.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>It was sad, yet joyful news to Minnie. The subject of going home was well discussed that evening, and the conclusion was that they would quit their mountain home and go to Charleston. The next day they returned to their cabin, only to find it a black mass of smouldering ruin and their cave had been sacked of all its contents. It was undoubtedly the work of some passing red skins. Darkness came on and they resorted to the cave for the night, hazarding all danger, it was, however, a long sleepless night. But morn came at last to their relief, and the sun streamed in her soft beams of light as beautiful as it had but a few days before. They ventured out to see if there were not some of the enemy in sight, when on<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6062-00000022"/> looking above them there sat a huge grizzly bear on a projecting cliff above the cave. At a given signal both fired and bruin came tumbling down the jaded rocks and expired at their feet. After eating a scanty breakfast, preparations were made to leave the dear old spot for ever—the place where many happy days had passed in that wild wilderness solitude. Getting into their saddles they took a long last farewell look on the cave and smoking embers of the cabin, then dashed away towards Cheyenne, which they reached the same evening. Gayloyd still wore his buckskin suit and Minnie with moccasins on and Macinaw blanket and tanned face look more like Indians than anything else. Minnie was not recognized by her most intimate friends in Cheyenne, she was so thoroughly changed in appearance. They now procured full suits of clothing in the latest style of American custume, and were ready to take the evening train east, which they did and arrived in Charleston four days later. However, before leaving Cheyenne, Minnie disclosed to her former deputy, who was now acting sheriff, how she had so miraculously departed, and her marriage of the prisoner she had taken, of her cabin home on the Cache-a-la-Poudre, also narrated their many fishing and hunting excursions, their fight with the war painted Cheyennes, their cave retreat, and many other incidents which happened while in solitude, she related to him but a short time before taking the cars for her old home in the sunny south. Now she was in the home of her childhood. Her mother, as she had written, made them a welcome home. Her father had died of pure grief for his long lost daughter. He had sought far and wide, but to no purpose, finally pined away, and died. Her mother's wrinkled face and gray hair also told a tale of sorrow which had nearly shipwrecked her physical frame. It seemed greatly to renew her age to have Minnie at home once more. But true love will have its course in defiance of consequences, it can never die. If all marriage contracts contained that true undying love which existed between Gayloyd and Minnie, there would never be any divorce cases in our courts. Marriage would be as from divine writ. What therefore God hath joined together, let no man put asunder. Gluttony is the great and first cause of intemperance, debauchery and unhappines in all of its phases, and finally divorce. We, as Americans, are gross gluttons, eating double what our bodies need for health, and it is this gormandizing and overloading ourselves with rich stimulating food which keep our bodies in a heated fever, a constant craving for something stronger, and under this intoxication and bodily<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6062-00000023"/> excitement the boy craves for a cigar, and finally strong drink, which may carry him to a drunkard's grave. Ninety per cent. of the ills of our country is the direct result of gluttony. Look at our sour, sore-headed dispeptics, and weep.</p>
               <p>A majority of our marriages in modern times are not consumated in true love. It is nothing but a union of the baser passions, causing the opposite sexes to unite in what is falsely called marriage. It is not a union of living hearts, blended in one, as it is with this heroine woman. Such love is worse than poor skim milk, hence the cause of separation and divorce. They came together through an inflammation of the baser passions, caused, as I have said, by some form of gluttony. This is not the case of all but a majority. Could we glance behind the curtain of every domestic home in the land, we would find that not more than one family in ten lived in connubial happiness. Could you creep in the closet and listen, you would hear an unkind word from the husband, a scold from the wife, an uncalled, for jealousy on one side and a real cause on the other. So it would go from bad to worse, until even their skim milk love was all gone. Then comes a row, a separation, and finally a divorce is granted, and each is at liberty to form other partnerships only to be involved again. Mothers, don't urge early marriages for fear your daughter would be unmarketable before they are out of their teens. There are occasional cases where it would be adviseable for parents to urge their daughters in marriage at fourteen or fifteen, but this is only rare. A great many mothers in modern times think all her daughter needs is a refined education, can talk French, German and Latin, can dance, sing and play the piano, and bankrupt her father in her wearing apparel, when she can pride herself that she has never washed a dish, made her own bed, or even made a pan of biscuit, then she is marketable, yes, and so she is in one sense of the word, for there are plenty of young men who have a passionate love for these guilded butterflies and even marry them. He marries her good looks, fine clothes, musical attainments and knowledge of hog latin. She marries him for his bank account, stove pipe hat, gold headed cane, and brainless cranium. Both have what they purchased, and no more. All may go lovely for a while but reserves come, the country is panic stricken, banks are broken, stocks become worthless, gold headed canes are useless, the plug is exchanged for a straw, and from fine clothes to common wear. He is dead-broke, yes, flatter than the ancients supposed the world to be. It is hard for him to come down to the common<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6062-00000024"/> vocations of every day life. In fact, he will not do it, and his wife knows nothing about a domestic life. She cannot cook even the simplest form of a meal. What can they do? they must come down to it, sink, or swim is all that will save life. The once gaudy peacock, is nothing but a buzzard. She is peevish, cross, discouraged and disgusted. Her husband is worse, he growls, frets, jaws, rips and tears and finally becomes a sour, soar-headed dispeptic, a good-for-nothing whelp. The last act in the play is fight, pull hair, separation and divorce.</p>
               <p>The cause of so many divorce cases can be summed up in a few words: marrying for good looks, fine clothes, and lastly but not least, gluttony. I have said enough on this subject and will now return to Minnie and Gayloyd.</p>
               <p>After they had lived on the old homestead one year and a half, Minnie's Mother died, and was buried in the old church-yard by the side of her dear father. A monument was erected, and a jessamine planted to commemorate the sacred spot. The old home now seemed dismal and forsaken. Minnie could not bear to live there since her mother's death. The estate was sold for fifty thousand dollars, and with this little fortune they moved into New York city, where Gayloyd invested his means in a lucretive Mercantile business, and is now one of the millionaires of the great metropolis. Minnie was always supreme ruler of her own household duties, and if necessary she could cook as good a meal as the steward of an Atlantic steamer, and much more hygienic. What came upon her tidy table was not tedious and tasteless. She was economical, prudent, and graceful. She could entertain a common beggar or the bon-ton of society, with etiquettical precision. Her education, with common sense and early training was now being used to good advantage. Occasionally Gayloyd would dress up in his wild mountain buckskin suit, and Minnie in her novel squaw attire, to the great merriment of an evening party.</p>
               <p>I must now bring this little volume to a close, and before doing so, must say that, that youthful love which existed between Edward Gayloyd Farnham and Minnie C. Dunbar was still burning with a livid brilliant flame, and there never lived a more happy family, for they were blessed with three bright eyed boys, and a little girl with golden tresses which they called Minnie. Hoping that this may teach its many readers a lesson of true love, women's and men's rights in their right place, which will be a benefit to them in all time to come.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>