<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7680">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Running a Time Table </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7680</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2136</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Running a time table</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 p. l. 16 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>H.A. Johnson</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Burlington Vt. </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1873">[1873]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-03-04">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Running a time table</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7680-00000001"/>A THRIILING TALE.   A BRAKEMAN'S STORY.   PUBLISHED BY HENRY &amp; JOHNSON, '.13 . BURLINGTON, VT. all e   Entered According to Act of Congress, in the year 1873, by HENRY &amp; JONSON, in the Office of the Librarian of Congress at Washington, D. C.   &#xD;<pb n="0Advertisement-1" xml:id="VAC7680-00000002"/> Forty years since, Elder Downs first man- ufactured his Elixir in Northern Vermont, and its remarkable cures at once brought it prominently before the people of the United States and Canada. No other medicine has maintained such, an enviable reputation for such a length of time. While the sale has rapidly increased every yeari other medicines have been pQpular for a few months or years, but their lack of, intrinsic value has con- signed them to comparative oblivion. In justice to Downs' Elixir, be it said, that it is a duty the people owe to themselves that they continue to use the article that has always cured them of their coughs and colds, rather than to take or try every new medi- cine that is puffed up, and may be worthless. N. a. Downs' Vegetable Balsamic Elixir is warranted to give entire satisfaction, or the price paid will be refhnded,by the agents,to the purchaser. SPFCIAL DIRECTIONS FOR U8sINx N. H. DOWNS' ELIXIR. ; In all cases Fsake the, Bottle- well before using. CommoxB Co,--Dose for an adult should be a large tea-spoonful after shaking the bottle, on going to bed, and half the amount int-e morning; and if the pressure of the lungff  continues, the dose may be repeated once-an hour until the patient is relieved. And as there is a great variety of constitu- tions, as a general remark we would observe, that to take a sufficient quantity at night to create a little nausea at the stomach, is the desirable point to be arrived at, and owing to the -diffusibility of the medicine, half the quantity only in the morning will be re- quired to have the same effect as it does at night when the body is at rest. If the pa- tieartshould be quite sick on taking an over dose. by taking */tea-spoonful of- medicine clear, or without shaking up the bottle, it, till make   him vomit gently, or entirely remove the sickness. If the' patient should Vomit, as soon as you can give another tea- spoonful clear or without shaking the bottle, which will allay all irritation of the stomach, and the patient may rest assured that the cold will be entirely removed. As this effect does not often happen, it is only named to quiet any fears that may arise in the mind. S ti The same course may be pursued in all cases of  Coughs, Catarrh, Whooping- Coughs, Asthma, or pressure of the lungs by the secretion of impure matter; in all such onaes, this course is to be pursued until the *patient raises freely without any particular   effort, and the cough is perfectly. loose and , easy. Where extreme sickness succeeds the taking of the medicine, it will be well for I the patient to cover up immediately in a i warm bed until the effect is carried off, which * will not be long. FIRST STAGE OF CoxsuMpriosN.-When this insidious disease is suspected, no time should be lost in taking the Elixir. Keep -warmly dressed, with flannel next to the body. Ex- ercise as much as your strength will allow in I the open air; eat the most nourishing food you can get-do not burthen the stomach with anything like nuts, cake, or unwhole- some food. If the skin is hot and dry, the whole body should be sponged with spirits and tepid water as often as -once a day. Great benefit will be derived from rubbing the chest well once a day with a mixture composed of equal parts of Kill-Pain, or Henry's Vermont Liniment, and sweet oil. Have a bottle of Elixir by you, and take a small dose every time you have a bad coughing spell-you can soon regulate the dose to your case. On going to bed take a tea-spoonful, in the morning take a light drink of good Bourbon whiskey, with a very little sugar, and not take any Elixir until one hour after eating breakfast. This treatment followed up carefully, has permanently cured many who supposed they had got to die of consumption. In the second and third stages of this dis- ease, the Elixir, taken in small doses after severe coughing spells, has proved beneficial in most cases; and many a good night's rest has been secured to the afflicted patient by taking one or two tea-spoonfuls of this med- icine upon retiring at night. CROUP.-This disease is confined to chbil- dren, and the dose should be small. For a child of six months, from ten to thirty drops may be given, repeating the dose once in fif- teen minutes until they are easy or vomit. This Elixir has been successfully used in many cases of female weakness.  It has also been found a, desirable addition to the Nursery, to soothe and quiet restless children. Put up hereafter in 2 and 12 oz. bottles. Price 35 cents for the small and one dollar for the large. You get as much in the large bottle for $1 as you would for. $ 2.10, if you buy all small ones to get the same quantity. We do not put up the nmedium size now. AMENAY &amp; JOHNSON, Sole Proprietors, Burlington, Vt. $ucVs OMs  to RBv. N. I DowWn, J. M. IIUrY &amp; Sos8, JossN . HxNT &amp; Co, and HENaY &amp; Co.   / BRAKEMAN '; ;TORY.   r have been a "Railroad man" yl for a great many years-have, as the expression goes, grown grey in the service. I am certain, how- ever, in all my experience, I never saw a road that was the equal of the Valley Air Line, upon which I was, at the time of the incident about to be related, a brakeman. The Valley Air Line was one of those roads that spring up sud- denly out of the imaginations of a few men. One cannot say that it sprung from their purses, for if they had the seed in them to grow anything, it was never put in the Valley. There was, as nearly as I can now remember, a capital stock, which was never paid up, a little town and village credit, and a large amount of preferred stock, first and second mortgages, etc. As a result, the road was built in a Bung- ling manner, grades were bad, road bed was poor, bridges and culverts were thrown together in the worst possible manner, because the worst was the cheapest. The iron was a light and frail mass, manufactured especially  for  the American market, .while the rolling stock had been worn out in services on other roads and sold to the Valley Air Line -on credit and long time. The reader will see from this truthful statement that the Valley was not the safest road for travel- lers in the country. It was not. Innumerable were the accidents we had, and it is a wonder to me that none of them were serious. While we had many narrow es-   capes, we still managed through sheer good luck, slow time, and great care, to get on without breaking bones; but I positively assure you that time did not ac- custom us to the road, and we never ran into the depot at night without feeling thankful that we were alive. When I say we, I mean the conductor, engineer, baggageman, fireman and myself. How the passengers felt I do-not know, but I do know that they ought to have felt as thankful, as the roadmen that their bones were in good condition to allow them to walk from the depot to their homes. Ignorance may have been perfect bliss to them, however. The engineer of our train,-the Lightning Express,-was one of the most sober, careful, thoughtful and industrious men that ever handled a throttle. He possessed more than the ordinary share of thoughtful prudence, of his class, and it was owing to this fact that so great a degree of good fortune came to us. A few moments before the train was to start one morning, Gardi- ner, the engineer, called me to his cab. He appeared unusually down- cast that morning, though at the best he was by no means a "gay" fellow. "Bob." said Gardlner, after a few  seconds talk about general matters, "Bob, I want you to be very careful to-day. I know you, are a good fellow and al- ways do your duty well; but to- day I want you to do more. I want you to stand by your brake  &#xD;<pb n="2 (Advertisement) -3" xml:id="VAC7680-00000003"/> N.. H. DOWNS' VEGETABLE    BALSAIIC   ELIXIR, ' FOR THE SPEEDY CURE OF Coughs, Colds, Consumption, aWhoop ing- Coufh, Croup, Asthma, and all diseases of the THR 04 TA, CH EST ES D L UN GS.   THS valuable medicine is purely vegetable; the discovery of which has been the result of many years' close study (while suffering under those for- midable diseases which prey upon the organs of the chest) in order to discov- er the causes, the symptoms and the cure, viz.: Consumption, Asthma, Ca-, tarrh, Colds, Coughs, Pleurisy, Influ- enza, Hoarseness, Spitting of Blood, Bronchitis, and every species of op- pression ot the Chest and Lungs... In all cases where this Elixir has been duly administered its effiacy has been inva- riably manifested, convincing the most incredulous that even CONSUMPTION is not incurable, if properly attended to. As consumption at its commencement is but a slight irritation on the mem- brane which covers the lungs, then an inflammation, when the cough is a little more observable, but rather dry, then becomes local fever, and the pulse more frequent, the cheeks are flushed, and chills are more common. In its next stage the external parts of the lungs themselves begin to participate in the fever, the strength fails, the flesh wastes', ;and perspiration is common; as debility and emaciation increase, small ulcerations or white hard specks appear, the bowels become irregular, the sleep is disturbed; in the last stages, violent coughing, profuse cold sweats, and constant diarrhoea, with hic-coughs, close the scene. This Elixir, in curing the above complaints, operates so as to remove all morbid irritation and in- flammation from the lungs to the sur- face, and finally expel them from the   system, by perspiration and otherwise. It facilitates expectoration, and thus relieves the patient from a load of tough phlegm which cannot otherwise be wholly removed from the system. It heals the ulcerated surfaces and re- lieves the cough and makes breathing easy. It supports the strength, and at the same time reduces the fever. It has at least one peculiar advantage over other articles in common use for the same purposes, it is free from strong opiate and astringent articles, which are of so drying a nature as to be in great danger of destroying the patient; whereas this medicine never dries or stops the cough but by removing the CAUSE, generally destroys the hectic before the cough is entirely gone; con- sequently, when the cough is cured the patient is well. It may be relied on as perfectly safe in all cases of cough and irritation of the lungs; the ,ery best medicine for coughs in every fever from commencement to end. It will cure a slight hoarseness and cough when occasioned by a cold, in a few hours, and generally when severe and obstinate, in a few days. It almost in- variably cures children of croup, and has in many instances, when eminent physicians considered them past hope, cured them in a few hours. AWShake the bottle well before taking out the cork. N. H. DowNS. PRICE, small, -  -  35 cents. "  large,   -  81.00 HEMY &amp; JOHNSON, Proprietors Burlington, Vt.   SWWe sincerely wish that every body knew the REAL worth' of Dowrs' ETaxmR. "An ounce of preventive is better than a pound of cure "--one small Bottle of Elixir taken in season -has saved many a. valuable life, and large doctors' bills.    every second of the trip-not to leave it for a moment, and when I signal, I want you to set them up as you never did before, and promptly too. I know you will do it for me, won't you, Bob?" I was too astonished to speak for a-second, and then I asked: "Why, what'under the sun is the matter with you, Gardiner? You know the brakes are so nearly worn out that it is impossible to set them up, and you know too---" "I know it all, Bob, and that is the reason why I want you to be careful. I am going to try and make the time-table to-day; if it is possible, I will do so. I feel just as though something was going to happen, and am more than half sorry that I promised; but I'll do it though. Now promise me, Bob, and off to your brakes." I promised and took my post, not a little mistified at Gardiner's words, looks and actions. We left the depot and went rattling on over the iron. Passengers looked at each other in surprise and won- dered what under the sun was the matter with the Valley-if it had suddenly awakened from its long sleep, and now proposed to be a railroad in earnest. When the conductor came through the train, and came along by me, I asked: "What is the matter with Gard- iner this morning?" "Oh," was the reply, 'he and the old man have had a blow-out this morning. You see our train never makes connections--passen- gers always lay over, and of course they growl. This morning the old man called us into the office and the whole..thing was out.- Gardiner talked like a father to them, and, as he grew excited, he said that it was criminal running the road in the condition it was. He told them the time-table, as made up, was fast, even for a first-   class road, and if we undertook to run it, a frigh'tful accident could not be avoided. When Gardiner said it was criminal to run the road as it was, Supt. Brown was very hot. He fairly boiled over. He declared that there was no better road in the country, and that GCardiner was a coward who ought to go on to a gravel train, and if lie didn't -make time he'd have him there, too. The -road was losing its business and there had got to be a chance. Brown also said that in Valley Creek, where he lived, he had noticed that the train always slowed and lost time enough there to lose the connections. Gardiner replied to this, that at the Creek there was a down grade, the bridge was unsafe, and he ,was obliged to slack up for safety. More than this, the track passed through the play-ground of the Creek school, was not fenced in, and they could not go through at a rapid speed without danger to the children. Then Brown burst out, with an oath, that if parents did not want their children run over they must keep them oft' the track. It would be a good thing to run over one or two of them, as it would teach them a-lesson. Of course, he didn't mean this, but he was " hot" you see and did not' know what he did say. He added, that Gardiner's family lived near the track, and that Gardiner's sole reason for slowing, was to have a chance to chat with them as he went through. This set Gardiner's anger on fire, and he then and there declared that he would make time, let the, consequences be what they might, and if disaster happened, Brown must assume the responsibility.-- You see he is keeping his word, but the old fellow feels bad though," We dashed on over the frail iron at a frightful. speed. You could almost hear the bars crackle as we  &#xD;<pb n="4 (Advertisement) -5" xml:id="VAC7680-00000004"/> :D:'E:. w'vO      D'wV' jI=SD'S STILLINGIA COMPOUND. For thbe Cure of Scrofula, in some of its forms, Eruption and, Cuta- neous Diseases, sucht as Salt RhlezeruM, Scald eHead, Rigffworm, Blotches, Boils, Carbuncles, Chronic Ulcers and Chrownic Rheumzratssm, Chronic Affections of the Liver and Spleen, Enlargement of the Bones, Joints and Glands, frorn, Cancerous, Scrofutlous and Syphilitic ceases. Epi- lepsy, Chorea or St. uitz$ Dance, Dropsical Swellings and certain Constitutional Disor- ders; besides all Diseases originating from arn impztre and imVperfect state  of the blood.   Every Physician understands that there is a class of cases where an alterative is especially indicat- ed, and we claim that this prepar- ation is vastly superior to any of the Sarsaparilla and Yellow Dock Alteratives ever offered to the public, as any educated Physician who has made himself at all ac- quainted with the effect of STIL- LINGIA can testify. The combination, as presented, possesses marked diuretic and lax- ative properties, which wonderfully increase the alterative effect of the STILLINGIA, thereby assisting greatly to eliminate morbid depos- its from the system. Great pains are taken in its'pre- paration to get the entire strength of all the ingredients, and we be- lieve, for the diseases enumerated, it will give better satisfaction than anything of the kind ever before   offered to the profession and the public. We do not claim that it will cure everything, nor that it is ab- solutely infallible in all cases for which it is recommended; but we do claim that it is a scientific com- bination, prepared on scientific principles, and it is better adapted to cases where an alterative is re- quired than any other preparation now in use; and the day is not far distant when the base of the Com- pound-Stillingia-will stand at the head of the long list of altera- tives. Physicians can be supplied with the Compound at a much cheaper- rate than they can prepare it in small quantities; and on applica- tion a sample bottle will be fur- nished  any  Physician, free of charge, also the formula, that he may know what he is using.   b Prepared by J. B. W;OOD W'ARD, M. D. DIRECTIONS FOR USING STILLINGIA COMPOUND. Shake the Bottle well before taking out the cork. For an adult,    - -  -  .   One table-spoonful. a child 10 years old,   -  -  Two large tea-spoonfuls.  "L 4  "  "   -     One tea-spoonful. s As 1 3        's Ad -e- Half a tea-spoonful. "3 "W  1 year     - .    Twenty drops. To be taken three times a day one-half hour before meals; KQtIn long-standing, severe cases, the patient should use 5 to 8 bottles, in order to effect a permanent cure. You will find it the cheapest Doctor's bill you ever paid-war- ranted to satisfy. Price One Dollar per Bottle, or 6 Bottles for Five Dollars. Sold by all dealers in medi- cmies.                HENRY &amp; JOHNSON, Proprietors, BURLIaGTor, VERMONT. To whom all orders should be addressed.   went. The cars surged froom east to west, forcing passengers to fairly cling to their seats. N'ot for- a second did I leave nly brake. We were nearly down to Valley Creek, on timne. As we approached the long stretch of down grade, I felt by the shaking that Gardiner had slackened up, as if the danger were really too great; and then, as if his promise had come full upon his mind, had again carefully opened his. throttle. Down the Valley we went, our rapid speed startling the birds, the cattle, and even the staid old forest trees into new and strange ideas. I grasped the brake firmly; the engine whis- tled and screamed, warning all to keep clear of it. I held my breath, well knowing that if we left the track it would be to go to destruc- tionl. Suddenly the whistle ceased, and- then there came three un- earthly yells from it; they pierced my ears and made them ache.- How I set up the brake, for I felt there was danger ahead. I knew this when Gardiner suddenly re- versed his engine. The shutting off, the reversing, and the brakes set up so tight that I feared the chains would break, did not seem to lave the slightest effect upon the train.  On, on, it went, at its dan- gerously rapid speed. I stretched my neck out as tar as possible, clinging nervously to the railing. I could see that Gardiner was at his post, looking out as I did, and moving his hand energetically, while whistle and bell were unit- ing their protest. What was -the matter I could not conjecture; but was anxious to know.   Springing upon the rail, I made my way to tle. top of the car, and the mystery was revealed. There on the track was a sight that sent a thrill of horror through me. Only a few feet ahead of us on the track, stood a mere child- unconscious of its danger-para-   lyzed so that it could not nlove. Just clear of the tltack I vy a wo- man, evidently helpless. I looked for Gardiner, to see what he was doing ere I closed 113. eyes to shut out the horrible sight. The poor fellow had not been idle. Plainly seeing that he could not drive the child from the track, and that its companion was helpless, he left his cab and climbed forward on his engine, to the extreme end of the cow-catcher, leaned over, and while clinging with one hand, reached out with the other. There did not seem one chance in a mill- ion to save the- child-not one,- but anxiety overcame horror, and I looked, and shuddered as I looked. How my heart leaped into my very throat ats I saw the train dash on, but saw that as it did so, Gard- iner, with almost superhuman ef- fort, raised the child by its arm from the track and clasped it to his bosom! Then he sank down on the cow-catcher faint and pow- erless. His fireman clambered out to his side, and you may rest as- sured I was not long in getting to their assistance. The unusual noise of the steam had brought every person in the village out to witness the sight, and as they realized it they shouted their joy until their throats must have been hoarse. The fireman and I clung to Gardiner; there was no need to hold the child, for although rigid and helpless, Gardi- ner held the little one to his breast with an iron grasp. Very soon we crossed the bridge and struck the up  grade where the train slowed and flirally came to a full stop, nearly in front of Gardiner's house. With the help of some of the villagers we took by force the child from  Gardiner's arm m and carried the engineer into the house and laid him on the bed. As he sank down the little life in him seemed  &#xD;<pb n="6 (Advertisement) -7 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7680-00000005"/> PROFESSOR MOTTS MAGIC HAIR INVIGtORATOR. This valuable preparation justly deserves the reputation it has earned for removing Dandruff, Scurf, and all Impurities from the Head; for Dressing and Curling the Hair; Preventing the Hair fromn falling off; causing new Hair to prow luxuriantly; Exciting the Scalp to new and healthy action; curing those Eruptive Diseases which so often appear upon the Head; giving to the Scalp and Hair a rich, healthy, vigorous, and beautiful ap- pearance, unequalled by anything of the kind ever before offered to the public. All diseases of the scalp, and decay in the growth of thb,hair, are due to an absence of vigorous action in the nerves of the scalp. This Invigorator will restore action to the roots and vigor to the hair. In getting up this preparation, Professor Mott experimented for a long time. lst. To find some ingredient that would excite action in the nerves of the scalp, increase the vigor, &amp;c., without injury to the hair. 2d. To effect the removal of dandruff, scurf, and all substances which tend to stop the pores of the scalp, thereby killing the hair, and 3d. To combine with the others the substance which would keep the skin and scalp soft and moist, without the use of oils, pomades, &amp;c., which tend, without an exception, to fill up the pores of the scalp, gathering dirt, and creating heat which of itself engenders Dand- ruff, Scurf, &amp;c. If those who have lost their hair by disease, or otherwise, will but use this Invigorator for a time, they Wvil find themselves very soon possessed of a more abundant growth of hair than ever before. It removes all unnatural harshness and dryness of the hair, giving it a beautiful soft and glossy appearance; and aside from the virtue of the article in the above use, its odor is so very beautiful, and its perfume is retained for such a length of time that it will command the patronage of a discerning public. DIRECTIONS FOR USING.   Shake the Bottle well before taking out the cork. Brush'the head smartly with a hair-brush, until the scalp becomes quite red. Apply with a sponge enough to moisten the hai r and roots, once in one, two, or three. days, or as often as the hair mav need dress- FOR RESTORING HAIR TO BALD HEADS.- Apply the Invigorator once a day, brushing the head as above; also rub or brush the head thoroughly after each application. FOR REMOVING AND PREVENTING DAND- RUFF.-Apply as above, brushing the head before and after an application; combing the head occasionally, a very little, with a fine comb, using great care not to injure nor irritate the scalp. FoP CURLING AND THCKENING THE HAIR. --Apply as above directed, and rub it well into the roots of the hair with the fingers, not using a very stiff brush. To PREVENT THE HAIR FROM FALLTING OrF,-Great care and gentleness should be observed; not pulling the hair with a fine conmb, nor brushing it harshy; but, gently   parting the hair, rub the Invigorator into the roots with the fingers. It is also very desirable to wear the hair quite short, if con- venient. To CuRE HEADACHE AND TO KILL HAIR- EATERS---Apply as in restoring hair to bald heads, brushing quite hard for several mo- ments. To CURE CHAPPED AND ROUGH HANDS.- Pour enough into the palm of the hands to moisten them well, and rub thoroughly; af- terwards wash with warm water and soap, wiping perfectly dry. To REMOVE TAN AND FREOKLES.-Moisten a soft towel with the Invigorator, and rub the face thoroughly; let it remain about five minutes; remove by water and soap, as above. If any one using this Invigorator should require more oil upon their hair than the Invigorator yields, they will find HENRY'S GREEN  MOUNTAIN  HAIR OIL, a beautiful addition to the Invigorator. A few drops applied after the Invigorator. has been used will produce a pleasing effect.   lAW'We put up two sizes. Retail price, 50 Cents and $1.00 per Bottle. HENRY &amp; JOHNSON, Proprietors, 127 CHURCH ST., BURLINGTON, VT. For , , ,. by 'gents ineTo whom all orders should be addressed. For sale by agents in every town and city in Canada and the United States.   VEGETABLE WORE    LOZENGES. A Pleasant, Safe and Effectual Remedy for Worms. Ii     S    Of all remedies designed for a spe- cial purpose, the great desideratum is to procure the best. Having had oc- casion to deal largely in vermifuges, many years, and knowing the adapta- bility of such remedies to the purpose for which they are intended, we have no hesitation in saying that the article we now offer to the public is far supe- rior to all others, inasmuch as it is more effectual in its results, less objec- tionable on account of the taste, and generally obviates the necessity of taking castor oil, or any other nau- seous laxative to carry off the worms;   thus acting in the double capacity of a vermifuge and a cathartic, removing the cause of disease, and restoring to health. In using these Lozenges, as in all other medicine, the exercise of judg- ment is necessary, as constitutions vary, and what may be a small dose for one, will be a large dose for another. It is better that a low diet be maintained for a day or two before using; and also during their use, as an over-crowded' stomach impedes the action of the medicine.   DIRECTIONS FOR USING HENRY'S WORM LOZENGES One to three years old - - - - One to two Lozenges, night and morning. Three to six    "  - - -  - Two to three  "   " " Six to twelve   "  - - - -   Three to four  "   "     " For adults             Five to six " "          " In case the above is not found sufficient to move the bowels, take an addi- tional lozenge, or part of a lozenge, or a moderate dose of castor oil, if neces- sary, so as to produce an evacuation. These Lozenges are put up in LARGE BOXES, and for sale by all Druggists and dealers in Medicines everywhere.   Price, 25 cents a box. HENRY &amp; JOHNSON, Proprietors, Burlington, Vt. If you need a COUGH MEDICINE, we advise you to try N.-H. DOWNS' Vegetable Balsamic Elixir. No family should be without it in the house. In all cases of Coughs, -Colds, Croup and Whooping-Cough, it cures as if by magic! Perfectly safe for children and adults. Sold by all Druggists. Every young, man after he has chosen his vocation should stick to it. Don't leave it because hard blows are to be struck, or disagreeable work performed. Those who have worked their way up to wealth and usefulness do not belong to the shiftless and unstable class, but may be reckoned among such as took off their coats, rolled up their sleeves, con- quered their prejudices against labor, and manfully bore the heat and burden ,of the day. Secrets of Health.-First, keep warm; second, eat regularly and slowly; third, main- tain regular bodily habits; fourth, take early and very light suppers; fifth, keep a clean Rkin; sixth, get plenty of sleep at night; seven"th, keep cheerful and respectable company; eighth, keep out of debt; ninth, take Henry &amp; Johnson's "Choice Family medicines," as they always do good and never do hurt. Good Advice.-If the poor-house has any terror for you, never buy what you don't need. 'Before you pay three cents for a jews-harp, see if you can't make just as pleasant a noise by whistling, for such nature furnishes the machinery. And before you pay $ 7 for a figured vest, young man, find out whether your lady love would not be just as glad to see you in a plain one that cost just half the money. If she wouldn't, let her crack her own walnuts, and buy her own clothes.  &#xD;<pb n="8 (Advertisement) -9 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7680-00000006"/> DR. BOYCES' TONIC BITTERS; OR Blood  Renovator. COMPOSED ENTIRELY OF VEGET A RTrS-   The effect of this medicine is truly wonderful. It acts directly on the bowels and blood and is a mild but thorough Cathartic. It expels all morbid secretions and obstructions from the body, stimu- lating the internal organs into healthy action, cleansing the sys- tem and purifying the blood,' caus- ing it tQ flow anew through every part of the body, giving health'and new life to the frame. Are you suffering with any of the diseases that follow a torpid or diseased liver, such as Jaundice, Dyspepsia, Bilious Diseases, Foul Stomach,   Costiveness or Weakness?. Then these Bitters will do you good. MANDRAKE, one of 'the ingredients of this medicine, is now admitted to -be one of the very best agents known for restoring the liver to healthy action; has almost entirely taken the place of Calomel with all good physicians. DIRECTIONS. For an adult a tablespoonful in sweetened water three times a day before meals. The dose may be increased-or lessened as the case may require Price, 50 cents.   DR. ASAI- OLDRIDG:E'S GREEN PLASTER. The strongest Adhesive and best Healing Plaster in the world. For dressing and healing all kinds of CUTS AND WOUN TDS, With but a SINGLE application. Also BOILS, OLD ULCERS, FELONS, WHTLOWS, FESTERS, WARTS, CORNS; BUNIONS, All Rheumatic Pains, Ague in the face, &amp;e. Certain cure for corns and warts. ' ALSO FOR CUTS AND WOUNDS ON HORSES--A ND CATTTIE. For positively and permanently CURING GALLS made by saddle and harness, allowing the animals to work with ease, and at the same time efiecting a cure. - DIRtE-orCTIONSS. For a cut or wound spread a plaster of cloth or soft leather, and cleaning the wound of all blood and moisture, compress the wound as firmly and accurately together as possible, then warm and apply the plaster, and in a few days the wound will be healed, whether it be large or small. In applying it to cattle and horses, the plaster should be spread thicker, and heated on with a hot iron. iA&amp; Spread plasters with knife blade warmed in lamp blaze or fire. PRICE 25 CENTS. Manufactured by HENRY &amp; JOHNSON, Burlington, Vt., sole Proprietors, to whom all orders must be addressed.   THE BABYS LINE--EXQUISITE RESPONSE. AN eminent physician contributes the fol- lowing useful and capital article to the Hearth and Home: "An intelligent young mother inquired some days since how she could best preserve her child's linen clean and sweet, when changed frequently during the day. I direct- ed her never to dry it before the fire, but in the sun and open air, if the weather permit- ted. She followed my directions, but, as is too often the practice, dried and aired it in the nursery window. Her fastidious husband remonstrated in vain against this unseemly exposure. Believing that if she saw her practice as others saw it she would desist, he so directed their afternoon walk as to bring the nursery window in full view from the central part of the town.  Stopping abruptly, he pointed to the offending linen flapping conspicuously in the breeze, and asked sarcastically: "' My dear, what is that displayed from our window?" "' Why,' she proudly replied, 'that is the flag of our union.' "Conquered by this pungent retort, he saluted the flag with a swing-of his hat, and pressing his wife's arm closer within his own, sang, as they walked homeward, 'And long may it wave.-" THE SIGNERS OF THE DECLARATION. We present to our readers the following statistical facts regarding those illustrious men who imperiled their property, tiir liberty, and their lives by attaching teir signatures to that instrument which estab- lished our national independence: The thirteen states, then comprising the American colonies, were represented in the assemblage that passed the measure, by fifty- one- members.  Thirty-seven enjoyed the benefits of collegiate training; twenty were lawyers; four were physicians; five were clergymen; three were farmers; and the re- mainder were engaged in various mercantile pursuits, except Roger Sherman, the shoe- maker, and Benjamin Franklin, who boasted of being a printer, yet was a Statesman and a philosopher. Benjamin Frank n was the oldest among the members, and Edward Rut- ledge the youngest. Robert Morris was the most opulent, and was the financier of the administration, negotiating extensive loans for the use of the government upon his per- sonal credit. He died in prison, having been incarcerated for debt; a beautiful commentary on those laws that made no discrimination between the honest but unfortunate debt- or and the convicted felon. Daniel Adams was the most needy, his improverished con- dition being well known. The management of his pecuniary affairs made it necessary for him to seek a burial at the public expense. Josiah Bartlett was the first to vote for the measure, and first after President Hancock to   sign the document. Two of the number, John Adams and Thomas Jefferson, were subsequently presidents. It is a remarkable fact that these two men, having been pres- idents, associated on the committee that framed the "Declaration of Independence," and the first recognized leaders of two great political factions of our country, died on the same day, the 4th of July, 1826, the fiftieth anniversary of the day upon which they had contributed so much to the welfare of their countrymen. Charles Carroll was the only member that added his place of residence, and the reason of its being done in this instance is somewhat peculiar. The patriots that formed that convention knew full well that by their action on that day they hazarded their lives. When Carroll wad signing, some one near him remarked, "he will get off, there are so many Carrolls, they will not know which to take." "Not so," replied he, and immediately added "of Carrollton." He lived to see all the memorable men with whom he acted on that eventful day pass away, and enjoyed the prosperity of his country until 1832, when he, died'in his ninety-fifth year. The hardest thing to hold in this world is an unruly tongue. It beats a hot smoothing iron and a kicking horse considerably. How TO BE HAPPY.-If you wish to be happy, and to make others so, always be cheerful, and look 1tpon the bright side of everything. It is just as cheap, and three times as good for digestion. INTS TO FAmERS. Don't let your horses be seen standing much at the tavern door; it don't look right. Don't give the merchant a chance to dun you. Prompt payments make independent men. Keep good fences, especially line fences; they promote good feelings among neighbors. Decent, substantial clothing for your children makes them think better of them- selves, and keeps the doctors away. Don't starve your land; if you do you-will grow lean. Don't become surety for him who waits for the sheriff. A farmer, who had an invariably good- natured wife, longed to hear her scold for a change, and was advised that a load -of crook- ed firewood would make her very desirably cross. He tried it in vain. When the pile was gone, he asked her if he should get such another supply. "'0, yes," sliid she, "for that crooked wood you brought before does lie around the pot so nicely." He never tried again. If you have a yoke of oxen don't be ashamed of them, and give your note for a span of horses.  &#xD;<pb n="10 (Advertisement) -11" xml:id="VAC7680-00000007"/> IR. JOISHNSON'S A Superior Combination of Barks, Roots and Herbs.   Are you suffering with Dyspepsia, Lossof Appetite, Low Spirits, Weak- ness, and General Debility? Then try a bottle of these Bitters, and see how quickly they will make you feel like -a new person. Have you just had some debilitating disease, and want a good reliable Tonic? You have it in Johnson's Calisaya Bitters, as they are made from pure Calisaya Bark, which any good physician will tell you is one of the best tonics known, it being the "Peruvian Bark" from which Qui- nine is obtained, and the bitters might   justly be called "Quinine Tonic Bit- ters," as that is what they really are. They are not put up for a " whiskey. tipple," but for a good Tonic Medicine. DIRECTIONS. Adult persons who take these Bit- ters to give them an appetite, should use about a small wine-glass full three times a day, just before eating. Aged people will find these Bitters to be just what they want, to give them strength and assist nature. Price, $1.00 per bottle.   The shades of night were falling fast, As through a Down East city passed A boy, who hastened straight ahead, And ever as he ran he said, "Henry's Worm Lozenges." When people asked him, why so quick? He said, the baby's very sick, And I was told in haste to come, And with all speed to get him some "Henry's Worm Lozenges." The neighbors all have tried them well, And they most wond'rous stories tell Of children cured of many ills, By giving them, instead of pills, "Henry's Worm Lozenges." That boy, and  the neighbors all, were evidently sensible people, to use Henry's Worm Lozenges-as the Loz- enges are made from pure Santonine, which is the active principle of worm seed and may be relied on as purely Vegetable and are perfectly safe and sure to remove worms.   They are very pleasant to the taste, children eat them same as candy. We warrant them free from mineral poison. Mothers should never be withbut them in- the house, as prompt action saves life many  times. Children troubled with worms are liable to have worm fits and other sudden at- tacks of disease. . The same might be said of adults. Ask for HENRY'S Worm Lozenges, and take no other! Don't run for constable; you may get'the office and let the plow stand. Teach your boys to look up and for- ward, never down nor backward. Don't leave to memory what should be written; it makes lawsuits. When the labors of the day are past, let good books and newspapers invite the youngsters to the sitting- room.   Retail 25 cts. a box, and sold everywhere. HENRY &amp; JOHNSON, Proprietors.   to come back, and he whispered: "Whose child is it?" "'Superintendent Brown's," said a neighbor, to my astonishment. "Is it alive?" gasped Gardiner. "It is alive and well-thanks to your bravery,",I answered, and Gardiner sank back upon his pil- low. The child which Gardiner had so miraculously saved, was a son and only child of our Superintend- ent. It seemed singular that the morning talk of the two men should have so singular an ending; but so it was. The wife of the Superintendent with their only child had been out for a walk.- The little one runninog on ahead had strayed upon the track. /Hear- ing the whistle, the mother called the child to her, but the child, happy in its freedom, ran on, laughing and shouting, child-like, into the jaws of danger. It was too mluch for the mother; she made an effort to save her darling, but before she could overtake the little one, her strength failed her and she fell. Our elngine was injured so that it was impossible to go on, and another was telegraphed for. We tried all we could to bring Gardi- ner back, but the physician said that the excitement under which the noble fellow had labored, had prostrated him, and it would re- quire the greatest care and a long time to bring him back to life. He liad that care, you may rest as- sured. I was in Gardiner's house when Supt. Brown came in that night. The "old man," as we called him, had lost all sign of his anger;, and he wept like a clhild as he looked upon the strong mnan thus prostrate before him. He visited the patient daily, and his very life seemed 'to hang upon Gardiner's recovery, and when the danger was passed, the long fever which ensued was broken, and the   engineer began to recover, the Su- perintendent was as happy as a child. I may say,lin conclusion, that the incident was not without its result, for at once the Valley Road was thoroughly rebuilt in the best possible manner, newly stocked, and is to-day-olne of the best roads in the country, running its trains on time and giving great delight to the traveling public; thanks to the enterprise and energy of Supt. GARDINER, a kind-hearted, grey- haired gentleman, who is ranked among the best railroad men in the country. I go down twice a year to see him, and we always talk about the day when he under- took to run his time-table and the result thereof. This thrilling little sketch illus- trates in a very striking manner the noble qualities of a class of men of whom we are very little accustomed to think in this con- nection,-namely, railroad' men. People have become so accustomed to this expeditious mode of travel- ing, in comfortable, even luxurious carriages, without personal trouble or responsibility, as to regard it as a natural state of things; and for- get that such results can only be attained by constant labor and unremitting care and faithfulness on the part of these men, whom we are so ready to reproach and blame., The fact that we so readily trust our lives in their hands, proves that we believe them to possess these qualities of faithful- ness and fidelity; and how often do we see it proved in deeds of heroism as grand as were ever witnessed on the field of battle: when' conductor, engineer, fireman or brakeman goes on to certain death, if by doing so he has one chance to save those conmmitted to his care!  &#xD;<pb n="12 (Advertisement) -13 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7680-00000008"/> DR. DOWNING'S OR PAIN RELIEVER. A PURELY VEGETABLE PREPARATION, For; the Immediate and Permanent cure of all Internal and Exter- nal Pain. There is no Pain Curer, Pain Killer, or Pain Extractor in the world superior to this Medicine. glFRead carefully, FULL DIRECTIONS WITH EACH BOTTLE.   COLD-"T A KRTG COLD." Changes from  warm  to cool weather, or going to sleep in a room not properly aired, are said to occasion "a severe cold" not unattended with  danger. No doubt suppressed perspiration of- ten occasions a-severe illness, be- cause by the pores of the skin, in health,'we evaporate two ounces of perspiration per ,hour, forty-eight ounces per day. No wonder, then, we are sick when this ordination of nature goes not on with regu- larity. Kill-Pain is used with great suc- cess in breaking up a cold in its first stages,-( after it is seated on the Lungs N. Z. Downs' Elixir is the best expectorant now in use.) The patient should hasten (the very moment he feels chilly and as though he had taken cold) and take a foot bath, just as hot as can be borne, and cover up warm in bed; then bathe the soles of the feet well with Kill-Pain, and take one teaspoonful in nearly half a pint of warm water; add milk, and sweeten to suit the taste; and in twenty minutes repeat the dose, -unless perspiration starts freely. The Kill-Pain acts promptly in equalizing the circulation of blood,   thereby assisting nature very much to throw off disease by perspira- tion and otherwise. As a family Remedy it is very valuable, for the permanent cure of Neuralgia (see full directions for treating Neuralgia in circular around each bottle), common Cold, Cholera, Cholera Morbus, Nervous or Sick Headache,  Bowel  Complaint, Chronic Rheumatism, Fever and Ague, Crick in the back, weak Nerves, Spinal affections, Pain in the Head, Inflammation or Pain of any kind, Sore Throat, &amp;c. We refer the reader to the full direc- tions around each bottle, and feel confident, if you try one bottle and learn HOW to use Kill-Pain, you will never be without it in the house. If you are very Bilious, and Liver inactive, Dr. Johnson's Compound Mandrake Pills (Podo- phyllin) will assist very much to effect a speedy cure. Kill-Pain retails, small size, 25 cents; large, 50 cts., and is sold by dealers in medicines everywhere. W-Remember KILL-PAIN is an internal and external remedy, and it is well in cases of violent pain or suffering to take a dose before ap- plying it externally. Please READ AND CIRCULATE.   Could we for a moment see the world set back to its pre-railroad state, we could realize, more fully than we shall ever be able to do, the obligations we owe to railroad companies, and should perhaps be less ready to seek for faults in these valuable public servants. Next to the railroad man, or perhaps standing side by side with him as a valuable public servant, is the Physician. Entirely over- looking his own comfort and con- venience, he 'devotes himself to relieving the pains and saving the 'lives of his fellow creatures. Through summer's heat and win- ter's cold, through rain and snow, he goes, often in weariness and exhaustion, to administer healing medicines to the sick. Well and truly may the physician be called   a benefactor of mankind. Nor is he less a public benefactor, who places carefully compounded, safe and efficient medicines, all ready to be administered, within the reach of all-with full and explicit directions, so simple as to be un- derstood by a child. By these medicines, so conveniently at hand, disease may be attacked and overcome at its first appear- ance; when it might be impossible to obtain a physician, or when, as is often the case, the illness seems so slight at first, we think it is not worth while to call him in. When if we have at hand some tried and true medicine, which we can ad- minister ourselves, we attend to it at once, and thus save long sick- ness many times, and even life itself.   ,..=ANY OF HENRY &amp; JOHNSON'S ", CHOICE FAMILY PREPARATIONS " Have been before the American and Canadian People for more than a quarter of a Century. N. H. DOWNS' VEGETABLE BALSAMC ELIXIR was first introduced over forty years ago, and has had a re- markable history--it has won its way by actual service, until it has become a household friend in thousands of our best families-regular Physicians use and recommend it. Clergy- men, and all public Speakers, are its best patrons. Rail Road Employees, much exposed to Colds, Coughs, &amp;c., should al- ways use it'. Farmers, Lawyers, Merchants, and everybody, old and young, speak highly in its praise. Why do all speak so highly in praise of DowNs' ELIXIR,? Because it invariably cures Coughs, Colds, Croup, and all Ling difficulties, and is perfectly safe to give to the youngest child. Mothers should always keep a bottle ready for imme- diate use in time of need. In conclusion we wish to say, all of our Medicines are pre- pared Scientifically and are PURELY VEGETABLE.    We use no Mineral Poison whatever, in any of our Valuable Remedies.      '  J iWlOur medicines are supposed to be for sale by some one in every city and town in the, United States and the Dominion. If you do not find them in your town, please ask your- Merchant; or Druggist to order some at once from any wholesale Druggist.  &#xD;<pb n="14 (Advertisement) -15 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7680-00000009"/> 14 D . lO OHM:   O U VA AtB AKe PILLT          S A Purely Vegetable Preparation. Composed of landrake, Hyoscyamns, and other valuable infrelients.   DZtARoiAWSN is Cathartic, Emetic, Alterative, Anthelmintic, Hydragogue and Sialagogue, as a sure and active cathartic it deserves a high rank among our indigenous productions. We have no other native plant that answers the common purpose of Jalap, Aloes and Rhubarb, and which is more safe and mild in its operation. It acts principal- ly as a cathartic, if the doses administered are moderate. It promotes glandular action, exerting also a powerful influence on the condition of the cutaneous tissue, and regulates the circula- tory system. In bilious and typhoid febrile diseases, it is very valuable as a cathartic, or Emetic- Cathartic, often breaking up the disease at once. A moderate use of Mandrake is effectual in Chronic Liv er Complaint, and indeed in all hepatic derangements. The best, medical work in this country says of it:://' There is not its superior in the whole range of medicines, arousing the liver to a more healthy action, increasing the flow of bile, and keeping up these actions longer thin any other agent with which we are acquainted.   It promotes free action of the kidneys, I arousing the absorbents being a regulator of t all secretions, so far as any one medicine can s be, and exerts a complete'influence over the t pathologic condition of the blood, preventing , its strong determination to any part where congestion or incipient inflammation would be produced-as for instance, in the brain. iZMYOSCoOV'StL&amp;  S   is a powerful nar- cotic. In medicinal doses it is anodyne, hy- ) pnotic and anti-spasmodic; allaying pain, 3 soothing excitability, inducing sleep and arresting spasm. It does not produce constipation like opi- um, but has a tendency to act as a laxative. Is good in Chronic Cough, iration of the urinary organs and inflammatory cases at- tended with excitability, painful spasmodic affections, hysteria, rheumatism  and gout. It is much used by physicians in connection with griping Cathartics, to. counteract the disagreeable effects. Thereo are other very valuable ingredients used. in preparing these Pills and the pro- prietors assure all who use them that they do not contain mercury or any mineral sub- stance whatever.   DIRECTIONS.   Fon SICK AID NERVOUS HEADACHE, (in- duced by costiveness,) Indigestion, Foul breath, Jaundice, Liver Camplaint, and all Bilious disorders, take from one to two Pills on going to bed and repeat every night until you have taken from twelve to sixteen, un- less you get relief-before. FOR DYSPEPSIA, take one Pill every morn- ing a .half hour before breakfast, for three mornings and then omit for three mornings, -leaving tea and coffee alone for the time, and eat very little highly seasoned or greasy food,-and continue this treatment until you get relief. FOR NEURALGIA, take from one to two Pills on going to bed, and bathe the part   affected with  "Dr. Downing's Kill-Pain."- Read carefully the other side of this circular. FoB RHEUMATISM AND GOUT take two Pills on retiring at night for three nights, then omit three nights, and so continue until better. FoR  DtoPsY, Pains in the Side, Back, Stomach,.Limbs or joints, same dose as for rheumatism. FoB NIGHT SWEATS, or Cdold feet, or Wake- fulness the same as above. FoR FEVEB AND AGUE in the first stage of the disease, take two Pills on retiring at night, and one Pill half an hour before breakfast, and continue until relieved. Price, 5 cents per box   -  I  I DR, HENRY'S ELECTRIC OINTMENT, FOR THE RAPID CURE OF Scratches, Calks, Sores, Galls, Flesh Wounds, Salt Rheum, &amp;c., &amp;c.   3 to 6 applications will cure the worst case of Scratches. 1 to 2 applications will cure Galls and Flesh Wounds. 3 to 6 applications will cure Founder, when taken in its early stage. After the dis- ease is seated it cannot be wholly cured. The Ointment, however, will prove very beneficial.   i to 2 applications will cure Sores and Cracks in Cows' Teats. Farmers, try it! the effect in healing such Sores is truly magical. 2 to 4 applications will cure Salt3Rheum Sores. 1 to 2 pplications will cure Chapped, Sore and Cracked Hands, in the healing of which it has a very powerful effect.   Wr"his Ointment, used with Dr. Woodward's Stillingia Compound, Warranted to Cre Salt Rheum.   It is well known -to all that horses which are exposed to the mud, in the spring and fall, are liable to become lame, from the effect of Scratches; and then, follows a long delay in their use; when one application of this Ointment, in time, would have cured the disease. Hence we urge all to provide them- selves with a remedy. How often is it the case that a horse- (and perhaps a valuable one) is taken lame, slightly at first,the lameness even disappearing altogether for a time, only, however, to re- appear, in a worse state than the first I This may be followed up for a time, without any apparent danger; but are you aware that through this lameness the Scratches are lia- ble to fasten themselves upon the beast?-- that through it a disease may soon become seated upon the horse which ordinary treat- ment would fail to cure? Such, however, is the case; and unless taken in' its earliest stage a good deal of difficulty may be ex- perienced in mastering the same. This Oint- ment, however, not only will cure when the disease first assumes the nature of Scratches, but it will prove a speedy cure in aU caises of long standing. Care should be used, in difficult cases, to   purify the blood, whilst using this Ointmrent. (Johnson's or Chamberlin's celebrated Condi- tion Powders should be used freely to cleanse the blood while using the Ointment, and can be procured of dealers everywhere.) Keep a bottle of the Ointment constantly on hand, and when your horse first shows any appearance of lameness make one application, and have done with the troublesome disease. Yet bet- ter still would it be to make an application of the Ointment once a month, even without any appearance of the disease, as it would keep the skin soft and healthy, avoiding all possibility of a sore or lameness. This Ointment has been found .to possess virtues in curing Salt Rheum never before attained by any remedy for this disease; and we can assure all those troubled with the Salt Rheum, or with Chapped or Cracked Hands, that with a few applications they may 'dry those sores entirely up. Please try at once, and convince yourself. DR. HENRY'S ELECTRBI OINTMENT is the cheapest preparation, for an ointment, ever offered to the public; each bottle contains nearly double the amount of others at the same price. Retails 50 cents per bottle. Sold in every town and city.   HENRY &amp; JOHNSON, Proprietors, Burlington, Vt, To whom all orders should be addressed.  &#xD;<pb n="16 (Advertisement) -17 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7680-00000010"/> Use Dr. Johnson's Calisaya Bitters, -when your Appetite fails.   DOWNS"EVIXIE. D When the chilling winds of winter P Howl amid the leafless branches, , When from out the North the Stormn King Marches with his snowy Banners,- And with fierce and sudden conquest Lays all summer dead before him: X Every flower and every leaflet i He lays stark and dead before him; And the singing birds of summer a Fly away from all the Northland. O Where the air seems full of arrows, Full of sharp anc stinging arrows That will pierce ts, if we venture But to step outsic e the doorway, Then Consumption, fell destroyer, Sallies forth to seek his victims. * Coughs and Colds are his forerunners, Marking where success is easy; And, where these are not resisted - But allowed to hold possession, There Consumption, gaunt and ghastly, Soon will make his dread appearance, And will seize his hapless victims. Would you have a siife protection From this foe, so justly dreaded? A protection so unfailing That you need not fear his visits? Go and Buy some DOWNS ELIXIR, Some real N. H. DoSwns' Elixir; Made from all most hoaling Balsams Found in all the Northern forests,- Balsams of the Pine'and Fir treo: M ade-in Burlington--a city \ Standing near the Champlain waters; At one hundred tweinty-seven,  Very near the head of Church Street ' By the firm of HENRY &amp; JOHNSON, Medicine men, well known to many: ' And for sale at every Drug Store Throughout all the frozen Northland. 'Tis a safe and sure protection, Go and buy it, and be happy.   E    PROF. MOTT'S MAGIC HAIR INVIGORATOR. Every Lady should keep it on her toilet stand. It is a niceDressi Johnson's Condition Powders,'for Horses, Cattle and Swine   o .  .. I HENRY &amp; JOHN2SON, Proprietorv Ordmm SoWlct    127 Church St., Burlington Vt.   HOUPANDP OF PEOPLE ALREADY know tJe worth of ]. P. .  OWNP' ALIXIR, and know just HOW  to uze it, but if any one does not get t e desired, effect we advise them\to increase t1e dose and follow    directions around eac3 bottle, carefully. alife is precious and medicines should be taken promptly and at the rif-t time. 7Te large bottles are much cheaper in long standing Pulmonary com- plaints, as you should use the t Elixir freely. Price, small bottle, 85 cts. LEerge $1. 00.   DR. HE1NRY'S ELECTRIC OINTMENT Cures Scratches, Calks, Galls, Flesh Wounds, Salt Rhenm, &amp;c. 1 to 6 applications will cure the worst cases of Scratches. 1 to 2 applications will cure Galls, Flesh Wounds and Chapped Hands. 4 to 6 applications will cure Founder when in its early stage, (after the disease is seated it cannot be wholly cured.) This Ointment, however, will prove very beneficial. 1 to 2 applications will cure Cow's sore teats. Farmers, fry it.  HENRY'S' ELECTRIC OINTMENT used according to directions, with JOHN- SON'S CONDITION POIWDERS, is warranted to cure Scratches. DIl:S ECTIOi'-S. For Scratches, clean the part affected with Castile Soap; apply once a day enough to moisten the sore; rub it in thoroughly with the fingers. Never in any case use hot irons, nor -pick the scab off; which will form after the first application. For Founders, apply to the coronary ring, (the point where the skin joins the hoofs,) also to the frog of the hoof, once in three days. For Galls, Calks, Flesh Wounds, Chapped Hands, Salt Rheum, &amp;c., apply every day until healed, always observ- ing to rub it in thoroughly. For Salt Rheum, first cleanse the blood. JOHNSON'S CONDIITION POWDERS. For HORSES, ,CATTLE and SWINE. These Powders may- be given with great advantage in all cases of worms, loss of appetite, roughness of the hair or coat, stoppage of water and bowels, all coughs and colds, inflamation of the lungs and bowels, recent founders, swelling of the glands of the throat, horse distemper, hide bound, and also will check the heaves, and in recent cases effect a cure. In fact, there is no disease among horses, cattle and swine where these valuable Powders are not called for, and by their timely administration they will save the lives of many valuable animals. DI:%EICTIOTNS. The dose for a horse is from one to two tablespoonfuls, acording to severity of attack. in any feed a horse will eat, mixed in a little water. The same for cattle, and a little less for swine. For the young of either of the above, about one-half the dose. In severe cases. when the animals refuse to eat, it will be necessary to increase the dose a little, and mix it with a ball of meal and force it down the throat. Price 25 cents, or Five Packages for One Dollar. HXENRY &amp; JOHWNSON, Proprietors, BURLINGTON, VT. Henry &amp; Johnson's "Choice Family Preparations" sold everywhere.  &#xD;<pb n="18 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7680-00000011"/> ,J. 4. POWJ4 -ELIXIR, ETABLIPHED IN 1832.   K  -1832. We hope our friends will not fail to try N. H. DOWNS' ELIXIR FOR COUGHS, COLDS, CROUP, WHOOPING COUGH, SPtITTING BLOOD, ASTHMA, PLEURISY, CONSUMPTION, AND ALL "UNG COMPLAINTS.   1873. DR. DOWNING'S XTTTLL-PAIN IS AN OLD Reliable Medicine, AND FOR THE SPEEDY CURE OF CRAMPS, Bowel Complaints, NEURALGIA, Nervous or Sick Headache, CHOLERA MORBUS, SORE THROAT, Toothache, &amp;c. it has NO SUPERIOR.   It affords us much pleasure to thankl our many WIf-- friends, and customers, for past favors and patronage. WWe take this occasion to say, our stock of goods is cor- plete in every particular, and will be sold, as zusual, at a very small advance. We believe "Thee nimble sixpence is better than the slow shilling ff " O&amp;Our goods are all warranted as represented. Please call and see us before purchasing elsewhere. It is no trouble for us to show our merchandise. In conclusion we present this little Pamphlet and bespeak for it a careful perusal. M. B. CALLAGHAN, CHARLTON, N. Y.    &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
