<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7495">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Blind Girl's Offering, or, Stray Thoughts in Poetry and Prose </title>
            <author >Pratt, L. J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7495</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The blind girl's offering, or, Stray thoughts in poetry and prose</title>
                  <author >Pratt, L. J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >142 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >P.P.R. Ripley</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Swanton Vt. </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1853">1853</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-01-23">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The blind girl's offering, or, Stray thoughts in poetry and prose</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7495-00000001"/>  THE BLIND GIRL'S OR STRAY THOUGHTS IN POETRY AND PROSE. BY IL Jo PRATT.  BWANTON, VERMONT, P. P. R. RIPLEY, PRINTER. 1MS-,  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7495-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, 1853 BY. A.. J. SA MoON, In the Clerk's Office of the District ofVt.   PREFACE. In presenting this little work to the pub- lic, the writer would beg leave to say, that she does not make special claims to erudi- tion, or a style of writing, which shall at-  tract for its novelty. Having I been nearly deprived of the use of her eyes since the agv of ten years, she has made such use of her mental faculties as her kind Heavenily Parent has permitted and through the aid of her friends, presents in this little volume, some of those meditations which have occupied her mind, while the ex- ternal world in all its beauty and splendor has in a great measure been shut out from her vision. She can only hope that her readers will throw the mantle of charity over the many imperfections, which she is aware exists in these humble efforts, to give form and expression to a few straggling thoughts. She would respectfully ask that  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7495-00000003"/> PREFAC E. the "Golden Rule," might be the rule by which her cause might be tried, and then she may confidently expect that the "'Blind Girls Offering," will meet with a kind re- ception from an indulgent public. West Berkshire, Vt.   THE BLIND GIRL'S OFFERING. CHAPTER I. DIALOGUE BETWEEN SUSAN AND ELIZA. Good morning, Miiss Eliza, why are you not ready for the party? Eliza.-Because I do not intend to go. Susan.-Do not intend to go? why, Miss Wheeler and Miss Grant are to be there; and they have everything nice that town and country can produce. Would you miss of such a chance as this, Eliza? Eliza.-To tell you plainly, Susan, I have not a dress that would be suitable to wear on such an occasion. Susan.-Have not a dress, what can be the reason? I saw your father give you five dollars, only last week ; pray, what have you done with it? Eliza.-Come see my purchase, here it i^        J*       '  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7495-00000004"/> 8     TlTHE BLIND  GIRL'S Susan.--W'hat is here? a pile of cotton cloth and leather shoes; pray, what do you intend to do with this? Eizia.--I intend to clothe three little girls, to whom no learning hath been given, and send them to the Sabbath School, that they may learn the way to heaven. Susal.-Well such things are well enough, but I would not deprive myself of attending such a party for all the little girls and Sab- bath Schools in the world. Eliza.-Wcll, I consider my time and money better spent, than in attending such a party, I assure you. Susan.--I dare say a cotton dress, leather shoes,and home spun stockings, to only see my shoes are of the finest kid, and spangled too, my dress is muslin, worked complete, on- ly see how my bonnet shines, why I should fret myself to death, if I was dressed as mean as you. I always cry and teasc mas ma for every thing I see that is new, Eliza.-Why I should be a cruel child to tease mama, she gets me every thing she can und what more can I ask? Susan.--Why, what if there should be a  ball, and you should have a chance to go J   OFFERING.       9 and all the young misses dressed complete, would you appear among them so? Eliza.-A ball, I never went toone, I do not care for things likethose,we have amuse- ment among ourselves, and I will tell you what it is; I and- my sister take our turn to help our mother through the day, one will sew the other knit and this is what I like to see; then our father comes from work, after supper down he sits and takes a book and reads about some foreign country or else the book is laid aside and he tells some delightful story; now, Miss Susan, do you thinlr I should care for things like those t See, while we stand talking here the sun sets, and evening is come, now you may go to dancing balls andI'll enjoy my friends at home. CHAPTER II THE PEhCEIUL COTTAGZ. In a mall village, in the eastern part of Maine, lived, some years since, an ocd wo- man, who was known ,y the ui;am of- idt trious Mary. Her cottage was liilt ;wit  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7495-00000005"/> 10     THE BLIND 'GIRL'S logs and covered with slabs, but from the air of neatness which every thing about it exhibited, could not fail of attracting the notice of the passing stranger. Soon after the death of the old lady, two friends hap- pened in their travels to meet at this place and being invited by the beauty of the scenery and the desire of discoursing with freedom upon past events, to a walk in the fields they found themselves unexpectedly at the humble cottage, which a tall hedge had at first hindered them from seeing. While they stood admiring its neatness and simplicity and anxious to know something of its occupant, they were joined by a villager, who informed-them that it was then unin- habited and at their request proceeded to give the character of its late owner the sub- stance of which was as follows: She was a native of this village, and lived all her life here without any loose desire of seeking her fortune or fancy expectation of meeting with advancement in distant places. Being always averse to society she had no borrowed vices nor imitated follies, she was unacquainted with the false pleasures of   OFFERING.       " luxury, and what she knew nothing of, she neither desired nor envied. Her wants were the wants of nature ; she had not habituated herself to falsehood by flattering the vanity of a gaudy mistress, nor borrowed the art of shedding tears for trifles, or bearing insolence with an affected submission; but having thus escaped the general source of corrup- tion and at the same time, excluded herself from all hopes of any assistance, hut that of Providence, she maintained herself by an honest and unwearied industry, free from distress and above dependence. It is the right of every cottager to graze a cow on the adjoining common. This privilege was Mary's estate. She had many years ago purchased a cow with the money she had saved from the wages of her daily .labor.-- From her she was supplied with milk and butter and cheese part of, which she lived on, and part she carried to the market.-- In a little garden clese to the house she had a row of apple trees under which, when no other business called her away, she sat sew- ing with a contented heart and and a smil- ing face. Thus, what would have been wretchedness and poverty in the estimation ,' 5SP  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7495-00000006"/> 12    THS BLIND GIRL'S of those who have been accustomed to fash- ionable life, was easy affluence in the nat- ural condition of humanity. The neatness and regularity of her house made me often frequent it; her furniture and utensils of the cheapest sort were always clean, and al- ways in order and every thing about her seemed to be under the direction of Provi- dence and the smiles of heaven. When she rose in the morning her devotions were her first employment, her earliest and pur- est thoughts were given to her Creator in a form of humble adoration. She then read a short portion of the holy scriptures with a sincere and earnest attention, not with a view of reconciling them to vice, or of inter- preting them in her own favor; but of regu- lating her behavior by their unerring rules, nor till those duties were performed did she suffer her mind to fix upon the business of the day.  She then milked her cow and made her cheese, after which she sat down to her sewing, and except, the little time spent at her meals, worked till evening.- She never went far from home, hr longest journey was to the next market where she sold the "produce of her little dairy, re-   OFFERING.       13 ceived the price of her sewing, and bought what her own cow and garden did not afford her. At the close of day, she again milked her cow and concluded the day with reading and devotions. Thus was her life one uni- form scene of innocence and piety, not sad- dened by misfortune, nor varied by caprice. She -enjoyed almost uninte rupted health till the age of sixty, and then dying of a short illness was found possessad of seventy- five pounds which she had laid up, that when she should be able to work no longer, she might not subsist upon the labor of oth- ers. Such was the history of Mary, the in- habitant of the little cottage, a place, which by her industry and virtue, she rendered far more venerable than the elegant mansions of sloth and luxury. When we sit in solitude out of the sight of man and unbiassed by their customs, when we are not afraid of being ridiculed by wit, or wondered at by folly, is it possi- ble to doubt a moment which to prefer.- Can rational beings put weeks, months and years, trifled away in unimproving discourse, idle visits and empty amusements in compe- tition with Mary's useful labor. But if we  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7495-00000007"/> "   THE BLIND GIRL'S look farther into the conduct of those who stand in higher life, and add their vices to their follies, if with the time lost in thought- less diversion, we think that which is wast- ed by unlawful passions in ambitious pur- suits, or criminal indulgences, if we reflect on the allurements to wickedness and dis- couragement from virtue, we shall be still more convinced of the happiness of obscuri- ty. It is certain that with whatever con- tempt we may now look on so narrow a cir- cle of life, most of us will at a time when we shall think, and most justly wish that suck only had fallen to our lot. The devotion of Mary, so far as we may presume to judge was not disregarded since they were offered by one, who lived in the practise of all the duties that fall within the compass of ac- tion, They, no doubt, drew upon her the eyes of those angelic beings who look with contempt on pompous greatness, and turn with abhorrence from prosperous wickedness, and opened to her those regions of eternal happiness, whither many, who now boast their noble, ample fortunes and extensive capacities, will never arrive. When we are led to repine at our station and to envy the   OFFERING.       15 rich and the great let us look at their vices, their cares and their troubles, and we may learn to hush every murmur by contrasting them with the happy life and peaceful death of the contented, the industrious, the pious Mary.  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7495-00000008"/> 16    THE BLIND (IRL'A (CHAPTER  1. POETRY. Good morning to this noble band, You are united heart and hand, To walk in wisdom's paths, I trust, And never once your Lord distrust. Remember that his love is great, His mercy more than tongue can tell, He gave his only son to die, To save a guilty world from hell. He suffered much while here on earth, He groaned and died for all of us, With what submission did he yield, And drank that bitter cup indeed. A crown of thorns we have often read, Was placed upon our savior's head, With vinegar then a sponge was filled, Handed our Lord his thirst to quell. Then while we view him on the tree, Bleeding, dying, for you and me, What reverence then ought we to pays To our Redeemer every day. Children this is a narrow road, That leads to Christ our shepherd's fold, But if we choose him for our guide, We need not fear he will provide,   OFFERING.       17 Then when Gabriel does his trumpet sound To awake the nations under ground, We shall rnot stand in fear of him, Who did to us salvation bring. LINES TO A COUSIN ON THE DEATH OF HER MOTHER. Dear cousin, with a loss you've met, That this wide world cannot restore; A mother's love, a mother's care You need not seek it any more. You'll find this world an empty void Where sin and darkness reigns, Without a mother's watchful care Her kind advice and pious prayer. Yet while you mourn the loss of one, Who near, and dear, hath been; Remember that her sufferings past, Her sorrows are atan end. Her soul hath fled from earth to heaven, Her spirit is in the skies ; Prepare to meet your mother there, Where pleasure never died. Dear cousin, I would you entreat, From youthful snares to turn your feet; Choose Jesus for your only guide, Then for your wants He will provide. 3  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7495-00000009"/> 18    THE BLIND GIRL'S LINES WRITTEN ON THE DEATH OF A SISTER. Dear sister, thou art dead, Thy spirit now is gloe ; And why shuold I still linger Around this lifeless form? Lord leave me not to murmur, Thy spirit did her call From this cold hearted world, Unfriendly to us all. Thou sawest this plant was feeble, And here it could not bloom ; Thy hand hath now transplanted it In fairer climes to grow. Then why ,L^,, I still murmur, Or think thl c 1oo severe, While I am left to sojourn A little longer here? O, no, I do not wish her back To this unfriendly world ; Then why do I still weep Around this lifeless form.   OFFERING.       19 CHAPTER IV. DIALOGUE BETWEEN MARY AND SUSAN. Mary.-Good morning, Julia, where are you going with yonr basket? Julia.--I-am agoing on yonder hill to get some cherries, and have called for you and Emma to go with me. Mary.-Why, you have forgotten that this is the Sabbath day, and we are ready for the Sabbath School. Julia.-No, I have not forgotten but I am going to have some cherries, come let its see if Emma will go with us? Mary.--Emma, Emma, Julia Smith is going to get some cherries, and has called for us. Will you go, Emma? Good morning, Julia, then you are going to leave the Sabbath School for the sake of a few cherries, are you? Julia.-Miss, they are ripe and good now, and I am going to have some before they are all gone. Emma.-What excuse will you make to your teacher when she asks you the cause of your absence? * "   -1   &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7495-00000010"/> kV    -*Ug DulliU D iN 1 L'S Julia.-Why, I shall tell her that I was not at home. Emma.-What if she should ask you where you were, would you not feel ashamed to let her know that you left the Sabbath School for a few cherries? Julia.-Well, she need not know it, I shall not tell her. . Why, I have been to Sabbath School every Sabbath this summer, and where is the harm if I am not there to. day. Emma.-Well, Mary, what do you say, do you wish to leave the Sabbath School and go with Julia for some cherries? Mary.-No, I do not wibh to leave the Sabbath School, but I should like some cher. ries very much, why not go to-night, after meeting? -Emma.-No, Mary, that would not be right to be rambling over the fields, but if Julia will wait till some night this week we will go with her, but for my part I would not leave the Sabbath School for all the cherries on the hill. Julia.-Well, for my part, I am tired and sick of going to the Sabbath School. Emma.-Then you are tired of learning   OFFERING.       21 the way to heaven, are you? Why, Julia what if you were called to die? what thought would cheer the passing hour? would you not wish for one Sabbath more that ycu might learn the way to heaven? Julia.-O, yes, I want to go to heaven when I die, but can I not go and get a few cherries and go to heaven too? Emma.-Julia, you know what the Poet says: ," You must not work you must not play Upon God's Holy Sabbath day." Julia.-Well you have convinced me that I am wrong, I will go strait home, and change my dress, and then come back and go with you. DIALOGUE BETWEEN CECILIA AND CATHARINE. Catharine.-Good morning, Cecilia, then you are all ready for the Sabbath School? Cecilia.-Yes, only. my books, we are go-  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7495-00000011"/> 22   THE BLIND GIRL'S ing to have an addition to our library and then it will be more interesting. Catharine.-Yes, they are going to take up a collection to-day, I believe. Cecilia.--Yes, I suppose so. Catharine.--How much are you going to give?  Cecilia.-A quarter, how much are you? Catharine.-Not one cent, and I think you greatly beside yourself to give any thing. Cecilia.-Why, do we not have the books to read . Catherine.--Yes, but what if we do? let those pay who are better able than we are. Cecilia.-Well, what if every one should say so, what would become of our library, our books would soon become .old and they would not be at all interesting? Catharine.-Well, Cecilia, you know they are taking up a collection every now and then for something or other? Cecilia.-Well, I will tell you the rea- son, it is because there are so manypossess- ed with the same covetous disposition which you have manifested here this morning ; but if they would only pay us liberal as they !   OFFERING.       28 would to purchase some useless ornament to decorate their pers on wlm:i only fosters pride and makes them vain ; they would have enough at once and would not be under the necessity of taking up a collection so of- ten. Catharine.-Well, if I was as rich as Mr. Young or Mr. White, or many others which I could mention, I would not hesitate to give a dollar for any religious purpose. Cecilia.-Well, Catharine, many of those rich men which you speak of, will take a quarter and pinch it half in two rather than to drop it into the box, then drawing it back, saying I guess a nine-pence will do for me, alnd reluctantly dlopping that in to the box ; now if every one was possuesed with the same disposition what would be- come of our public institutions? Catharine.-Well, I do not think that is right, to be sure, and if I were rich I would not manifest such a disposition as that, but for my part if I have anything to give I had rather give it to some poor orphan child to buy him clothing. Cecilia.-That is very useful to be sure, but our laws have provided means to supply  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7495-00000012"/> 24    THE BLIND GIRL'S such wants and if you have a quarter to spare, I think it would be better to buy Ire ligious books which will teach them the way to Hteaven. Catharine.--Well, I do not feel able to give a quarter every now and then. Cecilia.-Well, they do not wish to dis- tress people, and if you do not feel able to give a quarter, give what you are able, a smaller amount will be very acceptable and add to the sum to purchase a library. Catharine.--Well, Cecilia, I do think that it is every ones duty to do all they can to promote the Sabbath School, and as there is nothing more required of a person than what they have the ability to perform, I will give a nine-pence this time and ere another collection is taken up I will save my money which I would pay for some useless orna. ment and give to, increase the library or for any other religious purpose for which the collection may be taken. Cecilia.-Well, Catharine, I am glad if you are convinced that you are wrong, I was '4iito sure if you stopped to consider a mo- ment that you would agree with me now let us hasten to the Sabbath School and hereaf-   OFFERING.        25 tor we will both endeavor to do all we can to promote the happiness of others as well as our own. CHAPTER V. "FE OF LUCY BRYANT. I will give my readers a faint sketch of the Life:cf Lucy Bryant. She was an amiable girl, prepossessing in her manners, and, in siort, admiured by all who knew her. Lucy had beOn blessed with a pious mother who had early taught her to love the Savior, al- so that he died to save sinners-that whoso- ever believed on Him should not perish, but have everlasting life. When Lucy was about eleven years of age, she had a long and painful illness. Yet she did not murmur or complain, but she sensibly felt that this af, fliction was laid upon her to show her the importance of being prepared to meet her God in peace, and faithfilly did she prom- ise her Heavenly Father that if He would  again restore her to health, she would endea- : vor, by His grace assisting her, to live the 4,  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7495-00000013"/> 26    THE BLIND GIRL'S life of a Christian. At length she regained her former health, and did not forget her promise as many children do, for she was a faithful follower of Christ, during her life. Mary Wheeler, a girl of about the same age of Lucy, was very sick, and her physicians had pronounced her disease incurable. Ma. ry, though but a child, felt very uneasy re- specting the welfare of her soul, and reques- ted her mother to send for Lucy Bryant.- Her request was granted, and Lucy soon ar- rived, and, on entering the room, Mary ex- claimed with great agitation, "Lucy, I am about to die, and I feel that I am a great sinner, and without an interest in Christ.- I have sent for you to come and pray with me." ' Well, Mary, you know that Christ died for the greatest of sinners, and if you ask God with all your heart to forgive your sins for Christ's sake, He will hear and an. swer your prayer.' "Lucy, I have tried to pray, and yet I do not feel any better. I wish you would pray for me now." Lucy knelt beside her bed, and prayed fervently to God that He would, for Christ's sake, cleanse her heart from sin, and let her find peace in believing in a crucified Savior. And   OFFERING.      27 before Lucy had finished her prayer, Mary was shouting aloud in praise to God. Lucy arose, and after talking for some time with her, took leave of her, promising to call a- gain. The next day, Lucy again called up- on Mary, and found that Death's icy hand was already laid upon her. As she approach- ed the bed ,where Mary lay, in the embrace of Death, she burst into tears. Mary, turn- ing towards her, said--"Lucy, do not-weep; I am not afraid to die now : I feel that I can say, ' Lord Jesus, come quickly.' "- Then turning to her mother, who was weep- ing by her side, said, "Ma, do not weep for me-I am going to rest, but we shall meet again in heaven to part no more. Then put- ting her hands together, she said, "My happy soul is on the wing;" and her spirit took its flight to the regions of bliss. Lucy then returned home, feeling a stronger deter- mination to live and die a Christian than Ae had ever felt before. She at length blo0ia' ed into womanhood, a mild and lovely being.  She was beloved by a young man who feared not God, neither did he keep His command- ments. But Lucy felt that, by the grace of God, she should overcome his stubborn heart,  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7495-00000014"/> 2I    THE BIND GIRL'S and persuade Charles Wheeler (for that was the name of her young lover) to forsake his sins, a'ld seek his soul's salvation. At l]eoth the day for her nup-tials a'rivcd, v1l n,:ty a LkysmpathPtle tcer t't '-.o.  :' u' y Charles A h elc r r'omIn,cd ,. to , I: place of ireside'oe, C?,he .; cry 1:, c ^1 lair "nd prot-n.':.; b4 b. *.'ls , e (t consist i i iches, fI Loucy .s 1Uot  Lucy prayed allnaost witout cctU;,a" hier unconverted husb and ; but twh  ver sio ta1ked with him upon the subject of' l'lii:on, he would fly into a passion, and say, *, I wish you would not trouble yourself so much about me; I think I am quite as good as those who profess religion." In vain did she try to have him read some passages of Scrip- ture, or listen to her; but he would not, and immediately leaving the room. Poor Lucy felt as though her heart would braak, and falling upon her knees, implored High Hea c yven to awaket her unconverted husb:and, and bring him to a knowledge of the trut!t. He at length refused to attend Church. In spite of all Lucy's warm entreaties, he wouldstill neglect the offers of mercy, and remain at homo. Time passed on, and he was at length q   OFFERING. ibligcld to leave hone on buE;ne.. for the pnacc of ten or filteen dc4ys, and requested Lu i' to 2.t a ch n) o o linien, into 1his v1- ]i:o. l"A.3 tho boat lc: v.; :3 .t on 3 o'clod;, I )         I i ..aj ..... '  ' 1-1 A :\v - to t ; iua out a ho0vu ." Wi o poc!;c-!'"B^)B id YIVLL) f i r:o t? * i , tur ii "'  ..a. vthile I m*u gone'. L -y said, I it Ulay be  comfo'it to you for e you retain." The ;Aime soon arr-ived for his dcpartnrc, and t... :ill:' up his .vaise, barde her "(Good after- :oon," and started for the door. iLucy repli- "d, "( Good afternoon,- may God be with you." Charles left the house, and c may God be itlh you" still sounded in his ear. In vain did h1r try to clive it awty, but he :ould not. After he went on to the boat, he ried to fornget i, tand amnse hiomself by walk- nlg 0on tho deck ; 'but sfthl " nmay (od be ith Sayo oe upiefd this nlind. He said with- go hiemsc it, "Wsill Godul prinot ist In^ asu an I,..nwoth woni as I?^ nd tLhus he went on a o re'ect upon hiwe former life. When he left tle boat, h"e resolved to open the pocket-Bi  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7495-00000015"/> 30    THE BLIND GIRL'S ble as soon as he reached his room which should be allotted to him for the night. And as soon as -he reached his room, he opened his valise, and taking out the Bible, said- "I will see what I shall open to,'i and open- ing it, the first thing that met his eye was, Prepare to meet thy God in peace." This troubled Charles very much. He. was not gone from home very long before he was ta- ken very ill, and his physician pronounced his disease fatal. Charles grew very much alarmed about himself, and asked the physi. cian if he thought he should ever get well. His answer was, "( Mr. Wheeler, I will be plain with you. I do not think you can live but a short time." Charles replied, with agitation, "I cannot die-I am not prepar- ed." Doctor W. tried to console him, and asked if he would have a minister come and pray with him. Charles refused, and reques- ted him to send for Lucy. The doctor re- plied, "Your request shall be granted," and left the room. Accordingly, a messenger was dispatched, and Lucy at length arrived. On entering the room where Charles lay, he burst into a flood of tears. Taking him by the hand, she imprinted a kiss upon his   OFFERING.        81 cheek. She said, "Charles, are you willing to die?"He exclaimed, " O, no! I can nev- er die in such a frame of mind." "Well, Charles, have you read any in my Bible?" ' O yes, Lucy, it is that which has brought ne to a sense of my duty." "Well, you know there is nothing but the blood of Christ that can atone for your sins, and if you will forsake your sins, and form the resolution that you will serve God while you live, He will abundantly pardon your sins, and make you to rejoice in a Saviot's love." "O yes, Lucy, I have formed that resolution, but I lo not feel any relieved-I wish you would pray for me." "O yes, Charles, I do pray for you; but I want you should pray with me now." Lucy was glad for this opportu- nity, and kneeling beside his bed, she pour- ed out her soul to God in prayer for her dis- tressed husband, both in holy and soul.- She prayed earnestly that God would restore him to health, if it could be consistent with His will, but above all to cleanse his heart from sin, and prepare him to meet his God in peace. And when she has finished her pray. Br, Charles prayed fervently for himself.- Charles had felt that if Lucy could pray  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7495-00000016"/> THE  BLIND GIRL';3 with hm, that his load of sin wou'ld be re- njoved ; and ho was not dlisap:ointed, foi' er1 an,:thier morn da-c;nedl, he 'eit that the lacd of sin wus cremoved, wan d ppraised God tha t he had beeon ,les: d with a pioU, cCrn p;is n;c. At lengt ,th c Lce n to recover, rnd in!the cor'le f two cr C1' l.'C - OC 1-h W as able to be rmvcd hc;;lol. L .oy fi-lt i lcUst s. tho-;: ahe i ;lad never known wht roal lppine.:s -;Vs until C .!rlcs was converted, for thoso rwerc ;the L, iStap i: tmt, cLr lo'er lif. Chatrls illil I dt hi c;vt;::l 4:t wi'th U-1        SCl'i .,  0-" L. Gcd, anrd cstab-i:;h, a f-;mily r( Gn hiS -i O tu .n hing, w. ro a:G d Liucj iitu- nod 1   1 '  thGnks to .God *r th e preccrv 1icn cf ' teir lives, tnd  a ..C-n i) isou   oo after, Lucy was a h'apy li ccr of' Ch;it- (Cvctiv  pS17,d :.:o,.ly on, uil sh h:xd rachedld he I riy-lhi:.3 y:\i: w'hu., th, Lord survive but a short time, sho sid, t Where is hnarles?" ie arefe and approachoio Inor wurv ve but af c u1- t t o  c, l-he Wct".":'I ' ---    .  .. rC!, bed, anhd taking ir hand in hi;, she id, "Charles, I am not afraid to die; but there   OFFERING.       33 is a tie which binds my heart to you but not my will, but Thine, O Godi be done.- Go on in the way which thou hast begun, and we shall meet in heaven, to part no more." She then requested them to sing the Dying Christian,' and she tried to sing: There is not a cloud that doth arise, To hide my Jesus from my eyes: I soon shall mount the upper skies- All is well-all is well; and bidding Charles farewell till they should meet in heaven, her spirit, on angel's wings, was wafted to its home, and left Charles to lament the loss of a pious and affectionate wife. CHAPTER VI. POITBY. The nearest friends on'earth must part, Though friendship doth unite our heartu; For duty calls us different ways, And the call we must obey. But what is life without a friend To soothe one's heart when filled with grief; A friend to help in time of need- A friend that is a friend indeed? 5  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7495-00000017"/> 34    THE BLIND GIRL'S But they are scarce upon this earth- There is few that care but for your purse: But let adversity arise, And then your friends will from you fly. But give me, while on earth, a stay-- A friend that will not tura away; And when adversity doth arise, Will not leave me alone to die. This is the last Sabbath I ever shall meet With this band who have assembled of our Saviour to speak; For I am agoing far away and leave you be- hind, Yet I trust that in heaven we all shall be join'd. Though we are separated by lakes deep and wide, Yet from our Savior we never can hide: Then let us walk on in this Christian road, Until we all meet in that blest abode. MY CHILDHOOD'S HOME. *    Sweet is the memory of my happy home, and fain would I pause and gaze upon those scenes when I enjoyed the blessings of pious O   OFFERING.       35 and affectionate parents. And well do I re- member, when kneeling around the family altar, the prayers that were offered to the throne of grace in my behalf, and how tho't- lessly I passed them by. O, could I recall the pabt! but in vain: they are gone-all gone. When I roamed through the green wood, my heart unshadowed by a thought of care, I little dreamed that the scene before me could be so changed. But alas! the truth too forcibly tells that dear father is no mnore. Death's icy hand fell heavily upon him, and blowly he pined and died; and they bore him slowly away to 'the narrow house appointed for all the living.' But memory lingers a- round the spot Where oft I have roam'd in childhood's hour, And chased the bee from flower to flower, And picked sweet grapes from our garden bower. And sweet the memory of that day, When I saw my father making hay- When I heard his gentle voice, then my youthful heart rejoiced. And when he came in from the barn, He'd always take me in his arms; Then, with a cheerful smile, he'd say,. "Now go, and with your mother stay."  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7495-00000018"/> 86    THE BLIND GIRL'S I little dreamed that he could die, And leave a child as young as I; For I was scarce six years of age, Yet I was not too young to leave. For ere the autumnal leaves were found Lying upon the frozen ground, My father he had tasted death, And sank into a heavenly rest. And Memory's left a sadness here, Which time will not efface, I fear: There's sadness on my mother's brow- She sighs and weeps for father now. A weeping willow doth o'er him hang-- My mother doth his grave attend: A marble monument we have raised, To tell us where dear father lies. And while we weep around his grave, His spirit's gone to sing God's praise; And when our lives on earth are past, May we meet him in that heaven at last. DIALOGUE BETWEE MR. AND MRS. BABCOCK, MR BROWN AND MRS. AND MSS HAGUE. "Mrs. B--- , here is a letter that Mr. Hague left with me for you."   OFFERING.       37 [Mr. B--- reading-Enter Mr. Brown.] Mr. Babcock--"Good afternoon, Mr. Brown." Mr. Brown-"A Good afternoon." Mr. Babcock--"Mr. Brown, I have just received a letter from Miss Hague, who has applied for our school, but as our school is rather large, I do not think a female teacher will answer our purpose." Mr. Brown-'"Well, as I have no teacher- engaged, perhaps she will be the very one for our school, if she is capable of teaching common branches, and good morals. I think as much of that, as any one thing; and no doubt 'she is, or she would not present her- self as a teacher." Mrs. Babcock--"Yes, I think as much of good morals and religious education, as any one. I think the principles which are instil- led into children's minds while yotung, serves to govern them through life; but parents and teachers are too apt to neglect that, the most essential part." Mr. Brown.-"Yes, people are too apt to think if they can secure a fashionable teach- er-one that is competent for teaching draw- ing and the piano, that is quite sufficient.-   &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7495-00000019"/> 38    THE BLIND GTRT3' The letter says, Mr. Brown, that she will be here this afternoon." Mr. Brown--"Well, perhaps she will be here before I leave." Mrs. Babcock--"Well, I hope she will answer your purpose, Mr. Brown, for her fa- ther seemed quite anxious that she should get a school." [Mrs. and Miss Hague enter.] Mr. Brown--"Good afternoon. This is Miss Hague, I conclude, who has applied for our school." Miss Hague--"Yes." Mrs. Hague-", Yes, my darter has cum tu be zamined." Mr. Brown-- * Well, I suppose you are fa- miliar with common branches, such as geo- graphy, arithmetic and grammar." Miss Hague-"- Yes." Mrs. Hague--"O yes, my darter is parfec- ly --iliar with jography, for she has lookt intu it more'n twenty times." Mr. Brown--"Well, we will hear you bound Vermont." Mrs. Hague--" O yes, darter, you can bound Varmount," [at the same time taking a pinch of snuff.]   OFFERING.        89 Miss Hague--"Vermont is bounded on the north by California, and on the south by New York, and on the west by Texas, and on the east by Moosehead Lake." Mr. Brown--"What is the capital of Ver. mont?" Miss Hague-"Jay." Mr. Brown-". What mountains are there in Vermont?"  Miss Hague-- "The Alps." Mr. Brown--  Which is the largest river in the world?" Miss Hague-"- Pike River." Mr. Brown-", Well, I guess I have ques- tioned you enough in geography--we will hear you parse ' the boys are in the house,'" Miss Hague--c" 'The boys' is a verb, par- ticular gender, and agrees with house,- 'house' is an adverb, and qualifies ' boys."' Mr. Brown--  Will you give your rule for that?" Miss Hague-"Rule fourth. The house' must be governed by the ' boys' that are in it." Mr. Brown-." Well, we will hear you spell Berkshire."  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7495-00000020"/> 40    THE BLIND GIRL'S Miss Hague-" ]3-u-r-k-s-h-u-r-e." Mr. Brown-"Franklin." Miss Hague--"F-a-r-n-k-l-yy-n." Mr. Brown--"How did you spell that?" Miss Hague--"F-a-r-n-k-l-yy-n." Mr. Brown--"Well, I guess I have ask- e d all the questions that is necessary." Mrs. Hague--"Why, you' haint axt my darter nothin' in rethmetic, and she is jaist as good in that as she is in enny o' the rest. We haint spared no pains whatever tu eder- cate aur darter." Mr. Brown-"I presume your daughter is just as familiar with arithmetic as she is with the rest, and I should think you had taken a great deal of pains, she answers eve- rything so correctly." Mrs. Hague-"Then you think my darter will answer your purpose, do you?" Mr. Brown--"Well, I do not think a fe- male teacher will answer our purpose: our school is very large this winter." Mrs. Hague--"Wal, I guess if you could see sum o' her patch-work you'd think she would answer : besides, she is an orful good hand in the Sabbath School; Wal, you'll   OFFERING.       41 5 give her a stificut, won't you, so that she can go sum whar else?" Mr. Brown---"Well, well, I am in some- thing of a hurry, and if I conclude to, I will send it by mail this week." Mrd. Hague-- "Wal, darter, I guess we'll be a guine: that's jaist the way raal worth is seldom appresheated." [Mrs. and Miss H. leaving]- Mr. Babcock--  Well, Mr. Brown, do you think she will answer your purpose?" Mr. Brown---"Well, she is one of the teachers, any way," Mrs. Brown--"Well, she is certainly one of them to spell, and I should like to see some of her patch-work'-besides, she must be an excellent hand in the Sabbath School." Mr. Brown--"Now we can see the impor- tance of giving our children a liberal educa- tion. For my part, I had rather spend what little money I have to spend in storing their minds with useful knowledge, instead of sas ving a few rusty coppers to decorate their persons with finery." Mr. Babcok---"Well, I do not make it a practice to laugh about people after they leave my dwelling; but I must say, she i 6  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7495-00000021"/> 4:    TH'E BLIND  GIRL'S the hardest customer that I have met with this many a day." Mr. Brown-"Well, it is getting rather late-I guess I must be a going. I think I shali not have to look any farther for a teach- er. Good afternoon."  Mr. Brown-"Good afternoon." Mrs. BE    Yes, I should think she would answer any one's purpose." Mr. B---, "Yes, I am sure one must be very difficult, if she would not." POETRY. Dear teachers, and my comrades too, I; now will join and speak with you; Though I am but a little boy, Yetw Iill not decrease your joys. Though I am scarce six years of age, Yet I've been taught to speak God's praise; 4A? whilje 1 traverse this world o'er, I wish my Savior to adore. "NBS WBLLTZi N ON T WEl R DATH OF A CBTLM. - - ,-,          m r ' ' - :inpgn bambee;, thou at -no more- - '  ;uast gone-home torat.:   OPji]RING.       48 Thy mother sighed *wen thou did'st soar Above, to join the blest. Thy mother loved thee, O! too well, To long enjoy thee here; But thou hast gone above to dwell With Christ, thy Savior dear. O, what must have been the feelings of Thy parents, when they saw Their blooming rose had its eyelids closed, Now sleeps in death, a calm repose'? But weep not for your babe, for he Is praising God in heaven; But seek God's grace, and He'll restore You to your babe when life is over. TRUE PA if-Y REWARDED. Some few years since, there might have been seen walking along the streets of Boia ton, a young man of some eighteen or tweun ty years of age, poorly clad and half famish; ed with hunger, by the name of Hairy0or- ban. Though destitute as he was, yet Hairy was too proud to beg, and faithfully, sought for employment, but I; vain;; and *ua, night spread its darkmiatltWte tw BK;   &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7495-00000022"/> "   THE BLIND GIRL'S Harry had but three pennys left in his purse, and tking one, bought a penny's wcrth of gingdrbread, and turned his steps slowly to- wards an open shed, where he had spent the night before, in an old cart. On reaching the spot, Harry sat down to reflect upon the past. Though he had been treated so coldly by every one, yet he did not feel disheartened, but assured himself that God would do something for him yet.- He then knelt bleside the cart, and poured out his soul in prayer to God, and thanked Him that he had been blessed with a pious mother, who had early taught him to trust in Him who hath .aid, "All things shall work together for good, to them that love God."  Harry then laid himself down for the night, and when the morning dawned, he arose and bent his steps towards a shop where he procured another penny's worth of gingerbread for his breakfast. He then en- tered a wholesale store, and asked for em- ployment for a few days, until he could do better, saying, "All I ask for my services is something to eat, and a place to lay my head." The merchant looked at him. Sur- p  tised that 9ne; so poorly clad lshuld present.   OFFERING.       45 himself for a clerk, very coolly said, "Ihava all the help I need." 'Mr. Wilson, an Ina- keeper, who was sitting by, heard the con- versation which passed between Harry and the merchant, and observing that Harry was no ordinary fellow, said, "Sir, you may have a home with me until you can do bet- ter." Harry bowed, saying, "Thank you, sir-Heaven will reward you." Harry pas- sed that day meditating on what steps to take next, and when night approached, after thanking his Heavenly Father that He had spared him through another day, he laid him- self down to rest once more, on a comforta. ble bed. Through the day, the words of Har- ry had soundsed in the ears of Mr. Wilson, "Heaven will reward you." "Heaven re- ward me  How little have I done to merit the reward cf Heatven!" From that time he resolved to learn the cause of Harry's destitution, and as far as it was in his poower, to befriend him. The next morning, Mr. Wilson said to Harry, 'Fol- lpw me," and leading the way to an upper room, and seating himself on a sofa, said, "Harry, sit down--I wish to talk with you, and learn the cause of your hard fortune.'"  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7495-00000023"/> "   THE BLIND GIRL'S Harry replied, "Sir, I will tell you as brief. ly as I can. My father was a merchant, and he and my mother both died but a short time since, leaving me the only heir to his estate. Soon after their decease, I was taken with the fever; and one night, about 12 o'clock, a fire broke out, whch consumed dwelling- house, store, and all that I possessed-not a thing was saved-even my clothes were bur- ned, and these were given me in their place. The next morning I was carried to the Hos- pital, where I remained until I have, in a measure, regained my former health, and was in search of employment the day I met with you in the shop." Mr. Wilson felt that it was in his power to assist Harry, and said, "Do you understand book-keeping?"Harry replied, "Yes, sir; but no one wishes to employ me." Mr. Wil- son easily guessed the reason, and getting up, said, "Harry, come, go with me: I will see what I can do for you." Harry quickly obeyed, while his heart glowed with antici- pation in hopes that Mr. Wilson would find him some employ. 'During their walk, Mr. Wilson took from his pocket a fifty dollar bill, and handing it   OFFERING.       47 to Harry, said, "There is fifty dollars, which will enable you to purchase a comfortable suit of clothes, and perhaps assist you in get- ting into business." Harry very politely declined, saying, "Thank you for your kindness, but I cannot take it ; I have no means to compensateyou." But Mr. Wilson urged it upon him with the assurance that he was in no hurry, and at some future day he might be enabled to re- pay it. Harry felt overcome with gratitude to Mr. Wilson, and, on reflecting a few moments, consented to take the money, saying, "( Sir, I can never reward you for your kindness to me, but Heaven will." They soon entered a clothing-shop, where Mr. Wilson and Harry selected a suit of clothes, such as they thought suitable for a clerk, and then returned home. After partaking some refreshments, Mr, Wilson said, "Harry, the day I met wita you, Mr. D---, the merchant, informedme that he was in want of a clerk in whom he could confide, and perhaps he will give you a situation, if he has no one engaged; and if you wish, I will accompany you to his shop, and ascertain."  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7495-00000024"/> 48    THE BLIND GIRL'S Harry very gratefully accepted the invi- tation, and soon they were on their way.- On reaching the shop, they found Mr. D-- alone, and Mr. Wilson introduced arry as his friend, and briefly told him his business. The merchant looking at Harry, seeming. ly much pleased with his appearance, said, "Sir, you may stop with me one month, and if we both like, we will arrange business for a longer perioal." Harry very respectfully bowed, and Mr. Wilson, taking his leave, left Harry alone with the merchant. The day passed, and soon the busy crowd had retired for the night. Harry was glad to find himself alone in his chamber, and kneeling beside. his bed, thanked his Hear. enly Father for his kind Droteiticn during the day. The newt morning Harry was up with th3 birds, ready to perform the duties devolving upon him. Day after day passed on, and at the end of the month M r. D.--  was much pleased with Harry, and arranged business for the space of one year. D iring the time, Harry was enabled to return the fifty dollars to Mr. Wilson, and save a handsome sum for himself.   OFFERING.       49. Ella D---- was an only child, of about seventeen years of age. She had a number of suitors, but none gained her esteem. But JElla sincerely loved Harry from their first acquaintance, and ardently solicited his com- pany. But Harry declined, saying, "Ella, you are an only child of a wealthy merchant- I am but a poor servant of your father, and he would never consent to our union-there- fore, we had better abandon such thoughts forever." "Harry," said Ella, " my father vill not raise one objection to our union-I will see to that myself." So saying, she left the room. Ella belie- ved that Harry loved her, and she was not deceived; for Harry had loved her devoted. ly, but did not dare to whisper it aloud. The next mornwig, after breakfast, Ella taking her father" into the parlor, informed him how affairs stood between herself and Harry. Mr. D--- wasmuch pleased with Ella's choice, but thinking that he would try her love, said, "Ella, did you know that Harry was but a poor boy, and nothing but his hands to help himself with?" 7  .  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7495-00000025"/> 50    THE BLIND GIRL'S Yes, father, I know he is not wealthy; but he is possessed of an amiable disposition and a noble mind." Mr. D--  smiled, saying, "Ella, I am well pleased with your choice:, I think he will be a kind and devoted husband, and I have enough of this world's goods to place you both beyond want, if prospered." TFlla was overjoyed with the prospect that she should, at some future day, be made the happy bride of Harry Corban. At length the day for their nuptials arri- ved. It was a beautiful day in June : the birds seemed to rejoice, and all nature be- spoke the praise of God. The guests had assembled, and Harry taking Ella by the hand, led her forth to be made his lawful and adorable bride. The day passed pleas- antly, and as the sun was fast sinking be- neath the western hills, each returned to their respective home. Day after day rapidly passed, and in a few months Mr. D  had erected a splen- did mansion, where Harry and his bride passed their lives in the profession and pos- session of the religion of Jesus Christ.- They were beloved by all who knew them, and were looked up to as examples of true   OFFERING.       51 piety, and died with the2blissful hope of an eternal rest beyond the grave. POETRY. Mother, I soon shall close my eyes in death; My spirit must depart: Angels now doth for me wait- They sing aloud at heaven's gate. Mother, when I am cold in death, And in my grave-clothes dressed, Let not one heart-felt tear be shed, Or weep that I am dead. Mother, do not reflect upon those days When with health my cheek did bloom- When pleasures crowned my youthful head, Or weep that I am dead. Mother, when thou shalt hear my funeral knell,  Do not with terror start;  If tears steal down thy pallid cheek, O bid them quick depart. When I am carried to the house of God, Where services are held, Do not lament the loss of me, Or weep that I am dead. And when the coffin-lid is raised To take thy farewell look,  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7495-00000026"/> 52    THE BLIND GIRL'S Rejoice that I so calmly sleep, Nor weep that I am dead. When in the grave I am lowered, And covered o'er with earth, "et not thy heart with anguish bleed, Nor weep that I am no more. And when the turf is o'er me laid, Then linger not around my grave; But quickly turn thy steps towards home, Nor weep that thou art left alone. Dear mother, now be reconciled- 'Tis God who doth me call: Remember that we soon shall meet To part no more at all. A WISH. Mary, may happiness all thy steps attend, And all thy sorrows be at an end; May all thy life as pleasant be, As the sunbeams are to a humming bee. And may your choice be made on earth, So as to gain a heavenly birth; And when .your spirit is released from clay, May angels waft your soul away. And when you reach that blissful shore Where trials and troubles are all o'er,   OFFERING.       53 May a crown of glory to you be given, To sing redeeming praise in heaven. POETRY. This is the last summer you ever will spend, At home with your sister, your sincere friend: Our joys and our sorrows we have mingled together, But now you are agoing to leave me forever. Many a season hath passed o'er our child- hood-- Many a night have I watch'd o'er thy couch; Many a prayer for thee have I offered- Many a tear have I shed over thee, Oft have we mingled our voices together-- Oft have we soothed each sorrow when told: Oft have we roamed o'er hills together- Oft have we drank from this clear running brook. Now, dearest sister, you and I must be parted; Your vows are now plighted to man, so false. hearted. 7Zou are leaving the home that you once fondly cherished, and cleaving to one whose love may soon vanish  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7495-00000027"/> 54    THE BLIND GIRL'S Now, dearest sister, I'll bid thee adieu: Oar walks and our rides we shall no more pursue: May he prove to you as sincere a friend As your sister you're leaving behind you, has been. DIALOGUE- BETWEEN HARRY AND CHARLES. Charles--"Good morning, Harry." Harry--"Good morning, Charles: we are agoing to have a dancing-school here this winter, if we can get sufficient signers: will you put your name to the paper?" Charles-"Yes, if you will convince me that I shall derive any benefit from it." Harry-"Why, it will learn us how to appear in company, and pass the long winter evenings very pleasantly besides. Father says, if a young man is only an accomplish. ed dancer, he will get through this world well enough if he has not much learning."- Charles--' O nonsense, Harry, that is a sad mistake: there is William Dix, he is as good a dancer as ever need be, and every one is laughing at him because he has got no learning. And on the contrary, there is Daf   OFFERING.       55 vid Smith, he is a pious and well-educated Fellow, and he never danced a step in his life; and everybody respects him, and even the young ladies think that they cannot have an evening visit unless he is present." Harry--"Well, it may not always be the case; buththen it is, for a general thing." Charles--"How many signers will it re- quire?" Harry--"Only fifteen, at three dollars a- piece-we can have thirteen schools and one public." Charles-"Fifteen--three times fifteen- a very liberal sum-forty-five dollars. Now how much good it might do if it was only put to the right use!" Harry-"Pray what use would you have it put to?" Charles-"I would have it equally divi- ded between th3 two widow women: thtat would relieve their wants in a great meas- ure." Harry-" O, you needn't preach to me in that way, if they can't take care of themselves, they may go to the poor-house." Charles--"Well, Harry, you know we ought to do unto others as we would that  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7495-00000028"/> A6    THE ]LIND GIRL'S they should do to us. Now, if you were sick or blind, and could not take care of yourself, would you like to be sent to the poor-house?" Harry--"- Well, no; and I should not have to go; for I have friends that would take care of me." Charles-(- Yes, but Mrs. Bliss has no friends, and I had rather give my three dol- lars to little Henry Bliss or poor James Hail, the blind boy. Now Harry, if either of us were sick or blind, we should be very glad to have people divide their spoil with us. ' Harry---"Well, Charles, I called on James Hail yesterday, and I must acknowledge that my heart moved with sympathy for him, and I would have shared my money with him, but 1 have only enough to pay my dan- cing tuition." Charles--- Well, for my part, I shall feel much better satisfied \when little Henry is dead and gone, to know that I administered to his wants inasmuch as it laid in my pow- er, than I should to spend my money in the ball-room." Harry--( Charles, will he die?"   OFFER  iN,  -     t Charles-" O yes, Harry, his physician says that he cannot live but a short time.- Now Harry, wouldit not grieve you to hear that Henry suffered for the comforts Of life during his sickness, when it laid in your power to relieve him?" Harry--"Well, Charles, instead of sign, ing this paper for a dancing-school, I will; sign it to relieve the wants of James and Henry; and my name shall be the first.- And I will influence every one that lays in my power to sign the paper." Charles--, And my name shall be the seo cond; and this will be doing as we. would be done by, and we will both call on Henry to. mor:ow." Harry.---"Good morning, Charle s-good morning." POTfiTY. Farewell, dear father, and mother too; I now must bid thee a long adieu: A crown of glory is prepared, i feel, And angels wait to welcome me. Farewell dear sisters and brothers alI, For Jesus hath your sister called  8  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7495-00000029"/> 58.   TiHTEE Bt   QoIRIL'S Though your circle here may broken be, You dry your tears, weep not for me. Farewell to groves and forest where I havo often strayed- Farewell- to birds and flowers, I can no lon- ger stay: Farewell to old acquaintance, I soon shall be forgot-- Farewell to young associates, I can no lon- ger stop. Frewell to pain atd sorrow, my peace i made with God- Farewell, I die ere towmorrow. to reign with Christ above: My joys are just beginning, my sufferings are past-- My songs are just ccmmencing, they will for ever last. I often wake at midnight hour, And turn sweet Memory's pages o'er; And call to mind those by gone days, When I was taught to read and pray. I often wake at midnight hour, And ask where is my mother now, Who watched -me with such ardent care, And knelt beside my couch in payer?   OFFERING.       69 I often wake at midnight hour, And call to mind those youthful scenes, When brothers and my sister dear Tneir merry voice I so oft did hear. I often wake at midnight hoar, When all is hash3 in calm repose; And pray to God, whom I admire, That he will guide me n evermore. FAKSTwMELL To A FRIEND, Dear friend, the day is drawing nigh, When these happy days will be gone by-. Then we can no more together meet, Can all the ties that Friendship's linked Arouni oar hearts in oblivion sink? Can the lapse of years from Memory steal The purest gem that earth can yield? O yes, dea r frien, a few short yars, All th oaghts of m? will Tiin e:iase; And she who was your sin ,:^3 fnienl, Will ba wrapped in Dtath's cold e:nlle. O then, dear frie:d, I soon s ell be By thee and thina thr3ptten; Bat should your ey o'e: c'hano to fall Upon this page, raiuem3r all. Remember all the hours we've spent Together in the dancing halls-  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7495-00000030"/> 60    THE BLIND GIRLKS The Smithville balls, the Berkshire calls- O yes, dear friend, remember all. And when in search of worldly gain, You sail far o'er the raging main, Then foreign lands will meet your view, And other friends will welcome you. Yet one wish to thee and thine I'll give, Before you go far west to live; That you may never sorrow know, And be blest and prospered where'er you go. May you, like Mary of old, be wise, And choose that part which never dies; That you may meet, when life is o'er, To sing God's praise on Canaan's shore., ON THE DEATH OF A SISTER. My sister's gone to worlds on high, Where Death can ne'er alloy; Her spirit's gone from earth away, To reap immortal joy. Physician's skill could not save Our dearest sister from the grave; She soon followed her dear boy, To brighter realms of endless joy. Her work, on earth, at last is o'er, And she can visit us no more:   OFFERING.       61 Brothers and sisters in that land, Now unite in a happy band. While in the morning of her life, Death has summoned her away, Where old and young, both rich and poor, Without distinction lay. She bid this world and friends adieu- Upward her journey did pursue, To dwell with Christ above the sky, Where sainted spirits never die. A sister's death we do deplore, For we shall hear her voice no more; Sorrow and sadness crept o'er our hearts, When sister's spirit did depart. Her trials, now, on earth are o'er- - Her spirit did to Jesus soar i She now is praising God on high, While we, frail worms, must faint and die. But when affliction's hour is past, May we to heaven ascend at last- All meet together in that land, Ne'er more to take the parting hand. FALSE ONE. Hast thou thy vows so soon broken? Hast thou all thy promises forgotten?  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7495-00000031"/> 82    THE BLIND GIRL'S Can that treacherous heart of thing, Find rest or peace in foreign clime? False one, thou now doth wander o'er Those lands whwre millions hath gone before, Though thou art in search of gold, Yet can thy sorrow in heart e'er b: told. O.t doth fond memory lead thee o'er Those hills where thou hast roam ed beore-- When thon wast blest with a mothe,'s praye., A brother's love and a sister's care. O were thy heart as free from sin As when thou didst ish from that running stream Whieh passed your fathor's farm, my boy, Taen you were your father's pride and joy. Where art thou now, my roving boy?  Dist thou ever taste of joy? CAn that treacherous heart of thine Ever feel sweet peace divine? No! that treacherous heart of thin3 Cannot find peace on the shores of time, Until thou' dost for mercy seek, And seek it low at Jesus' teet. Then thy heart once more may feel That love which none but God reveals: Then you may rove through foreign lands, And' dod will all your steps attend.   OTERITG.       63 CURISTasS aoaislNo. Happy is the Christmas morn, To those that love the Lord; With many a merry shout we hear "I wish you a merry Christmas here!" Then lads and lasses in their turn, Down the stairs they start and run- Take their stockings from the wall, To see if 'San Duolaus' did call. Then thrust their hands into the too, To see how far their treasures go; And when their treasures they've inspeoted Then their toys must be erected, Upon some mantcl piece or shelfi To sea which toy they like the best. Each one well pleased, their gift to see, And wondered where that ma could be. SECOLLECTION OF TZ PAST. CpOUsi, our childhood scenes are past an gone,      . Yet I oft recall them, to reflect upon; 1 love to turn o'er Memory's page, ,nd call to mind those by-gone days, Vhen we could roam through wood and glen, So care disturbed our bosoms then:  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7495-00000032"/> "  THE BLIND GIRL'S We had parents kind, to guide with care, Our feet from every youthful snare. O happy were our youthful beart, When seated in our little bark: Oft did we sing the fisherman's song, Sporting, fishing, all the day long But since then, years have swiftly flown, And thy heart hath sorrow known: Where art thy parents? let me ask- Methinks they've perished in the blast. Cousin, what'change hath Time wrought in thee? Dost thou still remember me? Though we are separated far and wide, Yet no raging sea doth us divide. THB rUWARD OF A DUTIFUL SOIL. Mr. Lewis had, by industry and economy, accumulated a large property, and was con- sidered immensely rich. But riches take to themselves wings, and fly away; and so it was with Mr. Lewis's riches, at the time of his death. He was greatly involved in debt,  and each of his creditors,eager to secure their full amount, crowded heavily upon Mrs. Lew-   OFFERING.       65 is. She was a very intelligent women, proud spirited, -and would have paited -withevery cent rather than one of his creditors should. remain unpaid. At length his-estate wasiset. tied, leaving but a small sum-for the support of Mrs. Lewis, an aged father, and one child, who was about twelve years of age. Mrs, "ewis soon left her splended mansion, with walks, gardens, yards, and all thatwas plea- sant within and without. She purhased a small cottage in a more retired part of the village, where she was enabled, by her indus- try and economy, to keep Charles at school until he had reached his eighteenth year; and, during this period, he had made great proficiency in his studies, Charles was a very bright, intelligent, and interesting fellow, -and a gentleman in every respects It was a beautiful evening in September- the moon poured forth its gentle rays through the windows of Mrs. L.'s cottage, as she and her son sat by the fire which was blaxisg up. on the hearth, until the village clock had tolled the hour of ten. Charles did not like to commence the subject, which had rested with such weight upon his mind through the  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7495-00000033"/> "   THji BLIND GIRL'S day; but he had resolved that he would not retire to rest until he lhd consulted his nmo- ther cccn:ein', l, dct?t ' ru to the village of T----, 1.   Vicnt h ho said with a traoma Ious voCiC, ;- -,t' fu; little b ank iSn tO ly 'edd, a ! thi.. h:d b-tt c-try to  securC a Sittu.:,.ticon in somo s:iop, ,l,',- soY salary will be stiienit to provido you and granldfaLthelr with t!h coin l. ts of lif ro As  was loVking' ove: a pa)pc?.- ytcrda, my yes rested an all dvetrtic ,rI t1 \wic1h stated thlat iMr C   , wholesale nlca.:hant in the vii. lage of T.- ,  xa.- in iwant oft a clerk, and if both li:ed, he would pay a liberal sun.- Now, mother, if you think best, I will prc. pare to leave lCheo on Monday, and pcrha s heo will give 7me a situation." TaLoro was a p' o ouncd silence f or some min- utes. At length she replied, Ywhile. the tears stole down her cheeks, Charles, we'should feel very lonely if you were to leave-us." Charles, perceiving the emotion of his -mother, said, with a cheerfua voice, ", Yes; but then it is cnly about seventy miles, and I sh ll visit you quits- often-besides, I shall write every now and then." Mrs. Lewis was not prepared for this di.   OFFERING.        67 lemma, althoug!l she well kneA that Charles must ore lcong leave home, to act for himself, and, sh1are the frion.-dship of a cold-hearted Oorld ; yet she locked unon it a nistainCe. ( Tuarles aid s , M s ai T 3T I am nnt prepared to give you ..n ns r-,er to-niht: I wlil thi?!; of it, ri'd .tal more. with you in the nmorninr, . Cha'rles saw that his mother was too much affectetd to prces the q icstion fiarther, and getting up, o bid her good. night, and left the room. On r achin5 his room, he knlt beside his bed, and pou)nr'e: out his soul in prayer to God, andc. c. rn ct! y beso ught Himn thr t H e would guidce n rld protect them thro' all th varied Scen33 of life : thnt their souls might be prepared for an cternal rest 'n hlea- ven, tC aarles-s'e ,tc thi't mngit in m1ittion, and anxiously looked fJ r t ho c4oming morn. At length the tanrdy morn appeared, and Charles arose to heoa the dleision of his moe ^M  ther, Charles, feoling so mu1sa aixiety upxon tte subject, could not wait for lhi mother to commence tho convrc3ation. "( Well, mother, 1 I how have you dclidei? Do ysu think I had bettcer try my fortune?" 6' Charles," said his mother, "I know that  &#xD;<pb n="68" xml:id="VAC7495-00000034"/> 68,:   THE BLI ND GIIRLI iteimvery essential that you should do some- thitngfor a livelihood. The thought of your leayingS home is heart-rending to me." "Yes, mother, it will be very unpleasant to be, separated; but I trust that in a few yearsJ H shall be enabled to save enough of my wagess to secure a comfortable home for you and grandfather: and thent we will en- joy each other's society- until we are sep ara- ted,-by ther icy hand of death." At length the day for his departure arri- ved. The carriage-wheels were seen rolling rapidly to the dock, and Charles, after ta- king his leave, seated himself in-the coach, leaving hisaafflicted mother standing in the: door of her cottage, Charles felt that this wraS the most trying scene that he had ever Bx perienced; and covering his face with his 1iands, gave vent to a flood of tears. OQn reaching the mansion of Mr. C----, e -immediately sought an interview with -i?, and. readily informed him of the object of his visit. Mr. 0----- was much pleased with his appearance, and informed him that he 'would give him employ. as long as they were both suited. Charles felt that Prov i lence had opened a, door whereby he might,    &#xD;<pb n="69" xml:id="VAC7495-00000035"/> OFFERINC.6       69 by ind stry and economy, proepar a homo for his bercft m oth'eir an91i, gr^ 3athlr. At Imlth I ho ni;^t n pronachc, and vhiAh w p31 alloti2t hIL 'C:.rlO.:, ",,c loo a i", LIcz Nund ;^t n,.t rt-0d i..;n t5}l ,. ,t,)s){,;e 1*ec * ; arvou;-ndi tho --.ni,; t, :?:t do'n to road a h:epter in the PibJe &amp;wich lhad bscn givon h:m. byc his mnerile' on I c d yv -fI his dc'p -.:- tu"e" After bo h-K flnitch-d the chapter, ho, knelt don 11 th  r pr^ en c ' H it ^ vo hth pl d^ed Hin: elf:hat. H' I     : not tulrn them a y s ,1'ty who i. i :t. , v w Tho nt . ' i-' nin) Chanrles: arce w\ith a i'.t hioct, to po:' forn the duios which dovo 1: s i n pcn im.- r,.3 .i w r a ;  i th t hI Iad bo n su e s. in a, C4. ew :y a 'a 1 ,I- c,. I i t i ' t o  "Li h i t funl1 p ptid  i; a A it h M e ,  . c . .---5.e, and prcmisd to write again :'t the end of tho mont h,  Da S and wees pa   t pleasaLntiy with Chiare, and at the end of the month he wrote a lon: and aff ctionate totter to his mo  er enclosin twenty dollars. He said, ' ere^ mother, i a little monoey which will be of' sCoe use to you; aind, before this is gone, I hope, by the blessing of God, that I shall be enabled to send yovu more." -c .  ?3'r .nC $ IJ    &#xD;<pb n="-70" xml:id="VAC7495-00000036"/> 70    TIIIE BLIND GI tL'3 Mr. C-   was one of the finst in in so- ieoty, and wished to have all a, ound himi bear an aristocratic appearance. Month af- ter month passed on, and Mr. C   - often looked at Charles, and wondered what could be the cause of his being so poorly clad.- One day, on entering the counting-room, he found Charles alone, and then resolved to ascertain the real cause. He said, in a mild tone, "Charles, if your salary is not suffi- cient to supply you with fashionable apparel, I will increase it." Charles seemed greatly embarrassed, and said, "O yes,: sir-amply sufficient." Mr. ---  saw that Charles was somewhat em- oarrassed, and left the room. Some few weeks after, Mr. C   was o. bliged to leave home for the space of eight or ten days on business, leaving his affairs in charge of Charles Lewis. Itwas a very warm day in July, and Mr. C   had rode many miles beneath the scorching rays of the sun, and on reaching a very respectable Ho- tel, he called to rest awhile in the heat of the, day. Mr. C    knew that Mrs. Lewis re- sided in this village, and after taking some refreshment, feeling aggreat anxiety to learn L 1 .. *       ' '  ' *    *  '  ' i     &#xD;<pb n="-71" xml:id="VAC7495-00000037"/> OFFERING.        71 her situation, hic inqlircd of the landlord whcre Mirs L-whis rcsi;dc . Tih landlord Osoon ilamf2 lviin' , and soon' ho was on his way to he cottage, 'under' the pretence of wishin- t;o purczasone it. On rea1:hing the cots t-ae, bo knokcd ot ho doo, an d was asco-s tcd by a mildd!-eLsd ;.iomaul, who vdt y p^) lito]y invHtcd him to walk in. Ho soon ino foried her of I i business, and asLkcl her if she wi'shoCd to d1isOse of her cottage. Mrs. L*-vis ho3it:;!l a mor ait, and thln sAil- "I can;ot give yol an answer until I hU eo consulted my son.' t"Your Bsc:--wh-cro is hoi, " ' He4s a cicr1, for a whoisczsa jlc me -ch a in the vill:g. of T----." ; What Is his a- nz iC icnqired Mr. C-- ; Charcls Lewizs," said the old woma:, 'and a worthly'lad he i'. Ho is all that we havo to dcend upon for our support, and  am quite sure that ho send us uall, or nearly all of his wages." "Charles Lewis!" said iMr. C---- (ap- gearing much surprised,) "6 he is my clerk." L Your clerk?.' rejoined Mrs. Lewis, while her heart beat with joy at the thought of hearing so directly from her long absent    &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7495-00000038"/> 72    THE BLIND GItiLXo son. After a long conversation, Mri. C-- arose, and placing a well-filled purse into the old man's hand, said-- "Here is a small sfm, which may be of some use to you, if you will accept it." The old man raising, his head from his staff, wlile the tears stole down his withered cheek, uttered, in a tremulous tone, "May Godt bless you!" - M. C    bidding them good afternoon, retraced his steps to the Inn, and proceeded on his journey. On reaching his home, he found that Charles had faithfully performed the duties which had been entrusted to-his care. Charles had been gone from home a long time, and wishing to visit his mother, he said- ", Mr. C---, if it would be convenient, I should like to be absent a week or ten days." " yes, or longer if you wish." Mr. C-   left the store, and on entering the room where Julia and her mother sat sewing, he said--. "So Charles is about to leave us." About to leave us!-Charles about to leave us!" rejoined Julia, dropping thework she had in her hands. i   OFFERING.       73 "Yes, child; and what is there wonderful in that?" "O nothing, father, only I thought we should be rather lonesome-that's all," while her heart swelled at the thought of being separated from the object of her affection, she arose and left the room. Mr. C---  saw her emotion, and soon followed her to her room, and thus address- ed her: "Tell me, my child, do you love Charles?' I never kept anything hid from you, neither wioll I now-I do love him sincerely; butdo not tell him for the world, for he has lever told me that his love was returned." "Never mind, I will see to that," said Mr. ,--T-, leaving the room. Soon after he e-entered the store, and found Charles alone. "Charles," said he, " could you not defer our journey a week or ten days?" "O yes," replied COarles, " or longer if ou wish."      l ( It would oblige me very much-as Julia about to be married, we wish you to attend Le wedding." "Married!-Julia to be married!" sasi harles, rising from. his seat, and walking e floor with rapid strides. 10    .  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7495-00000039"/> 74    THE BLIND GIRL'S Yes; and what is there surprising. in that?"  "Nothing-O nothing, sir: rather sud- den-that is all. But indeed, sir, I cannot stay." Why, you just said that you would." Well, indeed, sir, I cannot. Command me in anything else, and I will obey." Charles," said Mr. C- -,  tell me frankly, do you love my daughter?" Charles was sensible that his agitation had betrayed him, and said- "Had I the fortnue that she is worthy of, I should think myself the happiest being on earth could I obtain her." "Say nothing about riches, Charles-you shall have her." "Sir, I scorn to deceive you: I am poor - er than you are aware : I have a mother" "I know it-I know it all," interrupted Mr C0---. "I have enough to place you both beyond want. But, as your business is so ur- gent, we shall have to defer the wedding, for you cannot stay." "Beg your pardon," said Charles, daugh- ing,) " my business can easily be deferred, and that with pleasure."   OFFERING.        75 Mr. C.---- soon returned to inform Julia of the conversation which had passed between himself and Charles. At length the evening appeared. Charles and Julia, for the first time, confessed their love to each other, which they had so long cherished; and spee. dy preparations were then made for their mar- riage. Mr. C    soon ordered a carriage to be sent for Mrs. Lewis and her aged fa- ther to attend the wedding. Mr. C-  's mansion was furnished with the nicest and richest of everything, and that regardless of cost. At length the day for their nuptials arri- ved-the aristocratic guests were assembled, and all seemed to rejoice with the happy cou- ple, After the marriage ceremony was per. formed, they partook of the luxuries which had been prepared for the occasion, with great satisfaction. The time passed pleas- Intly on, until the hour arrived for their de- parture, leaving the happy group to enjoy the blessings which God had bestowed upon bhem. Mrs. Lewis and her aged father spent the remainder of their days in the enjoyment f the society of their affectionate children Jharles and Julia proved a blessing to Mr  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7495-00000040"/> 76    THE BLIND GIRL'S and Mrs. C--  , and were instrumental, in the hands of God, of leading them to the fold of Christ. Reader, remember that the Scripture says, "Seek first the kingdom of heaven and its righteousnessand all things shall be added unto you." THE ORPHAN CHLD. I soon must close my eyes in death, And who will receive my parting kiss? And-who will shed the farewell tear, When the last ray of life hath disappeared? Who will make the shroud for me? And who will my pall-bearers be? And who shall stand in the sacred desk, When my soul hath reached a heaven of restt And who'll prepare my narrow bed? And who will close the coffin-lid? Who will lower me in the narrow cell, When my spirit doth with Jesus dwell? And who shall watch the fragrant rose That decks the grave where 1 repose? And who will cull the rose that blooms Upon my meek and e:jrlv tomb . i4  ,* , R   OFFERING.       " Who will raise the niarble stone At my head when I am gone? And who shall read, as they pass by. They too, like me, must faint and die? POETRY. I love to sit, at dewy eve, Beneath the willow tree; And listen to the night-bird's song, Which seems so wild and free. I love to kneel at close of day Beneath the willow tree, And pour out my soul to God in prayer Who listens when I pray. I love to sing the Christian's hymn, It does my soul relieve; While angels listen to my glee, Beneath the willow tree, I love to know, that when I die, Beneath the green sod I must lie: I only ask that I may rest, Beneath the tree that I love best. On my marble that is raised, Let a weeping-willow be-engraved; And sacred to my memory place Those liEes which cannot be erased,  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7495-00000041"/> 78    THE BLIND GIRL'S Sweetly did she resign her breath-- Her spirit's gone to a world of rest; And peaceful now her dubt shall be, Beneath the weeping-willow tree. MY BIBLE, This Bible is all that is left me now; I'll press it to my heart; My God, look down from heaven above, And bid my sins depart. This Bible shall ever be my guide, Though months and years may onward glide; For in this precious book I'm taught To love and serve God as I ought. And as I turn these pages o'er, I pray that I may sin no more; But may I, with zealous care, Seek God's grace, and for death prepare.; That when I am lowered in the narrow cell, My spirit may with Jesus dwell; And join with saints above the sky, Where celestial joys will never die. THE HUMBLE COTTAGE. Beneath this humble cottage roof, Years hath sweetly passed away;   OFFERING.       79 And those who formed a circle here, Are mouldering back to clay. Could I recall those days of mirth, When we sang around this cottage hearth, The evening hymn we so much loved, And then united in prayer to God. But low in the narrow grave they're laid; The marbles Cell their name and age; And there, beneath the grassy mound, Their bodies-rest, low in the ground, Ah! who can tell the pains I feel, When to their silent graves I steal, And read their inscriptions, one by one, Which are sculptured on the marblestone, Come, thou grim messenger of death, And take from me my vital breath: Joyfully will my spirit go, And leave this world, and all below. My spirit longs to soar away And be released from this frame of clay. To join my friends in a happy band N'er to part in that glorious land. POETRY. Death's Cold embrace, I fear it not, Nor would I pass it by- Life hath no luring charms for me, I am conteRt to die.  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7495-00000042"/> 80    THE BLIND  GIRL'S My,hopes are like the babbles tossed Upon life's billowy sea- My cup o'erfloWsi with bitterness, My heart is filled with grief; There is no tie which binds my heart To thib delusive world; No pleasure can disperse my gloom Nor chase my grief away, O no, there is no spell that binds My soul to this unhallowed clime, Ily spirit longs to soar away, And quit this wasting form of clay. I then shall sing on Canaan's shore, Where sorrow and sighing will be no more - Great God, I ask that I may be Prepared to live and reign with thee. THE ELOPEMENT  Mary Allen had nearly reached her eight- teenth year, and she was an amiable and lovely being. Her hair was of a dark au- burn, and hung in glossy ringlets about her snow white neck, and her eyes were'of a jet black. She bad gained the esteem of her as. sociates, and had never tasted the bitter cup of sorrow. She was an only daughter, and had been blessed with kind parents who nev-   OFFElRNG.       81 er withheld anything which would add to her h4ppiness. One fine summer's day, late in the after- noon, an elegant carriage stopped in front of Mr. Allen's house, and from which a gentle- man alighted and rapped at the door. He was accosted by Mary Allen, who very po- litely invited him to walk in. He courte- ously bowed, and introducing himself as Mr. Carlton, her cousin, aad was received with much cordiality. Mary was almost elated at the unexpected arrival of her cous- in, though he seemed almost like a stra-u ger at first, for she had not seen him for a long time. After taking some refreshments, Mary invited her cousin to take a walk in the garden with her. He accepted the in- vitation, and after walking, about the gar- den and admiring the beautiful plants and flowers, and speaking of their different lan- guages, they seated themselves in a beauti- ful arbor to enjoy the cool breeze which rus- tled through the overhanging vines. They spoke of the many happy hours they spent together in their childhood, and of the many changes of life which they had passed through during their separation. At length thehea- S A l  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7495-00000043"/> 82    THE BLIND GIRL'S vy dew began to fall and they were com- pelled to return to the parlor where they spent the evening very pleasantly. At length the clock tolled the hour of ten. Mary, said Mr. Allen, if you will read a' chapter in the Bible we will attend prayers, for Edward is no doubt fatigued with his journey, and would like to retire. Mary ta- king the Bible from the table, and then sang the evening hymn, and knelt while Mr. Al- len invoked the blessings of the Almighty to rest upon them, and then retired to rest. Mary retired to her room, and seated herself beside the window, to reflect upon the short interview'she had enjoyed with her cousin. Can it be possible, murmured she, that the elapse of a few short years has wrought such a change in Edward? he is now grown to manhood, and he is certainly very admira- ble. Mary sincerely loved Edward; yet she strove to banish such thoughts, assuring herself that her father would never consent to their union. Mary spent that night in deep meditation, and anxiously did she look for the coming day. At length the tardy morn appeared, and Mary arose with a cheer- -ful heart to assist her xmother in the domes-   OFFERING.       83 tic affairs. Edward arose quite early and seated hmiself in the kitchen to observe the movements of his cousin. After the morn- ing services were past, Edward invited his cousin to take a ride on which she joyfully accepted, and soon they were seated side by side in the beautiful carriage and dashed away with great rapidity. It was a beauti- ful morning, the songs of the birds sweetly echoed through the wood, and all nature seemed to rejoice with this happy couple. Edward-had loved Mary from childhood, and had congratulated himself on making her his lawful bride, could he obtain her consent. He soon unbosomed his love to her, telling her that this was the important business which had brought him hither,  asking her if she could love him  well enough to leave her early home and seek protection in him, who had ever cherished the warmest affection for her and to share with him the cares and toils of this life, which they might chance to meet. Here he paused for an answer. Mary was-not pre- to answer this unsuspected question a:d: pausing a moment, she said- s ..    '  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7495-00000044"/> 84     TIE BLIND GIRL'S Edward, 1 could be happier with you than any other person, for I have never loved any save you, but we must banish such thoughts, for father will never consent to our union. This was a trying question for Mary to answer. At length she said, Edward, it would be very unpleasant for me to leave home under such circumstan- ces, and I think you had better forget me and love one that will make you happy; one that is fairer and more beautiful than I am. Nonsense, Mary, it is folly; for you to talk thus, I can never'love'another; I shall talk with your father upon the subject when I return, and if he will not give his consent, I shall leave here on thermorrow.' 'Nay, Edward, say not so, said Mary, gently placing her hand upon his shoulder, tarry with us at least a week, and perhaps father may"change his mind.' 'No, Mary, that oannot be,' sighed Ed- ward, it would only be inflicting the wound still deeper.' At length they returned home, and after partaking of some refreshments, Edward in- vited his uncle to accompany him to the ar-   OFFERING        85 bor. He accordingly did so, and soon they were seated beneath the green vines which twined themselves so thickly together as to entirely seclude them from the 'sun. Edward informed his uncle how affairs stood between Mary and himself, and asking his consent, at the same time pledging himself to do all that lay in his power to make her happy. 'Edward,' responded Mr. Allen, 'no, I shall never consent that my daughter should marry her cousin.' Edward saw that this question was fully decided, and rising from his seat he returned to the parlor, where he found Mary, sitting upon a sofa, with her head restingupon her hand. He warmly imprinted a kiss upon her cheek, saying, 'My dear cousin, this is probably the last evening that we shall ever enjoy togeth- er.' 'The last evening!' said Mary, resting her head upon his shoulder to hide the tears which sparkled in her eyes, 'do not say so, dear Edward, I trust that we shall spend a great many happy evenings together yet.' ,   .   &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7495-00000045"/> 86    TlHE BLIND GIRL'S 'No, 3Iary, that will never be, unless you will consent to elope.' 'Well, cousin I can never be happy with- oat you; but shall I be happy if I marry so much against the will of my father.' 'Mary,' said Edward, 'I know it would be rather unpleasant for you atfirst, but if you will consent to go, we will be married the first day we leave here, and you can write a letter to him after we reach home, and after we are married, he will become quite recon- oiled.' Mary had not fully decided that she would leave her father's house, and taking Edward by the hand, she said in a tremulous tone, 'Iy dear Edward, I am not prepared to give you a correct answer to-night, but I will decide the question in the morning, but whether I go or no, my heart shall be with you,' so saying, she left the room with her face bathed in tears. She retired to her room, where she spent the night in medita- ting upon what step to take. She seated herself beside her table, and taking a pen in her trembling hand, she addressed a few lines to her parents, informing them of her departure, with the intention of leaving it in   OFFERING.       87 some place where they would be likely to find it. It was now morning, and Mary was in the kitchen as usual. After the breakfast was over, a lady who lived about half a mile distant, was quite ill and sent for Mrs. Allen to come and spend the day with her. As soon as Mrs. Allen had left the house, Mary began to prepare for her journey. Soon she had arranged her bag- gage, and Edward, soon conveyed it to the carriage Mary informed her father that she was going to take a ride with Edward, and should not return until about three o'clock in the afternoon. She 'soon was: dressed and prepared to take her leave of all that she had loved from her childhood. She glanced around the little parlor and placing the note upon the table, she dashed the tear from her eye aiid started for 'the door. She could not restrain her emotion. 'Mary, my dear, do not weep,' said Ed- ward, trying to cheer her, we shall yet be happy I trust; come, let us away, there is no time to spare. So saying he took her by the hand, and soon they were seated in the carriage, and Edward flew rapidly away  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7495-00000046"/> 88    THE BLIND GIRL'S with his prize. About two o'clock they stop- ped in the little village of S--, and a bishop performed the marriage ceremony which bound them for life. After partak- ing of some refreshments, they re-commenc- ed their journey; Edward tried to pass the time as pleasantly as possible, Mary tried to appear cheerful; but the thouglts of home filled her heart with sorrow. Mrs. Allen did not return home until six in the evening, and on entering the parlor, she saw a note lying on the table directed to William Allen. Taking it up, she said this is Mary's writing, I am sure, opening it she glanced her eyes over it, and sank back upon the sofa'weeping. Mr. Allen, at that moment opened the door and found her weeping. 'What,' said he, 'what is the matter?' Mrs. Allen could not speak, but handed him the letter, on which he read as follows; "MY DEAR PARENTS:-I hope you will forgive me this rash move. Since you would not consent that I should marry tmy- cousn, I have eloped, and shall be imair:( to-day at twelve o'clock. I shall thea, ;- company Edward to his home, then I shall   OFFERING.       89 write you a letter. Please forgive me, for this ungrateful act. Believe me still to be your affectionate child. MARY E. ALLEN. The next day they reached Edward's place of residence. Mary was much pleased with the situation of her new home, yet she could not appear cheerful, for the thoughts of home filled her agitated breast. Edward did' all that laid in his power to make the time pass pleasantly. Months and years passed away, every thing looked prosperous around them, until Edward, was enticed to pur- chase a lottery ticket. He at first refiued but on being urged, he finally consented to try his luck. This was the first step of mis- ery, he began from that time to neglect his family and his business, plunged deeper and deeper into degradation. He frequented the gambling houses, and often returned home in a state of intoxication and perplex- ity. Mary spent many hours alone, and often idid she entreat him to forsake his downward course. One evening, as he was prpring to join his degraded asseoiates, h said in a mild tone, Edward, I wisliyou --^ ,- * -  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7495-00000047"/> Qui   THE BLIND GIRL'S would spend your evenings with me as you usd&amp; to when we were first married. We were happy then, but now everything bears a gloomy aspect. Edward flew into a pas- sion, and said-'if you have enough, that is suffcient for you; I will attend to my own business.' Mary felt that this was more than she could bear, and coveting her face with her hands, she burst into tears. Edward saw the. wound which he had inflicted, and tak. ianga chair, he seated himself by her side. 'Mary,' said he, I did not intend to injure your feelings, but I don't like to be confined to the house. I like to enjoy my liber- ty.' Mary reminded him of his promises to her when she left her father's house, and after a long conversation, he said, 'Dry your tears, Mary, and if you will for- give me. for the past,I will never purchase another.' Mary threw her arms around his neck, say ing, O, Edward, then, we shall again be hap, py  ,  There had been a protrated meeting   OFFERING. -91 held in the village for several days, and Mary invited her husband to acompaiyi hIr thither, which he reluctantly, jootsealt,- They had a very powerful meetig,ndadr 8s were convicted and converted. Edward and Mary -returned shof ith heavy hearts, yet neither of them .pOe a word upon the subject. iAocordingly they went again the next evening, nd aW -t ls- tening to a very affecting sermon, r:a init,- tion was given, 'that if, there areiray pl- sent who desire the prayer rof ref i!"- ple, they will please to come forward #pn those seats.' Edward -resolved to nmake one effbt to obtain religion, and taking Matryby itfe hand, he said, 'will you go forward?' on which she readily assented, and soon they were seated with many others. They sang a hymn, and then all knelt down, and a more powerful season was never witnessed in that town. Before the meeting was brought to a close, there were twenty souls converted and made happy in the love of God. Among whom was Edward Carlton and his lovely bride. They returned home that night rejoicing in a Savior's love,  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7495-00000048"/> 92    THE BLIND GIRL'S Mr. Allen soon heard of the change which had been wrought in Edward, and wrote a long letter, requesting him to dispose of his property, telling him that they were some- what advanced in years, and wished to spend the remainder of their days with their only child. Mary was overjoyed at this unexpected proposal. Accordingly, Edward disposed of hia property, and soon they arrived at her early-home,: where they were joyfully receiv- ed by their affectionate parents, where they lived and enjoyed each others society until death summoned tem to the spirit land, leaving a bright evidence of their acceptance i      i '0*d   DIALOGUE BETWEEN AMELIA, BLANCH, AND JANE. A..-This is the last walk Blanch, that we shall enjoy together for a long time. B.-The last walk! you are not in earn- est?  A.-Yes, I have lately received a letter from my aunt, and she wishes me to come and spend a few months with her in the ci- ty. B.--I amvery sorry, Amelia, that you are going to leave us, for I shall be so lone- ly when yQu are gone. A.-Yes, but then you know that the best of friends must part; here is a token of friendship, if you will accept it. B.-Thank you. A.-' This precious book, O let it be A guide and treasure long for thee- This New Year's gift, I pray thee take And keep it long for memory's sake. B.--And here is one in return. A.--Thank you. B.--  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7495-00000049"/> "   THE BLIND GIRL'S This little book is from a friend, Who wishes you in Heaven may spend A long eternity of joy, Where sin and death can ne'er annoy. Now let us pledge ourselves to read a chapter and pray for each other every day while we are parted, for you know that God is not confined to any particular place. ,A.-Yep, I know that He is not, and whenever we see our Bibles, it will remind us of our promise. Enter Jane, all speaking at a time. I wish you a happy New Year. A.--As this is the first time we have met, we will show our presents. J.-.Here is mine. Amelia and Blanche, speaking together. A ring, it is very pretty. And here are ours-both showing their presents. J.-Bibles, they are very nice. A.-Yes, I am well pleased with my Bi- ble, and if I am guided by the principles which it contains, it will add more to my eternal happiness than a gold ring. J.-Yes, but I like my gold ring very tell:.   OFFERING       95 B.-Then you would not change your ring for a Bible, would you? J.-Why if I could not have but one I 'I do not know but I should take a Bible, but I can have Bibles enough anywhere. B.-Jane, Ah! what is it? B.--Amelia is going to leave us. J.-Going to leave us? A.-Yes, I have lately received a letter from my' aunt, who wishes me to come and spend a few months with her in the city. J.-I am very sorry, Amelia, that you are going to leave us, besides we shall miss you in Sabbath School very much. A.-Yes, I regret very much to leave the Sabbath School, but then I shall not be de- prived of attending one, for they have Sab- bath Schools there; but I shall often think of you and our teAchers. J.-When are you going to leave? A.-To-morrow. J.-Then we shall not meet again. A.-No, I think not. Only see, th6 sun is almost set, it is getting quite late, I think I must be going.  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7495-00000050"/> 96    THE BLIND GIRL'S J.-Let us sing the parting hymn before you go. (All sing.) The time has come for us to part, Though friendship unite our hearts- For duty calls us different ways, An the call we must obey. And, if we never meet again While here on earth we do remain, May we three meet in Heaven above To sing around the throne of God. A.-I must bid you good-bye. B.-Good-bye, and when we meet again, I trust that we shall all be better prepared to serve the Lord than we ever yet have been. A.-Good-bye, Jane. J.-Good-bye, I wish you a pleasant jour- ney. A.-Thank you. Good evening. *        i* * * * *   OFFERING.       97 'POETRY. Welcome delightful day, Thou Sabbath of the Lord, The day on which our Savior ros: Victorious over death. When I into thy Temple go To calliupon thy name, Let me assuredly know That I am all thine own. And when the tenderlambs In holy baptism join, O, let thy power descend And sanctify the whole. When I around thy altar kneel To feed upon my Lord, Let me effectually drink Thy sanctifying blood. Then may I ever walk Blameless before the Lord, Since he has washed my soul In his most precious blood. 1A  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7495-00000051"/> 98    TIhj! lnM UlHL' THE INDIAN'S REVENGE OR TIE STOLEN CHLD. Mr. Derby was a man of more than ordi- nary talent, and of good moral character, who resided in the town of Pittsburg. He had a wife and one child--a lovely boy on whom he doated and almost idolized. George Derby was about five years of age, when a tribe of Indians entered the town and pitched their tents near his father' resi- dence. One day during their stay, an Indian called at Mr, Derby's house anid asked if he would grant him a favor. Mr. Derby was by no means a friend to the red men,'for he had ever been taught to shun and despise them as he would a serpent, and answering him with an air of disdain, he said, 'No, I wish to have no correspondence with you, and you will do me a great kind. ness to leave my premises and never trouble me more.' These words pierced the heart of the In. 4ian like an arrow, his eyes flashed vividly d   restiag,-them upon the agitated counte-   OFFERING.       99 nance of Mr. Derby, while his lip curled with scorn and indignation. He turned away with a contemptuous air, vowing in his heart, thet he would be avenged on Mr. Derby before he left town. Some few days after, this tribe of indians left the town, when Mr. Derby, once more felt himself secure from the depredations of the Indians. It was a beautiful morning in June, the birds were singing sweetly, when little George left his father's house, and bent his steps towards the grove, where he had spent so many hours of amusement with his little favorite Carlo, who was ever by his side. GeorgeDerby was a very bright, open- hearted child, and feared not the approach of a stranger. Skilo had left his tribe, and secreted him- self in a thicket of the grove, in order oto await little George's approach. As be en- tered the grove, Skilo's heart beat with joy, and leaping from his place of concealment, and approached him with a triumphant smile, and presenting him with a bow and arrow, and said, 'My little feowm, come, I will show youl,  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7495-00000052"/> 100     THE BLIND GIRL'S how to tip over the squirrels when they are eating nuts, if you will go with me, and giv- ing him some other small presents, which he had prepared for the pupose, soon gained the confidence of little George. On and on, 'he urged him in search of game, until he had entirely lost sight of home. Skilo then caught him in his arms, aind made his way to the river as fast as possible, where he had left his canoe, and placed little George by his side. At this, George seemed much pleased, for he was very fond of boat riding and away they went with all the speed that Skilo was capable of, and in a few hours they were many miles away. George did not return to his dinner as usual, which caused his mother great uneasiness, think- ing some accident must have befallen her son. As soon as dinner was over, Mrs. Derby put on her bonnet, and with a hurried step went to the grove, where he was accus. tomed to spend his hours. On reaching the spot, she called his name repeatedly, but to no purpose. Eagerly did she visit every house in the village in search of little George -and anxiously enquiring of every one if they had seen him that day. She Could find no   OFFERING.       101 proach of day. Although the morning so much desired, arrived, and the search was again commenced. They continued the search for several days, but could gain no intelli- gence of their boy, advertisements were sent in every direction, and a great reward was offered for the restoration of their lost child. The distressed mother gave up in despair, and mourned for him-as dead. Seven summers had already passed, and George had been taught to believe that his parents were dead, and that he must look to the Indians for protection. George had be- come a great favorite among them. He had been taught to hunt and fish, and had be- come very much attached to their wild mode of living. When he was thiiteen years of of age, the Indians wished to do all that his own parents would have done for him, alb though they regretted his absence, yet they were all in favor of sending him to college. George was much pleased with the idea of being an educated man. Years passed away, and George had made great proficiency in his studies he had a nat- ural taste for learning, and had so confined himself to his lessons, that at the expiration  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7495-00000053"/> 102   THE BLIND GIR   L'S trace of her lost child, and with Ian agitated mind she returned to the house and inform- ed her husband of CGeorge's absence, telling him that she had searched diligently for  him, but could find ing trace whatever, urg- ing him to go in search of their son. Mr. Derby accordingly set forth, though with less concern than that of his wife. He con- tinued his search until three o'clock, but in vain. He then notified the people, and in a short time there were hundreds of men in search of little George. They blowed horns, fired guns, rung bells, called his name, but all to no purpose. They searched the woods and river until night approached, and then were compelled to return home without the least satisfaction. After the people had re- turned to their respective homes, I called at the house of Mr. Derby in order to speak some words of consolation to the afflicted parents. It was an affecting scene; the ag- onizing groans which arose from the hearts of Mr. and Mrs. Derby, were heart-rending. Neither of them laid down during the night, but earnestly did they pray for the safety of their darling boy, and with intense anxiety and bitter tears, did they wait for the ap-   l bw OFFERING.       103 of five years, he was afflicted with a disease which forced him to leave school and travel for a season through different parts of the country to regain his former health. Duringhis travels, he was cordially re- ceived and kindly treated, and formed some pleasant acquaintances, from which he was sorry to part. After traveling one long rainy day in September, he felt that he was nearly exhausted, and resolved to seek for rest at the next house, he approached it, and saw a man sitting near the door, and as he approached him, he felt as though he had reached some old friend. After the usual salutation, he said, Sir, 1 am very tired, and have a severe headache, and if you will allow me a shel- ter through the-night, I will recompense you for it. After taking a cup of tea, which was cheerfully prepared, he repaired to rest. At length morning appeared, and found George unable to leave his bed; he had a high fever, and the pain in his head had grown more violent. The good lady did-ev- ery thing to ease the pain that lay in her power, but,to no effect. A physician was  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7495-00000054"/> 104   THE BLIND GIRL'S sent for, and on entering the house, he ap-  proached the bed where the stranger laid ; groaning with distress, and after a close ex- amination, he left the bed and seated him. '  self in adjoining'room beside a table,. and commenced preparing his medieine. ' Do you consider the stranger danger- ous t inquired the lady anxiously. 'Well,' responded the doctor, I cannot tell how it may turn with him, but I think unless he has the best of care, he will never recover'. He then gave her directions, telling her that he would call again thatafternoon, and left the house.  Day after day passed, and George suffer- ed much, yet he did not murmur, or com- plain but expressed great anxiety that he might again be restored to health. At, length his fever began to abate, and at the expiration of three weeks, he was enabled to sit up, and walk about the house. Mrs. Derby, (for that was the name of the lady) began to feel a strong desire to learn the his tory of the stranger. One beautiful evening as they were sea- ted in the little parlor, Mrs. Derby very po- litely introduced the subject.   OFFERING.       105 Madam, said George, my parentage is al. most entirely effaced from my memory. I was brought up by a tribe of Indians until I was thirteen years of age, then I was sent to college, where I remained until about six months since, when I was forced to leave in consequenee of poor health. I was taught to believe that my parents were dead, and I can^only remembler. that I once had kind parents, and was an only child, that I had a little dog which was a great favorite of mine, all save this, entirely gone from me. Mr. and Mrs. Derbyzlistened with great interest, when he had finished his narrative. Mrs. Derby said, while her,heart swelled between fear and joy, is there no scar or mark upon you, which could be detected. O yes, there is a scar upon my head, and two of my toes grow together upon my left foot. They needed no other proof than this to convince them-that the stranger was to oth- er thantheir long'lost George. In a mo- ment more he was encircled in the arms of his parents, while the overjoyed mother shrieked, and exclaimed, I4  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7495-00000055"/> 1e6     THE BLIND GIRL'S 'My son, my child, my long lost George.' Language would here fail to describe the joy which this meeting occasioned. There- fore I will only say, that George, never - re- turned to live with Indians again, but spent the remainder of his days in happiness with his affectionate parentse TItE EARLY GRAEEVa Mr. Ashand, who resided in the town of P -----, was by no means wealthy, but was considered a comfortable liver. He had a daughter, an qnly child, she was a great favorite with associates, and was con- sidered by all, the belie in the village of P..-.---. No ride, visit or dance, could pass pleasantly, unless the gentle hearted Ella Ashand formed one of the guests. She had by her mild and amiable disposition, won the heart of James Wilson, a school-mate of hers who had ever cherished the warmest affection for her. Mr. Wilson was a very proud, aristocrat- ic man, and was by no means pleased with thegrowing affection in the hearts of the young people.   oFFERING.       107 One beautiful morning in the month of August, Mr. Wilson resolved that he would seek an interview with James, and ascertain if possible, how matters stood between him and Ellen Ashand. As soon as breakfast was over, he accor- dingly turned to James, and said; 'My son, I would like to talk with you awhile.' Leading the way to his room, James re- luctantly followed, well knowing from what cause this interview proceeded. On reach. ing his room they seated themselves upo6ha sofa beside the window, while the cool, fresh breeze gently played through the rustling vines which twined about the window, James said Mr. Wilson, I have taken this opportunity to converse with you upon the subject of matrimony, and learn if possible what peculiarities there is about Miss Ashand that you should pay your addresses entirely to her. 'Well father, since you have expressed a, desire to know, I will tell you. Ella is very industrious, possessing a generous heart, a noble-mintd and a lovely disposition, which has won my affections.  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7495-00000056"/> 108    TIE BLIND GIRL'S 'Won your affections!' Interrupted his flther, 'then you really intend to marry a farmer's daughter, do you.' 'I do,' said James emphatically. Well, James, as you regard the wishes of your parents, I wish you would forsake the society of Ella Ashand, and pay your addresses to Miss Emegin Cornwell, who belongs to an aristocratic family, be- id4, she will have a fortune with her. 'Well, father, I do not think that happi- ness consists in aristocracy, for my part I had rather have a fortune in a heart than wi#t one.' 'Well, James,' said Mr. Wilson, rising from, his seat, while his cheeks flushed with anger, 'If you persist in marrying Ella Ash- land, you must not expect to find a home with me, for I will entirely disown you. James seemed somewhat puzzled at this denunciation, not knowing how Mr. Ash- land might feel upon subject, but resolved that he would know the worst, and immedi- ately set out for his dwelling. On reach-. ing his house he found Mr. Ashand in thei garden, who met him as he approached, i.    OFFERING.       109 with 2 cheerful smile, and invited him to take a seat in the arbor. James ac- cordingly sat down, and mustering all his courage, commenced the subject, telling him of the conversation which had passed be" tween him and his father, respecting his marriage. Mr. Ashand remained silent a few moments, then rising from his seat, he said. Well, James, if this is your choice, -you may have a home here, although I am not wealthy like your father, but I have enough to make us all comfortable. This was more than James had anticipa. ted, and after expressing his gratitude to Mr. Ashand for his kindness, they both entered the house. The day for their nuptials was appointed, and every pieparation was made for the oc- casion which would add to the happiness of the fair couple. Time swiftly glided and the appointed day arrived, and found the intended bride on her death bed. It was a beautiful morning in September, about nine o'clock, she revived, and calling her friends around her bed, she addressed - thiem as follows;   &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7495-00000057"/> "O   THE BLIND GIRL'S 'My dear friends, I am about' to leave you, and that in a short time. I have only to regret that I have not set a better ex- ample before my friends and associates, but I wish to be forgiven by them all, even as God has for Christ's sake forgiven me.- And now let me entreat you to prepare meet your God in peace. Life is uncertain; but one week ago I was in the bloom of health, and now my soul will be in the spirit land ere the sun shall set. Then taking her lover by the hand, she placed a lock which had been severed from her glossy hair, with a Bible, she said, 'O James, may this be a star of light which will guide you to the fold of Christ.' She then bid them all farewell, until they should meet at the judgment seat of Christ,' and in a few moments her spirit was wafted on angel's wings to the realms of eternal bliss. Poor James was not prepared for this heavy and unexpected blow, he had hoped for pleasure; but alas how soon was his hopes blighted. In one short day-ah! who can tell. James now felt that he had no friend to   OFFERING       1" whom he could unbosom his sorrow, but un- to Him who heareth in secret, and from that hour he sought an interest in Christ. In a few days after her death, he resolved that he would fit himself for a missionary, and in a short time he left for college. But it seems that this was not the office which he was designed to fill, for he had scarcely been there one month when he Was taken with a disease of the heart, which carried him down to the grave. He was then removed to his home, where he lived but two weeks after his return. During his illness, he talked much about Ella Ashand, and often requested them to read to him in the Bible she gave him. One pleasant evening in November, the family of Mr. Wilson was alarmed by the cry--'James is dying.'  They thronged around his bed and wept. James seemed unconscious of what was passing for some time, then opening his glassy eyes, and look. ing around him he said, 'Do not weep for me, but prepare to meet me in Heaven.' He then gave his favorite Bible to his sister, saying, s  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7495-00000058"/> "2   THE BLIN1  GIRL'S Put your trust in God, ani be guided by the precepts which is contained in this pre- cious book.' He then imprinted a kiss upon each cheek, and still holding his father by the hand,-he said,  'Father, i have one request to ask of you that I may be laid by the side of Ella Ash- land, and my monument may be precisely like hers, also I wish you to place at the head of our gr ves, a weeping willow; then turning to his afflicted mother, he said with a smile, 'O mother, I am going home,' and closed his eyes in death. Mr. Wilson felt that this was the most trying scene that he had ever been called to pass through. The funeral sermon of James Wilson and Ella Ashand, were both preached by G. G. White. There was not one dry eye among the whole congregation, which consisted of over four hundred. As we have said before, they were both great favorites among their associates, and every heart was bereft. at their loss, and could sympathise with the afflicted families. James was laid according to his request,   "$ by the side orlhis intended, and the monu- ments of the two la9ya:re placed upon the graves, witha wpn  wlow at the hea. t -  ltt *^ ; p t . l ON,  Who havepassed -on  fore.  Brother, aste thout art about to take, Whic$iW           4   e; Ponde is          i Befere,.foe; "JS tf44"I        - Life is a th'ria ith'ouj ow  Aiid youo iii   I To oho&amp;                  .  For a$ fi       t    . s And should you find a heart that's true, Then her happiness Will depend on you, Soothe each sorrow, share each joy, And then this lifeyotu will enjoy. And walk itwisdom's path:below, That youroul maybeprepared to go,  -To dwell with Christ above the sky,:  Where tears shall be wided froo every er. . 15 ' "*            , , A 4 7  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7495-00000059"/> "4   T'lHi BLINiD GtIRL'S POETRt. Lord if thou mysight doth take, O, may I not one murmur make, Nor think thy chastening too sever e, For a rebellious child to bear. But may I with great patience wait Until the summons thou dost relate' To call my new born soul away  To brighter realms of endless day. Butt is my soul prepared to die, And do I on Christ's words' rely? Have I an evidence within That I shall be with Christ shut in. If so, I am from trouble free, My soul is happy and relieved- If I can with with my God find rest, 'Tis all, I ask for nothing else.   OFFERING.'       " REMEMBRANCE OF CHIDHOOD. When on my pillow'd bed I rest, And naughtsave heaven is o'er my breast, I love to think of days long past, Which were too bright to always last. I love to think how oft we've played Beneath the green and forest shade, How oft we decked our hats with flowers; Ah, much I lov'd my childhood hours. I love to think how oft we walked Among the blooming flowers, and talked- And O, how often did we sigh That the sweetest flowers will droop and die. Ah, much 1 loved my childhood days, When seated around the fire that blazed Upon our cottage hearth at night, Our hearts they seemed so free and light. I love to think how oft we read In the Bible, that our Savior bled, And if we do on Him rely, Our souls may dwell above the sky. I love to think when life is past. That we shall meet in heaven at last, Then all our joys wil be renewed And paths of glory we shall pursue. x "fj  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7495-00000060"/> "6    THE BLIND GIRL'S POETRY. How-soon the-brittle thread of life - Will remove us from lthis world of strife, Then all the gold that we possess, i- Cannot restore ourvital breath. Then why'should we-so eager be To gain great wealthland honored be. As to neglect ourstoul' s salvation, ' When the gospel is 'preached. amobng our na- tion. We who neglect Christ's invitations, To join in the world's:wild recreatiois ,l Must not expect when the judge appears, That our cries for mercy he Will hear. Lord who among that class shall be Oh, grant that it may not be me, But may I reign above with thee,' When time on earth no more shall be. THE STOLEN CHLD. About twenty-eight years ago, a brisk Captain walking through the streets of - beheld, a very pretty child, about o seven years of age mourning for the loss of his' fa- ther,from whom he had accidentally straiy-   OFIFERIUNG.      117 ed acway. lHc ,soothed the child persuaded him to dry his tears, and told him he had orders from his father, who had. just set out for the country, to bring him along. The innocent victim, without suspicion of harm, followed his deliverer, as he thought, who carried him in the stage coach to .  , and there immediately put him on board his vessel, which sailed a week after for Ameri- ca. Still fed with the hopes of: seeing his father, and was going, but a short distance by water, where he should find him, and in- dulged by the Captain in all he desired,time slipped away, till the brute manifested by the vilest actions, his-aecursed designs. On arriving at the end of his voyage, the lad- was sold to a planter in South Carolina, for the sam of fifteen guineas. The planter, happened to be a man of great humanity, ta- king a fancy to the child, heard his simple tale, and perceived the villainy, but not till the vessel had sailed. He. enquired his  name, and immediately sent over to adver-' tise'him in the public prints, but before . this design could be completed, near two. years hai4 elaped, whenl his father and mother  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7495-00000061"/> "8     THE BLIND GIRL'S were both dead, and perhaps, the cause of their death was this very accident. In short, the master liked the youth, more and more, and as he was sober, industrious and intelligent, at length married him to an only daughter, leaving him at his decease, his whole fortune. Twenty-five years elapsed, and, tho' under great pain for the loss of his parents, yet happy in his -family affairs, he lived with great content, and was distinguished for his benevolence and his integrity. At the expiration of this period, a ship arrived with convicts, and as he went to purchase some servants, he was astonished to behold among the prisoners, the very captain by whom he had been stolen and brought from his' native country when a boy. The idea of thisbar. barous man was so strongly impressed upon his: mind, that he knew him at first sight, and immediately became his purchaser. A no- torious crime had brought him into these circumstances, and entirely ruined him, As soon as he had brought him home, he took himinto a private room, and looked himself in with him; but what, words could   OFFERING.-      119 express the astonishment and confusion of the wretch, when he understood into whose hands he had fallen! for he had no previ- ous notion that the gentleman who had bought him and the boy whom he had sto- len twenty-five years before and sold into slavery were the same. Struck with remorse and the fear of pun- shment, he fell upon his knees and begged forgiveness. 'Tho Lord has been very merciful to me' said the master, 'and has now delivered you into my hands, and I shall punish you to my entire satisfaction, you may remain here un- til morning, when you shall learn your fate. The wretched main spent that night in' great agitation of mind. The morning ap- peaed, and Coon the master opened the door and said, 'Now for your destiny, take off your rusty looking clothes, and put this suit or.' He immediately obeyed, though trei- bling with fear, expecting every moment to hear his dreadful sentence. The master ta- king a paper from his pocket, handed it to the frightened man, saying,  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7495-00000062"/> 1210   'VtHE BLEND GIRL'SS 'lHead your sentence.' -The blood quickly left his face whiteas mai ble. Glancing his eyes quickly over the paper, exclaimed, ; 'Free, am I free, such a wretch as I.' 'Yes ' replied the master; 'I forgive you that cruel, wicked act, and pray that your heavenly Father may forgive you. -Here is ten dollars,- which will be of some service to you, and may you from this time do as you would be done by. The wretched man sobbed convulsively, he could not find words to express his grati- tude, but faithfully promised his kind bene- factor , hthat he would lead a better life, and from tha t day he became a pious and devo- --  ted Christian, and lived many years in the service of his heavenly Father. DIALOGUE BETWEEN SUSAN, MARY AND JANE., AM.-This grave-yard, is a very solemn place to me.     - S. --Yes, but I .like to pass my hours her( beside her grave and read 'this Bible whid sifter gave we when dying.   OFFERING.      121 M.-O sister, that hour will never be ef- faced from my memory. When she placed her hand upon my head and said, 'do not weep, Mary, but prepare to meet your sister in that world where parting will be no more. J.-Girls, why are you here weeping, come, let us away and join that happy group yonder. S.-No, Jan,- I do not wish to join those merry hearts like your own. who know not how to sympathise with us, who are bereft of a sister, who lies low beneath this grassy mound. J.-Very true, Susav, I know not how to sympathise with you, but you have this thought to' comfort you, 'that her soul is at rest. M.-O yes, I have no doubt, but that she is at rest, for'she died in the triumph of faith. J.-Yes, I have often wished that I might die ashap as as she did. S.-Well, if we would die the death of a christian, we must live like one, for we know not how soon we may be called from this world to the spirit land. M.--I think religion is good to live by 16  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7495-00000063"/> 122     THE BLIND GIRL'S and die by, for there was old aunt Sally, ye know that she was very poor, and suffer much, hut her religion sustained her, and i the hour of death it did not forsake he Here is the hymn that sister so often sum with so much satisfaction. S.--Let us bing it. Sweet is the welcome sound of death, My fainting spirit longs to go, And bid all earthly friends adieu, Onward my journey to pursue. Then I shall sing on Canaan's shore Where tears and sorrow will be no more Chret God, I only ask to be Prepared to live and reigp with thee. Afflictions, may I bear them all Until thou dost my spirit call, To dwell with Christ above the sky Where sainted spirits never die. J.-Yes, if we can only be prepared t eigan with Christ, that is sufficient. S.-Yes, it matters not how msnh we su: fer here in this world, it is but for a shoi time . Qoae ^ Mary, the dew is falling fast, w have been here a long time, let us retur t; te 'house.   OFFERING.       123 M.-Jane, there is going to be a prayer meeting this evening, and if you will go home with us, we will all go. J.-Yes, girls, I will gladly do so, for I always like to attenda good lively prayer meeting. TO BE $POKEX1 BY TWELVE GIRL. 1. A Violet. I like the modest violet blue, Its color is so mild and and true, Besides it is the first in spring And then we hear the robins sing. 2. A Garden Violet. I like the garden violet best For it blossoms longer than all the rest, Besides, it richer colors bears, And in them all of us may share. 3. A Lilac. Better do I like the Lilac tall Which deek our yards and goaen jalls, Besides they scent the air sosweet, . That the hum-birds among their branches sleep.  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7495-00000064"/> 124   THEI BLIND GIRL'S 4. The Piony. The Piony fills my eye the best It is so'large and richly dressed, Its stalk is slender, hut it bears That blooming flower so rich and fair. 5. The Rose. I like the sweet and fragrant Rose That bedews the graves where the dead repose, And gladly wonld I have them stay, But soon they wither all away 6. The Lily. I like the Lily straight and tall That bows its head in reverence to all, Its dress, it is so rich and fine, I have often wished that it were mine. 7. Morning Glory. I like the Morning Glory Though its stay is shorter than the rest, It shows us that we to must die, Though blooming now, yetJdeath is nigh. 8. The Blue-Bell. The sweetness of this little Bell, There's none on earth but the Bee can tell, Its language does excel the rest, I'm sure I like the Blue-Bell best.   OFFERITN.       125 9. The Marigold. It shall ever be my rule To cultivate the Marigold, For its soft and velvet blows, Shows us that God gave us those. 10. Sweet William. The Sweet William is a pretty blow, It does beside our path in clusters grow; When it is blown then it must fall, That is the common lot of all. ". The Pink I like the Pink in bright vermillion dress- ed, Its sweet perfume excels all the rest, And I often sigh as I pass by That so sweet a flower must wilt and die. Sweet are the flowers you all like best, But they must perish with the rest- Those short-lived beauties must decay, For time soon sweeps them all away. \ 'OR THE TWr LVE TO SINO. Our hearty thanks we will return, To our Superintendent first For all his toil with his Sabbath School, And his unwearied pains.:  ,   '  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7495-00000065"/> 126    THE BLIND GIRL'S Then to our teachers we will say, We thank you for your care- May the instructions we received Guide us from every snare. This Sabbath School is nearly closed, And we all unite To sing to our dear friends we love, And bid you all good-night, THE BERRY BOY. In the summer of 1838, Mr. Benton on his way home from the Springs, where he had spent several weeks with his daughter, stopped at a hotel in a small village to rest awhile in the heat of the day. He had not been there long, when a lad about ten years of age came up with a basket of berries, whose eountenanee bespoke poverty and dis- tress. Mr. Benton looked at him with an eye of compassion, and with a sort of inter- est, and thinking that he would lighten his load, he said, 'What will you take for your berries, my little fellow?' 'Four cents a quart,' replted the boy, wi- :lis keen bla 6 eye sparkled with joy at the thought ofhii igFl    OFFERING       127 Mr. Benton had great curiosity to learn something of the- young, stranger's history, and said inquiringly, 'Do you go to school ' 'No. sir,' said the boy. 'I used to go be- fore my mother died, but now it is all that I can do to support my poor blind grandfa- ther.' 'Have you no father?' '0 no, he doied some years before my mo- ther,' said thq boy, while the tears run down his cheeks. What do you do for a livelihood; ' asked, Mr. Benton, while his heart moved- with sympathy for him. 'I saw wood, pick berries, go on errands, or anything else I can get to do.' 'You are a fine fellow,'said Mr. Bienton, 'but I will not take your berries, for you can sell to some oae else, and, here is five dollars- which will' lighten your burden a little. The boy looked at him with amazement, for he had never before had in his possession that amount of money, and he hardly knew how to express his gratitude, but after thanking him over and over again, he went bounding away like a dancing feather. 4  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7495-00000066"/> 128    THE BLIND GIRL'S Mr. Benton, watched the movements of the lad and soon saw him enter a small cot- tage where sat his grandfather, leaning upon his staff, and after carefully depositing his treasure in the hands of the old veteran, he immediately set out with his berries. Mr. Benton then resolved to befriend the poor orphan, and assist him in getting an educa- tion. In a few days after he reached home he put his resolution into practice,and im- mediately prepared a subscription paper for the benefit of the poor orphan boy. He signed ten dollars and being a man who ex-' erted great influence in society, and in a few days he had enough signed to aooom- plish his design.  Mr. Benton accordingly, enclosed the money in a letter addressing it to Simon Powell, for this was the name of the Orphan.      I will not pretend to describe the joy  which the reception of that letter occasioned the poverty strick- en heart, although his affectionate grandfa- ther had but a few days since been convey- ed to the silent tomb. I will only say that the money was carefully managed and Si- mon obtained a liberal education. ; When he was about eighteen years of. age, he let   himself as a- clerk- to Mr. Saxe, a wholesaJl merchant. By his induAtry;, honiesty,? and uprightness, gained the esteem- of -both Mr, &amp; Mrs. Saxe, and having no childreni 6f their own, he soon became their adopted, si' ltrtd was now known -by. the' ninme of Simoti  P. Saxe. Three years passed pleasintly away, but ere the fourth aututum appeared Mr. Saxe; wsas numbered with' ti- silent dea d. His death was lametited by all, espe- cially by the poorer class forb he was a very charitable man, abd no beggar ever leftshis dwelling without finding some relief.. All butsiness was now left in the hands of Simon P. Saxe, who managed it with such care and pradence, as to add a handsome sum yearly to his now large estate.  One evening n Septelnberl as Simona was reading the advertisements which are al*ways more or. less in a paper? his eyes rested upon: the well known name of Mr. Benton stating that his whole establishment Wtas to be, sold at auction for debt on the seventh of.,Octo- ber. Simon now felt that it was in his. power to befriend him, and, rsolved tl ,he would, At length the day, appeared, and  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7495-00000067"/> 180    THE -BLIND GOIRLS tionei 6f different classes were: upon the grotini viewing the:premises with gteat inthre st -Akong the rest was -Sizon tP. Saxe. At ohefo'clook-the sile commenced, and'to'the urwprise of all- the whole establishment was strunk off to Simon P. Saxe. He then en- tered the house with Mr. Benton to survey toisproerty. *Mr. Befton invite lhiu- into the parlor, 'nd introducing him to Mrs. and Miss Ame- lia Benton, sayibg, ,This is the-gentleman who now owns this establishment.' -At this, Amelia burst into tears, for she could not conceal her emotion.,' Simon was much affected by her grief, for he too, had tasted the cup of bitter sorrow, and turning to Mr. Benton, he said, 'Sir, do you ye:emet her t he poor orphan boy. woim- y  Ua befrieided -some fourteen Mr. 'etiton h'eitatitg a few moments, and thei id, yiesbut I shouild never thought ot--it      p oib.'  *Wel1, Iam thati person, it was by your afssiate that I obtained an education. I   OFFERING       181 then resolved by the grace of lbd, that I would repay you for that Sact of kindn ss, and as Providence would hae jit, I .a ?OW- enabled to befriend you. well know yu misfortunes. You will not re nd  . necessity of moving a       finle stic, for X have purchased this stand jfo the pErpose of giving you ample timeto reeem .it.' Mr. Benton and   , fta y wxeroe poercome with joy, and could not tp tqi?r t- tude, and all wqept eoP vsiwelJ. $iwon could but weep with. te ovrv y ed famy. As soon as'he oqUld lo eet  e f, he sat down and relatad. his Jistory fqm .. time that Mr. Bent met ffimiw, ase. X boy at the hotel, util the eset. tr much persuasiQo, he spent ,te n t ;wirth them very pleasa'tly. IroQ that rtimehe paid his addresqes to Ms Aielia Benen, who in less th n a year wPs madeo -fie .hpv bride of Simon P. Saxe. He I ten remoye herto his place of residence ,where they passed many years in happine3s wi t' i bereft widow.  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7495-00000068"/> 182   THJT BLIND GIRL'S TlHE GIPSEY  GIRL. Lizzie, the eroine of our story, was thl daughter of ha ipsey. Her mother died whoe she was about six years of ae, and from tha time she i ingled in the society of none sav that of hir father who at that time left hi, tribe, and betook himself to a secluded spot near the banks of the river, where he hopec to spend the riemaindfer of his daysyFin th( societyotfhis beautiful and gentle heartec Ljiize, regsolv to seclude her from the gaz( of theigossipping world, for fear of her beau tyj wouldtledepi've ihim of his onily treasure Herethey pent several years ins, appines u moested by the intrusion of 'any one.- Sh Vwas eveb   r by hefather's side, save ihei h went to market, and duiring lis absence she usually amuse'd herself by singing the Wild' 'Gipse sonigsl which her father hac leai id her, anid ;the most Qf them were fa rite pieces of mothers. , One beautiful evening in September, Liz zte, ad her father were seated unl er thei favorite tree singing their wild song whiel they usually sung at the close of the day   OFPERTIN.       13S when the sun was shedding its last rays over the earth. They had scarcely finished her song, when a stranger stepped from be- neath a thicket, where had been listening to the bird-like Voice of Lizzie. He approach- ed the spot where sat the old man and his beautiful daughter resting her head upon his shoulder, and very politely acpsteQ them. The old man was much disturbpd at his approach, and by no means gave him a hearty welcome. The stranger' looked at the fair girl with astonishment. He had often seen the 6id mdaniin 'the market, but had never dreamed of his having so beauti- ful a daughter. After a short interviewthe stranger perceiving that he was an unwel- come guest to the old man, took his leave. ,I am thankful that he has gone,' said the old man placing his hand upon Lizzie's shoulder. 'Why father, why did the presence of that gentleman give you so much pain.' 'I have my reasons, but it would not be proper for you to know. Come, child,' said he starting from his seat, let us go to our tent.'   &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7495-00000069"/> 34    THE BLIND-GIRL'S Lizzie asked many qmestions about the stranger, but could gain no satisfactory ans- wer. In a few days after, the old man was obliged to again visit. the market. As soon as be entered the market, th 4ranger saw him, and knowing that he usqally stopped there sometime, resolved that hpe*wQud seek an interview with the. fair Gipsey during her father's absence, and in oedj*tely -set out for her tent. Lizzie, zas soon a her fltler had gone, seated herself beneath the :hede of her fa- vorite tree, and commne4 s 'nging her-wild songs, looking up she saw -so Q e ne a dis- tance, whom she recognized as the stranger who bad accosted them hbt a few evenings before. He approached and taking 'er warmly ,by the hand, seated h'iself by her side. Liz- zie seemed much alared o finding herself alone with the stranger, and egged hiI to be gone, telling hi 4ha t :her father would ble very angry, should he find hi there on his return. Do not be frightened my dear ^jrl, said he, I came here to converse a while with ylou Ouring your father's absence, and will leave   OFFEhRlING.-       I 3  ere he ifiurnis:. But tell me, I entreat you why a eiing s6 fdir as yourself, should spend 1ier days here in this secluded spot; 'Sectidd spot!' said she with da air of :contenip - 'We are Gipseys, we have our mode dt living; arnd yott have yours. I ami happy in the society 6f my father,; and you, perhapg; iff the society of a wife or a:moth, o r.' 'Wife jUriimredi hee 'I hate no .wife, but had I one as b6autifil as youaself, true enough; I should be happy i"i her society.' 'But,' said Lizzie; 'sy 'no more, you must leave, for iny father will retrrAi soon .': He reTuctantly arose, ain taking her by the haand, said, 'We palt now, but not forever. These words rung in the eats of Liza ie; bat said slie, 'It will hever do, for me to even think of ' of him, for he is a stranger, besides father will never conseit for me to receive cadllI from any o6ie.'  Time passed on, and Lizzie thought more and more of the stranger and at times al- most wished that she could see him again.-  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7495-00000070"/> 136   THE BLIND GIRL'S At length the father was obligea to go th market. Edward, as tlit was the stranger'i name, saw t the old man as soor. as he entered the market, for he had watched each day for his approach. And imimediately set out to renew his visit with the fair Gipsey s he reached the spot, he found the fait gitla un- der her fa+orite tred but she seemed thought- ful and melancholy. He took the fair girl by the hand saying,.  'My dear Lizzie, I -cme here to declare to yott tte love which I have had foi you since first we met, and to offer you my heart and ha id, and seek yours ii return. -'But, stop, interrupted Lizzie, 'you arce too hasty, you would never marry a Gip; sey.'  'Marry a Gipsey! to be sure I would, atd shall be one of the happiest beings in the World if I can but obtain you. Oh no, that can never be, for I have ever been taught to love none but my father, and he would never consent to our union ; why Edward, would you not feel- mortified to in- tr6duce me to your friends as your bride? Feel mortified, dear Lizzie. No indeed., 1 should feel proud to call so fair a being   OFFERING       187 s yourself my own, It is true, you know nothing of my circumstances, one thing is certain-I have enough to place you beyond the reach of want, unless misfortune's hand is laid heavily upon me, if that should be our lot, we will share it together.' O itdward, how could i be so ungrateful to mn father, who has been so kind 'to me, as to leave him without a friend on earth to comfort him in his declining years. Ed- ward, I could never act so rashy, said she, while th etears fell from her dak eyes.  Edward drew her closely to liside, say- ing, 'Dear Lizzie, you need no 'leave your father aone, hfe sh ll always have a'home with us, only say that you will be ' mine. Say, Aear Lizzie, could you not be happy wit me, or sh6uld .you sigh for your wild home.' Lizzie leaninghher head upon ,hi s h4ilder said, I could be happy in your society, ,but my fathler will forbid our union.' "&amp;eyVer fear, de;r Lizzie,I will obtain dis consent, if'you will allow me to remain here until he returns.  ' .. f k  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7495-00000071"/> 138    THE BLIND GIRL#t 'You can do as you like, but I fear I will be very angry, and would remove v from this part of the world, and if we a: married it must be done privately. 'Well, Lizzie, then say the next tine you father goes to market, that I may come he] With a carriage and thatyou will accompan -ue to the. village Where we will have tE larriage ceremony performed. 'it'  a svd shee, 'what will my poor fath4 "think, 9rneurnjug and :iding me ab ept 'We willleave a letter here which wi explain all; Lizzie consented, and Edward took h leave, feeling that he had the promise  the fairest being in the world. 1izzie pn her father's returp, did not me him with the same Cheerful smile that sl was wont to do, and the sadness of her cou tena4ce attraeted her father's notice. ';' zie,' said her ther f , 'why are you , sad d are you not well ' )h' yes,' saidLizzie, thwi her arn : roa 4 I 4is nepk, and waymly imprinting kiss" upon his cheec. She strove to resun her usual cheerfulness, tt still herliea was- sad.     * '  was sad.   OFFERING.       139 As the time arrived for her father to go to market, Lizzie could not refrain from shed- ing tears. The old man saw the tears as they fell from her eyes, and drawing her to his side, aid, 'ily child, what is the cause of your wee- ping?'  '0 I was thinking how lonely I should be, were I to be deprived of your company. 'Do not allow yourself to think upon that subject, said her fatier, 'for we will never be separated until by the ruthless hand of death. On saying this, he imprinted a kiss on her cheek, and said,  'Be cheerful my child,' and left her, As soon as he had gone, she gave vent to a flood of tears. She called to- mind the many happy hours that she had spent with her father, and the thought of leaving her childhood borne, forever to go, she knew not where, was more than her poor heart could bear. She soon heard the carriage wheels as they approached. She sat motionless, as Edward entered-the tent.' 'Dear Lizzie, why are you weeping; you do not regret the promise you made, d yoti. You shall never want for the corfiri4  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7495-00000072"/> "O   THE BLIND GIRL'S life, and you Ahall ever find in me a kind and affectionate husband, and as for your father, he shall ever be a welcome guest with us. And here, said he,' is a letter for your father. Come, we must be in haste, for we have no time to spare.' Lizzie, then, with&amp; ashmuch composure as possible, soon took leave of her home where sorrow had evei been a stranger until now, and was soon rolling rapidly away. Lizzie's father returned sooner than usu- al, and on entering the tent, found his child gone, and a letter lying upon the table, and on opening it, he read as follows:, DEAR SIR.-I know: that you will feel much surprised at the absence of your daugh ter, but be calm and I will tell you all. Sir, the first time I saw your daughter sea- ted by your side, I resolved that she should be mine if I could obtain her consent, ac- cordingly I availed myself of the opportunri- ty to talk with her during your absence and to-day ere the sun shall set, Lizzie will be my. lawful and wedded bride, but in three days she shall return to you. She was very unwilling to leave, as, she saijd she was all that you had to care for in this world. But   OFFERING.        " let me say, that you need never be separated for you shall ever have a home with us. And believe me, your affectionate son, EDWARD BLAKELY. As he closed the letter, he sank kack in his chair, saying, 'I shall never see another happy moment for my only child is torn from me, and for me to leave my old home, and go to that of another, I never can bear the thought. No, I will live like aehermit, and when the Lord sees fit to call me. from earth, I will die alone, without one friend to bathe my throb, bing brow, or shed the farewell tear. For twelve years it has been my constant care to supply the wants of my only treasure-I have denied myself of every comfort for her sake, and is this the reward. The old man spent 'ie days in walking around -the solitary paths that hel used to traverse with so much delight when his dar- ling child was at his side, and at night, he would lie down upon his couch, but he could not rest for sleep had departed froi his iyes. At length the time arrived for the return of hisachhil. As JLizia aned f idwao d entered the tent, they found their father weeping. \ :J  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7495-00000073"/> 12    THE BLIND GtRL'S 'Oh! my dear father,' cried Lizzie, 1 Hase come to ask your pardon, and if pos. sible, persuade you t9 go home with me.' 'My dear lchild, I grant you my pardon, but I can never leave my home, But since here is the man of your choice, go and be happy. But for me, I shall never again be happy.' 'Say not so,' interrupted Ldward, ofor we will ever be all that a fond parent can desire. Now said Lizzie, I hope I shall pe enabled to repay your kindnesss to me; come, say that you will go home with us. Come, say you will go and see our home. After much persuasion, the old man consent- ed. They were soon seated in the carriage, and rolled rapidly along, until they reached their mansion, where they alighted and were shown into a parlor nicely furnished, where they spent the evening very pleasantly, and the old man quite forgot his sorrow Here he spent many happy years with 'his affectionate and happy, children. And he never regretted at leaving home. And Liz- zie ever found Edward a kind and affection- ate husband, and stood high in society. She was ever ready to lend a helping hand to the needy and-* shoe1dl y befal to knle her;   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>