<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7802">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Parson Beecher and His Horse </title>
            <author >Bricktop.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7802</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Parson Beecher and his horse</title>
                  <author >Bricktop.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >96 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Winchell &amp; Small</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1871">1871</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-04-06">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Parson Beecher and his horse</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000001"/>   A PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. A HUMOROUS ADVENTURE, BY  NEW YORK: PUBLISHED BY WINCHELL &amp; SMALL, NO. 48 ANN STREET AND 113 FULTON STIEET. 1871.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7802-00000002"/> ENTERED according to Act of Congress, in the year 1871, bY WINCHELL &amp; SMALL, In the Office of the Librarian of Congress at Washington.  PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. Now then, Sam, lead 'Duster' out, and let me show the gentleman his good points. Lively there, lively!" said Gouger, a well-known horse jockey, to a small chunk of animated India rubber that acted as his groom. "All right, boss, I'se gwine,' and into the stable he vanished like a shadow. "Now, sir," continued Gouger, "I know exactly what you want. You want a nice, gentle saddle-horse, one that has some 'go' inter him, and yet one as is nice an' quiet like," and he winked confidentially. "That is what I want, precisely, ' replied Parson Beecher, rubbing his fat hands with delight.  .. "Now  don't I tell yer? . Says H ter Bill Larkin only yesterday, says I, 'Now if some parson would only come along I have got a piece of fleshas would tickle him.' Says Bill, 'There's Parson Beecher.' Says I, 'Taint hardlym my luck that v should come for a horse, an' by gracious here you are. There's a finger of Providence inter it, I' bet ten to one." "I trust so, sir,' and the parson tried to look serious over the matter.  &#xD;<pb n="4-5 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000003"/> PARSON BEECHER AD HIS HORSi. "Don't I tell yer Pll bet onto it? Ahl! here comes my ,-my -darling; Duster-that's his name. Walk him ht, this wayr: m." Sa wVas no  shan in the at of horse jockeying if he s a boy, and with a few artful but gentle touches "he uixght Dteer ;Uxp before the parson in splendid style. r  '.f sas afour legged peculiarity As to Tyars he I  besti of the, and would never be young again ':  1 ^ lg in the reachh, innocent of fat as he 'Was of uty;, h  had a-eyeinX his, head that loked wied Dii hisevouSsthetasi miguhg  "Whoa, beauty!"' said Gouger, as'the anima" I can to a wistU '4Now yer reverence, just tke a look at him. tsayshow he is han'somebut he's dieadfiU good. M    !gohp 'spciayfor a mitaiter's horse. Hes ,a awful wiui' critter, pure .Hanibletonian, and when ye get OiWi with imj yz cane just talk with him right alng. ok at his fe,t ;,  legs, arin' they clean? XNeier saw any- naghleitter iniylif adr I've ^ee iin inthe horts' liess iLfl iiii^,^ ^        ^ ; viw. O 'o mii - r Fi d^      leet^    amiute- Whyblesa ; i, aa'nu oI 01ttfe I. ;:  &amp;aone .his &amp; mile i 2t 40 to rgon i:[ i, . t ita h s-$'ingle season.- But of course has seen his fastest days, or he wouldn't be for sale; an' th s fst, an' dont, ttk much dus!t from anybody's gig. ? kind and gentle as a lamb-a three-year-old- gal could   Po PR, oil lilt A to t t  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7802-00000004"/> 6     PARSON BEECHiER  ND HIS HORSE. drive him; warranted sound and kind; and seein' as how it is you, an5 you'll speak a good word for me round 'mong yer flock, I'll let you have him for an even five hundred. There now, he's worth a cool thousand," and Gouger looked and spoke as thlough he was injuring himself for the good of the church. "But, my dear sir, I don't wish to pay so much for a ::horse; I only want a nice, quiet saddle-horse. I am getting pretty well along in years, and as I live some distance from the church I find the walk is getting rather too much for me." Gouger said he had often thought the walk too long-for the old parson, and then added:  He's cheap meat at that figure, parson." "I daresay he may be, but I don't call him a handsome animal by no means." "Ah, parson, you-knows how it is as well as I do; han'- some is as han'some does. Now yer see, parson, I knows what human natur, is as- well as I knows what a hoss is, an I knows as how it likes-to go fast, whether it is a parson or a sinner. Now you'd rather ride a boss as won'tTake dust -its human natur', and the jockey nearly drove his fore- finger into the palm of his left hand for emphasis. Parson Beecher smiled, and for a moment plead guilty by his looks, for to -tell the truth he did like to ride a horse that was just a trifle previous to all others. Gouger saw the old fellow's shell open, and in went the knife of his logic clear to the hilt:   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      7 "Now, this 'ere boss is just the animal you want. He's a Sunday boss, or he's a week-day hoss. He knows who's on him and whar he's agoin'. When you rides him to church he'll jog along like a deacon, an' when you're'out for pleas- ure during weekdays he'll git up an git as though Old Nick war arter him." "Yes, but the--the price," said the parson, hesita- tingly. "Now. parson, he'll last as long as you do, an' that'll be a long time yet I hope, an' he'll be good up to the home stretch. But I don\t wan't to be hard on the Cloth -what do you say at four hundred an' fifty?" The parson smiled, but shook his head. "Now you see," continued Gouger, " if -sell hin less 'an that I shall lose by the operation, an' of- course you wouldn't like me to do that. Hey! Sam, get up and speed him a bit."          . Sam was astride of Duster as quick as a monkey, and in a cloud of dust they disappeared dclown the road. "Git! Why he takes no dust from anybodiy. I tell you a man can't get much nearer heaven in this world than when he is on a hoss that won't take no other hoss's dust. Here he comes back." As he - spoke Duster flew past at a rattling pace, and the parson fairly trembled with delight, though at the same time he tried to hide the emotion. He made up his mind to have that horse.    .  &#xD;<pb n="8 (Illustration) -9 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000005"/>  &#xD;
               <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7802-00000006"/> 10    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. , Is four hundred and fifty the best you can do?," "On my honor as a man and good citizen, if I sold him less I should lose money." "Well, r'll take him," said the parson, going into his inside coat pocket for his money. "I know'd you would-parson, I know'd it. I'll give you a clean bill of sale, and-- I say, have you got a saddle and bridle?- "No, I shall have to buy them." i'. "Let me sell you 'em cheap as dirt Got: a first-class rig I'll sell you for -well,'-11 tell-you what I'll do: Give me five hundred for -Duster and a good saddle and bridle- yes, I' ll-do better, I throw in a halter." - The parson made no reply but followed Gouger into the stable. The result was he got the old man's five hundred dollars, and in return the parson got his horse and the trappings.  Sam had Duster harnessed in no tine, and when tra- derand tradee came out of the house, .where they had been to transact their business, the horse was ready to go over to its new owner.  Duster had "a history that is not uninteresting. His g a, bItoi pedigree was somewhat obscure, although his different owners fitted one to him that was eminently high-toned and taking, save with thoroughbred jockeys and turfmen, who simply recognized .Duster as an eccentric, rough-and- tumble, with lots of "go" in him but not to be depend-   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.     " ed upon in a square race. He was "found" about twelve  years ago by somebody who evidently didn't consider it much of a find after all, since a tin-peddler bought him, still an unbroken colt, for ten dollars in trade. The tin-peddler broke him and christened him Duster, and in return the colt broke his cart and scattered the man's tinware and notions along the road between two vil- lages. The peddler gathered up his stock-inrl-trade, much of it second-hand by this time, and followed his animal into the next village, where he had been stopped, and proceeded to wollop him. Duster showed his spirit by biting off his owner's southwest ear, a portion of his nose, and pulling a mouthful of hair out of his, head, after which he put both heels through the dasher and laid down on the shafts to rest.  . That peddler became discouraged, and swapped him for an old mare that had long ago been turned out to die. But he concluded that he had come off lucky, and Whistled Yankee Doodle asi he lefit town as well as his damaged head-piece -would allow. His new owner attempted to make Duster work with a mate at a plow, but at this he revolted and turned upon his mate, kicked out an eye, broke two ribs, landed the farmer head first into' a furrow, and then ran away. The farmer never told his love. Ho o let Dster go. In course of time he was again found by the pound- master of a straggling village, who placed him in pound to /   &#xD;<pb n="12 (Illustration) -13 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000007"/>  &#xD;
               <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7802-00000008"/> "    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. o await an owner. He kept him six months, and as no owner ever came Duster was put up at auction. The charges for keeping, fine, etc., amounted to abouat a hundred dollars, but when the "find" was brought out and voted the ugliest looking horse that ever walked on four legs, the first and only bid that could be obtained was ten dollars. This was the figure he was knocked down at, and the purchaser looked as though he had rather have been knocked down ten dollars' worth himself than to have taken the horse even at that figure. From this it may reasonably be inferred that Duster was not a prepossessing or hopeful looking animal. Well, his new owner tried to work him, but he wouldn't work. He bit a piece out of a hired man, kicked over a row of bee hives and everybody got stung, after which he was tried in a chase, and after showing a mile or two of extraordinary speed he succeeded in running away and breaking the farmer's neck. Then he was turned into a lonely, out-of-the-way pasture, in holes; that somebody would steal him, but as his fame had got pretty well noised about by this :time nobody would touch him and he was boss of the whole pasture for a year. At last somebody did steal him, and everybody rejoiced. W:next hear of him in another part of the country, hitched to a peddler's cart again. For some reason or other he behaved very well for a year or so, during which period he was swapped and traded several times. At last a   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      15 country horse jockey got hold of-him, and found out that he could go-go fast. He won a race with him, and sold the horse for three hundred dollars. Then he got beaten badly on account of stopping to kick the driver out of his seat, and his owner was glad to get one hundred dollars for him. But still everybody knew that Duster had "go" in him. He passed through several hands, and at last Gouger got possession of him and sold him to Parson Beecher, as be- fore related, although he had greatly improved in appear- ance since his coltish days. - The parson walked around his new bargain once or twice with evident satisfaction.- His big benevolent face  beamed with the joy that was swelling in his honest old heart, and it is doubful if he would have taken two hundred dollars for his bargain as it stood. Taking the bridle rein he led the horse -to0 :the edge of a watering trough, and mounting it -he threw "'Inself into * i the saddle with all the agility of  - youthful jockey. Duster felt lis oats in an instant, but he also felt that the man who was on him was a thorough horseman, or at least no novice in the art. "Lord bless you, sir," said Gouger, holding up both hands in admiration. "Yer look at least twenty-five years younger. Go it!"           ,  The parson smiled and felt that Gouger had told the truth, and nodding-"good-by" to the jockey, he let Dus- ter have his head and started briskly down the road.  &#xD;<pb n="16-17 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000009"/> 16     PARSON BEECHER AND HS- HORSE. Gouger walked after him a few steps, watching the cloud of dust into which his victim had vanished, while the little darkey groom stood on his head and yelled with delight. Duster was in his glory, and so was Parson Beecher, although he began to think there was even more "go" in him :than he had bargained for. He kicked up a fearful eloud" of dUst, but would: take none from any other nag on the road. t   This-pleased the parson wonderfully, for if he liked one thing more than another it wasa fast horse. But there was aslight drawhack, or rather there wasn't a drawhack at all; for- :Duster: had taken- the bit between his teeth and the-idea into his headto "go," and the parson could not restrain!m with all his strength. '  In Vain-he "sawed' the bit, in vain he pulled, in vain  he hallooed "whoa!" -in vain he coaxed. Duster was out on a lark, and had no0 notion; of being- interfered with, If the parson didn't+ ik the sport ':e;could get off. But the parson didhke It, only he metoto many people on the road whom he knew, some of whom held up their hands and hung out their eyes dreadfully at the spectacle of Parson Beecher riding- through the town like a whirlwind, and on such a hort, too. They appeared to think that the old man had mounted Satan's Mercury and was imitating the renowned John GiHlpin.- At last the hors came in sight of the village-tavern   &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7802-00000010"/> 18    PARSON BEEOHER AND HIS HpRSE. where any number of sporting men and owners of fast nags usually congregated, and the bare idea of being seen riding in this direction at such a rate was almost too. much for the old fellow. What should he do? Duster seemed only just warming up to thefun, and had he been going in almost any other direction the parson would have been as ready for it-as the horse could possiblI have been. Horse after horse on the road attempted to have a brush with him, but it was no go, for .Duster showed them his heels in the half of no time. Everybody on or behind a horse wondered what the apparition meant. The poor old man almost fainted, and at last, in his des. peration, he raisedhtmself in the saddle and threw his arms around )Duster neck, pleading with him  to "whoa!" "whoa! for goodness' sake."- Duster liked oats no better than disobedience, and he lookled as though he joined heartily in the laugh of the crowd who stood on the tavern veranda as they flew past it. It was a sight to behold thesaid old parson clinging around the horse's neck in the" agony ofv disgust and despair.  But matters came to a head in a very few moments. Duster had travelled that road before, although it is safe to say he never had a parson on his back and neck before, or any one else, in fact, who took such a method of reducing his gait. Go it, old man!? shouted one.   ll'  PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.     9 "Fetch him down, boss!" said another. "Take him by the tail and he'll go the other wayl"  "Hang to him, pop!" "Blood will tell!"  "He's playing Injun!- "Duck!" shouted still another, as the horse turned the corner and headed for. the tying-rail, where he had often been before it would seem.'. The wisdom of this advice was evident, for the edge of the shed under which he must necessarily ride was scarcely high enough to clear the rider's heacld unless he lowered it; considerably.  Dashing under this shed and up to the tying-rail, be- hind which the hostler was at work, Duster flew like a "hot ball." What little hair the good old parson had was standing on end, and his two eyes stood out like those of a lobster about to be cooked. Up to this rail flew .Duster and stopped, but in such a sudden and unceremonious manner {hat he threw the parson over his head, and he would undoubtedly have gone home with a broken neck had it not been for the hostler, on whose shoulders he alighted, as he was stooping over a tub of water. As it was, the parson saved his own head and drove that of the astonished hostler, shoulders and all, into the tub of water, exactly as the artist has re-  presented it. The parson turned a hand-spring summerset, and landed in a sitting-dclown posture nearly a rod beyond.  &#xD;<pb n="20-21 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000011"/> 20    PARSON -BEECHBR AND  -IS, H OEf)RSV /  Duster whinnied, the parson grunted, iand the hos tler swore, He swore roundly, but the poor parson hadn' - breath enough left -in his 'body to remonstrate, if, indeed he really blamed the man for doing so. The hostler wiped and danced- the water out of his es,r and then .tried to find somebodyto fight with. He ;was sissing-hot fr it. 'He looked at the po or old man a he sat there utterly confounded, confused, and grunting, thut his heart fo-bade-him-:to seeksatisfaction on him. Sa hetum rne to Dusr who  ill stood as though admiring th= JR^b oha ahtdk dpn^. HH e 4dO lod up huisfit as though to give -him- one on the nose in return for what he :had done, Jbut the hqorss op ned hio moPu  and s looked so wi ked that he conq u4ed to seek v-ngeanpee elsewhere. "Fat: the divil does yees mane, at all, at all? Bacd luck to thjez two o' yees  - my neek -is Aearly broke," said Pat turning from one to the other. - : My dea friend, said the parson, faintly, .you have uave my life'    fat   divil business had I ter gave yer life, ye ula;hythin?: W ho are yes, anyhow?-" - Im a intnister,- whispereddthe p Urson faintly. "Och, the divii's own ministepr yees must be surely, -ter be rdin such a baste as that," and he hehe turned gain to- wards ..er with -his clenched fist, but "old wicked' agin opening his mouth, Pat pocketed his fist and con- tinued his growling.  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7802-00000012"/> 22    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. By this time a crowd of loungers rushed in and took a' survey of the scene. The parson still remained in his lame position on the ground. - Pat still dripped and cursed, and Duster looked approvingly on. A loud laugh was the most natural thing in the world under the circumstances, and there was no bashfulness manifested by anybody except those who had been instru- mental in bringing the entertainment about. One or two of the crowd recognized the parson, and went to his assistance.  "Are youlhurt, Mr. Beecher?" "Well, replied --the old man, as they assisted him to his feet, "I believe there are no bones broken, but it was a dreadful jar, a dreadful hoist."- "I should say so." .       o "The old varmint! ejaculated the parson, shaking his fist at Duster, who in return shook his head and opened his ugly mouth. But the ruling passion with the old man-the rendering good for evil-was strong even under such provoking cir- cumstances, and 'he ordered Pat to give- the horse a round measure of oats. "Och, be dad, I'd see him starved fust," said Pat, giving himself a finishing shake to get the water out of his ears. The old parson was assisted to a seat on the inverted tub into which he had unintentionally thrust the head of unoffending Pat, and one of the party started for the bar-   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      23 room for a " cocktail "--a medicine that many sporting men resort to when anything is the matter with them, whether it be a broken neck or a stroke of bad luck. Not a few take "cocktails" for corns, and have corns from one year's end to another. "Where did you get that horse, parson?" asked one. "Bought him from Mr. Gouger, just now," replied the old man with a sigh.  ! "And is this your first trial?"And a laugh went round. The parson looked up appealingly, as much as to say, "I acknowledge it, gentlemen; please reserve your com- ments." "How much did you pay for him, if it is a fair ques- tion?" asked one.         - "I wonder where Gouger picked him up?" queried another. - "Lots of material in him," suggested another, and so the questions and chaffing went on for. some time. "The fact is, gentlemen, you are mistaken. The horse is a good one, only we have not got used to each other's ways yet, that's all." A shout of laughter followed this, and one or two at- tempted to slap Duster approvingly on the hind quarters, but he resented any such familiarity with him in such a way with heels anid mouth that the job was hastily aban- doned.   &#xD;<pb n="24-25 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000013"/> 24    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.  Out, ye four-legged villin; does yees want ter play the divil wid another praste? said Pat, getting behind one of the party add shaking his fist. - "Will some one give my horse oats?" asked the parson. "I will see to it, pop," said another hostler, who had been attracted to the spot. By this tnime the man who had been after the " cocktail" returned. "Try this, brother Beecher, it will do you good." "What is it?" asked the old man feebly. "It is a mild extract of corn andjuniper; it is excellent for brmises and sudden stops." "You are quite sure that it is all right, are you?" "Oh, certainly. Drink it right off." The-parson glanced at the concoction, the flavor of which rose gratefully to his nostrils, and then to the young man who so kindly proffered it to him. "Well." He sighed and hid the " cocktail "-that is, he drank it. He contemplated its quality and its mission a moment, with his eyes fixed on vacancy, and then ventured to smack his lips and pronounce it good. In ten minutes he seemed like a new man. He rose to his feet and felt himself. Then he smiled and looked at the party, as much as to say,' "Rather rough on an old man, was't it?  "My good friend," said he, addressing Pat, the hostler, "I am sorry that I was the means of hurting you," - , "^   &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7802-00000014"/>  26    PARSON BEECHEA  AND HIS HORSE "Pshaw; best thing that ever happened Pat; he hasn't been so well washed in a month," said one of the party. Faith, an' if yees don't get rid o' that baste there'll be a pulpit vacant before long," growled Pat. "rm afraid so," replied the parson, smiling. "It isn't every day yees'll find a dacent man to fall on whon yer thrown," added Pat. "You are right, but PI'll yet break him off his tricks," replied the old man. It was evident that the "cocktail" was beginning to work and was givinghim new spirit. The crowd that had gathered gradually dispersed when it was found that no necks or bones were broken and that the old man was again on his pins as lively as ever, leaving him with Pat and Duster, who was quietly grinding his ration of -oats. The parson walked up to and around his lively bargain. He patted him fondly and familiarly, and called him pet names until Duster, if he could understand anything, must have concluded that he did a big thing in pitching his rider head-foremost over the tying-rail "Be jabers," said Pat, "I think yees must be a praste if yees can talk blarney to the loikes o' that baste." "Kindness will subdue the most obdurate," quietly re- marked the parson. , Obdurate I - Is that what yet call it? Faith, I thought it was the divil's own cussedness." The parson smiled and patted his horse, who really did appear to appreciate the only kind-words and caresses that   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      27 had been tendered him, for being tendered hard words and blows makes a horse tough quite as much as it does a man. The parson was a kind-hearted man, and he thought favor- ably of his horse-also of that "cocktail." "Patrick, here is a quarter of a dollar, will you have the kindness:to procure me another glass of that medicine?" Pat's mouth began to extend, and gradually a grin of the hugest dimensions spread itself over his rough face. "And, Patrick, if there is enough change left, I think it would be advisable for you to take Something of the kind, I feel that it has done me a sight of good." Pat took the quarter and started for the bar-room, where he procured the "cocktail ' and followed the suggestion of the parson in nearly a tumblerful of raw whiskey. This time the parson partook of his medicine standing. Pat stood watching him with a broad grin on his face, while Duster pricked his ears forward and the whole in- tellectual part of him looked like a tickled mule. This through with, our hero settled his score with the landlord and ordered his horse to be brought up to the door. But when Pat went to get him    Duster again lopped back his long earsjand opened his mouth at him. One or two others. tried to "bring him up,", but abandoned the job.  So the parson resolved to try it himself. He went up to his horse and the beast looked amiable in a minute. He took himr by the bridle and ledb him up to the horse-block, where he mounted without the slightest trouble.  &#xD;<pb n="28-29 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000015"/> iSON BEECHER AND HIS HfORSE. Bowing pleasantly, and still with an air of triurmhahe turned his horse towards the highway and started. The animal behaved very well-indeed, until another horse came up behind him, when he stopped, and deliberately turned square about -to take a look at the supposed rival, during which time the other horse and rider shot past him at a sharp trot. Duster's metal was up in an instant, and whirling again he set .himself agoing at a rattling pace to get out of that other horse's dust. Parson Beecher was a good rider, and it was well for- him that he was, for when Duster was all in motion he "rocked," "paced," "trot- ted" and "galloped" all at the same time. But he had :hard work, too, this time, for the horse he was after was a c stepper" and took but little dust from anything o'n the road. -But Duster went for him, not against the parson's 'feelings either, and for a mile or so the contest was spirited. Gradually he gained on him, while -the rider of the rival was giving: his horse the whip at every leap. The parson "clucked" now and then, but in all other respects he was fully occupied in keeping on top of the saddle. -The race was not a long one, for Duster was soon giving dust to his rival, greatly to the chagrin of the owner, who hailed the parson as he was flying by. After a few rods he brought Duster down a trifle, and by a little coaxing managed to get him to allow the beaten horse to approach.  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7802-00000016"/> 30     PARSON BEECHEI AND HS' HORSE. "Where did you get that horse, pray?" asked the man.- "Ihave just bought him, sir, of a man by the name: of Gouger." "Gouger!" and the man laughed heartily. "Why he is the most unmitigated scoundrel in these parts. Where did he get him, I woler?" "I couldn't tell you, sir." "If it's a fair question, what did you give?" "About five hundred dollars." The man let go a long whistle of astonishment. "!s he sound?" "I should say so, sir,' replied the parson honestly. "rIl give you a thousand dollars for your bargain." "No thank you, I didn't buy him to sell; good day," and bowing to the man and "clucking" to his horse he was soon on the road to-the parsonage.   . "So, so, thought he. "If I am not mistaken, I have a bargain. It is evident that his former owners have failed to get along with him on account of his viciousness; but I will treat him kindly and make him the best as well as the a fastest horse about here. A thousand dollars, eh? I wouldn't take two thousand, would I, -Duster?" he asked, patting him on the neck kindly. It seemed to be an-understood thing between them that each considered the other just about right, and when they arrived honie the parson displayed his new purchase with a deal of pride. He recounted the -favorable Dart of his   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.       31 achievements since he had bought him, together with the thousand-dollar offer that he had had. His wife didn't like the looks of the animal. He didn't look a whit like a minister's horse, and a few of his neighbors suggested that the animal looked a trifle "cranky." $ But the parson's mind was made up. He loved the horse, and was determined to keep him. While installing him in his stable he talked familiarly with him regarding his new quarters, and even went so far in his confidential  confab as to mention several owners of fast horses whom they would in the future get the best of. As the week wore away the parson became more and more in love with his animal, and although lhe refrained from racing he took him out on the turnpike every day for exercise, which exercise generally consisted in letting Duster have his own. way in dealing with the other horses whom he encountered, which way was-away ahead of them. In fact quite a little scandal had already been set agoing among his parishioners who had either seen or heard of the parson's racing horse. But as yet these gossipings had not reached his ears, although it is to be doubted if- he would have cared a snap if they had, so completely was he in love with his horse. But he went on writing his sermon during his leisure from attending to Duster, and when Sunday came he was up betimes and had a long confidential talk with his favor-       .,         /     &#xD;<pb n="32 (Illustration) -33 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000017"/>  &#xD;
               <pb n="34-35 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000018"/> 84    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS iORSE. ite, regarding how he must behave during the day. He was a minister's horse now, and when going about on Sunday he must always look and act in a serious and digni- fied manner.              * The parson's wife was an invalid and never attended church, and of course had no use for a horse, although the parson promised to buy a carriage and give herta ride now and then. - The old lady said he needn't- trouble himself about it; she wouldn't trust-what-little there was left of her behind such- a beast on no- account. Inr fact, nobody spoke a good word for his anid:ma {nd the parson began to. take itVmuch to heart. Well, when it came time to go to; church he placed his sermon in his pocket and' mounted his horse -Duster, who- was somewhat impatient; and had the ( parson known him as well then as he-learned him afterwards" he would have seen that he meant fun. - The-distant church bell was ringing for the last time in the morning when he set out. There were several ungodly people out with fast nags, and Duster, soon forgetting what his master told him about his Sunday behavior, closed- in for what "brushes" he could scare up. In fact, he seemed to be red hot for fun and frolic, greatly to the disgust ol his owner. When they had arrivedl to within about-a quarter of a mile of the church, Duster took, the bit in, his teeth and began to strike out -at a terrific pace. ITa vain did the ,.b   &#xD;<pb n="36-37 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000019"/> 36  .  PARSON BEECHER AND HIS 4ORSE. parson attempt to argue and reason with him, to hold him down to a Sunday trot; go he would in spite of every- thing. Mr. Beecher's hat flew off, and the figure that he presented as he rode past the church will never be for- gotten by the members of his flock who rushed to the door to see him. The involuntary fast man was almost ready to swoon with mortification and anger. He "sawed" the bit, but Duster held on like grim death, and went like the very Old Boy's blind nag. The parson tried to pull him to one side of the road, but no; he was out for fun and 'meant to have it. The ' pillars " of the church were horrified. It had been whispered about somewhat--the old parson's crazy horse with which he was in love; but that he should so far forget himself and his duty as at Christian minister as to ride like mad Jack Gilpin right past his gathered flock n the Sab- bath day, it was too much to trust their own senses with almost. They counselled together, and waited for his  return.  Now let as follow the parson and his horse, and then we can form some kind of a conclusion as to how long they would have to wait. As before stated, Duster was out for fun. Passing everything on the road, he again made for the tavern, where he appeared to be used to going, and where he had once before " spilled-" the worthy parson on top of the hostler, Pat.   ^-r /       '- '^ ^ ';'V '^  . I ! .,.,. flu  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7802-00000020"/> 88    PARSON BEECH1I AND HIS HbRSE. No argument of words and not a bit of anything else would turn him -go he would; and while the patrons of the place were discussing the great horse-race that was to come off that day, at the course a mile or two away, they were startled by seeing Duster and the parson again sweep into the yard and up towards the tying-rail. But this time he cut a less ludicrous figure, for although he had no hat, on he was seated naturally in the saddle, and appeared to have become mournfully resigned to his fate, whatever it might be. In fact, he hoped he might meet ,  with the man who offered him the thousand dollars for his bargain;- even though it was Sunday he thought he would take it. Duster had " go" in him, but he had too much of his own way about it. The horse held up in tolerable good order at the tying- rail, andtheparsondismounted in pretty good condition and more at his leisure than before. A crowd of admirers flocked about him in a minute, for the fame of the horse had got noised abroad and speculation was rife as to what the parson intended to do with him. Duster's pedigree had by this time been pretty well settled among the horsemen, as given several pages back. He was a dangerous horse to bet against as well as a dangerous one to own. The ques- tion still was, what would he do with him? The parson, as may well be surmised, was thoroughly out of humor at the conduct of his nag, and was not slow in telling how rascally he had behaved. But several jockeys i    -'   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      39 gathered around and praised the horse until the old man began to be ashamed of himself for even thinking hard of a beast that could beat anything on the road, even if he was a trifle wicked. "Try him to harness, Pop," suggested one. "I think he would behave better behind a carriage," said another; and various arguments were in a short time brought forward to prove that Duster would be perfectly lamb-like and Sunday going if he was driven in' harness. The parson resolved to try it, and no time was to be lost either, for it was now fifteen minutes past church time, and he must be back or there would be no services. "Have you a carriage you could lend me?" he asked of the landlord. "I have nothing with wheels to it, except a sulky," re. plied mine host. . .       - . "What is a sulky?" asked the parson. C Why, a two-wheeled carriage." "a Well,let me have that. Necessity knows no law,why should she know propriety? I must get back to my flock without delay."  - ,      '          ' "Pat, you and Johnhiitch the parson's horse up in the red sulky."  - : . After c onsiderable bother this was accomplished. "jNow: then have you a hat you canlend me? I lost my: own on the road."     ; ' "Let me see-I have a cap, if that would do" replied the landlord.  o ,'-                     &#xD;<pb n="40-41 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000021"/> 40     PARSON BEECUiE AND HIS HORSE. "' Yes, it will have, to do if you can do no better." The landlord disappeared and in aminute or so came out with a jockey-cap, which he placed upon the old man's head. "There, now you are all right, Pop, just let me help you to get in."  '. Thank you, you are very, kind., The landlord assisted him into the sulky and handed - him the reins.  Now then, keep a firm hand on him and you will have no. trouble." It was not without some misgivings that the parson drew the lines over, his favorite. He got a good send off, however, and started-down the road towards the church with a great deal of honesty. He trotted away so gentle that the party who stood on the veranda of the tavern said it was all right, and that there would be no more trouble with him.  In truth, Duster was behaving first-rate, and {he pas- tor began to read over his sermon fas he trotted quietly along towards- where it was to be delivered.-   " + But Dusterhad not yet had his sport by long odds. After going a mile or so very nicely. het came to a road which led to the race-course, and where there was , Sunday race, free for all? comers, for a nice little purse. - Duster scented the battle from afar, and darted down this road like a streak of tallowed lightning, so to speak. So sudden was this new  departure, the parson was   tl,.1 i ,. ---ow        7  ! ;s [}1.Sw   &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7802-00000022"/> 42    PARSON BEECHESi AND HIS H(RSE. nearly thrown backwards from his seat, and in catching suddenly at the reins he lost his sermon. Here was more trouble for the good old man. He tried with all his might to put a stop to Duster's little game, but it was no go, at. least no go on his part but all on Duster's. He headed for the course like mad. A casual observer would have failed to see anything resembling a ministerin the appearance of the parson as he rode along. In the first place, the horse himself was a flat contradiction to anything religious or steady-going, and then the sulky, the jockey's cap worn by the driver, and- the -peculiar "sporting look which he had, would have deceived almost anybody, although the good man was a victim to circumstances beyond his control. Reaching the main gate, which stood before the race course, Duster gave even another spring forward and dashed, in upon the track. The principal race of the day was just on the point of being run. The horses had just .go't the word "go,"' as Duster whirled in and joined them. Here was sprt tun- looked for. -Two other horses 'were entered, but Duster loke fk e, hos'       e at once took the lead and maintained it to-the end. ,. ..  As he flew past the judges' stand'the half-vexed,- half- pleased parson saw the announcement thrown out "2-40," while the other horses were distanced.  The parson did not stop to claim the stakes or the   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      43 honors. Just as soon as he could get Duster's head towards the gate he guided him out of- it. By this time the animal had got all he cared for just then. In fact, he was pretty well blown.  At last he managed to bring him down to a walk, and, finally, to a stand-still. Heavens and earth! I what had this wicked horse done? Why, how many sermons had he preached against this 'very sport, this very wickedness, horse-racing on the Sabbath, and now what had he done but engaged in one himself? And what is more, he had beaten all other competitors. Ah I there was just a grain of crude consolation there. Duzter had proven himself the fastest nag on the course. "2-4O!" whew! There was glory in that, even if it was Sunday and he should have been preaching while he s was racing. The 0old man almost chuckled as he contem- plated it, and how taken aback those sports must be at the sudden and unlooked for victory over them. It served them just right; they had no business to be racing on the Sabbath. e again renewed his love for Duster, and mentally raised his price to three thousand dollars, and with no particular desire to sell even at that figure. But while he was thinking and inwardly congratulating himself, he happened to think of his waiting flock, and suddenly the glory of his achievement vanished and he' begun to feel very bad indeed. He began to look about him. It was about where he  &#xD;<pb n="44 (Illustration) -45" xml:id="VAC7802-00000023"/> s k ill AC j. PROM-   PARSON BEEC ER AND HIS HORSE.      45 now rested that he had lost his sermon. He got down out of the sulky and began to hunt about in quest of it. Duster remained perfectly passive while his master was searching for the sermon, and could his facial expression have been interpreted it would doubtless have shown men- tal anxiety for those lost words of wisdom and comfort. While searching thus the parson happened to come across a copy of the well-known comic paper, Wild Oats, which some one had lost. He picked it up and glanced at its contents. Duster took a few steps forward and looked over his shoulder. The honest face of the parson immediately assumed a comical expression, while Duster pricked up his ears and appeared to enjoy the fun contained in the illustrations quite as much as his master did. In fact, the old express sion of " making a horse laugh " was fullyverified. Dus- ter laughed and so did the parson. But he suddenly remembered himself. What was he doing? what day was it? who was he, and what were the exigencies of the occasion? Where was his flock? what were they doing, and what was the opinion relative to his absence? X With this flood of convictions the old man suddenly looked serious, and so did Duster. That horse actually looked sorry for what he had done, and for what he had obliged his master to do. The search was resumed, and after a long time the par-  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7802-00000024"/> "    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. son found his sermon and again got into his sulky. He spoke to Duster, and that sagacious animal looked around to see what the matter was, or what new; trouble had overtaken his master.  "Get up, Duster," suggested the parson. Duster appeared to understand it, and yet he hadn't a fair comprehension of what was required of him, or, if he had, he resolved on having his own way about getting up." So he kicked up behind. "Whoa!",yelled the parson, and Duster kicked up again. "Get up," said the preacher. But Duster only "got up" behind, as before, and this time in such a way as to break the shafts of the sulky. The parson shouted lustily and grabbed Duster by the tail. He held on fo5ear life; it was a tail of woo not "whoa" with him just then,and he felt as though the very fates were against him, an hat Satan himself had certainly been instrumental in m kxingin up with that horse. But regrets did not save him. Over. he went into the dirt, tearing his clohes and bruising him terribly. Dster did not attempt to run away, on the contrary he quietly turned around and took a look at the old man as he was struggling to his feet. ) Any man could have bought that horse then for a mere song. The old parson not only held the animal cheap, but he felt dreadfully cheap9himself he felt dreadfully cheap himself -    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.     47 The thought of what would be said of him at church and among his firiends was now uppermost in his mind. He gathered himself up as best he could and begun to con- template the situation. Duster looked as honest as Cooper's cow," and a stran- ger would never have suspected for an instant that he had anything to do with the parson's discomfiture.  But something must be done. He was completely cov- ered with dirt. His swallow-tail coat was ripped up the back clear to the collar; his nose/was completely skinned, and about the various portions of his anatomy he felt thiat he had been sadly used, and looked as though he had been through a threshing machine. Haps or mishaps, time enough had already been lost; and now he resolved to trust only to his personal legs, and make his way back to his flock just as quick as they would let him do so. Taking Duster by the bridle he hobbled along, leaving the disabled sulky to "sulk " by the roadside. The horse looked sorry enough, and instinctively concluding that misery delights in company, he went lame first inM one foot, and then on another, as he humbly followed the demoralized parson.    . In this condition he reached the -church, and was met  by a crowd of its members.      - "Why, Parson Beecher, what uponiearth ails you?" "Are you hurt?"   * *, '.'  &#xD;<pb n="48-49 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000025"/> 48     PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. "Lordy massy, he's bleedin'!"  "Isn't it too bad-l" and a dozn other like expressions,: greeted the old man as-he led- hi horse into their presence. I am not much hurt, my friends,' said the parson, wiping the mud and perspiration- from his brow," but I'm dreadfully put about." Let me take him, parson; I'll fix himf' said oneof the deacons, approaching Duster as thouigh to chastise him.  Duster opened his mouth and lopped back his ears wickedly, and the deacon stood :back without asking. "Whoa! you varmint 1" - he'exclaimed, while the entire congregration gathered around at a respectful distance I think we have had about enough of this," suggested ' Deacon Doleful, with a 0look of pious indignation upon his pinched face.  . /  "-Whiat shall be done?" asked the parson. "Why, go on with the meetin'," said another deacon. -"In this plight?" he asked, looking at himself. I'll lend you my coat," said a j6,ly member. "Thanks; I wish I could also borrow your whole Akin., replied the parson, at whichi everybody, not maliciously pious felt/that they must laugh..   / . The deacons and the sorrowful sisterin looked'- horrified at the worldliness of their oldparson, to th'nk that he would i be guilty of uttering a joke or saying a funny thing anyhow. But the dilapidated parson took his horse round to the shed and tied him securely, after which he exchanged ti ,    --  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7802-00000026"/> 50    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. coats with his accommodating brother, and made himself as presentable as possible. - He thought how much good another one of those medicinal cocktails would do him at this time, but as there was no such a thing as getting one, he took some water, both internally and externally, and then entered the church. The excited congregation were allseated again, and, with the exception of a mischievous titter that ran around among the younger persons, everything was as still as it should have been. The deacons looked around and frown- ed on those who presumed to smile, and presently all was silence. The parson had by this time become composed enough to know what he was about, and proceeded to harmonize matters by giving out a hymn, after which he went through with the other and usual devotional exercises with much more force and spirit than might have been ex- pected.  But it required many more frowns from the deacons, and many stiff upper lips on the part of those whose risibles were easily excited; for the battered nose and the general "git up" of the old preacher would have provoked a laugh from a statue almost. The morning services were over with at last, and the parson led his horse home, leaving the congregation to manage the Sunday-school in the usual way. The occurrences of the morning created more food for   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      51 comment than the lessons did. The mothers of the church knotted themselves together and canvassed the parson's little adventure in all kinds of ways, although the general impression seemed to be that he should have known better than to have bought such a horse.    / The deacons and the leading lights of the flock also talked the matter over with great gravity.- To them it seemed entirely inexplicable. That a man of his age and position should have made such a show of himselfwas more than they could - understand. One or two of them hinted that the old man was slightly given to the allurements of fast horseflesh, and this point produced much additional sensation. In the afternoon the parson again took his place in the pulpit, dressed with his accustomed neatness, although a bad limp and a stiffened gait generally told that the rough usage he had received in thee morning had produced its effect upon him  This created him lots of sympathy, and when the services were over several of his flock gathered arouind and condoled with him, although those done up in the tightest religious corsets kept away and coldly started for home. The parson was not slow to note this action on the part of those who should have sympathized with him, and as he trudged and limped towards his home he entertained no very Christian thoughts regarding them. Had they mani- - ested any love or sorrow for him, had they suggested to  &#xD;<pb n="52-53 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000027"/>         . PARSON BEECHER AND HIS iiORSE. * him kindly that he had better dispose of his horse, he would have done so without loss of time.  As it was, he went directly to the stable, and held a communion with- Duster "No old fellow, I won't part with you now, if I have to with them- first," he said, encouragingly, as he patted the horSe's neck.  Dster appeared to understand it and whinnied ap- proval, lopping back his ears, and again bringing them for- ward with  snap. When the parson asked him if he was going to- be a" better -horse. in the future, Duster fairly da-nced affirmatively, and' then the parson gave him some hay, and left him alone, as much as to say, "This is the bond between us for your future good behavior." The next day he ordered a new set of harness; but the messenger made a mistake, and carried it to the house of Deacon Doleful, much to his consternation. By this means it became known that the parson did not intend to part with his fast horser; but, on the other hand, he was actually-trapping him out in regular sporting array. This news was quickly spread around among the faithful, and great indignation was caused thereby. Theffult-finders' and traducers increased every day, and not a few averred that they could detect slang in his pray- ers and- hrse-talk in his sermons, so certain were they that the old preacher had been seduced into the vile ways of the world through the instrumentality of that dreadful horse.   it'll IN  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7802-00000028"/> 54    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. In the meantime Parson Beecher was fast giving him- self away, not to the fleshpots of Egypt, but to horseflesh of the choicestkind, ,He was often seen on the road in the vicinity of where the owners of fast horses were wont to drive, and- he managed in a very short time to beat every- thing that came against him, and to win a reputation for Duster that any sporting man might envy.  The horse appeared to keep faith-with him, and to behave first-rate on all occasions. His former bad reputation was forgotten, and many a man tried to buy him, or to swap their fast nags for him, with " boot." All to no purpose, however. He was king of the road; and although the parson abstained from driving him on the course or elsewhere for money, yet he entered into all kinds of sport with him, and was the means of winning much money for those who bet upon him. But this was noised about and became a scandal upon the church ; not that he was not as good a preacher as ever, but his flock did not think so. The old ladies the mothers of the church took it greatly at h-art, and at length they formed themselves into a committee for the purpose of visiting the old man and inquiring into his conduct. They found him in his study, in his shirtsleeves, sur- rounded by. sporting papers and books on horses and horseracing. They were completely dumbfounded. This bee loved parson was clean gone, and no mistake. Sorrowfully they told their errand, and asked him why this was thus. ,  ./   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.       55 "Ladies, I shall not attempt to excuse myself if you consider that what I have done and am doing is wrong. I love my horse, and he loves me. I take infinite pleasure in driving him; and in knowing that he is the fastest horse in the country. I don't think you can find anything in the Bible that forbids a man from loving and enjoying a horse I think it does me good to partake of such enjoyment, and I propose to do so." "Oh, brother Beecher!" came in chorus from them all. But the old man was resolute, and all their " ohs " did not move him or convince him that he was wrong. Yet he was courteous and even more thani that. He invited them to stay to tea with him. At this there was a marked change in his favor, and so they all concluded to stay, for of all things a cup of tea and its natural accompaniments is the greatest female mollifier-that is, to those who have got past the delights of dress and are on the social home m stretch. It was quite late when they got up from the table, and as Sister Spumper lived fully three miles away, the, good old man volunteered to harness up his much talked-of horse and take her home. This was quickly agreed to, for she had a curiosity to see what the sensation wou"ld resemble, and besides, she could speak from positive knowledge regarding *the parsons proclivities, if ever there came a chance for doing so.- In a short time )Duster was harnessed to the new road- \?  &#xD;<pb n="56-57 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000029"/> 56    PARSON BEECEia AND HIS HORSE. wagon which the parson had brought, and Sister Spumper was assisted in. The horse was feeling splendidly, and the old man let him out a bit, or just enough to pass anything on the road. The slashing gait nearly frightened the wits out of the p ou s sister,'and she begged of the parson not to let him go do fast. But his assurances that he would drive slower, and that there was no danger, didn't amount to much, and when DUster espied a still faster horse ahead, he laid his long ears back and, startedcfor him. The frightened iistcr seizedvthearron around the waist.. "'For heaven's sake, do stop; we shall both of us be killed, and besides,;what will people say?  The: old man laughed, and Duster kept right down to buriess, but in order to beat his antagonist he went some distance beyond Mrs. Spumper's residence, occasioning much wonder and alarm in the household. But after he had passed this horse Duster quietly allowed himself to be turned about, and in a few moments stopped at the lady's house.-         , It Was a terrible thing all around.- Mrs. Beecher, how- ever, paid' but little attention to- what was said by every- body regarding. her husband, for she had enjoyed some spo0rt with Duster- in company with her husband, and be- sides she -concluded that -he knew his own business quite as well as she could tell it to him.  But the deacons and brethren of the church had taken -   as1 type !  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7802-00000030"/> 58    PARSON' BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. the matter in hand and resolved to pay the old man a visit and give him to understand that he must either dispose of his horse or resign his pulpit. They found- him dressing for the road, and his horse standing before the door demurely waiting. It did not take- them long to state the object of their visit, but finding the old man's love for D-Pster still strong they waxed wroth and at once came to the issue. "Well- sir, which had you rather give up, your fast horse or your pastorate?" "Mypastorate, calmly replied the parson. "That settles it," said two or three. "Play or payl!" put in the old man, as he stood boldly up before them. "You should be ashamed of yourself to bring such a scandal upon the church, and at your age too," said Deacon Doleful.'  "-Play or pay!" again replied the parson, smiling beautifully bland, and so childlike. "I am shocked," said Deacon Marrowhone, and they all held up their hands in pious horror. "Brethren, have you concluded your business?" The good men looked each. other inquiringly in the face -for a moment. and thenir concluded that they had finished, and that they might withdraw without offending the old man in the least. Left to himself the old man gave way to a long and serf-   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      59 ous course of reflection. Perhaps he was acting both foolish and wicked; perhaps he was acting too bold in doing as he did, and so when he wentout to exercise Duster he coaxed him down to a more pious trot and avoided all brushes. The next day he chanced to think of an old wig that he had in the house, and withit hexresolved to disguise himself and see if that would not abate the gossip and scandal. He tried it, and dressing in his-long duster and a broad brim- med hat he ventured forth for fun with Duster upon the road. Now, one of the gayest sports in the village, and the owner of one of the fastest horses, was Charley Doleful, the son of Deacon Doleful. He was fast, and so were his com- rades. -He was a great patron of the racecourse, and as. a natural consequence he took great delight over the conver- sion of Parson Beecher; and his parents, who had striven so hard to restrain his rapid career, found that it was like a warm shower upon their son's crop of wild oats, and lost all hope. While out that afternoon he saw the young man driving ahead of him, and wishing to show him that his was notthe fastest horse on the road, and to .take the conceit out of him a bit, he gave Duster iig head and - soon overtook the blood, who was doing his best to avoid it. The parson was confident in his disguise, but as he drove up alongside of the other team his hat and wig blew off and there he was} and no mistake. .          -   &#xD;<pb n="60-61 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000031"/> \ ua 60    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. "Hello, parson, I thought it was you," said Charley. Well, I beat you at all events," replied the parson, drawing up- his horse, and evidently feeling mean and discon- certed over it. A lad brought his hat and wig to him. The wig he crammed into his pocket, and thrust the hat over his head so far that it made quite as good a disguise as before. "I am glad to be beat by you, parson, and am glad to meet you on the road." Young man, horseracing is very bad business." "Yes. when you get beat." "No, it's a bad practice anyway; your father told me so:only the other day." "Heghe hanged X he is too slow and selfish for this world, and, no wonder he is trying to hedge for the next: You are right, and everybody with an ounce of brains or a spark of manly generosity says so." ^Do yu say so?"asked the parson smiling. "- ' To be-sure. What do you care for those old soulless fossils U S     - . . * ' But I may be turned put of my pulpit." :"Let her rip, what diyou care. Why, you have got twenty five thousand-, a -year in- that horse. That beats preaching all hollUwO,.: 7 The old man was silent, but he smiled with evident satis, faction as they drove quietly along side by side,  "Let us go to the tavern, and I will show you that your  .      .  ^     -   fq/,t/7I / ./f  ,      ' .  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7802-00000032"/> 62    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. conduct is approved by every respectable man in town, bar- ring fogies and garrulous old women." "Well, but I don't wish to be known as a sporting man." "Oh, I understand, you go in for the fun of the thing. They know that, and honor you for it. So come along, it's all right. I'm square, and will see you through anything." With this understanding, which evidently pleased the owner of Duster, they drove to the tavern, where there -were several well-known turfites and sporting men of the better class. They were just indulging in a bottle of cham- pagne as the parson and the deacon's son entered, and after an introduction they were invited to join them. The par- son hesitated. "Oh, you need have no fears; there is no one here but considers himself a gentleman, and would scorn to mention the facts outside. Come, join us.," It only required a little more argument of this kind to persuade-the parson to join them. He drank two glasses with them, and was just beginning to get interested in the proceedings when a great 'cry and hullibullu outside at. tracted their attention.+ Rushing out to the sheds they found that -Duster had become dissatisfied with the treat- ment -thaat Pat the hostler was bestowing upon him, and was holding him up by the seat of his breeches, while he was yelling all sorts of bloody murder. A few words, how- ever, from the parson caused Duster to open his mouth and   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.     63 drop the frightened wretch, who straightway made it his business to get out of the way. "Bad luck to the divids own baste," said Pat, when far enough out of the way ; "he has murtheredme entirely," and the way he rubbed what he usually sat down upon was in a manner by no means slow. After enjoying a good hearty laugh at the hostler's ex- pense, the parson gave him some money to get an antidote in the shape of whisky, which he applied internally, after which the party returned to the bar-room, and called for another bottle of wine. By the time this one was disposed of the entire party, and- the parson especially, was feeling well-feeling hiqh in fact.. But he was not quite dead to the truth that somebody might come in and catch them at their wine and hilarity, and so they went- into one of the private parlors for the pur- pose of having another bottle. Here the old man felt much more comfortable, and be- gan to give way to the influences which came upon him. The young fellows started a song and the: parson joined in it with much unction. They saw how things were working, quietly tippedthe wink to each other and- called- for another bottle. . While this was going on the old man engaged fer- ventiy with one of them in talking horse and sporting mat- ters generally. He was not only an enthusiast bout an apt scholar at the lessons before him, and- they all concluded that if it was  &#xD;<pb n="64-65 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000033"/> "    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. really true that it is hard to learn old dogs new tricks, the old parson must have been pretty thoroughly trained in his youth, and was just now coming upon it again. An other and another bottle was called for and disposed of, unti!.at length the old fellow was as mellow as a peach. He was even more than that, he was almost ripe enough to drop off. Some one proposed his health and called upon him for a speech. To this he assented without hesitation. "Get up on the table, Pop," said they, and with the as- sistance of. a couple of them he pulled off his coat and mounted the table. "Brethren-that is, friends, hie!" he began, as he held aloft his champsgne-glass, " horses is splendid. - Chaps as, hiel as drives 'em's splendid also. Here's your very -good health;, may you live long and prosper."  After saying about so mucl, and being loudly applauded, he concluded he had said about enough; and getting down all'in a heap from the table, he called loudly for his horse. Now, the same wine that: had made 'the old parson so oblivious to almost everything, had also put the devil into the heads of his youthful companions, and they resolved on further fun at the old man's expense. - One of the party staid with him in the room, while the others went out to bring his horse up to the door. Instead of doing so they found a. mule and cart which somebody had left standing under the shed, and so they brought that up to the door instead of Duster.   Oa ----- \l I   &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7802-00000034"/> "    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. Leading the old man carefully out, they assisted him into the cart and handed him the reins. Supposing himself to be behind his own horse, he called out to his companions to come on, aMid seehow easily he would beat them. -A couple of teams were about starting off, and relishing the sport, they accepted his challenge, and away they went, followed by the parson and the mule, and a yell of laughter that might have been heard to the next town. The old man was red-hot for sport, and the way he did yell to that poor mule would have shamed a Camechee chief. The sports held up their horses pur- posely, that the delusion might be kept up that he was behind Dustetr, and that everything else on the road was behind- him. Presently the board which had answered for a seat broke in two, and the old man fell backward into the bottom of the cart, still holding on to the lines, and yelling, "Whoa, Duster--whoa!" A dozen or more teams were following in his wake, including Duster, who was with much difficulty kept from rushing- to the front. ; ut at- last- that mule became dis- couraged, and without saying a word he lay down upon the: - shafts, snapping them both short off, and pitching the parson head foremost on top of him. The fright half sobered him, and hastily regaining his feet -he sat down upon the side -of the refractory and de- moralized mule with the intention of holding him there, ,  an.;   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.       67 but all the while crying in the most conciliatory and pacific way, "Whoa, DDuster-whoa!' The remainder of the party drove up, and, hastily dis- mounting, they inquired if he was hurt, and- finding that he was not they assisted him to his feet and the poor mule to his. - Both mule and minister loolked bewildered and dis- eouraged. They also looked demoralized. "What is the meaning of this?" asked the old man. CWhy, how happened you to take this mule?"- asked one of the party, in all sobriety. The parson looked first at the mule, and then at the crowd of young sports who stood around looking the very pictures of innocence. His face gradually became distorted by a look of wonder that was perfectly comical, and, after viewing it for a moment, the party could hold in no longer, but exploded into a perfect storm of laughter. "Young men," said the old parson, "I don't understand the meaning of this." a I will tell :you, Pop, the champagne got the best of you," replied onei of the sports, "Where is my horse--my beloved Duster .B" "Here he is," said Charley Doleful, pointing, to the horse, who stood close by contemplating the old man more in sorrow than in anger. "I think this is a trick; but, lat all events, I acknowledge the corn, as you fellows say.- Where- is my hat and coat, and  what shall be done with this animal and the broken cart?"  &#xD;<pb n="68-69 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000035"/> SON- BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.  ".Here is Pat, the hostler; he will take him back and , get the shafts mended," said Charley.           All right! Paddy, my man; take it to the wheel-   wright's, and -tell him to mend it and send the bill to me," said the.-parson.  -"No, no, that will never do; the whole affair would be-  come known. Tell him to send the bill to me," said Abe  Checksnap; a well-known wealthy sport.  "All right, 'sir,' said Pat, as he took the mule in hand. "And-tell the owner," continued Abe, "that the whole thing was the result of .a mistake, and that I will pay him  any damage: he- may wish. Now then, here is a couple of  dollars for yourself. Be off now, and see that you keep your mouth shut. "Och, be gab, I'd have it sewed up for two dollars," re  plied Pat, as -he commenced lashing together the splintered shafts of the donkey-cart." -Everything being arranged, the young men assisted the parson on with his coat and hat, and then into his own wagon, and handed him the reins. The fall and subse.  quent excitement perfectly sobered. the old man, and when he; once more drew the reins over Duster he appeared to  be himself agaiW quite as much as Richard ever was.  "Now, boys,'if any of you would like a brush, I think Duste and I can, acommodate you. "I'll go you-one for fifty, said Charley Doleful.  "Oh, no; I never bet," said the parson.    &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7802-00000036"/> 70-    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. "i'llgo you one forty wine-supper," said Abe Checksnap. "No, no, I've had wine enough." "Nonsense I a hair of the same dog will cure the bite," said another. "Well, I'll accommodate you; come onl" said the parson, drawing up the reins. "Which way?" "Say a two-mile dash, or- from here to Tom Nob's blacksmith shop. Is it a go?" "I'm satisfied;" and the two contestants brought their carriages up abreast oi each other. ; "Are you ready P" asked Charley. "Ready ' both responded. "Then, go i" At the word they both spoke to their nags, and away they leaped 'as though fully comprehending the situation and the-terms of the' bet. The road was wide and level, and a better two-mile dash could not be found outside of the race-course. For the first half-mile Checksnap's horse. was nearly a length ahead, and to the minds of those who brought up the rear it was somewhat doubtful whether the parson would win the race or not, although their sympathies were all with himand his homely horse. -At the :end of the first mile DWkster was still behind, and the parson was "in a- great swe'at, not so much on ac- count of having to pay for the supper if he got beaten as the dread of bing beaten at all. Gradually, Duster ate up to his antagonist, who was doing splendid work, and was   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.     71 handled finely, while Duster was doing just'about asi he pleased, as he always did. When they had arrived to within half a mile of the blacksmith's shop, Duster was still half a length behind, but he seemed to be just warming up, and on the last quarter he put forth a burst of speed that left his antago. nist fully three lengths behind when they arrived at the blacksmith's shop, where a crowd of people welcomed him with loud plaudits. But Duster was not satisfied with what he had done. To win a race with such a horse as Cheeksnap drove was nothing for him; so when the horse came up alongside of him and stopped, he just opened his huge ugly mouth and placed it firmly on the other's neck, as though indignant at his presumption in attempting to race with him. The parson yelled "Whoa!" and pulled back with all his might, while Checksnap leaped from his wagon and ran forward to the rescue of his horse. After biting and shaking to his heart's content, Duster released his hold and sent his hind legs up at the parson, smashing in the dash- board, and bobbing the old man out among -the wheels. "Whoa! you villain Hwhoa!" he yelled, as he scrambled around and tried to regain his, feet. Duster turned- his head and looked back at the old man with a wicked expression in his face, which said as plainly as words could say it, "Have you got enough, or shall I heave them again?"   &#xD;<pb n="72-73 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000037"/> 72    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.    i : 'Whoa!' you rascal!-whoa!" plead the parson, drop. ping the reins and crawling out from between the wheels.  The blacksmith's helper made a motioni to hold Dufster's head; but the beast opened his mouth at him, and, the fellow fell back in good order and without offering to ex- cuse himself.        . "Whoa! Duster--whoa 1 there's' a good boy-whoa!" and the old preacher patted him soothingly on the head." It's all right, old fellow; I forgive you." "Areyou hurt?"A:sked Checksnap. ", No; is your horse hurt?" "Not, much; but what a devil-horse that is to be sure. If I had him I'd break every bone in his body." "C Well, then, you wouldn't have a fast horse if you did; you would have to break his back to break his viciousness." "Why don't you muzzlehim?",' ", That is a good thing; -but would you like to try it?" - "I think I had rather be: excused*' , -( The trouble is he wasg mad to see how hard he had to work :iit order to get abeadi of-you'r horse." "Perhaps; but youe beat 'me handsomely, and now we will'go and have -the' supper."   At that noment the other members of the party drove / up and learned particulars. Three cheers were given for ther-parson and for Duster,- and after fixing his dashboard, Ithe eiltire party started for the hotel to partake of the champagne supper.  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7802-00000038"/> 74    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. It was a grand affair, such as turfmen most always enjoy; but, as they had seen all the sport they cared to at the old minister's expense, at least for one- day, they behaved with more moderation, and so got up from the table right side up and regular. The parson thought highly of it, and now understood why rational men could enjoy such things and fanatics railed against them; in fact, he was fast be-- coming liberal in his ideas, and felt that actual experience was doing him more good than all the, theories in the. world. The party sepairated, and drove. to their respective. homes ; but the doings of the minister had not escaped the notice of his watchful and disgusted flock on this occa- sion any more than on former onest..- A church-meeting was held, and it was voted to depose the old man and get a new minister. With many misgivings land mueh: sorrow, the church voted on the question, and Parson Beecher was turned out to grass. A new ministeri a -young man, was procured and installed. It was a great occasion,.and became the talk of the country for. miles around-; but the old parson took little noticei^of: -the, affair, so. ardently had he given himself over to, the- spor-t' of horse-racing. Three months rolled away. The, new minister did not come up to the expectations of the church, and there was considerable grumbling. Nor was thii all; he was un- married, and thereby hung several tales.; In .the church   PARSON BEECUERBU AND HIS HORSE.     75' there were at least fifty marriageable women of various ages, and, of course, each one " set her cap " for the young dominie. This- created dissensions and jealousies. They all wanted him, and as they could not all enjoy such felicity, they talked about and back-bit each other until there was scarcely any brotherly, and not an ounce of sisterly, love in the church. Meanwhile, Parson- Beecher was enjoying himself some- times, and'sometimes Duster enjoyed himself at-the old man's expense; in fact, -he appeared to be determined that his master should not have all sweets and no bitters. As for ; bitters, he was not averse to them when par- taken of in the usual way; but this having 'em as Duster directed gave the old man many bumps and much trouble.- Yet he was still king of the road, and maintained his title against all comers. One Sunday the old man had been- out with him upon the course, when he had managed to pocket quite a stake" indirectly," or, as a celebrated mayor once held, " ministerially,'" and was slowly walking hisr horse homeward when'the sound of church music greeted his ears. He looked up from his reverie and found himself oppo- site his old church. The tune was a familiar one, and com- ing from familiar courts and well-known voices, he halted and listened. His conscience smote him. He was almost persuaded to go in and enjoy the old time again. n fact he felt guilty and sinful.  &#xD;<pb n="76-77 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000039"/> 76    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. As the music died away, he drove his horse up under one of the open windows and listened to the voice of the newpreacher, who began his evening sermon. He became more  d more interested. Now and then words reached his-ears and- pricked his conscience. He stood up, and resting his elbows upon the window-sill con- tinued to listen. The members of the congregation did not at first notice him, but by and by some of the boys began to snicker, and then they pointed up to the window at the familiar face of Parson Beecher. It wasn't!long before every face in the church was turned up towards the window. Those in the gallery were just- dying to know. what the excitement was all about, whilst  everybody 'who ould -see- was wondering what it meant that Parson Beecher/sAhouid he seen in such an attitude. The minister could notgsee the, old miian from the pulpit, and became very much annoyed at the" inattention of his eongregation. One whisperedto the other, "The old par- son has repented;" another, 4He has been touched," "Seen the error of his ways," and before the old man, who- was deeply mterestein esth 7e ermon,was aware of it, he had not only tcreatei a enssation:but:a favorable impression' among an;, especially the old ladies with marriageable daughters. Seeing that he was disturbing the meeting he sat down in his wagon again and listened until the sermon was over, after which he gathered up the reins and headed Duster &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7802-00000040"/> 78    PARSON BEECHERt AND HIS HORSE. for the turnpike. WBe started to go back to the tavern but his conscience reproved him, and agamturning hiz horse he started for home, wrapped in a profounde-and rathel uncomfortable reverie. But Duster concluded that there had beenjust sentiment and shenanigan enough for one day, and so laid back his ears and started. The parson attempted to check him, but he refused to be trifled with. "Whoa, you wicked beast i See what you have brought me to.'. Just as he spoke Duster gave a rear and a plunge, and over the hand-rail of a small bridge he went, taking wagon and driver over with him into the muddy stream below. It was an unceremonious baptismal such as the old man was not prepared for. But he clung to the reins and rose to the surface blowing like a grampus and yelling like one possessed. The people were by this time coming from church, and hearing his cry several of them hastened to his rescue. They arrived just in season, and just in time to seize Duster, *who was trying- his best'to scramble up the bank, and to drag-his owner out of the mess he had got him into. - The old man was bruised, wrenched, shocked, and most emphatically ducked. The wagon was broken, and his hat was probably sticking in the mud where his old head had so recently been thrust. His friends assisted him out and carried him home. Great sympathy was everywhere man-   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      79 ifested, and during the fortnight's sickness which followed scarcely a single one of his old hearers neglected to visit and to condole with him. Dnring this time Duster had a good resting-spell, al- though he often went hungry on account of his playfulness with the hostler who had been employed to attend him while the parson was laid up. But Duster was for sale. He had cut up one too many times with the old man, and now that he had time to reflect on matters dispassionately he concluded that Duster was -for sale. During the many visits that his old hearers had paid to him during his confinement they had told him inconfidence of the jealousies and dissensions that were astir in the church, the causes of which they were not slow to speak of. Even more than this was hinted at. It was the general opinion that the new minister could never be useful, on ac- count ofthere being so many girls in the church who want- ed to marry him. If he smiled on one, forty-nine others and their parents frowned on him; and if he spoke privately to one, the others were wild with envy and made it a subject for gossip for the next week, or until he spoke or smiled upon another. Things had come to a bad pass, and everything but jealousy and hatred was getting decidedly lukewarm. One after another of them hinted to the old man that if he would give up his fast horse and buy a slow one (in fact,  &#xD;<pb n="80-81 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000041"/> 80    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. they would give him a slow one), they would gladly forgive 'the past and restore him to his old position of usefulness These -expressions of love and returning confidencetook "Closeholdupon .theq old man's heart, and' he privately an: /:nounb'ed- to a few of his friends that hia horse was for sale. This was soon noised abroad, and several large offers  .were sent to the old man by letter, knowing that he was not -well enough to converse on the subject.  }But.-the old parson- soon got able to go out, and none were emore delighted to see him, apparently, than Duster, f who whinnied and danced.  "Oh, you old. rascal! you are glad to see me,. are you, : i, afier.,as the deviltry you have done-? Arn't you-ashamed :   .yo rself?" "'   - -  '  ": I Duster flopped his loungears back and forth, and whin- -: nied affirmatively. He said, as plainly as horse-talk could :;, siy;;it,:tt the was dreadfully sorry, and that if he would; gie- him -another trial he would be as honest and sober :  :heair ehorse,  t-'!Noy'Ou-- don't,"-f continued the parson; "you have - .earil;:.broken my neck a-dozen of .times, and I have lost all-faith in your pretensions to honesty, or promises to ido better. Duster, you are a bad beast, and I am going to sell.- you if I can find a man who is fool enough to pay my price, or have you at any price, in fact." While he was holding this little confab with his horse,   &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7802-00000042"/> 82    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. the stable-door was darkenedc by the entrance of a short, thick-set, black-eyed man, who had a carpet bag in his hand, and who looked as though he had lately alighted from a- train of cars. "'HaveI the pleasure of addressing Parson Beecher?" "Yes, sir, you have," he replied. ": Well, sir, my name is Robert Bonheur; I reside in New York; you may have heard of me."  "It;seems to me that I have," mused the parson. "I have heard' of the remarkable doings of your horse, and only -yesterday I learned that you had concluded to sell him; is that so?" "Well, sir, I have said that I would sell him provided I could get my price." ".Is that the horse-I should judge it was." "Yes, that is the animal." ' D1uster-isj that his name?" "That's the name he came to me by, and I have never changed 'it." "Suppose you harness himup and let me see his style for a few miles." The old man hesitated; he had promised himself that he would never drive him again: but as this was to drive a bargain, he finally concluded to do so, and assisted the stable boy to harness him. Taking the great horse-fancier into the wagon, he drew   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      83 the reins over Duster once more, and away they went like the wind.  The horse never felt better or more honest, and never before equalled the speed-he showed on this occasion. He gave the go-by to everything on the road, even with two in the wagon; and after driving him ten miles and back, he scarcely showed that he had noticed it. Mr. Bonheur was delighted. Hle was a horse jockey, however, and was determined to get the horse just as cheap as he could; so he began to find all the fault he could with his general appearance, his awkward gait and homely head: but just to show that he meant business, he resolved to make the old man an offer. - Would ten thousand dollars be any inducement to you to part with Duster "' "The old man opened his eyes in wonder. Mr. Bonheum thought he was offended at the smallness of his offer. "( Well, would fifteen thousand move you?" "Why, sir, I am surprised," said the parson. "Well,you know you have not set a figure on him yet,and I had to offer at random. But I think I could make a fast horse out of him: what do you say to twentythousand?" "Say!-wh^J say I will take it," replied the parson with eyes and mouth agape. c; All right! Give me a clean bill of sale, and I will give you a draft on my bank for the amount." 4. ^ .  &#xD;<pb n="84-85 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000043"/> 84 ;,  PARSON BEECHiic BAND HIS HORSE,. There was, but little, further talk; in fact, there was but little occasion for it, as both parties to the trade' appeared to be perfectly satisfied. "But I must tell you one thing, Mr. Bonheur; I could not sell that horse under a false impression: he is wicked as Satan himself.' - Ha old man, you do not know me; I would rather have a vicious horse than an honest one. I love to ex- periment on them.' "Well, you will find experimenting enough on this one, I will warrant you; but beyond this, he is sound and good as you see him." - All- right I I am satisfied." Without further loss of time the bill of sale was made 'out and the draft given for it. The next day he was to call for the horse, and so the old parson passed an hour or so h*     ;  2 ^  *,  t  *m- with him that night, talking over old times, as it were, and reminding him 'of the many tricks he had played upon him, and the'many things he had broken,'including many seeningly-honest promises to behave himself and be a better horse. : The next'day Mr.. Bonheur called to get his horse. Duster did not appear to be 'a senseless'spectator of what was going on. More in sorrow than in Bl;oer, he seemed to comprehend the fact that he had been sold out-that the good old: parson'was about to replace' him with an old cob, possessing a greater stock of honesty and less speed. &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7802-00000044"/> So when Mr. Bonhuer entered the stble in company with a Celtish groom, Duster laid back his long ears and began to dance in- his stall. "Bring him out, Mike," said Mr. Bonhuer, pointing the groom to his new purchase. Mike went to obey. Duster allowed him to come into the stall beside him, and then, opening his huge mouth, he picked the Celt up by the waist and threw him  over into the next stall. "Whoa'!" shouted the great jockey;  and the brute looked around as though anxious to get a shake at him, about it  groaned ike as he drew himself out into the Frightened, is it .  ell, one more such a fright wd make a wake of me, so it w      ut. Is that  the baste  ye a ther giving twenty thousand for ?" "Never you mind; bring him  out." "Go you in and bring him." " Sir; what do I hire you for ?" "Nowt for horsebait, I guess. f in and bring him out,  sir,' thundered M  Bon- her,   "' My life's not insured, an there's Biddy and the chil- der.? ' "Confound your cowardice. Go in 1  "Will yees be afther paying me funeral expenses?" "Yes, yes;! go in." u' And take care of Biddy an the childer?"  "Yes!" he yelled; C( go in, I tell you." Mike again approached the stall, and Duster began ,to dance. Both owner and groom said  "Whoa!"and uWhoa, ye divil!" but neither seemed to reach the horse's nerves. Just as Mike had arrived at about the right distance, and Duster could calculate to a nicety in such things, he let fly his heels, knocking the Irishman's hat off and just graz- ing his head. . Mike never stopped till he was safely out of the stable, and both men shouted to the tops of their voices. This brought the parson from the house, and he was soon made aware of how matters stood. ( Yes, I told you there were lots of experimenting in him," he replied, smiling honestly. "All right; let me once get him out of his stall and I'll teach him a lesson. I never saw the horse yet that I would give up to. He is a very devil.'  "Be gob, an yer right, Mr. Bonhuer, an as prastes can dale with the divil better nor anybody else, let him be wid the praste," replied Mike, who had agrain ventured into the stable. ,  &#xD;<pb n="88-89 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7802-00000045"/> -88 v,  .ARSON BEECHtW AND HIS HORSE. : - I will bring him out and put a bridle: and saddle on  him," said the parson. ,            { ' "That is all I will ask of yon. Buthave the kindness to put this curb-bit- on, instead-of your old-fashioned one;" and once let me get into the saddle and I will take all further risk,' replied the new owner, handing the parson a curb- bit bridle that he had brought on purpose. The old man went into the' stall alongside of Duster, who danced and capered around somewhat, as though still annoyed at the presence of the other men'; but by consid-'. erible patting and - coaxing he suffered himself to be bridled sand saddled, and led outs into the yard. Mike, in the mean- time, kept at a respectful distance, and stood half bent in anl attitude which -plainly told that he was ready to run hisor is lX Tthe first alarm. '"Telie. ehe is, sir," said the parson, ;: Mr. Bonhuer, being no novice, at once approached, and before Ducster was aware of it,'he was upon his back and jpmly selated. He reared and, plunged several times, but finding himself in the hands of a master, -he seemed greatly * puzzled Then he atteimpted to take the .bit beten: his teeth and not run, but the lever and the cub were too much for him, and he .found himlsef conquered. A better behaved horse, from -that time out ,it would be hard to fi'd." he had never before met -his master, and :now:hthe teemed to 'comprehend-:that' the days'oft his wild    *  -        f' iur ii-r  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7802-00000046"/> 90    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. oats were over, and that thereafter business and honesty must be attended to, whether or no. With but little trouble he transported him to New York, when he soon became king of Mis stued and also king of the turf, as --the world has Since learned; and although still dosed to" out up with thohostler and his compan- ioni taeershe isthe tmost reliable horse whenever his mas-' ter is aboUt which is all that is required Of him. Now let nasturn to our hero, Parson Beecher. The fact of his selliug his eccentric horse soon became noised all over town. The sporting fraternity were indignant that the owner of all the fast horses in the country should also possess Duster, but beyond this class of the townspeople, everybody was delighted to :know that the cause of so much mischief had been taken away. It was not long before a few of the old parsons personal friends and admirers began to talk about the propriety of presenting him with a serviceable but a more sober and reliable horse. This was thought favorable of for several reasons. There was a great good work to be done in the community, and it was thegeneral feeting that no one except the old parson, who had tilled the field so long, could do it effect- ively. Several influential members of the church really wished to get him back into the church aud pulpit again, and this was-looked upon as the best first step they could- take to get on good terms with the old man once more.    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.     91 So they bought a worthy cob and presented it to him. Thi  s act completely won the old parson's heart, and the next Sunday he rode his gift to church, and listened to the sermon of the new preacher. It was the greatest sensation of the year, in fact the parson was about the only one who listened to the sermon at all. All eye s were entered on him, and when the fore- noon services -ere over he was co mpletly beseged bythe crowd of friends who floceked around him. Old and an young, rich and poor, gathered to shake the old man's hand, to express their delight -'at eeing h'im again in church. The two men were in ecstacies. Some of them were moved to tears as they gathered arounad thei old- spiritual adviser, ana during the reception the new minister passed out of the church in company with Deacon Doieful and his daughter, scarcely noticed by any one else.  The old parson ssocinal mgeim, his great good humor and sympathy carried all befor him, and could it have been then and- there put to a vote he wod have een reinstate without a doubt.  ' "Lordy massy, how good it does see," said one. - "Oh, deary, I haven't felt so good since Christmas," r, plied another. "Don't it seem natural " - Oh, don't it though."'? "Dear me, if he would only come back and preach."  &#xD;<pb n="92 (Illustration) -93" xml:id="VAC7802-00000047"/> tj Ir 1 % -1Uj f        t  ",1f   PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.      93 "We must have him." "What happy times we used to have, oh, dear " "There wasn't nco wrangling then," said a fond mother with four marriageable daughters on her mind, all of whom wanted the young dominie as well as dozens of other young ladies who felt it to be their duty to marry him. And little children flocked around the old man, and strong men nearly wrenched hisarm -out of its socket in the warmth of their greeting, while those who couldn't get a chanceto shake his handpunAled his coat tail]:.  During the next week a comminittee of theleading meem-, bers of the church called on him for: the purpose of sounid- ing him on the question of assuming the place be hade fomai&amp;  erly held, and of gathering up the: broken threads ;in f0t6e church web, and they found him niot averse,- provided he was recalled by a unanimous vote, and 'tieothe eri minirer^-. could be provided with a situation-. ' *  This they promised to blook-after,;and so w ithdrew, feel- img good and leaving good feelings- behind. The next day a deputation of miothers of the church called on him, and notwithstanding they were composed of the' same members,alm6st, thiat ealled on lim before, relative to his fast eccentricities with Duster, stmlthiey were feeling altogether different now. "Oh, parson, do comer back to us," said one. i' Yes, we can't seem to get on without you." ' Parson Pounder's preaching don't seem^; ter-strike in."  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7802-00000048"/> .... VL DJiUtiK AND HRS HORSE. said oneing her ol dd favorite by the hand, "and there's nothin' but in' and wranglin'on account of his not bein married, I don't believe in a parson's not bein' married, no how, it allers makes trouble in church." "Only to think of all the nice sewing circles we used to have, and the prayer meetings," said another. "Ain't been no such times since." "It don't seem one bit natural-like to have a young spruce-looking parson calling around among us, asking us how we feel; and there'smy Sarey Jane she lost nigh unto half of her good name by having him call on her twice." What!" exclaimed Parson 'Beecher, turning to the speaker. "I mean," she added, " that the other gals as wanted him, tharselves war mad as hornets, and talked shamefully about her just because he took. a little notice on her." '"Do come back, parson," was the burden of their united song, and dismissing them with his blessing he made them  hope for the best, and the best would surely me.- -  Such a happy community and 'nth all such an excited e- was- seldom- ever seen before. The new parson was provided with a wife in the person of- Jane Ann Doleful us mollifying the deacon, and with a flock a few miles away, where -his usefulness would not be subjected to so many drawbacks as it- had been here.    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.,     95 Then came a church-meeting where ;the question come up relative to reinstating the parson,.and there was not an opposing vote. The old man was led into the vestry by a mixed com- 'mittee composed of brethren and sisterin. Such an ova- tion is seldom awarded an ordinary mortal. The mothers in Israel threw their arms about his neck, and rested their heads upon his shoulders./ The young women smiled and looked happy (the young parson wasn't such a catch after all, and they were really glad that -Jane Ann Doleful had him and taken him away), while the deacons and brothers generally renewed their allegiance to the old man, and everybody was happy. The next Sabbath the good man again took his place in the pulpit. The experience that he had partaken of had given him new life and vigor. Never before was he so powerful, or so well listened to. Nearly every one of the " sports" in town came to listen to his sermon, and he just went for them like a fellow-sinner, bound to win in this business, as he had while mingling with them in what was more congenial to their tastes. Gradually, he won them over to his way of thinking, and Sunday races were abandoned, together with many other wicked excesses that no other man could have reached as he did. Great Shakspeare says, "There is a divinity that shapes our ends rough hew them as we may," and truer words were never written. "         ' *';  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7802-00000049"/> 96    PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE. So in the end good came of the whole transaction, and to this day the town has no occasion to regret the advent of Duster, or the adventures of PARSON BEECHER AND HIS HORSE.    &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>