<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7970">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Lime-kiln Man, or, The Victim of Misfortune </title>
            <author >Swayze, Jason C.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7970</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The lime-kiln man, or, The victim of misfortune</title>
                  <author >Swayze, Jason C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >1 p. l. [5]-98 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >DeWitt &amp; Davenport</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1855">1855</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-05-30">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The lime-kiln man, or, The victim of misfortune</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7970-00000001"/>THE OR, THEI  VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE. By JASoN   C. sW ATZE, mUsiHO OR 3 nKTm EDWAUDSif "THB TWO FAIMDS," "TOR 00XVICT," mr MY; 6,RA^ Br VICTI OP    AXFOTUE  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7970-00000002"/> ps As Y Iwtexed pcan to Ad; d Ca g, Iqn the year tES5,       BY DBlWIZT &amp; DAVENPORT, lll tfhiCl-t?ofiee of the Uit State",for the Southern Diatricf of Nea To*  THE LIME-KILN MAN. CHAPTER     IL "There is a very singular oinolidenpe assoiatedl with your dream, with the ms   you really heard' saidarr-Uy Bluoe to his amiable sister Rose, who wai repeating a dream she wad had the previous night, as they sat 'ta breakfast, at tleir h6me i Bleecker street. it was about like this:."  ' She had reached the Lime Kilns of Mr. Knapp mi Fourteenth street, when a tomb which rppeardd at the entrance seemed to rock at her .approach. Whilst iestitting whether to retire or advanee, the tomb became enveloped in an asoending vapor. In a moment the place echoed the groans of one in the agofies of death; and as the vapor. dispersod, there appeared kneeling on the tomb a most beautiful female, naked to the waisti Her eyes were swollen wIh weeping,.her hi$r wss .aishevened and fro/m her 'wounded breast blood trickled down profusely. while her hands in vain attempted to remove a dagger, the ftal point of wlich 'as buried deep in her bosom.   Rose's attention tothe speptre was so intense and bewilderinag that. she:a idnot:.i&amp; the' form of a man whQ stood contemplating w'ith smiles, t-i agonies of the female, until the sound of a harp, which he touche a   use  her.' ifigure was   adome, a rapd'anner arousie           was handsoe, hS 1 x e s  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7970-00000003"/> f6          THE LIME-KILN MAN, OR complexion was dark brown, and dark hair curled in confused ringlets on his forehead-his voice which accompanied the harp, was melodious. Listening to his lively strain, Rose was struck with horror and astonishment at the following rhapsody- Flow softly-gently-vital stream; Ye crimson life-drops stay; Indulge me with this pleasing dream Thro' an eternal day. See-see my soul, her agony I See how her eyeballs glare I Those shrieks delightful harmony, Proclaim her deep despair I Blsrise-i--Infernal spirits rise, Swift dart across her brain-- Thou Horror, with blood-chilling cries. Lead on thy hideous train. O, feastmy soul--revenge is sweet- Louisa, take my scorn- Cursed was the hour that saw us meet; The hour when we were born I Scarcely was the last stanzas sung, when the trembling Rose awoke from her dream; doubting for a moment, whether what she had seen and heard was not a reality. Just as she had over- come the impression arising from so horrible a vision, the night wind wafted by the casement of her chamber the tone of an in- strument so similar to those she had heard in fancy, that starting up in her bed, she drew aside the curtain, under an apprehension of beholding, awake the vision of her sleep. The chamber was in total darkness; but the same sounds were repeatied: and hearing them now more, distinctly, her heart sank within her with terror at the certainty. She determined to quit her bed, and feeling her way to the window, opened it. The same sounds were heard again, yet more distinctly, and were ascertained to proceed' from a seranading party in-the street,. "Do you remember," said Harry, continuing his interrogations, "enough of the place you supposed was the Lime Kilns, to com- pare what you saw in the dream with the place itself!" "Beyond a doubt," said Rose. d; We will take a ramble there in the evening," replied Harry; "and should there be a tomb in the old Kilns resembling that in your dream, I think we should relate the whole to father, Mur- der is a crime, above all others the most offensive to the Diety; and if ever the Omnipotent, displays a miracle, I can conceive nothing more likely to occasion his supernatural interference, than detection of so foul a crime." They seperated. Harry went about his business, and at dinner time as usual, was on his way to Gale's Dining Saloon, No. 15   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.    ' Spruce street, (that excellent place for good dinners,) when he encountered a man of large and cymetrical form, his face quite brown from exposure to sun and storm; his hair, naturally dark, was dyed by a substance that appeared on it, and hung in light golden ringlets over his shoulders; his beard reached his breast, and was in a similar condition with his hair; his dress, always the same, was quite dilapidated; and he had on several coats, and as many pair of pantaloons. This singular man will be recognized by every resident of the city of New York, as William McFarland, or as more generally known "The Lime-Kiln Man." Harry had often seen him, and thought from his eccentricities that some grevious misfortune had befallen him, and he had thus given himself up to the charity of the world; and feeling anxious to know something of his history, he thought a better opportuity might never offer him for that pur- pose; accordingly he invited him to dine with him. The old gen- tleman bowed politely, as he turned towards the door, not waiting for a second or more pressing invitation. They were soon seated at a back table, and their eatables were call ed for. He would have nothing that had ever enjoyed life-nothing in whica sugar was an ingredient; and his drink was water. He never smiled; and the only pleasure he ever appeared to enjoy was the triumph of argu- ment. To obtain this pleasure, he would constantly controvert the most obvious truths; he delighted in attacking revelations, and was indefatigable in discovering the scruples of his hearers on religious points. The irremediable evils of society were his dearest topics, and the climax of his felicity was, by the. abuse of the eloquence he possessed, to render discontent triumphant. He seldom spoke to any one first-when he did so it was his invariable custom to single out one much younger than himself, with whom he would abruptly begin a conversation. Harry had asked him several questions during the time he was eating, which he merely answered, but as soon as he had satisfied his appetite, he tapped a young man who was sitting by his side, on the shoulder, and asked(him if he had read the last novel, so much talked of. "( I never read novels," said the stranger, "Why not!" asked the old man. "It is throwing away one's time, to say the best," was the reply, ":I make a point never to read anything of that sort. I never  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7970-00000004"/> 8    .     THE LIME-KILN MAN, O0 read a novel in my life, and I never will-they're well enough for girls   . "Prejudice-Prejudice-Prejudice--how art thou worshipped in this isle!" exclaimed the Lime-Kiln Man. "I suppose, then, you plunge a pretty good depth in literature of a more obscure or erudite nature," continued he. "Have you looked into the last political effusion by the Rev. ---." "I make a point never to read works of that description. If I understandits object correctly it is to turn everything topsy-turvy; and I feel no sort of inclination to be made giddy- I leave  this sort of things to your revolutionists."' '; Prejudice again," cried the old man-- perhaps then, you dive into the mines of science. You read --- "Oh, no, believe me, not I. I was obliged to do something in that way at Princeton. But I've done with lectures, completely ; and, to own the truth, the only science I care about now,'is to make an estate of ten thousand a year bring me 'happiness in the way I like it." "I crave your pardon then," said McFarland.!"Had I known you were in the possession of ten thousand a year, I shpnld by no means have suspected you guilty of possessing a mind." "Is there no prejudice in that observation, sir " said Harry with ma smile of modest diffidence. McFarland, instead of answering, fixed a pair of large hazel eyes on Harry; and folding his arms upon his breast examined everv feature of his countenance. Aftet a considerable pause, he said-                      4 "You I believe, do not possess ten thousand a year, but if I am not much, indeed deceived, you have materials of which a skilful artist might form a great mind. Allow me to ask you -have you a father ." "Yes-" answered Harry.  "Do I know him-r-is he of this city ." Harry satisfied his curiosity. "What business do you follow," "Keeping books." "Unfortunate Hunfortunate indeed! that such materials should have fallen into such hands.' You, of course, endeavor to compel your reason to adopt all those doctrines which priestcraft teaches." "Sir," replied Harry, with the glow of indignation on his   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.         9 cheek, " the honored person to whom, without knowing him, you apply a common-place epithet, never strove to inspire a sentiment in the breast of his children, to which the most enlightened reason could object." *' You rejoice me," cried the old man-" you have not then im- bibed the jargon of superstition called religion."* "Superstition and religion in your dictionary then, are synoni- mous terms," said Harry. "In the dictionary of truth they are so," replied McFarland. What is religion, but ceremony, or a set of ceremonies? 'How absurd, how degrading to a human being, with faculties so cqm- prehensive that all nature bows before him, to which she unfolds her sEcrets and submits her laws. I say then it must be beneath the dignity of such a creature to bend his knees, to bow his head, and mumble syllables of absurdities strung together cenituries ago, when, by the exercise of his own powers he might be introduced into the arena of great nature herself." Harry replied-" the dignity of human nature, sir, is no new subject to me. My father taught it me truly, and exemplified his doctrines by his conduct. He taught me, sir, that the dignity of our nature cannot be degraded by a public acknowledgment of our obligations to the Author of Nature, accordingto the customs and manners of our country; and that it is better to sanction bv -example, even prejudices, which cannot be momentarily and safely removed, than by ridiculing those institutions, which the mass of our fellow citizens hold sacred, to give the reins to uncultivated nature, "There is a vein of independence in your redasoning  I admire exceedingly, however much we may deviate in our conclusions,' said McFarland. This introduction led to a long conversation, in which each seemed to take a deep interest. McFarland appeared less and less disgusting in the eyes of Harry, and Harry delighted the old gentleman, who expressed a wish that this would not be the last of their conversations. They seperated after the following dialogue- *Some readers may deem it an impertinent interruption, if not an Impeachment of their understandings, to be reminded- , that the sentiments which are put into the mouths of 'various personages in a novel, are for the illustration of their various characters, and ought never to be viewed in any other light , But the author woulA rather incur the - blame of an unnecessary interruption, than suffer the possibilty of supposition that it wras his wish to disseminate principles, which it ix his aim to destry.,   &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7970-00000005"/> 10         THE LIME-KIN MAN, OR "I can see you any day at dinner-time; by being here, I sup- pose," said McFarland. "For the present," said Harry, "but in a week or two I shall quit this place for Philadelphia." "For Philadelphia!" exclaimed he r: "what takes you to that focus of corruption and folly?" "( My father has most kindly entered into a treaty with a mer- chant there, a share of whose concern is to become mine, after the usual initiation." "A merchant!" cried McFarland--" can you confine your capacities then to the boundaries of a counting house ledger-and condemn your noble faculties to calculations of sources of ex- change X Have you thought what you are about?" "I believe I have thought too much about it "' replied Harry. "To speak candidly I have been at rio small pains to make a match between duty and inclination; but the latter receives the addresses of the former, even yet, but coolly." "Mr. Bunce," said McFarland earnestly, "s as you value your happiness for life, reflect-now is that important momnnt, in the period of your existence, that will gild with pleasure, or darken with discontent, every scene as yet behind the veil of time. , I feel a lively interest in your welfare; and if you can trust your. self with me for an hour to-morrow, I will venture to say you will not regret it. Remember, you will find me at the Lime- Kilns in Fourteenth street at four o'clock. CHAPTER      II. At times, and under certain circumstances, it is pleasing to hear old friends recodnt the incidents of their past lives. So thought Harry Bunce, and presuming that the Lime-Kiln man would en. tertain him, he was determined, if possible to hear his story. Surely an abundance of romance was in it, and something being promised him, he withmuch anxiety awaited the appointed time. It is seldom the desire of an aged man, to close his mortal career without first making known to some favorite friend, the   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.       " little secrets he has so long cherished. In this instance the favored one was Harry Bunce, one well worthy the honor confer- E ed upon him. The time fixed soon came around, and found Harry punctual, as was always his first rule, and in the presence of his relater at the Lime-Kilns. "And you are really come," exclaimed he. "Is it the spur of curiosity that has urged you to this pompliancc? Comej be hon. est, sir, I have read the wondrous volume of this world. I have / been amongst men, I have bustled in the crowd. I have also been secluded from the herd, and in silent musings of full many a year, I have contemplated the strange variety of human nature. f Perhaps there is no passion, no impulse of the mind, that I have not experienced. Man is familiar to me-I know the whole ma- chine-its movements-and the nature of the material of which it is composed. You have an honest mind; by which I mean, that you are sincere; that your tongue utters what your heart dictates, and your reason/prompts. Now tell me what kind of a man you think me to be. "(Forming my judgment on observations/and appearances, I should suppose you a disappointed man; one whom misfortunes have induced to quarrel with the world." i "The very notions I should, have enter ined, had I seen my present resemblance at your age-for thy I viewed mankind through the same fairy telescope that you ct now. But to my story,   . "The father of the man you see before you, was a farmer, and resided in the little town of Brigallen,* Scotland. His family consisted of three besides myself, two brother's and a sister. The brother's names were Thomas and Knox, and the sister's was Maria. He was unfortunate in the concerns of life, somewhat negligent in consequence of misfortunes, and at last, broken- hearted with disappointment, sank poor to the grave." "My mother had gone there long before, when I was little over five years old." "It may be well to remark to you a few traits of my earliest years, as perhaps you may- trace a resemblence. I remember perfectly well, that when only four years old it was frequently my amusement to mount upon a chair, arrayed in my mother's white *Bridge of Alle is the proper name, but it is generally called BrigaUen in this country, /s  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7970-00000006"/> 12         THE LIME-KILN MAN, OR apron, and assembling around me my brothers, an old woman my nurse, and ihy mother, to preach with considerable vehemence. "The prediction of course concerning me at that period, ele- vated my future fate to a priest. After my mother's decease, I went three or four times to the theatre, and I still recollect the wonderful impulse I felt to leap upon the stage, and join the per- formers." A similar sensation often seized me at church, when I almost wished myself in the pulpit. ' I know now that this was ambition in embryo; and had my parents situation in life placed an army within my early views, I doubt not I should have felt the same im- pulse to have seized the standard from a General, as I did to dis- place the clergyman from his pulpit, or thrust the performer from the stage.          ,       - "At seven years old I possessed the gravity of a sage. The pastimes of other boys were my aversion. Books of all descrip- tions that came within my reach I read, with +hat delight that an. imated me in scribblihg over every piece of paper I could procure with what I called my studies. The effusions were generally of a similar nature with the book I had last read; and, of course, I was a theologian, a dramatist, a poet, and a novelist, in turn. - Noth- ing, however, at this period was a greater treat to me, than to be permitted to remain at table after dinner, when the other children were sent to play, that I might listen to the discourse of my elders. "My bodily frame was such as may be expected from an in- dulgent mode of bringing up, and my own sedentary inclination- weak and- delicate. This consideration induced my father for some time, to object to placing me in' a public seminary, where a relative offered to provide for me. Poverty, however, advancing rapidly towards his humble dwelling, and, quickening its pace after domestic economy had quited it with my mother, made him soon accept the offer of his cousin. I left my native roof ere I was eight year old, and became a member of a daily school in Edinburgh, This I esteem the first grand era in my life. A public school is a little republic, where the honors and advantages of the community lie open to all; and  in no other soil can the seeds of ambition be so well cultivated. Soon was the spark of emulation felt within my bosom, infusing energy and vigor into every action., The middling classes beheld me with envy pass their ranks; and the highest wondered at my p      THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.       13 * swift approach. Success urged fresh endeavors, and ere I hadaat- tained my thirteenth year, I was qualified for the university; where I already was in fancy, struggling for academical distinc- tions. Just before my fourteenth birth-day;, was the second grand era in my life. My father died insolvent. A letter from my father's cousin, my benefactor, acquainted me that, c. in consequence of some considerable failures in his speculations, his fortune was much reduced, and that he could not fulfill his intentions of sup- porting me at the university," adding, that as I was now of age to go into the world, he wished me to think of some trade I should like. You, Mr. Bunce can conceive my feelings at this freak of for- tune. In the first moment of my disappointment, rage, conquer- ed reason, I considered my benefactor worse than an assassin. "My, God i"I exclaimed, " is he not a murderer? Has he not made me the parent of the fondest hopes, the brightest, dearest, expectations? Did he not, himself, beget these preams of bliss, which I, have cherished? and now, with a word, hemurders every hope!"-Trade!-My soul sickened at the sound, as he would re- peat it. Apprentice l-horror was in the word, and every hope of happiness vanished from my sight. In another moment different thoughts agitated me. My warm, romantic fancy, could not at once relinquish the views it had fostered. Pride aided fancy; and I persuaded myself, that were my genius but known, it would most certainly be patronized. I resolved to write to a celebrated character, at that time a patron of literature. The same evening on which I received my cousin's letter, I wrote one for this person, intending to send it the following morning; but in the morning my mind was in a different frame. I resolved to see my benefactor. He was an opulent tradesman, and resided in Edinburgh. "You, have received my letter, William," said he. "l amn sorry you should be disappointed in your views, though I have not a doubt but you will do much better in trade, than by drud- ging all your lifetime over books. Have you any choice?" "None that I can follow now, siir. I have indulged a hope that my industry at college might possibly have recommended me-" "To be some great man's toad eater," interrupted he, " is that what you mean 2 It could do nothing else for you. The church *             4  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7970-00000007"/> "        THE LIME-KILlN MAN, OR is absolutely beset with hungry suppliants. There's no arriving at the bar, without a fortune; and as to physic, a man's talents will never recommend him to a patient, if he keeps no car- riage. I wish to be your friend, William, and I think I know how. It must be by placing you in a situation, as however, disagreable it may appear on entering, will lead you to independence." I began now seriously to reflect upon the troth ofI these obser- vations., I recollected I was speaking to the only friend I had on earth; and though my pride suffered a severe wound, my judg- ment was improved in my own estimation. After a pause, I yielded my assent to the truth of his observa- tions, and expressed a wish that,I could write d fine..hand, as it might possibly procure me a genteel situation in some merchant's ,counting-house. "My friend smiled at my wish.--"You are in the same error there," said he "I believe no'set of men labor more, in general, than persons of that description, and what is their reward . A clean shirt, and a shining pair of shoes, which is pleasant enoaugh for a man in his teens. But think of the situation of such men, if they marry-if they live to old age; a mechanic who earns two pounds a week is a prince to them. I by no jmeans control you- if you think genteel misery desirable, you shill be a merchant's clerk.  I was humbled in my own sight; my heart no longer throbbed in the expectation that had delighted it; I felt it sinking, and a passive acquiescence in my friend's sentiments was the conse- quence. We parted with a promise from him to send me the address of a grocer the next day, and on whom I was to wait as my future master. My colleagues at school saw an alteration in my countenance, and soon discovered my future destiny, which attracted the scorn of some, the pity of many. Instead of sleeping that night, my mind was busily employed in contrasting the real with the fancied situation that was to suc- ceed my school days. My thirst for'literature swas never more to be indulged, but conquered. "Ah! ifatal delusion!"I thought it might be conquered. But the thirst of know-edge is occasioned by an unquenchable spark, and must be gratified, or will consume. Imagine not I sanction idleness, which oft asstmes the work of /genuis, but is not, cannot be allied to it. Inagine not that I e   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.        15 approved that morbid sensibility so oft mistook by its possessors for heaven-born genuis-by no means! But if the soul perceives with itself that active principle, which ease nor gain can satisfy; which almost overlooking common things, soars into the regions of sublime inquiry; and creative fancy gazing with eagle eye, even on the source of light-Oh! then let him who feels the heavenly guest obey its sacred voice-for I who have contended with its power, know that genuis is not to be subdued!  Let such a man resist the natural impulse he will feel, to yield his inclinations to the well-meant, but fatal advice even of parents. Let no commands, no tears, no supplications, even of another, bias him. Let sincerity be his guide, and firmness of mind his staff, and his pilgrimage will grow pleasanter in his progress-but if, to dry a momentary tear, or escape a momentary pang, he submits to smother genuis, he seals his own misery, and deceives, beside himself, his friends. William McFarland did so, and mark his history. "I waited on Mr. Arnold the grocer, and was received in a lit- tle room at the back of the shop, where Mrs. Arnold was sitting. They appeared plain, plodding sort of folks, remarkably neat in their dress and precise in their discourse. After a variety of questions, Mr. Arnold inquired if I were sensible of the importance of an interest in the merits and sufferings of my blessed Saviour. Imagination must describe the astonishment this question occasion- ed me. Mr. Arnold saw my surprise- "Well, well," said he, "I see you have not been brought up with a proper sense of your eternal welfare. It is a great mercy however,' that you have been directed to this roof where you will have the benefit of instruction and example in the right road. You may tell Mr. Collwell, (the name of my benefactor,) that I like you very much, and shall be ready to receive you toemorrow, and after a months' trial you may be bound." "Every necessary was provided fc:, me at Mr. Collwell's ex- pense, and I bade farewell, with a sigh, to my school and school companions. "I passed my month of probation. Night after night, as I laid upon the pillow, I meditated upon my situation; and strong was the struggle between what I esteemed my duty and my inclina- tion. , "Often would the swell of, independenoe elevate my mind to the contemplation of the most impracticable schemes. As of0te  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7970-00000008"/> 16         THE LIME-KILN MAN, OR would a sense of gratitude to Mr. Collwell, as well as an implicit faith in his assurances that my (present almost intolerable) situa- tion would lead to future ease and comfort, baffling the sugges- tions of my romantic fancy. ' Thus were the embers of genuis and ambition dampened, and the powerful energies of a thinking mind depressed by the duties of a mean destination. The progress of my tale will show, that totally to extinguish the former or destroy the latter, is be- yond the power of circumstances, while the senses remain un- impaired. "As yet, sir, you have heard -nothing.!" have but just lifted the veil which seperates the present from the past. As it is forced up higher and higher, and the light of reason, is aided by the cursed memory of other and more happy days-you will hear all--I will reveal all."             \ Here the old man shook convulsively, the tears trickled down his furrowed cheeks, and-with an extended hand he said, e"Would to God, my story ended here," and after a brief pause he continued, "Bust, will you listen to me? Promise me, that you will; and though painful the task, my solitude shall be broken by the recital of a history overwhelmingly filled with sorrow, and which must soften even an adamantine heart." I shall never forget the deep anguish which beamed from his eyes, as he faintly articulated these words. And then, as if sud- denly seized by an inspiration, he concluded- "Meet me again to-morrow. Remember, four o'clock to-mor- row;' CHAPTER      III. A summer day drew near its close, when Harry was seen on his way to the rendezvous of his, now interesting old friend, the Lime Kn Man. He was received without scarcely being noticed, but was pointed to a seat, consisting of a board, one end of which rest. ed on the sill of the building, and the other on a block of wood.   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.       17 Harry obeyed, and sat in silence for some moments; the old man's eyes were fixed upon the ground, till at length he slowly raised his head, looked Harry steadilv in the face and said- "You are punctual, sir, and I doubt not, you are ready to hear me proceed with my sorrowful tale-or, as it could better be called, horrible experience; the thought of which alone, makes me shrink from the recital; but as I have promised, I must proceed. "The menial offices which my situation compelled me to per. form, at first, were galling to my pride; but I soon discovered it to be a false pride, and by degrees I became its master. I could stand behind the counter and weigh sugar without feeling the shame of a mean action; but I was often rousedfrom a reverie by my master, when I was weighing teas, and at the same time busily employed in the regions of fancy. " When the business of the day was ended my apartment was the kitchen, my companions a methodist old woman who was the servant, and her friend, a black cat, Here I might have regaled myself with reading, but unfortunately, the old lady's library con- sisting of the Pilgrim's Progress, the Holy War, and a volume or two of sermons, was at that time little'suited to my taste. The pious discourse of the old dame was still less pleasing; thus, too much fatigued for bodily employment-sleep, or meditation were my only. alternatives; and from these I was'frequently roused by ,the tabernacle hymns, to the time of which the old woman mended her stockings. "On Sundays I  regularly attended the church to which my mas- ter belonged, where I was compelled to hear doctrines, at which my blood chilled, and my heart grew faint. "The gloom of Calvanism, the disappointment of my first hopes, the conquest of my pride, the dull and cheerless life I led, in a short time so cooled the ardor of my mind, that, if it is too much to say that I was heart-broken, I was reduced to that state of mind which sees no. brightening prospect in futurity, and which, ceasing to hope, studies and struggles to endure. "Such was the state of my mind when with a trembling hand, I signed the indentures that consigned me for seven years to the gloom ofa cloister, without its consolations or tranquility "Mr. Arnold, previous to my being bound, had often hinted to me, that I was slow in business, and thinking of onething while I was doing another; and having once caught me in the attitude of  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7970-00000009"/> 18         THE LIMEKILN MAN, OR study, leaning on a broom, with which I was sweeping the shop, he exclaimed: ' William, this wont' do; you seem more fit for a philosopher than a tradesman." "With this opinion, which was certainly a just one, Mr. Arnold ought not to have taken me as his apprentice. But Mr. Arnold was not a rich man; and Mr. Collwell had promised him a pre. mium of six pounds per annum. "From what I have related, you will readily conceive that I made but poor progress in the art and mystery of the grocery business ; and though cheerfully and willingly obeying my mas- ter in all his commands, I yet failed to please him; the natural consequence of a want of that energy in my business, of which in- clination must be the authority. t "I was more fortunate with my mistress. She was of a mild temper and humane disposition, and was -a strict Calvinist from sincere convictions. Superior to her husband in intellect, she would frequently, when opportunity offered, enter into conversa. tion, andI discovered an amiable heart. She was mistress of all the controversies upon theological topics, and felt great delight in confuting the arguments of the opponents of Calvin. "When you recollect that Mrs. Arnold's was the only conversa- tion I enjoyed, which embraced in any degree mental topics, you will not be surprised, that, notwithstanding it was religious, I es. teemed it highly, in short, I became delighted with these occasion- al recreations from the jargon of Twankay, Hyson, Black, Green, Hyson Skin-Java, Mocha, Maracaibo-St. Croix, Cuba, Musco- vado, Porte, &amp;c. &amp;c. "Still more delighted was I to hear her, while she qualified the doctrines and labored to reconcile the benevolence of the Creator withthe doom of the created, and the unborn. Her language was warm, her colorings exhibited the strongest lights and the darkest shades. She staggered my reason, opened new scenes to my view, and so far conquered my objections as to make me wish and pray that I could believe her creed. "She perceived the crisis, and gave me permission to take what books I pleased from her book case, which contained the whole element of Calvinistio divinity. Thus two or three years passed away, at the expiration of which, I had become a zealous Calvin- ist. "Power of the universe!-how I shudder, when I think upon   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUOEB       A9 the thousands, who at this hour, cherish iun their breast those horq rible ideas of Thee, which at that time formed my preed! 'I was about seventeen years old, when Mrs. Arnold, qne evening, was sent for in great haste tA visit a stranger who had. late- ly taken lodgings at the next door, and who was then at ,the point of death. ' This stranger was a man, who having obtained early in life the possession of a considerable estate, had given reins to his passions, and had indulged in every pleasure that a vitiated taste and;corrupt principles suggested. On the bed of sickness his heart smote him. "Chance led him to the house he was in, and' the landlord ;of that house was a strict dissenter of the same persuasion as Mr. Arnold, whose,sanctity and upright conduct had been frequently proclaimed in the hearing of th6 dying man. He requested to see him; derived a pleasing consolation from his discourses and pray- ers, and placed in his breast an ample confession of his crimes. "There was only one object living, for whom, in his present situation he felt any concern; and that was a daughter, the fruit of an unlawful intrigue in the West-Indies. "This daughter he had broqght up with the true affection of a father, having bestowed a very liberal expense upon her:educa- tion at a very eminent school in the vicinity of Edinburgh, where sheethen resided as a boarder. "For this daughter Captain Willis felt an increasing concern as his own end drew nearer. Himself grasping eagerly at the hopes and promises of eternal happiness offered to him by Mr. Arnold on the simple condition of believing; he became anxious that his Pauline should share the sam blessings, but which he now fully persuaded himself she would never taste, unless converted to the same faith with that which he' himself had embraced. "Such at length, was the -: confidence he reposed in Mr. 'Arnold, that he made a will, by which he bequeathed an entire and consid- erable propqrty and funds to his daughter, upon the express con- dition of her residing with Mr Arnold till her twenty-fifth year, or till her marriage with his consent. "The captain died. Miss Willis had visited him two or three- times at his lodgings, and was apprized of his intentions regarding her. A day was appointed for her removal, and I was ordered by my master to take a coach and bring Miss .Willis and her appur- tenances to her home that was to be,  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7970-00000010"/> O  .       TEU BLIMJEILN N, SOB            "Well do I remember the scene;of, her parting with her school mates. Aiffetion truly: maternal glowed in the charming counte- nahice of the governess;: who threw her arms round the neck of her departingi charge, and burning tears of sensibility told her loss. Thle young ladies, her companions, saluted her with, a Warm and sincere affection, while even the youngest of the scholars clung to her, Kissing her hands, and twitchihg her robe, while- a buzz ran round the room, of ' Remember me Miss Willis-Pray, remem- ber mi  '  "] My native tdnderness was rising; but the gloomy principles I then nourished, checked every generous feeling of the heart, as allurermenits frminthe, love of heaven! "; Miss Wiliis at length burst from their embraces, and hurried into the coach. I 'itook my seat opposite her, and imprinted on my memory a face and form, never-no, never to be erased 1" The old man dropped his eyes to the ground, and drew a deep sigh?,and then starting up, as though he had remembered some. thing, said, t I will show you her image, a sketch token when we were both under out master's roof, ana when I indulged no thought but of her. It is not to artistic as it nfight have been, but is a correct And opening a little rough box, hoe presented before Harry a ppencUi sketch, and udder it wAs written--"Pauline Willis." While he was yviewing it, he thus continued, "She was not, perhaps, the most beautiful woman in the worid -her complexion,. when she left Jamaica as an infant, was rather tinged ,with anr orange hue; but her features were thb notices of those inmates of the female;heart, .which charm the soul of mamn- sweetness of temper, and conquering submission; whilst, the soft expressions of her eyes indicated the superior eultivation of an exquisite mind., She broke the silence of some duration by asking me if I was the son of Mr. Arnold, which led to several other questions; the result of which was a short description of-the family she was about to join, for which she expressed her thanks, though I saw the pain which the intelligence occasioned; her. I pass over her introduction to her guardian and M. Arnold, but must n6t omit to mention a conversation which took place in the evening, while I was assisting in unpacking some boxes inr;thE^   atrttamnt allotted for her eiamber. ThSBrwere :sofe shelVes in the closet--  "I am glad to see those shelves," said Miss Willis, for I have books enough to fill them." "Books-books!" exclaimed Mr. Arnold; " what books, child 7 Let me see-it's proper I should see what books you have." "Certainly, sir," was the reply, " though I flatter myself you will approve the sele eion, for they have reeeived; the approbation of my dear Mrs. Madison." "I dare say Mrs, Madison i; a good sort of moralwoman, but what are her religious sentiments,? Thoee is the impOrtait point." By this time I had untied the cord, and began placing the books upon the floor. Mr. Arnold took upl a volume, and opened it-- "What is this child, eh!--outlandish jargon, I take it. What is it 1" "It is'a system of geography in French, sir," replied Pauline. '"French! ah, well? it may be Dutch; or Greek, or Algebra, or anything else, for what I know, but I -must take this here book, and all them there, that I doh't understand myself-pack of non. sence, I dare say-but they'll cut up for the shop." "Oh, dear, sir," said Pauline, " you would not surely destroy my library!  If you do not approve of my reading FrenchlI pledge my word, I will not. But pray do not destroy the books, several of them are invaluable to me." "Pledge your word-yes, yes--pretty pledge enough, No, no --the safest way is to put it out of your power. I stand in a most awful situation, child. I shall have to answer for the great charge of your soul, that has been so providentially committed to my care; and nothing-shall you read that I do not understand." Pauline looked astonished, but Mr. Arnold did not notice her having laid his hand upon another book- "Mercy on us! here's a play book!" exclaimed he. "Did your Mrs. Madison know of this too?" ' O dear, yes sir; there are eight volumes of them-they are the immortal Shakspeare's." '"God forgive you, child! Immortal!--yes; he is, doubtifass; i "mmortal torments.   Here, William, take the immortal Shdil- peares away.'    -                ,  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7970-00000011"/> - THs LtMEKLU MAN, OB Poor Pauline trembled-Mrs. Arnold. saw her distress, and aid-  'You; should consider, my dear, Pauline has been brought up by worldly people; and though it is an infinite mercy that brought 'her to our. roof, there must be an inward change wrought in her before she can be brought to see the folly of her worldly wisdom." -How I blessed my mistress. She spoke my thoughts. Mr. Ar- nold made no reply, but proceeded with the true zeal of an in- quisitor.       ( Milton's Paradise Lost'! aye, put that on the0helfif you will," said he. "Gray's Poems, that you may take. But here, put all the rest up in the box, William, and carry them, for the present up to the loft; take a hammer and nail the box shut; I can't "stand looking now, JIve got something else to do. So child, If you want books to read ax Mrs. Arnold, and she'll put what's proper into your hands'; though I think the needle suits best of week days; and on the Sabbath you may read the bible." ' Surprise, regret, and something like anger, mingled their influ. ence in the mind of Miss Willis, and a tear stood quivering in her eye. I obeyed:so much of my master's orers as to carry the box Into the loft, and intended to finish my commission when I went to my chamber, which was one story lower than the loft. But, O, sovereign gehuis-invincible power-inextinguishable spark:- then, again thy smothered embers blazed! Taking my candle and my Jammer, I ascended to the loft, I placed my candle on the floor, and was about to drive the nail, when a sudden impulse of curiosity seized my arm. "Suppose," thought I, "I just look over these books." 1 They are profane," said Calvin; " they are the productions of men -destitute of the enlightened spirit of God, and may tend to draw your affections from holy things." "Only one peep," cried curiosity, perhaps I may meet some old acquaintance that I have forgotten; for it was full three years since I had looked into any book, save the theological labors of calvinists. Down I dropped upon my knees. "If it be a sin, God forgive it; if it is a temptation, Lord deliver me." I opened the box, trembling; I took up a volume and opened it. Jt was a volume of Shakspeare, and the passage that caught my eye was the speech of Porti on mercy, in the Merchant of Yenice, Act IV, Scene first.   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUnE.       23: As I read, my heart grew warm.: as I proceeded, it grew warmer; and when I came to the line- '"It Is an attribute to God himsel=f6 it literally glowed within me. This speeeh had been my favorite at school, and I had spoted it a hundred times. It brought to my recollection another, for which I eagerly searched and found in the same volume- ' To be ornot to be, that is the question :- whether 'is Wnobler in the mind To suffer the stings and arrows of outrageous fortune," A&amp;. My spirits seemed to have gained a deliverance from fetters: my heart beat quicker than for a long time past; and I went on devouring the contents of the box with as much appetite as a hun- gry man would a dinner. I tasted every dish that presented it. self, and found each a dainty. Nearly at the bottom of the box was a volume of Walter Scott.   Conceive the interest I felt; and judge my regret when I heard the clock strike three, and saw the approaching departure of my light, which glim. mered in the socket of the candlestick. I found my way to bed in the dark;- but sleep was far off. The Spring of reason, that had been compressed to impotence by bigotry, seemed by this accident to have recovered its activity, and once more resumed its operations. O superstion; how great- ly to thy prejudice-        .           '  I recollected the scene in Miss Willis' chamber. I placed be- fore my fancy the ignorant piety of my master, and the profane intelligence of his ward. Hdared even to: trace the origin of their principles, I did more, I inquired, if it was, a consistent idea, to  suppose a benificent Creator would grant a'special light to a few t of his creatures, By which they only should be guided to eternal bliss; while the multitude are doomed to wander throngh a dark  passage to the precipice of everlasting woe t And' when I ad mi; quired--I blushed I ,Mmmmgmm,  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7970-00000012"/> TA LmE-KILN MA2, on CHAPTER IV, Various were the emotions wnich agitated the mind of Harr as he strolled towards the Lime-Kilns. He: entered deliberately, buapts he came under the gaze of the old man, he trembled. ,' Erei weparted sir," said McFarland, abruptly, . I think I had introducedMiis .Willis to your acq uaintance, and bestowed:some ; praise upon her person. It is absolutely impossible to portray her mind, at once so, smple and noble, so. condescending and dig- nifid.,.: ;I willi not, attempt even sto sketchits. outlines, but shall confine myself ,to-a .narrative .of facts, in whiCh/her actions will, mere:faitkful! y unfold, her mind, than can the ,mot, laboring de- sqriptinos. ;:       ;:         , t  ' ,9owever. dissimilar the:manner of the Arnolds were to thoso which a polished society had made. her own; however abhorrent,; thW gloomy. notions of religion to a mind of exquisite sensibility, and;,an understanding of uncommon strengthbad cultivation, havO in.:qncP brought hersalf ito believe it her duty to obey the in., junctions of her father's will, she submitted, without sullenless to their-,pde of. life,: and paid, a, descent respect p tthose dutieg whichhtheir, religion enjoined tem, to observe. .ut do not imagine she played the hypocrite. She never avow, ed her dissent from their doctrines, and scrupled not to confess her dislike, t their recluse way of living. Hpnqored-vshall Inot say besd, with th4e confidence of. this charming woman, my situation seaeed 4anpged4 from, the mot: cheerless to the most blissful. W e read, o conversed together; we wrote, and -submitted -onr prQ0uctions . the aritioisms,f each other. In short, we seemd pl  pre lu..mesach. other's soiety. What. the libraryio the lof tl .aeft U;,:u fijohede, Miss Willis' onyversation completed: and my soul once again glowed with hope. I looked forward with impatience to the termination of my set. titude, when I imagined, I should burst upon the world as a prod. iy of genuis. The hours of pleasure which were heretofore gloomily spent in reading the horrors of Calvinism, were now em. Voyed in perusing vrarious authors, or in the composition of verses. The subject of my verses of course, was my Pauline. I Having, one day, stolen a volume of Moore from the box in the toft the melody of his metre chimed in my ears, and I strung to- gether some lines, which I will repeat to you, that you may form'   THBE .VICTII'M OF rBfI         25. some jud1met,of .,my romautionotions, Yoqi wil remember., wa, q'ite oung.           ;  ' .Ah;! whther s .happiness fledW  Ah I w'her;eis contenimdntcnieealel .. . ... 1 :-  ; "'   ; .' } : 'llieek them in yon lonely she . . .. , ,' Through shade-triees and, fidweFs reeii"1.    Thereheathband' contentment keside, ;: *  There happiness oft is Is a guest; ^ t .r Mirth glows iln the .4neIpiide, . -. Andlove locks the cradle o rea't.  Affrighted froro cities they fy, ' 'Whee' PleaBdreT enmorighowl, ,.; Gives birth to the tear and the sigh g :  - - ' ' .Sed ces!aand:poison :theth.! ';.,I ': , , ,  Where Treachery calls itself Trade.  'td BAdHiiobl'6 ntdGfw!: .. .T . .:,. - -  .Where the ioicle heart i displajevd- b - ; t t X t AilehU oft th 'i r gn ' t ; n - j , , ', ; i t-, *l' 3 '- ^  sfwee t PiE C i &amp;t ^Wt U ' * -. "a" ' ; ,. ToTo you my'ambitio9th alro; f i , . . . X ;"r ) 2 $ *fi sel   ?aid  '* h n    - '/ ., . :'b;Yovr hiea' thile! wffwlfii:th ri'.'... , i   Amd add cn  eartC uient ,1t ,th  "'er iifinocence, baluit'ga;love, :    ;"  ;. :  , l'm happy iandfsigh for .io mors., , . -  Having copied this effusion for Miss ,WllHis,an foyrtu n ae t : lft it p Pun -my master's des$k, ,Hfound it. .Not xith more v- raoiou psss does the hung y "t tger 'eize .' " t.. prey' . . . .1. Mr. Arnold up on myipor ,scroll. , Famiong with ,anger, h .fly , towards, me, and tearing into a thousand, atoms,: the cause ,of ; i. indignation, he threw them in my face. :  "Here's going on!" he exclaimed,; "'here's: 'itefnilo";itoi ness. Whyits an abominabie heathenish hymn, or 0love elesgy  some such stuff; trumped up to seduce te a;ffections of mywa-, But I'll put a stop to it  If ever I see you speak 'a 1 or! lo^f at her, '1! ----" Here, choked with atnger, ' sfaped ifi dtt; ad ahi e' do^ three pots of honey; an accident th'at by noim'in;sM elpea o re stdirehiim 'to: 'easoi..  The consequence of this discovery was an abridgmet , of t l opportunities of conversing with-.my ,Paule,sand a :more t ling of ionduct towaids Miss WSifisl herselft ^: :. ., 'Shortly: afterthis event). another becurredpf? tnost decisive oon* sequence to us both.: A relation of :Mrs.,:Arnold :wasrtaken :ill  and,,.equested her attendanee. ;She- wentto resid ,with her ffew weeks at Gretna Green, On, Saturdayl r, Arnold wenBt to sl there, apd ,returned :usually. -on :Monday morni'g,, s Js W, was left at homeias guardiap of the house., .',On one ofthessr . urdays Pauline and myself had planned to bribe the od4,Wom^, 'have mentioned as servant, to. secrecy ,ad to embraoe the oppqF /   .                -  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7970-00000013"/> 26         THE' LME-KILN MAN, OR tinty 'of going to see a play. The olddame, would never, haveo consented to our visiting the "Devil's House," as she termed the theatre; and therefore it became necessary to deceive her with the tale of a visit we, were going to pay Mrs. Madison, the former governess of Miss Willis.- But we could neither of us use argu- ment sufficiently weighty to induce her to permit us out of sight, so long as Mr. and Mrs. Arnold was away. Still, we did not- give up; if a little deceptive tale would not do--stratagem must --so we gave up our p r6ject altogether in the sight of the old wo- man, and as evening amea  on, we retired seperately as if going to our chambers-but it was quit' the opposite we were soon to- gether; after we were safe from intrusion; from the old dame, and had arranged a cord and passed it out of the window of Pauline's room, I sprang out and slid gently down, and after. me came Pau. line in a-similar manner. We then stood outside our doleful pris- on wall, and like an escaping prisoner, looked carefully around to see:'if'we' were observed. I'CiJc cow see a great inconsistency in Miss Willis' oouduct, as Well n at great impropriety in my own, in thus abusing the confi. dene  lacd in. us both,. But at the moment I am speaking oft temptation was irrtsistable, youd cannot conceive its power. P Pauline was as passionately fond of theatrical performances as myseif. I had not seen one in the space of four years, nor had dii sice her entrance into our family; nor was there the remotest' probbity that , any other opporiunity would offer during'our stay with the Arnolds. ' :,The play to be performed that evening was Romeo and Juliet; and the,RQmeow:awsMacready!. ,  M,           a There were several scruples to conquer;- but in the end temp- taoion conquered. ' Taking some precaution to ,disguise our persons, we mingled- with the crowd that had assembled at the, door of the theatre* Unaccustomed to the place, and surrounded completely by a con- eourse of people, Pauline began to tremble with terror. ?The announcement of a; famed actor had drawn an unusual: theih;', the heat and pressure became almost insupportable to wiss'Will^, and adding to-her fright,: st length overpowered her. 8h :told me she felt' herselffainting, I attempted to; make a re, treatthrbuigh the- crowd It was irmipossible:.: She fainted in my rmi  At: the same iistant, the-doors: opened, and, being deprived ih    THE VICTIM OF MBFOBT 2Nt of the use of my arms, we both sank together, and I became sense. Iess .  -         '    ,  *     " When my senses returned, I ,found myself in a strange bed,. with several persons standing around me. Astonishment seized me for a moment; but'when the memory of the scene that had passed had recurred, it was like an arrow,' shot through my brain--"The lady Hthe lady HPauline HMiss Willis,!- is she alive!-where is she!" exclaimed I, in the agony of the most torturing suspense. In lifting my hands to my head,. I found I had been bled. The people around me stared in my face, and at one another, but made no reply to my questions. ",MXy God! will you not tell met" They shook their heads insign of pity. "She is dead H-she is murdered then?"I A- claimed. "Poor youth!" cried a man who stood nearest to me; "poor youth Hhis Irain is quite disordered. I believe we must take a little more -ood." '  "( You'dWetter look, whose to pay you, first," said a fat mania the rear; "H think instead of bleeding, we'd better see and get . a cart, and take him to the worklihose.' He ca't stay here'all night Idon't know' what business some folks have to, bring all' neck- broken, leg-broken, and run over and mangled bodies to my house." "Why as to that, Mr. Brown," said a decent looking man, , where could'we taele him so proper--who would have thought. to look at him, but that he was dead; and in that case, the Cor'g ner would have sat upon the body at your house, and you'd'have hadno objection"     ' ', Where am I,I then 1"' exclaimed. L   Where are you i" cried the fat 'man; "why, you're at 'the -ouse in Queen street, and as you seem in your senses now, young man, pray, where do you live:-who are your friends'T              .         I My God! what a thunderbolt was this question. Ipstead of an- swering this man, I repeated my: question concerning Paulins, but could tocure no intelligence. My anxiety mide me strong.' I detetrmned to arise; nor could the whole College :of Physioians have prevailed upoh me to relinquiish my purpose.. I was severely bruised in several places, but had received no material injury. 'It was nine o 'dloek when I: lft the --, House. My in-  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7970-00000014"/> ' 28'       . ;TO,-U a L AAjR, O , r quitrfi after ail'te. weiro4Ora il ongi timo:, frnitless. 1 ,th infie telligence that I could gather in the neighborhood of the theatre ws that a-W.: yotnmg jl a d y;kad be, en;tr ^rplodito, death, an. do nveyed away in a carriage, but whithejno, .,oo neW.  -; '6iient hbme, with i faint hope of finding her there; I rang the 'tMS the old woman-appearte and her first inquiry was-- . .  What fi  bu dbie i-th            ; WI, "thout ianswer  'ier q4estiorn, 'l-ran -way. I retuinea, it tlior 8 Oagie it'legqi;byadif^r/m theitinxietySof miud,:played the antips of a madman.  '         ;  ; - he wh'oe o tfhe6-lhtt ]} wanEideed iup iad doni the, streets, stgopoing -evyefry, hatkney C, acq inqui oft ytran!gr iftr thth obieot of' my. searc. mgilnatlon toribhm it ha " rwith'a th'Usarnd horrible ieas- aw  er dead!-- oAse tthin aeadl-- SaW her persn- violated!-I heard her shrieks H saw her agonies' i-and ,myteasbn absolutely reele. Morhing appeared--*I had walked tie whole nigli-l' hiiatakendn6 r'freihmb:f t ; :id i fund my sf. sinking with fatigue.  Asl:Ispinkirdg .C0o Huesbme 6  distacee up town, tifi ser- ts   r   g d n te siutters. Iwentin; and eing a nid  hia  P:upon .athbl e,indulged; m'1 ient grief I remained' in tit pitiw  some to im ,ml t . se ver per., sons aame mito the i6m After them was a short neatlooking man, who seated hmselfn Haw is yor patetths mornig, Mr. BrooI a" s'id a gSe tleman to him.. , , "$hhe still remamin esensible," he replhed; buth feverii lower;"  , Poor thing '" said the othqr, and. was there nothing about het that could give you any, idea who she is 'There asome i aching h  ts op ,her aco0unt b , . me,' I , 1 '"  ,fIMeroiful Providence I.-have I .then found her in exelimed 1, in a tone that alarmed the whole company. "u If you haei a ny hebart!: if, yu wopldWelieow the mo4st, wretchedbeing on e arth - IwontinWaed;,:" pray takei me to Imy Pauine., The ,people gtihered,:around me withlastonishment. An,er plahttipiotodok plaCe; i It was my PuTlin. , The, hu manitfMr Brooks, who twasa ,bookseller had: svd. jtl. r- life,;, adsd she ,w t    I h en,:t she nus e ,enear .:   ;ael ou 1 Isaw heri but she knew ne not; thoughm teo awtly mou   THE VIOM OF IStORTOMB.        3f9t: ingisentene ishe ,uttered, my., nam  -was often mentioned. A physician had, ittepded- her, :who, pronounced her out of danger, v:: Relieved-from the heaviest part of my atxiety I hadinowileisure to-think odr m'y own situation-;' buteould not reisove howrto-'aadt. Mr. Atrnold, I datred not see; MrColwellw T I shudderedito' neet.    :  : ' ' * ! t! : ^i I made Mr.: Brooks my confidant, who' huim/n'ely: offeredAejan' asUylum in iis own h0s' tiil he'cMtiidte e me t"Mr. A nold or apt' least to Mr. Cdoll1e, wHom he detmtinea ,t see hiie fUlld ing morning.'                    . His endeavors were unavailing with,both. The fqrmer fiji ' protasted against ever receiving me aganm into his house; ,afi so represetted me to the latter, that hiS' heartf was combpletely ste Hed against me.: Thus did one trivialt'vent deprive i'm of te onil1 " friend I had on earth,; Thus were nearly 'fiveyars --ofimy life: thrown away, without affording the least aitvantage'i o; mySeif; &amp; satisfaction to my benefactor..'    ' .;      t  IJhad novindieed, my libeamty; but indepenaden ecametoo,lato apd in too melancholy a way.          : But, I must be more brief. One incident leads on insesibly to another. , lmust ontent myself, therefore, with a more general account. Passing over then, many tender, and affectionate interiews I had ,with Miss Willis, on her, reGovery, at the house of Mr, Btooks, ere she was well enough to be removed to her. guardian's, I 5i coafine myself-O, the one ,in which a mutufl oonfession .of Qve tfook,place.                     , beShehad t tt gmona received a letter from Mr. Arnold uTg herreturn ,                     , And when o, -you mean -to go, Miss WiUlis, :" sd I,  ".T Nverri!pei9dshe witht firrmness. "I will  never .sa i independeneea!d .,ppiness,to wealth 1         1  "Miiss fWillisi, are you seorfous  -"-I .m resgolved. . I .went ther Iin: obedience to my fathe^s will. I found the situation barely tolerable. After this,unfo, rtu ate, accidentto will. longer beso. I .,shall, therefore ,ralinquis  all daim tofmy ,.frotune, and retain thorights o-fa ,hum. :beqijl? ^8,.5 My God, Psuline ritnmadam, : what-:.are. ;you, -pursuing-ma , means, ofliving, *hat .prospets. even of -a subiatence iavetayu hi  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7970-00000015"/> 80         THE LIME-KILN, MAN, OR "Let me retort your questions, sir. You have on my account,. lost your late prospects. What is your determination 1' "1I--I-madam-I am-a-man." "And is the privilege of procuring a subsistence confined to men exclusively? Have women, then, no hands to labor, no- judgment to plan, or resolution to pursue a project? I am ready to concede to your sex superior prowess in bodily exercises; but I am yet to be convinced that nature made the female that passive animal, which custom exhibits in our cities. My resolution is fixed my plan is arranged, Mr. Brooks approves it-at least acquiesces in it."  A  "May I ask the nature of it " I have no desire to keep it a secret, particularly from you. I am going to commence author by profession. For the present I shall remain in this house, a boarder. 'Tis no hastily formed pro. ject; but the result of serious consideration." I was struck dumb with surprise and regret. "What ails you,- William?" said she; "are you unwell!" "Why did you not acquaint me with this plan yesterday," said L "It perhaps would have been possible to have procured some similar employmeht myself." "Ce0rtainly; nothing is more easy. Mr. Brooks himself intends to offer you a proposal this very day." "Why did he hot propose it yesterday?" "What happened yesterday? Is it too late I Tell me, what of yesterday .?" "O, Madam!--0, Pauline!-yesterday was a fatal day. De. pressed with gloomy ideas, I wandered through the busy streets df this metropolis, ruminating 'on the past, and on the future; I looked back, without'much regret, at what I had done. I had sac, rificed the most important part of my life in an implicit submission to anothers judgment. I had lost that tide of the affairs of men, which leads to fortune, and nothing but miseries and sorrows pre- sent themselves in the rest of my voyage. -In all the: boundless ocean of futurity, I 'ould behold no single spot on which foe cast Hope's anchor s       ( ";As I walked oh, musing in this strain, the carriage of a cele  brated lawyer passed me, in which he lolled at ease; and opposite to him sat: his son; a youth seemingly about my own age, I sigh- ed; perhaps (I ought to own the truth,) I envied him . Yes, Pau- hne, envied him; for that which is emulation, where competition ti   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.        31 -open, is envy where it is shut out. Would) 1[ were that happy youth, said I. What admirable exercise for the :mind does such a profession open! What opportunities for displaying its. pow- ers! And it is mere prejudce to imagine a man cannot possess a liberal mind, who is a lawyer. c, The carriage stopped-instinctively I followed ,them into the Hall of Justice. The courts were sitting. A case was arguing- I listened-I became interested in the arguments-I wondered at the omission of many, which would have made for or against the question. The judqge rose to give his opinion. I had anticipated much: that he said. My proud heart fluttered; I was a pleader in imagination, I applauded myself--was happy in my fancies. The verdict was given; the 0rqwd dispersed; and then I -felt what I really was!  ":As the concourse of people separated at 'the door, one cried, shaking another's hand-' I must go so and so'-' such business calls me!' :Another replied,-' I should have been at such a place.' Every one appeared to be running after some object that occupied his mind, and brought emolument to himself. ' And where shall I go? sighed L "In Chambers street I met a mob, dragging a poor wretch to justice, who had been detected in picking a pocket. I mingled with the crowd to hear the examination."  "What means have you of getting a livelihood X" said the Mag- istrate. The culprit was silent. "Why then, to save you from the gallows, I shall send you for a soldier."  "What means have you of getting a livelihood!" rung in my ears. I traversed street after street. Often would I check my- self with the question-' what means have I of getting a liveli- hood?' Where am I going .? ,Not to my father, mother, sister, or -brother; these are unmeaning sounds to me! Not to my home- even that cheering sound, which delights the poorest, was 'but a mockery to me. Then darted across my mind-yes, let me own it-your image, Pauline. I saw, at that moment, the utter im- possibility of your ever being mine-nay, bear with me a mo- ment! I saw you given to some rich old idiot, whose bigotry might please old Arnold; and I almost cursed existence .?  ' "Just then the martial sound of fife and drum struck mv ears. A -reoruting party appeared; I paused! what means have you of  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7970-00000016"/> getting a livelihood! still rung in my ears. Frenzy seized me,-I ran to the Lieutenant, and offered him my hand-PIlU serve the King! -cried 1. , The men pulled of their hats and gave three cheers, The Lieu- tenant shook me by the hand; and after. looking in my face ex- claimed with an oath- "'William' MFarlandl' te had been, my chum at Brigallen"' "Merciful Heaven I and I; have been the cause of this?" cried Pauline., "  thentit is time to throw, off every little affectation of our sex, fid let you see my heart-a heart, my William, that 'whether you-accept or reject it, is only;yours. I love you, Wil- liam, and go where you will, no earthly power that leaves me li; shall separat- re frnd m you.' "Excuse these few drops of weakness," said; the old man, as he wiped lils eyes. 'They are sacred to the; memory of- a martyr! Yes, sit, she made thiirfrank avowal; of her love, while her beaut- ous face 'concealed its virgin blushes in my bosom. O I memory, memoryIs tobffkithful memory!" And again the tears would flw, but he soon continued-, A declaration so frank, so noble, sd worthy of her uncommon character, was met, on my part, by one at least as sincere, as ar- dent, as disinterested as her own. The Lieutenunt beingi my friend, by his interest I obtained a discharge from my rash engagement, and Pauline and myself were shortly after married. Mr. Brooks continuedthe friendly rook on which we built our little bower of bliss. His counsel directed, his benevolence aided, his generosity mufhificently remunerated our labors. He was en- gaged in a very extensive concern, and found us abundant employ. Pauline wrote a novel, which succeeded well. We published jointly a volume of poetry; and we:mutualy labored at transla. tions. Competence was the sweet reward of our labors, supplying us; with all the inecessaries, and many of the decent luxuries of life; we resided in a-small but neat cottage at- Brigallen; only visiting the city occasionally, The life I then led was the very reality 'of that picture which imagination had taught my youthful bheart to doAt upon; and yet possessing this reality, Iwasnbt :content. When literary compo- sitions became the means of fmy subsistence, I found it irksome ; I .faned/.it amean employ of talent: taolet it outfor hire: I grw   dissatisfied; I formed 'a valety of new schemes, which alternately delighted 'ando disgusted me. A period, however, approached, which compelled me to submit to the irksomeness, and even meanness (as I deemed it,) of my employment. My Pauline bore me a daughter. t wept teas of joy; my heart beat with rapture; for at that\ moment, sir, I did not dream how, many curses, in disguise, T hailed as blessings-I sometimes laugh to think how my silly heart cheated me."? Hereithe old man laughed, but in a manner thatconveyed the misery and horror of his recollections! He continued- S A,.year or two marched onward in the track of time, unmark. ed by any record of the memory; but about the time my little girl Wa$ three yearsold and began to prattle, there: happened an evOnt,.hiih is so 1firmly printed.,on my, mind's, register, that not even theflaming fingers ofthe fiends of Hell can burn the pages nor:al Btherpitying dews that drop from angels', eyes, blot out the, bloody characters. "But spare me. now a task I feel beyond my powers-retire, re- tirt, my youngrfriend. See me at nother time; and come pre. ' paored, to, hear .a tale of horror!"  Thea anguish of his; heart was visible in the struggling features of his face, and he breathed painfully acoNulslve sighs. lCrry pressed his hand and retired in silence.   ' CHAAPTER V. "*This tale of horror, to which he alluded," said Harry; musing, on his way home,' "must b' th'e murder of the Louisa of his bal- lad,' that was overheard in RPose's dream, and' the Pauline of his tale. Why does he change the name then?1" Thus conjecture upon conjecture passed through Harfrys mind, and stillthe could:not arrive at any decisive conclusion; unless it was really to conceal the real name, shouldhe in::anyiof hisdecla- mations be-overheard. The ,night and day-passed. away,and dis- coveredHarrymnui-re:anxious'thbant onoiformer occasiodisj to: boi at "his'po'st: Hfoundth old mran in:his sual, posiiBbi,: hu poaie  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7970-00000017"/> Q84         HBnM, LPtmt-nls MAN, OB aspproached, he looked up quite cheely, s mu  as tmu sa ay :- 'Your presence gives me joy. I already feel the load grow lighter that, is so fast crushing me to the earth. After some im- ,material ,conversation he commenced: My brother Knox resided near oqr cottage at Brigallen. He then possessed the luxuries of fortune, and was a frequent visitor :at our house. He was a man of uncommon genuis,; and ardent feelings. ' ,  , : This brother, with a number of others of, similar, dispositions and talents,: had formed themselves into a club, for the purpose of candid and free inquiry. - I had the honor of being invited armem- -ber. ,   '    .         ,  My, brother poisessing, from his fortune, a considerable influence with. the -club, his patronage procured me at respect I otherwise was not' entitled to; and I was elected their secretary i. I say notiing of our labors, which Were published at a joint expense, and circulated with zeal beyond description. Experience, however, rhas taught me one truth that every struc- ture of morality or philosophy we raised upon the ruins of tho"ise we overthrew, is uuable to stand the test of practical experiment, anid are, many of them at least, greater nuisances in society than those we attempted to destroy. As secretary of\this society, my house became a sort of rendez- vous for its members. My Pauline and I were delighted at our good fortune in this respect as it-offered us many hours of rational amusement in the conversation with men of taste and educa- tion. My brother's business was that of a painter. His person was a composition of manly beauty; a countenance expressive of the most tender sympathies.; his manner was engaging, his converse truly :captivating. -Wei delighted in his company, and ,he seemed to receive an equal satisfaction in ours. His gratitude for the humble, entertainment our roof afforded him was beyond all bounds. His paintings were the ornaments of our:rooms, andfthe testimonies of his favor.             .  We passed the greater part of a year the nearest to bliss I ever Bawon earth. Fortune seemed determined:to heap her favors on us all at once; for in the course of this period :Mr. Arnold the grocer died; and smitten with the injustice of possessing. the fortune which Paulines conduct bestowed upon him, on his death-bed '         . '    \       -- Ta vzo1mc oF msQoIRTUNz.      35 made a will, by which she regained her right, to a property that made us completely independent. Now, mark the fickleness of fortune. Just as the sun of pros- perity was ascending the meridian, and his , beams had gilded a wide and beauteous landscape of enchanting hopes, a little sable cloud sprung up, and iioated in a corner of the hemisphere. It sailed towards my dwelling. It swelled as it drew nearer; it in. creased till the sun. was hidden from my sight, and then descend- ing, burst upon my head, o'erwhelming all prospects of the hopes I had beheld, and left me nothing to contemplate, save the frightful desolations of despair! To dwell as little as possible upon a subject that shakes every nerve with horror at its remembrance, know then, young man, that this pretended moralist, this zealous friend, this smooth speeched brother, proved himself a consumate villain. He came to our dwelling, and found:peace, innocence and love, its inmates; he saw as fond a pair as Natnre ever designed for each other's happiness. What, then, was that principle that could excite within his breast the horrid pulpose, the execrable, vile design to mar such bliss? With the dissembling visage of benevolence, he must have borne a heart that languished for the muder of his species; or how could he deliberately have planned the destruction of one of Nature's noblest works! You have not yet felt the influence ofl oeve; you cannot, there- fore, feel like those who have. Butif you shall ever love, if all the mental energies, and: all the glow of passion that consitute the es. sence of existence in your nature, ever centre in one point, fix on one object-you may then conceive-what I experienced, when all at once, I found that object vanished. O ! what a chilling void I felt in my  breast! Such it became, soon as suspicion pointed to her dishonor-but, when I: tell you----Alas! my poor brai h cannot bear the recollection t   ' Here the: old man  struck his hand against his bowed forehead. and thus remained for some time. It was :not sorrow that appear- ed to overpower him, but a fierce-chillseemed to pervade his mus- cles. B'e presently raised his head, his face wore an expiession that' was really startling, -and he' continued-. Circumstatces awakened in my   breast a jealousy: of Knox, and Ideterminedto watch his every emotion.    ,  .. ' Start not-my jealousy was well founded-the damn'd darts of  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7970-00000018"/> the arch fiend succeeded--virtue was suedhued, and treacherous lust triumphant-0- ! that the lightnings of/heaven had blasted him or me, ere I had seen the smiling murderer! One fatallday, when having pretended a day's absence, I con- cealed myself at home, I saw her enter her chamber, and in a few minutes my b----r--  can I call him brother! no! he deserves but the name of fiend--followed. This was conviction: and all the powers of my reason fell beneath the impulse of revenge,. My hand instinctively grasped a dagger that was near me. I rushed into the room, and aiming a justs reward at the seducer's heart, the cursed villain shrunk from my vengeance, and it fell on the poor, lost Pauline!  The coward fled, and I was discovered kneeling by my bleeding wife, the fatal weapon still buried in her breast. In'that moment of agony I, know not what occurred. I was dragged by force from the body, and confined, in my own house, under the care of some medical gentleman. )  In a few days my senses returned, and I was able to give some account of the horrible transaction ; which being corroborated by the circumstance of Knox MO]farland's flight, the coroner's jury  returned a :verdict of accidental death, and the remains of my poor Pauline were interred.                   t Though I was not then deemed a madman, my reason had sus- tained a shock it never has perfectly recovered. .       r When I looked back upon the happiness I had enjoyed, and gazed h upon the dreadful wreck around me, my blood now chilled to ice- P now flowed like burning lava through my veins--and mny affright- 1 ed reason fled, at the horrid view. My adoration of the object would scarcely allow me to believe her false, and my love seemed N uniaccountsbly increased!                   A After her interment, I secluded myself some, months from the th ,mbrld. Human nature suffered a degradation indeed in my esti- ro mation. I grew disgusted with mankind, and with the system of the universe, yet I had not then experienced more than half the ho misery I have -since endured. .                wi My cottage at Brigallen now became frightful. Every room re. Af minded me of some -scene, and brought to my Hind my Pauline!  see They brought to me my child. 0O how it chilled my blood to look wit st her U!- I thought her little eyes seemed to darts reproach and . vengeance on her mother's murderer--I could not- bear her pres- whi enaei! X :iEfl,:          I            bro infli f           '    THE VICTIM oF MSPORTU'E.       37 Revenge! sounded louder and louder in my ears, and I deter. nined to quit my home, and seek the villain who had made it des- olate, and wreak my vengeance upon him.  I placed my daughter under the care of a respectable person in le neighborhood, and made an ample provision for her education, ad, in case I should never return, had left her the whole of her other's fortune. I supposed Knoxhad gone to America, and I determined to low.  I shipled at London on board a merchant shio. Fair nds wafted us onward at a lively pace.  I began already speculate upon the satisfaction of revenge; when early one arning, a stern voice cried out, as I was walking the deck: "' Ship alloy!" [ was startled by the unlooked for command, and looking in the ection from whence it issued, I beheld through the dark mist, form of a vessel making direct for Us, and as they neared I ob- ved the flag of the skull and cross bones. was not the least confused, but only felt that I should like to ;ify my  wish to shed the blood of him I hated; and then I ld willingly submit to anything-even being massacred by tes. hey neared us-came along side, and boarded us without any stance on the part of the captain,; resistance, however, would : been useless, as we were taken by surprise; had we been ared their superior numbers would have overpowered us, and is at their mercy. it had I expected to see one amongst them known to me? jr, would I have believed it, had my own eyes not served me. who think you it was?  It was Knox McFarland, the leader, iptain and commander of a pack of bloodhounds, who thus the seas to plunder and kill. crew of our ship were tied hand and foot, and put into the vith the exception of two besides myself, who were favored i transportation from the merchant vessel to the pirate ship. they had ransacked the ship from the top to thebottom, and d all her valuables, they scuttled her, and she went down ie groans of those she carried with her. t   came the putting of things to order on board the pirate, in avocation the prisoners were not favored. I thought my r knew me as he stood over me, and had saved me, only to r more satisfactory death than seeing me sink beneath the  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7970-00000019"/> 38        THE IIMBE-KILN MAN, OR- waves. I looked him in the face and was on the point of gra-p ing him, and cursing him, when I bethought me that he did not re- cognize me, from my extreme thinness caused by a troubled mind. I refrained from speaking to him. The other prisoners I knew would be with me in any scheme I might devise to escape, or to revenge myself of the wrongs he had so unscrupulousy done me. I kept my raging passions down, and by degrees got in the con- fidence of the crew. I at length thought that I had quite a num- ber of friends on board, and so they proved to be. I told them my secret, and they sympathised with me, and said they did not like him as their commander,-and would cut his throat if I would take his place.  " That task be mine,"' said I. X I owe him that for a better cause than you do. Say you agree to it, and this night is his last." They agreed that their captain should die, and urged that I should take his place. Night came. It was a beautiful night. The bright moon was peeping through the broken clouds, and not a breeze was stirring. Knox had been ondeck admiring the beauties of nature, and had unconsciously sat himself down against a gun carriage and fallen asleep. This I was not slow to see, and as soon as he was dozing, with dagger in hand, I advanced with some of my friends near me, and cautiously walking on my knees till I could reach the spot I wished, I poised my dagger more sure than I did the first time it was aimed at him. And then the-blow, sent its cold point cutting to his heart. I fell back in hysterics, at my soul's satisfaction, of having at last acomplished the prominent wish of my heart. He was tumbled,into the sea without form or ceremony, and I was chosen as their commander. We cruised about several weeks but accomplished little, and at length were chased ashore by a man-of war, on a little island. Both vessels were crushed to, pieces as they struck on the rocks of the island. Few of the crews of either saved themselves. When all, were ashore that could be found, there proved to be four--three of the pirate's men, and one of the man-of-war. Raised to a high state of excitement by relating the foregoing scenes, McFarland arose from his seat, and began, walking to and fro, withont saying a word, but groaning in a manner that made Harrvr feel unomfortable, and he arose and quitted the place un- so  *"j . ,               .     perceived by MoFarland; but before he got out of hearing he heard him say-- "What! has he gone I why did he not wait until I had further relieved my troubled memory." And he sank insensibly in his sealt CHAPTER VI. "Whilst I was residing at Brigallen," said McFarland, when Harry again visited him," I became much attached to a child, whose parents lived a few doors from me; he was somewhat older than my daughter, and possessed that show ofbeauty and elegance, seldom witnessed in a person so young. His parents were wealthy, and liberally contributed towards his education. A  fancy would often come to me that I should be happy in my older days to see my little one wedded to a man such as he prom- ised to be. I, one day, when he was busily engaged in playing with my little girl, sat by my Pauline, and said to her. It Pauline would you not be satisfied if you could see our girl grow to be a woman, and marry a man like Charles!" "That, indeed, would be a blessing," said Pauline, " but how sadly may we be disappointed if we indulge in a hope like this." "But can we not train them to love each other?" said I, " and when they arrive at a marriageable age they will think of nought but each other." "' True, with the love of a brother and sister," replied Pauline; "but the love of lovers, is quite different: 'it is not a flower that grows on the dull earth; springs by the calender; must wait for sun-for rain; matures by parts-must take its time to stem, to leaf, to bud, to blow. It owns a richer soil, and boasts a quicker seed! You look for it, and see it not; and lo! even while you look, the peerless flower is up, consumate in the birth!'" Little did I dream that my happiness was so soon to be wretch- edness; even there the evil spirit was lurking near: but thought I, then, a brother could be so heartless, as to make miserable, one who has always been his warm-hearted friend and assistant?  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7970-00000020"/> 40         THE LIME-KILN MAN, 0R But, we will leave these too well-remembered scenes, and re- treat to the island on which I was wrecked as a captain of a pirate ship.! I was in the South Atlantic ocean, near the trade line from the Cape of Good Hope, though so far from that line, as. never to be in the way of any trading vessel unless driven out of its course by a storm. The island was one of rocks, with here and there a small oasis, or level portion, which' was very fertile. When I reached the island, no other was yet there, but soon two of my comrades stood by me; we could do nothing to save the lives of the rest of the crew, as ,the heavy sea then run. ning, beat madly towards the beach.. After we had been there some hours, we saw a man coming, tumblng about on the mad waves, and was thrown up near us, by a heavy breaker, which retired and left one of the crew of the man. of-war with us: we kept our station till near night when we be- gan to thinkof ra place to sleep, or at least to rest. We started to find some shelter, but-to our surprise, foundourselves on a small island, entirely uninhabited. We returned to the beach where we had landed; and now the storm had increased to a gale, and brought large portions of the ship ashore, besides some of the. stores, These were all taken careeof by us; in this occupation the whole night was spent. Morning came with a calm, and found us pros- trate with fatigue. After securing all the provisions we could find along the beach, we all started to explore the island, and see where we were. The day passed and found us again at head quar- ters. All felt discouraged; ho sign of a habitation, or of a living, human being exhibited itself on the whole island. After a con. sultation'was held, we determined to build a- hut and - take our chance of hailing a passing vessel. The first few weeks we spent in looking continually for a sail, but not one was to be seen ; the thought of starvation began to come upon us; our provisions were disappearing, and no source from whence to replenish our stores; we began looking over our provision barrels, and amongst them found two-filled with potatoes, and one filled with whole corn. These we immediately determined to plant, as we had several beautiful plots, and we doubted not the fertility of the soil from the luxuriant growth of grass and shrubbery upon it. Our water casks were being emptied at a rapid rate, and water we could not do without, so in one of these spaces, between two rocky ledgeNs "we dug a well, and to our agreeable surprise found water.   T3$ VICTIM oF MSFORTUNh.         41 Time passed sviftly on, and still no sign of relief-we had enough to live on, from the products, of our potatoes and cor which yielded abundant crops; and the cultivation of the:n gave us partial employment. 1 was of that composition that would not allow   me to be idle, so when I was not employed in the cultivation of our crops, I would retire to a favorite rock, where I could procure large thi slabs of slate, and there have I sat hour after hour, and pencilled my thoughts.    Poetry was my  favorite style then, and as I had not the  material to complete anything very   voluminous.  The same theme   was a characteristic of all my compositions while there, and one I remember was this- .. Spirit of the lost Pauline ' . Hear a wretch lament thy doom  Drops of warm blood from his bosom, Sanctify thy early doom. Spirit of my lost Pauline, Whither d ost thou roam to night-t  Art tkuhz present-dost thou hear ;m 1 Take some form and bless my sight I Slave of guilt, how rash thy prayer? Lo I the horrid vision speeds.-   ,    '  Lo I a female form approehes.. Bee! her wounded bosom bleedes From her cheeks have flied thp roseas Round her eyes no lustre plays  Death has clasped his arms around h l All that form his touch betrays  I      pale and wan, and cold her face is, And her heart has ceased to beat- Worms now revel in her ringlets, Worms now play roundher feet. Monster!  ask the loathsome spectra. W  hy it leaves the peaceful grave? to it to revenge foul murder?      .  Is it innocence to save? Hlarkt-above loud thunders rattle I From below the flames arise I Hark-a voice, eepulchral, murmarr: "I'll not rest till William dies I1 Wretch prepare thy soul for torturek, ' Torts es are preptared forthee I UNfurderarof youthful beauty, "Endless pain thy portion be P' You can imagine my  discontent when this was the topic of my thouhts; and often as I   would be walking along I thoug  ht  could see her image  before me, sometimes p   itying, sometimes upraiding me, and at other times cursing me.,      s A   year had passed away, and .yet h no p iospeet of escape; I passed another year and was still aprisoner; two     ooer mdea had in the tim  e died; leaving one besides myself, the :ony rea   1 dents on the island. and it appeared to me the    only ones likely  to  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7970-00000021"/> THE LIME KILN MAeT, OR be. The third year had almost made its course, when one fine day, as were arranging our gardens, a dispute arose between us, and from words it canme to blows; we clenched and came to the ground; and in that position I killed him! Poor fellow, I was sorry for what I had done, after my passion had abated, for I was now alone in my little world. I now had no one to provide for me, or I for any-one, but lived from day to rday in my garden, or was seated in my favorite haunt, pencilling some sketch, or composing some verses. Every view I could get on the island, I had faithfully committed to my slatei beneath each one writing a descriptive couplet. I had given up all hope of ever being rescued, and therefore made myself as comfortable as circumstances would permit. The climate was warm the year round, and thus I was saved from per- ishing, when my clothes became worn out. In this manner nine years passed away and still left me the sol- itary being of the island. A had in this time contrived and con- structed a sort of boat, with which I went out to fish-an occupa- tion I often amused myself with, having procured some fishing tackle from the wreck. I was one day seated on a high bluff, watching the foaming breakers, as they tossed with mad ferocity upon the beach; and casting my eyes to windward I beheld a ship just rising into the horizon, and appeared to be driving with might and main before the gathering storm direct for the Island. It cheered me; my heart leapt with joy at the thought of a hu. =an being within sight. I quickly hoisted from the highest point my signal of distress, though I could scarcely expect it to be no- ticed in consequence of the storm that was coming fast upon them. They neared the island, and yet bore steady for it; they appeared not to heed the danger they every moment were approaching. I was happy at the thought that they should be wrecked, and that I might once more behold the face, and hear the voice of a living human being,       . They still bore direct for the land, and in a moment more, a crsh was heard-the masts fell to the deck; the. bow of the ship was run high on the rocks while the stern sunk precipitately be- neath the waves; boats appeared to be in readiness for the shock, in they, immediately. emerged from the crushed vessel filled with mon. As they neared the shore, I perceived that they were all wamed to the teeth with swords, pistols, axes, spears, cutlasses, 4.         ,  , *  v '   -u VIUwTIM OVf MSFORTUNE.      43- &amp;ce I began to fear for my life-I took them for pirates-and then I thought I was nothing more or legs when I was driven there, and they would perhaps for that reason sympathize with They  hded, and after watching the beating fo pieces of their ship for some time, they began to look about for entertainment, I took courage and started to meet thym ; they saw mne approach and stopped to await my coming; T stepped up to the one I took for their leader and spoke 'to him, and the answer I got was a shake of the head. 4He could not understand me. Their dress and features at once told mre that they were Chinese. However, hle pointed toa woman they had with them, and made signs that I should talk with her. I addressed her, and was answered if tones that again suddenly brought to my distracted recollection, my Pauline. She was beautiful, and evidently of a first-class family of Europe. I asked her how she came to be in the hands of such ruffians, and her answer was- ", with two others of my sex, were all that were spared from the remorseless deathinflicted upon them, by this band of outlaws and robbers; we were taken on board their ship about two weeks ago, and were treated like brutehs. A fesw days after that a ves- vel came  in view which proved to be an English man-of-war. Theyv gave chase; but the pirate being a smpart- sailer, kept the dis. tance between them  about the same; the chase Was kept up for several days; sometimes the vessels would barely be- in sight of. each other, and at others they were almost within hailing distance. One night a  gale sprung up and it was very dark; the pirate shift- ed his course from north-West to south-west, and when morning came, not a  sign of the pursuers were to be seen; a calm succeed- ed, and left us laying motionless on the water, and while there, a strong breeze brought in sight the same  man-of war from the niorth-west. All sail was set but to no purpose; before the breeze reached the pirate, her pursuers were close upon her; but when her broad canvass caught the wind she stood away like a sea bird, and was chased, with the pursuers in sight until yester- day, when the watch discovered. this island, A consultation: Was held by the leaders and they determined, if the chase was keptup to run the vessel ashore, and thus, you see me a captive of a gang of lawless ruffians. Can you not save me from their perseecu tions e' ' She was about to throw hers elf at my feet, when a grasp ar-  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7970-00000022"/> "        TUE LIME-EILN MAN, OR rested her, and threatening grimaces, and loud chattering among them told me-I was in danger, if I persisted in showing any favor to the prisoner. T kept alpof for the time, and answered their signs as best I could. I conducted them to a part of the is- land the most remote from the part my garden occupied. The tender chords of:my heart were touched with sympathy for the lady, and I determine4 if possible to rescue her from the hands of such wretche ,though I could scarcely make myself be- lieve I was any better than themselves. I left them and retired to my own home, which was now a cave in the rocks, the entrance of which was quite small, but afforded plenty of room inside. I began to devise a plan to effect theescape of the lady from those she so much detested. I at length hit upon a plan, I thought their ignorance would not detect. CHAPTER VII. Several days passed, sfter the wreck of the 'pirats, and my haunt was yet unknown to them, although my gardens had fallen a prey to their ferccious appetites. By stratagem I obtained a meeting with:the lady, and gave her instructions how to act. She possessed the confidence of her masters, and was therefore, free to go where she pleased. ,On a fixed day, was to go into opt eration the plan I had suggested. I went as usual to visit them, and found them much disturbed at the -disappearance of their prisoner; search began to be made; I of course helped them, and' at last repaired toothe beach, and surewenough,%agreeable to our arrangement there found a slate on which were written these words-- U I have found it impossible to' escape with life, from a gang of thieves and murderers, andito rid myself of their infernal b haviour towards me, I here bury myself beneath the, briny Wb I took it and read it to them; and, interpreted it by signs. They appeared to be satisfied, and retired to their favorite cave,   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNB.       45 on the directly opposite- side of the island to mine. I went to a place appointed, and there found the English girl anxiously wait- ing for me- She thanked me again and again as we walked towards my cave'. But, now the point I had aimed at was gained; how was I to secrete my prize from these insolent villians? Should they discover that their prisoner was in my possession I would meet an immediate and horrible fate, as well as the one I had rescued from their insolence. After arriving at the cave, we had a cool and deliberate, discussion, and at length determined to keep them in ignorance, as long as it could possibly be done, and should they gain a knowledge of the lady's existence, to resist every attempt to regain her, even if it resulted in death to us both. The night was passed, and the sun again lit up the heavens with its beautiful crimson. I felt inspired with new life and vig- or. Iwas happy at the thought of speaking and being answered- not by an echo, but by the real voice ofa fellow being. I dared not allow Ellen--as she called herself, outside the entrance of the cave, for fear of a discovery by her persecutors. I ventured out, and looked around; none of the Chinese were to be seen. I told Ellen we were safe from being discovered then, and brought her out to enjoy the prospect with me. No sooner had she a view of the ocean than she exclaimed- "A sail! do you not see a sail!" and pointing in the direction, she fell upon her knees, and imploringly looked to heaven. And then again she steadily gazed upon the approaching vessel. It was yet a great way ff, and kept bearing to the left of us., I hoisted my signal of distress, and it was noticed, and immediAtely she bore down upon us. As she neared, Ellen cried out, ("We are at last safe. It is the same good ship that tried so hard to catch these assassins when they were free on the ocean." "Let us repair immediately to the beach," said I, "that we may not be detained, should any of them find us.' We went to-my boat which lay in the edge of the water, in -a little eddy; and was then half a mile from where the ship had an- chored. We seated ourselves, and I was pushing out towar;ds the ship with a light heart when happening to look to our right I no- tibed that the Chinese had not only discovered the ship, but us; and was giving chase to rescue their prisoner. Their boats were of a regular build and consequently were fast gaining on us, I hav. ing but one paddle, and they four to. each boat. Life or death  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7970-00000023"/> A4P         THE LIME-KILIN MAN, OR Was on either side of us; we felt safe if we could reach the ship in time to shield ourselves, from the merciless Chinese who had been so completely duped. We were anxiously watched from the ship, and as soon as the motives of our flight became apparent to those on board, they seemed interested to the greatest extent in behalf of the little craft bearing the pursued. As we neared the ship, we were but just out of reach of the savage Chinese, and the next moment would have been certain death, when to our great relief and un- bounded joy, we saw'-the pirates fall back, and turning to the ship, we found the cause to be a rather savage looking muzzle staring them in the face, from a port-hole that had been thrown open. The captain beckoned us on, and we were soon handed up the side of the English ship, and well provided for. ' After taking some refreshments, I was questioned in regard to the circumstances that brought me on the island; also about the Chinese, and after hearing tmy story as you have heard it, two boats were dispatched filled with men, to capture these felonious butchers.  The boats disappeared behind the promontory, where a short time before, the pirates had retreated. An hour's suspense, and I was satisfied at seeing them re-appear with the savage looking devils with them-not all, however, alive. A stout:resistance had been offered, and before they would surrender4,wo of their num. ber were shot down. They were all well taken care -of, and the ship weighed anchor and bore leisurely away to the northwest. The weather was fine, and the conversations I had with the crew, had in a few days almost driven sorrow and past recollections from me. The lady too, whose benefactor I hyd been, was ever ready to soothe and interest me, till indeed she became ny fayor- ite companion. I would sometimes forget that I was on boar&amp;a  ship, and thought myself atmy beautifil littlehome atBrigallen, but such dreams were not to be indulged in--reality only aggravated the already lacerated wound, and made me shrink from human sight when the true picture would force itself upon my view. One day, about two months after I was taken aboard, as I was pacing the deck, turning over in my mind the real and the imagiq i nary, a voice from mast head sang out- L anid ho!"  "Where away V" shouted the captain.   THE VICTIM OF M ORTUNOE.        47 On larboard quarter," was the reply. "Let her drive, we are nearinghome boys," said the captain. I immediately applied to the chart and found we were passing Cornsore Point, Ireland. My heart leaped with joy, when I thought myself so near my native home. Liverpool was our desti- nation, where we arrived safe. The- English lady was soon on her way for London, the place of her nativity! and after seeing the Chinese pirates properly taken care of, I too, took my leave and started in the opposite di- rection for Edinburghl, where I arrived in due time. But I could scarcely remember Fe place-change upon change had been wrought. The first object that brought to my mind other days was the old theatre. It still stood, and it seemed but a day or two, since the catastrophe that so materially altered the course of my life, happened before its doors. I pondered a mo- ment, thinking whether I should enter, and witness the perform- ance of the tragedy  of Hamlet, which was to be rendered that evening by a celebrated artist; or if it would best become a pa- rent, to first greet his child. I shuddered at the thought of again attempting to approach the door of the theatre, and therefore resolved to see my daughter at the home of her adoption, as sood as I could be carried there. i procured a conveyance and was directly on my way to my once happy, but now cheerless home.  The night was passed in travel. ing, and before day-break, I was set down in front of the village inn at Brigallen, I took a room but could get no rest; my for- mer troubles came back upon me with redoubled weight, and I could do nothing but walkIthe floor, until thehour came when I could be admitted to see my Elinor, the only object in the world for whom my. heart felt a glowing interest. She often started to the vision of my  memory, and impressed me with the dreadful antici- pation of her fate in such a world of treachery and woe. I left my  room, and the first person I saw I asked in regard to my   daughter, when to my horror I was told-- The old man's eyes filled with tears, and utterance was not in his power. After regaining his self-command, he continued- As I was going to say I was told she had eloped about a fort- night before! Any attempt to describe my  feelings at this intelligence were vain. I  reproached myself as the uthor of her guilty fate, in hav ing abandon ed her education to strangers.  * ts '   &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7970-00000024"/> 48         THE LIME-KXL1N MAN, OR 'A severe illness followed this intelligence, which threatened my dissolution. 'Every effort; to discover her, proved unavailing, where she was, or whether' she existed at all, I knew not. As soon as it was known that I was in, the village I was visited by some of my friends, and amongst them' was young Randall, my former little friend, and the often anticipated bride-groom of my daughter; he knew me, and informed me of the particulars of the affair ; which are of too great length and too little interest to tell you now. Kind friends and strict attentions soon revived my spirits to an extent that would allow me to exercise and walk out.,  The hollow sound of revenge! again sounded in my ears, loud- er than before, and I at length yieided, and determined to blast the traitor from earth, could I but trace, him and discover him. I started for London, where I arrived safe, aud after spending some time in searching boarding house lists, I almost despaired of ever seeing-my sweet child again, when one day I was informed by an acquaintance I had made, that there was to be a masquerade that evening and that a general invitation had been tendered to all who wished to attend. I immediately prepared myself for the oc- casion. My dress was that ;of a Hermit. As I entered the hall, remarks were passed in regard to the oddness of my dress and manners. "Does any one know him? does any one know him?9 was buzzed about the room. I recognized among their voices one I had heard before; It was Charles Randall.  -"The man should be confined," said a tall man dressed as a Monk, "he must absolutely be mad." "Somebody had better take care of him," cried a lady in the vest of a Nun; " he may commit some mischief." "Its excessively unpleasant to be so bored with his sermons," said a swarthy lord. "Insects, away!"I cried, in a voice Charles immediately recog- nized. "Insects, away!--ye flies of fashion!-ye fluttering noth- ings!-Devoid of thought-caprice impels, or folly leads your steps. Leave me-leave me to my own reflections--aye-can *you laugh!,-Grin on--'tis'Levity's meridian now, and this the paraldise of Folly! Oh, how delightful to flutter in the breeze of such a sun t sipping the dews of pleasure, afnd breathing the soft - .       .,.   THE VICTIM OF' MSFORTUNE.      - 49 gales of amorous respiration!-'Twere well were this your ever- lasting region. But, O! ye silly- ones--how Will ye bear the nipping frost, when chill adversity obscures a distant sun!--how will you palate the bitter cup of miser! 'How will you meetthe herald of your dissolutions, who have nyver fostered-the unfortun- ate, or sympathized with the miserable' di the:dying!" Charles had stood silently observing what passed, but when I and the crowd had passed him,: he exclaimed- "'Good Heavens; the last man in the world I should have ex- pected to meet at a masquerade,!"  I presently spoke to Charles, and we left the place together, without any information as to the whereabouts of my daughter, more than a repetition from my young friend that she was un'- doubtedly in London. CHAPTER     VIII. Charles Randall had' been well educated, and possesesd a talent for a more elevated calling than a me're book-keyper. But such was his 'father's notion, and consequently, Charles was sent to Lon- ion to be made a merchant of. For the first-time, Chailes entered the metropolis--for the first time, breathed the fashionable air of Portland Pi,  where Mr. Robinson-Charles' employer-resided. From  the .adount Charles' had received, of the meanness and avarice of traders, from an old acquaintance at home, he was not a little surprised to observe the' elegant appearance of Mr. Robin- son's residence. ,",His astonishment increased, when, upon admis- sion into the hall, he was surrounded by four or five stout, tall fellows' i blue and silver, large buitihes of flowers in their bosoms and white cambric handdkerchiefs in their hands. The youth Was absolutely confused, and felt some difficulty in persuading these gettlmeft of thec ceremoiiies to proCe him an: auience with Mr. Robinson, whoo was 9entertaining :the ca/inetminsters that evening at dinner, at his oWnh table.: '    '   '  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7970-00000025"/> 50         TEE GIB KINT MAUNP, O90 They c0ndescended, however atlength, to show him to a parlor, where, in about an hour afterwards, Mr. Robinson came to him, Ch!arles having sent in his name. " Instead of the merchant of the old school Charls expected to meet, Mr. Robinson was a man of elegant deportment, and dress- ed in the extreme offashion.  He entered the room in a style so commandingly, yet easy, that his presence bespoke: the most accomplished manners. "I am extremely concerned, sir,' said he', "very particular peo- ple are with Ine to-day-, and prevent my receiving you more agree- ably with my wishes, and the respect due to a nephew of Sir Wil- liam Randall.- Allow me, however, to cangratulate youuponyour g safe a'rrival, and to introduce' you to Mrs. Robinson, and her daughters.         ' Charles apologized for his appearance, and would fain hsive avoided the introduction C "O, by no means," said Mr. Robinson, ringing-." In what part of the house is your mistress," said he to the servant who ap- peared. "The ladies have drove down to the Pavillion this morning, sir, and will not return untill to-morrow." "That is unfortunate indeed, but you will excuse me, I am sure; we shall be better acquainted soon, and apologies will become un. necessary, William, serve dinner in this room to my friend, Mr. Randall, and telithe butler to bring what wine he orders." With a cordial shake of the hand, Mr. Robinson left his young frienid to a soliloquy, full of wonder, at the scenes before him. The manner in which he was received tastonished him. Cabinet ministers dining with a merchant was a novelty to him; but more strange than anything else, appeared to him the idea of a,man pot knowing whether his wife and daughters, were at home, or in the country,        , .,   , '  ' A profuse dinner was served up, consisting, of every delicacy that the season afforded, and in a style of elegance beyond every- thing Charles hadpever seen, It wasmiear ten o'clock, when he had finished his sumptuous dinner; and about eleven, he retired, but pleasing recollections would not let him slep.;          . From the spimqns he hd seen that day, Charles was prepare to. expect a very; different ,8style of living, frnom that which .he had anticipated in the country, and such wasz;the reality,    THE VICTIM 0'F MSFORTUNE.       51 RIe was established in Mr. Robinson's house in the capacity, rather of a private secretary than a clerk. Instead of being ;on. fined from an early hour in the morning till late at night, in post- ing ledgers, and copying invoices, as his uncle had taught him to' expect, and as was the case with all merchant's clerks Whe: he -was in the'trade, Charles found that the sons or nephews of mert chants who threw a capital into the firm, underwent no such drud- gery, which is consigned- to boys who had learned to write' fine hands at charity schools. This leisure for a considerable time was also solitude to Charles who had refused several invitations to visits for the vulgar reason of not liking the party.  A well stored library was his usual lounge after dinner; and in the evening he amused himself with music; or drawing; and occa. sionally in attempts at poetry, of which he was fond to excess. The library of Mr. Robinson comprised an assemblage of liter. ature in all its branches, and the privilege, of aceess to such a store was, perhaps the greatest happiness Charles had ever expe- rienced.  :I ving one afternoon finished reading the life of the unfortua. ate CQaitterton, he was detected in tears, by the servant who brought himr his tea and the evening papers. Charles hastily snatched up the newspaper to conceal his emo' tica, and casthis eyes rapidly over its contents.  While his heart beat indignant at the fateof Chatterton, a para. graph presented itself, in which the enormous sums paid in one s(eon to Didelot and his wife for dancing at the opera were enu. merated.                   ' , "Good God!" he exclaimed, when left- to himself, ," how small s portion -of this wealth might have saved to England, and t the 'orld, another Milton!"e 'His ardent mind pursued the melanbholy thought, andhe penned ,he following sonnet-      - "SBlush-blush'ye groit! to hear the frequaet gh,' Depair xtort s friom may a Briton'y. brest- Ipire dby Genui, ind by want deprest,  Whose life i,pmiery-whose hiope-to die  W^hilst in your gorgeous' teatres ; behold; ".  *. :From oelgn siore s a( pantomimie band , .  Sublimely daring-on one lekg to sa,  Delights your folly I and receive s your gold. O sons of Levity, with hearts, of air, Awake I arise from Fashion's fowery bed t '  Go search where Geaiui s Iles hioued, unfid: And rescue suffering merit from despai ; Unbend stern Sufeides determined blow, l cause his psbfed heart with gratitude to 10W p  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7970-00000026"/> 62         THB LIMB-KLX MAT, OR SuCh were . is pursuits-- such his propensities; A conduct so different from most other young men of his age, that he was the source of ridicule all over the house Thefootmen, as theypicked their teeth after dinner, wondered " where the d---- the Hotten- tot was bred " The maids "never saw such an insipid creature in their lives-.supposedhe had left his heart behind him, if, in- deed, hee ever had any ;" whilst the housekeeper, vowed that she "verily believed, for her part, thathe was sent intothe house as  spy to watch their conduct." This latter suspicion aroused the jealous resentment of the but- ler, and the whole coTs of domestics resolved upon a war of inso- lence against him, which, however, the engagig suavity of his manners soon converted into the homage of grateful respect. New senes now opened. The reign of dissipatio n commenced for the season by the arrival of C Irs. Robinson and her daughtersh Charles was introduced by M, Robinson. "Lord, child," said Mrs..Bobinson,'* you can't think how ex- cessively I've been longing to see you, ever since I knew. of your arrival. Well how do you like London Is .it not ilighfully charming t Don't you think .yourself transported to Paradise'? Whatt do you think of the theatres 2 Which do you like best, Drury Lane, or Covent a rden t  Haveyou seen th Parisot? iave yon u herd the Bant i.  .  Charles was never so onfused in his life, asaJthe ubrupt queries of this lady. He was thinking how to reply to her string of questions, whenll I of a sudden she exclaimed-- ";O,'pray do me the favor to write B -note to my friend, Mrs. a, to say we are come to town, and mean to be at the opera to night: and do :me the favor to write to the Misses-,. Oh, no, now Ithink it will be quite delightful toetake them all byi surI prise-and I'll positively frighten themout oftheir senses. Come Emma-ome Lucy"looking at her wLtch,' we have just time enoughto drive around the:suare before we dress; and away they flew, leaving Charles in a state ofperfect astonishment ' ^   W     W    ^   ::^Kfsein i 10, ' t h ar Chrls   a "ver o c6                n   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.      8 CHAPT ER IX .    ..  The winter was passed by the fashionable family of :th 'Ro bn- son's in a round of amusement, of whih the repetition would be tedious' . Theft h eatres,the :opera, concert,: balls routs,*bld4faro banks at length, however, yielded their:influede e oter thee beauties and various attractions of summer.,- i   , - Away flew the. Robinsons to- the Pavillion: whiioh:was mW'st beautiful villa, built by r Mr r Robinson firoma design/on otfoe: bank of the;Thatnes, D ear Richmond        . , i ; To this delightful spot Charles frequently rodeon oan eveitfug and returned to town in the morning'; or sometimes would :re- main ;there two or three days, The whole family delighted hin his company; and though the Pavillion was never without a party of six or seven besides themselves ;syet the additional society of Mr. Randall was' always- a  matter of pleasure.' But to C none was whis converse so sweet, his manner so pleasing, as to the daughter of a merchant, and. an acquaintance of Mrs. Robihton. -  Nor was her well. cultivated mind-her wel grounded principles her grace,/her elegance of manner, arid winning s oftne of dispo- tion unnoticed by Charles, - A mututl :esteem wasS tte result. It may be properly calleds esteem, for it was the h6magg of the judg-' ment and the heart, unblended with pasion it was! the delightful dawning of love; a serene, pleising' :Sensation of the'mind,.un- ruffled by desire.  ;  In their walks, they would oftimes hear of 0each others boeneo- lenee from the neighboring cottage. ' In their- mixed Companies, a smile of approbation frd* i one," re. warded the expression or sentinments from the other. In thelifib ry their choice of authors was frequently: thee same whilst their private conferences still more rfully discovered their conformity of sentiment and taste.       ... Dividing his time between the P-avillion and Portland Place, al. ternately enjoying the society of'his city friblds and the amiable ' Anna, with just enough of business to makle hUs leisiure ore  agreeable, Charles, pagsed the moiths of this suum er more pleas. antly than any former pertiod of his ifeS -  Sfich was Charits Randal;l when twards: the lo8se of day about the fiddle of September; I muffled mysel up m "'ioie k aioak, inquiled for' him in Portland Place; and 'upon bein i;own ingto , ,                      .  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7970-00000027"/> 54         THE LIME-KILN MAN, OR an apartment discovered myself to him. I had grown paler, and muchb thinner, than whefi Charles saw me last. "Are you alone?"I asked. " Y'ol ",'* replied Charles. '    . Are you at leisure :i Does no banSquet wait for you?" ' NMone,! assure. you;,. Mr. Robinson ,is at Buxton, and the rest of the ifamily at the Pavillion."  "Is the door fast?-bolt it-I. lave a secret to impart," :i CGrles, began to survey;me mote closely. ;,But obeyed me how- eyvr,:,and repeated his;.assurance that we were altone. "When I last saw you I gave you a minatUre," I said, "Have ypu ita bout'you"     ,    .   Qhal!es drew it from his bosom. "'!Yet; dwont show it me ;--confirmation is unnecessary. Put it up! -O, horrible!"                   i' Ranath was affected; by my agitation, and, said- ',What new sorrow,: ir," afflicts you thus?-may I be entrust- ed:        -    * - ,    ' 'J  o    "( Sorrow! give it4not$so lsoft a name!: Fools, women, children can be sorry.., If it raits, if the dew of hgaven wet their silks they are 0orryt:; If a dance is: :,tponed, or . pl&amp;y deferred, or' a dinner zpqiled:; flks .#re ,sorry, i What, ,thn, but horror is it /that a man manust feel, *who haing. .murdered hjis ownwife drives his child to perdition!--my Elinor'!-rmy daughter, L i  "Haye you any tidings of your daughter, sir ." said Charles. ; '"Look at that miniature. Is if thecounterpart of that which Yot, possess," and . handed it to, hjm;. : :        : ; I felt an impulse to walk--I left(,my,: seat and, walked three or four times up apd down the room:hifph. happend to be a dining parl qr an drank a tumble' ofS water Wtioh stood on the:sideboard and; threr; myself into a chair, .. .  .  "' It was pyinnttion when ytqatao-e. t0q res ide her, of which I: was apprised, to have visited vou,but a strange disvCry, prevented ', me. Sauntering, ne day, through the $treets of the metippolis I wajatttracted by billiant sow^ of jew elry and trinketts in th0, window of a pawn^rok er Among; a coawd;, of other. articles, in one,po99er of the. indow,vW e.. thre, miniatures, on of, fwNich struck me as greatly resemblin4g ,whst. I had- seen., Upon a closer examinatioD, not a doubt remained of its being the counterpart of that, whichl I presentetto you at, Bir allenl M. y villainous bPro- ther, mn our happy days aited the two, kenes. Q One ,as w y   o  TUB VICTIM OF MSFORTUNrE. poor Pauline', whieh I gave you; the other wasfgiven to ti*e go- corness of my daughter, to be presented to her, and I know was presented to her on her twelfth birthday. "To see this miniature, then, was to see my daughter, ahd brought to my mind the painful recollections of heruncertain fate. I pulrchased it; and then, with an earnestness that surprised the pawnbroker, requested him to relate to me all feklkew oncerning it.                 m    enwcnenn 'Barren was his intelligence, amounting merely to the recol- lection, that it was pledged thereby% whman who lived as ser- vant to some:/adies, at that time lodging nearly opposite, at, a hlouse that had since'been pulled down. "'The woman,' he continued, still very often comes her ; and you may perhaps learn something fuJrther from her.'  ' "Day- after day, forgetful ofevelyrling' else, Waited on the pawnbroker, and in about a week, was iformed th e widow'had been there and left' her address. I sought her residence-a Inise- . able one it was. Oh, how my heart sickened at the pictlreof misery and vice, wretchedness and debauchery .and how fearfully: I gazed in each countenance, dreading to behold. among the hire- lings of prostitution, my poor, abandoned child! "I doubted no longer. Ellen, Ipersuaded myself, was an ' b rigement of her own name; and I determined not to rest until I had discovered her retreat if living-her grave if dead. : "The clue I gatlhered was, that s after the miniature was parted with, these unfortunate women quarrelled and separated . Ellen went witha young nobleman to Bath, and the other unfor- tunate went abroad. "To Bath, the next day, I travelled;  ad,  by inquiries, found  that  the poor w retch resided there about six months, and then quitted that place for  Bristol, where she opened a little shop w ith the wages of her infamy, the nobleman having quitted her. Hereshe resided nearl twelve m onth  when having met with impositions and lOses, she became involved in debt, and was compelled once more to seek refuge from:her cred- tors in the crowd of this metropolis, and returned to a miserable traic of shame. O  , what a year of misery have! since en, dured ! "Every place of amuse ment, every haunt of pleasure, every mart of shame,;I have visited. I hav e strolled whole nights through the streets of London, viewing each female with dread . \ii ahf  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7970-00000028"/> 56        ' THE LIME-KILN MAET, OR ful curiosity; but all was in vain, till about a fortnight ago, at the corner of the Strand, Ii met the woman to whom I first ap- plied. She knew met and accosted me- "'(Ah! sir' cried she 'poor Ellen.' "I seized her by the arm--'what of Ellen? where is she! an- swer me!-show me where she is!'-I exclaimed. "' Haven't you seen her, then sir . Poor thing, she wouldn't know you now, then-she's quite delirious.' "' Take meto her this moment,'said I. I followed her silently through several lanes and alys; till at length she stopped at a dirty old house, kept by Ha woman who sold green groceries. Feeling my way up two pair of dark stairs, I entered a miserable apartment. The walls had once been white-washed, but were now covered withsmoke and dirt. A dull light was admitted through a small casement, darkled by pieces of old rags stuffed in several/ places where the glass was broken. Not a chair nor table was in the room, no grate, nor stove was in the fire place. But a few bits of wood were burinng in one corner, over which an old wo. man, covered with rags and filth, was warming something in a p W? . .. , . f -t , , a ','  . i' ' "    . "On the floor--on :thej/chr! Mr. Bunce," repeated McFarland was a sight to agonizea heart of stone! A thin mattrass only was between, the, loose boards and the poor emaciated wretch breathing out thel!ast sigh of anguish and despair! "' There's poor Ellen, 8ir,' said -the woman who, conducted me. And then addressing herself to the old woman--' here, Mother Andrews is a good gentleman come to see poor Ellen!' "' God bless him for it,' said the old woman; 'but I'm afeard it is all over. I've been warming her a little tea-it's all I've got to give her.' ("All this pass6d during my profound silence, for I could rot speak. I knelteby the poor dying object-I took hers senseless hand, but in vain searched for the resemblance of my Elinor. The agonies of death had already deformed the countenance, and and in a few moment with a groan she expired! I dropped a tear upon the lifeless hand--the first I had for a. long time shed--it greatly relieved me. "'God receive her poor soul? said the old womani "This aroused me.' '"IlI fated child r of an jll fated mother!' I cried and embraced the senseless corpse. '0, what a change from   THB1 VICTIM OPMSFORTUNE.       57 the blooming cherub of innocence, that I abandoned!' At length the voice of the old woman again aroused mne--  'Is there a Deity!-is there a Deity ' I exclaimed; 'sand is this his world-and are we his creatures?-O, no, no, or these things "It was an ejaculation extorted by the keenest anguish that ever pierced the human breast. Tile poor wretch gazed at me with a sort of horror.                a "'Ah, ir!' cried she; -don't talk so! There is a God who knows what's best for us all; and if we sufferin this world hemcan reward us in anot her ! and I am sure, poor soul, she went through enough to atone for her folly. Poorcreaturenobody knows but them that sees, what they go through!, "'And who are you, that have seen so much ' said " 'Come -sit down; (there was a washtub and an old box, which served for chair and table) and, if you can; relate to me the story df :this poor wretch!'       "I only knowed her lately. In their best days they kepthigh- er company; I have lived ten years in this house; and, though Ellen is the first that died here, I have tended many a, one an- that bed. But if they grow worse, they generally got into some hosw Vital, or went to their parish?' "'And were there no hospital or parish for her?' "Why, you shall hear. Its about two months ago, sinee, one very rainy night, this poor creature was brought here by one that had tormerly had half of my bed. She waS thatday thrust out of doors by a hard hearted creature who thought herself an angel truly, because she did not send the poor soul to jail, for about two and foity shillings, that she owed her. '"  ' She was as thin as a lath ! and had a cough; it made one's heart ache to hear it. The clothes upon her back, and two shil liings and a pocket-piece was all she had in the world. "'The girl that brought her was a tender hearted thing' and promised that, if I would let her have half of my bed, she would see me paid my  four shillings a week regularly ; ;'and for a while sure enough she did, and brought her poor friend , now and then a raspberry tart, and a little wine. But all of a  sudden she left it off , and I  have neverseen her since. God kno ws but she may n owr "b  e in want herself!            .  "' This is Society [ ' said I  shaking as wit h an - age.  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7970-00000029"/> 58         THE LIMB-KILN MAN, OR ("' What, sir,' said the old woman, not understanding me. She went on. :" ' So, then, I was obliged to break into her two shillings ; one went all at once for a bottle of stuff for her cough; and soon the other was spent too. Then the poor clothes went; one thing af- ter anotheir. And at last she grew quite delirious. '4' I had saved up about a crown, but that I know'd wouldn't last long; and as I could do no washing for the other girls while I tended her, there was nothing coming in; and so I was obliged to apply for her to be removed to the hospital, where she was to have gone this morning; but,: last night she changed so for the worse, I thought it cruel to move her and as she wantea onlya little moisture in her mouth I said I'd tend her till she was .re- leased, and they might send for a coffin--' "'No--no' I exclaimed, ' I will provide what's wanting now. Perhaps an earlier meeting might have saved her life.' "She was decently interred. The good Mrs. Andrews was re- warded. Good, I call her, for whatever in her youth she may have been, she now possesses a heart that wills all good imagina. ble to her fellow creatures. "Thus far I had acted upon the presumption of her being my child. There was a little doubt upon the point indeed; but still it was not certian; a circumstance took place that confirmed me more in doubting than believing. I applied to the woman who so inhumanly thrust her,from the house, for information, but she could - give me none. There was a trunk of her's she said in her posses- sion, which upon paying what was owing I might receive. She believed it was full of letters. "I eagerly consented; and, upon opening the trunk, found it, as she said full of letters. Among them was a bundle written in a female hand. J untied the bundle, and found the letters signed "Elinor." They were compositions of uncommon merit as to style and manner, but the matter though ingenious, was highly exceptionable. 'This circumstance staggered me extremely. That the letters :were written by my-daughter, is beyond a doubt. They had been sent under cover, and began "Dear Friend," but no address was ,upon them. "The only conjecture, then, that can reconcile the deceased's having these letters, written by herself in her possession is, that   THE VICTIM 0o MSFOrt  .     -  ' 59 'they have'been returned from the person to whom they were written.'" "It may be so,"'said Charles; -' but surely it is not too much to hope, that the deceased, after all, was the friend who resided with your daughter; and that she herself may yet be living." "Not for the wealth of worlds would I change the certainty of her death for such a torturing suspense. No-no, I will cherish the thought of having laid her in the silent grave though it be a '  delusion. "Come with me-come I'll show you the spot where she lies. I'll repeat to you the story of her sufferings: for, O, young man, - n   such a house as this, these lessons are not common. The riot, the mirth, the glitter of guilt alone, you behold here. Come-- come to the abodes of the dying, and the graves of the' dead and learn its certain consequences. And we started-together." CHAPTER X. A  few days after my visit, and while the Robinsons were yet at the pavillion, Randall received the following letter-- 'Sir, It is with extreme reluctance that an unhappy stranger obtrudes herself upon your notice. The forms of society do not so strongly condemn me as the emotions of my own proud heart, but adversity weakens, even where it does not Conquer pride-and I  have known adversity. "Though perfectly unknown to you now, as an acquaintance, I hope you will not spurn the  fortunfortunate. It is indeed, almost too much to solicit the favor of a visit, though they tale I am corn- pelled to relate, I should be unwilling to trust on paper. I will venture, then, to beg one hour of your time, whenever it can be best spared from more cheerful occupations, to listen to the dis- tresses oft "Sir,  "Your most obedient servant, ELINOR   iMAION . Berners street. P, S.-I shall take the liberty of ordering my servant to call for an, answer in the evening.         E M  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7970-00000030"/> 9O        TTHE LIMB-KILN MAN, OR Curiosity and compassion, were awakened by this letter in the breast of Randall. Repeatedly and distinctly, he read its con tents. There was distress, yet delicacy peculiarly blended in its phraseology-then in the warmth of his first impressions, he was going immediately to Berners. street; but the impropriety of such a step soon occurred to him. This incident occupied his entire thoughts-he formed a variety of conjectures, formed his conduct according to the suppossed -cases, and as speedily renounced his imaginations as absurd. That the purport of this visit was to afford him an opportunity of displaying his generosity, seemed certain; and he began a cal- oulation of his finances, His father had remitted him large sums, His expenses though great, were well managed. Hewas i strict economist, and therefore, though his hand had been liberal, his purse was not empty. "If, therefore," thought he, " a temporary assistance will avail, I shall have the satisfaction of affording it; and if, on the contrary a more deep calamity, than my ability can disperse, claims the just notice of discriminating benevolence, there is my uncle, or Mr'. McFarland, who, I am sure will thank me for the information, and surely the writer of this letter cannot be unworthy of their favor. Such were the reflections, of experience, and such the feelings of a benevolent and uncorrupted heart. He wrote an answer, appointing the next morning, at twelve o'clock for the interview; and felt no inconsiderable anxiety till its arrival. At the appointed time he repairedto Berners street, and was ushered into a very neat and elegant drawing room. In a few minutes a lady entered, in deep mourning, with a work basket in her hand. She seemed almost sinking with diffidence; and the 'struggles of her wounded pride appeared depicted .in her counte- nance. Charles rose, and bowed respectfully. "This condescention, sir," said she, hesitating; "' the condeseen- tion of this visit, is, at the same time, the source of so much satis- faction-and pain!-that I must request your pardon;-but-I really-I---," and she sank into a chair, and applied her hand- kerchief to her face. Randall stood mute with surprise. Instead of the female of his imagination, worn with woe, and wasted with despair-a formand face had appeared to his view, the most beautiful hehad ever seen.   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE. 6! Her figure, considerably above the middle size was majestic, dig- nified and elegant--her countenance admirably corresponded with her person. Dark hair, flowing in luxuriant ringlets, on'her fore-: head, and hanging loose on her neck greatly heightened theeffect of a most delicate complexion, still farther assisted by well formed eyebrows, and lips of coral hue. Her dress was-sirmply elegant, and displayed the beateous sym- etry of her person to advantage. After a pause of some dura- tion, she said-- "Pray, be seated, sir; for Randall, unconscious that he did so, had stood silently gazing on the forem before him-" how weak are our strongest resolves!" continued she. "I had imagined, pre. pared myself for this interview; and' thought myself strongly armed against all the attacks of pride--but the remembrance of what they have been, is among the last things with which the un- fortunate are compelled to part." Charles, extremely afflicted at her distress, attempted once or twice to speak himself, but failed in the attempt. The lady con- tinued- "Many and powerful, were the struggles I have encountered, ere I resolved upon soliciting this interview; but the character of Mr. Randall-so opposite to the volatile and unthinking youths oP'fashion to whom a story of distress is the source either of spleen or scorn--added to the very encouraging traits of benevolent sym- pathy so strongly portrayed in his countenance, at length embold- ened me to take a step, I have since, more than once, repented. I have therefore, sir, to entreat your pardon for so great a liberty, and hope you will completely erase from your memory the indis- creet request I have made."     , "Madam-I--if I can-if it is in my power--I shall be happy, madam-I hope-if there is anything" Such were the incoherent words of Randall, in whose breast pity, which was its constant guest, now mingled its influence, with a new and strange Sensation; so strange, so new, as to create a wild alarm, not only in his countenance, but in his words and manners. *'I perceiveyour generous intentions; but I cannot--I ought not to take advantage of so much goodness --Hoew strongly you resemble you' worthy father!" "You know my father?" ' Yes. sir, I knew him once. They were happpy- days When I  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7970-00000031"/> 62         THE LME KILN MAN, OR knew Mr. Randall! I little dreamt how severe adestiny was too succeed those joyful days., Butalas, how feeble is our hold on earthly bliss--how fleetingour joy-how unstable our hopes of happiness! O, painful to coritemplate the picture of what I have beenh--tad view the gloomy scenes before me. Wealth and friends and hope were then all mine. Now poverty, and enemies, and fell despair surround me; and the worst that fate can ordain tot mortals is my gloomy expectation?" Randall had struggled to overcome his embarrassment; and collecting himself as much as possible, he said-  "If the calamity, which has wrought so unhappy a change, may be communicated without pain, believe me, madam, the confidence with which you honor me shall be respected, by one who has ever felt for the unhappy, but who never felt so unhappy as at the pres. ent moment." *' Ah, sir!" said Elinor, and sighed-'" the soothing voice of friendship, has been so long unheard; my ear has been so used of late to the sounds of anger and defiance, that the tenderness of your expressions has the influence of music on my mind., But when you- are acqhainted with my story, I much fear that your ]an- guage will be altered:; and that ceasing to pity my misfortunes, you will only censure my misconduct."  U Pardon ne, madam," said Randall. "The emotions of pity are arbitrary sensatibns, for :the justice of which we cannot be pre. sumed to be responsible; but the voice of censure ought at least to have the sanction of experience, and the motives of prevention. So add poignancy of reproof to'the stings of convictions, betrays an unfeeling heart at all times; but most unpardonable, indeed, would it be to pour reproach into the breast that seeks by confi- dence' the balm of consolation.     ' "Cease, sir! I beseech you, cease to speak thus! You are not aware howemuch you increase the wound you seek to heal!" Then rising from her chair, and walking with considerable emo- tion about the room she continned-  "I have born oppression, I have suffered with some degree of dignity, the stings and arrows of outrageous fortune; bat your pity, your sympathy, Mr. Randall, disarms- me ,of my purpose, and increases the weakness I had almost subdued. I will hasten to relate to you my errors, that yourscorn and contempt may sib- due the baneful effects of your too cruel tenderness!" "'Mysterious!' exclaimed Randall, in a low tone.   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTU"iS.       63:, '"Hear me, sir-my name is Marion-my family is one of the most ancient and respectable .in the country where ,they, reside, My parents both died ere I had attained an age to be sensible, of, th eir loss. I was the youngest ot six,orphans. My eldest broth- er, who so;ucceeded, to the estates of his father, was atthe period, of his decease, a student at Cambridge University; :another brother was! an ensign in, the military of the country - 4d a: third served As a midshipman in the navy.  "I had two sisters, who with myself, were taken, underthe guar- dianship of my mother's brother, the Dean of------ . w ith this gentlemanweM resided, enjoying every :ad:vantage ,which his for- tune or abilities could bestow. As my father died intestate, and the whole of the property was in landed estates, every branch of the family was left dependent on the discretion and generosity of my elder brother,.   . "Poor Edward! Thy memory shall never, be insulted by me however severely the consequences. of the error, fall on thy unhap- py sister. /Suffice it then, to observe, that therindiscretions of the youth at college were made the means of enriching a few worth- less characters, who preyed upon the openness of his soul, and con- signed to poverty and dependence those, who were born with far better expectations.. i "The remorse he,felt, that a fate so unworthy of his family should be brought upon them by himself, drove the ill-fated Edward to those wretched expedients, ;which feeling for a moqment the pangs of recollection, increase the dread of thought, and hurry those who seek them to a grave of shame.  - .   .  "So it was with my poor Edward! Peace to his, spirit I my other brothers are each rising to wealth andtieminence ia their pro-  fessions. The eldest of my sisters marriedto'thp satisfaction of the Dean, and is now the happy mother of, everal children. My other sister died.                4 i Now, sir, I am to speak of myself. Fr9m .s long residence in his family, from his parental fondness, I had imbibed for the Dean, my uncle, all the tender feelings of a: daughter. His house. was asimy native home; and every desire that theyjoung heart could appreciate, was gratified as soon as known. It, was:hpre I once was honored with the society of your father. He was an excel- lent man. I have no particular event to detail, till about two years ago, when a distant relative of my uncle, who had been some time upon a visit at the house, did me the honor to offer me pro.  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7970-00000032"/> 6ffi4       THE ETHE LIME-KILN MAN, OR posals of marriage. It was not the first offer I had received, but it was the first that had received the pressing recommendation of the Dean. I answered, however, to'this proposal, as I had, done others; and canididly intimated, that I did not feel that affection, on which alone TIbuilt my hopes of happiness in the married state ; and without which it wAi mny firm determination never to approach the altar! "Why, then did he still pursue me? Why did he commence a persecution, that can only terminate with my existence . Oh why! Oh,' tmy beloved unele! 4why did-the cold calculations of interest outweigh, in thy breast tht pleadings of nature! "1 miustcheck tmyself.. The wealth and honors of the gentleman who was my siitor were among his inferior reeommendations. "Elegant in his persons and manners; happy and:uniform in his temper mild and betevoletlt in his disposition Ilearned without pedantry; witty, without satire; he possessed almost every qual- ification that can render him amiable and estimableb Yet, sir, I felt for Lord Tyrone nothing like love. I admired his accom- plishments: 'I respected his virtues; but, alas!. this state of mind is far short of love. Ybu perhaps, Mr. Randall, as well as amy self, are, I presume, sensible how different the operations of our hearts are from the Cool exercises of our understandings." The abriuptneiss of this appeal, and the penetrating look that accompanied it, overwhelmed with confusion the youth to whom it Was addressed,' Randai blushed dee ply; he stammered, but his words were incoherent sounds.. Of love, as :a passion' he had hitherto Known nothing but the name,  There*was, perhaps, something extremely like the begin- nings of love now struggling for existence in -his' bosom ; but it was a new, a strange sensation of whoseorigfn he was ignorant of whose influence fie had no conception. Elinor whose penetration and aft equalled her beauties, ob- served with satisfaction, with delight; the infatuation of' which she well knew herself the creator. 'And ;rising she- abrtptly, quitted the room, 'thiuking her strange captivation, would in silence, and faney'bind him istrorger to her.   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTNRS.        '5 CHAPTER. XI. "My uncle," said she, after being absent a few minutes, MEd again seating herself near Charles' chair; "My uncle so warmly espoused the cause of Lord Tyrone as to descend to, threats of his displeasure, if I persisted in refusing his proposals. iHe is naturally a humane man; but, in this instance, his anger over- came him, and his, expressions were harsh and cruel. Still, sir, I persisted in myarefusal. "My brothers were appealed to.  MySmarried sister,and her lord, were also made my judges; and with one voice they. all condemned me to the cruel alternative of marrying -a man, for whom I felt no preference, or of forfeiting, for ever, their protec- tion and esteem! " The most insulting and unfeeling motives were attributed to  me in rejecting so splendid anc honorable a,proposal. I was shunned by the whole family.  My walks were watched; at last prohibited.  IJ was detained a prisoner in my uncle's castle,- nor even plemitted to walk -beyond the boundaries of his park. "( As my relations increased in their cruelty towards me,. Lord Tyrohe redoubled his tenderness and attention; obtaining by his interest, occasional liberties, and some few marks of concern from my tyrants; but, instead of gaining by this conduct, any advance in my esteem, it:sunk him beneath the former level of indifference and I became disgusted with the man, who would consent to re- ceive such mean advantages. "My situsation grew .daily more and more intolerable., A faith- ful. servant, who had attended me for many years, was discharged upon the. pretended suspicion of aiding me in an ideal; corespon- denoe^. which ,teyaid I carried on with some low' bori wretch, who I had the meanness to prefer to the man of their hoi'e.  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7970-00000033"/> (oG0        THE LIME-K'ILN MAN, OR "Alas! how much were they mistaken, if, indeed, they imag- ined my heart at that time had a preference among mankind. No, sir, not even a friend beyond poor Mary, who they discharged, had I in the world. When she was gone, they placed over me a cruel, insolent old woman, in the capacity of servant, but with the power of a mistress. "Debarred the comforts of society, of reading, drawing, or any other amusement; my mind, unshaken in its resolution, became desperate; -and after duly weighing all the obstacles that opposed themselves to such a step, I determinedto quit for ever, the house that had hitherto been my asylum. "  , My faithful Mary found means to acquaint me, in my captivi- ty, that, after her dismissal, she hadtravelled, at her own expense twenty-eight miles from the castle to an old lady, who was my  father's distant reation, but an inveterate foe to my uncle, and to all my mother's relatives. "This lady, a widow, and childless, was extremely rich, and though she had never seen me, such was the success of Mary's. tale of my sufferings, that she commissioned her to tell me, she would receive me as her daughter, if I could escape from the castle. '"I did escape; and Mary and I were received by my relative with every mark of respect. "My uncle soon discovered my retreat, and wrote a letter filled with indignation at my conduct, and a formal renunciation, in which he was joined by my brother and sister. "It my new situation,I was for some time as happy as I could wisi; till an event-' -but let me stop in time. If I proceed with sincerity to relate the cause of my Unhappiness, I am- afraid--in- deod Mr. Randall--I am much afraid, the loss of your esteem would be the painful consequence, and Heaven only knows how highly I esteem your good opinion." (' Madam?" exclaimed Randall. "Aye, sir, you may wh be -surprised! My face, my voice, are neew to you; not so yours to me."  "t Indeed!".said Randall. "Where, pray; have you seen it?" "i No matters sir-since I now see it for the last time!" "I hope not!" said Charles, with warmth. Stranger as you are to ime, madam I feel so deeply interested, so much concerned in yoburwelfare, that excepting my sister and my mother, I know no person in the world I more ardently desire to serve" -    THE VICTIM OF MSFORITUNE.      67- "You are kind-you are very kind!" said Elinor. "Can I serve you, madam "- "You alone can serve me; but you will not, nay, you shall not serve me."' "' You speak mysterious, and look wild. Fear not, I beseech you, to confide to me your sorrows!-my bosom shall be their sacred repository." "Generous-generous youth!" exclaimed Elinor-, and with a beaming unconsciousness, threw her arm upon his shoulder-then appearing to recollect herself, hastily withdrew it. Every moment now, increased the desire of Charles to be made acquainted with the causes of her distress. HHe gazed earnestly upon her countenance.  He ventured to take her hand- "Dear lady, let me entreat you to delay the recital of your woes no longer. Of whatever nature they may prove, God only grant me the power to remove them, and I shall be the happiest of all men." "Your generosity of mind, your tenderness of heart, are indeed the objects of my admiration! But, alas! my- calamity is of so peculiar a nature, that the most generous mind, the most suscep- ' tible heart cannot conceive anything that can alleviate it. Mine is a silent sorrow, thatchroods within my own breast. A sigh is its only expression--a tear is its only relief. No tongue has pro. claimed it-no ear has received its complaint. To you it desires to speak-to you alone it will ever speak; but spare me, pardon me; leave me!?' and she wept. How strange is her behavior, thought Randall--how wild, yet how mournful her countenance! After a pause, Elinor recov- ered her former serenity, and continued-- I am to blame, sir, thus to trifle' with your time. I will en- deavor to conclude my dull narrative, and at all hazards venture to' explain the motiverf my request to see you. "My benefactress, whose bounty was my only resource, con- tinued to treat me with the affectionate regard of a parent; my days'rol1ed on in comfort; and my heart knew no distress, till that event to which I before alluded. O, God! how shall I relate it! But it must be told. "There resided near our dwelling a family of respectability, but not wealthy; they therefore did'not visit our house, but we sonce or twice met in. the neighborhood. Of the father, of the mother,  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7970-00000034"/> VO        'Tlfi  'J 1.MfTlfiMEJ LN X AMj, OU of the daughter I shall say nothing; but of the son! Pardon me, indeed I cannot proceed!" "6 Waive this reluctance," cried Randall. Confide in me as your brother; you shall(find me as tender of your feelings, as zealous in your service, as if we each, recognized the same parent." "What do I hear!" cried linor, quickly; "is it possible! Did you say, you love me as a brother! Happy, happy mo- ment!"She took his hand, and kissing it with warmth, exclaim- ed- "My brother--my brother!" Randall starting from his chair, and snatching away his hand seemed thrown into a delirium; while Elinor appearing to recol- lect herself, hung down her head, and blushed. ;' In the name of heaven, Madam, tell me, who and what are you? Finish, I beseech you, this mysterious tale, and quickly, that I may, if possible, serve you ; or if not, may instantly escape a presence that creates emotions of pain and pleasure, too powerful to be long endured!" "( I entreat your forgiveness," cried Elinor, "'But go, sir-go- ere you know the misery you have occasioned-the storm of ruin that you have faised--go ignorant of my wretchedness, which to know, would perhaps excite a painful pity in your breast, but no re- lief to me! Since to behold me is so painfadl--" "I did not say so!" cried Randall, "or if I did - " "I see, we are both too much agitated," interrupted Elinor. "Your surprise, and perhaps your pity, have overpowered you; whilst Ham the prey of feelings which rack my bosom with tor- ture inexpressible.!' ( 'Tis suspense alone that tortures me?, said Randall. ," Your manner-your mysterious words, and the wildness of your eyes, make me dread a something which I fear-yet ask to know!- You speak of a youth who resided near yomu-you talk of ruin, of misery, of which I am the author--you request to see me---you ' desire me to leave you, as ignorant as I came! Whence Spring such inconsistences?" 4' From a source you never dreamed of --- From love!'" Her countenance was now altered from the picture of contend- ing influence to a portrait of determination. Her eyes were fixed firmly on Randall, She: remained silently gazing on his face a considerable time. RandaJl was dumb. "'Tis, over!" at length she cried;, I hbav conquerred! The   --........ w U..i..VI IU nf'jf - oU youth to whom I have alluded, is Charles Randall!--yes! -he it is, whom Fate had ordained my destruction! For him, I quit my friends, my country. For him, I forfeit affluence, and embracethe horrors of poverty, in a foreign and distant clime. Was it, then, too much to ask the favor of one hour's interview, whereby to de. clare how ardently I love, and how largely I sacrifice to a hopeless passion! O Nature!--can I thank thee for the liberal share of personal attractions thy hand has given me, since they have served to. heap upon my head the persecutions of a train that I cannot help despising, while on that heart alone, which I esteem, their in- fluente is too weak to impress even a cold regard:!"  Randall was lost in wonder. After various attempts, he said- "I dont remember ever to have seen you before!" "I can easily believe you, sir." "And yet, I think, if ever I had beheld such a countenance as yours, surely, madam, I could not have forgotten its interresting traits!" "Nay, sir, I must not hear you, if your voice assumes that. strain. A Do not imagine sir, my declaration meant to claim your pity I No; my resolution is fixed as firmly as the decrees of Fate. One moment longer let me detain your ear and then, fare- well for ever! Briefly, then-the same persecution though from different quarters, rendered the abode of my benefactress as mis. erable as my  uncle'&amp;with this addition of wretohedness--that in the latter, my'heart was wholly disengaged; in the former, your image, your worth, barred all avenues to affection for another. The object so dear to me was unknown to my benefactress--to all the world, but myself. My refusals were therefore deemed ob. stinancy: my  perseverance became rebellion; and I was at length driven to the dreadful alternative of quitting for ever, the refuge I  had obtained, or to approach the solemn altar, and vow fidelity with my lips, whilst my heart would be adulterous for ever. Such was the choice held out for my adoption-and could I hesi- tate? No, not a  moment! I  waited not to be driven from the house. Voluntarily I  departed. I have remained some time in the metropolis-I determined to see you, and now, will forever quit the country that gave birth to my existence and my woes! I will seek in some corner of a distant land, that grave, which alone can restore peace to my heart by an oblivion of you!" She ceased. Randall who had risen from his chair, and was walking about the room, was deeply involved in thought, corn.  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7970-00000035"/> 'SU        THE LIME-KILN MAB, OR batting one suggestion of his fancy after another, till his head be- came giddy. He threw himself on a sofa, and leaned his head on his arm. Elinor with the tenderest expressions of concern, took his hand, and pressed it warmly. "t If I have given you pain-if I have relieved my own breast at the expense of a moments uneasiness to you, what a source of eternal regret! Or, if I have rendered myself odious, by a dec- laration which custom condemns, and have erected a monument of scorn in that remembrance, where I sought to deposit the pearl of pity. O, how miserable has my folly made me! Say then, only that youdo not abhor me-and I will never-never-trouble your quiet more!" "His heart must be differently moulded from mine," said Charles, " that can despise,or abhor you, madam. Your confession has so much influence onmine, I would say more-but at present let me entreat of you not to quit this place, till I have been favor- ed with another interview. I have a mother-I have-" "Hear me on my knees, Mr. Randall," interrupted Elinor ; "' if you do not wish to drive me to the most awful crime our nature can. commit grant me my request;, silence, eternal silence to my story. There is not a calamity in life I should so hardly bear, as the discovery of my imprudence! Then swear to me--nay, I will not quit this posture till you do swear to me, that you will not, to your dearest friend, utter a breath, that may betray me!" ," Good God, what do you ask p" cried Randall"in the most try. ing situation of my life, would you deprive my inexperience of their superior counsel, who love me, and have wisdom to direct me?" "What council can you want-what is there to determine?t cried Ellinor. "By to-morrow's setting sun, I shall be the oceah's charge. All that you have heard will then be only as a vision, that may occasionally ask a sigh; while it reminds you that there is one in the universe, on whom the night will never steal, or the dawn break, without a prayer to Nature's Author for your heart's peacee! Why, then, should you wish to make her er- rors tales of common tattle, er give her conduct to the examina. tion of beings who have not her feelings? Will you deny me the oath then"--   -     ' Rise! I beseech you, rise." "Not till I have received your solemn promise i"   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.       71 Charles hesitated some minutes; during which time she held his hand between her own, and leaned her warm cheek upon it. ' Will you then, promise me," said Randall, " to remain here till to-morrow?" "By no means!" "Will you permit me an interview this evening?" ( For what purpose ." "Nay, I know not; but my heart tells me that I am to blame. I would prevent the necessity of your leaving England." "Necessity /" exclaimed Elinor,--', it is my choice!" "But if-if-why-why do you wish to restrain me from  con-, suiting my friends? I have an important, very important point to decide; and I dare not trust my feelings with the decision." "' I understand the insult now!" cried Elinor, rising scornfully. "You would insinuate that-if your relations can find no just ob- jection to my character, and fortune, you might condescend to pity me, and perhaps if, and supposing so and so, you would then offer me a love, not the offspring of my creation, but a conde. scending acceptence of overtures, you may-imagine I have made to you!  I had conceived your heart a different composition, Mr. Randall; or mine would never have been known to you." "You judge wrong, madam, I assure you! Your candor, your noble-mindedness, have impressed me with a reverence, not con. tempt; and if this new sensation in my bosom be not- But spare me only' for a few hours-permit me to see you in the oX evening-and if, then, you require the oath, I will most solemnly take it; and till then not a whisper shall escape my lips concern- ing you." After a  pause, she continued-  "I cannot see the necessity for this, Mr. Randall. Why should we meet again? Why not immediately separate for ever?  But since your request is otherwise-be it so, sir. I shall expect you in the evening; till then, farewell!" "Adieu, madam," said Charles, and tremblHngly he retired. Va  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7970-00000036"/> 72  ax     THE LIMB-KILN MAN, OR CHAPTER XII. In the most profound reverie, Randall passed the distance be- tween Berners street and Mr. Robinson's. The bustle that sur- rounded him, the rattling of carriages, were insufficient to arouse him from a sort of stupor into which he had fallen. When he arrived at home, he rushed through the hall, and hurt rying to his own room, threw himself into a chair---"Marion!- Marion!" muttered he; "I have never before heard the name; I have no recollection of the face--O, what an important day! those looks! -that form!--never will my soul lose the impression!" He sighed deeply, and painfully. "Love me?-yes, she loves me. She owns it-nay, her behavior declares it more powerfully than her words! What a wondrous effect has she wrought upon me? What means this swelling of the heart, this difficulty of re. spiration Can I imbibe a partiality so instantaneously? Are :our natures indeed so susceptible? Surely, it cannot be It must be pity for Elinor-for her suffering-that pains me thus. Then let me soften them as much as possible-let me send her in writing the oath she requires, and spare her the pain of another interview!--andyet-never to see her again! Why do I feel a dread at that thought? Suppose she should be already gone? Forbid iit heaven! Once more-once more, let me behold a form so lovely! What brilliant expression in her eyes!--what sense? s what animation in her countenance! How happily might I pass my life with such a woman! But then her situation-my own too! Madness alone can suggest such a thought. She is proud. I dare not offer her pecuniary a;d. Where can she go? What part of the globe does she seek? Unhappy Elinor! Would I had never seen you!-would to God 1 had never seen you!" Such were the meditations of Randall-Elinor absorbed all his thoughts, while her beauteous form floated in air before his imagi- nation. Never, till this day, had his imagination been heated by the charms of woman! In others he beheld amiableness, modesty and beauty that won the esteem of his heart, and the approbation of his understanding; but in Elinor he saw far more attractive qualities.   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.       73 This woman was beautiful in the extreme. Nature had indeed been liberal of her gifts, and education had increased the value of her beauty. Elinor had once possessed everything desirable in the female character; for she once possessed virtue and innocence. But she parted with innocence, and' in its stead had admitted, as the guest of her heart the most accomplished cunning. At an early period of her life she had surrendered all claim to chastity, and had since then submitted to that miserable traffic, which is the most severe libel on civilized society. Too aspiring to herd with the unhappy class to which she haa reduced herself, her strong and towering mind was perpetually busied upon schemes more valuable to herself, and far loftier in the scale of wickedness than the generality of those unfortunate beings, whose daily infamy is their daily bread. In her own fall, she was-the-dupe of a professed rake; and her own schemes upon the tranquility of others, were all infused with a large portion of revenge. Man at large, she deemed her enemy; and the talents, and the charms she possessed, she considered as her weapons of revenge. Unlike many a sighing wretch, whom severe distress urges to compunctive acts of shame, Elinor was systematically' vicious. The present world bounded her views of futurity, and the strug- gles of the present scene ended, in her imagination, the drama of ,existence. Thus, no principles of a religious nature swayed her thoughts, no checks of conscience'ever intervened between the inclination, and the deed. Pity, and all the tender sensibilities which many natures fee], were her inward derision; but their semblance was perfectly at her command. Such was Elinor!  Such was she, for whom  Randall at first sight, had unconsciously imbibed the most powerful love'! She had never once seen Randall after her departure from the scenes of their childhood for the school where her father had placed her. But having learned his movements-thegreat confidence re- posed in him by Mr. Robinson, the large sims of money entrust- ed to his care, she, was not long in arranging a method to ensnare him within her power. For this purpose, she had spared nopains to obtain the intelligence she had gained concerning him, and had feigned the story she had related to him, and which did not contain one syllable of truth. Her sentiments, her tone of voice, her gestures were studied for  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7970-00000037"/> 74         THE LIME KILN' MATj, 'OR the occasion; and she was guided from movement to movement in the ,lan she would pursue, by the effect which her penetration discovered she had wrought on her victim. Thus artfully had she prepared the ground-work of her plot; and had thus far succeeded to the extent of her wishes. The interval between his departure and the hour 'at which she expected his return, was anxiously spent by Elinor; and she re- pented more than once, that she had suffered him to leave her--a step to which she consented, chiefly to carry on appearances, and from a persuasion, in which she was not mistaken, of her power oaver him. Meanwhile, he, for whom her machinations were devised, was planning the means of making her happy. Many and various were the resolutions he fobred, but all unstable. His heart had admit ted a spark, which his reason was too impotent to extinguish, and which was rising rapidly into a flame, of whose influence he was ignorant, but whose. warmth he began to discover. If the imagination of Randall was already wrought to a danger- ous warmth, the next reception he met with in Berners street was well calculated to increase it. On a crimson damask sofa, placed under a brilliant mirror, illu- minated by wax lights, reclined the Syren, Elinor. A most, ele- ganit white dress had superseded the sable weeds of the morning.; with a turkish turban, ornamented with gold studs and tassels. The solemn air of dignified sorrow was exchanged for the most fas. Cinating smiles; -and instead of the reserved and bashful demean- or, Randall had prepared himself to meet, he was thrown off his' guard by the most alluring glances. She did not rise when he entered the room, but holding out a most beautiful arm, encircled at the wrist with a brilliant brace- let, she said, with an enchanting softness-  "4Mr. Randall." Charles approached with the most profound astonishment, and received her offered hand. "Am I not a strange creature!" continued she. 'My trap- pings of woe, you see, are soon thrown off. But, in truth, I did not think it consistent with the pleasure I expected in your society to wear the semblance of sorrow!" Charles was petrified with amazement, and doubted, for a mo-  ment, wheth-er the woman of sentiment he had seen in the iorning s'   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.        76 and the wanton form before him were the same. As she stillheld his hand in hers, she fixed her sparkling eyes full on his face- '"You have an uncommon countenances" said she. "You are very severe-and yet have great sensibility. You are a com- pound of the stern and tender. I scarcely know which predomi. nates in your nature. You do n14t lack courage or fortitude; at the same time you will weep at a tale of misery, and the unfortun- ate are sure of your tympathy. Is it not so? Now, let me try if I am mistaken. Place that harp near me, and I will sing you a ditty about a door simple maid- w * * 'who never told her love, But let concealment,) as the poet says-and so on--now be silent," He placed the harp, and Elinor changing her features from the wanton to the languishing, gave him the manuscript to hold, while she sang and accompanied a simple pleasing ballad with exquisite taste and melody. The expression of her eyes was perfectly in unison with the words; and her voice uttered the sweetest sounds. It was a pathetic story and affected Randal extremely. ' Thiere," said she, "I knew you would weep, at a fiction too! Ah, Mr. Randall, to me only are-you insensible! My abrupt sin- cerity has made me the object of your scorn! Yes, cruel and in- sensible, you return the most glowing affection with the choldest disdain." "Disdain!-O, no," said Randall--" say, rather, admiration and esteem. Where is the being, who could,gaze on such charms and disdain their possessor? How must the heart be formed that can remain insensible to so much beauty?" 9"There are hearts, I fe;r," said Elinor, (, round which the hand i of worldly prudence forms  a circle, that freezes every passion of the soul. Tihele are beings, who can have according to a scale of reason, and model their affections by a standard. But I do not-cannot think so of so young a heart as your's " ': Our reason," interrupted Randall,' with a satirical smile. "And where did you learn that maxim t I suppose some pon- derous folio so says. But have books hearts? No, no, Mr. Ran- dall. Ask those who wrote the senseless lies, what is this reason, that isso omnipotent? Where is to be seen-or who possesses it 2" "Astonishing!" said Randall. "Doyou-then deny the existence of Reason?" fo  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7970-00000038"/> "Yses, such Reason as the black letter gentlemen depict. Can reason quench the thirst. or satiate the appetite of hunger? Ah! no -no. Ahd is the fstroingest impulse of our motions to be so easily swayed, y Reason then? Why have we passions--merely to torment us? O, infamous libel on the author of our existence, -who has given his creatures allthings to enjoy. Well, the poet sings.? 'To enjoy is to obey!'" The airs, the doctrine of Elinor now roused, for the first mo- ment, as suspicion in his mind of her intentions which startled  Randall. lie sunk into a profound reverie, his eyes cast on the floor. Elinor observed it, and saw the struggles that was risingin his breast. Perfect mistress of her art, she was aware how im- perceptible her bold advances had stolen into his heart, and with a cunning caution restrained her efforts, and changed her opera- tions. Instead of attempting to continue an argument, at which she well knew he, revolted, she touched the strings of the harp, and raised an enchantment of melody, from the slowest and softest to the most brisk and lively measures, her fingers swept the trem- bling chords, The effect on Randall was instantaneous. In vain did the enamored youth aim to repress the rising flame-in vain he attempted to resist the maddening impulse of desire! On the precipice of danger, he was ignorant of his situation. His cheeks flushed, his eyes looked wild, and he fell back on the sofa, over- come with the force of such new and powerful emotions. The syren saw her time. She struck the harp again, and- "Softly sweet in Lydian measures, Soontfhe soothed his aoul to pleasures." She sighed--she gazed with looks of warme st love-she seemed to yield her soul to her desires-sank by the side of Randall--r- clined her head upon his cheek-presed the warm lips to his, anl conquered. ,-   - ....... v. a -so-LfVit 'UNJ. " CHAPTER XIII. About an hour before the time appointed for Randall to be in Berners street, the following letter was handed to him- "Author of my future destiny! my conqueror!-my bus band!-(will you allow the title!)-still dearer name, my Ran- dall!-your trembling Elinor throws herself upon vour generos- ity. She trusts implicitly on a heart that has so effectually mas- tered her awe! "My uncle is in pursuit of me-for worlds I would not at pres- ent behold him. He bas inquired for me in Berners street, I was of course denied.  He is to be there again this evening. "Oh, how I wanted your advice; why had you left me.? As it was, I was compelled to decisive conduct. I discharged the lodgings immediately, ordered a post-chaise, and drove to Picca- dilly. "I write from the house of a tradesman, whom I had formerly employed; and leave your feelings to express to you, how impa- tiently I wait your arrival! what shall I subscribe myself? Oh! Randall, for both our sakes, let me entreat your presence! And let fate play what part it may, I shall ever be C, YOUR OWN." "The bearer will drect you." Thunderstruck at such an unexpected procceeding, Randall was for some time incapable of deciding what step to take. While he hesitated, I entered the room. "He still held the letter in, his hand- "You are engaged?" said I.. "No, sir--yes, sir-that is-I-" Well, sir," I  interrupted, ' I'll not intrude. I may, perhaps, bring stale news top., I have inquired twice to day in Bemners street. At first the lady was not visible; the second time, I learned that she had taken post horses, and left town. You may possibly know the route." "4 No, sir-yes sir -" said Randall again hesitating. "Ah," said ,   " how difficult does motive find the winding paths offmean dissimulation!  If you would retain your peace of mind,  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7970-00000039"/> 78         THE LIME-RILN MAN, OR Oh, youth, retain sincerity. And remember, that shame or dan- ger will prove as unwelcome at the end of a maze, as if boldly met at their first appearance!" Ere Randall could reply, I took his hand affectionately, and said- "One caution let me impress upon your memory, and I am gone. Make no promises of secrecy! Farewell." Randall, had not the power, nor indeed just then, the inclination to detain me, and I retired. "He has called twice in Berners street," said Randall, after my departure. "Perhaps, then, Elinor may have imagined his in- quiries to be her uncles. But why that caution as to promises of secrecy? Surely Elinor-. But while I am arguing, she spends the moments in anxious expectation." He rushed towards the door, and desired the man, who waited, to conduct him to Elinor. Immediately they met, she ran to him, apparently in the great- est distress of mind, and hiding her face in his bosom, cried-- "Oh, hide me-hide me, my dear Randall from my pursuers." 'Dispel these fears, Madam!" said Randall. "Your alarms may be groundless. It is possible you may have mistaken the description of another person for your uncle." "I have seen him. He pursues me, and will tear me for ever from those loved arms! Oh, how cruel-how peculiarly cruel is my destiny. Perhaps already he has traced my chaise to this very door, and will soon be here. Let us quit the house!" Randall, alarmed and greatly concerned for her distress, thought of nothing at the moment but relieving it. , Where will you be safe?" he exclaimed. "Alas! I know not! But let us this moment quit this place. my trunks may be left here for the present. Come-come!" She hurried on her cloak, and leaning on his arm, walked to- wards the door. They had walked a considerable distance from the house ere Randall had sufficiently recovered from the surprise her. conduct had occasioned. "I am faint!" dried Elinor. This aroused him, and being near the coach stand at Hyde Park Gate, he called a hackney coach. When they wete seated-          .    o "Where am I drive, your honor V" said Ohe man. Elinor leaning her headn against the side of the coach, remained   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE.       79 , silent. Randall knew not how to answer. After a considerable pause, he said- "The case is this-this lady is just arrived in town, and, we want lodgings. Drive slowly along the Brompton road, and if you observe an advertisement at any door stop there." The coachman obeyed. They stopped at a house kept by a widow, and Randall hired the lodnings at the rate of two guineas a week. Elinor, thus placed in a safe retreat, as she pretended from her uncle, gradually reassumed her serenity of countenance, and expressed her gratitude to Randall in the warmest language, and by the most seducing endearments. The pretended fears of Elinor, so admirably played, completely answered the purpose for which she had assumed them. Her pene- tration had easily discovered-that Randall's mind, if time was allow- ed him for reflection, would too scrupulously examine the question of propriety. She therefore artfully resolved to take him by sur- prise. The apartments in Berners street, she had taken for the express purpose of their first interview, where she had resided but a few days, and had actually discharged them in the manner she had related. The story of her uncles pursuit was entirely a fiction. Her present aim was to obtain a habitation at the expense of Ran- dall, and this it is seen, she accomplished. Having thus far succeeded, a pause in her operations was nec- essary. She therefore, dallied with the unfortunate youth, who was the pliant victim of her arts, and evaded all his inquiries as to her future designs. When an air of sadness marked his fea- \ tures, she would sing-when he hinted his wish that they were \ married, she sighed deeply, turned her head away from him, and talked on some different subject; when be spoke of his friends, she effected the extremest agitation; wept (for she could weep at wilD and implored him, as he valued her life, to retain their con- nection an inviolable secret, for at least some time to come. 'Randall started as this caution I had given him," never to prom- ise secrecy," rushed across his memory- "Why, why should there be secrecy?" he exclaimed. "My old friend, MoFar--" "' No matter sir, our fates have rendered it most necessary," she interrupted. ' Ah! Mr. Randall, you know not yet all the per- plexities that rack this heart. Pardon the mysterious veil that for a moment conceals it, and confide in the, assurance, that it is  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7970-00000040"/> 80.        THE LIME KILN MAIT, OR wholly and forever yours. It is to be wished, that we, yes, we, (for I will not affect to throw the guilt wholly on you) had not yielded to the too powerful impulse of our passions! .But who can recall the past? How useless, then, is it to repine! Let us, my dear Randall, rather conquer than submit to our fate, and em- ploy ourselves in a prudent anticipation of the future, in prefer- en"O to a gloomy retrospect of the past." S i h were the blandishments with which-the syren soothed the regrets of Randall, and such the arts by which she bound him in unfelt fetters. At his return home, the following morning, he found a packet of letters from his uncle's. Soon as he saw the well known writing, his heart smote him. For some days previous to the unfortunate affair with Elinor, accident had prevented his writing to his sister, with who he had hitherto regularly corresponded, since his arrival in London, and the events which had occurred since then were such as he felt no inclination to relate. With the just apprehensions of reproof, therefore, he broke the seals, and read the following letters- "ETTER I. "My Dear Son, t"I am very uneasy at a silence of which I know not the cause. If you are as happy as usual, why not let us be equally so, in knowing that you are? If otherwise, why so sel- fish as to retain, in your own breast, cares in which others have a right to participate . Ns it possible you can forget that you have a sincere friend in '"Your most affectionate mother, ' M. RANDALL." "ETTER II. "My Dear Brother, "It is with pain, and agitation, I am compelled to complain of you, even to yourself! Ignorant as I am of the cause of your silence, ten thousand tormenting supposes are rapidly succeeded each other. You paint the amiable Emma in such pleasing tints, that I sometimes suppose you devote my little portion of your time to the study. of your favorite picture, Yet, if so, say I to myself, surely:he would delight in recount- ing the charms he discovers. Suppose some face, or some mind, more engaging than Emma's has supplanted her in his approba.   THE VICTIM OF MSFORTUNE..       81 tion, would he not have been eager to htve displayed to his sis- ter those superior attractions? Suppose he should be reclining on the uneasy pillow of a sick bed! Thusi my dear brother, do I tor- ture imagination to find excuses for your conduct; but as imagi. nation has yet offered nothing in your favor, to the satisfaction of your judge, you are now called upon for your defence. Speak then, sir. You have a powerful pleader in the breast of your sis- ter, and if you can make but a tolerable excuse, you may assure yourself of a ready acquittal. It is necessary to conclude by way of memento, in the old fashioned style, that ' I am, de* brother, Your affectionate sister, ELIZA RANDALL." "ET TER III , ;Dear Nephew, I take this opportunity of expressing to you my approbation of your conduct, the report of which, from Mr. Robinson, gives me great pleasure. I am sure it is needless in me to give advice to one who so well knows what is right; at the same time my wishes for your welfare make me remind you how important the effects of your present actions are in forming your future comfort, or otherwise. I hope you pay par- ticular attention to your expenses, and never suffer yourself, for * the sake of momentary pleasures or false pride, to go beyond the mark, which would compel you to descend to real meanness, or bring on lasting uneasiness. You will take this as caution, not re- proof. I have every reason to rely upon your prudence, and shall fall with quiet into my grave, if only I am permitted to see my brother's son settle respectably in life, and become the guardian and protector of his widowed mother and his sister, which if you like, will be enabled to be. I hayveremitted you a draft for fifty pounds. Should any emergency, at any time, occasion you a pe- cuniary want, let me be your friend; and I charge you, by no means to lie under any obligations of this sort to any one, but to your y' Most affectionate uncle, "(JAMES RANDALL." These letters, the simple, genuine effusions of affectionate hearts were perused by Randall with mingled sensations of pleasure and  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7970-00000041"/> 83         i THE LIME-KILN MAN, OR pain. When he compared the last of these with his situation with respect to Elinor, he shuddered. "What steps shall I pursue?" said the distractpd youth. i' They charge me with silence-how shall I ever write again! I have pledged myself to Elinor-I have sworn to be seoret. If I write, therefore, I must conceal from them my perplexities -I must disguise my feelings-must invent occurrences to ac count formy time. Dreadful situation! And who can foresee its durationS. How long may the too lovely Elinor envelope herself in this im- penetrable mystery? "' I have incurred a certainexpense in a provision for her-per- haps too far. Oh, God! what a precipice am   I descending!- There is no. possible way of sustaining my ground, but by a timely disclosure of my errors-and from that I am prevented by a rash oath! Long this secrecy cannot last. Liberal as my uncle is, his generosity cannot equal wants of which he never dreams. Why did I make so rash a promise? Why should she exact it  So contrary to my nature, to my' practice, too. I hate, I abhor se-' crecy. It is but another name for deception! I will fly instantly  and retract my engagement Iwill convince her how necessary it is that our marriage should immedihstely take place, and be de- clared; then, even if the anger of my benefactor should overpower. his tenderness and affection, I have the world before 'me. "Indus- try shall supply the necessities of nature; and the sweet reward of sincerity, my hearts approbation, shall make emple amends for the luxuries I lose. But to continue the mean paths of dissimula- t tion--to start at every noise-to tremble at every glance-xeist under the uplifted rod of fear, is worse, much worse, than any evil wtiich can result from an opposite conduct. This is the voice of prudence, of interest-and is in unison with the lessons of morali- ty, and the precepts of religion." I will obey it instantly. Such were the inward musings of Randall; such was the noble resolutions of his heart. As he was completely' master of his own time in Mr. Robinson's absenrce, he answered someiletters received that morning fdiom Buxton, and went'immediately to Brompton. t s'  *    i  ---- ,v'nmMor bTi/tt CHAPTER XIV Elmeor, a she reeeived him wr.. we,  , Radall , sitd though w' n eould glatl hao dispendt reiae; , visitd!" i1ried Rnda seriously; "be first cerina, thatmy "BT so grae anaddres, you terrify me!" sh cried, pIreteiid: ig exoessiWe alarm. "Tel m e, my dear CharleSl/ "r SE you so serious Wherearethose smiles that have gainledi suh tri umph?"eec "They are absent, I hope,' only for a time," said Randall. ,It is in your power to recall them.' "Ob, say by what means 2 , "Give me back my oath of serecy, for I cannot be scret-it -"y counten ance is a lib erty." wl er be at eas e t ill Serecy my Chiirles, is a vi,rue of the first c'lass in the present "ystem ofthings; and the-being-is as madw'ho throws it aside, a s Ihe who rushes with a naked br ast upon A hostile siiear! You are t oo u nacqha inted with a trickingwrrld, my C hi ariles.' W heii' yvshall kn ow its wiles, how will you laugh atyo present "Then may I never know them I cannot, and I wil not be a hypocrit e!', ^o -l .wl g 'Y  Randall spoke this with so much earnestness, that ElnOr trem b^lld b or its consequenes.: TUrning her powers, therefor% agin'sT tihis ri sing strength of resolution, which a larmed hr , sh e bursl into a flood of tears, and throwing herself'nto a cha ir- "Gsos,   aethen, proud youth; pclaim through the wide ircle do y,),r Friends, the tieumph yuhavegained; dlsplaythe espoilyour cqe ng charms hae won; exhibit my disgraic: suRmmon t. *"--^ ^WMvbe  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7970-00000042"/> my ears the songs of scorn; and give to foul-mouthed calumny j the prey that you despise!" "How wild you talk, madam!" cried Randall, still struggling to resist the tender influence he felt. "Madam!" echoed Elinor--" madam!" 'Pardon me- myw- what name-what title shall I give you v Why will you not this moment give me a right to call you wife'?" "' Merciful Heaven i" cried Elinor;, " are you delirious 3. What mean you. thent Do you alludte to the mummery invented for the use ' o those who have not faoultiesof their own to define the laws of nature? Am I the less your's-are you' the less your Elinor's because a ceremony is omitted,?"  "No, Elinor, no; in my own estimation, you are mine as sa. credly as possible. Have we not sworn a, mutual faith in His presence, who is every where! Our vows are registered by him. The solemnity of an earthly temple, or the sanctity of temporal altars, therefore, cannot increase the force of obligation with a mind, that thinks as mine does! But O, Elinor! I am, not a solitary being. I have a mother, a sister, whose happiness is wove with my own. I have a benefactor, too, whose generous kindness deserves the warmest gratitude! Can I tell them, that I-could I introduce " C; 'Tis because you can not do this, that I required your secre- cyg (' But you will permit me to add, that if we had the sanction of custom (not to say the obligation of Law) to our connection, there would exist no cause of secrecy! Those who love me will receive you as my wife; and-." "Surely-surely you will not imagine, my dear Randall, that from choice I throw an obstacle in the way of your proposal; it is impossible you should think so! But at present, for some-time at least, we cannot marry!" (' What mystery veils you, Elinor! Oh, east it off. There cannot be a thought that either Bus should engross to ourselves -let me beseech you to confide in me." "Only for a little space of time, my Randall, spare me. Soon -l -" the veil, that now conceals my heart, for ever be removed- shall our breasts be the common repositories of our mutual :.  hts-there shall not be a hope or a fear of one unknown to \. s;her; but so blended shall become our very thoughts, we ^l. togetheform but one extstence!"   "And why is that moment postponed?" "You know not, my dear Charles, how you wound me by this useless importunity. I do not form my resolutions on caprice, but on the existing right or wrong I see before me; and therefore I never change my purpose, but with the revolution of existing causes. I act from motives, not from impulse; else I might, by your persuasions, be moved to reveal, a secret, that my reason now denies you .However much, therefore, your importunities may afflict my heart, they shall not, they cannot, subdue the soV- ereign power of intellectual decision!" "Extraordinary woman!" cried Randall. " ow, then, am I to act Say Elinor, had you a mother and a sister whom you loved, and to whom you had been accustomed to reveal your in- most thoughts, could you refrain from recounting such a train of interesting events as have occurred to us within these few import- ant days?" "What can be more easily decided than your question? Ask yourself, what benefit you can expect from revealing these events? You would merely create a host of painful apprehensions in those breasts, which you wish should be the mansions of peace; and the only possible result of their knowing what has passed, would be a painful anxiety to know more than itis apresent in your power to reveal."1 "And yet, to conceal the true state of my mind, I must feign a satisfaction I do not feel; I must assume an indifference to which my  heart is a stranger. How pan I answer suchlettersas these?" Randall then gave her the three letters he had received in the morning. When she had perused them, she said-- "Your sister is an amiable girl; and your mother is doubtless a good woman, but I scarcely know how to pronounce on your uncle. His letter of prudence seems more the acquisition of hab- it, than the suggestions of his own reason. He is very rich I presume?" "I understand so." "And has no children?" "None." Your mother and sister reside with him--of course to acquaint -them with our connection, would be the same as informing your 4"Does that follow?" "Yes; unless they can manage to feign a satisfaction they do ton they do  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7970-00000043"/> 86         THE LIME-. ItN MA)T, OR not feel, and assume an indifference to which their hearts are strangers, you know." ahndcall smiled, "I perceive the state of your mind, my Charles. It has hither- to been too much swayed by prejudice, early imbibed, and still unexamined. But as you adv, ance in life, you will discover that the wisest and best of mankind find it impossible to model their actions by given rules. The incidents of life hinge so entirely on chance,: that our situations, relatively and individually, assume many complex shapes; and are perpetually at variance with de. fined notions of duty. It is therefore impossible to exhibit a standard of vittue or vice. "Let us apply this observation to your conduct and present situation. You say you cannot be a hypocrite! I grant you, hypocracy is classed amongst what are called vices; but will any one say, that to distress the feelings of a mother and sister, to wound their hearts with the arrows of perplexing, doubts and ap- prehensions, is more virtuous, than simply to conceal the events which' have passed, and which were not the effects of our own de- signs? -Such a doctrine scarcely merits a roment's thought!" By these and similar arguments, did this mistress of dissimula- tion, at length defeat the hoble purposes of that sincerity which hitherto had dwelt in Randall's breast, and he fatally resolved to keep his friends in ignorance of his situation. In the honesty of his nature, he had confessed to, Elinor, that he had mentioned the'affair to ore friend; but that he was igno- rant of any thing that had occurred since their second interview; and overcome by her tears, her arguments, and her pers(asions, he promised he would never allow himself to mention 'heir again even to this one friend, nor would ever suffer him to name .her to hinself.            - This was the precise point which the arts of Elinor aimed to accomplish; for she knew that, among the many and va'rious er- rors to which youth and inexperience are exposed, there is none more fatal in its consequences than the concealment of having committed them. The first deviating steps from the paths of rec- titude, may often be retiriced by the aid of friendly council; but he who denies himself that timely aid, will in vain implore its effi- cacy when entangled in the maze of deception; and when every avenue on the return to happiness is obstructed by some unex- peoted obstacle.   VICT Y1'MT OF MSFORTUNE.       8 CHAPTER X-V. The next day Randall received the following letter from his sister :-  "My Dear Brother, "There is something wrong; you are un. happy, and you have renderedus sotoo Whiaka letter was yOur last." Engagements of various kinds!--Particular circumstanes I -Want of time!"What excuses are these from ote, who had used to delight in recounting every ittle incident that might enter tain; every thought that might imprve his sister! Did 2fancy it, or was your hand. indeed, unsteady hile you wrote? Oy ,  .; ed, b ,ud while you wrote. Oh! Charles, you are a sorry eactor! In vain you aim to fit a mask upon your soul-'it spurns it, and will burstthefetters of ecep tion. It must not be concealed ; we concluded from the incohe- renlcies, the contradictions of your letters, that someting as wrong; and the anxiety as to the nature of the'evil, is greater be- yond all comparison, than a certain knowledge of'it, be it what it may. Leaveus no longer, then, in'the pu rgatory of 'onjeture "Engagements*' you speak of. It was your uston todescribe to us the events of every day. What thein is the nature ofhose engageents you keep back from ourknowledge? Your situation must be changed, indeed, ifpress of business has so quikly suc- 'needed a leisure, of which you formrly complained! AhCharles, that leisure, in such a place as London, ever occasioned our lear parent some concern for you. But ^when we found it devoted to improvement of the mind, to the elegant pursu s literature, and particularly when spontaneously you devote so large a portion of It to a correspondence, that brought us, as it were, daily into each other's presence, Wer heart glowed with gratitude to the memory ef him, who is now no more, as she hailed with joy the sweet blossoms of his early cultivation. "Shall we then be deceived at last! Say, m y brother, w ere those blos  soms so tender, that Te mptationts tempest can have blighted them I Forgive thethought-itcannot-cannot be! b"VYc                   'be r r  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7970-00000044"/> 88         THE LIME-KILN MAN, OR It may have checked them; it cannot have destroyed them. Some indiscretion has, for a While, shed its sombre influence over the mind, that cannot be at once in error, and at ease. Is it so, my dear brother? I have a right to presume it is, from your conduct; for on no other ground can I define it. And if it should be so, what have we ever done, that' our hearts are denied their just right to a knowledge of you imperfections? How often have the imperfections of human nature been our theme! How often have we pitied the poor disciples of modern philosophy who boast the reverse. We have heard persons declare, that they have never repented of one act of their lives, and we have smiled. It must be false shame, or false fear, then, that has betrayed my dear brother into the concealment of his errors. "Perhaps you may imagine, that to acquaint us with, them. would occasion us pain; and that what we do not know, we can- not regret. Fatal delusion! How many wrecks of promised happiness has that rock occasioned! Most who approach it, perish. Examine this specious suggestion of Pride. It is no more. We are unwilling to descend in the esteem of those we love, and we conceal from their knowledge indiscretions, which we imagine would have that effect; forgetting that by the very concealment, we practice a crime, instead- of committing an error, and are guilty of the meanest hypocrisy, in passing ourselves upon our friends for such miracles of perfection, as make a comparison with their own experience, painful. Besides the meanness of this deception, it will be found impolitic., it is the unwarying law of nature, that all causes produce effects. Indiscretion, then, must have its con- sequences. And how frequently is it seen, that the consequences declare the indiscretion to those, from whom we have sought to connceal it, and then. how contemptible do we appear, from the very fact, which we vainly imagined the prop of our characters! "Pardon me, dear Charles, in thus reminding you of truths gathered from yourself; and believe me, that my heart would not have rested satisfied, had I said less. Anxious will pass the mo- ments till I hear from you; and if you are not indeed angry and offended at an officiousness, of which the tenderest love, and dear- est interest, are the parents, you will not hesitate to repose in a mother and sister's breasts the distresses or perplexities of your- own. "It is scarcely necessary to observe that our benevolent uncle- has remarked your silence. But be assured, our correspondence   at present; is confined to those, who onlyprtibe a woind, they per. suade themselves, you' have received, thdlithey miay With mere ef- feet administer toitscure. I amVc&amp;niad nded to remit ybi; tie blessing of your mother, and with that unite the warm and sincere affection of your sisteir, t     ,      E  .  The heart of Randall suffered the severest conflicts from thepe. rusal of this letter. The fallacious arguments of Elinor, respect. ing the propriety o concealment were answered, ias completely as if he haad ex'pressed them to his sister. :His mind was learly con- vinced of the folly, as well as guilt, of any furthjrsecrecy; and he' once more determined to acquaint Elinor, that he could no longer submit to a clandestine connection. As he entered the room, she met him and exclaimed- ' Why, my dear Randall, is your brow thus constantly cloud- ed?"  i  He answerei not, but threw himself on the s6fa.  "I shall never be happy again," murmured he. , Oh! IElinor, what a wretch have you made me!' I was, bathing. in bliss-... knew not a painful reflection anird now, I cast neither Ronsult my friends, nor my own heart. -I lhavegrown despicable in the esti. mation of both. You have destroyed my tranquility for ever!"  "From you this language, Randall!  From  you, for whom I have sacrificed nobtonly friends, but fortune--nay, for whom I have sacrificed the delicacy of my sex--and have indurred a shame never to be effaced! Who is most the suffere/- Randall:-you have shared equally in all the pleasures of our connection, and, ' the world's opinion have obtained a triumph-or I, who for , portion of rapturous moments have to encounter the evilsofyes unbdon-? Yet will I never repine. I, who am a' woman,will y be philosopher enough not to lament the price of my pleasure: No, my  Charles," throwing her! arms around h'mneck, Inm though existence was that price! What, then, can you repine. at' "At the mystery which encircles her Ilove-at the necessity secrecy which I abhor. Elinor, I feel about my heart .the weight of a crime!- Never shall I feel one happy moment till :tan intros duce you to my friends-solicit their :forgiveness andtiregaian their esteem. Let me, then, hasten the return of happiness to Us both, by, the only means that are-left us."  .  "I understand you, Randall. I  perfectly understand you, and ; would to God that obstacles, insurmountable obstacles, did not'  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7970-00000045"/> 9z.       . g I  ts  woRs pr,entourpti9 n ,f thoe twes.   Bul, one for sh, know that t satep, to whnich y0o ^lude, is quite impossible!" ' Jmpossi e l--bl lipo tt ,d ay r ; ,ghtly-i mposible " Elinor rwepmand sihe4nt., ",Tell me most mysterious woman, and, by, one word, forever seal hy' doom. Are you already, marhed T! ' i;, , /answer me I bieseech you. The certainty tht it is so cannot e more tormeuntlg than this supes, 1Tel me, then, at one, how uSilrty and o miseraxble a weth I;am. "!Oht ria l'l, your 'cruel penetration has wounded ,my soul, I ai--nay, start not, fly not from me-I am-already marraed! Randall, in an gony, burst from her arms, and rushed towards the door. 'Heihad' eized the handle of the iok, 'when, with a shrink ElitiEr hinted on the sofa. H{i itenderness returned in an instant, and he saw her beauteous-person extended lifeless on the sofa. He rang thebell Violently ;a servant came up, andassisted inq faang; ,ndd spr. kling the:face pfthe sufferer. Half opening her eyeai thl arttl. Elinor, obseryvedhisasttentions-- "He has lft me-rhe .is gone-he is .gone forever!"  Then ap- pearingto eoverd starting a tfte, sight of him, she aught his hand; ndkiing it. wturously, ex4laimed-- !"'*Oh., hiisgod-like indeed!" iRandall, finding she recovered, dismieissedthe servant, and ten. derly asupportsd her I ;his own arrma He could not, however, so far disguise his feelingS, as to .appsr otherwise than offended. "'Al why. wasthb cruelty,exerte d." pad sheo, "why bhave you saved ime,fromi death if ,thus :yougaze onme! Never! never IsupporttyaUtranger, Randall, Thisscornful silencetoo!- e bitter,eproachbes wre, kinder than this cold silence,Pan- 'UWhat anstlay to :you, you, dangerous woman t You, Eli. r, may:deem adultery no crime; but H" ' You Char]s,are nouadultrer; you ,are innocent. I am in- ,d, ,guflty. S 'But the love I oherish for you is all my heart ap- provesi ,: .Compelled to marry another, I have vowed at: the altar tobelhis,; but never have Athose vows been, sanctioned by my hearthey  weretorturedfrom my lips--but never has my per- son yielded to such legalized pollution. From -that meoorable day I bqeaef lfugitive, and only apprached the altar with that vieW. s' prisoner* in the,stricsttsene, I hadno other alternative   THB 'VICIM OF MSFORTUE.       9 than to yield my hand to a loathedbridegroom, whom, from :that hour to this, I neverhave behold;'* " ;   *   ':  Randall sat!silently nusing: on the sofa'; his/hands were folded in each other, and his eyesfixed on the floor.- .. '  "Still you are silent :Charles. , I tse ,thei rising iscorn ;that; sits upon your lips. I know the innate delicacy of your pure ,mind revolts at the desperate aotions of a phrensy striekeh woman, who cruel tyranny and unbounded love unite to plunge into despair. -I will not aim to lessen your disgust; it icthe oly- remnedy for my - ill-fated passion. Go: then, too lovely youth;: go, and .forget for ever, the lost-lost Elinor! Go, and, in sdme Iother's , arms be blest.! While 1,; in a: lone, corner of i T arthb mourn o'er thy memory, and bless thy name.", ?  "Yes, Madam,"  said Randall, starting -from his reverie. "I perceive no other mode of action. There appears the only outlet from this sea of guilty pleasures; where, longer to remain must be destruction!" . '" I know your dreadful meaning, sir. It is cruel, but it is nec- essary we should part; and, since I have become so loathsome to your sight, the rudest deserts will be preferable to your presence: No, I could never stay tO bN depit s'byy ' ulb ' Here the syren shed a flood of artificial tears, that tortured Ran- dall to the very soul. The extreme sensibility of his nature sub- jeted himn to extremies in sentlmenit-now, msit tenderly he pitied the miseT'es bfEindr ' ti'hen; the' fiemiy of his ' family bushed across, his mind-he saw their indignant frowns, he heard their re- bul es; fQe a oniduct so unworthy of themi, and'ofhi1mself. Again when [he reflepted 'oA the' dreadful fate of he who had' abaimoned so Inuch forhis sak: he was :readj ;o extend his hand, -and:vow eternal truth., AgAitn, the taints of the world, :thelie evetngobf an injured husband, and the ighe loriny to himself and friends,' ofi pub- lie accusation, checked the ofttness' qmvering ofn hisa lips,:which only escaped by a painful ' 'h.         - In this'corifoet of his mind, memory placed before him' a, vision he had seen in his sleep--he felt the aliusiohn of the'- Scene: most strongly ; the very countenance of his father was present, anid sum- moned a resolution in his breast thsat con quered'erety opposition. Approaching the sofa with tremulous voice, he dda; -  ti'Pasnfl: to rie, Elinor, are;thos-e tears ibut after the know- ledge I have obtained of your situation, t'eonttnue :asonneotion." "I know it must not be," interruptdsted { "I t kl ow- thei jaen. \  .   , , .    -   &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7970-00000046"/> diced ee Iof prejudice views itihall the:hiddous 'colorings of yicet I ask it hot, my Charles-heart breaking iA thel sacrifice; but ,to, your, peace ofmind, I will surrender,eeven yoursel! Yet, do pot add to the horrors of suohA separation :by inflicting the,misery of thinking ,that Lam despised by you. Say that you do:not hate me; and-"P         - , .  ,  ' . "Hate you!-Oh, Elinor, have I preferred you, even to virtue! And notr, if you knew the struggle of my heart, you would /see it is, impossible to ;hate you!'? ,  "Generous-- generous Charles!t whyshould the cold., and rigid arbitration of an ill judging world sever: such hearts as ours!" As she spoke, she twing her arms around his neck; her palpit tating heart beat against hms bosom, and her warm kisse brought on a delirium of ecstay...  CHAPTER XVI, "Not at home all night!"I exclaimed as the information was given me in the hll at Mr. Robinsons. "Not at home all night," I repeated, But while I was speaking, Randall knocked at the door. Atlthe sight of lme he started back, and hung down his head. His hair was undressed, his eyes were red and swollen, and :his whole ap- pearance proolaimed the revelry in which the night had passed. I sryeyed him leisurely from head to foot; during which time he reeooveredfrom ,his surprise, and invited me into the parlor. 4"Ha ing a few hours of leisure this morning," said I, 'seating myself, "- yes- Hyour old friend McFarlafid-have come to converse with you,on various matters. I am sorry that my visit is so ill timed. I really had no -intention ofbreaking in upon your hours of rest; but my vulgar idea had not associated going to bed , with the suninthe meridian.  ("You are satirical," said Charles endeavoring to force a smile. "You are, hypocritical," I replied.  ; "Sir," exclaimed Randall. "e   "He who attempts to put aLsimper on his -countenane whilst lis heart aches with remorse, is a hypoorite" : Randai's 'cheek glowed" with the blush o6f shame. "Young' an,"' I continued, " acOident first brought ui together. I love you, sincOerely love you. I have wealth--I have no one' to inherit it. The gmirae has received those who were mine;. You know my history,-you know my heart-.I4 ask in return, yours-- Give it me. Let me know its emotions-its trials Teat from it with noble indignation, the veil that would conceal it.: I know it is human--I knowit cannot be perfect. Oh,.-let me at leastre ceive from a life'of painful experience, the rewarding pleasure of being useful 'to you. I know by your ct'ntenance, that you have committed some act, which reflection, condemns as indiscreet, per- haps viscious. Tell me, sincerely where you have spent the night --in whose society--in what pursuit V" "Spare'me-spare!" cried Randall. I have fallen sufficiently in my own esteem. Let me not forfeit yours!" "You, Mr. Randall who possess faculties of no common magni- tude, cannot have so far descended from thw dignity of a human creature, as to have surrendered the distinguished powers',of intel. lect to the. grovelling pleasures of the glass. You have not, I am sure devoted a whole night to inebriety:t"  "; No-no, indeed I have' not."        I  "Nor can 1, for a moment suppose you have yet sunk into the despicable character of a gambler!" ' Never-never, friend William, shall you haveto upbraid me with so mean a vice ' "There is but one conjecture more, then, but that would scarce - ly make yon sad! Besides, at your age--in this hot bed of the passions, London-I presume chastity has long:been relinquished as a virtue unsuited to the times in which you live; anlincum- brance, indeed, which young men of fashion must not be suspected of retaining. , Long, ere last night,/therefore--"' .  "Forbear, I beseech, you, sir," said Randall; "you strike a painful chord! Till quite: recent I hadn ot to upbraid myself with a crime, beyond all others base-seduction!" , "Hold-hold! if you would not have me curSe you! Do you not remember thatI once possessed an, angel, till seduction tore her from my arms!-that I had once a daughter!--tht I abandon- ed her; and' that she too was seduced!--driv6n to infamny!-to death,! And can you 'confess yourself a seducer! Ohhow often  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7970-00000047"/> gft,       , y  WB M LMYB-KI  MAN, 08 ha&amp;e ,I voskeldeteml vengeance o0 the betrayer of confiding in- nocence,! Recall the adioPu charge, ori you will beoome more loathsome to my sight thn leprosy. But it is impossible. You a seducer! I0r annot be! The deliberate seducer must be a be- ing,all1ied tonatures differing from human. His heart musthe of salamander, his head the cool repository of design and artifice. The passion that fob other men of prudence, increase his cunning, and, render him the agent of the deepest villainy! Such you cLn- nothe I ' But you are agitated- speak too warmly-my feelings must excusefor me.' Andx hanging my voie, and msnner into the softest #ud most gentle, I eased not my :'.fportunities,t1iU Il had obtained from Randalallll that had  passed between himself and Elinor. When I had heard the whole narrative, I said- "'Tis a strange tale! a very strange story! But as you relate iyt youdharge yourself with too large a share of blame. I have strong doubts of this Elinor." "' Oh, asiri you have not seen her, or her countenance would pre- vent such undeserved suspicion. , ' . ,you-,have promised to see her again, of coure," I remarked.  n'i4ee heriagain " cried .Randll," what tortures would be se- vere enough for the wretch whp could abandon her!" ' Do you mean to marry her, then I' Randill: started at the question; "YouF uncle, your mother, ;your sister, perhaps will scruple to receive into their family a relation of so mysterious a character!" "You have taken me by surprise, sir: I have as yet determined upon: nothing. My Aind has not yet recovered fromn the emo- tions that have Soippwerfully agitated it. I thank you sincerely for yourt generous concern; but I want reflection--I want to be alone!,  , ;     . .  , "I'wil leave you,:then, to yourself awhile; but I will not re- linquish my claim to your confidence. To-day I leave for Rams- ,gate. Accoident has just discovered to Ae the wretched voman, iwho aided the cursed designs of the betrayer of my daughter's hon- or., She resides at &amp;amsgate, and I go in the hope, that she will ditect me" to find the villian, who, if he lives, shall feel the ven- geaee' of an injured father; and the death of my Elinor shall yet -be -avenged I Adieu."       . --  .... Randall immediately retired to his chamber, and threw himself upon th6 bted, and was soon ifiguring in the regions ot fancy.   TUN VICTIS OF, A9floRtCNB.    ,                    .       . OHAP TER     XVIi     .. A few days after my departure for Ramsgate, Randall had 0c- casion to viritthere, in company with Einor: and *while there I encountered him. i immediaitely toldhim of the discovery I had made, and said to him,  "The monster shall niot, escaope the vengeancer due to, his' enor- mous crimes. I will be revenged- a daughter's shArie-a' daiugh- ter's death must be revenged-Mathetws, or MoFIa;nrid dies." "' Mathews!" exclaimed Randalli ' Aye, Matlews--Captain Mathewsg-;thefriend, the intimate, the familiar of your Mr. Robinson. He it was who destroyed the innocence a father had abandoned! However, I shall 'hate the satisfaction of taking his life. I met him to day, and was not very delicate in accusing him, of what I am now certain he is guilty of, and his reply was this- "Sir, I will not brook this conduct. Let me see this injured fa- ther, you speak of, and I will confront him to hi face!" "You will-then do. Behold him   you reptile! behold him here!" said I, rising, and folding my arms on my breast; stood op. posite to Mathews; when the astonished Captain staggered back a full pace and trembled. "-You don't know me. I am not one, who frames, destroys, and frames anew his resolutions.! I came not in the moment of passion, to wreak revenge, but calmly to inflict upon a villain the punishment of death!" ,( You come to murder, then?" cried Robinson. "Sir!".said Mathews, after a long struggle of cowardie-e" sir, I-see-thiat-you-are determined, not to listen to anything I offer in my defence; and therefore name yourjplace adid tim'g; and take what satisfaction you please- .. ' ' T-:morrow, at break of day, behind the mill, two fields- from the adjoining lahne, said I.   '  "I'il meet'you there4' said inathiwsi-W ho; 6fihs, ooeslonUir as "                        .'1ne o lee  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7970-00000048"/> indeed a coward; though till this moment, he had always retained :: , .  the credit of great courage. "Shall we meet alone, or shall those who are now present at- tend us there?"I asked. "Is it impossible to prevent this meetingS? said Robinson. Can no concessions-no recompense  " "Are you a father," I interrupted, " and you talk of recompense. If indeed, he has power to raise the dead, and make that pure and spotless, which his lust has sullied, there might be meaning in your speech. I know no other recompense that he can offer, or I can receive. The meeting was arranged. It was agreed that Mr. Robinson and yourself should attend. You will be punctual V" "You can rely upon me, sir," said Randall, and we parted. Morning . came, and found Randall and myself within sight of the mill. We had not arrived three minutes before we were join- ed by Captain Mathews and Mr. Robinson:   The paces were measured, the pistols loaded, and the antagonists took the ground. The surprise which had made a coward of Mathews, had worn away and he now resumed the courage for which he was celebrated. We were to fire together, at a signal from Mr. Robinson. The word was given. My ball grazed the shoulder of Captain Math- ews, who fired in the air? "( How is this?"I exclaimed, " why did you fire in the air?" "Having received your fire, sir, I presume I may now without the imputation of cowardice,.solicit your attention for a few mo. ments to some observations I would offer. When you have heard me, it shall remain for your decision whether the affair shall pro- ceed. If it is your wish to fire again, I shall think myself justified in returning it, after the explanation I may offer, and the satifac. tion I have already afforded by receiving your ball." "I cannot refuse to hear you, sir; but our situation requires you should be brief." "If I could prove from the most certain evidences," said the Captain, '" that your daughter lives---" , :My daughter lives!" exclaimed I, "Pshaw, pshaw!-I saw her die--I saw the earth recieve her poor remains into its bosom r Why, then, the paltry evasion?" "I am patient," said the captain, I bear with the effusions of sorrow-----but, believe me, sir--if the unfortunate girl whom the madness of desire urged me to seduce, and whose name was   McFarland, residing at Mrsi Arthu-if, sir, this, was your daugh- ter; she still lives,;I saw her last:night,' . ::-' Saw her list night," I repeated, clasping my: hnds together. "I hope not-o-,no noit eannot beI-saw, her die." I ' You-tiust haoe been deceived, -ir, by somAe strong resemblance of person, or some striking coincidence of circumstances-for, by Heaven, I repeat, Miss McFarland lives!" "Wonderful, wonderful!"I sighed. "After the strong impression of her death, which you have re- ceived, nothing will, perhaps, convince you of her existence unless you were to see her." "See her! see her!"I exclaimed, fearfully looking around me. "Is she nesr me I would rather embrace; the severest tortures cruelty ever framed! See her!-horrible!" and my whole frame shook as with a convulsion. "Your arm, my friend," I continued to Randall, ( I am faint." I reclined my head on Randall's shoulder. Mr. Robinson then advanced, and proposed retiring to his house, that Captain Math- ews might relate the story of the preceeding evening, from which I might draw my own conclusions. I submitted, and. by a slow walk we arrived there. I asked for a glass of water, and after ta- king it requested Captain Mathews to proceed. "It is a very considerable time, sir, since Miss McFarland and myself seperated. I would, if possible, avoid shocking your mind, but I am compelled to say, that Elinor's infidelity was the cause." "Facts, facts, sir, if you please, and spare your comments," said I. "Since our separation, I understand she visited Rome, Flor- ence, and several of the Italian States, in company with a young nobleman, whom at length, she left, and sunk into, that way off living." "I understand, sir, pray, go on," "From that period till last night, I have remained ignorant of her entirely, when I met her in company with Mr. Randall. She resides at present. in a; small cottage near the sea shore, and as- suati the name of Elinor Morton,. 4 A' .. indall turned pale as death; his knees shook, and his head sunk upon his breast. "What," said I, is best now to do . I am then, still, the fa- ther of a living child; and she a common prostitute Oh! Hea- ven, that 1 could have been spared this intelligence! Give me a  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7970-00000049"/> ^      2W %tl KILO21MAN, OR, g ;riJSci2kd .91 o"fi- Jte' fiih TriH  snr ibles; fith? aBfe Though. such an ,t, is, ni; ot  fd peh   i :oua nmudi: :'afri'xii yhd :th iftii, ig that;vi :,e O would be rImy' own daughter-no, no.,-k, &amp;AwntWhat I, no on6-to :wreak myven geance oa-in66-oe gity iut' mypoor Mhild*-O! -I b I fatW84 , , ' , , .... ',';    to :C,G  tt .- , : A:,few;.da'j 'erdttie/srgS[Og :nes'were' enaced i had ,my pasiage secured :nboard'a papcke! 'hipfor America, where aved safe in dae tthie. About the tenth -year of "m residence in the New'Wdld, iotin f my. frle'ns recired: [nteHllgcil c )kofrptn ode'ncehim, mY., daugpter a  Charlk andal!, and!nediate!yv c6muniated i to mte. The story rad'thns f- , My haufaer Et4nbr;tfi!f t hir b ; rtrifulntm , had'cphlpetel. y gubdued her victn   ftrdal^ rItee ed;hiinon;nd on, iUmvled 'ohim ioto diffictii ti(qs, fow I ^   hs a to bxii f-im'elf liy'some,66 heis f'r#a4k:, itBf ie tlecaid har'plied0fctmentinetUh offen'eednied less reoiuotinig tha ftit O q, i e L aol ' g:t, ; W; nttg .iw ;prevaied' upn to comrmit a forg'ry to. gratify te extriaasance foi fijir: destiroyer. Sspiciou was evtaded or a timie, b/if W it:&amp;'i Ste g;4ii-;deteoNtQj in f)tgn alarger aitmoot. ?He q;..;:ipS: sedI :: ,w then-pesueadte!ny qElnqr'hatle cold iouly F     Mvaq^e. .! is ritiq "by; govteting 6lbttin ,ibtisOnQu thif 'e way. 'd'Rada ir 8ai  cithe,d:lling^f, his frien :andsvift"m, d plunfged4,*adaggea,..tajd^,hA^:f, $;h'drt.,f;,;himwo hohd once loved hlmn as. a .on.  Tbe murderer -.as pursue/ ab bot the assasin' and p1 sior *eretarrbsted. irawttfea0tti ^ ai Le ufcli^ that the, wealiest merchant of London had been murdered; the greatest excitement prefailqd, andthe crqwd hat gathered ,bout the prison could with difficulty be dis- ' ua'ded' fi;6am en6iniigh 1 io t'ls6her' and execAtinghimowo thottie .pot. A twilentuie  ;Rlste      .t be:hug at TYburn. Elinor folloqied, him tothe gallows. an :fli:-tr"imphed b5ver ht ttirtjPiiibv:dra big conDtent to labor-I gave up all claims-to acquaintane, and fromthat. time Ihave made-Lime-Kins fifi'ohn, 5nd. have dpesded upon the bi6eintifPl for my support, w4ch ,Waj s6ometiMi,.f ' tf -,rjo.- 'IOcould'wi %r-ater / '.other,:.tyjdeo rAh'gh/g ia.! ,., iigh ,d I hFQ neverjet li! - cited iHduthful. , *   "if, 3But ctia; 'msiptnBe i'e l:tctt ^WfN! :ss i, , to o m chiid; .*he , ebetisr' whether  i sheisatq Ipw,/nQts,.Taisyr y wei&amp;4ghs delft my decl9Jii years; and y ittlive-live in d^iS 4fA l&amp; 4 a, a' to bedW f Iat'e' yoW not pity a miserable old man, almOW diseroted; aiAiatonnix ergte. t l :TakO h!I. Htt.!q-;9isi.';be a b- is nme is, M # --.Z P tIc to I  jutietohs trywic hee erea yu       i?  '^    I /   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>