<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7514">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Refugees, or, The Union Boys of '61 </title>
            <author>Pritchard, Paul.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7514</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1967</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The refugees, or, The Union boys of '61</title>
                  <author>Pritchard, Paul.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>80 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T.W. Strong</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1862">[1862]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-01-26">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5. Inserted OCR text. Linked image files</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The refugees, or, The Union boys of '61</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7514-00000001"/>Yal unver~tyLIDfay7&#xD;
'TE REFUGEES'&#xD;
TH   N ORB YSOF611&#xD;
&#xD;
A TALE OF THE REBELLION.&#xD;
&#xD;
A&#xD;
A'&#xD;
&#xD;
PAUL PRITCHARD.&#xD;
tt,&#xD;
&#xD;
NEW YORK:&#xD;
T. W., STRONG, PUBLISHER, No. 98 NAssau SaRU.&#xD;
&#xD;
I l. '&#xD;
PI&#xD;
&#xD;
F                   M  "&#xD;
'73  .,, F-_ ; _  ".  e ''  " }  ,.  "   fi&#xD;
&#xD;
K&#xD;
&#xD;
t       L I&#xD;
iiiaajr~&#xD;
&#xD;
'r&#xD;
E&#xD;
=r&#xD;
r&#xD;
a&#xD;
i&#xD;
z&#xD;
f&#xD;
i&#xD;
3&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7514-00000002"/>&#xD;
Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1802,&#xD;
BY THOS. W. STRONG,&#xD;
In the District Court of the United States, for the Southern District of New York.&#xD;
&#xD;
Ix~&#xD;
&#xD;
'             .J&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES;&#xD;
&#xD;
THE&#xD;
&#xD;
UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
t&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
INTRODUCTORY.&#xD;
TUE ELMS.&#xD;
WITHIN about a mile of the Greenbriar river, which&#xD;
flows near the town of Lewisburg, Virginia, in a&#xD;
beautiTul valley, between two spurs of the Alleghany&#xD;
Mountains, there stood an old mansion house, erected&#xD;
many years ago, by one Piercy Morley, a descendant of&#xD;
one of the best families in the West of England. - Piercy&#xD;
Morley was a younger son, who, disregarding the wishes&#xD;
of his family, who had selected the church as a profession&#xD;
in which, through political influence, his prospects could&#xD;
be better advanced than in any other way, threw, up the&#xD;
gown and emigrated to the then colony of Virginia, about&#xD;
the year 1762, and settled in the neighborhood we =have&#xD;
described.  He was prosperous, soon attaining a high&#xD;
social position, and was elected a member of the House&#xD;
of Burgesses. Heedless of family ties, and sympathizing-&#xD;
Warmly with the spirit of Independence which -led' to the&#xD;
&#xD;
'i&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
0&#xD;
&#xD;
_                              x&#xD;
pay.&#xD;
a  5-*      Y.             r  t  a&#xD;
Egli"&#xD;
'; f.   lF   tt  s  t 1 "           1&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7514-00000003"/>&#xD;
6              THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
TIhE UNION BOYS OF '61.       '7&#xD;
&#xD;
War of the Revolution, on the breaking out of hostilities;&#xD;
he. enthusiastically espoused the cause of the "Rebels,"&#xD;
and raising a regiment, composed of the very flower of&#xD;
his adopted state, he fought at its head, until the Inde-&#xD;
pendence of the Colonies was achieved, and then, return-&#xD;
ing to his plantation, lived for many years to enjoy the&#xD;
fruits of that Liberty, which he had contributed so much&#xD;
to gain. At his death his large estate, known as "The&#xD;
Elms," passed into the hands of his only son, William&#xD;
Morley, who inherited all the patriotism of his father,&#xD;
and, served his country as well in her councils, as his an-&#xD;
cestor had in the field. He had married ,at an early age,&#xD;
the fruit of his union being.a son and a daughter. The&#xD;
son died sighting under his country's flag, upon the&#xD;
bloody field of Resaca de la Palma, and as the mother&#xD;
had, died some years previous, William Morley was left&#xD;
alone with his remaining child, Rose Morley, who, at the&#xD;
time we are writing of, was a beautiful girl about eighteen&#xD;
years of age.&#xD;
In the neighborhood of "The Elms," there resided at&#xD;
the same time, another family by the name of loughton.&#xD;
They were wealthy, but there were dark whispers afloat&#xD;
as to the manner in which old Ralph Houghton had ae-&#xD;
quired his wealth. He came from Louisiana, and had&#xD;
been a seafaring man up to the time of settling upon the&#xD;
estate he had purchased in South-Western Virginia, and&#xD;
had been, according to the declaration of some, engaged&#xD;
at one period of his life, in the slave trade, and the more&#xD;
censorious of the country gossips, did not hesitate to hint&#xD;
that he had taken part in even more lawless and reckless&#xD;
enterprises ; one old woman affirming, - that in going&#xD;
through the house one day, she had seen in a sort, of hum-&#xD;
&#xD;
ber room incautiously left open, various weapons of a&#xD;
murderous character, and a black flag, bearing upon its&#xD;
folds the terrible death's head and cross bones. Be this&#xD;
as it may, his society was generally avoided by the better&#xD;
families of the neighborhood, and the visitors at his home&#xD;
were few and far between. His son, Miles Houghton,&#xD;
was a reckless, daring man, who took an active interest&#xD;
in the field sports of the country,! and was somewhat&#xD;
prominent in local political circles. He was not over&#xD;
nice in the selection of his associates, and as he spent his&#xD;
money freely, he collected around him a, large number of&#xD;
such as were always ready for a spree or at frolic, and&#xD;
enjoyed all the influence that a leading position among&#xD;
such a class, gave him. He had been an aspirant for the&#xD;
hand of Rose Morley, but on the first intimation of his&#xD;
design,l he was met by an indignant refusal, and 'received&#xD;
a hint from William Morley, that any repetition of his&#xD;
advances would be construed as an affront. This re-&#xD;
jection, however, did not altogether check his passion&#xD;
for the young girl; and without making any particu-&#xD;
lar manifestation of his feelings, so far as the verbal ex-&#xD;
pression of them went, hopersistently crossed her path&#xD;
upon all possible occasions, and in various ways insisted&#xD;
upon making her conscious of his preference.&#xD;
Among the most welcome visitors at "The Elms," was&#xD;
Mark Lee, a young man who had originally came from&#xD;
the State of Massachusetts, and who had established him-&#xD;
self as a lawyer in the neighboring town of Lewisburgh,&#xD;
where he stood high in the estimation of all who knew&#xD;
him. He had been elected to the lower house of the&#xD;
State Legislature, and was noted for his staunch patriot'&#xD;
ism, and unwavering fidelity to his friends and any cause&#xD;
&#xD;
'cv a&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7514-00000004"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; OR,-&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.          9&#xD;
&#xD;
ie espoused.  He. had long since found- favor in the&#xD;
eyes of the fair Rose, and the day of their marriage had&#xD;
been fixed at no distant period, shortly before the events&#xD;
we are about to relate, occurred. This preference had&#xD;
awakened all the worst passions of Miles lioughton,&#xD;
and he had often been heard to declare, in his more reek-&#xD;
less moments, that he would be revenged upon the Ismooth&#xD;
faced Yankee, as he called Mark Lee, and he left no'&#xD;
means untried to injure him in his profession, and his po-&#xD;
litical and social position ; without effect, however, as the&#xD;
Mfe of the young lawyer gave the lie to every slander&#xD;
which his traducer put into circulation.&#xD;
Mark Lee and Miles Houghton, both of them, took an&#xD;
active part in the political canvass which resulted in the&#xD;
election, of the present incumbent of the Presidential.&#xD;
chair. Mark espousing the cause of the Union ticket,&#xD;
represented by the names of Bell and Everett, while&#xD;
Houghton, with less ability but more unscrupulous en-&#xD;
thusiasm, was an active worker in the ranks of the ultra&#xD;
Southern party. As is well known, tlie State of Virginia&#xD;
gave the majority of her vote for the Un'ion candidates,&#xD;
and the rancor which existed in the heart of Miles Lough-&#xD;
ton, was not diminished by the evidence of the superior&#xD;
influence of his rival, as displayed in the result in their&#xD;
own district, where the majority for the Union ticket had&#xD;
been overwhelming. Thus matters stood, when the first&#xD;
gun in Charleston harbor sent its fearful reverberation&#xD;
all over the country, and roused up the dead demon,&#xD;
War, which set brother in arms against brother, father'&#xD;
against son, friend against friend; which developed the&#xD;
deep laid treasonous plots of years, and called up the&#xD;
~men of the North to .do battle for the flag ยฃ01' which their&#xD;
&#xD;
sires had shed their blood, and to sustain the government&#xD;
under which the nation had grown to bethe marvel of&#xD;
the world. In the wild excitement which followed, none&#xD;
were allowed to stand neutral, and among those who&#xD;
were loudest in their defence of the South, and most de-&#xD;
riunciatory of the North, was Miles Ioughton. Mark&#xD;
Lee, on the contrary, took high conservative ground, and&#xD;
used all his efforts to quell the increasing spirit of insub-&#xD;
ordination which every day became more demonstrative&#xD;
in western Virginia. His enemy of course took advan-&#xD;
tage of this, and used every means in his power to excite&#xD;
the people against him. For a time his efforts were vain,&#xD;
but at last, Mark Lee began -to be shunned, then openly&#xD;
denounced, and so violent (lid the manifestations against&#xD;
him grow to be, that, at last,. he was obliged to flee for&#xD;
his, life, and took refuge under the friendly roof of old&#xD;
Wiliam Morley, who also took sides against the rebel&#xD;
cause. Miles Hloughton, meanwhile, was not idle; by all&#xD;
the means in his power, he added fuel to the flames of&#xD;
treason, and raised a body of nien in defence of the rebel&#xD;
flag, which everywhere disgraced the place of the glo-&#xD;
rious old banner. Knowing the birthplace of Mark Lee,&#xD;
he denounced him as a Northern spy, and managed by&#xD;
the sheerest mendacity, forged papers, letters, &amp;amp;c., td con-&#xD;
vince the people that he was a secret agent of the ultra&#xD;
Abolitionists of the North, and one of the friends of the&#xD;
mad fanatic, John'Brown, whose insane raid had created&#xD;
so much excitement and bitterness but a short time before.&#xD;
Under the effect of these misrepresentations, the excited&#xD;
populace would have torn Mark Lee, limb from limb,&#xD;
could he have been found, but he had suddenly disappear-&#xD;
eod, and all search for him being vain, it was generally be-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7514-00000005"/>&#xD;
1 ;ITE UNION BOYS OF '61.      zIl&#xD;
&#xD;
lieved that he had returned to his native State, and joined&#xD;
the Federal army.&#xD;
Miles, however, more than suspected that he still lurked&#xD;
in the neighborhood, and his jealousy prompted the suspi-&#xD;
cion that he was secreted at "The Elms."  These suspi-&#xD;
cions were confirmed by several minor circumstances&#xD;
which came to his knowledge, and determining to know&#xD;
the truth, he succeeded in obtaining a warrant for his ar-&#xD;
rest, on the charge of being a spy, and a traitor to the&#xD;
Confederate government, to which Virginia had given in&#xD;
her adherence, ald at the time our story opens had de-&#xD;
vised means, for putting his revengeful plans into immrne-&#xD;
diateexecution. With these few explanatory words, we&#xD;
proceed with our narrative, which, with the exception of&#xD;
the names of the principal personages who figure therein,&#xD;
is strictly true.&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER I.&#xD;
THE sun was just setting behind the western ridge of&#xD;
the Alleghanies, and the whole surrounding landscape&#xD;
was bathed in golden light, as a young girl emerged cau-&#xD;
tiously from a bridle path, which, traversing the woods&#xD;
which bound the eastern side of the Greenbriar river,&#xD;
emerges into the road which leads to Lewisburg in West-&#xD;
ern Virginia. She pursued her way with cautious steps,&#xD;
pausing to listen every now and then, with beating heart,&#xD;
looking anxiously upon this side and the other, and occa-&#xD;
sionally stopping to gaze behind her, as if she feared pur-&#xD;
suit. Suddenly a sharp turn in the road brought her to&#xD;
the edge of a high blufl, from which she could overlook&#xD;
the surrounding country, which lay spread out like a map&#xD;
at her feet. Through the lovely valley, which lay below,&#xD;
the' river meandered on, in its zigzag course, looking, as&#xD;
it reflected the rays of the setting sun, like a belt of bur-&#xD;
nished gold, while far off to the right, the high peaks of&#xD;
the Blue Ridge might be seen towering to the. sky. The&#xD;
cattle grazed peacefully in the rick green pastures; the&#xD;
stacks of corn, which rose here and there, betokened&#xD;
plenty, and the whole scene was calm and peaceful. As&#xD;
the maiden thus stood, her ears were suddenly startled by&#xD;
the sound of a bugle, and the hoarse shouts of men.&#xD;
Quickly turning to the left, and half screening her form&#xD;
&#xD;
10              ME REFUGEES ; OJ9&#xD;
0&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7514-00000006"/>&#xD;
TE REFUGEE ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
behind the giant trunk of a huge 'sycamore, which spread&#xD;
its branches high above her head, she saw a troop of&#xD;
horsemen emerge from a dense wood below, and take&#xD;
their way along the river bank, in the direction of Lewis-&#xD;
burgh. The cortege numbered in all about two hundred&#xD;
men. They were not uniformned. Each wore such gar-&#xD;
nents as suited him, but all carried swords, and carbines&#xD;
Lung from their shoulders. At their head rode an officer&#xD;
im.the uniform of the United States, bitt the flag which&#xD;
was borne immediately behind him, showed that he was a&#xD;
traitor to the government whose glorious insignia he&#xD;
wore, and thpt he belonged to those, who, with fratricidal&#xD;
hand, had risen in arms against it. As the young girl&#xD;
gazed upon this sight,:ber eye dilated and her lovely lip&#xD;
curled in scorn and indignation.&#xD;
"So so," she muttered between her teeth, "you have&#xD;
consummated your hellish wish at last, Miles Houghton.&#xD;
Traitor and renegade that you are! Ha !" she exclaim-&#xD;
ed, as the troop turned into a lane which crossed the&#xD;
main road. "Ha! they are going towards 'The Elms,'&#xD;
and Mark Lee.   There is no time to be lost.  I can&#xD;
reach the hut before them, and may save him yet. They&#xD;
know not of the hiding place."&#xD;
Giving one last look at the receding band, she darted&#xD;
quickly away, and taking to the woods, sped swiftly&#xD;
along, with the evident intention of getting in advance of&#xD;
the party of insurgents whom she had seen in the valley&#xD;
below. Heedless of all obstacles, she pursued her course&#xD;
through the dense woods for at least a mile, when she&#xD;
was suddenly startled by the unexpected appearance of a&#xD;
negro, who suddenly emerged from a thicket, and stood,.&#xD;
with hands upraised and mouth wide open, directly in&#xD;
&#xD;
12&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
her path. He was as dark as Erebus, small of stature,&#xD;
and though not passed fifty years of age, looked at&#xD;
least twenty years older. His limbs were crooked. he&#xD;
had but one eye, and so warped and distorted were his&#xD;
hands, that they looked more like the talons of some&#xD;
huge bird than a portion of a human being.&#xD;
"IHi, hi !" he exclaimed. "Gracious Solomon, what's&#xD;
de matter, missed, dat you're a lopin along trough de&#xD;
woods, like a deer on de full jump? Why, you looks as&#xD;
sheered as a rabbit wid de dogs after it. What's de&#xD;
matter ?"&#xD;
" Ah, Cupid,'is it you ?" asked the young girl, gasping&#xD;
for breath, "You frightened me dreadfully. But I have&#xD;
no time to waste in words ; danger is at hand. From&#xD;
the bluff above I observed a party of arined rebels, with&#xD;
Miles Iloughton at their head. They are moving in the&#xD;
direction of 'The Elms,' and I fear me with no good pur.&#xD;
pose.' Miles knows that Mr. Lee has been our guest&#xD;
there for a week past, and in his hate and jealousy he will&#xD;
be capable of any act of cowardly violence. The mo-&#xD;
ment I saw the traitorous wretches I hastened to warn&#xD;
him, and-"&#xD;
"Dat's right, Missee, data's right !" interrupted the ne-&#xD;
gro, " Mass'r Lee mustn't be caught dar like a woodchuck&#xD;
in a hole. I'll go right along and fix it all right. Ise&#xD;
only a cripple, but I'd run dese old legs off for Mass'r&#xD;
Lee, or any other man wot don't go back on de old flag.&#xD;
As for dat trashy Miles Houghton, I just wish dis nigger&#xD;
had de fixin' ob him, dat's all! Come along, Missee,&#xD;
come along. I'll go ahead to de Elms. You go right&#xD;
straight along to de old cabin by de creek, and I'll have&#xD;
Mass'r Lee dar afore you, suih1"&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
13&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="14" xml:id="VAC7514-00000007"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
Without waiting for her reply, the old negro darted&#xD;
off with an alacrity which his crippled form made sure&#xD;
prising, and in a moment was out of sight.&#xD;
The girl, evidently experiencing a sensation of relief,&#xD;
then followed with hasty steps, and in a short time reach-&#xD;
ed a solitary log-cabin, which stood in front of a high&#xD;
rock, by the side of a wide brook, which brawled on its&#xD;
way to the neighboring river.&#xD;
Hastily opening the door, she entered the humble lodge-&#xD;
nient and gazed anxiously around her.&#xD;
"Not here," she exclaimed, as she finished, her hasty&#xD;
survey. ",ray Heaven the warning arrive not too late.&#xD;
But.he may be in the inner room." Going to a door to&#xD;
the right, she pushed it open and entered another apart-&#xD;
ment, less spacious than the first, and fitted up as a sleep-&#xD;
ing chamber.&#xD;
"No, he is not here."&#xD;
As she spoke she turned to leave the, room, when a&#xD;
noise, proceeding apparently from the Iloor of the cham-&#xD;
ber, attracted her attention. Instantly stooping, she look-&#xD;
ed cautiously around, paused a moment as if to make sure&#xD;
that no one was approaching, and then, taking a key from&#xD;
her bosom. she pressed it against what appeared to be a&#xD;
knot in the rough floor. As she did so, the knot sank,&#xD;
leaving a small aperture in the rough plank, at the side of&#xD;
which appeared a key-hole, into which she quietly insert-&#xD;
ed the key, and turning a bolt, she half rose, and placing&#xD;
her hand 4 the space left by the sinking knot, raised, a&#xD;
trap-door which concealed the entrance to a subterranean&#xD;
passage, then bending her heady she listened. For a time&#xD;
she heard no sound save the beating of her heart and her&#xD;
own loud breathing, but, presently, the noise of' distant&#xD;
&#xD;
14&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="-17" xml:id="VAC7514-00000008"/>&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF' 61.            17&#xD;
the lovely girl in his arms, and pressing his lips upon her&#xD;
fair brow, "How shall I thank vou for your kindness and&#xD;
your care? my own dear Rose-2"&#xD;
Hush !" she said, interrupting him, " we have no time&#xD;
to waste in words. You must go, and quickly. Miles&#xD;
Houghton is even now in hot pursuit of you. Should he&#xD;
find you, I cannot foretell the consequences. You know&#xD;
his hate, his desperate character, his lack of principle, his&#xD;
vow of vengeance !&#xD;
".The miscreant !" exclaimed the young man. "The&#xD;
vile traitor, and the malignant coward!  Because you&#xD;
would not smile upon him; because you preferred myV&#xD;
honest love to his wild, reckless passion, he seeks to take&#xD;
advantage of the maddening excitement which these vile,&#xD;
traitorous wretches have produced by their specious lies&#xD;
and misrepresentations, to crush me from his ith. iHe&#xD;
calls me traitor ! He, forsooth, who turns his back upon&#xD;
the flag my father died to make triumplhant, and under&#xD;
which we, as a nation, have grown great, prosperous, and&#xD;
happy! He has trampled that sacred banner under foot,&#xD;
and raised in its place the foul emblem of disloyalty.&#xD;
And because I will not so disgrace the patriotic blood&#xD;
which flows within these veins, I am denounced, a price is&#xD;
set upon me, I am hounded from place to place, obliged&#xD;
to avoid the open day, to hide in secret nooks and cor-&#xD;
ners, to fly my country, which I love, and thee whom I&#xD;
adore! Oh that Amerjcans should be obliged to blush&#xD;
for their own countrymen !"&#xD;
"Dat's all very nice, Mass'r Lee," here interrupted&#xD;
Cupid, who, meanwhile, had kindled a fire on the hearth,   i&#xD;
and lit a pine knot, which threwv a lurid glare around the&#xD;
little room. " Dat ar's all very well, but if you stay har,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7514-00000009"/>&#xD;
18              THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
dey'll trap you suah! It don't make a dif o' bitrance&#xD;
whether he's right or wrong; .he's got hold ob de heavy&#xD;
end ob de stick, and you can't do nuffin but make for de&#xD;
camp ob General MeLennan, and you'd better be mighty&#xD;
quick about it too. Par aint no time to be lost. De Se-&#xD;
ceshers is thicker than mush around heali, and if any one&#xD;
on 'etn gets hold o' you, you're a goner, suah !"&#xD;
"But," answered Mark Lee, " where can I go ? How&#xD;
shall I escape?  My existence in the neighborhood is&#xD;
well known, and my appearance familiar to every man,&#xD;
woman, and child for miles around. I am single-handed,&#xD;
without a friend, unarmed! There are, none safe your&#xD;
honored father, dear Rose, who would shelter or protect&#xD;
me, for the unfortunate have no friends !"&#xD;
" Alas.! I feel the truth of all you say, dear Mark," re-&#xD;
sponded the lovely girl, as tears of love and sympathy&#xD;
streamed rapidly down her cheeks, " but here, the danger&#xD;
is increased by every moment's stay. Houghton and his,&#xD;
band of marauders may return at any minute, and should&#xD;
they discover you, you are lost!"&#xD;
"Losti lost !" exclaimed Mark, with asperity., "Hunt-&#xD;
ed, and waylaid on all sides-and for what? Oh, just&#xD;
Heaven, thou hast been pleased to bless, this, my native&#xD;
land, with all that can make it lovely, happy, and pros.&#xD;
porous. Thou hast made it teem with plenty. Thou hast&#xD;
given it broad rivers, wide lakes, valleys, and mountains&#xD;
teeming with the bounties of thy hand. Thou hast made&#xD;
it a dwelling place fit for angels, and yet, those to whom&#xD;
thou hast given it, are striving to lay it waste, to make a -&#xD;
wilderness once more of that, which the hands of patient&#xD;
industry have made a paradise! It cannot be that flea.&#xD;
yen will look calmly on and see this wickedness succeed I&#xD;
&#xD;
TIHE UNION 4 BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
19&#xD;
&#xD;
Oh were I free, once more under the folds of that dear&#xD;
flag, whose every star sheds light and hope upon a free-&#xD;
man's heart !"&#xD;
"Hope, hope, dear Mark !" sobbed the girl, as she lean-&#xD;
ed upon his breast.&#xD;
" Hope !" he repeated, bitterly. " Ah, Rose, there is no&#xD;
hope. No hope for me or for my country! And thee,&#xD;
Rose, thee whom I love so tenderly, thee whom I thought&#xD;
to call my bride, within a few short days. Ah, how can&#xD;
I separate myself from thee? How leave thee ?"&#xD;
"But," replied Rose, "you know, dear Mark, that your&#xD;
presence here, may destroy me as well. Were it once&#xD;
suspected that I harbored a Federalist, all their hatred&#xD;
would fall on me, and we know of what such hate is ca-&#xD;
pable."&#xD;
Here a loud rap was heard upon the door. All started&#xD;
in aifright, and stood as if spell-bound at the alarm.&#xD;
Cupid was the first to move. Without saying a word,&#xD;
he made signs for all to keep silent; then seizing Mark&#xD;
Lee by the arm, he pointed to the trap-door. Once more&#xD;
taking the weeping Rose to his arms, Mark obeyed the&#xD;
sign , and in a moment disappeared. The rapping still&#xD;
continued, while Cupid reclosed the opening and led Rose&#xD;
to the door of the inner chamber, when he pushed her&#xD;
gently in, and proceeded deliberately to unbar the door,&#xD;
yawning and gaping meanwhile, as if just awakened from&#xD;
a deep sleep.&#xD;
" Helld! Hello ! Who's dar ?" he asked, peering out&#xD;
into the darkness. "What de debbil you come liar, dis&#xD;
time o' night for, 'sturbin de old niggah out o' his nap?&#xD;
Who's dar, I say ?"&#xD;
He had not long to wait, for even as he spoke, a man&#xD;
pushed him aside and strode into the cabin.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7514-00000010"/>&#xD;
20             ThE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER II.&#xD;
THE man who entered the little apartment, was not a&#xD;
fearful object to behold. He was-rather below the me-&#xD;
dium size, and was dressed in a suit of linsey-woolsey&#xD;
much too large foi' him, and which gave him the appear-&#xD;
ance of having shrunk in his clothes. He wore a grey&#xD;
felt hat, with a very wide and limp brim, which threw&#xD;
into deep shadow a strongly marked yet not unpleasing&#xD;
face. He had a firm, compressed mouth, bespeaking&#xD;
much determination, and wore a pair of green spectacles,&#xD;
which completely shut out his eyes, and added very much&#xD;
to the oddity of his appearance. He carried a walking-&#xD;
stick under one arm, and under the other a book of pecu-&#xD;
liar shape.&#xD;
As he entered, Cupid looked at him in great astonish-&#xD;
ment, which increased to such an extent when the stran-&#xD;
ger deliberately turned his back to the fire, and com-&#xD;
menced to hum Old Hundred, that the bewildered son of&#xD;
Ham quite forgot to shut the door, or say a single word,&#xD;
but stood, like a misshapen mummy, with eyes and mouth&#xD;
agape, gazing at what he evidently took for a newly in.&#xD;
vented style of apparition.&#xD;
Why in thunder. don't'you shut the door?" asked the&#xD;
stranger, without changing his position, and eyeing the&#xD;
old negro with some severity, through his green glasses.&#xD;
&#xD;
"Reckon you was brought up in a saw-mill, wasn't you?&#xD;
Shut the door, I tell you, you blamed, grinning ape ! I'm&#xD;
cold !"&#xD;
Cupid obeyed, mechanically, still all abroad.&#xD;
"Now put up the bar, and if you've got anything in the&#xD;
shanty that a white man can drink, trot it out! I m dry!&#xD;
A little hog and hominy wouldn't go bad neither{ if you&#xD;
aint out o' rations."&#xD;
Gradually Cupid began to realize that the object he&#xD;
was gazing at was not a ghost, and his face subsided into&#xD;
something akin to his natural expression, as he spluttered&#xD;
out:&#xD;
"Hi! hi! mass'r, God fo'gib me, but I tuck you for a&#xD;
ghost! Who de debbil be ye, anyhow, and what do you&#xD;
want ?"&#xD;
"Who be I? I'm Handel Hayden Beethoven Brown,&#xD;
Professor of Psalmody, and teacher of Botany, Geology,&#xD;
and Mathematics. That's who I am. What do I want?&#xD;
Shelter, warmth, some whisky, and a right smart chance&#xD;
to eat. The first I've got unless you put me out, a thing&#xD;
you aint shaped to do, and the other you are going to trot&#xD;
out, if you've got 'em; ef not, I reckon I can do without&#xD;
'em, as I have before."&#xD;
So saying, the stranger backed nearer to the fire, and&#xD;
opening the book which he had carried under his arm, he&#xD;
commenced to hum one of those old-fashioned hymn tunes,&#xD;
go popular with the negroes.&#xD;
Cupid did not seem at all satisfied either with the ex-&#xD;
planation or the demand upon his hospitality, but stood&#xD;
eyeing the suspicious stranger askance through his soli-&#xD;
tary orb. As he did so, the Professor seemed to become&#xD;
absorbed in the tune he was humming, and his voice grew&#xD;
&#xD;
d&#xD;
&#xD;
21&#xD;
&#xD;
lo&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7514-00000011"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
louder and louder, until, at last, it burst forth in a strong,&#xD;
ear-splitting strain of nasal melody.&#xD;
In direct proportion to the loudness of the strain, Cu-&#xD;
pid's one eye and his mouth distended themselves, his&#xD;
head, arms, and feet keeping time to the music, until,&#xD;
Ihially, he could resist the impulse no longer, and joined&#xD;
i the melodyTwith a loud and not unmusical voice.&#xD;
The stranger, apparently unheeding him, continued&#xD;
singing' until all the verses of the hymn had come in for&#xD;
their full share of vocal effect, when he suddenly stopped.&#xD;
Then Cupid brokeout:&#xD;
"Lor' a g'u'ry, mass'r, dat does here nigger's soul good !&#xD;
Ii, hiI"  You kin hal) anything dis here nigger's&#xD;
got! you kin ! Lor' bless you, mass' r, you sings just like&#xD;
a bird! Anything dis nigger's got," and going to a little&#xD;
cupboard, he produced a stone jug, a tin cup, a piece of&#xD;
bacon, and some corn bread, which lie placed upon the&#xD;
table.&#xD;
lhe stranger did not wait for any further invitation,&#xD;
but drawing up a three-legged stool, sat down at the ta-&#xD;
ble, and pouring some of the contents of the jug into the&#xD;
tin cup. put it to his nose.&#xD;
Whisky, mass'r," said Cupid. " Good, too. None o'&#xD;
your nigger rot-gut, mass'r. Drink hearty! 'Twont hurt&#xD;
you."'&#xD;
Thus enlightened, the stranger drained the cup at a&#xD;
draught, and cutting off a piece of the bacon, he placed it&#xD;
on a piece of the corn bread, and commenced eating vo-&#xD;
raciously.&#xD;
" Does you belong in dose parts, mass'r ?" asked Cupid,&#xD;
with a quick glance of awakened curiosity beaming in his&#xD;
single eye.&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
"See here-what's your name?" asked the stranger,&#xD;
without answering the question.&#xD;
" Cupid," answered the negro, grinning, " dey calls me&#xD;
Cupid, cause I's so handsome."&#xD;
"Well, Cupid," the Professor of psalmody went on,&#xD;
"don't ask any questions, but answer mine. You live&#xD;
here, of. course ?&#xD;
"Lived here all my life, mass'r."&#xD;
"Know the folks about here pretty well ?"&#xD;
"I reckon,"&#xD;
"Know the Morleys?"&#xD;
" Right smart. I belongs to Mass'r Morley, I does."&#xD;
" He owns you, does he?  Well, I reckon he's proud o'&#xD;
that. Then you know his daughter, Rose."&#xD;
What you want to know dat for ?"&#xD;
"Didn't I tell you to ask no questions?" -&#xD;
Well, sposen I do, what den ?"&#xD;
"And a young man named Mark Lee ?"&#xD;
"No, rnass'r, I doesn't know nuffin at all about em!&#xD;
" See here," replied the Professor, rising, "if you lie to&#xD;
me, I'll choke you! Tell me the truth. You do know&#xD;
them !"&#xD;
"Well, spose I does ?"&#xD;
" Then listen to me. I know your master is a straight&#xD;
out-and-out Union man. Don't say a word-I know it--&#xD;
that's enough. So am I."&#xD;
"See here, mass'r, I don't know what de debbil you be,&#xD;
or who de debbil you are, 'cept what you told mec. -But I&#xD;
tell you one thing," said Cupid, beginning to growv warm,&#xD;
"if you come here to suck anything out o' me, I'm blamed&#xD;
if you won't git sucked in your own self! Dart! Now I&#xD;
don't know nothing I"&#xD;
&#xD;
I1&#xD;
&#xD;
'I&#xD;
J1&#xD;
iI&#xD;
I  y&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
it&#xD;
' f&#xD;
''i&#xD;
t I&#xD;
t  Y&#xD;
1 }fTil&#xD;
1.-&#xD;
A&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7514-00000012"/>&#xD;
24&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
"Shut up, you darned fool, you can't tell me anything I&#xD;
don't know. I know Squire Morley to be sound. I know&#xD;
Mark Lee to be sound. I know Rose Morley to be sound.&#xD;
i'm sound, and so are you, you black imp of Satan. So&#xD;
listen to me. The hounds are after Mark. They. passed&#xD;
the place wlre I. was hid, not half an hour ago. They&#xD;
have gone to the Squire's to look for him. But he aint&#xD;
there, I know that. I don't know where he is, but I reck-&#xD;
on you do, and so does Miss Rose, and I'd bet a quarter's&#xD;
teaching in psalnody agin a green punkin, that they paint&#xD;
a thousand miles away from this here place."&#xD;
"See here. mass'r-" Cupid began, but the Professor&#xD;
interrupted him:&#xD;
"You know where they be, and so maybe do I. You&#xD;
see, I'm a geologist; a geologist is a man who knows all&#xD;
about rocks and things. Well, in hunting around these&#xD;
rocks last summer, I found a cave. It aint a very big one,-&#xD;
only a long fissure in the limestone formation about here.&#xD;
It leads from the Devil'si Pulpit, back of the orchard at&#xD;
the Elms, as straight as a bee line to this cabin, and that&#xD;
cave contains at this very moment, Mark Lee. But I'll&#xD;
have him out. The opening is here!"&#xD;
With these words he rose quickly, and bursting open&#xD;
the door of the inner chamber, he was about to enter the&#xD;
apartment, when he staggered back at the sight of Rose,&#xD;
who stood upon the threshold, holding an axe in her&#xD;
hand, which the flush in her cheek and the determination&#xD;
in her eye, proved she would not hesitate to use-.a&#xD;
"DBack, on your life!I" she exclaimed, raising the axe&#xD;
above her head. "Back, I say! I will defend him to&#xD;
the last 1"&#xD;
Cupid, meanwhile, had seized the long wooden bar&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF 61.&#xD;
which had served to barricade the door, and advancing in&#xD;
the rear of the Professor, called out.:&#xD;
" Leave him to me, Missee Rose! leave him to me! I'll&#xD;
fix him!"&#xD;
Thus threatened both in front and rear, the Professor&#xD;
stood for a moment bewildered, but collecting his presence&#xD;
'of mind, he raised his hands, and half turning to Cupid, in&#xD;
order to guard against any sudden belligerent impulse of&#xD;
the excited darkey, he said in a tone entirely different&#xD;
from that which had heretofore characterized his manner:&#xD;
"For heaven's sake, Rose Morley, listen to me! Mark&#xD;
Lee is indeed honored in having so bold aid fair a de-&#xD;
fender. But so far as I and Iy intentions are concerned,&#xD;
your alarm is groundless and defence unnecessary. Do&#xD;
you know me now ?" With these words he removed his&#xD;
hat, and with it the long flaxen hair and spectacles which&#xD;
.he had previously worn, and throwing the disguise at Cu-&#xD;
pid, said with a laugh, "And now, Miss Rose, please to&#xD;
take down that murderous looking axe. I do not think&#xD;
you will find further occasion for its use 1"&#xD;
Rose gazed a moment in complete bewilderment, then&#xD;
dropping the axe, exclaimed in a tone of wonder:&#xD;
"Carlton Howard1"&#xD;
" Mass'r Howard, as I'm a nigger I" exclaimed Cupid,&#xD;
letting the bar fall, and bursting into a laugh. "Yalh I&#xD;
yahi! ha! And I didn't know him. I'll go right away&#xD;
and butt out dis stupid nigger's brainsI"&#xD;
"And now, Miss Rose," said Carlton Howard, extend-&#xD;
ing his hand, you will not object, perhaps, to my proposed&#xD;
interview with the young gentleman whom you have so&#xD;
bravely defended ?"&#xD;
" Ah, Mr. Howard," said the young girl, extending her&#xD;
&#xD;
A.&#xD;
&#xD;
ae&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7514-00000013"/>&#xD;
26                THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.             2&#xD;
hand, "how shall I ever be forgiven ?  Suppose I had---akw                a    R   -&#xD;
.t.iB t I am known, and Rose-&#xD;
Oh heavens, I sicken at the thought! But why this dis-   "I ,,hall remain&#xD;
guise ?sh!" saidHoard."       I a   f     d    e"I ha ye a little business to transact in this vicinity befor&#xD;
bei                                                       d ",i tr"Hush  !"  said  Howard.  "9I  heard  of  the  danger N in&#xD;
which Mark was placed, and I assumed this disguise, in  I leave the neighborhood, and can protect her too. The&#xD;
order that I might be the better able to aid him, and also  Umon Boys of Western Virginia are not asleep, and ere&#xD;
to protect myself, for you know, Rose, that should I be  many days have passed, the Stars and Stripes shall again&#xD;
discovered, my situation would be far woise than his, for  loat over the Old Dominon, and every rebel be driven&#xD;
I am actually in arms against this cursed rebellion, and if from the soil he pollutes, or forced to recant and once&#xD;
h tdmore renew his violated allegiance! The Union camp is&#xD;
from the first tree. But there is no time to be lst. If  not far off. Before a week, Houghton and his maraud-&#xD;
fM' frtre.Bthrein im oelo  d  ig crew will be in the hands of the brave McClellan and&#xD;
he is concealed here, let inc see him at once. Miles and&#xD;
his band may return at any mornent. I have come to out of the way of doing further harm. Then away at&#xD;
on1ce! Take the, shor test cut towad rnln      n h&#xD;
save him, and by heaven's help I will. I have lost too&#xD;
much time already, bat I did not know how far I could  south branch. When you reach Hunterstown, inquire for&#xD;
one Morris Brice. Give him this letter arid he will do&#xD;
trust Cupid, here !                                    a&#xD;
Why, Lor' bress you, mass'r, I'd die ten times an hour  tat you require. Have you money ?"&#xD;
"None !&#xD;
for Mass'i' Lee, Missee Rose, or any ob de family, and I'd&#xD;
be hUngionc and eek H anshotu bia   houreforndehflag o ere you reach your journey's end," urged Howard, forcing&#xD;
de Union and Hail Columbia."                          a well Iilled buckskin purse into the hands of his friend.&#xD;
"oar slatriogtism anid savoion the youhonore,"bu sAidnd her'e," lie Continued, handing Mark a brace of -pis-&#xD;
Hwmusar, apn t. ee sa o               tols, are a couple of staunch friends, who will not desert&#xD;
Sc           le               arou in your need. Each one has fe mouths to spek for&#xD;
SiHere!" exclaimed Rose, who had raised the trap-door, o, and if you use them, as I know you can, you will find&#xD;
and now advanced from the inner room, -leading Mark thatteIaLbtswlla            ak!&#xD;
tat they can bite as well as bark I'&#xD;
Lee by the hand.,                                               t   k !       .yo&#xD;
"Yes, here," said Mark,.seizing Howard's hand and     i   aktha            inspire me with new courage"&#xD;
shaking it warmly. "Here, to thank you all for your de- said Mark, taking   pistolsandagainsha         his&#xD;
1end's hanid wairmlv. "If I reach h  a&#xD;
votion, and bless you for your kindness. From my hid-                                          p&#xD;
be sure you shall hear a good account of me !"&#xD;
ing-place I have heard all. What are your plans ?"     a         .j i," r-heUiois."Oc&#xD;
" You must leave this neighborhood, and that natant- behevegai, ' replied thelUnoisto "thne underdthi&#xD;
ly,", said Howard.aneeleeed.PQ&#xD;
Oct it with your life! But time presses. -Even now, me&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
i&#xD;
J&#xD;
1&#xD;
1&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7514-00000014"/>&#xD;
28&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
thinks, I hear the sound of a distant bugle. Take off&#xD;
your coat and put on this of mine. 'And here, Cupid,&#xD;
hand Mr. Lee the hat, wig, and spectacles, which nearly&#xD;
cost me my life just now; they will help to save his."&#xD;
Almost as quickly as suggested, the change of apparel&#xD;
was effected, ,and Mark Lee was transformed so complete-&#xD;
ly as to defy recognition.&#xD;
"Gorry, mass'r," exclaimed Cupid, grinning all over&#xD;
his black face with glee, "your own mother would not&#xD;
know you!"&#xD;
"Now away !" urged Howard. "Keep to the-left bank&#xD;
of the rivei'.  When you reach Tiger creek you will&#xD;
come'to a cabin, upon the ioof of which you will see a&#xD;
branch of a pine tree standing. Knock fearlessly at the&#xD;
door. A man will answer you. He will ask you 'How&#xD;
the river runs?' You will answer 'North.' He vill re-&#xD;
spond 'Yorktown.' You may then mention my name.&#xD;
He will ferry you across the river, and put you on the&#xD;
road. When you part with him, tell him that the eagle&#xD;
will leave his nest when the moon is at its full. He will&#xD;
understand you. Do not forget anything I have told&#xD;
you-and away !"&#xD;
"Rose, farewell !" exclaimed Mark, pressing the young&#xD;
girl to 4is heart, and imprinting a kiss upon her paling&#xD;
cheek. "Farewell! We shall meet again, if not upon&#xD;
earth, at least in heaven! Bless you!1"&#xD;
Rose did not respond, but her heaving bosom told how&#xD;
keenly she felt the separation from her lover, and how&#xD;
anxiously her loving heart beat for his safety.&#xD;
"Good-by, Howard! I hope soon to stand shoulder to&#xD;
shoulder with you, doing battle in defence of our dear&#xD;
country! Good-by, Cupid, I know you will be true to&#xD;
the last."&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
With these words Mark cast a last glance of affection&#xD;
upon her lie loved, and stepped towards the door. As his&#xD;
hand touched the latch, the loud blast of a bugle sounded&#xD;
clear and full.&#xD;
All started. Had a thunderbolt fallen in their midst,&#xD;
the consternation depicted in their faces could not have&#xD;
been greater. Cupid rushed instantly and barred the&#xD;
door.&#xD;
Howard was the first to speak.&#xD;
"Too late! too late!1" he exclaimed, in a low voice.&#xD;
"They are even now at the door! Quick, the cave !" and&#xD;
he moved towards the inner apartment, drawing Mark af-&#xD;
ter him.&#xD;
"But Rose," exclaimed Mark, "I cannot leave her thus&#xD;
exposed to-"&#xD;
"Fear not!" said the brave girl. They will scarcely&#xD;
dare to harm me. Secure your own safety. Cupid and&#xD;
I can defend ourselves!"&#xD;
As she spoke, a sound as if the door had been struck&#xD;
with the butt end of a gun, fell upon their ears, and a&#xD;
rough voice exclaimed : "Open quick or we will break&#xD;
it in!"&#xD;
" Quick ! quick !" urged Howard, and almost forcing&#xD;
Mark along, they reached the mouth of the cave.&#xD;
"Down with you," Howard murmured, in a suppressed&#xD;
but firm voice, as the noise outside the door increased in&#xD;
violence. "Down ! It is freedom or nothing !"&#xD;
Thus urged, Mark jumped into the opening below,&#xD;
quickly followed by Howard. Cupid sprung instantly to&#xD;
close the trap, and had barely done so, when the door was&#xD;
violently burst open, and three men strode into the cabin.&#xD;
&#xD;
i       I&#xD;
&#xD;
29-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7514-00000015"/>&#xD;
30&#xD;
&#xD;
\-&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES: OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER III.&#xD;
&#xD;
THE  first who  entered  the  cabin  was  Miles Houghtoi&#xD;
lie was a tall, broad-shouldered man, with a low, si]&#xD;
sister expression, to which a deep nar upon his cheek&#xD;
served to add. his eyes were small. jet black, and pie&#xD;
cing as an eagle's. He had a low forehead, over wh&#xD;
his coarse )lack hair fell in disorder. His beard a&#xD;
moustache were slightly grizzled with straggling gr&#xD;
hairs, and his whole -appearance indicated a manm of e&#xD;
ergy, recklessness, and determination, unchecked and nu&#xD;
guided by any strong moral principle. He was dress&#xD;
in the uniform of a United States officer, and wore rour&#xD;
his waist a belt, in which were inserted a pair of lar&#xD;
navy revolvers, and a dragoon's salbre dangled at h&#xD;
heels.&#xD;
Of the two men who followed him, one was named Jeo&#xD;
Black, a low-sized, rowdyish looking fellow, who acted&#xD;
the Lieutenant of the rebel Captain, though he wore 1&#xD;
uniform, and the other was known as Tom Dill, a wil&#xD;
haram-scarum fellow, fatuous in the neighborhood for h&#xD;
love of whisky, poker, dog fighting, and his general shil&#xD;
lessness. He had a rolicking, good natured expressio&#xD;
generally, save when he attempted to speak, when his fl&#xD;
underwent the most hideous contortions, and every hia&#xD;
in his body sesmned to writhe as if he were tormented&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
31&#xD;
&#xD;
some invisible fiend. He rarely uttered more than half a&#xD;
word at a time, but would return to the effort to express&#xD;
himself, again and again, until he succeeded in making&#xD;
himself understood. He was familiarly spoken of as&#xD;
Stuttering Tom, a soubriquet which he certainly earned.&#xD;
As these three worthies entered the cabin, Houghton&#xD;
called in a rough tone to the mhen outside: " halt where&#xD;
you are! Keep a good lookout, and if anyone attempts&#xD;
to escape, shoot him !"&#xD;
Cupid, the moment the door was broken had seized a&#xD;
large pine stick which stood by the fire-place, and had&#xD;
planted himself in an attitude of defiance in front of the&#xD;
inner room, with the determination of protecting his young&#xD;
mistress and her lover with his life, if necessary. He&#xD;
.f .c               ss.y- .&#xD;
still maintained his position without speaking a word.&#xD;
Hello, you black scoundrel, what the devil are you&#xD;
doing there, and why did you not open the door when I&#xD;
rapped, without putting me to the trouble of breaking it&#xD;
in?  Come away from there, and tell ne where that ren-&#xD;
egade, Mark Lee, is concealed-for you know-or I'll put&#xD;
daylight through that black carcass of yours in a mo-&#xD;
ment!" exclaimed Houghton, drawing a pistol from his&#xD;
belt and leveling it at the negro. " Come away from&#xD;
there, I say, and take down that stick !"&#xD;
"See here, Mister Houghton," replied Cupid, bracing&#xD;
himself still more firmly, and spitting on lis-hands, in or-&#xD;
der to get a firmer grasp on his extemporized weapon,&#xD;
you kin shoot if you've a mind to. 'Taint no more than&#xD;
a nigger could spec from you, any way. But dis here is&#xD;
my shanty, and not a foot furder into it do you git dan&#xD;
you be now, as long as dis 'ere nigger's got one bit o'life&#xD;
in his body. Dar So stand back!"&#xD;
&#xD;
,&#xD;
'=F:&#xD;
s&#xD;
t?&#xD;
;F =&#xD;
.  s&#xD;
#   i&#xD;
ja)k&#xD;
f&#xD;
.i xi&#xD;
,i  .i&#xD;
i   4&#xD;
;&#xD;
'&#xD;
Y&#xD;
e'&#xD;
F  ]I&#xD;
j-, ' -&#xD;
'i&#xD;
i '' #&#xD;
;;i&#xD;
r :.ยง   :&#xD;
! 't   i,&#xD;
f_ ,&#xD;
{;  ,,3 .&#xD;
F  i  't&#xD;
c' '&#xD;
;, F&#xD;
,   ' {-&#xD;
F i;&#xD;
+ ,  :    '&#xD;
i     _j,&#xD;
+  ,&#xD;
1   t&#xD;
#  . a&#xD;
,tt4&#xD;
# ?'&#xD;
,  1 E&#xD;
F   d  :;&#xD;
4,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7514-00000016"/>&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF' 61.        33&#xD;
&#xD;
32              THE REFUGEES ;. OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
"I'll teach you to threaten a white man, you black&#xD;
mangy cur !" growled Houg'hton, lveling his pistol full&#xD;
at poor Cupid, who looked with his one eye upon. the&#xD;
threatening muzzle wildly, but neither trembled nor gave&#xD;
way. "If'you aint away from there in one second, I'll-n"&#xD;
Ere he could finish the sentence, his hand fell, and he&#xD;
staggered back as though he had been shot himself, as&#xD;
Rose, pushing Cupid on one side, stepped from the inner&#xD;
room and stood defiantly before the traitor's face.&#xD;
" Or else you would murder him, Miles loughton.&#xD;
That is what vu mean. Shame on you, shame I" The&#xD;
traitor's cheek turned ashen pale, and his eyes glared like&#xD;
those of a wild beast, as h gazed upon the lovely being&#xD;
before him, and saw her lip curl in indignant scorn as she&#xD;
looked upon liim..&#xD;
" I did not expect to find the proud Rose Morley in,&#xD;
such a place, at such a time," answered Houghton, sul-&#xD;
lenly.&#xD;
"What do you here?   You are trespassing. This is,&#xD;
my father's property. I bid you begone !"&#xD;
"Yes, get out o' dis," exclaimed Cupid. " Get out!&#xD;
We'll hab de law on you suah! Ebery white man's hum&#xD;
is, his castle, and ebery nigger's cabin is his shield and&#xD;
buckler. So git out and git !"&#xD;
"Silence!" roared Jem. " Shut up or I'll split that&#xD;
thick skull o' yourn."&#xD;
"O-o-o---" stammered Tom, "O-o-o---" but he could get&#xD;
no further, so he cut his remarks short by burying the&#xD;
lower part of his face in the tin cup which he had nearly&#xD;
filled with whisky, and thus left the world for ever in ig&#xD;
norance of the thought with which his mind was exer-&#xD;
cised.4&#xD;
&#xD;
"What bringsyou here ?" asked Rose.&#xD;
"Our errand is plain enough," responded Miles Hough-&#xD;
ton, roughly. " We are in search of a renegade and a&#xD;
traitor-a poor puling, cowardly doughface, who Chas de-&#xD;
serted the cause to whicl he naturally owes allegiance,&#xD;
and who is more than suspected of being a spy in the ser-&#xD;
vice of the Yankees. He is not at "The Elms," where&#xD;
we know he has been concealed for some days, and we&#xD;
have good reason to believe that he is concealed some-&#xD;
where hereabout."&#xD;
"When you apply the names renegade and traitor to&#xD;
to Mark Lee,",responded Rose, "your ownJheart, Miles&#xD;
Houghton, tells you that you speak falsely. 'Tis you who&#xD;
are the renegade and traitor, and not he I You have desert-&#xD;
ed the cause of your country in her utmost need. You&#xD;
have turned your back upon her flag, when enemies assail&#xD;
it upon every hand. You have, like a coward, taken ad-&#xD;
vantage of the present time, when treason dares to vaunt&#xD;
itself in mid-day, to pursue and crush a true man, whom,&#xD;
were it not for the number like yourself, who stand at&#xD;
your back, you would not dare to face. 'Tis you who are&#xD;
the traitor ! You the coward! Mark Lee is worth a thou-&#xD;
sand such as you, and when you do meet him on equal&#xD;
terms, you will rue the day !"&#xD;
"Nay," answered the rebel, with a powerful effort,&#xD;
smothering the rage which filled his heart, "I can forgive&#xD;
your words. But listen to me. This man cannot escape&#xD;
us. The whole of our men are on the lookout for him.&#xD;
We are on his track, and we shall surely run him down.&#xD;
If he is taken, I will not answer for the consequences.&#xD;
The men are very bitter against him, and if his life does&#xD;
not pay the forfeit of his unpatriotic course, he will at&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7514-00000017"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
least suffer long and sorely. But if you really feel the&#xD;
interest in him which' you profess, it is in your power to&#xD;
save him."&#xD;
How ?" asked Rose, earnestly.&#xD;
By promising to see him no more, and by giving mn1&#xD;
but one kind look, one smile, one word of hope !"&#xD;
"Such words to Ine!" exclaimed the girl, proudly.&#xD;
You forget yourself! Begone !"&#xD;
a ._.&#xD;
Oh, your pride is not broken yet, I see !" grumbled&#xD;
Miles, " Well, come here, nay, come, I will not harm&#xD;
you. I'll show you something that may humble it, strong&#xD;
and unyielding as it is." And ioughton. stepped towards&#xD;
the door.&#xD;
"I do not fear you, and I will not leave this spot," she&#xD;
answered firmly.&#xD;
"Look out, my pretty bird, beware! You carry it&#xD;
with a high head, but remember that I have but to say&#xD;
the word, and your !iberty, if not . our life, is forfeited as&#xD;
much as his !"1Then turning to the two subordinates who&#xD;
had entered with him, he said quickly: "Lieutenant&#xD;
Black and Sergeant Dill. commence the search, leave no&#xD;
nook or corner unexplored, and if you find the renegade,&#xD;
bring him out dead or alive !"&#xD;
Thus ordered, the two men commenced the search, and&#xD;
entered into the inner room.&#xD;
You a: e welcome to search," Rose said, in a bantering&#xD;
tone. Hie is far away ere this, beyond your reach !"&#xD;
"Perhaps," replied Houghton, "but if not and he is&#xD;
found concealed, I swear whatever his fate may be you&#xD;
shall share it!"&#xD;
." There is no one here, Colonel, said Lieut. Black, now&#xD;
returning to the outer room. " We have. searched every&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
35&#xD;
&#xD;
hole big enough for a mouse to creep through. If he was&#xD;
ever here, he's gone."&#xD;
"We fo-fo fo-fo-fo !" stuttered Bill, " we fo-fo-fo-"&#xD;
"There, postpone that till next week, or else write it,&#xD;
Sergeant," said Houghton, roughly. "I have no time to&#xD;
wait for the birth of that piece of information."&#xD;
The Sergeant had recourse a second time to the whis-&#xD;
ky-jug, and smothered his indignation in its contents.&#xD;
"I swear I will not be thus baffled! You have aided in&#xD;
his escape," almost shouted Houghton, and by heaven&#xD;
you shall pay the penalty !"&#xD;
"What mean you ?" asked Rose, with somewhat of fear&#xD;
in her tones, you surely would not-"&#xD;
"I would do anything," he interrupted, "I would brave&#xD;
hell, your hate, the hate of all mankind, to be revenged&#xD;
on him! Seize that woman, and bear her with us! She&#xD;
is a traitress, and has aided and abetted in the escape of&#xD;
the renegade, Mark Lee !"&#xD;
The man addressed did not stir.&#xD;
"What. am I disobeyed ?"&#xD;
"Col-col-colcol-" began Tom Dill, but Houghton cut&#xD;
him short by commanding silence. "By heaven!I he&#xD;
exclaimed, "you shall not slip from my hands! If you&#xD;
will not be mine you shall not be his !"&#xD;
With these words Houghton advanced towards Rose,&#xD;
who retreated in terror into the inner room, where Miles&#xD;
quickly followed her, and was just about to seize her in&#xD;
his arms, when the floor seemed to open at his feet, and&#xD;
Carlton Howard stood before him!&#xD;
Leveling a pistol at the head of the rebel ruffian, he ex-&#xD;
claimed:&#xD;
"Stir but a hand, and you are a dead man!1&#xD;
&#xD;
rii&#xD;
- ,&#xD;
&#xD;
itll&#xD;
Ji4&#xD;
f 1!"&#xD;
(ii)&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7514-00000018"/>&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
THlE REFUGEES5; Oft,&#xD;
&#xD;
Miles iougjhton staggered back in surprise and won-&#xD;
der, while Rose, springing forward, passed behind Cupid,&#xD;
who had opened the trap, and who stood with the axe&#xD;
raised high above his head, ready to repel any assault up-&#xD;
on his young mistress or himself. She leaped down into&#xD;
the cave and disappeared, instantly followed by Carlton&#xD;
howard, leaving the rebel leader alone with Cupid, and&#xD;
for a moment in a state of complete bewilderment. Quick-&#xD;
ly recovering his presence of -mind, however, he discharg-&#xD;
ed his pistol at Cupid, and without waiting to see the re-&#xD;
suit of his shot, shouted at the top of his voice:&#xD;
Hither, Black ! We shall have them now !"&#xD;
Then giving, orders for the bulk of the men to spread&#xD;
in all directions, in scouting parties, and commanding a&#xD;
few to follow him, he jumped into the cave, with a wild&#xD;
shout and was lost to sight.&#xD;
The cabin was. instantly filled with men. Jein Black&#xD;
was the first to follow his leader, and he was succeeded&#xD;
by Stuttering Tom, but his attempt to follow the example&#xD;
set by his Colonel and the Lieutenant, was not successful,&#xD;
for as he jumped, the skirts of his coat caught in the edge&#xD;
of the opening and held him suspended, so that he could&#xD;
neither get up nor further down, thus effectually blocking&#xD;
up the opening and preventing the others from going in.&#xD;
F-fo-for" he began, "If-fo-fo-for G-gg-g-od's sake,&#xD;
ho-ho-ho-hold me up, or cu-cu cu-cut off my co-co-co-coat&#xD;
tail !"&#xD;
As it took sdme time to get this sentence into anything&#xD;
like intelligible shape, and as, meanwhile, his body went&#xD;
through the most terrible contortions, when, at last, he&#xD;
had succeeded in making the suggestion, the necessity for&#xD;
its execution had passed, for he had fairly wi-ithed himself&#xD;
&#xD;
out of his garment, and slipping from its hold upon him,&#xD;
lie dropped with a dull thud into the cave below.&#xD;
The rest instantly followed, and then Cupid rose un-&#xD;
harmed from the corner where he had fallen at the report&#xD;
of the pistol, and after first shaking himself, and then feel&#xD;
ing himself all over, to make sure he was not hit, he&#xD;
quickly-ran into the front room, and seizing the pine knot,&#xD;
which still blazed on the hearth, he placed it in the mid-&#xD;
die of the floor-then dragging the bed from the other&#xD;
room, he tore open the mattress, and heaped the straw&#xD;
upon the blazing wood, upon which, as soon as he saw it&#xD;
fairly ignited, he quickly piled all the furniture;, then&#xD;
hastily quitting the cabin, and going down to the bed of&#xD;
tle creek, he crept cautiously away.&#xD;
By the time lie had gone a few hundred yards, the light&#xD;
of the burning cabin lit up the scene for some distance&#xD;
around. As the negro saw the effect of his desperate&#xD;
act, he chuckled aloud :&#xD;
"Ki! ki! I reckon dat'll fix you! If you don't find&#xD;
de oder end of de cave, I reckon you'll stay dar for some&#xD;
time, if you isn't sufekated wid de smoke, and find you-&#xD;
sefs done gone altogeder. But good golly, what de deb-&#xD;
bil's dat?" hs exclaimed, as he lqoked up and saw a still&#xD;
brighter light reddening the sky in another direction.&#xD;
Streams of flame and volumes of dark smoke rose be-&#xD;
fore him high in air, and dense showers of sparks were&#xD;
borne far away upon the evening breeze.&#xD;
" Oh Lord o' massy ! Who's been and gone and done&#xD;
dat? it's de Elms! It's de old place! It's de Squire's&#xD;
house on fire! Oh de lord.; de debbil is let loose suah !"&#xD;
It was too true. The homestead of the Moneys, the&#xD;
dear old Elms, was one vast sheet of flame.&#xD;
&#xD;
86&#xD;
&#xD;
37&#xD;
&#xD;
((I&#xD;
Ji,3&#xD;
&#xD;
.; {   t i&#xD;
,.  r ,&#xD;
:,&#xD;
; ;&#xD;
,&#xD;
,  4&#xD;
;,&#xD;
1 s }&#xD;
.&#xD;
7&#xD;
t ; f&#xD;
t4&#xD;
1  f }&#xD;
_&#xD;
ff&#xD;
k&#xD;
&#xD;
t 1&#xD;
S3 '&#xD;
E&#xD;
f&#xD;
1&#xD;
tยฑ&#xD;
i k&#xD;
E, { 1&#xD;
t,' ;t!&#xD;
}E  l! S&#xD;
t  ; L&#xD;
't t&#xD;
U&#xD;
a.&#xD;
kk,&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7514-00000019"/>&#xD;
8&#xD;
&#xD;
THlE MYE UGEES ; OR!&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER IV.&#xD;
MARK LEE, on reaching the cave in company with&#xD;
Carlton Howard, could not, although his life depended&#xD;
upon his escape, make up his mind to flee and leave her&#xD;
he loved in the power of his bitterest enemy. He knew&#xD;
his reckless character, and rightly judged that he would&#xD;
stop at nothing which might tend to serve his purposes,&#xD;
and that Rose, woman as she was, though brave and&#xD;
strong as he knew her to be, would be powerless against&#xD;
the cowardly and base designs of Miles Houghton, and&#xD;
he felt that it would be selfish and unmanly in him to&#xD;
leave her in the power of the bad man who sought his&#xD;
life, and the destruction of her peace. So refusing to lis-&#xD;
ten to the entreaties and prayers of Carlton Howard, he&#xD;
resolved to remain at the mouth of the cave, in order if&#xD;
possible to screen her from insult and from harm, even&#xD;
though his own life, should be sacrificed in the effort.&#xD;
With beating heart and burning brpin, he heard the con-&#xD;
versation which was being carried on in the cabin above,&#xD;
and, but that the door was fast, and would not yield to&#xD;
his strong efforts to force it open, he would have sprung&#xD;
from his concealment, and struck the villain in whose&#xD;
power she was, dead at his feet.. At last the trap moved&#xD;
upon its hinges, and he was about to spring upward, when&#xD;
Carlton Howard seized him by the arm, and without say-&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
39&#xD;
&#xD;
ing a word, pulled him back, and, as we have seen, leaped&#xD;
into the room. In a moment he reappeared, followed by&#xD;
Rose, who, almost fainting, was received in the arms of&#xD;
her lover, who stood below.&#xD;
Come! Not a moment is to be lost," le said, lifting&#xD;
the fiuinting girl from the ground, and bearing her along'.&#xD;
" We must hasten to the mouth of the cave. The distance&#xD;
is not great, and if we are speedy, we may escape them&#xD;
yet!"&#xD;
"Let me lead the way," urged Howard, "I have ex-&#xD;
plored this cave before ; not far from here there is an-&#xD;
other passage, .which leads to the right, and, where we&#xD;
may secure a hiding place until these miscreants have&#xD;
passed, should they be so bold as to follow us."&#xD;
So saying, he pushed by Mark Lee, and led the way.&#xD;
Rose, meanwhile, recovering her strength, insisted upon&#xD;
being allowed to follow unsupported, and placing herself&#xD;
immediately in the rear of Howard, proceeded with them&#xD;
on their dark and uncertain journey. They had gone but a&#xD;
short distance, when it became evident that they were fol&#xD;
lowed. The voice of Miles Houghton could be distinctly&#xD;
heard urging his men to hasten on, and the .fugitives&#xD;
quickened their steps and fled along with as much speed&#xD;
as the rough and narrow passage made possible. But&#xD;
fast as they went, the pursuers were evidently gaining on&#xD;
them. They could hear the sound of their heavy footsteps,&#xD;
and distinguish their loud curses, as they stumbled over&#xD;
the various impediments which obstructed their path.&#xD;
The passage was quite dark, not a gleam of light was to&#xD;
be seen, and with all their exertions their progress was&#xD;
necessarily slow.&#xD;
At last the voice of Houghton sounded but a few steps&#xD;
&#xD;
;&#xD;
3;'#!}&#xD;
.  f;&#xD;
:-'{'&#xD;
'# .&#xD;
:s =&#xD;
.,&#xD;
_&#xD;
 '   i&#xD;
;a 3&#xD;
_&#xD;
$ :&#xD;
;jf  t&#xD;
i{&#xD;
t&#xD;
jt t&#xD;
E;  }&#xD;
.&#xD;
}i&#xD;
_&#xD;
i&#xD;
i _&#xD;
r&#xD;
x&#xD;
s&#xD;
't&#xD;
'j  1&#xD;
'1   +     ;&#xD;
1  f    }&#xD;
3&#xD;
t  f&#xD;
i&#xD;
i&#xD;
=f&#xD;
i&#xD;
i&#xD;
'&#xD;
L" .  f&#xD;
&#xD;
*1&#xD;
&#xD;
:'&#xD;
j&#xD;
i&#xD;
' i&#xD;
t{&#xD;
.&#xD;
;&#xD;
,,&#xD;
,.&#xD;
;,&#xD;
}!&#xD;
' .&#xD;
1 :f i&#xD;
,t&#xD;
ivq }&#xD;
R e:  i&#xD;
:&#xD;
1     ,&#xD;
,r  {i&#xD;
{i'&#xD;
#ยฐ   ,&#xD;
f&#xD;
i&#xD;
,(&#xD;
,,,&#xD;
i&#xD;
i      '&#xD;
tit&#xD;
i&#xD;
4;&#xD;
tx    1&#xD;
,&#xD;
i&#xD;
{&#xD;
t     1&#xD;
i     ]7i&#xD;
t       1&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7514-00000020"/>&#xD;
THE' UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
behind them. Rose's heart beat with fear, and she almost&#xD;
sank to the ground, but she spoke not, and summoning all&#xD;
her energies, exerted herself to the utmost to keep up&#xD;
with Howard, who still led the way.&#xD;
The slight distance which intervened between the pur-&#xD;
suers and the pursued, decreased at every step. It seem-&#xD;
ed impossible that they should escalpe when all of a sud-&#xD;
den she felt herself seized by Howard and borne on one&#xD;
side.&#xD;
"To the right! Quick !" exclaimed Howard, in a whis-&#xD;
per scarcely above his breath. Mark heard it, and turn-&#xD;
ing quickly; to the right, he left the direct course of the&#xD;
fissure, and in a moment all three were standing, with&#xD;
suppressed breath, and palpitating hearts, in a side pas.&#xD;
sage, which led from the main opening,in pitch darkness,&#xD;
but secure for the present, at least, for they had hardly&#xD;
stopped, ere they heard the footsteps and voices of their&#xD;
pursuers, as they passed the spot where they had turned&#xD;
off, and continued on their errand.&#xD;
As their voices died away in the distance, and nothing&#xD;
but a confused rumble indicated their presence in the&#xD;
cave, Mark said in a low tone, "Now is ourKtime! Let&#xD;
us proceed at once to the mouth of the cave ; they will&#xD;
not imagine that they have passed us, and will, of course,&#xD;
proceed directly to the Elms. Come, dear Rose, lean up-&#xD;
on me. There is hope yet !"&#xD;
"You are right," responded Howard, "and the sooner&#xD;
we follow them the better. But see! There is a light in&#xD;
the main passage ! I see the glimmer of it upon a point&#xD;
of rock before us. Hush! Do not stir upon your lives.'&#xD;
I will make a reconnoisance !"&#xD;
So saying, he left them, and cautiously and noiselessly&#xD;
&#xD;
pursuing his way, soon reached the main passage, when&#xD;
peering cautiously around, he discovered a bright light at&#xD;
the upper end of the cave, and could distinctly hear the&#xD;
crackling of flames, and perceive fragments of burning&#xD;
wood fall into the cave from the aperture above.&#xD;
"Haste, haste !" he cried, guessing at the true cause of&#xD;
that which he saw. "Haste! they have fired the cabin,&#xD;
and retreat is impossible. We must gain the outlet or&#xD;
we are lost!"&#xD;
Mark and Rose instn.ntly obeyed the summons, and&#xD;
guided by the light, which now lit up nearly the whole&#xD;
length of the narrow passage, tiy reached the end of the&#xD;
branch in a moment, and the three swiftly fled along, di-&#xD;
recting their footsteps by the red glare of the flames at&#xD;
the upper end.&#xD;
Meeting with no further obstruction, they shortly near-&#xD;
ed the mouth of the cave, when, to their surprise, they&#xD;
saw the glare -of another fire, which threw a lurid light&#xD;
directly in front of tlhemn.&#xD;
"Great heavens !" exclaimed Mark, " they have fired&#xD;
the cave at the other end likewise! Ah, I see their plan ;&#xD;
they have suspected the trick we have played them, and&#xD;
are resolved to keep us here until the morrow, when, the&#xD;
fires having been extinguished, they will resume the&#xD;
search. There is to hope now ! Let us sell our lives a,&#xD;
dearly as we can !&#xD;
"Do not despair !" said Howard, encouragingly, "let&#xD;
us go on as far as we can, at anyrate. Heaven may yet&#xD;
provide some means for our escape. Come on!"&#xD;
" Courage, dear Rose, courage !" said Mark, addressing&#xD;
the almost exhausted girl at his side, "Howard is right!&#xD;
Heaven will not allow so villainous a plot to triumph I"&#xD;
&#xD;
1:jsL&#xD;
&#xD;
I -;z&#xD;
t    a&#xD;
,j&#xD;
+1&#xD;
t        ,y&#xD;
S&#xD;
1        t&#xD;
s&#xD;
1&#xD;
&#xD;
if f ,3 1&#xD;
1&#xD;
&#xD;
40&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
41&#xD;
&#xD;
I i&#xD;
i3&#xD;
i}   f&#xD;
}F&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7514-00000021"/>&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS o '61.           43&#xD;
&#xD;
"Do not fear for me," she replied, in a low voice, and&#xD;
clinging closer to his side. "I am but a woman, and am&#xD;
weak as one, but my soul is strong, and I do not despair..&#xD;
Whate'er your fate may be, I will share it by your side.&#xD;
If they drag you from me, I will die ere I submit to aught&#xD;
to tinge my cheek with shame, or make me less worthy of&#xD;
your love."&#xD;
"Bravely spoken!" said Howard, cheeringly. "But&#xD;
see, we are wrong! The fire is not at the mouth of the&#xD;
cave, it is-"&#xD;
"Alas! it is the Elms," exclaimed Rose, as they stood&#xD;
the next moment at the outlet. "The vile wretches have&#xD;
fired the old homestead. Oh, my father! my poor fa-&#xD;
ther !"&#xD;
As the te'ible truth rushed upon her, the overwhelm-&#xD;
ing anxiety which filled her heart, overcame her, and the&#xD;
unhappy girl fell senseless to the earth.&#xD;
Mark knelt for a moment by her side, and lifting her&#xD;
lovely head upon his knee, imprinted a long, long kiss up-&#xD;
oi her cold lips; then turning to Howard, he exclaimed&#xD;
in a voice choked with emotion : " Heed me no longer;&#xD;
my course is taken. Guard her and protect her as you&#xD;
would your life! My presence will only expose her to&#xD;
more danger." Then, laying the still senseless girl upon&#xD;
the green sod, he rose, and shaking Howard by the hand,&#xD;
drew a pistol from his belt, and before his friend could&#xD;
utter a word, he bounded away.&#xD;
On he sped on the wings of the wind, straight in the&#xD;
direction of the burning house, the .flames from which&#xD;
were rising high up in the heavens, lighting up the land-&#xD;
ecape for miles around, and casting a lurid glow upon&#xD;
every object.&#xD;
&#xD;
As Mark proceeded, he began to hear the shouts of&#xD;
men, and when he had reached within a few hundred&#xD;
yards of the house, he perceived by the light of the flames&#xD;
the troop of horsemen commanded by Houghton, grouped&#xD;
around the burning pile, and heard their shouts of joy, as,&#xD;
one after the other, the rafters yielded to the flames, and&#xD;
fell into the seething cauldron below.&#xD;
"The poor old man '1" he murmured to himself. "The&#xD;
wretches will murder him! Pray heaven I be not too&#xD;
late "&#xD;
A few moments more brought him to the burning house.&#xD;
For a second he paused, not knowing exactly what to do,&#xD;
and during that second he felt his arm grasped as in a&#xD;
vice,  ie turned and saw Cupid, his eyes streaming with&#xD;
tears, and his face wearing an expression of the greatest&#xD;
anxiety.&#xD;
"For God's sake, mass'r, do something quick! Poor&#xD;
old mass'r's in the house. I know he is. I habn't done&#xD;
seen him- anywhere around."&#xD;
" It was a cussed shame not to find out if the old maa&#xD;
was safe. When the row commenced, he fled to the cel-&#xD;
lar, and has not been seen since," Mark heard a man,&#xD;
standing near him, exclaim.&#xD;
"Do you hear dat, mass'r ?  Come on, I know de way,&#xD;
urged Cupid, quietly. " But for de Lord's sake, don't let&#xD;
nobody see you, or you're a goner."&#xD;
Thus advised, Mark, still wearing the spectacles which.&#xD;
he had received from Howard, pulled his slouched hat fur-&#xD;
ther down over his face, and strode rapidly away. Press-&#xD;
ing through the crowd of people, and past the rebel horse-&#xD;
men, who were gathered in knots in every direction, Cu-&#xD;
pid led the way to the rear of the house, which was comn-&#xD;
&#xD;
42             THIS REFUGEES ; OR&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7514-00000022"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; On,&#xD;
&#xD;
pletely deserted, to a low door fitted into the stone foun-&#xD;
lation, against which both Mark and himself threw them-&#xD;
selves at once, but their united strength proved inadequate&#xD;
to burst it open. Finding their efforts useless, Mark's&#xD;
eves lit upon a neighboring wood-pile, and rushing to the&#xD;
spot, he seized a large log, and throwing it upon his shoul.&#xD;
ders, as though it had been a feather, he ran with it to the&#xD;
door of the cellar, bringing the end of the log to bear&#xD;
with all its momentum against it. The experiment was&#xD;
successful. The door flew open, and in a moment both&#xD;
entered the cellar. It was filled with a dense, suffocating&#xD;
smoke, and not an object was discernable. As they were&#xD;
groping about, a low, dull, creaking sound from above fell&#xD;
upon their ears.&#xD;
The roof is falling in," exclaimed Mark. "We are,&#xD;
too late! too late !"&#xD;
"flurry, mass'r. and let's' get out o' dis, de ole man can't&#xD;
be here," urged Cupid.&#xD;
But at this moment Mark's foot caught upon an object&#xD;
on the ground, and stooping, hastily, his hand came in&#xD;
contact with the prostrate form of a man.&#xD;
"Thank God !" he ejaculated. He is yet alive! Help,&#xD;
Cupid, help !"&#xD;
In an instant Cupid was by his side, and together they&#xD;
raised the insensible body of the man, and bore it quick-&#xD;
ly to the open air, and some distance from the house.&#xD;
They had scarcely done so, when a heavy crash resounded&#xD;
through the air, mnyriads of sparks floated upwards, filling&#xD;
the sky with fire, and the late stately old mansion tottered&#xD;
to the earth, a heap of ruins!&#xD;
William Morley, for it was surely he, quickly revived&#xD;
under the influence of the fresh breezes of the night, and&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
raising his aged head, silvered with the frosts of sixty&#xD;
winters, looked wildly about him.&#xD;
He did not recognize Mark in his 'disguise, but turning&#xD;
to him, said in a faint voice:&#xD;
"Whoever you be, receive an old man's thanks! But&#xD;
where is my.daughter? Where is my dear child ?"&#xD;
"Fear not for her," replied Mark. "She is with one&#xD;
who will, I trust, protect her from all harm. Had'I not&#xD;
thought so, I should not now be here."&#xD;
"Ah, that voice!" exclaimed the old man, rising to his&#xD;
knees and gazing upon Mark. " Surely I should know it.&#xD;
Are you not-"&#xD;
"Yes, yes !" answered the young man. " But do not&#xD;
breathe my name! Come, this is no longer any place for&#xD;
you or me. Let us away at once. I will tell you all&#xD;
hereafter."&#xD;
Slowly Morley rose to his feet, and shaking the hand&#xD;
of Cupid in a grateful manner, he followed the faithful&#xD;
black, who led the way towards the barn, which stood&#xD;
but a short distance off, the old man heing supported by&#xD;
the stalwart arm of his preserver.&#xD;
They had pursued their way in silence but a few rods,&#xD;
when a party of men, coining from the front of the house,&#xD;
discovered them. By the light of the blazing ruins, the&#xD;
features of Wn. Morley were easily discernible, and the&#xD;
foremost of the party shouted:&#xD;
"Yore they are! Yere's the old man! Hurrah, we've&#xD;
got the doughface now!&#xD;
Instantly a crowd of men rushed towards them, among&#xD;
them the leader of the band of rebels, Miles Houghton.&#xD;
Flight was useless, and for an instant Mark felt his&#xD;
heart sink within him, but quickly recovering his energy&#xD;
&#xD;
tf     ;&#xD;
if&#xD;
{ 1&#xD;
Y"&#xD;
7  r&#xD;
e'&#xD;
i!&#xD;
t !   c&#xD;
t F   f&#xD;
1   A,&#xD;
4  t  ;&#xD;
.t {&#xD;
f l&#xD;
t&#xD;
2&#xD;
prE&#xD;
fy f&#xD;
I1&#xD;
f {&#xD;
,k a&#xD;
i&#xD;
ff .&#xD;
if, t&#xD;
i&#xD;
Fs !&#xD;
} {  t&#xD;
fl&#xD;
c&#xD;
Y&#xD;
Y&#xD;
&#xD;
TUB tTNIoN Boys or 6L&#xD;
&#xD;
45&#xD;
&#xD;
44&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7514-00000023"/>&#xD;
46&#xD;
&#xD;
TUE' REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
and resolution, he looked 'about him, and discovering'&#xD;
among the promiscuous crowd, who had been attracted to&#xD;
the spot by the conflagration, several whom he knew to be&#xD;
true to the Union cause, he stopped, and drawing his pis-&#xD;
tols, and handing one to William Morley, he shouted:&#xD;
"Stand back! The first man who lays his hand upon&#xD;
these grey hairs, dies! What, are you men, that, not sat-&#xD;
isfied with the crime you have already committed, you&#xD;
should wish to dye your hellish hands in the blood of this&#xD;
poor old man ? if there is a man here who loves his Ta18&#xD;
tive land, who would frown upon rapine, arson, and on&#xD;
murder, I summon him to my side! Union men to the&#xD;
rescue!",&#xD;
By this time, every person, not belonging to the troop&#xD;
of horse, had reached the spot, and as Mark uttered the&#xD;
last words, some dozen men, all armed in various way s&#xD;
sprang to his side.&#xD;
"I know that voice !" shouted Miles loughton. "It'.&#xD;
Mark Lee's, the Abolitionist! Down with him! H&#xD;
there, men ! Mount! Charge! This way ! This way!&#xD;
As he uttered these words, he sprang forward toward&#xD;
Mark, followed by several men. He was met by those&#xD;
who had gone to the rescue of Mark,-'on hearing his p&#xD;
triotic summons, and several more, and a general mel&#xD;
ensued. Several shots were fired, and one or two fell&#xD;
both sides.&#xD;
Meanwhile, Mark was forcibly seized by some one bi&#xD;
hind him and pulled to the rear of the crowd, and&#xD;
hoarse voice whispered in his ear&#xD;
." Go! You'll git chawed .up ef yer don't. You'll fin&#xD;
horses hitched behind the corn-crib; take 'em and&#xD;
away like lightning."&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF' 61.&#xD;
&#xD;
47&#xD;
&#xD;
Mark turned and found himself in the arms of a tall,&#xD;
brawny man, whom lie had never seen before. He was&#xD;
dressed in deer-skin,-and bore a long rifle on his arm.&#xD;
Seeing Mark hesitate, he guessed the cause, and again&#xD;
spoke, in a low voice : " The old mian is there waiting.&#xD;
I gin Cupid the hint. They are off. Foller 'em quick,&#xD;
or you'll be chawed up as clean as a mushrat's tail! I'll&#xD;
kick up a shindig and keep 'em off your trail!"&#xD;
With these words he dashed forward into the front of&#xD;
the fight, and Mark, thus urged, and seeing the body of&#xD;
horse already mounted and dashing at full speed towards&#xD;
the scene of the combat, which was every moment grow-&#xD;
ing fiercer, sprang away, and turning the angle of the&#xD;
barn, which was a few steps off, was lost to sight of his&#xD;
pursuers. Then starting on a run, he reached the crib&#xD;
which stood some twenty yards from the'barn, when he&#xD;
found his strange preserver had spoken truth, for there,&#xD;
ready mounted, were the old man and Cupid.&#xD;
Without exchanging a word, Mark leaped into the sad-&#xD;
die of another horse, and calling out, "Follow  me!"&#xD;
dashed into the neighboring field, which they crossed, and&#xD;
then paused a moment on the edge of the dense woods&#xD;
which skirted it.&#xD;
The short struggle between the small party of Union-&#xD;
ists and Houghton's band, was already over, for lie heard&#xD;
the shouts of the triumphant party, and the voice of&#xD;
Houghton rose clear and distinct above the din, urging&#xD;
his men to the pursuit of the flying Union men.&#xD;
"My time will come !" Mark muttered, as urging his&#xD;
horse forward, he dashed into the wood, followed by Mor-&#xD;
ley and Cupid.&#xD;
&#xD;
ii&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7514-00000024"/>&#xD;
d8&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER V.&#xD;
TAE three fugitives pursued their way through the&#xD;
woods for some distance, in silence. No sounds were.&#xD;
heard save the tramp of their horses, and the distant&#xD;
shouts of the baffled rebels, who had, evidently mistaken&#xD;
the direction they had gone, and were off, on a false scent.&#xD;
At last they reached the Greenbriar river, and Mark Lee,&#xD;
who was in advance of the little party, pulled rein and&#xD;
came to a halt. The others followed his example.&#xD;
Mark was the first to speak. " We must make the best&#xD;
of our way," he said, hurriedly, " to the camp of General&#xD;
McClellan. Once within his lines, we are safe 1"&#xD;
"But Rose! What will become of her ?" asked Wil-&#xD;
liam Morley, with paternal anxiety.&#xD;
"She is under the protection of Carlton Howard," an.&#xD;
swered Mark.&#xD;
"Carlton Howard !" repeated William Morley, in sur-&#xD;
prise.&#xD;
"Yes. But for him she would now be in the power of&#xD;
that scoundrel, Miles Houghton," replied Mark, and then&#xD;
went. on to relate, in as few words as possible, the occur-&#xD;
rences which took place at Cupid's cabin.&#xD;
"But we are losing time," Mark added, as he finished&#xD;
his narration. "Let us on, once more! We must follow&#xD;
the river's course.  Come, let us forward!  We must&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
reach the cabin which Howard spoke of, 'ere morning.&#xD;
Fear not, all will yet be well." " When we arrive there,&#xD;
I trust we shall find Rose and Carlton before us."&#xD;
"Say you so ?" exclaimed Morley. "Then let us lose&#xD;
no time, but onward with all speed I" and thus speaking,&#xD;
lie urged his horse forward, followed by Mark and Cupid.&#xD;
They had proceeded about a quarter of a mile, when.&#xD;
as they passed ,a sharp turn in the road, they saw, not ten&#xD;
steps in advance of them, a group of three men standing&#xD;
directly in. their path. Instantly they drew rein, and&#xD;
came to a sudden halt.&#xD;
"There are but three of them," said Mark, snatching&#xD;
his pistol from his belt, while William Morley followed&#xD;
his example, and drew theweapon which Mark had placed&#xD;
in his hand, after they had been attacked in the vicinity&#xD;
of the Elms. "There are but three, and they are on foot.&#xD;
while we are mounted. Let us make a.dash, charge upon&#xD;
them, and fire as we pass1"&#xD;
He was jest about to rush forward, when one of the&#xD;
three men advanced toward them, shouting:&#xD;
" Hold on, Squire! Hold on, Mark Lee! Don't be&#xD;
skeered ! It's only me!"&#xD;
" Who are you ?" asked Mark, leveling his pistol at the&#xD;
still advancing man. "Stand, or I fire'&#xD;
" Well, if you do, you'll let them cussed, murderin, devils&#xD;
know where you are, and you'll have the hull bilen on 'em&#xD;
down on you in the crack of a rifle. -They aint far off.&#xD;
I seed 'em pass, and they are a laying for you in the&#xD;
woods to the left."&#xD;
"Who are you? How do we know that you. are not&#xD;
of them?" asked Mark, still keeping the man covered&#xD;
with his pistol. "Answer!I&#xD;
&#xD;
49&#xD;
&#xD;
TAE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7514-00000025"/>&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.        51&#xD;
&#xD;
50&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES,; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
"You're a looking for a cabin with a pine branch onto&#xD;
it, aint ye ?" asked the nian.&#xD;
" I am," answered Mark.&#xD;
Well, I'm the proprietor of that ar clearing, and-"&#xD;
"Which way does the river run ?", asked Mark, inter-&#xD;
rupting him, and thinking of Carlton Howard's instruce-&#xD;
tions.&#xD;
"North !" answered the man. "Put down your pistol.&#xD;
Your ears aint very, good, or you'd have know'd mo&#xD;
afore."&#xD;
By this time he had advanced close to the side of Mark,&#xD;
and by the clear light of the moon, the young man recog-&#xD;
nized in the person before him, the stranger who had so&#xD;
providentially appeared in his defence at the Elms, and&#xD;
who had directed them to the horses.&#xD;
" Why, it is-" Mark began, but William Morley inter-&#xD;
rupted him, exclaiming&#xD;
"Hank, the Hunter! I know him! A. better fellow&#xD;
never lived, or a truer man. We may trust him. He is&#xD;
a friend 1"&#xD;
" Thankee, Squire !" said the man.  "I reckon thar&#xD;
aint no treason in me, no how. But it aint no use to&#xD;
stand gabhin' here. Jest as soon as the scrimmage was&#xD;
over, inc and themt two friends o' mine, we put! I know&#xD;
the digging s pooty well, so I tuck a short cut and got here,&#xD;
half an hour before them pisonous seceshers went along.&#xD;
I watched 'em, and arter they had gone on here a piece,&#xD;
they got off their horses and began to hunt for your trail,&#xD;
which, as you hadn't made none, they didn't see. So they&#xD;
led their horses into the brush, and are a waiting till you&#xD;
come along. But we'll fix em !",&#xD;
" What must we do ?" asked William Morley, seeming&#xD;
&#xD;
to place all confidence in the shrewdness and faithfulness&#xD;
of Hank. Then turning to Mark, he said, in a low voice,&#xD;
" We cannot do better than put ourselves under his direc-&#xD;
tions."&#xD;
"Be it so," answered Mark. "But have you seen no-&#xD;
thing of Carlton Howard ?" lie asked of Hank, with some&#xD;
anxiety. " I had hoped he would have been here before us."&#xD;
I reckon he'll take care of himself," answered Hank.&#xD;
"You needn't be oneasy about him. But there'll be more&#xD;
o' them seceshers by here, maybe, afore long, so we paint&#xD;
got no time to lose. Follow me and don't make no noise.&#xD;
But you'd better git off your bosses. So 'light, and I'll&#xD;
lead 'em into the brush. They'll be safe there till morn-&#xD;
ing, and then I'll take care on 'em. Maybe they'll be&#xD;
needed."&#xD;
"Now look a' here," said Hank, on reappearing from&#xD;
the woods, whither he had taken the horses, " we've got&#xD;
to git the best o' them 'ere fellows some way or another,&#xD;
and if we kin git the Squire and Mr. Lee out o' their pi-&#xD;
sen clutches, without a fight, so much the better. Not&#xD;
that I keer a dried apple about 'em, but a bullet shot by a&#xD;
nigger, if it's aimed right, is jest as sure death as though&#xD;
it war fired by the best white man that ever drawed&#xD;
breath, and I don't keer about having the Squire or Mr.&#xD;
Lee sent to kingdomeome by such derned trash as these&#xD;
here pisonous rebels is. 'Sides, Gineral McClellan has&#xD;
got use for 'em. le wants jist sich men, and if I kin&#xD;
help him git 'em, count on me !"&#xD;
ยฐ' You are right, flank," answered Mark. "If we can&#xD;
avoid a conflict with these murdering and incendiary&#xD;
dogs, so much the better just now. Not that I value my&#xD;
life a pin's fee. What I am, and all I have, is my coun-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7514-00000026"/>&#xD;
52&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
try's, and I would preserve it for her sake, in the hope of&#xD;
doing good in her sacred cause."'&#xD;
"Dat's so !" put in Cupid, who, until now, had been a&#xD;
silent listener. " One live man is worf a dozen dead ones,&#xD;
any day. Dat's so!. If dey kills me, I aint no account,.&#xD;
no how. But if dey should kill Mass'r Lee, it 'id be&#xD;
mighty bad, suah !'&#xD;
"We must cross the river. It is no use trying to reach&#xD;
the bridge, because by going in that direction, we shall&#xD;
undoubtedly fall into the ambush whMich has been prepared&#xD;
for us," said William Morley, "and besides, it will not be&#xD;
possible to reach the camp of McClellan by the main&#xD;
road, as we should undoubtedly fall in with Garnett's men&#xD;
if we made the attempt."&#xD;
"There's only one way of circumventing the rebel&#xD;
devils," said Hank. " We must get in their rear! My&#xD;
canoe is tied on this side, not far above here. If we kin&#xD;
only reach it, it will be all right. So let's take to the&#xD;
woods, and if we're right smart, we shall git there afore&#xD;
daylight."&#xD;
"Then lead on!" exclaimed Mark. " Every moment is&#xD;
precious."&#xD;
Without saying another word, Hank struck off into the&#xD;
woods to the left, followed by Mark, William Morley,&#xD;
and Cupid, Hank's two companions bringing up the rear.&#xD;
In a short time they heard the barking of a dog, and the&#xD;
sound of voices in advance of them, and to the i-iglit.&#xD;
"That's them," said Hank, "but we are between them&#xD;
and the river, and if the dog don't scent our trail, we'll&#xD;
fool, 'em yet."&#xD;
They continued their course, cautiously, for awhile and&#xD;
theu, as they put a greater distance between themselves&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '1.        -5&#xD;
and the rebels, more rapidly, until they reached the river,&#xD;
and proceeded onward on- a line parallel with its course.&#xD;
They had reached to within about two hundred yards of&#xD;
the place where Hank's canoe was tied, when they were&#xD;
startled by loud shouts behind them, accompanied by the&#xD;
yelping of a hound.&#xD;
"By the lord, they have 'got on our trail" exclaimed&#xD;
Hank. " That infernal dog has snuffed us out. There is&#xD;
no time to be lost. Follow mse !" and he started off at&#xD;
the top of his speed along the river bank, followed by the&#xD;
:est.&#xD;
The sounds grew nearer, but they had reached, the canoe.&#xD;
"Now pile in," exclaimed Hank, as he drew the heavy&#xD;
dug-out along the bank. "Get in, Squire. Get in, Mark&#xD;
Lee. And here, Cupid, you take the paddle, and paddle&#xD;
straight across. I'll hold these pups at bay. Be quick !"&#xD;
Almost as soon as the words were spoken, his direc-&#xD;
tions were obeyed, and in less time than it takes us to re-&#xD;
late it, the two fugitives and Cupid were seated in the ca-&#xD;
noe, while hank, jumping from the low bank onto a log&#xD;
which lay beside it, caught the bark by one end, and&#xD;
swinging her head round, pushed her, with lightning&#xD;
speed, from the shore, while Cupid plied his paddle with&#xD;
all his skill and strength. By this time, the crackling of&#xD;
the branches under the swift feet of the pursuers, and the&#xD;
sounds of their voices, were distinctly heard.&#xD;
Hank dropped on his knee, while his two companions&#xD;
secreted themselves behind the large sycamores, which&#xD;
grew along the river's bank. They had hardly done this,&#xD;
when a large, rough-looking dog, of the hound species,&#xD;
came up 'yelling, and made directly for flank, who, as he&#xD;
sprang towards him, seized the animal by the throat with&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7514-00000027"/>&#xD;
54&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
one hand, and in the twinkling of an eye, plunged a large&#xD;
hunting knife deep in his breast, from which the blood&#xD;
spouted in a thick, black stream, showing that the steel&#xD;
had penetrated his heart.&#xD;
"So much for that varmint," Hank muttered, between&#xD;
his teeth, as he threw the dying brute into the river, and&#xD;
once more grasped his rifle. " Now for his master 1"&#xD;
As he spoke, two men reached the river bank, not twen-&#xD;
ty yards above him. The foremost one exclaimed:&#xD;
" There they are ! quick ! fireI"&#xD;
Simultaneously both raised their weapons, but, at the&#xD;
same moment, the sharp crack of a rifle was heard, and&#xD;
the foremost fell into the stream, with a bullet through&#xD;
his brain, directed by the unerring aim of Hank, while,&#xD;
almost at the same time, a second shot was heard, and the&#xD;
other rebel uttered a loud yell, and leaping sonie feet into&#xD;
the air, fell forward a corpse.'&#xD;
Now, then, boys, away !" shouted Hank, "before the&#xD;
others can reach here. The Squire will be safe on t'other&#xD;
side, and we out of reach ! See, they are more than half&#xD;
way! Hurrah !" he shouted at the fugitives in the, fast&#xD;
receding canoe. " Hurrah" "&#xD;
Mark waved his hat in response, which, as soon as&#xD;
Hank saw, he darted down the stream at the top of his&#xD;
speed, followed by his companions.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
I-&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF' 6l.&#xD;
CHAPTER VI.&#xD;
&#xD;
IT was three days after the incidents related in the last&#xD;
chapter transpired, that, towards the close of the after-&#xD;
noon, three persons might have been seen to emerge from&#xD;
a deep ravine in the side of a mountain, at the foot of&#xD;
which lay the town of Beverly, Virginia. All three bore&#xD;
about them the evidences of a long and tedious journey,&#xD;
and as they emerged frontn the dense undergrowth of the&#xD;
woods, and stood upon the open. ground, they looked&#xD;
about them with caution, as if in dread of some sudden&#xD;
surprise.&#xD;
Th'le party consisted of Squire Morley, Mark Lee, and&#xD;
our old acquaintance, Cupid, who had thus far succeeded&#xD;
in evading the vigilance of their pursuers, and who had&#xD;
now.arrived within a short distance of the camp of Gen-&#xD;
eral McClellan.&#xD;
"iWell, dar !" exclaimed Cupid, whose courage had not&#xD;
for a moment flagged, but who had proved his devotion&#xD;
and fidelity at every step. "Well, dar! we's out o' de&#xD;
woods at anyrate, and I reckon we's all right! But, lor'&#xD;
o' massy, wot's we going to do for supper? I's orful hun-&#xD;
gry, and I s'pose we all is. Two squirrels and a possum,&#xD;
widout salt, and no dodger, isn't much for tree men in tree&#xD;
days; and, golly! a little old baldface- wouldn't be bad,&#xD;
neider ! Look a' heah, Mass'r Lee, you and de Squirejist&#xD;
&#xD;
4     ,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7514-00000028"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ;.OR, -&#xD;
hole on heah a little while, and let de ole nigger go .d&#xD;
see what's to be picked up. I's as honest a nigger as ever&#xD;
was, but by de lor' Harry, if dark's a chicken anywhar's&#xD;
around heah, he'll have to roost high if I don't get him !"&#xD;
Nono. Cupid," answered Mark, laying his hand upon&#xD;
the darkey's shoulder, as he was about starting on his self.&#xD;
appointed mission, " we will still go on together. We&#xD;
have a friend hereabout who will supply all our wants, if&#xD;
we can only find him.&#xD;
Whom mean you?" asked William Morley.&#xD;
I mean," answered, Mark, producing from the lining&#xD;
of his hat, the letter given to him by Canton Ihoward,&#xD;
" the person to wv hom this letter is directed-one Morni&#xD;
Brice. lie is a friend to the good causle, and will Provet&#xD;
ours, can we but find him. lie lives in yonder town,&#xD;
and-"&#xD;
" Morris Brice !" ejaculated Cupid, interrupting Mark&#xD;
in the midst of his explanations, "I knows hih,; mass'r.&#xD;
What a gall durned chuekle~headed nigger I is !  know&#xD;
him 1 1, been dar ! Why, I didn't know war we was! lI&#xD;
knows now. I been gone to his place many a time, and it&#xD;
aint more'ti a mile from here ! Why, bless yoN, mans'r&#xD;
I kin take you right to the spot. Follow me.tC, Mass'r&#xD;
Lee l" and Cupid took a step or two in advance.&#xD;
"Stop 1" interposed Mark, " we had better keep to the&#xD;
woods, and not attempt to reach the house of Morris&#xD;
Brice before nightfall."&#xD;
" Just as you say, nass'r ; if you kin stand it I kin.&#xD;
and I'm e hungry as a woodchuck in spring ! If' I don't&#xD;
disremember, dark's a bridge across de road, on de toder&#xD;
side o' dis strip o' woods, and we'd better get on toder&#xD;
side o' dat, and den lay low till night. I knows dis heahi&#xD;
&#xD;
THE TNION BOYS Or '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
67&#xD;
&#xD;
country like a book, 'cause, afore Squire Morley owned&#xD;
nQ, I b'longed;to Major Brown, wot lives jist on de norf&#xD;
side ob de hill yonder."&#xD;
" Well, then," said Mark, "lead the way. and be cau-&#xD;
tious. Come, Mr. Morley, let us on1" the young man&#xD;
continued, as he turned- towards the father of Rose, with&#xD;
an effort to appear hopeful. " Courage! Rose is in good&#xD;
hands, and is, I dare say, by thistime within the Union&#xD;
lines, awaiting our arrival."&#xD;
." Heaven grant it may be so," replied William Morley,&#xD;
raising his eyes to heaven, as'they once more entered the&#xD;
woods and pursued their way, led by the faithful Cupid.&#xD;
A fter traversing a distance of about a mile, they cane&#xD;
to the bridge of which the black had spoken. It was a&#xD;
narrow structure, just wide enough for one of the large&#xD;
wagons of the country to cross, and spanned a rapid&#xD;
mountain stream, which at the time we speak of, was&#xD;
about twenty yards in breadth. Beyond the bridge there&#xD;
was a steep hill, on the other side of which lay a little&#xD;
hamlet, consisting of sonie half a dozen houses, and on&#xD;
each side of the stream the ground rose almost precipi-&#xD;
tously to a considerable height, so that in order to gain&#xD;
the hamlet where Brice resided. it was necessary that they&#xD;
should keep the road. According to their plans, how-&#xD;
ever, it became also necessary for them to avoid the pub-&#xD;
lic highway while light lasted, and after they had crossed&#xD;
the bridge, and proceeded up the road some fifty yards,&#xD;
Mark halted.&#xD;
" Don't stop heah, mass'r," said Cupid, with some en-&#xD;
ergy. "About twenty rods furder ahead, dere is a place&#xD;
whar we can hide for a month. Come on, quick as xou&#xD;
can, too, 'cause I tinks I hear hosses not far off.&#xD;
&#xD;
'r i'&#xD;
'  i&#xD;
;   ;&#xD;
,j}  1&#xD;
,&#xD;
",,;1;   !&#xD;
i=;&#xD;
_ ,&#xD;
{  r&#xD;
I I  g&#xD;
'^,  +,&#xD;
i ,.&#xD;
&#xD;
5&#xD;
.#&#xD;
}&#xD;
ly&#xD;
r 3&#xD;
yL&#xD;
#&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
do&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7514-00000029"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
Even as he spoke, the ,clattering of horses' hoofs fell&#xD;
upon their ears, and voices in conversation were distinct,&#xD;
ly audible.&#xD;
"You are right,', exclaimed Mark- "On, quick!&#xD;
Cupid did not wait to be told twice, but dashed ahead&#xD;
as fast as his deformed legs could carry him, closely fol,&#xD;
lowed by the others. When he had advanced a short dis-&#xD;
tance, he turned short to the left, beckoning to Mark and&#xD;
William Morley to follow, and led the way down the&#xD;
steep side of a gorge which set off from the road, and did&#xD;
not halt until he had reached the bottom, which was cov-&#xD;
ered with a dense growth of paw-paw trees, the heavy fo-&#xD;
liage of which would completely conceal any object under&#xD;
them from view.&#xD;
"Now, den, Mass'r Morley and Mass'r Lee, lay low,&#xD;
and de debbil hisself wouldn't find us here."&#xD;
" I hope," said Mark, as he crept into the friendly shade&#xD;
of the bushes, "that this is the last time we shall ever be&#xD;
obliged to hide in secret places like hunted wild beasts."&#xD;
"God speed the hour of our deliverance," ejaculated&#xD;
William Morley, firmly.&#xD;
While they were thus seeking shelter, a party of horse-&#xD;
men emerged from the wood, upon the road they had so&#xD;
recently left, and came to a halt a few yards in advance&#xD;
of the bridge.&#xD;
They were some twenty in number, and were led by&#xD;
Miles Houghton, who, as soon as a halt was called, beck-&#xD;
oned to his side Jem Black and Stuttering Tom, and a&#xD;
consultation took place.&#xD;
"I fear we are too late, curse upon it !" growled Miles,"&#xD;
gritting his teeth and biting his lips alternately. " I know&#xD;
they have taken this direction, and reel sure they are not&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
59&#xD;
&#xD;
far off. It will not do to push forward now except with&#xD;
caution, or we may come upon the cussed Federal pickets,&#xD;
and-"&#xD;
" Well, let us cross the bridge at anyrate," said Jem&#xD;
Black.&#xD;
"No," answered loughton, "I reckon we'd better stay&#xD;
where we are, some of us, at any rate !"&#xD;
"I-I-I-I---" Tom Dill commenced, "I'll-"&#xD;
"I know what you are going to say," said Miles, inter-&#xD;
rupting him. "You will stay here. Is that it?"&#xD;
"T-t-t4-t-exactly !" replied Stuttering Tom, after a per-&#xD;
sistent effort, in the course of which his body  went through&#xD;
as many contortions as a dying eel. and his face assumed&#xD;
every painful expression of which the human countenance&#xD;
is capable.&#xD;
" All right! Remain here, then, while we proceed fur-&#xD;
ther on. If they do not make their appearance by dark,&#xD;
cross the bridge and join us. We shall camp on the other&#xD;
side of Hunterstown. I will leave you three men to&#xD;
keep you company 7"&#xD;
Torn nodded his assent, after a vain effort to express&#xD;
himself in words, and Miles Houghton selected the three&#xD;
who were to remain with him. Then turning to Captain&#xD;
Black, he;said, "There are but three of them-Mark&#xD;
Lee, William Morley, and that blasted imp, Cupid. Rose&#xD;
Morley is not with them, and it is not unlikely that hear-&#xD;
ing the direction her father has taken, she may attempt to&#xD;
follow. There is no way of reaching the Federal camp&#xD;
but by this road. So sloe and they must pass here if they&#xD;
have not done so already. Come, boys, forward! And&#xD;
hark ye, Tom Dill! keep your eye skinned  . If we suc-&#xD;
ceed, you shall swim in whisky, and if we fail, through&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7514-00000030"/>&#xD;
60               THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
your neglect, I'll put a bullet through your carcass!1 Do&#xD;
you understand ?&#xD;
Tom nodded his head, and began a reply in full, but be-&#xD;
fore he could manage to hitter a syllable, Hfotighton and&#xD;
the rest of the party had crossed the I)ridge.&#xD;
Ton gazed after them for a few momeiit, and various&#xD;
expressions-passed over his face as he did so. At first the&#xD;
seemed inclined to follow Miles, and actually took several&#xD;
steps with that intentions. but halting  suddenly, he turned&#xD;
quickly toward the three men, who were to be his con-&#xD;
panions, and with much difficulty said&#xD;
"I say, boys, I reckon we might as well take things&#xD;
easy. So s'pose we jist 'light and hitch our losses! Dis-&#xD;
mount !" he shouted, as he leaped off his horse, a thing&#xD;
which the others had done at least five minutes before,&#xD;
having anticipated that which he was making such despe-&#xD;
rate efforts to speak."&#xD;
They aiit likely to come along in a hurry," he wenit&#xD;
on, as they led their horses slowly in the direction of the&#xD;
woods,1" and I'll bet some of 'em licv gone over already.&#xD;
ut I reckon we'll hev to obey orders, so you jest lay low&#xD;
here, in the woods, and I'll keep a look-out, at the bridge,&#xD;
though I reckon it won't make much difference if we all&#xD;
fall asleepI!"&#xD;
So saying, Tom hitched his horse to a tree near the&#xD;
edge of the wood bordering on the road, and after seeing&#xD;
that his companions did the same, he took his ,'canteen&#xD;
from his side, and raising it to his lips, winked, and put-&#xD;
ting the mouth of the vessel to his lips, elevated the bot-&#xD;
tom in the air, keeping it in that position foi' several sec-&#xD;
onds, a low, gurgling sound, and the quick risi ngand'fall-&#xD;
ing of that part Qf the human anatomy knowi\ as the&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
1&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
"Adam's apple," giving ocular and audible demonstration&#xD;
that the contents of the canteen were rapidly finding an&#xD;
outlet. After he had taken a long draught, he withdrew&#xD;
the vessel from his lips, and wiping the mouth of it with&#xD;
the back of his hand, uttered the word " Whisky !" as if&#xD;
it had been shot out of his mouth, and handed it to the&#xD;
irmen, who successively went through the same operation,&#xD;
on a limited scale, for, as soon as Tom thought that one&#xD;
hai taken his full share, he cut him short by snatching the&#xD;
canteen from his hands, and handing it to the next, until&#xD;
all had drank as much as he thought the circumstances of&#xD;
the case required.&#xD;
This ceremony over, Torn returned the canteen to its&#xD;
place at his side, and walked towards the bridge, stop-&#xD;
ping within about ten feet of its nearest end.&#xD;
Looking around him, lie espied a rock a short distance&#xD;
off, which he went towards, pondering on his way, and&#xD;
finally took his seat upon it.&#xD;
 This here is a nice kind o' business !" he muttered to&#xD;
himself, without the slightest hesitation observable in his&#xD;
speechi, for the most inveterate -stutterers, strange as it&#xD;
may seem, have no difficulty in uttering their thoughts&#xD;
aloud, when there is no one to look at or listen to them.&#xD;
" This is a nice kind o' bisness for a man to be in. Run-&#xD;
nin down white men, jest as if they was runaway niggers!&#xD;
Dod rot it, Mark Lee never did me no harm. Didn't he&#xD;
git nc clear that time I was afore the Court for licking&#xD;
Bill Miller, 'cause he stole my shot-pouch when I got&#xD;
drunk at Phil Logan's doggery, and put axle gcease in my&#xD;
har?  I don't b'lievc he's ary Abolitionist. He didn't&#xD;
vote for Abe Linc'n, sure! Besides, what in thuhder do I&#xD;
keer abdat seceshin. 'Taint a going to do~ me no good,&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
'e:&#xD;
&#xD;
THE.tUNION BOYS OF' 61.&#xD;
&#xD;
f!&#xD;
&#xD;
61&#xD;
&#xD;
;&#xD;
,,&#xD;
[E&#xD;
t&#xD;
3&#xD;
iM&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7514-00000031"/>&#xD;
62               THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
I was jest as well off afore seceshin, as I reckon I shall be&#xD;
arter it. Then there's the old Squire. A better man&#xD;
never gin a fellow a drink, when he was dry, and his&#xD;
latch-string was always open to me. What on airth do I&#xD;
want to interfere with hiiii for, like a mean, dogon, ornery&#xD;
cuss? It aint a goin' to do me no good, a doin' dirty&#xD;
work tor Miles Houghton! What does he care for me?&#xD;
He'll put a bullet through my carcass, will he? Well,&#xD;
maybe he will, but if he does, I'm domed.&#xD;
With this'ejaculation he rose to his feet, and poising his&#xD;
short carbine over his shoulder, he took another pull at&#xD;
his canteen, and then cutting an enormous slice of tobacco&#xD;
from a plug of that weed, which lie took from his pocket,&#xD;
put it in his mouth and chewed it savagely, walking up&#xD;
and down, meanwhile, in a state of great mental agitation.&#xD;
He continued this for some minutes. Then turning a&#xD;
quick and inquiring glance towards the spot where he had&#xD;
left the three men, he exclaimed : "I'll do it! Dogon if&#xD;
I don't! Hurrah for the Union, and Secesh go to thun-&#xD;
der ! Here goes for Gen'l McClellan and the ole flag !"&#xD;
With these words lie started across the bridge, and in a&#xD;
few minutes disappeared in the distance.&#xD;
By this time the sun was near its setting, and the shad-&#xD;
ows thrown by the tall trees by the side of the road, ex-&#xD;
tended themselves far away into the forrest. All was si-&#xD;
lent as the grave. No sound was heard save the soft,&#xD;
murmurs of the evening breeze, or the brawling of the&#xD;
stream as it went tearing over the rocks, through its nar-&#xD;
row channel.&#xD;
Suddenly, however, the men who had- been left in the&#xD;
woods by Tom Dill, and who were reclining at full length&#xD;
upon the thick moss which covered the base of the enor-&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
63&#xD;
&#xD;
mous trees which grew by the side of the wood, were&#xD;
aroused from their lethargy by the sound of voices, and&#xD;
rising quickly, cast their eyes up the road in the direc-&#xD;
tion from which the sounds proceeded.&#xD;
After waiting a few morhents, two persons came into&#xD;
view, riding side by side, and engaged in conversation.&#xD;
The one who rode upon the left was a man in the full&#xD;
flush of early manhood. He was dressed plainly, but a&#xD;
brace of pistols bristled at his waist, and over his shoul-&#xD;
der he carried a long rifle. On his right rode a fair&#xD;
young girl, whose lovely 'features were marked'-by' a shade&#xD;
of deep anxiety, and whose beautiful eyes were red as if&#xD;
with recent weeping. Their horses moved slowly, as if&#xD;
they had been over-ridden, and the general appearance of&#xD;
the travelers indicated a long and painful journey.&#xD;
'Hush !" exclaimed one of Houghton's men, in a low&#xD;
voice. "That's them!"&#xD;
"Them? Who ?" asked one of his companions.&#xD;
"Why, Squire Morley's daughter and Carl ton Hotwrd.&#xD;
I wonder where on earth Tom Dill has gone? 'I saw h m&#xD;
go on t'other side of the bridge. Let's lay low a niy e,&#xD;
any way, until they get past."&#xD;
By this time the two persons had ridden to within a&#xD;
short distance of where the men lay concealed, so that&#xD;
their conversation could be distinctly heard.&#xD;
" We are nearly at our journey's end, for to day, at any-&#xD;
rate," said Carlton Howard to Rose, for the man had&#xD;
been right in his declaration of their identity. " We&#xD;
have scarcely a mile to go. Summon all your energies,&#xD;
then, Miss Morley, and I trust, ere morning, to be able&#xD;
to restore you to those you love."&#xD;
" Alas 1" replied the young girl, "I fear I have miscat&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
i&#xD;
3&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
f    {  A&#xD;
S    $&#xD;
f  '&#xD;
tjRR   4&#xD;
j       r&#xD;
}'&#xD;
j      d&#xD;
L&#xD;
S&#xD;
.   ,&#xD;
i&#xD;
.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7514-00000032"/>&#xD;
64               THE .REFUGEES  OR,&#xD;
culated my power. I have scarcely strength to retain my&#xD;
place upon this poor jae&#xD;
and the excitement of the past few days, added to the hor.&#xD;
rible uncertainty I feel as regardS my father, and-"&#xD;
I can well understand all you feel," interrupted Carl-&#xD;
ton Howard," and wonder that you have borne up against&#xD;
such an accumulation of misfortunes in the manner you&#xD;
have. But one effort more, and soon, I trust, all will be&#xD;
well. Come-courage! courage ! we have but to pass&#xD;
yonder hill.&#xD;
By the time the last words were uttered, Carlton and&#xD;
his fair charge had passed out of hearing, whereupon the&#xD;
man who had first spoken, rose, and going to his horse,&#xD;
mounted with all speed. The other two followed his ex-&#xD;
ample.&#xD;
We must head them off!" he exclaimed, before they&#xD;
can cross the bridge. But don't fire, unless he is spunky&#xD;
and won't gin in. Come! "&#xD;
Instantly the speaker led the way, in a diagonal direc-&#xD;
tion towards the bridge, which Rose and her protector&#xD;
were slowly approaching, with the view of intercepting&#xD;
them before they reached it, but they had proceeded but a&#xD;
short distance, when the quick ear of howard detected&#xD;
the sound of their horses' feet, and reining his own horse&#xD;
suddenly, lie caught at the same time the bridle of the an-&#xD;
imal ridden by Rose. ,&#xD;
Thlis did not escape the observation of Iloughton's men',&#xD;
and the foremost one now seeing the impossibility of' get-&#xD;
ting any closer without being discovered, put spurs to his&#xD;
horse and dashed at once towards the road, followed by&#xD;
his companions, and in a moment the three were dashing&#xD;
up the highway, in full view of Howard and his charge.&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF 'Ol.            65&#xD;
"By heaven !" he exclaimed, "they are a part of Hough.&#xD;
ton's men, and there are three of them! What's to be&#xD;
done ?"&#xD;
He did not hesitate long, but at once urged on his horse&#xD;
and that of Rose; but the jaded beasts could not be in-&#xD;
duced to move beyond a walk. Flight was therefore use-&#xD;
less, and by this time the leading one of the three men&#xD;
was within a few yards of him.&#xD;
" Halt !" cried the man, riding up. "Halt and give an&#xD;
account of yourselves."&#xD;
Quick as thought, Mark drew a pistol from his belt,&#xD;
and leveling it quickly at the man, fired. With a loud&#xD;
exclamation of pain, the man instantly fell back in his&#xD;
saddle, bathed in blood, for the fatal bullet had pierced&#xD;
his body, while Mark, pointing his long rifle at the others'&#xD;
who were approaching, cried out:- "Keep back, you&#xD;
murdering hounds! Keep back! Halt, I say! Move&#xD;
one step further and I fire!"&#xD;
The sight.of their companion weltering in his bloods&#xD;
and the determined air of Carlton Howard, had the de&#xD;
sired effect upon the two men, for they both reined up&#xD;
their horses and stood motionless in ,the road, not more&#xD;
than ten yards off.&#xD;
"If I can but gain five minutes time," said Howard to&#xD;
the almost fainting girl, "Hank and his party will be&#xD;
here. So for heaven's sake push on! I will defend their&#xD;
passage of the bridge with my life. Fly and save your-&#xD;
self. I believe the villains are unarmed, save the sabres&#xD;
which they carry, and I am a match for a dozen such.&#xD;
Fly and stop at the second house on the right, after you&#xD;
have passed the other bridge, not a mile from here. There&#xD;
you are safe, and will, I hope, find your father and Mark&#xD;
Lee! By God's help I'll join you soon. Now go !"&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7514-00000033"/>&#xD;
66&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
Thus urged, the young girl once more turned her horse's&#xD;
head up the road, and exclaiming, in a voice overflowing&#xD;
with emotion, "' Heaven preserve you, Mr. Howard !" she&#xD;
urged her horse forward, this time with more success, and&#xD;
in a short time had crossed the bridge, and commenced&#xD;
the ascent of the hill. She had not proceeded far, how-&#xD;
ever, before her progress was arrested by the appearance&#xD;
of an armed man, who dashed suddenly out of the woods&#xD;
to the left, and standing directly in the road, made signs&#xD;
for her to halt. She obeyed instantly, trembling from&#xD;
head to foot. -The man came towards her at once, his&#xD;
face distorted to a fearful degree, while lie uttered a series&#xD;
of unintelligible sounds.&#xD;
Her nervousness, the excitement she had already under-&#xD;
gone, her sense of danger, the bloody sight she had just,&#xD;
witnessed, and the horrible contortions of the man's face,&#xD;
all tended to destroy her presence of mind, and uttering&#xD;
a shrill, piercing scream, the reins dropped from her&#xD;
hands, and crying, ,"Help! Mark! Mark!" in a loud&#xD;
voice, she fell back fainting.&#xD;
"Blast it, she's swounded !" exclaimed Tom Dill, for it&#xD;
was he, and now that there was no one to listen to him,&#xD;
he found no difficulty in speaking. " What did she want&#xD;
to do that for?  I warn't agoin to hurt her."  But seeing&#xD;
that she was quite insensible, and was about falling from&#xD;
her horse, Stuttering Tom gently lifted her to the ground,&#xD;
and carried her to the road side, where he at once com-&#xD;
menced some rude attempts at restoring her to conscious-&#xD;
ness.&#xD;
It was not yet quite dark, and in. the dusk of the even-&#xD;
ing Carlton Howard had been enabled to, observe all that,&#xD;
took place. He still held the two men at bay, and the&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
67&#xD;
&#xD;
horse ridden by the man who had fallen, being freed from&#xD;
his rider, had approached to within a few feet of where&#xD;
howard stood. His resolution was taken in a moment.&#xD;
Quick as thought he leaped from the back of the animal&#xD;
he had been seated upon, and seizing the rebel's horse by&#xD;
the bridle, vaulted upon his back, and dashed off, at full&#xD;
speed, across the bridge, to the rescue of Rose, supposing,&#xD;
of course, that she had fallen into the hands of her en-&#xD;
eny. 'He had no sooner done thus, ere the two horsemen,&#xD;
taking heart of grace at his disappearance, followed in&#xD;
pursuit.&#xD;
As Stuttering Tom heard the clatter of the horse's&#xD;
hoofs, he looked up, and seeing Howard approaching, and&#xD;
the other two pursuing, he left his charge and fled precip-&#xD;
itately into the woods, and again took a course towards&#xD;
the bridge, with the intention of intercepting his former&#xD;
companions. This lie succeeded in doing by running into&#xD;
the middle of the road, and by signs ordering them to&#xD;
halt, which they did, and a conversation ensued between&#xD;
them, in the course of which he learned the fate of the&#xD;
man who had been foremost in the pursuit of Howard.&#xD;
Meanwhile Howard reached the side of Rose Morley,&#xD;
and. was about dismounting from his horse, when he was&#xD;
surprised by the sudden appearance of Mark Lee, from&#xD;
the woods on the left, followed by Cupid and William&#xD;
Morley.&#xD;
"That voice! those cries !" exclaimed Mark, in great&#xD;
excitement.  "Surely my ears did not deceive me! I&#xD;
heard my name called, and cries for help by one-ah !" he&#xD;
exclaimed, for the first time catching sight of Howard,&#xD;
but not recognizing him, "-this time we meet man to man,"&#xD;
and drawing his pistol, he rushed towards him.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7514-00000034"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ; OI1,&#xD;
&#xD;
"HoldI".do you not know me?" exclaimed Howard,&#xD;
hastily jumping from his horse and raising his hand  "It&#xD;
is I, Carlton Howard! Put up your weapon, man, and&#xD;
hasten to Rose, who has fainted !"&#xD;
"6 Great heaven!" exclaimed Mark. seeing the senseless&#xD;
form of poor Rose, and rushing to her side. " What does&#xD;
this mean? and why did Rose utter those cries ?"&#xD;
"I will explain some other time," replied Howard.&#xD;
Just now we have little time for talking. See to the girl&#xD;
while I look after these scoundrels. Follow me, Cupid.&#xD;
Quick !" exclaimed Carlton Howard, as he once more&#xD;
mounted his horse and dashed down the road.&#xD;
&#xD;
68&#xD;
&#xD;
,&#xD;
P&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION Boys OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER VII.&#xD;
NIGHT had now fallen, but the moon, which was about&#xD;
half full, shed her brilliant light upon the scene, and by her&#xD;
beams Howard saw the three men standing in the middle&#xD;
of the road, some distance front the bridge. As he rode&#xD;
rapidly forward, his rifle poised upon his arm, ready for&#xD;
instant use, he was somewhat surprised to see Stuttering&#xD;
Tomt approach him, making signs of a pacific character,&#xD;
but suspecting it to be a ruse, he drew up his rifle and:&#xD;
brought it t?,,bear upon him. At this, Tom threw up&#xD;
both hands, and then stopped and laid his short carbine&#xD;
upon the ground, in token of submission, whereupon&#xD;
Howard again rested his rifle across his saddle-bow, and&#xD;
riding up to him, demanded to know what he meant.&#xD;
Ton's body instantly began to go through a thousand&#xD;
contortions, but he managed to stammer out, "A-all&#xD;
right, M-m-ister toward. I have concluded Secesh won't&#xD;
pay and I've joined your side. I was running avay, when&#xD;
I diskivered Miss Morley going over the hill, and I was&#xD;
afeared she would meet the Capt'n, who is coming this&#xD;
'ere way, and 1 stopped her to tell her she'd be tuck, sure,&#xD;
ef she kep on, when she up and f-f-fainted. Jist as I was&#xD;
agoin to help her, I saw you a coining, and as I know'd&#xD;
you'd shoot me afore I could git out a word, I run."&#xD;
&#xD;
69&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7514-00000035"/>&#xD;
70&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
All this was said in a very low tone, and with great&#xD;
difficulty.&#xD;
"How do I know you are not lying ?" asked Howard,&#xD;
suspiciously, and putting his hand upon one of the pistols&#xD;
which he carried at his waist. "This may be but an ex-&#xD;
cuse to detain me here, until the rest of your murdering&#xD;
band come up."&#xD;
By this time Cupid had reached the side of Howard,&#xD;
and stood, pistol in hand, ready to go in on the slightest.&#xD;
signal from the Unionist.&#xD;
"Don't talk so loud, stammered Torn. "Them 'ere fel-&#xD;
lers will hear, and though they're the biggest cowalds I&#xD;
ever see, it's just as well to keep 'em in the dark. I'll&#xD;
tell you how you kin find out whether I'm true grit dir&#xD;
not!"&#xD;
"How?" asked Howard.&#xD;
" Why, jist make b'lieve you've gin in. You kin keep&#xD;
your rifle, and go down to whar they be, and help me tie&#xD;
'em up to a tree in the woods yonder. The blamed mean&#xD;
cusses aint worth killin', no how, and I kinder don't like&#xD;
to put a bullet through 'em in cold blood, but if we don't&#xD;
do something, they'll dig off and have the Capt'n after&#xD;
you in a twinkling."&#xD;
"Do you mean what you say ?" asked Howard, not yet&#xD;
convinced of the sincerity of the new convert.&#xD;
"It's as true as heaven !" answered Tom, as earnestly&#xD;
as his impediment would permit him to speak. "I've&#xD;
been a mean, ornery cuss, I know, I've drank a heap o'&#xD;
whisky, and bin in a heap o' fights, but Tom Dill won't&#xD;
lie, nor steal. I'm white, I am, and if you'll help me, we&#xD;
kin fix them 'ere fellows in two minutes."&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
71&#xD;
&#xD;
"I'll trust you, come on !" said Howard. "How shall&#xD;
it be done?"&#xD;
"Just you and Cupid follow me as if you'd gin up, and&#xD;
wanted to settle terms. That'll put 'em off their guard,&#xD;
and when we getalongside on 'em, you jist take one, and&#xD;
leave tother to nie.&#xD;
" Go on, then," said Howard, "but mind, on the first&#xD;
suspicion that enters my head, that you are playing false,&#xD;
I'll put the contents of this rifle into your brain."&#xD;
"All right!" responded Tom, and picking up his car-&#xD;
bine, he moved slowly forward towards the men. The&#xD;
moment they reached the two horsemen, Tom signed to&#xD;
Howard to pass quietly behind them, and then gave the&#xD;
order for them to dismount.&#xD;
" What for ?" asked one of them.&#xD;
"None' o' your business. Git off o' them ar losses !"&#xD;
replied Tom, in his impetuosity forgetting to stammer.&#xD;
"That's my order, so git off !&#xD;
The men did not move, but murmured something in a&#xD;
low voice, upon which, without uttering a word, Tom&#xD;
dropped his carbine, and motioning Cupid to seize the&#xD;
horse by the bridle, lie sprang upon the neck of the beast,&#xD;
with the agility of a cat, and seizing the man by the&#xD;
throat with one hand, while he wrested the sword from his&#xD;
grasp with the other, threw him violently to the ground.&#xD;
At the same moment, Howard, drawing a pistol, and put-&#xD;
ting it to the head of the other trooper, said in a firm&#xD;
voice, "Take your choice, throw down your sword and&#xD;
yield yourself a prisoner, or die where you sit. You&#xD;
have not more than two seconds to make up your mind !"&#xD;
The man turned his hedd quickly, and brought his ear&#xD;
in contact with the muzzle of the pistol; then turning in&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7514-00000036"/>&#xD;
the other direction, and seeing the fate of his companion&#xD;
who lay stunned upon the earth, he threw down his&#xD;
sword, and turning to Howard, exclaimed:&#xD;
"Don't shoot! I gin in."&#xD;
"A precious pair !" muttered Howard, contemptuously.&#xD;
Then in a firm tone he added : "Dismount, you cowardly&#xD;
ruffian!" dismount at once!"&#xD;
The man obeyed, and in a few moments the arms of&#xD;
both the men were firmly pinioned behind them, and they&#xD;
were led by Tom and Howard, into the woods, Cupid re-&#xD;
inaining behind to take care of the horses.&#xD;
After binding the two specimens of Virginia chivalry&#xD;
to a tree, and securely gagging them, Howard and Tom&#xD;
returned to the road.&#xD;
"Well, I recon you believe I'm sound now. don't you ?"&#xD;
asked Tom, after going through the customary gyrations&#xD;
of body, and contortions of facial muscles, "I told you&#xD;
Tom Dill wouldn't lie !"&#xD;
"You are an honest fellow !" exclaimed Howard, giv-&#xD;
ing him his hand, "and well out of such, bad company.&#xD;
But you mentioned something just now about the return&#xD;
of the Captain. Do you mean Houghton ?"&#xD;
"He went by here not more'n an hour ago," said Cupid.&#xD;
"I seed him from de side of de road, whar I was a look.&#xD;
ing out."&#xD;
" He reckoned you'd gone ahead, or he allowed ef you&#xD;
hadn't, Mister Lee had," stuttered Tom, "and he left me&#xD;
at the otherside of the bridge, with them ar fellers, to&#xD;
keep a lookout for you and the Squire's daarter. He'll&#xD;
be back afore long, I reckon. So we'd better get out of&#xD;
the way, without you think it's worth while to hold on&#xD;
herse and gin him a brtish.. He threatened to put a bullet&#xD;
&#xD;
72&#xD;
&#xD;
THE R " tJGEES -; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
OTHE UNION BOYS OF '61.&#xD;
&#xD;
through my head this afternoon, and I wouldn't mind get-&#xD;
ting first shot !"&#xD;
" How many men has he with him ?" asked Howard.&#xD;
"Well, nigh on to twenty, I reckon."&#xD;
"Armed ?"&#xD;
" Right smart on 'em !"&#xD;
"With rifles ?"&#xD;
"No, right smart o' swords and shot-guns-sorne car-&#xD;
bines.'&#xD;
"Did he promise to return?''&#xD;
" Wal, no, he allowed he'd camflp other side o' Bar Run,&#xD;
beyond Iluntersville, but the shot you fired. and my not&#xD;
getting back, may make him think;sornethin's going on."&#xD;
Howard paused a nioment in reflection, and then mut-&#xD;
tered to himself, " Where can flank linger? He should&#xD;
have been here before this."  Then turning to Tom Dill,&#xD;
he said, "Is there any way by which we can pass round&#xD;
their camp ?"&#xD;
"I reckon I know a trail through the woods here,&#xD;
which leads to Carrick's Ford ; by taking that, we can&#xD;
cut over and come out on the Beverly Road, if we don't&#xD;
meet with none o' the pickets."&#xD;
We will run the risk of that. For various reasons,"&#xD;
Howard continued, "I would. rather not risk an encounter&#xD;
with the scoundrels to-night. So let us take these horses,&#xD;
join our friends, and make for the ford with all speed.&#xD;
"My horse is tother side o' the bridge," said Tom," I&#xD;
reckon I'd better git him, and thar's your hoss down tha'&#xD;
in the holler. Horseflesh aint to be throw'd away these&#xD;
times."&#xD;
"You.are right," answered Howard. " I will lead these&#xD;
horses up the road. Cupid can go and secure muy horse&#xD;
&#xD;
it&#xD;
i&#xD;
1&#xD;
t&#xD;
;}&#xD;
&#xD;
73,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7514-00000037"/>&#xD;
r&#xD;
i&#xD;
!j.&#xD;
t,&#xD;
i&#xD;
;i&#xD;
z&#xD;
t&#xD;
It&#xD;
k !i&#xD;
t!,&#xD;
ta{&#xD;
it&#xD;
i y(}i&#xD;
,0 ,&#xD;
i&#xD;
,&#xD;
c F&#xD;
f&#xD;
{1!&#xD;
1.&#xD;
,&#xD;
.&#xD;
,&#xD;
&#xD;
while you regain your own- Hasten, I will await you&#xD;
return above." With this, Howard took the reins from&#xD;
Cupid, and leading the horses, st rted to rejoin Mark and&#xD;
the others whom he had left some Xninutes since.&#xD;
He found Rose entirely restored to consciousness, an&#xD;
ledning' her aching head upon the shoulder of her father&#xD;
who sat by her side, pouring words of comfort into he&#xD;
ear, and uttering thanks to heaven for her restoration t&#xD;
him, while Mary stood b)y, her hand clasped in his, an(&#xD;
his face expressing every mark of joy at finding the ob&#xD;
ject of his love once more.&#xD;
As soon as Mark became aware of the presence o&#xD;
Howard, he gently released the loving hand he had held&#xD;
andproffering his own to Howard, said, with much feel&#xD;
ing, "I can never repay the debt I owe you. Be assure&#xD;
that gratitude and devotion deeper than ever man felt&#xD;
will dwell in my heart for ever !"&#xD;
" He deserves it all," said Rose, partly rising, and als&#xD;
extending her hand to the Unionist. " He has been&#xD;
friend, protector, comforter, and brother to me, dea&#xD;
1ark 1".&#xD;
"An old man's blessing be upon you, for being the in&#xD;
strunient in the hands of heaven, in the restoration of m3&#xD;
child to me!" said William Morley, rising and placing hit&#xD;
hand on Howard's shoulder.&#xD;
"I have done no more," said Howard, modestly, "thai&#xD;
any man would have done under tihe same circumstances&#xD;
The pleasure I feel in seeing you so happy, amply repay&#xD;
me for all. .But," lie continued, " we must remain here n(&#xD;
longer. loughton and his band may surprise us at an3&#xD;
moment, and, weak as we are, it would scarce be pruden&#xD;
to risk' a meeting with the traitorous scoundreL' It wil&#xD;
&#xD;
9' 4&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
74&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.             75&#xD;
be useless now to attempt to reach the house of Brice, and&#xD;
as we have a new recruit in the person of a deserter from&#xD;
Houghton's troop, who knows a by-road to Carrick's Ford,&#xD;
we had better mount at once and start. The distance is&#xD;
not great, and if we usedispatch, we may reach thd Fed-&#xD;
eral lines ere sunrise."&#xD;
r     "I fear that Rose-" Mark began.&#xD;
"Fear not for me. I am quite strong again," inter-&#xD;
rupted the fair girl, rising, and endeavoring to throw&#xD;
off the air of fatigue, which was too plainly visible.&#xD;
"I will not be a burden or a hindrance to you. I am&#xD;
quite refreshed, and shall be able to keep up with the best&#xD;
of you."&#xD;
"Then let us mount at once," said Mark, and to-morrow&#xD;
a long rest will compensate for all the dangers you have&#xD;
undergone, for all the fatigues you have endured."&#xD;
By this time Torn and Cupid had reached the party,&#xD;
o- and after assisting Rose to mount, Mark was about to be-&#xD;
a.stride one of the horses of the captured troopers, the&#xD;
r   other having been already appropriated by William Mor-&#xD;
ley, when Cupid, who was not provided for, and who had&#xD;
gone higher up the hill, came rushing towards them, ex-&#xD;
y   claiming:&#xD;
''"Hi, hi! Mass'r Lee! Here dey comes! Here comes&#xD;
de rebels. Dey's a running like de very debbil, and I&#xD;
n   reckon dat he's after 'em; if it aint him, it must be Gen'1&#xD;
McClellan !"&#xD;
SAt the same moment, the sound of horses dashing over&#xD;
o-the bridge, came from the right, and Carlton Howar d,&#xD;
turning quickly, perceived, by the light of the moon, some&#xD;
ttwenty horsemen approaching at a rapid gallop.&#xD;
l  " Thankheaven, it is Hank at last !"' heecliedn&#xD;
&#xD;
'I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7514-00000038"/>&#xD;
ll&#xD;
t&#xD;
i&#xD;
I1&#xD;
'!&#xD;
&#xD;
THE REFUGEES; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
leaping into his saddle, lhe said quickly, " We are pre-&#xD;
pared for then uow. Mr. Morley, you had better take&#xD;
your daughter under your protection ; we shall have warm&#xD;
work here in a moment."&#xD;
To the hollow !" said Mark Lee. " Quick !" confiding&#xD;
Rose to the arms of her father. "Away, there is no time&#xD;
for words. Bless you, Rose! If we do not meet again&#xD;
remember I shall die in a good cause."&#xD;
",God bless you, Mark !" Rose ejaculated in a trembling&#xD;
voice. " Do your duty, and leave me to the care bf hea-&#xD;
ven !"&#xD;
" Away at once !" urged Howard, for by this time Hank&#xD;
and his party were within a few yards of them. " We&#xD;
shall make short work of it, I iope! To horse! Mark&#xD;
Lee, to horse !"&#xD;
Thus urged, Rose and. her father once more sought the&#xD;
shelter of the wood, and Mark. mounting his horse rode&#xD;
to the side of Howard.&#xD;
In a moment the foremost of the approaching party&#xD;
rode up.'&#xD;
"Who goes there ?" exclaimed Howard.&#xD;
" Who wants to know ?" asked a tall man, dressed in&#xD;
deer skin, and carrying a long rifle on his arm, and who&#xD;
was evidently the leader of the pai'ty. "Is that you,&#xD;
Cap'n Howard ?"&#xD;
"Yes," answered Howard, " and you are Hank Red.&#xD;
fuld !"&#xD;
"That's me, sartain !" he cried, riding up to Howard,&#xD;
and calling upon his men to halt.&#xD;
"You are later than I expected," said Howard, quickly,&#xD;
"but there' is no time for explanation now. Houghton&#xD;
and his party are approaching from the Beverly road,?&#xD;
&#xD;
pursued, as I hear, by the Unionists. We must give hin&#xD;
a warm reception !"&#xD;
No words can express the delight with which Hank and&#xD;
his hardy men received this intelligence, and in a few mo-&#xD;
ments Howard had placed the forces at his command, in&#xD;
position to receive the advancing foe, who were rapidly&#xD;
coming on, little dreaming of the preparations going on&#xD;
in their behalf.&#xD;
" When I give the word, charge !" said Howard, in a&#xD;
low voice, as he turned to see that each man was ready.&#xD;
They had not long to wait, for even as lie spoke, the&#xD;
foremost of the rebels caine into sight over the brow of&#xD;
the hill. The clank of their horses' hoofs was plainly&#xD;
discernable, and ioughton's voice was heard urging on&#xD;
his men, while in the far distance could be heard the&#xD;
shouts of their pursuers and the roll of drums.&#xD;
With beating hearts and firm lips the -little party of&#xD;
Unionists waited their appearance until they were scairce-&#xD;
ly twenty yards off, when Howard gave the word to&#xD;
charge, at the same time dashing forward, accompanied&#xD;
by Mark Lee.&#xD;
On they went, that small but compact and unflinching&#xD;
band, and in a moment the melee commenced.&#xD;
The assault was terrific. Both parties fired simulta-&#xD;
neously, and several of Hough ton's party fell from their&#xD;
saddles. Shrieks, oaths, and groans filled the air, but&#xD;
loud above the din sounded the voice of Mark Lee.&#xD;
Down with them!1" lie cried. " Union and victory!"&#xD;
As he uttered these words, Miles Houghton recognized&#xD;
him, and springmig for ward, seized him by the throat with&#xD;
his left hand, while with his right lie drew a long bowie&#xD;
knife, and raising it high above his head, exclaimed :&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF 61,&#xD;
&#xD;
77&#xD;
&#xD;
76&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7514-00000039"/>&#xD;
THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
&#xD;
" Ha! ha !" Mark Lee, we meet at last. You shall no&#xD;
escape me now&#xD;
With the grasp of a giant Mark seized his uplifted arm,&#xD;
and endeavored to wrest the knife from his grasp, but&#xD;
Hioughton still kept his fingers' tightly clasped to the&#xD;
throat of his victim, and Mark began to feel his strength&#xD;
giving way, when he saw a dark object descend q'ckIy&#xD;
before his eyes, and in an instant the hold of Hou htou&#xD;
relaxed, and Mark was free.&#xD;
"Golly! I fixed him dat time !" exclaimed Cupid, who,&#xD;
armed with a heavy club, was laying about him like a&#xD;
fiend. "I reckon dat ar arm won't be much use for&#xD;
awhile, anyhow. Give it to him, Mass'r !"&#xD;
This was addressed to Mark Lee, who, the moment he&#xD;
was free, rushed upon his antagonist, but Houghton, find-&#xD;
ing'himself disabled, did not wait for his near approach,&#xD;
but turned and fled, calling out to his men to follow him.&#xD;
A Babel-like confusion, followed. The rebels, such o&#xD;
them as were not shot down, or otherwise put hors de&#xD;
combat, fled in all directions, when Houghton, finding him&#xD;
self left alone, once more turned, and called, "Shame, yo&#xD;
infernal cowards! What! do you desert me now? B&#xD;
God, I will not go until I pay some part' of the debt&#xD;
owe 1" and dashing forward with desperation, he made ft&#xD;
Mark Lee.&#xD;
As he did so, Mark slowly raised the pistol which hb&#xD;
carried in his hand, and fired. With a loud yell, th&#xD;
rebel bounded from his saddle, and the next moment fe&#xD;
to the earth a corpse.&#xD;
"Bravely done !" exclaimed Howard. That shot di&#xD;
good service. It has rid the country of one of the blac1&#xD;
est hearted villains and traitors that ever cursed it. Noi&#xD;
&#xD;
THE UNION BOYS OF '61.            79&#xD;
to the woods, brave boys, and cut off the retreat of these&#xD;
flying cowards. Look to Rose and her father," he said to&#xD;
Mark, "and follow on."&#xD;
Mark did not hesitate a moment, but instantly dis-&#xD;
mounting, and giving his horse in charge of Cupid, made&#xD;
for the friendly dell, in which Rose and her father had&#xD;
taken shelter, and in a few moments the two lovers were&#xD;
locked in each other's arms.&#xD;
To place the young girl and her father upon a couple&#xD;
of the horses which had been taken by the Unionists, was&#xD;
the work of a moment, and the whole party started in the&#xD;
direction of Huntersville. Just as they reached the vil-&#xD;
lage. they were met by Morris Brice, who had been on the&#xD;
lookout, and Rose and her father, now quite exhausted by&#xD;
the excitement and fatigue of the past three days, were&#xD;
left in the charge of his family, while Mark Lee, Howard,&#xD;
and Hank, and his brave men, with the exception of one&#xD;
who had fallen in the late skirmish, and two who had&#xD;
been wounded, proceeded to meet the advancing Unionists&#xD;
who, Brice informed them, wcre rapidly approaching by&#xD;
way of the Beverly road, over Laurel Hill.&#xD;
There had been a brilliant skirmish at Buchanan, the&#xD;
day before, in which a party of rebels had been defeated&#xD;
and scattered, and Gen. McClellan had immediately ad-&#xD;
vanced with his whole force to dislodge the rebel force at&#xD;
Laurel Hill.&#xD;
The events of the next three days are matters of his-&#xD;
tory. The brilliant battle of Rich Mountain, the defeat&#xD;
of the rebels at St. George, and the subsequent occupa-&#xD;
tion of Beverly by the brave McClellan and his victorious&#xD;
forces, are among the most brilliant of all the achieve-&#xD;
meats which marked the campaign in Western Virginia.&#xD;
&#xD;
II&#xD;
iii{&#xD;
&#xD;
VIII&#xD;
h&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7514-00000040"/>&#xD;
80               THE REFUGEES ; OR,&#xD;
In all these victories Mark Lee and Carlton Howard&#xD;
took part, and were distinguished as the bravest among&#xD;
the brave. At the end of the campaign, and after Wes-&#xD;
tern Virginia had been freed from the presence of the&#xD;
traitor troops by the Union forces, both Mark Lee and&#xD;
howard were chosen to represent the Loyalists of the&#xD;
State in the Convention at Wheeling, from which Mark&#xD;
returned covered with honors to claim his young bride.&#xD;
On the death of Miles Houghton, his father disappeared&#xD;
from the country, and the estate being declared confis-&#xD;
cated, was purchased by Win. Morley, where he now re-&#xD;
sides temporarily, until the mansion at the Elms shall be&#xD;
rebuilt.&#xD;
Shortly after his marriage, Mark Lee and howard&#xD;
were appointed Colonels in the Union army, and are now&#xD;
battling for the Constitution and the laws, under the glo-&#xD;
rious old flag.&#xD;
Cupid still lives, and is known among the Union boys&#xD;
as the bravest among all the " contrabands" in camp, and&#xD;
it is the boast of Colonel Lee that he has the ugliest and&#xD;
best servant in the army.&#xD;
Hank, the hunter, is captain of a company of sharp&#xD;
shooters, raised by himself among the mountains, and to&#xD;
him and his brave woodsmen " many a good tall fellow"&#xD;
in the rebel ranks, is indebted for his quietus.&#xD;
Those who desire to follow his fortunes, and become ac-&#xD;
quainted with his various adventures and achievements,&#xD;
will have an opportunity of doing so, as they are detailed&#xD;
at length, in the forthcoming Tale, entitled :&#xD;
HANK, THE HUNTER;&#xD;
OR, THE RIFLEMEN OF KANAWHA.&#xD;
&#xD;
/             4&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
 &#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD; &#xD;
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
