<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7690">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Ruth </title>
            <author >Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7690</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Ruth</title>
                  <author >Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >64 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Gould and Lincoln</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1864">1864</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-03-05">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Ruth</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7690-00000001"/>R'U T     H: $ m TBg bBgI7 t' There, hand in hand, firm linked at last, And heart to heart enfolded all, We'll smile upon the troubled past, And wonder why we wept at all." BOSTON: GOULD      AND LINCOLN, WASHNGTON STREET. 1864.  &#xD;<pb n="-3" xml:id="VAC7690-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1864, by GOULD AND LINCOLN, In the Cleri'  Office of the District. Court of District of Massachusetts.    THE writer hopes, by this little narra- tive, to reach a few of her sisters in sorrow. If to some it should seem to fall below the key-note of Christian privilege, they will remember that there are many whose expe- rience is not yet true to all she has said. It is of those she has thought. "Silver and gold have I none, but such as I have give I thee."   &#xD;<pb n="4-5 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7690-00000003"/> I . THE NIGHTFALL, ............................. . ." THE CONFLICT,...................................................20 "I. THE VISION, ............................................3 IV. ' THE DAYSTA R,...............................4  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7690-00000004"/> &#xD;
               <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7690-00000005"/>   IT was about an hour since they had told her, and she was now lying quite still, with her eyes closed and her hands tightly, clenched on her breast. In the darkened room her face looked gray and death-like. She seemed scarcely to breathe. "It is such a sudden blow," her sister  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7690-00000006"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT.' said, in a whisper; "it was only this afternoon she got one of his letters." '"Oh, Amy! it will kill her, -my poor child! Ruth, darling?" Her mother bent over the bed, with her hot tears fall- ing like rain on the girl's dry, cold cheeks. "Ruth, shall I pray?" "Yes." The changed, chilled voice! it frightened them. The mother thought words would freeze on her lips; but as she knelt, a  prayer came to her,-was uttered for her, perhaps. She prayed as her dead husband might have prayed, with strong crying unto this sovereign God who had laid his hand heavily on her child-her 10   THE NIGHTsFALL. eldest-born. She pleaded with the Christ who wept at Bethany, and who was no more here to bring back the dead whom he had taken utterly away. Would He not come near to this poor, crushed heart, which even her mother could not comfort now? Would He not tell her that the brave soldier had found rest with Him, where. the shock of war, and garments rolled in blood" should never be, - that all his pain had ended, - that it was for love of him and her that the great Captain had called him home,? He who tempers the wind to the shorn lamb, would He not surely do as much for her child?    &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7690-00000007"/> A -SONG IN THE DESERT. The voice which had tried to pray broke down in its faltering "Amen." Amy's sobs fell heavily on the air; but there came no moan nor cry from the pale lips which could yet frame no prayer of their own, -- poor, quivering lips, which no warm  kisses could ever mpre make glad.   She unclosed her eyes at length, and turned with a child- like, helpless movement toward her mother. "When was it?  Tell me about it." "It was day before yesterday; the battle was in -the morning, -don't ask me, Ruth, darling,- don't!  Wait till you can bear it better." 12   THE NIGHTFALL. "CI can bear it now. Did he,- did he live long after it?" "No; his sufferings were very short." "Can they, - will he come home?" A long silence answered this question; then, - "My  poor, poor child! he cannot come."  A long shiver passed over her frame, but her anguished eyes did not flinch from asking one more question. "There was no time for any message," was the reply. Hearing this, she turned away so that they could not see her face. "I would rather be alone," she said. ,-  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7690-00000008"/> A SONG IN THE DESER T. So, they went, her mother stopping to give her a long, lingering kiss, to smooth her tangled hair, to feel the chill of her white face, to know that she could do nothing, nothing for her. She must leave her alone,-her child; her poor little Ruth, who had been all hers to love and help, since she came to her, a little wail- ing baby, so long ago. Now she must go away; she could not comfort her. She closed the door, and in the silence which fell on the dim room, Ruth was left alone. To stand face to face with God who had smitten her, to feel sure of nothing in earth or heaven but his changeless 14      b   THE NI GH TFALL. will and her own consciousness of agony, --this belongs to those things which are "within the vail." She was alone with Him, - what avails it to say more? After a while her mother came softly in and drew back the shutter. The green of the trees by the river-side, the sparkle of the waters, the shadows on the hills, and the broad line of gold in the evening sky, glowing and fading in its grand unrest, the flickering light down in the valley 'where the village children were at play, this was what Ruth saw. The same world, was it? Did the light fall just so yesterday through the old, familiar trees? Did the happy river 15        -  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7690-00000009"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. wind so among the meadows? -Were those the voices and laughter of the little children whom she had known so long? She closed her eyes with a long, low moan, and her mother, hearing it, drew the blinds again. Presently Amy stole in with a cup of tea. "Please, Ruth," - holding it to her lips. Feeling its heat, she pushed it away, shivering;--he was so cold, so cold now, what had she to do with anything warm and life-giving? "Amy, I   can't,-I can't!  Mother, you had better go now, - both of you, -the night has come." Is  :      -   THE NIGH TFALL. The broken wail of her voice rang in her mother's ear for hours, and Amy sobbed herself to sleep. Ruth lay in her little room, with her hands still crossed - on her breast, holding up a great prayer -in their clasping, and her eyes wide-open to the darkness all night long. They had been all to each other,--she and Frank. He had come to her in her sunny girlhood, making all her days a beautiful promise; she had not thought it could be broken, - had not God spoken it? -And now he had gone from her,- had gone away utterly. You know how she loved him; you need not words to tell you. By your own 1 *        t  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7690-00000010"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. heart, too, you will measure her loss. She had been so happy, how could she bear it to wake from her dream, and know she should never more be glad? Hers had been such a trusting heart, it had clung so closely to him and his love, how could she stand alone, with all that had been her help lying mute and still by that far-off southern river? How could she come back to the wilderness of life, in which she could find henceforth no voice to answer her? How could she take up these weary hours and days which must make her future, remembering what they might have been, and how he would have blessed them and made them bright? ]    THE NIGHTFALL. Her mother, going about the darkened home sorrowfully, in the days when Ruth would be alone in her still room, thought and prayed much over this in her anx- ious heart. What should she ask for her child? Hown ould she, her mother, call her back to her desolate life?  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7690-00000011"/>  SHE came among them at last, but she was not of them. Wherever she went, a shadow rested. The children shrank away, frightened at her black dress and white, changed face. Amy cried in secret over the sisters he had lost, and her mother's mute eyes. followed tearfully her every motion. After a time, however, Ruth took 20   .    THE CONFLICT. up bravely her daily household cares and ministrations of love, interesting herself in the children's little joys and troubles, and teaching them all to find her warm kiss and helpful hand, even more loving and more patient than before. Yet it was pitiful to see her, with her slow, sad step about the house, all the- bright girl-look gone from her face; her eyes grown so large, and dark, and full of pain; her trembling lips trying- to smile,--such a lonely smile it was! It was hard to hear the hopeless patience of her voice; to see how dully she looked out on the fields, all bright with the green shadows she used to love so, where - 21,         X  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7690-00000012"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. the dash of glad waters, the hush of pur- ple hills and glowing sky and the tender- ness of tremulous white clouds lay before her as of old; and then to see her turn away from them all as if they hurt her; to see how her face paled when the twi- light fell, and how she would steal quietly away,-so quietly they would hardly miss her,- and to know that the burden of the day had grown so heavy, she could no longer bear it. The long months passed away, and each one found her amore patient, more mindful of all thoughtful deeds and words of love. She had long since taught her lips to pray again; she thought she was   THE CONFLICT. trying to make them frame the Abba Father of a life of suffering. She -had taken hold of the hand of One who wept for her; she knew He loved her, she knew He would never leave her, she knew He had given her a life with which to glorify Him,-she knew it, but that was all. If she had looked honestly into her heart, she would have seen that she was not taking it up as life,--not even for Himn who spent long years of toil and suffering for her; she would have, seen that she never once had lost the wish I had almost said the persistent wi/l--,to die. Her recalled smiles and: gayer words c'    &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7690-00000013"/> A -SONG IN THE DESERT. were only like perishing flowers which had root in the depth of this one cease- less hope. Her friends looked on sorrow- fully and felt that they were helpless, yet watched her with ceaseless prayer. They had all been together one even- ing in the sitting-room, the children play- ing before the open fire, and Ruth and Amy shelling corn for them  to parch. Their -mother sat by, listening to the laughter of the little boys, and Amy's happy talk; but her ear caught most quickly the lowest of Ruth's quiet words, and her eyes fell oftenest and perhaps most lovingly on' the little dark figure,. with its pale face, and tender, helpful   THE CONFLICT. hands. She saw how happy the childrenJ were with her, how their arms clung about her neck when it came time to say " good-night," how she returned their warm kisses with a smile, and then, when they had left her, how her eyes sad- dened, looking dreamily into the fire, some faint, new pain seeming to creep into them. "Ruth;' said Amy, after a pause, "Sarah Greyson asked me, to-day, why you didn't come to see her as you used to, and if I didn't suppose you could do some dis- trict visiting down town with her this year." Ruth  compressed her lips, and her ,                 .,  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7690-00000014"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. hands twitched nervously, but she made no reply. "And, Ruth, dear, - " "Well?" "'You have never come back to your old place in the sewing-circle; and our reading-class ask me every week- if we shan't see you again soon." Ruth turned quickly, her face full of pain. "I cannot, Amy; it hurts me so to go about among people: I'll help the poor in a quiet way; but a year is a long time to think about; and as for the reading, I do not care for that- what use is it now?"   THE CONFLICT. She turned her face again to the fire.' Amy was silent, and soon rose to go up stairs, coming to kiss Ruth before she went. "Amy, dear, I didn't mean to scold you, -you understand?" " Oh, no, you never are cross to me or anybody; you're a perfect angel here at home,  only somehow, Ruth,- I don't know, - I wish -." There was a puzzled look on her bright face. Ruth kissed it away with a laugh, and Amy left the room. "Ruth," said her mother, after" a long silence, "come up here and sit by me." She came, sitting at her feet, her head  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7690-00000015"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. resting on her hand as if she were tired. "Ruth, dear,you are doing everything you can for us at home, and I wonder at your gentleness and patience every hour; but, don't think I am blaming you, my child,- but don't you suppose you could take up some of the work you used to love so, and mingle a little more with some of your old friends?" I cannot do it, mother, --I cannot go back to any more of the old life, it is all I can do to get along from day to day at home." There was something sharp in her voice as she spoke. v1         .   THE CONFLICT. "But, my child, there is One to help you; he will give you strength." "He doesn't." "Do you really wish Him to give it to you'?" "Why, yes; I wish to work for Him. What else have I left? I wish to work, if it might be short." "'You make no- plans to do for HiTm, beyond a week or a month, my daughter. Why is this?"  "Because--. Mother, it's no use for us to talk about this; it only troubles you."     . "Why is it, Ruth?" "Because I cannot, cannot live!" C .---- .     29   &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7690-00000016"/> A XSONG IN THE DESERT. The firelight fell full on her face, so old and wan, with the lines on her fore- head. It would not take much more of this, her mother thought, to give her the rest she longed for. No hoine-ties could keep her, the love of the dear Christ himself only taught her to endure, and no more. What else remained?  Who could help her child in this weary way? "Ruth, what would Frank wish?" she said, at last. This seemed almost cruel, her lips quivered so, her hands clasped her mother's so helplessly, there was such a piteous-.entreaty in her stifled sobs. Her mother's arms gathered her, as if r   THE CONFLICT. she had been indeed a little child. She could do nothing but love her; she must leave the rest with God. "O mother! mother! do let me go!" and Ruth crept up to her with a little, low cry, as if the wind were wailing. After a while she went ups-tairs and sat down in her room by the window. Amy was asleep, and it was quite still. She looked out to see the winter wind tossing the branches of the gaunt, leaf- less trees, and driving masses of cloud gloomily across the sky. In relief against the darkness, she could just see the out- lines of the village church, and the low stone wall which bounded the cemetery  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7690-00000017"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. behind it. There- her eye rested long- ingly; there was quiet, there was repose; to sleep there would be to find Frank. She had no dearer love for all the bright world now, than just that it held a little space in which she could lie some day, and be at rest, with the sweet breath of violets and daisies and the melody of singing birds above her. How had she the strength to think that another year might find her still away from Frank? But, - if this were the will of God? She was startled at the answer her heart gave to this question. She had thought herself submissive,- she had thought herself resigned to his care. , h   THEI CONFLICT. The truth came suddenly to her. She saw how faint was' her trust in his love, how feeble her best endeavors to serve Him in the lot He had appointed her, how utterly she did, in fact, rebel against his will, when that will decreed that she should live. She saw in herself the nar- rowed influence and dwarfed energies of a crushed, thankless life, taken only as a burden and borne as if she were a slave and not a child. And why was this.?   Because God had taken away her treasure.  But should He not do as He pleased with. his own? Had He no more claim upon her love because one of his golden gifts  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7690-00000018"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. had been recalled? And yet,--and yet how could she give it in the way He wished? With the persistence of grief, she came back to her old self-ex- cusing. Would not her Master be satis- fied if she did for Him all she could, from day to day? How could He ask her to accept a future into which Frank could never come?   OOKING out upon the clouds as 1 3S9 if for an answer, she thought at last they moved and bright- ened, and a glory of light shone through them, turn- ing the night to day. As she gazed, a form appeared therein; and moved toward her, a shining path growing before it, till it came to where she was. A sense of purity overwhelmed her, but she felt no CT,  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7690-00000019"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. fear. Looking up into the bright face above her, she saw why. "Frank!" She waited breathlessly for his answer, gazing into his eyes, as if so she thought death might come to her. He smiled,-his old familiar smile it was, yet changed into something so per- fect in its joy, that, she wondered to see it. He called her by name, his voice like a strain of music that might wander forever about the Throne, yet tender still and full of human love. She stretched out her hands to him pleadingly. "You have been sent to take me home, Frank?" A change came over his face, a look   THE VISI ON. such as angels must wear in their speech less moments, when, but for this mystery of angelhood, they might weep. "It is not willed," he said; "you can- not come to me yet." She bowed her head with a bitter cry. TheI voice from the cloud called her again. "Ruth, I wish you to stay." "You wish it?" "His will is call mine now; I know no other." "I cannot, cannot bear it, it is so long," she cried. His face seemed to grow dim as she spoke, his smile fading; she tried to touch his hand, but she could not      ,  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7690-00000020"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. reach it; he stood far away from her, the golden light about him deepening and glowing, as if it were the very whiteness of the Throne. And she seemed to know suddenly, though it was not his voice which told her, that so every hour of this, hopeless murmuring placed more of dis- tance between him and her. That even he should expect her to stay without him! -this was hardest of all. Hearing her sharp cry, he spoke again. "I cannot so look on it, my poor Ruth; to us who have seen God, the life which he gives, even in its pain, must be thankfully accepted. I do not forget earth's anguish, or its love; louder than   THE VISION. all the music of our angel choirs, I have heard your low moaning; but to see you rebel against Hm, to see the love with whichi his hand has separated us, and then to see how you let it crush you, as if it were a harsh and cruel thing,- Ruth, all the pain that can -enter heaven is in my heart for you." "Oh, Frank! what will you have me do?" she wailed;-C "take this bitter gift from Him?" "This blessed gift." "Be thazfutl that I suffer?" ' That you suffer for Him." "Take up these weary years as if they were not filled with misery?" 89  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7690-00000021"/> A SONG IN THE DE'SERT. "Take them  with rejoicing because there is something yet to do for Him." Seeing the great prayer for help on, her lips, he drew near to her,-his face brightening as if to bless her. "My work was not finished," he said-; "what I left undone on earth is given to, you, to bring to God for us both. Will you do this for Him, Ruth?  See -." Turning, he pointed to an opening in the clouds, where a long, lonely path stretched! out before her; and looking, she saw that it was hers to tread. The way seemed to lead through a desert, but, as she ob- served it more closely, she saw that all along its sands homely duties, and kindly   THE VlSIONX. words, and tender helps to the poor and- lowly, sprung and brightened like flowers, and the joy of sad hearts whom 9nshe should cheer was like the lull' of foun- tains in the parched air. Ftar in the dis- tance a soul crossed her path, which, but for her, could not be- saved; and as she * listened to the dim sound of its blessings, and loolked eagerly forward, it might be, perhaps, there were others whom  God had chosen her to bring to himself, she was not sure. A voice broke the stillness of her long gazing, '"Your work - nd imine, - we will do it togrether, Ruth."' And, turning to answer hinm, she saw, by the deathless love in his  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7690-00000022"/> A S ONG IN THE DE;SERT. eyes, that he would not leave her to toil alone. While she struggled with her tears for speech, the pure, bright face faded slowly from her sight. She stretched out her hands imploringly; she called his name; but his smile was her only an- swer. She awoke with a start, to find her dream had faded, and she sat alone by her window. Amy still slept soundly, and the room was cold and dark. Turn- ing, with a sick sense of disappointment,; to look out into the night, she saw that the clouds were breaking away, and in the bit of clear, still sky above her head, a single star shone like a smile. The first whisper of possible peace she   THE VISION. had heard since Frank left her came, as she bowed her head, her lips moving as if in prayer.  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7690-00000023"/> COjT was only Ruth's clinging kiss on her mother's lips, and a smile bright with deepened love turned on Amy, which told them that in the watches of the night God had spoken to her a promise of better things, and sent Frank to help her. But they looked at her in wonder, as every day she followed the voice which   THE DAYSTAR. led her on, seeing how resolutely she tried to dispel the gloom that her grief had brought into their home, and how she struggled to recall in its stead some of her old playful ways, which were the charm of all their household memories. The dearness of her sister-love, which they had sadly thought was gone, as everthing else had gone which held her to the past, came back to gladden them, and they knew it truer, tenderer than before. The little boys felt no longer that they must hush their noisy plays before the shade on her face, for,a smile was there too, and they thought only of that. 45  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7690-00000024"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. Ruth liked to play with them and see them happy, and Ruth was so patient with them; Ruth made all hard tasks so easy, Ruth had such a pleasant way of settling their troubles; they had such talks with Ruth at twilight, after they had said their prayers, when she came up and sat down on their little bed-! The buoyancy of Amy's girlhood was no longer checked because of her sister's loss; she came, at last, to confide to her again all the joys and plans, which had never seemed half hers unless Ruth could share them. "And as for Pother," she would say, --"why, Ruth, I believe she lives by   THE DAS TA R. loving you." And Ruth, turning with her cquiet smile, would see in her mother's eyes that which made her go up very softly to hide her face on her shoulder, and feel the caressing hand on her hair. But it was not in her home alone that her patient heart drew the blessing of others to itself. There were old friend-' ships to renew, and almost forgotten oc- cupations to take up again for their sake. There were many, too, whom God had ' smitten, who knew .'Him not as a Com- forter. These-called to her, and her own suffering made her eye quick to find them. So she went down among those who  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7690-00000025"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. were poor and despised of men, as her Master had gone before her, seeking the sorrowful. ones whom she might help. At every step she met them. She had -not known before how much unaided miisery there was around her. From their stifled factories and squalid homes, they came to her. She drew near to them to call them friends, and that with humbled heart, for grief had made desolate ways for them as for her, and the same Saviour who had been her Helper loved them. She could tell you of discourage- ments which threatened to overcome her strength, of ingratitude where she had A 0   THE DAYSTAR. labored most and hoped most surely, of temptings to fall back into the selfish indolence of her grief, of hours when her struggles with the wish for death were bitter, of hours when the rod seemed sharper than she could bear. But she would tell you, too, of a Help that always waited for her, of a Strength that gave her courage, of a Love that never forgot:her. She would tell you, with a faint flush on her cheek, and moistened eyes, that it was very little she could do; but per- haps that would be -accepted, and some time she might see that -her efforts had not been all unavailing. Some time / Her  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7690-00000026"/> A soNG IN THE DESERT. fingers would turn her betrothal ring unconsciously as she spoke, and you would know at once what she meant. But-,she was not to wait. for this, to see the results dof her work. Though we cannot know how brilliant the crown may be at last, some of its jewels will fall in our path as we walk. She thought of this thankfully one night, when she had planned a festival for a crowd of little children, whom she had taught, in her patient way, for many months. They came from their dark, unwholesome homes to frolic under the trees and in the garden, - the same gar- den where she and Frank used to walk.   'tHE' .DA S TAR. She thought, with a smile, how it would please him to see them there. The little ones had brought- their mothers and sisters with them, shyly,- sometimes a whole family, indeed; for, "didn't the lady ask 'em all to come; and Molly and brother Tom had a holi- day, and thought they'd walk along, too; and didn't she want to see the baby, which couldn't come without mother, no-how, and could creep all round into everything since she saw it?"And the little thing would be sure to find its way over the soft grass to her knee, and she would take it up to kiss it and play with it, the proud mother standing by. 1       ,  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7690-00000027"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. -One neatly-dressed woman cast her keen eye over the lawn, to single out three or four -rosy children from the -group, and spoke suddenly,- "To think," she said, putting her apron up awkwardly to her eyes,--to think how them little things was used to be left without a morsel to eat all day long, in their -miserable rags, and me lying drunk on the floor, or beatin' of 'em and thrashin' of 'em about, - poor innocents! --till they didn't know what mother meant, but a- sort of devil! and then to see 'em so clean and tisdy, and me so happy, and the rum-cupboard all cleaned out, and filled up with their little books 62   THE. DA Y S TA R. and clothes; and to think how you come to me, when I was. goin' to shut the door in your face, for I hated such like you, who was rich and good; and how you said, in that soft voice o' yourn,'didn't I want somebody to help me bringup the little creeturs decent, and learn 'em how to love me, and, H I - God bless you! I keep a chokin' and tallcin' -both at once, and make a fool of meself thinkin' on it all!" While she stood there, hiding her rough face in her baby's neck, another voice joined with hers,- a slight woman she was, with a pale face and a mourn- ing ribbon on her bonnet. She looked (7-  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7690-00000028"/> A S ONG IN THEE- DF S8ERT. at the laughing baby with hungry eyes. "Mine was so pretty!" she said, in a sort of appealing tone to Ruth; 'just so, warn't he? And my heart was broke for him till I see you." Ruth took her hand very quietly, with the quick tears in her eyes. "You told me," said the woman, - ' you told me where he'd gone to, and taught me the way to find him, and told me he'd wait for me, and love me, with his pretty ways, in heaven, just the same. Yes, he was a winsome baby, was my boy! I was just thinkin' how he'd have looked, with his red cheeks, tumblin'   THE DAYSTAR. round among them little things, an( comin' up to kiss you along with 'em." Just then, a gentle pull at her dres caused Ruth to turn and see a pair oi very sad childish eyes fixed on her, an( to hear the story which had darkene( them:. "Father had drank -Up all th money, and mother was lying sick a, home, and they hadn't no dinner all day and would she mind her saving he: supper, when it came time to eat, ae( carrying it home? she wouldn't let no body know, and would hide it -right ofl quick in her pocket." She had scarcely comforted the child and brought back the light into its eyes (I      , ------ --- ----.  g  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7690-00000029"/> A SONIG IN THE DESERT. before Amy called her to start some merry game under the trees. With her smile ready for them in a moment, she turned away and joined the children's sport. After that, a happy mother came to her, spelling out last week's letter from her soldier-boy, that Ruth might read and rejoice with her. Then it was a shy girl telling a story of her lover's long furlough, and how brave and good he was, and, he wanted to see the lady; "'would she mind dropping. in, wher she was down, to say a bit to him, or should she fetch him up to the house with her, some time after mill-hours were over?" t            . 5-   THE DA YS TAR.  Close behind the blushing girl, another stood waiting to speak,--so close that she heard the happy talk, and turned ' away with 'a sudden motion like one in pain. It was not long before Ruth stood by her, looking into her face, pale with its stamp of early widowhood. What were Ignorance and Poverty that they should rise up between them now?; In their kindred loss, Ruth thought, they met on common ground. She drew the girl's hand through her arm, and wan- dered down into the garden with her. There was little to say,--only a few kind words, and then to follow them by a silence in which the touch of the cool  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7690-00000030"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. air, -and the light among the flowers, might bring their own soothing to the tired heart. So they came to her, one by one,- these neglected ones, into whose dark lives she had brought such brightness,-- they came to bless her and go on their way rejoicing. You would have wondered to see her passing among them, with the sunlight on her quiet face, and the smile on her lips, so patient she was and full of tender- ness for them, so full of courage for their future, so earnest in her sympathy with their joys, so quick to divine where their troubles were and give them comfort. -8   THE DAYS TAR. The children, made happy by their plentiful supper, had grown tired with their sports, and gathered around' her, rubbing their eyes with their little brown fists, to say good-night,- and at last she was left alone. She sat down under the trees where the birds were chirping sleepily over her head, to watch the group in the road, the women hushin their babies, to sleep as they walked; the happy children counting their store of apples and candy drowsily, and treadi ng down the daisies; the young    people stealing home, two by two, in the twi- light, and a, solitary figure, in a dark dress, lingering behind them  all. That' (bJ      R       * I  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7690-00000031"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. figure would turn again and again, to look at her, as she sat there alone, in the grey of the evening, as if it longed to come back and tell her how the broken hearts for which she cared prayed God to speak to her the same promise of peace she had spoken to them. She watched the girl till her form grew dim in the dusky light, then, bend- ing her head, listened for the last sound of the children's laughter. When that had died away, she covered her face with her hands. All these had blessed her,-- had blessed her! Should she let their voices call to her in vain? Should she not thank God o ---T--L31,   THE DA iS TAR. ' that she and Frafik could so work to- gether for Him? One upon earth, indeed, and one in heaven, but never parted; and both his who gave them each to the other, she thought, and raised her eyes to the west- ern hills, where ethe sky wa clear. There was a prayer in their gaze that could not be uttered. Amy came up with the children to say "good-night," and, taking' their little hands in hers, she went' slowly up to the house to find her mother. "With a fearless eye she looks now on her future, for she knows who has de- 3  -------------------  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7690-00000032"/> A SONG IN THE DESERT. creed its every moment in love. What it may be,  how long, how short, be- longs not to her care. She sees in all the kindliness of daily life, a sweet incense which may rise to heaven like a prayer, and make- her strong. All the thorns in her way she will press to her heavy heart and turn to flowers for his sake whose grief alone deserves such sharp crowning. What if her steps do falter on this rough way? She knows her Saviour is there; she only asks to hear his voice, and she will go wherever it shall guide her. He will not ask of her too long a journey. He knows how she loves her 62   TSE DA YS TAR. soldier, ano^rill, in his own good time, % bring her to the home in which He waits . for her. So, hand in hand with Christ, she treads the Desert. She learns to gather, note by note, the broken harmony of her days. This is the burden .of hersong:- Pe am O Lord, mand t Len whi tihoA * Most gseun mI /A  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7690-00000033"/>   &#xD;
            </p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>