<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7984">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Tales of the Times </title>
            <author >Ludlow, Fitz Hugh, (1836-1870)</author>
            <author >Sikes, William Wirt, (1836-1883)</author>
            <author >Sedgwick, Catharine Maria, (1789-1867)</author>
            <author >Irving, John Treat, (1812-1906)</author>
            <author >Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, (1793-1864)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7984</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >[Tales of the times</title>
                  <author >Ludlow, Fitz Hugh, (1836-1870)</author>
                  <author >Sikes, William Wirt, (1836-1883)</author>
                  <author >Sedgwick, Catharine Maria, (1789-1867)</author>
                  <author >Irving, John Treat, (1812-1906)</author>
                  <author >Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, (1793-1864)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >96 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >H. Dexter</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1861">1861]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-06-01">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>[Tales of the times</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7984-00000001"/>THE TAXIDERMST. BY FITZ-HUGH LUDLOW., I.-THE  OLD MAID'S CHAPTER. -- DIE if dying I may give Life to one who asks to live, And more nearly, Dying thus, resemble thee I' ' CIEL! Zat is ze true heroique! Zat is ze very far finest ting in all ze lit- erature ar-glaise I Zere have not been made vun more sublime poesie by your immortel Villiams Shakyspeare! Glorieux! Vat a grandeur moral of ze woman who vill vonce die for her love! ' ' Once? I knew a woman who died thrice for hers.' The enthusiastic admirer of Longfellow was a French Professor in one of our American Colleges, by name Gautier Bonenfant. The person who met his panegyric with such a strange response, was Orloff Ruricson, by birth a Swede, by adoption a New-Yorker, and by trade the proprietor of a Natural History Museum. These two, with myself, were sitting on the west piazza of the little inn at Kaaterskill Falls. All of us hard-working men in the hard- working season; but on this tenth day of July, eighteen hundred and fifty- nine, soaking the dust out of our brains in a bath of sunlight and mountain air, forgetting in company that life was not all one sweet vacation. Bonenfant and I looked at Ruricson-with puzzled faces. Though a good fellow and a wisely humorous one, he seldom said any thing whose cleverness lay in a double-entendre. 'Pray, who is that remarkable woman?' said I. 'It is my wife,' replied Orloff Ruricson soberly. 'And she die, von, two, tree time?' asked Bonenfant, with uplifted eye- brows. 'And she died three times for her love,' repeated Orloff Ruricson. Perhaps you would have no objection to tell us exactly what you mean?' said L. 'None at all, to you two. With this proviso. I know that you, John Tryon, write for the magazines. For aught I know, Bonenfant here, may be a correspondent of the Constitutionnel.' 'Mais non I am ze mose red of Red Republican I' 'Perhaps you are Ledru Rollin, then, travelling in disguise to hunt mate- rials for a book. At any rate, I must exact of both of you a promise, that if a single lineament of the story I am going to relate, ever gets into print through your agency, it shall be represented as fictitious, and under assumed names.' 'C'est fait ' 'It's a bargain I   &#xD;<pb n="2-3" xml:id="VAC7984-00000002"/> THE TAXIDERMST 'You! see, I live by my Museum. And if the public once suspected that I was a isionary man, the press and the pulpit and general opinion would run me down immediately. I should be accused of denying the originality of the human race inferentially, through my orang-outang; of teaching lessons of maternal infidelity through my stuffed ostrich; of seducing youth into a sea- faring life by my preserved whale. No more schools, at half-price on Satur- day afternoon, accompanied by their principal; no more favorable notices by ditors, 'who have been with their families,' for you, Orlof Ruricson I 'And what I am going to tell you Will seem visionary. Even to you. nevertheless, it is as real as any of the hardest facts in my daily life. Take :solemn word for it. When I was ten years old, my parents emigrated from Sweden to this country. At the age of twelve, I lost my father. At thirteen, I was appren- ticed to a man who stuffed'birds in Dutch-street. At fourteen, I was mother- less. At twenty, my 'term was out, and I began to think of setting up as a taxidermist on my own hook. There I The Biographical Dictionary can't beat tiat summary of ten years, for compactness I '! m adea very liberal offer to my master; in fact, proposed to take him ipto partnership He nobly refused to avail himself of my generosity. Bird- stuffng, ey u New-York, was not a very lucrative business, and would hardy support two, he suggested. What did I think of one of the river towns? Albany, or Hudson, or. Poughkeepsie, for instance? I did not tell him-what; but in reality, I thought so little of them, that within ten days after, my indentuSre was cancelled, I had taken a little nook in the Bowery, with window enough to show off three blue-jays, a chameleon, and a very young wild cea, (whose domesticity I may, at this day, acknowledge to have been slandere by that name,) and sufficient door to display the inscription: ' ORLOFF RUBICSON', Taxidermist and Aviarian Professor.' Even at that day, you see, Bonenfant, we impostors had begun to steal your literary title.' 'Sacrebleu I I do very moshe vish zat ze only ting ze plenty humbug pro- fessors now-akdays stuff vas ze birds!' 'Weil, I may have stuffed the public a little, too. At any rate, they pa- tronized mefar betterthan I had any reason to expect, By the time I was of age, I had nioved my business one door farther up, to a shop trebile the size of the first; and instead of sleeping under and eating on top of my show-ease, as I began, I occupied lodgings with a respectable cutler's widow, second-story front of a brick houseon Third Avenue, and came down to my store every morning at nine o'clock, like any wholesale grocer. '.I had been installedr in my comfortable quarters only six weeks, when a new lodger came to the boarding-house. The first thing that I knew of it, was my beholding, directly opposite me at a Sunday dinner, the most preter- naturally homely face I had ever seen. As I took my seat, and opened my napkin, the cutler's widow inclined her head in the direction of the appari- tion, and uttered the words: ' Miss Brentnall.' I cast a glance and a bow in the same quarter, pronouncing the name after her. ' Mr. Ruricson,' said the landlady laconically, and nodded toward me. 'Mr. Ruricson,' repeated the   THE TAXIDERMST.              3 miracle of plainness, in a voice so sweet that I could not rid myself of the impression that it must be the ventriloquism of some one else. At the same moment she smiled. The smile was as incongruous with the face as the voice; and for that glancing half-minute, Miss Brentnall was a dozen shades more endurable. ' ruikshank, acting a s collaborator with Salvator Rosa, would fall short of.- any thing more ambitious than a slight sketch of the woman's unearthly. homeliness. I dare hardly attempt describing her in words, but for yolr sake, let me try. 'Her hair was like Bonenfant's Republicanism, 'the most red of red,' but without the usual characteristic of that color, silky fineness. In fact, unless you have been through a New-England corn-field in the dog-days; and noticed the very crispest of all the crisp tassels which a brazen sun has been at work baking for the month previous; unless you have seen some peculiarly un- sheltered specimen, to the eye like dried blood, and to the fingers like dust and ashes, you cannot imagine the impression produced by Miss Brentnall's hair. I really trembled lest our awkward waiter's sleeve should touch it, in serving the vegetables, and send it crumbling from her head in the form of a crimson powder. Her forehead was in every respect immense--high, broad, and protuberant enough for the tallest man who ever prided himself on his in- tellect; still, it might have been pardoned, if it had been fair withal, instead of sallow, wrinkled and freckled. A nose, whose only excuse for its mam- moth maturity of size and its Spitzenberg depth of color, lay in the fact that it was exposed to the torrid glare of the tresses, depended, like the nest of the hanging-bird, between a pair of ferrety eyes, which seemed mere pen- knife gashes in a piece of red morocco. At that day, I could not swear to the pupils; but a profane man of sensitive mind, might have sworn at 'them, for they seemed to be a damp - not a swimming but a soaked damp - pale blue. Flanking the nose, imagine an inch and a half on either side, of dingy parch- ment, stretched almost to tearing, and you will get the general idea of the sides of Miss Brentnall's face; I will not travesty the word 'cheeks,' by call- ing them that. Below the nose, a mouth which would have been deformedly small for a child two weeks old; below that, a chin which hardly showed it all in front, and, taking a side view, seemed only an eccentric protraction of the scraggy neck to which it was attached. Now for the figure. High, stooping shoulders; a long, flat, narrow, mannish waist; the lower extremi- ties immoderately short; immense feet: group these in one person, and you have a form to wh'ch I know only two parallels out of the world of night- mare, a German wooden doll, and Miss Brentnall.'        i 'Diable ce laideur I You see zat viz your own eyes?' t 'Yes, Bonenfant.' 'And yet you be yourself not vare ugly, after all ' ' So I have heard, Bonenfant. You will be still more surprised to feel that this is the case, when you know that I lodged in the same house with Miss Brentnall a whole year. Indeed, she occupied the very next room to me. I  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7984-00000003"/> 4            THE TAXIDERMST. was second-story front, she second-story back, during all that time; and do you know that I became very well acquainted with her?' 'Ahl It is pos-sible for a gentleman to be vare polite to vare ugly wo- man I' "'Yes, but from preference, I mean. I could shut my eyes, and hear her voice, or open them at the transient moment when she was smiling, and forget that she was homely at all. I discovered that she was the only remnant of a large family: that awakened my pity. In addition, that she was very well- informed, thought and conversed well: that aroused my respect. And when, in spite of a face and figure which by poetic justice should have belonged, to Sin itself, I perceived that she had the kindest of hearts, and the most deli- cate of sensibilities, I am not ashamed to confess that I soon became attached to her.' 'Attach? You have fall in love viz zat e-scary-crow? You have marri-ed her?' 'Hear me. through, Bonenfant, and you will find out. In the present in- stance, I mean, by the word 'attached,' nothing but a pure Platonic friend- ship. I do not make acquaintances easily. I visited nobody in New-York at that time. There was no one whose cheerful fireside I could make my own for an evening; and my natural tastes, to say nothing of any other feeli4rg, kept me away from drinking-saloons. Moreover, I had an insatiate longing to make something of myself. I wanted the means for buying books, for travel- ling, for putting myself into what I considered good society. Accordingly, I often brought home, at evening, the specimens I had been working upon all day, and continued my labors long into the night. While I was busily en- gaged with the knife or the needle, the gentlest little tap would come at the door, so gentle, so unlike any other sound, that, however'absorbed I might be, I always heard it, knew it was Miss Brentnall, and said: ' Walk in! '. So, in hopped that little eighth world-wonder of ugliness, now with an orange for my supper, now with some pretty-ornithological engraving, of which, by the, merest chance, she always had a duplicate copy, and whose effect she would like to see on my wall. When she went out, she always forgot to take it with her; and in a few months, my room, through such like little kindnesses, be- camle quite a portrait-gallery of celebrated birds. Sometimes, Miss Brentnall spent the whole evening with me. On such occasions, it was her greatest de- light to stand by my table, and see some poor, mussed, shrivelled lark or Canary grow plump and saucy again, through the transformations of my art. She called it 'bird-resurrection.' For an hour at a time, she would stay close -at my elbow, perfectly quiet, holding a pair of glass eyes in her hand. 'When I asked for one of them, she gave it to me with all the happiness of a helpful child; and, when at last both eyes were fixed in the specimen, I have seen her clap her hands, and jump up and down. In process of time, she became of real assistance to me. So apt a mind had she, that from merely witness- ing my methods, she learned to stuff birds herself; and one evening, when I called ' come in,' to the well-known tap, I was surprised by seeing a parrot in   THE TAXIDERMST.              5 her hands, prepared and mounted almost as well as I could have done it my. self. It was a little present to the Professor, she said: she had been at work upon it for the last two days. Prom that time, her voluntary services were in my constant employ, whenever I worked of evenings. 'I was not so ungallant, however, as to let Miss Brentnall do all the visit- ing. Whenever a lazy fit took me, and I could not have worked, or studied, or walked, if I had been offered ten dollars an hour for those exertions, I a!P* ways forestalled her coming to my room by going to hers. She had a largei rocking-chair, which always seemed to run up to the fire-place of its own ace cord, and hold out its arms for me, the moment I came in. I would drop into' that, shut my eyes, and say, ' Please talk to me,' or, ' Please read to me,', with as much abandonment as if I were speaking to my own mother. It fever felt like exacting impertinent demands of a stranger, I was so marvellously at my ease in Miss Brentnall's room.' 'Ze man of mose mauvaise honte be not embarrass, I have observe, viz ze vare ugly lady.' 'I don't think it was that, Bonenfant. I used to ask myself if it might not be. But I always came to the conclusion that I should feel the same, were Miss Brentnall the most beautiful person in the world. There was something in her mind, especially as expressed in voice and style of talking, that lulled me when I was most irritable, that lifted the weight of self and pride quite off me for the time being. I knew that we both liked to be to- gether; that was enough; I did not care, indeed I never once thought, how we either of us seemed to any one else. 'I could not help being aware that the other boarders talked about us. Having a pair of tolerably good ears, likewise of eyes, it was difficult not to know that old Mrs. Flitch, my landlady's half-sister, smelt a match in my in- timacy with Miss Brentnall; that she considered it ill-advised, on the ground that I was twenty-one, and the lady at, least forty; that she could imagine no possible motive in my mind, except a view to Miss Brentnall's snug little property; that, as a consequence of these premises, she regarded one of us a very mean knave, and the other a doting fool. It was difficult not to under- stand the meaning of Miss Simmons, an acid cotemporary of Miss Brentnall's, possessing all her chances of celibacy, half her homeliness, and one-thou. sandth of her mind, when, as I took my seat next her at the breakfast-table, she asked me, with a pretty simper, if I had spent the last evening as pleas- antly as usual. It was difficult to avoid seeing the gentlemen wink at each other when they passed us talking together in the entry: it was also diffi- cult, as I perceive from Bonenfant's face he would like to suggest, not to pull their noses for it; but reflection suggested the absurdity of such a course. This is one of the few objections I have to your native, and my adopted coun- try, Tryon, that notwithstanding the great benefit which results from that in- timacy between a man and a woman, in which each is mere friend, and neither present nor expectant lover, our society will not hear of such a thing, without making indelicate reference to marriage. Still, I suppose, they would have talked about us, any where.  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7984-00000004"/> THE TAXIDERMST. 'Miss Brentnall knew this as well as I, and like me, never gave it a thought after the momentary demonstration which recalled it. We passed one whole delightful year together in the Third Avenue boarding-house. I felt my own mind growing, becoming richer in all sorts of knowledge, freer and clearer in every field of thinking, with each succeeding day. And as for Miss Brentnall, she was so kind as to say, and I knew she sincerely meant it, that to her, all lonely in the world, our friendship was in all respects inesti- mable. At the end of the year, Miss Brentnall was taken ill. For the first few days, neither she nor I felt any serious alarm with reference to, her case. The doctor pronounced it a mild type of typhoid fever. It proceeded, so he said to me' in private, more from mental causes than any tangible physical one. Had she been unfortunate in any way? he asked me. I could only re- ply that, as her intimate friend, I was unaware of the fact. Probably. she read late, then, he suggested. I said that might be. At all events, her mind had been very much overtaxed: what she needed was perfect quiet, good nursingi and as little medicine as possible. Upon his giving me this view of the case, I:sought out the most faithful, judicious woman within reach, and hired her on Miss Brentnall's behalf, to stay by her bedside night and day. My own income, from the little shop in the Bowery, was now so fair, that I felt able to repay, in some measure, the debt of gratitude I owed my kind friend for her many contributions to the walls of my lonely room. Accord- ingly, whenever I lighted on any new engraving or book of art, or any embel- lishment to a sick-chamber, which seemed likely to attract without fatiguing a strained mind, I brought it up to her in the evening. If I had not been in her debt already, I should have been a thousand times repaid for these little evidences of friendship, by the appreciative delight with which the childlike woman talked of them, for their own sake, and the grateful enthusiasm she bestowed upon them for mine. 'The opportunity to be kind and thoughtful was very short. At the end of the third week, the doctor gravely told me that typhus pneumonia was be- coming alarmingly prevalent in New-York, and that Miss Brentnall's disease had taken that form. Furthermore, that unless some change for the better occurred in the course of the next twenty-four hours, she would die. . ' I heard this piece of news without the least outward sign of sorrow. It did not seem possible to me that I could lose this best, kindest friend I had in the world. You will think the reason whimsical perhaps; but, merely be- cause she was not beautiful, I felt as if she would not be taken away from me. 4 Only the beautiful die, only the beautiful,' I kept saying to myself all day, in the shop or at the work-table. In the evening, when I came back to the house, Ifound that two things had occurred. Miss Brentnall's pulse had become feebler, and she did not seem to me so plain as before. Then, for the first time, I began to be afraid. 'In the morning, the doctor took me into the entry, and told me that his patient might live till mid-night, but not longer. Would I take the painful office of breaking the intelligence to her? 'Yes,' I replied, hardly knowing what I said.   I   THE TAXIDERMST.   'I entered the sick-room. As I came toward the bed, Miss Brentnall open- ed her eyes and smiled. "Martha,' said she, in a feeble voice, 'you may go down-stairs, and get me some arrow-root.' 'As soon as the nurse had shut the door behind her, Miss Brentnall con- tinued: "I shall be dead in a few hours, Orloff. I have something to say to you alone. I am sorry to go away from you. Very sorry. You have been kind to me, Orloff. More than any body else in the world.' 'I took Miss Brentnall's poor, parched hand, but could not answer. 'Or- loff--kind as you are to me-in the bottom of your heart, you know that I have the most repulsive face you ever saw. Say yes, Orloff. You do know. it. I have been sure of it, since I was a little girl, six years old, thirty-four years ago, yesterday. I was never sorry for it, more than a moment at a time, un- til a year ago. And now you may tell me you see it, without hurting me at all. Pride is past. Say that my face is the most unlovely in the world. Say it to please me.' 'I saw she was in deep earnest, and I brought myself to answer for her sake: "Well. But your soul is the most lovely.' "I thank you 'for saying it, Orloff. And now, now that pride is past, I may tell you something which life would hide forever, but death wrings out of my very soul. You have been a friend to me, a dear, kind friend, Or- loff; but nothing more. I have been something else to you. A dying wo- man may say it. I have loved you.' 'For a minute we were both silent, and then Miss Brentnall resumed: 'Passionately, passionately. Without once deluding myself; without once dreaming that there was a shadow of hope. Had you been blind; had you been deaf; so that you could never have seen what I am, or heard a word of it from other lips; even had you, under these circumstances, loved me, I would have felt it base to give you, in exchange for yourself, such a-thing as I. But you did see, you did hear, and I knew that I loved, impossibly. You came in, now, to tell me that I would not live till to-morrow, did you not, Orloff?' "I meant to, if I could,' was my reply. "I had a dream just before you came in. I thought I saw you, and you told me so. Do you know what a strange thing happened, just as you seemed speaking? But you are not angry with me, for what I have said al- ready?' "Angry? My dear friend, no l' said I instantly, "Thestrange thing was this, As you spoke, my deformed face fell off like a veil, and my body, like a cloak, was lifted from me. At the same moment, I had the power of being outside of myself, of looking down on myself, and I was -very beautiful. I was not proud, but I was glad. I drank in a whole fountain of peace at every breath. At that instant, I began to float farther and farther from you; but as I went, I heard, oh I such a sweet voice I say-  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7984-00000005"/> 8            THE TAXIDERMST. ing: 'Again I Again I You shall meet again I ' As you came into the room, I awoke. And I have dared to uncover my whole soul to you, Orloff Ruric- son, because those words are still in my ears. We shall meet againI And when we meet, I shall be beautiful/'  4With all my -respect for Miss Brentnall, it was impossible for me not to feel that she was raving. Indeed, from this very belief I took hope. I had seldom heard of cases like hers, in which patients, almost in the very last hour, continued to be delirious. I therefore, doubted the doctor's diagnosis, and persuaded myself that, since she had not arrived at the lucid interval pre- ceding death, she was not so near it as he suspected. ' Comforting myself with the assurance that I should see her well again, or at least, that there was no immediate danger, I went down to my shop in the Bowery, leaving orders to send for me immediately, if any change took place in Miss Brentnall. 'After transacting the business of my trade, all day, I came back earlier than usual at evening, greatly depressed in spirits, but without any idea that I had seen my friend for the last time. As I put my latch-key into the door of the boarding-house, it opened. I saw the pale, frightened face of Martha, the nurse. She was just coming out after me. Miss Brentnall was dead. 'And again I was alone in the world.' II.-THE FLICCKER'S CHAPTER. 'THERE was a quiet funeral where I was the only mourner. There were days of loneliness succeeding, in which it seemed to me that the small isthmus by which I had been for a year attached to my fellow-men, had been suddenly covered by the rising of a dark, cold tide; that I was an islander again, and the only one. ' There was a will to be proved in the Surrogate's Court. Miss Brentnall's nurse and the landlady had witnessed it. I thought this strange at first, re- membering what a friend the dead had been to me; but my surprise at not being a witness was soon supplanted by the greater one of being sole legatee. 'There was a monument to be placed over the dead. To every detail of it I attended personally. I remember how heavy even that- simple little shaft seemed to me, how much too heavy for a head that had borne so much of heaviness through life. Then I thought of her expression 'bird-resurrection,' of her perfect faith in the coming of better things; and if the monument had been a pyramid, I would have known that it could not press her down. ' It is, one of my eccentricities that I fear good-fortune; not bad-fortune, at all. For I have seen so much of it, that it only looks to me like a grimmer kind of father, coming to wake his over-slept son and tell him that unless he leaps from his feather-bed, and that right, suddenly, the time for every thing good in-life will have gone-by. I fear good-fortune, because I am not sure that I shall use it well. It may carry me till it has dwarfed me; I may lie on its breast till I have lost my legs; then whisk I it may slip away from under me and leave me a lame beggar for,the rest of my life. ' I resolved, therefore, that I would not touch a farthing of my new property   THE TAXIDERMS?               9 until I had become qu' te familiar with the idea of owning it. It las all in stocks when I found it. I converted it into real-estate securities, and as fast as my interest came in, deposited it in the bank. Meanwhile, I supported my. self well upon the little shop; bought books, and laid something by. 'I was busy one morning at my stuffing-table in the back-room, when the bell over the street-door rang: and running into the front-shop, I found a new customer. He was a private bird-fancier, he told me, and had brought a special men, which he wished mounted for his cabinet. As he spoke, he slid back the cover from a box which he carried under his arm; and as I looked in,' expect. ing to see a dead bird, a live one hopped out and sat upon my finger. I declare that is very curious ' said the gentleman; ' the creature never did such a thing before! I have had it eight months without being able to domesticate it -in the slightest. It will not even eat or drink when any body is in the room; yet there it is sitting on your hand.' ' I had never seen such a bird before. It resembled the northern meadow- lark in size and shape; in hue, its wings were like the quail's, its breast ash- color, its tail mottled above, like the wings, and of a delicate canary yellow beneath. But the greatest beauty it possessed was a bright crimson crescent, covering the whole back of the head. ' What is this bird?' said I. "It is a  Flicker,' answered the gentleman. 'It was sent me by a friend liv- ing in Florida.' ' Why do n't you keep it alive? ' ' 'For the reason I 've told you. It's perfectly impossible to tame it. My children and I  have tried every means we can think of without success. If we confine it in a cage, it mopes all day and eats nothing; if we let it fly about the room, it sculks under the furniture as soon as we enter; if we take it in our hands, it screams and fights. There is a specimen of the execution it can do in:an emergency with that sharp, long bill I ' 'And my   customer showed me his finger, out of which a strip of flesh an inch long had been gouged as neatly as it could have been done with a razor. ' It is nothing but botheration, that confounded bird I ' he continued.  ' It does nothing but make muss and  litter about the house from morning till night; and for all our troubles, it never repays us with a single chirp. In- deed, I  do n't believe it has any voice.' 'Just then the Flicker, still sitting on my finger, turned up its big, brown eye to my face and uttered a soft, sweet gurgle, like a musical-glass. ' Good heavens I ' exclaimed the gentleman; 'it never did that before I ' ' Suppose you let me take it for a month or so,' said I; 'it seems to be fond f me, and perhaps I can tame it. I never felt so little like killing any bird in my life. We may make something of its social qualities yet.'  "Very well,' answered the new customer. 'Keep it for a month. I'll drop in now and then to see how its education is getting on.' ' You may hold me responsible for it, Sir,' I replied; and the gentleman left my shop. 'All day the FIicker staid by me as I  worked. Now it perched upon my shoulder, now on my head. At noon, when I   opened my basket, it took lunch  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7984-00000006"/> 10           THE TAXIDERMST. with me. When I whistled or sang, it listened until it caught the strain, and then put in some odd kind of an accompaniment. The compass and power of its voice was nothing remarkable, but the tone was as sweet as a wood-robin's. I could not be enough astonished with the curious little creature. ' Still, every kind of animal takes to me naturally. I accounted for the pre- vious wildness of the Flicker on the ground of mistaken management in the gentleman who owned it, and as a matter of professional pride, Determined to make something of the bird, were it only to show, like your Sam Patch, Tryon, that some things can be done as well as others. When I went home in the evening I took the Flicker with me, and made it a nest in an old cigar-box on my mantel-piece. 'The next morning, when I awoke, the bird was perched above me on the scroll of the head-boardl  Again I carried it down-town with me; again I brought it up in the evening. After that it was my companion every wherd. You will hardly imagin$ how it could become better friends with me than it did immediately upon our introduction. Yet our acquaintance grew day by day, and with our acquaintance the little being's intelligence. It had not been with me a fortnight before it knew its name. You may think it curious, per- haps unfeeling, but you know it was my only friend in the world, and in me- mory of the one who had lately held that place, I called it 'Brenta.' ' Brenta I ' I would say as I sat before my grate in the evening, and wherever the little creature might be, it would come flying to me with a joyful chirp, light on my finger, dance on the hearth-rug, eat out of my hand, or go through the pantomime of various emotions I had taught it. If I said, 'Be angry, Brenta,' it would scream, flap its wings, and fight the legs of the chair. 'Be sorry, Brenta,' and it would droop its little head, cower against my breast, and utter notes as plaintive as a tired child's. ' By the time the month was up, it could do almost any thing but talk. Its owner, who, to his great delight, had paid it several visits during the progress of its education, now came to take it home. ' (I have become very much attached to the little thing,' said I; 'won't you let me buy it of you? ' I I You should have asked me that when I first brought it,' was his answer ' You have made it too valuable for me to part with now. To show you how much I think it is worth, here is a ten-dollar piece for your services,' 'I took the money, feeling very much as if I were receiving the price of treason. ' If you ever change your mind,' said I, 'remember that I am always ready with a generous bid.' ' When we came to look for the Flicker, it was nowhere to be found. I could not believe it possible that it had heard and understood our conversa- tion, but other hypothesis to account for its disappearance was not at hand. After hunting every nook and corner of the shop, I forced myself into the traitorous expedient of luring it by my own voice. 'Brental' I called, and the poor creature instantly hopped ,out of my coat-pocket, climbed up to my shoulder, and nestled against my cheek. ' The little rascal I' exclaimed the gentleman.   THE TAXIDERMST. 'I could willingly have knocked him down I It was not until I had under- taken the business with my own hands that we could get the Flicker into the cage which the gentleman had brought with him. Even then, the poor thing continued clinging to my finger with claws which had to be loosened by force, and went out of my shop-door screaming piteously and beating itself against the bars of the cage. 'I had no heart for any thing the rest of the day. At night my room seemed lonelier than a dungeon. The very next morning, the owner of the bird came back with it in a terrible passion. ' You have been teaching the thing tricks!' was his first exclamation. "To be sure, said I mildly.  ' Was n't that what you wished me to do P' "Wrided you to do . '  To mope, and wail, and lie on the carpet like a dead chicken? Never to sing a note or eat a morsel? To peck at the hands that brought food, and-and   ' ' 'I am sure I cannot help it, Sir, if the bird has become attached to me, and mourns when away.' You 've taught the creature to do it I  Look at this finger, will you  another piece taken clean out of it! PieeeI say --steak, I mean I The bird's a  regular butcher I Here, kill the creature directly, and have it stuffed for my cabinet by this day week.' 'And as he set down the cage on the counter, the Flicker, with a joyful cry, jumped to the wicker-door, and tried to pick  a way out to me by its beak. ' There I you see what you 've done I Why do n't the wretch act so to me?' I  really can't say, Sir. Perhaps because I've had a great deal to do with birds, and naturally know how to manage them.' Well, I   do n't care. Stuff the thing, and I shall be able to manage it then myself.', ' May I   make you a repetition of my offer? If you have n't a toucan in your collection, there is a very fine' one I '1I give you for the Flicker, stuffed only last Saturday. Here's a young pelican--a still rarer bird. Or how would you like a flamingo?' "G ot 'em all,' replied the gentleman curtly. 'And if I had n't, I count the  Flicker.  Kill the thing, I say, and stuff it.' 'Just then the bird cast on me a  glance as imploring as ever looked out of human eye. For a thousand dollars I could not have tone the wrong. ' 'Really, Sir,' said I, 'I prefer not to take the job. I am very much at- tached to your bird. I cannot bear to kill it.' Pon my soul  I ' he exclaimed,  ' if that is n't pretty for a taxidermist ! I should suppose, to hear you talk, that you would faint at the sight of a dead sparrow! Well, you can get your courage up to stuff the bird, I suppose  As for the killing, I  'll d o that myself.' 'As the man said this, he thrust his hand into the cage, and caught the Flicker by the wing. With a sharp cry, his victim struck him again on the fin ger, enraging him mor e than ever. He opened his pen-knife, pulled the bird  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7984-00000007"/> 12            THE TAXIDERMST. out, drew the blade across its throat, and out of the cruel slash there poured, mingling with the blood, a bitter cry, like a woman's. I heard it, and every drop of my own blood returned to my heart. He let the bird drop upon the counter: it gave one hop, tumbled over in my hand, and its eye-lids slid shut. ' This day week, remember,' said the man, and went out of the shop, wip. ing his knife. ' I took up the bird, laid it in my neck, and, I am not ashamed to say, cried over it. "There are a good many things which may happen between now and this dlay week. I am not one of those people who regard every misfortune that occurs to an enemy the judgment of HEAVEN in their behalf. But I must say, that the event which occurred before that man's week was out, always seemed to me a direct blow from Nemesis. He was a very passionate fellow; subject to temporary fits of insanity. One of them came on in the morning while he was shaving, and he cut his own throat as he had the Flicker's. ' When his estate was settled, nobody thought of the bird. I inclosed the ten dollars he had given me for its education in an anonymous note to his executors, simply stating that my conscience demanded it; and having thus quieted that organ, kept the Flicker for myself. With a daguerreotype of Miss Brentnall's, found among a parcel of papers labelled, ' To be burned up,' and upon which alone, of all the parcel, I could not persuade myself to execute her will, I put the stuffed bird by. When I was too lonely to dare to be utterly alone, I went to the trunk, where they were preserved and looked at them. "I.--THE MARMOSET'S CHAPTER. AFTER the loss of my second only friend, a painful change came over me. I had risen from the shock of Miss Brentnall's death with an elasticity which surprised even myself. Partly for the reason that my constitution was better by several less months of anxiety, grief, and application to business. Partly because I felt assured that, as she said, we should some time or other meet again. ' When the Flicker died, I felt that this only thing hitherto left to love me, could never reappear. The kind heart of the woman would beat again; the kind heart of the bird no more forever. And strangely enough, the whole sorrow that I had passed through for Miss Brentnall's loss revived, and I went about my day's wor] bearing the weight of a two-fold melancholy. 'The first thing that the bird-fancying public knew-indeed almost the first thing I knew myself, so abstracted, so moody was H a paragraph ap- p peared in the morning papers, to the effect that the celebrated Taxidermist and viarian Professor, Orloff Ruricson, was about to close his business, and make a voyage to Europe, Asia and Africa, from which parts he hoped to return in two or three years, with a large and interesting collection of rare animals, to establish a Natural History Museum. 'I had caused the appearance of this notice myself; but when I read it, felt quite as surprised by it as any body. In nerve and mind I was so worn out,   THE TAXIDERMST.            13 that although thoroughly resolved to make the move, the consolidation of the purpose into such a fixed form shocked me. ' When the novelty of the idea passed off, I disposed of all my stock to vari- ous amateurs who knew me and had every disposition to help me by paying large prices. I put the thirty thousand dollars I was now worth into such a shape that I could get its increase in regular remittances; packed the bird, the daguerreotype, and a small wardrobe, and took passage by barque for Genoa. 'At sun-rise one Monday morning, the barque's yawl took me out to her anchorage. As I went up the ladder at:the side, I heard an opera-air playing on board, and when I reached the deck, the first thing that met my eyes was an Italian grinder, with his organ and monkey. ' ' Is that man going the voyage with us? ' I asked the captain. ' 'Yes, Sir,' he replied; ' but he shan't play without permission after we get to sea. He's a Genoese, who has made enough in this country to keep a fruit- stall in his own, and so he's going home.' ' Home! He had a home, and was going to it I I would have handed him my bank-book--taken his monkey and organ -to be able to say that; I As the tug hitched fast to us and we began walking down toward the Nar- rows, I crossed to the other side of the ship, that I might take a look at the fortunate man. ' Certainly, I said to myself, Fortune is blind. He had a home; but he was one of the most ill-favored rascals I ever laid my eyes on. No body would have taken him for a Genoese--the New-Englander of Italy--rather for a Romanesque cut-throat, or a brigand of the mountain, who had found his stiletto or his carbine good for only the slowest kind of shilling and taken to the nimble six-pence of the hand-organ, on the principle that honiesty was the best policy. You have seen a thousand pen-and-pencil pictures of the fellow, and need no description of him from me. ' As I stood beside him at the bulwarks, his monkey leapt upon me. ' Pardon, good gentleman,' said the Italian with an abject smirk, and gave a jerk to the chain that brought back the little animal flying. II Never mind that,' said I; ' let him come to me. I am fond of. monkeys: I would like to look at him.'        ' ' As it pleases, then,' replied the Italian, with another smirk, and loosed the chain again. ' Go, Beppo ' 'Beppo needed no command, but jumped instantly upon my arm and laid his cheek upon my bosom. As I patted his head, I examined him curiously, and found him the most beautiful little monkey in the world.. A Marmoset with a great brown, tender eye like a gazelle's; a face which varied its ex- pression constantly without ever degenerating into the brutal leer of the com- mon ape; a winning, confiding mien of head and hand that was human, child- like; and a soft coronal of golden fur around his little skull, that added still more to his baby-like look, giving him the appearance of some mother's favor- ite, dressed for a walk in a bonnet of down. I do n't know how I could have- been guilty of the folly of becoming attached to the little fellow, after all the lessons of warning my life had taught me. But I did take a great fancy to  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7984-00000008"/> "           THE TAXIDERMST. him. Never a day passed during the whole voyage, in which he did not get many a tit-bit from my hands. He spent far more of the time with me than with his own master, and before long obeyed me with a hearty good nature, which he never thought of showing toward that musical brigand. ' One sunny afternoon; when we were three weeks out, the captain, the grinder and myself stood upon the forecastle-deck, trying to make out a sail just visible on the horizon ahead of us. As usual, Beppowas cutting his pranks about me. For a moment he would sit demurely on my shoulder and ihold his tail to his eye in mimicry of the captain's eye-glass. A second more, and he would be sitting in the fore-top. The next, and he came sliding down a halliard to his old perch. These antics interfered with our look-out, and I put my hand into my pocket to feel for something which might keep him still. Finding neither prune, nor nut, nor string, but only the purse which I always carried there, I drew it out and opened it, to look for a copper. As I com- mitted this incautious act, I saw the eyes of the Italian cast a sidelong, sly glance at the gold that shone there, and I shut the clasp with an uncomfortable sense of having been very silly. At the same moment, he stole away, like a cat, to the fore-stays, and pretended to be more earnestly interested than any of us in the sail. 'The nights grew still warmer and warmer as we sailed on. The cabin be- came so close, that I ordered the steward to bring my mattress upon deck, and usually slept there under a shawl, unless we had rain. 'I had lain down at about half-past eleven, upon one night in particular, utterly fatigued, sick at heart, despairing. As the tall masts nodded past the stars--the stars rather than the masts seemed moving--and in my heart I believed that even heaven itself was not permanent; that all things flickered and danced, and passed away as earthly hope had passed from my heart; nothing was fixed, certain, and to be striven for. Finally, I only wished to sleep. ' Let me die this temporary death of slumber,' said I; ' there is happi- ness therein, and therein only.' I was more of a Lord Byron at that instant; more of a moral desperado; less of a Thomas Carlyle, a Goethe, sanguine Yankee, who believes that the best way to get rid of misery is to suffer and mork out, if you fall, always to fall on your feet and scramble out, than I had ever been in my life, Messrs. Tryon and Bonenfant I So, said I, let me go to sleep. 'Would you believe it, that confounded little Beppo would not hear of such a thing 1 Over .my face this minute, over my legs the next; now tumbling down on my breast from a line; now, as the sailors say, working Tom Cox's traverse, up one hatchway and down the other, past my side, ' I could not get a wink of sleep. I tossed and I tumbled; I swore and I grumbled. I called Beppo to me, and for the first time without success. 'I was just about going after Luigi, his master, when I saw that person creeping to me in the shadow of the mizzen-mast. By the high cove of the after-hatch, I was quite hid from the stern, and the only person who happened to be there, the second mate, could see Luigi no more than me. ' At that instant the monkey gave me a tweak of the hair that nearly made   THE TAXIDERMST.             15 me scream -out, and then ran away noiselessly forward. Luigi crept on and on. As he drew nearer, I could perceive a stiletto in, his hand. Its blade gleamed faintly now and then in the star-light, so indistinctly that at first it seemed like a trailing white ribbon. ' I did not believe his first intention was to kill me. That would have been absurd as well as cruel. So I lay still and let him come close. I feigned my. self fast asleep and snored heavily. ' He knelt at my side, and holding the knife over my heart with one hand, felt with the other in my pocket. Still I slept away for dear life. He found the purse: drew it out with a slow, gentle motion, and crept forward again on his hands and knees, thanking his saints in a whisper. I was on his back be. fore he could turn around. -He was lithe, but he was feeble, and I had him pinioned, prone upon his face, with the purse in his hand and the thanksgiving in his mouth, while it was yet only half-changed to a curse. Thus I forced from him both the stiletto and the purse, -and threw the one over-board at the same time that I returned the other to my pocket. Then I arose, and we stood' up face to face. qu Shall I have you hanged at the yard-arm in half-an-hour?' was my first question. 'The Italian looked me full in the face, his olive cheeks were like chalk, his lips quivered, but he did not speak. And then, as if suddenly understanding the cause of his failure, he ran forward to the fore-stay, where the marmoset was clinging and chattering. 'I hurried after him. Catching him by the shoulder, I whispered in his ear: 'If one hair of Beppo's head is hurt, you are a dead man before you can say your prayers. You came after my money. You are a  villain, but you shall have it-two gold pieces, ten dollars, at least--if you sell him to me on the spot. Is Beppo mine, on these conditions? If he is n't, I will arouse the crew, and you shall dangle aloft before the next watch is set. Yesorno?' "You shal have the monkey,' replied the Italian, with another of his in. fernal smirks. ' You shall have him, but the gentleman will not find him good fortune.' The devil take you and your fortune H If he b ngs me no better fortune than you deserve--and for the same reason--I shall wish, and not wait, to die.' So I  brought the monkey aft, and made  Luigi acknowledge him mine, while I  counted out the ten dollars, in the presence of the second mate. 'After that night, warm as it might be, A u will readily believe that I slept in the cabin. Beppo nestled by me, occupi a ." much of the berth as his little form required; and I declare to you, that had he 'needed it all I would have given it to him, and stretched myself on the floor, so warm an affection had I for the creature who had saved my money: possibly my life. 'At that time, perhaps you will say because I was young and visionary, 1 often believed that Beppo knew what he had been the means of doing for me. At this day I shall be still insaner in your eyei;for I hold that he was not only the   sens, but the intentional aget. I m ust stop. I am forerunning my story. NW  ?t i,  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7984-00000009"/> 16           THE TAXIDERMST. ' It was amazing how I improved as soon as I had something to love I I be. came so strong, so hearty, that I was quite ashamed to think of having aban- doned America for my health; and meditated going back with the barque's return voyage. Nothing but the presence on board of that cursed Luigi pre- vented my spirits from being better than since I could remember. 'We reached Genoa, and anchored in Quarantine. My trunk was on. deck, and in all respects I was ready to go ashore. Already the infernal Italian had taken his seat in the health-officer's boat; and, with his elbow resting on his organ, looked upat me over the gunwale. Beppo, for very joy of seeing land again, had climbed clear to the main truck, and was chattering audibly as he whisked his tail. " All ready, BeppoI ' I cried: ' come down, boy I '  'Inh is haste at hearing my voice, as he tumbled head over heels -down the main shrouds, for the first time in my life that I ever saw a monkey do such a thing; he missed his hold on a ratline, and tumbled into the water of the harbor. I sprang to the side, and called to the oarsmen of the boat: I Save that monkey, and you shall have - whatever you ask,! ' Fool! I was talking English, and every man of them was an Italian 1 A language I had some understanding of, but could not speak. "What says the gentleman?' asked one of the boat-crew, in his own tongue. 'And then I heard that olive-skinned brigand wretch, the organ-grinder, reply to the speaker: ' He says the beast who fell overboard is sick of the small-pox, and you must not touch him.' 'As he made this answer he turned around to me with one of his diabolical smirks, kissed his hand to me, spit at the drowning Beppo, then asked me blandly: L Did I not tell the good gentleman his buying would be bad for- tune? Are we settled of accounts, good gentleman? ' ' I to hear this I I to look over the side; hear my last friend screaming his poor wordless agony; see him look up at me with that supplicating child's eye of his; see him fighting the water despairingly with his little unlearned hands, then go down in a bubbling circle out of sight; I who could not swim a stroke I 'The captain, seeing my distress, humanely put his own boat after the poor creature. With the boat-hook a sailor brought him up after he had gone down for the last time., And thus they laid him on the deck at my feet. I lifted him up; his child eyes were closed, and the golden crown of his fur lay malted and dripping over them. I tried to warm him in my bosom. I laid my hand on his heart: it had stopped. 'Beppo was dead. The Marmoset whom mature had given, only of all, to love the man I 'And I went into Quarantine at Genoa, once more alone in the world.' Ciel! and vat you do vith zat cursed Italian?' 'I? Nothing. Ten years afterward I saw him rowing in the galleys at Marseilles. He knew me; I knew him. He smirked as of old, but with such very visible teeth that I was glad he was chained; and passed on without fvena asking the overseer his crime.   THE, TAXIDERMST.            17 IV.--THE YOUNG MAIDEN'S CHAPTER. 'MY wanderings, dating from the day I landed at Genoa, would fill with their narrative a book far larger than ' Livingstone's Travels.' I journeyed over all the traversable regions of Africa; in India I have been wherever the foot of the white man has trodden; I spent a: year and. a half in China; almost as long in Syria; and I went every where over the continent of Europe. Then I passed six months in Sweden; most of that time living at my native town, Jonpoping, until at last the sound of my mother's tongue spoken by., stranger mouths became absolutely unbearable to me, and I left the country never to return. I will see Great Britain, I said. No better place for that purpose, at least to begin with, than London. So I went there; and, with all the curiosities I had collected in my vagabond life, opened a shop as Exhibitor and Taxidermist, in Piccadilly. . ' By this time, you will perceive, I had quite abandoned my original idea of returning to America to open a museum. It takes no longer for the world in general, or the world of New-York, to forget its largest man, than for a heap- ing measure of grain to close up the gap after a hand is withdrawn. And I was a long way from the conceit of fancying myself even a large man. Pro- bably, I said to myself there are a dozen in my place by this time. I will not go back to revive a name wiped out; it is at least more entertaining to stay here and try chalking out a new one. If I fail, why, the remittances still come regularly. ' So up went the old sign on a fresh board: ' Orloff Ruricson, Taxidermist and Aviarian Professor.' In about three months from the opening of the es- tablishment, the collection was a little more than self-supporting, and the Tax- idermy throve at the rate of ten guineas a week. I got some favorable critiques in the Times; some body called me the Minor Zoological Gardens; and gradu- ally my aviarianism came into play. Lord Crinkum consulted me about his Chinese pheasants, and Lord Crankum got my general views on fighting-cocks. The Honorable Miss Dingleton, like Mr. Pecksniff, only with more money to bestow on the object, th6ught she would like to see my ideas of a grotto. I gave it to her, and of course every alderman's wife must have me fussing, about her cobble-stones out in what she called a suburban wilier. That 's the great beauty of art in England, looked at in the paying light; the moment you're so fortunate as to get a lord by the nos e, you lead all Cockneydom whithersoever you will. It's a country where every body shuts his eyes, and grabs the next bigger man by the coat-tail. So, on the whole, I got along.' ' That was all very well, looked at in the paying light, as you say,'inter- rupted John Tryon, ' but you must have been terribly lonely during the long winter evenings. Did n't you have any body to speak to: any body to love?' 'Nobody. I had learned the misery of that by lessons enough, I should think. Even in the desert I never made a pet of my camel, and most people do that, to the -extent, at least, of complimenting the lovely beast upon his ' patience. I had nothing to care for and cared for nothing. I was now thirty years old, you see, and had travelled. o   &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7984-00000010"/> 18            THE TAXIDERMST. ' I had kept the shop in Piccadilly for a year. I stood one morning, at the expiration of that period, in a room of the back-shop, where I prepared specie mens, and was consulted. My clerks had just taken down the shutters, and were chattering to each other behind the counter. I was pensive that morn- ing, a mighty unusual thing for me, and their gabble disturbed me. I medi- tated calling out to them to be still, when the shop-door. opened, the front-door looking on the street, and some one said: 4 Please, Sir, can you give me any work?' ' Good heavens I I started to my feet, and yet seemed in such a dream that I could scarcely move them after I was erect. Who spoke? It was a low, sweet, woman's voice, the like whereof Ihad not heard for nine years! Not that it was low, or sweet, or a woman's, not that it was all these to- gether, but that it was the voie. '( Glet out with you, beggar I' answered the chattering clerks, with unani- mous fierceness; and I heard the front shop-door shut slowly, as by a tired, feeble hand., ' In a second more and she would be gone; I should never see her again I 'That thought awakened me, and gave wings to my feet. I dashed through ithe shop; my clerks looking at me as if they thought I had suddenly gone :mad. I jerked -the door open, and saw a lithe girl's figure moving wearily :away among the hurrying crowd: her back toward me. ' Who asked' for work?' I called out aloud. 'Among the few that turned to look was this lithe figure. She turned hastily, -anxiously, deprecatingly, and again I heard that-wonderful voice. "It was I, Sir.' "Come into the shop, if you please. Let us talk about it.' You are not vexed with me, Sir? ' ' As the girl said this she cast her great brown eyes upon me so piteously, so helplessly, seeming so intensely to fear displeasure, yet so wistfully to beg help, that all at once there flashed before me the harbor of Genoa I I saw it ifor an instant as distinctly as we now see the Kaaterskill Clove; saw the vil- lainous Italian smirking across his organ; saw the glassy, shining waters of ithe Mediterranean; and the drowning face of Beppo going down therein; witl those same eyes in it! "Vtexed with you? With you? GOD knows I am not l' was my first wild exclamation, as soon as. this strange phantasmagoria passed by; and I ,saw Piccadilly, and its crowd, and the slender girl, again, standing there un- cared for, like myself, in the great ocean of London being. ' Come in, I say! Come in I For the love of GOD, come in 1 ' I continued passionately, reckless who heard me. ' Work, food, money, help, any thing, every thing I I will give you all.' ' This I said beseechingly, yet neither this nor the passionate command did the girl, timid as she was, seem to regard as at all strange or out of place. She only came confidingly toward me, put her hand in mme, and I led her into the back-shop, while the chatterers stared. ' I bade her take off her faded bonnet, and sit down. As she obeyed, her golden brown hair caught on a pin in the bonnet behind; its soft, well-grown   THE TAXIDERMST.'             19 mass lifted from her neck, and there I beheld, close where the brown joined the white, a small red crescant mark reaching almost from ear to ear I ' I seemed to be wandering through a chain of dreams. I tried to speak, but in vain. To think, but as vainly. She disengaged the bonnet, and let it droop upon her shoulders. Her face, thus disclosed, was the most beautiful array of human features, flushed through by the light of the most beautiful human soul, I ever saw, or mused of; or believed in, in my life I 'She sat in the chair opposite me. As for me, I gazed and gazed. 'Mod- estly inviting questions, she looked me frankly in the eyes; and then, as in wonder that I did not speak, threw her head' backward, and perused my face curiously. This posture elevated her chin.  I was about to say something, but just then I saw under that chin another crimson *mark, the slenderest of slender lines, as if thefinest knife-point dipped in blood had been drawn 'clear across the throat by a nervous hand.  I durst not say to myself what I was reminded of by that. , Not even to think of it at all. I half-feared that I had become insane, rubbed my forehead, and kept repeating: 'Oh I it is only her bonnet-strings tied too tightly, that is all! ' I would not trust myself with questioning her then. Not a word of any kind did I speak to her, except to say gently, that she might consider herself my apprentice in the art of bird-stuffing; and that all her necessities should be provided for. 'I had a little bed made for her in the ro6m of the old Yorkshire woman, who minded my solitary establishment for me. She was an orphan, so she said afterward; and had walked all the way from the Stafford Potteries, where her only relative, an aunt, was just dead: hoping to find work in London, that might keep her from the street. She was eighteen years of age, and had never known father or mother. 'Once more I had a living creature to feel an interest in, to become attached to. Whatever was mysterious in her arrival, her appearance, or her voice, I dismissed from my mind as mere curious coincidences, at once too frivolous, too perplexing to be followed up. There was the real substantial fact: a girl without home or friends. Now what was to be done with her? 'I settled that question gradually day by day. H taught her, in the day- time, to help me. at my specimen-table; in the evening, to read and write. The rapidity with which she caught by the right end, and made her own every new process, either of brain or fingers, was astonishing. She was my constant wonder and delight. So imitative yet so original; so talented but so modest withal; so bright and sportive, so docile and grateful; she soon became my right hand and right eye in all I had to do.   - 'As soon as I had dressed her presentably, the Clerks saw her superiority as they could not through old clothes, and did it unquestioning reverence. But for this reverence I verily believe they would have come in a body, and thrown themselves at her feet, entreating her to take her pick within the first month after she was domesticated with me. For they were all desperately in' love with her: devouring her with their eyes as she went in and out among them so modestl and yet so loftily, like a queen in disguise.  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7984-00000011"/> 20            THE TAXIDERMST. I Well, Idid not wonder; I could forgive them. For, six months after she had entered my shop-door, the homeless wayfarer, I awoke to the fact that I was in love with her myself. For the first time in all the days-of my man- hood, did I know what it was to feel a woman wrought into the texture of my life, so that pulling her away seemed an endless pain to look forward to; and before I knew that it had happened. And that combination of circum- stances only, as I view it, is adequate to constitute love, on which marriage may be honorably founded. 'As soon is I knew that I loved Bessie Cartwright--thatwas her name--I began to torture myself with the question whether I ought to tell her of it yet. Whether, if I did so, her simple heart, out(f mere gratefulness, would not instantly give itself up as a matter of debt and honor to the man whom she regarded only in the light of a benefactor. And I had rather have any thing happen than this, my own loneliness till I died even, than this, so galling to me if I discovered it when it was too late, so ruinous to every thing that was best im her young growing womanhood. 'As in the old days, it was my custom still to look at the memorials of my lost friends, When times went hard with me, and my spirits fell. So, one evening, after I had been musing painfully in my room for a couple-of hours, I took from my battered old trunk Miss Brentnall's portrait, the Flicker, and the Marmoset, which I had embalmed after his death in the harbor of Genoa. '1 ranged them on my table, and with a feeling of mournfult pleasure gazed from one to the other, dwelling upon all the past which they recalled. 'As I sat thus employed, I heard Bessie's tap at the door; I called, ' Come in 1 ' and .she entered, with-her reading-book for the evening's lesson. Seeing the unusual array upon my table, she asked me: ' What I working still?' ' (No; not working, Bessie,' I replied; ' thinking.' "May I see who that is?' said she artlessly, pointing to the daguerreo- type. "'Oh! certainly. Though you must not laugh at it. It is a very homely lady, but a very good one; and, while she lived, my dearest friend.' So i handed it to her. ' She-bent her brown head down to the shaded drop-light on my table, and held, the, portrait close to it.- I watched her to see the effect of that strange world-wronged face on the beautiful, Heaven-favored one. ' I saw Bessie COrtwright grow pale as death I Her eyes became fixed like a cataleptic person's. But her head moved, from the portrait to the Flicker, from the Flicker to the Martioset. The portrait fell from her hand, she grasped hurriedly at the table, and then fell to the floor. "Dead: dead like the rest! ' said I, with a fierce coldness; ' and because I have loved her.' ' I pulled the shade from the drop-light, and drew it to the edge of the table, so that the light fell full on the prostrate girl. I called her by name, and got no answer. I loosened her dress, and in doing so pushed the heavy knot of her brown hair away from her neck. That scarlet crescent" glowed -there in the midst of the marble whiteness, like a flame I   THE TAXIDERMST.             21 'I turned her upon her back, and beneath her chin saw thie s ender cxihnson line, burning also brighter than ever, while: all the throat was deadly pale. ' Bessie I Bessie I speak to me once, only once more.' I spoke passionately at her ear. ' Still no answer. I looked in agony at the dead things which had. once been mine; saw plainest of all the Flicker; and again that strange suspicion which I had felt the first day I ever saw the girl, awoke in my brain, 'I bent my mouth to her ear, and softly said: 'Brenta I' At that instant her great dark eyes opened, she read my face wistfully, and then her lips murmured: ' Orloff, dear Orloff! I told -Yu I would meet you again; I have kept my word.'                             . ' It was the voice that became silent ten years before in the sick-room next my own! "Miss Brentnall I ' I exclaimed, not knowing what I said. "Orloff, dear Orloff I' replied the voice, once more from the lips of Bessie Cartwright. 'And then the blood came rushing back to the young girl's face. Timidly she sat up, passed her hand across her eyes, and said faintly: "Oh I I have had sucMh a dream I ' ' What was it, dear child?' I asked. ' I thought that picture you showed me was I. Then I felt myself dying. You were by me till all the room grew dark. I hardly remember what came then; but I have had, oh I so many strange thoughts, and been in so, many strange places I I thought I was killed with a little knife: Tw'as/on the sea; I was close by a great town that rose from the water's side i I was drowning' then I was myself again in the old dress I wore when I came to you; then I seemed to be all things at once, and you called me a name I had heard before, when I lay in the bed dying; and oh I forgive me, Sir, I called you by your Christian name, Qrloff, dear Orloff I I said, do forgive me: I will never do it again.' "You must do something else than that,' said I, no longer awe-stricken and trembling,- for in a moment the mystery of my life had parted like a fog, and I saw its meaning beyond in the clearest of heaven's twilight. ' Something else than that, Bessie. You must never call me by any other name than dear Or- loff I Can you call me that? For I love yo /  GOD only knows how I love you. Can you?' 'The girl looked at me with parted lips; caught her breath quickly;. hid her face in my bosom; and once more after all those years the beloved voice, knowing what it said, replied: 'Orl1 dear Orloff.' ' Bessie Cartwright is my wife. Not until years afterward did I tell her. the meaning of her dream; i nor how through lives and deaths she had followed me to save and claim her own. She knows it now; we both keep it for the grateful wonder of our prayers; a mystery like all mysteries had- we but the  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7984-00000012"/> 22           THE LITTLE PEASANT. key, with its grandi beneficent meaning, unmeaning, contemptible only to those who read it wrong or not at all.,' 'And you do mean to tell to me zat ze beautiful lady you have now espouse, be vonce in ze body ofze vare ugly woman, ze red-head bird vat you call him, and ze marmosette; you mean to say to me zat?' "'d like to ask that question too,' said John Tryon. ' I mean to tell you both, answered Orloff Ruricson, 'that you can put your oown interpretation on mty facts. Also, that if you ever break our confi- dence in telling my history with its proper names, then good-by to your friend- ship with Orloff Ruricson.' I have been permitted to state the facts witut the names. Let me also be permitted to state them withoult my interpretation. THE WIVES OF THE POETS. BY THOMAS BAILEY ALDRICH. 'By the grace of GOD we are here assembled.' ON examining the biographies of literary men, the reader cannot but be o struck by the obscure part which the woife plays in the drama of such lives. Her history, as a general thing, is unwritten. The encyclopedias record the date of her marriage, and sometimes condescend to say when she died. Much more than this we are seldom permitted to know. Her liege-lord neglected to write her epitaph, however glad or sorry he may have been to have the oppor- tunity of doing so. That the wives of poets should have so often escaped the celebrity which keeps their husbands forever young, cannot always be pleasantly explained. In- many cases they have been inferior women, unable, through a lack of in- tellectual sympathy, to reach that enchanted sphere wherein moves most that is holiest and enduring;of the literary man . if they have loved, it has been with the heart wholly, and with the brain not at all.' Poets, it is said, require a two-fold love--one for themselves and one for their art. When the fool in the play asks the lover how tall his mistress is, the lover neatly replies: ' Her height, prithee? As high as my heart I ' When 'an author's wife is also as high as his brain, 'it is then truly that the intercourse of the sexes becomes the most refined pleasure; ' and, ten to one, she laughs and weeps and is deli- cious forever in a novel, or dwells, with all her graces, in the rhythm of a lyric that perpetually sweetens the lips of the world. She so far fails in answering the requirements of her station who is shut by incapacity from her husband's demesne of thought. Such unions are fire-side tragedies-the more tragic,   THE WIVES OF. THE POETS.            23 inasmuc! as the actors are Souls rather than bodies, the more hopeless because the agony of the play isgpurely intellectual. For one reason or another, the wives of the poets, as a class, are a sadly ne. glected group of ladies: in proof of which I am cruelly bent on making a live poet bear testimony. My witness is Mr. R. H. Stoddard,* who has recently appeared as the editor of a volume of that peculiar kind of poetry in which he himself excels as an author. The fact is (and it is rather a pathetic fact, if you wish to think so) literary men have been very chary in their praises of married life - especially the poets who are popularly supposed to be the legal guardians of the blind little boy with the bow and arrows. In looking over Mr. Stoddard's 'Loves and Heroines of the Poets'-the most faultless collection of love-poetry in the language--an ill-natured person might smile at the meagre number of poems which' the poets have addressed to their own  wives. Even these few poems, with eight or ten exceptions, lack the flavor and felicity which characterize their authors on other less laudable occasions. They are not the   real sparkling champagne, but very'still Catawha.'  If the editor had restricted his selections to readable 'Stanzas Addressed to my  Wife,' he might have put all his material in a pocket-book. He would have found few such noble verses as Bishop King's ' Exequy.' For those poets who   have made themselves famous  by singing of Chloe and Amaryllis, whom they did not marry, are generally as mute as moulting robins concerning Maria and Clementina, whom they did marry. From this point of view the lady-love appears to have been every thing, and the wife-nothing. 'THonm ypn, if LAIvA had been PETBARca'S wife, He would have written sonnets all his life ' Now, for my part, I am cynical enough to believe that he would have written much better sonnets, and may be an epic or two, by way of variety. It requires something more terrible than a  noble woman to spoil the verses of a decent poet. One of the chief pleasures in contemplating the lives of the old English singers, is to know that some of those master-spirits were blessed, in their rough pilgrimage, by gracious wives, whom they loved, though, they neither dedicated folios nor always wrote flowery poems to them. Perhaps they held domestic love too sacred to sing about it. At all events, they sang but seldom, and then not always excellently well; In Mr. Stoddard's volume we have one hundred and twenty-six poAts. Of these one hundred and twenty-six, sixty are married men. Of these sixty about thirty have sung the praises of their wives. And of these thirty only about fifteen have sung any thing worth the singing. There may be some slight error in these figures, for I am distinguished for my horror of mathe- matics; but the statement is sufficiently correct for the occasion. The limits assigned to a  magazine article will not allow me to discuss in detail the ladies of these sixty poets. But what a curious history they would * T    LOVES AND  eROINm S or THE  POr . Edited by R CIARD HBNRY STODDARD. With Illustra tions by Cats. A. BARRY. New-York: DERBY AND JACKSON. Quarto: pp. 450.  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7984-00000013"/> 24          THE WIVES OF THE POETS. make I' How their stories would involve kings, courtiers, beggars, fools, and knaves I What royal women some of them were, what spendthrifts, what sweet-tongued creatures, what scolds I How, some of them ruined their lords with no other. charm than the crimson thread of their lips. It is odd that Disraelin in his I Calamities of Authors,' neglects, as I believe he does, to men- tion woaon. - The shrews of literature, with a minute account of the life, suf- ferings and death' of hen-pecked authors, would make a long and comical chapter. But a longer, though not So comical a chapter might be furnished by ihe pale ghosts of neglected wives. As I lean over my friend's book, what phantoms from the dark night without, from old, mossy English kirk-yards, hover about me in the dim gas-light of my4celamber, each whispering some strange fale of cruelty and neglect, telling oft nvalued loveliness and patience and devotion I ,     t OFr love that never fgund his earthly close, What sequel? ' Ah 1 yiou poor little women, some of you have been shamefully not taken care oft Dante wove such a wreath of laurels for Beatrice, that the beauty of the Florentine woman, with her blood-red dress, has stood the test of five hundred years. The wife of the gloomy Tuscan is the merest shadow beside her im- mortal rival. Howard, Earl of Surrey, wraps the Lady Elizabeth Gerald in a pretty name, and pens sentimental sonnets to her eye-brows--just as if his own wife had no eye-brows, and very charming ones I But he seems to have no music left for his cousin Lady Frances Vere, to whom he was betrothed in his boyhood. The elaborate Sir Philip Sidney wasted his anapests and dactyles on a pair of restless court fire-flies, to the neglect of a lovely woman, the pink of whose little-finger nail was worth a whole race of such female fops. And Shakspeare, too. Shakspeare has a sweet mysterious lady. embalmed in. his sonnets, like a fly in amber. There is not a beautiful flower, according- to the bard, which does not steal its shape, its color, or its perfume from her per- fection. The stars are lighted by her eyes. She causes day and night by her coming and going. In her praises he makes mellifluous words fall into line and sweep on with triumphant music. But what of Mrs. Shakspeare?-the gentle Anne Hathaway I He leaves no immortal verse to her, only an old bed- stead in his last will and testament I ' Milton has three wives, and writes one sonnet on Mrs. Milton No. 2 - after he buries her I ' METHOUGHT I saw my late espoused saint Brought to me, like ALCESTIS from the grave.' We are all acquainted with Mr. Waller's Amoret, and Saccharissa who gave him a cold shoulder, 'as he deserved, for he was an insincere piece; ,we all know his reply to Saccharissa when in after-life she, in her rouge and powder, asked him:                         ' 'Mr. Waller, when will you write such fine verses to me again? ' 'O Madam I' replied that gallant old boy, 'when your ladyship is as young again.'   THE WIVES OF THE POETS.            25 We know these things, and a great many more not so much to the credit of this sparkling, velvet butterfly; but we have not had the,. pleasure of meeting either of his two wives in the society of the muses. I fancy he did not trouble himself much about them; but he made the brides of other-people famous. This hasty and by no means complete list of celebrated ' loves' and unknown wives, is growing too long; but-I must add to it one wife and one love. more pitiful than all - Stella and Vanessa, 'the two ill-starred ladies rendered his- torical personages by Swift's verse and Swift's cruelty. Mr. Stoddard has told their story very pathetically in his note on Swift. These two women lavished on the savage Dean such pure idolatry as the world has seldom witnessed. By what wizard spell he possessed himself of these unfortunate hearts, it is difficult to surmise. For yeai9he, held their souls in his hand, tossing them to-and-fro as a conjurer tosses the gilded balls. To Stella he was married, though the marriage was not publicly acknowledged, and the parties never met except in the presence of a third person. Vanessa, after cherishing for eight years the hope that Swift would make her his wife, could I longer bear the suspense which was undermining her health: she wrote to her tival, pray- ing she would tell her whether or not she was Swift's wife. Stella immediately answered in the affirmative. After suffering such mortification and misery as would have driven any man but Swift to suicide, Vanessa died in resentment and despair. Four years after this, Stella lay on her death-bed. For four- teen she had waited in vain for love to dawn in the bosom of this poor wretch. It is said that a brief conversation then took place between them relative to their unproclaimed marriage. Only Swift's reply was overheard. ' Well, my dear,' he said, ' it shall be acknowledged, if you wish it.' 'It is now too late,' said Stella, with a sigh. It waas too late. She died of lingering decline in January, 1728. 'After Stella's death,' says Mr. Stoddard, ' and probably after Swift's, one of her raven tresses came into the possession of an antiquary. It was wrapped'in paper and labelled, in Swift's hand-writing, ' Only a woman's hair." As I read tlis bitter page of secret history, spectral hands seem to turn over the leaves for me, and spectral fingers to rest sarcastically on the glitter- ing tropes and flowery nothings with which Swift garlanded his victims. I shall have to turn up my gas-light and read 'The Legend of Good Women,' and think of happy ones, to exorcise those complaining ghosts that come and go in the shadow of my book-case. The reader will remember the charming Lucy Herbert, who might have been a Duchess if she had not chosen to walk out of the purple and wed the poet Habbington, who sang her praises as maid and matron, and loved her, not- withstanding she was his wife I I will let a woman* say that 'his poems to Castara form one of the most elegant monuments genius ever raised to the memory of a wife.' The amiable and lovely woman whose early death drove Parnell, to destruction, should not be forgotten; nor Anne More, the wife of Dr. Donne, whose fidelity through poverty to death is loftier than any poetry, , Mrs. JAMEcON.  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7984-00000014"/> 26         TTHE WIVES OF THE POETS. certainly much loftier than any of the Doctor's. And later still is Lady -Lyttelton, whose fight from this world, in the flush of her youth and beauty, taught Lord Lyttelton the only noble number he ever uttered.  In times nearer-our own, we. recollect several poets whose lives have. been broken by the severing of these domestic ties which so many have worn but lightly. In view of these and similar cases, a witty French author once prepared an ingenious treatise in which he attempted to show why a literary man should not marry at all, He says that twenty poets are unhappy because their wives died, and twenty are wretched because their wives lived. In one case the hus. band trembles for fear his consort will leave him, and in the other--for fear that she won't I The humorist had proceede# thus far when the ingenuity of his own logic made'him an idiot, and he really completed the essay with a solemn protest against marriage I While we smile at the entertaining French gentleman, it is worth observing that many of the finest tributes paid to the gentler sex have emanated from old bachelors -the light-hearted Benedicks who never lived to be married I Tasso made Leonora immortal, and Herrick his Prudence Baldwin--and these were the most incurable of old bachelors. There is one of Herrick's lyrics to his sweet-heart, so diminutive and chaste and perfect--like an agate-stone on the fore-finger of an alderman '-that I can never think of it without quoting it: ON HIS MAID PREW. ' IN this little urn is laid PREWDENCE BALDWIN, once my maid, From whose happy spark here let Spring the purple violet! I No reader of recent biography is unfamiliar with Lady Byron's unfortunate marriage, nor with the love of Jean Burns, nor the touching account of Shelley's two wives, nor with the tender care with which the wife of Tom Moore watched over thesplendid ruin of his intellect. The memorials of Thomas Hood by his son and daughter, lately republished in this country by Ticknor and Fields, present us with a delightful picture of domestic literary life. The book itself is not a remarkable specimen of biographical writing, but the characters of Hood and his wife are so full of human goodness, so touched with all delicate graces, that one forgets every thing else. Mrs. Hood's letters are delicious un- revealings of herself. She was, A SPIRIT, yet a woman, too. A creature not too bright or good For human nature's daily food; For transient sorrows, simple wiles, Praise, blame, love, kisses, tears and smiles.' Our own day and our own literature are not barren in instances of such unions, nor lacking in painful household histories. The time has not come when it would be proper to speak of the wives of those authors who are still living, or who have but newly passed away from-among us. Many women who to day are moving quietly and gracefully through the light and shadow   SONNET.               27 of fire-side life, are to be known hereafter. Their names will be gracious words to other generations. They shall have justice done them, for the nineteenth century, among other inventions and discoveries, has discovered Woman 1 It was not enough that she was placed in the garden of Eden for, us. We were blind for many thousand years. When the *world was young, we made her fetch our wood and cook our food and play the menial. In'our days of chivalry Wve taught her to be a pretty Amazon, to dress our wounds, to bind her scarf about our helmet, to receive a fantastic and insincere adoration. Then, as if there were never to be an end to our nonsense, we fancied that she was an Arcadian shepherdess, or a lovely wood-nymph with confused ideas of virtue. Then was the sickly, sentimental, pastoral age in full blast. Then did she tap us on the cheek with her fan, and smirk and smile, and paint and powder, and wear her hair four stories high. That was the courtly age. But by-and- by she wearied of these follies. We began to treat her with more sense: then little by little she began to assert herself; the[ better we treated her the more she asserted, until at last we cried out like Frankenstein, 'What monster is this we have created?' But it was not a monster-- it was only a4 Woman! Great in her weakness, noble in her charity, beautiful in her patience. We have found her out I She was never so recognized as now; we have dis- covered that she has brain as well as heart; that she can write verse like Mrs. Browning, paint pictures like Rosa Bonheur, and still be all that is gentle and lovable like Florence Nightingale. go  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7984-00000015"/> 28 THE REV. MR. TYMPAN'S MISFORTUNE: RELATED AT SECOND-HAND. BY WILLIAM WIRT SIKES. MY misfortune is, that I do not hear so well as some people--not, I would distinctly state, that I am pastor of a little church in the pleasant country village-where I reside. When I was at college, fourteen years ago, I was walking one day with a couple of fellow-students, one of whom was my chum, George Argent, since banker, ad the other a freshman named New, who was killed ten years since by falling from a mast-head at sea. As we turned a corner a run-away horse cahmedasing across the side-walk, striking me squarely on my back and toss- ing me twenty feet plump forward. As I flew through the air a splintered thill flew after me, hitting me with its sharp point directly behind the externall; left ear, tearing that organ partially from my head and smashing certain internal arrangements that I had hitherto found useful. To make sure work of it, the horse took occasion in passing to put his foot on my head, and though he did not pause to use precision in that act, he could hardly have planted his shoe-corks more squarely on my skull if he had taken mathe- matical observations of the premises. A crowd picked me up, very limp, very bloody and very stupid, so much so that a council of physicians declared there was no life in me, and I was spread on a table to get cold. But for one circum- stance, this had undoubtedly been my last appearance in public; that circum- stance was, that Dr. Worth of New-York had arrived by the last train on the Cum and Gow Railroad, and had been invited to call and see ' the young man who was killed.' Dr. Worth was not a, distinguished physician --he was only my father -but he was enabled to continue me in the land of the living, partly, I have never doubted, through that faith which moves mountains. I was restored to my usual health in the course of three or four months, except that it was found I could not hear so welD as some people. I continue in that condition to the present day. When I discovered that I possessed defective acoustic properties, I was very much cast down by the weight of my misfortune. I found that it acted as a continual draw-back on me wherever I went, whatever I did. In my class, I could not understand half the Professor said, and was compelled privately to request him to elevate his voice a little in future. He was a very obliging man-I remember him with affection; he elevated his voice, till I was in an agony of apprehension lest he should tear his vocal organs to shreds, and in my tremor begged him, in the presence of the class, to ' come down; I was not so deaf as that.' He came down, and I never heard him make a re- mark afterward. Participation in debate was my greatest delight; but with such ears as   THE REV. MR. TYMPAN'S MSFORTUNE.         29 mine, such participation was simply impossible, except by compelling my fel- low-students to lay themselves open to bronchitis. So I dropped debating; and a consequence is, that I am to-day just as incapable of making an er- temporaneous speech as though I were a deaf-mute instead of a dominie. Then, among other things, I affected female society extremely, (a weakness from which I have since nearly recovered,) and I found that, sitting in a quiet drawing-room, in company with ladies and one of my own sex, I was as effectually kept in the back-ground as if I had been a mummy and my male companion a Sydney Smith, whereas the truth might be that my friend was a conceited ass and myself a young fellow with quite a ready flow of ideas and good command of language, but a little deaf.  [I say this might have been the case; I do not say it was the case.]  The change that became manifest in me extended beyond my ears. From having been a very gay, rollicking, merry chap, I became melancholy. Ex- posed to, mortifications more numerous and varied than the tribulations of Job, I at last came to look upon society as a sort of instrument of torture devised for my especial sorrow, and charged each item thereof with being a direct de- scendant of Tantalus, and inheritor of that ancient's most offensive pecu- liarities. I grew lank and yellow, whereas before I was fleshy and of good color; my face assumed the repulsive aspects of a cynic, whereas before it was good-natured and complacent; my breath grew offensive, whereas before it was sweet; my hand grew lean and limp, whereas before it was plump, and held a cordial grasp. This metamorphosis was observed of course, and I fell into dis- like among students and friends every where- a fate which I do not pretend to say I did not deserve, though I do n't know but I might have wished some body had called public attention to Addison's familiar lines, in connection with my case: ' CONSIDER why the change was wrought, You 'll find it his misfortune, not his fault.' It must not be inferred that I permitted myself to be thus vanquished by the imps of blue-devil-dom and dyspepsia, passively. It must not be supposed that I did not fight my dismal fate in the most desperate manner. It was a hard struggle to get me down, but once down, I became hopelessly non- resistant, and my dreary misfortune stretched its ghoul-like wings over me; it became the vampire that clung to me closer than a brother, and sucked my life remorselessly away, more terrible far than those unhealthy grave-yard tenants that used to creep from their cold and mouldy quarters o' nights, to visit the victim in his bed, and fasten their horrible lips on his tortured veins, more terrible far than these; for it left me nor day nor night, but followed me, mocking and torturing me through the sorrows of my stumbling and awkward daily experience, and through the bilious visions of my uneasy slumbers. How fervently I was wont td wish that I were a deaf-mute I What wild projects I entertained from time to time-of doing fearful violence to the ear that that villainous buggy-thill did not pierce I of putting beans into the meatus; of puncturing the tympanums with ferocious cobbler's awls; of running hot -ires up my nose, and through the Eustachian tube into the inner-works, to  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7984-00000016"/> 30       THE REV., MR. TYMPAN'S MSFORTUNE. do destruction at one fell sweep to malleus, incus, orbicularis, and stapes; but ili1-? sage reflection convinced me I should not mend the matter much, if any. 'Onice i tried to enliven my spirits by endeavoring to remember whether there had' not been people of eminence in the world who had groped under the shadow of my misfortune; but, do my best, I could call to mind only Harriet Martineau and Tom Hood, who were partially deaf, while on the instant, as if determined on torturing me past all endurance, there came rushing on my mind a perfect hurly-burly of names of distinguished deaf-mutes: Jean Massieu, Ferdinand Berthier, James Nack, Pedro de Velasco, Richardin, Juan Fernandez deo Navarette, Walter Geikie, the Baron de Monthret, Lieut. Phillips, et cetera almost without end, confounding and overwhelming me. [I have since observed, in reading anew Shakspeare's tragedy of Julius Caesar, that the noble Roman was himself afflicted precisely as I am, that is to say, deaf in his left ear. Proof: Act I. Scene II., Caesar says to Antony, with whom he is conversing respecting the lean and hungry Cassius: CoME on my right hand, for this ear is deaf;, And tell me truly what thou thinkst of him.' Is not this conclusive?] Disheartened and wearied by my vain efforts to find consolation in this direction, I was led to fall back on gentle Tommy Hood as the man of my heart. I took to reading him with all the avidity of a soul hungry for sym- pathy and solace, and though I grew not fat thereby, I found my greatest com- fort in poring over the pages of the dear little invalid who coined frbm his throbbing heart the 'Bridge of Sighs' and the ' Song of the Shirt,' and who wrote the marvellous history of the eloquent but brimstony peddler of ear- trumpets-him who, in testimony of the superiority of his auricular aids, mentioned the deaf woman who bought one of them, and ----'TE very next day She heard from her husband at Botany Bay.' This last poem I committed to memory, as 'ladies' men' commit to memory Moore's melodies, and as politicians get at their tongue's end the war-cries of the campaign. It was scarcely ever out of my head; I took a grim delight in muttering the tale to myself on every occasion when the spirit moved me. It became a part, and a very important part of my ' inner life,' and dear Tommy Hood became my pet literary amicus. How I eventually graduated, without overwhelming disgrace; how I also went through the Theological Seminary at X-  , and emerged therefrom with no special blot upon my name, though positively without having made a real friend during all the time I was at X --; these are matter of history, as is also the fact that I was called to the pulpit of the church, where I now remain. The call had reached me entirely through the efforts of influential friends in the church, and I had not been compelled to go through the preliminary per- formance of showing off my points for the criticism of the congregation. I had been taken 'for better or worser;' and this fact made me even more nervous   THE REV. MR. TYMPAN'S MSFORTUNE.          31 than I should naturally have been, at appearing for the -first time in my new position. The eventful morning found me in my place, however, and with tolerable self-possession I conducted the preliminary service, scarcely glancing once at the upturned faces before me, but directing my gaze choir-ward. At length the reading and prayer having soothed my nerves somewhat, I arose and announced my text with little manifest trepidation: ' I was in the Spirit on the LoRD'S day, and heard behind me a great voice, as of a trumpet.' (REVELATION 1: 10.) Having done this I became dizzy, the congregation commenced to swim, and I presently became conscious that I was in the open air, with Brother Smith holding my head, Brother Jones sprinkling me with water, and Brother Robinson feeling my pulse. I had swooned; and the reason why I had swooned was this, four old ladies sat in a row in one of the front-pews, each with a monstrous ear-trumpet yawning up at me, like so many bottomless pits, or trombones, or spittoons. I entirely recovered from a raging fever about a month thereafter. As I was sitting in my easy-chair on one of the early days of my convalescence, the awful vision of those four monstrous ear-trumpets arose before me, and I shuddered at the thought of being compelled again to confront them from- my pulpit and belch divine truths into their yawning depths. I resolved to preach no more. I would quit the ministry. I could never do my duty in the pulpit under the shadow of a misfortune like mine. I would peddle books; I would edit a paper; I would turn a grind-stone; I would perform any given species of drudgery, but I would never preach again. Having arrived at this conclu- sion, I felt easier in my mind, and ventured to think again of those fearful trumpets. I presently found myself giving the subject a more philosophical consideration; and shortly I was humming the words of my old favorite Hood-iac: AND the very next day She heard from her husband at Botany Bay.' I hummed myself to sleep with the story of the fiendish peddler of ear. trumpets.- Presently at the open door before me a man appeared with a pack on his back. He saluted me with a grin and a duck of his little head, covered with wiry black hair, and then unceremoniously swung his pack from his back and commenced to open it at my feet. Willing to be entertained by any thing that offered, I made no objection. He turned back a cloth and exhibited his hoard. Prominent in a wilderness of pins, thread, rings and perfumery - centre-piece to a very Salmagundi of knick-knackery-lay an ear-trumpet. The peddler said: ' What will you buy '  I grasped the ear-trumpet. 'It is not good for much,' said the peddler. 'You see I am honest,' grin- ning and ducking again, while he rummaged his-pack. Who are you P.' said I suspiciously. 'Your servant, Sir,' he answered hastily, continuing: 'Ahl here it is- here is an article, Sir, that I can recommend that will answer your purpose.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7984-00000017"/> 32       THE REV. MR. TYMPAN'S MSFORTUNE. With it you can hear the blood rippling in your neighbor's veins, or the fall of a mosquito's feet as it alights on your carpet. Try it, Sir; put it on. You just insert it in your ear; it will fit the orifice as perfectly as if I had myself  made it expressly for you before coming up from my warm fire-side last night; but I assure you I did not. Here, Sir I ' I took the article. It was simply a little black, flexible tube, which I placed in the meatus in such a manner that it was entirely invisible. ' A peculiarity of this instrument,' said my mysterious visitor, ' is that you can regulate its action with your will. If you hear any thing you do not wish to hear, by an effort of your will you may cease to hear it. Thus you can instantly shut off the stream of a tiresome conversation, or hush a grinding- organ beneath your window, as you wish. Thus you-- . But how do you like it, Sir? ' Howdid I like it? I was beside myself with delight. I could hear the breathing of my host's sleeping baby in the next room. I could hear the peep- ing of. a brood of chickens in the barn-yard. I could hear any sound I chose I to hear, distinct from a medley of other sounds, Marvellous I How did I like it? What was the price?-that was all I wanted to know. 'The price, Sir?' said the grinning peddler; ' oh I I make you a present of it. Nay, no objections, please; it is my delight to bestow gifts upon those with whom I expect to become better acquainted by-and-by. I bid you good- day, Sir.' As my mysterious benefactor retired, I could hear his feet clattering curi- ously on the carpet, and looking at them, I perceived they presented a most extraordinary case of tlipe varus. Feet so hard and small, so remarkably clubbed, I had never seen before, and--it struck me as very curious --but he wore no shoes, and his step sounded more like the foot-fall of bone than flesh. I heard him distinctly as he passed out at the gate, and tramped over the dis- tant hills out of sight. What a blessing seemed my new-found treasure I I was deaf no longer. What new delight was given to existence I How I blessed my unknown but club-footed and eccentric and no doubt highly respectable visitor Happy me.          I What cared I now for those four unfortunate old ladies with their harmless and inefficient ear-trumpets? I reconsidered my intention of retiring from the ministry, and made my preparations for again essaying my pastoral debut with an ardor such as I never before had experienced. I wrote a sermon that as- tonished myself as I rehearsed it in my chamber. It was then to prove a blessing to me, after all, that I had taken fright at the apparition of the trumpet-guard in the front-pew, for my introductory sermonwas now marvel- lously in advance of any thing I had ever before produced. I walked to the church the next Squnady morning with a minac full of tranSquil rapture, and entered the pulpit with a youthful step.' I presently became aware of an unpleasant circumstance: I could dis. tinctly hear my congregation making whispered commentaries on my personal appearance:   THE REV. MR. TYMPAN'S MSFORTUNE.          33 FIRST VOICE: ' Looks pale; guess he's had a tough time on 't.' SECOND VOICE: ' Pale?--pale as a hedge-fence; he's too black to get    / pale.' THIRD VOICE: ' Handsome? -not by a good deal I Ido n't think any but white men are handsome.'                     .  FOURTH VOICE: ' What's he want to wear's hair that-a-way fur? Scares me to look at 'im.'                        .  FIFTH VOICE: ' I do n't believe he can preach . He looks stupid.' SIXTH VOICE:  Sophomoric.   Just from the apron-strings of his almo mater.'                               . . .  This was decidedly disagreeable information to reach my ears. I foUnd; that by exercising my will, I only 'shut off' one speaker to open the mouith, of another as uncomplimentary. This was a new feature. I now for the first- time bethought myself of the propriety of removing the instrument temporarily from the place it had occupied since the peddler's advent. I could not stir it I It would be vain to attempt to picture the tortures that now grew thick upon me. With beads of perspiration on my throbbing forehead, with hollow utterance and blundering enunciation I managed to stumble miserably through the preliminary service, though the criticisms on my personnel went on, inter-' mingled with like animadversions on different members of the congregation. At last I arose to commence my sermon, and was inexpressibly glad to notice that the gabbling had entirely stopped, and every eye was on me. I discharged the words of my text into the yawning mouthss of the four up- turned ear-trumpets, and proceeded to spread the wings of my discourse. For perhaps ten or fifteen minutes all was quiet, and then the Babel'set in. I con- tinued to read my manuscript, but with the articulation of an automaton and the action of a stick; but I was no longer conscious of the words, I uttered, for I was frantically engaged in exercising the will-ful function left me of regu- lating my now tormentor--only 'shutting off' one disagreeable speaker, how ever, to 'turn on' another- for the congregation seemed utterly to have for- gotten me, and were engaged in conversation among themselves, the medley reaching my active ear in fragments like this: 'Beginning to pile up the agony, an't he? An't no orator, though; can't begin to come up to- -' 'Snuff?  Help yourself; my  ' 'Dear Nellie, I shall die if you act so? Why do n't you sit up ---' 'On the top of his head I Never saw such hair; and then plastered all over his ears like a --' 'Professional burglar from Boston. Got in with false keys. Stole more than --' ' A five-cent piece, my dear? I've nothing for the missionary collection, and want to use it in a -- ' 'HornI   FactI Queerest box y'ever saw; all quirleened up.  Right fancy  '   &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7984-00000018"/> 34             POOR MARY. ' That style of preaching at all; nothing solid about him. A perfect --' !     'Angel Gabriel, with his trumpet. Devilish good joke, was n't it? The boy--' ' Had a forked tongue, and was nigh twelve feet long, they said. Shot him with a ' Hole-in the ground, six feet deep. I never saw it at all till I - ' Sent a constable after him, and he said he did n't owe -- 'Dear me, how tiresome I I wish he 'd stop his droning.' I bore the agonies of this species of infernal torture, (of which the above is but a faint indication) until I could bear it no longer, and then rushed from the pulpit half-crazed and hatless, pausing not. until I had reached my chamber. Locking the door, I buried my head in the pillows of my bed, striving to still the horrible tumult that rung in my ears, in vain; there was evidently but one means of relieving the ineffable agony I experienced, and that was suicide. I sprang for my razor, applied it to my throat, and awoke. I sat in my easy-chair, looking out upon the lovely landscape, verdant with the emerald of June, and aromatic with perfume. The song of birds reached even my dull ears-my still partially-deaf ears--and the lowing of cattle came like sweet music on the twilight air. And from that hour I was reconciled to my misfortune. r    O-BED      GROOT. BY JOHN T. IRVING,? AUTHOR OF 'THE QUOD CORRESPONDENCE.' Is that distinguished part of the world, known as. Queen's County, on Long Island, in old times, not a great while after the Revolutionary war, thero -lived about half way between Mosquito Cove and Jericho, a hard-drinking hard-swearing, roystering gentleman by the name of Tom Floyd. He kept his hounds and his racers, and led a helter-skelter life. But his hard-riding, hard- swearing and hard-drinking came to a sudden end by his breaking his neck as he was following his hounds after a fox down the Cedar-Swamp road, which leads to Mosquito Cove. He was taken up dead. - But wild stories -got in cir- culation about him: some said that the moment he fell dead the fox sprang up a bank, spread out a huge pair of wings, and flapped off in -the air, and that there was the print of a cloven foot in the bank where he disappeared. Above all, it was well attested that this hard-riding gentleman still kept up his hunting habits; and on the anniversary of his death, he swept down the Cedar-Swamp road in his red jockey-coat and yellow small-clothes at the heels of his hounds; and wo betide the belated straggler who fell in his way on that night, for it was said that he preferred human game to all others. On such occasions the good farmers and their wives, and daughters, and sons, and sons-in-law, and daughters-in-law scampered off to bed and buried their heads beneath the bed-clothes until the infernal crew had passed out of hearing. Indeed, it is said that such was the haste and confusion with whichh they beat their retreat, it not unfrequently happened that the wrong persons got info the wrong bed, which sometimes led to unpleasant consequences. Be that as it may, it was a well-authenticated fact that the tough old 'Squire still kept up his annual chase, and there was but one person in the whole country who doubted it and dared to say so. This was a man named Obed Groot, who lived on the Cedar-Swamp road in a large house surrounded by rich fields and teeming barns. He was a keen, bitter fellow, with an eye like a rat's, a nose like a hawk's, and a mouth so tight shut and with the corners turned so far down, that there seemed to be some risk of their meeting under his chin and beheading it. He had set out in life with a determination to become rich, and by letting nothing stand in his way, and shutting his eyes and ears to every thing that did not tend to that particular end, he succeeded. To be sure, he had not stopped to secure many friends by the way, but he did not want them. Friends were always wanting something, or telling about some case of dreadful want, or of some fellow with a broken leg and starving family; or in other words, always endeavoring to circumvent the iron button that kept watch over the breeches-pocket in which lay his purse, and which button seemed to glare out at all the world like a great eye, defying any one to get the better of it.  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7984-00000019"/> 36             OBED GROOT. /;     Obed had once been married, and his ;,ife had died many years before; whether he had starved her to death, or whether she had died because her heart became frozen for want of any warmth in his, it matters not; she died, and he buried her decently, though some said he had hinted it was a pity when she went that she had forgotten to take with her a little girl which she had borne to him and left behind. But the child was left, and though neglected and almost forgotten, she throve; and as she grew older and sat and watched him with her earnest, solemn eyes, a feeling almost akin to fear would come over him. It was observed, too, that when he had driven a more than usually hard bargain, or one in which there had been a more than usual economy of honesty, he kept out of her way. As time passed on, and Obed grew in years, and Esther--for so was his daughter called- grew in youth and beauty, he began to feel a kind of pride in her, and sometimes listened to her words and to her reading from the Good Book, for he had become a man of wealth and note, and having secured a fair share of the treasures of earth, he had no objections to make a small venture for those of heaven, It was said that once or twice, at her request, he had opened a small corner of his heart to an ap- peal for charity. 'T is true his acts were rather insignificant; and then, as if frightened at what he had done, he buttoned his breeches-pocket tighter, and was harder than ever. But still the ice had melted once, and there was hope that the time might come when there would be a general thaw. It had been a hard year upon the farmers. Little rain had fallen; their crops were cut off, and there was general distress throughout the country. Obed Groot, with his usual fortune, had escaped. It chanced at the time of which we speak, that he was sitting in a room in his house, with one eye on his ledger and the other on the road, along which he saw a man approaching. As the man came near his gates, Obed raised the ledger eye also, and watched him with both. The man paused as if hesitating and then came in. If there was hesitation in his manner at first, there was none now, for his tread, was firm and strong, and his single knock at the door loud and bold. ' Come in,' said Obed. The stranger came in. He was large in frame; his tread denoted strength and resolution; his eye was clear and frank; his hair slightly streaked with silver; his features heavy and massive, like those of a mastiff. He looked for a moment at Obed, who returned his look with an eye keen and watchful as that of a terrier, then nodded to him. ' Good morning, John Wakeman; I'm glad to see you,' said he. The words were kind, the tone was cold and harsh. 'I suppose you know my errand, Sir,' said the man with some embarrass- ment of manner. 'I have not the least idea of it,' replied Obed tartly. He fidgeted as he spoke, for he knew it well. I came to ask for time to pay my debt to you. It has been a hard year: every thing seems to have gone wrong.' Obed's face grew hard as flint, and this time the corners of his mouth very   OBED GROOT               37 nearly met under his chin. At last he snarled out: 'That's the cry of every one just now.' ' What can I do?' said the man. 'If you can't give money, give what you can. I 'll take your farm; it's worth something,' was the sharp reply. 'But if I part with it, how shall I live? ' 'There are plenty of people in the world who do n't own farms: live as they do,' replied Obed. 'Mr. Groot,' said the other, ' my farm is but a small one, and not worth much; but it is all I have, and the only home, I have for my wife. If I were alone, you should have it this very hour as it is, I will not see her turned out of doors if I can help it.' 'Just as you please,' replied Obed. ' I would rather have the mo'ney. I have more land now than I can use.' As he spoke he waved his hand with some complacency toward the window which commanded a view of his own land. The man drew a long breath as he looked over the wide fields, and ample barns and granaries filled to bursting, and thought of his own blighted harvest. He said nothing, however, but stood looking on the floor and apparently pondering something in his mind. ' Well,' said he at length, ' I suppose my errand here has been a waste of time?' ' Entirely.' The former stood for a moment, as if he would have urged his plea once more, but at last turning to the door, he wished Obed good morning in a quiet, civil tone and went out. Obed watched him until he had passed the gate, then turned to his ledger. ' I was just making out that fellow's account when he came in. It 's very odd.' As he spoke, there was a quiet footstep in the room and Esther came in, and took her seat at his side. He was too much engrossed to notice her, but kept on adding up the figures and muttering to himself: 'Every body wants time. I never ask for time, not once--and I 'll not give it.' His mouth closed, and the corners went down again and his chin ran a great risk. ' I hate poor people,' said he, poising his-pen over the paper while he ran his eye up and down the page to see that he had omitted no item. 'Ninety-five dollars and seventy-five cents. I verily believe there never was a poor man who was an honest one --not one; I think it is absolutely wicked to be so confoundedly poor.' He felt a hand pressing on his. He looked up: a pair of soft, remonstrating eyes were searching his. ' Well, Esther, what now? ' 'Father, there was once ONE SO poor that HE knew not where to lay His head.' 'Eh! what,' said he, looking round and still holding his pen poised over the paper, ' so poor as that; who was he?' 'ONE who healed the sick, gave sight to the blind, raised the dead, pointed  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7984-00000020"/> 38             OBED GROOT. out the path to heaven shown by acts of loving kindness and mercy to man, and who at last died for us.' Tears came in the girl's eyes as she bent forward and looked earnestly in the sharp, hard face which peered so curiously in her own. Oh I ah I ' said he, as the meaning of her words slowly made its way into his mind. ' All yvery true, no doubt--a matter of religion. I never mix re- ligion with business. You 're a very good little girl, Esther. I 'm glad that you read your Bible. Let me see I where was I?' He bent his nose to his ledger. ' Ninety-five dollars and seventy-five cents.' :The girl said nothing more, but got up and left the room. Obed kept on with his'nose as close to his ledger as ever, but he could not get on with his account; for every now and then the idea of how strange it must be to have no place to sleep in, would come across his mind, and bother him as he was adding up a column. At last his mind wandered so much, that he could not follow up his accounts, and he gave it up. . He buttoned up his coat, went out and strolled about his grounds. He looked into his cribs and barns and cattle- stalls. He was quite jocose with his workmen, but his merriment was hard and biting, and made their teeth chatter as they laughed. As it grew later in the day, he went in and tackled his accounts again. By this time the idle fancy which had bothered him-before was completely out of his mind, and he soon had found out the exact amount of John Wakeman's debt, and had calcu- lated the interest on it up to that very hour. It was now late in the day, and at last it grew dark. Candles were lighted. Obed drank his tea, drew his chair to the fire, and toasted his feet, but he did every thing mechanically. His daughter took her usual seat at the fire-side, but he did not notice her. In truth, in going over those accounts, he had discovered that John Wake- man was in his debt more than he imagined. It was but a trifle, perhaps John knew it; but if he did not, or had forgotten it, it might not be amiss to refresh his memory. He got up and looked out of the window. Every thing outside was black as jet; and -the wind was rising as if a storm were brewing. Still that 'difference' in his account worried him. ' Father, you had better not go to John Wakeman's to-night,' said the girl abruptly. The old man started, for her words were the echo of his thoughts. What put that in your head?' demanded he testily. ' Were you not thinking of him .' asked the girl. A denial was trembling on his lips, but he gulped it back before it had got far enough out to become a full-fledged lie. ' It's no matter, child, what JI was thinking of.' But whatever might have been his intentions, he abandoned them and went to bed. Still, through the night that ' difference' perplexed him in his dreams, and made him toss and tumble in his sleep, until at last he got John Wake- man, his ledger and 'the difference' so mixed and jumbled up together, that he could not tell whether 'that difference' was John Wakeman or the ledger,   OBED GROOT.              39 or something else, or what it was. In the midst of this confusion he awoke, and found the day-light streaming in the room and the rain pattering on the window-panes. All day long that 'difference' haunted him; but the storm kept on. He flattened his sharp nose against the window-panes, and blew his breath on them, and watched the sky, but still it stormed. Late in the evening the rain ceased, although the night looked black and lowering. Obed could restrain -himself no longer, and ordered his horse. His daughter attempted to remonstrate, but he chid her sternly, and with his feeling sharpened and his venom increased against his debtor by the oppo- sition, he left the house. 4 Guy I Mas' Obed,' exclaimed his negro Sam as he led out the horse. 'A won'ful bad storm is coming won'ful bad I Ef I was you, Mas' Obed, I'd stay to hum. It's Tom Floyd's night. He 'll be out sure as my name's Sam, Whoa! I Pepper I Whoa I - Even the ole hoss don't want to go.' ' He'll want to go before I've done with- him,' said Obed roughly. As he spoke he brushed the hand of his old retainer from the bridle, and set out at a brisk trot. Sam shook his head. 'Mas' Obed don't b'lieve nuffinl But he'll larn some day; he will.' Obed rode rapidly on; for dark clouds were drifting across the sky, and the deep sighing of the wind showed that the storm was not over. The light of the young- moon was completely hidden by the black masses which swept over it. Although it was dark when he started, yet before he reached his place of destination he could scarcely see the road, and the rain began to fall. Pepper, however, kept steadily on until a light gleaming from the window of a house at the road-side showed that he had reached his journey's end. Dis- mounting, he led his horse under a shed, and tied him there; then groping his way to the house, he knocked at the door. ' Come in,' said a voice from within. Obed pulled up the latch and entered. John Wakeman was sitting at a table mending an old shoe. Near him sat his wife, a pale, anxious-looking woman. They both looked up as Obed entered, and a slight expression of pain crossed the man's face when he saw who his visitor was; and the woman cast a quick apprehensive glance at her husband, but neither spoke. The man instinctively pushed a chair toward their visitor. ' I want no chair, John Wakeman,' said Obed gruffly, ' nor do I want to waste words. I came here about that account of mine. Here it is.' He extended the paper to the man, who took it and held it to the light. ' It's right, I suppose?'                 . ' Quite right.' 'Well,' said Obed somewhat staggered by this prompt admission of a mat. ter which he had supposed would be disputed. 'I want my money.' As he spoke he planted himself firmly in the middle of the floor, and crossed his hands on the top of the chair which had been pushed to him, as if he intended to remain there until his want was gratified.  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7984-00000021"/> 40             OBED GROOT. 'Mr. Groot,' said the man in a grave serious tone, 'I will pay you as soon as I car. I have not got the money; I have told you so before, I tell you so again.' As he spoke he placed the shoe on the table, and came round to where Obed stood. 'My sheep have died. The storm has beaten my grain to the ground and destroyed the crop, and the drought killed my corn - a whole year's labor lost. Others have suffered as well as L The hand of the ALMGHTY is upon us, and we must submit.' ' I do n't see what I have to do with that,' replied Obed testily; 'that's a matter between you and PROVIDENCE. I do n't see why I should be mixed up with it; and I won't be,' said he resolutely; ' I won't be I I did n't come here to hear sermons.' ' Others, who have met the same misfortunes, have found indulgence,' an- swered the man; 'why should not I?' 'Because you are dealing with me and not with others,' replied Obed sharply. 'I let no man tell me how I am to manage my affairs, and I follow no one's example. I've got a head,' said he, tapping his forehead with his fore-finger, 'and I judge for myself. I will not be swindled out of my money. If you have not honesty enough to pay your debt, I 'll make you.' His lips quivered, and he shook his thin finger in the very face of the farmer. The man's eyes flashed at the last words; the red blood flushed his cheeks, and he took a step forward: as he did so, he felt a touch on his arm. It was but the slight pressure of his wife's fingers, and even in his anger he turned to acknowledge the anxious yet affectionate glance which was fixed on him. 'Do not fear, Mary,' said he. ' These things are hard to bear, and I forgot myself for a moment; but it's over now. Let him say his say, I 'll bear it.' Obed turned sharply on the woman. 'As to you,' said he tartly, 'I must and will say --- The farmer laid his hand heavily on his shoulder and looked in his face. ' Say nothing that may in any way reflect on her. She 's a hard-working, loving woman. She bears her heavy lot without repining. The little sun- shine which GOD sends into this house comes from her. Say nothing of her, for unless your looks belie you, you will say what I will not bear. To me she is all that is left of fortune or friends, and next to GOD I honor her.' There was a grave sternness in the tone and manner of the farmer as he spoke, and a kindling of the steady eye which warned Obed that he was tread- ing on dangerous ground. ' As to your wife, I have no fault to find with her,' replied he; ' she owes me nothing. I never deal with women, never--never I' 'It 's well,' said the other, with the same grave manner. 'And now, as you have said what you came fdr, and I have given you my answer, it is use- less to speak farther about the matter. The night is a rough one; will you stay here until the storm abates? ' 'Stay here I' screamed Obed, fairly excited beyond hi patience by the sturdy calmness of his debtor; ' not a minute ' As he spoke he made for the door.   OBED GROOT. -a            41 'Think again,' said the farmer; 'the nihbt is dreadful, and there, is win work going on without.' 'I 'll go, though the devil himself were in my path ' As he spoke he pushed past the farmer, and opening the door, dashed out into the darkness. He was absent but a minute when he returned. The farmer was still stand- ing where he left him. 'John Wakeman,' said he slowly and in a. tone of concentrated wrath, 'you've braved me this night. Now, mark my words, I 'll hunt you down.' The farmer eyed him calmly, and then raising his hand slowly, pointed up- ward, but said not a word. 'I suppose that means PROVIDENCE again,' said O0ed with a snarl. 'When- ever a man loses money, it's always PPOVIDENCE ; but when he makes it, it 's always himself. We 'lllsee what that same PROVIDENCE will do for you when you get me after you.' Again he left the house, but as he did so he turned and looked back. The man stood with the same unmoved expression, aid his finger still pointed to heaven. "et him point,' growled he. ' If I do not teach him to pay his debts, may -    He did not finish his sentence, for he had reached the shed under which he had tied his horse. He led him' out, and battling with the wind and rain, contrived to mount him and turned his head homeward. The man was right, it was a wild night. The wind swept down the valley in long gusts. The trees creaked and groaned, and the lightning flashed across the road. The sky was inky black, and his horse splashed heavily through the mud and water which deluged the road. But Obed's venom was too much aroused and his bosom too full of vindictive plans, for him to heed the turmoil around him. ' Let him point to heaven,' muttered he, ' we'll see what it will do for him. If I do n't hunt him down, may I Again he paused, for his ear caught a sound which came sweeping down the valley, mingling strangely with the wailing of the storm. Pepper too grew restive, and made one or two strong efforts to dash off. 'Dogs out on such a night as this;' muttered he. ' Whose can they be? ' For a moment his heart stood still, and a strange dread came over him, for he recollected the last words of his negro Sam and associated them in his mind with the noises which were borne along on the wind. But Obed was not a , man to yield to idle fancies. His life had been hard and practical, and with a feeling almost of contempt at himself, he again turned his horse homeward. But Pepper had grown so restive that he could Scarcely hold him, and he seemed half wild with terror. His pace was quickened to a gallop. His rider, however, was able to govern him, until the' same wild cry again came ringing in his ears and close at hand. Obed glanced behind him. As he did so a bright flash of lightning flickered- through the darkness and showed a pack of hounds coming down upon him, with lolling tongues and fiery eyes; and he also recognized the red coat and buck-skin small-clothes of Tom Floyd. In- stinctively a prayer rose to his lips; but at the same moment his last words to John Wakeman flashed through his mind and choked it in his throat.  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7984-00000022"/> 42             OBED GROOT. It was no moment for hesitation. He gave reins to his horse and dashed off at furious speed. He assaulted the sides of Pepper with a shower of blows and drove his heels into his ribs. For a moment he thought that he was gain- ing upon his pursuers.. But it was only a turning in the road which-had shut out their cry. The next moment, nearer -than before, he heard the deep bay- ing of the phantom hounds amid the bellowing of the storm, and loud above all the cry of the goblin'horseman: * Hunt the miser down I ' Obed set his teeth, for amnd his terrors the feeling of resistance was strong. There was no need now to urge his horse, for wild with fright and startled by the sharp flashes of lightning and the roar of the thunder, his speed was terrific. Down the Cedar-Swamp road, toward the village of Mosquito Cove, Obed scoured along, the mud spattering behind him, his coat-tails fluttering in the wind, Pepper had got the very devil in him; bit and bridle were but as threads to hold him in. At every yell of the hounds he seemed to leap a hundred feet. Through the village, up the hill, across the fields of the Valen- tines, down Fresh-Pond Lane, through the swamp at the end of it; along the borders of the Sound, across West-Beach, and over the upland of West-Island, he tore along; and close at his heels, fast and furious, followed the goblin pack. In the centre of the island was a large house, occupied by a hard-riding, jovial old fellow, who kept his hounds and lived with open heart and open hand. The sound of the approaching chase roused him from his lair; and as Obed sped by, he saw the old 'Squire standing at his window, with his, night- cap in his hand, yelling like mad and cheering on the hunt. He thought that he could hear sounds of mocking laughter and loud greetings interchanged be- tween the goblin rider and the 'Squire. He made an effort to pull in his horse. He might as well have tried to rule. a whirlwind. Down the bank he bounded, over the bridge, along the causeway, through the mud, and water; across East-Island, along East-Beach, up Peacock's Lane he dashed, his hoofs strik- ing fire at every leap. The stiff-sided inhabitants of Buckram were aroused by the fiendish shouts. They knew too well the sound of Tom Floyd's hounds; and Obed saw them scampering in every direction as he flitted by. Through the valley of Buckram, across by Meadow Side, over the hills of Oyster Bay, along the upper road, and through the quiet town of Jericho, the hunt swept on, until the dark waste of Hempstead Plains opened to view. Full twenty miles had Obed come, and still no signs of flagging in his steed; and now before- him stretched out a barren waste: dark, dreary, and almost without limit. He knew that far off to the east lay the village of Hempstead; and he hoped that the horse might turn in that direction. But he was disap- pointed. Pepper headed toward the east, and dashed across the plains until he came to the great south road. Trees, houses and fences, seen dimly in the dark, flitted past like shadows. Occasionally a deep bark would burst from the throat of some startled watch. dog as Obed fled by, changed into a yell of terror at the goblin pack which followed at his heels. The longer Pepper ran the more furious grew his speed.   OBED GROOT.              43 Obed began to grow delirious. He yelled and screamed, now shrieking for help, now joining in the loud shouts of his pursuers. Thus he was carried on through South Oyster Bay and Babylon; when once more the horse turned to the north and homeward. But Obed now was past all thought. He was carried on he knew not how, he cared not where; thought, feelinrg, fear and sense were all gone. Instinctively he kept his seat. He knew that he was hurried through bushes and thickets, over ploughed fields and fences; he felt that Pepper was master, and that farther struggle was useless. He yielded to his fate, and was whirled on as in a dream. He knew not how it ended, nor when nor where his horse stopped. He had an indistinct idea of hearing voices about him, and of trampling feet, and anxious 'faces, and of being car- ried to a house; but it was all confused. When he came to himself he was in his own bed.-- There was a feeling of pain about his head, as if he had received a blow. His daughter was sitting at a table near him; but still his mind Was not clear. He looked around -him and muttered something about 'that difference,' and ' hounds and Tom Floyd and Pepper,' and while he was speaking he dropped off into a- doze; Late in the evening he awoke again. His head was clear, and his mind was ripe for business. He called his daughter to him. ' Where's Pepper?' Esther looked at him with a strange expression. 'He's in the stable.' , 'Alive? ' ' Yes; what should kill him? ' Obed had it on his tongue to tell his story, but he remembered that he had not figured to much advantage in the night's adventure; so he held his peace, although he did mutter: 'That horse's wind and bottom are tremendous.' Again he sank back on his pillow, and with half-closed eyes lay watching his daughter as she worked. As he watched her dreamy eyes and finely- chiselled -features, with the delicate and almost ethereal bloom on her cheek, and the glossy hair which rested on her brows, he thought that angels must look as she did. 'Angels have nothing of earth in them,' said the girl. Again that startling echo to his thoughts. Her eyes were fixed on his, and again that searching unfathomable glance which made him cower. At that moment he heard a firm strong tread on the door-step, and a single loud bold knock at the door. He knew it well, although he could not hear the voice; and he knew well the step which was mounting the stairs without haste, deliberate and resolved; and it did not need the glance which he gave to tell him that John Wakeman was coming in. 'Ah I know it's about that difference,' muttered he watching his visitor with eyes brilliant with feverish excitement. John Wakeman wasted no words. 'I 've brought your money, Sir,' said v he, taking out a well-worn leather purse. He began to count the money on the table. The girl drew back and watched the two with an expression of the most intense sadness.  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7984-00000023"/> "             OBED GROOT. 'As he finished the old man stretched out his hand to grasp it, when the girl hastily rose and put her hand on his. '0 father I do n't touch it. I know that it comes from a wrecked house- hold, from a broken heart. Do not tke it, I implore you, as you value all that is most dear to you. There is some wealth which comes coupled with a curse, all such is that which is wrung from the heart-blood of the poor. Touch it not.' She bowed her head over his hand, and held it clasped in both of hers. 'Take it away,' said she abruptly raising her head and speaking fast. 'Tempt him not to his ruin ' The .farmer looked steadily at her. There was an expression of honest admiration in his eyes, and for a moment his voice faltered. ' The money is 3jUtiy:his; I tempt him not. There is no wrong in my giving nor,in his receiving what is due to him.' 'There, therel Estherl you hear him,' said Obed in a querulous tone: 'he says it's mine.' The girl heeded him not. 'The money is due indeed, and that you offered it, is right, but is there nothing due from the rich to the poor? Is there not somewhere an account .kept which shows that although the debtor may owe gold the creditor owes mercy? I've read it somewhere. . John, now answer me?  Has it not cost you sorrow, perhaps tears, to procure this money?' 'It's honestly come by,' said the man. 'I know that well,' replied the girl taking his hard hand, 'but are there no tears on that gold?' The man was silent. Esther stood looking in his face with the same grave earnestness. 'I 've heard of your misfortunes,' said she. ' Would not this aid you to get on again?' 'I cannot say but that it would,' replied the man. 'You hear that, father?' said she eagerly. ' You know that he has lost nearly all he had on earth. You will let him lhave it until better times. Will: you not?' Obed turned testily on his bed. ' The girl's mad I Reach me that ink- stand, John. I will write you a receipt for the money.' ' Father--  'Not a  word more not a single word! Hitherto you've been a quiet, obedient girl. Od rat the girl, what's in her?' The farmer reached the pen and ink to the old man, who sat up in the bed, and wrote the receipt. The other took it, folded it up, and put it in his pocket. Before he went he approached Esther and took her band. ' I once had a daughter. Thank GOD, she died before we came to what we now are. It was a heavy sorrow then; but I can see the kindness of it now, for it would have added a  great weight to my heart'to have dimmed her young youth with the sorrows which overshadow me. But if she had lived I feel that she would have been like you, and I could have asked nothing better for her.'   OBED GROOT.              -45 He turned abruptly from her, and his heavy step was heard as he de. scended the stairs and left the house. Once more Esther approached the bed. 'Father, let me call him back before he is gone too far; I implore it for your sake; I implore it for the love of heaven. Oh I you know not all that is depending on your words and acts this night.' Despite the sadness of her tone, Obed was fairly roused to wrath. ' I tell you no I a thousand times no! Were the very hell-hounds which placed me here, in this very room, I 'd tell you no /' Esther drew back, and a mysterious change came over her as she spoke: 'Now hear me yet again. It is not too late.' In her voice there was a tone of solemn sadness such as he had never heard before, and which filled his heart with foreboding; ,butthe#tegrim demon, which had griped it so long still kept his hold there, and struggled hard to keep his holier feelings out. He shook his head. She did not regard his gesture, but spoke on: I From my childhood until now I have been with you. I have seen you grow from poverty to wealth. You were an earnest, striving, frugal man; you struggled and fought your way on; you placed dollar by dollar, and as you saw your store increase your heart grew glad.' The old man chuckled in his bed, and rubbed his hands, his eye gleaming with satisfaction. ' Ay, girl, money is power, remember that, always remember that.' But she waved her head and went on: 'As your heart rejoiced it also grew hard and strong. Its better feelings one by one were frozen out, until at last but one single overwhelming passion filled it: crushing to atoms all others, and sitting there alone -' the sordid love of gain."' The old man made a gesture of impatience. 'I'm no worse than my neighbors,' muttered he, ' not a whit worse.' The girl went on: ' I watched this feeling as it grew. Child as I was, I tried to battle against it, and turn you to better things. I hoped as I grew older, and as coming years gave weight and influence to my words, I still might redeem the past and win you from your threatened destiny. Itwas #a hard task, for all went well with you. When blight and mildew swept the lands of others, you gathered in your harvest rich and plentiful. No murrain' touched your flocks. You turned to other ventures, and still success followed in your train. Wherever you went, whatever you did, the gifts of GOD were   showered on you in rich profusion. But amid them all, your heart still clung to earth and them. It was never raised in gratitude to the GIVER, nor did it dream of the object of the gift.' ' You're wrong, my child, indeed you are,' said the old man with a tremu- lous voice, ' I was grateful, indeed I was. I said my prayeIs always.' 'Idle words bearing no fruit I What acts of yours ever showed that the blessings which you received were extended by you to others?' demanded the girl sternly.  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7984-00000024"/> "             OBED GROOT. Obed mauttered something about throwing away mercy on wasteful impro- vident vagabonds. 'The poor were about you by hundreds, nay by thousands; the earth was teeming with'them.: Their cry for help, by you ever unheeded, from you went to heaven with the story of its wrongs, with not one voice to saythat you had sheltered, fed or clothed. Such as sought you, you taunted with the calamities which HBAEVN had cast upon them, as crimes of-their own committing. The result came. Your house was shunned by every one who-felt that sorrow and sutfering formed a claim to aid and sympathy from all who belonged to the gieat brotherhood of man. I was your child, and had an. errand to fulfil. Time was waning fast; the frosts of age were' on your brow. What if eternity were'reached an-d fOudyou-lto st to mrcj 'and t'o o'- '-Who are you$t?,jeniand{lthe- ld man sitting up in, his bed, 'that you speak thus to me'  'As yet your childl ' '! was afraid you had forgotten it,' replied he, 'now let me tell you I'll have no more of this.' The girl looked sadly in his face. 'Be it as you have said, my mission 's ended.' As; she spoke, she stood before him no longer a timid shrinking child. She still wore the semblahce of her former self, but there was an air almost of glory about her person, and a majesty in her clear eye, from which all earthly passion had fled,- and her low startling tones spoke like conscience. ' Now hear and see the hidden past, and from that divine the future.' All about him seemed to whirl. The room, the furniture, the bed whirled and whirled, and then became a mist. The mist gathered into masses which filled all space, and pressed upon him. He shook with mortal fear, and closed his eyes, for he shrank from what was to come. Again the voice of Esther came stealing on his ear: so quiet yet so commanding that he could not but listen. 'Now hear the past as you know it not, and yet as you know it well. The flight of time rolls back upon itself, and as the curtain which shrouds the past draws back, I see a feeble, sickly boy with his head bowed at his mother's knee, his hands clasped, and his lips uttering a lisping prayer: a very feeble-prayer to reach so far; yet whispered as it was, it ascended to the Great Throne, borne upward by the strong fervid supplication of her who brouight him into being, and now sheltered him beneath her strong love. I saw her borne to her grave, and the boy, as yet a child, left to the care of strangers, beneath whose neglect the lessons of his childhood were swept away. His nature became stern, and he grew up a cold and hardened man, strong to fight the great battle of life, and struggle for the rewards of earth, without one thought of her who had sheltered his young life, without one thought of the great reckoning to come. Again I see him in his youth a plod- ding striving man, with earnest anxious brow and toil-hardened hands. He is sitting at a table with a book in his hand thumbed and well worn. It marks   OBED GROOT.              47 the progress of his gains, and he pores and ponders over it, turning from it only to look at a small box near by which holds those gains, the, story of which is written in the book. Upon a shelf near by there lies another book. It is dust-covered, and has been undisturbed for months; a spider has woven his- web around it, and rests there in security. It is a book of promises, of promises which never fail.' Obed turned uneasily in his bed. 'I know it well,' muttered he. 'My mother's BIBLE. She gave it when I was a boy, a very little boy.' The girl did not seem to hear him. ' Promises made when the earth was in its infancy and humanity was- tainted first with sin. - Promises which have ever been. fulfilled, and ever been renewed, as man's wants called them into birth, and whose:glad realization ,ahall. exist. when earth and man shall be swept away, and Time itself merged in the: great oceanuof : thich it,- forms a drop-- Eternity.: Obed raised his eyes, but he could not bear the earnest mysterious gaze that met his own.' He trembled at her words; and yet he could not but love and reverence her, for he felt their truth like Holy Writ. 'Speak, I charge you,' said he with half-imploring, half-shrinking gesture; 'let me know the worst, who are you?' ' Hear the rest,' answered the girl. ' From childhood until now there was one commissioned from on high to guard and direct the footsteps of that man as he journeyed along the road which leads to the dark valley; and to point out the seed of good workswhich might be sowed on earth, and yield a glo- rious harvest for the garners of eternity. But he would none of her counsel. He heeded not her whisperings. Seared in conscience and flint in heart, he turned away from the calls of HEAVEN and fixed his eyes on earth.' O0 my child! my child I do not rebuke me thus,' said the wretched man clasping his hands, and bowing his head upon tfiem. I If I were hard to others I was never so to thee. If I labored to become rich, it was that you might enjoy it. If I loved gold, if I perilled all to get it, it was because my love for you was greater than all else I Do not speak thus. I cannot bear it.' He bowed his head upon his clasped hands, and the tears trickled through his fingers. 'Your love to me was the last hope of heaven. The guardian spirit took her station at your side through life. In form your child, the object of your love and care; but still your guardian, with the same solemn duties, with the same high trust committed to her, and with that holy love alone as the last, link of the golden chain to lead you from earth to heaven. With mortal form came mortal frailties, but far above all earthly cares was the high and holy purpose for which she came. Now tell me bqfore I go, for earth is passed with me forever, was I recreant to my trust?' The old man spoke not, for his heart was filled with its own conmmunings. The memory of the past was sweeping through his mind, wasted opportuni- ties, the great omissions, time speeding on and pointing to age, decrepitude- and death. He dared not look up at his accuser. He dared not answer. At last the words, 'My child,' burst from his full heart, ' speak one word of  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7984-00000025"/> 48             OBED GROOT. pardon for the past.' There was no response. Once more he looked up. His daughter lay lifeless before him. With a wild cry he flung himself at her side. ' Esther, dear child of my heart I guardian spirit! whoever thou art, come back; oh 1 leave me not forever I ' The lifeless form moved not; and as he struggled to raise her from the ,ground he saw standing at her side the semblance of herself, ethereal as a phan- tom, serenely beautiful, yet calm and passionless as ice. He stretched out his hand imploringly. 'If thou art she who has been life-long at my side, to keep me from sin, come back I By HIM who died upon the cross, I implore it. By HM who heard the dying cry of one who led a life of crime, and sought His mercy only in the throes of death, and pardoned for Hxs holy sakei pardon and return.' 'Man I ' replied the ,piriti.'I can never again be child of thine. While mortal means could lead you right, my errand was on earth. That time is past; the future, is in the hand of Hin whom we all obey.' ' Yet--hear me once again,' said the wretched man rising up and confront- ing the form, whose dim outline was shadowed still before him. LBy your own value of man's salvation I as -you would -not abandon a human soul to perdition, and consign it to everlasting woe, I charge you desert me not in this my hour of utmost need and deepest agony, when all that is good within me is battling for life against the power of evil. Daughter , spirit I whatever you are I you dare not thus desert me for whose redemption such a price was paid. There is a promise in the bootk which you, even you, oft read to me: ' That no call for mercy, however late, shall be unheeded; that no sin, however dark, but can be washed away.' You dare not thus desert your trust, and take your flight to HM who sent you, with your errand unfulfilled; for my cry for mercy and pardon would follow you to His very feet and condemn you there.' There was no response to his passionate appeal; and as -he held out his hands, imploringly, the dim form faded from his sight, all about him seemed to change, and a mist which had obscured his brain swept away. He was lying in his bed. The sunlight was streaming through the window; a bird was carolling on a tree near by, and his daughter was sitting at his bed-side holding his hand in hers. The old man clasped his arms about her and held her fast. 'My child, my own dear child I I promise all. I'll do all you ask. I never knew till now how great a debt I owe and how little of it I have paid: the great debt which riches owe to poverty.' He bowed his head upon her shoulder'; his gray locks mingling with her bright tresses, and still he kept his hold. He whispered in her ear: ' Send back John Wakeman's money. I '1I not take it.' His daughter looked at him with a bewildered air, and passed her hand affectionately over his gray hair, but made no reply. 'Do n't tell me that it 's too late,' said he passionately. He locked at the table where John had left the money.  There was nothing there. 'Where is it?I saw him count it out on that very table.'   OBED GROOT.              49 Esther took his hand gently. ' -You've been dreaming, father. You nad a   Si fall from your, horse, and have been dreaming ever since.'  -        ? Could that strange sad scene be but a dream! If it were, he thanked GOD that it was so, and not a stern reality. Like the Israelite King of old he turned his face to the wall, but in silence, and with that silence were mingled prayers; prayers which were no longer idle words, but throve and bore fruit; and when he arose from his bed of pain--for he lingered there some days - his . resolutions had taken shape, and settled in the one fixed purpose of spreading sunshine in his path and gladness in that of others. He felt that the dream was a revelation from on high, and that his daughter all unknowing was his guardian angel still The first thing he, did was to v eit Pepper. He eamrqned him from head-to heel, and thumped his ribs, There had always been,a prodigious display of bone about Pepper, and it was all there still. 'That horse is a wonder,' mut- tered Obed. Pepper looked over his shoulder at him as if he agreed with him. ' We 'll keep what we know to ourselves, won't we, Pepper? ' He tried to do so, but it was useless. Two old negroes and a woman had seen him on his mad race, and the adventure got wind. He denied it stoutly; but with his denial its circulation increased until it obtained the full credit which it merited; and it passed into a proverb when one was dealing with a hard creditor: ' May you ride on Obed Groot's hunt ' From that eventful night he changed his ways. He sent for John Wake- man, and not only gave him time to pay his debt, but helped him forward in the world; so that in a few years he/ became a thriving, prosperous man. As Obed indulged the feeling of benevolence and kindness to his fellow- man it grew and throve; so that his heart, from being of the size of a dried currant, waxed large and generous in its impulses; and a poor neighbor, whom he had rescued from poverty and vice, swore that it was as large as a pumpkin. From being shunned, his house became the seat of hospitality; the corners of his mouth lost their old habit of turning down, and his chin was safe. His daughter was with him still, with her calm counsels cheering him on, with a husband to help her; and with several little guardian angels to tease and worry Obed, and climb his knee and pull his hair; but he gathered them in his . arms, and declared that all the world could not produce their equals. His only regret was, that he had not discovered the grand secret of happi- ness until so late; and that so much time had been wasted ere life's true labor had been commenced. e.  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7984-00000026"/> o50 A FADED LEAiF FROM THE 'FAIR RIVEK.' BY JOHN P. BROWN, U. B. DRAGOMAN AT CONSTANTINOPLE. IT is now more than thirty years since I last stood on the banks of the Ohio. How many changes have taken place on that 'fair river,' and in me, during that space of time I With what varied emotions I look back and along the narrow pathway of my eventful life; the varied scenes through which I have passed in the four quarters of the globe I I recognize, with a grateful heart:and tremulous lips, the great 'mercy which endureth forever,' which has guidedty wandering Stepri and preserved me from harm, even in my erring ways; and, while this companion of my youth, and that elder friend of my boyhood, have been swept away down the swift current of life, I have been spared to return again to the 'fair river,' and standing once more on its loved banks to collect a few of the * faded leaves' which, like myself,. are tinged by autumnal frosts, In this space of time, I have only had twice the satisfaction of visiting my native village. It is one of the earlier settlements of what was once the ' Far West, and it has little increased in proportions within the period mentioned. Surrounded by dear old hills, blessed with a fine soil, an industrious and thrifty population, it is one of the most flourishing and happy valleys of Ohio. On the occasion of my first visit to my boyhood's home, an incident oc- curred which I may now relate as one of the ' faded leaves ' stowed away in the strongholds of my memory. Should the persons alluded to in them ever peruse these lines, they will not, I am confident, be displeased at my pointing a moral by the narrative of an event which has had so beneficial a result, so happy a termination. On landing from a steamer at Cleveland, and seeking the means of con- tinuing my way southward - in those days rail-roads did not run through all parts of the State as at present - a young woman, dressed in black, and bear- ing a very young child in her arms, inquired of me the quickest and cheapest route to  , the same place to which I was proceeding. She had heard me ask for. a ticket to that place, and, with a hesitating tone, made the inquiry. Her youth-she was not more than eighteen-the pallor of her countenance, evident unhappiness and mental suffering, and her personal beauty elicited my attention and sympathy. Her infant was very young, I would not ven- ture to fix its age; and, as it lay wrapped up in the mother's shawl, half-wak- ing, half-sleeping, its sweet little mild blue eyes immediately excited my too great sensitiveness. I would add that the woman, I may call her the lady, was tall and slender, and possessed personal charms well calculated to speak in her favor. To her question I replied: ' I am going there, Madam, and will be happy   A FADED LEAF FROM THE 'FAIR RIVER.'         51 to be of any service to you in my power. Have you taken a ticket and at- tended to your baggage '  After a moment's hesitation, her countenance showing evident confusion) she replied: 'I have no baggage, Sir, and I have not, I fear, sufficient-money to pay for the passage of myself and child. Here is my little all; pray do not leave me here among strangers; and if you will add whatever is deficient in my means I will try and restore it to you when I arrive among my friends.' On uttering the last word 'friends,' she repeated it, and added: 'Alas! if in- deed I now have any.'                       a During my protracted travels, I have not unfrequently been exposed to im. positions on the part of both men and women, which, I must admit, havein- spired me witheas sinal! portion of incredulity and sxuspiion for the tales of woe and misfortune suddenly told me without preface,:' orome: previous knowledge of the party. On the other hand; I have a strong impulse, which leads me to offer any succor or alleviation in my power to the unhappy or the wretched, if they seem so, without seeking to know the cause of the misery before me. Actuated by this feeling, I begged her to take a seat while I en- gaged her ticket. On my return I sat down beside her, and handed her the ticket and the paper containing her little money.- She took them from my hand mechanically, and pressed them in her own without uttering a word. She turned her face from me to the window for some minutes, during which the carriage moved on, and it was easy to perceive that her feelings prevented her from speaking, and that her eyes were filled with tears. During the first half-hour or so of our journey I advanced casual remarks upon the scenery on the road, which withdrew her attention from herself, and somewhat calmed her distress. However, now and then the prevailing feeling would come uppermost in her mind; she sighed heavily, would press her sleeping infant to her breast, and then turn away her face from me. Though unwilling from principle to intrude, either my consolations upon her grief or to seek to know its history, I finally ventured to inquire whether she was a native of --, and who were her relations and friends there: add- ing that I asked more in the view and hope of rendering her still farther ser- vice than from simple curiosity. Gradually she gained confidence, and to my X very great surprise gave me her name, Ellen C--, the daughter of one of the oldest friends of my parents, and a warm patron of my youth. Her brothers had been my constant companions and school-mates; their home had been my htme, and my home theirs; I had followed two of them in my boyhood to their uStimely graves, and the memory of them is still fresh and deeply impressed in my heart and memory. One, the eldest, had since married, and gone to the farther West, and one only remained with the father. Even now, after the lapse of so many years, I cannot recall the figures of the two who died in their youth without emotions of the saddest nature. In later years, after my de- parture from my native village, I had heard that the mother had borne one more child, a daughter, of whom I knew nothing, and died in giving life to her infant. The loss of his mate had almost left the father, now well advanced in years, in a state of distraction bordering on insanity, and it was only by the  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7984-00000027"/> ADED LEAF FROM TiHE 'FAIR RIVER.' repeated exertions of his neighbors and friends to console him, and by re- minding him that the existence of his infant daughter required his love and care, that he regained tranquillity. Ellen C-   went on to tell me, without knowing that I had the slightest knowledge of her family and home, that about a year ago a young man from Montreal visited her village, and through her brother became intimate at her father's house. She did not mention his name. He was more handsome and attractive than, as is seen in the sequel, he was honorable and virtuous. He engaged her affections; she loved him with all the strength, fervor and confi- dence of a first love. Her mind was frank and simple, and she thought of no guile or wrong. The young man's business soon called him back to Montreal. Well knowing that i agedfathe would never permit her to leave him, for he doted on her anthat it would be hopeless to expect to be united in the vil- lage, even clandestinely, she lent ear to the Canadian's promise to convey her to his own home, there marry her, and this once effected, to induce his own parents to allow him to return to her village, and establish himself in busi- ness. She detailed to me the struggle which this plan created in her mind. Brought up without theecare of a mother, almost in seclusion and ignorance of the world, and the wiles of evil designing men, she consented to elope with him,. fully expecting to return in a few weeks. She left a letter on her table where it would be seen by her father as soon as he rose in the morning, ex- plaining the plan which she accepted, assured him of her early return with her intended husband, and asked his forgiveness of the step and his blessing. As usual she kissed her unsuspecting parent good-night, and then, as con- certed with her lover, met him on the way-side, where he waited for her with a carriage. In a few days they reached Montreal, and she was taken not.to her lover's own home, but to a room in an obscure part of the city. Various excuses were offered for this course by him, which to her simple and unsuspecting mind were at first satisfactory, but which soon failed to convince her of his probity and honesty. She was, however, no longer in a position to act with independence; and had no means either of writing to her father or brother, or of making her situation known to those who might possibly have protected her. She ascertained from an old woman, to whom the house in which they resided belonged, that her lover's parents were Catholics, and that she need not indulge in the hope that they wouHl ever allow him to marry her. As the  period approached for her to become a mother, he began to neglect her, to treat her even with unkindness; and when she ventured for the first time to expos- tulate with him for it, and for his deception, he told her that he wished she was back in her father's house. Whether or not her father and brother had taken any step toward ascertaining her fate, she had no means of learning. Her seducer's harshness finally grieved away her love, it became insupportable, practised probably in the view of getting rid of his victim, and after a severe mental struggle she determined, so soon as the age of her child permitted it, to seek her way back to her father's house. 'What I suffered,' said.she, 'no one can- imagine. Contrition, shame, remorse and despair filled me with the   most harrowing reflections. Ignorant even of my father's continuance in life, and knowing well the misery to which my false step and desertion must have reduced him, I thought even of putting an end to my own existence. Yet a sense of religion, and the presence of my innocent child, drove the cruel thought' from my mind.' By selling her wardrobe, through the intervention of the woman of the house, she procured sufficient means, as she thought, to defray her expenses; and on the plea of taking a walk, left the scene of her sufferings. She reached Buffalo, and thence Cleveland, on her way to the southern part of Ohio, where my acquaintance with her commenced, as afore related. What occurrence could be prodictive of deeper'interest than the return'of an only daughter sinfuli and'penitent to  a ged aid_ tlessly'heart-broken father I Here waS a poor, simple-miinded, deluded gifl,'crushed with the full conviction of her cruelty toward an only parent, whose whole existence had been wrapped up in the warmest love for his child; whose very birth had brought desolation to his heart, and deprived him of the solace and comfort of a wife, just when he had begun to need it most. Was he yet alive: would he consent to pardon and forgive such desertion? For the world she took no thought; her whole soul was bent on regaining the hearth and home of her childhood; to implore the forgiveness which she well knew she had forfeited; to hide her shame and repentance under the paternal roof, and devote her en- tire future existence to the. innocent babe which 'lay smiling and looking up into the face of the heart-broken mother, wholly unconscious of the hot tears which flowed fast down her cheeks, more than one dropping on its little face. I offered her all the consolation which, in the state of her mind, I could venture to express. Rather sensitive myself, and easily affected by the sight of so much grief, I will not attempt now to explain what were my own feel ings. They form one of those 'faded leaves' which I treasure up in the store-house of my memory of the 'long, long ago.' It was nearly night-fall when I reached my native village. Ellen's father resided a 'couple of miles from the village, and I engaged a light vehicle to carry her and her babe to his house. Believing, from the many years which had elapsed since the old man had seen me, that he would not recognize me, I offered to drive her there myself; and not to leave her until I could learn the result of her interview 'with her father. From some of the bystanders I learned that her father still lived, though quite feeble and bed-ridden with age. Even this first news occasioned Ellen much consolation and relief. In a short time we approached the house. It was much changed from what I recollected. As a boy it had always appeared to me to be a veryJlofty edifice, and the hills which surrounded it quite mountains; now they seemed diminutive in size: such is the effect of time, and the means of com- parison afforded us in after-years. There was the same orchard in which, with her brothers, I had gathered apples as a boy; the well with its long pole was the same; and the tall poplars before the entrance seemed but little affected by time. Leaving the carriage with Ellen at the gate, I ventured in to break her re-  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7984-00000028"/> 54      A FADED LEAF FROM THE 'FAIR RIVER.' turn and communicate with any member of her brother's family whom I might find there. Fortunately his wife and children were there in charge of their good parent. With some embarrassment, I must admit, I .broke the news of the penitent's return to the daughter-in-law, her husband being absent, and begged her to break it to the father. She at first hesitated, and said she feared he would never consent to see held, that her elopement had quite crushed him, and that he now seldom mentioned her name, except when in his sleep the memory of her visited him in his dreams, or his mindiwandered, as it often did. It was then clear, she told me, that Ellen was constantly in his re- membrance. Her cruel act had grievously wounded the respect of her parent and her sister-in-law,and it was only afteilhad related to her something of what fiilen had tolmedassured" thedf her, hearthgOken condition and, her deep repqntiate, that i siucceededa in gaining her assistance. She at length consented to convey the tidings of her return to her father, and I waited the result with no ordinary feelings of anxiety and apprehension. On her return she told me that she feared the shock was more than he could bear; that he talked incoherently, now looking round the room as if in search of his lost child, while again he refused her. admission to his roof. It was, however, decided between us that Ellen should be brought before him, in the hope that her presence, thot of her innocent babe, and her tearfulsimplorations, would procure her forgiveness.  On my return to the carriage, where poor Ellen awaited me with the deepest impatience, my heart was too full to permit me to say more than to bid her come rith me. Taking her babe in my arms, we entered the house, where the daughter-in-law embraced her in silence. Then leading the way into thc- chamber of the aged parent, we all three stood by his bed-side. Never shall I cease to remember, with the freshness of a yesterday's occurrence, the pain- ful scene which ensued. Raising himself on his pillow, the old man, trembling withemotion, looked poor Ellen for a moment in the face; then falling back, he covered his eyes with his hands, and exclaimed in an agony of grief: ' Great GoD! is it possi- ble? No, it is not her; I have no daughter; the child I once had has deserted me, and, covered with sin, can never be restored to me again.' His hand fell helplessly. on the bed-side, and his eyes turned upward, as if to heaven, showed the struggle which agitated him. Poor Ellenl Overcome with remorse and the most poignant grief for the desolation she had brought to her aged father's breast, she threw herself upon her knees, and seizing her father's hand covered it with kisses and tears. ' 0 father ' she cried, 'have mercy upon me; I am your own Ellen, a poor, heart-broken, sinful creature, come to implore forgiveness where she well knows she merits none.' The father evidently attempted to withdraw his hand, and turned his face away from her; on seeing. which Ellen fell lifeless on the floor, startling the aged man with the noise, so that he turned again to gaze at the form of his fallen and prostrate daughter. Overcome with the scene before me, I scarcely knew what I did or said. While the sister-in-law looked after poor Ellen, I approached the father's bed.   A FADED LEAF FROM THE 'FAIR    RIVER.'      55 side and implored him to forgive his sinful, his deeply repentant daughter. 1 conjured him for the sake of the love he had borne for her departed mother, for that of his two sons, whose names I mentioned, and who had died in their youth, to say but one kind word to his daughter. I reminded him of the pre. cedent of that dear SAVIOUR of repentant sinners, who forgave the, erring woman, and in place of sending her away in grief and despair bade her kindly: 'Go, and sin no more.' These Qords seemed to touch the parent's heart, for he had always been a pious member of the Presbyterian church of. my native village; and the tears which gushed from his eyes told me that I had not ap: pealed thus in vain. As he raised himself again upon his pillow to gazyUpon the still prostate form of poor Ellen Hemthraceda the-opportunity to .  y .sleeping babe 'before him, telling him that it was his daughter's child. AAh I then you should have witnessed the effect which the sight of the sweet infant had upon the old man's heart. Again he exclaimed: ' O GoD I is this possible: is this indeed my child's child? Merciful FATHER I this is greater than I can bear. Ellen Il Ellen I ' he added in a tone of the deepest tenderness: 'where is my own Ellen? ' As if the sound of her father's voice, in tones of affection and forgiveness, had been more effectual in arousing her stunned faculties than the remedies used by her sister-in-law, Ellen sprang to her feet, and in a moment 'was clasped in her father's arms. For a few moments neither could find utterance to a word. Ellen was the first to speak; all she could say was: 'Forgive me, forgive me I O my father I' and her prayer was responded to with: 'Ellen, I forgive thee, for the love which I have for thy sainted mother and thy brothers! ' I need dwell no longer on the scene of forgiveness. I sat down for a moment to seek composure before bidding the parent and daughter farewell. I never shall forget the look of gratitude and surprise which poor Ellen gave me as I told her my name - one well known to her - and pressed her hand in mine. Many years have swept by since the occurrence which I have attempted to narrate. I have again been an absentee from my much-favored native land: a wanderer in the wide, wide world. Long ago Ellen's father was interred in' the little graveyard within the orchard, by the side of his wife and sons. Her babe, which she named Mary, after her own mother, had grown up to woman- hood, and married a worthy young farmer of the neighboring country, and resides with her mother at the homestead. Some months subsequent to the return of Ellen and, her father's forgiveness, an elderly lady, a friend of her family, having learned the part which I had taken in her return, wrote me a letter which I preserve, and of which I may now add an extract as a moral to my ' tale,' if so it be: 'Although not personally acquainted with you, I feel a pleasure in ,writing you these lines. Allow me also to thank you for your timely assistance to my- friend Ellen C--, and to offer you the blessing of one who will before long follow her dear mother to the tomb. If we knew the amount of temptation  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7984-00000029"/> 56      .SONNET. to which weak and confiding young females are exposed by wicked men, we would certainly have pity on them when repentant. Parents overlook the re. peated sins of their sons, while they give the whole weight of their anger and unforgiveness upon their erring daughters. If mothers would receive back their poor daughters, when crushed under a sense of grief, remorse, and con- trition, how many young women would be rescued from lives of sin, sorrow, and death-beds without repentance; and4ilhus, restored to their maternal arms, enjoy the dearest hope in which parents may indulge-that of meeting them in the life to come. v That you may ever be happy, and be spared the trial of Ellen's father, is the fervent prayer of opr sincere friend,           M. a. B. "^'  9    \ '  e ;  . i + In - . ,  SONNET. BY  HENRY  W. ROCKWELL. A PECUNIARY CONSIDERATION FOR A. FAIR CREDITOR. ' Quosque tandem.'-Pop. Rom. vs. Cataline: Cicero, Dist. Att'y. ' I O.U.'-Wall St. Brok. Mem. Stk. Ex. et pass(h)im. ' Time, how long, is put in the accuwative.' -Latin Grammar. Old Ed. CREDIT.: Oall Round Every Day, I 'll Trust. DEBT., : Do n't Every Body Trust? THE rose itself matures by falling dew; And Day, the creditor, demands of Eve Her earliest dews, so I do not perceive But all things are in debt, as I to you. , Streams fail, storms burst, and morning mists go Ap; The steadfast hills themselves at times cave in; The morning breaks, nor is it deemed a sin; 'T is best, when breahking, to the eye of Hope. The sweet wind sues the streams, and they in turn Have their affairs in constant liquidation; There 's not a star in heaven that doth not burn In the full glory of procrastination; But the attachment you have served on me: How shall I meet it at maturity!   OUR. OLD 'MEETING-iHOUSE-.' BY MSS C. M. SEDGWICK. MEETING-HOUSE - not church. That designation originated with the Romish hierarchy, and was continued by its elder sister the Church of England, an4d of course was rejected by the Puritans ; our ' Old Meeting-House' in S-- hag passed away. It is now only remembered by that thin congregation, 'the oldest inhabitants' and in their mi'idstit is associatedpth few pleasant memb; ries. It was a huge unsightly edie, irthout fromeliness, built on a bleak hill-side in the geographical centre of the town, Mi the proximity of but one family; thus putting every other under the necessity of breaking the Fourth Commandment by making the horses work on the Sabbath day, which at that period was observed in our Puritanical districts with judaical strict- ness. A bitter quarrel between the agricultural population at the northern extremity of the township, and the aristocratic centre, 'the village,' had been appeased, by no means settled, by an arbitration which decreed this site. Instead of one party being made gracious and happy by a triumph over the other both were dissatisfied and discontented, and met weekly with an ill-sup- pressed hostility most unfitting the day that should be hallowed by peace and good-will. That generation has passed away. ' The rude forefathers of the hamlet' sleep in peace in the village church-yard, and the bickerings and silly jealousies that bespattered and sullied their lives are forgotten. GOD forbid that we should recall them! It is not for this unkind purpose that we revert to the 'Old Meeting-House,' but to preserve the relics of Puritanical observances and rustic manners that are becoming irretrievable. On every Sabbath morning the whole population of the town tended to the Old Meeting-House,' then Cromwell's church. The old Independent Congre- gational regime was our only authorized Christian organization. We had no stronghold for papacy like the stone edifice now in process of erection under the consecrating shadow of ' Laurel Hill;' no indication that the august Pro- testant Episcopal Church, (from whose ordinances our ancestors had escaped,) could ever exercise its ritual here as it now does at its ' St. Paul's in the very centre of our village. There were few Dissenters. A handful of Methodists might worship in sequestered groves; or a little band of Baptists might unmo- lested immerse their followers in obscure brooks. There were few scoffers so audacious as to shirk the Sabbath duty, and very few vagrants that escaped its coercion. On every Sunday two coaches, (there were then but two within the boundaries of our township,) wagons, ' one horse shays,' riders and pedes- trians might be seen traversing the roads from north, south, east and west that conducted to the old ' meeting-house.' Our way led over a sandy plain, and along the declivity of the hill which  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7984-00000030"/> 58         OUKR OLD. ' MEETING-HOUSE.' the meeting-house surmounted. The road was narrow and without a railing, and the monotony of the day was not unfrequently relieved by the perils of restive horses and reckless drivers oyer this dangerous passage; and now and then the lovers of excitement were gratified by wagons overset, and their liv- ing cargoes rolling over the hillside, not always escaping broken limbs and  . scarred faces. The pedestrians had the bestopf it, secure from accident, linger- ing by the way-side at the 'stations,' under'he broad shadows of willows and :ns; and sure, like Charles Lamb, of coming away with the earliest, though they arrived with the latest. There were two ' stations' deserving grateful remembrance. Aunt Silla's humble dwelling, where the rich damask rose blossomed in luxurious profusion, and j, fireely bestowed on her favorites, who;Q *w!er invited,t9^^l^^e ie .a lests-e ref 8im'^ fromi a white earthen mug-A&amp; write fle   d  io    e  -X mio'set thin potation - bit far superiof woura  !:rIjj ection, to the Champagne and Chartreuse of these our latterdasys. Aunt Silla's way-side charities didn't stop here. We were allowed to pluck out of her little garden green stems of caraway, ' dill,' and fennel, pleasant spices that were helps to old women and children through the' tedium of the sermon. Our last station was a clear cold spring in a rocky nook under the hill--a place worthy the shrine of a saint. There hung a tin cup from which we all drank, (we were not fastidious in those days,) prepara- tory to the dryness of the services.. And even during the services wearied little urchins were often seized with a panic of thirst that could only be relieved by permission to go down to the spring, where they remained as if the curse of Tantalus had fallen on them. The * Old Meeting-House' was a hideous structure of huge timbers and rat- tling shingles, a most rude and unsightly building, that might have been modelled after a nightmare vision of some Puritan-hating cavalier; and oh! how it rocked and cracked and groaned complaining and threatening to our frightened senses through all our windy months. Nothing but the awful voices' of a ship in a storm was ever so terrible. And how we used to look around in vain for sympathy to the fossilized faces of patient listeners; and wonder that the preacher could enforce the doctrine of election through a 'ninthly' and ' tenthly' when it seemed that we were all, without any election, condemned to instant destruction. But the 'Old Meeting-House' stood, and our. good old pastor, Dr. W--, preached in it for more than sixty years, while generations of the blooming girls in the ' singers' seat' exchanged glances with the ' tenor and base:' mated with them, bore children, and passed away. There was one'architectural peculiarity in the ' Old lMeeting-House,' an ab normal arrangement, a crotchet that originated in the brain of an old bachelor, and by some audacious little jesters among the boys called after him ' the Par tr idgf nest.' -This was the' high pew,' a long open box appended to the west- ern wall, and elevated above the gallery. From this .pew there was a view of nearly every member of the congregation. There sat, a sort of demonstrated in- dependence .of all social relations, the little wiry old bachelor himself. Nature   OUR OLD ,MEETING-HOUSE.'            59 was too strong for him, and could not be thrust out of his heart.: He avoided  !! all legalized claims from wife, children and friends, but he bestowed freely the earnings of- his diligent life on kindred to the tlird and fourth generation, , Beside our par excellence ' old bachelor,' and beside the vagrants who sat in the ' high pew,' because they had no rights or privileges elsewhere, there, in frightful conspicut, were stati ed the ' tithing men,' (called by-.lisping chi4ld; ren 'tidy men,') the police of tht church, whose business it was to detectthh commerce of smiles and glances between the lads and lassies; and whose du4y (it seemed to us their delight) it was to mark for condign punishmentsthaist little wretches who were betrayed into playing,. or surprised into laughing in -meeting-time: th phrase yet ringsin our ears likle akncl . There were /lyb/b/teiiat/ci!   '?   M    BOl douse:.' Pusancus- toms' that coulfd ha V6beewn't m aiditained 'only^a i pl   a pillory,. was an every day matter, and martyrdom a familiar thought. :.r- ...  The solemn axiom that ' it is better to go, to the house of mourning than to the house of feasting,' colored our lives. Every instance of mortality was fol- lowed by a funeral sermon. The preacher at its close was used to say, ' Now the mourners may stand up! ' and the mourners - there might be a multitude of them, or only two or three weeping trembling little orphans - stood up in the wide square pew, scanned from head to foot by curious staring eyes, while the preacher analyzed their griefs, dwelt on the character of the departed, and sometimes coolly and cruelly calculated the chances against them at the tribu- nal to which they had passed. We distinctly recollect one occasion when the ' pride of the village' had been smitten down; when her young companions, her pall-bearers, who loOked as innocent as their symbolic white frocks, and the white roses in their Hiands, were warned to flee from that wrath to come to which their companion's sudden and unconscious death had borne her. But this audacious sentence Kid not come from our dear old pastor. His spirit was of the gentlest and tenderest. His heart, full of all charities, triumphed over his ecclesiastical creed, which circumscribed the acceptance of the ALMGHTY FATHER to the few elect who concurred in the belief of the dogmas of his sect. Still through the ever-open portals of his cheerful heart came the sunbeams of charity, casting a ray of hope upon the darkest individual case. No bit of poetry was so dear to him, or so often quoted by him, as the old distich with which he closed his oracular remark at the death of some wretched outcast' who had sinned himself out of all charity, but this good man's 'we don't know how it is with him; it is not for us to judge; he was not worse than he of whom it was said: - BETWEEN-the saddle and the ground He mercy asked and mercy found.'  And yet this sturdy little preacher would prove logically in his next Sunday's sermon that none but the Hopkinsian branch of the Calvinistic family 'ever were,' or ' ever could be (his favorite limitation phrases) saved.' Thank GOD, these dykes of dogma and bigotry were swept away by the potent stream of love that overflowed the good man's heart.' e The stern discipline practised in our 'old church' - and we believe it was  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7984-00000031"/> 60(         OUR OLD ' MEETING-HOUSE.' not less severe in other Puritan societies -now lives only in tradition. Of- fences of 'church members' were never pardoned till the culprit, in vulgar phrase, 'walked the broad alley,' that is, till he made his circumstantial con- fession in the middle aisle of the church. This was the Protestant substitute ,for the confessional; and the greedy ears of a whole congregation were in the Place of the one authorized priest, who, by the grace of GQD, might dismiss the p enitent with that expression of divine compassion: 'Neither do I condemn thee: go and sin no more I'  ?Ve remember one poor old woman (the Aunt Silla of the way-side kind- nesis we have recorded) who had the best of hearts, but the weakest of heads. She was a saint for the ,pQSt part, and o0nta, sinner in the smallest degree. L She hades genial temit, and w-^s&amp;   mtimes 'iotercome,? The smallest and thinnesit potl ;titia tomu fcfh her feeble head; and self-convicted she ' walked the brboad ailey' 0o Often that one of her rustic friends 'guessed Aunt Silla had a-most sinned out her sevebnty times seven.' We remember, too, a confession made in that old church, too solemn for a smile, too deeply tragic for tears, and 'involving consequences to which, even at this lapse of time, we may not advert. Death has a blessed ministry when its curtain falls over deeds that have rent hearts and dyed families in shame I But the 'Old Meeting-House' had its comic scenes too, and one so gro- tesquely contrasting with its usual solemnities, that one can hardly hope for full belief in describing it. It was the custom in those old days, at the close of the ' term' at the ' Academy ' for the aspirants for future forensic and cleri- cal honors to recite poetry, speak speeches, etc. On one occasion, after a flourishing 'term' under a master whose taste or ambition inclined him to Thespian accomplishments, a play was to be enacted which required more ex- tended scenic facilities than the Academy afforded; and the stage was trans- ferred to the ' Old Meeting-House.' We rather suspect that Puritanic rule was already in abeyance, for no opposition was made to this extraordinary use of the sacred purlieus-and no desecration seems to have been suspected, cer- tainly none was intended. The stage, with the stage properties' occupied about one fourth of the area of the church, and was erected over the pews and immediately under the pulpit; and the drop-curtain not reaching to that height, we, the younger part of the audience, who occupied the gallery and the high pew, had the advantage of seeing the practical jokes and artless preparations behind the scenes: the transforming of the fairest boy in the school, with flaxen curls, into the heroine of the play, etc. Before this time, our good old Dr. W--- had gone to rest, and the then incumbent of the place (who filled it faithfully) was betrayed by some blind and lucky misconstruction which we never could understand, into presiding in his own place, in the pulpit, at this jubilee. The play, of all others, selected for this occasion, was Kotzebue's 'Rob- bers I ' a play proscribed by the potentates of Europe; rather, however, we be- lieve, for its tendencies to liberalism than to licentiousness. But in any view. of it, this was a singular demonstration for a New-England rural district. Its tendency was somewhat qualified by an after-piece of a scriptural character.   SONNET. We have no precise recollection as to the musical prelude: from the     : promiscuous nature of the entertainment, it may have been ' Yankee Doodle,' or a march from 'our Paganini,' the mulatto musician of the village, or there may have been an anthem  from the school; but we are very sure that when the stage-bell was first rung and the curtain drawn up, we had, instead of the canonical prologue, a prayer, in which (according to custom) . there were few of the striking Exigencies in the history of the human race . that were not remembered. With that all solemnity ended.  The pastorl had one or two clerical brethren in the pulpit with him. It was evident! their ' first play,' and they enjoyed it with the eagerness of novices and simplicity of children. As it was, eacted, it was in truth pastoral-comical scene indivisible and trfgic4  K   ;   r     whom some-f the audience thought incapable of the  o inr e c fl a     liko ia, merry boy. Indeed he seemed completely, as the French nigfhtsay?,/tti ow; for after the play was finished and the after-piece, -'Daniel in the Lion's: Den,' was to begin, he made another prefatory prayer, in which he seemed to sec in vision the miracle wrought, and the Prophet on whom 'no manner of hurt was found, issue from the lion's den.' To our open, disenchanted eyes, the boy who personated the Prophet, and restlessly awaited his cue in our cousin's square-corner pew, (for the nonce, the lion's den,) seemed quite safe, and the- lion, 'an innocent beast, and of a good conscience.' But all this was long ago. The tragedy and comedy of real life have filled a great space between them and now. Not one board remains upon another; not a shingle is left of our 'Old Meeting-House.' The hill-side road is grass- grown. Aunt Silla is safe from temptations and small lapses, and alas I her foaming beer-cup and delicate herbs have fallen into disuse I A new church is erected on the site of that where the missionary Brainerd and the great metaphysician Jonathan Edwards ministered to the Stockbridge Indians.  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7984-00000032"/> 62 BOB     O' LINK. BY FITZ-JAMES O'BRIBIT. IT was 'noon in summer. The earth lay breathless in the heat, with its thiusand tohigues in wood and field too faint for their accustomed low, myt- te6Ous speech.- The Long Island shore, white and crescented, bared its bpsom " -Danae to the golden embraces of thr:sun. In the meadows the heavy- , cre2 idisasses withk i :*gheadsb6hbt^fiiete 1t6swhet ish of waves upon tulip-tre/ifrbtedqt^d'1reit' iiel te green, held up to heaven with branching arms a thousand' golden chalices. Far away across the Sound lay the Con- necticut shore trembling through mist, while behind me, from the green re- cesses of a deserted garden, the oriole poured forth his monotone of sorrow. As I sauntered down the little path that led from the old house where I was boarding for the summer, to my favorite haunt by the sea-shore, with cloudsnf insects springing from the grass like a living spray at every step I took, I suddenly heard the saucy notes of that low-comedian of birds, the Bob o' Link. As I have always had a friendly feeling toward this ornithological farceur, I set to work to obtain an interview with him. I was not long in dis- covering his whereabouts. He was sitting on the stump of a rail chattering vehemently, and as well as I understood his language, impudently; preening his feathers, cocking his head on one side, as if he had a passion for seeing Nature upside down, and shaking his wings as though he contemplated an im- mediate migration to the coast of Africa. About every half-minute or so he would suddenly leave his perch, and flying a little distance, flop into the long meadow-grass, whence instantly. would proceed a most astounding vocal effort, after which he would reappear and resume his rail in triumph. His frequent journeys to the same spot led me to suspect that he had some private interest in that quarter-a nest, or a young bride perhaps, and that he was in fact passing his honey-moon, so I walked toward the place in which I saw him dis- appear last, determined to be a witness of his domestic bliss. It seemed to me that a human head was lying alone and bodiless in the deep green sea of grass that surrounded-me. A beautiful youth's head, blonde and spiritual, looking up at me with a calm, unfrightened look, while nestling close to its pale, rounded cheek,. hushed and rather astonished by my appear- ance, sat Master Bob o' Link. The head, however, was not without a body. The long bending grass met over the form, leaving exposed only the pale, beautiful face, which looked like an exquisite Venetian picture framed in gold and green. ' Good morning, Sir,' said the youth in a sweet voice as I bent over him, looking I suppose a little bewildered at this sudden apparition, and fondling at the same time Master Bob o' Link with long slender fingers. 'Good morning, Sir.   BOB 0' LINK. .            63 'Good morning,' I answered, 'You seem to be taking things quietly here.' He gave a sudden glance downward toward his feet, and a sad smile flickered over his lips. 'I am obliged to take things quietly,' he said. ' Ah! an invalid I suppose. I am sorry.' ' I am paralyzed Sir.' No words can paint the tone of utter despair in which he made this terrible statement. If you have ever spokea with a man who had spent tw;enty years in solitary confinement, you will hae noticed the unearthly calm of his voice, the low monotone of sound, the loneliness of accent. Well, this lad's voice sounded so. He talked like, one. shut- out of life. I mnade a place for myself in the geass and sat down beside him.  ]. . 'l was attracted by your bird,' I said; iI thought he had a nest here, and so followed him. I trust I am not intruding.'  ' Not at all, Sir; I am glad to have some one to speak to., As for Bob, he has a nest here, but it 's in my heart. He is the only thing on earth that loves me.' ' You take too sad a view of life, my friend. Your calamity is great, no doubt, but still --' ' Ah I Sir, it's all well enough to talk so when you have limbs and health and freedom. When you can work and go out into life and tread the earth with the full consciousness of being. But when ever since you can remember you have been but the moiety of a man, utterly helpless, utterly dependent, an infant without an infant's happy unconsciousness. But what's the use of my talking to you in this way; here, Bob, show the gentleman your tricks.' Bob, on this summons, left his post by the lad's cheek, where he had re- mained perfectly still, taking an inventory of my person with his round bright eye, and apparently measuring me for a suit of clothes, and suddenly flew into the air, where he summersaulted and pirouetted and affected to lose the use of his wings and tumble from an appalling height, invariably recovering himself before he reached the ground, after which he gravely alit upon his master's breast and thrust his little bill affectionately between his lips. 'You have tamed your bird wonderfully,' I said to the boy. ' It has been my amusement during many solitary hours,' he answered with a feeble smile. ' How is it that you have been left so solitary? ' I asked; ' you live in the neighborhood? 'In that house up yonder just peeping from behind that clump of maples,' and he pointed as he spoke toward a respectable farm-house. ' And you have friends- a family?' 'Ah! Sir, they are kind enough to me; but they must be very tired of me by this time.' 'Come,' said I encouragingly, laying my hand on his shoulder, 'come, tell me all about yourself. I'm a good listener: beside, I am interested in you, Bob here looks as if he was anxious for a story. This is a charming nook that we are in, so I 'll just light a cigar, and do you talk.'  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7984-00000033"/> "            BOB O' LINK. The free and easy manner I assumed seemed to surprise him. He glanced shyly at me out of his large blue eyes as if suspicious of my sincerity; then he heaved a little sigh, stroked Bob's feathers, as if to assure himself of the presence of at least one friend, and saying, 'As you please,' commenced: 'I am eighteen,' he said; 'you would not think it, for I know I look younger than I am. Confinement and suffering have made my complexion pale and transparent, and the sun and the winds that harden other men's skins and age their- features, have had but little to do with me. Ever since I can re. member I have been paralyzed in the lower limbs. For years I lay upon an innlined plane of board, looking up at the ceiling with a mind very nearly as blank as the white plaster I gazed at. My,father died when I was a mere in- fant, and there waso o left in the-houe but mother and Cousin Alice and me.'  Cousin Aflie, said  who is she?' His eyes wandered timidly toward the house behind the maples, as if he expected some apparition to start from thence on the very Instant. 'Cousin Alice,' he repeated vaguely, ' well, she 's - Cousin Alice.' ' Excessively explanatory,' I said, laughing. ' Is Cousin Alice young?' 'My age.' ' Is she pretty?' One deep, reproachful look of those large blue eyes told me all. Poor fel- low, there he lay maimed, useless, passing his days and evenings in the pre- sence of some beautiful creature whom he could never hope to possess, but loving her with all that concentrated intensity which belongs to the passions of the deformed. He seemed to know what was passing in my mind; for without a word -from me, he continued : She is engaged to Ralph Farnwell, who lives down yonder. She is very fbnd of him, and he of her. It is they who bring me down between them to this place every fine day, and I sit here with Bob while they go off and pick nuts, and - and --' and here the picture was too much for him, and the poor fellow burst into tears. No wonder. To have his misfortune paraded through necessity before the woman he loved. To be carried about like a piece of furniture by her and his rival. How often that poor heart must have been smitten bitterly I How often those crippled limbs thrilled with agony I I took his hand in mine, but did not say a word. There are times when consolation is cruel. It was better than all words to let him feel by the pres- sure of my hand that he had found a friend. We sat this way for some time, until I was aroused from a painful reverie into which I had fallen by a long, black shadow being projected across the spot in which we were sitting. I looked up and saw a tall, handsome young man with bronzed cheeks and curly chestnut hair, on whose arm was hanging an exceedingly lovely young girl, whose face was a perfect treasury of archness and innocence. They looked rather surprised at seeing me, but I explained how it was that I came -to be there, and they seemed satisfied. ' Harry, is n't it time to come home? ' said the young girl. ' Ralph and I are cowe for you.'   BOB O' LINK.              65 'Thank you, Alice; but I'd like to stay an hour longer. The day is so bright and sunny that it is a shame to be in-doors. You do n't want to go home yet,' and he looked at Ralph as he said this with a bitter expression of countenance that perhaps I alone observed, but which seemed to say: It will give you an hour more to wander together. Of course you do n't want to go home. ' Well, as you please, Harry. Ralph and I will go off to the pond in the cedar grove and come back in about an hour. But I say, Harry, look here; is n't -this pretty?' and as she spoke she held out a little box for his inspection. He opened it, and disclosed a pretty little ring set with garnets. While he looked at it, Alice stooped over and with ablush whispered something into his ear, owhich made him to my keene sigtt iverin all t   of him that; was alive. It was but momentary, however, for he restorea t'ox, saying coldly: ' Well, I wish you both every happiness. You will find me here when you return.' As they walked slowly away, he followed them with his eyes, then turned to me. 'They are to be married next Sunday,' he said. I felt all the meaning of his words. I pitied him. Solitude is a need to him at this moment; I will leave him. As I pulled out my watch and pre- pared for my departure, he said to me: 'I am exceedingly obliged to you, Sir, for your company, but I want you to do me one more favor before you leave. You are strong and I am light. Please take me to the giant's chair. I love to sit on it and dip my hand in the salt wash of the sea.' I But are you not afraid of slipping and falling in?' I asked, for the giant's chair was a fantastically-shaped rock a few hundred yards down the beach, around whose rugged base the sea at high tide washed clamorously. 'Oh i no,' he answered; ' there is a cleft in it where I sit quite safely. And when Ralph and Alice come to look for me, I can easily shout to them from where I am. Do take me, Sir, if you please.' Of'course I obeyed his wishes. I lifted him in my arms, and with Bob flying alongside of us, carried him down to the huge old rock which was regally draped in the rich brown tapestry of the sea. I found a comfortable, dry cleft in which I stowed him away, and with a promise to come and see him the fol- lowing day, I left him, with Bob chattering away on his shoulder, gazing., dreamily across at the Connecticut shore. About an hour and three-quarters after this, I was strolling down the road smoking my after-dinner segar, when I heard hurried steps behind me, and the young man named Ralph ran up pale and breathless. 'For GOD'S sake, Sir, where did you leave Harry?' he cried. 'We can't find him any where I ' ' Oh! you have n't looked on the giant's chair, then; I took him there. I left him snug and comfortable.' 'But we have, Sir. We knew how fond he was of sitting there, and when we missed him from the meadow, concluded that he had got you to carry him there. But there's no sign of him, only the Bob o' Link flying wildly over the' spot where the rock dips in to the water, and crying as if its heart would break.'  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7984-00000034"/> "             SONNET. 'Not in the giant's chair I ' I cried, with a sick feeling about my heart. 'Good GOD I he has drowned himself.' 'Drowned himself! Why, what for?' asked Ralph with the most un- feigned astonishment. ' He was in love with his Cousin Alice; and you are to marry her on next Sunday,' was my only reply. The man was stunned. He saw it in an instant. All that secret and mys- terious love which had racked the heart of the poor cripple, unknown to him or his betrothed, was now laid bare. He groaned and buried his head in his hands. 'This will kill Alice, Sir,' he said to me. ' Come and help me to break it to her.'  y., conjecture, p^r" ect. About a week after this, the body of the poor paralytic Jwa wcai ed ashore some miles down the beach,; holding wth despe./ rate clutch in one hand littl daguerreotype of his Cousin Alice. And Bob; he missed the accustomed hand. For days after his master's death he used to fly down to the old place in the meadow and hover around there, waiting for him who never more would come. This lasted for about a fortnight, when one day Ralph in passing by found the poor bird dead in the -grass, which still bore the impress of his master's form.   DERRICK VAN- DAM. BY JOHN T. IRVING, AUTHOR OF *THE QUOD CORRESPONDENCB.? AMONGs the mass of valuable information accumulated by my respected kinsman, the late Barent Van Brunt, I came across another manuscript in the hand-writing of Mr. Volkert Van 'Gelder, relating to the founder of that family at Matinecock. In a former number'of the KNICKERBOCKER were set forth some of the troubles and annoyances wlihtcl hhad, beset thithdiNtinguished man when in bitterness of spirit he turned lis back iupi hids naeti city and buried him- self and his grief in the unexplored recesses of Matinecock. ! The various aggressions of the pioneers who had preceded him, and who had endeavored to deprive him of his territories, rankled in his mind long after these difficulties had been adjusted. The ringleader in these acts of hostility had been one Ebenezer Cock; a tall, stiff, raw-boned New-Englander, with a face like parchment, a high nose, with eyes close together, and looking straight forward, like those of a lobster. He was one of your hard-headed, close-fisted disputants, Who never become excited, but are endowed with untiring perse- verance and immeasurable wind. To him Teunis Von Gelder bore a mortal antipathy, for he had not only laid claim to the lands on which the Dutchman had settled, but had added the farther insult of proving his claim to be just. The claim might have been borne, but the insult was intolerable. But if Ebenezer had powers of argu- ment, the Dutchman had tenacity of purpose; and the warfare was carried on with cautious perseverance on one side, and on the other with vehement ani- mosity, backed by an obstinacy which had never been known to yield. In the midst of this turmoil he had no friend nor confident, except his trusty negro Ryck, who had grown up with him, had followed him in battle, and now shared his exile. Together they used to patrol the place, keeping a watchful eye on the adjacent country, the old man recounting the glories of his native city, and thanking GOD that his only son was safe in Holland, where he could hear nothing spoken except his mother tongue, and was beyond the contaminating influence of the conquerors of his beloved town. At this time the monotony of his life was interrupted by the arrival of one- Derrick Van Dam, a distant kinsman, who had recently returned from abroad. He was a gallant, stalwart fellow, of about three-and-twenty. He presented himself one day to the astonished eyes of Teunis and the admiring ones of Ryck, without notice or word of warning. He had been so long absent that the veteran did not recognize him, but instinctively was girding up his loins for battle, when the light, ringing laugh of his relative stole across his ear like a strain of long-forgotten music, touching some chord in his heart which had been long unstrung. The old man took him to his arms, and with a feeling of almost childish desolation, wept upon his breast. The weakness was but mo-  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7984-00000035"/> 68           DERRICK VANT DAM. mentary. The next moment his martial spirit revived, and he forthwith began to calculate how much strength this recruit would add to his garrison. To his kinsman he recounted his. grievances and described the persecutions of the myrmidons of the neighborhood with so much earnestness, that the feelings of the young man were fairly enlisted, and he pledged himself to stand by his an- cient friend through thick and thin. He scouted the idea of defensive warfare, but suggested an immediate onslaught upon the enemy, that they should be smitten hip and thigh, and that particular attention should be shown to the, indefatigable Ebenezer Cock. He proposed to sack the city where he dwelt. The dim eye of the veteran fairly glowed to find an ally so much after his own heart. He applauded th, spirit which dctated the proposition, but suggested as an obstacle thatch-i ^ss no city to sack.  ' What can te. do? Has he no property?' 'Yes, large lands and crops.' ' Has he any sons? I'll challenge them I'  The veteran shook his head. 'He has but one child - a daughter.' ' Is she handsome?' Teunis replied that she was. 'Say no more I' was the prompt answer. ' I'll make love to her. The thing's settled I ' Teunis regarded his confederate with a shrewd eye. Whatever his thoughts may have been, he kept them to himself; and when his visitor retired he rubbed his hands with an air of keen enjoyment as he bade him good-night. No time was lost in carrying out their warlike resolutions; and the success of the young man in making his mark was such that not a settler within ten. miles but had heard of him. The women declared that he ought to be ashamed of himself and the men that he ought to be hung. So vain-glorious did old Teunis become, that he began to entertain vague ideas of laying claim to the whole territory between Matinecock and Flushing, and of expelling every Cock from the country I While Derrick Van Dam was thus running riot and carrying dismay throughout the land, all idea of attack upon the domicile of Ebenezer seemed to have passed from his mind. His hardihood, what a terrible fellow he was in a hand-to-hand encounter, what a fine-looking fellow he was too, his generosity and his deadly animosity to the entire Cock family, were the sole topics of talk in the sparsely settled district, and were not long in reaching tho ears of the daughter and heiress of Ebenezer Cock. Freelove, for such was her name, had grown up beneath the shadow of her father, and the acid eye and warm temper of a step-mother. Under this colm- bination of heat and cold she had ripened into a fine blooming maiden, warm of heart, somewhat quick of temper, and as unconscious of her charms as young beauties usually are. She was also known to be one of the best brought-up girls on Long Island, having had every fault carefully held up to her disap- probation by her watchful step-mother, whose rough tongue was the terror of the country and had rasped Ebenezer down to skin and bone.   DERRICK VAN DAM.             69 When the report of the menaces of Derrick Van Dam reached the ears of the maiden, she espoused the cause of her father with great vivacity. She vowed undying animosity against Teunis Van Gelder, was particularly bitter in her animadversions on his young ally, and usually concluded by stat- ing that she would like to have an opportunity of giving him a piece of. her mind in person. Whether the fear of encountering her sharp tongue had any effect in preventing Derrick from carrying out his menace, I cannot say; but certain it is, that although once or twice he had accidentally seen the girl near her father's house, and had been not a little struck witha' her charms, he continued to keep aloof from her, having no doubt learned in the course of his foreign travel that a woman's tongtd is a weapon diffiiult to parry, especially if she be young and fair.   .   .' " The girl soon had other matters to think of. She had grown up with that antipathy to the opposite sex, which is the peculiarity of young girls, and vowed that she would never marry; yet the fame of her beauty had extended far beyond her paternal domains, and several young vagabonds of that class who usually admire young maidens, had made overtures for her hand. In reply to these, Ebenezer put on his spectacles, looked them full in the face, investi. gated the length of their purses, and returned a decided negative. Nor did he trouble his daughter by communicating their proposals. At length a new candidate made his appearance. He was a stern, iron- strung soldier, who had been a hard fighter in the Indian wars. He was named Seth Pinchon, and was possessed of a large tract of land not far from Oyster Bay, consisting principally of sand-bars and salt-meadows, and prolific in clams and musquitoes. Seth Pinchon had been the right-hand man of Captain John Underhill in most of his battles with the Indians both on the main land and on Long Island. He had made himself memorable in the desperate fight with the Massapequa Indians, when their fort was destroyed and the power of the tribe broken. He was gaunt and raw-boned, with a face seamed with scars, and a complexion hardened and tanned by exposure and service, until it had assumed both the color and consistency of sole-leather. He had also been an active partisan against the Dutch in the disputes between them and the English. As long as the Dutch had maintained their domination over any part of the Island, these broils had given him constant occupation, occasionally varied by his chastising a refractory Indian tribe which might have dared to maintain that their territories were their own. However, the battle with the Massapequas was the last great struggle of the Long-Island Indians. The Dutch, too, were subdued, and Seth Pinchon re- tired to his lair at Oyster Bay, near the abode of his old commander John Underhill. His occupation being gone, he bethought himself that he was be. coming stricken in years and -that it was high time to settle in life. In one of his marauds he had fallen in with the daughter of Ebenezer Cock; and although he was not prone to tender feelings, yet she had made such an impression upon him, that now when the pressure of his various avocations was removed, her image rose in his mind as his future help-meet. He set about the  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7984-00000036"/> 70           DERRICK VAN DAM. accomplishment of his object with-that directness of purpose which was his great characteristic. Having bestowed more than usual care upon his person, he mounted his horse and directed his course to the dwelling of Ebenezer Cock. It was a quiet, snug little farm-house, built upon the borders of a forest and command- ing a wide view of fields of grain, which sloped off to the Sound. Every thing about it indicated ease and comfort, for Ebenezer was known to be a thrifty man.  ' As the cavalier rode up, Freelove met him at the door with a beaming smile. Sli had no suspicion that she was at the bottom of his visit, but the renown of the campaigner excited in her a desire:. t obtain from him that admiration which the gentler sexe is :apt to crave from those who have made a name by courage and prowess-in arms. . Seth Pinchon felt more embarrassment at her salutation than he would have done in storming a fortress. . He dismounted and shambled into the house with a side-long gait, having more the air of a sheep-stealer than of one on his way to storm a fair lady's heart. Ebenezer Cock received him with cordiality, but with the erectness peculiar to his race. He heard his proposal with stern satisfaction, for he felt that amid the aggressions of Teunis Van Gelder, a son- in-law of a calibre like that of the staunch campaigner at his elbow-would be a powerful auxiliary. He accepted his offer at once, Ind told him that he might consider the matter settled. There was one, however, who heard the proposal and its acceptance with very different feelings. This was Freelove herself. She had not accompanied the soldier into the room, but had lingered at the door, and had over-heard all that had passed. With a sinking heart she stole off to her own room, and kept out of sight until the heavy tramp of hoofs told her that Seth Pinchon was departing. From the window she caught sight of his erect figure as he rode off. In the form of the fair Freelove there was not a little spirit; and every feel. ing was in arms at being thus unceremoniously disposed of. She determined that the grim warrior who had so little knowledge of female nature as to over- ,look her wishes in such a matter, should meet his match. She kept her own counsel, but maintained a keen watch over the movements of her father. No sooner was it noised about that Seth Pinchon was to carry off the much- coveted prize, than the whole country from Flushing to Huntington was in a blaze of excitement. At last, rumors of the intended wedding reached the ears of Derrick Van Dam, who had been for some time past ensconced in the fortress at Matinecock, hatching hew projects of mischief. He forthwith sallied out for information; nor was he long in learning that though betrothed to Seth Pinchon, the heart of the girl had little share in the matter. Had she been about to wed one of her own age, and to whom she went heart and hand, a spirit of high-bred chivalry, a dash of which was mingled with his reckless character, would have prevented Derrick, notwithstanding his former menace, from interfering. As it was, he looked upon Seth Pinchon as little better than the corsairs, who were scouring the Mediterranean and Adriatic, and making prey of every fair maiden upon whom they could lay hands. He did not   DERRICK VAN DAM.               71 hesitate to declare his intention to take the field against his military rival, and to proclaim openly that. Freelove was the fairest maiden on Long-Island, and that he would marry her in spite of Seth Pinchon. This menace reached the ears of Freelove. At any other time it would have excited her ire; but matters were approaching a crisis with her, and the prospect of escape, even by being carried off by a scapegrace whom she had never seen, and whom she had denounced on all occasions, seemed a positive relief. Still day after day slipped by. Rumors of his pranks, of his reckless forays into the territories of the Cocks and the Lattings and the Frosts, the Wrights and the Weeks, his utter disregard of territorial rights and Indian grants, rang through the country.; but no incursion of his had extended inside the dwell- ing of the Cocks, nor had there been the slightest .demonstration of a more tender character.                - In the mean time these vaunts had excited Ebenezer Cock's wrath to a white heat. He declared that Derrick was no better than a freebooter, and that he would have him hung if he got him in his power. Freelove's heart sank at these menaces: it was heavy too on her own account; for the house was alive with the bustle of preparation for the wedding. Apples were hanging in festoons at the windows; pumpkins were brought in for pies; sheets, toweling, and all the various items of house-wifery which denote that a daughter and an heiress is to launch her bark in life, were about her. Amid all, she drooped and the bloom faded from her cheek. In vain, well-meaning friends endeavored to cheer her by sounding the praises of her intended bridegroom. They told how many Indians he had scalped, how many towns he had sacked, and recounted his numerous ad- ventures by flood and field. Had these exploits been connected with a young and handsome person, it is not improbable that they might have added to his merits in her eyes; but as they only brought to her mind the gaunt, battle- worn exterior of Seth Pinchon, she turned away and said that he must be a cruel wretch. As the fated hour approached she would steal away and wan. der through the woods, endeavoring to plan some mode of escape, yet feeling that her plans and schemes must fail beneath the iron will of those who con trolled her. One afternoon, under the influence of these feelings, she wan dered off into the woods, too much absorbed in her own thoughts to notice whither she directed her steps. She had gone farther than usual, and was about turning homeward when a twig, snapping beneath a foot-step, caught her attention. Indians at that time still lurked in the forests, and suspicious characters were known to be prowling around the settlements, living equally by plundering the savage and the white man. With a feeling of trepidation the girl turned toward the sound, and beheld a young man standing within a few feet of her. He was gazing at her with a look of extreme surprise, which look was equally reflected in her own face. The stranger raised his hat re spectfully. 'I think I have the honor of addressing Miss Cock? ' There was something in his air which inspired confidence; and lthough he gazed at her with an expression of the most intense admiration, yet his tone was so respectful that she could not take offence. Whom could he be? He  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7984-00000037"/> 72           DERRICK VAN DAM. was evidently a stranger in this part of the country. His appearance differed from that of one brought up in the wilds of Long-Island. While these thoughts were passing through her mind, shewas directing her steps homeward. Tbo Stranger hinted that Improper characters were said to be prowling about, and suggested that he should escort her until she arrived within sight of her father's house. The girl seemed to acquiesce, and he took his station at her side. By degrees as they went on, their steps became more and more slow; their convert sation was carried on in a tone so low, that although there were no listen- ers, it was scarcely above a whisper. The color'in the girl's cheek, too, came and went as she listened. Once or twice in the course of the conversa- tion the name of Seth Pinchon passed between them. Gradually the stranger spoke more earnestly .ilJreeove, didv t iok up; hier eyes were fixed on the grounds :he ma.  er of the', other became -more urgent; it was evident that he was making a passionate appeal. ' In this hope,' added he in conclusion to some xemark, 'I have lingered here from day to day, and until now I have watched in vain.' The girl ventured to steal a glance at the handsome eyes which were bent upon her own ; her heart throbbed at the gaze which they encountered. It was evident that the declarations which he had poured into her ear were genuine. None other could come from a person with such eyes; but as yet the stranger had mentioned only his love, not his name; it could do no harm to know it, even if she had to tell him that he must be disappointed in his hopes. So, with a fluttering heart and a faint voice, she said it was very odd that such a proposal should come from an entire stranger. Her companion hesitated and stood looking on the ground. At last he said sadly . 'I fear my name is not one that you will like to hear. I fear it now a thousand -times more than I did an hour ago, for then I might have forgotten you, but now --' He did not finish the sentence, but the sad gesture which accompanied his words convinced Freelove that if he lived to the age of Methuselah, her image would never be effaced from his bosom. She stood expecting his reply with some apprehension, and yet with it was mingled an odd kind of feeling, which she did not understand, but which she knew that she did not entertain toward Seth. 'Well,' said the stranger, drawing a long breath, 'I am Derrick Van Dam ' A vague surmise that such might be the fact had already entered the mind of the girl, and for an instant her heart beat wildly; the next moment she be- came deadly pale. Derrick seized her hand in both of his, and poured forth his protestations of devotion in language that might have melted half-a-dozen female hearts; but there is something unaccountable in the ways of a woman, and he who would trace out the windings of her heart must be a more profound philosopher than I am; for although but a short time before she had been hop. ing and longing for this very occurrence as her last chance of escape, yet now. when Derrick stood before her, glowing with manly beauty far greater than she had expected, and had ventured to utter the words which she had been so   DERRICK VAN DAM.              73 anxious to hear, she received him with an air of chilling reserve, and did not fail to let him know that his boast of wooing and winning her had reached her ears. Indeed, she carried her imprudence farther, for she concluded by telling him that he might look for a bride among those who held themselves more cheaply than she held herself. Derrick's hopes, which had been high, were completely dashed by this sudden change of tone. He was a bold fellow where hard blows and round knocks were going on; but his heart was as tender as a child's. Her receptio! cut him to the quick; for all that he had of love, he had unconsciously be- stowed upon her, and what with dreaming and pondering over her perfections, he had become deeply involved. ,Zere were all his day-dreams scattered to the winds. He was a  inmanly, frn/ et Te d .ife o 1i did not uhderstand the caprices of the little heartwhich w ash beating beneththe trim boddice bet fore him, nor could he fathom the glance of the soft yet mischievous, eye, which was already relenting, as it watched him. So he took her hand respect- fully as he said: 'I suppose it was wrong to speak as I did, and you have done right to tell me so. I am a stranger to you, and yet I have loved you well, more than I can ever love aniy one else. 1 should not have spoken to you to- day, but I had heard that you were to be married soon, against your will I and the time was so short that I dared not wait. It would have been wiser if I had delayed. Good-by.' He bent over her dimpled hand and pressed it to his lips. As he did so the soft, warm fingers clasped his own. He looked up: two dark eyes, moist with tears, were beaming on his face. 'Do n't go, do n't go,' was all she could utter. The next moment she gave way to a paroxysm of tears and buried her face in her hands. Derrick was beside himself. He reiterated his protestations of attach- ment; he swore that he would never leave her; he begged her to let him know the cause of her sorrow. If there was any thing that she would like to have done, he would do it. If there was any one whom she would like to have ex- terminated, he would strangle him with pleasure; she had but to say the word, for he was her most abject slave. Freelove gradually became composed under these assurances, and commu- nicated the cause of her trouble--her approaching marriage with Seth Pinchon. She said that matters were progressing with alarming speed. 'We are to be married in a week.' ' A week 1' exclaimed Derrick. 'It's an age. I 'll marry you in an hour.' It cannot be denied that a smile of satisfaction brightened the face of the girl at the ardor of her youthful suitor; and that this headlong mode of court- ship was playing the very deuce with the prospects of Seth Pinchon. It is useless to dwell upon a scene where both were of accord, and nothing but maiden modesty prevented the girl from yielding to the wishes of her new suitor. Still it was agreed between them that this interview should be kept secret, and that they should meet on the following day to devise means of thwart- ing her father and Seth. The propriety of making a formal demand of her hand was suggested by Derrick, but the girl seemed to fear that it might precipitate  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7984-00000038"/> 74           DERRICK VAN DAM.. her marriage with Seth. No conclusion was arrived at except that she pledged herself to become Mrs. Van Dam at all hazards. Matters being thus adjusted between them and sealed in due form, Derrick mounted his horse, which had been tied to a tree close at hand, and galloped off to Matinecock to take Teunis Van Gelder into his confidence; while the fair Freelove stole back to her home with a heart lighter than it had been since the shadow of Seth Pinchon had first darkened her threshold. Teunis listened to his confederate's story with a kind of paternal interest. A feeling of grim satis- faction pervaded his bosom at the idea of circumventing Ebenezer and his hard. fighting son-in-law. Yet for a moment his eye was troubled, and placing his hard, brown finger on the arm of the youn man, he looked-full in his face as he said:.I Remembre l-.!*seis but a'girl; you would not wrong her?' ' GOD forbid, '.was the earnest reply. 'Then Ir'm with you., But you had better marry her without asking Ebenezer. It would save much trouble and a great waste of words. He's a very windy fellow.' This advice harmonized well with the wishes of Derrick, and he con- cluded to sleep on it and to make up his mind in the morning.  The re- sult of the night's deliberation was a determination to obtain a second inter- view with Freelove, to reconnoitre the ground again, and to be guided by circumstancess  In the mean time, it was necessary to keep a watchful eye over Ebenezer and Seth, for at that time a species of law, administered in later days by Judge Lynch, was in vogue on the borders, and Derrick felt that with Ebenezer and Seth as judge and jury, and himself as the culprit, the law would be rigidly enforced. He was, however, a person not apt to trouble himself about grievances which might never occur, and beside, there was something pleasant in the bare idea of invading the stronghold of the Cocks, and carrying off their treasure. Moreover, he was raised above all paltry considerations of danger by the confessions which he had drawn from the fair Freelove on the previous day: He set out with a word of caution from Teunis to enter into no arguments with old Cock, and also with a hint from Ryck 'to keep his eyes skinned' when he got in the neighborhood of Seth. He went on foot to es- cape observation better, and reached his place of destination without molesta- tion and without meeting a single person. For some time he kept in the woods near the house watching for the girl. He was there at the appointed hour, yet she had not arrived. He cleared his throat; he whistled, and made various demonstrations to attract her in case she were concealed in the neigh- borhood, but no Freelove appeared. He felt certain that something must be wrong, and he determined to approach the house. He stole up cautiously, so as not to be seen, until he came near a window. He raised his head above the sill and looked in. As he did so, he encountered not the f..ce of Freelove, buit the grim, scarred visage of Seth Pinchon, who with instinctive readiness for emergencies, griped him by the throat the moment he saw him; at the same time, he called out for assistance. Derrick was not to be captured so easily: he returned the gripe of the veteran by a similar grasp of the throat, and for a moment it Was a  question who should strangle the other first. During the   DERRICK VAN DAM.             75 struggle Derrick fairly dragged the old soldier out of the window and they fell upon the ground, where the battle raged furiously, until Ebenezer, aroused by the noise, came to the assistance of his son-in-law, accompanied by one of his workmen,I and by the combined efforts of the three, Derrick was overpowered. He was taken into the house, confined in an upper room, and told that as he seemed so anxious to see the inside of the dwelling, he should have a chance. The Indian fighter had been too watchful for the young man. He had ob-,. served him lurking about the premises for a day or two, and had been on the look-out for him. His boasts respecting his intended wife had reached his ears, and he had a welcome prepared for him whenever he should cross his path.. Ebenezer was not a little alrmed at the effect of this proceeding. , He knew that Teunis was not ta m'a' t-ti,pem his fnidito be seized with im- punity, and his heart sank at the: ideaof the;fury. of the hardyheaded Dutch- man. But his grim confederate was as obdurate and imnpemous to fear as Teunis himself, and he insisted that Derrick should be kept in durance. He even suggested the propriety of hanging him on the spot. In his wars against the Indians he had acquired a habit of doing these things which he found it difficult to break. Nothing was settled except that time should be taken to deliberate. Seth Pinchon, with that keen relish for strife which had become a part of his nature, penned a note to Teunis in characters as stiff and down- right as his own blows, informing him that Derrick Van Dam had been de- tected in the act of breaking in the house of Ebenezer Cock, and had been se- cured; that as the crime was by law punishable with death, he presumed that he would be hung. Having penned this epistle without the knowledge of Ebenezer, he dispatched it, and passed the rest of the day in quite a complacent state of mind at the idea of the uproar which he had inevitably excited at Matinecock. He was right in his surmise as to the anger of the Dutchman, but he had not calculated on his promptitude of action. No sooner had he read the letter than he turned to the bearer of it and told him that he could not leave the place. 'Here, Ryck, lock up the fellow in the corn-crib, and set the dog to watch him.' A sharp whistle called to his side a dog with a square muzzle and eyes pro- truding from fat and ill-nature. He walked stiffly up, eyeing the prisoner and Ryck as if to ascertain the nature of his duty. ' Do you think I can't get out of that?' said the man, pointing to the place of confinement with a contemptuous sneer. ' Try it,' replied Teunis. ' The dog will be kind to you if he catches you at it.' This was all that passed; and Ryck, accompanied by the dog as an auxi- liary, hurried the prisoner to the corn-crib, bolting him in. The dog quietly stretched himself on the ground in front of it, and watched the prisoner through the bars, without winking or removing his eyes from him. A hurried consultation was held with Ryck, and then the veteran and his ancient body-guard sallied out, and long before Seth Pinchon dreamed that his missive had reached its destination, Teunis was on his errand of retaliation.  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7984-00000039"/> 76           DERRICK VAN DAM. He was mounted on a tall, raw-boned trotting steed, as head-strong and fiery as himself, while Ryck followed him on a strong-built cart-horse. They were both armed to the teeth. They took their course through Lattingtown, until they came to the remote region which is now known as Buckram. Their war- like appearance created no little consternation, for, like the Ishmaelite of old, the Dutchman's hand was against every man. It was evident from their equip- ment that mischief was on foot, and none knew where the blow would fall. They did not draw rein until they arrived at the dwelling of Ebenezer Cock. Seth Pinchon, not expecting so speedy a reply to his letter, was absent; but Ebenezer had descried them in the distance, and had a glimmering of the nature of the visit. He had no objection to meeting the veteran in the field of argument, but he hada miiortal antipathy to bodily encounter, and had with- drawn, leaving the: Aeld" tohis adversary and his dwelling garrisoned by his wife, in whose :powers he had such confidence that it is said his face lighted up with a solemn smile at the idea of the reception which would await the veteran when he ventured to assail the stronghold of the Cocks. The loud summons of Teunis was answered by a shrill response, telling him to come in and say what he wanted. Teunis was a man of few words, and his errand was a simple one. He produced the missive which he had received from Seth Pinchon, read it aloud, and said: ' That he had come in quest of Derrick Van Dam, who was detained by unlawful means.' Mrs. Cock, like many of her sex, was better at vituperation than at argu ment, and as she could not deny that she knew where the prisoner was, she did not attempt it, but let loose upon her visitor the flood-gates of her voice, and inundated him with a torrent of that kind of eloquence which had been so effectual in quenching the spirit of Ebenezer and of bringing the whole neigh- borhood Funder her domination. For once she was at fault. Teunis eyed her in grim silence; he uttered not a word, but waited until she had got through, and paused from sheer want of breath, when he told her plainly that what she had said was no answer to his question, which he now repeated. ' Where is Derrick Van Dam?' Again the flood-gates were opened, and out came another deluge; but the breath was giving out and the torrent was less impetuous. Another pause for breath followed. Teunis was as cold as ever, but a little more resolute; his lips were compressed and his fingers griped the back of a chair on which he had been leaning. Again he asked the question. This time Mrs. Cock carried off her guard by the indifference of the soldier, fairly shook her fist in his face and told him that she knew where the gallows bird was: that he was in safe keeping, where all the Van Gelders in creation could not reach him, and con- cluded by a sincere wish that he were hung. The grim, glowing eyes of the Dutchman showed that he was fairly roused, and when she paused again, he told her that he must have either Derrick or her; that he had come to rescue hig friend, and that he wag determined not to return empty-handed,   DERRICK VAN DAM.                7  No ruffled hen was ever more indignant. Her eyes fairly flashed. She seized a broomstick, and dared the veteran to lay a finger on her. Teunis was too chivalrous to make the attack himself, but turning to Ryck he gave orders for the assault. Ryck immediately charged her in person. Resistance was vain. The broom- stick was shivered across Ryck's grisly poll, but it might as well have encoun- tered one of the boulders of Matinecock; and before Mrs. Cock had recovered her wits, she found herself mounted in front of Ryck, scouring across- the country at headlong speed. On a table were the pen and ink, where Seth Pinchon had left them. Teu. nis stopped to write a few words, and left the paper on the table. Then mount- ing, he followed Ryck.        .       .         . No henin the clutches of a hawlk was ever morevoCiferous than Mrs. Cock, and as she was borne on, a stream of abuse and vituperation escaped her, ed- dying far back in the rear, untilit impregnatedthe atmosphere for a mile. Her captors paid no regard to it, nor did they stop until she was landed at the dwell- ing of the veteran, very much dishevelled and bedraggled, and desperately out of temper at the hustling which she had received in her involuntary elopement. Teunis found his prisoner as he had left him, gazing ruefully from between the bars of the corn-crib, and the dog assiduous in his attentions. The Dutch- man's first business was to open the door and let the captive out, after which he told him that he might go to those who had sent him, which permission was accompanied by a kick in the rear to help him on his way. Great was the dismay throughout Buckram and Lattingtown, when the news of the abduction of Mrs. Cock was bruited abroad. The desperate cha- racter of Van Gelder was already a matter of notoriety; but that he would have the hardihood to tackle Mrs. Cock, and carry her off to the fastnesses of Matinecock, never entered into the head of even the most visionary of them all. Ebenezer was in a ferment. He sent for his martial son-in-law, and they laid their heads together to discover some mode of circumventing their resolute foe. Seth Pinchon was for marching to the fortress, storming it, and putting the whole garrison to the sword: proceedings of that kind had been every day matters with him in his forays into the Indian borders. The country was be- coming dreadfully peaceful, and he looked upon a sharp encounterkas an agree- able interlude in the monotony of his present life. Ebenezer, however, suggested that it would not be the means of delivering Mrs. Cock. iWhat would he do with her? ' ' Hang her,' replied Ebenezer. ' Here's his letter,' said he, producing the scrawlwhich Teunis had left on the table. ' He swears that he will, and he 'll keep his word.' Seth Pinchon looked about him cautiously, and cast an inquiring eye on his intended father-in-law. ' Suppose he did?'  Ebenezer returned the look. For a moment his face was brightened by a  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7984-00000040"/> 78            DERRICK VAN DAM. grisly smile; but his features relapsed into their- usual stiff expression, and he shook his head. ' It won't do. We 'd be 'the talk of the whole country. But several times his eyes glistened as he thought of it; for there was some- thing pleasant in the idea. After much deliberation, only one course seemed open; and that was to effect ran exchange of prisoners, and to trust to chance to get Derrick again in their ?hands. : ?  This was acceptable to neither, but was especially unpalatable to Seth, who stood out staunchly against it. At last it was determined that they should visit 'te fortress, and see if it could be taken by assault. If that could not be done, iftwould be time enough to adopt the other alternative. ; To this propositidox-Ebenezer was fan to assent. Having called his daugh- ter to Wim, he :told[ thi f'iit kf' his eirrand, and eaditioned her to be espe- cially waihtlul'   pris6e r . i tth e prisoner. e comitted to her charge the key of the chamber Wheri' Derric was confinied, and from which as yet he had made no effort to escape. , He hinted that'his daring character had been greatly exag- gerated; for that the most chicken-hearted fellow he had ever met with, would not have submitted to imprisonment as tamely as Derrick had done, Having thus made all secure at home, he and Seth felt moreat- ease while on their way to beat up the quarters of their old foe. When they came in sight of the fortress, they descried the head of Teunis Van Gelder and the end of a blunderbuss protruding from a window in the sec- ond'tory; and the black face and white eyes of Ryck, similarly supported, in a dormer-window in the roof; while the square-nosed dog patrolled in front of the house, with the gravity of a sentinel. From a small window high up in the cock-loft, was to be seen the disconsolate face of Mrs. Cock, who on the ap- proach of her allies waved some article of female attire from the window, in token of her presence, and that she was ripe for assistance. There was something so formidable in the attitude of the beleaguered forces, that Ebenezer Cock deemed it prudent, before venturing further, to parley; and forthwith tying a white rag on the end of a stick, he dispatched Seth Pinchon with it as a flag of truce. Teunis Van Gelder maintained his attitude of defiant caution. He made no offer to molest the ambassador, until he arrived within speaking distance, and then commanded him to stop and disclose the nature of his errand. ' I 'm come for Mrs. Mehitable Cock,' said Seth Pinchon. 'Then, you've come on a fool's errand I ' was the somewhat uncivil answer. 'If you do n't give her up, I 'll take the law of you! ' shouted Ebenezer, from the distant spot where he had posted himself. Teunis -replied by striking a light, putting a pipe, between his teeth, and glaring out from beneath the clouds of smoke. In the nean time, Seth Pinchon was reconnoitering the premises. Things certainly looked unpromising. The blunderbuss of the veteran covered him wherever he turned; and the dog followed him with his nose in unpleasant proximity to the calves of his leg, ready to commence hostilities on the slight. est intimation from the war department. He slowly made a circuit of the house,   DERRICK VAN DAM. the dog at his heels; and from each window as he proceeded, the head of the veteran and the end of his blunderbuss appeared. Ryok, in the mean time, kept watch on the motions of Ebenezer. Having satisfied himself that nothing could be done in the way of attack, he determined to make an effort at intimidation. ' Look ye, Sirrah t ' said he, ' we 've come for Mrs. Cock, and Mrs. Cock we will have I ' Teunis made no other reply than the volume of smoke which he puffed from his lips. ' By thunder I Sir,' exclaimed Seth, waxing angry, I ll storm the house.' ' Storm and be d - d I ' was the, curt reply. X Seth Pinchon was evidentlyled; forfrom    he  knewof the iron cha  racter of the Dutchman, he felt sure- th' any'su/ h att empt would ; draw upon him a discharge of fire-arms from the besieged.:' In thi meanwhile, Mrs. Cock from her perch in the cock-loft, was at one moment urging on the attack, at another bestowing torrents of abuse on her captors and on the discreet pu- sillanimity of Ebenezer, who kept beyond range of the artillery. While the perplexity of the besiegers was at its height, and Seth was on the point of suggesting an exchange of prisoners, by way of compromise, all parties were startled by the clatter of hoofs. The next moment, the messen- ger who had delivered Seth's letter dashed up at full gallop, and shouting at the top of his lungs. He brought word that the prisoner had escaped, and what was worse than all, had carried off Freelove with him. The uproar was prodigious I Ebenezer forgot his fear of gunpowder, and rushed up to communicate the news to Seth, and the two consulted in eager tones with the lady in the cock-loft, while a loud bellow of satisfaction burst from the lips of Teunis in the second story, echoed in stentorian tones by Ryck from the dormer-window. Seth was for starting off at once in pursuit, and would not listen to any thing which spoke of delay. 'But think of Mrs. Cock,' put in Ebenezer. ' What about her? ' 'D - n Mrs. Cock! ' was the rough answer. Mrs. Cock caught the words, and her rejoinder was shrill and sharp; but Seth heeded it not. He was already on his way to Buckram. Deserted by his ally, Ebenezer was fain to make good his retreat. But Teunis hailed him: ' When Derrick is safe, I'll send back that baggage in the cock-loft. But if any harm happens to him, she shall swing, if there's a tree at Matinecock which will bear her weight. Be off, now, or I 'll set the dog on you.' Ebenezer waited no second bidding, and disappeared, followed by his ser- vant, leaving Mrs. Cock once more ,to the tender mercies of her captors, and brimful of wrath against her intended son-in-law. Seth Pinchon and his intended father-in-law instituted a vigorous search for the fugitives, but they could learn nothing of them. Seth was furious with dis- appointment, and Ebenezer was inconsolable for the loss of his child. At the end of a week, Teunis Van Gelder received a dispatch from Derrick.  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7984-00000041"/> 80        THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK. It was written from one of the towns on the Hudson River, and informed him of his marriage with the fair Freelove. On the receipt of this, Mrs. Cock was discharged from custody, and onco more returned to her domicil, from which she forthwith expelled Seth Pinchon. The warrior attempted to resist, but it was idle. He found that the tongue of , Mrs. Cock was keener than any weapon that he had ever encountered, and after )several sharp skirmishes, in which he was signally defeated, he deserted the field. :i: As time rolled on, Ebenezer's anger began to abate, and at last he sent an aitation to his son-in-law, to bring his wife to Buckram. His wrath had been sDusiding for some time, and became completely extinguished when news reached him tht Derrick had z. pectely inbhiW  the property of Rip Van Dam, the  JAngre -hlod-lolo         R e Derrick accepted the invitation; but there was little congeniality between him,and his father-in-law, and the most of his time was passed with Teunis Van-Gelder. After the return of the two to the city, the feud between Teunis and Ebenezer was revived and was kept up until Teunis slept with his fathers. THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK. BY JOHN T. IRVING, AUTHOR OF THE QUOP CORRESPONDENCE.' MANY years since I had a relative on the mother's side, an elderly gentle. inan, who prepared to write a history of Long Island. He was a man of great acquirements and thorough research. He was eminently qualified for the task, for there was no fact so astounding that it staggered him, nor any tale so re- markable that it was beyond his'belief. He did not confine his investigations to books alone. He visited spots rendered classic by the deeds of departed worthies. He commenced his explorations at Coney Island, and terminated them at Montauk Point. To sum up his character and qualifications: he was a gentleman of great perseverance and extraordinary swallow. Under these circumstances, it is much to be regretted that he did not live to complete his work. The odd scraps of information, and the strange tales which he had gathered in the course of his labors, fell into my hands -for he was my third- cousin, on the mother's side; and after careful examination, I am satisfied that there is much information contained in these blotted manuscripts of a kind that is not often met with; and that I shall be doing a great favor to the pub-   THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK.            81 lie in general, and to historians in particular, by bringing it to light. The fol- lowing account of Matinecock and the Van Gelder family is from his papers. The Volkert Van Gelder referred to was a personal friend of my respected relative, and a man very much of the same kidney. The same taste for anti- quarian research and for forgotten lore, was a strong feature in the character of each. In the case of Van Gelder, it led to no useful results; in that of my re-  spected relative - had he lived - it would have culminated in the production. of a work of research, which would have shed undying light on the history of Long Island, and would have been a blessing to future generations. About thirty miles from the city of New-York is a headland jutting out into, Long Island Sound, fortified againsfte wash of the sea by huge boulders of rock. The banks of the shore are 'rough 'adfrugge? i bear marks of .the wear and -tear of the waves. On the upland are tall trees, twisted into fan- tastic shapes by the force of the winds which sweep down the Sound. Be- tween this promontory and the mainland is a land-locked bay, from whose borders a dense forest stretches off in various directions. The whole of this region is known by the name of Matinecock. Matinecock is a place of great antiquity, and derives its name from an Indian tribe, which once held sway there. Like many places on Long Island, it is very much behind the rest of the world in matters of every-day experience; and being situated at the end of several very crooked lanes, and hemmed in by water and sand-beaches, it is no easy matter for the world to get at it. In this neighborhood stands a large rambling house, made up of gables and angles, with low roof, and over-shadowed by lofty trees, which show the growth of centuries. It was originally built of squared logs, and was quadrangular in shape; but each successive owner added a wing or an elbow as it suited his fancy, until it seemed to be made up of odds and ends of architecture. It had been founded nearly two hundred years by one Teunis Van Gelder, a stalwart warrior, who had followed the Dutch Governor, Peter Stuyvesant, in his various campaigns. His portrait was in one of the rooms of the man- sion. It represented a stark warrior with high cheek-bones, a mouth closed like a steel-trap, shaggy eye-brows, and a slash across the nose and part of the cheek as if from a sword-cut. The whole denoted an iron character. He had been a staunch campaigner, and had stood by his old commander' until the city of Manhattan capitulated to the English. But he would not re- main to see it under their domination. Bestowing on the invaders his male- diction, he turned his back upon it forever, and retired to the fastnesses of Matinecock, where he took possession of a tract of land without inquiring who was the owner, erected a dwelling, and set himself down to brood over his wrongs, and to meditate revenge. Scarcely, however, had he got warm in his new nest, before he was beset by the myrmidons of Matinecock, led on by one Elbehezer Cock,-a tall, hard-fisted pioneer of the New-England breed. He claimed the ground on which the Dutchman had settled, by virtue of a grant from the Indian owners of the soil. He flourished under Van Gelder's nose a parchment signed with the hierogly- phics of four Sachems of the Matinecock tribe, by which, in consideration of  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7984-00000042"/> 82       THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK. three shirts and a shoe, the aforesaid sachems had conveyed to Ebenezer Cock, Eliphalet Frost and Sampson Latting several thousand acres of ground about Matinecock. This was too much for the gunpowder disposition of the warrior. He glanced grimly over the instrument, then handed it back, and swore he would defend his rights against all the ' Cocks' in Christendom, and prepared for battle.  There is no, doubt, however, that matters were compromised without re- course to arms, For, among the old records is a memorandum dated some years after in 1676, of his going with 'his man Ryck and his square-nosed age to meet one Ebenezer Cock and others on the subject of his difficulties A:bute the lands of Matinecock.' WhatyeVyr ay have been the nature of the compromise, it is cer ht Tenis Van. Goeder retained his possessions, and transmittefd them tois deascedts. Years passed while he, yet Rived there. He had grown gray, but not one whit!ess gri'm, :The nature of his first reception rankled in his mind, and he held-his neighbors at arm's length. He kept a keen watch on all their move- ments, ready to show his teeth at any symptom of aggression. He looked upon their assault upon his domain as but a continuation of the wrongs which had driven him from his native city; he was ready to renew at any moment, in his own person, the war between Holland and England, and was equally ready ito take to his bosom any one who avowed animosity to the English. At that time Captain Kidd was buccaneering on the Spanish Main. Rumors ,were rife of his having been seen in various quarters. At one time he was :said to have-been seen off Montauk, heading for Gardiner's Bay; at another at Sandy Hook. These reports would die away, and then would be revived by ,the arrival of some vessel which had been chased by the redoubted L Rover' in tthc Carribean Sea, and escaped only by night setting in. Late one afternoon, a tall, gaunt courier, mounted on a switch-tail mare, gal- loped through the county in hot haste. I He brought news that Kidd had landed at Sag Harbor, and had rifled the town. Teunis Van Gelden rubbed his hands in keen satisfaction, and-his eye lighted up with a kind of venomous ,glow. He longed for a sight of the gallant freebooter, who was in a manner visiting -upon the English commerce the wrongs which the nation had com- anitted on his native city. On that same -night he was aroused from his sleep by a sound like the re- Tport of a gun booming across the water. He opened his casement and gazed -out. In the distance he observed lights dancing on the Sound, and appa- rently. approaching the land. Shortly after there was a loud hail from the shore. Teunis thrust his head out of the window, and answered by a bellow which might have been heard a mile. Guided by his voice a figure groped its way through the rocks and bushes, and stopped at his door. The Dutchman was always on the look-out for plots and pitfalls on the part ,of his foes, and was prepared for emergencies. He seized his gun and sallied -out to meet-the stranger. At the door stood a square-built, storm-beaten fel- low, with a keen watchful eye, a nose like a hawk's, and a mouth like a bull-   THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK.          83 dog's. He had a cutlass and a pair of pistols in his belt. As the veteran eyed him, and marked his gaunt, hard features, he felt that he was a kindred spirit, anid his heart warmed to him. A few words sufficed to explain that he was se  con d in command of Kidd's vessel, which was at, anchor a- short dis- tance off and in want of supplies. No news could have been more acceptable, no visitor more welcome. Teunis received the freebooter with open arms. His house and all that. he had were placed at his disposal. For several days groups' of slashing fel- lows, armed to the teeth, were seen hanging about the premises, carousing, shooting at marks, swearing hard, and making the neighborhood ring With their revelry. Teunis was in the thick of them; and as they related their en- counters on the Spanish Main, their hand-tohanndlh, and described the din and thunder of battle, the martial spirit of the teeiran fairly broke out, and he swore to Kidd that he loved him as his own son. During *their sojourn the old house fairly echoed with their carousals; and the fierce indomitable spirit of the Dutchman, and his bitter animosity to the English, so won upon the buccaneer, that under a solemn injunction of se- crecy, he took him into his confidence. .His want of supplies was but a pre- text. His vessel was laden with treasure, and he was in quest of a place to secrete it. He suggested Matinecock Point, but Van Gelder shook his head, and cau- tioned him against the marauding spirit of the neighborhood. He declared that no honest man was safe there, that they were a hybrid race, a cross be- tween the Quaker and the steel trap, and that he might better trust the ' Old Boy.'                  ' The freebooter shrugged his shoulders and remarked, 'that they might trust a worse person than the one last mentioned.' Teunis did not argue the point, but suggested Sand's Point as more remote and safer, and added: ' Ryck can show you the way.' 'Agreed,' replied the freebooter. That night at midnight several boats, heavily laden, set off. Van Gelder took a warm interest in the whole proceeding, accompanied them to the boats, and swore to watch over the treasure as if it were his own. He gave minute directions to Ryck, and stood by the shore until the boats were hid by the' darkness. Late at night Ryck returned home, grinning with satisfaction at a broad gold piece which had been bestowed on him. He and his master were closeted together for more than an hour, and they parted with a caution to !secr ecy on the part of the latter, accompanied by a promise to curry his hide in case of his failure. As Teunis was very exemplary in keeping promises of this kind, Ryck remained true to his trust. After the execution of Kidd, it became known to the English government that he had communicated to Van Gelder the spot where his treasure was buried, and Commissioners were appointed to examine him. They found the- veteran in the extreme of age, gaunt, grisly, with dim eyes, like:an old hound, and tottering up and down the walk in front of his house, supported by a  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7984-00000043"/> 84       THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK. witl ered,negro, as decrepit and time-battered as his master. He heard their errand in savage silence. For a minute his energies rallied at the idea of an encounter with his old foes. It was but an expiring flash in the socket. He refused,to give them any information, and turned his back upon them. Ryck shared all his master's antipathies, was equally taciturn, and they departed with their mission unaccomplished. ; In a week from that time Teunis Van (elder was gathered to his fathers. Ryck, after languishing about the place for a few weeks, was found dead, siingon hisa old master's grave. d!The present owner of the house, a lineal descendant of Teunis Van Gelder, is a little dried-up, fellow named Volkert, who, seemed to have grown up be- hind: ; apir of large, -dlA;rimmed spectacles ,through which he views the world on, jim nagnifi4 ed 8^, . y The feu&amp;ds ard animsity which had existed between Teunis and, his neigh- bors died with him, and his descendant was regarded by them as a kindly disposed and well-meaning little man, somewhat peppery in temper and fan- tastic in his notions. Much of This time was spent in out-of-the-way research and- ferreting in the dust-holes of- the past, from which he now and then would fish up some un- savory fact or useless piece of information. Those twilight portions of his- tory in which fable and fact are mingled, were his delight. He would travel a day's journey to visit a spot where a ghost had been seen, or a murder com- mitted. He regarded a superannuated negro as a mine of legendary wealth, and would hold him by the button by the hour to get at the truth of some incident recollected by the negro's great-grandmother, and detailed to him when he was a boy. In fact his foibles were so well known, that every vaga- bond in the country who could coin a plausible story, half-romance and half- fact, was sure of a welcome and a hearty meal in his kitchen. He was not a little proud of his Dutch descent, and had small respect for any whose genealogy was not, like his own,-lost in the fog which surrounded the Dutch dynasty. His prime minister and confidential adviser was a gray-headed, wrinkled negro named Zeb. He had been in his youth a sturdy fellow, but had dried up into an old codger who looked like a frosted persimmon., He was tough and leathery, with a head as hard as adamant, an obstinacy of disposition which required the full strength of his skull to keep it in. He had been born and bred on the place, and looked upon it and his master as his own property. In early life he had been somewhat of a reprobate, so that his name and the gallows had frequently been coupled together in a very familiar manner; but he had disappointed all their prophecies, and in spite of his faults had steered clear of the halter. As he grew old he became proportionably steady in his habits, and his evil name seemed to peel off. By the time he had become entirely useless and good for nothing, he had acquired quite a good character, and of late years he had never been known to swear when he had his own way, nor get drunk at his own expense.. He, however, retained the habit of shooting with a long   THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK.           85  bow, and the marvellous character of his stories was only exceeded by the pertinacity with which he stuck to them. His memory was a perfect magazine of mysterious experiences, of encoun- ters with spirits of every denomination. The whole neighborhood of Dosoris, Matinecock and Lattingtown was but so many weird spots, noted in his mem-, ory as scenes of ghostly adventure. He could point out the very tree at; Flag Brook where Ralph Crafts had a friendly chat with the Devil, who volun;- teered to whip Ralph's wife for him, and was beaten himself; and he could show the large tulip-tree at Dosoris, under which Parson Woolsey had an en- counter of a more hostile character with the same personage, in which he :so exorcised the Old Boy in bad Latin, and raised such a din about his ears with hard Scripture texts, that he itk i fiight and never dared show his- hoof there while the old clergyman lived' -.    't Volkert Van Gelder pretended to turn an incredulous ear to these tales when Zeb happened to speak of them in public, and put his old retainer off with a ' pish;' but he always took occasion when no one was by to glean from him the full particulars. These were committed to writing, and ;towed away in an ancient book-case mounted with brass, which is a perfect repository of ab- struse history. Zeb, however, had a crony in his own sphere, though not of his own color, equally versed in legendary lore. This was an old weather-beaten fellow with a red nose and a moist eye, of the name of Nick Wanzer. Nick was born and bred at Matinecock. Many of his Lfamily, had gone of to seek their fortunes in other parts of the world. Nick quoted the old saw, ' A rolling stone gathers no moss,' and staid at home. He grew no richer, but in process of time he certainly acquired a kind of moss-grown look, as if he were reaping the reward of his resolution. He was addicted to strong drink and long stories, and by dint of constant indulgence in both, it became a matter of doubt whether his head or his stories had become toughest. He was usually to be met with -either on the borders of the Dosoris mill-pond, with a fishing-rod across his shoulder, or trudging along the sand-bars, carrying a gun as battered as himself, with a slouch- tailed dog at his heels. He however was indigenous to the place, and be. longed to, that class of worthies, one or two of whom hang about every conn. try village, and who drift through life always in sight, living no one knows how or where, and winding up their career by being found dead under some hedge or in some hay-mow. In his youth he had been a harum-scarum fellow, S keen sportsman, and a persevering fisherman. Every rock from the Stepping Stones to Lloyd's Neck, was as familiar to him as his own dwelling, and there was not a corner of any swamp, or nook of woodland, which he had not traversed with dog and gun.  He had been terribly harried in the early part of his life, by a termagant wife, but he had at last deposited her in the Lattingtown church-yard, with a heavy stone over her to commemorate her virtues and to keep her quiet. He had been too much cowed by stringent petticoat government, ever to  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7984-00000044"/> 86       THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK. be the man that he had been before his marriage; but it was a great weight off his mind to know that she was at rest, as well ;as himself. From that time he ;hd been his own master, loitered about the country, attending to every body's business except his own., When the weather was fine, and the Sound-!smooth, he and Zeb passed -whole mornings in a rickety boat, paddlang about in search of fish. , When the fish did not, bite, the worthies might be- descried upon one of the rocks at Martinecock, philosophizing over the past, while Nick's dog slept in the sunshine at their feet. 1iOf: late Volkert had shown a strong yearning toward Nick. There was something in his good-for-nothing character which harmonized with the taste-of Volkert, who had a weak spot in, his affections for vagabonds. Nick, from a casU#a!;loiterer about thplace, was gradUl'Uy become a kind of appendage to it: rilnniine Of errands' ahi a eso f sh o dr  g a few woodcoS at okte sa door; -rim the noses^of his pigs, and maling himself generally useful. "But- the eat secret of their :intimacy was a certain adventure which Nick had met with, many -yeara previously, in which TeunisVan Gelder bore a conspicuous part, It did not speak very well for the old *pioneer, butYVol- kert took a strange pride in the evil odor which -hung round the skirts of his ancestor. He forthwith took Nick by the hand, and although the tale was scouted by many as the fabrication of Nick's drunken brain, Volkert cross- examined him faithfully; tookl the whole down in writing, decided it to be both plausible and true, and forthwith deposited it among the arcana of his historic lore, from which I have drawn it. The adventure was as follows : NICE   WANZER'S ADVENTURE. NICK had been passing an evening many years since at a husking-frolic. Like most persons who are good for nothing else, he was in his element there. He was a lusty dare-devil fellow then, ready for a fight or a frolic, and full of that rash yet jovial recklessness which makes friends of the men and plays the very deuce among the other sex. The party had been merry, and when the time came for breaking up, their merriment had become boisterous. Nick, overflowing with good cheer, took his leave of his host, shook hands with the mothers, kissed the prettiest of their daughters, and set out on his return to his own quarters. The road was dark and gloomy, but he knew every inch of it. He was mel- low with ale,/apple-brandy and hard cider. He knew that he had to pass through a weird neighborhood, and all the tales which he had heard of ghosts and hobgoblins and Kidd and old Teunis Van Gelder were circulating freely through his brain, and, as he afterward acknowledged, what with the spirits within and the spirits without, his head was in somewhat of a turmoil. He had a  small boat drawn up in a creek near Peacock's- Point, and as the road became somewhat unsteady as he proceeded, he determined to return home by water. Taking a short-cut across the fields and floundering through a  swamp or two, he finally reached the creek, drew out his boat, and pushed o  it into the Sound.  It was one of those quiet still nights when there was scarcely a ripple on   THE JAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK.          87, the water; every star was plainly reflected on its surface, and the moon hung in the sky like a huge globe of silver. Nick pulled lazily along, thinking at one time of a farmer's daughter with whom he had passed a few love-passages behind the door; then of the ale and cider and apple-brandy; then of the tales of Kidd, with which an old, black fiddler had regaled them at intervals during the evening: until he had got the apple-brandy and the farmer's daughter and Kidd and his treasure terribly, jumbled together. He had been wondering where the freebooter could have out hisi money: and whether it was in gold-dust, or in bars or coin, and as- in deep speculation as to whether it would be possible for him to discover it, dig-it up, buy up the whole country round,; and marry the girl just spoken of, when his attention was arrested-y7a loudhail. ' Boat a-hoy I boatla-hiy t '  The sound appeared to c-om frome om the Point at Matinecock, whichwas nearly half a mite distant; and yet the voice seemed to, be scarcely fifty feet off. . Nick dropperhis oars and listened. . 'B-o-a-t a-h-o-oo--y I ' again sounded across the water from the same direction, and yet apparently close at hand. Nick looked about him in every direction, to ascertain if any other craft were in sight. The moon shone brilliantly, and its reflection rested like solid silver on the water: not a thing was to be seen. ' It's very strange,' thought he, ' but it can't cost much to answer.' So he put his hand to his mouth and gave the response: ' Hallo i' 'Come ashore; you 're wanted I' was the rejoinder in the same singular tone. Nick did not altogether relish the summons, but he was a good-natured fel- low, so he turned his boat toward the land. As he approached it, he saw a figure seated on a rock at the water's edge. He supposed the hail might come from one of the neighbors who wanted a lift on his way home. But on nearer approach, he saw that the man on the rock was a stranger. By the light of the moon, he appeared to be a tall, gaunt man, black and grim, and dressed in a red shirt. A dark hat was slouched over -his face, from beneath which two eyes glowed out like fire, and in his hand he held a club. Nick eyed him for a moment, waiting for him to speak. But he sat without a word, and with his glowing eyes fixed, on him in a way that made Nick's flesh creep. ' Do you want me? ' at last inquired he. ,' Not I,' replied the other in a gruff voice. ' You want me.' - 'You? I never laid eyes on you before,' said Nick. ' I 've been at your elbow for the last half-hour; ever since you were think- ing of Kidd's money. I have charge of it.' 'Whew-w I ' Nick drew a long, low whistle, and laid his finger with a sort of drunken gravity on His nose. 'Then you know what I was thinking of ' The other nodded. '  You 're not Kidd ' The other shook his head. 'Nor Teunis Van Gelder?' ' No.'  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7984-00000045"/> 88       . THE VAN GELDERS. OF MATINECOCK. 'Then you must be --'  Nick paused, as be did not like to be disrespect- ful. 'You must be The other nodded. ' You 've bit it.' ' The old Nick,' added Wanzer.. 'Your namesalke/' replied the stranger. - And'you have charge of Kidd's money? ' inquired Nick. .The stranger nodded again. V: But can you tell mne here it is?' asked Nick in an insinuating tone. 'It's, of no use to any one:now.'. r The stranger looked about him, and then said in a cautious tone: ' I sup- pose I might, but rt would be a breach of trust; I promised never to reveal it.' ', :think you observed that you are the0d-Boy,' remarked Nick. 'The Old Boy, Old ick,  Old Harry, Old- Scratch, among friends! My enemies are. less curteous .in their titles,' replied the other. , 'Well,' said Nick,- in a very insinuating tone, 'that being. the case, a trifling breach of trust can't hurt you. You know that your character is none of the best;- I do n't mean to say that you deserve what is said of you,' added he in an apologetic tone, 'but people oill talk, and they some, times make very free with you.'        /  'I know it,' replied the other. 'I'm used to it; I do n't mind it.' 'Well, said Nick, returning to the subject of the gold, 'if you could put me in the way of getting that money, I would do something for you d---d handsome.'  'I can't venture,' replied the other resolutely; 'I don't mind Kidd so much. He's bad enough, and has some desperate fellows leagued with him; but the worst of all is a hard-headed Dutchman, one Teunis Van Gel- der. Since he came into our quarters, he and Kidd have struck up a kind of partnership: I've led a dog's life.' 'But they can't use the money,' urged Nick. 'Can any miser use his. money?' inquired the other, 'yet no miser will part with it. They like to know   it's there. I tell you, Sir,' said he, striking his club hard on the ground, and- speaking with much emphasis, 'if they lost that money, they'd make my quarters too hot to hold me.' 'Well,' said Nick, 'I did not think that they could increase the tempera- ) ture there; but if they did kick you out, would you mind it?' 'I was brought up there,' answered the other, 'and am somewhat used to the climate.. I do n't think I would feel at home any where else.' Nick was unwilling to give up the chance of getting hold of the free- booter's treasure. 'Who is to tell them that you revealed it?' asked he; 'I would not.'         , The stranger seemed impressed by this promise.  ICan I rely on you, Mr. Wanoer?'   ! Nick was vociferous in vindication of his trustworthiness. 'But there must be a consideration,' suggested the stranger. 'I never do any thing without it.' 'Just as you please,' said Nick, who was becoming  reckless; 'I agree to any thing   THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK.           89 'You know what my price is?' 'I've heard,' replied Nick. 'Give me the money, and make your own terms.'                     .  'Enough,' answered the other. 'Jump in your boat, and pull for Sand's Point. I'1 meet you there.' Nick waited for no second bidding. He sprang into his boat, pushed off from, the shore, and tugged away lustily at the oar. The exercise had the effect of taking off some of the fumes of the liquor which he had dranki and of bringing him to his senses. He. began to think over his promise , and to wonder if he had not got himself into a scrape; but before he had settled the matter to his satisfaction, the boat grounded on the beach, aind he found the stranger standing at 'his side, with a shovel in his hand. 'p-e beckoned to Nick, who followed' hiimuntil they camet.; where a huge boilder, known as Kidd's Rock, juts out from the Point., Here he paused, threw the shovel to Nick, and told him to dig. Nick was disposed to parley, but he felt the glowing eyes on him, and his heart failed him. He dug lustily, throwing ofit the sand in great shovels- full. At last he struck something solid. He eagerly cleared away the dirt, and discovered a chest, secured with iron bands. He struck it with the shovel, and could hear the jingle of coin. All his scruples vanished at the sound. 'Now then, Nick, you remember your promise--about your soul,' said the stranger, jumping in the hole and planting himself firmly on the chest. 'There's the money.' ' Ay, ay,' said Nick recklessly; ' devil take the soul. I want the money.' 'Give me your hand,' said the other. 'It's no bargain until we have crossed hands.' Nick had extended his hand, and already was that of the Great Adversary reached to grasp it, when a loud unearthly shout rang through the air. Nick bounded from the hole at a single leap. The next instant, with a yell, two figures pounced upon the stranger in the pit. There were appalling screams and cries and all the struggle of fierce encounter. They seemed to breathe fire and smoke at each other: at one time the fight raged in the hole, then it seemed to be up the bank near Kidd's Rock, at another time in the air. In the moonlight Nick could see his friend hard beset, and he noticed that' he suffered most from a grim old fellow in a cocked hat, with a slash across his nose. The other was square-built, with pistols in his belt, and a hanger at his side.                          ' As Nick began to doubt how the battle would terminate, he quietly slipped into his boat, put off a short distance from the shore, and rested on his oars to watch the result.           - In a few minutes he heard his name shouted from the beach. Nick was too wary to be entrapped by any feeling of sympathy. He kept a dead silence. The noise and uproar lasted for a short time longer, and then grew more and more distant, until it died away in the woods of Great Neck. Nick now plied his oars vigorously, occasionally pausing to listen. At the  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7984-00000046"/> V90      . THE VAN GELDERS OF MATINECOCK. same time he was not free from an'apprehension that on looking round he might find his late visitor stationed in the bow of his boat. But he reached Matinecock in safety. As he stepped ashore he was not a little dismayed at discovering the stranger seated on a rock, apparently as cool as if nothing had happened; but on, closer exaninatin Nick observed that his dress was very much dilapidated, and his face begrimed with smut and dirt. 'I hope you're not hurt,' said he, in a tone which was meant to be sympa- "'thing. ' Those fellows were a little too much for you.' ' ;I told you how it would be,' said the other in a savage voice. 'They got :wihd of it somehow.' '.ho, were they?' ..                     ' 'Nomatter. They ae'the most. troublesome of allmy boarders.' 'And-theimoney?' inquired Nick, 'It 's where: you left it,' replied the other. 'You can get it if you like. Y   ouknow ourbarigain: you're mine.' 'Not until. I finger the cash,' replied Nick. 'And unless you are more lucky than you have been to-night, I do n't think you'll put me in the way of doing it in a hurry.' ' Mr. Wanzer,' said the other, ' do you mean to break our bargain?' 'Where's the money?' demanded Nick in reply. 'If you mean that I should take it while those two pleasant gentlemen are mounting guard over it, you are much mistaken. I will see you to the -- yourself first. And if you mean that I am to get it as I can, and be pestered by them while I live, and by you afterward, I won't do it. Do you think I did not recognize old Teunis Van Gelder: I've seen his picture too often. If he's too much for you, I'd like to know how I would come off in a scuffle with him; and if he and Kidd hunt in couples why damme I 'll have nothing to do with it.' 'Nick struck his feet resolutely on the side of his boat. ' You 're resolved?' said the other sternly. 'I am,' said Nick. 'Then take the consequences.' He raised his club, but at that moment the same loud unearthly yell which had startled him before broke through the air, .and two figures sprang toward them: the one in a cocked hat gray and grim, the other armed to the teeth. Before the club could descend, the stranger bounded from the rock, and disap- peared in the direction of Dosoris, the two following in full cry at his heels. Nick hurried off, and made the best of his way to his cabin, where he was found in the morning in a sleep so sound that some thought it might have been the result of deep potations, but which Nick himself attributed entirely to the excitement of the scene which he had gone through at Sand's Point and Matinecock. IN a note in the margin of the above manuscript my respected relative re- marked, that Mr. Volkert Van Gelder, after full and mature investigation of the matter, had come to the conclusion that the adventure of Nick Wanzer was not a mere fabrication, but an actual occurrence.   THE RAIN.               91 He was forced to this conclusion by strong circumstantial evidence; for it was established beyond a doubt that Wanzer was at a husking-frolic on the very night alluded to, that he set out for home late, and somewhat involved in liquor; and also that he did own a boat which usually lay in a creek at Pea- cock's Point. Nick Wanzer himself pointed out the rock on which the stranger sat when [ he first made overtures to him; and the situation of Kidd's Rock at Sand'*"; Point is, a matter of public notoriety. Under these circumstances, Mr. Van Gelder felt that to express farther doubt would be to cast an unjust imputa- tion upon the character of a worthy and well-meaning citizen.  : In commenting farther my respected relative observed, with his usuai is- crimination and acuteness, that itXwas a very nice point to decide. Thatthere certainly was: Strong c 'oWbr o at'idyevidenc 0of . th[ruth 'of the: story:' and that although it was out iof the usual course of things, yet 'that Matinecock was an unusual kind of place, and events night transpire there which would not happen elsewhere. Under these circumtstances, and after fully Weighing the evidence, he thought that Wanzer's statement was worthy of full credence from all persons of strong faith. THE RAIN. PATTER, patter comes the rain, Aslant against the window-pane: I can see the large drops fall- Mystic globules, perfect all: See them speed their downward way, Fall, then weep themselves away. So, against my weary brain Thoughts come tapping like the rain: Radiant thoughts, from far-off spheres,  1 Strike, then spend themselves in tears. O ye rain-drops clear and bright I O ye thoughts on wings of light I Will ye never, never tell Of the regions whence ye fell? Tell us whence ye come, and why When ye reach us then ye die? Are ye voiceless evermore, Only moaning, moaning ever, When your beauteous forms are driven 'Gainst the cold and glassy pane - 'Gainst this hardened, earth-worn brain, In your fruitless, vain endeavor To convey to mortal ears The language of the far-off spheres?  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7984-00000047"/> 92 THeE      RAIN B O W. A CHIPPEWA ALLEGORY.* BY HENRY R. SCHOOLCRAFT. A PROPHET lived near the falls of St. Mary's for many years. He was now an old man, and he was regarded as one who ever lived in close communion with the Great Spirit. He could read the clouds.  He could understand every mystic sound: There was no hard question put to him which he could not answer, He was a wise man. He had made mysteries his study, till all mysteries were plain to him. He possessed a small stature, and a thin body, and small legs and arms. Some thought his bones were hollow, like a bird's, he was so light. But his eyes were black and sparkling, and his voice had a peculiar intonation. 'His her was long and as white as snow, and the older he became the longer and whiter it grew. He had been married when a young man, and had a daughter named Alla, whom  he tenderly loved and cherished, and to whom he had taught some of his songs and arts. Alla was the pride of her village; modest, kind and re- spectful, she became an example and pattern for all the maidens. But she was taken very ill one day in her father's lodge and died before any -relief could be given; while it was observed that a rainbow from the Falls rested on the top of her father's lodge. Whether it was this incident, or some early dream that  had given him the name of the Rainbow, or Hair of the Sun, is not known. Many thought that the girl had been miraculously transferred to the skies, and he sided with this opinion, for he had often seen her sitting and gazing in- tently at the sky. He had a little drum, the rim of which was covered with hieroglyphics; and a curious stick, upon the end of which was tied a string of deer's hoofs, which made a sharp noise at every stroke. And he sang these words with a solemn tone: 'HEAR my drum, ye spirits high; Earth and water, air and sky, Ye to me are common ground; Spirits, listen to my sound-- Walking, creeping, running, flying, Near or distant, living, dying, Ye are but the powers I sway; Hearken to my solemn lay - I compel you hither come: Hear my rattle, hear my drum, From your highest circles come.'   THE RAINBOW.              93 The bark rolls of his lodge had been lifted up while he uttered this incantation, and the gorgeous red and green rays of the rainbow rested directly on his head. They seemed to be mingled with his long hair; and when he put up his hand to disentangle it, he found himself rising by a strong attraction, and he rose up to the skies by these light and silky filaments. Very long and bright silver lodges, and open green plains, were the first things that presented themselves; and he saw that the smoke which issued from them in large sheets of blue, pink and white, formed the clouds surround- " ,ing the globe. He was kindly received at the chief's lodge, where a wide circle^ of scarlet-red chairs were occupied by chiefs, who sat smoking their pipes,. He saw that at every exhalation of the smoke there were bright little flames, and this is the cause of what we call cannung, or the stars. Very soon his daughter stood before him in a beautiful robe of pale green. ' Father,' said she, ' I have expected you a long times I told those tall and majestic chiefs yonder that if they would untie their girdles and let, down the silken threads of their long sashes which bind their robes, you would come up. But father, it is not here as with you on earth. We do not live in want at all. We do not hunger; we do not die. There are no marriages here; there are no births. We are all spirits; our senses are keen and high. We can hear the slightest whisper from below, and see the smallest thing. It seems the distance is not broader than my hand. Your drum and rattle sound plainly, and the words of your songs are instantly understood. There is no war or bloodshed here. There is no hunting; the animals come out of the woods un- hunted. The high and sharp rocks are only shadows; we can walk through them. Every thing is pleasing, and all are happy here. The Great Spirit only visits us by angels. He dwells in yonder region, surrounded by bright -stars. ' I see you have brought along your drum and rattle. Sit down on yonder green bank by the crystal waters and play, while I go to report your coming to a higher power.' He played. The music he made was of unusual sweet- ness; and when he looked, the instrument was changed into a bright sub- stance like silver. He had played but a little while, when there came on the waters stately white swans and birds of bright plumage, and when he looked around him he saw droves of deer and antelopes and elks in peaceful gambols. Where he took his seat he remained sitting;, and this is the reason of that bright planet called the Evening Star. It is only one of the little ornaments which surround the Great Spirit; and when it rains in heaven, you behold those bright lights Jeebiug Neemiiddewaud, or the Dancing Ghosts, called by white men Aurora Borealis. Youthful listener, wouldst thou be instructed? Behold in this legend the history of the aged prophet Miscogaudic-aub or the Rainbow-Chief and his daughter Alla, and their translation to the abode of the Great Spirit.  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7984-00000048"/> " TIIE LITTLE BLACK SLIPPER. BY BHNRT P. LELAND, ' SAID I, ' HARRY, where did you get that slipper?' Said he,' JAMES, this is the tale: 'If any thing will alleviate the little miseries of a two days' diligence-journey, it is having as pretty, good-natured, and cosmopolitan a little widow for your opposite travelling companion, as I had from Cordova on the Guadalquivir, to Madrid on the Mnazanares. Tumbling into the 'interior' of a diligence at two o'clock of a June morning after a few hours spent in a vain attempt to sleep, rendered vain and profane by a legion of those tirailleurs d diable, longhorned mosquitoes, one is by no means as serene in temper as one should be. The writer was savage that morning; and not until the mayoral (conductor) had brought a light to see if the passengers were all properly packed in, revealing the cheerful little face of a pretty woman opposite to him, did his good nature shine out as a patent reflector and dissipate the fog of discontent. "A long journey before us: let us make ourselves comfortable,' said the lady, the departing mayoral with light just enabling me to see that there was a smile on her face. Then there was a shaking of black silk skirts, Gracias a Dios I there were no steel or whalebone petticoats on her blessed form; two little feet sought refuge on my side; two good-sized ones searched for an asylum on her side the diligence and behold, we were disposed to be friends for life. I do n't know whether TUPPmR, in his ' Proverbial Phi- losophy,' mentions under the head of ' Friendship' that it is ' a travelling shawl,' but in his next edition he'd better do it, you know, BECAUSE IT is I At least that morning, when I spread mine over my legs, and extended the courtesy to the limbs (Lingua Americana) of the fair widow, she accepted the woollen with a kind acknowledgment that made me feel blessedly pleased with myself and with her. The bells of the eight mules pulling the diligence were jingling; the postillion on the right leader had settled himself in his saddle; the arr'iero had hold of the reins; the mayoral jumped into his seat in the Imperial; and the zugal, holding his calafies hat tight on his head, sprung out of the door of the diligence-office, uttering fearful yells and cracking his whip with the ferocity of a mad monkey; when - creak, bang, slide, slip! and we were launched on our journey to Madrid. ' I went to sleep and had a pleasant dream of being a cherubim, the kind that flew round NOAH when he was building the Ark, and had no legs I and having a dear little pair of gaiter boots for wings; while I had for a companion, another aeronaut with large black eyes, a propos of which - * I NEVER loved a dear gazelle, And gazed upon its soft, black eyes, But what it turned out a d -- sell - A damsel heaving gentlest sighs '- who was all thy's and thou's. In addition to black eyes, she had black hair and a travel- ling-shawl, and she had feet; and both the tiny little ones were somehow thrust into the pockets of my shooting-coat, and -- I woke up and found that there were a pair of   THE LITTLE BLACK     SLIPPER.         n* little, high-heeled, black slippers, with w hite sil k stockings attached, resting on the : cushion by my side. You may talk aboutream-books, and explanatio  ns of dreams, but such bona-fide realizations p lease me most : an d I looked down at them an d d eter mined they should be mine if I had to go a han on them-matmonially of course, la mo  de &amp;e ' I 'd offer thee t his hand of mine ,' with piano a ccompaniment . ' But she woke up, and as the sun was now s hining brightly, sh e saw m e regarding ;^ , those 'leather mice,  ' whereupon she at onc e hid them, not by rudely w ithdrawing themnd wa:l but b y cuddling them up under one endof the travelling-shawl; whic h end was in closi , proximity with my pantaloons pocket. Now reader fanc y m y feelings nursinga pairpfi twins lik e those; belonging to a very pretty woman - moreover a w idow . d.  i c 3enas da, Senor l' It was so cheerfully, pleasantly spoken, and with Ski I  wininng smile, and the dark eyes beamed so softly u nder the long blac k e ye. a h t it elicited all the writer's storPl of amiai;ty;in return It am e out inu onvershtit at the lady was from Seville, was a widow, dta ner -frlst na . aias n rA . a -iBll ou So-and-S ) and as I had passed many P..       ..s a , ,'V b' ,' a0s:s s  - venirs of ' The Marvel,' we were. soon in ehimt ab oui its n-tdr   i8 anaies. She was charmingly naive in conversation, an d showed ii eremaw   hat is an exception with Spanish ladies--anintelligent and animated disposition. At Bilen, where we dined, I lost my heart whenI handed her from the diligene--beside, she, faintly pressed my hand with her gloved hand, and showed methose feet t ' There is no use doing things in a hurry, so I determined, as we were yet thirty-six hours from Madrid, to wait until we were within three hours of the city before I formally proposed for her heart, hand, and- highheeled shoes. BAy, -ue gusto, uf e placer I ' Again was ttie old diligence en rote; again theshades of night were on us, and cool air brought out the travelling-shal; and again a joint partnership was entered into between JUANITA and me. Somehow, nea Las Navas de Tolosa, the diligence gave a fearful lurch, and JuxmTA was pitched nearly into my arms; seems to me, she must have assisted the shock, else how, in all the darkness of night, for it must have been nearly ten o'clock, and raining, could I have kissed her and taken charge of her for nearly a minute, while the diligence was coming to time? , QUIEN  SABE' That's the way to get over the difficulty in Spain; in Italy with a- 'CH LO  SA! or to hunt it up to head-quarters in Arabic: 'MA ARRIF! if you want it at home:                   - ot WHO KNOWS! That was a rose-colored' rainy night--the diligence pitched several times with equal Success. Imade up mind to turn Spaniard, buy one of those velvet tiles, a black lamb-skin jacket, knee-breeches, pounds of silver waistcoat and coat buttons, leather gaiters with long leather fringe; learn to roll cigarritas and become a ciarrista. Go twice a week to the Circo Gallistico, ' where roosters do combat ;' bet my duros on the winning gallo, (not gall oh! but on the contrary;) attend every bull-fight, and mass once a week, to keep my hand in; dance the bolero; drink aguardiente very cautiously; shoot red- legged partridges all the year round, and, to sum up, come out strong as a full-blooded majo! either this or edit a paper in Madrid progresisto. ' Again the morning broke and up came the sun illumining our breakfast at Valdepeas, where the wine comes from, at least the baptismal name to table-wine half over pain T determined to edit a paper in Madrid, prlogresisto I /**w '";, " " ;' 'A    * ,  &#xD;<pb n="96" xml:id="VAC7984-00000049"/> 96          THE LITTLE BLACK SLIPPER. The day wheeled by until we arrived at Tembleque, where our diligence was wheeled on to a railroad-car, and we were to make the fifteen leagues between there and Madrid with great diligence by steam. Temnzbque means a diamond pin; it sticks me with pain when I think of it, for there, yes there! JUANITA was lost to me (as a wife) forever. 'At Temblque, while taking a hurried lunch, I saw a bill announcing a bull-fight to ; come off in Madrid next day, and was glad to be able to enjoy this amusement once Emore; on my return to the diligence, i communicated to the widow the interesting fact. i Ojala I' said she, ' how I do love bull-fights! And to see CUCHARES with the capa - "n ne hand and sword in the other, feIsoos I he is a spada; but you should have seen JrA, (pronounce WHAN,) he always killed first blow. Ay Carambal there was a man for ylu-- and such clothes and such legs-poor soul that last black bull from the motWitains was too much for him.-too much, too much I' and here the widow paid a tribute of two tears to his memory, and flourished her little hands and white cambric disconsolitely.    . 'This -tL :did not please me, although he had succumbed to the bull, and was gone where good bill-fighters go; the tribute to his memory made me a little-slightly jealous. But concealing my feelings, I asked as unconcernedly as possible: 'Well, who was JUAN ' ' JUAN?' replied the dear widow, ' JUAN? why, he was my husband!' Farewell, orange-flower wreaths, white lace veils, and slow on-farewell, ideas matri monial. I, HARRY BUTTONS DE BUTTONVILLE, marry a bull-fighter's widow! By the shadow of my respectability, never! 'JUANITA, I never can be thine!' said I, in a burst of feeling. "Ay Caramba I but you will see me home in a carriage, when I arrive at Madrid, won't you? ' asked the widow. I did- and she gave me the slipper.' i   I Ii I I   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>