<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7697">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some Passages in the Life of Geoffrey Clinker, Esq. [pseud.] : </title>
            <author>Sands, Alexander H. (1828-1887)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7697</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2152</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some passages in the life of Geoffrey Clinker, Esq. [pseud.] :</title>
                  <author>Sands, Alexander H. (1828-1887)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>MacFarlane &amp; Fergusson</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Richmond </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1854">1854</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-03-16">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5. Inserted OCR text. Linked image files</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Some passages in the life of Geoffrey Clinker, Esq. [pseud.] :</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7697-00000001"/>/&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
REPRODUCED FROM THE COPY IN THE&#xD;
HENRY E. HUNTINGTON LIBRARY&#xD;
FOR REFERENCE ONLY. NOT FOR REPRODUCTION&#xD;
&#xD;
~:t~ ~Iinkcr Ian stipt~.&#xD;
/&#xD;
SOME PASSAGES&#xD;
&#xD;
IN&#xD;
THE LIFE OF&#xD;
GEOFFREY CtINKER, ESQI&#xD;
WRITTEN ~BY HIMSELF.&#xD;
C~7 ~&#xD;
'RICHMOND:&#xD;
MACFARLANE &amp;amp; FERGUSSON.&#xD;
&#xD;
I,&#xD;
.'&#xD;
&#xD;
18~54!                 I&#xD;
&#xD;
'1'&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7697-00000002"/>&#xD;
*   J~ ~                     -~&#xD;
&#xD;
-p&#xD;
Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1854,&#xD;
BY MACFARLANE &amp;amp; FERGUSSON,&#xD;
in the Cler1~ 2Oflice of the District Court of the United States,&#xD;
in and for the Eastern District of Virginia.&#xD;
&#xD;
IINTROIDUCTORY.&#xD;
When a mere lad, I frequently saw on the streets an odd lookir~g old&#xD;
man, who had lived ~tnd flourished, if he flourished at all, at a period&#xD;
when our republic was yet in its infancy. His manners and address&#xD;
indir- familiarity with the best modes of polishediif'e in the cob-&#xD;
njal p a of c r State. He was urbane and courteous to a fault, and&#xD;
though I was at first repelled by his odd appearance, I became in an ex-&#xD;
traordinary degree attached to his society upon a more familiar acquaint-&#xD;
ance. During our intimacy-such an intimacy as would be likely to&#xD;
grow up between a young man and one who had lived so long in the&#xD;
I past-the old man would frequently recount the history of the stirring&#xD;
periods of our revolution, and I well remember with what enthusiasm&#xD;
and boyish ardor he described his first meeting with the g~eat and yen-&#xD;
erable LaFayette, just after the memorable surrender at Yorktown..~&#xD;
Many of the historic reminiscences connected with that event, and which&#xD;
no chronicler of the period has preserved, were detailed to me in these&#xD;
conversations. I learned, too, that this gentleman had been in the habit&#xD;
of putting his thoughts on paper, and I was favored with more than one~&#xD;
of his sketches of the home life of our young Virginia, while yet she&#xD;
acknowledged the sway of his majesty, King George the Third.&#xD;
The old man died, bequeathing his manuscripts-his only possession-&#xD;
to a descendant who has since kindly submitted them to my inspection,&#xD;
with the liberty of giving such of them to the public as might be deemed&#xD;
suitable.&#xD;
The following chapters, bearing his autograph title in bold upright char-&#xD;
acters, purporting to be a synoptical view of his own life, are now publish-&#xD;
ed as a proper introduction to other of his manuscripts having particular&#xD;
reference to the historic details of the time. Indeed, I have eliminated&#xD;
chapters of this description found in this volume, because they might&#xD;
more properly be introduced in connection with other essays from his&#xD;
pen.&#xD;
It will be observed that the current of his life seems to have run in very&#xD;
nearly the same channel with ours of the present day.&#xD;
I. W.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7697-00000003"/>&#xD;
9 ~ ~&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
)&#xD;
(&#xD;
)                                        K&#xD;
)                                        K&#xD;
(&#xD;
~ ~ - -&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
SOME PASSAGES IN THE LIFE OF&#xD;
GEOFFREY CLINKER, ESQO&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER I.&#xD;
SHOWING HOW I BEGAN LIFE..&#xD;
&#xD;
It ~as a marvellous thing-I assure you-my boy-that of&#xD;
being born into this strange world, anti though some seventy&#xD;
odd years have passed by since then, I never think of it now&#xD;
without astonishment. iLet me see. There was old Parson&#xD;
Dowdy there, to be sure, for the Parson was never absent on&#xD;
such occasions. lie had a good reason for being attentive to&#xD;
them. It was rumored, that while yet a yoi~ng man he had lost&#xD;
two very bar~isorne fees by his absence, the little strangers&#xD;
having in both instances left the land of the living as soon as&#xD;
they reached it, without waiting to be christened. Parson Ji~ow-&#xD;
dy was there-and my mother's eldest sister, her of the blue&#xD;
dress and tremendous oversleeves. I remember her as well as&#xD;
if it were yesterday. That was many years afterward~ though.&#xD;
She sat at my father's table knitting me a pair of socks, every&#xD;
now and then heaving a deep sigh, and saying in s~4rcely au-&#xD;
dible tones: poor Nancy! Nancy was my mother's name.&#xD;
Then, father! yes father was there, and I have heard that he&#xD;
spent a night of sleepless anxiety and was careworn jand&#xD;
thoughtful on that morning. My father always had a thought-&#xD;
ful look. I never saw him smile, and I wondered at it, for&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
(&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7697-00000004"/>&#xD;
I'&#xD;
47&#xD;
&#xD;
6           Some Passages in the Life of&#xD;
all-around him were merry and gay, and he~~;~ not a moros4&#xD;
man. lie would frequently take me up in his arms and hu~&#xD;
me to his bosom, aiA I could discover whenever he did so the&#xD;
large tear drops stealing down his manly cheek. I loved my&#xD;
father. But I am getting away from the subject. Beside&#xD;
these, there was none other person present save the neighbor-&#xD;
ing physician-a good, kindhearted man who went about from&#xD;
house to house dealing out his charities and kind deeds without&#xD;
expecting any return for his services. Poor man, he had had&#xD;
many such cases, but never a one which was to terminate so&#xD;
seriously. My mother-i never saw my x~iother. She was a&#xD;
beautiful woman, so my aunt has told me~ She had soft silken&#xD;
hair, the color of flax, a dimpled cheek and skin of fairest&#xD;
white, and a voice an gel-toned, it was so pure and sweet. My&#xD;
mother was very sick. She could not recover. Her pulse was&#xD;
low, and its strokes were feeble and yet feebler. She was going&#xD;
every moment. A few more and she would bi~eathe her last.&#xD;
There lay i, the innocent occasion of her death. She had gone!&#xD;
A birth and a death at the same hour: The house of joy con-&#xD;
verted into the house of mourning.&#xD;
CHAPTER ii.&#xD;
MY SCHOOL EXPERIENCE AND WHAT I LEARNED THERE.&#xD;
The school-house was 1o~ated just outside of the corporatee lim-&#xD;
its of the city I wa~ then proud to caW my birthplace. It was&#xD;
a neat log building, scarce fifteen feet by twenty, consisting of&#xD;
a single room. There was a green plot in front of the door, and&#xD;
what was known as the lawn stretched out in the rear. Enter-&#xD;
&#xD;
aeoffrey (Junker, Esq.              7'&#xD;
ing the house early in the morning, before the pedagogue had&#xD;
mounted his chair of state, you might have discovered a state&#xD;
of affairs somewhat resembling the condition of Bedlam and&#xD;
Babel combined. here mounted on a stool, just three feet&#xD;
high, stood a promising young lad of the same height, bawling&#xD;
out a command at the top of his voice to another to keep quiet,&#xD;
while in an opposite direction two qrthree little urchins were&#xD;
exercising their milseles at the expanse of each other's bones.&#xD;
These were occasionally relieved by outcries resemthing cat-&#xD;
calls and the like emanating from different quarters of the&#xD;
spacious building. Suddenly; as in a flash, you would discover&#xD;
the tum~ilt cease and die away into a sing-song tone, as each&#xD;
little urchin took his place to hum over the morning recitation.&#xD;
Mr. Thomson, the teacher, was a jovial old man, scarce turned&#xD;
of ~fty, who had preserved his good spirits and gee d temper&#xD;
amazingly well, in view of the trials they had severally &amp;amp;ncoun-&#xD;
tered. lie had no taste for extra exertion, and this was one of&#xD;
the reasons assigned by the boys for his entire absence of an-&#xD;
ger, save on the most provoking occasions. I do not remember&#xD;
ever to have seen him macI l)ut once, and then, strange to say,&#xD;
it was a pure mistake. The boys had a habit of ducking each&#xD;
other, at certain seasons of the year. Unfortunately, the ped-&#xD;
agogue was mistaken for one of these mischievous urchins, and&#xD;
as he entered his school-room he was saluted with a bucket full&#xD;
of water, which ran down his savory person, leaving his phiz&#xD;
and his person a ~b spectacle for gods and men !" The poor&#xD;
little boy whose mischief it was, trembled like an aspen leaf&#xD;
on the occasion, and barely escaped the rod, and his coumpan-&#xD;
ions-one and all-were soundly berated upon the practice and&#xD;
strictly enjoined to abandon it from that day forward. And,&#xD;
&#xD;
(&#xD;
&#xD;
9&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7697-00000005"/>&#xD;
8           /S'ome Passages. in the Life of&#xD;
strange te say, this command was obeyed to the letter.&#xD;
treaties of                               already&#xD;
never had much fancy for school. It was an irksome busi-&#xD;
ness, make the best of it, I thought. But I had  passed&#xD;
beyond the limited period of long clothes, and, spie the en-&#xD;
my aunt, who had had me under her pupilage these&#xD;
ten years, I was sent to school.&#xD;
On the fearful morning in which I *as ushered into the pr -&#xD;
sence of the pedagogue, my knees smote each other with terr r,&#xD;
and I could with difficulty utter a word; but the ordeal passed,&#xD;
the day wore quickly away and I felt there was nothing so&#xD;
horrible in going to school after all.&#xD;
At school it was-at this little village school-that J coin-&#xD;
meuced the first serious business pursuit of my life, and the&#xD;
exact character of ii pursuit may be guessed at when I in-&#xD;
form you, my son, that the old village schools were the resort&#xD;
of both sexes where boys and girls were allowed to mingle in&#xD;
the fray together. Already had the girls been parcelled off to&#xD;
their respective admirers, and there was not one of the fair&#xD;
sex who had not her especial protector among the other.&#xD;
There was little Polly Dawson, scarce entered upon her fifth&#xD;
tear, with as much of the shrewdness and quickness in discern-&#xD;
ing "the times and seasons" as her elder sister at home, who&#xD;
had been caressed and courted by the entire town, and Polly&#xD;
had her admirer too-a boy not half my age. Little Jack&#xD;
Dowdy-for that was his name, and a name he was never&#xD;
ashamed og was the son of the parson who has been already&#xD;
introduced. Little Jack loved Polly, and Polly loved Jack, and&#xD;
it was every where agreed that Polly and Jack were suited to&#xD;
each other. At the time I entered, it fortunately happened&#xD;
that a little fairy had just been transported to the city from a&#xD;
&#xD;
Gcoff~cy clinker, Esq.&#xD;
&#xD;
9&#xD;
&#xD;
neighboring county and was to be entered. This was my sole&#xD;
chance, for every other of the girls had been claimed and won.&#xD;
Betsy was the name of the fair one. To attempt a description&#xD;
of this child at this distant period, with the feeble pen and fee-&#xD;
bler intellects of an old man, might seem like child's play.&#xD;
But her image, on the day on which she entered the schoolroom&#xD;
is as distinctly painted in my mind, as if I had her now before&#xD;
me. Betty wore a pink calico dress, neatly tucked, with a&#xD;
white apron, just i'eaching the hem of her frock. Her hair was&#xD;
parted in the middle and fell in auburn ringlets about her&#xD;
shoulders. 11cr manner was brisk, half hesitating, half ad-&#xD;
vancing. She would speak in a (1uick but quiet manner and&#xD;
every thing she said or did was with rapidity and ease. She&#xD;
had the merriest laugh I have ever heard-and it was this&#xD;
which first woke within me so much admiration, I may say,&#xD;
love for the little fairy. Betty carried to school a little bag&#xD;
in which she put her books and refreshments and I usually did&#xD;
myself the honor tc~ carry them home for her. I was in love.&#xD;
CHAPTER III.&#xD;
CHILDHOOD ITS LOVE.&#xD;
It is a foolish thing-this childish love. It scarcely deserves&#xD;
the name. But why is childish love a folly? If it be, then love&#xD;
itself is a folly altogether. If in the first gushing out of exis-&#xD;
tence, while the heart is yet in its virgin youth, and the rank&#xD;
weeds have not overgrown it, it may not love-when shall it first&#xD;
begin to experience the emotion of affection? Does the ivy&#xD;
wait until the chills of winter have blasted its vigor or the&#xD;
summer's sun has burnt and destroyed its vitality, before it&#xD;
&#xD;
K&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7697-00000006"/>&#xD;
10         8ome Pas8ages in the ]9~fe of&#xD;
clings to the protecting oak? So neither should the heart of&#xD;
the child, my boy, if it find a fitting object on which to lavish&#xD;
out the fall tide of its feeling and its joy, tarry till it has encoun-&#xD;
tered the rude blasts of the wintry storm before it clasps, at&#xD;
least in memory and in thought, the object of its early adora-&#xD;
tion. Grant that the object is not always a proper one? can&#xD;
the affection of the mature claim that it never errs? We love&#xD;
we know not why, and the instinct of the chibji which teaches&#xD;
it to love may claim a direeter guidance as emanating more&#xD;
immediately from the source and fountain of all true love.&#xD;
I do not believe that childish love is an improper passion.&#xD;
When but a child, with the face of Betty Brown daguerreotype&#xD;
on my thoughts, this truth was an axiom and needed no rea-&#xD;
soning to support it, and though many, many years have rolled&#xD;
by between these youthful experiences and the time at which&#xD;
I write, and many, many sad clouds have passed over my&#xD;
spirit, and the world has grown dim and life unsteady I can&#xD;
look back upon these boyish freaks, and my old heart grows&#xD;
young again and I feel n~yself bounding anew with the an-&#xD;
imation of this first and earliest love. Would that I had learn-&#xD;
ed no other ill, and that subsequent events had not written other&#xD;
and bitter experienceswhich have blurred and blotted the pages&#xD;
of my life.&#xD;
CJJAPTER IV.&#xD;
BETTY'S BIRTh-DAY: FROLIC AT FARMER BROWN'S: BETTY CETS A&#xD;
COUSIN wno hAS SOME CONNECTION WITh MY STORY.&#xD;
If childish love be a folly, boyish jealousyis no trifling mat-&#xD;
ter. I speak from experience.&#xD;
&#xD;
Go~frey Ulinker, Es~q.            11)&#xD;
v~.&#xD;
Betty Brown w~s now quite a young lady. The day was not&#xD;
far off when she was to be ushered into sweet thirteen-an&#xD;
event, which it was then customary to honor by assembling all&#xD;
the young folks of the neighborhood to make the hours pass&#xD;
~me rrily and happily away.&#xD;
Thus far. I had been regarded as Betty's especial chain-&#xD;
pion-her chosen protector. Our school experiences had been&#xD;
as happy as the average experiences of boys and girls who&#xD;
thought more of their fa\ writes thai~ their books. We had suf-&#xD;
fered for each other, even under the hands of the genial James&#xD;
Thomson, a few martyrdoms in the shape of whippings for&#xD;
neglected les~ons-the time which should have been spent in~&#xD;
tracing out the courses of rivers and memorizing the names of&#xD;
Capitols, having been occupied in the other and more delight-&#xD;
ful operations of blackberry-huntin~r, push-pin and house-&#xD;
building. Beside these, I had on mor~ than one occasion, taken&#xD;
up the weapons of war to avenge her from real or imaginary&#xD;
insults and then bore upon my person the scars of honor re-&#xD;
ce~ved in this knightly service. I felt therefore that I had a&#xD;
to Betty, but as my claim had never been disputed, I had&#xD;
right&#xD;
no&#xD;
opportunity to vindicate it. Of course, her champion looked&#xD;
forward with unusual interest to the day on which she was to&#xD;
enter upon her teens. The day came. 11cr father's house was&#xD;
prepared for a brilliant i'eception of tile young and fashionable&#xD;
neighbors. Betty herself was decked out in her newest silk,&#xD;
lately unported from the mother country, and wore the mem-&#xD;
~orablc shoes which had been bought~ some six months before&#xD;
~and reserved until this day of honor. The gay throng passed ~&#xD;
the time before the hour of tea in the childish amusements d&#xD;
date, a part of which has retained the ascendancy until&#xD;
&#xD;
~&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7697-00000007"/>&#xD;
'A&#xD;
&#xD;
12          Some Pas8age8 in the Life of&#xD;
this day. There were "hunting of the slipper;" "grinding the&#xD;
bottle," and beside, the exercise of memory in which "four&#xD;
squeakiifg wild geese" played a distinguished part. In all of&#xD;
these, as in duty bound, I was quite active and neve~ absent&#xD;
from the side of Betty, save when the necessity of th9 play&#xD;
(lelnanded it. The evening's amusements wore away quite hap-&#xD;
pily. Then the ample feast was prepared and the youth gath-&#xD;
ered about the festive board to participate in the good cheer of&#xD;
farmer Brown. his stores were ai&#xD;
uple and the supper was, for&#xD;
that date, a inagnilkent one. True, it lacked all the elegancies&#xD;
of modern life. We had neither the glare nor glitter of chan-&#xD;
delievs lio'hted Pp with the brilliant lights of the present, nor&#xD;
en a service of silver plate, but every thing was in keeping&#xD;
with his station in' life, and was substantial and good. The&#xD;
bowl of tea and the wheaten cake and the Indian corn, with the&#xD;
best of fowls and venison, served sufficiently to supply our&#xD;
bodily wants. After supper, ~e withdrew to the parlor, and&#xD;
spent the evening in similar amusements. These were inter-&#xD;
rupted by a fresh arrival. Mr. Robert Lesslie, had been men-&#xD;
tioned by Betty several times in the course of th~ evening and&#xD;
I noticed that there was an unusual dancing of her bright eyes&#xD;
on the occasion. As soon as his name was announced, Betty&#xD;
rushed to the door and threw herself into his arms and im-&#xD;
printed a half dozen kisses upon his cheek. Robert was unques-&#xD;
tionably a fine looking fellow. lIe wore a black suit from top&#xD;
to toe, and every article of his apparel was in the neatest order.&#xD;
Just of an ag~, too, to suit Betty. He but just arrived at man-&#xD;
hood, and ~he in her thirteenth birth-iiight. Ii deemed it wrong&#xD;
to cherish such thoughts, but they would come thronging my&#xD;
brain, and though th~ hours passed by more merrily for this&#xD;
&#xD;
*'f~,    j                            7""&#xD;
&#xD;
aeoffrcyc11inkerB8q.13~&#xD;
arrival with the rest of the company, I could not help wishing&#xD;
that cousin Robert had delayed his coming a while longer. Fool-&#xD;
ish boy. Robert was not in your way. - The silly little heart of&#xD;
Betty Brown might have made him a rival, but he never cher-&#xD;
ished the thought of wrecking thy happiness or casting thee off~&#xD;
as a waif in the world without an owner.&#xD;
CHAPTER V.&#xD;
BETTY'S cOL~5IN. A SAD MISHAP. HOW I LOST MY WHITE HAT.&#xD;
Robert I~islie was a young man of rare qualities of head and&#xD;
heart. I have never known one more generous or noble. He&#xD;
had been trained in the best schools of that period and had ac-&#xD;
quired something more than a smattering of the Classics. His&#xD;
mind had been strengthened as well as his memory st'~5red, and&#xD;
on all occasions calling for the exercise of vigorous intellect or&#xD;
accurate learning, Robert Lesslie was not wanting. These ex-&#xD;
cellencies I had noted with some degree of anxiety, and thought&#xD;
I can not say that "I marked his virtues to despise them," I&#xD;
confess I should have been better satisfied if he had less. He&#xD;
k~ew or, at least, I thought he know. that I looked upon him&#xD;
a) a rival, and he did every thing in I powerto (lisabuse me of&#xD;
tKat impression-yet I did not at the moment so understand his&#xD;
excessive courtesy toward me, and his efforts to 1)e my friend.&#xD;
Despite my surmises, Robert's kindness kindled within me sen-&#xD;
timents of regard toward himself, and, strange to, say, in a very&#xD;
few weeks we were on terms of the closest intimacy, and my&#xD;
thoughts had become so entirely changed, that I felt that if&#xD;
Betty were to be given up to any other person, Robert would be&#xD;
niy preference-yet 1 could not consent to yield her to hini.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
II&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7697-00000008"/>&#xD;
14          Some Passages in the Life of&#xD;
Early one morning-I had just breakfasted-Robert met me&#xD;
at the door of my father's house, and taking me by the arm,&#xD;
proposed a walk to theoutskirts of the city. I could discover&#xD;
that he wore a careworn look as~if all had not gone well with&#xD;
him, and, as soon as opportunity offered, inquired the' cause.&#xD;
In answer, he stated that it would require a detail of his life,&#xD;
and he proceeded to sketch rapidly the current of his history&#xD;
up to this period. Ilis career had been a chequered and a sad&#xD;
one. He had commenced life with brilliant prospects. His&#xD;
father was possessed of an ample fortune, which was yearly&#xD;
increasing. From a child, he had gratified every wish of his&#xD;
heart. He ha(l been taught at home by his mother until he&#xD;
had arrived at an age to enter a neighboring collegiate insti-&#xD;
tution-his only companion an elder sister. Thus he had grown I&#xD;
up to boyhood and manhood, with an abiding reverence for hi&#xD;
parents and the fondest devotion for his duly sister-one, of&#xD;
whom he might well be proud. But the cloud had rested upon&#xD;
him. his father asnd mother were both laid in their graves&#xD;
and shortly after, his sister followed them. Robert was alone.&#xD;
I will let him conclude his story in his own words:&#xD;
*1&#xD;
Thus thrown upon my own resources, with no one at home&#xD;
~to cheer my drooping' spiritR or to dissipate the gloom that&#xD;
hung about my path, I have for several years past spent the&#xD;
vaca~Lions of ~ny collegiate ternis in tours throughout the coun-&#xD;
try. Two summers ago, in one of these trips, I met with a&#xD;
family on the border line between Pennsylvania and this Stat'e,~&#xD;
who received me with open arms and with a friendly greeting,&#xD;
such as I had received alone in the limits of Virginia. This~&#xD;
was not its only attraction. A gentle daughter was the magnet&#xD;
which drew me there so frequently afterwards. Lidort~ P&amp;amp;v&#xD;
&#xD;
aeoffrey Clinker, Esq.              15~&#xD;
ton won me by her genial smiles and pure womanliness of feel-&#xD;
ing. I 'will not call her an angel but I could not deem her less.&#xD;
We parted just two months ago on the banks of a stream re-&#xD;
sembling in its flow the beautiful river that now dances beneath&#xD;
our feet. She bid me an adieu with a smile and a teai~; and we&#xD;
fondly hoped that ere many months, ~we should me again.&#xD;
A letter reached me a few days since, bearing tidings of her&#xD;
death. She now sleeps beneath the tree on which we sat togeth-&#xD;
er when last we mat, and here am I, again, a lone wanderer&#xD;
over the wild waste of waters. -&#xD;
Robert had scarcely finished his narrative when we were both&#xD;
surprised by an outcry of terror from the river. Leaving my&#xD;
companion, I rushed to the water's edge and there discovered&#xD;
the source. Little Polly Dawson-of school-boy memory-had&#xD;
been prevailed upon the morning in question by Mr. Jack&#xD;
Dowdy to take a sail on the river. Jack had possessed himself&#xD;
of a neighbor's craft, and procuring a sail large enough to run&#xD;
a good sized man-of-war, the two had ventured into the stream&#xD;
without other ballast than the manful heart of Jack. A sudden&#xD;
whif of wind in an unexpected quarter had upset the craft, and&#xD;
in dohig so emptied the precious burden, Jack 'and his Dulci-&#xD;
nea, into the stream. Jack was a good swimmer. Polly was&#xD;
* not an adept in the art. The former was in a quandary, but~&#xD;
determining to rescue his sweetheart at the risk of his life, he&#xD;
had caught her by her raven locks and was towing her safely&#xD;
to the shore. Polly preferred a more substantial hold, and&#xD;
catching Jack around the body, the little fellow was umible to&#xD;
swim with ease, and finding himself sinking every moment,&#xD;
roared lustily for help. Throwing myself into the stream, I&#xD;
reached them just in time to save Polly and her lover from&#xD;
&#xD;
IF&#xD;
I!&#xD;
&#xD;
f I&#xD;
:&#xD;
&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7697-00000009"/>&#xD;
2.2&#xD;
&#xD;
lii         Some Passages in tite Life of&#xD;
..-~--.. (&#xD;
under. The sail  a was reralnea and set      and&#xD;
going               bot       b            upright&#xD;
(we reached the shore in safety, my only loss being a new white&#xD;
(hat which I had worn on the occasion. Polly and~Jack heaped K&#xD;
(upon me a thousand thanks, and I thought I heard Polly sooth-&#xD;
ing Jack in an undertone-" Never mind, Jack, nobody is&#xD;
(hurt-mama will never know it and if she does, 'twasn't your K&#xD;
fault." i envied Jack his treasure from the bottom of my heart.&#xD;
~Would Betty Brown have~ treated me thus, if I had given her (&#xD;
K                                                      C&#xD;
such a housing? I had no time to stop to meditate. My clothes&#xD;
were1&#xD;
soaked through and through, and bidding the party good&#xD;
morning, taking Robert by the arm, I hurried home to doff my&#xD;
apparel for something more comfortable. Jack and Polly did&#xD;
the same.&#xD;
A&#xD;
ChAPTER VI.&#xD;
SOMETHING ABOUT TILE TENDER PASSION. CRUSTY OLD BACHELORS&#xD;
AND GRIM CRITICS ARE REQUESTED TO SKIP OVER THIS CILAPTBR.&#xD;
Thus far in niy journey through life I had owned but one god-&#xD;
(                                                      C&#xD;
dess-had adored but one deity. The merriest among the&#xD;
C                                                      C&#xD;
merry-hearted-the gayest among the gay, the loveliest among&#xD;
C                                                      C&#xD;
(the lovely, had no charms for me in comparison with the little&#xD;
girl whom in infancy I had fondled, in boyhood I had admired,&#xD;
and in manhood I had loved. Betsy was the star of my being,&#xD;
the joy of my life. Rayless and cheerless would have been my&#xD;
journey, were it not, (as I hoped,) to be brightened by that ray&#xD;
~of sunshine. But human expectations are vain. An original&#xD;
suggestion, it is true, but one which weighed upon my heart at&#xD;
that time with a freshness and anxiety which one who has&#xD;
&#xD;
- p&#xD;
&#xD;
~eoff~wy (Junker, Esq~               ii,&#xD;
not felt it could not describe. I loved, loved ardently, hope-&#xD;
fully, with my entire being-with my manhood and strength.&#xD;
It was not an idle passion, a whim of the moment, but it had&#xD;
entered into and formed a part of my mental stature, my exist-&#xD;
ence. So keenly sensitive was I on the sui~jeet, that the most&#xD;
instantt allusion to the ~bject of my idolatry would crimson my&#xD;
check with fire-'~ndAt times 1 have become so nervous, that&#xD;
leo uld hardly pr ounce, her nam&amp;amp; without a tremor.&#xD;
Ii was hardly a lit subject, in such a state of mind. to attempt&#xD;
the conquest of a heart like Betty's. She was light, joyous. gay,&#xD;
happy! She could laugh and cry by turns, and seemed to take&#xD;
as much delight in the one as the other. A perpetual simn~hine&#xD;
settled on her head and heart, and though I bad tried once&#xD;
an(l again to draw her into seriou~ oonverwttion, ~ ith a naive-&#xD;
ness almost surpa~iflg description ~shc would avert the su~jcct,&#xD;
and with some slight fancy, apparentlyy without etlbrt,) would&#xD;
turn me ofF to pursue my meditations alone. it was manifest&#xD;
to me, that all this was not the pure effect of a child-like sim-&#xD;
plicity of charaetcr, though I wuld fain have believed k such.&#xD;
I had determined to test the mnjtter. I chose for the attempt a&#xD;
moment as opportune as any whineh circumstances would allow.&#xD;
Betty was in her back parlor, when I was ushered ~dtO1&#xD;
her lresenee on that evening. I found her in tears. ~ ii&#xD;
knew not and scarcely dared to inquire. I had met on my way&#xD;
one who might ha~ e had some connection with it, and the&#xD;
thought itself was daggers to me. It was not iobert Lesslie. I&#xD;
~Concealing as fir as practicable my surprise en the occasion I I&#xD;
drew near her seat, and taking' her hand in mine, began a sen- I&#xD;
ous talk upon the subject. She dii iiot withdraw it, (the hand,)&#xD;
but let it lie there just as if it were my own. I felt that it1&#xD;
2                 _&#xD;
&#xD;
,~&#xD;
&#xD;
if&#xD;
I,&#xD;
'ii&#xD;
&#xD;
.4&#xD;
14&#xD;
1~'&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7697-00000010"/>&#xD;
K'            ""&#xD;
&#xD;
~5~~&#xD;
5'&#xD;
&#xD;
18          Some Passages in the Life of&#xD;
ought to be, and gaining courage from the fact, entered boldly&#xD;
upon my task. She listened to me patently, while I proceeded&#xD;
to speak of my boyish love, my youthful devotion, how I had&#xD;
never bowed before another shrine, and, looking her calmly in~&#xD;
the face, my heart beating a tattoo the while, I asked her&#xD;
to pledge me in return for my bye the oiily price which I&#xD;
would accept-herself! She heard it all-calmly, passively&#xD;
thout a movement-and in words which now bu~im into my&#xD;
art while I write~ them-she stated that I had lost the golden&#xD;
oment-I had spoken too late-her heart and her life were&#xD;
edged to another and could never be mine! ! ! This she ut-&#xD;
tered in the same calm manner and without expressing any&#xD;
surprise, or even sympathy, proceeded to turn the conversation&#xD;
upon some other topic. She never looked more beautiful in&#xD;
person-yet I thought her instantly transformed. An angel&#xD;
she had been to me-a bright winged messenger of love and&#xD;
peace. She had in a moment been con~ erted into a messongcr~&#xD;
I of destructiom-of woe. I hardly knew how to comprehend her&#xD;
language. I could not believe it true. A few shorf~ weeks' de-&#xD;
lay had s'eale~ my fate-and Betty Brown, the pride of my&#xD;
heart, the joy of my existence, had passed into the hands of ano-&#xD;
ther-and that other !-but Ii must let the tears that now flUb&#xD;
so freely while I write, blot out the conclusion of the sentence.&#xD;
Perhaps in another hour I may have the boldness to record it.&#xD;
To continue, I left the house with far other feelings than those ~'&#xD;
with 'which I had entered it. In a moment the current of my&#xD;
existence seemed to change, and instead of flowery meads, and&#xD;
pleasant jourucyings, which in my dreams I had pictured, the&#xD;
future seemed pregnant with dark clouds about to burst in&#xD;
angry torrents over my head.&#xD;
&#xD;
Goffrey (JUnker, Esq.               19~&#xD;
CHAPTER VII&#xD;
rismi or ANOTHER SORT. A WHOLE 5T~W OP FRESh ONES.&#xD;
If amiy of my mime, into whose hands this manuscript should&#xD;
fall, shall imagine that I died of a broken heart, because of the&#xD;
occi~rrences previously detailed, they are sadly mistaken. It&#xD;
is a ~motto with the C1ink~r family-' nOver to give up for trifles,'&#xD;
and Though Ii (lid at the time regard Betty Brown's conduct as&#xD;
a very serious trifle, I would have been heartily ashamed of&#xD;
myself 'to have ~huflbed off the mortal coil' I~)r her or any body&#xD;
else. But I came as near to it as 1)Ossible. I took to. my bed&#xD;
and kept it for several weeks in succession, a thing so very re-&#xD;
markable in our annals as a family, that I cannot forbear re-&#xD;
cording it for the benefit of posterity. When I arose, however,&#xD;
it was with new feelings and new hopes-not that I had forgot-&#xD;
teniny earliest love. That I have never (lone, though my hairs&#xD;
are now whitened by more than threescore winters, ~n(l she&#xD;
has, togetherr with her affianced one, passed over the (lark&#xD;
valley-where I must ere long follow her. But my thoughts&#xD;
were directed to another object, if not as mild or as lovely,&#xD;
certainly as pure and childlike and angelic.&#xD;
Next door to my father's mansion in which I then lived, there&#xD;
had dwelt for a short period a family of English extraction,&#xD;
lately removed from that country tO this, who had sought the~&#xD;
city in which we lived for its retirement and ease. It was&#xD;
rumored to be wealthy, but no evidence of this was given in&#xD;
the exterior of the house they dwelt in, or in their apparel.&#xD;
They were a frugal, industrious and cheerful family, consisting&#xD;
of a half-dozen sons and ~n only daughter; both father and mo-&#xD;
ther were alive; and they dwelt in comparative seclusion, never&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
V&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
'I&#xD;
&#xD;
5-5&#xD;
51&#xD;
5"&#xD;
p.&#xD;
F&#xD;
&#xD;
s&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7697-00000011"/>&#xD;
U&#xD;
V )1&#xD;
&#xD;
20          Some Passages in the ]4e ~t*&#xD;
for the space of many weeks and months at a time, intruding'&#xD;
into the mansion of a neighbor save on some special occasion,-&#xD;
such as sickness or the like. The old lady was a matron in&#xD;
~1srael-aboundin~ in charities and in the short of time&#xD;
she had spent in the city previously to this, had succeeded in&#xD;
endearing all the poor to herself by her kind deeds. The sons&#xD;
thoughtful, steady boys, WJi() followed the occupation of&#xD;
farming, and were never known to make the concerns of their&#xD;
neighbors, either their fortunes or their character, a matter of&#xD;
speculation or talk. Such families are exceedingly rare, ~incl&#xD;
when they are found they deserve to be noted. It was during&#xD;
my illness that I first formed my acquaintance with the Charmi-&#xD;
ons, amid here too I met with the angel which was to beckon inc&#xD;
on in my future career and to gladden and bless my life. Jane&#xD;
(5harmion was a girl of some sixteen summers, though one not~&#xD;
f'uniliar with her age would have thouo'ht her much further ad-&#xD;
vanced. At this period she used to dress in a handsome black&#xD;
plaid frock without other ornament to her person tham~ a simple&#xD;
cameo which she wore in memory of an endeared relative who&#xD;
had left it to her as a memento of affection. Jane was the&#xD;
companion of her mother in all her missions of mercy, and&#xD;
ventured even farther sometimes than the caution incident to&#xD;
old age would allow her mother to do. During my long illness,&#xD;
she was my constant attendant, anticipating every wish and&#xD;
gratifying every want and whim with the tenderness and soli-&#xD;
citude of a sister. I verily believe that to her kind attentions&#xD;
and assiduous care I owed my life. This from a comparative&#xD;
stranger was too much for one constituted as I was. Jane&#xD;
little thought how necessary her presence became before the&#xD;
termination of my illness and how much I desired it after my&#xD;
&#xD;
G~eoJfrey Ulinker, Bsq.             21&#xD;
recovery. She had planted beside my younger love another,&#xD;
which, as will be seen, was destined to bring forth other fruiL&#xD;
ChAPTER ~\TIhJ&#xD;
It was not without  purpose-that resolve-nor has it been&#xD;
without its results. It was formed after the best m~eflection that&#xD;
one in my state of nerves could then have given it, and heave~be~&#xD;
thanked, it has been kept, m'eligiouslv kept, in its letter and&#xD;
spirit.&#xD;
I resolved to marry Jane Charmnion.&#xD;
Jane had evCry requisite to make mue happy. 11cr associa-&#xD;
tions were agreeable, her conversation interesting, her manners&#xD;
almost incomparable. She had a good heart, had spent an ac-&#xD;
tive youth, was, in short, just the woman my dear mother)&#xD;
would have selected for me had she been alive. And my aunt&#xD;
said, she bore a striking resemblance to Nancy. This would&#xD;
have been enough of itself to alter the current of my feelings,&#xD;
but they had been altered before.&#xD;
The next thing to be (lone after forming a resolution, is to put)&#xD;
it in Practice-and this I did, after ~i fashion. I knew that&#xD;
Jane Charmion had heard of my attachment to Betty Brown.&#xD;
It was the town talk, and had been so for years, and Betty, her-&#xD;
self, was no stranger to Jane. I had seen them together more&#xD;
than once. To break the matter abruptly to ~Jane just now&#xD;
would have been consummate folly, madness.&#xD;
My friendship grew apace with the family I have described,&#xD;
and in a short period I found myself as cordially attached to&#xD;
them, as if I had known them all my life.&#xD;
&#xD;
'A&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7697-00000012"/>&#xD;
I ~&#xD;
ii'.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
&amp;amp;me Pcls8ctges in, the Lfe of&#xD;
James Charmion, though not the sprightliest of her brothers,&#xD;
was certainly a boy of ~i~connnonly vigorous intellect.&#xD;
I had favorable opportunities of testing its strength on my&#xD;
visits to his father's htnise, which at this period were by no&#xD;
means infrequent. An intimacy grew up between un and my-&#xD;
self which prolnise(l to wax into a warm and si cere friendship.&#xD;
He had far more learning than I could boast, and was much~&#xD;
more faniiliar with the literature of his own country, but I was&#xD;
prompter, of quicker intellect, anti could enjoy a joke with,&#xD;
much more avidity and zest. We began to be on the best pos-&#xD;
sible terns with each other. Never a day passed, in which we&#xD;
did not spend a few hours in company to our mutual edification&#xD;
and improvement. Jane was with us frequently at these inter-&#xD;
views, and was not an indifferent or unobservant spectator. ~&#xD;
Gradually she grew fonder and fonder of them. Iler brother&#xD;
once remarked in our presence he thought Jane and I were&#xD;
made for each other! The thing may never have occurred to&#xD;
Jane's mind before-but it certainly had occurred to mine, and,&#xD;
though I blush to say it, I was clad it was spoken, as it opened~&#xD;
the way into anti explained sundry little attentions which be-'&#xD;
fore Jane had received at my hands. In a moment, they seemed&#xD;
to flash upon her in a new light, and I observed that afterwards,&#xD;
whenever I brought any little present for her, if it was reeci-&#xD;
~ ved. she would attempt to screen her face as if it were doing&#xD;
something it oughtuot to-I think she blushed ! Thus matters&#xD;
went on. Betty Brown, meanwhile, was not tbrgotten. At I&#xD;
times, the memory of h~r sad conduct or of my own indiscreet&#xD;
delay (I hardly knew which,) would rush upon me, when I&#xD;
was in the presence of Jane, and I could not restrain a sigh.&#xD;
Yet I had tried to forget her-and determined never again to~&#xD;
&#xD;
aeuffrey Clinker, Es&#xD;
mention her name to another-and s far as possible to keep&#xD;
aloof from her society, and that of icr courtier.&#xD;
CHAPTER IX.&#xD;
JIM BOWYRS, AND IllS GREY COAT.&#xD;
n ~ ~vcre injustice to the reader of these annals to overlook a&#xD;
oted character who figured in the days of which I write.&#xD;
Jni BOWERS was a man of mark. lie had never been accused&#xD;
of modesty, else he might have blushed at the charge. He&#xD;
never blushed at any other, though several had been preferred&#xD;
against him of which the criminal courts of the country bore&#xD;
ample testimony. But Jim had thus far escaped the hangman&#xD;
and was yet in the land of the living ready to accomplish any&#xD;
feat of prowess from the robbing of a hen-roost to the bolder&#xD;
and more arduous enterprise of invading the hog-pens of his&#xD;
neighbors.&#xD;
Jim was a fellow of some shrewdnesst had a good deal of&#xD;
"mother-wit," and enjoyed an enviable reputation for cooking&#xD;
the best suppers and making the best barbecues in the county.&#xD;
So that, with all his frailties, (and who has not frailties?) he&#xD;
was tolerated in the community. Indeed, he could not well I&#xD;
have been spared.&#xD;
I met Jim once near Mr. Dowdy's poultry-yard shortly after&#xD;
he old man had laid in a fresh stock of fowls previous to one of&#xD;
was evidently surprised to see me, but he put the best&#xD;
he festive occasions he was in the habit of giving his parishion-&#xD;
ace on the matter, and at once entered upon the most tender&#xD;
and touching inquiries in regard to my health. lie had heard&#xD;
&#xD;
A&#xD;
1~'&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7697-00000013"/>&#xD;
~1&#xD;
I&#xD;
~&#xD;
&#xD;
:L~-/ ~j~Y&#xD;
&#xD;
24          Some Pa~sage~ in tite Life of&#xD;
that I had been in a monstrous bad" fix and was. glad to see&#xD;
me out. Branching out from one subject to another, he man-&#xD;
aged to get my ear and, as he thought, to divert my attention&#xD;
altogether froni the fact that he was where he ought not to be.&#xD;
At length he touched upon a theme which havLg some slight&#xD;
connection with this biography, his words may be repeated.&#xD;
"Mass Clinker, I hearn tell you gwine to marry that Miss&#xD;
Ja~ne Cha~nine-is itso? mighty nice gal-Mass Clinker! that&#xD;
she is. A'nd what's more, the old man has mighty nice fixing&#xD;
and things for a son-in-law."&#xD;
Jim's interrogatory went unanswered, but I agreed with him&#xD;
as to the merits of the family.&#xD;
"Well, Mass Clinker, he! he! I wonder you don't make&#xD;
haste about it-arter you known how you were cut out of Miss&#xD;
Betsy by that fool face Tom Ilardin. Tom IJai~di~was a mighty&#xD;
book-larut man, they say, but didn't have sense enough for Miss&#xD;
Betsy. I knowed Miss Betsy ever since she was so high-not&#xD;
as high as my knee-and I was inolistreus sorry she took him,&#xD;
a brazen-faced fellow, to you."&#xD;
"Jim! you judge Mr. Hardin too ~y. lie was a very&#xD;
proper man in his way and you must learn to speak with more&#xD;
respect of white persons."&#xD;
"Well, now, Mass Clinker, I didn't intend to say any thing&#xD;
about Mr. Ilardin, but lie played the cu~sedest trick upon&#xD;
me once you ever hearn tell on. You see this coat, Mass Chin-&#xD;
(&#xD;
her. This coat's gone through the wars, I tell you. Miss Betsy-&#xD;
that used to be-give me this coat. It was a long time ago, and&#xD;
I had run of an e~vnd for her and come back in a great hurry,&#xD;
and Miss Betsy went up into her father's room and brought&#xD;
down this old coat-it was then nearly new-and asked inc if&#xD;
&#xD;
acoifrey (i7inker, Esq.            25&#xD;
wouldd fit. Well, it did fit, and II have had it ever since. But&#xD;
I am getting away from Mr. Hardin. Mr. Hardin shortly arter&#xD;
he married Miss Betsy went to live at Mass John's house-you&#xD;
know where he lives-and I was there just on a visit, you know,&#xD;
sitting down in the kitchen 'mong the colored folks, reeking&#xD;
myself with the odors as they rose from the stewed chicken (it&#xD;
was near dinner time.) I had not been to Mr. Brown's before&#xD;
for a long time and had never seen Mr. liardin, but who should&#xD;
pop in just while I wa~ setting there but the gentleman himself.&#xD;
In a decent sort of way II ~ot up and offered him a seat when&#xD;
he flew in a passion and asked 'who the deuce' I was and what&#xD;
I was doing there? I deigned to give him a civil answer and to&#xD;
tell him that I was a neighbor of his and had come on a visit to&#xD;
his folks when he drove me out of the door and~ told inc to take&#xD;
myself away. I was never treated so before and I have been to&#xD;
white folks houses ever seuce I knowed myself. Poor Miss&#xD;
Betsy ! she was mighty mortified when she heard me tell on it.&#xD;
But the man was in liquor and I suppose he was somewhat&#xD;
excusable on that account. And, if he had stopped there, after&#xD;
driving me out, I should have been better satisfied; but he&#xD;
actually ordered me to be whipped, and those rude niggers&#xD;
~ caught hold of inc and stripped me, tearing the white sleeve of&#xD;
my coat, and whipped inc like a rogue! And, now, while I&#xD;
~ think on it, m~r old coat is getting much th~ worse for wear,&#xD;
Mass Clinker, and if you liaye the likes on it at home, I would&#xD;
like to get one after the same pattern."&#xD;
I promised Jim the coat and we parted. Since then I have&#xD;
~ learned that Jim~ s version of the whipping story differs mate-&#xD;
rially from the true state of the matter. He had only changed&#xD;
the venue, as a lawyer would say, in time and place, from the;.&#xD;
&#xD;
3&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7697-00000014"/>&#xD;
K                                                                                                                -~                                                                 4'-&#xD;
&#xD;
'V&#xD;
&#xD;
'p&#xD;
V&#xD;
jji&#xD;
Ill&#xD;
114&#xD;
i~&#xD;
'11&#xD;
V&#xD;
&#xD;
26          Some Pc&amp;amp;sctges in the Life of&#xD;
barnyard to the kitchen, and from the hour of 10 P. M. to the&#xD;
hour of 4. But Jim's memory was never very exat.&#xD;
TILE I'AR5ON'5 FROLIC.  ChAPTER X.&#xD;
ROBERT LESLIE AND SALIAB DAWSON. JIM&#xD;
ROWERS' 5 COI~RT51IJP.               )&#xD;
If I preserved an accurate diary of the doings and sayings of&#xD;
this period, instead of writing a book of readable dimensions,&#xD;
I should be emulating at least in size, the vast tomes which&#xD;
barristers parade on their book-shelves to inspire terror in the&#xD;
uninitiated, and I fear that even you, my boy, would imitate the&#xD;
aforesaid barristers in allowing your father's '~Life" to lie be-&#xD;
tore you unopened, unread. I shall, thei~cfore, omit what is not&#xD;
absolutely necessary to the current of my history.&#xD;
It was not long after the hero of the grey coat had narrated&#xD;
to me the unfortunate accident which befel him, when the same&#xD;
coat played a distinguished part on another and more satisfac-&#xD;
tory occasion to its owner. Parson Dow~y, as his manner was,&#xD;
was about to give his annual feast of good things to his parish-&#xD;
ioners, in the shape 'of a superb dining party. It wouldibe no&#xD;
discredit to a better preacher than himself to say that these an-&#xD;
nual festivals were much more highly prized than ~he weekly&#xD;
feasts which h&amp;amp; was in the habit of dispensing from the village&#xD;
church. We are apt to value a thing in proportion to its rarity,&#xD;
and when the parson invited the parish to come t~ his annual&#xD;
feast for the body they all caine-as to his Weeklies, they were&#xD;
rather slimly atte~ded. For fear that some one might accuse&#xD;
the people of that period of great lack of piety, on this account,&#xD;
I may just add that in this regard they all strictly followed th~&#xD;
/&#xD;
&#xD;
aeoffrey clinker, Esq.&#xD;
example of their preacher-it being a x~ell understood fact that&#xD;
Parson Dowdy, himself, as partial as he was to his ~wn ~nd&#xD;
his double, and the village church, was a little more partial to&#xD;
a good dinner or a glass of claret. But away with discussions&#xD;
of the sort. The parson's party was to come off shortly, and as&#xD;
a matter of course, Jim Bowers was in demand. Jim did him-&#xD;
selfjustice on the occasion. It was beyond all question the best&#xD;
dinner ever gotten up in that locality, and the praises of our&#xD;
guest, and the hero of the great coat were sounded on all hands.&#xD;
The feast was a feast of fat things, and the entire parish, i. e.&#xD;
its inhabitants young and old, flocked to the pars6nage to partake&#xD;
of its hospitable cheer. Could I daguerreotype the scene for you,&#xD;
~ in y son, you would have a full length portrait of my native&#xD;
~ village in the year 1773 done up in its handsomest colors. Of&#xD;
K course, every body wore his smiles that day. My little friends&#xD;
Jack and Polly were in the merriest mood. Jack was always&#xD;
~ something of a wag but his peculiar excellences in that line&#xD;
never shone more brightly than on that occasion. Here was a&#xD;
couple deeply immersed in the mysteries of small talk, and&#xD;
K. over there a plain honest old planter was holding forth on the&#xD;
K.&#xD;
virtues of his tobacco crop, evidently elated by the news of the&#xD;
last       which had just reached him.  He had a copy of&#xD;
K the Gazette in his pocket. Here a gentleman with a red face&#xD;
wasdiscussing the relations of the colonies to the crown, and&#xD;
just opposite a bevy of girls were amusing themselves and their&#xD;
~ieghbors by charades and conundrums, occasionally interrup-&#xD;
ted by a merry laugh that rung through your brain and made&#xD;
~ your heart glad that this is not altogether a weeping world.&#xD;
The Parson was an ubiquitous personage on the occasion, with&#xD;
young and old, matron and maiden, though I observed he was in&#xD;
* We j*/ 0~~P pe&amp;amp;~.4~r 'D1ftI1.eIT~sEC&#xD;
&#xD;
~ V&#xD;
4 4&#xD;
4',&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
L.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7697-00000015"/>&#xD;
/&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
'V&#xD;
U&#xD;
I&#xD;
i~f&#xD;
~1~1&#xD;
~iJ~i&#xD;
p&#xD;
1K&#xD;
11&#xD;
~i1&#xD;
4'&#xD;
43&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
28          Some Passages in the ~       of&#xD;
great measure the companion of the red faced polith~d gentle-&#xD;
man, and they would frequently, while excited in talk, draw&#xD;
neftr, as if involuntarily, to the punch-bowl, and sip pretty free-&#xD;
ly of its contents. There were jolly parsons in those good old&#xD;
times, my boy-and though I cannot say, their example made&#xD;
us any better, they were at least a more cheerful race of men,&#xD;
and, in some instances, I dare believe, more pure hearted and&#xD;
true than many who now decry them.&#xD;
I searched the room for Jane Charmion. She certainly in-&#xD;
tended coming but something had interfered, and being thus&#xD;
left to (10 as I pleas&amp;amp;, I was in quest of an adventure, when&#xD;
Robert Lesslie entered the room, with a lady under his charge,&#xD;
~ who has been mentioned before in this history. Polly's sister,&#xD;
Sallie, was a fine model of the lady of elder time. I cannot de-&#xD;
scribe her dress on the evening of that day-but it was superbly&#xD;
~ elegant. There was that, too, in the graceful sweop of her w~lk,&#xD;
and her erect form, and flashing eyes, which at once arre)ed&#xD;
~ every eye in the assembly. Even the red faced gentleman ~top-&#xD;
ped for an instant to admire. Robert himself was clad in his&#xD;
usually simple attire, and seemed to be in a more cheerful mood&#xD;
than usual. In a few moments I found myself engaged in&#xD;
earnest conversation with the couple, and thus contrived to&#xD;
while away the time.-&#xD;
Well, friend Dowdy," remarked the red faced gentleman,&#xD;
more cheerful, "you have done yourself credit in the selection."&#xD;
for a season, leaving the discussion of~ politics for something&#xD;
"Not at all, Mr. B. I could not have chosen any other.&#xD;
His reputation is now without a ~ivai in that line. his services&#xD;
are invaluable and with all his faults, I should regret his being&#xD;
stretched."&#xD;
-P~ 2~.b.e SWq i~%   ~44V.0t&#xD;
'U            .                      4&#xD;
&#xD;
i~ ~i&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
MA&#xD;
&#xD;
aeoffrey Clinker, E~q.              29&#xD;
This snatch 9 conversation was doubtless intended for the&#xD;
hero of the grey Ooat. Just at this moment that gentleman en-&#xD;
tered the room with an enornio ~ waiter of good things loaded&#xD;
to the l)rim. Jim was happy. lie had fon his identical grey&#xD;
coat, and his ivory glittered beneath his pper lip in significant&#xD;
attestat'io of the amount of felicity lie experienced. I detailed&#xD;
to my co anion the story of the coat.&#xD;
"Just i ie him," Sallie replied. "lie has repeated that iden-&#xD;
tical stor at least a dozen times, and never fails to create a&#xD;
sympathy which he hopes will result in substantial advantage&#xD;
to himself. have von ever heard his courtship ?"&#xD;
"I was not aware that Jim ever suffered with the tender&#xD;
passion.&#xD;
"Indeed he did. My father's house was the scene of his ad-&#xD;
ventures, and as they are somewhat unique I will detail them.&#xD;
Dinah and Judy-they are my fathers servants-were each&#xD;
desperately taken with Jim on his first visit in this region of&#xD;
country. All day long they would snap at each other without&#xD;
the slightest conceivable cause, and as Judy was our washer-&#xD;
woman and Dinah the cook, they were each mutually gratified&#xD;
with frequent opportunities to annoy the other. Dinah was the&#xD;
better looking, but Judy, so Jun had heard, was possessed of&#xD;
the more ample fortune, i. e the latter could boa~t a new teas-&#xD;
ter and bureau, and the former had neither of these very useful&#xD;
articles. Jim was therefore at a standstill between the rival&#xD;
candidates for his person and honors. One visit he would be-&#xD;
stow more favors on Dinah, and the next he would flatter Judy;&#xD;
and in this manner lie succeeded for a series of months in&#xD;
keeping those charmers in the delightful state of' anxiety and&#xD;
humor incident to such occasions. Thus far Jim had been&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7697-00000016"/>&#xD;
11&#xD;
is&#xD;
ii&#xD;
SjTh&#xD;
A&#xD;
Iv&#xD;
Ill&#xD;
&#xD;
Some Passages in the Life of&#xD;
~            ,~&#xD;
without a contestant for the honors of either ha~yl, but, sud-&#xD;
denly, as if by magic, a host of coidred gentlemen invaded m -&#xD;
fat her's mansion, each in search of a wife. Here was a bother.&#xD;
The selection was to be made. Jim decided the matter, and the&#xD;
wealthier Judy was his choice. In due season he made known&#xD;
to her his intentions, and the lassie at once acceded to them&#xD;
The day was appointed, but in the course of events before the&#xD;
~ happy season arrived, Jim, who now felt himself authorized to&#xD;
S inquire more particularly, began to discuss matters subsequent&#xD;
to their marriage in a familiar style and contrived to hint at the&#xD;
nice pieces of property they would have to start with-enume-&#xD;
~ rating the identical articles which had curedd his affection.&#xD;
Judge of his astonishin~nt when he learned that they were&#xD;
S the possession of the fair Dinah, who had placed them in the&#xD;
keeping of her neighbor because she had more than she had&#xD;
room f~r in her apartment. Meanwhile Dinah's hand had been&#xD;
sued for and won, and the faithless Jim was about to leap into1&#xD;
the gulf of matrimony, without securing the object of his affec-&#xD;
tions. Alexander-like, he cut the Gordian knot by at ohee&#xD;
declaring that he couldn't think of undertaking so responsible&#xD;
a relation in life without the means to make them comfortable,&#xD;
and as his fair Judy had them not, she must wait until he se-&#xD;
cured them! Since then, Jim has studiously eschewed the pre-&#xD;
mises, and it is rumored he is now engaged in making obser-&#xD;
vations in a different quarter of the heavens. Judy, poor girl,&#xD;
wept for awhile-but she has taken to her washtub again, and&#xD;
is as cheerful-hearted as if the faithless hero of the grey-coat&#xD;
had never stormed the citadel of hei~ affections."&#xD;
Thus the hours wore on. Other subjects were introduced on&#xD;
the tapis and dispatched. Betty Brown and her husband--&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
/                                          I&#xD;
&#xD;
Geoffrey Ulinker, Beq.              31~&#xD;
Polly Dawso n and Jack-Parson Dowdy and his dinners and&#xD;
his sermons were all severally served up for our edification and&#xD;
amusement, and ivh~n we parted with Miss Sallie at her door&#xD;
at&#xD;
th evening, I thought her a charming creature-so she was.&#xD;
-              ('HAPTEli XY.~&#xD;
JANE cHARMLON.&#xD;
But tell me something of your matters with Jane. What~&#xD;
became of her?&#xD;
To all appearances that young lady was as well off at home&#xD;
as any where else. The evening of the Parson's frolic, she had&#xD;
spent in company with a relative who had visited the city, and&#xD;
this accounted for her absence. She was not, however, indiffer-~&#xD;
ent to what transpired at Parson I)owdy's a~d on my first visit&#xD;
to her afterwards, which was the next morning, I was surprised&#xD;
to learn that she could tell the n ne of every body there, with&#xD;
all they did and much of what they had said. The matter&#xD;
was readily explained when I learned that his Highness of the&#xD;
grey coat had breakfasted in the kitchen of Mr. Champion that&#xD;
morning. Jim had been the evening before unusually attentive&#xD;
to our little party, and I did not discover his object until the&#xD;
affair leaked out in this way.&#xD;
Jane met me with a smile that morning-an arch smile that&#xD;
K d something in it, but just then I did not choose to interpret&#xD;
italoud.~ She was in error.&#xD;
We were now on the best possible terms with each other.&#xD;
* Just here I have eliminated a series of chapters not necessary to the&#xD;
detail of Mr. Clinker's life.                 r. xv.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7697-00000017"/>&#xD;
{&#xD;
&#xD;
32          Surne Pa.~ages in the L~j~ of&#xD;
There had never a word been uttered on either side, yet it Was&#xD;
all understood and she thought she had a right to my society,&#xD;
and I acknowledged it, claiming hers in return. This state&#xD;
of affairs remained for several years. Meanwhile, Tom Hardin&#xD;
and his wife had removed from the neighborhood to a distant&#xD;
county. Robert Lesslie had entered upon the practice of the&#xD;
law and was gradually rising in his profession. I~'Dawson&#xD;
and her admirer Jack were on as good terms as ever, and there&#xD;
were but few of the old company in the same condition in life&#xD;
in which they had been just ten years before. Parson Dowdy&#xD;
yet held on and gave his annual feast at the old parsonage. We,&#xD;
however, had experienced sad changes. I was left alone, after&#xD;
laying in the grave a father anti an endeared 'aunt, and Jane&#xD;
had performed the same solemn offices to her aged parents.&#xD;
Just then, we felt the need of the new association which had&#xD;
long been agreed upon between us and we were united in the&#xD;
old village church, Parson ~JI~dy officiating on the occasion in&#xD;
the presence of a numerous assemblage of-blacks and whites.&#xD;
Ten months after a new entry adorned the old Family Bible,&#xD;
which lay on the able in the dining room. It was written in&#xD;
the legible han of the venerable parson: "BORN, James, son&#xD;
of Geoffrey Clinker and Jane his wife on this 2nd day of Oct.,&#xD;
1783, and christened by me.-JAMEs DOWDY."&#xD;
CHAPTER XVI.&#xD;
CONCLUSION.&#xD;
The old Family Bible contains now other entries which with&#xD;
trembling hand~ and feeble pen I have traced upon its pages.&#xD;
~fane and myself spent several years of happiness together,&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
~tI&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
~~eqjfreyC1zfl1cerEsq.33~&#xD;
a~appiness beclouded however by the death of a cherub girl,&#xD;
a meek, gentle child who left us while yet without the impress&#xD;
of earth upon her soul. And the messenger came again to bear&#xD;
away the companion of my mature years from her home on&#xD;
earth to her home in heaven. her eldest born and the young-&#xD;
est sleep beside her in the village church yard, and you, my boy,&#xD;
are left alone to transmit the memory and the nameof youij&#xD;
f~ither's house.&#xD;
*.     *      *      *      *      w&#xD;
Thus far in this chronicle of an old man's life, for the use of an&#xD;
only child. That child has since ripened into manhood, has&#xD;
married, has died, leaving a little boy, his very image, behind&#xD;
him.&#xD;
To the reader it may not be without profit to sketch rapidly&#xD;
the career of others who have passed before us.&#xD;
Robert tesslie continues the practice of his profession. The&#xD;
early sorrow has never ceased to agitate his manly heart, and&#xD;
though he has since been elevated to high political positions, he&#xD;
still wears the sad smile, and whenever he talks with me of&#xD;
the olden time. his eyes fill with tears and he heaves a deep&#xD;
sigh~-whi~h~Q1ne5 welling up from the deep fountains of his&#xD;
heart and tells of the loss of an early love.&#xD;
Betty Brown lies beneath the willow which casts its grateful&#xD;
shade over her grave on the right, as you enter the church&#xD;
yard. Her husband in his new home had met with one reverse&#xD;
after another and becoming evei~y day more dissolute, he had&#xD;
run the gauntlet of vice and terminated his life in a dungeon to&#xD;
which he had been confined on a charge of felony. Poor Betty&#xD;
returned to her old abode with a broken heart, just as I had&#xD;
3&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7697-00000018"/>&#xD;
Y&#xD;
&#xD;
34 Some Passages ~ ~he Life of aeoffrey Clinker.&#xD;
laid i~i~he grave the mother and natural protector of my lost&#xD;
boy. s~d story had already reached me and I at once&#xD;
offered, er a home in my house. There she remained until&#xD;
the day of her death, and as I write, Ben, my boy's boy, has drawn&#xD;
near his grandpa's table and in his simple touching manner&#xD;
asks me "Why I weep? is it for ma-ma ?" I can not unravel&#xD;
to him the stery and I confide to after ~tears these revelations of&#xD;
a pobr old man. When he opens them, as I shall direct him&#xD;
to do, after I have passed hence, he will then know what now1&#xD;
my heart fails me to tell.&#xD;
Jun Bowers is still the hero of the grey coat. lie has not&#xD;
yet been helped outof the world by the hand of the hangman,&#xD;
and as Jim has latterly 1~ecome a reformed citizen, it is hoped&#xD;
he~will die in a na{uraly~ay. Since his defection in the case of&#xD;
the fair Judy he has rie.ver essayed the hardships of love and&#xD;
promises to become a confirmed Benedict.&#xD;
Polly Dawson has long since become Pohly iDowdy and they&#xD;
live over the old stand of honest John Grocer and are as merry,&#xD;
as cheerful, and 'as happy as on the day I first met them in the&#xD;
school house of genial James Thomson.&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
REPRODUCED FROM THE COPY IN THE&#xD;
H~NRYE. HUNTiNGTON LIBRARY&#xD;
FOR REFERENCE ONLY. NOT FOR REPRODUCTION&#xD;
(&#xD;
&#xD;
It&#xD;
4&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
11                                                                                                                                                                                                        '6&#xD;
I                                                                                                                                                                                                      $~lt&#xD;
'I                                                                        I&#xD;
&#xD;
II,.&#xD;
I&#xD;
it,&#xD;
4&#xD;
i&#xD;
jt.&#xD;
1,&#xD;
A&#xD;
Ill&#xD;
J~:i&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
(&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
 &#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD; &#xD;
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
