<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7900">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Haps and Mishaps of the Three Jolly Students </title>
            <author>Stanton, Benjamin F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7900</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2347</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The haps and mishaps of the three jolly students</title>
                  <author>Stanton, Benjamin F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Gaywell Webster &amp; Gabbles</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Manchester N.H. </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1866">1866</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-05-02">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5. Inserted OCR text. Linked image files</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The haps and mishaps of the three jolly students</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7900-00000001"/>Vjub(4t at tie 3 equ5t of ~pt~~u  dns&#xD;
q/7/A ICTW             IZ,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7900-00000002"/>&#xD;
c  e  rxa 4!aj  tdt&#xD;
&#xD;
2o the past and present .Members&#xD;
of the&#xD;
&#xD;
CLUB&#xD;
2his book is most respectf/iy dedicated by&#xD;
the compiler,&#xD;
H 4LA4E .TF.2,.d.. &#xD;
&#xD;
A few weeks ago three students dwelling in this&#xD;
goodly city of ours, having wearied their brains by&#xD;
studying hard days and playing cribbage late nights,&#xD;
sort to recuperate their overtaxed powers by making&#xD;
a trip to the mountains. These three worthies were&#xD;
known by the names of King Charles, Prince Albert&#xD;
and Doctor Johns. After due consideration and long&#xD;
deliberation they came to the conclusion that,.inas-&#xD;
much as their legs were, just then, longer than their&#xD;
purses, it would be inexpedient to incur the -expense&#xD;
of riding. 'They therefore decided to "huff it," (we&#xD;
use the clasasic language of King Charles.)&#xD;
Behold them then, on the morning of June 13,&#xD;
1866, preparing to start on their travels. They are&#xD;
packing their baggage in a wagon, to which is at-&#xD;
tached a gallant steed.&#xD;
This  s the      and this             before&#xD;
gallant steed    the wagon            mentioned&#xD;
Illustrations of         the baggage which&#xD;
a portion of             they carried.&#xD;
About 9 o'clock they started on their winding way&#xD;
watched by a few friends and many strangers. .Va&#xD;
rious were the comments made by curious bystanid-&#xD;
&#xD;
'&#xD;
&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7900-00000003"/>&#xD;
At&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
ers as the party moved away. Some said they were&#xD;
hard characters whom the police jlge, in the kind-&#xD;
ness of his heart, had granted penisiiiioi to leave&#xD;
the cityfin one hour; others thought they were gyp-&#xD;
sies wh' had been on a thieving tour and were now&#xD;
returning to their tribe ; but the prevalent opinion&#xD;
was that they were Fenians about to invade Canada.&#xD;
But however much the crowd differed as to the object&#xD;
of our heroes, it was unanimous upon one point, viz,&#xD;
that they were three tough looking cusses.&#xD;
We propose only to make a note here and there as&#xD;
we follow our travelers on their journey.&#xD;
Nothing of moment occurred the first day. As&#xD;
theywended their way through the classic grounds&#xD;
of Hooksett, passing that virtuous retreat-ihe&#xD;
halfway house-and on through Pembroke with its&#xD;
many sacred spots, they saw the green grass growing,&#xD;
the yellow grain waving, (or at least it will be yellow&#xD;
when ripe), and the gentle herd feeding by the road-&#xD;
side.*&#xD;
The gentle     herd feeding       by the roadside.&#xD;
Our tourists tented out the first night in a barn&#xD;
kindly loaned to them by an obliging' farI -'- the&#xD;
rain forbidding them to tent out of doors."*  They&#xD;
were awakened early in the morning by the shrill&#xD;
crow of chanticleer, more commonly called rooster.&#xD;
The cock        that crew.&#xD;
Resuming their march they passed along the shore&#xD;
bf the beautiful lake Winnipesawkee, upon   the&#xD;
S    d gw      pshire 4dvertiser, June 2, 1866.&#xD;
&#xD;
5&#xD;
bosom of which floated the steamer Lady of the take&#xD;
as gracefully as a goose upon a frog-pond; while just&#xD;
before then moving slowly over the road was the old&#xD;
stage coach, 110w superceded almost every where by&#xD;
the railcar and steamboat.&#xD;
The swift float-            _     the slw crawling&#xD;
ing steamer,                       stage-coach,&#xD;
and&#xD;
the lightning                     ie express train.&#xD;
On the fourth day they found their first fishing.-&#xD;
They had a good many bites at their faces by black&#xD;
flies, and a few at their hooks by small fishes.&#xD;
This fish was caught  and this one by&#xD;
by King Charles,    1)'. Johns,&#xD;
While this dog came devlish near&#xD;
catching Prince0 Albert.  [The reader will&#xD;
at once notice the absence of the greater part&#xD;
of the dog. The fact is, the dog saw the Prince was mak-&#xD;
ing such good time that he would soon be cut of sight un-&#xD;
less he (the doe) ran faster,'and that he might do so he&#xD;
16f1 his body'behind, while his head continued the chase.&#xD;
When the above cut was taken the body had not arrived,&#xD;
consequently only the head could be sketched.]&#xD;
hiat night they pitched. their tent in a beautiful&#xD;
spot on the borders of the lake, beneath the friendly&#xD;
shade of a huge oak tree. As they neared the wel-&#xD;
comed spot a noble eagle-." king of birds " etc:.&#xD;
rose majestically from out its broad branches and&#xD;
soared away. They saw him for full ten minutes af-&#xD;
ter he was out of sight rising higher and higher and&#xD;
wiukiug at them frst with one eye and then the otlh&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7900-00000004"/>&#xD;
6&#xD;
&#xD;
7&#xD;
&#xD;
er, as if he would say, " Don't you wish you could&#xD;
follow."&#xD;
soaring eagle&#xD;
The hugh    oak tree and the      what winked.&#xD;
The next morning our travelers took an early start&#xD;
and soon found themselves entering North Conway,&#xD;
"the prettiest village we have yet passed."*  So&#xD;
beautifully is this village "in the Saco river" describ-&#xD;
ed hy the'Prince iii his private note-book, that we&#xD;
cannot refrain from making a brief extract. He&#xD;
says: " Every hotel without a sign is a house ; piaz-&#xD;
zas and pianos ornament the dwellings, and f resli&#xD;
white paint and green blinds are seen in the rooms,&#xD;
while the inhabitants bear a strong resenibimee to&#xD;
the high-priced patent medicine bottles labelled Do&#xD;
me and P'll try you good.' "*&#xD;
We next introduce our heroes to the reader camp-&#xD;
ing near Newry, Maine. This is a thriving village-&#xD;
in the north part of the Pine Tree State, consisting&#xD;
of three houses and a sawmilll.  The inhabitants&#xD;
The village of               Newry, Maine.&#xD;
subsist mostly upon "spruce gum and black-flies, as&#xD;
big as hornets do abound." Near this place one of&#xD;
our tourists nearly lost his life (perhaps.) The Dr.&#xD;
started out one morning with his gun with the in-&#xD;
tention of shooting a partridge for dinner. The&#xD;
natives had told some big stories about bears, and&#xD;
* NoTE. -We are aware this extract reads differently in&#xD;
the Advertiser of June 28, but we claim that the above is&#xD;
exactly as the description appears in the note-book. What&#xD;
condition the writer was in when the notes were taken we&#xD;
leave th6 reader tojudge.&#xD;
&#xD;
the Doctor kept a bright lookout lest he might run&#xD;
against one of those savage" critters." The snap&#xD;
ping of a branch, the rustling of a leaf or the dis-&#xD;
tant murmur of the babbling brook, were to his fev-&#xD;
ered imagination ominous sounds which portended&#xD;
danger. After half an hour's travel he reached a&#xD;
spot from Which the wood had been clear a few years&#xD;
before, but which was now thickly covered with scrub&#xD;
oaks and other low bush s. " Here," thought the&#xD;
Doctor, "is the place for bears!" Just as the tho't&#xD;
tashedtherough his mind he heard a rustling in a&#xD;
thicket near him. For a moment the power of mo-&#xD;
tiol seemed to leave hin i--is knees smote together,&#xD;
while his trembling hiid could .car'cely hold his gun.&#xD;
With nevrous trepidation le discharged his piece;&#xD;
then turned and ran. Ran with the spied of the&#xD;
frightened deer, when lie hear the deep bay of the&#xD;
hound, or like the little ragged urchin seen steal,&#xD;
ing his mother's preserves, who knows full well if&#xD;
caught he will get a sound spanliking; ran like-&#xD;
iikc--.--ike the devil, and never ceased running&#xD;
until lie arrived, in camp; when lie immediately&#xD;
fainted. His sudden advent in tle'midst of his com-&#xD;
panions filled them with consternation. King Charles&#xD;
with wonderful presence of mind, dashed a dipper-&#xD;
ful of hot water in his face, while Prince Albert seiz-&#xD;
a poker and commenced pounding him "to keep up&#xD;
a circulation of the -blood." Under this (s)killful&#xD;
practice the Doctor soon began to rally and in a short&#xD;
time was sufficiently recovered to tell his story.-&#xD;
"My dear friends," the Doctor said, "congratulate&#xD;
me upon my lucky esape from a terrible, horrible&#xD;
death. I have been chased by a er Ybe0, boysiby&#xD;
4 BEAU   ! and had I not discharged ny gua full ii&#xD;
&#xD;
r.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7900-00000005"/>&#xD;
!&#xD;
,&#xD;
3&#xD;
}a&#xD;
_&#xD;
i&#xD;
1&#xD;
k&#xD;
N&#xD;
1&#xD;
t&#xD;
z&#xD;
&#xD;
8&#xD;
his face and thus checked him in his course, I should&#xD;
now have been. food for cubs. It was a monstrous&#xD;
BEAR, [the Dr. always empasized this word] as&#xD;
large as an ox !"  "Are you sure you killed him?'"&#xD;
inquried the Prince. " Of course 1 kill him. I wait-&#xD;
ed until I could see the ' white of his eyes ' and then&#xD;
fired." " If you killed the bear why did you run,"&#xD;
querried the King. " Why did I ril? Why [-I&#xD;
thought he might have some near relatives about&#xD;
there!"  A proposition was now made by the King&#xD;
that the partygo out and secre a portion the beat&#xD;
for sippCi.&#xD;
Gentle reader ! did'st thou ever see the fierce sav-&#xD;
age of the forest in lii native wild, as he followed the&#xD;
trail of his eternal foe, the pale face ? See how slow-&#xD;
ly and noiselessly he moves along! With what care&#xD;
he notes every twig and every spire of grass ! How&#xD;
quickly he stops, how anxiously he looks around, and&#xD;
how earnestly he listens if but the slightest noise ho&#xD;
hears! He knows not but the next moment his dead-&#xD;
ly enemy imay be upon himi  If'thou has't seen him&#xD;
thus thou can s't form som6e idea of the cautiouis man-&#xD;
ner in which our three worthies approached the spot&#xD;
ivhichh ie Doctor pointed our-as the place where he&#xD;
had nearly lost his life in the pursuit of-a dinner.&#xD;
It is a momentous period, in the life of all! A bear&#xD;
znay spring upon them at an y iouieit, and their&#xD;
bones, divested of flesh by the cruel teeth of cubs,&#xD;
lie unbaried---bleaching in the boundless forest which&#xD;
surrounds Newry, Maine!! As the1 tourists stand&#xD;
close to a bunch of bushes behind winch the bear lay,&#xD;
they form a picture which woi d rejoice the heart oft&#xD;
an artist. On the right etoo9l Prince Albert armed wichi&#xD;
Slong lnife; at his left stood King. Charles with a&#xD;
&#xD;
huge stake in his hand, while Dr. Johns brought up&#xD;
the rear bearing the gun, the muzzle of which pointed&#xD;
exactly at the Prince's stern, and if it had been dis-&#xD;
charged his pants would have needed to be re-seated,&#xD;
although HE might object to being seated at all. Now&#xD;
the Prince takes off his spectacles and wipes the glass-&#xD;
es on his coat-tail, that he might the more readily see&#xD;
danger and be first to run. Gently he parts the&#xD;
branches and peers over and beholds-A HOG quiet-&#xD;
ly sleeping!  "SAFE! WE ARE SAFE! !" the&#xD;
three exclaimed as with one voice. The King and&#xD;
the Prince looked at the Doctor. The King said "I'll&#xD;
take whisky;" the, Prince said "Let mine be brandy ;"&#xD;
the Doctor said "All right-at the next tavern." And&#xD;
that's the reason why the bear adventured did not ap-&#xD;
pear in the letters of the excursionists.&#xD;
What 'the     Dr. said he What he&#xD;
Whattheshot.       really did 1   shoot-at d&#xD;
We have space to chronicle but one more' of the&#xD;
many interesting adventures through which our&#xD;
friends passed. When near the Canada line they&#xD;
were halted by a squad of soldiers and arrested for&#xD;
Fenian invaders of Canada. In vain the Doctor&#xD;
protested. against and swore about the outrage ; in&#xD;
vain the Prince argued at great length the laws of&#xD;
nations bearing upon this point, the reciprocity trea-&#xD;
ty, etc.;.,in vain the King wrung his hands, and wept&#xD;
and blubbered, and finally fainted--the soldier knew&#xD;
his duty and was bound to perform it. Unexpected&#xD;
deliverance came, however, in the shape of the offi-&#xD;
The U.S. soldiers.   and     officer of the day.&#xD;
cer of the day. He ordered their discharge at once,&#xD;
&#xD;
A&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7900-00000006"/>&#xD;
10&#xD;
"For," said he, "such a cowardly looking set of rag-&#xD;
rhuffins can do no harm. They may frighten the old&#xD;
women and children-and truly they look bad enough&#xD;
to scare the devil-but will never fight."  With&#xD;
grateful hearts our wanderers pursued their way and&#xD;
soon the Old Man of the Mountain broke upon their&#xD;
view.&#xD;
Old Man of the Mountain as  he appeared to the tourists&#xD;
After spending a few days around the Mountains&#xD;
our travelers moved westward with the purpose of&#xD;
passing into Vermont. When they, arrived at the&#xD;
Connecticut river they found a toll-bridge interposed&#xD;
between themselves and the Green Mountain State.'&#xD;
This was an unexpected barrier. Pockets were search-&#xD;
ed in vain for six cents to pay the toll, but only half&#xD;
enough could be found, and with sorrowful hearts&#xD;
they turned back.&#xD;
[It has sorely tried our patience and eyes to de-&#xD;
cipher the last few pages of the Prince's manuscript.&#xD;
In fact, some portions we have supplied, the Mss.&#xD;
being made up of broken sentences. Whether this&#xD;
was caused by the' writer's long exposure to the&#xD;
weather or by partaking too freely of Canada whisky&#xD;
we do not see fit to hazzard even a conjecture. Be-&#xD;
low we give a sample page from his note-book, to&#xD;
show the reader the great disadvantages we labored&#xD;
under in the compilation of this Work. A few ex-&#xD;
planatory words will be found in brackets.]&#xD;
First night in the Green [Mountain] State-Pret-&#xD;
ty village situated picturesquely'upon the banks of&#xD;
the "Father of Waters" [the Prince's ideas of local-&#xD;
&#xD;
I-                                     s&#xD;
&#xD;
I,&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
11&#xD;
ity is evidently confused] inhabitants painted white&#xD;
and houses very courteous-Left W. the day we&#xD;
did    Followed down the bed [valley ?] of the riv-&#xD;
er    passed many pretty farm-houses, before the&#xD;
doors of which long rows of shining milk-maids&#xD;
[pans] were spread out to dry, preparatory to receiv-&#xD;
ing the milk which the dairy-pans -[maids] would&#xD;
draw from the "sweet-breathed cow" [the Prince&#xD;
gives no credit for the above quotation,] in the even-&#xD;
ing. As we moved along the nimble birds skipped&#xD;
about beneath our heads and the squirrels flew above&#xD;
our feet. [Was the Prince standing upon his head ?]&#xD;
Just crossed a splendid trout brook  saw a beauti-&#xD;
ful farmer's daughter [beautiful probably refers to&#xD;
the daughter and not the farmer] -had a devilish&#xD;
pretty leg    wonder how it is further up ? [he&#xD;
doubtless has reference to the trout brook, as is evi-&#xD;
dent from the next sentence] should like to fish&#xD;
there.   This day came to Concord-neat little vil-&#xD;
lage, but think the citizens are much given to drink,&#xD;
the King, Doctor and myself being the only sober&#xD;
people in town.-Kimball took our picture; should&#xD;
think he was awful drunk, as he requested us to sit&#xD;
in an arm chair so our bodies would not see-saw---&#xD;
Got very good likeness of my companions but failed&#xD;
decidedly in my own case, inasmuch as he left out&#xD;
all the surprising beauty with which kind Providence&#xD;
has blessed me--Took a little whisky at the Phenix,&#xD;
a little more at the Eagle and considerable at the&#xD;
American ; after which the people of Concord were&#xD;
drunker than before-    Found our team and, after&#xD;
enquiring the way, started for Manchester, thinking&#xD;
that if Concord was n't rained upon like Sodom and&#xD;
Pompeii, why then there was no use in Lot being&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7900-00000007"/>&#xD;
12&#xD;
turned into a pillar of salt, a camel hung about his&#xD;
neck and pitched into a whale where a sea swallowed&#xD;
him up, after which Moses smote him hip and heels-&#xD;
over-head he went into the Isle of Patmos where&#xD;
poison serpents do abound. [The Prince's head was&#xD;
somewhat muddled when he wrote the above.]-&#xD;
We next found ourselves -  [Here the notes ab-&#xD;
ruptly end,.but'with the liberty of a compiler we&#xD;
shall finish the sentence with--"too d-d drunk to&#xD;
write, talk or think."]&#xD;
In due time the wanderers reached their homes&#xD;
much the worse for wear, where they were warmly&#xD;
welcomed by their numerous creditors and friends.&#xD;
We conclude our illustrations with a picture showing&#xD;
the very affectionate manner in which his dear&#xD;
AMANDA EMBBACED THE DOCTOR.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
 &#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD; &#xD;
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
