<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7523">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Red Bridge </title>
            <author>Talmon, Thrace.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7523</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1977</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The red bridge</title>
                  <author>Talmon, Thrace.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>321 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>National Temperance Society</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1875">1875</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-01-27">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The red bridge</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7523-00000001"/>  THE RED BRIDGE.  THRACE TALMON, WMROI OF "EDITH HALE,.?' "CAPTAIN MOLLY," "THE NEW GLUM, BTC. ETC. NEW YORK: NATIONAL TEMPERANCE SOCIETY AND PUBLICATION HOUSE, 58 READE STREET. 1875.  &#xD;<pb n=" (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7523-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1867, by J N. STEARNS, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the Eastern District of New York   CONTENTS.              CHAP.                   PAGQ I. WITH THE GUARDIAN, . .  .    .  7, 9    - II. CONSEQUENCES, . .  .    . .  39 "I. GOING TO THE WAR, . .  . .    61 IV. IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL, . . .  .  88 V. IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY, .       136 VI. EXAMNATON DAY,     .   .  .  165  VII. SEMNARY LIFE, .    ..   . 210  VIII. REVERSES, . .  . .  .  .   242 IX. THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT, .   .  .  275 X. THE SURPRISE,   .    .   .  309   :  &#xD;<pb n="-7" xml:id="VAC7523-00000003"/>   AH! they have come!"  "Who have come?" "My new wards, - children of my old college friend, Winslow, who, you  will remember, died at his parsonage, a few weeks since. I told you we might expect them about this time."    The first speaker was an intelligent    man of high bearing, standing at one of the windows of his residence in the aris- tocratic part of the city of C--. He (7) &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7523-00000004"/> 8     THE RED BRIDGE.  addressed his maiden sister, who resided with her bachelor brother, and superin- tended his housekeeping arrangements. The coach had stopped, and the young wards soon after were shown into the presence of their guardian. "Glad to see you, my children. I have forgotten your name," offering his hand to the oldest, a boy of sixteen "Wil- liam! that is good to bear the name of your excellent father. And this young lady of some fourteen summers, is" - "Mary," said the boy, bowing slightly. Their hands were both warmly grasped, when a presentation to the sister ensued. "We must make these youngixple at home with us, Miss FRlia. Will you call Kenneth to show them to their rooms, for dinner will be on the table in an hour."    WITH THE GUARDIAN.    9 When the young people had gone out, ,  Gilbert Jameson entered the adjoining room, which was his library, opened the door of a closet, took down a decanter, from which he poured a glass of some kind of liquid, and drank it off without pausing for breath. He then sat down at his writing-desk, and made the follow- ing entry in his journal:- "Alexander had a profound affection for his noble nurse Lannice, the daughter of Dropidas. Winslbw's excellent mother   i once took the finest care of me when I  was at his house for a visit, one college- vacation, and had a dangerous fever. My  fellow-student turned out a country parson,  and, dying early, left the two children  with but a paltry hundred, or so, apiece. , Their mother died soon after the last one : was born.  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7523-00000005"/> -t6   THE RED BRIDGE. "As I have never done much to bless the world, as they call it, with my liberal patrimony, ,I thought I would step for- ward and  take these precious, forlorn lambs into my own fold, and see what I can make of them. "I have not chick nor kin but Eliza, and who shall say I love not wisely? "The boy has a daring, spirited look that I fancy prodigiously. I can mould him into a fellow of the first quality. But the girl I shall turn over to my sis- ter. She is not in my way; her quiet, sensible manner will just suit Fliza. She cultivates 'Mercury's moly,'-the plant which breaks the charm that sometimes comes from the good old wine given by the host of the Circean palace to his sure feited guests."   WITH THE GUARDIAN. 1S The contents of the ruby-colored glass, from which he had just drank, began to work in his brain. "How thrillingly pleasant it is to be rich, and know that your foundations, like the Glitner palace of the Scandi- navian mythology, are built on pillars of gold! One feels so independent who can open his doors that the needy may come  in and sup and abide there! "I do not know as Winslow would fan- cy my sort of training for his boy; but, at all events, he is too far over the other side of the dark valley to know or care much, I reckon. He grew so solemn along the last of his life, whenever I saw him, which : was not often, that distance lent enchant-  ment to his society. He was a thoroughly good fellow to me, in the days of old, and :  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7523-00000006"/> 12     THE RED BRIDGE. stood by me because I was his chum, as far as his tender conscience would permit. I used to call him Baldrian, after the just and innocent god, in honor of whom, the whitest flower received its name. But his boy here will make no Baldrian, or I mis- take." While this was being written, the two young people had joined each other in Mary's apartment, and thus communi- cated:- "What a grand and beautiful place!" said William, with animated countenance, "I had no idea we should drift into such a harbor." "Yes," said Mary, "it is very fine; but these people are all unknown to us. There are no friends like our dear father,-- no home like the old house under the green trees of Blendale."    WITH THE GUARDIAN.    13 "Fudge on your nonsense!  That is like you, - always moping." Mary said nothing, as was most often her"habit when ridiculed by her brother. "We shall fare here, tip-top," he went on, "while at home, life was plain and sol- emn enough to make a fellow hang himself for the sake of variety," The servant now announced " dinner " at their door, and they went down. No bless- ing being asked, their attention was at once attracted by a wine-glass at each plate, while several bottles of an unique and costly pattern, stood near the plate of Mr. Jameson. William's eyes kindled at the sight, but Mary secretly wondered what could be in those bottles. If it were wine or other strong drink, would it conflict with the 2   &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7523-00000007"/> "     THE R)D BRIDGE. pledge they had both signed, up at Blenw dale? By and by, when the conversation flowed itasantly and naturally, Mr. Jameson or- dered one of the waiters, who stood near -his chair, to pour a glass of Madeira. This he handed to his sister. He then asked William if he would drink some- thing light, like white Constantia ' "I will, thank you," replied William. Mary moved uneasily in her chair; she ventured to speak:-"Brother, you know at you signed the temperance pledge more than a year ago." What of that?" exclaimned their host, laughing lightly; "life is one thing up in that little steady country-place, and quite another, here in town." But ought we not to be temperate as   WITH THE GUARDIAN.    L.5 much here as there?" asked Mary, eying anxiously the attractive liquor as it flowed into the glass beside her brother's plate. "Why, the fact is," said Mr. Jameson with just a shade of annoyance in his tone, ' all our best families here use something of this kind with dinner, as much as they do coffee or tea. It is thought nothing of, I assure you." "You have promised, William, not to taste of any such drink," she said, as she saw that he was about to take the glass. "I didn't know any better then; and the lecturers on such things told such aw- ful stories about how people who drank, ;urn out. I was ready for any such hocus- pocus," the youth replied. "Certainly," said Mr. Jameson. "You vill learn here to hobnob as people in good  lociety ordinarily do."          :  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7523-00000008"/> 16     THE RED BRIDGE. "But do you never see anybody round here injured by intemperance?" inquired Mary. "No, -that is, but slightly, if at all." His sister's eye rested fully upon tht of their host. He quailed a little, and added, - "Sometimes, indeed, a body gets to drinking hard; but 'tis generally one who, tried at first to abstain totally. When they went at it, for want of being used to good living, they didn't know how to stop, and so made fools of themselves." Mary looked at the flushed, spotted face of the speaker, and wondered if he were injured by this habit. William had now put the glass to his lips. , "O brother, don't!" exclaimed Mary.   WITH(THE GUARDIAN.    17 "What would our father say, if he were to see you?" ' Nonsense, child!" returned their guar- dian; "take a glass of Tokay or Claret yourself." "Not for worlds," cried Mary. As she saw her brother drink off the contents of his glass with a keen, delighted gust, she burst into tears. Mr. Jameson laughed so loudly at the spectacle, all were startled. "Do not ridicule the child," said Miss Eliza; "there is truth in what she says." "I dare be bound you think so. For one, I prefer sparkling Champagne or good old Bordeaux. Here's to your health and right reason, young miss," he said, as the 2  servant poured the effervescing wine, while : 2*    *  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7523-00000009"/> 18     tHE RED BRIDGE.  he held the glass with a hand so unsteady as to be noticeable. William soon became very loud and positive in his tones, affecting an unusual nonchalance to prove his perfect indiffer- ence to the wounded spirit of his*sister, and his ability to assert his own manhood desite her opposition. No sooner had they retired from the table, than he took a covert opportunity to rebuke her. sharply for her "foolish behav- ior." "I should have judged," he said, in ex- cited tones, "that you would have had more consideration than to have thus at- tacked my honor before others, and espec- ially such persons as these. You know that my honor was always dearer to me than my life."   AS WITHl TDHE GUARDIAN.   19 "Dear William, how can you reconcile your honor with the breaking of a sol- emn pledge, which our father valued so highly? Mary ventured, timidly. "Can't you see the difference between country and city life, you little simpleton? Circumstances alter cases. Here I am a gentleman; there I was a parson's son." "Do gentlemen call their sisters names, like what you just now called me?" "How provoking you are! You have much to learn," William proudly ejacu- lated.  "I have yet to learn that it is'right to do things here which we knew were very sinful at home," said Mary. "But, broth- er," she continued, very tenderly, as if hardly able to keep back her tears, "let us go to, God w;th this important matter,  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7523-00000010"/> 20     THE RED BRIDGE. as our dear parents, if they were here, would desire us to do. He has promised, if we lack wisdom, to give to us liberally, and he upbraideth not." "I do not call the drinking of a little  good wine at dinner, when urged upon you by your wiser friends, such an impor- tant matter. I guess, too, that he is too great a Being to descend to such trifling supervision," returned William, m re and more irritated. Mary went to one of her trunks, and took out a pocket Bible. She said, as she opened'it,- (This, you know, was our dear father's last gift. He told us, whenever we got into any perplexity to open that, with fer- vent prayer in the heart, and attend to the instruction we found there."   WITH THE GUARDIAN.    21 She opened it reverently, scarcely expect- ing to find anything so relevant as what met her eyes. She read: "In the day of our king, the princes have made him sick with bottles of wine; he stretched out his hand with scorners. For they have made ready their heart like an oven, while they  lie in wait; their baker sleepeth all the night; in the morning, it burneth as a flaming fire." Hosea vii 5, 6. As she concluded, she lifted her eyes to0  those of her brother, and there was much meaning in her look. "What do you make out of that?" he asked, with a dry, scornful laugh; yet he was somewhat impressed despite himself. "We learn, from these sacred words,"  said Mary, "the effects of what we saw  to-day upon the dinner-table. If you drink  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7523-00000011"/> 22     THE RED BRIDGE. of those bottles, you will scorn everything that is good." "Especially your good advice, eh?? "And then," continued Mary, without noticing his last remark, "your heart will become prepared for passion like an oven, while your tempters lie in wait. Your conscience will sleep during the night of vice. But, observe, there is a morning of awaking, and then it will burn as a flaming fire." "Quite a little preacher, isn't it?" said William, throwing himself upon the bed. 'But you tire me like all tedious sermon- izers and speechifiers." "O brother!" said Mary, "why will you not be warned in good time?" he could not go on for her grief. "Before it is too late, is what comes   WITH THE GUARDIAN.    23 next, according to orthodox fashion," he said.       - She gathered herself on a low stool be- hind one of the window-draperies, and gave way to her sobs. William was soon fast asleep. Every loud, heavy respiration painfully reminded his sister of the effects of his potation at dinner. By-and-by she became more calm; and, rearranging her disordered appearance, went to join Miss Eliza in the parlor. :"Where is your brother?" asked Mr. Jameson, entering at the same moment. "Asleep, sir," replied Mary. She was about to add, "in consequence of the wine at dinner;" but, remembering their de. pendence upon the guardian, she checked her speech. "I wanted him to take a turn on horse. 7       .;  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7523-00000012"/> V14    THE RED BRIDGE. back with me; but never mind, let him rest. He hasn't got used to affairs here, yet." Miss Elizas reserved, stately manners forbade any attempt at social interchange of conversation on the part of Mary. She found a fine library in the house, from which she carried, books to her own room, where she spent much time in reading. William -soon commenced attending school in the city, in order to complete his preparations for college. For a time, on Sunday, he at- tended church with his sister; but gradu- ally he absented himself from the house of God on the Sabbath, and spent the time in pernicious reading, or in sleep to recover the strength which he wasted by a pro- tracted vigil on Saturday night. His sister, getting alarmed when she dis- -4   WITH THE GUARDIAN.    25 overed his late hours, questioned him;  at he evaded her queries by some unim- ortant, but false reason. She then re-  Irred the matter to their guardian. He said was probably visiting with some of his Ohool companions; she bad better not give erself any more concern. He was a fine llow, and very much admired by some of ie best fellows in town. . "Last night," said Mary, 'I could not eep for thinking aboit him, and I shut )t my eyes till long after he came in. I oked at my watch when his foot was on e stairs. It was half-past two o'clock!" "Well, that was once he happened to be it," said Mr. Jameson. I will speak to in about it. I presume there is some )od reason for the delay. It is not wise dog these high-mettled young fellows 3 '.1  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7523-00000013"/> 26    THE RED BRIDGE. too closely. They have a spirit which nei- ther you nor I can break." The next night, Mary did not retire, but sat up and waited for her brother. The clock struck eleven. He had not come. She then went to the housekeeper's room and asked -her to go out with her in search of her brother. "I overheard him talking with Mr. Jameson, yesterday, about being down at the club in Delane's buildings I wish to go there and see for myself." "It is not safe for us to go," said Mrs. Kenneth; " but I will speak to my brother, who works in the next house, and perhaps he will accompany us." A half hour later the three went out together. When they had reached the place, the brilliantly-lighted windows indi cated the rooms. They ascended the pub   WlTHi THE GUARDIAN.   27 lic stairs, and coming to the doors, the top of which were glass windows with red cur- tains, Mrs. Kenneth's brother said he would go in while they might stand back in a dark angle of the space. If William were there, he would remain by the door, draw aside the curtain within, so that they could see for themselves, while tht dark- ness without would prevent their being seen. He entered and was gone without any sign, a long time, it seemed to the anxious watchers. At last, he came out and said, "I found the poor boy lying on a lounge in one of the ante-rooms they have in read. iness for their tight ones. They told me he was asleep. But I looked sharp, and if he is not dead drunk, my name is not  James Rowley. They are all gambling ;                O ' ..  * ' -.  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7523-00000014"/> 28     THE RED BIDGE. around the tables there, and your brother, like enough, was fleeced nicely before they got him well stupefied." "I must go to him," said Mary, pushing towards the door with a half-frantic gesture. "No, miss; that will not do. They would all take you for a woman about the town, if you were seen in there." "I care for nothing but my brother,- my  poor, ruined William. My father would wish me to dare life itself for his res- cue. I must go! Stand aside." Before they could prevent, she had sprung through that door, and the next mo- ment stood alone in the midst of that scene of brilliant and half-demoniac rev- elry. Her large, dark eyes now fired with   WITH THE GUARDIAN.    29 an agony so intense they seemed to burn in their sockets like superhuman fires, lit up her almost death-white face with a. startling expression. Even those hardened men, those reckless youth, and the accus- tomed attendants, were arrested in their several pursuits, and paused like persons struck by a spell. For a moment she stood still, as if to collect her senses sufficient to discover the way to the apartment in which was her brother. Then, pointing with her finger towards a gray-haired man, who sat at the head of a faro-table, she called out to him in a voice not to be mis- taken, as the utterance of a spirit ut-  terly abandoned to woe, but yet reserv. ing an irresistible purpose,-- "Tell me! - where is my brother?" 3*  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7523-00000015"/> 30     THE RED BRIDGE. He neithr spoke nor moved. -After you have accomplished his ruin, -my once innocent, good-hearted brother! -will you not tell me where I may find him, and weep tears of blood over his beastly intoxication?" 'Then turning to another, who sat next the confounded man, -"It is William Winslow I am seeking. 'He is here, and I will go to him if it costs every life-drop in my veins!"  By this time her attendant, James Rowley, had followed and gained her side. "Here," said he, in a low voice, "I will show you where he is." He led her to the side of the intoxi- cated youth. Mary's eyes took in the. whole truth at a glance. She knelt down by his couch, and suffered her head to fall beside his flushed, bloated face, while she spoke not a word. ,          s   WITH THE GUARDIAN.    31 The now excited crowd of frequenters of that place rushed to the door of the apartment to see what had become of the "insane girl," as they termed her. But the spectacle which met their eyes, one after another, caused them to turn back, with a sharp remorse glancing athwart their souls, even as a lightning flash across a dark storm-sky. "The door should always be kept locked," said the man who seemed to preside over those orgies; "hereafter, if this is not attended to, I will knock down the first servant who disobeys orders." "It is one of the curses of life, these women who prowl around after folk8 where and when they have no business," said another. "My young wife will be looking me  f  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7523-00000016"/> 32     THE RED BRIDGE. up next," said a third; "she has been insufferably cross lately." "'Drink, said Philip to his companions, 'drink, all is safe for Antipater is awake. So say I to you, fernorseful Benedict. Drink, and I will keep awake to watch that no more of these silly girls disturb our felicity," now spoke a heavy, stern- browed man, who had surveyed the scene for the last few minutes, apparently more amused than disturbed. Meantime the poor girl had literally bathed the face of her stupefied brother with her tears, while James, with an at. tendant, had made efforts for his restora- tion to consciousness. It was, however, a full hour before the young man opened his eyes with a look of consciousness. AWhen his gaze fell upon his half-dis.   WITH THE GUARDIAN.    33 tracted sister, who sat near wringing hei hands, and vainly trying to choke down her convulsive sobs, he started like one with the consciousness of having been shot.  "Why are you here? Has anything happened?" he quickly asked. I guess, said James Rowley, "the sooner you get up out of this place and go home with us, the better it will be for your sister, and perhaps for your- self." "Do you intend to insult me?" quickly demanded William, with flashing eyes. " brother!" now spoke Mary, " ask no more questions. YQu have been intoxi. cated." "Yes," said James, " we found you here a while ago, dead drunk." OD  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7523-00000017"/> , 34    THE RED BRIDGE. "What! what!" stammered William, confusedly trying to stand erect, " do you implicate my honor?" James now took him by the arm, while Mary followed like a soul-stricken mourner, behind; and they walked out through that long saloon, filled with rioters, drunkards, and gamblers. "What think you, pretty inspector of customs and so forth, of this place? ' called' out one of the boldest of the bacchanals, * as she brushed past his chair. In a state of desperation bordering upon frenzy, she replied, with a tone which sent a cold chill to every one of those hearts, hardened to flint though most of them were, - T' THE PLACE OF A SKULL. Your wine is ming led with a poison which shall gnaw you some day, to the quick of your souls!"   WITH THE GUARDIAN.   3 The door closed with a clang. She was gone. "I hate such scenes," said a man, sad- der-eyed than his fellows. "It would be worth while to die, to get rid of all of them." "It is a question whether we should not then be jumping out of the frying-pan into the fire. We might make a bad matter worse, I reckon," was heard in reply. No sooner had the staggering, stammer- ing brother been safely conducted to his bed, than Mary went to her own room, but not to rest a moment that night. The recent terrible excitement, for which her delicate organization and refined nurture had rendered her totally unprepared, had wrought too subtilely into her very being. The next morning she was found in a  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7523-00000018"/> 36     THE RED BRIDGE. state of high fever. Her delirious cries le- specting her brother, were enough to shake the stoutest heart. William visited her bedside as rarely as possible; and then, notwithstanding his efforts to maintain the appearance of a " gentleman " and a " man of honor," he really seemed more like a cul- prit in the presence of the sister whom he had so much injured. At length the physician said that her life hung, as it were, upon a thread. She might not survive the approaching crisis. William seemed now fully aroused to her critical situation; and his good angel was allowed to so far recover the ascendency as to persuade him to cry unto God for the precious life of his sister. "If she dies," he groaned bitterly in the soitude of his own thoughts, "I shall be /   Wiml THE GUARDIAN.    37 her murderer. The brand of Cain will evermore be on my brow. Then spare her, O my Father! Spare her, and I will vow to reform and be a new man. If I keep not this vow, and her life is once more given to me, thou mayest take my life as the price of the broken vow." On the sad night which was to decide her fate for life or death, William remained like one fixed by invisible chains in the sick- chamber. He scarcely dared move or speak. About midnight she appeared to be dying. The windows were thrown up and the doors opened.  "'Terrible, terrible!" he thought; "the last time she ever saw me in the face, I was half-stupefied with liquor, -and I have killed her. My poor sister! What 4.  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7523-00000019"/> 38     THED BED BRIDGE. tidings will she bear to my father and mother?" Next, a low, faint cry was heard. "Water, water," murmured the sick girl, unclosing her eyes and looking around from one to another of the anxious watchers. "It is beautiful," she said, as it was held to her lips. I just saw father. I would have gone to him, for it was so lovely where he was, but he shook his head and said,-- No, my child, not yet.' It was just as natural as though he had really spokto me." "She will live," said the physician; and he motioned William to leave the room, lest the sight of him should prove dangerous in her present weak condition. William went to his room, fell upon his knees, and repeated his vow.   IL T was now early June, and Gilbert Jameson, with his household, had fl left the city for his country-house in Welfield, a small village some half- score of miles from the city. Mary had so far recovered her strength as to keenly enjoy the change to the pure country air, the stillness, and the rare beauty which surrounded the residence on every side. On the day following their arrival, she sat in her chamber, awaiting the return of her brother from the city,- whither he went daily to continue his attend. Or (t9)  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7523-00000020"/> 40     THE RED BRIDGE. ance at school, until the vacation. A thin mist, but half-blending the chrome- green leaves of the trees, spread softly over the valley which lay in undulating beauty between the place and the build- ings of the thriving little village, from /whence William would walk from the depot. This gossamer mist was a thought- making softener of landscape-effects, hov- ering like a dream over the wet grass of early summer, which grew so magically in the humid atmosphere, the god Heim- dal, as of old, could have heard its deli.  catest waxings into newer life. Mary wrote rapidly in order to cone clude her self-imposed task before the coming of her brother,-which was the copying of one of his school-compositions, she that particularly liked, into her note.   CONSEQUENCES.     41 book. But as the twilight stole on, hardly perceived, she was forced to drop her pen. Then, turning her back to the window, from which she had once more strained her vision to catch a glimpse of the beloved form, in vain, she looked away into vacuity and repeated the title of his Theme: "He conquers, who con- quers himself." Thoughts of the possi- bilities of the rather dark-looking future welled up in her soul. William had not appeared of late as he had for several weeks after her illness. He was more irritable when questioned, and there was something about his manner which in- dicated a concealed anxiety and unrest, for which she was at a loss to account But a day or two since, he had applied to her for the loan of her quarterly al- 4*  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7523-00000021"/> 42     THE RED BRIDGE. lowance from their benevolent guardian; and when told that she had not yet re- ceived it, he had said impatiently that she must ask Mt. Jameson for the money, on some pretext or other, that she might' obtain it for his use. She asked him what disposition he made of his own ample allowance. He had assigned sev- eral reasons why it had not proved sufficient, but none of them had been satisfactory. C If I only had entire confidence in him, how different I should feel!" she sighed to herself. "He conquers, who conquers himself,- vincit, qui se vincit,"- she repeated. "But has William half conquered himself yet? True, he writes finely upon the noble theme, and when I have been talking with   CONsEQUENCES.     43 him, since my days of hovering between life and death, he has sometimes spoken tenderly, and has even wept with appar- ently deep emotion. "'It is so hard,' he said, but yesterday, 'to resist the strong temptations which al- lure on every side, when one has a dispo- sition to please one's self.' In your own strength, it is indeed hard, I said; but do you depend on Him who alone is able to preserve us from falling? 'I am afraid not,' was his reply. Iytoo, am afraid that he neglects secret prayer, the true safeguard of the soul, as our father often has said. When I remind him of these important du. ties, he laughs, and says I am supersti- tious." Mary now opened the pocket Bible, ac- cording to her custom in moments of anx-  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7523-00000022"/> "    THE RED BRIDGE. iety. She could scarcely discern one word from another; but she made out,--"This is the victory that overcometh, even our faith." That divine word faith touched the cur- rent of her pulsing thought, as words sent by angels only can. A new revelation of meaning opened before the drift of her emotion. As in matematics certain numbers are wrought into given quantities by means of affixed indices or powers, so these power- \inspired words have hidden meanings,- revelations within revelations, which grow iupon the spiritual recognition until the simple word-stone, cut out of the eternal mountain, fills the whole soul. "I will go below," she said, at length, "and see if William has not come. The   CONSEQUENCES.     45 time of his arrival must have been due some minutes 'ago." She had scarcely reached the landing, when she met a strange gentleman, fol- lowed by Mr. Jameson, whose excited manner at once arrested her attention. Her first apprehension was for William; and she was about to ask her guardian if anything had happened to him, when they both brushed by, apparently intent on busi- ness of their own, and, after making the circuit of the principal rooms in the house, repaired to the library, and locked them- selves within. With a confused impres- sion that all was not right, Mary sought Miss Eliza. That lady sat motionless; but the rigid, tense lines of her face revealed that a great emotion of some kind was shut up in her  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7523-00000023"/> "    THE RED BRIDGE. soul. To Mary's hurried inquiries, she an swered in the briefest possible manner, finally requesting to be left to herself. But Mary found Mrs. Kenneth more intelligent upon the matter. "Who would have dreamed'we should ever have lived to this day?" she ejacu- lated. "Pray do not keep me longer in sus- pense," said Mary. "' What can have hap- pened?" "I can't exactly say for certain," she re- plied, "but Jones (indicating the coach- man) says that the stranger who came out to-night, and has been prowling around 4 here for the last hour with master, is a sheriff. He overheard them talking to- gether, and it seems that master has met with great losses lately, by giving bail **i   CONSEQUENCES.     47 for some friend or other; and things have smashed up so that all the property here and in town is attached." "t readful!" exclaimed Mary. "When Mr. Jameson is so kind, too!" "Yes; it isjust like him to ruin himself for his friends, any day; that is, it is like him for these few years last past. Be- tween you and me, Miss Mary" dowering her voice to a whisper), 4master has greatly changed from what he was once. He used to be a right shrewd man; but, - I don't know as I ought to tell you,- haven't you noticed nothing since you came to live with us?" "To what do you refer?" asked Mary. "Don't you think master carries a rather red face, and isn't he a great deal more social, sometimes,-just after dinner, for  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7523-00000024"/> 48     THE RED BRIDGE. instance,--than he is in the morning? And what do you think he shuts himself up for, sometimes, whole days together?" "He says he has dreadful headache spells," returned Mary. "But you never hear Miss Eliza say so of him,-do you?" "I don't think she does." "Not she, nor I, nor any of us who know. It is something much worse than a common headache, I assure you. Poor man, it is such a pity he can't drink just enough, and then stop." No," replied Mary; " the pity is that he drinks at all. Just enough is not any, which quantity alone is safe." "Perhaps so," she said; "for there is Jones and Pelley, who always drink what is left at dinner, and steal out of master's   CONSEQUENCES.     49 wine-cellar a bottle or so whenever they can; and they get half-seas-over every once in a while. They have both been threatened with a walking-ticket if they're caught at their old tricks again. I hope they'll get their ilues before long; for two more silly, obstinate fellows the sun never shines on, than they both." The outer door was now heard to shut, whereupon the footman returned to the kitchen, rubbing his hands and looking mysterious. " ho was that?" asked Mrs. Kenneth. "Couldn't be after telling yer honor at all. It's niver safe to commit big sacrets to women; for they's no sacrets iver after, sure."  "I know," said Mrs. Kenneth, with a confident air. 5  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7523-00000025"/> 50    THE RED BRIDGE. "And what did yez be after axing for,  thin?" "To sae if you knew as much as I do, which, of course, you do not." "Do you know whether my brother has returned to night?" now asked Mary of Pelley. "I haven't seen him at all, miss, an' I be thinkin' he'll stop over in the city to- night, as the cars have been here and gone this more'n thin an hour." "I am so sorry!" ejaculated Mary to herself. "Yes," said Pelley; "it's a pity a young gintleman of the likes of him couldn't be after a little more of the sobriety. Ye see, miss," he continued, perceiving Mary's look of astonishment at his words, "nme cousin it is who lives in   CONSEQUENCES.     51 one of the grand saloons of the city; and he was jest up to tellin' me, last Sunday, what a botheration it was to have the young gintlemen with a plinty of money in their pockets a comin' there, and then a gettin' drunk for him to look after them; and thin, whin they'd gambled away all their money, they'd nothin' to git away with, till he had to go round an' borrow enough to git thirn off away in any dacent shape, at all." "Did your cousin say that my brother was one of these?" asked Mary, turning very pale. "Why, ye see, miss, I shouldn't be after letting on what he 'tells me about his business, and perhaps, -perhaps Master William wasn't there among the lot o' fellows."  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7523-00000026"/> 52     THE RED BRIDGE. "Of course, he wasn't, said Mrs. Ken- neth winking at Pelley with a look of alarm. Mary now went away and hurriedly sought her chamber. "Don't you remember she took so sick with that fever, all because of that worth- less brother of hers? Why could you not take my warning and hold your lips in season?" said Mrs. Kenneth. "I'd be blasted if I's after thinkin' at all, at all, and she as white as a shate all the time. She's a nice young leddy, is Miss Mary, and Id see the apple of me own eyes drop oot and fall to the ground, be- fore I'd wound her illegant feelings, if I'd ha' thought. Och botheration!" "While the world stands," said Mrs. Kenneth, "there must always be somebody   CONSEQUENCES.     53 like that good-for-nothing brother of hers, to torment a good woman's soul out of her body, piecemeal, as it were." "It's very fortunate, Mistress Kenneth, that your sek is made to be endurin' the sufferin', an so ye jest take to it naturally like. If it wasn't for the likes of us, ye'd have nothin' to do, worth mentionin' at all, faix!"  It was indeed fortunate for the Irish- man that he made his escape at that mo, ment, for had he remained, it is doubtful if the other "sek" had not suffered the most on this occasion, at least in the war of words. It was not very late that night when Mary heard a knock on her door, and, obey- ing the summons, found Miss Eliza there, in a state of excitement of such a nature 5*  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7523-00000027"/> 54    ITHE RED BRIDGE. as she had not supposed that apparently impassive lady to have been capable. "My brother is very sick," she said in suppressed tones, "and both the men-ser- vants, it appears, took this occasion to get into such a state of intoxication, that they knew not their right hand from their left, and so I see no other way than for you to go to the village for a physician, as Ken. neth's services are required with me in attending to Mr. Jameson." "Certainly," replied Mary, (I am glad to be of help to you." After all," said she, "I suppose -you do not even know the way to the doctor's house, and, as it is in the evening, it would be unsafe for you, even here in this quiet place. Would you dare take Kenneth's place with me at his bedside while she goes for aid?"   CONSEQUENCES.     55 "Dare? Why not?  I am not unused to sickness," returned Mary. "But you are probably unused to such sickness as this," that lady returned, bit- terly. Mary followed Miss Eliza without fur- ther delay, but when they reached the sick man's door, Miss Eliza stopped as if dreading to enter. "Do not be frightened," she said; "he is out of his head to-night, in consequence of the great pressure of business to-day." A strange sensation fell upon her mind, as Mary followed the sister into her guar- dian's room and heard his wild ravings, for she was all unused to madness in even its mildest forms. Mr. Jameson's bloodshot eyes glared on her as she entered, shiat she moved bee  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7523-00000028"/> 56     THE BED BRIDGE. hind the figure of Mrs. Kenneth, who was about going out, to collect herself for the dreaded spectacle. "You need not be afraid," whispered that woman, "for Miss Eliza and I have bound him into his bed with such strong cords it will take him some time to break them. I saw that the fit was coming on, and while he lay for a few minutes in one of the stupors, we got complete mastery of him." "Give me some brandy, will you, girl?" he said in a tone of persuasive command. "There, in my closet, you will find a pretty good supply for the present. What! do you hesitate?" he continued in a louder tone, "when there sits the demon Ruin, with his horrible grninng, and those snakes crawling up from the floor, with    CONSEQUENCES.     57 their mouths open at me! The electrical eels of the Orinoco and the slimy glym noti which you see there all over the wall, are here to do my bidding." Miss Eliza held a glass of liquor to his mouth, which he drank off with a beastly ferocity. "That is the bibendi', he cried; "the imp, there, over the chandelier, ap- proves. See here, Mary, you once asked me if drinking wine did not injure any of us? You have here convincing proof of the good there is in all sorts of liquors. I have fourteen different brands in my wine- cellar, and every one is a golden flower from the wreath of immortelles, which crowns Beelzebub. 'Drink, and remember ycur misery no more,' cries Ruin, there!" The poor man gradually ceased his ravings, grew incoherent, and finally lapsed into a temporary fit of stupidity.  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7523-00000029"/> 58    rTHE RED. BRIDGE. Mary, sick at heart, turned her eyes awa  from that scene of wretchedness. In o doing, they accidentally rested upon an open manuscript-volume, which lay on the writing-desk, just behind her chair. Without any effort, in the full light of the chandelier, she read, in the well-known chirography of her guardian, as follows:- "Welcome my Journal in these moments of new and exquisite anguish? A de- cisive blow has just been struck at my heart, and I bleed at every pore. Yester- day, I thought I was good for at least a cool half-million, To-night I find myself a victim to inevitable ruin. I lent my name,-fool that I was!- to my old friend Dillingsly, to back him in some grand speculations, which he calculated would make a splendid return. They have all   CONSEQUENCES.     59 broken and gone up to the idle winds. My fortune, which my father toiled so long and so hard to amass, has gone with them'! "I should have known better, I sup- pose, than to lend my nane to so much paper; but he always used to get me into his house and order on some new, choice liquor he had just imported, which he wished me to try; and then, after I had well drank, he could come the wool over my eyes. I see it all when it is too late. There is no remedy now; my mind and soul may as well keep my estate company in ruin.             i "I will drink without stint till my cellar is drained, and then,-why, then I will go mad, and shoot myself, for aught I know."  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7523-00000030"/> 60     THE RED BRIDGE. Mary closed the book to shut from ,ight the record of the wasted life, which touched her own heart even to blinding tears. The poor victim to delirium tre' mens now, attempted to beat something in the air above him; then, unclosing his eyes, seemed to listen a moment. "One of the voices just spoke to me from up there in that rift in the clouds, he said. 'Gilbert,' I heard as plain as ever my mother spoke to me when she was alive. My name! how it sounded on those pure lips! Anxiously I waited to catch what the voice said next; but, just then, a dark spirit came, and spread his choking wings all over my face, so that I could see nor hear no more." 2 At this moment the village physician entered, and Mary gladly resigned her post of watcher over the sick man.   IIl. gring to it isr. THE next day Mary received the fol. lowing letter from William:- "MY DEAR SISTER:- "When you were seized with that fearful sickness, I reflected much on what I was,/and what I had been, and I made a vow to God that if he would spare your life, I would reform and hence- forth take a new and different course. I also vowed that if he heard my prayer so as to spare your life, and I should fail of keeping my promise of reformation, I 6       (61)  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7523-00000031"/> 62     THE RED BRIDGE. would willingly give up my life as the penalty. "For some time after your life was given back to me, I was r : irmed. I attended steadily to my appointed duties and re- gained some of my lost standing in my classes. When my old companions who helped lead me away tried their influence anew, I was strong enough to resist them all and go right on, looking neither to the right nor the left. But one day, when you and Miss Fliza were out, I dined with our guardian, and he pressed me so hard to drink with him, I yielded. An hour after, I went out on the street in order to walk down my remorse. I met one of those wild young bloods who know just how to go at a fellow the right way to lead him on to his ruin; he took me by the arm and   GOING TO THE WAR,    63 before I was hardly aware, I was in the old club-room again. It was then early evening, and as a few of the choice ones were already there, they urged me to sit down and play for a new and attractive book which was offered as the stake. I hesitated, remembering distinctly my vow. "' But after all,' thought I, ' it is only for a book, and anything so trifling as such a stake, can hardly be scrupulously included in the spirit of my vow. I yielded. The game concluded and the book was mine.' "'Good! ' cried my companions; ' he de- serves something after his long vigils in si- lence and seclusion. This will cheer him up.' "The rest of them soon engaged in a new game with a stake of fifty dollars. Just one more fellow was wanted to complete  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7523-00000032"/> "-    THE RED BRIDGE. the compliment of players desired. They fell upon me with the most friendly and persuasive words. I refused, and then they taunted me with meanness. My blood rose immediately, for my honor could not stand a charge like that. I joined them without further parley. "This time, the successful winner was not me, and. I was one of five who must make up the sum.   I took out my porte-monnaie and found I had but nine dollars, and two of these I had received from you, with which to exe. cute a commission to the bookstore. I resolved to say nothing, but to play one game more, when I might recover the lost sum, and, perhaps, make some. thing. Four games more I played, and found myself just one hundred and   GOING TO THE WAR.    65 twenty-five dollars in debt. I was so chagrined I readily accepted the liquor proffered me by my 'good friends' who had fleeced me. I drank till I was a beast again. The next day I went to our guardian for money, representing my urgent need to defray some school-ex- pe nes. He kindly gave me one hundred dollars. Still I was in debt, and the next night did not hesitate to play. I won and I lost, won and, lost, till I was nearly in a state of frenzy. This caused me to so neglect my studies, I was first reprimanded by my teachers; then I was suspended; yesterday I was expelled in disgrace. Last, night I took my resolu- tion. . I have enlisted as a common solb dier, to join the regiment which leaves to-morrow, hoping that I shall be shot 6*  4  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7523-00000033"/> "    THE RED BRIDGE.     , by the rebels at the first good opportu. nity. I will keep at least one vow I have made in my life.  So end my dreams of college. "Mary! the great mistake of my life was the breaking of the Temperance Pledge which I signed when we lived at home. You did your duty. Oh! that I had taken heed to your warning words! But it required a stout heart to resist the temptation of seductive liquors, on every dinner-table, before one's eyes,-a stouter one than mine, with my self-will and high spirit, which father never made to yield. "If ever there was a miserable per. son in the world, it is myself. Not yet but a month over eighteen, and ruined, hopelessly mined!"-- "Oh! say not those bitter words, my   GOING TO THE WAR.    67 dear brother!" cried Mary aloud in the solitude of her own room. "While there is life, there is surely some hope!"But she read on: "My sister, I passed a great tempt&amp;- tion a few days ago, and did not yield. Mr. Jameson sent by me to withdraw five hundred dollars from the bank, fi him. I wanted the money.  I thought it all over, and I could not do it. I might have kept it, and said I was robbed; but, you see, I can resist. At all events, I am not a knave like what that would make me. My bounty-money I shall divide with you. Enclosed, please find a draft for two hundred and fifty. It is my last gift to you. The rest I shall have to take for my outfit, and to pay my debts contracted by play.  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7523-00000034"/> 68     THE RED BRIDGE. Offer my thanks to Mr. Jameson for all his kindness, and for his written con- sent to my enlisting, which I obtained by means of a friend. I enclose a list- of articles which I wish you to send to me without delay, as I shall not go out to Welfield again. If you have a "nd to take your last look of your brother, you will find me at the South- street depot, to-morrow afternoon, at half- past three. Our company leave the city by the four o'clock train. "Yours in haste, "WTLLTAM WINSLOW." Many have been' the sad partings be- tween hearts knit to hearts by the tender- est ties, before the departure of military companies bound for the war; but few   .     .   GOING TO THE WAR.    69- could have been more touching than that between the brother and sister on this sorrowful occasion. There are certain events in life, which fall from the regions of divine Providence, upon our consciousness, like those aero- lites, or meteoric stones, which come down from above, as a reminder of the changes which are going forward in a sphere be- yond the scope of our penetration. Cer- tain other events may be likened to that ominous pause which invariably precedes the approaching earthquake. Portentous silence and gloom! We know not then what the coming moments will bring. Imagination, ever powerful to heighten the possibilities within the scope of dread, pictures a sketch which often proves of greater and more formidable proportions than the reality.  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7523-00000035"/> 70     THE RED BRIDGE. When the long box brings home to us all that relnains on earth of our bee loved one, who bravely sacrificed his life for liberty and patriotism; or when the telegram arrives, announcing that our heart's treasure has been shot and is to be buried on the strange, far-off field of carnage, we have a certainty, -sud- den, terrible, astounding; nevertheless, a certainty. There are innate capabilities for grappling with the sternest realities. But the dread, fortuitous circumstances, which brood over suspense, are thridded with a power which gnaws, little by little, till the very foundations of the life are undermined. Perhaps this is the saddest of all the sad scenes of our life,--this giving our beloved ones to the dread chances, or we   GOING TO THE WAR.    71 may better call them the solemn provi- dences of a military campaign, far away from home and home friends. Who, that has ever participated in this unspeakable event, cannot say with an infinite index of meaning, "I know." Doubly sad was this parting, for there was lacking the: sustaining consciousness of uprightness, integrity, which, i pre- served, cancels many, if not all, of the bitterest pangs of life. "So you thought you would come to see me off," said William, as he met his sister on that afternoon, advancing through the crowd at the depot. "Nothing but an insurmountable ob , stacle would have kept me away," replied Mary. "Let us go aside, where we can remain  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7523-00000036"/> 72     THE RED BRIDGE. by ourselves," said he, offering her his arm. "We have but a short time, and then we part to see each other's faces no more." "Say not so, brother," said Mary, en- deavoring to assume a hopefulness of manner which she could not feel. "I deserve nothing less after doing what I have done," he continued, bitterly. Mary wisely saw that this was no time for recrimination; if, indeed, this time ever comes, and she strove to encourage him, and kindle high and pure hopes for the future. ( Again and again have I resolved to reform," hesaid, "and now see what is the result,- ashes of hopes!" "But as from the ashes, the ancients believed a beautiful bird to have sprung, *  *    ^  -+   GOING TO THE WAR.    73 so from the waste and desolation of your spirit, my dear William, .suffer the dove to fly upward, bearing aloft new aspira- tions and ambitions, in the name. of Him who alone hath power to forgive and re- store. Believe me, it will return one day with the olive-branch in its mouth." William shook his head and sighed. "There is poetry in your figure, but not truth. Iron-faced reality portends an- other vision.' "Your iron-faced reality, like Janus, has two sides. The one is gloom, the other joy. If thou doest well, thou shalt be accepted; if not, sin lieth at the door. There is forgiveness with God. The dis- ciple, who thrice denied his Master, was restored to favor. No one is so lost, but there is hope for him. This is the un- 7 4  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7523-00000037"/> 74     THE RED BRIDGE. utterably glorious provision of the gospel of our Lord and Saviour, and this it is which makes the atoning Name above every other name." 4C Mary, I was born for woe. I remem- ber, when we were children, being struck with the difference between you and my- self."@ His voice faltered so that he could 'not go on. Yes, dear brother, I, too, remember those days, and you were far more tender and loving than I was. You could not bear to have me out of your sight, scarcely a moment. Father used to speak of it to our visitors, and he said he supposed it was because we had so early lost our mother. He also said that you were like her and her family. William, she is in ex- istence now, and, though I cannot prove it, I believe she watches over us." , .       .   GOING TO THE WAR.    75 I hope not," said William, much moved. "To me the idea is, a beautiful one," Mary went on, " and yet not half so pre- cious as the actual consciousness of the truth that there is One, who ever liveth to make intercession for us, who knoweth our frame .and remembereth that we are buL dust, and who for all our temptations is faithful to provide a way of escape, if we will but accept it."  "There is no Escape for such a broken vow as 1 have on my soul. I promised my life, and I am going to keep that promise, at least." "Dear brother, can you not see that your idea of this is not less a temptation to sin? Last night, after I had read your letter for perhaps the tenth time, I turned to the Dictionary of Theology and found  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7523-00000038"/> 76     THE RED BRIDGE. that a vow is 'a promise made to God of a thing which we think to be agreeable to him, and which we are not, on other grounds, obliged to render to him.' Now it is clear to me, that it is not agreeable to him that you should make such a rash vow. Your life is not your own, and you have noright to throw away what belongs to another." "Right or wrong," said William, "it is the best thing I can do. If I live to man- hood, I shall be good for nothing, because I cannot resist strong drink, and then when I drink, the neit thing is play." "Hitherto," said Mary, " you have tried to reform in your own strength, trusting to the valor of your own indepen- dent will. If you will rely entirely upon God, pray often to him to keep you from   GOING TO THE WAX.   " falling, and watching thereunto with all perseverance, as the holy word teaches, you may yet come off conqueror. Oh, my brother, my twin spirit, how can I give up that you will not be yet all that the high hopes of my heart once promised for you?" ' Did Mr. Jameson, send me no mes- sage?" now asked William. "Have you not heard what has hap- pened to him?" returned Mary. No, - what can it be?" "But two days since, it came out that he is ruined as to estate, and I fear in mind, as well." She then related the circumstances as best she could, not omitting the wretched scene f his attack of the delirium tremens, from which he had not yet recovered  7*  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7523-00000039"/> 78    THE RED BRIDGE "What now is to  become of you, Mary?" was William's next question. "He who careth for the sparrows, will not forget the poor orphan," she said with quivering lips. "And you were not going to say any- thing to me of this great affliction which has suddenly cut off all your prospects?" "I thought you had difficulty enough of your own," she added after a silence on both sides. "If I had known this," said William, "I would have saved all my bounty-money for you. Poor child! what will you do?" "What is that you are doing with your gun?"' now asked Mary, in order to divert his attention from the painful subject. "Since we sat here, I have been cutting your initials on my gun-stock, that when-   GOING TO THE WAR.    79 ever my eye falls on them, I may think of you and of this bitter moment." "I will imprint a kiss on them," she said, bravely choking back her tears. "And I, also," said he, "that the deed may be strongly sealed." At this juncture, a signal was given to get aboard the train, which would now leave in a few minutes. The brother folded all he had to love closely to his heart, bathed her brow with kisses, then dashed through the growd and i left Mary standing among the hurrying persons like one in a dream. Suddenly a loud, prolonged noise, like the mad yell of an Indian, smote all the air. It proceeded from a source so near to Mary, who stood before one of the car-win- dows, she sprung like one who had been  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7523-00000040"/> 80     THE RED BRIDGE. hurt. She looked about her hurriedly, and perceived William at a window a few steps away. He motioned her to approach. "It is a drunken man of our company," he said in a low tone. "' He has been using his canteen for the last half hour, and now he is in such a state he hardly knows enough to keep on his seat." "Dreadful!" exclaimed Mary, turning deathly pale as the memories of the past floated before her vision. ,Another beastly screech now escaped from the soldier, whose uncovered head was rolling from side to side, while his body was' partially supported by one of his companions. His eyes wore that ex- pression of maudlin abandon which is far more frightful to behold than the fixed, cold stare of the corpse, and his tongue some. -/   GOING TO THE WAR.    81 times protruded beyond his open lips, as he attempted to call out to his fellow for more drink. "Far -fare-we-well--well--ell!" now screamed the poor fellow, giving a lunge forward, and endeavoring to thrust his di- shevelled head from the car-window. "Dearest William!" exclaimed Mary, "Iook there," indicating a poor woman who sat back on a step of the platform, with her face hidden in her hands, while her sobs convulsed her whole frame; " that is his mother, I know by the way she just looked at him. What a parting with a son who leaves her for the war!" The bell rang. "Mary, believe me, from this moment 1 will try to be a different man, for your sweet sake" said William amid tears.  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7523-00000041"/> 8fl.    THE RED BRIf)E. "Heaven help and bless you, brother" Another yell from the inebriate, the cars moved off, and Mary stood there for the first time fully conscious of her desolation. The sight of the poor mother now reminded Mary that there were those who had cause for deeper woe than herself. Half unconsciously she advanced towards her, and said, in tones of heartfelt sym- pathy, "It is very sad, is it not?" Nobody knows what real misery is, here, as I do," replied the woman, lift. ing her head, and discovering an ex- pression of sorrow which haunted ary's vision for weeks after. "My son, my son! would to God I could die for you!  she continued, wringing her hands convulsively. "And he was once so   GOING TO THE WAR.    83 good and true-hearted, - the pride of his widowed mother's heart! Why was I born for such trouble as this?" She rose up, walked away, and Mary saw that face in reality, no more. On returning to Welfield, she said to herself, in the solitude of her own cham- ber, "A new life is before me. Here- tofore I have been a timid, dependent girl; but now I must take up the bur- dens of life, and bear them onward alone. My course in the future is all undefined, but I will seek direction from Him who turns not a deaf ear to the cry of the humble and desolate., I re- member that it is written: 'In all their affliction, he was afflicted, and the angel of his presence saved them.'" While Mr. Jameson remained a vice  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7523-00000042"/> 84     THE BED BRIDGE. tim of his illness, she forbore to intro- duce the subject of a change in her intentions to Miss Eliza. When he so far recovered as to be abl to appear out again, it was evident thaMe was a ruined man in more senses than one. His mind was no longer under his con- trol; for a few moments' he would con- verse with his former brilliancy, but soon these flashes of intellectual strength and naturalness would be succeeded by a childlike simplicity, or even worse, by an almost fearful querulousness. Some- times, for hours he remained in his arm- chair upon the portico, gazing at the far-off hills or into vacuity without ap- parent consciousness if one approached and addressed him. At such periods, Miss Eliza led him within the house ' ,8.    GOING TO THE VAR.    85 and sat by him till he fell asleep upon the lounge. "Before the close of summer, the sheriff's sale took place, and it appeared that the estate was involved far more than it could meet. The poor man would have been utterly deprived of means of pro- curing a home, had it not been for a few thousands which Miss Eliza had. not entrusted to the care of her brother, and which now remained in her own right, beyond the reach of his creditors. Hence- forth they were to occupy a small house in Welfield, without any domestics, save Mrs. Kenneth. Early in the autumn, Mary took her departure for a distant academy, where she purposed to remained until she was 8  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7523-00000043"/> 86     THE RED BRIDGE. fitted to instruct a common country school. Here, amid new faces and new scenes, while yet the orphan's heart was very desolate and sorrowful, the Lord raised up a new and invaluable friend in the person of Mrs. Comfort, the lady with whom she boarded. This lady gave her the advice, the encouragement, and the motherly instruction which she so greatly needed. Her large and true heart never failed Mary's application for assistance. Once, only, Mary received a letter from her brother. It was brief and hurriedly written, as he was in circumstances which forbade anything more. He wrote that he was well; had, thus far, been enabled to keep his last resolution, and had no intention of doing less in the future   GOING TO THE WAR.    87 They were to engage in a pitched bat- tle on the following morning. If he survived, he 4ould write her as soon as. possible. If he was among the fallen, he trusted that God would forgive him and receive his spirit. After a long and agonizing suspense of weeks, it appeared that among the killed in that engagement was William Wins" low. "He acted very nobly all that day," wrote a comrade to Mary, "and as he made a dashing charge on the advancing foe to save the life of his commanding officer, there is no doubt but that he would have been promoted, if he had survived."    &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7523-00000044"/> IV. T was a sultry afternoon in early summer,--very sultry it seemed to those within a small white school- house, standing on the corner of a worth- less acre of land, which was passed on two sides by a country road. There were no cool, green window-blinds to the hap- less-looking building; nothing but one great butternut-tree, to protect it from the searching rays of the afternoon sun. But within were curtains of dark chintz, that proved a partial amelioration for the ex- cessive exposure. It was now a few minutes before tile (88)   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  89 last recess. The children, generally, were very restless. One or two of the smaller ones had worked themselves out into a sound sleep. Tom Harding and Sam Wilkins, the leaders of mischief, were so harassed with the evil spirit that abode within them, there seemed some danger of their taking on the capability of losing their heads and reproducing new ones, like certain individuals of the worm tribe. Their very eyes dilated with sharpened perception, so that not even a fly flew near without active efforts being put forth for its capture within their soiled palms. There was electricity in the air, and the clouds in the north and west were of that black-and-blue tone which constitutes the dark-purple of thunder skies. The sun drew water, one of the children ssaid, 8 *  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7523-00000045"/> 90     THE RED BRIDGE. "whole buckets full." And as the human mind is supposed to sympathize with the state of the elements, the restless, discursive condition of the children may be reckoned as the natural result of affairs. Our friend, Mary, or. Miss Winslow as she was now most often addressed, stood at the post as presiding genius of this little community. Her own spirits par- tially harmonized with those of her pupils. Her best scholar - the girl who rarely failed in her recitations-- had missed sev- eral times that afternoon, and was now in her seat with her face hidden in her tear- stained handkerchief. "Was there ever such a place as this, and such a school!" exclaimed Mary, in her thought. She sighed heavily  Her face was   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  91 flushed with excitement, and she wore that nervous, tired look, which is seen upon a person of her sensitive organiza- tion when overtasked. "Here I am shut out- from the world of intelligence and refinement, with no one to take the least interest in me or my work," she continued, to herself; "and it must be that God has forgotten me!" A heavy rumbling sound was heard in the distance. That's thunder," whispered one of the restless urchins to his seat-mate. "No, don't you hear the wheels? It's the stage," was the reply. The sound increased, and the advanc-t ing coach was welcomed by a general, though half-suppressed, sensation among the children.  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7523-00000046"/> 92   - THE RED BRIDGE. "Teacher," said one of the largest girls, on the back seat, "the stage has stop- ped, and there's a lady getting out." "Be quiet," replied Mary Winslow, yet there was a tone accompanying this in- junction which betrayed that even the teacher was not wholly devoid of inter- est. A smart rap was now heard upon the outer door. Miss Winslow walked out,/closing the inner door behind her. "I guess it's her sweetheart' aunt," said Tom Harding. "No, 'tis a spirit come to pull your hair," said a pert-looking girl. While similar conversation was going on within the school-room, let us follow the teacher to meet the visitor. "' Why Mrs. Comfort!" exclaimed Mary. If this isn't you!"'   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.   93  "Well, how does Mary Winslow do?" asked a quick, cheerful voice. The face was lighted with an irresistible smile, and bubbles of gooa cheer welled up in the eyes. "'Oh, I am so glad to see you! But who would have 'thought that you would have taken pains to have come here to such a place!" "Why not, child? I was going to see my married daughter, who lives about a score of miles beyond, and thought I'd stop over one day with you. I wanted to see how you got along." "Oh dear! I have but a poor time, 1 assure you. I'm ashamed to ask you in- to such a place. And the children are so rough,-that is, most of them." "Well, you know  we must make A\.  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7523-00000047"/> "    THE RED BRIDGE. the rough places smooth, when we find them." These words were accompanied by such a pleasant, congenial, hopeful look, Mary smiled despite herself. Mrs. Comfort now followed the teacher into the inner room, and took a chair in the desk, while she looked around with a kind of sunny, but silent how-do-you- all-do-here glance, that Sam Wilkins, who scorned to think amiably of anybody or anything but his own jack-knife, whispered, "That's a beat of a woman." "There's where your head is clear," re- plied Sam Harding. "Boys, stop communicating there," said Miss Winslow,-  and attend to your les- sons." They took up their books, but their eyes were not long off the face of the visitor.   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  95 A few moments later, and recess was announced. "How nicely they all go out," said Mrs. Comfort, "and some of them have the look my father used to tell about,- as though they'd set a barn a-fire one of these days, for being so smart." A laugh escaped, followed by a rippling tone of delight, that nobody, except a per- son looking at the remains of his last hope, could resist. Inquiries were now quickly made by Miss Winslow respecting her old friends of the academy. She had formerly board- ed with Mrs. Comfort, who was a widow, and had sometimes accommodated a few students with a home. "Those, indeed, were happy hours," commented Mary, with a deep-drawn sigh.  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7523-00000048"/> 96     THE RED BRIDGE. "Yes; and are not these, also?" "No, indeed! How can I take one mo- ment's peace here in this unsightly room, surrounded by these children, the majority of whom are more like so many cubs, than human beings! Then, to crown all, they gave me a boarding-place so far away, I am obliged to stay here during the intermissions at noon. I bring a book every day with my dinner, and when it is pleasant I go out to the grove, over yonder there, and I read. But when it is unpleasant weather, never was there such another place as is this. Their yells and imotions are almost terrific." "Let's see, dear," said Mrs. Comfort, "if something more inviting can't be got out of this hard shell. We'll break it to get the juice, and not keep looking at it,   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  97 whole and hard and rough-rinded." One of her own irresistible laughs now escaped, by way of parenthesis. "In the first place, I don't believe in your reading, of noons, when you've been using your brain all the hours before, and have got to do the same again right away." "But, really, Mrs. Comfort, what would you have me do?- sit listless, and, with folded hands, think over the pleasant scenes of days gone by, as I inevitably must, had I not something like a book to take up my mind?" "Now, if I were you, it seems .to me, I should get up something that these ni-'%y boys and girls could help about. I would take them over to those woods, and get some evergreens, and make wreaths to hang around these walls,- kill two birds 1a  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7523-00000049"/> 98     THE RED BRIDGE. with one stone, you know.  Come to think, it would be three or four birds before you got through. You would add to the beauty of these walls" (another laugh), "keep the children out of mischief, and get health for yourself. Then they could find nice mosses and make some baskets. You know you used to like to do such things."  "I don't believe they would care to,' said Miss Winslow. "Yes, I think they would. Children, even the rudest, are' always interested in Sything that puts the mechanical to na- ture. Going out to gather these things would give vent to their restless spirits. It would quicken your own vital energies, so that you would soon see sermons in stones, books in the running brooks, and good in everything,' -even this school-house."   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  99' Miss Winslow now remembered a beau- tiful spot in the edge of the woods back of the school-house, whither she had gone one day, and likened it in her heart to a fairy bower, it was so affluent with vines, mosses, pensile wild flowers, and nice old stones just fitted for seats. "Perhaps I should have gone out more since I began the school; for some days I have stayed in here from nine o'clock in the morning till half-past four in the after- noon," she said. "No wonder the children looked so strange to you. I should have thought you would not have known yourself when it came night. But after your supper, I sup- pose, you took the air?" "No; I fought my walk home quite sufficient. I usually went to my chamber,  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7523-00000050"/> 100    THE RED BRIDGE. and read in some book when I had no sewing to do or letters to write. Some- times I sat by the window, and thought till the tears would come despite myself." "Now, Mary Winslow," said Mrs. Com- fort, " there's no use in taking life this way. You may just as well look at the bright side as the dark one. I knew your father when he was a young man, and he used to say he would not give one cent for a character which had no obstacles to overcome. I expect this summer's work is going to do more for you than the brightest, and what you called happiest, seasons of your life." It was now time to ring the bell for the scholars to return; from recess. Mary smiled at the sunny face of her friend, and resumed her duties at a lighters pace. But, as she werit to the window to ring the bell,   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  101 she noticed that the clouds had gathered deeper blackness in the west, and the shower was soon to be overhead. "It is going to rain right away," she said to her visitor, "and it looks now as though the shower would be heavy." "We need rain very much; it is so dry I hope we shall have a good smait shower. I always enjoy it right well," returned Mrs. Comfort. '\ "But not the thunder and lightning?" "Certainly; why not? There is a gran- deur about these demonstrations of nature, as illustrations of God's power, which ex- cels every other spectacle but that of- teaching school with a happy, contented spirit." And the old pleasant ripple of the heart was heard again. To say that Mrs. Comfort laughed was the poorest possible ,.       9*  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7523-00000051"/> 102    THE RED BRIDGE. way of representing het sunny outgush of feeling, there being so many different lan. guages to that expression. The mere folly, the dry sarcasm, the vacant sense of titilla- tion, the contagious imitation were not in the spirit of her laugh. In short, this wo- man was like no other in this respect. One recitation after another now came on, and, owing to the weather or somew thing else, every one failed of meeting the teacher's expectations. Her mouth fell down at the corners, and her lugubrious face was accompanied by such an anxious tone, Mrs. Comfort thought to herself that John Rogers' widow, with the nine small children, could not have felt much worse. The younger children, on the front seats, having accomplished their last lessons in reading and spelling, began to annoy each *^   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL. 103 other, and disturb the general work not a a little. Miss Winslow had no heart to bestow summary punishment before her visitor, and she contented herself with sprinkling a few light rebukes here and there, like pepper-corns in a soup. At length the last lesson was heard, the hand of the clock was on the point of four, and she declared the school dismissed. It had rained very delightfully for the last hour, but now the drops ceased, and the sun was struggling from behind the clouds. "Oh, I am so glad!" exclaimed Mary; "the last one is gone! another day is told off from this dreary round!" "My dear child," said Mrs. Comfort, as she prepared to walk home with Mary, "how much you lose by not enjoying your- self!"  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7523-00000052"/> 104    THE RED BRIDGE. "How can 1, when there is so little to enjoy?" "You know I talk with you as though you were my own daughter, and so I must tell you a few things, - shall I?" "Certainly, my dear friend; what can I not bear from you?" "In the first place, you must take more interest in your scholars. You must love them more; no matter how uncouth, un- lovely they are,--remember that Christ, God's well-beloved Son, died for every one, and that they are all stamped with that aw- fully significant seal,- immortality. They are now forming characters for the endless ages. You are dowered with that high commission from heaven to help mould and fashion these minds. Is not the idea an important one?"   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL. 105 Mrs. Comfort lifted her eyes towards heaven in silent prayer, as was her custom when she would seek the blessing of Di- vine Power upon her words. Miss Winslow was silent. The lady continued, - "Love is the great counter-current for all the electricity of evil. When your pupils recite, you must look at them with a kind of a loving interest, as though you expected they were going to say the right thing with a little of your encouragement. If you look at them doubtfully or with an uncon- genial condemnation, they will easily keep on the plane where you put them, which is dislike both to their tasks and to yourself." ",But those younger children, i-vhat kind of electricity will hit them success- fully?"  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7523-00000053"/> '106    THE RED BRIDGE. "Let them have something to do when they have finished their little tasks. Get their parents to procure them some slates and pencils, and set them to writing and drawing. To require them to keep still is little short of cruelty." "Perhaps it is; but I had not thought of it in this way before," Mary returned. "You must seek to be cheerful," con- tinued Mrs. Comfort, "and then everything will look differently to you. We can make life whatever we will. 'If you look so un- reconciled, you will hinder your own suc- cess in life." "Do I look unreconciled? I did not know it. I don't think I am in the habit of looking so." "I am not sure of that, though you did not use to formerly, I well remember. But   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL. 107 I heard a gentleman speak of you in the coach this afternoon as we were riding from the city, in such a way as to induce me, in ' addition to my own observation, to form this opinion." "A gentleman speak of me? Who was it? And what did he say?" Miss Winslow's curiosity was fairly aroused. "I could not have told you, except to prove the truth of what I have said,- and all for your good, my dear child." "Certainly; but do tell me." "There were five of us passengers, when we left N--. Three of these stopped at the centre of this town. They seemed ac- quainted and commenced immediately to converse together. As I had nothing better to do, I listened. One of them, it appeared, #  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7523-00000054"/> 108    THE RED BRIDGE. was a member of the School Committee, ana ne was questioned respecting the schools. Among the new teachers who had recently come into town, your name was mentioned. This young man said that Miss Winslow might make a very good teacher were it not for one thing." "What was that?" asked Mary, quickly, as Mrs. Comfort hesitated. "The queer part of it was, at this very moment when my heart was on tiptoe to hear the criticism, the driver called out to one of the passengers to know if she would stop at the house where we then were. This put a period to the conversation. The passenger stepped out, and the second one of this party which had been conversing said he guessed he would not ride any fur- ther, as he had to stop at a store but a little further ahead. So this broke it all up."   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  109 But I was not to be baffled in this way, for I wanted to know what that one thing was, that I might help you out of it if I could. I knew it would not do to tell him that I was acquainted with you, so I mere- ly said,- "A teacher's life is a difficult one, sir; and excuse me if I say it is easier for the committee-men to see faults than to rectify them so as to be wholly free themselves, when they chance to teach." "Oh, yes, madam," he replied; the lady teacher to whom I just alluded is evidently well qualified. In fact, I should say she is a superior girl." "But what then is the matter? I have several friends who teach school, and I am interested to know for their sakes, --for the sake of one young friend in particu i" 10  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7523-00000055"/> "O    THE RED BRIDGE. "Do you reside in this vicinity?" he now asked. "No; my home is in another county,- quite a distance from here. I was never through this country before," I said. "Well, then, madam, if my opinion is worth anything, it is this; no one should so disrelish his or her employment, as not to work with a determination to get the most happiness out of it possible. In order to that, they must make up their mind it is just the place God designs them then and there to fill It is a great thing for a teacher, or any leader of other minds, to be cheerful. In fact, it is more than half the conquest." "But does not this Miss Winslow seem cheerful in her school? I asked, as uncon. cernedly as I could.   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  1" u She is not cross, but ill at ease," he said. "Perhaps she is bashful, especially in your presence," I continued. "I think not; she is too proud for that. A fine girl, but out of her element." He bowed and descended from the coach, which had stopped before a building, on which I read, "Henry Alton, Counsellor at Law." "Was that Esquire Alton?" exclaimed Mary, while a warm blush overspread her face and her eyes suffused with tears. "I did not intend to wound you, my dear; but I thought it might be a bene- fit to you to know what a committee- man said." "I would not have chosen to have made such an impression on him," said  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7523-00000056"/> "2    THE RED BRIDGE. Mary, trying hard to keep down her emotion. "Is he married?" asked Mrs. Comfort. "No; but I don't care anything about that." "Of course npt," said Mrs. Comfort, drily.  "He is one of the most influential men in town, and perhaps the best edu- cated." "And a real gentleman," added Mrs. Comfort, "as I saw by the way he helped make me comfortable in the coach." "Yes," said Mary, " he was very con- siderate when he came into my school the other day, though, it seems, he had a poor opinion of me, all the while." "Oh, no; it is only for the good of teachers that he satd all that," said Mrs. Comfort, smiling.   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL. 113 They had now reached Mary's board- ing-p ace,-a fortunate occurrence, as it seemed that Mary could not much longer have preserved her self-control. Mrs. Comfort took everything as a matter of course which she found at the common-looking farm-house; her cheery way won all hearts at once.   Even Mary wondered that she could ever have thought the place so uncomfort- able. Mrs. Comfort spent the evening in telling all the pleasant news of which she could think to her young friend, be- sides dropping, here and there, a prac- tical hint of much value. Mary awoke in the morning to find her friend up betimes, already dressed, and reading from the pocket-Bible she generally carried in her capacious pocket. And when, after- 10 *  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7523-00000057"/> "4    THE RED BRIDGE. wards, she poured out of the abundance of her soul her prayer to God, Mary said to herself, "This is the secret of her content; for He giveth the oil of joy for mourning, the garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness.'" She resolved to be more fervent in prayer, in future, that her spirit might be sustained, and delivered from its bondage of unrest. "Now, Mary," said Mrs. Comfort, when she was about to leave her, to resume her journey, that morning, "promise me that you will try, hereafter, to look on the best side of all things, and to love everybody." "I will make the effort," returned Mary; "that is, I will try to like all but the legal committee-man."   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  115 "Oh, dear," said Mrs. Comfort, "you mean just the contrary; I have seen girls before." But, after the departure of her friend, Mary thought much of what had been said to her. This proved one of the way-marks of her life. She was wise to resolve on a change.  Perhaps this good resolution resulted not a little from Mrs. Comfort's prayers for her friend, for she ceased not to remember her before God, when she had passed on to new scenes and new faces. About three weeks later, Mrs. Comfort received the following letter from Mary Winslow:  "DEAR MRS. COMFORT:- "If you had dropped in upon me in  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7523-00000058"/> "6    THE RED BRIDGE. the old school-house a few days after you left, you would have found a very different place from what it was the day you were with us. First, I had it swept and gar- nished, giving the pupils several familiar exhortations upon the importance of a fine appearance of our house, and sum- ming up with an invitation to accompany me, at noon, in search for something rare and beautiful for its adorning. They looked upon me in astonishment, seem- ing hardly to credit their own ears. I suppose I had, hitherto, seemed very in. different to them, out of school,- and, possibly, too much so when in my usual round of duties. Every child of them was on the alert to help forward the en- terprise, and those who had given me most trouble in school, now proved them- selves the most useful.   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  117 "We found beautiful evergreens which ran along the ground, for rods and rods. Then there were bitter-sweet and life-ever- lasting, which we made into wreaths that will keep for months. When I found how pretty these were, I devised the getting-up of a motto, which we could not complete for several noons. At last, we had it hung up over my desk, directly opposite the door, - Godliness with Contentment is great gain.' I think of the spirit of these beautiful words many times every day, and it does me good. Some of the older girls who know how to make moss-baskets, have made several for me. One of these I keep on the desk. They fill it with fresh flowers every morning. "In addition to these natural graces, I have introduced quite a number of new and  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7523-00000059"/> : : :4TH:  R EPD B IDQl   . interesting exercises, in which they engage just before recess or the close of school. These are geographical, mathematical, and orthographical. We have some very amus- ing times, I assure you. "The old school-house was looking just its freshest and best, when who should ap- pear, to-day, but Esquire Alton, for an offi- cialvisit of inspection. I was secretly glad to see that notwithstanding his eyes have rested upon the grand, old scenes of foreign travel, he gave a slight start of satisfaction, as he first took in our homely, unpretending little adornings. He sat down .quite with the air of the man who feels he has got into an endurable place. And what was yet more gratifying, my pupils pro'ted by some of my recent lessons on behavior, so t:ih t they contributed not a little to the good   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  11i appearance. As I had 'watched' the night before (of which I will tell you as soon as I come to it), I made but a very poor spectacle myself. I was stupid and anything but that cheerful angel which he pictured to you, as his beau-ideal of a school-teacher. I felt his keen eyes resting upon me occasionally, and colored till my face must have glowed like a red holly- hock. The more I tried to be indifferent and independent, the less I succeeded, and I was ready to escape with vexation through the hole for the funnel in the ceil- ing, when he announced that he would like to address the school for a few moo mqnts before his departure. "(He said several complimentary things, I believe, about the school and its teacher; but I did not care much about them after  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7523-00000060"/> 120    THE RED BRIDGE. what I knew he thought of me; and I think he was a little surprised that I showed no more consciousness of such a high opinion from a rare individual like himself. I sup- pose you would chide me for these words, if you were here. "Last night, Sam Wilkins' mother rode over to ask me to go and see herisick boy. Sam has been very sick for a number of days, and as he had been doing well recent- ly, I missed him very much. I hesitated to go. She had come in an old, rickety chaise, with a strange-looking horse, and she was vastly queer herself; but I remem- bered what you told me about making the best of all things and loving everybody, so I went. When I got there, the boy was evidently glad, but he said little. I read a chapter ih the Bible and talked with him   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  121 about being prepared for heaven. He lis- tened, and finally asked me what he should do to be good and fit to go to heaven. I told him as best I could, though I wished, Mrs. Comfort, you had been in my place by the side of that sick-bed. "After a while I spoke to Mrs. Wilkins about going back; but she said she could not carry me till mrning, and I must stay all night. I believe I should have felt very un- reconciled to this arrangement, as it was. the poorest house I was ever in, if I had not re- membered your parting words. I conclud- ed I could sit up with the poor boy part of the night, that his mother might get some rest. She was very grateful, for she had not found opportunity to sleep only in her chair for some time. The old house- clock ticked heavily. The boy's breathing ",  (I  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7523-00000061"/> 122    THE RED BRIDGE. was loud and troubled; else all was silent I should have been frightened, all unused as I am to such scenes, had I not recalled that my dear heavenly Father had prom- ised to shield all those who trust in him. It was well I thought of this, for about the time the clock struck twelve, I heard the sound of steps, as of some one walking down the garret-stairs and then approach- ing the room where I was. The door was ajar, and the light which had been kept in the kitchen, burned just sufficiently for me to faintly discern objects. I confess that I felt a desire to be elsewhere at that minute. Slowly advanced the uncertain sounds, till the door was opened wide, discovering a figure wrapped in a large, white covering like a sheet. I saw the strange, pale face of a man, with wild eyes fastened on mine   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  123 My first imp e was to escape; but I felt that would avail nothing, for there was no other door save the one in which this person stood. ("'Young woman,' spoke a voice, slow and hollow, 'the child will die. He is even now struck with the fatal arrow.' "I was uncertain what to do in my great fright, when I heard the voice of Mrs. Wilkins from the bedroom across the kitchen: 'John! what do you   come down this time of night for? Go back to bed, will you?' "'No, I have come to see my child.' He emphasized the word' my' as if his right would be questioned. Mrs. Wilkins had now reached the room, also. I was glad for this, I cannot describe to you how greatly. *  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7523-00000062"/> 124    THE RED BRIDGE. "He went to the bed, looked at the sleeping boy for a time, silently, then he covered his eyes with his hands and cried bitterly. "'The boy was the only one who cared for the poor drunkard,' he said, turning 'towards me. "'Don't trouble her with your talk,' said Mrs. Wilkins, evidently much morti- fied to have: me make this encounter with her husband. Sam now turned in the bed, breathed softly, and opened his eyes. He saw his father, his mother, and myself, as one who has just awoke to a pleasant but strange discovery. 'I have had such a great dream,' he said, ih a voice very un- like his own I had so often heard at school. I can't tell it all, though I never shall forget it. 'I thought I was in a wide and open   iN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  125 place like the Smith-pasture. It was all so green, ana yet so bright as though the sun shone, softly like, while it rained great drops of crystals and gold, and purple stars. I laid down right beside the water, which went along through the place like a clear brook, and I looked down into the water, and I saw, just as plain as day, myself with two beautiful things like wings. I was so glad in my sleep, I went right to saying, ' Now I lay me" just as I do before I go to sleep. Pretty soon I saw coming tow* ards mly shadow there in the water, a ma'i I took to be you, father, and I said, 'He is clothed and in hisright mind,' which was what Miss Winslow read to me out of the Bible, before I dropped off to sleep. I laughed right out, and I clapped my hands for joy. "It will surely be," somebody seem- "*  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7523-00000063"/> ': 1','26T THE RED BRIDGE. ed to say to me, "but pray." 'Now, father, continued the boy, 'I feel I am going to die before long. I asked God to forgive my sins to-night, when Miss Winslow had done talking to me, and he did forgive me, I know, because I feel so calm-like and so happy. I want you to kneel down here, right by my bed, while I pray for you and mother. Oh, yes, "pray" is the sweet word I heard so clear in my dream. Was ever word like that, as it sounded then to me!' "We were all much moved. The poor man sobbed like a child, but he stirred not. Mrs. Wilkins was almost prone on the mat at the foot of the bed, groaning aloud. ' Father, you remember when I saved you from drowning down in the meadow, that you promised to do some great thing   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  127 for me some day. I claim that now. I ask you to kneel down and call upon God for mercy,' continued the boy. Still he moved not. "'I have not long to ask anything of you,'- "'I will, Sam,-yes, I will. Do you hear? I will kneel,' now spoke the father, falling helplessly beside the bed, while Samuel laid his hand upon that of his father. "O thou dear Father in heaven, dear Jesus, who died to save sinners, be so kind as to come here now, and cause my poor father to see how bad it is to drink and have a wrong mind to do things that al- most break my mother's heart. Make him like the father I saw in my sleep, all fair and good and clean. Let him  be so changed that, when he dies, he will come    &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7523-00000064"/> 128    THE RED BRIDGE. where I expect to be. For I shall soon go to that beautiful land where the sun shines through the showers of purple light, and the waters run on and on, between the softest banks of green and many- colored wreaths, and such flowers! Oh, I am glad I am going there so soon!' "His voice wandered into inarticulate, broken murmurs. "Mrs. Comfort, never can I forget that hour! I would write you more about it; but my watch warns me that it is time I prepared to go to school. "EVENING. "My good, far-off friend, I cannot fold up this already long letter without tell- ing you that I have lived to number one pupil in heaven. I heard the bell toll this morning just as I got to the school-   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL. 129 house. We all stopped to count the age. It struck fourteen times. We knew, then, who it was. Every voice was subdued, and a sad, solemn look was on all the young faces. Soon after, a man rode, along, who had just come from the Wil- kins' house, and he said that Sam died early that morning. It was just two mornings from the one I left him, when he had said,' Good-by, teacher. I thank you for all your kind, good words; but please pray for my poor father.' "I am very grateful to you, Mrs. Com fort, that you showed me the more excel- lent way, in which, I humbly trust, I am now walking to my peace and profit. "Your affectionate "MARY WINSLOW."  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7523-00000065"/> -xV    THE RED BRIDGE. Mrs. Comfort's reply:  "DEAR MARY,-- As I never taught school myself, you must not expect me to write letters like a practised hand. I don't believe in apolo. gies, though, so I will write what I have to write without navigating around Robin Hood's barn, as my father used to say. "You did very well with your poor sick and dying boy, but acted foolishy with the young committee-man. But, if he is as wise as every man ought to be, he will understand that a young girl's ways, like folks' dreams, go by contraries. At least, they used to when I was young; but now-a-days, around where I am at the academy, girls are so forward that they seem to think the more they act right out   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL.  131 before the young gentlemen, the smarter they are, You didn't use to be so here, I well remember; and that's one reason why I took such an interest in you, from that time to this. There were some others, too, of your sort; but I fear they are getting precious fewer and fewer every year.  ( I am afraid you have got too much of what my father used to call myhighgilius (strange for pride) to get along just right in life. Now, Mary, you must take these plain words from your old and true friend, as you ever have my advice to you. I re- member the day that you first came to live under my roof, and what I thought of you then. ' She is just about right, with a few exceptions,' I said to my daughter. You had seen sorrow, I knew from your general appearance; but, as you were  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7523-00000066"/> 132    THE RED BRIDGE. young, this in time would pass away But not so soon would pass away from your manner, a certain incomeatible hedge- row, as my father used to call it, which showed that, somewhere behind that, you had a pretty good share of independence. And this, in part, serves you well. You were much beloved here by those who knew you, except those who knew just enough to envy your gifts. Never mind them, however, for such people must ap- pear at every turn of this world; and be consoled with the thought that 'envy never runs down hill.' If you could get along without any such times, you might know you weren't of much account, any- way. In order to be happy under all circum- stances, we must be as straightforward as !   \    IA THm DISTRICT SCHOOL. 133 posible. I knew what I want to say, but I cannot express it to you as I would. That is, when the young lawyer came in there to see yoP and the school, you should have silently lifted your heart to heaven for wisdom, and then gone right on as calm as a gentle brook through the meadow. 'Flurry and fustigatioi,' my father used to say, 'come right from the spirit of evil; but an even try-to-do-your-duty sort of way, is from the Lord.' Throw away your own will, and you can see clear that you are helped by the Mighty One, and helped, too, in a way that needs no repair nor going over. "You do well to pray much, and pray also for others. The Lord turned Job's captivity when he prayed for his friends. Seek to say an encouraging word, as often 12  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7523-00000067"/> 134    THE 'RED BRIDGE. as you can, to that poor man who wishes now to lead a new and better life. It will cost you some effort, I know; but' to do good, and to communicate, forget not; for with such sacrifices, God is well pleased. "Before I close, you must suffer a word of caution from Hannah Comfort. It is this: don't try to do too much with your scholars all at once. If you do, they will get disgusted, and return to some of their old habits of rebellion. You know how the ants build their heap, - little by little, -and they are paragons of wisdom. We are in danger of going to extremes in everything. "Young plants require a gentle water- ing once or twice a day; they cannot stand a deluge. A word to the wise,' etc.  ,    ; .)   IN THE DISTRICT SCHOOL. 135 In great haste, as I have forty-eleven things to do to-day, "Yours truly, "H. COMFORT.' *                *   &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7523-00000068"/> InZxiaons bg   ige fad HE day came for the funeral over the earthly remains of Samuel Wilkins. It was agreed that the school-house should be closed that afternoon, and the teacher, with all the pupils, should attend together as mourners. At the first thought of this, Miss Wins- low refused in her heart. From a child she had shrank from attending these sol- emn rites, having cherished nervous and false notions of the dead; but now to go there before all the neighbors, in her o ficial capacity, on such an uncongenial occasion, was more than she well knew (136) /   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  137 how to do. "If Mrs. Comfort were only here in my place!" she reflected. But no friend was near to bear her burden. She was now the head of a school in a large district, and, as such, new responsibilities stood ever before her to hedge up her pathway. If I go to the funeral, what good will it do? Besides, it will greatly harm myself, for I shall see the livid form for days to come," she continued to revolve in her mind. In her vexation of spirit, she fell upon her knees in prayer, and then after- wards opened the Bible for a divine les- son to her soul. She read: "For the administration of this service not only supplieth the want of the saints, but is abundant, also, by many thanksgivings unto God. While, by the experiment of 12*  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7523-00000069"/> 138  I  THE RED BRIDGE. this ministration, they glorify God for your professed subjection unto the gospel of (Shrist, and for your liberal distribution unto them, and unto all men." 2 Cor. 9: 12, 13. It was then applied to her soul, that, if she performed this service, she not only did what, was acceptable to God, as a Christian, but gave cause for much hap- piness in her own )soul. Many thanks- givings would result for this subjection unto her duty to others and to herself. "God is able to carry me peacefully over all thorny or hilly paths," she con- cluded; and, dismissing her fears, she went about her duties with a comparatively cheerful spirit. To one differently reared, this indeed would have been no cross; but Mary   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  139 Winslow was the child of delicate and peculiar nurture; still, without the expe- rience of years and varied observation; and, withal, endowed with that exqui- sitely imaginative temperament, which, if not properly trained, becomes a fruitful source of misery. For her life, in its most ordinary phases, had four-fold more meaning and index than for many others. She enjoyed, she suffered, she hoped, she feared, with an intensity of which another, differently constituted, would have never dreamed. On that still summer afternoon, accom- panied by a score or more of her pupils, she neared the old brown house, just be- hind the grove of beeches, with a feeling of'awe too deep for words. "There's his dinner-basket hanging on *  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7523-00000070"/> 4 "O-    THE RE)D BRIDGE. the old cherry-dee," said Tom Harding, with a tone a little more subdued than usual. "I guess the last thing he ever did, out-doors, was to try after the cherries." "Yes," said one of the girls, "his mother said his head ached so that he had to hurry down off the tree to keep from falling, that afternoon he was taken sick." "It's dreadful to think of," said an- other. "I don't think it is," replied a thought- ful girl; "he's gone now where he'll get things better than cherries, without climb- ing trees after them."' "The best of all is, he wont have to study any more," said Tom Harding; "I wish I knew, though, just what he's do. Sing this minute."   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  141 "Singing, of course, if he's gone up to heaven," said a little girl. "That would be hard work for me, for I never could steer straight through Old Hundred," said Tom. "Why, do you think such a boy as you are would go to heaven!" exclaimed another. "Why not?" said Tom, more soberly. "You swear, and you teW lies, and" "Hush!" said Miss Winslow, in a low voice, "wea are getting so near we shall be heard by the people around the house." "Depend upon it," whispered the girl to Tom, " if you die, unless you become a different boy, you'll have no chance to sing or do anything else that good spirits like." "You had better turn your eyes to  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7523-00000071"/> "2    THE RED BRIDGE. home," replied the boy, much excited; "you look in your books when you are reciting, if Miss Winslow does not stand where she can see you; and what is that but cheating?" The girl now hung her head, and was glad to find that they were too near the entrance to allow her opportunity to reply. But when the officiating clergyman af- terward said that we must each die for himself, be judged alone for himself, as though there were not another individual soul in the universe, these children thought of the words they had lately exchanged, and became sorrowful. The house was crowded to overflowing with people; for in such country places, a funeral, even of a child, is an event which   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  143 is observed with rare attention by the neighboring families for miles around. A clergyman has then an opportunity to pro- claim the most practical solemn truths, sometimes to hearts which, else, he has no opportunity to reach. Many people will listen attentively on these occasi9ns, when no consideration would induce them to enter the house of divine worship. Woe to him who shall, then, for the sake of securing local popularity, + Peace, peace, when there are no scriptural grounds for it. Let the chosen preacher of right- eousness, also beware of proclaiming that personal judgment, which belongs to Him who only can rightly read the heart and life. Miss Winslow and her pupils occupied a vine-sheltered arbor, which adjoined the  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7523-00000072"/> "4    THE RED BRIDGE. front-room of the house. There, rustic- seats had been prepared for them,. which were much more comfortable than those in the crowded rooms. On one of these, near the open but half-curtained window, Miss Winslow was sitting, unconscious of her proximity to others, when the low sound of voices in conversation unavoid- ably arrested her attention.  "I understand your son died in great peace and triumph, which must be an un- speakable consolation." Miss Winslow started at the sound of that voice. "Oh, yes, sir, that it is," replied the mother, yielding to a gush of grief. "Our excellent minister heard of his sickness, the day before he died, and was about to come over here, but his horse *! ,ebt i os   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  145 was lame and the arrangement he made to come, fell through for that day. The next morning it was too late. I thought I would bring him here myself, to-day." "Itis very kind in you, Esquire Alton. But I have fo friends in the midst of this great troupe, that God alone could have raised up for me." "You have good-hearted neighbors." "Yes; but Miss Winslow, our school- teacher has been as an angel of heaven to us all, and especially to my poor boy. "Indeed! how is that?" "Why, she told him what it was to re- pent of sin and get ready to die. She spoke softly to him,--so that he heard her, in a good way, and thought over what she said. She came here when he wanted to see her, and she watched with him, one 13   &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7523-00000073"/> "6'    THE RED BRIDGE. of his last nights. He thought much of her, and one of the last things he said was "'tell isHss Winslow, I thank her for all that she has taught me, - most of all, that she has helped me to die.' Yes, sir, it is a great thing to help anybody to die. And my poor Samuel " The mother again yielded to sobs. Esquire Alton being now obliged to make room for some newly-arrived mourners, he went out, and, seeing the company of children in the arbor, joined them. "Is there room for me, here?" he asked in a low voice, "Yes," said the oldest of the boys, there's a seat in the corner." The young lawyer glanced in the direc. tion indicated, and now for the first time perceived Miss Winslow. He bowed,   IMPESSIONS BY THE WAY.   1VI asked permission to occupy the seat nexl her, and then entered into a low conversa- tion respecting how she liked the vocation of a teacher. "It is a noble one," replied Miss Wins. low, " though it has some evils, like all others." "For instance, the greatest of these evils?" he queried. " Are the examination first of the teacht er and then of the scholars, by the august members of the school committee?" The young man smiled quietly, but ap- pearing not to notice the drift of her re- mark, continued,- "I have thought it would be well for all parties if the visiting member of the committee could inspect -he school, incognito." Undoubtedly; for in that way, truth  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7523-00000074"/> "8    THE RED BRIDGE. might be gained, which, otherwise might lie at the bottom of the well," returned Miss Winslow. After a slight pause, she went on with a touch of spirit in her tone:  --"He would not do her the injustice to think her stiff and cold-hearted, when she was only timid and unpractised. Her ap- parent lack of popular cheerfulness would be set down to its right cause." The young committee-man now fixed nis eyes with a searching curiosity upon hers, and, despite his air of the travelled man of self-poised ease, was unmistakably hit by this caustic observation. What he would' have said in reply to this, did not transpire, for at this moment the funeral services were commenced by the minister who stood in the door-way. While the minister went on with his   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  t49 solemn words, Mary's eyes wandered away to the hills and upland orchards in near view; and she reflected that the eyes of her pupil, which had so often taken in the same prospect, were now closed with that seal which no man can open. How soon, at the longest, thought she, will it be thus with my own? Why should I then con- cern myself much about anything, only to fulfil the duty of the present hour with the fear of God ever before me? "Suddenly the Angel of Death knocks at our door," now said the minister, "and sometimes we contrive to keep him out and send him away; but it is only for a season. He returns, and the time, ay, the moment comes when he will not go away without one of our beloved ones bear him company into that land, which, though the 13 * ;  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7523-00000075"/> 150    THE RED BRIDGE, j most .mportant of all realities to us, is yet but a regioln of the great unknown. We waft our sighs thitherward after the dark messenger has gone with our heart's heart, but they return to us void of tidings. Im- plumous, they fly only the length of a this- tle-down, when they fall to the earth with- out even a brush of the edges of the low- est heaven. Inspiration, alone, has power to afford one solid hope to our stricken hearts; and, as was said of old, are the consolations of God small with thee? This is the victory which overcometh the world, yea all things, even our faith, - that faith which is the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen. The author and finisher of this faith is Jesus! Glorious Immanuel! What words pronounced by human lips can set forth   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  lib the blessedness of this name which is above every name! Who dares say in his, heart, 'I will not love and follow this dear Saviour of sinners?' Is there a child here who is old enough to look upon yon- der coffined form of the departed play- fellow and friend, and there read the alpha- bet of death perhaps for the first time, who will not here and now resolve to love the dear Jesus who waits with outstretched arms to bless all those who run to him or but touch the hem of his garment, for sal- vation? "Do you ask what it is to run to Jesus or to touch the hem of his garment, when you cannot see him as the people once saw him on earth among them? It is this,- hasten to give your hearts to him, by seeks ing to do every deed and speak every word  i  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7523-00000076"/> 152    THE RED BRIDGE. which shall be right and good in his sight. Touch his garment by your humble trust and meek obedience. Remember that he once endured the cross, despising the shame, and this not to please himself, but to do the will of his Father. Resolve, then, my dear children and youth, to consecrate your wills to his service and to receive his blessing into your inmost hearts;-that when the Dark Angel shall come for you, however sudden, and he shall say, 'John, or Mary, or Charles, you must go away with me to-day to be seen here no more forever,' you will, though perhaps surprised, be ready and willing to obey, as one who -starts upon a pleasant journey into an un- discovered country, joyful with the pros. pect of going to your beloved Redeemer, where there are only pleasures for ever- more."   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  153 And thus the good man spoke, till every heart around him was moved with the solemn yet intensely interesting realities of life and death. The next day, an unusual thoughtful- ness prevailed among the children, and at noon, they asked Miss Winslow to go with them to their bower beside the wood, for they had some things they wanted to talk about. "We will not gather leaves or mosses, to-day," said one to another; "it is better to learn what we can about what we heard the minister say, yesterday." Miss Winslow was likewise very sol- emn, but realizing her inability to say, of her own self the fitting words to each young inquirer, when they had 'all gath- ered around her in the bower, she proposed  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7523-00000077"/> 154    THE RED BRIDGE. that they should kneel down and silently pray to God. "I never prayed in my life," said Tom Harding,'; and I don't know what to say; I think you, teacher, had better pray out aloud for us all. We will keep still and hark to every word you say." Mary had never prayed before such a company, and she felt abashed at the first thought of this effort. But how dare I refuse," she reflected quickly, " when it is written, Quench not the Spirit!' and the Holy Spirit is evidently striving with these hearts." So she knelt and reverently offered there her soul's desire to Him who has promised to hear while such are yet speaking. Be- fore she had ceased, there were sighs and sobs all around her, from the stricken penit /.   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  155 tents. Afterward, every one of that group had some questions to ask about what they should do to be saved. She pointed them, as best she could, to the Lamb for sinners slain, and recommended each not to give over the struggle in their hearts until they had resolved to be Christ's own followers throughall coming time, and had received the evidence that he accepted them for his own. Several of them then went farther into the wood to pray for themselves. Some of these found unspeakable peace in this sweet exercise of penitent faith. Tom Harding, however, declared that he could not believe anything in these things. "I try," said he, "but all is dark before me. There are some, I find in the Bible, who never become good, after all that is done  . l  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7523-00000078"/> 156    THE RED BRIDGE. to save them. I believe I am one of them."  l Miss Winslow mentioned his case to a pious friend, and also wrote, to Mrs. Comfort respecting him, asking what to do. "I am yet young in years and new in the good way, so that I cannot be ex- pected to have the needed wisdom," she added. "Humbly claim the promise that where two or three are agreed touching any- thing, it shall be done unto them," re- plied Mrs. Comfort. She then named :stated seasons to pray for the divine truth to find' place in the heart of the inquir- ing boy, requesting Mary to observe 'those times in the same spirit of supplicating faith. A short time after this, Tom Harding ' .    IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  157 joined Miss Winslow on her way home from school one afternoon, and though he forbore to speak of the subject upper- most in his mind, his evident manner of seriousness, as though a weight rested upon his spirit, induced her to inquire if he still felt, respecting the consecration of his heart to God, as he formerly had when  conversed with upon the subject. "I don't know," he replied, hesitat- ingly. "Have you prayed for yourself?" "Oh yes! many times." "Do you think God does not hear your prayers?" "-He hears them, but he does 't an swer them as I expected." "How' did you expect?" "  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7523-00000079"/> 158    THE RED BRIDGE. I supposed, by what I had heard peo- pie say, that I should have great joy when I had prayed as I ought to, and this would be because my. sins were for- given," "Some people do not have this joy." replied Miss Winslow. "If you have truly repented of your sins and embraced the Lord Jesus Christ as your Saviour, by a living faith, you have a -right, by his divine word, to call yourself one of his children. The Bible says, 'For ye have not received the spirit of bondage again to fear; but ye have received the spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father'" "What do you mean by living faith?" asked the boy. "It is something like this," she replied. ,            .   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  159 "Two men started in a boat to cross a lake to a certain point where they wished to go. One of them said to the other, 'I will go with you, though I have not the least idea that this boat will' serve to get us across.' "'Why do you start, then?' said the other. "' Because it may just chance we shall get across; and yet, as I said, I have not one wellgrounded hope of doing so. "'If you have so little expectation of success, I should think you would choose to stay on the shore,' observed the one who believed in the boat. "' If I stay, I shall be destroyed by the wild beasts, it is certain, so I have made yu my mind to make the trial of getting across.'  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7523-00000080"/> ; 1^60   THE RED BRIDGE. "'I have not one doubt but that 1 shall get across, because the man who owns the boat said it was perfectly safe,' replied the other. "Now,' in the one case, you see," said Miss Winslow, "that the man had a faith which was living and worth much to him. The other had a sort of faith, but a dead one at the best. It is just so in your present state. If you do not be- lieve that God hears your prayers, when you go to him as he has commanded, although you may pray, it will jbe a dead faith." "But it is so hard to believe," said the boy. "In that case you must say as did one of whom we read in the Holy Scripture: "ord I believe; help thou mine un- belief."   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY.  161 "Did the Lord hear such a prayer as that?" asked Tom. "Yes. He hears all the sincere yearn- ings which go up to him from all the varied, imperfect hearts of his creatures, and from the abounding perfection of his grace dispenses blessings according to our  necessities, in the plan of Infinite Wis- dom." "I can't see it, exactly," observed the boy. "You know how all the plants of the earth of whatever kind, small and great, if they hae enough of life in them, are nour- ished and strengthened by the sun? Well, they get the nourishment and strength just in proportion to their capability of receiv- ing it, and their favorable locality. If they are in deep and dark shadows, they es- "  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7523-00000081"/> 162    THE RED BRIDGE. cape the precious blessing of the sun's rays. So, if we have any divine life in our hearts that enables us to look upward towards God, he blesses us With his  grace, unless we are in the ungenial shade of sin and worldly-mindedness. We then have but an unnatural, sickly growth, of- ten die before our time, or else become encumbered with the fungus of vice, and so have but a useless existence at the best." "It is so hard to understand," Tom said, as he was about to turn off towards his home. "No; you need not try to understand in order to be good enough to be ac- cepted by God. You have but to look and live. The way is so plain, you can- not err therein. Only make up your   IMPRESSIONS BY THE WAY. 163 mind to start in it, and what wisdom you need as you go on, will be given you, day by day. Will you try'?" "Perhaps I will; but I am troubled with many hard thoughts." "Leave them all behind you." "If I only could!" "Have you ever read about Christian at the Wicket Gate, in Pilgrim's Prog- -ress?" "No, ma'am, I haven't." "You must read it, then, as I have it with me at my boarding-place. I will bring it to you to-morrow. Good-by." The boy hesitated to go on. At last, he called after Miss Winslow, saying, "Couldn't I go along now and get that book?" "Certainly, if you like," said Mary, do ,  . -     -    . -  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7523-00000082"/> 164      THE RED BRIDGE. much pleased to discover the interest of her pupil,--one, too, whom she but ree cently would not have suspected of this. It was now  within a few days of the close of her school. One project, which had been upon   her mind, was yet un- developed.  This was to impress upon her pupils, in some way, the imperative necessity of being whole-hearted friends to the holy cause of temperance.    How to present the subject, so as to rightly attract these young minds, was a ques- tion now frequently revolving in her mind. There were, apparently, parents in that district who would oppose any such at- tempt.  She resolved to make  this a special subject of prayer.  '      *     VI. -amirnaton gag. HE Roman emperor who had his own figure painted on a canvas, one hundred and twenty feet in height, must have experienced that "touch of nature " which " makes him kin" to the smallest school-child on that memorable occasion,- examination day. It is this great event which brings out the numer- ous capabilities of the beautiful, the use- ful, and the intellectual, which else might lie latent, so far as the recognition of the surrounding world is reckoned. What heart not wholly devoted to cynical self. ism, can fail to throb with pleasure on (165)  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7523-00000083"/> 166    THE RED BRIDGE. beholding the little boys and girls, and the great ones as well, all nice and fresh in their equipment for the "last day" of the school. Bodies and minds are en- veloped in a beauty which is accompanied by a satisfaction, such as, perhaps, no other scene in after life can eclipse or even equal. There they were around the old school- house -under the butternut-tree, or within its sweet, clean room, which had been adorned with garlands and pretty rural devices "too numerous to mention," wait- ing for Miss Winslow to make her appear- ance at the top of the hill--the first point where her recognition was pdssible. At last a straw hat with black ribbons, under a black parasol lined With white, made its appearance. A half-dozen of the Tr.   EXAMNATION DAY.    167 girls were off immediately to meet and es- cort her to the door. "How beautiful she is in her spotted white-muslin!" said one. "So trim  and so spruce!" observed another. "And such splendid hair!" was heard from a third. "I know what makes them call her all these fine names," now spoke up Tom Harding from an open window, at which he stood gazing after the crowd. "How is that?" asked a boy beside him. "It's because she has been real good and kind to us.' If she had been cross and ugly to us all summer, her gown would have been like a toad's bask, and her hair as horrid as the sun's in our old Farmer's Almanac."  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7523-00000084"/> 168    THE RED BRIDGE. "But then, Miss Winslow is a nice. looking person it can't be denied," said the other. "All in the way you look at things, you may depend!" "How shall we look at you, then?" "As a lion, wild and free in his native jungle. My mother sometimes says to me,' Thomas, my lamb, go and do this or that.' I can't bear to hear it. I hate to be called a lamb." "Perhaps a cub would be more in char- actery". Tom now resented this speech by be- laying his companion after the style of similar boys in his situation. In the me- lee the boys fell against a smaller one who was not spry enough to escape the circuit of the combatants. Thereupon a   EXAMNATION DAY.    169 high scream was heard to pierce the trano quil morning air. By the time the teacher and her fairy-like attendants had entered the school-house, the scene was enough to appal the angel of beauty and order who was supposed to preside over this choice occasion. "What has happened?" queried Miss Winslow of the little child who ran tow- ards her in his affright and tears. ' Tom Harding is licking John Roe, for he called him a lamb or some such thing." "'Twas a cub I called him," said John, now disengaging himself from Tom's grasp and pushing back his hair from his flushed forehead. "And I wasn't a-going to bear it," con- tinued Tom, laughing," we'd a done well 15  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7523-00000085"/> 170    THE RED BRIDGE.  enough, if we hadn't hit that great calf there!" Another gush of grief from the newly- injured boy who had been set down in the beastly score of affronts, prompted Miss Winslow to announce in a tone of authority that all these words and ac- tions must cease. "Thomas, I am very sorry, for I had thought better things of you!" she said, looking on him so reproachfully he turned away with an unmistakable look of regret. "It is too bad," said the girls, " when we had "got'everything so nice and fine, ' and we were so proud to have teacher see it all, to think those great boys must spoil all the first good effect!" "Just, too, over a few animal names, exclaimed one of them, "when they arc all a set of noisy creatures at the best.'   EXAMNATION DAY.   171 "What do you call us?" inquired Tom, reappearing with an air of good-humor. "I call you," said one of the elder girls, "the serpent who appeared in the beautiful garden and spoilt all their fun at the beginning." "Very good. That's bully," said Tom. "Call me anything but a lamb. That is so soft." "Do you not remember," said Miss Winslow, "that our adorable Redeemer is compared to a lamb in one place in holy Scripture; while in another he is called by this name? How can you affect to despise a name which was so dear to him that he said in accents of the utmost tenderness to one of his dis- ciples, 'Feed my lambs'? I had hoped that you were one of these precious ones, .  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7523-00000086"/> 172    THE RED BRIDGE. for whom the Lamb was slain from the foundations of the world, and that you were now fed by the heavenly manna of which, if one eat, he shall hunger no more." I'  "I didn't mean that," replied Tom, "but our Saviour was also called the Lion of Judafi, was he not?" "He was thinking about Daniel Web- ster, who was called the lion of the north," said his sister. "No I wasn't, said Tom, coloring. "Never mind now what he was thinking abouit,' spoke Miss Winslow, who had compassion on the boy's confusion. "We are all thoughtless at times, so that we need the charity of our felldw-beings, most of all, of Him who knoweth our hearts. Thomas, let me dismiss this subject by giving you one text to remember, Serv-   EXAMNATION DAY.   173 ing the Lord with all humility of mind.' Acts xx. 19." The children were now called to take \their seats. Miss Winslow took a few moments before the arrival of the visit- ors to say to them as follows: "I trust that none of you will be guilty of such rudeness as to stare at the people, either upon their first appear- ance or afterwards. Whoever may come or whatever may happen, do not ex- change smiles, or in any other way be- tray an emotion of ridicule. This laugh- ing at others' peculiarities is a mark of weakness of mind and badness of manners." She then called upon one of the younger pupils to give what she had just told them in his own language,-- which was her custom when she wished 16 *  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7523-00000087"/> 174    THE RED BRIDGE. to impress any observation of importance, not less for the good of the individual called upon, than for the benefit of the whole school. Joseph May, a pert lad of nine years, stood up and said, "You don't want any of us to look at the folks that come, as though we were all wild beasts who had never set eyes on any- body afore to-day." A universal laugh now interrupted the boy, and Miss Winslow was obliged to hide her own smiles behind her fan. "But," continued Joseph, emphatically, "if any of 'em have on anything ever so queer, or make a mistake and set down on the floor instead of a chair, we are not to move a nose of our faces more'n as thoughi we were at a funeral."   EXAMNATION DAY.    175 "And what is laughing at the pecu- liarities of others?" continued the teacher. "'Tis a sign of-of a soft head and a -The boy could not quite tell the rest. "Any one?" said Miss: Winslow. "A rotten heart, " said another. "That phrase is too inelegant," she said. Tom Harding now raised his hand. "What will you say of it, Thomas? ' "It's a mark of a boor and a bear, both." A loud knock was now heard on the door. Several of the parents and friends of the children had come. Arrivals con- tinued until the old house was crowded, for, to the rare praise of this district, be it recorded that they cultivated such an inter. est in the common education of their chil- dren, that few events had for them more scope for attention than an occasion like  &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7523-00000088"/> 176    ,THE RED BRIDGE. the present. Two of the committee had arrited, but where was the third,--the young lawyer whom Miss Winslow had been anxiously expecting for the last half hour? "Something has probably newly occurred to prevent his being here, to-day," whis- pered one of the official gentlemen to Miss. Winslow; "but you had better proceed, for he will not be likely to appear now, as he is usually very punctual." Mary would not have confessed to her- self that she was disappointed at his non-appearance; but the fact would have been evident to an eye-witness of the emotion of her secret heart. Mary had taken unusual pains with her pupils in their reading. She would not have assigned the reason to have been   EXAMNATION DAY.    1" the real fact of Mr. Alton having called  especial attention to the importance of- this exercise being rightly managed. He was a fine reader himself, and appreciated good reading. She had hoped that he would have been present to have wit-  i nessed the results of the efforts made in this regard during the term.  But one class after another was examined, yet he did not come. There was yet her first class, with which she had taken so much pains. She would defer this till just before recess The half-hours flew by. 'Every one did their best, even better than Mary had ex- pected. "If he had only been here!" she thought. It was getting warm, and the fans of the lady visitors did effectual service; but ,/  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7523-00000089"/> 178    THE RED BRIDGE. their interest flagged not. Everything was orderly, nice, and sometimes so novel in its procedure, they thought not of weariness. Now there was a heavy step on the old door-stone; then a knock with a cane. Mary's heart fluttered. It might be Esquire Alton, after all. She was glad that Tom Harding had not declaimed yet, and that the oldest class had not read. Mary went to the door with a light step. "Friend," spoke at strange, hollow voice, from under a very wide-rimmed white hat, "I was passing along here on my journey, and, from what I saw and heard, I con- eluded that this was the closing of thy' school. Will thee suffer a tired traveller to turn in and rest awhile under thy roof?" ( Certainly, sir," answered Mary; "walk in." She then led the way within the ins   XAMTNATION DAY.    179 ner room, and assigned the traveling Friend a seat next the gentlemen of the examin- ing committee. But he said, "I will take a lower seat," and stationed himself on a chair near the water-pail by the door. It was well that the scholars had received such preliminary training, but a short time ago, respecting the propriety of not staring nor laughing in the presence of unexpected and odd-looking individuals. For this man, with his coal-black beard and long black hair under the curious hat which he did not remove from his head, his long, drab- colored coat and his sharp-toed shoes with silver buckles, was almost enough to move the risibles of better-trained muscles than those of the children around hin. "He is a shaking Quaker," wrote one of the girls to her seat-mate.  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7523-00000090"/> 180    THE RED BRIDGE. Rather an itinerant beauty," was writ ten back. "I guess it is Jeff. Davis, come as a spy," whispered one of the boys. "He looks as if he could take all the free States through this school-house, by passing round his hat," said another. Miss Winslow tapped with her pencil and motioned her pupils to preserve or- der. "I wish this man had kept out," she said to herself. "His very presence in- fects the whole school with just what I warned them against. They were doing well till he came in among. us." The sons of God, in Job's time, could hardly have been more disturbed by the appearance of their unbidden guest. The committee left off watching the classes   FXAMTNATION DAY.    181 n their new  interest in the strange Quaker. But the object of all this stir pre- served the tenor of his ways with most exemplary equanimity. He noticed none of the curious glances, but made up for the visitors' diminished interest in the classes by bestowing a double share him- self. At recess some of the boys said, in so loud a voice it must have been heard by the subject of their remarks, who con- tinued to sit near the open door, "If ever I had to hold on to keep rrom laughing, it was in there; but I reckoned it would hurt Miss Winslow, af- ter what she said to us, so I just looked away from old Broadbrim, and thought 16  &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7523-00000091"/> L82    THlE RED BRIDGE. of the cucumber-vines over across the road, which I could see from my seat." The writing-books, maps drawn by the pupils, with the school-register, were now passed around, when, on their coming to the stranger, he took out his spectacles from a large steel case, and, carefully adjusting them, examined the books with a notice which was very complimentary to all the interested parties. The time came at last when Mary de- clared her part of the exercises of the occasion finished. The gentlemen of the committee then exchanged several loud- ly-whispered communications, after which the oldest one, who was a much-re- spected clergyman of the town, rose, coughed a little, placed his chair before him, and began by saying, that he was   EXARINATION DAY.    183 much gratified to see the large and in- terested company of spectators present on that occasion. Meantime he looked very frequently in the direction of the open door where sat the strange guest. He then said several other things, which had reference to their proficiency, good appearance, and, decided success; but as the time was rapidly passing away, he would give way to his friend of the committee, who, he trusted, would be followed by other visitors, who might have a word to add on the occasion. The "friend of the committee" said pretty much what he had said a score of times before on such emergencies, hoping that they would not lay aside their books during the long time which intervened before the fall school, and that  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7523-00000092"/> 184    THE RED BRIDGE. they would be grateful to the kind friends who had thoughtfully provided such lib- eral advantages for their securing an education in the morning of life. There was then a long pause, when an invitation was again extended to any friend present, who might have some- thing edifying to offer on that occasion. The strange Friend now slowly Lose from his seat, while he took off his spectacles and deliberately placed them in the case, which he shut with a loud snap, then, folding his arms behind his back, began accoringly: "Friends of thy town and friend Mary Winslow, as I perceive thou art named in the register of thy school, with all these young friends about me! in behalf of a plain people who love the good common- 7   EXAMNATION DAY.    185 school, I take this opportunity, most unex. pectedly, to greet ye all! "I judge ye have done well in the past, each in his place, teacher and learner; may ye do as well in the time yet be- fore ye. We read that there was once a statue of black marble set up in Thebes in Egypt, to the memory of Memnon, and that, when the earliest rays of the dawn struck upon this statue, it would give out sweet tunes, as if rejoicing. Now, this marble statue may be compared to the human mind, and the earlier the rays of knowledge strike on it, the sweeter will be the tones in response. By and by, When the sun was up in the heavens, the dark marble was doubtless very beautiful in the golden beams, but there were heard no gentle, rapturous notes of harmony. +  ,26 #r r  &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7523-00000093"/> 186    THE RED BRIDGE. "Possibly it gave out true responses, al. most like a god, when men came to it for wisdom; but it made no music only early in the morning. So must ye, my young friends, look at the fountain of wisdom early in life, also early each day of that life, and early in the opportunities of that day. 'Know your opportunity' said one of the seven wise men of Greece. And the saying is good for each of us, to-day. Never let slip an occasion to get or to do good by thy delays. "Remember it is the first ray of the dawn that brings out the music. Now, if any of you'have reasonable plans for the future, strike on them at the earliest opportunity, and not put them off till thee lose thy chance." Here our strange Friend ceased, which /   EXAMNATION DAY.    187 was well, for his voice, being as peculiar as his outer garb, excited the merriment of the school and even some of the spectators Miss Winslow was much pained at these demonstrations of disrespect to one, ap- parently so many rears their senior and withal a stranger. The Quaker saw that he was ridiculed by nearly all present, except the teacher, and taking his cane, he bowed to her, and then made a movement to go out. But an afterthought detained him. Turning back once more, he said-"Friends! though all of you except thy pastor and thy teacher, are discourteous to the de- spised Quaker, one day ye will know he is able to do ye good or ill." He then walked away. When the exercises had all concluded,  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7523-00000094"/> 188    THE RED BRIDGE. and the company had left, except one or two of the parents who resided at a dis- tance, and waited without the door, to be accompanied by their children, Mary re- sumed her position in the desk and after distributing the prize-books to those pupils who had excelled in their several classes, she said she had something to present to each of thedm, provided they would accept it and write their names, each pupil, on the gift. Every eye now kindled with a new interest, and there was a general sen-  sation throughout the school. "I hold in my hand a box which con- tains just as many juvenile Temperance Pledges as there are members of this school," she continued, at the same time opening the box and displaying the beauti- ful pink, blue, orange, and red cards on   RXAMTNATION DAY.    189 which was printed the Pledge. "NoW, JI propose that we form ourselves into a little Temperance Society, as a memorial of the close of this pleasant term of school, and every girl and boy who is willing to join in this good work will sign his or her name to the card, and then keep it as a testimonial of their interest in this holy cause and alsoq of my regard for each of you." She then circulated the cards among them, saying that a few days previous she had sent to an energetic and wise advo- cate of temperance for pledges, and these had been the result, with a cheering letter, which she proceeded to reac aloud. The children read upon the cards:- i "Oh, if for me the cup you fill Then fill it from the gushing lill."   &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7523-00000095"/> 190     THE RED BRIDGE. PLEDGE I I, the undersigned, do agree to abstain from the use of ALL INTOXICATING DRINKS, as a beverage; and will use my influence to persuade others to do the same. I also agree to abstain from the use of Tobacco, in any of its forms." "What say? will you sign?" asked one of the boys of Tom  Harding, in a loud whisper. "I think not. I like to smoke father's pipe, and a cigar now and then," said Tom. "And I," said another, "like the wine which we make from our grapes." "We can drink cider, if we do sign this?" asked one of the boys of Miss Winslow. "No, indeed," said one of the girls, "for I have seen- people just as near drunk as a body could he, on old cider."                  .Y   EXAMNATION DAY.    191 "Anything which is fermented, if drunk in sufficient quantity, can intoxicate," spoke Miss Winslow, "and some pelple think that cider produces a worse effect on the temper than even wine or other liquors."  "I guess I can't sign," spoke up a little boy, "for I drink lots of cider and chew cuds, too, whenever I can get them." A heavy step was now heard in the entry. It was doubtless one of the parents who had been listening beneath the open windows.  Mary's heart sunk within her. "It is all a failure after my pains to get the pledges and leave a good work well rounded in this place," she said to herself.  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7523-00000096"/> 192    THE RED BBIDGE* The door opened and a pale, haggard man, who trembled in every limb, stood before them. Mary would not have recognized him, had not one of the scholars said to her seat-mate so loud as to be heard, "It is old John Wilkins, what used to be our Sam's father." A hush pervaded the whole of that group for it was no common spectacle which met their eyes. John Wilkins was now rarely seen beyond his own door. Forme y, long before the memory of the oldest of these children, he had been a thriving, capable man, but "intoxicating drinks" had wrought ruin both to his property and health. He had been con- sidered for some years as partially insane, and had it not been for his unusually '   EXAMNATION DAY.    193 smart and energetic wife, everything which nominally belonged to him, would have hopelessly sunk to the depths of wretchedness. "Boys," said he, extending his quiver- ing hand, "do any of you stop about signing that pledge? I came here to see your teacher once more, and'I heard out there what you said. If you feel now that you can't give up the accursed stuffs,-the rum and the wine and cider as well, with tobacco, why, then, now look at me and see what you'll come to, one day. I have been a mean, wil- fiul slave to all of them, and shoulod have died a fool or a crazy man, if it hadn't been for what I promised wher my poor boy died, this summer. I'm now mis- erable old John TWilkins, good for noth- 17  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7523-00000097"/> 194    THE RED BRIDGE. ing to myself or anybody else.  Mv strength is all gone so that I can hardly feed myself. And I'm the most to be pitied of anybody there is around here. What's done it all? This drinking and smoking! "Do you want to grow up just such curses to your folks, as these things will surely make you? "Why, what do you suppose it would have been worth to me, when, I was a boy like you here, if somebody had come along with one of these pledges, and I had signed and then kept it! It would have made me a man with a thriving farm, a plenty of money in the bank that I could have educated my' children with, and kept my poor, abused wife something as respectable folks keep their   EXAMNATION DAY.    195 wives. Oh dear!"-  His voice faltered, and he burst into tears. The children began, likewise, to cry. Tears were seen in the eyes of the teacher. "My poor boy- little Sam, that's dead and gone - suffered dreadfully with shame over his drunken father. I've seen him slink back when anybody came along, and beg of me to hide away, too, I used to be so ragged And wretched. And I I beat him- yes, I have whipped him when he spoke to me about it"- Again he yielded to his sobs. "But my poor child is now where he wont have to be ashamed of drunken folks. He's got on a clean robe, a white robe "- "My dear children," now spoke Miss Winslow, " if you had seen what I have  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7523-00000098"/> 196    THE RED BRIDGE. seen from the effects of drinking strong drink, you would welcome these pledges as bright messengers of peace and good fortune. Turn over the cards and see the other side. Thomas, you will please read aloud from the back of your card." Tom  Harding looked rather abashed as he read in a loud, firm voice:- "Who hath woe? who hath sorrow? who hath contentions? who hath bab- lings? who hath wounds without cause? who hath redness of eyes? "They that tarry long at the wine, they that go to seek mixed wine. Look not thou upon the wine when it is red, when it giveth his color in the cup, when it moveth itself aright. "At the last it biteth like a serpent, and stingeth like an adder."   EXAMNATION DAY.       190 "Taste not I hear what wisdom saith; Should'st thou taint thy pure, sweet breath  Quench thy young eyes' lustrous light 'Neath its baneful, blasting blight? No, by God's sweet goodness, no! Taste not! Bid the tempter go." "TOUCH  NOT THE UNCLEAN THN." Oh, forge no fetters for thy soul' From evil habits flee; Yield not thy youthful heart to sin Its strength may master thee." "I'll take  a tred one, Miss   Winslow and  please to  lend me your pen," said Tom, as he finished reading. "And  I," said another, "want a    blue card to put my name on." ' It's dreadful hard to give up dad's old pipe, and the cigars," was now heard in another direction, "but for the sake of the thing it can be done." "Smoking don't do    no  hurt," put in 17 *  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7523-00000099"/> 198    THE RED BRIDGE. some one, at this juncture; "if it did, our folks, I guess, would have been hurted clean dead." "Smoking, or chewing," said  Miss Winslow, "is a vile habit, which injures the brain, the stomach, and the nerves. No man nor youth, who yields to these practices, can be what he would without them. Besides, think of the expense of these things! The money you would spend in this way, would get you quite a library in a short time." "I'm in for the beautiful pledges," was now the general cry. Old Mr. Wilkins now advanced a step, and looked around him, with a smile struggling to come out on his face. "Walk forward, sir," said Mary, "and take a seat with us."    / EXAMNATION DAY,    199 "I've not lived quite all my life in vain, after all," he said; "this sight does my heart good." "I rejoice that you came here," said Mary;" and I hope that your angel-boy is now where he can see us.  There must be joy in heaven to-day." Tom Harding went around among the boys and girls, pen and ink in hand, urging where it was necessary, and when they were too small to write, carrying the cards to Miss Winslow to write their names. At length, he cried out, "They've all signed, Miss Winslow." Mary then expressed her gratitude for the noble act they had done, reminding them of their dependence upon God for strength to keep the promises they had  &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7523-00000100"/> O0    THE RED BRIDLE. solemnly made. All then bade her fare- well with much tenderness. Tom  Har- ding, in a low voice, told her he had made up his mind, also, to be a Chris- tian. "Pray for me that I may escape hell," were Mr. Wilkins' last words to her. She was enabled to say appropriate words to each. On entering the door of her boarding- place, she was not a little surprised to find the strange Quaker there, partaking leisurely of milk, bread, and cheese. His hat was still on his head, and she had been in the room some little time before he showed any consciousness of her pres- ence. At length he turned towards her and said,- "A philosopher has written, 'Patience   REXAMNATION DAY.   201 is bitter, but its fruit is sweet.' Thee can now take the opportunity to reap some of the rewards of that virtue." "I fear I do not deserve much credit for patience," replied Mary; " wilittle I owned was nearly all wasted to-aay, at one time." "As how?" "I had given them a careful lesson upon the importance of showing no unbecoming emotion in the presence of visitors. After that, how ill they behaved in that re- gard!" "I noticed that in thy scholars, friend: but since thou didst not lend thy counte- nance to such deportment, it bodes me no ill to speak of. Moreover they were not so much to blame, as they knew not what manner of man I am."  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7523-00000101"/> 202     THE RED BRIDGE. "Will you permit me to inquire, sir, who you may be?" asked     Mary, who had now her curiosity fairly aroused. "That thou mayst do." "Well?" said Mary, adding to herself, "Why don't he tell,-then.?" "It is not expedient for me to tell thee now; but thou shalt know hereafter." Mary was annoyed at this reply, but said nothing, for there was something about him  which impressed her with re- spect, despite herself. "Dost thou have it in thy mind to teach soon again, friend Winslow?" he asked, after a long pause, during which he had been occupied with his repast. "I cannot tell you now, sir," she re- plied. He turned his eyes on hers, to read if K                  ,   EXAMNATION DAY.    203 she, in this reply, were intending to an- swer him after his own style. She looked away, indifferently. "I hope I shall know my opportunity," she added. He smiled, but was silent. The articles of food were liberally paid for, and he rose to go. "Have you far to go, sir?" inquired the lady of the house. "I know not," he said; "the journey of life is uncertain in its length. We are here to-day; there, to-morrow; one man on this occasion, another on that. We are the creatures of change; but as it is written in Ad Populum, 'Let Heaven and Earth, and Angel and Man, and all . change; still, still, Ego Deus non mutor,- God he is the Lord of all, and he chang-  &#xD;<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC7523-00000102"/> 204    THE RED BRIDGE. eth not.' Farewell, Mistress Swan, and friend Mary Winslow." He was gone. "How did he know  your name?" asked Mary of Mrs. Swan, the woman of the house. "He is crazy!" exclaimed that woman with an alarmed air. 'Let me look to it that my silver is all safe. Where is little Jackey?" indicating her youngest child who was just old enough to toddle about. She sprang hurriedly to look out after him. ' There he is," said Mary," walking off up the hill with that man, who leads him by the hand. They are talking together like old friends." The frightened mother darted quickly away after her boy. "Jackey, Jackey, Y    EXAMNATION DAY.    205 come right home!" she cried. The stran. ger stopped, looked back with unfeigned surprise at the advancing mother, then motioned the child to go to her. But Jackey now set up a loud cry to go on with the Quaker. "The despised stranger is understood by one, at least," he said, as he resigned the child into his breathless mother's hands. "All he knows," said thq mother, impa- tiently leading him away. That night all the doors in that neigh- borhood were fastened with greater care than usual, and Mrs. Swan, as she averred, never shut her eyes to sleep a single wink. For several days after, inquiries were made if any one had seen a mad Quaker anywhere on the up-town road, or if there 18  &#xD;<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC7523-00000103"/> 206    THE RED BRIDGE. had been a new-arrival at the poor-house of late? Miss Winslow concluded that he was a traveling agent for some beneficent or ed- ucational institution, and by no means agreed with the general opinion of his insanity. She had gone away to spend her vacation with an old school-friend who resided some twenty miles distant from the locality of the district-school, when she received a letter in a handwrit- ing unfamiliar, yet not wholly unrecog- nized. She hurriedly opened it and read as follows: "Will Miss Winslow pardon. the bold design, with its successful execution, by the 'absent member of the school-com- mittee,' that considered observations taken   EXAMNATION DAY.    207 Sincognito' would prove more valuable to one, who, in some unaccountable way. had fallen under the ban of her ill prej- udice? "The Quaker garb, inherited from the maternal grandfather, with the aid of hair- dye, proved useful if not beautiful. "Impressions were thus received of char- acter which no other 'opportunity' could so abundantly have furnished. As con- sent was first obtained to the incognito, it is reckoned that all has been done fairly. "Respectfully yours, "HARRY ALTON." "Was ever anything so trying!" ex- claimed Mary on reading this letter. "To think I did not mistrust him, while I  &#xD;<pb n="208-209" xml:id="VAC7523-00000104"/> 208    THE RED BRIDGE. /  tthought I was patronizing an unpretend. ing wayfarer!"  She looked farther and saw a post- script:-. "If it is not asking more than I have any right to, I shall reckon it a favor to have this little episode a la the 'Knight of the Green Plume,' retained undisclosed to my fellow-citizens around me." * Some young ladies would have an- swered this by a long, elaborate epistle; but after considering the matter, Mary decided that she should not continue the correspondence, unless formally invited to do so. There is nothing gained by forestalling matters, or by pursuing any slight advan -I   EXAMNATION DAY.    209 tage which may chance to occur of this kind," she said to herself; "besides, I trust I have wisdom enough to know that my 'opportunity 'is not to be seized, but rather accepted when presented to-me by the unmistakable hand' of Providence. 18* 9  &#xD;<pb n="210-211" xml:id="VAC7523-00000105"/> VII. anminzar'g Sife, CIE  next find Mary at Blenheim Fe' , male Seminary,--one of many A)' popular resorts for the young la- dies of our land, some of whom desire to obtain an education, while others are satisfied with the name of so doing. She was admitted on these conditions: -to be a member of the senior class, which would graduate in one year, and also have the charge of several classes as instructor. After her graduation, if nothing transpired to prevent, she was to be engaged as a regular teacher. Her straitened circumstances, pecuniarily, ren- (210)   S SEMNARY LIFE.    2" dered this arrangement especially fortu- nate. It is sometimes the case with reliable persons that their lot is cast with the giddy and uncertain ones, for the sake of the general good; and so Mary was assigned by Mrs. Harrison, the Principal, to room with Miss Wallingford, a gay young 1ady from the neighboring city. As this girl was generally popular with the members of the school, her influence which set at first in favor of Mary, proved of good service add contributed not a little to the establishment of a feeling of content and satisfaction in her desolate heart. Everything seemed new to tend to. wards her prosperity, for she succeeded, even beyond her expectations, both as a  &#xD;<pb n="212-213" xml:id="VAC7523-00000106"/> 212    TEE RED BRIDGE. pupil and teacher. She was resolved, as was the habit of her life, to throw her whole soul into her work; and her life was devoted, day by day, to the fulfilment of her duties, in the most creditable man- ner. Her career as a student bade fair to be more brilliant and satisfactory than that of any other member of the school. But life has lessons for those who watch the order of divine Providence, of which she had learned scarcely more than the alphabet. One of these is, that "Every branch which beareth fruit, He purgeth it that it may bring forth more fruit." Another is, "They that live godly in Christ Jesus must suffer persecution." Mary supposed, if she did' well in all respects, every one would acknowledge. her goodness, by using her fairly and on p    SEMNARY LIFE.    213 terms of love and confidence. But no soonef ad her excellence become con- spicuous, than the evil eye of Envryfell upon her with its blight and blackness. She had ever conducted towards her room-mate with irreproachable friendli- ness, but, after a time, that young lady began to wonder within herself why she was not respected and admired by teach- ers and pupils as- much as was Miss Winslow. From this she came to think that her room-mate gained more of popular favor than was her right. And, without being herself aware of the sinister spirit she had suffered to enter into her heart, she watched for an "opportunity to cut away some of Mary's desirable founda- tion on which she rested in Blenheim Seminary.  &#xD;<pb n="214-215" xml:id="VAC7523-00000107"/> 214    THE RED BRIDGE. The opportunity was slow to present itself, for Mary was ever so kind and obliging, withal so faithful in the dis- charge of her duties, it was not easy to find entrance into her reputation. But, one day, Miss Wallingford was slightly ill, arid required the aid of her room-mate, which had always been cheer- fully given. Miss Wallingford was touched with gratitude at Mary's great kindness on this occasion, and her feeling of envy was fast giving place to a nobler one, when, happening to remember her old habit at home of dosing with wine, in order, as she averred, to invigorate her system, she asked Mary to procure her some for her present use. "Wine will do you no good," said Mary.   SEMNARY LIFE.    215 "Oh, yes, chum," said Miss Walling- ford; "I have taken oceans of the best quality at home. You don't know what you are talking of, when you say anything against the proper use of wine." "I know something about the effects of it," replied Mary, "though never from my own use of it. I would as soon take poison myself." "Well, then, get me sorme brandy, if you object to wine," continued her room- mate. "That is even worse," replied Mary. "What spirit do you choose, then?" asked Miss Wallingford; * "None," said Mary, emphatically. "What! not in case of sickness?" "There may be cases of disease," she replied, 'when certain spirits, prescribed !  &#xD;<pb n="216-217" xml:id="VAC7523-00000108"/> 216  -  THE RED BRIDGE. by a careful physician, prove a benefit; but these, in my opinion, are very rare, -much rarer than generally supposed. I have known some of the worst cases of inebriety to have been the result of a habit of drinking liquor, first authorized by a physician." "But don't you suppose a doctor knows better than you do?". said Miss Walling- ford, laughing derisively. "I pretend to no superior wisdom," Mary went on, "and I think that many intelligent and, conscientious physicians would agree with me that the use of liquor, even as a medicine, should be very cautiously recommended. We are such creatures of appetite and impulse, that none can foretell the results of apparently very harmless beginnings in the use of   SEMNARY LIE.     217 strong drink. In most cases, if these re. suits could be foreseen in their startling. reality, the bane would be totally eschewed froin the first." "I have taken a glass of wine before going out to a party, or any such place, many a time, to set me up when I have felt down at the mouth," said Miss Wal- lingford, "and it did me a world of good, I assure you.  Mother and I always go to the closet for some sherry as soon as ever we get into the house, after a long, tedious morning of shoppipg, round town. Sometimes, she prefers a little good gin, and [ some equally good Madeira. Oh! I wish had some, now.  The next time I go  ome, I'll bring out a bottle of wine."  The bell having rung at this moment,  [ary went out to attend a recitation, and  1 9   '   i     . '  &#xD;<pb n="218-219" xml:id="VAC7523-00000109"/> 218 I   THE RED BRIDGE. no more was said upon this subjec that day. On the following day, Miss Wal. lingford was out among the girls, and Mary occupied the room, for the most part, alone, save during the inevitable evening study-hours. One of Mary's most congenial friends, had, been Ellen Rice, the daughter of a physician, and, soon after this time, she began to miss her accustomed calls to walk with her in recreation hours: On going to that young lady's room to see if anything had happened, she was pained to notice a slight change in her manner, and she plead imperative engagements which would prevent her from accompany- ing Mary. Although she occasionally called on Mary, after this, yet it was evident that she was no longer the good 4   SEMNARY LIFE.    219 and true friend she had formerly been. A certain coldness and want of entire confidence, however much she attempted to conceal it, characterized her manner towards Mary, which wounded her sensi- tive spirit to the quick. It was not long before Mary thought she perceived a similar absence of cor- diality in other of her former friends, but as she was unaware of having given occasion for this manifestation, and fear- ing that she was becoming suspicious without cause, she hastened to reassure herself that affairs were really better than at present they appeared. The Literary Society connected with the institution at this time, proposed to hold a public meeting. As Mary had been an efficient and valued member  &#xD;<pb n="220-221" xml:id="VAC7523-00000110"/> 220    THE RED BRIDGE. since her coming to Blenheim, she was requested by the President to prepare a colloquy, in which a number of the mem- bers could appear on that occasion. After some demur, Mary undertook the task. When a short time had elapsed, it was written and submitted to the committee of the society. It was a scene illustrating the evils of intemperance, and, being writ- ten with much spirit and taste, was pro- nounced exactly what they wanted. The whole affair, however, as was customary, was kept as secret as possible, save with those directly connected with its repre- sentation. When the evening arrived for the exercises to come off, before a large and intelligent audience, the temperance colloquy excited considerable expectation, as it had escaped among the people gen   SEMNARY LIFE.    221 erally, that this piece was strikingly origin nal and interesting. Miss Wallingford now  envied her room-mate more than ever, and her hos- tility was no longer disguised under the thin veil of politeness. When she read Mary's name upon the programme, as the author of the colloquy, she exclaimed scornfully to a group of her companions, --"Well worthy Miss Frogalette Croaker. who thinks all the wisdom of the sages is boiled down into her own head." "What kind of liquor would you call it, then?" asked another, who was listen- ing with pleasure to Miss Wallingford's remarks; "not spirituous, certainly?" "Sap, or the juice of liquorice," said Miss Wallingford. 19  \,'  &#xD;<pb n="222-223" xml:id="VAC7523-00000111"/> 222     THE RED BRIDGE. "Why, what makes you    so caustic, Belle," now asked one of6-the group. "You would be caustic, if you   had roomed with Madam   Frogalette as long as I have. A more selfish person it has never been my ill-fortune to encounter. I asked her to go to the store to get me something I particularly wanted, when 1 was sick, one day, and, do you believe it, she actually refused." "Possible!"  "I could not have be- lieved it!" exclaimed several voices. "She says a great deal in her Sunday school class against the sin of selfishness," now spoke up one who wass a member of the class, and who had hitherto re- garded her teacher with much confidence and affection. "I dare say," said Miss Wallingford, *   w            Xn   SEMNARY LIFE.    223 "as it is always the way with those who talk the loudest, their private deeds are the most contemptible." "I sh ll not appear in her class any more, for I will not lend my countenance to deception," thought that young lady, "and yet I have always loved her dearly," came likewise into her reflection. The audience being called to order, a period was put to this conversation. The innocent and unconscious object of these poison-shafts of envy now appeared upon the platform. Ah! there was new food for the insatiate foe; for, lovely as Mary ordinarily was, never had she appeared so exquisitely charming as on this evening. Her simple dress of white, without orna- ment, was most befitting her classic style of face, framed by a wealth of dark hair,  &#xD;<pb n="224-225" xml:id="VAC7523-00000112"/> 224    THE RED BRIDGE. which school-girls term "' perfectly magnifi. cent." Her eyes large, of a dark blue, and somewhat sad, were the chief attraction of her else beautiful person. These in- dicated a pure, elevated, and consecrated soul. Her assignment was now the opening address, which, being well written, and read in an impressive, yet modest, and perfectly womanly style, elicited unusual applause. Several choice bouquets signalized her de- parture from the platform. On reaching the ante-room, one of these arrested the notice of her companions, as it contained some of the costhest flowers of the season. Beautiful, exceedingly!" cried a young lady; "and see, Mary, here is a note hidden ,among the leaves!"     ^   SEMNARY LIFE.    225 Mary hurriedly opened the  delicate missive and read -"From friend Incog. nito." "Is it possible that Mr. Alton is here?" she exclaimed to herself; (I should not have read with any repose, had I known that he was' among the audience to- night." She soon recovered her usual tranquil- lity of spirit, although occasional flashes of curiosity, respecting the presence of Mr. Alton, kindled the latent interest in her heart. When the colloquy came on, she re- tired by a back passage communicating from the building, and, borrowing a veiled hat and shawl, entered among the audi- ence, and made her way to a seat, wholly unobserved and unrecognized. She wished  &#xD;<pb n="226-227" xml:id="VAC7523-00000113"/> 226     THE RED BRIDGE. to make observations from this position; and also to hear the criticisms of some of the auditors, which else might not reach her ears. As the scenest went on, every one seemed to sit almost breathless, and it was observed that some of the per- gons around her were affected even to tears. In one of the pauses, two voices *of gentlemen in a seat just behind her own, attracted her attention. "Harry, there's truth in this bit of literature. I wonder where the authoress of it obtained her characters. You say you have met her before?" "Yes; but do you remember our old college friend, Harmon? He died with delirium tremens, last spring." Marv started at the sound of this voice, which she recognized as that of "Friend'   SEMNARY LIFE.    227 Incognito." Her first impulse was to look around, and see of a truth that it was really himself. But a second thought held her motionless. "Harmon was a splendid fellow, if it hadn't been for drink. I was afflicted when I heard of his death. How well I remember of his urging you to drink with us, and your inflexible No!" said Alton's companion. "I do not regret my negative. It saved my life once." * "As how? "When I was in Germany, I was sick of a dangerous fever. Finally, they all gave me up. I sunk lower and lower, and my attendants pronounced me dead. 'Let us pour some brandy down his throat,' said the physician. At this, I made a des-  &#xD;<pb n="228-229" xml:id="VAC7523-00000114"/> 228    THE RED BRIDGE. perate effort to rally; the idea of being choked to death did not agree with me. I knew all that was going on ; but [ could not move to save my life. They got the brandy and begun to force open my mouth, when I roared out such a decided No, my doc- tor dropped the liquor all over my face, and"- At this juncture a new scene of the col- loquy commenced and the conversation ceased.  By and by, the gentleman said to his companion, "Alton, I begin to think you know more about this young lady than you choose to divulge." "I wish you had kept your programme," eturned Alton; "I want to see what these scenes are called and how they come along." Mary remembered her own crumpled   SEMNARY LIFE.    229 programme in her pocket. She withdrew it, and wrote thereon with a pencil. "I'd like to catch a glimpse of her again. Haven't seen her since I threw the bouquet," now spoke Alton. "Would she understand the incognito?  At this moment the scene closed; Mary rose from her seat, her face still closely covered with a brown veil. "Madam," said Mr. Alton, reaching for- ward, "will you oblige me by lending your programme a moment?" Mary bowed slightly, and gave it to him. She then passed out. He took the sheet, and his eyes rested directly upon a writing in pencil on the blank space around the scenes of the colloquy.' He read, "The bouquet is gratefully acknowledged by kcognita." 20  &#xD;<pb n="230-231" xml:id="VAC7523-00000115"/> 230    THE RED BRIDGE. "Did you notice that lady who just left the seat here in front of us? ' asked Alton, hurriedly, of his companion. "That horrid thing, in a stifling, umber. colored veil?" ' She could not have been horrid." "Why not? for she certainly was." "That was the writer of this piece,- Miss Winslow," said Alton. "Possible!" returned his companion. "Let's see,- did we say anything that it would be -awkward for us to have her overhear?' "In return for my incognito, it appears she was executing the incognita. I can forgive her, however, since she has ren- dered-such good service to the cause of temperance." "Yes; this little performance was a capital thing."   SEMNARY LIFE.    231 When the exercises of the evening were concluded, Mr. Alton waited with his friend, hoping to see Mary again. She did not make her appearance, and, as it was already a late hour, he was forced to leave without the desired meeting. He was stopping with an old college ac- quaintance in the adjacent city, and hear- ing of this public meeting of the Literary Society, they had rode out. Previously aware that Miss Winslow was a member of this institution, this opportunity had  been gladly accepted by him. On the following morning, a letter came to Mary from her old friend, Mrs. Comfort, requesting her to accompany the bearer to a city some miles distant, and there pass the coming Sabbath with Mrs. Comr fort and her friends. Mary gladly obeyed  &#xD;<pb n="232-233" xml:id="VAC7523-00000116"/> 232    THE RED BRIDGE. this summnors, for her heart throbbed with new pleasure at the prospect of again beholding the face of her friend. Mrs. Comfort had planned a little excur- sion for that afternoon, which she thought would prove pleasant and useful to Mary. It was to make a visit of inspection to the U. S. Armory. Ever thoughtful of the pleasure of others, she had exerted herself to effect arrangements so that Mary might have this privilege. She met her young friend with the same cheery laugh, which, in the past, had so often lightened Mary's heart. "I thought this bit of change would do you no hurt, seeing that you must be pretty well occupied out there at the seminary," she said. "How few persons," said Mary, " ever think it worth the while to invite a teacher ,   SEMNARY LIFE.    233 away from the dreary round of their op- pressive cares!" "I suppose," returned Mrs. Comfort. with another of her expressive smiles, "that most folks think  that teachers have such an easy and perfectly delight- ful time in their own " spear, it is not best to attempt to dispel their fond delusion. I've heard some say, too, it was best to keep teachers down, lest they should be lifted up with a sense of their superiority." "I only wish," said Mary, "that such persons would exchange lives 'with a teacher for just one month. Perhaps they would think there was less danger of "- "Taking'an excursion on an elevator," interrupted Mrs. Comfort. "Oh, well," she continued, in a lighter tone, ".every place in life has its trials, and if it was * 20*  &#xD;<pb n="234-235" xml:id="VAC7523-00000117"/> 234    THE RED BRIDGE. not for earth, as my father used to say, we shouldn't know how to appreciate heav- en. Then, let us make the best of every. thing and love everybody, you know." "I am happy to say," concluded Mary, "that since I have been a teacher, I have found some friends who are a most honor- able exception to the majority of whom we have been speaking. And if blessings can descend upon those for whom we ask them, from full and overflowing hearts, surely plentiful will be their reward." Of the numerous objects of interest, ancient and modern, connected with the armory, one building awakened Mary's curiosity more than everything besides. She was told by one of the attendants, as she with her party approached, that it was the place of deposit for the guns used ir the recent war. *'.  - ' f*   SEMNARY LIFE.    235  A powerful sensation stole over her whole being, as a cloud passing before the sun causes a shadow to fall across the landscape, which, but a moment be- fore, had been bright with the ghlden rays of the mid-day sun. Memories of her brother, --his words as she saw her initials upon the breech of his gun, and her last look upon his beloved form, possessed her heart, so that she had scarcely strength to go on within the building. "If he had only lived," she reflected, "I know he would have been a good man, for my  earnest, agonizing prayers to Heaven, in his behalf, would have been heard by Him, who can touch the soul with the true, vitalizing power of refort mation." Striving to conceal her emotion,  &#xD;<pb n="236-237" xml:id="VAC7523-00000118"/> 236     THE RED BRIDGE. she entered that building with her friends; though like one half in a dream. The sight of the rusty, blood-stained muskets and carbines, with the thought of the his. tory which each would reveal, if it had a voice accompanied with intelligence, was enough to excite an imagination much less highly-wrought than hers. On every side she turned her eyes, there they were, piled closely together, or standing in dense files, like grim ghosts of the grimmest episodes of a civil war, or like skeleton sentinels of the long, bloody array of ap- palling facts in the past, over which, like herself, mothers, sisters, children, and friends had wept blinding tears! "Dear William! my brother! would to Heaven I had died for you!" she cried, in the Aesolate anguish of her spirit.   SEMNARY LIFE.    237 Half falling'down upon a step, she cov- ered her face with her hands. "Come, Mary," said Mrs. Comfort, "we are going down into the basement to see the old guns there. To be sure it is pretty much what we have seen; but then one wants to explore all there is, you know." "Excuse me, this time," replied Mary. "Oh, no," she cried from below, having now descended the stairs which led to the cellar, come down, and find for yourself how delightfully cool it is here. It is so warm everywhere else to-day, it will do you good." As Mary went downi, a cold shiver, almost like that of death, struck her frame. The descent into a sepulchral vault would hardly have impressed her more solemnly. Through one of the open north windows  &#xD;<pb n="238-239" xml:id="VAC7523-00000119"/> 238    THE RED BRIDGE. a pale light came in sufficiently to make the muskets in that direction distinctly visible. "If the Peruvians," said a gentleman of the party, "thought that gold was 'the tears wept by the sun,' we may well call these guns the groans wrung from mortal anguish, grim despair, and a fierce sense of underlying wrong." 'Mary cast her eyes backward over a dense mass, in the farther part of the cellar, which was just enough enveloped in the darkness to heighten the effect of sublime mystery, which shrouded all that place like a heavy pall of supernatural gloom. A divine chord in. her soul vibrated in unison with the stillness, the indistinct- ness, and the consciousness of these sur- rounding memorials of war and carnage,   SEMNARY LIFE.    239  so that she saw what no other there could perceive, and felt that of which they had no conception. The past, with its sad processions of sacrifice, or its yet sad- ler paeans of triumph, was there, dimly, but with a terrible earnestness, to confront and sicken. The grief of comfortless hearts, for the moment, was communicated to her own. She trembled  ke a plant, smitten with the chilled wind of uncongenial skies.  "You have too much sensibility," said Mrs. Comfort, passing her arm around her, and gently leading her forward, near the open window. "See this gun," said one of the gentle- men, taking one which lay a little de- tached from the mass; "' it looks as though it had known service. There's blood on  &#xD;<pb n="240-241" xml:id="VAC7523-00000120"/> 240     THE RED BRIDGE. 's that breech! And here are letters." tHe -took out his handkerchief and rubbed them. "M. W.," said he, slowly. "Precious tokens of some loved one," said one of the ladies. While he had been doing this, Mary had pressed forward, and eagerly strained her eyes upon the gun and the letters on the stock. No sooner were they pro. nounced than she fell forwards, as if lifeless. All the ladies, except Mrs. Comfort, were in consternation. Her form was borne above stairs in a state of insensi- bility. When she was partially revived, she murmured, at intervals: "O  William! why did they not spare you?  Surely,   SEMNARY LIFE.   .241  .+- you would not have touched the fatal cup again. A sister's tears and prayers would have stood between you and ruin. Dearest one! speak to me once more!" It was the work of hours to restore  her sufficiently to be taken away. Inquiries were afterwards made respect- ing the circumstances of that gun being ' found there; but, as it was only one of a ',:t vast multitude, nothing definite could be ascertained.  &#xD;<pb n="242-243" xml:id="VAC7523-00000121"/> VIII. il   es. FTER the public meeting of the Literary Society, in which Mary's success had been so brilliant and decided, she found Miss Wallingford more unamiable than ever; and the few who. had evinced coldness towards her were now gathering numbers daily. It soon reached Mary's ears that several of this party, among whom was Miss Wallingford, had taken offence on listening to the tempers ance colloquy, for the reason that they believed it had personal allusions to them- selves. One of the most prominent of the pupils declared that she must have (242) *    - REVEiSES.     243 intended to take her off, and she was overheard to promise that Miss Winslow should suffer as much as she had caused her to suffer that evening, and since, whenever she had thought of it. Mary was deeply pained on learning some of these accusations, and hastened to visit the offended parties, and offer them all the explanation in her power. But the more she said, the more unrecon- ciled they became. There was an im- penetrable coldness in their manner; their faces were set against her, and nothing that she could do or say had any effect to mollify their asperity. Had she been less gifted, and less conspicuous in her success, all this would have been passed over as of little consideration. But now they were determined that she should pay dearly for her superiority.  &#xD;<pb n="244-245" xml:id="VAC7523-00000122"/> 244    THE RED BRIDGE. Miss Wallingford having desired the Principal, Mrs. Harrison, to assign her another room, as she no longer wished to room with Miss Winslow, one of the youngest and most uncongenial pupils was placed with Mary. This, she felt was not only unpleasant, but disrespect- ful, yet her sense of dependence forbade her remonstrance. The effect of these unpleasant occurrences was to renew her zeal in acquiring proficiency in her studies, so that her progress continued decidedly in advance of' all her classmates. It was now the close of the second term of the school year. There was an undis- puted prospect of the highest honors of the senior class falling to Mary. As this class was more numerous than any pre- ceding one, it would be a success of more  .  .   REVERSES.       245  than ordinary attraction. And this would also strengthen her claim  to the much- coveted position of instructor, she reflect- ed with much satisfaction. The present vacation was to be a short one, and Mary resolved to improve it by recruiting her overtasked energies.  Her room-mate had gone home; relief from daily, irksome restraint was intensely de- lightful, and she planned the accomplish- ment of not only neglected duties, but a few simple enjoyments, one of which was the setting in order her plants which reminded her of the dear old home in Blendale. "Then like a bow long forced into a curve, The mind, released from too constrained a nerve, Flew to its first position with a spring."' It was the second evening of the vacat 21*  &#xD;<pb n="246-247" xml:id="VAC7523-00000123"/> 246    THE RED BRIDGE. tion. Mary was sitting in her room, look. ing over some old letters which her father had written her when she was scarcely more than a child, away at school, when her eyes fell upon this sentence, penned by the beloved hand now mouldered to dust:--"My dear child, it is by trials we ever attain true success. This is the inexorable law of our being. Therefore, when they come to you, remember, how- ever sharp and strong they seem, they are a part of the divine plan, whereby, in infinite mercy, you may conquer." "I did not understand these words, when I first read them, nor yet fully years after," she thought; "but now, it must be I have some adequate idea of- their real spirit and significance." A knock upon her door interrupted her   REVERSES.      247 reflections. A message had come from Mrs. Harrison, requesting her' to go to that lady's room. She obeyed with a glad heart, for, conscious of her recent success as both teacher and pupil, she thought that the interview must be unusually pleasant. "Perhaps," she reflected quickly, "she is going to make an arrangement, so that I shall be allowed a little com- pensation next term, in order to defray the increased expenses attending my grad- uation." On entering Mrs. Harrison's room, she was motioned to a seat, and some minutes elapsed before the business in hand was communicated. hat lady seemed much preoccupied with he examination of some papers which lay on the desk before her At length, raising her eyes, while they  &#xD;<pb n="248-249" xml:id="VAC7523-00000124"/> 248   . THE RED BRIDGE. continued partially averted from Mary, she said, 'I regret that I have unpleasant news for you, Miss Winslow." Mary started, and a cold chill struck her heart, for, so many unexpected shocks had already been her portion, she knew what these words portended more than one without experience could have fore. seen. "And yet," she quickly thought, "as Mrs. Harrison sometimes indulges in a little facetiousness, it is possible she takes this way to announce exactly the con- trary of what her words signify." "It seems," continued Mrs. Harrison, now turning her eyes fully upon Mary, "that we shall be obliged to dispense with your services here." Mary could hardly believe that- she ' r        .   REVERSES.     249 heard aright. Aweight, like ice, fell upon her spirit, so that she sat motionless with- out saying a word. "Complaints have recently been brought to me, from some of my best patrons, against you, so that it will be for the good of the school, and for all parties concerned, to have our present connec- tion cease at this time," continued Mrs, Harrison. "'Complaints against me!", Mary now found voice to say, while the expression of her countenance affected Mrs. Har- rison, despite all her efforts to preserve entire composure. The bruised reed withered suddenly beneath this libation of nitre. That powerful acid which has a solvent power over gold, the king of the metals, and hence derives its name  &#xD;<pb n="250-251" xml:id="VAC7523-00000125"/> 250    THE. RED BRIDGE. of aqua regia, finds its parallel in the sudden announcement of bitter import to a sensitive and superior nature. The imperial waters of affliction, when held to the. wan and rigid lips, have a taste of the olden words heard by the stricken ones in the garden,-"In sorrow shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life." Yes," replied the lady, I am exceed- ingly sorry to learn that you have caused disaffection among many of our ladies. The course you have taken here respect- ing 'temperance, though doubtless well intended, shows an error in judgment which is irreparable." "This surprises me," returned Mary, "for I am not aware of any such intention. I thought I had used unusual caution, and I wondered when some of the young    .         .   REVERSES.     251 ladies seemed to take offence at the colloquy." "Before that," said Mrs. Harrison, "it appears that you were imprudent in your observations, -so much so as to wound your room-mate and Miss Rice, with some others, who had been your warm friends." "Miss Rice!" exclaimed Mary, "there must be some mistake, for I certainly never exchanged a word with her upon anything which had any relation to that subject." "You have forgotten," observed Mrs. Harrison, waving her hand, impatiently; "for Miss Rice is a lady who would not be guilty of falsehood." "Did she tell you this?" inquired Mary.  &#xD;<pb n="252-253" xml:id="VAC7523-00000126"/> 252    THE RED BRIDGE. "It is unnecessary for me to relate to you all the details of this unpleasant affair, Miss Winslow, but I have author- ity when I say that you have offended Miss Rice, in some observations respect- ing physicians prescribing ardent spirits for medicine." Mary remembered her conversation with Miss Wallingford, and she could now account for her former friend's cold- ness. She related the circumstances to Mrs. Harrison, who listened, apparently unmoved. "It appears, likewise," continued that lady, "that some of the characters and scenes in your colloquy were taken, by a number of persons present, as most inex- cusably personal." "I intended to represent nothing but   REVERSES.      253 what I had learned before coming to Blenheim," replied Mary, "and regret to find," she added, with a touch of asperity in her tone, " that the coat, so innocently shapen, proved a fit to any person here, and especially to any of my own sex. If they had not acknowledged the fact, I should not have suspected it. The course they have taken towards me not only illustrates their guilt, but their unquali- fied meanness and inferiority of soul." "This is not an occasion for recrimi- nating remarks on your part," said Mrs. Harrison, "for I cannot allow aspersions to be cast upon some of my most liberal and respectable patrons, I may call them. They are offended so as to threaten to leave the school if you do not withdraw, and you see what is my only alternative." 22  &#xD;<pb n="254-255" xml:id="VAC7523-00000127"/> 254    THE RED BRIDGE. "Have I not been a faithful teacher since my stay here?" asked Mary, with renewed feeling., "You have done very well in your classes," said Mrs. Harrison, coldly. "I must be allowed to say," continued Mary, after a painful silence, "that this seems very hard to me.  Without a home, without friends, no prospect be- fore me -when I had planned to stay here and graduate, and then "- Her voice failed. "You  should cultivate self-control, Miss Winslow; though, when the first ebullition of feeling has passed, you will, doubtless, resume your accustomed serene manner, which, I must say, I have al- ways regarded as highly creditable to you. ,   REVERSES.     256 "It is now so late in the season, it will be impossible for me to secure another situation where I can teach, and you are already aware of my narrow circum- stances," said Mary. "I know it would have been better for you to have known this before," said Mrs. Harrison, "but I thought, to avoid any unpleasant excitement, it would be most expedient to inform you after the term had concluded. Last year, when one of our teachers was going to leave, there was so much confusion in getting up a presentation for her, I deemed the most quiet course, in your case, the best for all parties." Mary looked at Mrs. Harrison steadily for a moment, as if to convince herself that she was not mistaken in her identity, then said, -  &#xD;<pb n="256-257" xml:id="VAC7523-00000128"/> 256    THE RED BRIDGE. "May the time never come to you or to any of yours, madam, when words will smite your heart, as yours, this evens ing, have smitten mine." "You had better retire now," said Mrs. Harrison, turning white about her lips, "and you need not leave here for two or three days, if you do not find it con. venient before. Good-evening." She turned her back and resumed the examination of her papers. When Mary had returned to her room, the great disappointment which  had come to her seemed   well-nigh over- whelming. But to the child of God there is a present help in time of trouble. The moonlight, which streamed into her window, fell over her form as she knelt there in her woe and desolation, J  I      * *  I  *1   REVERSES.       257 and poured out her soul in prayer to God -yea, the  orphan's God!   "My  help cometh from the Lord, which nrade heav- en and earth," she cried in the language of the Psalmist, "He shall preserve thy going out and thy coming in from   this time forth, and eveior evermore." For hours of that night she remained in silent communion with her heavenly Father, the Keeper of Israel, who " neither slumbers nor sleeps." At last there came to her mind a part of an old hymn, which was a favorite one with her father: "He over-rules all mortal things, And manages our small affairs; On humble souls the King of kings Bestows his counsels and his cares. "Our sorrows and our tears we pour Into the bosom of our God; 22   &#xD;<pb n="258-259" xml:id="VAC7523-00000129"/> 258     THE RED BRIDGE. He hears us in the mournful hour, And, helps us bear the heavy load." She was partially comforted. Hope sprung anew in her fainting soul, Ibr she believed that her present affliction was permitted by One whose eye was on her lot, and who would cause all these things to work together for her good If the prophet Daniel, in the gardens of the palace of Susa and on the banks of the Ulai, saw visions which clearly foreshadowed the career of Alexander, how much more do the angels of these little ones, beholding the face of their Father, contemplate the divine plan, and  al- though in its devious windings it may display a strange conjunction with seem- ing evil, they comprehend all, but to won. der, love, and praise!   REVERSES.      259 "Truly," may the devout heart exclaim, "the Lord is good and his mercy en- dureth forever, to such as keep his cove- nant and love his testimonies." "I wonder how she feels now," reflected her enemies, as they sat in their homes among their loved ones,-"for by this time she knows she has got to go away from Blenheim. I guess she will conclude that we are as smart and powerful as she is." The triumph experienced by evil and ignoble minds in the result of successful envy and base revenge constitutes the keenest joy of th(eir existence; but, as it is the nature of all sinful passions to soon consume themselves with their own fires, leaving only the ashes of satisfaction, such triumph is short. Godlike passions, alone ,   &#xD;<pb n="260-261" xml:id="VAC7523-00000130"/> 260    ThE RED BRIDGE. possess the power of perpetual life and delight. Love, forgiveness, mercy have the divine element of immortal good. If any one is disposed to doubt this, let him open the soul to the free entrance of these angel-virtues; and this, not alone in beautiful theory, but in the practical result of a bitter experience of wrong;- then shall he understand that the *iohest and most profitable of all the good and perfect gifts which come from the Father of lights, is even that embodied in the unequaled words, "Forgive them, for they know not what they do."  Mary had many friends, but none to whom she felt at liberty to apply for ad- vice in this emergency, but Mrs. Comfort. As in the great Prototype of sorrow, it may be written of most persons in their eonduct   REVERSES.      261 towards the one who is suddenly over- taken by calamity, " they all forsook him and fled." Some souls "stand aloof to see what will come of it;" if anything transpires to render the side of the suf- ferer popular, they are loud in their as- sertions of favorable regard; but if, on the contrary, the tide of fortune appears to bring up a continued augury of ill, --"they always thought so,"- and are careful to pass by on the other side, on the principle that " self-preservation is the first law of nature." Mrs. Comfort, however, was in no-wise of this ilk. Afraid to defend the cause of the innocent and meritorious, however temporarily overshadowed by dark clouds? -it was not in her thought, far less in her practice! She rather gloried in tribu-  &#xD;<pb n="262-263" xml:id="VAC7523-00000131"/> 262     THE AtED BRIDGE. lations both for herself and her best friends. They offered new scope for the exercise of her fertile invention, which could make the most and the best of difficulties; and never was her cheery laugh heard to ring "Iike the true metal" as when she found herself, as she expressed it, "in a strait betwixt two evils, --one on each side." She therefore lost no time in replying to Mary's note, which stated her difficul- ties, as follows:--  MY DEAR GIRL,- "It is an ill-wind that blows nobody any good, as my father used to say. Can't you see that it is all for the best, which has happened to you at Blenheim?  Your heavenly Father has something better for you to do than to stay there any longer,    REVERSES.      263 submitting to so much unpleasant drudg- ery, and so he pulls you out, although it goes hard to your present feelings. What your enemies meant for your evil will turn out for your good, and this, I dare say, in no ordinary degree. There are always times when the spirit of evil ap- pears to get the upper hand; so that, as I used to read in my old Spectator,- "' The doves are censured, while the crows are spared.' "The first thing you had better do, is to pack up all your things; don't leave so much as a pin behind, and come right here where I live as soon as ever the cars will bring you. 'If they persecute you in one city, flee to another, and shake off the dust from your feet as a testimony against them.'  &#xD;<pb n="264-265" xml:id="VAC7523-00000132"/> 264    THE RED BRIDGE. "I met that young committee-man again, that I saw in the coach when I was on my way to visit your school last;year. It was at a friend's in. the city. His name is Alton, I believe. He, with the son of my old friend, had been out to attend some public affair at Blenheim, a few days before. He spoke of you, and when he found that I. knew all about you, he asked me forty-eleven questions, or less. The reason he gave was that he wished to engage a teacher to assist in the High School in his place of residence, and thought you would be just the one. I told him I thought it would be of no use to ask you now to go, as you intended to remain, where you were and graduate. ' He said he had called to see you on the day following that evening; but your   REVERSES.     265 roor-mate had told him that you had gone away.  "I think it would be well for you to write to this Mr. Alton now, and let him 'know that you would like the situation. I hope it- will not be too late. "Whatever shall come, keep up a good heart, and a stiff elbow. In haste, "Yours, in all kinds of weather, "HANNAH COMFORT." Mary received this welcome letter with a glad heart, and lost no time in address- ing Mr. Alton, respecting the school. Having formally applied for the situation, she stated that necessity compelled her to engage in teaching as soon as possible, so that if this place was lost to her, shA 23  &#xD;<pb n="266-267" xml:id="VAC7523-00000133"/> 266    THE RED BRIDGE. would be glad to secure one of the district schools in his town, adding a hope that it would not prove too late in the season f6r her success. Mary took her departure from Blenheim amid the tearful benedictions and regrets of all the domestics of the establishment. "What can have happened to send such a lovely young lady away from here!" cried one to another. "Never the likes of her shall these eyes see again," exclaimed the Irish cook. Beautiful creature! may the saints in heaven defend her from all the harm in this life, and bring her safe to dwell in heaven at last." These words from her humble friends were not a slight consolation to her wound- ed spirit. Mrs. Comfort was now engaged in take   REVERSES.      2()7 ing a few select boarders, as a means of obtaining a livelihood, and as she was far from being bountifully furnished with provision for a subsistence in her declin- ing years, Mary keenly realized the extent of her rare kindness, in this act of her hospitality. It was her frequent prayer that the time might come when she could repay her benevolent friend. She could ill conceal her anxiety to hear from her application to Mr. Alton, and it seemed that she would become a victim to a fit of illness, so intense was her suspense at this time. "It isn't time yet for a reply to your letter till to-morrow at the earliest," said Mrs. Comfort;" and my advice to you is to take all the peace and pleasure you can while you are here."  &#xD;<pb n="268-269" xml:id="VAC7523-00000134"/> 268    THE RED BRIDGE. "But I feel that I am such a burden to  you," said Mary. "Fiddlesticks!" cried Mrs. Comfort, rve not yet got so old that a grasshopper is a burden, as the Scripture says. It seems right good to have you with me. Since my daughters married and went away, I miss their society very much, and you are next to them in my heart. Now I think of it, I don't know what I should have done these days, if you hadn't been here to cheer me up." "A letter for you, miss," said the car- rier, the following morning. Mary took it with trembling fingers, while the color quickly forsook her face. She recognized the handwriting, at a glance. The much wished-for intelli- gence was now about to come. Would   REVERSES.      269 it be favorable or otherwise? So much was depending for her, she had hardly strength to open it. She read:- "HIGHBRIDGE, April 5th, 186-. "MISS WINSLOW:- "Dear. Friend, - for such may I ven- ture to call you? "Yours of the 3d inst. is received and its contents noticed. Allow me to in- form you that the vacancy in our High School has just been filled. All the dis- tricts, so far as I can learn, have already engaged their teachers"-- Mary saw that other words were writ- ten, but a mist came before her eyes; the letters swam in darkness. "Why, Mary! what's the matter? Are you going to faint, away?" cried Mrs. 23 *  &#xD;<pb n="270-271" xml:id="VAC7523-00000135"/> 270    THE RED BRIDGE. Comfort, who sat attentively watching her countenance. When Mary recovered her conscious. ness, she found herself lying on a lounge in Mrs. Comfort's own room, while that lady sat beside her, laughing so irnmod' erately, Mary scarcely knew whether to be astonished or grieved. "Dreadful strange things come tq pass when we least expect them!" said Mrs. Comfort, bestirring herself to induce Mary to take another draft of the peppermint- tea which her maid had brought. "Mrs. Comfort! how can you find a heart to make light of my misfortune, though you are so cheerful generally!" said Mary, now yielding to a gush of tears for the first time since she had been called to this series of trouble.  J . .     r   REVERSES.     271 "Do you know," she sobbed, "that he offers me no prospect of a situation?" "As soon as I saw that you were coming-to in Bridget's arms, I took up the terrible letter and hastily ran over its contents. You did not read far enough, child." Another laugh, accompanied by a queer look of satisfaction, caused Mary to in- quire if he had mentioned any other place where a situation was obtainable? "He has made you an offer of some- thing better than a school," said Mrs. Comfort, handing her the letter. "What can it be?" asked Mary. "Read for yourself, now, and forgive me for getting the news first," replied Mrs. Comfort. Yes, it was true; something better than I   &#xD;<pb n="272-273" xml:id="VAC7523-00000136"/> 272    THE RED BRIDGE. a school was offered to Mary in that let. ter,-even the heart, the hand, the home of Harry Alton. It seemed that he, too, was an orphan, without-brother or sister, but with an inheritance, which the people of Highbridge used to call "as rich as a Jew," she remembered. His home was that mansion on the hill overlooking the village, towards which she had sometimes cast her eyes, on wending her way to chur6h, when she taught the lonely dis- trict school, and thought the owner must indeed have cause for gratitude. And, as she saw him among the people of God when they observed the sacrament of the Lord's Supper, she said in her heart, that the crown of his good fortune, was his fidelity to goodness and truth. Now, in the' hour of her utter ex.   REVERSES.     273 tremity, all this, with the pure and noble heart in unison with her own con- cerning those interests so dear to her, was laid at her disposal, in language so deli- cate and considerate of her feelings, noth- ing more could be desired. Was she not dreaming? There were the words before her, and there, too, was Mrs. Comfort with such a cheery face, no words can do it the least shadow of justice. "What do you think now, Mary? Does God desert those who put their trust in him?  Is he not even better than his most excellent word?" she said. "When my husband died in the midst of a prosperous people, who seemed to think everything of him as their pastor, and left me with young children, it did seem rather dark to me. We were poor,  &#xD;<pb n="274-275" xml:id="VAC7523-00000137"/> 274    THE RED BRIDGE. and my health was quite miserable then. But I was enabled to hope and toil on. My boy, on whom I depended to see me through in my old age, was taken next. One after another they were called home, -all but my two youngest daughters, the last of whom was married last year to a minister. I have a great deal to be thankful for, and I've made it the rule of my life to make the best of every- thing, and to love everybody, so far as I could. But it's been dreadful hard work sometimes." Mary had many things in her over. flowing heart which she would have said to Mrs. Comfort, in this moment; but she durst not trust her voice to speak. She covered her face with her hands, and silently prayed.   IX.  IT was one of the coldest mornings of the cold winter succeeding the events of the last chapter, that Mary bade good-morning to her husband as he started for his office. "It is going to be a stormy day," he said, "and you, with Mrs. Comfort, must see to it that Margaret keeps the house warm, and especially the conservatory, so that the plants do not freeze." "I wouldn't have the three, that Mary used to keep at Blenheim, freeze, for the price of a term's tuition there," said Mrs. Comfort, laughing. (275)  &#xD;<pb n="276-277" xml:id="VAC7523-00000138"/> 276-    THE RED BRIDGE. "No; they must be nursed to keep her memory green," replied Mr. Alton. "Be careful that you yourself don't freeze to-day on the street," said Mary, as she closed the door behind him. She went to the window to look after him, as he made his way amid the hur. rying clouds of snow which flew around his slippery pathway. It is a dreadful day," said Mary, "and how glad I am, my dear Mrs. Comfort, that you came to live with us before this severe weather.' "And I, too, am glad, I guess, to get rid of keeping house for myself this cold winter of high prices. But, Mary, what put it into your head to send for me just the time of all others when it did me most good to come?" said Mrs. Comfort.   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  2" "The same good spirit who directed you to be so kind to me, when I most required your aid and comfort. 'What- soever measure ye mete, it shall be meas- ured to you again, " was Mary's reply. Mrs. Comfort's eyes filled with tears. "It is the first time I ever saw you look in that way," said Mary; "it is my turn, now, to administer joy and consolation to you. While I have a home, be assured, my good friend, you shall never want that blessing. You have come here now, Provi- dence permitting, to spend the remainder of your days. You may go out on visits to your relatives and friends whenever you so please, but here is to be your abode, the sanctuary of your home-loves and interests." "But come here to the window," con, 24  &#xD;<pb n="278-279" xml:id="VAC7523-00000139"/> 278    THE RED BRIDGE. tinued Mary, in another tone, for she per. ceived that Mrs. Comfort was much affect. ed. "See how the snow- wreaths, itself around the head of that poor, struggling traveler. He looks almost exhausted in his combat with the storm.  His long white hair blowing in the blast about his haggard face gives him the appearance of some genius of the storm such as I have seen in pictures of winter. His clothes are so poor and scanty, the cold must pene- trate even to his very life. He is coming into our avenue," At this moment a tap on the door of the parlor was succeeded by the appearance of Margaret, the Irish serving-maid. "An sure, ma'am, there's a baste of a villainous thafe a-coming in, an shan't I be afther a-lockin' all the doors?" she asked, excitedly.   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  279 "( He is suffering from the cold, I pre- sume," said Mary, "and we must not turn him away, especially such a day as this, until he is warmed and fed," Margaret went away, muttering about the dangerous thafe, yet with enough good humor remaining to cause her to go to the door and admit the stranger to her kitchen fire. "I must go out and see how Margaret comes on with her guest," said Mary to Mrs. Comfort, a few minutes after. Mary found the man trembling violent- ly, while his ungloved hands which ap- peared unusually delicate, were extended towards the stove. His head was bowed down and he seemed to be talking in a low tone to himself. For a time she could not distinguish what he said, but  &#xD;<pb n="280-281" xml:id="VAC7523-00000140"/> 280    THE RED BRIDGE. she addressed him, when he seemed suf. ficiently composed. "You found it very cold walking this morning. I hope you have not far to go?" "'For as when merchants break, o'erthrown Like ninepins, they strike others down,' were the words of the poet. Madam, you have heard of the poet? Well, he knew how a man felt when he was struck down." At the sound of his full voice, Mary started. There was a familiar tone which fell upon her ears. Whose was it like? But, as he remained with his head down, so that his face was nearly concealed by his slouched hat, she could only conjecture the stamp of the man whose words were so unusual.   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  281 "(He is clane daft," whispered Margaret.' "for sure if he wasn't beside hisself, he'd niver be after talkin' the likes o' that, ma'am." "Wont you have something warm to take, - some ginger tea?" now asked Mary. "Something to drink?  Ah! woman of the delicate brow, you don't know what you say. Something to drink has brought me where you see me now." He had lifted his eyes fully upon hers, so that she could see his face. "I am what I was not. I am poor, perishing, wretched. I was once richb munificent, flourishing, joyous. It doesn't take long for liquor to bring a man where you see me to day, without a home or 24* /   &#xD;<pb n="282-283" xml:id="VAC7523-00000141"/> 282    THE RED BRIDGEO friends. But my home was once better than yours." "I know it," replied Mary, in a calm voice,'though her heart was ready to cry out in its surprise and grief. She sav that the poor wayfarer was crazed, and she wished for time to reflect on what course it was best to pursue. He was recognized. It was her old guardian, even Gilbert Jameson! But it must not be known, at least by her serving-maid. "Where is your home now?" she in- quired. "A certain passehger at sea" says -the old fable, "had the curiosity to ask the pilot of the vessel what part of the world he called his home? Replied the pilot,- "Tis where the angel in the Revelations was,-one foot on the land, the other on   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  283 the sea.' Thus, madam, is it with me. I, B flat, live at C sharp, and L long, reversed." Every other question which Mary asked, in order to learn something of his present history, was answered in a similar style. He did not seem to know her; and .of this she was glad. At last he asked for a cup with a little water, which being given him, he with- drew a bottle from his pocket, and plur- ing out some whiskey, mixed it with the water. Half afraid to remonstrate with a man opt of his senses, Mary hesitated to speak the words which trembled upon her tongue. But when she saw him pre- pare to drink it off, and remembered the fearful night when she had watched him in a fit of delirium tremens, she felt that something might now be ventured  &#xD;<pb n="284-285" xml:id="VAC7523-00000142"/> 284    THE RED BRIDGE. With prayer to God for strength in her heart, she fixed her eye steadily upon his, and said, in a decided voice, - "Sir! hear me now a moment. It was * but a few years since you were a gentle- man with those about you who looked up to you with regard. Strong drink has brought you where you now are." "But I lost all my property by being bound," he interrupted. "Had you not drank so as to have im- paired your judgment, you would not have been bound to such a ruinous extent." "How know you that?" "I know it, and you know it. Now, why will you continue to take the poison which has reduced you to this? Why not stop right where you are, and try and   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  285 redeem that you flave lost? There is hope even at the eleventh hour'" "Woman, you talk well," he replied, "but you are not so old as you will be if you live long enough. The die is cast. I sink lower and lower every day of my life. I can no longer swim. Not many more days of wretchedness remain for me. So long have I indulged in this habit, which I allow is the ruin of him who once well fixes it in his soul, I can- not turn about now. There is a snake gnawing at my vitals every moment, and the only way I can keep him from eating through to the seat of life is to liquor him every hour. But, for all that, he gains on me. He will kill me before long. Yes, I must drink or die." And he poured down the liquor'with-  &#xD;<pb n="286-287" xml:id="VAC7523-00000143"/> 286    THE RED BRIDGE. out stopping for a respiration, so eager was he for the fatal draught of slow poison. ' Let me go to your stable and lie on the hay," he said, when the fumes of the liquor began to steal to his brain. "It is cold,I know, but I feel warm now. The fire within me burns on through summer's heat and winter's cold. The sky overhead is wrathful to-day. My head is now bound with what Humboldt calls -do you hear, lady? -' differently inflected isothermal bands.'" "Sure ma'am, isn't yees afeard of a crater likes o' that?" said Margaret, in a low voice. But Mary only sighed in re- ply. She remembered there was a lounge in the warm conservatory, and thither she told him to go and sleep for a while. She   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  287 could not assign him'xho had once given her a good home, to the place which he asked. "An' it's mighty quare that mistress takes so much care of the puir drinkin' crater," said Margaret. "Why Mary!" exclaimed Mrs. Com- fort, How dare you trust a stray fellow out of his head, in a place like that!" Have you not often said that we should make the best of everything and love everybody?" replied Mary. When, a short time after, she opened the glass door and looked in upon him, he was soundly asleep. Picture of wretch- edness! There he lay with his hat un- der his head, his finely-shaped brow nearly concealed with his uncombed, straggling locks of gray hair, his coat old and torn, -but his face,- Oh! the expression of  &#xD;<pb n="288-289" xml:id="VAC7523-00000144"/> 288    THE RED BRIDGE. the sleeping drunkard! What pencil, save that which was dipped in the lurid hues of an anaconda's blood, could ever do it justice! The angel of the apocalypse who poured out his vial to scorch men with fire, had passed by and overshadowed him with his fearful plague. Unrest, de. spair, with a gnawing consciousness of the nobler destiny which might have been his own, are chiselled with deep furrows and hideous angles upon his countenance, while the spots of the leprous taint of sin heighten the woful effect. "Oh ye who think that a draught of good liquor is what is right and pleasant, now and then," exclaimed Mary to her- self, "and ye who drink with the dinner because it is in becoming style with your rank, and ye who laugh at the warnings   THF BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  289 against the cheering dram when tired and dispirited, -all ye who deem abstinence from liquorta mild delusion of certain in- feriorly-constituted minds, - would that ye could come now and behold this picture, no! this living reality which I now see, --this great and terrible blot upon the else fair scene around me! "Here, amidst these luxuriant plants and fragrant, delicate flowers, which bend gracefully beneath their burdens of waxen beauty or roseate glow like the hearts of the fairest sea-shells; these long sprays of bell-shapen blooms with their tiny treas- ures of gold; these thick and ever-aspiring vines, clambering over their trellises of wire and rosewood; these great urns from which wander the greenest of moss, vying with the richest, costhest velvet,-- lies 25  &#xD;<pb n="290-291" xml:id="VAC7523-00000145"/> 290     H RED BRIDGE. this fallen man, whose nature is divinely originated and whose talents were ranked with the highest quality of intellect, - lies like an idiot, a madman, demented, be. sotted, ruined, all for this one fatal cause, Intemperance  "Would that the eyes of the whole world could be infixed as a single eye and here behold for itself!" fhe went and brought a warm woollen blanket, which she threw over the wretched figure, and turned away to commune with her own heart in its grief. Then she thought of the sacred words which she had once read to her brother: "For they have made ready their heart like an oven, while they lie in wait: their baker sleepeth all the night, in the morning it burneth as a flaming fire."   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  291 "He held the cup to my poor brother's lips," she reflected, "and now he reaps the curse. But I forgive him, and would gladly spare him the punishment which God, in his fearful judgment, wrings out to him. Oh that it were in my power to save him!"  An hour later she went and looked in at the glass door. Still he slept. She then placed a small stand near him, on which were arranged several dishes of tempting food, that when he awoke he might partake of them  without con- straint. Requesting Mrs. Comfort to have him in charge, she put on her warmest gar- ments and went out, notwithstanding the inclemency of the weather. Her errand was to see her husband in his office, for )  &#xD;<pb n="292-293" xml:id="VAC7523-00000146"/> 292    THE RED BRIDGE. she wished to communicate to him what no other of her household must know, Not another lady bad ventured out, and the few gentlemen she met on her way stared as though it must be an important affair to bring her forth that day. But, when the burden which now weighed upon her heart impelled her, she was equally indifferent to the cold blast, or the look of curious surprise. Her husband did not disappoint her il this emergency. The noble heart of Harry Alton was true to her highest convictions of duty. He, who had once befriended her when a needy orphan, should now find friends who would mete out to him, un. mindful of his degradation. He had thrown on his overcoat and was preparing to accompany her home, v    THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  293 when his office-door opened and a stran- ger, heavily muffled, walked in. "How are you, sir? Are you an at. torney?" he asked in hurried, decided tones.  "I am," returned Alton, surveying the man with some attention, as he handed him a chair near the stove. "I am in pursuit of a thief, just rode out from the city, and have tracked him as far as this village. I want a writ." ".What was he like?" asked Alton. "' Like nobody ever seen round here be- fore,' said the man he stole the liquor from. He dealt in poetry by the ounce, and I should think he was crazy, if he hadn't got possession of the whiskey so like a man who had full use of his brains, and a good deal of them, too." 256  &#xD;<pb n="294-295" xml:id="VAC7523-00000147"/> 294    T D BRED BRIDGE. Mary looked at her husband, from her position partially obscured from the con. stable, and motioned him to come that way.  While he continued talking, she wrote on a paper which lay under his eyes: It is my old guardian. Save him, if you can." "Why didn't you get your writ made out in the city " he asked. "In too big a hurry to stop. I thought I should overtake him, it was so cold and stormy, if I got right off without'any de. lay. But somehow  he got on another road, I guess, took a shorter cut, or may be he started sooner than we thought for." Mary had nosooner written those words for her husband than she went out. Hastening home, she hurriedly inquired of Margaret where the stranger was? :    TIE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  2959  "He's after going a good bit ago,  ma'am. When he came to hisself again,  I told him he might ate the feed ye'd put there for him. He put a sup of the tay into his mouth, and some of the mate into his pocket, and said he must be after gitting along, thin. He asked for the leddy of the house, and whin Id be tellin you'd be gone out, ma'am, he axed for a bit o' paper and a pen to write with. An' he writes the like of what I niver see afore, and Mrs. Comfort is sayin' that same herself." "Where is it?" inquired Mary. Mrs. Comfort brought it at this moment. Mary saw that it was a writing in ci- pher, the same, she remembered, that Mr. Jameson had once taught her to use. After some study, she recalled the key, and read as follows:   &#xD;<pb n="296-297" xml:id="VAC7523-00000148"/> "My dear old ward, I have sturbled whither I would not. I go hence that I may not disgrace you.  Hippasus and Heraclitus both taught that fire is the principle of all things. If so, I am a man of principle, although they hunt me as a thief, and hoot me as a drunkard. Fare. well, my child; God reward you for your kindness to your miserable guardian." Meantime, Mr. Alton referred the consta. ble to a trial justice for a writ. That per. son being absent, he was obliged to hasten on to the next one, who resided in a neigh. boring town. Where the poor crazed wanderer betook himself, no information could be obtained, though it was supposed he had concealed himself in some of the comparatively corm- fortable barns of the vicinity, until the   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  297 xcitement had subsided and the storm was  ver.  As Mary stood at the window that night  nd gazed. out into the darkness, which was nly relieved by the light that dimly strug-  rled out from the angry and hurrying  Iouds, and heard the boisterous wind roar i  )ver the hills and around her own roof  which sheltered so much comfort and hap-   ?iness, she pressed her cheek against the  sold pane and sighed to herself, "Surely  he way of the transgressor is hard!"  For days and nights succeeding this sor-  rowful encounter with her former guardian,  she partially expected his return; but he  3ame not. She then addressed a letter to his sister, informing her of his appearance  at her house, but as she had several times written to that lady since leaving her, and :: " "*  &#xD;<pb n="298-299" xml:id="VAC7523-00000149"/> never had received a reply, she had now little hope of intelligence from that quarter. But, at last the letter was returned to her by the Postmaster of Yelfield, with the in. formation that Miss Eliza Jameson had been dead for some months. Before the snows of winter had fully left  the hill-tops and the shadowy places by the hedges and woods, Mary saw in one of the daily papers an account of the body of a man found on the outskirts of the un- frequented side of the forest, which lay to the north of a neighboring town. It stated ;hat the man had probably wandered thith- ?r in a fit of intoxication, where he had ain down and frozen to death. By his ide was a bottle in which, strange to relate, ras a closely rolled manuscript written in ipher.   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  299  The key to this writing no one could un- erstand, but it was preserved by the coro- er who held inquest over the body, so that  any persons should identify the individ- al, the manuscript would be at their dis-  osal. A handkerchief in the pocket of ie dead man, bore the initials, "G. J." 1 Mary immediately-knew that this was D other than her poor, old guardian. Her . isband sent for the manuscript, and, as  te had supposed, the cipher was easily anslated by herself. The following was hat Gilbert Jameson had written, proba m y on the day be died:-          i ( Now I am at the end of the long red  idge and see what is before me, I can  -i )mprehend what formerly was partially  : iveloped in a mist. When I was a )y I dreamed that I stood on the brink ..4?9  &#xD;<pb n="300-301" xml:id="VAC7523-00000150"/> 300    TEE RED BRIDGE. of the deep and rushing river of life, over which spanned two bridges. The first and narrowest of these bridges was like the purest white marble, its crystal arches set with jewels with a key-stone as one diamond, and all of its many pieces were of solid gold. "The other bridge was of a glittering red color; its arches were of twisted black wood, with a key-stone as of a snake's-head, and the piers were the sculptured forms of grinning satyrs. I stood contemplating the two bridges in order to decide which I had better choose for my own passage over. As there were several connections estab- lished all the way along the bridges, until the last section of each, so that the way- farers, if tired of one, could pass over to   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  301 the other, it did not appear a great matV  ter which I did start upon. As far as my eye could reach, there seemed many more persons on the red bridge than on the white one, and so there were much ex-I citement and pleasure in this route, while the other looked cold and comfortless with its crystals and marble.  "I was just stepping my foot on the red bridge, when a grave-looking man came up and gently touching my hand, said to me, 'Young  man! beware of this bridge! You will find it safe to take the other.' 'But I can cross over to the other any time, if I get sick of this, as I go along,' I replied, considerably annoyed at this interference with what I considered my right of choice. It is the dangerous nature of this .bridge,' he said, 'to fascia 26 ^*  .1;  &#xD;<pb n="302-303" xml:id="VAC7523-00000151"/> 302    THE RED BRIDGE.  / nate those who once walk thereon, so that, although they may know their peril ahead, they are impelled sometimes it would seem by an invisible whirlwind, and they fly along over the way, without power to break through the cruel charm and es- cape to the other bridge. It affects different persons variously. Sometimes they are charmed with a power which causes them to go slowly for a time, and then their- feet acquire such an artificial accommodation to the way, that they feel it would be impossible for them to break away and cross over to the white bridge.' t But I see some now crossing over,' I cried in exultation. 'They will have the pleasure and the benefit of an experience on both the bridges.'   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  303 " cTrue,' said the grave personage at my right shoulder, 'a few, resolutely looking upward for strength have the will-power to quit this dangerous passage before it is toe late. And such afterwards go on their way over the fair, clean, white bridge, re. joicing and shouting to their old friends on the red bridge to come over likewise before they get along so far they will lose  all power to do so. For you must know it is also the nature of this fatal route to cause its patrons to acquire ease in progress with every foot of the way, till near the last they get to going with such perfect adaptation, no human voice can arrest their attention sufficient to induce them to change.'  "'You will also observe at this moment,' spoke the warning voice of the man, 'thai 9' ;  . *  '  &#xD;<pb n="304-305" xml:id="VAC7523-00000152"/> 304    THE RED BRIDGE. some who had crossed over to the white bridge, have got sick of the new and better way, and are now crossing back to the old, fatal track. Oh that I could shout in their ears- Beware of the end! Come now, young man, be warned by these poor, deluded ones, and start aright.' "' I guess not,' I replied, 'since my father and many other friends have gone on this bridge. Besides, there are almost all my young friends who take this way, and they would deride me were I to go over there with only the unfashionable and humdrum folks. So saying, I dashed on; but he called out to me with such a terrible voice, I stopped right where I stood and heard him plainly say, -Re. member that the white bridge is safe all the way to the end, where are green pas-   THR BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  305 tures and fruitful gardens; but the red bridge breaks off before the river is crossed, and whoever reaches that place never sees the yawning chasm until he is too far gone to turn back. Closing his eyes, to shut out the fearful sight of the inky waters, he steps off,--a loud cry or a silent plunge and he is gone down to be seen no more!' ' Well, I guess I'll risk it if so many respectable people go on be- fore me,' I said; 'and at all events if I get tired of it, it is time to think of going over to the other bridge when I have tried this.' "But oh! had I given heed to that warning when I started, or to any of the voices which shouted to me from  the safe way, as I hurried madly on! I took my own course, and laughed at the croak- ers. I have had my own way,-alas! 26 *  &#xD;<pb n="306-307" xml:id="VAC7523-00000153"/> 306,    THE RED BRIDGE. what a way after the first few stages of excitement, triumph, and self-indulgence1 For a long way back there have been only losses, crosses, sorrows upon sorrows! "Sad, indeed, is the memory of my being urged on when I began to falter, by those in whom I had the utmost confidence, and who told me that the red bridge was by far the safest for my health of body; that I should lose my strength and spirits ;if I went over to the other. "I remember no, when I had nearly resolved to quit this ugly way, that I fell sick, and then it was that the maddening advice to keep on the red bridge increased my velocity fourfold, while my capability to quit this way was nearly annulled. "Ah! what judgment will not be meted out to these deceivers of themselves and   THE BOTTLED MANUSCRIPT.  307  ? others! When I think of the power of personal influence in regard to this fatal  course, influence of word and of alluring example, I shut my eyes against the over- whelming picture! "But the saddest thought of all is, that I have been the means of inducing others, who else )ould have kept along on the safe track, to come over and join this destruction-doomed company. One prom- ising young man I recall with deepest self-accusation. He was an orphan who took my guiding-word instead of his father's, which he had lost. And how did I discharge the responsibility? "I now gaze over to the other bridge, only to see the peace and happiness I have lost. Maddening thought! Torturing pice ture of unattainable happiness!  &#xD;<pb n="308-309" xml:id="VAC7523-00000154"/> 308    THE RED BRIDGE. "I am now just on the brink of the fatal chasm, against which the friend of my youth, so' long ago, warned me! One more step, and I go down into the cold, dark waters I see before me,- down! down! down to hell! "It is cold, but I feel it not, for the unquenchable fire burns within me. I will drain the bottle once .more, and then within it deposit this record, which, may some deluded mortal find in time to be warned against my fate. "Eliza! thou art dead! I know it by the way thou lookest on me now; and there is no track in the snow as thou passest by! Hast thou come for me? It grows colder. I must hasten. Oh, this red bridge which hast brought me to the dark chasm!" l   I Xe { N the summer there came to the Alton mansion a lady, who was a distant relative of Mr. Alton, from a west. ern city. She spent a few days with them on her route to the sea-coast. "I find that our local customs differ from yours in some respects," she said to Mary, one afternoon, after several visitors of an hour had been present. "Why so?" asked Mary. "With us," she continued, " it is thought indispensable to hospitality to order wine for our guests of even a brief, formal calL" (809)  &#xD;<pb n="310-311" xml:id="VAC7523-00000155"/> 310    THE RED BRIDGE. "Do all your people observe this prac. tice?" inquired Mary. "Nearly all in our particular circle. There are, to be sure, persons of some of the religious societies who do not follow this rule, but they are the exception." "Do you find your rule to work well?" "Oh, yes; we are a social people, who hold to getting the most enjoyment out of life, consistent with good morals and good society. We don't believe in going to heaven as the crusaders went to Jeru. alem, with hard peas in 'their shoes." The lady laughed, but Mrs. Comfort, who  was present, seemed remarkably serious, although the:e might have been  seen a curious look in her eyes, which in. dicated that this subject was by no means near exhaustion.  *    THE SURPRISE.     3" "May I suppose your people  never stumble with their smooth-going shoes?" said Mrs. Comfort. "Why no; though sometimes 'acci- dents happen in the best-r gulated families,  as the old saying is," rturned the lady. "Then you confess there are some slips  zfter the cup has reached the lips?" said Mrs. Comfort. "The truth is your eastern people make ;he worst work of our customs, when they -ome out and find themselves at liberty to lo as the Romans do. A lady from one of rour cities spent some time in our city this ieason. She stopped with a family of our  et so that I met her frequently. She was ut returning some calls with her daughter Ind a friend, one afternoon, and, as at every ' louse they offered them wine, this lady, it  &#xD;<pb n="312-313" xml:id="VAC7523-00000156"/> 312     THE RED BRIDGE. appears, drank as though she was glad of good wine, such as she didn't often see at home. At the fourth place in her round of visits, after drinking off 'again a fine glass, she fell down upon the floor in a state of perfect intoxication. Her daugh. ter, a fine, high-bred girl, was so alarmed at the spectacle of her mother rolling on the carpet in her abject degradation, that she fainted. As it was the residence of one of our most aristocratic families, the friend who accompanied them was ready to die of mortification. She ordered a coach and got them off out of the scene of their disgrace as soon as possible. 'Poor Mrs. Wallingford!' exclaimed the lady of the house where this took place, when she was commenting upon the cir- cumstances afterward to me; 'she has   THE SURPRISE.    313  yet to learn just how much good wine she can bear. Her head is rather small of her age!' " "Mrs. Wallingford did you say?" now inquired Mary, anxiously. "Did I mention the name! I ought to have been more prudent, certainly. Since Ihave betrayed it, then, I may as well go on with the whole. It was a lady from your city of---, and her daughter had been attending a celebrated semi- nary - I think it was - at Blenheim." Mary exchanged glances of surprise  with Mrs. Comfort, who said, "I guess that woman was glad to get back again to a more temperate latitude, where  her temptations would be less numerous." , "She never appeared there again in  public, and she went away a few days 27          'r  &#xD;<pb n="314-315" xml:id="VAC7523-00000157"/> '314    THE RED BRIDGE. after, although she had intentions of re. maining some months. I felt very sorry for Miss Wallingford, her daughter, as she seemed to have captivated a young gentleman, who "is reckoned an excellent match. But after that disgraceful scene got around, he never called on her again." "Very inconsistent, unreasonable peo- ple!" ejaculated Mrs. Comfort. "How is that?" inquired the lady. "It seems they do not hesitate to put the cup to their neighbor's mouth, and then if one. chances to get a little too much so as to bring on an awkward scene, she is con mnned and derided. I should think the right course would be not to tempt people with that which turns them into beasts in their appearance," said Mrs. Comfort, with decision.   THE SURPRISE.     315 "I don't think it would have made .- quite so much of a sensation," observed the lady, "had not the young man so suddenly have visited judgment upon Miss Wallingford; and he was, doubtless, influenced very considerably by a young gentleman friend, who was formerly from the east, and who is such a rabid temper. ance man, he is an anomaly out there among his acquaintance." "By the way," continued the lady who desired to change the subject, as it was becoming slightly unpleasant, "this other young man has a very peculiar history, which I heard from his own lips with deep interest. Shall I relate it, Mrs. Alton?" "t If you please," answered Mary. "He said he enlisted into the Federal army about the time the war commenced, ;   .         , i  &#xD;<pb n="316-317" xml:id="VAC7523-00000158"/> 316    THE RED BRIDGE. was shot, and left for dead. Afterwards he was picked up by the rebels and im- prisoned, where he suffered terribly. Oh, it was heart-rending to hear him describe his situation at that time! While he was in prison he remembered all his past life, and some things, I should judge, troubled him very much. After staying there till he was almost worn out, he was released. It seems he did not want to go back to his friends, until he had done something to distinguish himself. In particular he wished to prove that he was reformed from some of his old habits of intemper. ance. So he wandered around until he did something one day that attracted the attention of a Federal officer, who soon after &amp;ngaged him as his secretary. He remained in this position, true to his   THE SURPRISE,     317 good intentions, until he obtained the fine situation of secretary to him who is now  Governor of our State. Here he said he . was tempted every day to drink. again; but he resolved to live one year and see  if he could endure the ordeal, when if he came off conqueror, he should write home to his friends and let them know where he was. The strangest part of it is, he was anpnly brother, and his sister believes he is dead. She will be overjoyed when, he makes himself known, for he has be- come one of the finest fellows I ever met. The governor thinks highly of him and  entrusts him with unusual responsibilities.  He told my husband he was worth every-  thing to him now, and especially for his  habits of strict devotion to principle, so  that it was always safe to trust him. The  27*              A  &#xD;<pb n="318-319" xml:id="VAC7523-00000159"/> 318    THE RED BRIDGE. young man told me himself that he owed everything to his sister. Then, said I; why don't you make some return by discovering yourself to her?. He said he was going to, when the time of his self- prescribed probation had expired, which is very soon now, I believe." "Alas!" sighed Mary; "I had an only and beloved brother in the army, who was killed. I know how to feel for that young man's sister." She arose and went to the centre-table where she found a photograph-album. Turning to the picture of her brother, she showed it to her guest.. "It is astonishing how much this pic- ture resembles that young man," ex- claimed the lady. Certainly, I should think Mr. W inslow sat for it, himself!" s   THE SURPRISE.     319 "Mr. Winslow!"  cried Mary, turning pale. tYes; that is his name, let me think, his first name is William. I remember it, because it is the same name of my oldest son who died many years ago." "William Winslow!" gasped Mary, "then it must be my own lost brother!" "Possible!" exclaimed the lady. "He told me his home was in this State. He said he had kept himself aware of his sister's getting along, by means of an old friend who was in his secret. I remember now he told me she had married very well to a young lawyer of property; but I little thought it was any relative of my own to whom he referred." "You will excuse me to retire to my own room," said Mary, while the tears came  &#xD;<pb n="320-321" xml:id="VAC7523-00000160"/> 320    THE RED BRIDGE. rapidly,-tears of grateful, overwhelming joy, such as angels might behold with sympathetic emotion. For some time Mary sat alone by her open window, and, looking upward to the blue, unclouded skies, reflected upon the goodness of her heavenly Father. Her heart dissolved in penitential grati- tude as she thought of the mysterious way in which he had led her up to the present moment, which was now so laden with mercies. Opening the beloved Bible, to which she had so often resorted in the trying seasons of the past, and also in moments of faith and consolation, she read:- "And he shall sit as a refiner and purifier of silver, and he shall purify the sons of Levi, and purge them as gold and   THE SURPRISE,         321 silver, that they may offer unto the Lord an offering in righteousness.    Then  shall the offering  of Judah   and  Jerusalem   be pleasant unto the Lord as in the days of old, and as in former years."  &#xD;<pb n="322-323 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7523-00000161"/>   OF THE            -     ? National Temperance Society  AND  PUBLICATION HOUSE. THE NATIONAL TEMPERANCE SOCIETY, organized in 1866 for the purpose of supplying a sound and able Temperance literature, have already reotyped and published three hundred and fifty publications of sorts and sizes, from the one-page tract up to the bound volume of 5oo ges. This list comprises books, tracts, and pamphlets, containing says, stories, sermons, arguments, statistics, history, etc., upon every ase of the question. Special attention has been given to the department For Sunday-Schpol Libraries. rer sixty volumes have already been issued, written by some of the best thors in the land. These have been carefully examined and unani- usly approved by the Publication Committee pf the Society, represent- the various religious denominations and Temperance organizations of a country, which consists of the following members: PETER CARTER,         REV. J. B. DUNN, REV. W. M. TAYOR,      REV. A. G. LAWSON, A. A. ROBBINS         REV. ALFRED   TAYOR, REV. HALSEY MOORE,      R. R. SINCLAIR, T. A. BROUWER,         REV. C. D. FOSS, V J. N. STEARNS         JAMES BLACK,  REV. WILLIAM   HOWELL TAYOR.        ,  These volumes have been cordially commended by leading clergymen all denominations, and by various national and State bodies, all over eland.                               - The following is the list, which can be procured through the regular nday-School trade, or by sending direct to the rooms of the Society:  v. Dr. Willoughby and his Wine. i2mo, 458 pages. By Mrs. MARY SPRING WALKER, author of "The Family Doctor," etc,  .  $. -1 .t This thrillingly interestir.- book depicts in a vivid manner the terrible influence exefted by  se who stand as the servants of God, and who sanction the social custom of wine-drinkitng. s fair and faithful to the truth. It is not a bitter tirade against the church or the ministry - the contrary, it plainly and earnestly acknowledges that the ministry is the friend of moralit , the great bulwark of practical virtue.  Lion's Mouth. i2mo, 4o0 pp. By Miss MARY DWINELL CHELLIS author s of "Temperance Doctor," "Out of the Fire," "Aunt binah's  Pledge," etc.,. ..........$1  This is one of the best books ever issued, written in a simple yet thrilling and interes : style. It speaks boldly for the entire suppression of the liquor traffic, depicting vividly W  ery and wrongs resulting from it. The Christian tone is most excellent, showing the 8eceg -. of God's grace in the heart to overcome temptation and the power of appetite, -and *e  uence which one zealous Christian can esert upon his companions and the community. ,  *    ,  's'fj as  e3 , ,         *:?t  &#xD;<pb n="324 (Advertisement) -325 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7523-00000162"/> Aunt Dinah's Pledge.     x2mo, 318 pages.  By Miss MARY DWINELL EHi SLLIS, author of "Temperance Doctor,"   "Out of   the  Fire," etc.,......... $1 25 Aunt Dinah was an eminent Christian wo- man. Her pledge included swearing and smok- ing, as well as drinking. It saved her boys Who lived useful lives, and died happy; and by quiet, yet loving antI persistent work, names lof mauy others were added who seemed almost beyond hope of salvation. The Temperance Doctor. i2mo, 370 pages., By Miss MARY DWINELL CHELIIS, .      ......$1 25 This is a true story, replete with interest, and adapted to Sunday-school and famnily read- ing In it we have graphically depicted the 1ad ravages that are caused by the use ol intox- icating beverages; also, the blessings of Tem- perance, and what may be accomplished by one earnest soul for that reform. It ought to find readers in every household. Out of the Fire. 12mo, 420 pages. By Miss MARY DWINELL CHELLIS, author of "Deacon Sim's Pray- ers," etc.,   ... . .     $1 25 It is one ol the most effective and impressive Temperance books ever published . Ihe evils 6f the drinking customs of society, and the blessings of sobriety and total abstinence, are strikingly developed in the history of various families in the community. History of a Threepenny Bit. i8mo, -=6 pages,.  ...... $0 75 Thha Is a thrilling story, beautifully illus- trated with five choice wood engravings The story of little Peggy, the drunkard's daughter, is told in such a simple yet interesting manner that no one can read it without realizing more than ever before the nature and extent of in- temperance, and sympathizing, more than ever with the patient, suffering victim. It should be in every Sunday-school library. Adopted.   x8mo, 236 pages.    By Mrs. E. J, RICHMOND, author of "The McAllisters," . .     $0 60 'This book is written in an easy, pleasant yle, seems to be true to nature, true to itself, and withal is full of the Gospel and Temper- ance. The Red Bridge.    iSnio, 321 pages. By THRACE TALMAN,     . . $0 90 We have met with few Temperance stories centainin- so many evidences of decided ability tad highterary excellence as this. a   The  Old  Brown   Pitcher.   x2mo 222 pages.   By  the Author oi "Susie's Six Birthdays," "The Flower of the Family," etc., $1 0o Beautifully illustrated. This admirable vol. ume for boys and girls, containing original stories by some of the most gifted writer for the young, will be eagerly welcomed by the children. It Ni adpte I alike lor the family circle and the abbath-school library. Our Parish. i8mo, 252 pages. By Mrs. EMLY PEARSON, . . $0 7 Thle,manifold evils resultintg from too 1' still " to the owner's family, as well as to the families of his customers, are truthfully presented. The characters introduced, such as are found in almost every good-sized village, are well poi. trayed., We can unhesita ingly com nendit, and bespeak for it a wide circulation. The Hard Master,    i8mo, 278 pages. By Mrs. J. E. MCCONAUGHY au- thor of"One Hundred Gold Dol- lars," and other popular Sunday- ,School books, ...     ..  O . 8 This intteresting narrative of the temptations, trials, hardships, and fortunes of) poor orphan boy illustrates in a most striking manner the vilue of "right principles," especially of honesty truthfulness, andTEMPt:RANCE. Echo Bank.   x8mo, 269 pages.   By ERVI, ........$0 8 This is a well-written and deeply interesting narrative, in which is clearly shown the suffer- ing and sorrow that too often follow and the dangers that attend boys and young men at school and at college, who suppose they can easily take a glass or two occasionally, with- out fear ot ever being aught more than a mode- rate drinker. Rachel Noble's Experience. i8mo, 325 pages.  By BRUCE EDWARDS. $0o90 This is a story of thrilling interest, ably and eloquently tole . id is an excellent book for Sunday-school libraries. It isjust the book for the home circle, and cannot be read without benefiting the reader and advancing the cause ol Teniperante Gertie's Sacrifice; or Glimpses at Two Lives.   i8mo, 189 pages. by Mrs. F. D.    GAGE,.  . . $050 A story of great interest and power. giving' '4 glimpse at two lives," and showing how Gertie sacrificed herself ap a victim of fashion custom, and law.   Time will Tell.'   2mo, 307 pages. By Mrs. WILSON,   . . .   f00 A Temperance tale of thrilling interest and unexceptionable moral and religious tone. It is full of incidents and characters of everyday life, while its lessons are plainly and forcibly set before the reader. The pernicious results of the drinking usages in the family and social circle are plainly set forth. Philip  Eckert's  Struggles   and Triumphs. i8mo, 216 pages.     By the author of "Margaret Clair," $0 60 This interesting narrative of a noble, manly boy. in an inteinperate home, fighting with the wrong and battling for thie right, should be read by every child in the land. Jug-Or-Not.  i2mo, 346 pages.   By Mrs. J. McNAIR WRIGHT, author of "John   and  the  Demijohn," "Almost a Nun," "Priest and Zun,"etc.,  ...... $1 25 It is one of tier best books, and treats oi the physical and heredit try effects of drinking in a clear, plain, and familiar style, adapted to )opular teading, an't which should be rentd by allfclasses in the community, and find a place in every Sunday-school library. The Broken Rock. 18mo, 139,pages. By KRUNA, author of "CLitt a Little," etc.,.$.       . $0 50 It Deauti ully illustrates the silent and holy influence of a meek and lowly spirit upon the heartless ruitmseller until the rocky heart was broken. Andrew Douglass. i8rmo, 232 pages, $0 75 A new Temperantce story for Sunday-schools, written in a lively, energetic, and popular style, adapted to the Sabbath-school aind the family circle. Vow at the Bars.   i8mo, ro8 pages. $0 40 It contains four short tales, illustraLit'lfu, r important principles connected \v tli the 'remi- perance movement, anmdis well a lap:ed for the family circle and Sabbatht-school libraries. Job  Tufton's  Rest.   2110, 3 pages, ..  ..     . .   $1  o A story of life's struggles, written by the gifted author, CLARA LUCAS BALFOUR, depict- ing most skilfully and truthfully manty 'a life- struggle with the demion of inte riperance Riampy Dumpy. mo, 316 pp. B Rev. J. J.   ANA,    ...$1 2 In thi book, a cemr grocery i the sounrce of muck evil, and a mlssloa sckool by its Cr  atiMu thhlrgs, the meana of wJagM many de th drowarl   pAth,   Frank Oldfield; or, Lost and Founa. 12mo, 408 pages, . .    .  $1 50 This excellent story received the prize of. E100 in England, out of eighty-three manu- scripts submitted.; and by an arrangement with. the publishers we publish it in this coun- try with all the original illustrations. It is admirably adapted to Sunday-school libraries. Tom Blinn's Temperance Societ)}, and  other Stories.   i2mo0  316 pages, ........$1 26 This is the title of a new book written by T/ ,. ARTHUR, the well-known author of"Ten Nights in a Bar-room," and whose fame as an author should bespeak for it a wide circulation. It is written in Mr. ARTHUR's best style, corn posed of a seriet o tales adapted to every famill and library in the land. The  Harker  Family.   I2mo, 336 pages   By EMLY THOMPSON, $1 26 A simple, spirited, and interesting narrative, writteni in a style especially attractive, depice- ing the evils that arise from intemperance, and tile blessings that followed the earnest offorts of those who sought to win others to the paths ot total abstinence. Illustrated with threo on- gravings. The book will please all. Come  Home, Mother,    i8mo,  43w pages.  By NELStE   BROOK. I,- lustrated with six choice engrav- ings,  ..... .      .  $0  0 A most effective and interesting book, de- scribing the downward course of the monthr, an{tgiving an account of the sad scenes, but ef- fectual endeavors, of the little one in bringing hier motther back to riends, tnd leading her to God. It should be read by everybody. Tim's Troubles. I2mo, 350 pages. 'By Miss M. A. PAULL, .     .$f 50 This Is the secondI Prize Book of the Unlte# Kingdom Band of Hope Union, reprinted in this country with all the original illustrations. It Is the companion of"Frank Oldfield." written in a high tone. and will be found a valuable addition to our Temperance literature The  Drinking   Fountain  Storles. i2mo, 192 pages, .$1 00 This book of, illustrated stories for childrem contains articles from some of the best wrttes for chiltren in America, and is beautifully t1- lustrated with forty choice wood engr,-vings, The White Rose. By Mary J.!Redt es. x6mo, 320 pages, . .. The gift of a simple white rose was the mamm of leadine those who cared for it to the Savite. Hlow it was done is very pleasantly told, wr - Iso the wrongs resulting m the use of stmr rink forcibly shown.  &#xD;<pb n="326 (Advertisement) -327 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7523-00000163"/> ioHpedale  Tavern,  and  What  it Wrought.   I2mo, 252 pages.   By J. WILLIAM VAN NAMEE, . $1 00 It shows the sad results which folloWed the 'introduction of a Tavern andBar in a beauti- fut and quiet country town, whose inhabitants had hitherto lived in peace and enjoyment. The contrast is too plainly presented to fail to produce an impression on the reader, making all more desirous to abolish the sale of/all in- texicants,           / Boy's Search; or, Lost in the Cars. 12mo, 364 pages. By HELEN     C. PEARSON, ....... $1 25 This new Temperance book is one of the mest interesting ever published-written in a fresh, sparkling style, especially adapted to please the boys, and contains so much that vill benefit as well as amuse and interest that *e wish all the boyb in the land might read it. How Could He Escape? I     mo, 324 piges.   'By MRS,   J. NCNAIR WRIGHT author of "Jug-Or- Not." Illustrated with ten en- gravings, designed   by. the  au- thor, ........$1 25 This is a true tale and one of the writer's / best productions. It shows the terrible effects of even one glass of intoxicating liquor upon the system of one unable to resist Its influences, and the necessity of grace in the heart to resist temptation and overcome the appetite for strong drink. The  Best Fellow   in  the World. 12mo, 352  pages.   By  Mrs. J. MCNAIR WRIGHT, autnor of "Jug- Or-Not,"  "How   Could He Es- cape?" "Priest and Nun," $1 %5 "The Best Fellow," .whose course is here portrayed, is one of a very large class who are led astray and ruined sitmply because they are such " good fellows." To all such the volume speaks in thrilling tones of warninr, shows the Inevitable consequences of indulging in strong drink, and the necessity of divine grtcce in the heart to interpose and save irom ruin. Frank  Spencer's  Rule  of  Life. x8mo,  80o pages.'  By JOHN W KIRTON, author of "' Buy Your Own Cherries," "Four Pillars of Temperance," etc., etc., . $0 50 This is written in the author's best style, making an interesting and attractive story tor ifAildren. Work and, Reward.    i8mo, 183 pp. By Mrs. M. A. HOLT, . $0 50 It shews that not the smallest effort to do good is lost sight of by the all-knowing Father, and that faith and prayer must aeorpany all temperafa effore. 4   The Pitcher of Cool Water, i8mo, i8o pages. By T. S. ARTHUR, author of"Tom   Blinn's Temper. ance Society," "Ten Nights in a Bar-room," etc.,        $0 60 This little book consists of a series of Temn, perance stories, handsomely illustrated, written in Mr. A'THURS' best style, and is altogether one of the best books which can be placed in the hands of children. Every Sunday-school library should possess it. Little Girl in   Black.   i2mo, 212 pages, By MARGARET E. WIL- MER, .   .  .....      $0 90 Her strong faith in God, who shi believes will reclaim an erring father, is a lesson to the reader, old as well as young. Temperance Anecdotes, X2mo, 288 pages, .   ....... $1 00 This new book of Temperance Anecdotes, edited by GEOROaG W. BUNGAY, contains near. ly four hundred Anecdotes, Witticisms, Jokes, Conundrums, etc., original and selected, and will meet a want long felt and often expressed by a very large number of the numerous friends ot' the cause in the land. The book is hand- somely illustrated with twelve choice wood engravings. The Temperance Speaker.      By J. N. STEARNS, ......       $0 75 The book contains'288 pages of Declamlations and Dialogues suitable tor Sunday and Day- Schools, Bands of Hope, and Temperance Or- ganizations. It consists of choice selections of prose anti poetry, both new and old, from the Temperance orators and writers of the country, many of which have been written ex- pressly for this work. The MeAllisters. i8mo, 211 pages. By Mrs.: E. J. RICHMOND,. $0 50 It shows the ruin brought on a family by the father's intemperate habita, and the strong faith and trust of the wife in that Friend above who alone gives strength to bear our earthly trials. The Seymours. i2mo, 231 pages. By Miss L. BATES,     .   . .  f006 A simple story, showing how a refined and cultivated family are brought low through the drinking habits of the father, their joy and sor- row as he reforms only to fall again, and his final happy release lIn a distant city. Zoa  Rodman.   i2mo, 262 pages. By Mrs. E. J. RICHMOND, $1 00 Adapted more especially to young girls' reading, showing the influence they wield in society, and their responsibility for mnuh of itt drihakiag usages.   Eva's Engagement Ring. I2mo, i89 pages.  By  MARGARET E. WIL- MER, author of "The Little Girl in Black," ...... $0 90 In this int/eresting volume is traced the career of the moderate drinker, who takes a glass in the namne offriendhslip or courtesy. Packington Parish, and The Diver's Daughter. i2mo, 327 pages. By Miss M. A. PAULL,     . . $1 25 In this volutne we sce the ravages which the liquor traffic caused when introduced ill a hitherto quiet villa'ge, and how a minister's eyes were at length openied to its evils, thonug'h he had always declared wine to he a "good creature of God/' meant to be used in moderan tion. Old Tirnes.  I2mo.  By Miss M. D. CHELLIS, author of "The Tem- perance Doctor,"   "Out of the Fire," "Aunt Dinah's Pledge," "At Lion's Mouth," etc., . $1 25 It discusses the whole subject of nioderaie drinking in the history of a New Engliand vil- hlae. The incidents, various anid amusing, are all facts, and the characters nearly 'all drawn from real life. The five deacons which figure so conspicuously actually lived and acted as re- Vresented. John  Bentley's  Mistake.   i8mo, 177 pages.  By Mrs. M. A. HOLT, $0 50 It takes an important place among our tetm- perance books, taking an earnest, bold stand against the use of cider as a beverage, proving that it is often the first step toward stronger drinks, forming ani appetite for the more fiery liquids which cannot easily be quenched. Nothing  to Drink.   12mo, 400 pages.   By  Mrs.  J. MCNAIR WRIGHT, author of "The Best Fellow in the World," "Jug-or- Not,"How Could He Escape?" etc.,   . .  ..... $1 50 The story is of light-house keeper and thrilling adventures at sea, being nautical, scientific, and partly statistical, written in a charming, thrilling, and convincing manner. It goes out of the ordinary line entirely, most of the characters being portraits, its scenery all from absolute facts, every scientific and natural-history statement a verity, the sea in- cidents from actual experience from marine lisasters for the last ten years. Nettie Loring.   I2mo, 352 pages. By Mrs. GEO. S. DOWNS,     $1 25 It graphically describes the doings of sev- eralyoung ladies who resolved to use their influence on the side of temperance and banish wine from their entertainments the bscorn they excited, aad the good results which followed,   The Fire Fighters. 12mo, 294 pages. thor of "The Hard Master," $1 25 An admirable story, showing how a number of young lads banded themselves into a society to fight against Alcohol, and the good they did in thie comunintity. The Jewelled Serpent.    12mo, 271 pages. By Mrs. E. J. RICHMOND, author of"Adopted," "The Mc- Allisters," etc.,.. $1 00 The story isv written earnestly. The charac- ters are wh delineated, and taken from the wealthy anid fashionable portion of a large city. The evils which flow frotm fashionable drink- inig iare well portrayed, and also the danger arising frotm the use of intoxicants when used as medicine, foriming an appetite which fast'ns itself with a deadly imold upon its victmhn. The Hole in the Bag, and Other Stories. By Mrs. J. P. BALLARD author of "The Broken Rock," "Lift a Little," etc. i2mo, $1 00 A collection of well-written stories by this most popular author on tIe su'bject of temper- ance, inculcating many valuable lessons in the jainds of its readers. The Glass Cable. i2mo, 288 pages. By MARGARET E. WILMER, au- thor  of "The   Little Girl in Black,"   "Eva's   Engagement Ring," etc, .....$1 25 The style of this book is good, the characters well selected, and its temperance and religious truths most excellent., The moral of the story shows those who sneer at a child's pledge, comnparing its strength to a glass cable, that it is in Imany cases strong enough to brave the storms and temptations of a whole lifetime. Fred's  Hard  Fight.   1zmo, 334 pages.  By Miss MARION HOW- ARD,    .   ...$1 25 While it shows the trials which a young lad endured through the temptations and entice-. ments offered him by those opposed to his firm temperance and religious principles, and warns the reader against the use of every kind of alcoholic stimulant, it points also to Jesus, the only true source of strength, urging all to accept the promises of strength and salvation offered to every one who will seek it. The Dumb Traitor. i2mo, 336 pPp. By MARGARET E WILMER, $1 26 Intensely interesting, .showing how the prospects of a well-to-do New England family were blighted through the introduction of a box of wine, given in friendship, used as me- dicine, butproving a dumb traitor in the and.  &#xD;<pb n="328 (Advertisement) -329 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7523-00000164"/> Esther Maxwell's Mislake. x8mo, 936 pages.  By Mrs. E. N. JAN- visR, author of "Andrew Doug- lass,".......$1 00 This book is full of Gospel truth, and writ- ten in a simple but earnest style. showing tie Utter absurdity of endeavoring to lornet trou- ble by the use of strong d ink, which Estlher, like many others, found soon I orned habits not easily broken. Her sudden awakening to this fact, and turning to her Saviour for pardon anIi help to renounce the temptation to drink, make one ot the most touching narratives ever written. Wealth and Wine. t2mo, 320 pp. By Miss MARY I)W1NILL CHELLIS, author of "Temnerance      Doc- tor,"At Lion's Mouth," $1 25 This book Is written in her best style, show- ing the deception of the wine-cup and the power of womana's influence, together with t ie evil influence of social and mo.!erate drinking. Its moral and Christian tone is excellent. and nose can rail to be profitul by its teachings.   The Life Cruise of Captain Bess Adams.   12mo, 413 paces.    By 'Mrs. J. MCNAIR WRIGHT, author of Nothing to Drink, etc., $1 g0 A s!a-story, filled with thrilling adventure, on the deep, and intensely interesting sceun on hind ill the nildst of a quaint old sea-coast town,-proving effect tally that alcoholic drinks are not needed on shipboard or on laid, and should be absolutely banished. The biavr Christian character of Captain Adamq and the heroism ot his dnugher, Riess. together with the pure religious tone pervading ecery pMe, mal;e this one of the most interesting booki  ever written. The Model Landlord.     x8mo.  By Mrs. M. A. HOLT, author of ' John   Bentlex 's   Mistake" Work and Reward.". . $0 60 It shows how a "tmodel landlord " whe keeps a gildedt saloon lor fashionable wine. drinkes s, though he may attend church, give money to the poor, and circulate In the "alnt society," may be the great"st instrument is leading the young down te destraction.   Miscellaneous Publications.   The Bases of the Temperance Re. form, 12mo. 224 pages. By Rev. DAWSON 1I'RNS .        $1 00 This is an English prize assny, which took the second prize undtet the liberal offer of James Tear- for the best essay on the entire temperance quest ion. Bacchus   Dethroned.    x2mo,  248 pages.  By IRiKDRICK- POWELL, $1 00 This is an English prize essay, written in re- Bponse. to a prize offered by J1mes Teare, of Englanid, for t he best temperance essay. The qun-stion is p' esented in all its phases, physio. ltrCHal, SCil, political, moral, m and ieli- gioue. It is very conmprehensive. The National. Temperance Orator. rzmo, 288 pp. By Miss L. PEr NEY, $1 00 This Is issued! in response to the many ur- gent calls for a book similar to the 'New T tnmperance ,-peake ," used widely through- oat the count y. Is contains articles by the beit tenmp,-rnce writeis of the day, poems, :recitations, reltings, oialogune, and chloice ext-a cts, rom speeches from some ef the ablest 'temperance speakkr;s in t(h country.?or the uip O' all temiper;nce workers, Loilges, Divi- sions, Bands of Hope, etc., etc. augle Notes for the Temperanice Army.   Price, paper,/covers   30 cents; boards,...       . $6 3s A new eelleetion of Songs. Quartets, and *Iies, for the use of all Temperance gather- age, glee clubs. et., together with the (Ides of tih Sase et Tem pvraoe rJad Q d Templars. I'   Temperance    Chimes.   Price, in paper covers, 30 cents, single copies; $25 per hundred.     Price, in board covers, 35 cents; per hundred,. ..... $00 A Temperance Hymn and Tune-Book of11: 8 9page, comprising it gret variety o' Glees, Songs, and Hymns desigited for the use ofem. perance Meetings and Organizations, Banda of Hope, Glec Clubs, anid the Home Circle Many of the H ymns have been written expressly for tl!s book by some of the best writers in ti cotn try Bound Volumes of Sermons, $1 50 Seventeen sermons 'deliveredt upon the invi- tation of The National Temperance Society, and published in the National Series. have all been bound in one volume. makinig 00 page. of the best temper ince matter of thie kind ever published. The sermons are by Revs. Henry Ward Beecher, T L. Cuyler, T. De Witt Tal- mage, J B. Dunn, JohnHall, .1. P. Newman, J. W. Mears, C. D. Foss, J Romevyn Berry, Hferrick Johnson, Peter Stryker, C. H. Fowler, H C. Fish, H. We Warren, S. it. Tyng. and W. Mi. Taylor. Text-Book   of Temperance.     By Dr. F. R. LEES,   .... $1 50 ' We can also furnish the above book, which is di-vided into the following parts: 1. Temper; ance as a Virtue. 2. The Chemical Historyof Alcohol. 3 The Dietetics of Temperance. 4. The Pathology of Intemper ince. 5. The Medi. cal Question. 6 Temperance in Relation to  the B ble. 7. Historical. 8. The National Question and the Remedy.' 9. The Philosophy of Temperance. It   Forty Years' Fight with the Drink Demon    121110, 400 pages.   By CHARLES JEWETT, M.., . $1 50 This volume comprises the history of Dr Jewett's public and private labors from 1826 to the present time, with sketches of the most popular and distinguished advocates of the cause in its earlier stages. It also records the results of forty years' observation, study, and reflections upon the use of intoxicating drinks and drtugs, and suggestions as to the best methods o01 advancing the cause, etc Thle book is handsomely bound, and cittl:aiits illustrated portraits of early champions of the cause Drops of Water.   12mo , 133 pages. By Miss ELLA WHEELER,      $0 75 A new book of fifty-six Temperance Poems by this young and talented authoress, suitable for reading in Temperance Societies, Lodge Rooms, Divisions, etc. The simplicity of man- Her, beauty of expression, earnestness of thoughlt, and inobleness of sentiment running through all of thenm make this book a real genm, worthy a place by the side of any of the poetry int the country. Bound  Volume   of  Tracts.   500 pages, ........$1 00 This volume con'ins all the four, eight, and twelve page tracts published by the National Temperance Society , tid comni0ises Argur ments, Statistics, 1.ketches, and Essays, wiltch make it an invaluable collection for every friend of the Temiperace Reform, Bound Volume of Tracts.     No. 2. 384 PP., ...... .1 00 Containing all the twenty-four and forty- eight page pamphlets and prize essays publish- ed by the National Temperance Society since its erganiatien, Scripture Testimony Against In. toxicating Wine.    By Rev. WM. RITCHE, of Scotland,   . . $0 60 An unanitswerable refutation of the theory that the Ser ptures fiavor the idea of the use of intoxicating wine as a beverage. It takes the different kin s of wines mentioned in the Scriptures, investigates their specific na- ture, and shows wherein they differ. Zoological Temperance Convention. By Rev. EDWARD HTCHCOCK, D D , of Amherst College, $0 7T This fable gives an interestinig and enttertai ing accounllt of a Convientioti of Atnimals Ibel in Central A rica, and reports the -  maute on the occasion.   Delavan's Consideration of the Tem- perance Argument and History $1 g0 Tills condenised and comiprehensive work con- ta tns E&amp;says aind Selections from different au- tihors, collected and edited by EDWARD C. DM- "AVAN, Esq., and is one or the most valuable ttxt-books on the subject of Temperance ever issued. Bible  Rule  of  Temperance;   or, Total Abstinence from all Intox- icating Drinks. By Rev. GEORGE DUFFIELD, D D., . . . . $0 60 Tihis is the ablest and most reliable work whiiclih hts been issued on the subject The im- imtor:lity of the us , sale, an I iaminufacture of intoxicating liquors as a beverage is cons dered inll the light of tie scriptures, and the will and i:iw ( f God clerlyl ,presen tedi Alcohol: Its Nature and Effects.' By CHARLES A. STOREY, M D., $0 90 This is a thoroughly scientific work, yet written in a fresh, vigorous, and popular style, in language that the masses can understand. It consists of ten lectures carefully prepared, and is an entirely new work by one amply conm- petent to ,present the subject. Four Pillars of Temperance. By JOHN W. KIRTON, . . . $0 75 The Four Pillars are, Reason, Science, Scrip- ture, and Experience. The book is argumenta- tive, historical, and statistical, and the facts, appeals, and arguments are presented in a most conviecin g and masterly manner. Communion Wine; or     Bible Tem- perance. By Rev. WILLIAM M. THAYER.   Paper, 20 cents; cloth, $0 50.O An unanswerable argument against the use of intoxicating wine at Communion, and pre- senting the Bible argument in favor of total abstinIence Bible WitV!s;; or The Laws of Fer- mentation   and  Wines  of  the Ancients.   12mo, 139 pages. By Rtrv. WM. PATTON, 1D DI. Paper, 30 cts.: cloth   . . .   $0 60 It presents the whole matter of Bible Teumi perance and the wines of ancient titmes in a new, clear, and satisfactory manner. develop- ing the laws of fermnentation, and giving a large number of references and statistics never before oollected, showing contclusively the existence of unfermented wine in the l4den time. Alcohol: Its Place and Power, -by JAMES MLLER; and The Use and Abuse of Tobacco, by JOHN. Li- :  ZARS,  .....$1 00  &#xD;<pb n="330 (Advertisement) -331" xml:id="VAC7523-00000165"/> The Medical Use of Alcohol, Three Lectures by JAMES' EDMUNDS, M D., Member of the Royal Col- lege of Physicians of London, Senior Physician to the London Temperance Hospital. i2mo, 96 pp.  Paper cover, 25   cents; cloth, .   . . .   . .$0 60 Dr. Edmunds is one of the ablest phylsiclans of England, has thoroughly studied the whole question from a Medical stand-point, and not   in the Interest of the canse of Temperance. It is, however, clearly shown that Science and Temperance both point in one direction, aid this book should find its way into every hous. hold in the land. The three Lectures are as follows : 1. The Medical Use of Alcohol. 2. Stimulants for Women and Nursing Mothers. 3. The Dietetic Use of Alcohol, It is a full and reliable exse-ition from one of the ablest physicians of the world, and we hope it will be widely circulated.   The Youth's Temperance Banner The National Temperance Sciety ap( Publication House publish a beautifully illustrated Monthly Paper, especially adapted to children and youth, Sunday-school and Juvenile Tern. ,:perance Organizations. Each number contains several choice engravings, a piece of music, anda great variety of articles from the pens of the best writers for children in America. It should be placed in the hands of every child in the land. TERMS IN ADVANCE, INCLUDING POSTAGE    Single copy, one year ...... .... $0 85 Eight, to one address ........... 1 08 Ten,  i     S  . st1 08 Tent, " ". . .........' 1 85 Twenty, "   .... ...... 70 -       2 70   Thirty copies to one address....$4 05 Forty,    "     ............ 5 40 Fiftundred,    "   .     67 One hundred,   "   ............ 13 00   THE NATIONAL TEMPERANCE ADVOCATE. The National Temperance Society and Publication House publish a Monthly Temperance Paper, the object of which is to promote the interests of the cause of Temperance by disseminating light from every quarter upon its moral, social, financial, and scientific bearings. The best talent in the land will be secured for its editorsandcontributors. Terms in advance, including postage, one dollar and ten cents a year. 10 copies, to one address $10; 20 copies, to one address, $18, All over 20 at the last-named rate, which includea postage. Twenty-four Page Pamphlets. (With Covers.) Five Cents each; 60 Cents per Doz.   Is Alcohol Food t Physiological Action of Alcohol. Adulteration of Liquors. Will the Coming Man Drink Winel History and Mystery of a Glass of Ale, Bible Teetotalhsm.   Medicinal Drinking. Drinking Usages of Societyl Fruits of the Liquer Traffic. Is Alcohol a Necessary of Life! A High Fence of Fifteen Bar The Son of My Friend.   Band of Hope Supplies,   Band of Hope Manual. Per dozen,   $0 60 Temperance Catechism. Per dozen,    60 Band of Hope Melodies. Paper,     10 Band of Hope Badges Enamelled, $1 25 per dozen; 12 cents singly. Plain, per dozen; 10 cents singly. Silver and Enamelled, 50 cents each.   Juvenile Temperance Speaker,    - M-  Illuminated Temperance Cards. Set of ten, -        .-  -    35 Juvenile Temperance Pledges. Per100, 300 Certificates of Membership. Per 100, - 300 The Temperance Speaker,  -  -  -  5 Catechism on Alcohol. By Miss Julia Colman. Per dozen,     -    6   Sent by mail, post-paid, on receipt of price. Address J. N. STEARNS, Publishing Agent, 58 Reade Street, New Yor *                 e   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
