<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7494">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >La Belle Zoa, or, The Insurrection of Hayti </title>
            <author >Pratt, Frances Hammond.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7494</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >La Belle Zoa, or, The insurrection of Hayti</title>
                  <author >Pratt, Frances Hammond.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >96 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Weed Parsons</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Albany </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1854">1854</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-01-23">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>La Belle Zoa, or, The insurrection of Hayti</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7494-00000001"/>  LA BELLE ZOA; OR THE  INSURREECTION OF HAYTI. BY FRANCES HAMMOND PRATT.  ALBANY: WEED, PARSONS AND COMPANY. 1854.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7494-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year eighteen hundred and fifty- three, by Miss FRANCES HAMMOND Pu&amp;TT, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States, for the Northern District of New-York.   Mans HENRIETTA POTTS, PHILADELPHIA. To you, my dear Mrs. POTT, the companion of my juvenile days, who, while I was studying the rudiments of the French language, in pleasing colloquy, learned me its harmony of sound, I dedicate L'HISTOIRE DE LA BELLE ZOA; OR INSURRECTION OF HAYTI, hoping it may serve as a memento of that friendship on which neither time nor distance can have any effect. I can, in retrospect, see your venerable grandmother, as she wiped the tear from her intelligent eye, while relating the murderous scenes of the insurrection; and though I have failed to relate many of the incidents told me by her, yet I think L'HisTOIE Di LA BELLE ZOA is a copy of facts. Your aged grandmother, who witnessed Ob so much of the exterminating war, is now beyond the reach of the black man's rage, and the tear for the butchered colony will no more tremble in her eye. That the same friendship, that united us as we were entering on life's eventful career, may continue through its perilous journey, is the sincere wish of  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7494-00000003"/>   AUTHOR'S APOLOGY. IT is not to trample indirectly on the laws of the South that I give to the world a small portion of the Insurrection of Hayti, for all aggression on a privilege conceded by law I hold to be absolutely wrong. That slavery is a sin, a curse to the slaveholder, is sure; but where is the individual, or who are the class of individuals, endowed with wisdom, will and power sufficient to eradicate the evil, with justice to all parties? It is a matter unworthy a moment's contro- versy, whether the intellect of the negro admits of cul- ture equal to the white man's; but, reasoning from analogy, is it not probable that he varies in features of the mind as much from the white man, as in features of the face and skin? Admit that the families of the earth rise in ability one above another, in consecutive grades, does it follow that the more powerful should  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7494-00000004"/> 6       AUTHOR'S APOLOGY. enslave the weak, or treat with wanton contumely a brother alike subject to the same laws of nature, and amenable to the same common "Father of all?" F. H. PRATT.    LA BELLE ZOA; OR THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI. THAT portion of the Island of Hayti subject to the French government, was, about the year 1791, the theatre of a scene as dating and bloody as any recorded in the annals of history. So deep and well concerted was the conspiracy, that the blow fell, at the same moment, upon all of the devoted country. On the evening of the fatal insurrection, nothing unusual was observed; in fact, nothing alarming could be discovered by the most scrutinizing observer, save the marked taciturnity of the blacks. Their words were few, and their looks seemed sharpened, as if for some deadly act; still, no low whisper, no exchange of expression from face to face was seen. The splendor of the setting sun, lost in the western horizon, gave place to delight- ful twilight; and the beautiful landscape of Hayti, to an improved mind, might have charmed more than  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7494-00000005"/> 8       LA BELLE ZOA; OR the festival and the dance; but to the giddy French of Hayti, I might almost say infidel in thought, there was little in the works of God that could please; little, except the volatilizing circle, the jovial song and the merry dance, that could exhilirate. Monsieur Docou, one of the most opulent planters of the island, varied in character, for he was thoughtful, benevolent and wise. He had a beautiful daughter, in whose mind he had instilled, for the colored population, feelings of humanity. Zoa's fine exterior, added to a highly polished mein, rendered her intellectual endow- ments more captivating; and wherever she appeared, the cry was, "Voici la belle et bon Zoa." At the eventful epoch when sullen revenge burst the manacles of slavery and plunged the murderous dagger into the bosom: of an effeminate population, Zoa was seated at her harp, while the quadrille and waltz were the pas. time of the lighter portion of the devoted French. She was in her sixteenth year, and until that time had wept only tears of affection and joy. She had a brother, known only to her in her childhood, he being in France to finish a collegiate course and acquire a Parisian polish. Monsieur Docou sat listening to the music of his lovely daughter, when his attention was arrested by Adelle, a yellow girl, the waiting-maid of Zoa, who entered the parlor without a summons or the least ap- pearance of vassalage or respect. She placed in the hands of Monsieur Docou a note,   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.      9' and abruptly withdrew. It was written by herself; not perfect in expression, but the spirit of the communica- tion was this: A"My prophetic visions have been the emancipation of my colored race. I have learned from: the historic page that the concentrated energy of the oppressed will insure success; we determine upon a war of extermination, for we have physical strengths courage, no fear of death, and the justice of Almighty God to aid in retribution. Were our bondage merely like that of the children of Israel, we would submit; or, indeed, were we to pass under the harrow or the axe, we would not complain, for we would choose total ex- tinction,rather than protracted suffering; but the plan of our salvation is matured, and the destruction of the French, at this unexpected moment, will be like that of the Trojans when assailed by furious veterans from the wooden horse; but you, sir (for I will not pollute my lips with master), need not fear; your kindness, and that of Mademoiselle Zoa, have saved you. We shall take your plantation, but you can have your money and goods, and are, privileged by Toussaint to embark to whatever place may best suit you. Remain in your house.. You are old and can do nothing.. We are united. We have all the strength of Hayti, and wise and powerful leaders. Precisely at seven the blow will be struck,: and Hayti, with all its wealth and beauty, will be otrs.' I will return and give you notice when you can leave the island." *1  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7494-00000006"/> 10      LA BELLE ZOA; OR "It is what I have long kenned," said Monsieur Docou, as he sprang to raise his daughter, who was fainting with terror at the contents of the note. A mo- ment more, and the bell rang for seven. At this con-, certed time the negroes rose to a single man, and being prepared with murderous weapons, fell upon the unsus- pecting French. The shrieks of women and children, and the groans of the dying, and reiterating yells of the blacks, every moment increased. Almost instantane- ously the streets were filled with mangled bodies. Blood ran in torrents, while the loud voice of Christoph roared in tones of vengeance, urging the infuriated blacks to deal death among the French. At this awful moment the door was opened, and a bleeding body laid at the feet of Monsieur Docou, but,he regarded it not, for at that instant he thought of his wife, who was in delicate health and with her nurse, but before he could reach her door terror had driven her from her room. As she entered the parlor, her eyes fell upon the bloody corse before her; she uttered a piercing shriek, as she threw her arms around the inanimate form, and in wild accents of grief exclaimed, "My son! my son i"Her feeble nerves, too susceptible for a scene like this, her reason gave way; idiocy succeeded insanity, and she regarded only with a vacant stare all that was passing around her. A faint stupor came over Zoa as she heard her mother sing, whisper and laugh around the dead body of her brother, whom she now perfectly recog- nized. Monsieur Docou summoned fortitude sufficient   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     " to lay the body of his son in a remote apartment of his house, while the only requiem was a mother's maniac song. ,/ Francis Eugene Pallette was in his seventeenth year ' ,at the time of this bloody insurrection; he was an emigrant from France. His father having entered into the views of Roland, became obnoxious to his friends, many of whom were of the Jacobin party, and fled for safety to Hayti. Death soon placed him beyond the din of politics, the vortex of revolution, the prison and the block. Francis Eugene had all that enthusiasm which characterized his father, but, without many of his virtues, he was rash, impetuous and headstrong. He loved La Belle Zoa, and his passion was reciprocated. To his widowed mother, he was kind, dutiful and affec- tionate. Entering the parlor a few moments before seven, he presented his mother an exotic plant he had taken much pains to procure. He saw the tears of ma- ternal affection drop on the blanched petals as she took it from his hand. "s It is an emblem of innocence, my son, and may your mind, like its unsullied blossoms, be always unstaiped by vice." She gave the plant to her yellow slave, telling her to give it to the gardener. In a moment the gardener entered, but, as Madam Pal- ]otte thought, probably for some directions concerning the plant. He had the plant in his hand; the clock struck, and seven o'clock bells rang. His countenance lit up with unearthly fury, as he drew from his garb a concealed knife. An instant more, and it was plunged  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7494-00000007"/> 12    :LA BELLE ZOA; OR. into the bosom of Madam Pallette. She fell lifeless on the floor, for so adroit was the black, that she did not even utter a groan. The blood of Eugene rushed furi- ously in his veins; with giant strength he grasped the arm of the black, and turning the knife- to his breast, made him his own assassin./ A shout of joy, uttered in Creole, drew Pallette from his mother's lifeless form. He saw from the window, by the light of the flambeaux, a victim raised high in the air, the entrails on the,side- walk, and around which was Adelle, whom he had al- ways seen attending La Belle Zoa. She was dressed and adorned in fantastic costume, performing an ac- cursed spell, instigated by Christoph, probably to inspire the blacks with certainty of success. "La victoire!" rent the air, as they lowered the victim to the earth ; then raising the eviscerated body, a shout of "Vive "Adelle!" was repeated again and again. To which Adelle replied in a lofty tone, "Donnez la an Chien." The body was then thrown, to the dogs, the pole raised agiin, around which the blacks danced in ecstacy. 'Pal- lette opened the door, regardless of his life, for he thought the victim might have been the mistress of Adelle, his lovely Zoa., He singled out the leader, who was giving orders in Creole, and coming in contact with Christoph he seized his arm: "It is you, Diable noir, who, lurking around Hayti this year past, have been the instigator of all tlis. I swear by the Holy Virgin I will avenge on you the murder of my mother!" "Rash boy," said Christopb, "just emerged from the nursery;   THE INSURRECTION OF IIAYTI.     13 you wish to contend in single combat! I do not box with boys. Does a white skin render the ties of affec- tion more binding than a black one? I will not stain my sword with your blood. Filial affection is sacred." In a moment more he was seized by the iron grasp of Toussaint and dragged to a dungeon. We will now return to the dwelling of M. Docou. His son (as if to fill up the measure of misery) had just returned from France, in all the pride of accomplished manhood, no doubt glowing with self-esteem in the attainment of the enlightened arts, as well as the more polished etiquette of France, to realize a mother's tender embraces, a father's approbating smile, a sister's love; now weltering in his gore and laid in a remote corner of the mansion, to be thrown thence, whenever it best suited the blacks who were soon to take pos- session of his splendid domain-the tumult of female shrieks, and cries of defenceless children for that pro- tection which parental fondness could not give, echoed in the merry tone of his raving, maniacal wife, his daughter alternately fainting in his arms, together with the conviction that his lordly possessions were passing into the hands of those whom he had hitherto consi- dered as forming. a part of his wealth, shook his manly firtitude; but, though alive to every feeling of parental affection and conjugal love, he could not even weep. The noiseless footstep of time chased away the dark- ness of that horrible night, and beautiful aurora again tinged the eastern horizon. Monsieur Docou could per-  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7494-00000008"/> "      LA BELLE ZOA; OR ceive that the French were rallying their troops to sub- due the rebel blacks, but to leave his lunatic wife and fainting child was not in his power, however much his heart bled for the distress of the French. The sun had. scarcely risen again when a tremendous battle com- menced. He saw the elite of the French- troops fall before undisciplined blacks, led on by the desperate Christoph (who in energy and skill might rank with Hannibal of old), and as he gazed, his heart refused to pulsate, till he sank for some moments in senseless stupor. At this moment, Adelle, the heroine of the in- surrection, entered the room. She was in full English costume: her light form was covered with a rich veil reaching nearly to the ground, her regular features set off with an English chapeau, with dancing plumes of the most costly kind, while round her neck blazoned the diamond and the pearl-her eye lit up with the, blaze of victory, and a lofty air which seemed to say "I am your mistress;" but her heart was not steeled to feelings of humanity, for as she gazed on the languid face of M. Docou, his fainting child and maniac wife, to whom, but the morning before, she had bowed in servile. subjection, her feelings of triumph were sub- dued, the hauteur forsook her face, and deathke pallor succeeded the sanguine flush. She raised the head of Monsieur Docou, applied hartshorn, bathed his face and temples with cologne; she then poured cordial into his mouth, but the angel of death seemed intent on destruction. Adelle for some moments had her doubts   THE INSURRECTION OF IIAYTI.     15 whether he would ever again breathe; at length a faint sigh announced to Adelle that there was life. He again opened his eyesl; he seemed for a moment be- wildered, and could not conceive the meaning of all around him. A moment more, and reason regained her empire. He uttered a heavy groan and exclaimed, "I am, indeed, a ruined, fallen man." "Not wholly, my dear master," said Adelle; "you have one faith- ful slave who will not forsake you. I know your afflic- tion; I saw your son as he left the phaeton to enter "hotel de Dieu; I ran to save him, -for I perfectly recollected his features, but before I could reach the spot he fell with the doomed passengers. I informed Christnph of his fate, who ordered him to be taken to your house. Master, my dear master, was the note I handed you too harsh, too disrespectful? I said I would not pollute my lips with the word master, but I retract. Were I the queen of an empire  would acknowledge you my own dear master."  Monsieur Docou recovered strength sufficient to rise. He walked to and fro across the room; he regarded Adelle with kindness, but his lips seemed sealed. A moment more, and another tremendous battle; in. an instant Adelle was out of sight. Her whole soul was in the insurrec- tion, and to the French she no longer felt bound to either render service or show respect. Monsieur Docou again saw the blacks triumphant and his coun- trymen routed or slain. A fearful day passed off, and with it passed Madam Docou. She closed her eyes in  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7494-00000009"/> 16      LA BELLE ZOA; OR a convulsive fit and opened them no more. Monsieur Docou gazed on the object of his early love, but he wept not, for the fountain of his tears was dry. Zoa cried aloud, as she assisted her father in the obsequies of a tender mother, and saw her laid by her brother's bloody corse. The contest for a short time ceased, and the French endeavored to obtain help from abroad. But France was at that time a theatre of anarchy, and could not (or but feebly) assist. Monsieur Docou saw from his window, in the houses deserted by the French, female blacks, dressed in the rich clothes of the murdered owners, and ornamented with the jewels of plundered shops; saw their merry dance and heard their jovial song, forming a dread contrast with the groans of the dying. He, so highly venerated by the blacks, that no one would intentionally do him harm; yet, as he now was, life could scarcely be called a boon. Adelle entered the superb dwelling of her former master. So sudden a transition of power overcame her. She threw herself at the feet of Monsieur Docou and wept for his affliction. Recovering herself a little, she said in a tremulous voice, "Mademoiselle Zoa, your lover, Pallette, is in chains, but it is in your power to -save him. He is doomed to be brought from his dun- geon at midday, eviscerated while alive, the spell of haruspicy performed, and his body thrown to the dogs. But go to Toussaint; beg the life of your lover; he will   THE INSURRECTION OF TAYTI.     17 listen, for Christoph shall escort you." Zoa, who was prepared for every species of affliction, with less emotion than might have been expected, said, "Father, shall I go!" " have nothing to say," was his response. "De- prived of you, I could not exist; but I am only a withered stalk, upon which the tempest of grief beats heavily; yet you cling around me for protection, like a tender vine around an impotent support, that crumbles at the touch." A few moments ,discussion, and Zoa set off with Adelle to beg the life of her lover. They had walked but a few steps, when a tall, graceful man, clad in English uniform, approached them. His eyes were a clear blue, his hair rather inclined to curl, and his face yellow. His whole appearance was commanding, and his expression seemed lit up with the fire of con- quest. He took the arm of Adelle, who for the first time articulated the usual form, "This is Monsieur Christoph Briant." In all the etiquette of the day, he kissed the hand of Mademoiselle Zoa, and led her forward to Toussaint. As she approached the hero of Hayti, who was giving orders in Creole to troops of color, clothed in the uniform stripped from the bodies of the fallen French-as she caime near where he stood- as she looked on his athletic form, his martial air, and marked the fire of his dark eye, the blood fioze in her veins, andher limbs refused to support her. Falling on her knees before the sable warrior, in tremulous ac- cents she made known her. request. "You beg the life of De Pallette; he has outraged the chiefs, heaped on  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7494-00000010"/> 18      LA BELLE ZOA; OR us sarcasm and contempt, and consequently must feel our power. You say, without your lover you cannot live; suppose his doom irrevocable, would you deem it a boon to die with him "Zoa raised her soft blue eye and assured Toussaint that the sight of her lover would take from her all fears of the executioner's knife, and to his proposal she would accede. Toussaint regarded the beautiful creature before him, and replied: "4 Rise, fair lady; your beauty, more eloquent than words, has prevailed.. Your lover shall be released; and ever bear in mind, that the mossy curl and dark skin are not always. the appendages of a hard heart. Your known kindness to our now emancipated race ,merits that es- teem which the benignity of your countenance inspires; but, dear lady, the Marquis is fiery and vindictive--I greatly fear he will not prove a companion equal to your merit. Frenchmen are fickle and inconstant. What delights them, to-day may to-morrow be an object of disgust. I therefore decree that your own hand take off his fetters; then gratitude, full often more lasting than love, will bind him to you. At six o'clock I will appoint my guard to attend you to the prison door, and Adelle may be your companion." Zoa's graceful countenance told the overflowing of her grateful heart, and to the hero of Hayti was more powerful than words. Presenting Toussaint with a string of diamonds, and, her miniature, set in gold, she left without uttering a word. Precisely at six o'clock i   THE INSURRBETION OF -AYTI.    1 Adelle was at Monsieur Docou's to attend Zoa to the prison of Pallette. "We will lose no time," said Zoa, as she hastily caught the arm of Adelle. ' Pallette may, ere this, have fallen a victim to his own fears, for who can invent torture thSt equals a negro's rage. But hush! My dear Adelle, you know me: I do not implicate all. Beneath a dark' skin there are hearts where all the kind emotions, all the virtues reside." Protected from the fury of the blacks by a guard of Toussaint's, in a few moments they were at the prison //of Pallette, where, with the most horrid forebodings, he had been awaiting the completion of his fate; exhausted with suspense, tired nature could no longer resist the influence of sleep, and Pallette, for the first time in this dread abode, was insensible to the horrors of his condition. Zoa approached Pallette, and laying her fair hand on his pallid brow, articulated the name she so much loved. Pallette started at the well known voice; he opened his eyes in wildness, and said: "Where am Hin a world of spirits? and Zoa with me! I see, by the dim taper before me, her angelic form; but ha! I feel the chain that binds me. I am, O horrid! I am to be a sacrifice; my body the subject of hellish divination; my tortures to terrify even those who inflict them. O Zoa, Zoa! art thou free from this scene of blood?. Is it thy beloved shade that visits me? Come, then, ye monsters of cruelty; the tortures  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7494-00000011"/> 20  i    LA BELLE ZOA; OR of flaying cannot last forever: it's a short job. I shall soon be with you." Zoa wept aloud, as she hastened to unfasten his chain. Pallette was conscious of Zoa's real entity when he felt the chain fall, and was raised to an erect posture. "I know not by what miracle I am released. I fear  everything. Zoa, my own adored Zoa, why did you jeopardize your life for me? An eternity of devotion could not repay the gratitude I owe you." "Love and gratitude," soliloquized Christoph, who stood within hearing, "how powerful the combina- tion!" "May whole life," continued Pallette, " if I escape the black man's knife, shall be to you, my love, one continued act of recompense. The sight of you, my angel, has restored me to a vitality which, I had thought could never again be mine." Zoa answered only with tears, as she conducted her lover, escorted by a guard, to her father's house, which but one week before was the seat of domestic peace; but now dismal, replete with dire foreboding, and, withal, the repository of the dead. As they neared the mansion of Docou, no porter, as once, opened an entrance; no golden goblet, filled with the choicest wine, bespoke a welcome. In place of the brilliant saloon, lit up with waxen candles, a dim taper only was burning, near which sat Monsieur Docou, his head reclining on his hand, his spectacles raised above   THE fISUtRRECTIOl OFP HAYTI.    21 his eyes, and beside him lay the Book of Life; on a blank leaf before him he had pencilled the words: "Vetgeance belongeth to me, and I will repay it, saith the Lord." He rose and gave Pallette his hand, looked on his prison garb, his haggard face and changed expression. "Our misery, though the most favored of the French, is almost beyond endurance. Heaven has recognized ,the bondage of the blacks, and our retribution is just. We may be the most fortunate, for we have some pro- tection, and a small portion of our wealth allowed us; but what is to be our fate? Here are swarms of piratical men, who, under a fair exterior, a show of kindness, gather the gold of the island, fill their vessels with the richest goods, and then set sail, leaving the wretched owners to sure destruction. This has already been done, and the same fate may be ours. The en- raged blacks are monsters of cruelty; but the subtile plotting white men surpass them in treachery. Zoa, you must prepare a little food for Pallette; a cordial, if you have it. We are without attendants; we are almost without the articles necessary for our susten- ance. Our lot is hard; but I cannot, in looking on the past, reproach myself for cruelty to my slaves. They have been obedient; nor have their bodies borne marks of my infliction." At this moment Adelle en- tered, for the safety of the Docou family was at her heart.  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7494-00000012"/> 22      LA tBELL1L 20A; on - I come," said Adelle, "to tell you that there is disaffection-among the leaders. Dtessailles and Regaud are not pleased with the release of Pallette, but Tous- saint is a cool, calculating chief, and will no doubt soon restore unity.. I would advise Pallette to keep out of sight, that is, from the open window; for, if seen, all may not be well." Pallette turned on Adelle an eye that had lost some. what of its sarcastic expression; his haughty spirit was 'not, however, subdued by the prison, fear of torture, and death. He gave not in return for the intelligence she brought him, the slightest indication of gratitude. "Master, dear master," continued Adelle, "the lead* era are in consultation; they propose, for your former kindness to the colored portion of Hayti, to give you annuallythe avails of your plantation." At this, Monsieur Docou raised his head from the escritoir before him. :!I shall feel myself unworthy of the boon, for my own conscience reproves me. I have bought and v  sold, yes, disposed of my slaves, reckless of the cha- racter of those with whom I entrusted their lives; and though the black man may grant me pairon, still incensed Heaven may not affix a seal of foxriveness. But you must tell me, Adelle, before you again leave, the rules of this exterminating war, for rules you must have." "Certainly we have; every slave is privileged to show kindness to a kind master, provided no proof   THRiE NtStMftCECTION OP HAYS.   28 positive be brought of his former cruelty, He may be assisted by his slaves to leave the island, and take all his slaves see fit to gather up for him ; their gold and silver coin they are allowed to keep; but no one but master is protected solely by Toussaint. No rules to prohibit plunder when houses and shops are deserted  yet an account of plunder taken is handed to Dessailles, who registers the sum.- Female chastity is not to be violated; still to this rule there is not implicit obedi- ence. I could not have believed the negroes so cruel, so revengeful: though my own color, I do not justify their deeds." Here Monsieur Docou whirled his gold headed cane, as if an important idea had passed through his mind; He knew that but a small portion of the negro blood ran in her veins.             ' "You' have not told us all," said Monsieur Docou I "you must tell us how this conspiracy was managed, that the exterminating blow was at the same' moment struck throughout 'the island, and how such secrecy of puipose has been kept among the blacks." "I will first order your nouriture; you see I have changed from waiting-maid to steward." In a few moments Adelle returned and commenced the detail: 4 It is twelve months since I first thought that sla- very was the determined will of God, and that out race wore the mark that ratified the decree.  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7494-00000013"/> 24      LA BELLE 2OA; OP. "You know how I used to go to and from your country laundress; and as I was ond day returning with heavy luggage, I sat down under an orange tree. Being much fatigued, I fell asleep; while slumbering under its shade, a strange vision rose before me. I thought I saw coming towards me a stranger of martial mein, holding in his hand a vine scorched with the intense  heat of the sun, and covered with blessures, from which issued blood and sweat. A strong feeling of sympa- thy overcame me, which the stranger observing, desired me to draw near and breathe on the vine. I did so. It instantly ceased to ooze blood and sweat; it branched forth, the leaves assuming the freshness of May verdure, and rising in height, while it overshadowed the Island of Hayti. I saw our dark race pass and repass under its shadow. I saw churches and halls of science rise, from which came forth people of color. Meanwhile the stranger remained with his feet firmly fixed on the ground, around which the vine clung for support. "I awoke and saw before me my black brethren, bending in a field of cane, reeking with sweat, the blood dropping from many, whose limbs had been bruised by cruel taskmasters, men callous to every feel- ing of humanity, and whose savage look was the expression of the infernal regions. As I looked, my heart quailed within me. Is this, thought I, the deter- mined fate of the black skin and mossy curl? No alternative'-no mitigation! Going again to your laun- dress with linen for her to cleanse, I sat again to rest A,. . .:   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.    25 under my favorite tree and took my book to read; at that moment I saw coming towards me a stately figure, whose yellow skin- told me he could claim relationship with the whites; the force and dignity of his air, brought to my mind the bearer of the vine. He approached the place where I sat, and asked me what I held in my hand. I trembled, and endeavored to place the book in a bundle of the linen, saying, 'Mistress has forgot- ten to take her book.' He approached and took the book in his hand. He eyed me sharply, and after a mo- ment's pause, said, ' Your intelligent face tells me that you can read; are you a free mulatto, or a slave' ' A slave,' said I, almost fainting with terror. ' Be not afraid,' said he, ' I am a free mulatto, but a friend to the slaves;' then taking the book, with a look that won my confidence, 'he said, turning the title page to me, , What book is it ' The History of Greece,' said I. ' Read, then,' said he, ' for I believe you can.' i lost all fear and read a page. 'It is enough,' said he; ' a pro- digy, indeed, what no one could have thought,' viz., that a slave could read; 'Now tell me,' said he, 'nor fear that I shall disclose the secret, how came you by your knowledge of letters ' I then told him a secret, hith- erto unknown to you. V  "During the visit of your English friend, Madam Howe, she entrusted her little girl to a careless nurse, and often it was my good fortune to save her from the most imminent danger. Once she fell into the large reservoir;, I plunged in and rescued her at the peril of my own 2  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7494-00000014"/> 26      LA BELLE ZOA; OR life. The English are grateful, and Madam Howe tried every way to requite the service I had rendered her. She gave me an embroidered scarf, which I re- turned, telling her it did not suit a slave. 'How then,' said she, ' shall I reward you for the services you are daily rendering me? I will purchase your freedom, whatever may be the price. I will learn you to read and write.' An electric shock passed over me at the lat- ter phrase; I fell on my knees before her, and said, 'My mistress will not part with me; she is not in need of money; she would not sell me for all the wealth in Hayti; but, dear mistress, will you learn me to read here ' She seemed greatly affected, and remarked, ' The laws of Hayti forbid learning a slave to read.' But after a long silence, she said, I' will do it. I rise early; come to my room when the rest of the family are in bed, and I will teach you; I shall soon be again in England, and there the Haytian laws cannot hurt me.' I rose in transport, and the next morning she commenced the task. ' It seems, she would often say, 'Adelle, that you Have supernatural aid.' Indeed, my tact for learning was wonderful. Always attending a kind mistress, I profited by her teachers almost as much ao herself. I marked the way each word was spoken, and imitated it. I learned to read writing of Madam  Howe; and a kind master seeing me so anxious to learn, gave the word of encouragement, in opposition to the laws of Hayti. Five different mas- ters came daily to instruct my mistress, three of whom   THE INSURREOTION OF HAY'I.     27 were of equal importance to me as to her. Of her reading master, I learned correct pronunciation; of her writing master, the manner of holding and using my pen.; and of her master who taught her history, I ac- quire'd a love of liberty. Christoph listened as to an oracle, and when I had finished he said; ' Adelle (for I had told him my name), look at the exuberance of this fertile soil; mark the richly diversified landscape be. fore us, as if nature, with plastic skill, had exhausted a store of munificence. Observe, too, yon rolling curricle, bearing the sportive French to the merry dance, there reveling in festivity until tired nature refuses to partici. pate; the interim is passed in concerting new and varied scenes. Look at those well trained vassals in the field of cane, lashing with a bloody scourge our degraded brethren, whose sweat purchases the wealth of Hayti, furnishes,dissipation, which enervates the Frenchman's mind and heightens his licentious passion. But think you that nerves strung with vigor will always brook this outrage on humanity? No! aided by Almighty God, I swear to avenge my black brethren, to pursue with the weapons of death these vile oppressors, until Hayti shall present to the wondering world a revolution achieved by those considered the scum of earth.' "His pathos stilled the flow of life; I stood motion. less, as he advanced and put into my hand a small par- cel, enveloped in blood and curls from a black man's head. ' Take this, and swear by the living God that you will keep the secret of our conspiracy; it is for you,  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7494-00000015"/> 28      'LA BELTT ZOA; OR -life or death.' 1 knelt down and took the oath. 'Pre- serve,' said he, the parcel in your hand; it is, from the head of a traitor, who, to gain preferment, betrayed our secret to his master; but I had timely-knowledge of it, and have placed both where I fear no farther de- velopments of our plot; in like manner will Christoph deal with all who attempt divulging our secret. Adelle, you can read and write; to-morrow, you will find in the hollow of this tree a paper, telling you who I am and what are my intentions.' He walked off, leaving me in bewilderment. I rose, and as I looked around, the face of nature seemed changed; .the dazzling eclat of entire liberty blazoned before my mental vision. I walked homeward with bright anticipations of the future; silently pondering the nature and obligation of the fiarful oath I had taken." She then took from her portfolio the paper found in the hollow tree, and read the  HSTORY OF CHRISTOPH. "My first recollections of life were with a fiendish master. I was born a house slave, and eye witness to acts of cruelty that even now curdle the blood in my viens. I had a mulatto mother, and as near as I can recollect, she was perfect symmetry in form. I was always with her, for she was cook or second cook, and it was my business to go at her bidding. After the toil of cooking was over, she would take me in her-arms $1   THE IWS JRRECTION OF HAYT.     29 and shed tears of maternal affection on my little face, calling me her love, her joy, her own dear Cittie; but there came a day, never to be effaced from the pages of memory, a day that dropped in my heart a bitter seed that shall germinate and grow until the leaf shall absorb the blood of the Haytian slaveholder; full well do I remember each transaction, each event that transpired before me on that fearful day; I well remember the extra- ordinary movements around the superb mansion of my master; the dazzle of splendid furniture, the magnificent eqqipage of horses, carriages, and entire men liveries of mulatto slaves, all struck my juvenile mind with wonder. "s My mother was dressed in plain white lawp, and on her head she wore a turban of scarlet hue; I thought her beautiful in the extreme, and even I felt a boyish pride in the new cap-a-pie. As for myself, I was dressed in a new scarlet robe, 'iy waist was encircled with a belt, seemingly transpareht and fringed with gold, a splendid plume was put in my hand, the handle of which seemed of pure gold; I heard the trumpet, and immediately the air was rent with ' Vive le roi!' I can now fully comprehend the meaning of all that then passed-Louis Caput and Maria Antoinette were on the island; many of the grandees of France were in the train, a party of whom were to dine with my master. My mother, though the most skilful cook, it seems, was selected to arrange the tables. Seven damask cloths of the finest texture, placed one above the other, to be removed each one with the removal of the dishes, when different fopd  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7494-00000016"/> 30    .  LA BELLE ZOA; OO was served, and even the dessert required the removal of them, wine and brandy being all the while-kept on the table. When the first cloth was removed, a large spider lay concealed; it darted forth and dropped on the rich dress of a Marchioness, who either fainted or feigned to faint. All was confusion, and my mother, foreseeing her destiny, left the room; my master follow- ed her; I saw him strike a blow-she fell; I saw the brute slightly examine the body, to see, probably, if life was extinct; I heard him order her thrown- into a 'deep hole-the slaves' sepulchre; I followed and saw the order executed; I returned and was summoned to my former task of brushing away the flies, and saw my master among his gay companions, he being the gayest of all.  / "From this moment a new nature took possession of me; what had hitherto delighted my childish fancy. was no longer a source of joy. One deep and absorb- ing passion predominated, and was continually nur- tired and fed; my day dreams and nocturnal visions were one constant study to gratify the dire revenge that rankled in my breast. I writhed in the agony of my soul, but was unobserved by all, excepting one who was an English gentleman (and a frequent visitor), cast on me a look of compassion, and often, as he passed me, unobserved by the rest of the company, put into my hand small pieces of money, I do not recollect how much; he had often done so, and my mother would expend it for confectionery; but now it looked like a t   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTL     31 worthless article, for I had no mother to take me by her, and smile to see me enjoying the avails of his generosity. After some months, I saw the foreigner no more; for a few, years my life was monotonous. My mistress was extremely penurious, and more than once stepped between me and my master's uplifted hand, which had it, with the bludgeon he held, descended on me, it would have consigned me to the sepulchre of my mother. I do not attribute those acts to goodness of heart, but to fears of losing What was a thrifty French- man's wealth. My master was the vilest of the vile; I will not attempt to enumerate his many acts of cruelty to his slaves, farther than related to myself. Once as I returned from the place where they had thrown my mother, bathed in teals, he laughed heartily at my grief, and asked me why I did not bring her along with me. I cast on him a look of vengeance, and said, 'You may throw me with her, for all I care;' and muttered low, ' The time will come when I may pull out your tongue for this;' the expression was prophetic. I felt a burning thirst for vengeance, a thirst that has deepened with years, and, modified by classical lore, has ripened into retaliation; for the destiny of the French is, fixed - their days are numbered -the decree has gone forth-the deadly blow is sure -a blow that no earthly power can avert. But to continue: I cannot exactly tell my age at this important era of my life. My ignorance; when a slave, was such that I took no note of time, but I was probably some twelve years or more I  .  j  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7494-00000017"/> 32      LA BELLE ZOA; OR old, when an, English foreigner visited my master. He was received with great cordiality, for he was remotely related (as I have since learned) to my mistress. He would fix on me a long, steady gaze, and often, when my name was called, I thought I could see an affec- tionate: glance. I was always in attendance, for I was waiting slave. "The Englishman, Lord Briant, said, as I ran to hand his golden beaded cane (seeing he was about to walk out), 'Hayti has improved in wealth since I last visited the island; owing, I suppose, to the increase of blacks.' ' A herd of miscreants,' said my master;' they .cost more whipping than the amount of gain.' 'Suppose then you sell me this little fellow ' ' And what would you do with him in England 1 they are death on slavery in your country. ' Oh, he might have his liberty; he would serve me just as well.' 'Yes, so you say, but we slave-holders know better.' ' Has he a mother ' 'No; his mother, by inattention to her business, highly offend- ed me; I gave her an unlucky blow; the cause was just, but it cost me her full value, for in an instant she was good for nothing.' Dead, do you say ',. Yes, dead as a door nail.' Lord Briant seemed agitated, for I watched his motion; for at that time I could not comprehend what liberty meant. After some moments, Lord B. said, 'I will give you five hundred guineas for this little fellow.' Half of that sum,' said my mas- ter, 'is more than he is worth. He is a refractory blade, and ten to one, if I keep him, if I don't crack   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     38 his skull, and he would do me nothing.' -The Sum was soon agreed on, and I was the property of Lord Bri- ant, who sailed a few hours after the purchase. A prosperous sail soon landed us on the English shore; a happy land, where worth and intellect are the standard, and slavery cannot exist. "Lord Briant could speak the French in its purity; I could understand it, but'spoke Creole (imperfect French), for my master always spoke to his slaves in that style. I now realized-the blessing of perfect liberty. I was clad in the habiliments of a tyro, and placed under the tuition of select teachers. I was led-step by step through the various departments of science; but when I entered the military service, all the enthusiasm of my nature was lit up, and I longed to emancipate my dark race, and unfurl the banner of freedom in Hayti. Powerful associations continued even in my sleeping hours, and I often started from a nocturnal vision, as I seemed confronting and dealing death to the oppressors of my black brethren. In these hallucinations of thought, I full often came in conitact with the assassin of my mother; tore out his cruel heart and mocking tongue, that could jeer the filial sorrow of my boyhood. The conflict of my mind impaired my health, and my physical strength gave way., Lord Bri- ant observed the change and inquired the cause. ';You seem,' said he, ' at times, to be in bewilderment.' Hii kindness of manner inspired me with confidence, and I frankly confessed all. I told him I thought the laws of nature had not bound the negroes to degradation, or *2  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7494-00000018"/> 34      LA BELLE ZOA; OR stamped them as subjects of abuse; that the French of Hayti were enervated by dissipation, and conse. quently a feeble race; that the Jacobin tornado had swept off the force of France, and the busy war-mak- ing Bonaparteb had use for the soldiers left; that the recent oppression of the free mulattoes would enlist them in the cause of freedom; that a war of extermi- nation would be of short duration, and no doubt suc- cessful. 'An exterminating war!' said Lord Briant; you little realize what you say.' He rose, wiped the large drops of perspiration from his face. He walked to the window, seeming anxious to hide the emotion of his manner; then went to his library, took down a book and looked at the statistics of Hayti. I could not tell whether there was assent or disapprobation in his mind; he made no farther remarks, but retired to ano- ther apartment; the next morning I was summoned to Lord Briant's room; he was sitting in an arm chair, his face enveloped in a large pocket handkerchief, and so absorbed in thought that he did not at first notice me. I walked across the room and placed myself on a settee. A few moments' silence, and Lord Briant raised his: large hazel eyes, in which glistened a tearful ex- pression. ' Christoph, said he, your mirror must long ere this have told you that your features more nearly resemble the white than the black man. But trace not your paternity to the fickle family of France; nobler blood courses your veins. Yes, Chrisloph, you are my own kin; and let your future course, your courage,   TILE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.    35 stability of purpose and perseverance, prove you worthy of your illustrious progenitors;' then handing me a letter, almost worn out with frequent handling, he walked out and left me alone. An exact copy of the letter reads thus: "' MY DEAR BROTHER--My sun is now setting, and the darkness of the tomb will soon gather over me. A life spent in the whirl of dissipation, plants with thorns the pillow of death. And my agony in looking back on the past, my repentance for self indulgence, and all that rashness that has marked my career of folly, efface the guilt that broods over me. I should be fully acquitted, but my own contrition will avail nothing without the intercession of Him who died that the guilty might live. I am urged to have a priest and receive absolution, but the very words torment me; the Catholic faith leads to infidelity, and is sealing the fate of the French. Brother, dear brother, shall I tell you all? shall I tell to the sole survivor of our family, crimes that stain our noble name, and will red- den the face of a brother whose whole life has beeh spotless rectitude Yes, brother, I will tell. Before this will reach you, 1 shall be in the world of spirits. I shall not meet the keen look of a brother, which even in imagination fiightens me. My physician has come, he says I may continue a few days. I must cease writing and attend to his directions. It is all over with me; my wounds are mortal; they have been examined  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7494-00000019"/> 36      LA BELLE ZOA; OR and pronounced incurable; this I knew, but when coming from the medical attendant, it sets the last seal, aind almost distracts one. Brother, I have in this place a a child, a mulatto son. I see the crimson tinge your manly front. You hate me; 'tis well. I hate myself, but I am not callous to. the voice of nature; the tie of bcosanguinity is strong, when the father is not a brute. His name is Christoph. His mother was a mulatto, of superior mind, and was for a slight offence, or rather for ho offence at all, struck dead by her master. I was ,a guest at the table when the wicked deed was done. I saw her master give her a withering look; I believe it was for some malarrangement of the table, I could not exactly tell what, for we were all merry with wine. She quailed in his presence and went directly out of the room. He followed her; 1 heard one groan and no more. Christoph followed, but in a moment returned with swollen eyes and performed the duties of his task to a charm. I did intend to have bought the child and taken him with me to England, for his features, though regular, hear no resemblance to ours. It is my dying request that you buy the child. I leave it with you; deliberate, in your mind. my petition; and if you concede, may the God of heaven bless you! But, brother, I-have not done: I will gather a little more strength end tell you the sequel. I have frequented the gaming table, and drank deeply of the inebriating bowl; in 4.moment when the fumes of brandy had lit up my passions to fury, I gave the mad challenge that has   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     37 destroyed me. I have participated in all the fashion- able vices of dissolute Hayti, and am now festering in wounds which, but for a broken constitution, might be healed. I think of Christoph, and feel the yearning of a fatherjowards him. I would he one day in England breathe the pure air of liberty, for liberty is not to be found in Hayti. Were I to choose between the vassal- age of-the black and the white man in Hayti, I would choose the latter; the slavery of vice binds its votaries faster than the fetter binds the slave. .The dealings of God are just; I do believe the slaveholder is cursed with more galling slavery than that which he inflicts. When Babylon shall be called to give up the cup of the wrath of her fornication, then the slaveholder will appear. My pulse grows tremulous; the excitement of writing is too much; the attenuated thread of .life will soon break asunder. Let my body remain in this land of pollution; it is the fittest place for your repent- ant, dying brother.' "My feelings, when I had finished reading this letter, beggar description. I laid it down and groaned aloud. In a moment, Lord Briant was with me; I knelt before him and wept; he mingled tears with mine, for my emotions were reciprocated. It was the first time, since the days of boyhood, that I recollect of having wept. The tempest of feeling began to abate, for in tears I found relief. The busy hand of recollection turning at will the pages of the book of memory, a panorama of  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7494-00000020"/> 38      LA BELLE ZOAj -OR the past floated before me. I could easily comprehend why the Englishman at the table had shown so much sympathy for me. Lord Briant rose from his seat, but not self-possessed; the effort to speak seemed great; at length, but not with his usual equanimity of manner, he said, 'Chiristoph, you have now the secret of your birth ; you are my own kin, and are, or soon will be, the sole representative of our name. Take my name, not as from master to slave, but with my sanction, as a legitimate right. I am frail, and shall soon pass away; my eyes will soon be closed on all earthly possessions, and to me my large fortune will be of no use. I have, for reasons best knowl to myself, chosen a life of celibacy; fortuitous circumstances in early life deprived me of the only one I ever loved; farther than this I will not say. It is not a time, when the fingers of age have torn from my head the curls of beauty, to relate an affair of love; I only say that I have no warmer affection for any earthly object than for you, conse- quently you will soon become my heir. I could have wished that you might have watched over the cradle of myold age, but I will submit. The sins of Hayti call for an avenging hand, and you must go. Should you fall in the hazardous contest, my fortuneis bequeathed to various charitable institutions; but should you become 'the sole possessor, to you I leave the provi!ce of doing good, and may Almighty God prepare your heart for acts of charity! It matters not, whether in Hayti or England you bestow your charity; only be judicious in   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     39 your selection of objects, nor suffer your beneficence to extend to the undeserving. I fully sanction your enterprize; let your ingenuity devise, and your bravery strike, a blow that shall liberate the slave and place high in the annals of fame the name of Christoph; and when you have achieved a conquest, and Hayti presents to the wondering world a revolution, the like not known in the 'history of age-, stain not your glory by a mar- riage with the French, but choose a mulatto companion; and may Heaven direct you in your choice.' These are the words of the great Lord Briantl; and as he walked out of the room I could see the big tears roll down his furrowed cheek. I shall say no more of what passed until I arrived in this place; I found that Toussaint, Mocaga, L'Ouverture and Rigaud had superseded me in a plan to liberate the slaves. I concealed my English origin; for they, being French mulaltoes, have an in- stinctive dread for the English. I have identified myself with them- the negroes are and will be sure of the. exact moment of insurrection; you are now one of our confederates, and have the seal of secrecy, the parcel of blood. A wretched negro, to gain preferment from his master, betrayed us; by subtlety, I decoyed them both to a place where I put it out of their power to make known our plot. I was aware of. his perfidy by an accidental word of his, for negroes are not remarkable for secretiveness; and when I told him our plans were discovered, that he was the traitor, he trem- bled in my presence. We have, by a chemical process,  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7494-00000021"/> 40       LA BELLE ZOA; OR  preserved his blood and that of the white man. We  mingle it together, ard having preserved the curls from the black man's head, we envelop a sinall curl of -the latter, as you see in the mixture, and give each negro the token. I know it is of no use to hand it to you, Adelle, declaring it a spell, a charm, a species of necro? mancy, as your cultivated mind is superior to imposition, but on the ignorant black it must be practiced; it is the only thing that will inspirit them and insure success. This is the sequel of the words of Christoph." The next-morning Adelle returned. The prelimi- naries of 'embarkation are made," said she; " choose your place of future residence, and gather your gold, your gold and silver plate, for I know, with all the protection our chiefs can give, your lives are in danger,  It is, O, it is a dreadful sight .to behold! ' I have just seen a company of blacks tearing out. the heart of a cruel taskmaster, while the wretched sufferer yet lived. Little indeed did' I realize, when I took the parcel in blood, the horrors of this day. I have bitterly, very bitterly, repented of my arrogance in handing you a note at the time of insurrection. Never did I think the negro race could have been guilty of such acts of cruelty as I have witnessed; I never saw, in all my life of slavery, one act of cruelty in my master or mis- tress' dealing with slaves. Master, dear master, can you forgive me for my haughty conduct. on the evening of the rebellion?" f.  ,                  . .   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     41 Monsieur Docou, whose heart was softened by afflic- tion, tenderly replied: "Yes, Adelle, you are forgiven. I have not felt towards you the least unkindness; and were the French victorious, order restored, and we again in possession of our plantation, freedom should be yours, and a for- tune from my own funds," Adelle threw off her rich English dress, and resumed a costume more in keeping with her, former station. The grief-stricken family gathered the most valuable movables, together with all the gold Monsieur. Docou had in his possession. A sallow, thin faced, sailor-like man entered, in company with Christoph; the latter respectfilly approached Monsieur Docou, and was ex- tending his hand. A rude yell in the street announced that more soldiers from France were at hand; Christoph lost the etiquette of his manner and abruptly left. "So," said the rawny boned man, "You are pick- ing up; you don't mean to leave much forr the black dogs. I can't understand their jabbering in Creole, for not one speaks good French; but as near as I can make it out, I guess they are sure of being master. The black lubbers! I'd like to sink the whole crew of the rascals." "Liberty," said Monsieur Docou, "is deeply rooted in the heart of man. We can look with more tolerance on the cruelty of blacks than that of masters to their slaves; the latter were receiving the emolument of their labor, and had the slaves been treated with more hu-  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7494-00000022"/> 42      LA BE T;T ZOA.; oR manity, this insurrection would not have been. I have myself trampled on the rights of nature, and am now reaping the bitter fruits of aggression." "Well, well," said the sailor, "( we have a confessor in our ship; so, in case of storms or danger, he can put you heavenward." "I was not born a Roman Catholic," said Monsieur Docou.  I quarrel with no persuasion. My wife was a Catholic, and tutored Zoa in that faith; but my Bible teaches me that the mercy of God is not purchased with gold." "You are right, you are right, sir. I don't believe, myself, a man can sin all the days of his life, and then, when his money is no longer of use to him, buy a seat in Heaven with it; that don't look like a fair thing; 'pon my 'word it don't. By that, what are the poor devils to do who have no money to pay for heaps of sin? I guess, boss, you'd find it good in our ship; we've got Protestants, too, who pray for themnselves. How now, girls, you've got heaps of gold things- gold table-spoons, ha!. 'pon my word, a gold coffee- pot; this ere barrel won't hold it all; I guess Boston -never seen so much gold all at once before. Pick it all up, girls; don't leave a bit for the black curses, who won't know how to use it. More yet! a gold waiter; I never seen the like. as much as I've .been over the world. I guess gold grows here, in Hayti; i'ts a devil of a shame to be obliged to leave this rich place for the niggers. I'll see it all sfe' aboard. The Nancy is a   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     43 good craft; our captain is an honest man -one of your stanch Protestants, who don't believe in paying money for sin. He can't talk French, but I'm the boy that can. You'll see his honesty, if he can't tell you, with- out you can understand. See, boss, that your Bible goes; that's the book for honest folks. Well, well, I see all's right here, so I'll just go and see how things go in the ship. Good-by, boss; good-by, girls." As the sailor left, Monsieur Docou rose from his seat with troubled brow. "This is a sad dilemma,of ours. I do not like that vortical sailor; he seems anything to suit his own inte- rest. His extreme anxiety to substantiate his captain's honesty is a bad omen; but, situated as we are,.we must venture, and leave the result with Providence." The next morning, Monsieur Docou, Zoa, Pallette and Adelle, saw that all was safely stowed on board the ship. The captain was the reverse of the interpre- ter, but no more prepossessing. His eye was downcast, his countenance sour, his figure athletic, and, on the whole, he seemed like one in deep thought, studying some deadly ruse. They left the ship and were wending their way homeward (if so it may be called), when suddenly a volley of muskets from the ship arrested their atten- tion. They looked towards the wharf for the cause; and when the firing ceased they turned around, and to their utter amazement missed Zoa. They saw a com- pany of blacks leading, as they supposed, a negress, but  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7494-00000023"/> "      LA BELLE ZOA; OR could see nothing of Zoa. The shock was electric -all were bewildered; the senses of Monsieur Docou seemed locked in stupor, Adelle ran for Christoph, and Pallette uttered a torrent of imprecations on the rebels, swearing that the negroes had made a league with Lucifer, and 'that the fiend of' hell was at hand to assist them. It was with difficulty that Monsieur Docou reached the house. As they were known to be the favored family, the negroes cleared the way and suppressed all insult. The steps of Monsieur Docon faltered as he entered his door; he was assisted by Pallette until he reached his arm chair. The morning sun arose with usual splendor, but the glory of his rays were sickening to Monsieur Docou; he was in the same position as when helped into his chair by Pallette. His senile form could ill support his accumulated miseries, and the vigor of his nerves gave way. A cordial was administered by Pallette. He opened his eyes feebly, then closed them again, as if it was too much to see the light of day. The light footsteps of Adelle were heard; she approach. ed the chair where Monsieur Docou sat. She was dressed as when a slave; her lofty air gave place to an obsequious expression, as she knelt before her former master; 'she then arose, and with her usual assiduity endeavored, by all means in her power, to restore his strength, for the expression of his eye indi- cated that his mind was stupefied, not deranged. As Monsieur Docou roused a little, and saw this affection.   THE INSURRECTION OF IIAYTI.    45 ate girl striving to bring back his wonted vitality, he faintly articulated, "Adelle, you are my child!" and relapsed into a stupor. Presently rallying again, he said, in scarcely an audible voice, "My punishment is just." Adelle, intent upon supporting his sinking ener- gies, and recalling his (as she supposed) wandering mind, did-not notice this expression, but on the ear of Pallette it fell with weight. Music in the street announced the guard of- Tous- saint; a moment more, and the door bell rang with unu- sual force. Adelle ran, and as she opened the door the beautiful Zoa was standing before her. Adelle took the arm of her weeping mistress, and led her to' her father. Monsieur Docou opened his eyes -he closed them again, and not until he felt the caresses of his child could he realize that she still lived.  Grief," said he, ,( and the weight of years, sap the fountain of my strength, and 1 feel that I am tread- ing the pathway of my second childhood. Zoa, my own dear Zoa, do not relate, until to-worrow's sun, the terrible adventure, nor shock my shattered nerves by a recital of the manner you were stolen from my sight. The recovery of my darling, I owe, no doubt, to the good Toussaint, or more subtle and energetic Chris- toph." Another day dawned on the miserable French of Hayti. Time, ever rolling and noiseless, will move on, while the voluptuary, in the intoxication of pleasure,  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7494-00000024"/> "      LA BT T1r ZoA; o0- would wish its wheels more tardy; the wretclhed, counting each moment, il the bitterness of their anguish think time moves too slow. The family of Monsieur Docou, comprising Adelle, for she chose to remain with them, sat taciturn, watching each coming event. Christoph did not appear to apprise them when they could leave the place of anarchy and blood. They did not turn back to the last page of the past, but were looking forwards with the most dubious forebodings. At length Christoph appeared, with a countenance that plainly said all was not well. "It is all over with you," said Christoph; " the ship has left. All your gold is gone, and no possible means of recovery." "It is of small account," said Monsieur Docou. I care but little for gold; I have a golden treasure - my dear child, and that is enough. My mother's miniature, the last relic of my mother, and is it gone? You have' her .picture in your heart; bear in mind her, virtues; imitate them, and you need no other memento." Silence again reigned, fot no one cared to speak, each one brooding mutely over the scenes of desolation and murder. Christoph politely took leave, observing, as he went out, "Toussaint will soon be here; he has your safety and future welfare at heart." The day passed, away, but Toussaint did not appear. A fertile mind can better imagine the state of this triune family than the most graphic pen describe.   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI..    47 With the light of another day came a most'tremen. dous storm. The heavens, as if to take part with the slave, shot forth volumes of livid flame, while the roar of the cannon was re-echoed by the loud peals of thunder. The population of whites was sparse; for the better portion were either killed or had deserted, while the more servile portion had coiled up in insignificance and acknowledged the black man their master. The family of Docou alone were the objects of negroes' care. Toussaint at length appeared, in company with Chris. toph, and was presented in all the form of modern etiquette to Monsieur Docou. ' You are," said the latter, my benefactor. To you I owe an obligation lasting as life-- the restoration of my child, to me the only object of earth that remains, the only tie that is pot torn asunder." As Toussaint looked on this superannuated old man, bowing under a weight of years, the force of which was heightened by the scenes through which he was passing, the warrior forsook his front, and he softened into tears. Yes, Toussaint, the great Toussaint, wept as he sur- veyed the misery the white man endured. "I have come," said Toussaint, in his softest tone, "to tell you that I have provided a ship in which I think you can sail with safety. We cannot look into the human heart, and consequently cannot always judge what dwells there, and do not suspect treachery until we have become its dupe. Were I to judge the States  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7494-00000025"/> 48      LA BELLE ZOA ; OR by the seamen who deceive the French, and under pretence of taking them to their republic, secure their gold and goods, leaving the owners penniless, I should say it afforded but an unsafe asylum for fugitives. Our insurrection, though just, is far more sanguinary than I could have thought. Having studied tactics, and served under France, I thought no war could have exceeded, either in anarchy or bloodshed, that of Ro- bespiere; I thought, after the first blow was struck, the French would have surrendered to superior force, and then, one coup de etat, and order would have been restored." The discerning Toussaint marked the conflict in the mind of Docou. Changing the subject, he said, "We are informed that the accomplished Adelle is your child. That you have acknowledged her as such, warrants the form of asking her in marriage with Chris- toph." Here the aristocratic pride of Monsieur Docou was stirred. He had but a faint recollection of what passed in his moments of mental langor. He remained silent, bending over his cane, with his eyes fixed downward. 4( Adelle," said Toussaint, "is all that is truly noble, good and great." This failed to relieve the embarrassment of Docou. Toussaint regarded this venerable old man, bending under a weight of years, whose fortune and family were wholly at the disposal of the dark man, now vacilla- ting between self-interest and pride. At length dire   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     49 necessity, which is ever ready to assume the garb of virtue, prevailed. "Yes, she is my child; I fully sanction the union. She is worthy of Christoph, even were he an hereditary prince." Toussaint left, and Docou fell into a reverie of gloom, from which he was first aroused by Adelle, who, hand- ing him a note, waited to return the expected answer to the bearer. Monsieur Docou no sooner finished reading the message than a new expression passed over his wo-fraught visage. "Go, Adelle," said he, "pour l'amour de Dieu, go to the house of Edward Fouliere and save the wretched inmates." Adelle hesitated a moment, and Monsieur Docou read the letter aloud. It was as follows: "I am informed that you have the protection of Christoph, and are about to leave. Dear sir, I placed my fortune in the ship of a traitor, who has sailed and left us doomed to fall by the black man's knife. Will you intercede for me? There may be safety in a ship chosen by the shrewd Christoph. I can (with pro- tecti9n) gather sufficient to pay my passage. My wife and five children await in deathke suspense the suc- cess of this note. I have given my gold watch to the bearer of this, who will wait an answer from you. "Your most obedient servant, "' EDWARD DE FOULIERE." 3  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7494-00000026"/> 50      LA BELLE ZOA; OR The humane Adelle went directly to rescue the dis- tressed family. As she entered, she saw the insurgents intent on plunder. "Where is the master?" said Adelle, speaking from the impulse of the moment. "Here," answered a martial looking mulatto, "here are the masters. Les Ciien Francais, you mean: there they are in the hall. They tried to make their escape, but we knocked them over." Adelle turned to the door leading into the hall, and there lay the murdered family: a little girl with her arms clasped round her father's neck; her blood, ining ling with his, ran in a stream. A breathless babe lay by its mother, whose mangled form and position a sensitive pen refuses to describe. The other children lay at a little distance, two of whom were dead and one still breathing. 4"Is it not to be feared," said Adelle, "that France will avenge on us this cruelty? Will not Bonaparte in person visit us, and with one cozp d'ceil destroy us?" "Let him come," said the mulatto, whose eyes lit up with unearthly fury, let him come; he'd not be taken away without a scar from my sword. I have studied the art of war in a school of France - fought and bled under Bonaparte -yes, braved every danger to secure victory to France, and place laurels on a monster's head; and what has been my reward? Aloof from hopes of promotion, a late oppressive act denies us privileges accorded to the French soldiers; but we have   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     51 broken the cords that bound us, and are trampling under our feet the still stronger fetters of the slave." Adelle, relying upon the deference paid her by the insurgents, presumed to say: "Bury, at least, these bleeding bodies." "Yes, yes," said the soldier; "throw them into a deep hole, as they did the slaves; out of the way with them! jean, boy; sqmuch scent of human blood is sickening." Adelle, turning away, walked slowly towards the house of her former master. As she passed thus pen- sively along, a faint shriek fell on her ear; turning her eyes, at a little distance from her she saw a negress With a heavy cane beating a superannuated French lady. "For the love of God," said Adelle, " let that old woman live; she can do no hurt." '"She can do no good," answered the black; "she eats our bread, as she said when she gave my poor crippled boy the dose of poison." Then giving her another blow, "There she lies, dead as a nutshell. Nous sommes les maitres " vociferated the black, as Adelle passed swiftly away. ' Alas, alas!" soliloquized Adelle, "will the spirit of revenge never be satisfied? Sufficient already of inno- cent blood has been shed to satiate the most ravenous beast of prey; but man, smarting under real or imagi- nary injuries, and goaded to madness by oppression, turns upon his tormentors with the malice of a demon; becoming drunk with blood and carnage, he revels  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7494-00000027"/> 52      LA BELLE ZOA; OR amid scenes of saughter with a zest more befitting a fiend of destruction than a human being. Will these ex- cesses, these extravagant and unprecedented cruelties, escape the notice of a justly indignant Heaven? Can revolutionized Hayti prosper while the laurels of victory are so deeply dyed in the blood of helpless innocence? Will not the atrow rebound- will not this tide of ill fortune, that is crushing the French, be rolled back upon the misguided blacks, who so ignobly tarnish their success and abuse their power? Surely this horrid state of things cannot last; or would to God I had never known the transit from a life of bondage to liberty! O, horror of horrors!" she exclaimed, as with a backward glance of the mind she surveyed the dire retrospect; "and is not this (in part, at least) my work? Am I not guilty? Have I not helped to sow the seed-to nurture the growing plant? But alas for the fruit! so unwholesome, so revolting to humanity, it disgusts rather than satisfies the craving soul. The ways of the transgressor are hard,' indeed; for every act of cruelty, either by myself personally or counten- ancing it in others, for every instance of pride and arrogance, no one better knows than myself that I have had answering pangs. Though the voice of conscience for a while may be stifled, full soon it be- comes clamorous in upbraidings; or if still and small, it is none the less distinct, especially in moments of soli- tude." With reflections such as these, Adelle arrived at the mansion of Monsieur Docou, the inmates of   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI     53 which were prepared and awaiting the hour for their departure. All have seen a sable-clad group of mourners taking the last farewell of a friend, just as the grave was closing over the beloved form: the mental anguish, now venting itself in heavy, unsuppressed sobs, as the earth rattles on the narrow house-now catching a last glimpse of the tenement where rests a dear com- panion of happier days - anon, as the spade throws over the last portion that covers it forever from their sight, the loud groans, as they turn away with the half uttered words, "I shall never more see good in the land of the living;" and yet all this but faintly portrays that agonizing scene when the fugitives were taling a last farewell of Hayti-of their beloved domain. Memory turned back but one page of the past, and Hayti was beautiful as the garden of Eden; but now, saturated with blood and covered with the bodies of the slain. The dome in which was heard the mellow sound of the harp, accompanied by the softer vocal note, was now silent, dismal, and withal the resting place of the dead; Pallette wringing his hands in agony, that he must leave the body of his murdered mother either food for the dogs or to fertilize the black man's field; Zoa knelt imploringly, and besought Christoph, when order was restored, to bury the bodies of her mother and brother; while Monsieur Docou, with clasped hands, united in the petition of his child. Christoph gave the kindest assurance that he would watch their  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7494-00000028"/> 54      LA BELLE ZOA; OR remains, and soon as posssible inter them in a ceme- tery of the French, telling them that all burying ground would be kept sacred, for so Toussaint decreed, but dropped not one word to console Pallette. Christoph, looking at his watch, reminded them that time was pressing; that the porters had conveyed their baggage to the ship, whither it was necessary for them as soon as possible to repair. 4 I must, before I leave, look into the room from which my mother came when she received the maniac shock," said Zoa, with a voice almost suffocated with emotion. "It was her sanctuary," said Docou, " where she usually repaired for devotion, and we must go." "It was the room she chose when in ill health, and around that room fond recollections cluster," answered Zoa. As they passed along, Zoa opened each door, the closing sound of which was responded to by Zoa in a half suppressed groan. Coming to the hallowed room, they found it locked. It was locked by my mother," said Zoa; "and here lies the key that, in her fright, fell from her feeble hand. I will myself unlock a door locked by my mother. I may in this room find something that, in a distant land, will afford a fond remembrance of her." As she opened the door, the first thing she beheld was the dead body of the yellow slave who was her mother's nurse.   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     55 "Wretch!" said Adelle, as she looked on the dead body; "'see, there is a murderous knife with which she intended to have killed her mistress. No wonder my poor mistress was frightened to idiocy; the wonder is how she escaped and locked her in. It is well her cries did not reach you; but perhaps she made none; guilt and fear might have kept her silent; for she promised, on her Catholic oath, to leave the house with the other yellow slaves, and neither plunder nor injure the family. She forfeited her word, for she thirsted for blood, and  has suffered for her perfidy; we will leave her to be thrown into the sepulchre of the slaves, for the grave of the liberated negro shall not be hers." At this moment they heard the clarion, the signal for the approach of Toussaint and guard. Quickening their steps, they looked not again on either side, but left the house and walked in sad procession to the ship. Toussaint now stepped forward; extending his hand, took leave of Monsieur Docou as follows: "The changes of fortune are many; and to me it has been a matter of regret that, in the vicissitudes of fate, philanthropy, integrity and benevolence do not more frequently meet a deserved reward. In this our war, all the varying emotions and passions of my soul have been brought by turns into exercise. True, I have planned, given orders and fought; but it has been my determined intention to protect the deserving French. This may not have been done, for in a war like ours there is little chance to discriminate; consequently, the  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7494-00000029"/> E56    LA BFTTT. ZOA; OR good may have fallen with their guilty brethren. But with regard to yourself, we are conscious that slavery was entailed, and by you neither sought for nor justified. This consideration, together with others of equal weight, has induced us to make sure to you, and your child if she survives you, the annual avails of your large plan- tation. And now, sir, in giving you the parting hand, I breathe, in the plenitude of my heart, the warmest wishes for your prosperity in life; hoping, as you now stand on the confines of the unknown world, your pass- port thither may be tranquil, and you safely moored on that peaceful shore where the clouds of affliction can- not again darken your prospect or disturb your eternal repose--where the redeemed of aD nations shall meet, and, together, strike the golden lyre in praise of Him who, with equal beneficence, created the white and the black man," Docou, too full to respond, bowed gracefully, and Toussaint withdrew his hand. Then taking an affec- tionate leave of Zoa, and bidding Pallette adieu, he left. Seated in the cabin, they endeavored to tranquilize their minds and await their destiny in a land of stran- gers, to which they were bound. Christoph entered the cabin, leading Adelle, and in a becoming manner told them that she was his wife; that in consequence of so much tumult of feeling, while they were preparing to embark he had forborne the intelligence. The usual congratulations, spoken in a   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     57 nournful tone, was brief,'for their hearts were too much charged with grief to admit one ray of joy. "I wish," said Monsieur Docou', "to know before Ae part, to whom I am indebted for ,the liberation of Zoa, when stolen by the blacks." ", To the good Toussaint," said Christoph, " you owe :hat obligation; but first let Zoa tell the manner of her capture." "I will," replied Zoa, "for the story is short. As we turned around to witness a contest, as we thought, of the French, quick as thought a mask was over my Face, and I felt a strange dress falling to my feet. I was forcibly led off and taken to a house deserted by the French; my hands were loosened and my face unmask- ed. Feeling in my pocket, to my inexpressible joy I found a potion that would rid me of life. I hastily swallowed it, and in a few moments was insensible of all around me. The first moment of recollection, I saw Toussaint, a mulatto doctor, and a charming yellow lady (whom I have since learned was his wife) attending me. My first words were, ' Father! where, O where is my father?' 'Take her to him,' said the medical man; fresh air will be a benefit, and his presence will do more than I can effect.' It was not until I was in my father's arms that I had a distinct recollection of what had passed." "Toussaint," resumed Christoph, " has a watch, whose business it is to see that his orders are not diso- beyed; it was owing to the vigilance of one of these *3  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7494-00000030"/> 58     .LA BELLE ZOA; OR men that the capture of your daughter was not attended with greater disaster. He informed Toussaint that he had by stealth discovered that La Belle Zoa was stolen from her father. Toussaint, showing the miniature given him by Mademoiselle Zoa, was told that it was a fac simile of the captured lady's face. -Toussaint entered the house pointed out by his watch, and imme- diately discovered that she had attempted suicide. His physician was instantly called and the dose ejected, and your child was in a short time able to comprehend to whom she was indebted for her life and liberty." The vessel was now about to sail. Christph and Adelle now arose to take leave. Adelle threw her arms around the neck of her former master and wept aloud, while the venerable old man returned her vale- dictory with equal warmth. The parting of Zoa and Adelle was affectionate; as they impressed the last kiss, they pledged eternal friendship.' Christoph now in due form stepped forward, and with all the measured etiquette of an Englishman took leave. The triune party now sat in their cabin, silent and sad. The captain, a corpulent man, with bushy hair and big blue eyes, entered the cabin, and seating him- self, in a familiar manner said: - "So you are bound for the land of witches?" "Truly," replied Pallette, " if that is what you call Boston." "To the letter: The witches used to ride from Sa- lern to Boston on broomsticks, turn old stables into   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTL     59 dancing halls, gray cats into fiddlers; and use little boys and girls for pincushions; but the good women of Salem, disliking the free use made of their children- declaring that so many pinholes in the flesh, particularly in the faces of their little girls, would destroy their beauty by spoiling the smoothness of their skin, said something should be done; so the good old Puritans put their heads together, and got up a plan to punish such trespass. They got all the accused, and then took them in a cart to the water and threw them in; those that sunk were innocent, their drowning being the proof; but those that made a shift to get out, they hung up by the neck for witches." This was accom- panied with a loud laugh, to which the fugitives re- sponded with deep sighs. "All in joke," said the captain. "Boston is a very godly place, and I dare venture you'll like it," Pallette observed, he would rather have gone to France.  "France!" exclaimed the captain; " haigh, boy! that would be like jumping out of the frying pan into the fire. They use men's heads in Paris as chicken butchers do their poultry.' I'd rather be a dog in Boston, in time of hydrophobia, than a sound politician in Paris. I see you are down at the heels, and no wonder; this negro scrape is a bad affair; bad to lose all your gold, but it's no use to cry for spilt milk. I've had my share of losses; all is, I whet up my brain and start anew. You're going," continued the captain, "to the right ,l   &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7494-00000031"/> 60      LA BELLE ZOA; OR place; Boston is made up of charity. Only get up a paper, stating that you are sprigs of the nobility- get somerof the big bugs to subscribe-just whisper in the ear- your name is all - only to make it a-go-- pay only as you please -I'll warrant you cash enough." "We hope," said Docou, "not to be objects of charity." "O, I didn't think; you French folks never beg- you had rather feel powder than charity; none of your 'God-bless-you' Irish beggars." Zoa turned on the captain her swollen eyes, who, finding he had not hit a right chord, rose up, saying: "Keep yourselves, good folks, comfortable. My ship is in good order; if anything goes wrong you shall be the first notified." To this last the fugitives returned an acknowledg- ment with all that politeness for which the French are so remarkable. "You see," said Docou, as the captain left, 'a speci- men of human nature. Had the captain thought us in possession of our former wealth, he would have been in our presence cringing, obsequious and diffident; but thinking us destitute, he has proffered that coarse con- dolence which the wretched are destined to endure." "How strange," said Zoa, "he did'appear! I could scarcely understand him. He speaks our language in- correctly." "It is so with most of the New England people, although they fancy themselves adepts in the French."   THE IN'SURRECTION OF HAYTI.    61 "He is an Englishman," said Pallette, " of that I am sure; and I mortally hate the English." "They are a selfish, monopolizing people," said Do- cou, "and would be glad, were it possible, to give laws to the whole world. They have always been trying to overthrow our laws-casting reproach on H-yti." Pallette observed, "It'is England that is the efficient cause of the insurrection; England educated Chris- toph, and Madam Howe taught Adelle." "Not England alone," continued Docou; "imprudent France did more. The oppression of the free mulat- toes, who studied tactics under the French government, destroyed our colony. But it is done; and it is for us to treat Christoph and Adelle, in our future correpondence, with kindness and respect, nor suffer a satirical word to escape the pen. You, Pallette, must bear in mind that satire, like mercury, is dangerous in unskilful hands. To the chiefs we are indebted for life, liberty and for- tune; the-latter by them might easily be withheld." Zoa acquiesced; but Pallette curled his lip-said it was necessary-but in his heart wished it in his power to blow out their brains. Sea sickness, old age and a'broken constitution, in a few weeks prostrated Monsieur Docou. When he saw the pale horse, and felt the hand of him that sitteth thereon press heavily on him, he called Pallette and Zoa to his bedside; and taking the hand of Zoa, he said: "I am rapidly passing away; a few days more, and I shall find a watery grave. My death, though not pre-  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7494-00000032"/> 62       LA BELLE ZOA; OR mature, is hastened by the: exciting scenes through which I have lately passed; and could it serve as a beacon to warn the wide world of the sin of slavery, I would close my eyes in peace, knowing that it had, together with my misfortune, resulted in good to a world from which I am now taking my exit.". Then placing her hand in Pallette's, he, said: "To you I give the last object of earthly love;' in your care I leave my child. Will you, in the fear of God and at the death- bed of her father, promise to be to her a kind, constant and' affectionate husband?" "I will," said Pallette. "I will, in characters drawn in my own blood, place in your hand a promise to that effect." "Always bear in mind," resumed Docou, "that, jeopardizing her life, she saved you from the horrors of evisceration-your body from the dogs. You are young, far too young, for an engagement of this kind; but fate has so determined and I submit." The physician now entered, and observing that a change was passing over Monsieur Docou, requested Pallette to leave, saying: My patient must have repose; his feeble nerves cannot bear the slightest impression. I greatly fear his mind has undergone some undtfe excitement, which will biffle my skill to relieve." All was now still. Monsieur Docou closed his eyes, and enjoyed for some time that sleep of nature which was soon to be exchanged for the repose of death. A I X   THE INSURRECTION OF HtAYT.     63 sound accompanying his breathing, told Zoa and the attendant that the angel of death was affixing the seal of his ministry, and about to bear off another trophy of his unlimited power. He-opened his eyes- once more fixed on Zoa an affectionate gaze-the blindness of death succeeded, and he saw her not again. Zoa was taken from the bedside of her father in a state of insensibility. Fever and delirium prevented her from seeing the body of her father deposited in the watery deep. As she awoke to reason and health, her affection deepened for Pallette, and in his society she forgot the past. A favorable gale soon wafted them to Boston. The next morning after their arrival, the seven bells rang the nuptial tune, and Pallette led to the hymenial altar the lovely Zoa. Fugitives from Hayti were announced, and the church was filled to overflowing. The attention of all was arrested with the beauty of Zoa and high- bred air of Pallette. A remittance from Hayti was already in Boston, directed to be delivered to Monsieur Docou, and in case of his death, to his daughter Zoa. If not claimed by the above parties, to be expended in educating the African youth in Boston. Pallette felt that his haughty, satirical spirit had drawn on him the disaffection and distrust of Toussaint, and that it was so managed that he must not only acknowledge to Zoa that to her he owed his liberty and life, but even his daily subsis- tence.   &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7494-00000033"/> "-      LA BELLE ZOA; OR The intelligence and sobriety of Boston afforded no pleasure to Pallette; the latter being a restraint on the 'volatility of his nature, obliging him to observe rules of decorum repugnant to his feelings. He passed most of his time with Zoa, for she was the idol of his soul, and in her society he forgot the turmoil of revolution, the clang of insurgents and groans of the dying. About the close of the first year of their residence in Boston, they received the following letter from Christoph: "HONORED FRIENDS - Your letter, informing us of your safe arrival in Boston, was duly received. Diffe- rent- feelings passed over our minds while reading the intelligence it conveyed. We rejoice that you reached Boston in safety--are happy that you are honorably united in marriage; but feel a sadness come over our spirits that your saint-like father found a watery grave. We thought when he was in Hayti that not merely the frost of age was wasting his strength, but that disease was closing the avenues of life; but did hope he would have reached Boston. It matters but little, however, to a philosophic mind, whether the body resolves to its original elements in water, or on earth; yet nature prefers the latter, it being the more usual mode. His memory will remain in Hayti, though not perpetuated by a polished marble, or his body resting in the sarco- phagus of the great. You are now quietly seated in Boston, a town, I think, of all others in the New World, most to be desired; settled by the humane children of   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     65 England, it wears, no doubt, the appearance of order, propriety and elegance. With regard to Hayti, all is unsettled. It is rumored that Bonaparte intends to visit us. We do not fear him; his twenty thousand soldiers will not frighten us; 8s long as we remain united he cannot injure us, save the loss of a little artillery. I know not why it is that the world in general (England excepted) is so opposed to the freedom of the blacks. The hearts of our mulatto generals are rivited to Hayti, and, though amalgamation may have regulated the fea- tures and rather changed the hue, yet it is with the black men of Hayti that we identify our names. In Hayti we will frame laws, wise as those of Solon, in which will be written as crime, all intermarriages with the whites. In concluding this, permit me to say that you have our warmest wishes for your happiness. I forward no message from Adelle- she is in her cabinet, writing to Madam Pallette. ' With due respect, your most humble servant, "CHRISTOPH BRIANT." "Sacre scelerat!" said Pallette, as he threw down the letter from Christoph. "Buried in England!" "It was in England that he emerged from ignorance," said Zoa. "Bah! A polished nation! They would have run with their blue jackets to this day, but for the taste of France." ( They are said to be humane and benevolent."  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7494-00000034"/> "      LA B ELLE ZOA; OR "A  clan of misers," answered Pallette. "You might as well wring blood from an Englishman's hand, as a single sou. They rave against the slaveholder, be- cause they have no need of slaves - were barbarians at first--could easily do their own drudgery, without the assistance of worse beings than themselves. Their country is populous, and their poor frequently starve for want of employment; while your benevolent, humane Englishmen ride in their carriages, with servants in livery, and would wish the poor to prostrate themselves before them." "Bonaparte," resumed Zoa, "is to be in Hayti." "Not at all. The mark is too low. He may send soldiers; but they will not fight without him. They had rather smell a snuff box than a nigger." Then looking at his watch, said: "It is time we go to the concert. Rawson is to be there with his long face and music that exactly suits it." A few weeks passed, and a letter was handed to Zoa from Adelle; "MY DEAR MISTRESS-For so I choose ever to call you. If, after being tossed on the waves of affliction, you are enjoying domestic quiet, it will gladden the heart of your faithful Adelle. But this is indeed an ever changing world; and around our fairest pros- pects full often gather the darkest cloud; and even in the very moment when exhilirated by some for- tunate event, we are impelled to drink deepest of the   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     6' bitter waters of grief. The intelligence of my dear master's death entirely overcame me, and for some time I could not even weep; but when tears-the balm of the wretched -came to my relief, I could think of and sympathise with you. And must it be so--after all the care, all the exertion, to secure the minutest article that could be thought necessary, either for his comfort or convenience on his voyage, he must pine and die i I know your own dear Pallette will weep with and console you; but when the heart is borne down with affliction- when the pale monarch has laid his potent summons before us, and in virtue of which bears off a dear friend, we cannot find consolation, even in the sympathy (however highly appreciated) of the dearest friend; but, ' Let me alone for I will not be com- forted,' is full often the language of the heart. I hope, my dear mistress, that reason and religion will support, you; for ' it is appointed once for all to die.' Wit- nessing, as I have, the blood of unoffending women and children flowing along our streets, it might seem incre- dulous that a death of nature could so affect me; but we are made up of a variety of passions and emotions, and when either is called into exercise, all others give place. This is my view of mind, drawn from a minute observance of my own. Christoph rallies me when I attempt to philosophize; but I cannot find in his books many ideas with which I have not been previously im. pressed. Write to your faithful "AJ)ELLE BRIANT."  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7494-00000035"/> 68      LA BELLE ZOA; OR "Very well done," said Pallette, when Zoa had finished the letter; "very well done for a darky. She has spun out her sympathy as fine as a spider's web." "Adelle is united with a man of science, carefully educated by a worthy man." "By a fidgetty old bachelor, who had nothing else to love but an illegitimate mulatto; a dough-headed old fellow, to give Christoph the right to a noble name. I wish he was here; he might find a wife among some of these relics of antiquity, who walk the streets as if nature never gave them a joint." ' I admire," said Zoa, "the manners of Boston." "You may, but I can never fay to such sanctimony. They march to church with faces as solemn as if they were bound to the guillotine; return home and'abuse their beer barrels for having effervesced in their absence." "Too much raillery," said Zoa. "O, they are well enough; they need only to be placed under a tropical sun a few days; that might melt away some of their formality." "MY DEAR ADELLE--The welcome testimony of your continued regard is before me. The sorrow you expressed for the death of my father is natural and just; for when you was a slave, you suffered very little restriction; your slavery was in the mildest form. I well remember one day, when alone with my father, of telling him that I thought some fairy being had   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     69 instructed you, for you looked on books with as much interest as if you understood the contents, and that I believed you could read writing, and sometimes even thought you could write. 'Impossible,' said my father. ' Must I let her have books?' ' To be sure; the lawcan no more hurt us for showing her a book, than a picture. Poor girl, she is very desirous to learn. I,-too, have noticed the intensity with which she looks on all printed paper. I have sometimes thought of letting her go with Madam Howe; she is very anxious to make the purchase.' 'Not for all England,' said I, ' will I part with her. If you sell her, sell me too.' My father smiled, and said he should have to pay if I went too in the bargain. I could see, however, that though he attempted pleasantry, a deeper feeling was laboring in his breast; but he is at rest. His eye will no more fill with moisture for his own or others affliction. The ample supply of cologne was of great use. He used, until towards the last, to bathe daily with it, and seemed to receive vitality from its diffusibility. He died, as he lived, firm in the Protestant faith; and though taught by my mother that the Catholic is the only true church, still I can but venerate that faith which softens the  pillow of death. I will give you a little description of Boston. It is a very civil, church-going place. There are many charitable institutions. This I judge from the frequent calls I have to contribute to their support. There are beggars in Boston of every grade, and one no sooner leaves than another enters; and when once  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7494-00000036"/> T0      LLA BELLE ZOA; OR known to be charitable, they have no mercy on youi purse. The ladies of Boston are modest, unassuming and domestic, observing the strictest propriety and decorum. Their appearance, in the street, is markec with an air of delicacy, and free from that eclat which seems inherent in the French nation. Pallette laugh, at what he calls their formality, but to me it has a peculiar charm. I cannot say but I am happy. Pal -lette is a kind, attentive and affectionate husband. ] often think how wretched I should be were he other wise, situated as I am in a land of strangers. He ii careful not to give me inquietude, by leaving me with out my knowing the import of his business, and a what hour he will probably return, and never fails o being at home at the time he appoints. That the same amount of connubial happiness may be yours, that fall: to the lot of your happy friend, is the sincere wish o "ZOA PALLETTE." "MY DEAR MADAM PALLETTE - Informed by AdellE that you had fled to Boston, and there taken refuge fron the storm of insurrection-had a yearly salary, the income of your plantation, allowed you by the blacks and being pleased with this news, I wrote, in due sea son, expecting an answer, and some particulars of the death of your father, my distant relative. I, however forgive the neglect; I know you are delicate; and t h appalling fate of the French colony (even if favorec with all possible protection), must have unstrung you   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.   . 71 or nerves and palsied the operations of your mind. Your mental faculties, I should say, must have by this time regained sufficient vigor to write; but of that you are the best judge. The fall of the French in Hayti is what I expected, and they too might have thought the same; might have foreseen that by partially educating the free mulattoes,* instructing them in tactics, taking them into their service, tantalizing them with prospects of ad- vancement, and then not only disappointing them, but drawing on them cords too galling for enlightened humanity to endure, would in the end result in rebel- lion. By gaining on their side the great Toussaint, a mulatto favored by France, an illegitimate, allied by blood to the nobility, their purpose was easily brought about; but there is an overruling Power, who sees with equal eye the oppressor and the oppressed; the tyrant and the slave; the pompous planter, who, regardless of the rights of nature, binds and scourges a fellow being, his helpless victim, with stripes which, if inflicted on a brute, would draw from a feeling observer tears of com- passion. Can we wonder that this impartial eye, that never sleeps, should take cognizance of the suffering slave - should dispense justice to those who withheld liberty, the right of nature, the sacred gift of Heaven, from the creatures of his hand . You are now in Bos- ton, the land to which the persecuted pilgrims resorted, and found a happy asylum, and fled too from a govern- * Universal History.  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7494-00000037"/> T2      'LA BELLE ZOA ; OB R ment under which I live. I do not consider that we, as females, as individuals, are blamable for the faults of government. It is not for us to attempt assuming even a slight hold of the reins; our impotent hands could not with masculine force propel the wheels of state. I do not blush to say that we are ' the weaker vessel.' My pupille, Adelle, is acting modestly the part of a great woman; great in every sense of the word, as it respects mind, for she is the friend and protectress of suffering innocence. Do not let love and marriage entomb your friendship for me; I cannot say but in wedded life I felt the same affection for friends as in my widowed state, or previous to the nuptial bond. I regret that you do not better understand English. It will be a barrier, an almost insurmountable difficulty, in forming acquaintance in Boston. You will, however, in time, become familiar with their style, and find them an agreeable, intelligent, humane and hospitable people. Will you write to me? .Do write. Do not fail of wri- ting to your affectionate "SARAH HOWE." The monotony of a few years affords nothing worthy of note, save the birth of a daughter, whose beauty, in the eye of parental fondness, exceeded the May rose. "And what shall we call our little gem?" said Zoa to 'Pallette, who sat admiring the infant she held in her arms.   THE INSURRECTION OF IIAYTI.    73 "Call her! why call her Zoa, to be sure. It is a charming name." "What say you my love to having her name Adelle?" Pallette tried to smooth his face, but in opposition to every effort laughed aloud. "Shrewd enough! I see you, are a chip of the old block. Christoph is rich-rich in Hayti; and no doubt will inherit the large fortune of Lord Briant. We are but pensioners, and this respect shown to his fair consort will secure a dowery fot our child. Adelle, Adelle! It sounds rather too much like the yellow skin; but no matter for that-11 est un .grand poistk at the end of the line." Zoa, who was hardly conscious of having a sinister view, said: "My father considered Christoph and Adelle our benefactors, and wished us to treat them as such." Surely; for by doing otherwise, said your father, our living could be withheld. Give Adelle to the nurse; it is time for us to prepare for the theatre. It isia bene- fit night;. the avails are to procure fuel for the poor, so there will be no objections on your part." Some few months passed and a letter was received from Christoph, who, with other news, informed them that his Majesty the King of England was about send- ing them help. This, said he, will humble the French and bring them to our terms. Zoa desired an explana. tion, but Pallette said he was not a politician; that the kindness of the English government always centered 4  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7494-00000038"/> 74      LA BELLE ZOA; OIt in self; that the black diables must manage their own card; and wished heartily that Christoph, after having aided in the destruction of the French colony, would say nothing more to him of the government. The next advice from Hayti announced the. entire overthrow of the English army sent to Hayti by his Majesty the King* for the purpose of subduing the blacks and taking possession of that part of the island they now claimed. "4 Three cheers," ejaculated Pallette, "for the humane English! Let the cannon roar iil honor of the darkies." "Rather novel," said Zoa, "to hear you exult in the Wiumph of blacks." '"It is not that I love the blacks more; but I do hate that government which, under a fair exterior, a show of benevolence, would gladly crush the laws of the whole world and substitute such as would conduce wholly to their own interest. Now let Christoph gather up the brains of his brethren, the children of England, and send them back to his Majesty in a Boston bandbox. Let him tell the English that, since their artillery failed to enslave the blacks, they had better withhold their invective from the slaveholder." About this time they received a letter from Adelle, expressing her gratitude for the honor they conferred in calling their child Adelle; hoping that she might be favored with clasping in her arms the little Adelle, and in person present that donation which would show the * Gazetteer.   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     75 high value she placed on a child having a name given in honor of heiself. She added that Christoph, having come in possession of the large fortune of Lord Briant, proposes giving a dowery from England -and adding, in pleasantry, . he must think a dowery from the for- tune of Lord Briant more pure." "I hope," said Zoa, laying down the letter, "that if our child has a dowery given by Christoph from the fortune of Lord Briant and remitted from England, you will lose a little of that inveteracy you bear to Christoph and England." "Not in the least. Think you, my Zoa, that I can bear aught but hatred for a man to whose subtilty of purpose I attribute the fall of the French colony, the murder of my mother, the confiscation of my estate? It is for your sake, not mine, that this kindness is shown. Were our living the avails of my estate, not yours, the humiliation would be less; but I am bound in degrada- tion, since to the mulatto chiefs I owe my daily subsis- tence. It is for you, my Zoa, that I live." "Not wholly for me;" taking her child from the nurse. The little cherub extending her tiny hands towards hel' father, he readily took her in his arms, and walked with hasty strides around the room until the tumult of passion began to subside. Soon the Gazette gave notice that twenty thousand soldiers, sent by Bonaparte to Hayti in order to retake their former possessions, were entirely defeated ;* but * Gazetteer.  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7494-00000039"/> 76      LA BLTYTjE ZOA; OR that they succeeded, however, in capturing Toussaint; that they had taken him to France and confined him in prison, where he soon died broken-hearted. The death of Toussaint affected the fugitives even to tears, "( Had it been Christoph," said Pallette, " they would have had the mainspring of the insurrection; but Tous- saint, poor Toussaint, was the most magnanimous of the insurgents." An epidemic now prevailed in Boston, and on the doors were daily seen badges that announced mourning within. And while Zoa and Pallette were watching the increasing loveliness of their child, its opening intel- lect, and anticipating the time when its mind would be displayed by the organs of speech, the fatal epidemic fastened on their child its deadly grasp, and bore off the helpless victim. When Pallette was called to-the death- bed of his child; when he felt her pulse cease to beat, and saw the attendent close her eyes, he raved in per- fect frenzy- cursed the physician - blamed the nurse, and even reproached the God of heaven for having taken away his child; while Zoa bowed to the will of heaven, and as she fastened the last look on her child, said, "Into thy hands, O blessed Virgin, I commit my child!" "HAYTI. "MY DEAR MSTRESS-You are no doubt apprised of the elevation of Christoph to the throne. It is an honor to which I did not aspire. It is too nearly asso- ciated with the prison and the block. History proves   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     " the fact, and France has written the truth of this in characters of blood. I greatly fear the unenlightened Haytians will not sustain a uniform government; but sufficient for the day is the uneasiness it brings. How different my views from those which passed over my mind when the first idea of liberty dazzled in my imagination! To be free-- mistress of myself- cre- ated visions more brilliant than rainbow splendor; the rich costume presented me by Christoph at first de- lighted me, connected, as it seemed, with freedom, and being presented by him. Let this account for my arl-  gance at the first moment of the insurrection, for my conduct was in direct opposition to my nature. I would that I could drink the waters of Lethe, that the bloody  scenes of the past might be forgotten. I will inform you of an important discharge of gratitude to a kind mistress. It is the interment of her remains and those of her son in our new cemetery. They were taken from their temporary graves three weeks since, and have marble monuments, on which are inscrihed their names, ages and manner of death'; with this inscription by Chriptoph:  Erected by Her Royal Highness, ADELLE Queen of Hayti.' To which I have added: 4 The tears of their former slave watered their graves.' Write often, and believe me yours, till death, i"ADELIE BRIANT."  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7494-00000040"/> /178   LA BELLE ZOA; OR "BOSTON. "My DEAR ADELLE-Not water to the thirsty traveler in a burning desert, could be more welcome than intelli- gence of that respect you have shown to the memory of my mother and brother; this testimony of goodness calls for an acknowledgment, which my pen can but faintly convey. The elevation of Christoph is not novel intelligence; the public prints have announced his regal honor; but, my dear Adelle, it ill becomes a queen to address a fugitive by the name of mistress. You must ait in accordance with the high station you now fill. Your situation is indeed momentous and replete with danger. The people over whom you preside are igno- *  rant, capricious and revengeful; accustomed to lives of slavery, they know very little of self-control. I hope, however, you will escape the danger incident to crowned heads. Memory, in spite of everyeffort, falls back on the past. Not to the bloody insurrection does my mind so frequently revert, as to the beautiful land- scape of Hayti; its luxurious fields, the rich foliage of its trees -the cocoa, the orange, the lemon, and the pine-apple; sunny days of childhood, when I thought only of the present, ignorant of the ills that chequer life. But all is now passed off, not by the silent lapse of time, but by the hurricane and storm; but I will not tire you with a repetition of my own misfortunes. The blow that fell so heavily on us might have been directed by an avenging God. That a long and properous reign may be yours, is the sincere wish of "ZOA PALLETTE."   THE INSWRECTION OF IIAYTI.     79 "BOSTON. "MY DEAR ADELLE-I have just read ydor brief epistle. Is it possible that you can devote no more time to me? Perhaps you do not know what to say, thinking that to talk of Hayti distresses me. Be that as it may, memory will linger around the place where I drew my infantile breath and spent the days of child-. hood. I am sorry to give either you or Madam Howe pain on my account. You say you feel distressed and wish me to tell you all. I cannot say that Pallette is unkind, as it regards his personal demeanor; although I realize none of his former tenderness. He seems like one obligated to look after me -see that all the neces- saries of life are provided - and then he is- away, I know not where. I will inform you of an important event: I am again the mother of an infant daughter, and call her*Harriet. She is seven months and five days old. She already begins to display the vivacity of a sprightly nature, and entwines herself around our hearts by playful innocence. Inured as I have been to disappoint- ment, 1 dare not anticipate pleasure in her physical growth or expanding intellect. I am groping along the pathway of life: 1 once amused myself with its flowers and inhaled its rich perfume; but 1 now feel only the laceration of its thorns and inspire the effluvia of grief. So passes the life of one who was once dan- dled in the lap of pleasure and fostered in the arms of parental indulgence. I am often requested to relate the treatment of slaves in Hayti. With regard to the stories afloat I know nothing. There was undoubtedly  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7494-00000041"/> 80      LA BELLE ZOAt OR much cruelty practiced, but in my father's domain all was peace, and each slave wore the sunshine of content. Had all masters been kind, Hayti would still have been ours. I amp however, incompetent to say much of the revolution, for before that event my life was one con- tinued sunshine, and I knew not but others were alike happy. At the time of the insurrection, I was so stupefied with terror that I cannot call to mind events as they passed. The Bostonians are inquisitive: could I relate with minuteness each scene as it transpired, my language is but imperfectly understood; so, as a matter of course, the Yankees (as they are called) would gain but little intelligence from me. Do not fail to write often to your affectionate "ZOA PALLETTE." HAYTI. "MYDEAR, DR, EAR MSTRESS --For so I must and will call you. The measure of my affliction is full. The for- tune of war is against us; Boyer is victorious, has over- turned the government and usurped the power. I have foreborne writing, not that I was unmindful of you, but I did not wish to tell you of the disturbance in Hayti, as it would revert your attention to the past - scenes that I would it were possible for me to forget. My Dear Mistress- I have a tragical tale to disclose. My hand trembles, my tears saturate the space on which I am about to write. Spare me the pain of telling you. Read the inclosed: it is an exact copy of Christoph's last letter to me, taken from La Journal Francais:   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     81 "' MY DEAR WIFE-I am a doomed man. To Boyer is awarded by fate the palm of victory, and I am a prisoner; but I will not fall into the hands of the Hay- tians whom I have served, I will not die by hands from which I have broken off. the manacles of slavery. A seeming miracle has placed a pistol within my reach, and I gladly grasp the deadly weapon. Adelle, my Dear Wife-Pleasantilhave been the hours I have passed with you. My home to me has been a para- dise; but I fotiear. I will not in this awful moment pour forth a torrent of endearing epithets - a flow of affection. Let the conduct of my past life speak my love, my respect for you; and richly have you deserved that tenderness with which I have ever treated you. I am now bidding you my last, my final farewell. The wheels of my life are about rolling over for the last time. I must die, but I wrest the infliction from my enemies, and choose to be my own executioner ;* conse- quently, you must not set down my death as deliberate suicide. I thought myself an adept in the nature of man; but my lack of acumen is proved by the' facility with which my enemies have effected my ruin. "The world will follow the emmet that picks up the white straw;" but there will be a time, however distant the period, when the Haytians will do justice to the name of Christoph. I have in my will bequeathed three thousand pounds, to erect a college in the place where. the orange tree stood under which I first saw you. I * Gazetteer. *4  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7494-00000042"/> 82       LA BELLE ZOA; OR even now, through the vista of years, see Hayti emerg- ing from the thick mist of ignorance and superstition, and taking a seat among the nations of the earth; then, when science shall pour its enlivening rays on Hayti, let my monument be erected. But my valedictory is not finished: I come to a tender portion. Zoa, my own dear Zoa! Must I leave you- leave you without a kingdom, which I once thought would have been yours? But I do not leave you destitute: I leave you with a mother, affectionate, virtuous and wise. Listen-to her, for in her counsel there is safety. I have written to Boyer, praying him to permit you and your dear mother to retire to England. It is the land that gave. birth to my mind, and there I would have my dear child edu- cated. And now, dear wife and child - I have taken my pistol (but not tremulously), and hold it in my left hand; with the other I write my last affectionate fare- well. t' CHRISTOPH BRIANT.' "You have read the inclosed and are -dropping for me tears of sympathy. How consoling the thought that, though the broad ocean may separate us, still we can communicate to each other the sorrows that oppress us. I have Boyer's permission to retire to England. Write me to London, as I am in readiness to go as soon as provided with a good ship and trustworthy , captain.      "Your faithful' "ADELLE."   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI     83 Christoph," said Zoa to Pallette, as he entered the parlor, " is dead." "( Yes, I thought I told you. He and Boyer could not agree which had the best right to govern; Boyer got master, and Chri toph, pauvre diable! shot himself." "There is a letter from Adelle; will you read it?" "I am- in haste; I am to dine with the French con- Sul." "He does not dine until three o'clock; it is not one yet." "I don't care much for your woman stuff. I suppose Adelle has pictured her grief like the Egyptian dark- ness, which, 'tis said, could be felt- wound herself up in it, resembling a cocoon; no danger but she'll come out again as fine as a butterfly." "Poor Adelle!" said Zoa, " her affliction is great." Not so very poor; Christoph was immensely rich. She is rather handsome for a darky; and not so very dark, neither," looking significantly at Zoa. "Age cannot have entirely destroyed her beauty; she has a princely fortune; and Boyer is not exactly married- has got the kingdom, and may probably take her in the bargain." Zoa made no reply, and Pallette rose up and walked towards the door. "Read, at least, the last words of Christoph," said Zoa, extending the letter. "Ne a point. He has gone to the diable, for the old fellow would of course take his own; but I must go."  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7494-00000043"/> 84      LA BELLE ZOA; OR "Not yet," said Zoa, looking at her watch. "I will play a tune for you-your favorite air." I care not what you play, only fait vite; I am in haste." "Well, then, I will play the Deserted Fair One: "Twas near a thickets calm retreat, Under a willow tree, Adelia chose her wretched seat,  To mourn her soriows free. Her lovely form was sweet to view As dawn at opening day, But ah I she griev'd her love not true, And wept her cares away.'  "O quit with your love-sick tunes; I never did believe in such foolishness." "Then your words have been at variance with the language of your heart." "When I was a boy I might have been imbecile; but I am a man now-have put off boyish whims." Pallette, too uneasy to keep one position, walked towards the half closed blinds - complained that the room was too dark. "O, if that's what makes you unwilling to stay with me, I can quickly remove the objection." Pallette, taking up his gloves, said," I had nearly for- gotten; I must be at the reading room at half-past one; it is that now. Rare news from Bonaparte! Really, my dear, you must not detain me." Then, taking her   THE INSURRECTION OF IIAYTI.    85 hand, endeavored to impress a kiss; but she withdrew it, scorning his false pretensions. "So I am again alone," soliloquized Zoa; " neglected by him who I once thought would have sacrificed his very being for me. I will divert my attention from him and write to Adelle." "BOSTON. "MY DEAR ADELLE-- Your affliction is great, and though far distant my sympathetic tears mingle with yours. We vary in our creed; still I do believe that Heaven is alike gracious to the devout Protestant as to those in the Catholic church, and that the religion you profess is equal to support you. I have known but little of the affairs of Hayti during the last year; for there is no French paper printed in Boston, and Pal- lette does not, as formerly, translate the English paper for me. Christoph did not mention me, but I forgive the omission of my name; I am accustomed to neglect. Yes, my dear Adelle, I am neglected by him who vowed to me, in characters drawn in his own blood, eternal constancy. You have told me your trouble; I will tell you mine. I love Pallette with fervency equal to that when first I plighted my faith at the altar of Hymen; but I am no longer the object of his love. Of this I am certain. Many are the resolves in my tortured nind, but Heaven has so far kept me from any desperate act. I sit alone, with my little Harriet in my arms, (for I refuse having a nurse); and as I gaze on her fair, infantile brow, I would that my tears might efface from  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7494-00000044"/> 86      LA BE TLT ZOA; OR her features the slightest trace of Pallette. This will probably be the last letter you will receive from me. My death will be tragical ; for I am growing desperate, losing all control over myself. More than once I have resolved, when Pallette was asleep, to plunge a knife in that heart which is no longer mine. I cannot endure the sight of Pallette: it is a paradox, but so it is. I shall forward to you my portrait and those of my two children. Keep them for ny namesake-your precious Zoa. Farewell! ' ZOA PALLETTE." "LONDON. "MY DEAR ZOA- I have just received a letter from you, in answer to the many I have written. I can readily pardon you for writing more frequently to Adelle, for she is your benefactress, one to whom you certainly are indebted for the annual avails of your large plantation. The insurrection would have been, without her assistance, and by means of her it fell less heavily on you. We are all aware that death, yes, in cruelest form, was the portion of that slave who should give the slightest hint of the plot, or resist any measure of the leaders. True, I am the one who educated Adelle, at least in the rudiments of the French, in which you know I am well versed ; but it has resulted in good to you, by rendering her more capable of speaking and acting in your behalf. I know the stigma cast on our nation by the slaveholder. Possibly I may have done ?   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     87 more than the laws would have sanctioned; but I blame not myself. I was first instigated by a feeling of grati- tude, which I could not otherwise repay. Who could refuse a supplicating fellow-being, on her knees implor- ing the light of science? We are told by the press that our poor suffer. This is true; but whenever the be- nevolent are apprised of the fact, relief is promptly afforded. Our country is populous and wages low; but education is generally diffused, and the world is wide, and all have the inestimable blessing of liberty. The profligacy of the French aristocracy, I know. affords an ample support for the poor, but dissipation is destroying the character of the nation; for what is France but one continual scene of anarchy and revolu- tion? Infidelity has breathed its poisonous breath over the kingdom, and the crafty priests have affixed the seal of its infamy. I speak to a friend- one liberal in sentiment and willing to hear the truth. Adelle is now with us, and receiving all that respect which her merit deserves. Grief has softened her fine features, and cast a 'gloom over a countenance which certainly is charming. 1 hope, my dear Zoa, but greatly fear, that you are not happy. There is a dejection in your let- ters which speaks a mind ill at ease. Pour in the bosom of your faithful Sarah your joys and sorrows. If happy, I too shall rejoice; if afflicted, I shall sym- pathise and weep with you. Farther than this is not in my power. I know the stability of purpose that exists among the Haytian chiefs, and that an ample  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7494-00000045"/> 88      LA BELLE ZOA; OR support will ever be yours. Write often, and believe me your very affectionate friend, "' SARAI HowE." Extract of a letter from Zoa to Madam Howe. BOSTON. "I have now informed you of the health and relative situation of your friends in Boston, and proceed to tell you of myself. I am, indeed, the most wretched of the wretched. Pallette no longer loves me. He feigns every possible pretext that his ingenuity can devise to leave home. I sit alone, without friends or condolence. Many are the resolves which passion dic- tates and reflection annuls. I have become capable of conversing in English with the ladies of Boston, at least so as to be understood; they are paragons of excellence. There is little deference shown to eclat of appearance, intelligence and propriety forming the line of distinction; consequently, the depraved in sen- timent have little or no chance to intermix with the good. Pallette seems embarrassed in their presence; this unfavorable omen distresses me. "Write often, and believe me your affectionate "ZOA PALLETTE." "LONDON. "Your kind letter is before me. I am grieved that you feel conscious of having lost the affection of Pallette. Beware of coming to this conclusion too hastily, and still more cautious of letting him realize your suspicions.   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     89 It is rather a national trait of yours to act from the impulse of the moment; guard against this weakness and treat him kindly; if good nature will not reclaim him ill humor will fail. I noticed in his early life a propensity to ridicule whatever to a well balanced mind would be proper and just, and am sorry to learn that this disposition increases with his years. You are becoming able to converse with the ladies of Boston; they vary much from those of Paris, and no wonder they are not the taste of Pallette. Their successful and untiring efforts to do good have stamped their name with immortality, and whatever may be your afflictions, you will find in them all that tenderness and charity which ennoble the female mind - ever emulous to pour in the wounded spirit the balm of consolation. Adelle has taken a permanent residence in England, and is, according to the dictates of the worthy Lord Briant, whose name she proudly bears, acting with his be- queathed estate as directed by his will. "With affection, "SARAH HOWE. "P. S.- Many thanks for the confidence you have reposed in me and the freedom with which you #lbur- delled your mind to your faithful "SARAi." Zoa was sitting alone, brooding over her sadness-the increasing neglect of Pallette; his cold averted look; his uneasy manner when in her presence; his ready  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7494-00000046"/> 90       LA BELLE ZOA; OR and severe retort, together with every other appearance, that plainly told her that she was no more beloved by him; now resolving on self-destruction; now praying to the Virgin Mary for the privilege to destroy with her own hands the accomplice of his guilt- when she was aroused from her reverie by the hurried step of Martha, the cook, who was in an instant kneeling before her, wringing her hands, her features distorted, and sobbing aloud. "Madam, dear madam, I will tell you all; I will conceal nothing; Robert, the false Robert, told me if I told you all I knew he wouldn't marry me. He said he hated a tattler; but he is a wretch; he has undone me, you see he has; he is married to-night, the wicked Robert!" Madam Pallette, looking at the object before her, saild: "Then Robert has deserted you?" "- He has, and so he has, and I can't help myself; T am a poor girl, took out of the alms-house and bound out; never knew anything but hard work and whip- ping." "Ad Robert is married?' "Yes, madam, by this time; and what do you think? yourltwn proud husband is there too." "What do you say?" said Zoa, raising her clasped hands. "What do I say? why I say Pallette is jest mean enough to go there all the time." "And can you point out the place?' - *c   THE INSURRECTION OF IIAYTI.    91 Yes, madam, I know it as well as the way to my mouth. I have carried letters there for Pallette. He said he'd kill me if I told you, but let him kill me; I had as lief die as live." "Conduct me," said Zoa, instantly putting on hei chapeau, " conduct me to the place." Martha did so, and Zoa saw through a window a com- pany who, in splendor, beauty and symmetry of form, exceeded the famed beauties of Cashmere. There the polka and the waltz were danced with measured step and perfect exactitude. A monient more and she saw Pallette waltzing with an apparently beautiful girl. As she looked her head grew dizzy, and she turned hastily away. Returning to her house, she took her sleeping babe, gave Martha a key, telling her she had another with which she could unlock the inside of her door. As she was retiring to her chamber, she said, "Come at early dawn; unlock my door; call in Pallette, for at that hour he will be at home, and I shall be ready for an interview." Pallette returned home at an unusual late hour. He stepped lightly to the door of his wife's chamber and listened a moment, no doubt thinking she might rise and reproach him; but all was still. He then went to his bed, but sleep was a stranger to his eye. There may be a superinatural power that, when a tragical scene is acting, troubles the spirit of those whom it concerns, without pointing out the. circumstance. We find it in Sacred Writ, that "On that night could not King ,  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7494-00000047"/> 92      LA BELLE ZOA; OR  Ahasuerus sleep." His mind was restless and troubled. He felt that there was guilt in the management of his affairs. He rose, and, by divine direction, leading to a chain of events, the plot of Haman was discovered; but Pallette knew he was the guilty one. He felt that a just God might espouse the cause of his injured wife, but knew not what had or was passing in her room. Martha, whose troubled mind kept her aloof from slumber, listened to the soliloquy of Pallette, determin- ing that whatever escaped his lips she would reveal to Madam Pallette. Wretch that I am! what have I done? I have, in the infatuation of the moment, given away the ring given me by Zoa. It was the first pledge. I will have it again, if at the expense of my heart's blood. It shall not adorn a hand so ill deserving the slightest token given me by my Zoa. Does my wife still sleep? And is she reckless of the conduct of her wayward husband? Compared to this, hell-flame would be a blessing. No, no, this cannot be. Affection, deeply rooted like hers for me, is not easily extinct." "That is good," thought Martha, "I'll tell Madam Pallette in the morning jest how he talked to hineelf. 'Twill make the poor thing feel glad. I'll make Robert give me the ring I gin him, and so I will. But it begins to grow light. 'll go and unlock the door. Won't the poor dear lady laugh to hear her husband come and say he's sorry? Poor thing.! how she did look when she took up her child. I thought she'd fall   TIlE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.    93 down, every step she took, she was so weak. Her face was paler than ashes, but 1 guess she'll feel better now." Martha unlocked the door as soon as daylight ap- peared, and going directly to the bed to communicate what she had heard, found it in nice order, and saw that no one had occupied it during the night. She turned around and saw Madam Pallette lying on the carpet by the escritoire, and her babe folded closely in her arms. "She is asleep," thought Martha. ' She fell down with weakness. 1 thought she could not stand up; poor thing! she did feel so bad. I'll wake her up and tell her good news." Then g(;ing near where she lay, the pallid features of Zoa told Martha that it was death thus depicted in her face. The timid girl screamed aloud; Pallette, ringing for his servant, requested him to go and see what had occurred. Otis went directly to the room. Martha continued to cry out for help. He saw both mother and child lying on the carpet. He took the hand of Madam Pallette: it was cold. He felt that her pulse ceased to beat, and that both mother and child were indeed dead. He then Went to Pallette and requested him to rise and go with him to the chamber of his wife. "For what?" said the frightened Pallette. "Come along, sir, and see for yourself. I cannot tell you, indeed I cannot." Pallette followed Otis, in breathless agitation, to the chamber of Zoa. He approached the place where his wife lay; he took her clay cold hand in his; he raised  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7494-00000048"/> "      LA BELLE ZOA; OR her up, but her arms hung down in weakness, and her eyes, though not closed, cast on him no expression of reproach. Her countenance, lovely even in death, wore ia placid expression, and even a smile seemed settled on her features. "i nd is this," said Pallette, " my lovely Zoa, who knelt before the dark man to save me; who unloosened the cords and delivered me from a fetid prison? Sweet innocent," said he, taking his little Harriet in his arms; " thy mother, in kindness, removed thee from a father unworthy of so bright a jewel. My whole course of wickedness stares me in the face, and I am humbled to the very earth. Could the wheels of time but roll backwards, and I again possess my lovely Zoa--my own dear wife-my whole life should be devoted to her." "It's too late now," said Martha, who could retain her feelings no longer. "It's too late now to repent." Pallette, whose haughty spirit was now entirely sub- dued, regarded Martha, and even seemed to feel the justice of her words. Otis, who had been, unnoticed by Pallette, looking over the last letter of Zoa, said, "Here is a letter." Pallette took the letter and read the contents. It was as follows: "The period of our correspondence on earth is done; my own eyes have witnessed your perfidy.  When shorn of country and friends; when my mother's terri- fied eye rolled on me in maniac frenzy; when my   THE INSURRECTION OF HAYTI.     95 brother's bloody corse was by my side; and my agonized father, in the imbecility of his age, crushed with the horror that surrounded him, I could have courage to live for base man -I thought of and loved you, and when my father, my last, best friend, was thrown in a watery grave, it was your presence that healed my lacerated, my bleeding heart. Yes, Pallette, when I looked on you, and thought myself the sole, the only object of your love, the multifarious misery of the past lost its sting. And oh God! before whom I am soon to appear, forgive me; for I have loved Pallette more than thee. But I am resolved; I will not endure the pain your presence would give me - no, I dare not see you again; the multiform visions of my bewildered fancy are driving me to madness; I see you in the voluptuous waltz; yes, with a vile daughter of infamy! Passion has the full ascendancy over my mind, and in my fury I might, weak and defenceless as I am, plunge a dagger in that heart which ceases to love me, or, fail- ing in the attempt, I might be victimized by him who swore, at the bed-side of my dying father, eternal con- stancy. My confessor has assured me of Heaven; I have nothing to hope for on earth. I will not share your love with a rival; no, rather eternal torments writhe me! Remember, Pallette, that, risking my life, I knelt before Toussaint and begged a life which, to me, was of more value than my own being. Your own conscience will speak my wrongs, when this heart ceas- es to beat and my pen to reproach you. I have my  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7494-00000049"/> 96       LA BELLE ZOA. own dear Harriet in my arms and a deadly potion ili my hand. I pause- the hollow tomb flits before me; what if it is dark and dismal, the light of day only shows a world that has not a charm for me, forsaken by the only one I ever loved. Ha! I have courage now -'tis done! I have swallowed a deadly poison; yes, and I have given of the same to my Harriet. She is no longer yours; you have severed the tenderest tie, and I will take with me all that is my own; I will give to our Blessed Mother my precious Harriet. I begin to feel a strange sensation come over me; life is reced- ing; passion abates; I have no charge to leave; I hold in my arms all of earth that is my own. How solemn, in this moment, are the evolutions of my mind! I feel all the kind emotions of my nature predominate; love, that unconquerable passion, pervades my whole soul. I would it were possible to eject the poison and go back to life, for the palsy of death is spreading over me; yes, live! could 1 but meet once mole your affec- tionate gaze as in days gone by, or even to say I forgive you. No other one can love you as I do, and may God forgive the transfer of your affection. I can even forgive her who has stolen your heart from me. I feel at peace with the whole world, as I wend my way along the dark avenue of death. Harriet, my child, do not struggle, thy mother holds thee; she feels the same. My eyes grow dim; my pen, I do not feel it; farewell." He laid down the letter; and taking his pistol,he aimed at the region of thought and fell lifeless beside them.     &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>