<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7505">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Love in the Nineteenth Century </title>
            <author >Preston, H. W. (1836-1911)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7505</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Love in the nineteenth century</title>
                  <author >Preston, H. W. (1836-1911)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >153 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Roberts</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1873">1873</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-01-25">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Love in the nineteenth century</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (Cover) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000001"/>  LOVE IN THE NINETEENTH CENTURY.   &#xD;<pb n="0Advertisement (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000002"/> BY THE AUTHOR OF "LOVE IN THE NINETEENTH CENTURY." A SPEND ALE. A STORY AND AN ESSAY. - I6mo. Price $1.25. Miss Preston's Translations. LIFE AND LETTERS OF MADAME SWETCHNE. Edited by COUNT DE FALLOUX. x6mo. Price $i.5o. WRITINGS OF MADAME SWETCHNE. Edited by COUNT DB FALLOUX. I6mo. Price $1.25. I PORTRAITS OF CELEBRATED WOMEN. By C A. SAINT-RBEUVE. i6mo. Price $150. MRfcIO: A ProvenCal Poem. By FREDERIC MSTRAL. Square ,2mo. Price $2.oo. ROBERTS BROTHERS, PUBLISHERS, Bostosn.   LOVE- IN THE NINETEENTH CENTURY.  BY HARRIET W. PRESTON, AUTHOR OF "ASPENDALE." Ah! what shall we say, then, but that earth threatened often Shall live on forever, that such things may be; That the dry seed shall quicken, the hard earth shall soften, And the spring-bearing birds flutter north o'er the sea. A,                MORRIS. BOSTON: ROBERTS BROTHERS. 1873-  &#xD;<pb n="0-1" xml:id="VAC7505-00000003"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1873, by ROBERTS BROTHERS, In the Office of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington.  CAMBRIDGE : PRESS OF JOHN WILSON AND SON.   LOVE IN THE NINETEENTH  CENTURY. I. EARLY in the pleasant summer of I870,. the widow of the late Deacon Morris Joy, of Morristown, in the Granite State, was relieved to find that her vacant room&amp;were nearly all engaged by season boarders. She was i mild, painstaking hostess; and only the unreasoning or imperfectly informed among her guests were inclined to censure her severely on the ground of kerosene lamps, excelsior mattresses, immature mut- ton, or plated spoons. Unhappily, these. were the very people who rented Mrs. Joy's largest rooms, and paid, with a certain' sense of injury, her most important bills. 1  &#xD;<pb n="2-3" xml:id="VAC7505-00000004"/> 2      LO VE IN THE But higher up, under the broad gambrel roof of the old homestead, which hardly seemed a homestead any longer, there were certain diminutive bedrooms; and these had tenants of a less expensive and less exacting order. Mrs. Jotham Grant's two nursery-maids abode in one, and the rest were occupied by artists, teachers, and people of that sort. If my reader Is par- ticular about his associates, he can pause here, and I shall not be offended; for the hero and heroine of what I hardly dare call my story both dwelt obscurely in opposite corners of this etage superieur. Hero was a young man attached to the editorial staff of a leading journal, who had overworked his eyes the preceding winter, and was now suffering three months of compulsory leisure in a mountain land, with a fierceness all American.4 He had described his condition to a solicitous friend in five graphic words,- "I am   NINETEENTH CENTURY.     3 resting like fury." Heroine, a reserved, soft-spoken girl of twenty-four, was under. stood to "give music-lessons, and certainly wore very little jewelry. Mrs. Grant con- sidered her haughty. Mrs. Joy affirmed that she "wasn't proud a bit."  The reader may make what he can of this conflicting testimony. The two-the youth and the maiden, of course I mean---had encountered for the first time on the narrow staircase which led to the attic rooms aforesaid, had glanced at one another indifferently, and each had been afterwards visited by the suspicion that they had somewhere met before. Being matter-of-fact young people both, schooled to unflinching research, the conscious heirs of twenty-three more ages than Plato, they had by no means accepted this vague presentiment as a divine intui- tion, but had pursued, captured, scrutin- ized, and finally identified it as the genuine  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7505-00000005"/> 4       LOVE IN THE though faded memory of a certain other summer, now many years gone, when a girl of thirteen and a boy of fifteen had been visitors in the same spacious house in a leafy, inland city. Hootings and revilings, frequent explosion of percussion- caps, and guerilla raids upon well-ordered baby-houses, filled up the outline of her reminiscences. Taunting airs and embry- onic graces, shrieks of alarm and, peals of defiant laughter, were prominent in his. Several days passed before either of our friends felt disposed to act upon their com- mon discovery. The woman considered curiously the change wrought in the square, boyish features that she remembered, by a dark beard, concave lenses, and a gen- eral look of national responsibility. The man - by divine right, I suppose -- gener- alized. He said to himself: "That plump, blonde, smiling type of face, which, in a child, is popularly held to be angelic,   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    5 makes the quietest and least significant of all countenances in a mature woman. And verily I think the coldest also." At length, one sultry evening, when the quartette - which sang nightly to Mrs. Joy's household for their sins -- was ranging itself about the piano, and the twice-mar- tyred journalist had turned his back upon the shadeless lamp with an inward groan and a muttered apology, my heroine suddenly assumed her prerogative, crossed the square parlor, and sat down beside him. "Are you not Julius May?" she said. He bowed. "And you are Clara Benson. I have been waiting to see whether you would know me." "And you see that I do. When did you hear from our mutual--I beg pardon- our common friends in Mayfield?" "Not for a long time. Bob, my com- rade, is living in San Francisco. What a delightful old- house it was! Have you been there lately?"  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7505-00000006"/> 6      LO VE IN THE "Oh, no! Emily, whom you used to tease along with me, is also married and never writes. Such is life. I have even heard that the Mayfield place was adver- tised for sale in the spring." "That seems a pity! I hope whoever gets it will realize the uncommon facilities for Hide and Seek, Follow my Leader, and other noble sports." "The lawn, too, must be very good for croquet." "Croquet is not a sport. It is only lan- guid exercise in the open air for ulterior purposes." "At all events, the exercise is what the newspapers call 'hygienic,' is it not?" "Oh, of course. And the ends to be subserved are mostly harmless, not to say necessary. But the popularity of the per- formance - I won't even call it a game - shows conclusively that we have wholly forgotten how to play." Then, after a pause, "Are you enjoying the music?"   -NINETEENTH CENTURY.    7- "I cannot say how much!" "All right," said Julius, more cheerfully than he had yet spoken. "Suppose we go outside for a little, and discuss our friends. And look at the moon, by Jove," added the halting sentimentalist, as they turned toward the door., "It is just rising." They went. Bob and Emily were duly analyzed, but theirs should have been typ- ical natures, so many large and momentous questions were suggested by the review of their characters and careers. There is reason to believe that among the themes broached by our young friends on that very first evening were the authority of the Scriptures, the antiquity of man, and the true theory of representative government. They did not touch upon the "woman- question," vilely so called, or the relations of labor and capital; but the omissions were purely accidental. Presently,as they were not really warming to their debate,-for  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7505-00000007"/> 8 -     LOVE IN THE both were as yet too deeply impressed with the vanity of all things here below for that, --but plunging somewhat deeply into it, Clara suggested that they had better go in. "Why? Because the formidable Mad- am Grant is eying. us askance from the front window?" Clara smiled so broadly as to show all her even teeth, a thing which seldom hap- pened, and replied, "That isothe reason, if you did but know it, why we have not been in before," and she led the way to the parlor. But their deep debate was destined to be resumed. It came to pass that for sev- eral successive evenings the music sent Julius and Clara to the moon (I beg the quartette's pardon, I do not exactly mean that it made them lunatic); and before a  week had ended, the spacious ground which they had reconnoitred in their first con-   NINETEENTH CENTURY.     9 versation was peopled by a host of lively young antagonisms. Julius laughingly commented on this fact one night, and a unique allusion to the dragon's teeth slipped into his discourse as naturally as if he had been writing a leader. "If our differences were of that sorti replied Clara, '"they would, presently de- stroy one another, and the field would be left precisely as it was before. And I dare say that will be the event. But who can have sown the seed of contention so liberally?"? "Mrs. General?" suggested Julius, nod- ding in the direction of the parlor window. For I am sorry to say that between the two this epithet had been allowed to attach itself to Mrs. Jotham Grant. "A stout Medea," replied Clara, shaking her head. "Jason never would have minded her."  "But, if there 's a woman alive capable   &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7505-00000008"/> 10      LO VE IN THE of cutting up and cooking a harmless old gentleman, I'll be bound it's she." "Come, come! we are getting scandalous and silly. After all," added Clara, with one of those swift retours which are char- acteristic of the feminine mind, gentlemen, - and equally of yours! " after all, there is a kind of fascination about these vistas of infinite divergence." "Queer vistas those, Miss Clara! Per- spective knows them not." "I meant difference, of course." "You meant convergence," said Julius, a ( little mischievously: " the lines always meet in the end." "Oh, do they?  I thought they only appeared to. What are parallel lines, sir?" with a school-ma'am air. "Parallel lines," replied Julius, in a nasal monotone, "are those which do not meet how far soever either way both of them be produced."   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    I I "Very good. To-morrow you may take the first proposition. No, not to-morrow, because 'tis Sunday, but next week. Arid mind you have a good lesson! ' Be abso- lutely perfect, that's all I ask,' as I once heard a proud mother say to her only child after setting her a task." It will thus appear that our young people were both mathematl and classical, and also that they were bec ming acquainted. to  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7505-00000009"/> 12      LOVE IN THE II. ON Sunday Clara was calm and prim. She went in the morning to the village church, wearing her brown shade hat; a proceeding which Mrs. Grant thought het- erodox, not to say immoral. For her own part that conscientious dame never neg- lected an opportunity like the present clearly to point the way of fashion in apparel to the benighted souls by whom she was surrounded. Julius, who had smoked more than was needful during the morning hours, waylaid Clara as she was slipping out after their early dinner, and began to quiz her about the sermon of the morning. He found her irresponsive. "What was the text?"   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    I3  / "I seldom notice texts. I attend to the teaching." "If any. Well, what did you learn?" Silence. "' Nothing, it appears. Did you expect to learn any thing when you went?" "Perhaps not." "Then the question is, why did you go?" "Am I in the witness-box?" asked Clara. "I don't remember taking any oath." "A smart answer, Mademoiselle, but eva- sive! H really want to know on what principle of self-mortification you sit for two hours of a fresh morning on a hard bench in a stifling room, and hear a melan- choly old mummy whine out commonplaces in which you have neither interest nor faith, while screams issue at intervals from a score or more of raging musicians at your back." "Pretty well for a paragraph," was the  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7505-00000010"/> 1 4     LOVE IN THE reply, " but flippant and - forgive me - a little professional. Preaching may be hack- neyed, but jeers at preaching are at least equally so, and what is called religious discussion altogether distasteful to me. Yet I don't mind hinting at the reason you require. You seem to think nothing of the end for which all this which you ridicule is done." Julius was a gentleman, and resisted the temptation to whistle. "And now," said the lady, "I am going away to read." He stretched out his hand with a smile for the book which she carried, but it was ,quietly withdrawn. "It would try your eyes," she said.: " the print is bad." And whether it were a Kempis, Huxley, or Sainte-Beuve, he never knew. Monday morning came, and Mrs. Joy, her maids, and her boarders relapsed into toil, - those, of providence; these, of pleas-   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    15 ude. Julius, who had already explored every gorge and land-slide, and scaled all the accessible and inaccessible, mountains in the region; who had religiously essayed trouting and -found himself much too ner- vous for success in the gentle art, now, driven of ennui, began to wonder what Clara did with her mornings. He had observed that she almost always left the house, sometimes alone, sometimes taking with her a few of the superfluous Grant children, the youngest of whom seemed a perfect Ginx's baby in high life, and rolled indiscriminately over the stairs in the hall and the clover on the lawn. When he had wondered certain days, it occurred to the modern mind of Julius May to take active measures of investiga- tion. He therefore followed at a distance --it were unkind to say dogged - the footsteps of Clara. In so doing, he crossed the dusty stage-road on which the Joy  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7505-00000011"/> i6      LOVE IN THE mansion fronted; crossed, carefully skirting the vine-clad stone wall, a mowing-field already whitening with daisies; crossed, or rather climbed, a long hillside pasture, haunted by murmuring bees and tinkling bells; and entered a narrow wood-path. A few rods only of devious footing through pleasant coolness, emerald lights, and danc- ing shadows, and then the trees once more divided, and our hero descried the object of his only half-acknowledged search. I " can't tell a lie," reader, - not even to pique your curiosity. The spot where Jul- ius emerged is indeed to become fatal in this small history, start not at the sound of rushing water far beneath, I do not mean mortal,--and so it must be described. A pretty spot it was, and most quaintly and effectually retired. A semicircle of fresh green turf was bounded along its base by the steep bank of a picturesque   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    17 stream, and around its arc by lofty trees, pines mostly, which cast a dense shadow upon the open space. A straggling fence of fallen boughs, dragged from within the grove, subtended a lesser arc of sward, within which Mol e and Edith Grant were housekeeping in all industrious content. The frail barrier I have described might not have sufficed to restrain the little ones within safe limits, but the mild authority of their self-chosen. day governess evidently did so. The -latter was reclining in a roomy arm-chair curiously built of granite boulders, with sewing-work on her lap and a book in her hand. The opposite shore of the river, now beauteous in morning sunshine, was also rocky and precipitous, crowned with trees and feathery with fern; and, vexed by its straitened limits, the river- tumbled white and foamy many feet below. A little way up the stream was visible the ' abutment of an adventurous old bridge,"  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7505-00000012"/> I8      LOVE IN THE carried off by a spring freshet ten years before and never rebuilt. The right line of moss-grown masonry relieved the eye in this wild place, as the contour of some lonely feudal tower will sometimes do in older and mellower lands than ours. Clara was not glad at heart to have her retreat discovered. Of courtesy not of coquetry came the faint smile and the brief welcome she gave the invader; but he, being untroubled by bashfulness, sauntered slowly onward, pulled the pink ears of Mollie Grant in passing, and dropped upon the grass. "So here is where you spend your days I How doth she improve her mind!" "A harmless pastime of a summer morn- ing. Try it." "Hang it! I have no choice," said Julius, a little querulously. "Oh, surely! I beg your pardon. Would you like me to read'aloud?"   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    19 "That depends on what you have. Is it Euripides or the ' Origin of Species'?" "It is ' Phineas Finn, The Irish Mem- ber,"' was the demure reply. "Trollope? Ye gods! Miss Benson reads Trollope!" "And so do you, I dare say, when you. read at all. You knew the authorship of my book right quickly." "I certainly have wasted some hours of my' probation,' as they call it, in that way; but I would not advise you to. Now, se- riously, it is weak rubbish." "Do you think so?" "I know so. Hackneyed plots or none at all; endless verbiage; a detestable style." "It would not answer for a journalist, I suppose; but I believe I like it. In the first place I like the author. He is so catholic and kindly and generous to every one. He puts on no grand airs of being a ' high artist or a representative writer, but  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7505-00000013"/> 20      LOVE IN THE spins his yarn in such an easy, merry, homely fashion that you are cheated about its real ingenuity. And then his humor- and how much he has! - is perfectly sweet; and that can be said of so few novelists ,now-a-days. Even Dickens, if it be not sacrilegious to say so now, was growing more cynical and morbid every year. The last really amiable story-teller was Walter Scott. And it is so very, very pleasant to be tickled and to laugh, and to think the worse of no one when the laugh is over. It seems to me that in ' Barchester Towers,' which I like best of all Anthony's books, and more or less in the whole voluminous Barset series, there is a great deal of whole- some fun and some true pathos. And next to Mr. Trollope himself I like his men and women, especially the men. I like this Mr. Finn. He is neither heroic nor profound. He is in fact very fallible; but he is modest and he is pleasant. He has a   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    2.1 good heart which does not disdain to express itself in perpetual courtesy. He is accessible to a good many kinds of temp- tation, ad yet he never does a mean or cowardly thing. I call that a very good sort of man." "And he is a beauty, if I remember rightly, which weighs more than all the rest." And Julius, who had taken up the volume, sneered at the illustrations and scowled at the type, now threw it aside; adding rather absurdly, "Well, you are welcome to him." "You can't forgive him his good looks," observed the lady, gayly. 6 But what of Mr. Trollope'swomen? Do you not like them? I should, think all 'men would do so, for they are irreproachably feminine without being tiresome." "I liked his woman pretty well when I knew her first, but she is getting passee, or ought to be by this time. He has but one."  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7505-00000014"/> 22      LOVE IN THEE. "I don't see that any except the few greatest masters of fiction have more than one,-- or two at the utmost. And Mr. Trollope's high-minded girl is a great deal better than Mr. Dickens's self-complacent goosie or Mr. Reade's purring cat." "'Pretty well for a paragraph;' but you are more than half right in your main statement. And upon my word I don't know that the great masters, as you call them, are any exception to the rule. Scott certainly had no variety in his female char- acters; and even Shakespeare "- "No blasphemy! Realize if you can the range from Portia to Cleopatra." "Well, leave him aside. He could make a world for himself, I suppose, if this one did not suit him. But suppose the rest of them, even those who have apprehended most of life and men, and who show all sides, have described but about one woman apiece, or less, --for often two of them   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    23 have described the same, --now  what would seem to be the inference?" (No doubt your flattering notion is that the sameness is in the real women. But that 's not the reason. Be patient and I will unfold it. 'Tis because, up to the present time, men, and especially great men, if only intellectually great, have been in the way, instinctively, and I dare say unconsciously, of regarding women, like other subordinate creatures, as something less than individuals. And so they have not thought it worth while to study them from life as they have their men, but in- stead they have given us their several ideals of feminine grace and goodness, or the reverse. Their men have been men, and their women have been types, abstrac- tions. The very fact that every author has had one of his own, and no more- than one, shows plainly enough )that the conception . has been" "Say subjective."  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7505-00000015"/> 24      LOVE IN TEE "Well, subjective. Now I am not quar- relling with the fact, which may never be different. On the contrary, I think it is interesting and instructive. I always meant sometime to make a regular careful study of the types of womanhood in fiction, and see if something might not be learned by collating the ideals of men. I think indeed that I have already learned something. Almost every famous author endows his women, or his woman, with some one vir- tue which real women are not very apt to possess " - "Are there any such?" "Don't be impertinent!- and this again shows that the character is purely ideal. Scott's heroines, for example, are trivial enough in some respects, but they have almost all high spirit and physical courage. And poor, dear Mr. Trollope,--his girls tell the truth even- to their lovers, and they do not flatter them "-    NINETEENTH CENTTURY.    25 "Tautology!" "You are in a very churlish mood this morning, but 'I forgive you, and you can't help yourself,' to quote Mr. Heep's great epigram."          - "You are very good. I 'll try to be more amiable, and worthier of so merciful an antagonist. But your women novelists,-- they draw more than one man, I suppose." "Now again It shall say just what I think; and you will hoot at me as really, if not as shrilly, as when you shattered my young nerves by giving cat-calls in May- field." "Say on. I am   getting -used to your words of exhortation." "Why, then, I know very well that, on the whole, so far, the women novelists are not to be compared with the men. I say on the whole. Of course there are some grand exceptions, the Georges notably, but I dare say we are both tired of their names: 2  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7505-00000016"/> 26      LOVE IN THE you, because there are any; I, because there are no more. But if ever we do come alongside of you, Mr. Journalist, in artistic and dramatic ability, there will be a new order of things in fiction. For we know you better than you think; better than we quite dare to say; better, I verily believe, than you know us. Is it not gen- erally allowed that women read character more readily than men?" "It may be allowed by those who-are too lazy to look into it. I have certainly heard the assertion a good many times. Now prove it, please." "It can be proved," replied Clara, frown- ing, " because " - with an ignominious lapse into that sort of logic which women alone (?) employ --" because it 's true. But, at all events, here is one consideration. Women have always been more dependent for their happiness,--their general peace of mind, I mean, not their petty comforts, - on the   NINETEENTH CENTURY.   27 characters of the men with whom they were associated, their fathers, sons, husbands, and so on, than men on those of their female relatives. You were going to say, ' Prove that,' but I shall not, because you know it is true;. and this dependence has made them very acute. All dependants are acute. How well your servants know you! And, besides, women have had only individuals to deal with and think of and plan for, and those for the most part their nearest  and dearest; but men have had masses, and such as were quite indifferent to them. But it is chiefly difficult," added Clara, with the slightest possible shade of mocking gruffness in her voice, " to put this demon- stration into a form that you will appreciate, because the knowledge I speak of is in part what you call --I dislike the term-- instinctive." "Oh-ho!" said Hero. "Yes; but," resumed the other, trium-  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7505-00000017"/> 28      LOVE IN THE phantly, " instinctive don't mean any thing at all in this case. What you clumsily call instinct in a woman is nothing more nor less than reasoning so rapid that you cannot count its steps,--reasoning winged by love or fear or some other emotion. By and by we may get mental magnifiers powerful enough to disclose the process. Meanwhile you know it by experience. You read over a mathematical proposition, and you look at the diagram which illustrates it, and you say to yourself, ' Of course that is so.' You give it the assent, not of faith certainly, but of what? And yet you might not be able, out of hand, to analyze your assent so as to make its grounds clear to an ignoramus like me, for example. Do you under- stand?" "I understand you to say that the female mind needs to be looked at through a mi- croscope, which sounds very much like treachery to the sisterhood. And for the   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    29 rest, I must say, Miss Benson, that I have by far the most confidence in the knowl- edge which can give a clear account of itself. As to the mathematical matter, I might not be able, out of hand, as you say, to go through with just the rubbishy A, B, C, D of the book; but I could give some sort of a rational demonstration, if I were good for any thing." "'Well, perhaps so." And then these two laughed frankly, content apparently with themselves and one another. "And now," continued the lady, "do you see where that shadow is? In fifteen minutes this place will be all in sunshin,-which means that it is dinner-time. Come, chil- dren,- come haste to the mutton!" "Like that tune?" asked Julius, after whistling the stave suggested by her words. "I 'll ask our quartette to sing it this evening." " -   &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7505-00000018"/> 30      LOVE IN THE "I. MY reader's mind is now, I trust, so far prepared, that no violent shock will be received from what is to follow. Many days had gone by. One moon had waxed and-waned, and another was following hard after it. More mighty themes had been essayed by those two idle inmates'of Mrs. Joy's, and other vexed questions vexed still farther, with the same impressive result as heretofore. The Franco-Prussian war had been declared, entailing a fresh outhreak of hostilities between our own belligerents; and Mrs. Grant said, "It was not her af- fair, but sAe considered it a deliberate flirtation." At length a day arrived when Miss Benson received a letter praying for her immediate presence in a distant part   lVIllYsLij1.  bb1Y] Ucji L  v  U ai . 3 x of New England, and did not allow herself to demur to the summons. She mentioned her altered plans the same evening to Jul- ius, who said:- "Ah, I am sorry you must go! I shall stay on a week or two longer, and then get back to work." The next morning Clara was busy pack- ing, and did not go to the river. In the afternoon she went somewhither, but not by way of the now shaven field and the hill- pasture. It was the hour of siestas; and Julius, after fidgeting awhile about the deserted porch and parlor, sitting down at the piano and playing a few bars of Chopin's "Funeral March" in a slow, square, ominous fashion, which produced upon the sleepers overhead the effect of distant thunder, arose, took his hat, and wandered off, his footsteps taking half- involuntarily the now accustomed way. She was there, after all,- of course she  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7505-00000019"/> Ad      A^ rjz, Jv v^j }'EY was, --seated in her rocky perch above the river, without a book this time, but with a basket of birch-bark gathered for one of the friends she was going to meet, who chanced to be a cunning artificer in wood- land trifles. The youth fancied that she looked a little grave and abstracted when he first caught sight of her. The maiden, however, affected no surprise at his appa- rition: only the intent expression cleared away from  her face as mist passes off a summer landscape when the wind blows west by north, leaving it bright and cool. The youth then opened conversation with the striking remark, "I never was here in the afternoon before." And   the maiden responded worthily, "It is usually very sunny here at this hour; but not to-day, on account of'the clouds." For the sky was veiled in tender gray. And   it is these shadowed days, let me  I ' 'I'   remark in passing, which prove the spell of summer. When the season of growth is at its height, and the land lies full green beneath the blaze of a vertical sun, there will be times when Nature seems. only one vast laboratory, and the sense of universal and bounteous production over- powers in the beholder the more spiritual sense of beauty. In the stress of what is doing we heed not what is done. But there are also times, rare- times of respite, hours of that deep calm which may or may not prelude storm; shadowy intervals when the ardent task-masters of the toil- ing earth repose awhile, and we see for the first time with undazzled eyes the miracle their energy has wrought.  Is this the world that lately smiled so shyly on us through the shimmering greens and change- ful lights of spring? that will presently flush with autumn and wither into win- ter? Oh to arrest and fix this hour. of ' 2*  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7505-00000020"/> absolute perfection! It is passing swiftly, and we had not known it until now!  A thought like this had been in Clara's mind when Julius came upon her. Some- thing withheld her from expressing it, but it suggested another which might freely be spoken, and she did not want long pauses. "I will tell you something strange," she said. "Days like this--cloudy, soft days in summer- always carry me back to one such a long while ago, when I was a little schoolgirl, and puzzled out from the second book of the Eneid the story of the fall of Troy. There was an open window near my desk, and I suppose the subdued loveliness of the world outside was appealing to my senses all the while that my poor young brain was trying to keep hard at work. Anyhow, the still weather and the sad, preposterous tale got themselves inextricably blended in my   mind, and I have ever since cherished a firm conviction that I saw Troy in its last lays, and that the weather was like this. And now  here comes William    Morris with his heart-rending 'Death of Paris,' and behold he has my very idea! He ascribes the selfsame weather to 'the last month of Troy's beleaguerment.' I can- not tell you with what emotion I read those exquisite opening stanzas, less for their beauty than because their atmosphere was so perfectly familiar. Do you remem- ber how 'The gray clouds big with the threat of rain Parted a space and on the Trojans shone, And, struck a glory from that shining one.' I am very much inclined to believe that Mr. Morris and I were both there in that city by the sea where the scholars 'rage for ever,' -and the critics 'imagine a vain thing;' but that he remained after I left, and has come at last to tell me more  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7505-00000021"/> o       ,utj" v2 . 1V  THE of what befell.   Don't you  believe it? and is it not a coincidence?" Julius did not answer; and Clara, after a quick glance at him, went on quoting Morris from   memory: -- "'I cannot tell what crop may clothe the hills, The merry hills Troy whitened long ago, - Belike the sheaves wherewith the reaper fills His yellow wain no whit the weaker grow For that past harvest-tide of wrong and woe, Belike the tale wept over otherwhere Of those old days is clean forgotten there.' "I hope you like that," she said, after another moment's silence. ( Rather," replied   Julius, who had been taking   a sudden  resolution; "but  never mind Troy or the coincidence! I have something practical to say." After which winning preamble, he disengaged a small stone from the turf on which he reclined, flung it far into the river, and went on. "The fact is, the more I think of your leaving this place, the less I like it. Our   acquaintance has been a very pleasant one, - to me, at least, - - and it has occurred to me that it might be worth while to con- tinue it. What do you say?" "Why," replied the lady, innocently, "I never meant to cut you. I don't consider it ladylike." Julius bit his lip. "Let me say," he exclaimed impetuously, "that one of the things I have liked best in you has been your singular freedom from coquetry and affectation. If you.,are going to put on the airs of other girls, I shall be disen- chanted." It was Clara's turn to change counte- nance a little. Her eye took a color, her, lip a curl, hardly perceptible, yet hardly reassuring. "You will not be, disen- chanted, I think," she said quietly, "and for the best of reasons." A pause. Then from our hero: "Oh, come, let us quit sparring! I, for once,  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7505-00000022"/> 38      LOVE IN THE am entirely serious. But, if it is your settled purpose to make light of my pro- posal, say so, and we will drop the sub- ject." This struck Clara as funny, and restored her good-humor.  But she quelled her rising laughter rather generously, and said in a tolerably steady voice, "I really don't think I quite know what the proposal was." "I think you do, though!  But why should I not be explicit? So here it is, Miss. I have enjoyed our intercourse, our walks, talks, nonsense, and so on. You have never told me, indeed, that you have done the same, but "-- "But I have. Else it would not have gone on so long." "Well, then, is it not possible," said Julius, with a little the air of one reading a legal instrument, "that this which you permit me to call our common gratifica-   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    39 tion might ripen in time into a more serious and stable feeling, a a suitability, a fitness for mutual assistance, a" --sim- pler words than his own rose to Julius's lips,--"a dear, sweet habit of living to- gether,"--but he repressed them, "I am not a spooney," he informed himself se- verely, and added, in an entirely business- like manner, "in short, into the love of husband and wife?" But Clara shook her head. slowly, an- swering in a tone of amusement which was yet a little sad, "' Our common grat- ification,' as you call it, has been only the pastime of a summer day. ' It is singu- larly unlike the love of fiction, and what the love of al life may be I have never been able to determine." "Nor I, upon my soul! And still"-- Julius hesitated, for, I grieve to say, his memory was once more assailed: this time by a line from Tennyson, "Dear, but  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7505-00000023"/> 40      LOVE IN THE let us type them no, in our own lives," but the sentiment issued from his lips shorn--rather--of its grace and pathos -"we might ascertain." "I suppose we might," replied the lady, quite frankly, and even sweetly; " but now listen to me. We know at least that our knowledge of one another is superficial; and has not even that slight acquaintance come of circumstances rather than choice? The house .has been so dull! No pretty school-girls to refresh your ailing eyes "- "But you are nice-looking, Clara,--in certain lights and attitudes, very nice-look- ing indeed." "Do   you think so? I wonder if I ought to take more pains to keep in those lights and attitudes? But you interrupted me. I was going to say that I, on the other hand, had probably been somewhat influenced by compassion for your priva- tions and evident distress of mind."    "Well, and, has not some weak-minded person said something or other about the kinship of compassion to a stronger feeling?" "Y-e-s, but our endless talks,--what have they amounted to?  Sparring, as you truly said just now. I know that I have scarce ever given you my deepest thought about any thing, and I should hope-forgive me--that you had not given me yours. It has been the 'strife for triumph more than truth.' I think that is a very significant line." "Alliteration!" with professional scorn. "Well, why not?  Alliteration is just as much a form of word-music as rhyme, -a kind"- "Keep to the point, please!" "Never fear! I can't say, as some would think I ought, positively and per- emptorily that I know you, and I could never be happy married. If I could, it / * I  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7505-00000024"/> 42      LOVE IN THE seems to me I should be the sort of per- son whom you might win easily, and afterwards be very sorry for having won. But I do think our present acquaintance affords the smallest possible ground for any such confidence. I have wondered all my life at the ignorant, unreflecting way in which people promise to love and marry one another. Marriage involves so very much. I should want to know a great deal more of a man first than I know of you. I must understand his temper, his history, his mode of life, and all he thinks about certain moral and social questions, and whether he have a religion, and what it is. And on some of the same points you want--or ought to want to be satisfied about me. And you want to know also whether I am a housekeeper and can darn stockings,-- which (is all fair. Now, on reflection, do you not? And then there are other   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    43 things. We know   something ot  one another's parentage --"   story-books , ' Poor but honest,' as the sto Yes.   That description will answer very well. As some one observes, it would be more to the point in this time and country to say rich but honest. But I do suppose also-you    y  disenchanted now  that we   ought to know something of one another's circum- "Very true! 'Tis never that sort  thing, let me tell you, that disenchants me. I like your little practical wisdom. Well leave out the ' little; ' for I see you do not like that. The very first evening that we fled from the ' warbles,' you made one or two us .;  hem  --- remarks of those sagacious lit--ahem-  res of yours, and I said to myself Here is a woman who is not far from the kingdom , of common sense. Besides,   &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7505-00000025"/> a a     v r -A Y 1 a'HE to have mentioned in the beginning that I have no money. My good father has a little,---precious little,--but he needs it all. And he lives with my married sister. He would like you." "And she?" "Why, she would like you too. Would she not? For the rest, I have a decent salary,--not much to live on, to be sure, in Trimountain; and I am still in debt, slowly lessening, for some things --we will say my education --at college. That is all, Mademoiselle!" "And I," said Clara, "am an orphan, as you know; and I have just seven thou- sand dollars of my own. This fortune is so very deeply and deliberately invested that it gives me four hundred dollars a year sure, and never more. Now, of course, I cannot live on that. But I have some rich relatives,-in this land of liberty who has them not?--and they   would be very glad, or think they would, to have me live with them. They say I could dress on my income and remain ' in society.' .Now you know I could not, or at least you do not know, but they ought certainly to do so, who spend four or five times that. I could not make my- self presentable in their eyes on four hun- dred dollars a year, without racking my brains perpetually, besides accepting pres- ents. All- of which would fatigue and annoy me very much. So I prefer to live in Minden, where there is, as you know, what somebody saucily calls a ' fresh- water' college, and where gentility is re- markably cheap. There I can give music- lessons at moderate rates to well-bred little girls or studious old ones, and so win another .four hundred a year or there- abouts. And on these, my revenues, I live at mine ease, and buy a few books, and have something to give away. The  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7505-00000026"/> "     LOVE IN THE girls in Minden must be accomplished, you see, but also it must be done inexpen- sively; and I teach them a great deal more scientifically than they would ordi- narily be taught for what they pay me. And so I serve Art, Sir.  'Oui, moi indigne /' Now have I not my niche? And as for society, don't I go as many as five times in a year in a stuffy old carriage to a prim little party? And the hack-hire is twenty-five cents, and the party is intellectual. What can Trimoun- tain offer me?" "Not .uch, to be sure! Well, I like UyOllp irit, although you are a pitiable political economist, and seem never to have considered that you ought, if only for the sake of the many teachers who have no seven thousand dollars, to receive the worth of your lessons. Now, if I were to write to you in Minden, could you leave your fascinating employments long enough to answer me?"   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    47 "I have no doubt I could. And I will even own that such a correspondence might give a new zest to life even in that merry town." "And then when you have had enough of comparing notes"- "Let us say nothing about the future," answered Clara, gently. "That will be most honorable to ourselves and one an- other. Three months from now it may not be I who will care most to be free." "As you please."  And Julius, who was at heart a little relieved that his rash- ness had had no more fatal issue, took up the basket of birch-bark, and they trudged homeward together. The cloud-veil was unbroken still, but a warmer tint suffused the edges of its folds like a flush upon a swarthy cheek. Beneath this sober canopy, meadow and woodland assumed a strangely vivid green, while the hills that lay around the horizon  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7505-00000027"/> 48     LOVE IN THE wore their softest bloom, dark blue, but not yet dim.  One doubted after all whether it would rain on the morrow. And did Clara sit long at her window that night, watching the moon in her struggle with the clouds? and did Julius pace the country road, and think of her? Not she. Not he. They both slept early and well, and parted next morning at the stage-door with smiles and a cordial hand-shake.   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      49 IV. ON the second week in September, Clara, going in person to the Minden post-office, received, along with a scientific monthly and three religious newspapers for the ladies of the family where she boarded, a letter which the white-haired official turned right side up with that air of pointed  benignity which appears a dis- tinctive grace of the village postmaster. The letter was as follows:- TRIMOUNTAIN, September, I870.  .. I have come back to the old treadmill, and none too soon. Your Frenchmen are giving us plenty to do. We feel obliged to cheer a little for their trumpery republic, but it cannot last six weeks. The stuff is not in them. Prussia, meanwhile, is carrying every thing before her; and all sensible people will say amen. 'Tis high time the world demurred a little to French dictation in politics, morals, literature, 3-  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7505-00000028"/> 50       LOVE IN THE * apparel, and some few other things. Apropos of ap- parel, or what I take to be a branch of that great subject, now that Eugenie is in eclipse, let us hope that ladies will wear their own hair, and learn once more to let it fall around the forehead as it used in my tender years, and as God meant it to do, instead of straining it away after the unseemly fashion of the second empire. I used to look at you last summer, Miss Benson, and long for that day to come, but little thought the stars in their courses were fighting to fulfil my desires. You see I do think of you now and then amid the "wreck of matter and the crush of worlds," and find that some of your aphorisms have really impressed me very much, although even you now and then gave utterance to a bit of cant. For instance, when you said to me that last day in Morristown, half-laughingly to be sure, "And so I serve Art!"Now it happens, although perhaps you did not know it, that just at present, in the city, what I call the art-cant is the most fashionable, and hence the most insufferable of all. It displaces re- ligious and even irreligious cant, and, as usual, is talked loudest by those who know least. Magazine critics are very free with it: "He is a true artist," "She has not the feeling of the artist," "Such a per- formance is thoroughly artistic or inartistic," as the case may be or may(not be; for most of them, as I say, have but the dimns idea of what they are talk-   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       51 ing about. Flowery divines preach a similar doctrine from flower-decked pulpits: "Love the beautiful, my friends," they say, waving their white hands toward the crucified lilies, " and you will unconsciously love the good." Very unconsciously indeed, par exemplZe  For your aesthetic devotees are notoriously apt to be the most supremely selfish of mankind. And then there is another class who very much affect this kind of- thing, and it is precisely because they do that I object to the faintest trace of it in your fresh talk. I mean -how shall I put it delicately?- the great unsatisfied, the anxious and aimless, the noble army of cultivated spinsters, in short. They have somehow become possessed of the idea that the higher life which they propose to lead presents a single alterna- tive, -love or art. They can't have the one, and so they are bound to have, or pretend they have, the other. Hence voluble comments and shrill raptures, fit almost to paralyze one's appreciation of Browning or Beethover. I believe I know, after all, the first cause of the mischief I have been bewailing. Was it not Mrs. Browning in "Aurora Leigh "? Has she not a great deal to say about art, and again about art and love in connection or antithesis?"Art is much, but love is more," or something of that sort? Now I admire Mrs. Browning enthusiastically. I like her better than I do her husband, and think she was the greater man; but the same thought that sparkles  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7505-00000029"/> 52       LOVE IN THE with light and oxygen when it first sees the day at the altitude of a soul like hers, becomes flat and tur- bid enough by the time it has percolated down to the level of those I have described. How is that - I was going to say, " for high?" but remembered just in time that you are a purist. I have gossiped on like any woman of them all,  and far overrun my time. The provisional govern- ment will have to be the sufferer, but no matter? It won't take long to do justice to that experiment. Let us know as soon as may be how you support life in the glassy cove where you elect to anchor. It must be about time for the annual shoal of Freshmen. How do they look? Frisky and scaly as usual, I suppose, and they flap their tails, don't they, with a sense of importance such as - alas! - they will never feel again? One thing I do envy you in sol- emn Minden, - the breath of the pine-woods. It is "more wholesome at least than the rich odor of rot- ting fruit which pervades all the streets and squares of Trimountain during the month of September. Adieu.   NINETEENTH CENTURY. ,     53 V. MORE than once during the reading of this letter, Clara lifted her eyes to heaven in pious deprecation of the self-conceit of man; but she replied with zest, and after no long delay. MNDEN, September, I870.  . . Many thanks for your letter, which gave me several things to think about. What a wonderfully assured sort of person you -are! I admire the way in which you set the French republic down with one hand, and the aspiring maidens with the other (not spinsters, by the way: the chief trouble with the class to which you allude is that they neither toil nor spin); while at the same time you nod encour- agement or reproof at the mighty Brownings. Is it the training of a journalist that does it? Am I laughing at you? Only a little. Do not be angry. I know very well that I do not know enough to laugh at any one, and-also that written sauciness is much less pardonable than oral. And, seriously,  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7505-00000030"/> 54       LOVE IN THE ! do sometimes feel that it would be the greatest possible blessing to be sure about any thing. This art matter, for example, which you dismiss so lightly, --I have thought about it a great deal of late, and so have other folks whose thoughts are far better worth than mine. It is one of the foremost questions of the day, and this again sounds like cant; but what is one to say? There is a day and there are 'questions, and this is of them. If shallow people talk froth about it in that "small, illiterate town" of yours (I quote Humboldt on Berlin), it is because profound people are stirring it up from its lowest depths. Why, the very brightest men in England and we all know in our hearts, and glory in knowing, that there are no, brighter - are beating their brains just now about the general subject of culture, of which this art question is one of the main branches. I know what you are saying. I have heard your voice all along, "monotonous and hollow like a ghost's,"- "State your question! State your ques- tion!"  Yes,sir,I will,-two of them. What place is art to have, or ought it to have, in that more complete and satisfactory human life we are all trying to realize? and how is art to be made avail- able to the many? For that which only benefits the few won't answer, and cannot be tranquilly enjoyed in this country, if it would. Voild/ Do not my questions read regular? Now respond!   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      55 I do not remember "Aurora Leigh " very clearly. We read it aloud at home, - the way I did all my best reading, - but it was when the book was young and I very young, and I don't think I took it in. I remember the story -of course, - it was a strange- one, -but not the philosophy and I seem to recall also a good deal about art in the book, and that Mrs. Browning says in the preface,- "My highest convictions upon Art and Life have entered into it." So perhaps Aurora would indeed shed light on my; present difficulties. I never liked Mrs. Browning's poetry, by the way, nearly so well as her husband's, but that is all natural. I mean to reread "Aurora Leigh " carefully. Yes, life is " glassy" in Minden; and art- native art, as exemplified in hearth-rugs and crayon heads-is rather primitive and formal. But I like the place. To-day the wide main street, busy down by the river, silent and classic up here upon the hill, is washed clean as a beach by the recent rains. The elms are in full foliage yet, with only here and there a golden bough, - Hawthorne's bough, Virgil's bough. How the fancies of the dead enrich our daily life! The real stone spires, whereof we are all innocently proud, stand out against a background of intensest blue; the grass on lawns and college- grounds and frequent open fields is greener than in June; the flower-borders in the little gardens are at  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7505-00000031"/> 56       LOVE IN THE their gayest. And here, in this roomy cottage, where I have boarded now three years with the widow of old Professor Faulkner, all is orderly and staid. That it is also shabby does not trouble me. The affecting poverty and inviolable refinement which these rooms reveal remind me of my own lost home, and suit me, as I sometimes thinlk,better than elegance. Mrs. Faulkner is perhaps a little grim. She is undoubtedly a "Hebraist," and has what you call the ' true Orthodox wrinkles" at the corners of her mouth; but the silver hair lies very smooth under her widow's cap, and what a clear head she has, and what a kind heart! Then the three Miss Faulkners, the youngest of whom might have been your aunt, - don't you wish you knew them? I do. They would correct some of your boyish errors. They are very skilful with their needles, and have great need to be; but they are not over fond of the sewing-circle, and two of them never drink tea. They read history, and study German and Botany and "The Evidences of Christianity," and come in pleased from their constitutional if they have had a bow from the President. But they never parade their researches into books, and when they are in company they keep well in the background, as befits people who have had the misfortune to be a good while in this world. Then they plant a flower- garden every spring, and tend it themselves; and   NIINE TEENTH CENTURY.      57 meanwhile watch with all the sick people, and make beautiful white wreaths and crosses for them when they die. And they do other things out ini their pleasant kitchen, which I shall not specify, because they are themselves rather shy and proud about them; but you would like one of their five-o'clock teas very well. And they don't in the least hate me because I am comparatively young; as the idiotic popular prejudice would, make them do, but rather admire and coddle me foolishy. Such a life may not be brilliant, but I don't see that it is contempt- ible. I think it Wvould content me very well. "Let not Ambition" (that's yourself) "mock their useful toil," &amp;c. And now I have a term of comparison for Minden. It is for all the world like Gray's "-Elegy in a. Country Churchyard,"- serious, formal, old-fash- ioned, a little pompous, but very pleasant. Frame the Elegy and hang it up in your sanctum, and you will have a picture ever'before you of the place where I remain Yours tranquilly,    C. B. P S. I forgot to ask you, apropos of our art dis- cussion, whether you know Matthew Arnold's "Cul- ture and Anarchy Essays." We are reading them aloud; and the Faulkner ladies demur so much, and are so sincerely pitiful of Dr. Thomas in heaven for the degeneracy of his son, that politeness alone 3*  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7505-00000032"/> 58       LOVE IN THE would lead me to repress any thing like girlish rap- ture. Nor does the book itself encourage one to be rapturous, but rather serene; yet watchful and recep- tive. The spirit in which this man writes is com- fortable to my very soul. He gives little enough in the way of positive instruction, but exemplifies brightly the temper to which truth is revealed. The book seems to me somehow provisional and tenta- tive, and reminds me, oddly enough, of the "first bell " which used to ring in the country on summer mornings, an hour before the summons to morning- service. As for the French, you know my sentiments about them. [Trhen in a slightly altered hand, as though written later yet, and under the access of some fresh emotion, was added:] Or, rather, I don't think you can know how very much I am in earnest in my French sympathies, or how positively hurt I am by the hard, Prussianizing tone of the press - and you. I read just now, in a volume of George Sand, about some calamity that fell "like a cozp d'tat upon a nation tired of anarchy;" and I thought to myself, "The key to all the late misfortunes of France is in these words." Her best spirits were "tired of anar- chy," and accepted, for the sake of rest, the despotism which has palsied the energies of their nation, and prepared the way for her unparalleled humiliation. This was their sin, and the whole of it. At least, I   NINVETEENTH CENTURY.      59 think it is among the more venial of political errors, and that it has been expiated. How can you fail to see that, amid the twofold prostration attendant upon war without-and disorganization within, France is making a desperate--oh, I hope not vain!-- effort to collect and control herself? Hor can you or any American withhold from that effort his warmest sympathy? And when aged patriots like Victor Hugo'a few days back, and the author I have just quoted,--generous dreamers who seem so- near the tragedy of a final disappointment, resolute suf- ferers for freedom's sake, whose faith in the future personal calamity has never extinguished,-when these lift up in behalf of their devoted country the voices which were once so eloquent, and whose very tremor now reminds us that they must soon be hushed for ever, it might at least be as well to listen in respectful silence. The complacent Philistinism which would drown these high, unsteady tones in a shout for the winning party, or an officious justification of, the ways of Providence, is not among the noblest manifestations of human nature.  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7505-00000033"/> 60      LOVE IN THE  I V-I. JULIUS lifted his eyebrows and shrugged his lordly shoulders at the unexpected ve. hemence of this appeal. "' Sentiments!'" he repeated with some scorn. "'Sympa- thies!' I am glad she don't dignify them by any other name, and when I write I shall tell her so! No, I will not," he pres- ently repented, "seeing that she really cares so much. But why should this be, I wonder?  Can she have   a lover in France? Or is it that, for all her quiet, reasonable manners, she has really intense feelings, which are so repressed in her present nun-like life that they force their way into remote and \unnatural channels? If that is the case, I think we want those fine emotions for home consumption. At   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       6  all events, I 'll say no more about the war at present."  And on the next Sunday, his first day and hour of leisure, he wrote:- "' Peace in her churchyard, wheresoe'er It be, a holy place.' I quote these lines from memory out of Dante Ros- setti's poems, much praised of late by our literary exquisites. There certainly is a prejudice against premature interment; but, if you like it, all right! "I read ' Culture and Anarchy' once, and it did not make a very deep impression on fie. I believe I thought it well-written and ill-arranged, dainty and ineffective. I am pretty much in the dark about the 'temper to which truth is revealed,' but I never imagined it to be either fastidious or desperate, and the- book in which you revel is both, I believe. But I like your simile of the church-bell. It suits the confessedly funereal character Of your surroundings. What can you care about either culture- or anarchy? Are they not one to you, where yoou are, like far and near,' absent and present, shame and fame to Brahma? "I send you by this mail Rossetti, of whom I spoke, and who seems to me weird enoughto suit even your inanimate or, rather, exanimzate state. Not that I have read the poems. I have only turned them  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7505-00000034"/> 62       LOVE IN THE over hastily, and I mention it because you seemed in your last to imply that one ought to have some special competency or preparation before pronouncing any kind of an opinion. If you think so, you can read and tell me. I really wish you would, though. I was foolish enough to take this book, along with half a dozen others, off the hands of poorHender- son, our ordinary reviewer. He has a wife and child sick out in the country, - the wife is declining, I 'm afraid, -and he must needs be away a good deal,-and has fallen behindhand in his book notices. But, if events crowd at this rate, the things will be out of print before I can attend to them. So if you will give me your notions about Dante Rossetti, I will'pay you the compliment of printing them either as my own or Henderson's, according as they please me more or less. Only take heed that your estimate be not too careful and learned, and that you speak with an air of assurance. A balance of opinion, let me tell you, is far too expensive a luxury for me at present. I cannot look forward to that for twenty years at least. "Speaking of my poverty, I am reminded of your questions. Pretty well put, I thought; although I suppose you know that each involves an assumption. In reply to the first,--'What place is art to have in that more satisfactory human life which we are all trying to realize? '- I might reply, ' Are we though?'   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       63 And when asked how art is to be brought within reach of the many, I should suggest that perhaps it is not so to be. "But, seriously, it is true, as you say, that thug subject of culture, aesthetic and other, is just now engaging a good deal of attention among those who / have leisure for thinking, and that very select few have decided among themselves that higher and broader- culture is the one thing needful to make mankind better and happier. But our favored phil- osophers overlook, as usual, some practical details. 'That 's good talk for Mr. Tupper, Clinging fast to Fortune's crupper, While he takes a stirrup-cup or Two: it's famous talk for him! But if he 'd but leave his dinner, ' And become a pauper sinner, He 'd know something of the inner Life, that now is rather dim.' If I and my compeers, for example, labor for any thing so grand as the improvement of the race, or even of ourselves, it must be indirectly. What we want and work for primarily is money. And is not money the indispensable basis of all culture? Reside six months in any city, even in intellectual and Puritan- ical Trimountain, and then tell me what substantial advantages of art, science, society, -or agreeable surroundings can be enjoyed without it. You your-  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7505-00000035"/> "      , LOVE IN THE self had to retire to a country graveyard because you could not dress appropriately here. One must be rich, therefore, before he can be cultivated or elegant; even, tftake it,'an elegant Jeremiah.' And so we come to your second question; and I say that if the many are ever rich, then the many miay some time appreciate and enjoy art. But history and political economy teach us that the many never will be rich. And so I have no strong hope of their salvation by aesthetics. I know some enthusiastic people think differently;. and along with, or rather underneath, all the nonsense and affectation I was deploring in my last, very earnest and generous efforts are just now -being made in our own city toward the furnishing a certain amount of art instruc- tion gratuitously to all. The ear, the voice, and by- and-by the eye of our populace, are to be trained' as well as we can train them. And you hear the singing of our public school-children, and say to yourself, with a glow of satisfaction, that much has already been done. But, when the pleasant tingling of your nerves is over, you inquire--or I do- what good will come of their refined appreciation and developed skill to the majority of those before you. It is only such as are destined by rare good fortune to rise out of the subordinate social sphere to which they belong who will profit by having once learned the spells of Handel or of Raphael. To   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       65 the rest such knowledge will serve only to make an additional discord with circumstances, until, under the coarsening and stupefying power of the latter, it finally fades away. "Methinks I grow solemn and rhetorical, The truth is--for somehow you always provoke one to candor in the end--I am smarting a little under that peculiar sense of injury which a just accusa- tion is apt to arouse. I fancy that I realize about as keenly as yourself, Miss B., that I deliver a good many crude and hasty opinions. Your friend Mat- thew Arnold, quoting some French friend of his own, talks aboutjugem'ents sazgrenus. I never recall, the expression without a certain grim satisfaction. It gives - excuse me - such a devilish good description of some of my own dicta. Yes, I do at times talk authoritatively about things which I have not suffi- ciently considered, and so do all the rest of my guild hereabouts,-- Bonney who does the picture-galleries, Malvern the musical censor, Bonney's eye-glasses are rose-color, Malvern's blue. I heard a pretty bon-not about Malvern the other day. Somebody asked where he sat at a certain concert, and the answer was, "Where he usually does, -on the performers." There it is, you see. Our judgments, in one way or another, are predetermined. We are not impar- tial, discriminating, ideal critics, equally apportion- ing praise and blame. But I, at least, know where I  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7505-00000036"/> O6       LOYVE IN THE fail, and regret the apparent necessity. For what I would impress upon you is, that this which looks like impudence is more my misfortune than my fault. The public, which I serve for bread and butter, demands, before evenr thing else, a parti pris. It has an insatiate, and, on the whole, rather healthful curiosity, but no leisure even to do its own guessing. It therefore hires some of us fellows to make guesses for it. I don't mean that it hires us to make given guesses. We are bot quite base enough for that: neither, to be just, is the public; but we are ex- pected to guess something on every new conundrum. And if we do not work briskly, and fill its orders as fast as they come in, the public will transfer our bread and butter to others. And so we acquire the habit of relying much upon our native wit, so called, and taking instant aim at every fresh phenomenon. And, undoubtedly, constant practice gives us a sort of dexterity, not to say precision, and we make a good many hits. Where we have no prepossessions, we are rather apt, I take it, to guess right the first time. You really must excuse me  if I adduce the European war as an example. I was absent, as you know, when that astounding call for a division came;  so what you used to call my 'innate Teutonism' could not tell. But before I  returned to work we had virtually espoused the cause of Prussia, and the event has-proved that we were quite right. Prussia I   'NINETEENTH CENTURY.      67 is the power of the future: France--well, I spare you. But it does seem to me that, with your appall- ing good sense, you cannot fail to see that your sentiments about the French are a matter chiefly of whim and of romance, and do credit to your sensibil- ities only. "I have made a long story and rather blunted the point of my defence, but I trust your acumen to per- ceive it. "Tis all very well for people in your cir- cumstances, or Mr. Matthew Arnold's, which I take to be similar, to weigh, to reflect, to reconsider, to pause, and to polish. But for 'us, who are actively engaged in life at a small pittance per month, the principal duty is to load and fire. "And yet---Minden! If I were the knight and you the mermaid, you would have to sing a -good while before you would lure me down there. What you denizens of the pine woods gain in 'sweetness' you lose I fdar in 'light.' I know your college- towns. I have lived in one five years as student and tutor; and if they are not the very strongholds of solemn trifling, petty pretension, and ' gentility with- out side-dishes, may I never see you again! I have wondered a great many times, and never more than after reading that apologetic little sketch in your last, how you, with your "fine democratic instinct, could endure the consecrated snobbery by which you are surrounded. I am not laughing at you. Those may  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7505-00000037"/> 68       LOVE IN THE laugh who win. I do really think you have a fine democratic instinct,--not to say a fine democratic hauteur, - and I used to marvel last summer at the effortless, nay, unconscious way, in which you frater- nized, or rather sororized with certain natives who positively offended my senses, whereas you are doubt- less a more finely organized creature than I. But now tell me, with a candor equal to my own, if in all you have read of noble and serf, Brahmin and pariah, --I had almost said sheep and goats,--you ever encountered any thing comparable to the 'great gulf fixed' between faculty and towns-people. I under- stand that you are all right at Madam Faulkner's. You sit and revolve abstract questions inside among the elect, while?take my chance with the toiling masses. How do you like this view of our relative positions? Write soon and tell me. "Yours, &amp;c.,        J. M."   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      69 VII. "MY DEAR FRIENP, - [Clara replied promptly] I obey your injunction to write soon, and even without it I should have made haste to tell you that I believe you are all wrong from beginning to end, and that I am the person who has a mission to convince you of error. Not to-day, however! The work is too vast to be done in a hurry. It can't be disposed of in the twinkling of an eye, like a mere question of the ascen- dency of nations. What I particularly write to say is that, much as I like in you the readiness to help your troubled associate, I'm afraid I can't do what you re- quest about Dante Rossetti. The book is thrilling, fascinating; the music of the poems piercingly sweet, and sure to haunt one a good while; but some of them are exceedingly distasteful to me. I could not even tell you all I think about them; and as for telling the public that, - or any thing else in fact, - the bare idea paralyzes me. I wanted also to tell you that I have reread ' Aurora Leigh,' as I said I would; and I find myself very much surprised by it. Surprised in the first place at its power. I confess that I did not think any woman had written so great a thing in  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7505-00000038"/> 70       LOVE IN THE verse. And then surprised at its ill-nature. Why, what a very unpleasant lady Aurora was! Sad, cyni- cal, horribly nervous and fretful; violent in speech; and, worse than all, coarse. I really pity poor blind, blundering Romney, whom we leave in her clutches at the last. . . . No ray of light is thrown upon the art question, - that is, the general question. Aurora's love and Aurora's art are played with, scru- tinized, balanced with consummate and splendidly imaginative egotism. The 'profound conclusion' foreshadowed in the preface appears to amount to this: that the heroine begins by scornfully rejecting love for the sake of art, and when she has tired of the latter teases for love back again. Oh, I do not like it! And do you know I think that what disturbs me most is this: I am afraid Mrs. Browning herself could not have been very happy when she wrote such a book. And I had long looked upon the marriage of the Brownings as the ideal,--the one perfect type." "It don't become me [replied Julius, in a gallop- ing scrawl, on a half sheet of official paper] to say much while the thunderbolt of your wrath is hanging over me; but I would just suggest that, if the Brown- ings were not happy, the obvious reason is precisely that they were both too knowing. One 'genius is enough in a pair. If a woman has an excess of wit, "   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       71 it ought to be balanced by a corresponding wealth of stupidity in a man, as yours might be by mine, and vice versa. Come on now with your denunciation, and let me see what havoc you can make with that last letter of mine, which, between ourselves, I thought rather clever."  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7505-00000039"/> 72       LOVE IN THE VIII. NATURALLY ignoring the theory which Julius had last propounded,--although I hold that she had brought the suggestion upon herself,- Clara replied:-- "I am ready, but I hardly know where to begin. However I will begin anywhere. In the first place, you care too much about getting money. You excuse yourself from slow and -fine work, literary and other, because you say you have your living to make. You mean you have your fortune to make, which is quite another thing. The former is essential, the latter not at all. You seem to agree with me and Matthew Arnold and Mr. Helps, and other nice and quiet folks, that culture is a very good thing,- the best of earthly things, indeed; but you find in this fact only an additional justification of your absorbing pursuit of gain. You turn upon me with what you mean to be quite an overpowering air, and inquire,' Is not wealth the necessary basis of all culture?' Mildly but em- phatically, Mr. May, I answer, No. I know what is the necessary basis of all culture. I have discovered that recently, and I will tell you by and by; but   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       73 wealth itself, - that is, any thing beyond the modest competence which even a day laborer, in our country, may usually win, - wealth, especially if self-acquiired, seems to me, in some cases, a positive obstacle to culture. I judge by what I have seen of people who have grawn rich; not vulgar souls who might be expected to rush incontinent into vulgar show, but persons like you and me, who possess already the rudiments of book-knowledge and certain refined in- stincts and preferences. Now, just so long as these people were effectually debarred from all pretence to fashion or social distinction, they had r6tom in their simple lives both for thought and charity. But how was their earliest superfluity spent, -a proper question, is it not?--since by that first-made channel so much would inevitably flow out? Why, naturally enough, perhaps, for what would soonest secure to them' the outside consideration which- they had always lacked: for material luxury; for rich carpets and fine clothes; then for carving, gilding, plate, smart equipages, and costly entertainments. You understand that, except- ing the last, I like all these -things well enough as the garniture of life, provided they can come un- sought, and so be used unconsciously. But I have a fancy that the moment we devote to their attain- ment, or preservation, time, thought, or any form of nervous energy (whereof how few of us Yankees have really too rich a store, or rightly understand 4  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7505-00000040"/> 74       LOVE IN THE the economical expenditure), we divert and dissipate forces which might have been employed for purposes of real culture. And just consider the sum of force thus wasted! Powers of observation, most minute, of other people's clothes and carriages; powers of comparison and competition anent the same; powers of endurance of heat, tedium, and carbonic acid gas; powers of organization and administration, since all these luxuries necessitate large and complex house- holds, menials to take care of them, and other menials to see that the first do not run away with them; and you may ask any competent mistress of a family among us if one of the first truths of American do- mestic life be not this,--that she who increaseth servants increaseth sorrow. It is the old story of 'the cares of this world and the deceitfulness (how apt the word!) of riches.' "It might, indeed, have been employed far other- wise, that first, most welcome superfluity; and then it would have been a blessed thing. It might have been used quietly and conscientiously, without any reference to imposing on the world, and compelling its cheap deference: for brief retirement into peace- ful, healthful places, rather than to gain a broader footing amid the crowd; for worthy books, and leisure to read them; yes, and, if you please, my friend, for leisure to reflect upon them, until the perfect crystal of a just opinion might form in an undisturbed mind, and so the gain to culture would   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       75 have been great, and always growing. Only, as I said before, I scarce ever knew a case where the first-fruits of wealth were actually so employed. Because the world would never be brought to terms in that way, and so few of us are really ready to renounce the world. "And now I -flatter myself that I have swept round imposingly to the delivery of my great truth. The necessary basis of culture is not money, but content,'- -content with outward things just as they are,- content, if it must be, with what you so plaintively call a 'subordinate social position.' Those lucky common-school children of Trimountain, whom you presume to pity, need never feel any agonizing dis- cord between their humble home surroundings, and the culture which a generous State has given them, provided they simply accept the surroundings, and do not fatigue and demean themselves by a frantic effort to make these grander. It seems exceedingly trite to say that a perception of great thoughts and great harmonies ennobles a simple no less than a showy life, but one would think you did not believe it. If the souls of Mozart and Mendelssohn are still alive and happy in blessing, and if they minister in person to poor mortals sometimes through the strains that abundantly live, - as what music-lover does not love to dream?-do you suppose they are particular about the locality of the, street, or the  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7505-00000041"/> 76       LOVE IN THE furniture of the room, in which they perform their angelic service? Oh! let us learn the grace to stand still, and receive what is given us, instead of crowd- ing and struggling after the truly boorish fashion of the day! It is this selfish and unlovely strife to get up, up, up, which leaves us no time for thought, no room for beauty, and no breath for song. 6"I have sometimes wondered, by the way, whether the reason why life in so many of our country towns is so undeniably stiff, barren, and unsocial, were not that everybody is vainly trying to show to the satis- faction of himself and others that he is first. But why first? one thinks. Why not second, or fifth, or fifteenth? What is the possible value of pre-emi- nence in such an order? You go about among such people, being connected with different ones by differ- ent ties, and you are surprised that folks who are individually so excellent, occupy so nearly the same plane, and have so much in common, should not mingle freely and pleasantly with one another. By- and-by, it appears that they are afraid, if they do, they will compromise some imaginary dignity, or belie some cherished exclusiveness, and so they grow more queer and narrow every day, until they wither quite away in their absurd isolation. I know two old ladies in Minden, whose gardens adjoin, and whose hens are mutually lawless and intrusive. The consequence is that they--the old ladies I mean,   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       " not the hens - exist in a state of chronic grievance, which their very high-flown self-respect does not often allow them to express. But now and, then, of course, human nature prevails ; and one of these good women--it may be either--says a spiteful thing. Whereupon the other makes haste to spread the, remark abroad, invariably adding, with an air of' mildest triumph, ' You know, my dear, no lady would have said that.' I always know what is coming, and I always want to laugh. 'Tis so funny a travesty of the glorious noblesse oblige principle, that I declare I am never sure whether the spirit shown is more respectable or ridiculous. "You see I don't pretend to extol country life indiscriminately. But to that phase of it which we see here in Minden there are two saving clauses which render it tolerably invulnerable by your cock- ney raillery. In the first place, the natural and confessed leaders of society here (no smiling!) the men and women who, by right of their accom-1 plishments, deserve and hold the highest place - arde a tolerably numerous class. There are eight or ten- families which are obviously on exactly the same- footing; and, what is better, they are all poor. In a place where the average income of the influential men is eighteen hundred dollars a year, there can't be any sinful luxury, and those who aim at distinction must depend upon intrinsic merits. And they do.  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7505-00000042"/> 78       LOVE IN THE Nor is it much matter that the struggle is made, as you intimate, a hard one, or that the rule of our oli- garchy is a little arbitrary and austere, and encum- bered by a certain quaint parade. It is a wise rule, on the whole. And here, in the pine woods, there has actually been fulfilled, after a fashion, the ideal of that dear old aristocrat, Count Joseph de Maistre: 'The chief use of an aristocracy is to secure the presence in a state of something more precious than gold.' "I dare say you are wondering at me for being so vehement. I do very seriously believe what I have been trying, incoherently perhaps, to express; and my belief is involved in the lesson of my whole early life, which I seem never fully to have learned until lately. But you know the sense of exhilaration which comes when we first feel that a task or prob- lem is thoroughly mastered and possessed. It is something like that which excites me at present. And I think I will tell you a little story about those same early years of mine, which I hold too sacred to be often or lightly quoted. You told me that you had met in. society my cousin, Adelaide Mann. 'A handsome, haggard old girl,' you called her, and I remember I did not at all like the speech at the time, but could not help thinking afterward-how accurately, if rudely, it described her.- Cousin Adelaide is, in fact, just four years older than I am,   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       79 and it seems to me that a creature gifted in mind and person as she was ought not to be worn out at twenty-eight. It seems so to her also, as you will see. "We were born and grew up in the same country town. We had each a brother and sister older than ourselves. Hers have lived and married, and achieved worldly success. Mine, as you know, are both gone to that possible new home where I shall be once more the latest comer. In the old times we were all poor enough, -poor and proud, the invidi- ous used to say; and I cannot deny that we chafed somewhat under our privations,-Ada and I in particular, for I was a tall, precocious little girl, and proud to be her chosen mate and confidante, - how we did deplore and deride our seedy gowns, and shabby surroundings, and scant advantages! How we did long to be rich, and plan what we would do, and how we would dress when the golden day arrived! Such extraordinary costumes! Such stately banquets and oriental luxury! We have laughed over our day-dreams many a time in later years, but then we fully believed in our opulent future. It could not be, we considered, that our singular fitness for the possession and disbursement of riches had been bestowed for nought. Secure in this faith, we were not unhappy in the, present. Ah me! I am at least glad of that. For we had always  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7505-00000043"/> so       LOVE IN THE in our meagre homes--I especially, and in those years of struggle our families had all things in com- mon-- a true intellectual life. New gowns were rare with us, and new carpets rarer; but, somehow or other, new books never failed. Oh the long winter evenings, when I had won the coveted per- mission to sit up till the elders went to bed, and when we gathered closely round our careful fire, while father read aloud to us in his mellow, measured tones! Sometimes it was fiction, sometimes history, often poetry: whatever it was, we lived in it, losing all memory of the anxious present, save as it added greater zest to our pleasure in the large, ideal life. How bright the comments used to be while the blessed spell of the reading was yet upon us,--my father's dry humor, my mother's irresistible satire, and the many-hued enthusiasm of us younger folks! How gayly we separated, running up through the, cold halls, into the barren chambers, as though we trod on air. So we grew fast in the friendly shade of our poor fortunes, and I think our natures kept a tenderness not too common in these days of flaunt- ing open-air life. When I was thirteen,- the year I saw you first, - and cousin Ada seventeen, - and how pretty! - her path and mine suddenly diverged. Uncle's affairs mended. He saw a prospect. of wealth to be gained, and moved away to the city. It seemed to me then as if they had entered Paradise,   NINETEENTH CENTURY      .  8 while I was shut out. I was sadly envious of Ada for the next few years; and she, it must be owned, rather towering towards me. The difference in our ages told then. She had blossomed all at once into a brilliant young lady, and I made her two or three visits in her new home, and returned rather dejected. And then to ourselves also there came a change,- new embarrassments, gathering clouds. My brother, who had entered college,- -how great an effort we had all made for that!- fell ill, dear boy, and came home in slowly-failing health. We were shut up to our few selves, of stern necessity now. Our needs, our wounds, were too many to have been half-hidden else. But the old life of thought was left, and we were at ease in it. The written Word -not in the one Bible only, but in many books of many lands - stood always between us and despair or defeat; and if I were a mystic, I should add, 'that Word was- God.' Our reading grew graver in those days. We had higher thoughts and clearer insight as Death for the first, time drew softly near our home. I cannot dwell upon that period. We grew familiar with Death's face,--I, the little one, most so of all. Thank Heaven, it is least fearful when best known. On my nineteenth birthday I was- alone, and, with my tiny fortune so full of pathetic associations, free. My uncle and aunt were very kind, and wanted me, as I once told you, to come directly to them. Cousin 4.'  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7505-00000044"/> 82       LOVE IN THE Ada wanted it too. She was just from abroad, not very happy, and beginning to tire a'little of her con- spicuous and seemingly triumphant career. I went to them for two years, and studied music assiduously. Some part of music had come by nature to us all: and there, again, sorrow and simplicity of life had helped to keep the home taste pure, and my few previous lessons had done me no harm. But, when that time was over, I chose the life I am leading now. Uncle and aunt were almost angry; Ada, for the time being, quite so. But they have forgiven me, and I am glad to go to them for a little time each winter. "Last year when I was there, my prophetic soul telling me nothing at all about you hard by in the office of the ' Solar System,' Ada had an illness, and I helped nurse her. She was not altogether a patient invalid; and one day, when I had been trying in vain to find something acceptable to read to her, she turned suddenly upon me in her peculiarly imperious fashion: ' Put all those books away,' she said,' I have no desire to make a martyr of you, and the truth is that I am no longer up to the level of reading which you enjoy.' I begged her not to be sarcastical; but she silenced me, as she always could, and went on, extravagantly indeed, but you who have only heard her talk society talk would never dream how pas- sionate and eloquent she can be. She cried out that   NINVETEENTH CENTURY.      83 she was degenerate in body, mind, and moral sense, and I knew it; shattered in nerves, spoiled in tem- per, broken in spirit, fit only for trivial pleasures and apathetic rest. It seemed to her less- so she said, poor dear! -that she had succumbed willingly to the tyranny of fashion and certain moral dangers of wealth, than that these were monsters who had seized her while she was young and ignorant, and compelled her to yield them the bloom of her beauty and the freshness of her powers, and then left her a wreck before youth was fairly over. 'For we had none of us too much vitality,' she said, 'but you grow more vigorous every year; while I,'- and she spread out her little bird-like fingers with all their diamonds, mockingly. 'Some people would say,' she went on, 'that I am   unhappy and disappointed because I have not married. Bah! I scorn to say that I have had opportunities. I don't remember ever to have had the opportunity to marry a genuine man, and I could not quite bring myself to marry a house like Maria' (her sister.) She has had her request, and you and I will be polite and not dwell upon the immense qualification. 'Ah, Clara,' she said, and this was the part of her tirade that moved me most, 'I always loved you in my way, although I used to lord it over you long ago; but just now I feel humble:. When you and I were first parted, almost eleven years since, I pitied you and you envied me. * I* v   &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7505-00000045"/> 84       LOVE IN THE But it was a kind fate that held you back, and shut you in until you were too old to be dazzled by vain show, and your soul had grown sufficiently to choose the good and refuse the evil. And it was almost a cruel fate which thrust me out into a world which flattered all my vainer instincts. I tell you fairly the growth of my soul stopped then and there. Whenever an appeal is made to me which presup- poses any thing of mental or spiritual experience, I have to refer back to my previous life. If I had been, born rich, no doubt it would have been different; but sudden wealth overpowered me. I hope you realize the difference, and are thankful. "I asked her-why she did not go away now into some remote place, and live simply for a while and rest,-- I felt sure it was all she needed,--but she interrupted me. 'Because I am perfectly wedded to luxury. I am so weak that to miss the least one of the foolish refinements to which I have used myself causes me unspeakable discomfort and irritation. And this,'I suppose, is the very seal of my intellectual dissolution.' Which was so obvious an anticlimax, that we both laughed, and I hoped the outhreak had done her good. But there had been a grain of truth in her wild talk. I did realize a difference in our destinies, and I was grateful. "What a scandalously long letter! One, - two, - three,--I dare not countathe sheets. Don't tell any one. Don't read it if you are hurried. C. B."   NINETEENTH CENTURY.     '  85 ^ TK. ON the next morning but one Clara re- ceived this: TRIMOUNTAIN, October, 1870.. .. I have just finished the last page of your letter, and I kind o' feel as- though I was under con- viction. Almost thou persuadest meto live in the back streets, and sit in the back seats, and wear an old hat, and all that. But the natural man rebels. And if the natural woman does not, the question arises, Is she a natural woman? But, if she were an unnatural one, should I admire and desire her. And that I do, - ergo - Thunder! It 's one o'clock! and plenty of work yet to do. I think you are a little mean about Dante Rossetti, but all the same you are an uncommon girl, and I am a miserable sinner.                J. M. But Clara, who had been so very unre- served and at such uncommon length in. her last letter, was visited, the moment the mail had swallowed that effusion, by one of those attacks of wholly dispropor- .  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7505-00000046"/> 86       LOVE IN THE tioned and insensate compunction to which some women are liable when they have done the least possible wrong. She had awaited the reply of Julius with an anxiety for which she scorned herself, and hardly heeded its contents in her horror at its brevity.  If he had been laconic, what was she when she wrote? MNDEN, October, I870. MY DEAR MR. MAY,--I see my mistake in at- tempting to convert you to any " views " of my own. Life must teach you, as it is, I hope, teaching me. Meanwhile I have encroached unduly upon your crowded time, and perhaps betrayed more than I ought of the secrets of other lives than mine. I rely upon your honor, and remain Yours very truly,  C. B. And I think it really creditable, at least to the intelligence of Julius, that he should merely have read this missive attentively twice, and then laid it carefully aside, without so much as whistling Donna e mobile, replying the next Sunday as fol- lows:   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       87 X.  . . "You are fast finding out, you see, what a shallow and irreverent mortal you have honored with your - shall I say friendship, or only acquaint- ance? What will become of me, I wonder, when you have nothing more to discover in this direction? But no matter: I don't propose to be a coward. "And now for a serious consideration of your last letter; for that resentful and reactionary little note of Thursday don't count, does it? "I know you paid me a great: compliment by telling me about your early life, and I hope I don't need to assure you that your confidence is sacred. As for your cousin, Miss Mann, she is only one of a class to me, - fashionable women and girls, between whom and me there is a gulf fixed, of which I at least am always conscious: who cut me dead half the times we encounter, and I dare say honestly forget me, for that matter; while the other half they are fluent and cordial. I don't mind them. "But your letter I thougi very- fine, I was going to say, onlljyhat wordiackneyed and what you call 'professional.' I thought it very high-  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7505-00000047"/> 88       LO VE IN THE minded and tender. Pardon me for saying, however, that I did not think it altogether practical. Your idea, if I understand it, is this : Those who have a competence must not struggle to be rich. Those who have a support must not even struggle for a competence. They must be content to be poor and unknown, and then they. will have time and strength to cultivate themselves highly; and by voluntarily foregoing luxury they will be sure to escape its demoralizing influence. Now this sounds a good deal like Epictetus; but can't you see that it is not a doctrine likely to prevail in the world? And I don't know that it would be well to have it prevail. In the first place, it is an intensely aristocratic doc- trine. All your simplicity and self-denial are to the end that you may attain a more lofty and difficult development. The retiring folks who rely for dis- tinction on purely personal superiority are ten times more inaccessible and intolerant than those who frankly surround themselves with outward splendor and show, and depend on these to impress their fellow-men. You concede as much in your account of Minden society, and there could not be a more striking exemplification of what I say than your patron saint, Matthew. He has arrived at that climax where high and low disgust him alike; and his famous classification of his countrymen into ' barbarians,' 'Philistines,' and 'populace,' I consider the most   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       89 supercilious effort of the "human mind, so far. Nor have you said a word to disprove my assertion that wealth must be among the antecedents of culture. If you and your author don't immediately depend upon it, 'tis because you are a step beyond culture, a trifle more than cultivated,-- that is all. This, I take it, is the usual order in human society: first industry, then wealth, then luxury, then refinement, then languor and satiety, then reaction. And by the time reaction comes, whether to States, families, or individuals, wealth is pretty sure to be exhausted and vitality at a low ebb. Then comes a revolution, an infusion of new blood, and the same circle is traversed once more. But let nobody despise the wealth; for its power of amelioration and cheer, if ( transient, is very great. "Do you say that you limited your strictures to those who toil and struggle to get rich, and made an exception in favor of those who inherit their wealth? Well, now, I hope you 'll allow me to say that I thought that as pretty a piece of feminine logic as ever I encountered. How, pray, is any one to in- herit wealth if some one does not first accumulate it? I may resign myself to poverty with lofty equanimity, but have I any right to resign my chil- dren? I rather admire the self-devotion of that great body of mercantile men, merchant princes and merchant commoners, who grind away in their offices /  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7505-00000048"/> go90      LOVE IN THE until apoplexy overtakes them; never pausing to enjoy the fruit of their labor, but heaping it up for those who are to come after them. At least their absorption in affairs has its heroic side. And money, I repeat, is a very convenient thing. There is nothing else in this world quite so reasonable as luxury. It means pure air and delicate food, and swift and silent service at table, which leaves one able to listen and free to talk and safe to sparkle. It means having our friends about us when we need them, and the ability to fly from them to the ends of the earth when we need that, as we often do. It means that when we come out of theatre or concert, -or fashionable church even, 'sad from the breath of that diviner mood, that loftier air,' (?) into the decidedly nether air of the Trimountain streets, we are not to risk our precious and significant lives by breasting the bitter north wind and allowing it to buffet our exhausted lungs, but rather step into a cushioned carriage and roll softly and safely away. And if that carriage is one's own, and so one is tolerably sure that no infection is lurking in its broadcloth, how much better still! Again, there is the luxury of giving. How can you, a creature all benevolence, - whereof I am a signal monument, - overlook that? I They had room in their simple lives,' you say, in the course of that enchanting aind preposterous reverie of yours, 'both for thought and   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       91 charity.' Ay, room! but how about the means? How is one to give unless one has a superfluity? If charity, as one sees it here, be not 'twice blest,' it is the recipients only whose profit is doubtful. What they who organize and disburse charity among us would do without their committees and sub-com- mittees, their cheerful and discursive debates, their morning meetings, their afternoon lectures, and, above all, their fairs, - the week-long junketing, the delightful flutter, and the general pecuniary lawless- ness of their fairs,- -I have never been able to imagine. The fate of the poor themselves, whom we are at least assured we shall always have with us, furnishes a much less perplexing problem. "And now that I have, according to the happy tradition of our intercourse, found all the fault pos- sible with your graceful plea for poverty, I am fain to concede that I fancy your letter may, after all, contain the germ of a great truth. If history and political economy mean any thing at all, - and, since neither is yet a science, they may not mean very much, - but if any thing,- then luxury has its very real dangers, and the point at which it becomes con- spicuous and pervading is apt to be a critical one- in the history of a State. It is possible, then, that a cultivated indifference may be the best substitute for the natural indifference of a primitive time; just as octors now-a-days are so fond of prescribing in  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7505-00000049"/> 92       LOVE IN THE chronic ailments a return to'something like the milk- diet of infancy. "Well, good-by- but stay!- I am very glad that you do not like Dante Rossetti any better. If I had known exactly what the book was I should not have sent it to you. And I am glad you do not want to write for the press. Have I not just read in an, exchange a column of 'personal' paragraphs about the unhappy women who do, which transcends, in familiar impudence, in literary vulgarity, and in gen- eral atrocity and inanity, any thing which I ever saw before even in a newspaper? I should think it enough to make these poor creatures curse the day they ever put pen to paper, or whatever it is women do when men curse. It may be bread-and-buttery to talk now-a-days about the I sphere of home,' but I should say a woman, rather than be scrutinized and reported in this way, would be glad to hide anywhere from the piercing eyes of the paragraph-maker. ':I hope you understand that you may trust me implicitly, and continue to express yourself with per- fect freedom. For if ever I find it expedient to repeat any of your observations and opinions, I will, as I hinted in a former letter, adopt them. "Yours, &amp;c.,         J. M."   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      93 XI. CLARA laughed a little at the irrepressible sauciness of the concluding paragraph; -but, on the whole, her reception of this letter was rather grave.  The truth is, there had dawned upon her for the first time, while she perused it, a doubt, not wholly welcome, whether she were still perfect mistress of the situation.   For my own part, I hardly see why this should have been. I consider the letter a little pompous, and just a little prosy. How- beit, the lady resolved to put less than ever of her own personality into her reply, and this is the way she kept her resolu- tion:  MNDEN, October, 1870 o. .. I don't see how you make it out that mine is an "aristocratic doctrine." I am willing to have less that all mar have more. That seems to me a  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7505-00000050"/> "       LOVE IN THE true democratic spirit. You mean to have just what you fancy, and others must fare as they can. You betray, by the way,- how little you have kept a car- riage. Don't you know that one's own horses and coachman can never be out late? This is just one of the places where wealth is hampered and poverty free. Then as to your slighting reflections on or- ganized charity: can a man be competent tomake such, who can ask with all your naivete how one can give if one has not a superfluity. Why, what is the merit of giving if one has? Do you remember about the widow's mite? I 'm afraid not. I 'm afraid you know far too little about the widow. It is perhaps the very giving out of immense superfluity which lends to your metropolitan charities the amateur and rather flighty character which lays them open to your raillery. And yet how much good they do, how much misery they relieve, and how innocent, comparatively, are the pastimes which the lighter- minded philanthropists associate with their work! I believe, however, that when I first spoke of charity, I did not mean mere alms-giving, but that personal consideration and care and generous regard for other people, of which the Miss Faulkners exer- cise so much, while having, I believe, for their private expenses, something like a hundred dollars a year apiece. I suppose there must be more of this kind of charity in small and simple communities than in   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      95 great ones. But all kinds of charity are good, are Christ-like, are they not? So why should we quarrel? It must be that we think very much alike; that if wealth were offered, we would either of us be willing to accept its responsibilities, but that we can see some positive advantages also in moderate means, and at, least no insuperable bar to making the utmost of our- selves. ... This letter ended rather abruptly, and just as Julius was about to answer it he was unexpectedly summoned to a distant city to make report of the doings of some convention  there.  Having  no time to lose, he hesitated just two minutes as to whether or not be should telegraph his abrupt departure to Clara, and then de- cided--delicately, as I think, whether astutely or not - that the footing on which their acquaintance then stood hardly jus- tified a telegram. So he merely wrote a hurried line aftersarriving at his destina- tion, and to this he received no answer  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7505-00000051"/> whatever for the unprecedented space of nearly three weeks. Many and varied were ,the doubts and conjectures that      I assailed his mind during this interval. He did not, as Clara would have done in like case, leap instantly to the conclusion that some evil had befallen his correspond- 'ent. He did not, like an inconsiderate youth, rashy accuse the postal service of his country. He knew -only too well pre- cisely how many millions of chances there are against the miscarriage of a letter. He persisted therefore, like a faithful son of his age, in attempting to reason upon facts in the absence of the same; and the effort proved so irritating that an un- wonted acerbity was observed in some of his articles, and for the first time in his life he had a libel suit presented to him as an alternative. Before he was actually  arraigned however, his manners were im- proved by the receipt of the following 'letter:- - 1   MINDEN, November, I870. ... I have been ill and had almost a fever. [Clara checked herself before adding, "this is why I have not written," for she thought, if after all he has not cared for my silence very much, it will be safer not.] I took cold, I suppose, in the underground vestry of our old church, where I was working with the Miss Faulkners in preparation for the inevitable annual fair. It would not have been a " week-long junketing " in any case, but only an affair of two evenings,--so mouse-like are we beside the dimensions of Trimoun- tain. I, however, fell ingloriously sick, or ever our "sad pleasure" began, and lost the opportunity of cultivating my practical talents in the capacity of a saleswoman. But I had compensation in the daily society of my precious old Dr. Bemis. Did I never tell you about him? A      man of wit and wisdom  and rich experience in the past, who came  to Minden some ten years ago, and likes it as well as I do. He says it is just the place 'for philosophers like us--him- self and me, he means!- to grow old in.  He  pro- fesses to like me very much, and indeed he seems to; and when I    tell you that he is a  French sympathizer, both ardent and intelligent, you will believe that I like him. The latest news, however, makes him very sad. 5  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7505-00000052"/> 98        LO VE IN THE He came yesterday while the others were at church. It was a superb morning, but all the brilliancy of it could not dispel his dejection. I bade him note how, as the flower-beds blacken, and the gayer trees grow leafless, rich sombre chords of color are developed in the oak-grove, and the air becomes as the " river of the water of life, clear as crystal." "Ah, yes!" he replied, for with him all roads lead straight to the beleaguered city of his soul, " it- was Mme. de Sevigne who first called the autumnal days crystalline. And do you know that there are but two people on earth who fully appreciate and ade- quately love the autumn, and these are the American and the Frenchman. The English know no such season. Out of summer they pass directly into mist and darkness, but the shrewdest Yankee becomes a poet in the rare 'fall' weather, and the love of it sings through all the sweetest places of French liter- ature like the wind of this bright day." And then he began humming fragments of a breezy little rondeau: "Doux vents d'automne, attiedissez l'amie! Vaste foret, ouvre lui tes rameaux! Sous les grands bois la douleur endormie, En y revant souvent calmne ses maux. La chasse court, le cerf fuit, le cor sonne, Pour prolonger ce que l'ombre pardonne, Vous menagiez le feuillage aux berceaux, Doux vents d'automne! *    *  *  * *   NINETEENTH   CENTURY.      99 O, ma BeautY, n'y soupirez-vous pas? Coeur indompt6, Pair des bois l'aiguillonne, "odeur des pins l'enivre. Ah, c'est assez! Quand la foret la va faire amazone, Soufflez sur elle, et me l'attiddissez, -Doux vents d'automne!" "That forest was Fontainebleau," sighed the doc- tor, " but who knows how long the Goth and the Van- dal will spare it." And then he fell into reminiscences of his happy life in Paris as a medical student of mature mind and genuine enthusiasm.  They had told him in England that he would find the acknowledged kings of physiological and medical science, the great French specialists, mere intellectual machines, eager to in- crease their knowledge at any cost of animal anguish, dealing with cases only, not with patients, careless of the sacred humanities of their profession. "And I found," he went on, kindling, " that insular dulness and self-complacency had never compassed a more stupid misconception! The humanity of these great French savans is of a somewhat too refined and tender type for John Bull to appreciate. Voild tout/ I came by 'God's grace to know some of them well, and I found that their untiring researches into the mysteries of human life and suffering had made them, almost to a man, humble, delicate, infinitely merciful. The  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7505-00000053"/> 100       LOVE IN THE claims on their thought and attention of the sufferer, or the learner, especially if a stranger, I never once saw slighted, or otherwise than most reverently and carefully considered. "I have seer Velpeau in his class, Velpeau, that intellectual giant; a mechanic until he was twenty, but rising thereafter to the highest pitch of scientific eminence, the author of works which a century of progress will not supersede; one of the very few who have been equally great in experiment and in theory. A 'plain, blunt man,' but his pupils adored him. I have seen him come upon them when convulsed with laughter over a caricature of his own quaint person, seize the paper, applaud the resemblance, join in the mirth with the utmost zest, and gayly criticise the drawing; then turning to his class again he identified the culprit at a glance, and grasped him by the ear. 'And it was you, you dog, who did it! I know your hand!' I have seen the same man accosted when on his hospital rounds by another, great in place and power, who began pompously to congratulate him on the success of a difficult operation just performed on a member of his own family. And the man of science waved the man of station aside silently, but not discourteously, and continued his own exposition. Wist not the dignitary that this worker must be about his Master's business? Ah, that was a man! "How well I remember," he continued, c" going one   NINETEENTH CENTURY.       IOI Sunday morning-an autumn day like this-with a friend to one of the principal hospitals. It was the vacation term at the Medical School, and there were but few students or visitors about. As we passed into the hall, we heard groans, evidently of -a child in great pain. The door leading to the sick- ward was ajar, and as we approached we heard the voice of a man talking earnestly with the little suf- ferer. There was something very affecting in the imploring tones of the child's voice and the tender and sympathizing replies of the physician, and it seemed to us no breach of etiquette to witness un- seen through the crack of the half-open door the scene that was passing within.  Oh a narrow pallet near the window lay a fine boy, nine or ten years old, dying of cancer developing itself between the eyes and behind the nose. It had not yet shown itself externally, but had destroyed the sight, and was attended by excruciating suffering. By his side sat a stately, white-haired man, holding with one hand the two of the little patient, while with the other he caressingly smoothed his hair. The child told the story of his pain, 'Ah, je soufre tant/' to which the old man listened patiently, promising to devise some relief. Then he rose to go, but first bent over the boy, and  with tears dropping from his eyes kissed his forehead lovingly as a mother. The white-haired man was the world-renowned Nelaton,  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7505-00000054"/> 102      LOVE IN THE -Nelaton, lately summoned to attend the fallen Emperor. "Another reminiscence of another Sunday morning in Paris. I saw brought in to the hospital a young working girl, whose leg had been crushed by a heavily loaded omnibus, and so badly as to require instant amputation. The surgeon on duty was the famous M. Richard. We were asked to assist that time. I gave the anaesthetic, and I remember he charged me to keep the 'poor child,' as he called her, unconscious not only during the operation, but until every trace of it had been removed. He intercepted a blunder- ing attendant who would have brought the tray of instruments within sight before she slept; and any thing equal to his patient soothing of her pain and terror, the delicate care which banished all that was unnecessarily agitating from the scene, the deliberate and exquisite pity which softened his every look and movement, I hardly hope to see again. That also was a man. "And if you come to types of manhood," continued the doctor, by this time with moistening eyes, " where, save in this same tempest-tossed and beaten France, will you look for the finest, at least in our day? Sim- ple, loyal servants of Science, of Art, --nay, and of Faith also, some of them,- they preserve even in their warfare an urbanity which the rest of us never attain. I marvel at the ingratitude, even of this shabby world, &amp;   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      I03 which, having enjoyed their fair example, now, in their hour of national distress and humiliation, speaks up on the side of the 'big battalions,' instead of pon- dering in silence on the strange truth that whom He loveth He chasteneth. 'France expiates,' they say, 'her social crimes and political blunders.' May be! Al nations have such to answer for; yet where are we to look for the fruit of human institutions if not in human character? And why s  luld I speak of De Tocqueville and De Broglie, of Lacordaire and Mon- talembert, dead only last winter, the brightest, sweet- est spirit of them all,--men who lived in the life of their country, and bore her sins and sorrows on their hearts, like veritable high priests?" The dear soul's love and grief are both so unpopu- lar just now that I could not, if I would, have re- sponded save'with words of sympathy and foolish cheer, --pleading that never, except by miracle, are nations either born or slain in a cay; that the tide must some time turn and the cloud lift, the Graces seek their chosfn home again, the boulevards shine, and the pulse 6f intellectual and spiritual life throb all the more strongly for its temporary suspension. "No doubt! no doubt!" he sighed, "'The old order changeth, giving place to new, And God fulfils himself in many ways,' but all the same the present disgrace of France is  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7505-00000055"/> 104       LOVE IN THE unspeakably bitter to me, and I am glad that Monta- lembert is in heaven." I have given you my dear old friend's lament as nearly as possible in his own ardent words. You, with your devotion -to evidence, ought at least to care for the personal testimony it contains. Meditate on these things, man ami, and adieu.   C. B.   NINETEENTH - CENTURY.      105 1 XII. THE reply of Julius was very prompt, and thus it ran:  . . " It was a pretty story you told me in your last, and Dr. Bemis must be a jolly old sentimen- talist. I wonder no more at your Gallic proclivities. I might go farther, and say that a lady's political views are very apt to have a personal basis. But I won't. I 'm only glad he is an old doctor. How old, by the way? "And why have a doctor? Why risk your life in an infernal vestry? You snubbed me a while ago for certain mild reflections on the charities of women; but are not you yourself a proof of something intemperate and ill-considered about them? Don't go to vestries any more. The life of one wise, gracious, tender woman is worth more than the financial prosperity of many little churches. What do-I say? I am not sure but that it is worth the Church Universal in her present asphyxiated condi- tion. You won't like this remark very well, and I don't admire it myself; but I am exasperated just &amp;,    ,  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7505-00000056"/> 106      LOVE IN THE now with what calls itself the Church and with its impotence to guide or console. Let me also tell you a story. "Do you remember my mentioning Mrs. Hender- son a while ago? She is dead, and her baby is dead too. I dare say she used to go to vestries, for she was of the enthusiastic and self-devoted sort, and she died in decline; but now please hear something more about her, and about the poor fellow whom she has left in the world so stricken and bewildered that I don't know what is to be done with him, or whether he will ever come to any good again. Theirs was a juvenile attachment. I believe they went to the same academy or high school far back in the country, and admired one another in the cross-lights of the same ugly school-room, and used to pair off at walks and picnics, and he did her algebra for her, and she once wrote him a composition on Cheerful- ness,-a subject on which he found it difficult to theorize. He offered her his heart and hand, as he has often told me, on the day after their last public examination, when they were busied in removing the evergreens and other rubbish with which the cross- lighted room aforesaid had been decorated for the great occasion. And she accepted him thoughtfully, subject to the approval of her family, which does not seem to have been withheld. They adhered to this unworldly arrangement for four years, while he   NINETEENTI1 CENTURY.      107 went to college and she kept school; and at the end of that time Fate flung her a morsel of money. I don't know how much, -one of your very 'modest competences,' I presume: but, at all events, on that and a certain acknowledged cleverness of his with his pen, they determined to begin the world. They bought an old-fashioned house, ten miles out of town, -a place I would not have looked at then, - but it had a sunny aspect, and I must say that Mrs. Henderson made it very pleasant. She was one of your spirited, all-efficient little women, with a knack at chintz upholstery and rustic frames for photo- graphs. She had, besides, the mysterious gift to make things grow: so that the blackest stick which \ she set in earth put forth leaves, and the dryest seed germinated. The consequence was that her ivies ran round those old rooms like green flames, and her geraniums made the windows gay as the tropics. They kept no servant. I used to go there often, and rather despise it all, and have very good times. Henderson and I were just in our first enthusiasm for Comte, Mill, Spencer, and Darwin; and we used to sit and corroborate and congratulate one another until Mrs. Henderson would say it was very stupid in us to agree so perfectly, and that she longed to have somebody less 'advanced' at her fireside. Yet she herself was quite as adventurous in her speculations as either of us. She was very bright. A witty and  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7505-00000057"/> I 08      LOVE IN THE rather distinguished woman, old enough to have been mother to those two babes in the wood, took a great fancy to Henderson at one time, and graciously offered to call on his wife; and I never shall forget her naive amazement at Mrs. Henderson's cleverness. 'The child has esprit/' said the lady to me after her call, 'she positively has esprit, Mr. May! What a shame for her to live there in that tomb! And it 's not even a receiving-tomb, you know!' I thought the image a very lively one, in one sense at least, and suggestive of immense social obstacles. And it was generous in my lady too; for she was undoubt- edly rather sweet on Henderson. But women are generous to one another, a great deal more so than I used to fancy before I knew them personally. "Well, and so things went on in the old house for a year or two after the most approved idyllic fashion, until a son and heir arrived. I own I thought that now the essential folly of their arrangements would be made manifest, but it really did not seem so. The child was a fine one, and grew like the ivies. I did not observe myself for some time that the mother was beginning to fade. Henderson would not see it. Long after I was convinced that every time I went there she had lost a little since the previous time, he repudiated the notion with something very like wrath. It was the cold weather; it was the spring weather; it was the heat, the drouth. At   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      I09 last, just before I got ordered off myself, he- became convinced that she needed a change. I can tell you that change was not easy for them to compass. I lent him all the money I had, and more too; and it 's lucky your tastes are simple, Miss, for if ever-- (which Heaven grant! though I don't know why I say so, with Henderson's despair before me), the last journey together of those two will have to come out of it. "'The first time I went out to their place after we all returned, I felt sure it was over with mother and child both. An aunt of Mrs. Henderson's was there (they have no very near relatives), one of those dry, joyless, fugitive women, who always appear in a house three weeks before a funeral, and seem to live but to be the harbingers of death. A faint, contin- uous wail from the sick baby sounded overhead, while we sat in the pretty parlor where we had embraced the development theory; and Henderson and his wife talked, she, in a whisper, of what they would do next winter--next spring! I did not go again until I went yesterday to Mrs. Henderson's funeral. The child died a week ago. I think it was the pleasantest late autumn day that even New England ever saw, misty and warm, with dropping leaves, and faint odors from the faded flower-garden, and deep yellow sunshine which seemed to be dis- solved in all the air,-the very reverse of your  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7505-00000058"/> IIO       LOVE IN THE 'crystalline' days. For once Nature appeared sym- pathetic, which is more than I can say for the young 'liberal' divine who stood at the head of the coffin in the dim, oppressive room where the young mother lay, read a few verses from the Bible in a strictly ceremonious manner, recited a catalogue of the poor little lady's virtues, or rather of the human virtues,- for I don't remember that he discerned what were peculiarly hers,--and then presented her to his Maker with a bow. "I was creeping away after this chilly perform- ance, feeling quite powerless to express my com- passion, when a slip of paper was passed into my hand. I opened it and read, 'Stay with me this evening, if you can. H.' I could not, but I stayed. Henderson took me into a little den of his own, made frightfully tidy like all the rest of the house. The scene of our old debates was occupied by two or three of the human birds of prey aforesaid. When we were alone, he kept silence for a time, making, as I could see, two or three vain efforts to speak. He was ghastly pale with watching and distress, but when at last he began his voice sounded almost indifferent. 'I don't want to embarrass you by my complaints,' he said. 'I mean to be a man, and to bear what comes in life as well as another. It is terrible, but I can bear it. That is, I could, if- The fact is, there are some things I want to talk over   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      I I I with you.' He paused a moment, and then added abruptly, ' Howican I now give up the doctrine of a future life?' "I can tell you I felt my profound unfitness for the office of spiritual adviser, but I said after a little that I did not see why there need be any question of giving up. If he believed already, and was only confused by the apparent tendency of modern thought, I would put all that aside for a time. I had never seen that immortality was disproved by recent discovery; and some of the very best minds of the day-  He interrupted me with great im- patience and a look that half alarmed me for his reason. 'Oh, quit your verbal niceties!' he said. 'Who told you I already believed? I only wish I did! I can no more believe than disbelieve, and this is precisely the dilemma in which I find myself. Talk of disproving immortality! Who ever proved it? The craving of mankind, the wild legend of Christ's resurrection, what are these beside proof as we are now taught to regard it? Yet these are all. And still, I own that, as I ran along with the current of my time, I had an unspoken, undetected thought that the hope of the ages must, after all, have some foundation, that the shore of faith always remained, and one might land at any time if the voyage should lose its wonderful fascination. I suppose my secret thought was a mean one, as one's  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7505-00000059"/> II2       LOVE IN THE secret thought is apt to be. A man should at least be thoroughly loyal to one side or the other. But you see, when the hour came to me of personal bereavement and intolerable separation, I soon found my mistake. To land is out of the question. The stream has widened infinitely, and the shores them- selves are but shifting sands. If the God of my childhood, toward whom I have occasionally had my sentimental yearnings, yet lives, he has indubitably hidden his face from our generation. And no one knows it better, I think, than his formal ministers of whatever persuasion, who stand in secret fear and mechanically point to the veil behind which his glory no longer shines.' "Would you, Clara, have known what to say to him? I did not. I could only think of two forlorn fragments of verse, - both, I believe, by your favorite Arnold:- 'Now he is dead. Afar he lies In the lorn Syrian town; And on his grave, with shining eyes, The Syrian stars look down.' And this other;- 'Waiting between two worlds, one dead, The other powerless to be born, With nowhere yet to rest my head, Like these on earth I stray forlorn.'   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      1 3 It seemed to me, however, that it must at least be better for Henderson to speak his wife's name, and at length I asked him as carefully as I could whether she herself had said any thing to him about the part- ing and the future. He -said she had. That about a week before, some days after the child's death, she bade him wait one morning while she told him slowly that she supposed they had both known for a good while that she, too, was going to die. 'We have been trying to bring ourselves to it apart?' she said, 'before we dared speak to one another; and now I want to tell you that with me that trouble is all over. I don't know how it is, but I woke this morning perfectly willing and almost happy to go. I don't want to hurry you about feeling the same,' she said to him, and it was very characteristic of her, 'because you will certainly do so in good time; but I would like, if you don't object, to see a clergy- man.' 'I suppose I looked a little surprised,' said Henry, 'for we had not, as you know, been very intimate with the clergy; but I asked her whom she would prefer, and she mentioned a certain white- haired Orthodox minister whose venerable beauty we had often admired.' She said, with a little smile, that she did not expect or even want absolution, but that it would gratify her. So he came, and was with her a good while; and when Henry asked her if it had been pleasant, she said, a little doubtfully, 'Yes;'  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7505-00000060"/> "       LO VE IN THE             . but that the old clergyman, although perfectly gentle and paternal, had seemed to require of her sonething which she had never experienced and could not simulate, least of all in such an hour. So he had himself gone away a little disappointed and doubtful about her. "'I was unreasonably angry at this,' said Hender- son, 'although she begged me not to be so, insisting that helrosen priest had been all that was delicate and kind. But I could not bring myself to have him here to-day, and employed instead the gentlemanly usher whom you saw.' "'After all,' I said, 'this peace of mind which you say she had seems to have been something beyond all benefit of clergy. Who knows but it is itself the new and simpler faith delivered to the saints of to-day?'  'It seems a poor substitute for the old, then,' he answered gloomily, 'instead of an affec- tionate personal remembrance and warm hope of speedy reunion, only the tranquil but vague sense of an Eternal Goodness, outside, afar, but drawing her to itself.' 'Was that all?' I asked. ' It seemed so,' he replied; 'but how could I  catechise her? There was certainly no dogmatic notion of "redemp- tion," so called. I did not dare to risk the question whether she expected to live on as herself, -whether she thought that she and I would ever meet again.' "I found I  could not comfort him, but only assure '   1NINETEENTH CENTURY.      I I5 tim in a general way that I cared for him and would ;tand by him, and then I had to leave for the last rain tn town. But as I rattled along-for I had he car almost entirely to myself - I found my houghts dwelling on the little home whose desolation : had just seen. It had been so simple, sweet, and lonorable a home, begun in so fine a spirit of mutual aith, defaced by so few absurd ambitions. One would have thought it was precisely the kind of home which our Lord, or the Eternal Goodness, or what you will, would have liked to see continue and prosper. Yet here it was an early ruin. And there had not even been left to the solitary survivor that vision of an eternal home to which mankind does really seem instinctively to turn. I don't know why else the sacred hymns of the world have rung with lomesick longing from the days of Bernard of Cluny to the date of ' I'm going home, to die no more,'-- a thing, by the way, which can never lack dignity to those who have heard soldiers sing it as they narched by in the night. But my friend, who is both honest and humble, two of the first moral requisites for the perception of truth, dares cherish no such faith. His case is certainly a painful one. "Would it then have been better, I wondered, if this brief home, which may not even be a type, had never been begun? Why, no! thrice no! Hender- son himself would not say so. The pleasures have  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7505-00000061"/> Il6       LOVE IN THE been exquisite. The memories are spotless and sacred. Time will soften the pain of loss, and the whole future wherever, if ever bounded, no doubt holds more for this dejected mourner than at present he can dream. And then I thought of you. Was I likely to review the home question long without it? But now I own I thought of you chiefly with reference to this matter of religious faith, and the long-pre- dicted and perhaps imminent eclipse thereof, and I felt for the first time a strong curiosity to know exactly where you stand. I cannot quite make you out. You are very reticent. You are conservative, and yet you are imaginative, and you are by no means timid. You have the repose that seems to belong to settled convictions, and yet you have a quick and keen sympathy with the inquiries of the day. You voluntarily select for your associates people excellent indeed, but whom, by your own showing, I cannot help regarding as rather narrow and severe. You live with these people, work with them: how far do you think with them? Come now, if the question be not impertinent, I wish you would tell me. If you have a clew, I should at least like to put it in Henderson's hands, who seems to me in a sad enough way.  For" myself, I'm afraid it is with the higher life as I told you some time ago it was with the higher literature, - I have not time for it. I am positively engaged, bound in honor to the lower.   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      117 There followed a sentence which I do not think it would be quite fair to quote. Indeed, as the letters of these two grow more intimate and serious, I am more and more doubtful of the propriety of giving them all to the world. I do not mean to imply that they were ever positively erotic,--far from  it. But they were inti- mate, as I have said,--intimate as one never is with many people.   But the sub- stance of Clara's reply to this last inquiry can at least be given:- "'I am very anxious [thus she wrote] to tell the --exact truth in answer to your question, which by the way I do not consider in the least impertinent, but I find it somewhat difficult to do so. My real posi- - tion is, I believe, a little strange and solitary; but I do not often think about it. I might say with regard to the daily associates whom you rather choose to consider uncongenial, but of whom you know that I am personally very fond, that circumstances have placed me among them, and that it only seems to me right and courteous to adapt myself, as far as I honorably can,Ato their habits and prejudices. But  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7505-00000062"/> this would not be quite all the truth. I suppose I am conservative, as you say,-at least in my tastes. I do not much like the company and the tone of esprits forts, especially when they call themselves so, and more than imply by their words and ways that all who differ from them are esprits faibles. I know the passages which you quoted from Matthew Arnold very well. Of course I do. But the two lines that follow the second, the address to the Carthusian monks, are to me more significant than either. Do you remember them? 'With nowhere yet to rest my head, Like these on earth I stray forlorn. Theirfaithz, my tears, the world deride:  /go to sh!d them at their side.  I dare say the poet has analyzed the feeling which impelled him to carry his burden of doubt into the shadow of the cloister, but I can only attempt to do so. I think, however, there must have lain below it at least a strong suspicion that, when all is said, every objection urged, every attack pressed, every weak * post abandoned and demolished by the foe, the balance of 'truth will still remain with the ancient church. The earthquake will be over some time, and then the old foundations will be discovered  inviolate, indispensable to the world: I think so, do not you? With all my heart I hope so. I know   one cannot yet tell how much is first to topple down. Sometimes when one hears preaching, that greatly abused and exaggerated function of the priest, or public prayers, or formal religious conversation, such as I rather often hear, and finds them so encum- bered with ceremonious phraseology, with effete sentiment, and the pale husks of dead and departed beliefs, one suspects that the overturn is to be ter- rible. But there is in me much of the feeling which would prefer a nest, a bivouac, amid the ruins of what had once been glorious and still was sacred, to ever so commodious and tight a shelter hastily run up upon open, unconsecrated ground. Above all things, I do dislike and repudiate the spirit of him. 'who can stand at what he considers a safe distance from the time-honored house, of his fathers, and chuckle aloud over every widening  crack and leaning tower. I see the old smile of superiority broadening on your lip, and hear the old cheerful accusation of sentimentality. Well, this time I will meet it boldly. Has it ever been 'proved,' as you say, that my sentiments are not as good as another's opinions? Have not sentiments, upon the whole; been more potent in the world than opinions? And there is one sentiment whose gradual disappearance out of modern - must one add democratic? - society bodes no good, I think, to the graces of living or the true dignity of character, and that is the sentiment of loyalty. &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7505-00000063"/> 120       LOVE IN THE "Poor, dear Mrs. Henderson I I wish I had known her. If I were to tell the Miss Faulkners with how vague a hope she went peacefully out of the world, their kind hearts would be rent with pity and ap- prehension, and they would quite understand the old clergyman's point of view. Mine, however, is strengthened, although quietly. It was God who gave her that late and half-unconscious acquiescence in his will, much more than which no saint ever attained. He is giving it perpetually. 'One of the most consoling facts in life to me,' Dr. Bemis one day said, 'is the universal readiness of man, when the end really comes, to leave it.' In hospital wards, on battle-fields, in homes comfortless and luxurious alike, the 'preparation of the heart' is still from him. And my fellowship -is it not our fellowship? - is not merely with Christians of every name, but with those in all time who, while not knowing or even ignorantly refusing that name, do yet exemplify in the patience of their lives the Christian -that is, the eternal -virtues. "' Faith and patience,' 'followers of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises,' - if I were a clergyman, I would preach at least one sermon from that text; and this is the way I would take it. The 'promises,' the future that we crave, are not alone for those who rejoice even now in the speculative sight of it, - that is, who have faith, -   NINETEENTH CENTURY.      121 but for those who live rightly and bravely, even though they never lift their eyes to the heavenly vision, or cannot, from natural infirmity, see so far. "And so I have some sympathy even with the young man who officiated at Mrs. Henderson's funeral. The complacency of his class is irritating, their stoical affectations often very much out of place; but their ideal is apt to be a high and difficult one; and at all events you were hard on him, and I will not knowingly be hard on any one. I have preached without being a clergyman. Forgive me."  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7505-00000064"/> 122     LO VE IN THE XIII. CLARA was forgiven. In what words it will not be necessary to say. I have undertaken to give some account of the wary siege-approaches of these two souls; but I must not be so minute as to become tedious, neither must I, as I said before, intrude too far upon their more earnest privacy. The first snow was on its noiseless and soft desct, slowly whitening all the sim- ple Minden landscape, when Clara finished writing as above. Laying aside her pen, and looking up, she smiled to see how truly cloister-like was the scene on which her window looked, and would look now for many months,--the straight wall of   NINETEENTH CENTURY.   ' 123 the college grounds, the bowed and laden trees within it, the level roofs and gray stone spires above, the dark background of the perpetual pine forest behind all. Clara liked the intense quiet, the quaint- ness which-many would have found dreary; and asked herself, recalling her absolute contentment of spirit in this place, whether the atmosphere of a cloister were not after all her native air. While she mused, the snow ceased falling, the vapors gathered themselves together, disclosing spaces of clear-tinted sky; a flash of sunset, far more vivid than on a summer evening she remembered, transfigured for a moment the unsullied fields and surfaces of cool gray stone, then paled into twilight. With a passing thought of the simple home of the Hendersons now deserted or delivered to strangers, of another simple home that might one day be and would also be tran- sitory, Clara turned -her face toward her  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7505-00000065"/> 124    - LOVE IN THEE winter life with that entire acquiescence in fate which seems almost to preclude  fl desire. I do not'know that it was a mood al- together natural or healthful in one so young. In fact, I am sure it was better that the serenity of it should have been ruffled a little, as it was, before the winter ended. By the time that the unknown Clara had acquired among the underlings in the office of the "Solar System " the so- briquet of " our special correspondent," and the unknown Julius was discussed by the Miss Faulkners over their plain sewing, with a little flutter of pathetic interest, all the more intense that their double-distilled delicacy would never allow them to ask Clara a  question about him, and so he acquired the proportions of a myth and a mystery,--by this time, I say, a trifling change appeared in the tone of what Julius wrote.  Military operations were appar.   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    125 ently suspended for the winter. His let- ters were still frequent, full and free, but they were undeniably less personal than at first. There was no more saucy assuming of a claim never fairly allowed. The airy allusions to a common future ceased alto- gether. Clara observed the difference, but would not own, hardly knew, that it made her unhappy. The truth is that in the heart of her lover, as I suppose we must consider him, reverence had been born. It was a late growth and a slow one, but it changed the color of his whole life,-- the past no less than the present and the future. The woman whom his intellect had first approved, whom with all the easy audacity (as he now saw it) of confident youth he had so abruptly asked to marry him, whose refusal had fallen on him so lightly, was becoming changed and glori- fied to him, withdrawn into a halo, elevated into something spiritual, prophetic almost  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7505-00000066"/> 126     LOVE IN THE         ' of something divine. More and more as the time approached when he was to see   her again, did he tremble before the risk i then to be taken.     - Meanwhile Clara, whwould not have    I been the Clara whom we know could she at all have realized herself as an object of reverence, meditated, doubted, regretted a little, then resolutely turned her thoughts away, only to doubt again, and to guard, with a little of the immeasurable pride that  was in her, the written words which, how-  ever, she did not withhold. The I st of  March, the time fixed for her visit to the Manns, came, and with it illness in the Faulkner household of the mother and one of tihe daughters. Clara stayed to nurse them more than willingly,--stayed even after danger was past, and Dr. Bemis had told her more than once that she was growing pale and interesting and had better be off. For it chanced that some   NINE TEENTH CENTURY.       I 2 7 weeks before, in the depth of the winter, the good physician had surprised a little copy of verses fluttering slowly floorward from the book his young favorite was reading. And he had caught them, and entreated their perusal so    coaxingly, yet so deferentially, that Clara had not van- ity enough to refuse it. And thus they ran:--- MNDEN, February. What means this air so fine That we inspire? Why does the hill-top shine With roseate fire? What shape with radiant brow Would us decoy? May Heaven-keep us now, For this is Joy! Sweet are thine eyes, O, spirit! But look not here! Sweet thy voice, but to hear it Thrills us with fear. For the stern gods of old Will not abide Thy brightness to behold Our path beside.  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7505-00000067"/> I28      LOVE IN THE Alien to our chill way, Thy sunny presence. Farewell, then let us say In all quiescence!  We through the shades will hie, Fearless and fast, Until this tyranny Be overpast.  "A shadowed youth," mused the doctor, even while he read. "A  present peaceful indeed, but too still and sinless for health.   She is wanted in the world, and this old man, at least, is not selfish enough to try and detain her;" then aloud, holding her slim hand for an instant after he had laid the verses in it, -- "-A pretty little heathen hymn, my dear, but do not be obstinate with Providence! I, too, am a bit of a Pagan, as you know, and yet-- I think - the 'jealous gods' are dead." Howheit the middle of April/was past, when there came to Julius, one morning at his desk, an envelope, containing a deli-   NINETEENTH CENTURY..   I29 cately written card, at the sight of which he started, flushed a little, then turned upon the beaming boy who had brought in the letters and severely ordered him off.  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7505-00000068"/> I30     LOV w IN THE           "ii XIV.            '  SPRING is very pleasant in that city whose  i identity I have so delicately and effectually concealed. I mean, of course, the few de- licious days which stand as a kind of alge- braic symbol for spring. There are wastes of east wind- and lowering skies between them.  There are floods of melancholy rain, and untimely snows on Easter lilies; but amid the warfare of these adverse forces, the grass upon that city's most ancient and illustrious pleasure-ground grows bravely and brightly green; the beautiful net-work of her old elm-tree branches becomes misty with bud and fine brown blossom before assuming its final pomp of foliage; the   o naturalized birds pipe so vociferously that one does not miss the equally tuneful frogs,    banished long since from their native haunt, out of affection, possibly, for those adopted citizens in whose home such vermin are not. The circle of palaces that surrounds the noble park in question, and the bright- ening garden grounds beyond it, throw wide their doors and windows on such a day, giving gracious glimpses, through swaying curtains, of the treasures of art and luxury they hold. The banks under their stately windows blaze with crocuses and hyacinths. On the spring in question, that of I87I, we had, as perhaps you remember, an un- usual number of truly vernal days. I as- sume that you may remember it, although I know very well that there is no sureir test of the fatuity of the human mind, and the feeble powers of observation possessed by people in general, than their utter inability to recall the weather of a given season. Ask five of your friends what weather pre-  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7505-00000069"/> 132     L LOVE IN THE vailed during some period of time which you have reason keenly to remember, and see if any two of them will agree. But I have such occasion to remember the spring of I871, and you may take my word for it that it was a fine one. And on one of its rarest mornings Julius May turned aside from the "dusky pur- lieus " of his daily toil into the charmed circle of which I have spoken, and walked westward under the thickening trees of the Holy Mall with a resolute step, feeling occa- sionally for a small package in the pocket of his light overcoat. His mind was un- usually active, insomuch that, although strongly bent on the immediate future, he had a vivid consciousness of many things in the past. He remembered well, if unwill- ingly, how, as a rising young man of toler- able connections, in a city of feminine preponderance, he had been a welcome guest in many of those circling palaces;   NIVz'I L'TEEv -/ V I .U-UI Xr. I33 and, until how lately, he would have consid- ered the idea preposterous, not to say unwor- thy, of himself setting up a city fireside on any scale materially less august than theirs. But now, if he got that on which his tardy heart was set, it would involve, he reflected, with a touch mayhap of unnec- essary heroism, a long and probably fi- nal farewell to the circle of palaces. But then, if he did not get it, palaces and cots would be alike disgusting to him. He knew that now, if it had taken him all winter to make sure of it. * Wherefore, for- ward! And he strode on until he acquired a momentum which carried him lightly up the long steps of one of the stoniest man- sions on the square, and drew the silver bell-handle without an instant's delay. Five minutes later, standing at one end of a drawing-room dim and rich as Tenny- son's Camelot, he saw Clara coming down its length, a fresh, pure, spirited figure, in  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7505-00000070"/> 134     LOVE IN TEE simple drapery of some -light neutral tint, an exquisite contrast to the Oriental splen- dors about her. She was paler, he saw, than she had been among the mountains; but the hand she cordially held- out to him was quite as steady as his own. "I am very glad to see you. What a lovely morning!" "Stop a minute," said Julius, lapsing suddenly under the familiar exhilaration of her presence into the tone of their first acquaintance, - which I am afraid we must conclude was only too natural to him,-- "Iet us waive the weather. The question is, have you found me out?" "Have I what?"The mountain color was fast returning. "Found me out, I say. Was not that what you wanted the winter for? And have I not stood all manner of cate- chising?" "Who has catechised most, I wonder?" *   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    35 "Well, how does it stand? What's my mark?" ' What an extraordinary question!" "Look here," said Julius, "let 's begin again. This is not at all the way I meant to do it; but when a man is afraid"-- "You were always timid." "He hurries and blunders. Now I had a much better plan. I brought you a. book," and he returned to his coat-pocket, and withdrew and unfolded a copy of Tennyson's "Princess." "What a lovely binding!" said Clara, innocently, touching the-creamy calf. "So-so. That 's my taste. But what I want to draw your attention to is this;" and, turning the leaves rapidly that his hand might not be seen to tremble, he found the passage (alrieady, it seems, old as Homer) beginning,- "Not like to like, but like in difference." "Read that over," he said, "unless you  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7505-00000071"/> I36     LOVE IN TEE know it by heart; and tell me once for all whether we shall try it. For, upon my soul," he added suddenly, in an unsteady voice out of which the banter had all departed, "the man to whom you have revealed yourself can have no lower ideal." He was either very fortunate or very sagacious. Like most controlled and un- demonstrative people, there were certain things by which Clara was even unduly moved; and this closing  scene of the "Princess" had never lost the power of making her cry.  The vision beheld by the great poet in the first dawn of our revolutionary era, and reflected since on so many forlorn horizons as the sad mirage of a  perfect marriage, --could it be that there was a man also to whom its signifi- cance was unique?-- "A dream That once was mine! what woman taught you this?" The youngest and rosiest reverie of her girlhood had held no sweeter fancy than   1VllVl ML1  EHiTU 1E ,V .tIUKl 1 37 hat of being wooed in the spirit of this assage. And now-- Sihe'bent her head over the book as he eld it open, bent it low that her eyes light not be seen, and sought as best he might half-blinded for the line under rhich her trembling finger at last rested: "'But I,' Said Ida, tremulously, 'so unlike.' " "Is that all?" asked Julius, very pale. Do you mean it?"Then after a mo- lent's keen scrutiny of her, "'All right!" houted the immortal boy within him. "I bought you had a heart all along, and I new I had." And he flung the edition de z:e into a chair half-way across the room hat his arms might be disengaged. By and by retreating a little, he ob- erved the glowing, tearful, sparkling face ow frankly lifted with an air of impartial ut very favorable criticism. "Why, Clara," e exclaimed, "you are a beauty!"  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7505-00000072"/> 138     LOVE IN THE "Indeed I am not," was the earnest response. "Don't begin deluding yourself at this late day, or our fun will soon be over. And I am not a princess, either." "Well, a queen, then, in your own right; and I am uncommonly like the prince in the story, an insignificant fellow enough, save as he had the sense to love a great woman." "I will say no more," answered Clara, quaintly: " this mood cannot last." Then  they quietly seated themselves on opposite sides of the bay-window, and relapsed into a truly congenial discussion of ways and means. "After all," said Julis, "I 'm afraid you have not the slightest idea what it will  be to attempt to live in a city, even this transcendental one, on an income like mine." "Exactly what is it?"' Julius named the sum. "You see," he   added, " that don't mean a house, nor yet an irreproachable boarding-place, nor an apartment at a fashionable and fine hotel. It means three rooms at the utmost just where they can be found, insuffi- cient attendance, and no visible position whatever." "No matter about the position. That never comes by observation. If we could build a kiosk on the mill-dam to-morrow, we could not, or we would not, go out and compel people to come into it. We should have to wait until they asked for admission, and we'should be under the painful necessity of turning away a great many more than we shall now. The most serious disadvantage of small means in a great city is, perhaps, that they oblige one to be so strictly ceremonious." "How is that ? I don't think I under- stand"  "Then I am sure I cannot explain. It   &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7505-00000073"/> I40     LOVE IN THE seems to me self-evident. But perhaps this is the better way to put it. 1 should think-for how can either of us know? --that one of the greatest comforts of comm nding place and actual affluence would be that one could act so freely, would be obliged to put up so few barriers, need take no thought for one's dignity. But, if one's position is from any cause weak, one has to defend it by double reserve, and be very sure to keep the letter of the law of etiquette on one's side." "' That sounds mysterious enough to be true." "Indeed it is." "You are sure, however, that you have faced the reality and are ready to begin the struggle?" "Please don't say struggle. That we will never make anywhere. But I have faced the truth, and I like the face of it."   NINETEENTH CENTURY.   14I "Bless you! But I hate the idea of your being hampered by petty economies." "Consider," replied Clara, gently, "how used I am to them. They are the habit -of my life. Besides, I never was ambitious. 'Tis you, sir, who have a hankering after satin draperies, majolica, and buhl." "I would have "liked to see you sur- rounded by pretty things,--appropriate things." "And I mean to be; only they will not be very expensive, you shall see! To this end was the popularization of Art, which we discussed so learnedly awhile ago. Besides, you persist in overlooking the'fact that I am an heiress! What's the good, pray, of my seven thousand dollars?" "I hope," replied Julius, with some scorn, "that I am above touching that. A woman's patrimony, be it more or less, ought to be sacred." "Perhaps you are right. I know you are altogether honorable."  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7505-00000074"/> "2     LOVE IN THE "My best bow!  But what will your uncle say to all this?" "Not very much. He knows I am in- corrigible. Cousin Adelaide may be more eloquent." "I dare say she will. Do you expect her to come and see you in a lodging of three rooms?" "She will do exactly as she likes. But I fancy she will come often, and that you will learn to like her very well." "To think, however, of her being in society, and you not!" "Still harping on society! I assure you that will take care of itself. You seem to be very much afraid of tete-&amp;-tetes. Now I think we ought, for a time, to be amusing to one another. If we cannot, I should say we had better not' try this' at all, as you call it." "By Jove, but we will! I only want to be fair to you. I shall have my work, but you"-   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    143 "I shall have my music." "To be sure! How glad I am you have that resource!" "And if time hangs very heavy on my hands, perhaps I can take some very little pupils." "No, ma'am! You will take no pupils except myself, so long as I can work! Your situation is that of strictly private ,governess. But if, in our sophisticated seclusion, you can teach me to appreciate Bach" "I see," said Clara, "with such a work before me I need never crave a wider ' sphere.' " Miss Mann was rather eloquent, not to say tragic, when Clara had told her tale. "The man is well enough," she said, "but three rooms! Three back rooms, very likely!" And she closed her eyes, and leaned back in her silken chair. "Clara, ' are all your taste, and all my pride in your ^ .  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7505-00000075"/> I44     LOVE IN THE- possibilities, to be buried in three back rooms?" "I shall be sorry to outrage your pride, dear; but my taste, I take it, is going to have a good time. It will be far easier keeping ugliness out of three rooms than out of thirteen." "Say no more," cried Miss Mann. "I perceive your cue. I see that aesthetico- economical parlor in my mind's eye now. I know the kind, and detest it. There will be an ironing-cloth on the floor, and wrap- ping paper on the walls. There will be plain book-shelves, and dull gray casts, and dismal carbon photographs pinned about, unframed, and not a speck of strong cordial color anywhere. The chairs will be of solid wood, and deadly angular. There will be 'sincere' brackets upon the walls, with Canton preserve-pots and pancake pitchers upon them. Five of your wedding gifts will be plaques of Palissy, covered   NINE TEENTH CENTURY.   145 with creeping reptiles; and these will stand in a row on your mantel, along with a pair of stout candlesticks of blue earthenware. Your grandmother's case of drawers, which is any thing but 'sincere,' since it is liable at any time to topple over, will occupy one recess, and your great-uncle's tall clock another. Or those of some other person's grandmother and great-uncle, for these last are commodities one sometimes has to borrow here. The place will be a mixture of farm-kitchen and model school-room. Oh, Clara, Clara! when you might have married some elderly nabob, had a coupei and a drawing-room in'blue and gold, and been a credit to your family!" Clara repeated all this to Julius, and they found it delightful bante,r. Thereafter, on returning from their walks, they did, not without malice, much vex the righteous soul of Miss Mann, by describing their ad- ventures in search of cheap lodgings. In-  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7505-00000076"/> I46     LOVE IN THE deed they walked a good deal, much affect" ing certain precipitous and, narrow streets in the older part of the town, which, begin- ning dubiously, lead the afternoon pedes- trian up a painful climb, only to transfix him, when arrived at the summit, by a scene that carries him to some old continental city: a sharp declivity, a vista of sunset, with tall, irregular, picturesque architecture on either hand, closed far below by a space of golden water dotted with idle boats, and a chain of violet hills beyond it. 'Now and then they passed the entrance to the great French Fair, then in triumphant operation. Julius always invited Clara to enter, and she as often declined. "I cannot fiddle when the city of my heart is burning," she would say (for those were the sorrowful days of the Commune): "I'd as soon think of holding a fair to defray the expenses of a funeral." And Julius would reply that enthusiasts,   NINETEENTH CENTURY.  1  4 he had observed, were very apt to be par- simonious. If they were not always as foolish as they might have been, they did at least grow more and more unwise, through all the remaining weeks of Clara's stay; and by the time of the Triennial Musical Fes- tival, for which she remained, Miss Mann declared they had become very nearly as distraits and tiresome to the world at large as ordinary lovers. I saw them repeatedly during  that festival week, - pleasantly memorable to us all, peculiarly so, of course, to them, - sitting side by side in a quarter of the Music Hall which I have ever since associated with them; and I own I thought that with their youth and strength, with the music inside and  the brilliant May weather without, with the clearness of their mutual faith and the bravery of their common resolves, these two had enough, although their earthly future were not a  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7505-00000077"/> "8     LOVE IN THE golden one. It amused me to see them diligently read the text of the music, day after day, under Clara's guidance. "They will have no rapture of emotion," I said to myself, "without a basis of clear under- standing. Well, it was not so in my time, but it may be best." On Friday afternoon when, as you remember, we had the Ninth Symphony, I happened to sit' very near them. The high and almost painful ecstasy of the choral portion, the fiery hymn to Joy, was a little overpowering to some of us. Weighted spirits do not easily ascend to such a pinnacle. It was glorious, but it was oppressive, almost ironical. I thought, however, that I read in the faces of this pair that they found it only natural and exhilarating. I caught also the quick glances they exchanged between the alter- nating airs of the celestial Adagio, exqui- sitely contrasted yet adapted as these are,   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    49 --sweetly modulating through so many keys, - and I fancied that to our friends, for the time being-,this peerless music was but typical of the perpetual answer of two perfectly responsive souls, on through the varying moods of a life continued into eternity. This was, let me see, two years ago of course, yet it seems longer, so indubi- table appears- already the success of our friends' imprudent experiment. I visited them when I was last in town. It is rather the thing to visit them now. I only hope they will not become too much the fashion. Their unconventional 'home proves a very fascinating one, and those who enter it once are so loath to leave, so eager to re- turn, that it must needs have become, in its way, a centre of hospitality. A hospitality which obeys no law save the generous im- pulse of those who dispense it, too informal  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7505-00000078"/> I 50     LO VE IN THE for comparison, too cordial for question, too unostentatious to impose an onerous obli- gation. The wit and sympathy of host and hostess, their unison of heart and purpose, and ever-growing social graces, combine to make an atmosphere where people of widely differing views and traditions are alike 'at home, forget their mannerisms, feel their keenest, think and talk their best. The visiting-list of our young people grows long, but it is still what would be thought a motley one. Famous and even fashionable names are not wanting on it, but some are wholly obscure.  In one thing, however, the bearers of them all agree; namely, in the wonderful sense of rest and expansion which comes to them in the bright freedom of this unambitious fireside. The ver-y look of the rooms is enchanting. .Esthetico-economical a cynic might call them still, if one could remain , \   NINETEENTH -CENTURY.   15 I1 a cynic after going there; but their air is wholly that of a refined and healthful home. "How charming!" says the great lady just lighted from her carriage; "How jolly!" the college lad; "How  com- fortable!" even the fastidious bachelor. Here comes Henderson from his lonely lodging, and warms into something of his old brilliancy. Here comes Miss Mann well-nigh daily, affirming that in her pres- ent debilitated state Clara's " asthetic teas" are the only form of social inter- course she can bear. Here always on his rare visits to the city, - and they are not, quite so rare as formerly, - comes Dr. Bemis, the stately and serene soul; adding, while he stays, the one absent element of beauty, the venerable, to the graces of the spot. The situation of this lodging also has always seemed to me poetically appro- priate. In the very heart of the city,  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7505-00000079"/> 152     LOVE IN THE where the pulse of her life beats most vehemently, where streets are narrow, cross- ings perilous, and every inch of the ground is twice historic, there is a little oasis of peace. A quiet place of ancient graves, not desecrated yet, and let us hope not soon to be so, where the sheltered turf and clustering trees are early green, and old- fashioned flowers bloom luxuriantly about the tombs and leaning headstones. To the sunny windows which command this pensive and yet gracious nook, the roar of the city's great thoroughfare, although close at hand, comes softened, the pageant of perpetually passing crowds turns dream- like, and the front windows of our young lodgers have this view. There are others which look by night into a brightly lighted gallery, where the immortal shapes of antique art gleam through the arched win- dows upon our happy householders, - too poor to possess, but not to enjoy such   NINETEENTH CENTURY.    153 treasures. And living thus, in a garden, in the city, with the gods of Greece behind them and the dead in Christ always before, theirs seems to me the very ideal of an existence that knowledge broadens, love glorifies, giving enriches, to which Art min- isters, to which Death itself will not look unfamiliar or unfriendly. 7* Cambridge: Press of John Wilson and Son.  &#xD;<pb n="154-155 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000080"/>   ROBERTS BROTHERS' "ATEST NEW BOOKS. WORK: A STORY OF EXPERIENCE. By LOUISA M. ALCOTT author of "Little Women." With Character Illustrations by SOL EYTINGE. 16mo, cloth. Price $1.75. (Ready in June.) mTHE INTELLECTUAL LIFE. By PHLIP GILBERT HAM- ERTON, author of "Thoughts about Art," "A Painter's Camp," &amp;c. Square 12mo. Price $2.00. TIPS AND DOWNS. AN EVERY DAY NOVEL. By EDWARD E. HAT,.T. 16mo. Price $1.50. JOHANNES OLAF. A Romance from the German of ELIZA- BETHR DE WILLE. By F. E. BUNNETT, Translator of "On the Heights." Price $2.00. BITS OF TALK ABOUT HOME MATTERS. By H. H. Price $1.00.  MEMOIRS OF REV. SAMUEL J. MAY. With a Steel En- graved Likeness. Price $1.50. WOMAN IN    AMERICAN SOCIETY.     By ABBA GooLD ' WOOLSON. Price $1.50. THOREAU: THE POET-NATURALIST. With Memorial Verse. By WIT TIAt ELLT RY CHANNING. 16mo. Price $1.50. SONGS FROM   TAltE SOUTHtERN SEAS. By JOHN BOYE O'REILLY. 16mo. Price $1.50. (In Press.) LOVE IS ENOUGH; OR, THE FREEING OF PHARAMOND. A Morality. By WILLIAM MORRIS, author of "The Earthly Paradise." 16mo. Price $1.25. Crown 8vo. Price $2.00. THE PERFECT LIFE. In Twelve Discourses by WILLIAM ELLERY CHANNING, D D. Edited from his manuscripts by his nephew WILLIAM HENRY CHANNING. 12mo. Price $1.50. WIT AND    WISDOM  OF GEORGE   ELIOT. With an Index of Subjects. Square 18mo. Cloth. $1.25. THE   INFIN ITE AND  'AtXE FINITE'. By THEIOPHLUS  PARSONS. Price $1.00. JEAN   INGELOWNS COMPL;1ETE POEMS. Diamond Edi. tion. Price $1.50. (In Press.)  &#xD;<pb n="156 (Advertisement) -157 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000081"/> 2 ROBERTS BROTHERS' LATEST NEW BOOKS. JEAN INGELOWIS POEMS. Embellished with more than one hundred Illustrations. A New Edition, with the addition of a new photographic likeness of Miss INGELOW from a recent sitting to Elliot and Fry, of London. One small quarto volume, cloth, gilt and black lettered, and gilt edges. Price $7.50. Morocco, elegant. Price $12.00. MORITZ RETZSCHS OUTLINES TO 1tjRGERPS BAL- "ADS. Comprising the Ballads of Lenora, The Lay of the Brave Man, and The Pastor's Daughter of Taubenhain, Oblong folio, cloth, black and gilt lettered. Price $5.00. Morocco antique and extra. Price $9.00. The Outlines are printed in Germany from the original plates made by Retzsch, and the book is a companion volume to our popular editions of "Outlines to Shakespeare" and "Lay of the Bell," by the same artist. Altogether it will be one of the most desirable- books of the present season. FROM THE NILE TO THE JORDAN. Footsteps of the Israelites from Egypt to Sinai. With fourteen Autotype Illustrations, after David Roberts, R. A. Small quarto, superbly bound in cloth, gilt and black lettered, and illuminated. Price $6.00. T1IORVALDSEN: HS LIFE AND WORKS. Translated from the French of HENRI PLON by Miss LUYSTER. With tlirty-seven highly finished representative Illustrations, printed in Paris from the original plates, on India proof paper. 12mo, cloth, bevelled boards, imitation Roxburghe. Price $2.75. MREIO. A POEM. By FREDERIC MSTRAL. Translated by HAR- BIET W. PRESTON. With vignette title by BILLINGS. One elegant red-line volume, cloth, gilt top. Price $2.00. Morocco antique, or calf, extra gilt. Price $5.50. []EMOIRS OF MADAME DESBORDES-VALMORkE. By the late C. A. SAINTE-BEUVE. With a selection from her Poems. Translated by HARRIET W. PRESTON. Square 16mo, cloth, bevelled boards, gilt top. Price $1.50. NILE SKETCHES. By CARL WERNER. Second Series. With magnificent Chromo-Lithographs, 18x25, mounted suitable for framing. Price $28.00. CHRISTMAS EVE AND CHRISTMAS DAY: Ten Christ- mas Stories. By EDWARD E. HALE. With Frontispiece by DAn- LEY. 16mo, cloth, gilt. Price $1.50. THE TALL STUDENT. From the German, by CHARLES T. BROOKS. With fifteen grotesque Designs. Square 16mo, cloth, gilt, bevelled boards. Price 75 cts. THE    WORLD-PRIEST.     Translated from  the German of Leopold Schefer, author of "The Layman's Breviary," by CHARLES T. BRooKs. Square 16mo, cloth, gilt. Price $2.25. SHAWL-STRAPS. By LOUISA M. ALCOTT, author of "Little Women." Being the second volume of "Aunt Jo's Scrap-Bag." With Illustrations by Miss HALLOCK. Price $ 1.00. Aunt "Jo" has here written down, for the delectation of her countless admirers, a sociable and humorous account of her recent trip to Europe.   ROBERTS BROTHERS' LATEST NEW BOOKS. 3 WHAT KATY DID. A STORY. By SUSAN COOLIDGE. With Illustrations by ADDIE, LEDYARD. Square 16mo, cloth, gilt and black lettered. Price $1.50. "T-he New-Year's Bargain," by SUSAN COOLIDGE, placed her at once in the front rank of story-tellers. Her new story will make her still more famous, and everybody will want to know "a What Katy Did." THE NEW HSTORY OF SANFORD AND MERTON. Being a true account of the adventures of "Masters Tommy and Harry," with their beloved tutor', L"Mr. Barlow." By F. C. BURNAND. With seventy-five Illustrations by LINLEY SAMBOURNE. Square 16mo, cloth, gilt. Price $1.75. MRS. ROBERT O"REILLY9S POPULAR STORIES: Doll World, Daisy's Companions, and Deborah's Drawer. With eight Ill;:s. trations to each volume. Three volumes, uniformly bound in clothe black and gilt lettered, and put up in a neat box. Price $3.00. VERY YOUNG AMERICANS. By LAURA W. LEDYARD. With many beautiful Illustrations by ADDIE LEDYARD. Square 16mo, cloth, gilt and black lettered. Price $1.00.         1 ITALIAN SCENES AND STORIES. By the author of "What. Makes Me Grow." With twenty Illustrations. Square 12mo, cloth, black and gilt lettered. Price $1.50. "TTLE LIVES. - Animal Stories in Prose and Verse. By the author of "Evening Amusement." With twelve Illustrations. Square 16mo, cloth, black and gilt lettered. Price $1.25. IN EXTREMS. A NOVELETTE. By Mrs. RICHARD S. GREEN- OUGH, author of "Arabesques." Square 16mo, cloth, gilt. Price $1.50. A   SUMMERWS   ROMANCE.   A -NOVELETTE.  By MARY HEALY; author of "Lakeville" and "'The Home Theatre." 16mo. Price $1.50. CHRISTIAN ART AND SYMBOLIS]M. By JOHN TYRWHTT. With an Introduction by RUSKIN, and Illustrations. 12mo, cloth, gilt. Price $2.00. GOD IN HUMANITY. By JAMES MARTINEAU. (In press.) CONCORD DAYS. By A. BRONWSON ALCOTT, author of "Tablets." 16luo, cloth, gilt. Price $1.50. THE THYEF IN THE NIGHT. A Novelette. By HARRIET PRESCOTT SPOFFORD, author of "The Amber Gods," &amp;c. 1 vol. 16mo. Price $1.25. THOUGHTS UPON GOVERNMENT. By ARTHUR HiLPS. 1 vol. 8vo. Price $2.25. A SHADOW     OF DANTE, Being an Essay towards studying Himself, his World, and his Pilgrimage. By MARIA FRANCESCA Ros- SETTI. With Illustrations. One volume, crown 8vo. Price $2.50. BIBLE MUSIC. Being Variations in many Keys on Musical Themes from Scripture. By FRANCIS JACOX, author of "Cues from all Quarters"Crown 8vo. Price $1.75.  &#xD;<pb n="158 (Advertisement) -159 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000082"/> IA PPY  THOUGHT     HALL. By F. C. BuRNAxD, author of "' Happy Thoughts." With Illustrations. Price $2.00. OFF THE SKELLIGS. A Novel. By JEAN INGELOW. 16mo. 670 pags. Price 1.7B. SIX OF ONE BY HALF-A DOZEN OF THE OTHER. A Novelette. By Mrs. HARRIET BEECtER STOWE, Mrs. A. D. T. WHTNEY, Miss LUCRETIA HALE, Rev. E. E. IALn, F. B. PERKIN, and F. W. LORING. 16mo. Price $1.50. AUNT JO'S SCRAP-IBAG. By LOUISA M. ALCOTT, author of "Little Women," "All Oldl-Fashioned Girl," "Little Men." With Illustrations. Price 1I.00. OUT   OF  TOWN.   By F. C. Bo .,.ND., autgor of "Hapy Thoughts." Price $1.25. OUTLINES TO    SHAKESPEARE.      )esigned and Engraved by MORITZ RETZSCH. One Huniredl and One Plates with Explana. tory Text. One volume, oblong folio, superbly bound in clotlh, gilt anl black-lettered. Price $9.00. MOIrocco antique. Price $15.00. "'HE  SERMON   ON TIIE  MOUNT.   Illuminated hy W. and G. HUDSLE. Illustrated by CHARLES ROLF. Chromo-lithographled by W. R. T-Mwrs. One volmnle, folio, superbly bound in illuminated raorocco-cloth, gilt. Price $12.00. FALSTAFF    AND   HS  COMPANIONS.    Twenty Designs in Silhonette, by PAUL KONEWKA. With an Introduction by HER BANR  KuRZ, and Explanatory Text selected from Shakespeare. One volume, square 8vo, cloth, gilt. Price $3.00. Morocco antique Price $6.00. 'IBE    UNKNOWN    RIVER:  AN ETCHER'8 VOYAGE  OF I)s. COVE;Ry. By P. G. HAMERTON, author of  "1 Thoughts about Art " and "A  Painter's Camp." With 37 Illustrations etched from Nature by the author. One volume, 8vo, cloth, gilt. Price $6.00. Morocco antique. Price $9.00. GOOD NIGHT AND GOOD IMORNING. A POEM. By Lord HOUGHTON. With Illuminations and Etchings on copper, by WALTEII SEVERN. One volume, quarto, illuminated, cloth, gilt. Price $4.50. SING SONG: A NURSERY RtYrIE BOOK, By CfIRISTINA ( ROSSETTI. One Hundred and Twenty Songs, with an Illustration t each Song, by ARTHUR  HUGHES, engraved by the DAtZIFBS. OD1 volume, thin 8vo, cloth, gilt. Price $1 50 THE   NEW YEAR'S BARGAIN.      A  CHRISTMAS STORY pre CHLDRE'N. By SUSAN COOLIDGE. With Illustrations by AvDla "EDYARD. One volume, square 16mo, cloth, gilt. Price $1 50. PAUL  OF TARSUS :    An Inquiry into the Times and the Gospe. of the Apostle of the Gentilef--y a Graduate. 16mtno. Price $1.50   MY   HEALTH.   By F. C. BURNAND, author of "Happy Thoughts." Volume X. Handy-volume Series. Red cloth. Price $1.00, ARAB UEQUES. MONARE - APOLLYONA - DOMTIA - OMBRA. Four Stories of the Supernatural. By Mrs. RICHARD S. GREENOUGH. With Medallions and Initial Letters. Red-line border printed on heavy laid paper. One elegant 16mo volume, bound in cloth, gilt. Price $2.00. ENGLISH  LESSONS FOR ENGLISH     PEOPLE. By E. A. ABBOTT, M. A., and J. R. SEELEY, M. A. (author of "Ecce Homo"). One volume, 16mo, cloth. Price $1.50. This little manual (reprinted from early sheets of the English edition Dy arrangement with the authors), intended not only for a text-book in advanced schools and colleges, but for the general reader, will be found to be an invaluable assistant to those acquiring a method of speaking and writing the English language correctly. Prof. Seeley, the author of "Ecce Hoimo," has the reputation of being one of the most perfect of English scholars. CUES FROZM   ALL QUARTERS; OR, LITERARY MUSINGS OF A CLERICAL RECLUSE. By FRANCIS JACOX. One volume, 16mo. Price $1.50. RADICAL PROBLEMS. By Rev. C. A. BARTOL. One vol- ume, 16mo. Price $2.00. THE TO-MORROW      OF DEATH,   OR, THE FUTURE LFE ACCORDING TO SCIENCE. By LOUis FIGUIER. Translated bG-. R. CROCKEl, Editor of the "Literary World." One volume, 16mo. Price $1.75. 'T'IE ROSE-GARDEN. A NOVELETTE. By thb author of "Unawares." 16mo. Price $1.50. UNAWARES.    A NOVELETTE. By FRANCES M. PERARD.   16mo. Price $1.50. SAILING   ON THE NILE. By LAURENT LAPORTE.    Trans- lated by VIRGINIA VAUGHAN. 16mo. Price $1.50. MRE1IO   A PASTORAL POEM.   From  the Provencal of M. MSTRAL, by Miss HARRIET W. PRESTON. Gilt top. Price $2.00. 'llTHEI VICARIS PAUGHTTER. A NOVEL.      By GEORGE MA0- DONALD, With many original Illustrations. Price $1.50. AFTER ALLT, NOT TO CREATE ONLY. WALT WHT- MAN'S AMERICAN   INSTITUTE POEM. 12mo, cloth, limped covers. Price 30 cents.  &#xD;<pb n="160 (Advertisement) -161 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000083"/> Office of "OLD AND NEW,' a Monthly. Magazine for the People, Edited by Rev. Edward E. Hale. "3, WASHrNGTON STREET, BOSTON, Summer of 1873. MESSRS. ROBERTS BROTHERS' GENERAL LIST OF WORKS. DP- The Books in this List, unless otherwuse specified, are bound in Cloth. All of our Publications mailed, postpaid, on receipt of price. ALCOTT (LOUISA M.). I-TTLE WOMEN; or, Meg, Jo, Beth, and Amy. With Illistration&amp;. Two volumes. 16mo. $3.00. HOSPITAL SKETCHES and CAMP AND FIRESIDE STORIES. With Illustrations. 16mo. $1.50. AN OLD-FASaIONNED GIRL. With Illustrations. 16mo. $1.50. LITTLE MEN: Life at Plumfield with Jo's Boys. With Illustrations. 16mo. $1.50. ALCOTT (A. BRONSON). TABLETS. 16mo. $1.50. With Portrait, full gilt, $2.50. ALGER (W. R.). THz POETRY OF THE ORIENT. 16mo. $1.50. A CRITICAL HISTORY OF THE DOCTRINE OF A FUTURE LiltS. 8vo. $3.50. THE SOLITUDES OF NATURE AND OF MAN; or, The Loneliness of Human Life. 16mo. $2.00. Cheaper Edition, $1.50. THE FRIENDSHPS OF WOMEN. 16mo. $2.00. Cheaper Edition, $1.50. PRAYERS OFFERED IN THE MASSACHUSETTS HOUSE OF REPiRI SENTATrVES DURING THE SESSION OF 1868. 16mo. $1.50. A VISIT  TO MY DISCONTENTED     COUSIN. HANDY VOLUME SERIES, NO. 8. 16mo. $1.00. A UERBACH (BERTHOLD. ON THE HEIGHTS. 16mo. $1.50. VILLA EDEN: The Country-House on the Rhine. 8vo. $2.00. EDELWEISS. 16mo. $1.00. GERMAN TALES. 16mo. $1.00. BALLANTYNE (R. M.). GASCOYNE, THE  SANDAL-WOOD TRADER.   Illustrated. I imo $1.25. BARING-GOULD (S.). CURIOUS MYTHS OF THE MDDLE AGES. 16mo. $1.25. BARNES (WM.). RURAL POEMS. With 12 full-page Illustrations. Square 16mo. 1Be elled cloth, gilt edges. $2.00. Handy Volume Edition, $1.25.   GENERAL   LIST  OF   WORKS.        7 BLACKFORD   tMRS.).              IIlustrate TIIE SCOTTISH ORPANS; and ARTUR MONTEITH.    lustrated. 16mo. 75 cents. BROOKS, (CHARLS T.). Ttm, LAYMA N'S BlEwVIArY; or Meditations for Every Day in the Yea-. From the Gierlman of LEOPOLD SCHEFER. 16mo. $2.25. A Cheaper Edition, $1.50. BUCHANAN (RoBERT). POEMS. 16mo. $1.50. B URNAND (F. C.). HAPPY TnO  F GHTS. 16mo. $1.00. MORE HAPPY THOUGHTS. 16mo,. $1.00.' BUTLER (SAMUEL). UDIBRAS. WitIh Notes, a Life of the Author, and mllustratlons 32mo. $1.25. BUONAPARTE (NAPOLEON). TABLE-TALh AND OPINIONS OF. 18mo. $1.25. CERVANTES (MGUIL DE)      . THE ADVENTURES OF DoN QUIXOTE DE LA MANCHA.- Translated by CHARLES JARVIS. Illustrated. Small quarto. $6.00. COWLEY (ABRAHAM". 'EssAYs. With Life by the Editor, Notes and Illustrations by Dr. HURD, and others. 18mo. $1.25. DALTON (WM.). TD HE TIO R PRINCE; or, Adventures in the Wilds of Abyssinia. Illustrated. 16mo. $1.25. DAY (TIIOMAS). SANFORD AND MERTON. Illustrated. 16mo. $1.25. DAVY (SIR H.).        , CONSOLATIONS IN TRAVEL; or, The Last Days of a Philosopher. 16mo. $1.50. SALMONIA; or, Days of Fly-Fishing. 16mo. $1.50. EDWARDS (M. BETHAM). DR. JACOB. A Novel. $1.00. ERCKIMANN-CHATRIAN. TH0E FOREST HOUSE and ATHERINE'S LOVERS. 16mo. $1.50. E VENING AMUSEMENT. With Twenty Designs by PAUL KONEWKA. 16mo. $1.25. FROLICH (L.). PICmTURE-BOOK, Mischievous John, Foolish Zbe, Boasting Hector. The Text by their Mammas; the Designs by L. FIOLICH. Small quarto. $2.00. GOETHE. HERMANN AND DOROTHEA. Translated by ELLEN FROTnINGHA Illustrated. Thin 8vo. $2.00. Cheap Edition, $1.00. GRAY (DAVID. POEMS With an Introductory Notice by Lord HOUGrHTON, .Memoir o! the Author, and Final Memorials. 16mo. $1.50.  &#xD;<pb n="162 (Advertisement) -163 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000084"/> 8      JESSRS  ROBERTS7   BROTHERS' HALE (EDWARD E.). TEN TIMES ONE IS TEN. 16mo. 88 cents. HAMERrTON (PTITLIP G.). A PAlNTER'S CA3IP. Book I.: In England. Book I1.: In Scotlaxnd Book Ill.: In France. 16mno. $1.50.. THOUOHTS ABOUT ART. 16m0. $2.00. THE UN'KN OW   RIVER. With 37 Etchings by the Author. 8vo. $6.00. DANDY VOLUME SERIES. 16mo. 1. HAPPY THOUGHTS. By F. C. BURNAND. $1.00. 2. DR. JACOB. A Novel. By Miss M. BETHA! EDWARDS. $1.00, 3. PLANCHETTE. A History of Modern Spiritualism. $1.25. 4. FDELWEISS. A Story. By BERTHOLD AUERBAOH. $1.00. 5. REAL1TIES OF IRISH LIFE. By W. STEUART TRENCH. $1.00. C. POEmts OkF RURAL LIFE. By WM. BARNES.    12 Illustrations $1.25. 7. GERIMAN TALES. By BERTHOLD AUERBACH. $1.00. 8. A VI61T TO MY DISCONTENTED COUcSIN. A Novelette. $1.00. 9. MORE HAPPY THOUGHTS. By F. C. BURNAND. $1.00. HEDGE (F. H.) THE PRIMEVAL WORLD OF HEBREW TRADITION. 116mo. $1.50. HELPS' (ARTHUR) WRITINGS. 6 vols. REALMAH. 16mno. $2.00. CASIMR MAREiIMA. 16mno. $2.00. COMPA2NIONS OF MY SOLITUDE. 16mo. $1.50. ESSAYS WRITTEN IN THE INTERVALS OF BUSINESS. 16mo. $1.50. BREVIA: Short Essays and Aphorisms. l6mo. $1.50. CONVERSATIONS ON WAR AND GEN'ERAL CULTURE. 16mo. $1.50. HELEN    AND  HER  COUSINS; OR, Two MONTHS A8 AT   H- FIELD RECTORY. 18mo. 50 cents. HEAVEN    (THE) SERIES.   16mo. Each $1.25. HEAVEN OUnR HOME. We have no Saviour but Jesus, and no Home but Heaven. MEET FOR HEAVEN. A State of Grace upon Earth the only Prepa- ration for a State of Glory ini HeavenI. LIFE IN HEAVEN. Thlre Faith is changed into Sight, and Hope tF passed illto Blissful Fruition. HOPE   (A. R.). A BOOK ABOUT DOMtINIES. 16mo. 75 cents. A BOOK ABOUT BoYS. 16mo. 75 cents. HOWITT    (MARY). FIRESIDE TALES. In Prose and Vers   16mo. 75 cents. -UNT   (LEIGH). TE BOK OF THE SONNET. 2 vols. $3.00. THrE  fR; or, Common Places Refreshed. 2 vols. 16mo. $3.00. A  DAY BY THE FIRE, and other Papers hitherto ullcollected. Edtte,- by "Tomg FOLIO." 16mO. $1.50. INGELOW'S (JEAN) POEMS. 2 vols. 16mo. $3.00. 2 vols. 32mo. $2.50. 1 vol. 16mo. Cabinet Edition. $2.25. TIE AIONITIONTS OF T 1HE UNSE;EN, and POEMS Op LOVE AND CH I L ROOD. 12 llustrations. 16mo. $1.60. Illustrated Edition. 8vo. $7 50; in morocco, $12.00. BoNaG OF SEVN. Illustrated. 8vo. $2.50. ,  ,  ,   ,   Cheap Edition. 20 and 30 cents.   GENERAAL LI'ST OF WORKS.           9 INGELOW'S (JEAN) PRO()E. STUIDIES FOR STORIES. Illustrated. 16mo. $1.25 STORIES TOLD TO A CHLD. First and Second Series. Illustrated. 16mo. Elch $1.25. A SISTER'S BYE-HOURS. Illustrated. 16mo. $125. MOPSA THE FAIRY. A Story. Illustrated. 16nlo. $1.25. POOR MATT; or, The Clouded Intellect. 18mo. 60 cents. INGRAHAM'S (J. H.) WORKS. 3 vols. 12mo. Each, $2.00. THE PRINCE OF THE HOUSE OF DAVID; ortThree Years in the Holy City. THE PILLAR OF FIRE; or, Israel in Bondage. THE THRONE OF DAVID, - from the Consecration of the Shephe-d of Bethlehem to the Rebellion of Prince Absalom. "JANUS." THE POPE AND THE COUNCIL. Authorized Translation from the German. 16mo. $1.00. JOHN WHOPPER'S ADVENTURES. 16mo. 76 cents. JUDD (SYVESTER). MARGARET: A Tale of the Real and the Ideal, of Blight and Bloom. 16mo. $1.50. RICHARD EDNEY AND THE GOVERNOR'S FAMLY. 16mo. $1.50. KONEWIKA   (PAUL). Silhouette Designs. SHAK ESI'EARE'S MIDSUMMLER-N-IGHT'S DREAM. With 24 Illustrations. Roval 8vo. $4.00. Morocco, $9.00. GOiETHE'S FAUST. 12 Illustrations. 4to. $3.00. Morocco, $8.00. FALSTAFF AND HS COM1PANIoNS.  21 Illustrations. 8vo. $3.00. Morocco, $6.00. EVF NIsNG AMUSEMENT. With 20 Illustrations. 16mo. $1.25. PUC'K'S NIGHTLY PRANtKS. Paper covers. 50 cents. "AMB (CHARLES). A MEMOIR. 'By BARRY CORINWALL. 16mo. $1.50. "ANDI)OR  (WALTER SAVAGE). PERICLES AND ASPASIA. 16mn. $1.50. "BIRARY  OF EXEMPLARY WOMEN. 6 vols. 12mo. Each, $1.50. MEIMOIRS AND CORRESPONDENCE OF MADAME ItCAMtrl . Trans- latedl and E1dited by Aliss LUYSTER. THE FRIENDSHPS OF WOMEN.  By Rev. W. R. ALGER. "FE AND LIETTERS OF MADAME SWETCRHE. By Count de FAL "OUX. Translated by Aliss PRESTON. SAIsNTEr -BE1UVE'S PORTRAITS OF CELEBRATED WOMEN. Translated by Aliss PRESTroN. THE IET'TERS OF MADAME DE SEVIGN:I. Edited, with a Memoir, by Mrs. SARAH J. HALE. THE LET'rERSit  ()F LADY MARY WORTLEY MONTAGU. Edited. with a Memoir, by Mrs. SARAH J. HAi E. "OWELL (MRs. A. C.).             - POSI ES FOR CHLDREN. 16mo. 75 cents. "UYSTER (I. M.) Miss LLY's VOYAGE ROUND THE WORLD. Undertaken in comlpan) with her two Cousins, Masters Paul and Toto, and Little Peter. Translatedl from the French by Miss LUYSTER. 48 Designs by Lo- RENZ FRO)LICH. 8vo. $3.00. THE IITTLE GYSY. Translated from the French of ED. SAUtAGR , by Miss LUYSTER. Illustrated. Square 12mo. $1.25. "YTTON'S (BULWER) DRAMAS AND POEMS. Containing "The Lady of Lyons," "Richelieu;" and '6 Money," and, Minor Poems. With a Fine Portrait on Steel. 1 vol. 32mo. Blue  &#xD;<pb n="164 (Advertisement) -165 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000085"/> IU     MElhSSRS. ROBERTS     BROTHERS" MACGREGOR (JOHN). A TnOUSASND MILES LN THE RO(B ROY CANOE: or, Rivers and Lakes of Europe. Map and Rlustrations. 16elo. Cfleap Edlition. $1.25. THE ROB ROY ON THE BALTIC: The Narrative of the 1Rob Roy Canoe, on Lakes and Rivers of Swedlen, Denlark, Norway, and on the Baltic aO d NortTH  Sea  Illustrat. 1 d6m.  16m. $.50. TAXE VOYA GE ALONURICE I THE YAW  "ROB RY," from Lonon t Paris, and back by Havre, the Isle of Wight, south Coast, &amp;c. 16mo MARRYATT (WILCAT.). TaE PRIVATEERSIAx. Adventures by Sea and Land. 11ustratmme 16mo. $1 25. MLLER (JOAQUIN). MAX AND IMAU RICE. A Juvenile History in Seven Books. Translated by CHARLES 1. BROOKS. With Illustrations. 12mo. $1.25. MORRIS (WILLIAM). THE EARTHLY PARADISE. Parts I. and II., Spring and Summet I Part II., Autulmn; Part IV., Winter. The work complete in 3 vols. Crown 8vo Edition, $9.00; 16mo Edition, $6.00; 16mo Popular Edi- tion, $4.50. TEHE LFE AND DEATH OF JA$o9N. A Poem.   16mo. $1.50. THA E LOERS OF GUDRUN.   With Frontispiece from Design by BILL- IXNGS. 16moe. $1.00. NEAL   (JOHN ). WAN*DEIRING  RECOLLECTIONS OF A SOMEWHgAT Busy LIFE.  An Autobiography. 16m Life ofGeneral Grant. $utrated1.50. 6o GRPOPULEAT YSERIES AD  LITTLE PLAGUES. A Story-bookfor YESoung and Old. 16mo. 75cents. PARKER (JosEPH). EcCE DEUS: Essays on the Life and Doctrine of Jesus Christ. With Controversial Notes on "Ecce Homo." 16mo. $1.50. AB- CLERUm: Aadvices to a Young Preacher. 16mo. $1.50. PAUL PRESTON'S VOYAGES, TRAVELS, AND RW.) MARPENDABLE   ADVENTUR .   Illustrated. 16m16. $1.25. PENNIMAN     (AJORE. T. H.). THE TAwN3ER BOY. A   Life of General Grant. Illuistrated  16mo $1.25. POPULAR FAIRY TALES. Containing the choicest and best known Fairy Stories. Illustrate- 2  vols. 16mo. Each, $1.25. PELLICO (SILVIO). MY PRISONS. Memoirs of SILVIO PELLXCO. With an Introductlou by EPES SARGENT. 12mo. $2.25. A Cheaper Edition, $1.50. PRESTON    ( MOHARRIET W). ASPENDALE. 16mo. $1.50. PUTNAM   (E. T. H.). WHERE: Is THE Cirvy? The Experience of a Young Man in search of the True Church; with Sketches of the Baptists, C gregationa istf AMethodists, Episcopalians, Quakers Swederg '  PiritU-t-,- Uivera i'sts, and Unitarians. 16mo. $1.25. PUNStI()N  (W.   MORLEY). TRE PRODIGAL SON. Four Discourses, with a  Prefiace by Rev. Gx,-; maT Ivx.   16mo. 50 cents. Papur covers, 25 cents.   ROSSETTI (CHRISTINA G.). POEMnS. 16mo. $1.50. COMMAONPLACE AND OTHER STORIES. 16mo. $1.50. ROSSETTI (DANTE GABRIEL). POEMS. 16mo. $1.50. Crow 8vo. $2.00. SAND (GEORGEa). IVAUPRAT. A Novel* Translated by VIRGINIA VAUGHANI. 16ne $1.50. ANTONiA. A Novel. Translated by VIRGINIA VAUGHAN. I6i1of $1.50. MONSIEUR SYVESTRE. bA Novel. Translated by FRANCIS G. SHAW 16mo. $1.50 THE SNOW LMAN. Translated by VIRGINIA VAUGIAN;. 16mo. $1.50 THE I1ILLER OF ANGIBAULT. Translated by M. E. DEWEY. 16mo $1.50. SARGENT (EPES). Ti'HE WOMAN WHO DARED. A Poem. 16nmo. $1.50. PLANCHETTE; or, The DesIpair of Science. Being a full account of Modern Spiritualism. 16mo. $1.25. SCHLEFER (LEOPOLD. TiE LAYMAN'S BREVIARY. 16mo. $225. A Cheaper Edition, $1.50. SCHLLER'S LAY   OF THE BELL.     , Translated by BULWER. The Designs by MORITZ RETZSCH. Oblong 4to. $7.50. SEE^LEY (J. R.). EC:cE Hoio. A Survey of the Life and Work of Jesus Christ. 16mo $1.50. ROMAN IMPERIALISM AND OTHER LECTURES AND ESSAYS. 16mno. $1.50. SEELEY (J. R.) and ABBOTT   (E. A.). ENGLISH LESSONS FOR EXGLISH PEOPLE. 16mo. $1.50. SHAKESPEA RE'S    WORKS. Tle Globe Edition. With all the Poems'and a Glossary. 16mo. $1.75 SHAKESPEARE'S MDSUMMER-NIGHT'S DREAM. With 24 Silhouette Illustrations by P. KONEWKA. lioyal 8vo. $4.00 SHENSTONE (WILLIAM). ESSAYS ON MEN AND MANNERS. 16mo. $1.25. STOWE (HARRIET   BEECH ER). PINK AND WaITE TYRANNY. A Society Novel. Vith Illustrations. 16m0o. $1.50. SWAIN'S (CHARLES) POEMS. 18mo. $1.00. SWETCHNE    (MADAME). "FE AND LETTERS. Edited by COUNT-DE FALLOUX.  TraiSiatet by H. W: PRESTON. 16mO . $1.50 WRITINGS. Edited by COUNT DE FALLOUIX. Translated by H W PRkESTON. 16mo. $1.25. TRENCH (W. S.). REALITIES OF IRISH LIFE. 16mo. $1.00 TYTLER (SARAH). SWEET COUNSEL. A Book for Girls. 18mo. $1.25. WEISS (JOHN). AMERICAN RELIGION. 16mo. $1.50.o YONGE (Miss). 'TRE PriG ' PT:. A 'Tal. of Rondhlh ad Times. 16mo. I 1.00  &#xD;<pb n="166 (Advertisement) -167 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000086"/> GEORGE SAND'S NOVELS. I. MAUPRAT.     Translated by VIRGINIA VAUGHAN. II. ANTONIA.    Translated by VIRGINIA VAUGHAN. 1I. MONSIEUR       SYVESTRE.     Translated  by  FRANCIS GSORGE SHAW. IV. THE   ATL4N OF SNOW. Translated by VIRGINIA VAUGHAN. V. THE MLLER OF ANGIBAULT. Translated by Miss MARY E. DEWrEY.  A standard Library Edition, unifoamnly boutnd, in neat 16tmo volumes, iack volume sold separately. Price $1.50.   t SOME    NOTICES   OF "MAIAUPRAT." ' An admirable translation. As to 'Mauprat, with which novel Io)berts Brothers introduce the first of French novelists to the American public, if there were any doubts as to George Sand's power, it would for ever set them at rest.  . . The object of the story is to show how, by her (Edmee's) noble nature, he (Mauprat) is subsequently transformed from a brute to a man ; his sensual pas- sion to a pure and holy love."- Harper's Monthly. '"The excellence of George Sand, as we understand it, lies in her comprehen- &amp;'^n of the primitive elements of mankind. She has conquered her way into the human heart, and whether it is at peace or at war, is the same to her; for she is mistress of all its moods. No woman before ever painted the passions and the emuotions with such force and fidelity, and with such consummate art. Whatever else she may be, she is always an artist.... Love is the key-note of ' Mauprat,' -love, and what it can accomplish in taming an otherwise untamable spirit. The hero, Bernard llMauprat, grows up with his uncles, who are practically ban dits, as was not uncommon with men of their class, in the provinces, betore the breaking out of the French Revolution. He is a young savage, of whom the best that can be said is, that he is only less wicked than his relatives, because he has somewhere within him a sense of generosity and honor, to which they are entire strangers. To sting this sense into activity, to detect the makings of a man in this brute, to make this brute into a man, is the difficult problem, which is worked out by love,- the love of Bernard for his cousin Edmle, and hers thr him, - the love of two strong, passionate, noble natures, locked in a life-and-death struggle, in which the man is finally overcome by the unconquerable strength of woman- hood. Only a great writer could have described such a struggle, and only a great artist could have kept it within allowable limits. This George Sand has done. we think; for her portrait of Beruard is vigorous without being coarse, and her situ- ations are strong without being dangerous. Such, at-least, is the impression we have received from reading ' Mauprat,' which, besides being an admirable study of character, is also a fine picture of French provincial life and manners." - Put- nam's Alonthly. "Roberts Brothers propose to publish a series of translations of George Sand's better novels. We can hardly say that all are worth appearing In English; but it is certain that the ' better ' list will comprise a good many which are worth translating, and among these is ' Mauprat,' - though by no means the best of them. Written to show the possibility of constancy in man, a love inspired be- fore and continuing through marriage, it is itself a contradiction to a good many of the popular notions respecting the author,-- who is generally supposed to be as indifferent to the sanctities of the marriage relation as was her celebrated an- cestor, Augustus of Saxony.... The translation is admirable. It iD seldom that one reads such good English in a work translated from any language. The new series is inaugurated in the best possible way, under the hands of Miss Vaughan and we trust that she may have a great deal to do with its continuaace. It is not every one who can read French who can write English so well " --01 nrd New Sold everywher   Mailed, postpaid, on receipt of the advertised pree,   ARTHUR HELPS'S WRITINGS. I. AEALMAH. A Story. Price $2.00. 2. CASIMR MAREMMA. A Novel. Price $2.00oo. 3' COMPANIONS OF MY SOLITUDE. Price $1.50. 4. ESSAYS WRITTEN IN THE INTERVALS OF BIUS INESS. Price $1.50- 5. BREVIA. Short Essays and Aphorisms. Price $.50o. 6. CONVERSA'TIONS ON WAR AND GENERAL CUL- TURE. Price $t.5o. 7. THOUGHTS UPON GOVERNMENT. Price $2.25. From the London Review. Tihe tale (REALMAH) is a comparatively brief one, intersected by the conversations of a variety of able personages, with most of whose names and characters we are already familiar through 'Friends in Council.' Looking at it in connection with the social and political lessons that are wrapt up in it, we may fairly attribute to it a higher value than could pos- sibly attach to a common piece of fiction." From a Notice by Miss E. M. Converse. "There are many reasons why we like this irregular book (Realmah), in which we should find the dialogue tedious without the story; the story dull without the dialogue; and the whole unmeaning, unless we discerned the purpose of the author underlying the lines, and interweaving, now here, now there, a criticism, a suggestion, an aphorism, a quaint illustration, an exhortation, a metaphysical deduction, or a moral inference. "We gladly place ' Realmah on the I book-lined wall,' by the side of other chosen friends --the sharp, terse sayings of the I Doctor '; the sug- gestive utterances of the ' Noctes; the sparkling and brilliant thoughts of IMontaigne'; and the gentle teachings of the charming ' Elia.' From a Notice by Miss H. W. Preston. "It must be because the reading world is unregenerate that Arthur Helps is not a general favorite. Somebody once said (was it Ruskin, at whose imperious order so many of us read ' Friends in Council, a dozen years ago?) that appreciation of Helps is a sure test of culture. Not so much that, one may suggest, as of a certain native fineness and excellence of mind. The impression prevails among some of those who do not ser a hir-'-. that Helps is a hard writer. Nothing could be more erroneous. Ilis man- ner is simplicity itself; his speech always winning, and of a silvery dis. tinctness. There are hosts of ravenous readers, lively and capable, who, if their vague prejudice were removed, would exceedingly enjoy the gentle wit, the unassuming wisdom, and the refreshing originality of the. authoi in question. There are men and women, mostly young, with souls trhat sometimes weary of the serials, who need nothing so much as a persuasive guide to the study of worthier and more enduring literature. For most of those who read novels with avidity are capable of reading something else with avidity, if they- only knew it. And such a guide, and pleasantest of all such guides, is Arthur Helps. * * Yet'Casinrir Maremma' is a charming book and, better still, invigorating. Try it. You are going into the country for the summer months that remain. Hlave 'Casimnir' with you, and have ' Realmah,' too, The former is the pleasanter book, the latter the more pow- erful. But if you like one you will like the other. At the least you will rise from their perusal with a grateful sense of having been received for a time into a select and happy circle, where intellectual breeding is perfect, and tile struggle for brilliancy unknown. Q,-1A ....,....r-.h,a  1Toil;rlA ret-n;id nn repor n (* f adver-  &#xD;<pb n="168 (Advertisement) -169 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000087"/> MARGARET. By  SYVESTER   JUDD.    One volume.    Price I.50o. SEI ECTIONS FROM SOME NOTABLE REVIEWS. From the Southern Quarterly Revieiw. "This book, more than any other that we have read, leads us to believe in tht possibility of a distinctive American Literature.... It bears the impress of New England upon all its features. It will be called the Yankee novel, and rightly; for nowhere else have we seen the thought, dialect, and customs of a New England Village, so well and faithfully represented. .... More significant to our mind than ainy book that has yet appeared in our country. To us it seems to be a prophec% of the future. It contemplates the tendencies of American life and character Nowhere else have we seen, so well written out, the very feelings which our rivers aud woods and mountains are calculated to awaken. .... We piedict the time wher Margaret will be ofie of the Antiquary's text-books. It contains a whole magazine tf curious relics and habits. . . . as a record of great ideas and pure sentiments, we place it among the few great books of the age." From the NortAh A serican Rezview. "We know not where any could go to find more exact and pleasing descriptions of the scenery of New England, or of the vegetable and animal forms which give it le. .... As a representation of manners as they were, and in many respects are still, in New England, this book is of great value." From the London Athena um. "This book, though published some time since in America, has only recently become known here by a few stray copies that llave found their wav over. Its leading idea is so well worked out, that, with all its faults of detail, it strikes us as deserving a wider circulation.... lThe book bears the impress of a new country, jond is full of rough, uncivilized. but vigorous life. The leading idea which it seems Intended to expound is, that the surest way to degrade men is to make ihermselves degraded; that so long as that belief does not poison the sources of experience, 'all thinrs'- even the sins, follies, mistakes, so rife among men - can be made ' to work together for good.' This doctrine, startling as it lay sound at first, is wrought out with a fine knowledge of human nature." From the A nti-Slavery Standard. "A remarkable book, with much good common sense in it, full of deep thought pervaded throughout with strong religious feeling, a full conception of the essence of Christianity, a tender compassion for the present condition of man, aid an abiding hope through love of what his destiny nlay be. ... But all who, like"Margaret, ' dream dreams,' and 'see visions,' and look for that time to come when -man shall have 'worked out his own salvation,' and peace shall reign on earth, and good-will to men, will, if they can pardon the faults of the book for its merit, read it with avidity and pleasure." From the Boston Daily Advertt'ser. "T'his is quite a remarkable book, reminding you of Southey's ' Doctor,' per- haps, more than of any other book.... Margaret is a most angelic being, who loves everybody and whom  everybody loves, and whose sweet influence is felt wheiever she appears. She has visions of ideal beauty, and her waking eyes see beauty and joy in every thing." From  the Christian Register. "Tais is a remarkable book. Its scene is laid in New England, and its period some half century ago. Its materials are drawn from the most familiar element* of every-day life. Its merits are so peculiar, and there is so much that is originas Iad rich in its contents, that, sooner or later, it will be appreciated. It is impossi- kle to predict with assurance the fate of a book, but we shall be much mistaker if Margaret does not in due season work its way to a degree of admiration seldom attaWed by a work of its class." Sold   everywhere.   Mailed, prepaid, on   receipt of prgce, by  Ite Publishers,   'TFHOUGHTS ABOUT ART. BY PHLIP GILBERT HAMERTON, Author of "A Painter's Camp." FIRST AMERICAN EDITION. REVISED BY THE AUTHOR. One Vol. i6mo. 400 pages. Price $2.oo., CONTENTS. i. That Certain Artists should write IO. The Reaction from Pre-Raphael- on Art.             itism. a. Painting from Nature.    II. The Painter in His Relation to 3- Painting from Memoranda.     Soci. Picture Buying. 4. The Place of Landscape Painting 2. Picture Buying. amnongst the Fine Arts.   I3. The Housing of National Art 5. The Relation between Photog-   Treasures. raphy and Painting.     14. Fame. 6. Wood Painting and Color Paint- 15. Art Criticism. ing.            16. Proudhon as a Writer on Art. 7. Transcendentalism in Painting. 17. Two Art Philosophers, 8. The Law of Progress in Art. I8. Furniture. 9. Analysis and Synthesis in Paint- i9. The Artistic Spirit. ing. Since The publication of that charming volume, "A Painter's Camp," Mr. Hamerton has published "The Unknown River: An Etcher's Voyage of Discovery," with thirty-seven illustra- tions, etched from nature, by the author. The Unknown River was the Arroux, a tributary of the Loire, and the voyage was peri formed in a boat built by the author, with his dog Tom for his only companion; and the illustrations were etched from na- ture on the way. Nothing can be more delightful than this volume; it is a marvel of artistic interest. "Thoughts about Art" will be mailed, postpaid, to any ad- dress, on receipt of the advertised price, by the publishers, ROBERTS BROTHERS, WETON.  &#xD;<pb n="170 (Advertisement) -171 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000088"/> THE LIFE AND LETTERS OF MADAM] SWETCHNE.    By COUNT DE FALLOUX. 1 vol. 16mo. Pric $1 50. THE WRITINGS OF MADAME SWETCHNE Edited by COUNT DE FALLOUX. 1 vol. 16mo. Price $1 25. MADAME SWETCHNE. BY LUCY LARCOM. A well-written history of an excellent and gifted woman, like the '* Life, al Letters of NMadatme Swetchine," by Count de Falloux, wiil naturally meet with welcome among people of the truest culture. Madame Swetchine was not woman who courted publicityy; but the thread of her life was so interwoven wit the political and religious movements of her time, it was impossible for her escape notice. And it brightens that da;rk period of strife between France an Russia, with which the present century opened, to follow the liU-track of th Russian lady, who seemed to have been equally at home in both countries. She was intimately acquainted with the noblest men and women of that r markable period, and there is not one of them upon whom her friendship does n, cast a beautiful glow. She was one of those rare beings who seem to have been created to draw o0 what is best in'others, by the power of sympathy and self-forgetfulness. She w a woman of uncommon intellect, and of wide reading; and every thing she rea was brought to the standard of a judgment remarkably clear and penetrative indeed, her conversion to the Roman Catholic faith seems to have been mostly matter of the head, - a choice between the Greek and the Roman ecclesiasticisnu Long before her decision was made, her life shows her to have been a humble al earnest Christian; and, as such, as one whose sympathies took wing higher ar wider than the opinions in which she had caged herself, her history has a rare valu One wonders at the amount of good accomplished by her, always a weak i valid. In order to understand how she lived, and what she did, the book must read through; but some extracts might give a hint of it: - "She rarely gave what is called advice,-an absolute solution of a givE problem : her humility made her shrink from direct responsibilities. She did n lecture you. She did not set herself up as a model or guide. She did not sa ' Walk thus; ' but sweetly. ' Let us walk together; ' and so, without making t slightest pretensions, she often gSided those she seemed to follow Young al old acknowledged her sway. She never evoked a sentiment, of rivalry, because 1 one ever detected in her a temptation to win admiration at the expense of other or to eclipse any person whatever. Her disinterestedness won pardon for h ouperiority. "Sick and erring hearts came and revealed themselves to Madame Swetchi in all sincerity; and she shed upon them, sweetly and gradually, light and tru and life. "In her turn she drew from this intimate intercourse, added to her own E quisite penetration, a knowledge of the human heart which amounted almost divination. She knew the science of the soul as physicians know that of the bod "fler charity was not a careless and mechanical practice. She consecrat to it all her strength and all her skill. Almsgiving was not, with her, the m(e fulfilment of a duty. She liked to give pleasure besides doing good, and h heart always added something to what her hand gave." Madame Swetchine lived a little beyond the boundaries of threescore and te It is only ten years since she died. Heaven does not ask to what communion s belonged, neither will posterity. The memory of her saintliness is a possessi to the church universal, in the present and in the future Such a record as he is an inspiration to all who read; such an example, the most imperative " t thou and do likewise." Sold by all booksellers. Mailed, postpaid, by the publishers.   -Aessrs. Roberts     Brothers' Publications. MSS PRESTON'S TRANSLATIONS. MEMOIRS OF MADAME DESBORDES-VAL- MORE.    By the late C. A. SAINTE-BEUVE.      With a Selec- tion from her Poems. One volume. i6mo. Price $I.5o. From the Globe. There was something feminine in Sainte-Beuve's genius, which made him sin- gularly successful in penetrating into the souls of women, - a combination of instinct and insight which few women, perhaps, have shown in the tolerant inter- pretation of each other's souls. ... He called her "'the most courageous, tender, and compassionate of feminine souls, she whom I do not hesitate to call the; Mater Dolorosa of poetry." Miss Preston, the translator of the "Memoirs," is already well known for Iier version of "Portraits de Femmes;" and this second attempt to introduce Sainte-Beuve to a wide circle of American readers promises to be even more popular than the first. From the Chicago Advance. Sainte-Beuve speaks of Madame Valmore as the most courageous, tender, and compassionate of female souls,--whom he does not hesitate to call the Mater Dolorosa of poetry. Early left an orphan by the death of her mother, she sought a livelihood as an actress. But at twenty, she says, her private griefs compelled her to give up singing, "for the sound of my own voice made me weep." So music turned to poetry within her. Possessed of -an exquisite tenderness of spirit, her heart was fitted for the extremes of delight and sadness. As Michelet remarked, she alone among them had the gift of tears. ' Deeply inte'esting as her life is, there was, of course, something morbid about it, -something which this sketchy Memoir does not explain. Such lives cannot be understood without first under- standing intimately the profound unrest and turbulence of French society in those revolutionary times during which her lot was cast. There are just enough points of resemblance between her career and that of the Cary sisters to give interest and instructiveness to the contrasts between them. The translator, Miss Preston, has again shown the fine skill which she has for such work. From Church and State. This volume is but another example of Miss Preston's remarkable ability as a translator. She has already done work in this department of literary effort which entitles her to the cordial thanks of all who appreciate the value of faithful and spirited translations. The work now before us is the record of a life which was rich in qualities appealing to our deepest sympathies. It was an unselfish life, whose tenderness and beauty shone through all vicissitudes, and brightened every dark hour. The story of Madame Desbordes-Valmore is but another illustration of gentleness patiently enduring the hardest shocks of privation and suffering ; of - nobility of nature asserting itself above the trials of poverty and physical pain . . . Of the manner in which this beautiful character has been presented, we cannot speak with too high praise. It is impossible not to recognize the finest qualities of mind and heart in the entire work. Fulness and delicacy of appreciation are united with the finest critical perception. It is a truly admirable biography, and could only have proceeded from a high-minded and rarely gifted man. Sold everywhere.    AMailed, postpaid, by the Publishers, Tf i 1V I o         r-o O TAftN T.  &#xD;<pb n="172 (Advertisement) -173 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7505-00000089"/> fMessrs. Roberts Brothers' Publications. MSS   PRESTON'S   TRANSLATIONS. MREIO. A Provengal Poem. From the Frencl of FREDERIC   MSTRAL.     One volume.    Square  12mo Red line. Price $2.0oo; morocco, $5.50. From the London Spectator. The revival of which M. Frederic Mistral is the most famous representativ recalls more than one episode in the history of literature. Such revivals, -howeve have been for the most part attempts more or less successful to reproduce the styl and thought of a better age in the midst of one that has become degenerate. I ' Mh reio " we see the revival of a language rather than of a literature. It stanc quite apart from any thing that remains to us, or any thing that we know, of the o] rovencal song. Its exquisite freshness and truth, the marvellous clearness alr force with which it pictures the rural life of the South, induced the Parisian critic to exclaim that it was, indeed, autochthon ; that here was a peasant photographir with a minute fidelity which no art could equal the scenes of his daily life. Bu in truth, these qualities are the result of an art that is exquisitely skilful. M. Mi tral is a gentleman who has had the education of a scholar; and his picturesqt and pathetic simplicity, which is, indeed, as effective as any thing that we know  poetry, is a literary attainment of the rarest kind. Of the merits of Miss Preston's volume, considered as a translation, we cann pretend to judge; but it certainly presents us with a very attractive and delightf poem. In the matter of metre she has chosen wisely. The versification of tl original is of a most elaborate kind, which it would be inexpedient, even if it we possible, to reproduce in English. Failing this, Miss Preston has chosen tl heroic verse of that easy fluent kind which Leigh Hunt was accustomed to emplh in his metrical tales, and which has lately been made an almost perfectly harm nious and flexible instrument in the hands of Mr. William Morris. Our translat uses it with great skill, often producing an effect of melodious ease which it wou not be easy to surpass. "M hireio," as we have it in the volume before us, is a distinct addition to tl literature of the English language. Fromz the Worcester Spy (Boston Correspondent). Frederic Mistral's "Mirbio " is a charming, tender, sorrowful love story, ri in descriptions of Provencal scenery, customs, and superstitios s; simple and not in style, delicate in sentiment. The poem excited the greatest enthusiasm France, and was translated in England into prose, and later into verse. It however, almost unknown here, but Miss Preston's translation, which is admirab ought to make the poem popular. W. D. Howells, Esq., discourses lovingly of ' Mireio," in the ," Atlantic.,&amp; I says: '"If any reader of ours is at a loss what to read on the loveliest day in summl let us counsel him to read ' Mireio.' He will be a little sad at the tragical end, E his heart will have been moved by the finest art, and his senses filed with t freshest pictures and with delicious music. ... His poem is full of lit delights, - birds chirping in covert, sun shining, flowers sweetly blowing, - wh the greater song flows on, which the quotation of no single passage can reveal. is, in a word, charming." E. P. Whitfle, in the Boston Globe. Miss Preston has produced a very attractive volume. She has executed laborious task with uncommon skill, and produced a book which everybody v read with pleasure, if everybody can only be induced to read it. It is fluent narrative, attractive in subject, simple, tender, romantic, tragic, and humane.   JMessrs. Roberts     Brothers' Publ      Ications. MSS PRESTON'S TRANSLATIONS. PORTRAITS OF CELEBRATED WOMEN. From  the French of C. A. SAINTE-BEUVE.       One volume. i6mo. Price $I-50. From tihe Universalist Quarterly Review. A book we can cordially recommend to all, but especially to our lady readers. Among other sketches with equal truth and skill ar Madames de Stael, Lafayette, Roland, and Guizot. We have all heard of Madame de Stael and Madame Roland; but few know much of Madame Lafayet   and comparatively 'little is known of Madame Guizot, and others in the list, who ell deserve to be known, Miss Preston has shown good judgment in her selection from the Portraits de Femmes  Her readers will thank her for an introduction to women whose dis- tinguished abilities and virtues, as well as generous culture, make their acquaint- ance as profitable as it is pleasant; and also for the good words with which she prefaces her introduction. From itze Dover MAorzingg Star. M. Sainte-Beuve has rare insight into the female character, which is partly intellectual and partly sympathetic. His apprec ation of what is truly feminine is very hearty, and his sensibility is stirred whenever he stands face to face with a true and noble womanhood; and yet he never loses his critical self-praise through admiration, nor fails to recognize and esteem the strength and active heroism which he deems the proper masculine qualities. He has his strong likes and dislikes; but he sees clearly even when his heart is throbbing with strong emotion, and his sense of justice keeps all his impulses under control when he is at work upon his canvas. With an ability that is rarely equalled, with a taste that instinctively seizes what is fit, and rejects all that is inappropriate, and with a style that combines accuracy, vigor, and an affluent richness, he gives us in these Biographical Essays a volume that deserves a wide circulation, and which will be turned to again and again by thoughtful and cultivated readers. The translator has done her work well, and the publishers have withheld nothing which they could contribute to make an attractive book.  g, Rev. W. R    r Alger, in Ithe Liberal Chrislian. A large number -of the essays of Sainte-Beuve deal with the writings, lives, and characters of the most remarkable women of his country, with many of whom he has himself enjoyed intimate acquaintance, and of all of whom he has been a keen and devoted student, not less generous in his appreciation than capable in his disl criminating insight. Some years ago he collected a volume of these papers and published it, under the title of "Portraits of Celebrated Women." They are among the best of his writin-s in those fine qualities of knowledge, sentiment, and expression, which have secured for him so wide and solid a reputation. Nine of the choicest of these portraits have been carefully transferred into happy English by Miss Harriet W. Preston, and set before the American public in a handsome form by the house of Messrs. Roberts Brothers. We were already indebted to this house for the '"Memoirs and Correspondence of Madame Hecamier,l and the "Life and Letters of Madame Swetchine," two of the most charming, instruc- tive, and exemplary works in modern literature. They have largely added to our obligation by the present work; for no cultivated and aspiring person can read it without delight and edification. Sainte-Beuve has done his work with all the strength and tact and grace of his refined genius. Miss Preston has accomplished her difficult task with uncommon skill, with pervading accuracy and frequent felicity. The publishers have i)ut the book in our hands in a shape at once attrac- tive, convenient, and inexlpensive. It only reimains for the favored reader to do his part, by perusing the volume with the docile and loving attention due to its costly and fascinating contents.  &#xD;<pb n="174 (Advertisement) -175" xml:id="VAC7505-00000090"/> Mressrs. Roberts     Brothers' Publicat'ons. ASPENDALE. By HARRIET W. PRESTON. One volume.   i6mo.  Price $1.25. From the Boston Daily Advertiser. t, Aspendale " is the title of an uncommon and thoroughly pleasing and interest- ing book. It is neither story nor essay; but bright, thoughtful, and suggestive talk about literature and society. By Harriet M'Ewen Kimball. If we may accept as an index of growing popularity the multiplication of quiet, unsensational, thoughtful, discursive, and slightly argumentative books, we may believe the public taste is being regenerated, and hence find unwonted pleasure in commending to readers in general the volume now before us. "Aspendale" has been styled " a story and an essay." After reading it, one makes a mental transpo- sition of those words, - the story being too slight for any other purpose than that of sustaining the dialogues, and the essay too continuous and admirable to give place in importance to the comparatively trivial incidents of the tale. The book opens charmingly. The characters are delicately and clearly drawn, and one cannot but think the "always harmonious"Christine, the gracious centre of the delightful group, is sketched from life. Miss Preston's style is simple. pure, forceful,- leaving the impression not alone of culture and refinement of no ordinary kind or degree, but of a reserved strength and wealth of thought out of which companion volumes may one day escape into print, as we trust they will. 7Aohn G. Saxe, in tkhe Albany oaurnal. "Aspendale," by Harriet W. Preston, has made a decided hit, especially among the literatni as an extremely clever essay, with a slight thread of narrative running through its pages, on many persons and topics very pleasant to read about. . . Miss Preston has a keen and brilliant wit, a good deal of humor, and never makes the mistake (so common with lady satirists) of supposing that coarseness is wit, or scolding satire. Indeed, her judgment, good temper, and good taste are as conspicuous in this charming little book, as her satirical acumen and polished pungency of style. From the Literary World. Perhaps the keenest and most enjoyable chapter in the book is that numbered V. It is one of the most direct and telling assaults on ipractical aristocracy," its representatives and defenders, we ever read. Oliver Wendell Holmes comes in for a scoring, every tingle and smart of which his scientific knowledge of anatomy will, no doubt, help him to appreciate. It has been his habit, as his many adcnir- ers are aware. to sneer at persons of " bucolic antecedents,' and to declare, in mellifluous and witty phrase, that a man with red hands, rude speech, and ill-fitting dress, can never enter into the most desirable heaven, which is reserved for the Brahmins, of whom he, O. W. H., is the High Priest and orator. Miss Preston has ventured to call him to account, and in thirty-odd strong and stinging pages subjects the modern Sir Piercie Shafton to most wholesome dlscipline. . . We should be glad to quote much more of this energetic and dignified rebuke of Boston Brahminism, and especially to reproduce the author's tribute to Abraham Lincoln, - who was not a " gentleman," according to the standard of Dr. Holmes,- one of the finest eulogies ever pronounced upon him; but our limits will not per- mit, and we must close this notice with a simple commendation of "Aspendale," as one of the brightest, freshest, heartiest, and strongest books that have been pub- lished in a long time. Sold everywhere.   Mailed, postpaid, by the Publishers, ROBERTS BROTHERS, BOSTON.    &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>