<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7049">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ashmore, or, The Reclaimed Husband, and Other Tales </title>
            <author>Laughlin, George.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7049</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1513</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ashmore, or, The reclaimed husband, and other tales</title>
                  <author>Laughlin, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mrs. Laughlin by J. Wilson</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1858">1858</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-09-28">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Ashmore, or, The reclaimed husband, and other tales</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7049-00000001"/>ASLMORE; OR,  THE RECLAIMED HUSBAND;  BY GEORGE LAUGHLIN, AUTHOR OP "THE OUTLAW OF MSSISSIPPI,37 ETO. BOSTON: PRINTIED FOR MRS. LAUGTTTTN tY JOHN WILSON AND SON. 1858.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7049-00000002"/>  ASHMORE; OR, THE RECLAIMED HUSBAND. PART I.  AsnMORE was about five and twenty; his wife, but eighteen years old. They had been married some sixteen months, and were blessed with one boy, the darling of his father, the idol of his mother. The husband and wife lived happily together; for their means were ample, their tastes cultivated, and their habits correct. Not an angry word had passed between them since the hour they were joined for life at the altar. Ashmore called his wife a model spouse, and she rewarded him with an attachment that bordered on adoration. She knew hisstep in the hall, and always welcomed him with smiles. Ashmore's friends would rally him occasionally , for his domestic habits, his regular mode of life, and  his strict temperance principles. One of thq; in particular, named Obre, who was very fond afood Oteod, *f  v           '  *.*  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7049-00000003"/> 6        ASHMORE; living, used to ridicule him without mercy at every opportunity. Lucy disliked this Obre: she dreaded the effect of his keen, polished, satire on the rather  sensitive mind of her husband; and she feared he might some day be the means of goading Ashmore into the vortex of that " gay world of fashion" for which she felt an utter aversion. The husband and wife were sitting together one winter night. Ashmore was reading aloud to Lucy, while she fondled her boy with all a mother's endear- ments. The door-bell rang; and presently a tall, graceful young man entered the room with the air ' of an old friend. "Missis Ashmore, I have the honor to salute you," . said he, bowing with easy elegance, as he addressed the lady: your husband should be the happiest of men;" and he smiled a winning smile. d "And so he is, Obre," said Horace in a tone of earnest animation; i" the very happiest of men, my ", Delighted to hear it, indeed," was the quiet re- joinder ut d'ye know, Ashmore, I would not like to be such- a very close housekeeper?" and he smiled again. Ashmore moved uneasily in his chair. "You know, oir dispositions are very different," s bd he. "Without doubt," retorted Obre: "they are in- deed. I am fond of variety, while you can only  , exist in an atmosphere of perpetual bliss." He glanced at Lucy, as these words escaped him; but - *       I  t    OR, THE RECLAIAMRED HUSBAND.    7 she looked grave, and did not seem to notice the compliment conveyed in his last remark. "Jny news?" asked Horace, anxious to change the subject. "Yes, stirring news. I've just come for you to, accompany me to the club-rooms, and decide a heavy bet in my favor." "How can I decide it?" "Easily enough. I staked a pretty decent little sum with Wilson, that you would drink a couple of glasses of champagne with us to-night at Morri- son's." "Indeed!" said Horace, evidently mortified at the information. "O ciary dear fellow! don't be alarmed. Why, one would suppose I had pledged you to drink prussic acid, instead of a glass of champagne." "You kpow my husband's aversion to wine and to-all. intoxicating drinks," said Lucy with studied politeness. Obre's smile was fascination itself. His manners were so easy and self-assured, and his tone so light, yet respectful, that it was next to impossible to be angry with him, and sit in his presence.  "Intoxicating drinks!" exclaimed he with affected horror: " why, I loathe all such myself; but cham- pagne is merely an agreeable beverage: 'twill not. hurt a child." "Any kind of wine is hurtful," persisted Mrs. Ashmore. *       . X   &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7049-00000004"/> 8         ASHMEORE; . "Doubtless it is; but two glasses ca ot injure any one," returned Obre. "What is the amount o- yur bet?" inquired Ashmore. "Only five thousand," was the careless reply. Mrs. Ashmore became uneasy, and her husband looked vexed. "How, in the name of common sense, could you be so thoughtless, Obre?" said Ashmore. "Thoughtless!" rejoined the incorrigible man of fashion: , 'tis an easy way to win five thousand;" and the bland smile played more blandly round his mouth. "If your bet depends on my drinking that wine, you'll lose to a certainty," said Ashmore. A sweet look from his wife assured Horace how much she was gratified by his wrds. But Obre   heeded not this by-play.  "You won't win for me, then?" said He.  / "Sorry you should lose your money; but, in this instance, I cannot help it." "What'! and you'll suffer me to lose this sum for the paltry matter of drinking two glasses of cham- pagne! Nobodywill believe it." "Then let e   erpody doubt it, and they will have their doubts for their pains." "You are resolute, then?"? "I am, indeed," said Horace., For the first time since he enteredthe room, Obre looked grave. %   OR, THE RECLATMtD HUSBAND.     9 "But, Ashmore," said he, "I need this money very much to pay a certain amount I owe to young Chesney.  "Better let Chesney wait." "But he threatens pains and-penalties." "Let him threaten." "put, to be frank with you, I cannot pay this five thousand, if I am to lose it." Ashmore looked irresolute. His wife approached him, and, winding her arms round his waist, said, "Dear Horace, do -not go." "But Obre will be dishonored, Lucy: think of that."  "Oh, pay the money, Horace; pay the money, and do not touch the wine!" The wife said this imploringly. "'Tis a debt of honor, ma'am," said Obre in a tone of wounded pride, -"- a debt of honor, which I alone must pay;" and he rose to depart. "O Mr. Obre! withdraw your bet," urged Mrs. Alhmore. "Impossible!" returned Obre, as he moved to- wards the door. Ashmore paced the floor with rapid steps. "Don't go, for a moment, Obre," said he, stopping abruptly before him. " You must suffer me to pay this mo- ney for you at present." Not a stiver, sir," said Obre haughtily. "No, no. If you will not drink two. glasses of harmless wine to save a friend five thousand dollars, then, sir,  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7049-00000005"/> 10        . ASH MORE; all I can say is, that your friendship is not very sincere." Saying which, he hastily withdrew. The husband and wife regarded each other, for a few minutes, without speaking. At length, Mrs. Ashmore ventured timidly to observe, What do you mean to do, husbatnd?" Why, to say the truth, Lucy, I begin to think that Obre is partly right in what h&amp; last said. It does seem a little absurd, that my friend should lose five thousand dollars for the matter of my drinking two glasses of wine. True, I would rather pay the money; but Qbre would shrink from me as he did but now at the mere attempt to do so. Besides, dear, five thousand dollars seem a considerable sum to throw away for nothing; and we owe a duty to our child to be careful of our means." "Ah, Horace! the best way to fulfil such duty is for the father to preserve his virtue.'" The husband started to his feet, while a flush of indignation suffused his manly features. "I trust, Mrs. Ashmore,". said he somewhat bit- terly, " that my principles are" not so very loose as to be uprooted by indulging in a glass of wine. You should have known me better by this time. But I now distinctly declare to you, that I am resolved to see the issue of this affair, for a twofold purpose: first to save my friend's money; and next to regain your good opinion, which, it would seem, I have somehow forfeited." He spoke thus with irritation and impetuosity,   OR, THE RECLAIMED HUSBAND.     " and, seizing his hat, dashed out of the apartment; leaving his wife bewildered for a time with surprise and grief. PART II The "Sporting Club " held its meetings in a mag- nificent saloon, furnished in splendid style, and illuminated by myriads of lights that Blazed from two large chandeliers. Newspapers, sporting maga- zines, and periodicals of various kinds, were strewed promiscuously on numerous tables. The walls were decorated with paintings and engravings of dogs, horses, deer, &amp;c.; while here and there, at inter- vals, were placed trophies of the chase from different parts of the country. Obre was a favotite w all the members of the club; for he was generous (f his money, fearless to bet, and prompt to pay. He could also tell a good story, sing an excellent song, and was a prime judge of horse-flesh. His powers of ridicule, too, were generally dreaded. They were known to be great; and men conciliated what they could not combat with any chance of success.' And so it happened, that when Obre entered the club-room, shortly after his inter-, view with Ashmore, on the night we speak of, he was greeted with general cordiality. It chanced to be a full meeting; and the saloon was crowded with members. Some were talking, some laughing, some  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7049-00000006"/> 12        ASHMORE; smoking, and all enjoying themselves with uncom- mon relish. They were mostly yqung men of leisure, possessed of the means to make time pass merrily, and fond of pleasure for the excitement it brought. Any bet out of the ordinary course was sure to excite general interest. So, when Obre returned from Ashmore's, hi was hailed with accla- mation; and they crowded round him to learn the success of his mission. "Will he toe the mark?" demanded one. "Ay, will he come to the scratch?" said an- other. "Did you unkennel the animal?" asked a third. "What's the chance for my bet?" inquired a fourth. "Have you sprung your game?" shouted a fifth. And so they went on, overwhelming him with questions of a like nature; to all of which Obre made no reply, but, coolly lighting a cigar, seated himself without ceremony, and smoked with apparent com- posure. The buzz of many voices still continued; but shortly there was a general pause, then an exclamation of surprise from some one, then a hur- ried whispering, and the eyes of all the members were directed to the door. Obre sprang to his feet, and, looking in the same direction, beheld, to his great surprise, no less a person than his friend Horace Ashmore, slowly advancing to the centre of the saloon.   OR, THE RECLA TMEDn HUSBAND.    13 "Is it possible!" said Obre to himself. "Why, this exceeds belief." Then aloud to Horace, "This way, Ashmore! -this way, my friend! Bravo! Hurrah! I knew you wouldn't let me lose!" Bravo!" echoed the crowd of members, as the two friends shook hands, and exchanged a few words in an undertone\ Obre raised his hand to enjoin silence; and, when the noise ceased, Ashmore spoke:- "I've come, gentlemen," said he, "to relieve my friend from an unpleasant position, but not with any intention of joining your club, as most of you would seem to imagine." This announcement created some sensation; and there were shouts of "Go it, Ashmore ;" Be one of us;" "Join us, old fellow;'" "No sneaking;" &amp;c., &amp;c. Then one of the members said, "Let's have no preaching;" then another member shouted, "Sup- pr waits!" and presently there was a general rush a long table, laid out with'a delicious supper, wines, &amp;c. Ashmore and Ober were borne along by the rush, till they found themselves at the table. "Come, take 'a seat, Horace," said Obre good- humoredly.  Here's a rare supper, my boy." Ashmore hesitated, but at length felt ashamed of his scruples, and seated himself at table with the rest. Then supper was discussed right cheerily. The laugh and jest went round. Humorous anec- dotes, funny stories, smart sayings, ludicrous jests, were the order of the night. Ao t \'  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7049-00000007"/> " ASHMORE; "A glass of wine with you, Ashmore," .said the E. President, from the head of the table; and instantly all eyes were bent on the guest. He filled his glass with a fikm hand, nodded to the President, and drank it off at once. The ice was fairly broken; and, although Ashmore did not that night exceed the two glasses he was pledged to drink, yet the ice was broken. *  t PThe secod  ART IrL The second anniversary of the night on which her Jhusband decided that bet for Obre closed upon Lucy Ashmore, and found her wretched. She held her boy convulsively to her breast, and rocked him to and fro with a low, sad song, that came from a breast sur- charged with bitter feelings. Two years of suffering had seamed her fair brow, paled her cheek, and dimmed the lustre of her large blue eye. Her whole appearance denoted suffering, - patient, voiceless suffering; suffering calmly expected, meekly endured, piously braved. The. poverty that now surrounded her in her bleak abode was stern proof of the volume of suffering through which the once affluent wife must have waded to her present wretched state. One by one, each cherished article of furniture or of brna- ment had been quietly surrendered to find fuel to feed the remorseless flame that consumed her infa-   OR, THE RECLATMED HUSBAND.     15 tuated husband,- the gnawing thirst for wine that possessed him like a demon. Lands, houses, fur- niture, ornaments, dress, - every thing, in short, that could be turned to money, - had been sacrificed to this hideous demon of thirst; and still it craved more wines Property, domestic comfort, self-respect, health, happiness, had all been sacrificed at the altar of this accursed fiend, and yet it was not satisfied. More wine, more wine, more wine! Yes, the man possessed by this demon must have more wine, though wife and child should perish. Wife and child!- what were these to him, compared with wine? Alas! there was a time, and that but twos brief years ago, when they were much, all, every thing; when they were his sum of life, -the world in which he lived, moved, breathed, and had his being. Wife! - she was the planet round which he had revolved continually. Child! - it was the mag- / net that had attracted him to the mother with love irresistible. Yet this planet, this magnet, were now obscured by a demon in purple, commonly known by the name of wine. Oh, how Lucy execrated the fiend, as she sang sad songs to her child, and counted the weary hours of the bitter winter night, awaiting her husband's return! She thought of the hundreds and the thousands of widows and of orphans intemperance had made; of the oceans of tears it had caused to flow; of the millions of sighs it had wrung from many an aching breast; of the murders it had prompted; of the deadly quarrels it had e  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7049-00000008"/> 16    '    ASHMORE; engendered; of the property'it had destroyed; of the hopes it had crushed; -of the joys it had blasted; of the mountain of human hearts it must have broken in its mad career. She thought- of all this, and shuddered when she reflected that her hus- band was in the gripe of this demon. Twelve o'clock hadestruck, and Ashmore was still absent. One o'clock came; yet he came not. Her child slept soundly;' and, as she drew her torn shawl more closely round it, a scalding tear fell on the little face. "Poor thing!" murmured the mother, now nearly exhausted with hunger, cold, and want of rest. She leaned her tead against the damp wall behind her chair, and graually sleep overpowered her. Yes, she slept; and soon she smiled in her forlorn sleep. Ay, the wretched mother smiled; for. He who "tempers the wind to the shorn lamb" beheld the suffering of His desolate child, and delighted the lulled senses with an enchanting dream. The mother wasiteaming of her youthful days, when she gathered flowers with her playmates, -- all artless, happy girls, in the spring-time of life. Then she thought she had grown to be a woman, and was walking along a rough, uneven, thorny road, where (here were many quagmires and pitfalls. Then she thought a frightful monster sprang from one of these pitfalls, and pursued her with great speed for some distance. At length, after toiling up a steep, rocky, thorny hill, she turned, and beheld the monster in the agonies of death, inflicted by a   OR, THE RECLAIMED HUSBAND.     17 slender youth, who held in his hand a bloody spear. The youth soon stood by her side, on the summit of the hill, and, pointing with his spear to the country before them, said, "Behold your route: go on in safety;" and suddenly disappeared. She s1dwly pursued her way; and the, road she now travelled was beautiful exceedingly. Rare flowers of every hue adorned the edges of the path, and filled the air with delicious odors. Plants, shrubs, and trees, of exquisite foliage, were grouped here and there through the glittering green fields; and swarms of birds, with golden plumage, poured forth floods of melody such as her ears had never heard before. She. beheld people moving through those fields, all happy and joyous, and radiant with delight. They looked at her as she passed, and smiled sweet smiles of welcome; but, further than this, they heeded her not. She went on, and on, and on, over ths path that led through these fields; and, as she advanced, the country seemed to increase in beauty, her steps seemed lighter, and a sense of ineffable happiness seemed to possess her. She beheld afar a gorgeous temple, surrounded by a great multitude of people; add to that temple she perceived the path led. Her approach to the temple was slow; for it was still a great way off: but at length she drew near enough to distinguish over the portals, in enormous letters of gold, the word TRUTH. She was getting yet nearer to the temple, when her dream was rudely broken by a fierce noise at the door 2  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7049-00000009"/> ASHMORE; of her humble abode. Startingvildly from her chair, she gazed round her for a moment with the delight- ful imagery of the dream still fresh on her mind; and, seizing a lamp from a rude chair, she hastily opened the street door. A bloated, fiery-eyed man, with dishevelled hair, rushed past her, swearing a dreadful oath, and ordered her to follow him quickly. She did so; and there, in the chair from which she had taken the lamp, was Horace Ashmore. Wine had made sad havoc with his fine, manly form. He was but the wreck of his former self; and now, as he sat before his wife, staring wildly at "her, and heaping frightful curses on her head, there seemed a glaring, unnatural excitement in his look, that foreshadowed madness. And he was mad indeed. "Wine " he hiccoughed. "I have not a drop," said the meekewife. " Liar! liar!" roared the drunkard, striking fiercely at her he had sworn to protect, to love, and to cherish. "Wine, I say!" thundered the baffled toper, aiming another blow at the helpless wife. She avoided it, and tried to soothe him; but her efforts only increased his rage. "Wine, I say! wine! wine!" yelled the mad- man, seizing the chair from which he had risen in- his excitement, and violently hurling it at Lucy with all his remaining strength. Luckily she avoided the missile, and again approached her husband fofr the purpose of soothing him, but was arrested by his looks. He glared wildly at her\for a moment,   like a tiger about to spring on its prey; then, throw- ing up his arms wildly in the air, he fell senseless at her feet. PART IV. Many weeks passed, and Ashmore lay on a sick- bed. He was slowly recovering from a dreadful fever, that had nearly carried him off. "Lucy," murmured the invalid, turning feebly on his pillow, " come hither. Give me something to wet my lips." The fond wife speedily administered some sooth- ing liquid; and the lick man regarded her with looks of powerful gratitude. "Lucy," said he, "if I am destined to rise in health from this fevered couch, you will find me an altered man, and you shall yet be the happiest of women." The wife's eyes glittered with delight; and the husband went on:  "Ah! there is nothing like a sick-bed for re- pentance. Surely, surely,' God loveth whom he chasteneth.' Alas! dear wife, what a villain I have been to you 1 but you shall see, you shall see, how the-remainder of my life will repay you. You haye borne with me beyond human endurance; and, during my weary days and nights of sickness, you have been-to me as a ministering angel." &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7049-00000010"/> 20        ASHMORE. "Upbraid not yourself, my husband: you knew not what you did. But your words of hope cheer me exceedingly, and assure me that we shall yet see happy days." "Do not doubt it, Lucy." "I do not. My hopes are great indeed." PART V. And Lucy's hopes were realized.  Ashmore recovered, and became an altered man. He abjured the wine-cup, an4 applied himself so diligently to work, that, in the course of three years from the period of his recovery, he and his faithful wife were surrounded with every worldly comfort. "We owe all this to you, Lucy,-all to you,?' Ashmore would often say to his -wife. "But for your angelic patience, I had been a lost man." And they gradually became rich. All enter- prises prospered with Ashmore; wealth flowed upon him; and he applied both time and money in the cause of temperance. "Avoid the wine-cup!" was his constant advice to young men,--" avoid the wine-cup, and be temperate; for temperance is the way to wealth, to health, and to all earthly hap. piness." ,   21 THE STrUDENT'S LAST OFFEtIING. "Our sincerest laughter With some pain is fraught; Our sweetest songs are those that tell of saddest thought." IN a splendid apartment of a splendid mansion, the abode of a merchant-prince, three persons were seated one night in autumn. They were mother, son, and daughter. The mother, an engaging ma- tronly lady, was occupied with some fancy needle- work. The daughter, a rare flower of exquisite beauty, was intently examining some choice engrav- ings. The son, a fine, manly, intelligent young man, was cutting the leaves of a magazine, fresh from the hands of the publisher. This is a touching group, mamma," said Emily, "so faithfully grouped round the deathbed of Wash- ington." "I was only a girl then," returned the mother, - "a very little girl; but I can well remember the universal feeling of sadness that pervaded the entire  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7049-00000011"/> 22   THE STUDENT'S LAST OFYifERING. community.  Truly, that was a deathbed. The New World then lost the spirit of its great deliverer, which soared upward to a better. Hero, sage, and statesman,-- the great hand of Time may trace many cycles o'er the dial, ere America shall behold another Washington." "I don't wonder you revere his character so much, mamma, it was so good." "Yes, it was unselfishness itself. His glorious maxim was, All for my country; nothing for my- self.'"             .  : "His'principles were godlike, mamma," rejoined Emily, turning over the engraving to examine an- other: "lofty and noble they were.  But here is such a Cupid! - such a dear, bewitching little fel- low.  What a roguish pair of eyes! What a mouth! Do, mamma, just look at this mischievous young imp;" and kte animated girl glided to the matron's side, engraving in hand, to share her delight with her fond parent. "Ha, ha, ha!" laughed the son, who had opened his magazine meanwhile, and perused nearly a page of a humorous article .that tickled his fancy im- mensely; " ha, ha, ha! there's a witty fellow, --- a right merry fellow indeed; ha, ha, ha!'" The mother and daughter looked up; while the son read a few more sentences, and, throwing him- ,self back in his chair, burst out afresh into irrepres- sible laughter. "You must have found something very interest-   4 THE STUDENT'S LAST OFFERING.   23 ing, Charles," said the mother, regarding her son with a quiet smile. "I'm sure it's very witty," observed the young lady, stealing softly to her brother's chair, and glan- cinfg over his shoulder; "let me see it, Charles;" and, quickly scanning the first paragraph, she also indulged in a merry laugh. "It's excellent, very excellent," said Emily, taking up the magazine. "It's the richest story I've read in an age," added Charles. "What a fund of wit that writer must have! - a perfect fund of wit;" and he laughed again. "You seem in very good humor here," said a stout gentleman of middle age, quietly closing the door behind him, and taking a seat near the table at which his son and daughter were occupied with the magazine. "O papa! there's such a laughable story in this magazine," exclaimed Emily; "Charles is so amused with it." "Let. me see the title," said papa, in whose fea- tures benevolence and a profound knowledge of human nature were admirably blended. He looked at the name of the article, read a few sentences, and the habitual smile that lighted up his agreeable fea- tures gave place to an air of sober gravity. The son and daughter were surprised at this; for their papa could relish genuine wit with unalloyed plea- sure. Papa read a few sentences more, and his air became yet more grave. He closed the magazine,  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7049-00000012"/> 24   THE -STUDENT'S LAST OFFERINGO and, handing it to his son, earnestly remarked, in the tone of a man familiar with every word the article contained, "Read it to the end, my son; and, when iyou get through, I will relate to you its his- tory: for it has a history, and that, too, at singular variance with its tone and spirit, so mirthful and so spirit-stirring as you think them." "It has a history, papa?" eagerly inquired the young lady, with all a young lady's pardonable curiosity in her speaking eyes.  "It has a history, then?" chimed in Charles, who inherited enough of Eve's blood to develop in him an inquisitive propensity. O It has a history," affirmed papa, taking from his pocket some letters, and breaking the seals; " a his- tory that I will relate to you when you have read the article, and not before." "And not before?" queried Emily. "Not before," repeated papa, unfolding his letters, and beginning to peruse one. The sister seated herself beside the brother, and together they perused the article with &amp;deep atten- tion; pausing now and then to indulge in uncontrol- lable mirth, and a few brief comments on the spar- kling wit of the author. At length they reached the conclusion, just as papa had concluded reading his last letter; and, turning to him, they cheerfully reminded him of his promise. "What think you of the writer?" said papa, ad-  dressing both his children.   THE STUDENT'S LAST OFFERING.    25 "Inimitable," rejoined Emily. "A man of talent, in whom the humorous evi- dently predominates," added Charles. "You think so. Then listen; and, when you have heard me through, let this simple history lead you to beware of judging from appearances: for, most assuredly, all is not gold that glitters." Papa put away his letters, and then related to his children the following short history of a story: - ,' Edward Staunton returned from college at the age of nineteen, a delicate, thoughtful youth, grave for his years, and highly educated. He was the only son of his mother; and she was a widow. He had a sister, - an only sister, - a bright, fair-haired creature of remarkable intelligence. His father had been dead for many years; and the slender income he had left was exhausted in educating Ed- ward: for the mother doated on her boy-; and she would stint herself and her daughter of all but the barest necessaries of life to have him qualified for an honorable profession. He was the apple of her eye, the pride of her widowed heart. She loved to falk of him to his sister, when he was absent at college, and to console herself with the reflection that his talents would yet procure honor and fame to himself, and a comfortable home for them all. She suffered, and pinched and stinted herself, beyond credibility, to supply him with the means of com- b pleting his studies,- how much she pinched and  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7049-00000013"/> 26   THE STUDENT'S LAST OFFERING. stinted herself, I care not to tell; and, when he returned to his humble home in the suburbs of a great city, he found that home cold and cheerless, and bare of every thing that can make a home com- fortable,--of nearly all but his mother's and his sister's affectionate embraces. "How he chewed the bitter cud of thought as his sharp eye: scanned the attenuated forms and worn garments of his mother and his sister; the damp, unfinished walls of their two narrow rooms, so scant of furniture, and so chill for lack of fuel; the struggle to preserve appearances; and the war with the giant grasp of Want, so apparent in all that he beheld! And Want was there indeed. There he was, in that high-souled student's home, slowly in- twining his hideous arms around those forms so dearly beloved; for they had not a morsel of bread to offer the son and brother, those meek-eyed, gentle sufferers. Needlework was their only means of support; had been their sole means of support for weary days and weeks and months, -needlework, so tedious to do, and so poor to pay; needlework that dims the sight, chills the blood, wastes the form, pales the cheek, seams the brow, sears the brain, hacks the chest; needlework that makes 'flesh and blood so cheap.' They could barely gain bread by unremitting toil, that consumed half the dreary hours of night: but they bore up patiently, and murmured not; for their faith in Providence yss firm as adamant, and they looked forward, with   THE STUDENTSS LAST OFFERING.    27 trusting heart, to the return of the absent one, hoping, wishing, believing, that he would soon find means to lift them from blighting penury. Hope, the sustainer, had buoyed them through many a weary night and day; had nerved them to conceal the real state of affairs from Edward; had raised their drooping spirits, and helped them to bear with calm resignation - 'The oppressor's wrong, the proud man's contumely, The insolence of office, and the spurns That patient merit of the unworthy takes.' "Thus far had Hope buoyed, nerved, and helped them to endure, till the absent one's return; and, now that he had returned, the gaunt visage of Want frowned on him from his mother's hearth- stone. 'Twas a bleak prospect for one so young and gifted; but it must be faced,-manfully and daringly faced, resisted, attacked, and overcome. 'Want is a fierce foe to grapple with,--a mighty, terrible, scathing foe, whose breath is baneful, whose touch is withering, whose presence is all-corroding. 'A mortal enemy to soul and body, muttered Ed- ward, glancing round the dreary walls, 'that I must banish from this abode.' The youth had some loose change left of his scanty store; and this served to supply them with bread for tilat night and a few more days. Meantime, he took possession of the cold sleeping-apartment that adjoined his mother's room of all work; and there he sat hour by hour,  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7049-00000014"/> 28   TH 8TUDENT'S LAST O. O'KtluG. and day by day, forming plans for the future, and studying how he should most effectively work to aid his mother and sister. He little knew how that mother and sister had noted his worn cheek, that flushed at intervals; his sunken eye and wasted form; and how painfully to their ears cam sound of the hollow, ominous, relentless couglhthat heralds consumption. He thought not of himself: he only thought of them, and of any feasible means by which he could support them. At length, he thought of the press; and, accordingly, he began an elaborate article for a magazine. Summoning to" his aid all his scholastic attainments, he spent three days and nights in polishing and perfecting, for pub- lication, his production. He worked eagerly, ear- nestly, and hopefully. -He had a vague idea that the article must bring him a good price: for he poured, without stint, the rich treasures of his cul tivated mind into its pages; and, in all the confi- dence of unhackneyed youth, he expected an ade- quate return. With a light ieart, he crossed his mother's threshold to carry his first offering to the press. With a heavy heart and drooping spirits, he repassed that threshold an hour after his de- parture, and, moodily flinging his hat on a table, shut himself up in his room alone. His sister en- tered, and sought to rouse him; but the only answer she could get to her kind, soothing questions was conveyed in the simple word 'rejected.' She left him, and returned to condole with her mother. * \ W   THE STUDENT'S LAST OFFERING.    29 "Too learned for our columns, and too long,' muttered the student in bitterness of spirit; and, sweeping the bare walls of his room with glaring eyes, he recollected that those dependent on him for support had not another day's sustenance, nor the means wherewith to buy. The visage of Want scowled on him from the wall, and urged him, goaded him, maddened him, into action. He seized a pen, and, fiercely ejaculating, 'I will try again!' braced himself afresh for his task. "*Days and nights wore away (six of them had vanished adown the dark vista of time), and the second article was not yet finished. 'I was in too much of a hurry with the first,' said Edward to himself, musingly. 'Perhaps that was the secret of its failure. I'll be more careful with this.' And he conned and weighed every word and every sen- tence with the anxiety of a diplomatist. But, while he conned and weighed, he did not notice, what mother and sister did, that his worn cheek grew more worn, his sunken eye more sunken, and his hollow 1cough more ominous. They had noticed this with bitter sorrow, and sought, by entreaty, to dissuade him from writing: but he calmly heard their remonstrances; and, eating abstractedly of the slender fare they placed before him, won by the weary needle, he only answered, 'Mother, we must emerge from the gripe of Want; we must indeed.' How rapidly he was gliding from the fangs of all want that is earthly, he, poor fellow! never dreamed.  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7049-00000015"/> 30   THE STUDENT'S LAST OlFFlRING. Singular fatality of consumption, that soothes its victims ever and always with hope and healthful years in the dim perspective! "At length, the second offering is ready for the press. He wends his weary way to the autocrat of types; and, submitting his production, is desired to leave it, and call in two days. Homeward he takes his weary way again; and the two ensuing days are passed in a state of nervous irritation, of alternate fear and hope, doubt and delight, hard to endure, harder to portray. The third morning dawns, lightens, deepens bright, clear, and blue. How anxiously he marked it dawn, lighten, and deepen! Eight o'clock struck; but that was too soon for his purpose: he would wait till nine. The hour wore away. Nine chimed lively and loud from a neigh- boring church-tower; and, taking his hat, he bent his steps, feebly enough, to the printing-office. He entered the room of the owner, and found him alone. He was recognized, his article drawn from a small pile of others, and quietly returned to him. The heart in his breast thumped against its bars, for a few seconds, as if it would burst, and presently felt to him heavy as lead. A cold dew broke out on his forehead; and, grasping a chair, he would have fallen, but for the owner,-a humane man, deeply absorbed in his trade, -who supported him to a seat, and begged him to rest for a few minutes. "' Your production has merit, sir,' said the owner soothingly,-' undoubted merit; but it lacks spirit. I           9   THE STUDENT S IAST OFFERING.   31 'Tis hardly lively enough for our pages. A little more vivacity, a few dashes of humor, and I would readily have purchased it. Be of good cheer. Try your hand again. Practice is indispensable to make a taking writer for the press.' "'That was it!' exclaimed Edward, eagerly start- ing up. -'You want a humorous article, sir. Will you purchase such an article, if I write one that will please you?' i "'Most willingly, and give you its utmost value,' said the humane publisher, glancing at the worn garments and sharp features of the youthful candi- date with an eye of deep interest. ' Bring it soon, and it shall appear in our next issue, hGadded in a tone of touching kindness.  "Blessed Hope! mysterious sustainer! gift most infinite! bravely didst thou bear up the mind of the feeble youth that night inhis cold, lonely room, and fill his brain with all manner of quaint fancies and mirthful conceits. Wondrous Hope! that canst heal the seared thoughts as by magic, and, in their stead, fill the vexed mind with teeming oddities and laughter-moving spells; drawing from sorrow, from misery, from suffering deep and unutterable, their most potent antidotes, - mirth and fantastic humor. Edward would think and write by turns, patiently; and, in those intervals, his eyes wandered round the bare walls of his chilly room, from whence the gaunt visage of Want had scowled at him before. It did not scowl now: it grinned and winked and mimicked,  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7049-00000016"/> 32-   THE STUDE*T'S LAST OFFERING. and flitted about; he thought; taking all manner of strange, uncouth shapes, and encouraging him by its grimaces to proceed with his work of wit. He felt a strong desire to continue. He was just in the mood for humorous writing. He would turn the mood to account, and, if possible, finish his article before morning. What he bad already written was much to his mind; 'twas, he thought, very laughable: he would therefore continue, and try to conclude before day. The room was bitter cold; but he cared not for that. His light was dim; but there was enough of it to last till day. His cough troubled him; but he only dreaded the noise troubling his mother and sister. They, fond creatures! had retired to rest two hours before, weary of entreating him to desist from a task that had tried his health so powerfully. He felt an irresistible desire to proceed; and pro- ceed he did. Hour after hour glided by, and sheet after sheet of his mirth-moving article passed per- fect from his wasted hand. Twelve o'clock struck, and found him full of rare conceits, which he traced on his paper with a rapidity or excelled by his thoughts. -One sounded solemnly, heavily, on the cold night-air. He dropped his pen, and surveyed with delighted eyes the fruits of his labor. The room seemed colder than usual: he shrugged his shoulders, and thought 'twas fancy. The cough hacked his feeble lungs with unpleasant severity; but he thought not of the cough. The visage on the wall grinned more merrily, add urged him to finish   THE STUDENT'S LAST OFFERING.   33 o his task. Conceits more quaint and strange than any he had yet known, now rioted through his brain with preternatural intensity, - inducing profound mirth, and wreathing his wasted features in ghastly smiles. Two o'clock clanged from the church-tower hard by, and the energy of the writer seemed abat- ing. His hand moved more slowly over the paper; his thoughts were less intense; his fancies were fading; and he sustained the spirit of his article only by great mental effort. Leaning back in his chair, overcome with lassitude, he surveyed the pile of sheets with a sigh; and, muttering, '-Only a little longer, and 'tis done,' he shortly resumed his pen and his task. Three o'clock boomed sullenly over the quiet city, and the work of the worn youth was ended. The feeble hand traced the last line, laid down the pen, and fell heavily by the side. The eyes, sunken and hollow, wandered round the bare walls for a few minutes, and then rested on the pile of manuscript. The head sank back against the chair in an attitude of repose. A sad smile played round the mouth, and the brow was damp with per- spiration. "And thus they found him a few hours later, the mother and the sister, when they entered with his scanty breakfast, - stark, rigid, and lifeless, staring at his last offering on earth in the body; while the spirit, having glided from the want that is earthly, had soared up to heaven with the angels. Such, my children," added papa with deep feeling,- 3  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7049-00000017"/> 34   THE STUDENT'S LAST OFFERING. "such is the history of the article that has amused you so keenly. It abounds in strokes of irresistible humor; but the writer is no longer of the living." "And how did you learn this history, papa?" urged Emily in a subdued voice.  "From the, mother and the daughter," was the answer. "The rooms they occupied were rented of my agent, who was about to eject them for non- payment of rent, when I, passing by accident ;inter- fered, and restored the widow and her child to their shelter." "'God will bless you for that, dear papa," said Emily, rising up, and kissing him fervently. "The proceeds of the article," continued papa, "have provided them with a few comforts, which I have increased; and recollect, Emily," added the benevolent gentleman, laying his hand tenderly on rich tresses of his daughter's head, --" recollect that they are henceforth under my care and yours; and yours, Emily," he repeated with gentle em- phasis.  ' "Be it so, papa. They shall be well cared for, the forlorn ones. I'll visit them to-morrow, without fail." And she did; and the benevolent daughter of that benevolent merchant has been, and is, a firm friend to the widow and the fatherless. ^ * t.6   35 WRITING FOR BREAD. "Dimuise. it as thou wilt, still, still, Poverty! thou art a bitter draught." STERBNE. DICK SENSITIVEo sat weary and desponding in the rickety attic of a rickety house in a back street of London, one dismal December day, in the year 1840. The air was very keen, and so was Dick's appetite: he -had not tasted food for forty-eight hours. Reader! permit us to inquire, in the most delicate manner imaginable, if you have ever known the pangs of protracted hunger. If you answer in the nega- tive, then we sincerely hope, were your years to reach a thousand, ydu may never feel yourself in a position to realize such unspeakable agony; but if, by rare accident, you have been enabled to reply in the affirmative, then we are satisfied that you can feel for Dick Sensitive. His eyes were wolfish, positively wolfish; and an occasional sharp, spasmodic twitch of his mouth denoted an'eager desire to scrape immediate ac- quaintance with a beefsteak. There are worse things in the world for an empty stomach than a tender beefsteA, done to a turn, and  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7049-00000018"/> 36      WRITING FOR BREAD. flanked by a creamy pot of porter. In Dick's opi- nion, there were very few better; and he felt, that if, by any sudden freak of fortune, he were to become master of such a treasure, he would not exchange it for its weight in gold. 4 He was wrong, theli decidedly wrong, as any man conversant with the rates of exchange could have informed him; for although gold is slightly indigesti- ble, slightly unpalatable, and moreover a trifle diffi- cult to cook, yet it is said to be (" all-powerful," and will buy a beefsteak: one! ay, dozens, tens, hun- dreds, thousands, millions of dozens, if you only have it. a There's the rub:" if you only have it. But Dick was poor. His treacherous memory was un- able to fix the precise date when his sole remaining sovereign was transformed into shillings and pence; his pockets were ignorant of silver for a week past; and two days had elapsed, two weary, tedious days, 'since he parted with his last copper to a kitchen-boy for a mouldy bone. And now, as he sat in his bare attic, pinched with cold, starving, and scant of rai- ment, he prayed for the possession of a single shil- ling, that he might stifle the vulture in his entrails. A paltry shilling, but twelve pence sterling, was the entire extent of his present ambitious desires. It would give him ease, animation, life; but how was he to get it? The question has puzzled, is still puzzling, and to the end of time will continue to puzzle, the brains of many men, with ten times the intellect of Dick Sen-   WRITING FOR BREAD.      87 sitive. .He leaned back, in his-keleton of a chair, to try and solve it. A variety of vague and indefinite thoughts flitted through his mind for a time; but the ignorant, cun- ning, selfish image of his landlady would be upper- most. The insolent demeanor with which she had threatened, but an hour ago, to " show him the door,' was positively torturing to his constitutional suscep- tibility. What was he to do? The gloomy, sullen surge of old Thames, as it fell on his ear, whispered a remedy, - a final remedy, speedy, yet sure; short, yet wicked. But Dick was a Christian, and banished the temptation with a prayer. He thought of work, any kind of drudgery, the meanest; then he thought of the brutal livery-stable owner, who had thrust him forth that morning, after an hour of arduous trial, because his hands were so tender; then he surveyed those soft, slender, wasted hands, and sighed. "The spirit, indeed, was willing; but the flesh -was weak." Here a fierce, sudden, blustering, whistling gust of wind rustled the old attic windows as if in mock- ery of human misery, and roused him once more. He glanced at' the wintry sky without, and all at once recollected that Christmas would be on the morrow. He thought of the merry, happy time he used to spend at Christmas, in the home of his boyhood, long ago, when his gallant father, and tender mother,  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7049-00000019"/> s8     WRITING FOR BREAD; and dear sister, were all the world to him. He thought of that gallant father and tender mother now in the dust, - of that dear sister lost to him for ever. A choking sensation rose in his throat; a single hot, blistering tear fell on his cheek; another and another followed; then, as a pent torrent, "the windows of his soul" opened, and he wept like a child. Powerful mental emotion is, for the most part, transient; and well for us it is so. , Dick's grief was intense while it lasted, and therefore soon at an end. A sudden twinge of the stomach contributed to shor- ten it. The gastric juice is somewhat imperative, and may not be neglected with impunity. Dick started to his feet, and paced his narrow attic with one abrupt step, while his tortured feelings found vent in bitter soliloquy. "Were I only a drayman, a hodman, a dustman, a coalheaver, a, sweep,-- any thing, in short, but the poverty-stricken son of a gentleman! It is hor- rible. Surely, there is something I might do to avoid actual starvation.", He paused, and gazed thoughtfully for a moment ,on the floor; then rubbing his forehead, like one who has made a sudden discovery, he elevateid his ;arm, and exclaimed, "I have it at last, Yes, let me try if I cannot write for my bread." No one can say but this idea seemed both reasona- ble and feasible; but, like many others, it was more easily conceived than put into practice. It was at   WRITING EOR BREAD.      39 least worthy of a trial, and likely to prove a more agreeable experiment than a plunge into the Thames. Dick was decidedly of this opinion: so he set about the execution of his project with wonderful alacrity for a man indulging in the pleasant luxury of a forty- eight hour's fast. From the skeleton of a consumptive trunk he produced a stumpy pen and a crumpled leaf of paper; then, seating himself once more on his frail chair, he prepared for a plunge into prose. Ten, fifteen, twenty, thirty minutes had elapsed, and his paper was yet unstained by ink: he was intently debating with himself as to the choice of a subject. But his worried thoughts were not to be dragooned into a decision: like Owen Glendower's spirit in the vasty deep, they " would not come when he did call for them." At length his wandering glance is arrested by a patient spider " spinning still, and still for ever spin- ning," his tiny web. 'He watches the unwearied insect for a moment; and his memory reverts to the magic effect produced by a similar sight on the drooping spirits of an imprisoned Scottish king. Properly handled, that historical incident might afford material for a sheet of judicious reflections on the necessity of perseverance in adversity. He has some thought of choosing that incident for his subject: lhis pen -is in the ink, - when a Boisterous, jaw-breaking, ear-splitting laugh is heard from an adjoining attic.   &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7049-00000020"/> 40      WRITING FOR BREAD. Dick dropped his remnant of a gray goose-quill, and wondered who on earth could be the author of such uproarious merriment. It was so reckless, so jovial, so very loud, that he felt satisfied the happy mortal, whoever he might be, was not likely to die of consumption. Neither did it seem that he was much afflicted with the trouble of this wicked world. Care, -if any he had, seemed to sit lightly on his heart, and still more lightly on his lungs. He must have dined too; for no man in his senses would undertake su!ch a laugh on an empty stomach. This contrast between his own desponding mood and the hilarity of his unknown neighbor had the effect of changing the current of Dick's thoughts entirely. He concluded to permit the incident of Bruce and the Spider to remain quietly in the page of'the Scottish historian, and instantly resolved to( write a chapter on LAUGHTER. He would anatomize and describe the various sorts of laughter in modern use, with their different effects on different individuals; anc, after a few flourishes about the general benefit to be derived from this delightful amusement, he would go on to treat of each particular kind of laugh known to hu- manity ; beginning with the chronic, and ending with the laugh that apes humility. The short, dry, sententious laugh of purse-proud arrogance; the inflated, preposterous chuckle of self- conceit;, the Confident, swaggering grin of commer- cial hypocrisy; and the smooth, oily, demure sneer   WRITING FOR BREAD.      41 of religious fanaticism-- these he would dismiss with a brief sentence or two. But the laugh which he would dwell upon in an especial manner, and point out as the one most worthy of being practised, is the pure, righteous, open, holy smile that adorns the face of him whose heart is warmed by the springs of benevolence. The result of this kind of laughter, he thought, if it were. only to become fashionable, might be a speedy improvement in the condition of the whole human race. Having thus arranged the plan of his subject in his mind, he proceeded to commit the details to pa- per; and, after an infinite number of blots, scratches, and interlinings, he succeeded in producing an arti- cle that would have been pronounced, in these days, "fairish for an amateur." When it was finished, he nervously folded the manuscript, and prepared to find a purchaser. Buttoning up his thin, threadbare frock-coat, he snatched from the floor what had once been a hat, and, with head erect and step elate, hurriedly descended to the street. As the door closed behind him, his ear was saluted by the remainder of a blasphemous prayer from the lips of his virago of a landlady, to the effect that she " might never set eyes on his miserable phiz again." He heeded it not, but quickly took his way through the dreary streAes. Night had fallen upon the huae city, and wrapped it in a gloomy mantle; the stars were obscured by piles of ugly, black, ominous clouds; a cold, sharp,  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7049-00000021"/> 42     WRITING FOR BREAD. drizzling sleet was whirled in the teeth of the lick- less wayfarer, and cut against his face like a shower of needles. Dick felt it keenly as he threaded his way; but his spirit was buoyed by hope. After an arduous walk, he reached the shop of an extensive publisher, and, with palpitating heart and tremulous hand, drew forth his manuscript, and ten- dered it to a middle-aged, shrewd-looking, spectacled individual, who was busily employed in piling away a heap of magazines fresh from the press. This person scrutinized Dick's appearance for a moment; then pointed to the manuscript, ancsharply inquired, - "What's that?" "An article, sir, that I wish to sell to some of the publishers," was the meek reply. "Take it elsewhere; I have no time to read trash." Dick thrust it into his pocket with a sigh, mut- tered something about being needy, and was about to leave the shop, when a well-dressed, pale-faced young man - who had been turning over the leaves of some periodicals, and was an attentive witness to this brief interview-laid a hand on Dick's shoul- der, and, in a voice of singular sweetness, requested a sight of the manuscript. In a second, Dick's face brightened; in two more, the stranger was attentively perusing his production. A slight mixture of surprise and pleasure became visible in his countenance as lie proceeded; and an o   [ . WRITING FOR BREAD.      43 occasional glance, directed at Dick, showed that he was interested. Slowly folding the manuscript, when he got to the end, he thrust five sovereigns and his card into Dick's hand. Telling him that he would be happy to see him again, he bowed, and, passing to the door, entered a cab, and drove rapidly away; while the wondering Dick stood rooted to the spot, amazed, delighted, stupefied, and completely bewil- dered by his good fortune. S       f  % C  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7049-00000022"/> " THE DREAMER. "While we look not at the things which are seen, but at the things which are not seen; for the things which are seen are temporal, butlthe 1\ things which are not seen are eternal."   ST. PAUL. "DOES Childhood love rich domes above, Or painted walls around P - Will marble floors arouse the step - That falls with lightest bound? Ah, no! ah, no! it is not so: The fair child goes To tread on tiny daisies, Where the green blade grows. Can Manhood's heart so strangely part With all that's fresh and true, That Care leaves not a loop-hole spot For Spirit to lodk through? Ah, no! ah, no! it is not so: 4  , His heart still glows When some old haunt he traces Where the green blade grows. We wane away, till, bent and gray, We creep where once we ran; And Age lies down, and ends his race, Where Boyhood's race began. 'Tis there we sleep where daisies peep, And sunset throws The promise of a morrow Where the green blade grows."    THE DREAMER.         45 And thus, where the mallow was fringing the shallow, The Poet One sung to the summer-lit stream; And then he grew dizzy with watching how busy The swallows were chasing the gnats in the beam. Then the minnow-tribe swimming, the lotus-cup brimming, Had charms for his fancy, and lured him to stay, Till One, wiser and colder, -a richer and bolder Among the world's denizens, - broke on his way. , What! still idle, thou dreamer, thou bubble-blown sche- mer! Still useless on earth?" cried the sneer-darkened lip: * Can that mortal inherit a shadow of merit, Who lives out the day seeing willow-leaves dip? You aid not in felling the wood for man's dwelling, t You twine not a thread for his doublet and vest, You've no sheaves for the binding, no mill for the grind- ing, No tool in the hand, and no corselet on breast! No vessel is riding that owneth thy guiding, Thou help'st not to fashion the hull nor the mast; You've no forge for her chain-gear, no loom for her main- gear, No ball in the battle, no rope in the blast! Thou art not a master of forest or pasture, Thy name is unknown in the commerce of gold; You've no dappled herds lowing, no purple grapes grow- ing; -58  No, stock have you bought, and no land have you sold!  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7049-00000023"/> "        THEE DREAMER. You delve not for fuel, you polish no jewel, You pave not the city, you plough not the sward; You help not a neighbor with sweat-drop of labor, - What right CANST thou have at Humanity's board? Where's the profit in -mounting the copse-hill, and count- ing The stars and the glow-worms that glimmer around P Why, why, dost thou wander where brooklets meander, And listen as though there were speech in the sound P What lore are you gleaning, while silently leaning O'er Spring's simple snowdrop and Autumn's dead leaf? Why waste your strong powers 'mid green sod and flowers, When wealth is so mighty, and life is' so brief P? Up, man, and be doing: no longer be wooing The smiles of the moonlight, and song of the bird: Muse no more on the motion of cloud, scud, and ocean; But mix where the hum of the Active is heard. Is it fair he should fatten and revel and batten, Who ' draweth no water,' and ' heweth no wood'? Shame, shame, to thee, dreamer! thou bubble-blown schemer! Thy presence among us here cannot be good." The dreamer replied not, he smiled not, he sighed not; A red brow was all that betokened his pride: But, while he was flushing, a Spirit came rushing In radiant glory, and stood by his side. "Look up, thou Rebuker! hard son of hard lucre!" The Immortal One cried, as the chiding One bent:   THE DREAMER.           47 "ris time thou wert learning, that he thou art spurning Is here with great mission and sacred intent. He was formed by the Maker a favored partaker    r Of all man can know of the Essence Divine: God sent him forth singing, like alchemist flinging A drop in the crude mass to melt and refine. Your barn-mows o'erflowing, your furnace-flames glowing, Your freights on the sea, and your stores on the land,- Oh! there's fear in the pleasure that springs from such treasure; For the heart is too apt to grow hard as the hand. The Creator, all-seeing, knew well that each being * Had strings of choice melody hid in his breast, Whose music, the clearest, the purest, the dearest, Could stir to wild gladness, or lull to sweet rest. Tis the music revealing Truth, Nature, and Feeling; But strings of such texture had soon gathered rust, If they met with no finger, about them to linger, To tune the rich soul-chords, and sweep off the dust. The loud chafing action of Gold, Toil, and Faction, Had drowned the fine echo from Heaven now heard, If no minstrel were\ straying among ye, and playing On notes that will only respond to his word. The strains he is chanting will set your souls panting With impulse of Freedom, and yearning of Love; The song that he teaches has magic that reaches Your brightest of earth-chains, and links them above. $  &#xD;<pb n="48" xml:id="VAC7049-00000024"/> 48        THE DREAMER. Ye are proud of the pine-tree, the oak, and the vine-tree ; The rose on your bush, and the fruit on your wall: But, say, would ye shut out the fresh wind, or put out The sun, bringing perfume and beauty from all P As the fresh wind that hummeth, the Poet One cometh, To stir into health the dense world-ridden brain: As that sun paints the blossom, he tinges your bosom With colors that shame all its clay-gathered stain. The charm in his keeping can comfort the weeping, - Can soften the rugged, and strengthen the weak: He wins with devotion, man's noblest emotion, And telleth the things that none other can speak. While thou art fulfilling, with sowing and tilling, The portion of duty God chose to assign, This One is intrusted with talents, adjusted To render his office far higher than thine. The power he holdeth, the scroll he unfoldeth, Your utmost of striving will fail to obtain: God's rarest bequeathing but lives in his breathing, And think'st thou such gift was allotted in vain? Go, go, thou Rebuker! hard son of hard lucre! Let the dreaming One rove as he list on the sward; And tremble, ye Toilers, ye Spirit-despoilers, When the Poet is thrust from Humanity's board!" 9)^      ELIZA COOK. t    1 O I f I i   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
