<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7907">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Dell Dart, or, Within the Meshes </title>
            <author >Steele, Rowena Granice.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7907</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Dell Dart, or, Within the meshes</title>
                  <author >Steele, Rowena Granice.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >69 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >San Joaquin Valley Argus Office</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Merced </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1874">1874</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-05-04">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Dell Dart, or, Within the meshes</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7907-00000001"/>DELL DART OR WITHIN THE MESHES.  WRITTEN BY Rowena Granice Steele,  AUTHOR OF "THE FAMLY GEM," "VICTIMS OF FATE," "EONNIE ST. JAMES," ' BLUE-EYED MARY.," AND OTHER STORIES.   MERCED, PRINTED AT THE SAN JOAQUIN VALLEY ARGUS OFFICE, 1874. &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7907-00000002"/>   THE AUTHOR'S PREFACe:  refate f ' Have yb the prettsd rFthdv , pleasahtly; areleasly suggests the publisher, A preface I oh, y t l Id rather Undertake td write tefl books with a, hoptef o 5s than to write 'on  pYeface. It Is .sd  emthrraming       . wkward. Introducing one's self and (one's brain-work 'rtiticisifii public and It eritieq(sing ntihd ali-pwerful  . in-'haile tVan praise the wel;lfnishstd artt(!le s f hi.  work withtht   speenmint egotistical. Th  ttrajmer ear rf the fdn? ptrodurt of his labor witHodut thtlng (gosid; c:- btaggadCld'i. The merchant can, ladd his fabrics intl and all clalfba of mert handli j it fl his prerogantivP O;R 'ht. The rlater'sailor, Withtiltt btlah or foitr of belng      . ;td with .elf ,oneeit, spekak  pltfudly of- rhe hPaht.' hit )td   of his ship. tiUt the works; hf the divine, tho      - iah, the mait or. woman of legal ability, and the ; mntlt .xpeak fir them selves. tow vpety ailll ift  sound for ah author to .q:. 1 , ttl ntr. ai.. rki in,.l;  !  . '.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7907-00000003"/>                     0 PREFACE.                  f( cannot be beat! It's a first-rate boolk, and no mistake! I  wrote it myself and ought to know!" No, a book must tell of its own merits or demerits. So with the little story I now offer to my patrons. I have not aimed at anything above or beyond my humble ability. I have endeavored to speak to the hearts of my readers in simple and truthful language. From my earliest childhood my sympathies have gone out for the unfortunate. Some of my 'high-toned" friends have been very much shocked and have even cut my acquaintance on account of the interest I have taken in the unfortunates. It may be a weakness, but it is one, never- theless, for which I thank God. Many of the old residents of California will doubtle s recognize my heroine--DELL DART. The story being founded entirely upon facts of course the names of the hero and heroine have been changed. The man known to the reader as Cheeney Dart, was a member of the California Legishture somewhere between the years of '54 and '64. He is dead now. Peace to his ashes! With these disconnected, preliminary remarks, I leave the reader to peruse the history of Dell Dart, the victim of the meshes. Yours Respectfully, ROWENA GRANICE STFErFE.   DELL DART;  ITHN THE ME SHES. o : Stept in so far, that should I wade no more, . Returning were as tedious as go o'er."            8 TILL fresh in my memory lingers the scenes of that clear, bright morning. The 15th of April, 18-, was one of Sacramento's most delightful days. It was one of the beautiful, tree- shaded, vine-clad, rose-creeping, sun-beaming, sha- dow-dancing, air-perfumed, "City of the Plain's" rosiest, briahtest and clearest. Birds sang with- out, and busy dames and  smiling, rosy-cheeked maidens sang snatches of sweet songs as they flit- ted about from room to room, putting things to rights. Those were the days of dainty, little parlors, not too good for general use.  Well! perhaps, every parlor was not just what the little parlors of N street were in those days. Perhaps in the big house a little way up the street, now occupied by the rich and great Governor Stanford, then owned and occupied by Mr. and Mrs. F., the original build- ers and owners, there might-have been in that ele- gant structure a room or two which were thrown &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7907-00000004"/> G)   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. open upon extra occasions. But most of the little parlors in that neighborhood opened out upon the front porch, and through the green blind doors the shadows of the branches and leaves of the trees and vines came in and leaped ahd capered about among the bright colors of the carpet, and peeped coquettishy in and out among the lace cur- tains, each fantastic leaper bringing in a puff of fragrance from the millions of roses climbing over the neighboring cottages, and scattering the sweets mingled with the fresh, bracing air into every nook and corner of the well-swept, well-dusted house- holds. I love to dwell upon the beauties of that paftic- ular morning, not that the story which I am about to relate has anything to do with the pleasant thoughts which reveled in my heart on that occae sion. No! The pleasant feelings were all my own as I stood upon the upper piazza gathering a bo, quet. My thoughts were busy with my first tri- umph in my literary attempts. Say whet you ill, great writers, you know that no after tri- ilmphs, no world-spread fame, haas ever brought brck that nervous, self-admiration With ivhich you viewed your first effort ih print. 'Tis like the feeling of a mother toward her firstsborn is that. first child of the brain. It is such a shy., modest pride! A pride that would blush at its own dail' ing. A pride hid awaky down in the heart. "Well, what has your pleasant emotions aln that particular morning to do with the victim who has been so ,unfortunate as to get entangled ill the ineshes?" whispers an inquisitive little elf. "Nothing ; I only wanted to say that I *as {i a\ very pleasant franme of mind and sort of half in love with myself and everybody and everything around me. One don't have tnany such gold tintz ed, heart-satisfied moments in life, and they Are Worth cherishing. Thev help to lighten the dark-   DELL DART ; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.  7 er, heavier burdens of our checkered lives. 'Now I will endeavor to confine myself entirely to the story. While standing there with a large boquet of roses in one hand and a glittering piece of golden coin in the other (the latter the reward of my first literary effort), dust-pan, dust-brush and broom un- der either arm, head pinned up in a towel, white wrappericonsiderable soiled, feet encased in odd slippers one of carpet the other a more dainty kid with bow and buckle, I started down the stairs singing at the top of my voice in my loudest if not clearest strain : "Yes, I would-like to marry, if I could only find Somue handsome, gay, young fellow-" That last word "fellow " brought me to the foot of the stairs, and face to face with as handsome a man as I had ever met. I felt like exclaiming, "Goodness gracious!"' half in apology for my un- tidy appearance, and half in amazement at the audacity of the man presenting himself so uncere- moniously into my presence. I was really so much confused that I never could recollect exactly what I did say but his polite and gentlemanly apology of "Madam, I beg your pardon for this intrusion," and the sad, almost tearful tones-in which the words were spoken disarmed me of all feelings of resentment. :Something in his pale, thoughtful  face--oh, it was more than thoughtful; it was anxious, troubled, care-marked-awakened a feel- ing of sympathy in my heart for this stranger. I threw open the little parlor door and said : "Please to wa;lk in and take a seat." Then laying down broom, dustpan and duster, dropping the coin in my pocket and disposing of the boquet, removing the towel from my head, I took a seat, and even in my earnestness to learn my visitor's business, T did not forget to put the best odd slipper foremost.  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7907-00000005"/> 8   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESIES. For a moment or two silence reigned in the lit- tle pallor. The man was evidently preparing to say as pleasant as possible something very un- pleasaont and disagreeable, and I was preparing my ear to hear and my heart to respond in sympathy: and thereby help to lighten the load which his face too plainly betokened was weighing upon his heart. "Dear madam," he began, "I hope you will for- give an entire stranger for thus intruding himself upon you. You, I believe, are the lady who wrote the domestic story which appeared in the ' Golden Era' of last week?" I replied by giving him my name. "Well, madam," he continued ; "if you write the true sentiments of your heart I am led to, be- lieve that you look with kindness and charity up- on the unfortunate. That you would not cast- off or spurn a sister woman who, although she had erred, had not fallen into the deepest, lowest deg- radation." None but the most cowardly or heartless would do so," I replied; '"I look upon an erring sister just as I do upon an erring brother, husband, fath- er, or son. All are deserving of our sympathy- if they have erred either from lack of strength of mind to resist temptation or through force of cir- cumstances. It is most certainly the duty, of the strong to stand by the- weak; then h0w cow- ardly, how contemptible it is, as we journey on through this. sin and temptatioiTbestrewqd path of life, to trample upon one of GQod', qrea- tures-one of our sisters or brothers-.-w'hose moral strength has failed. Who, ove romne by; thhe wily "iant, has sunk down by the wiaytideaQyerpo.-rpgd by the monster who is. constantly stalking abrod bedimming the brightest places and blighlting tie kindest, purest and dearest of the wQ ther-,hqat darlings.   DELL DART; OR, WITHIN TE MESHE S. I often wonder why the poor victims of the arts and snares of man should be held any more re. sponsible for wreck and ruin than the ship-wrecked mariner. He knows that there is danger lurking in the deep and yet, with a defiant air of bravery, he launches his friail bark and braves the angry waves, and if he is ship-wrecked tears of sympathy are shed, regrets expressed on every side. But, if the fair maiden all joyously launches her tiny bark upon the beautifil, smooth sea of love, and man in his devilishness sees fit in his manly strength and lordly rights to lure her out into the angry breakers with smooth words and honied caresses, and then deprives her of all means of returning or regaining what she has lost, the cry goes up, "Shun her, and make her feel that- &amp;' The dark grave, Which knows all secrets, can alone reclaim, The fatal doubt once cast on womnan's name." "Madam," said the stranger, " you speak warm- ly and earnestly in defense of woman, and truth- fully, too, I must confess; and, I believe that as near as you possibly could you would act out. your sentiments. I will no longer keep vou in suspense as to the nature of my business. You are an en- tire stranger to me. I am in trouble-deep heart trouble.  I never heard your name in my life un- til I read that little, touching story a week ago. I asked a friend if he knew you, he said he was slightly acquainted with you and mentioned your plae of residence, little thinking at the time that I should ever have occasion to test the truth of the sentiments expressed in the little story. I come to ask a  favor-ah! more, to ask you to make a sacrifice; and, with all of my confidence in you, I will not feel surprised at a refusal. I may feel bitterly disappointed, but not angry or surprised, for I feel that you can conscienciously ask to be excused from making the sacrifice without marring 2  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7907-00000006"/> 10   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. your true sentimelnts of charity or the natural im- pulses of your heart." After clearing his throat, he continued : "I have a sister fair and beautiful. I wish to place her under the protection of some lady for' the: present. We are orphans, without a relative on. earth, and in trouble of such a nature that for my sister's sake I wish to keep it a profound secret, I do not want her to suspect that I have even mentioned the word trouble to a stranger. If it is ever told she will be the one who will whisper the first. syllable. I understand that you are living here with your children as your only companions, Will'you take my sister for awhile--take her' as a companion?  She is thoroughly educated in all the English branches- and a splendid musician; gentle and amiable in disposition, she will require the kindest treatment; she may have whims and caprices that I know nothing of. She may also at times become very low spirited and act strange and Unnatural, or she may need a little excitenment, Whatever she wishes or desires, if money will sup- ply the demand she shall not lack that. I know that I am asking more than a favor; I am asking a sacrifice, and although I am most anxious that you should say yes, should you decline I will try and bear the disappointment and look further."' "Do you think that your sister is deranged'?" 1 "asked. The question appeared to startle and embarrass him for he arose from his seat and walked' twice around the room before answering me. I looked up into his face, large tears were streaming from his eyes. "Sit down," I said, " and excuse me for asking sly strange and abrupt a question." "' I do not blame you," he said; "perhaps my sister is a little insane." The tone, in which the words were spoker   DELL DART ; OR, WITHN THE '.':EHES.   "   sounded as though a new idea had been awakened by my interrogation, and a sort of sad,. pleasart, but very faint, smile crossed his colntenance, while he continued : "Poor girl! She has gone through enough to wreck her brain; still she is very mild and pleas- ant and at times appears cheerful. She may pos- sibly tell yTou her history-- mean the cause of' her sorrow. At present it must not be spoken of; and I would rather that she wou-la be treated as though her only sorrow or cause of sadness wa s occasioned by the death of our mnother, and her lonelv condi- tion as an orphan. - I must leave the city to be absent for an indefinite period, perh aps a month or more. Are you willing to take her with this mystery which holds the unfortunate past,?" I am perfectly willing to. do so," I said. ' I think that, I fully understand the case, and fortu- :nately I am not very inquisitive, and rather enjoy a mystery, and always prefer watching develop- ments to hearing facts." This I said in Ia light tone of voice as a reassur- ance of the trust he might place in my' knowing how to treat his sister; for, to tell the truth, I had just enough romance and love of mystery in my composition to make me anxious to enter upon the duty of taking charge of this singular girl. "Well," said he, "now that, you have so kindly consented to take charge of my  poor sister, there is another important point -to be discuseed. Oh, by the by," he exclaimed, laughing, "I had entire- ly forgotten to mention our names.  My name  is Cheeney Dart, my  sister's is Dell Dart; and the important point I spoke of is that she has no ladies' clothing." I  thought the word " ladies" superfluous and could not help smiling. He looked a little puzzled and said: "I  mean that she has lost her clothing. She is  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7907-00000007"/> "  DELL DART ; OR, WITIN THE MESMB5. entirely destitute of a single-article to make a change, and I would like for you, if not too much trouble, to go to some store where ready made clothing can be obtained and select such as will do for present use. Here is the length of her skirt and the size of her waist." I stood a moment thinking how strange that he had not asked me to go to his sister, and was about to say something to that effect. He seemed to understand my thoughts and said : ,' Remember, this is a mystery! Please do not question me." I took the measures and said : ,( Excuse me bfor a moment." I ran up the steps which led to my bedroom, and in a few moments was convinced that Dell Dart could manage to wear any article of clothing within the humble limits of my wardrobe. "A little stouter," I soliloquized ; "but this wrapper will be just the thing." I went on selecting one article after another un- til I came to boots and gloves. There is always an uncertainty about the size of the hands and feet of one whom you have never seen. A small woman may wear a number five, while a large, fleshy, well-developed woman may require but a number two. So with the hands. Well, I had everything except boots, gloves and hat. I had not forgotten a dainty, perfumed pocket-handkerchief, collars, cuffs, and even pins, hair-pins and ribbon. I then returned to the par- lor and said: "I have everything required for present use, except boots, gloves and hat." "( You will please get a thick veil," said Mr. Dart, handing me a purse of money. "What sized boots does your sister wear?"I asked. , Number four," was the answer. "If you will    DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MURSTRS. 13 have everything ready," he continued, "I will call just in the dusk of the evening for them, and in about an hour after I will bring my sister. Should you have company is there a back door through which we can pass unobserved '!" "I seldom have company, and what few friends I entertain take no of:ence at being told by me that I am engaged. They know that many hours of the time are not my own. I want no, visitors who are not friends, and I want no friends who do not take interest enough in me to allow me to go on with my business during my business hours. Should any of these true friends call they would take no umbrage at my telling them that I should be engaged. So, although I shall give your sister a room up stairs. she will not necessarily be' con- fined to any part of my little house. I have no trifling, inquisitive callers, and know no more of my neighbors next door or opposite than I used to in the city of New York. That is the way I was brought up, and the old associations of youth cling to me still. Come with your sister at just what- ever time suits you and I will be here prepared to receive you." With a polite bow Mr. Dart left me. I walked back into the little parlor, took a seat in a rocking chair and began to ruminate over the strange scene which had transpired within the last half hour. Had my natural love for adventure led me into something which might get me en- tangled-draw me into difficulties from which it would be impossible to extricate myself without injury. I had already borne as much of life's trials as any one woman ought to have to bear. Had I blindly plunged deeper. Too late for such reflections! Anrd the eafme voice which had so often before and has since during my life whispered mysteriously in my heart, "Falter not in your life mission! Lift the fallen, cheer the unifbrtunatel  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7907-00000008"/> "  DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MER;SHES. fLet the world mi sjudge your motives, but faint not 'by the way. There is a hand, although it may- lead you through dark, winding, uncertain by- ways, will bring you out to the beautiful golden light at last." And these dreamy, heart-cherishing, spirit-whis- perings threw a kind of nimbus-like circle before my visionary dreams of evil, which dispelled the- oppressive thoughts of doubt, and sweet Charity resumed her seat in my ehlrt. I felt an almost child-like restlessness for the time to come when I could extend my hand to the unfortunate girl. I will not attempt to deny the truth that I found myself fifty times during that day wonder, ing at the strangeness of the afi-air; and what seemed most strange of all was the fact of her ihaving no clothing. So very queer, to use a quaint expression, that he did not mention how she lost her clothing!  At this suggestion a horrible thought darted into my mind: Could she have escaped from some asylum, or worse, from prison? I was getting nervous; yes, very nervous. I recollected that he had said she did not use hair- 'pins; but that was nothing, half of the fashiona- ble ladies at that time wore their hair short, and to drive away these suspicious misgivings I began to sing and busy myself about the house. During the afternoon I went out and purchased the necessary articles, and just at sun-setting Mr. Dart came and took themn away, saying he would return with his sister in about an hour. As soon as the evening meal was over I put the children to bed, drew the curtains down, closed the, green blind doors, lit the lamp, and then of the mysterious sat down to await the coming of the mysterious visitors. I was not long kept in- waiting. Pres- ently I heard footsteps on the porch, then a light tap upon the door. "Walk in," I said.   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MEESi'. 1 The door opened. I arose and advanced, and Mr. Dart said: "This is my sister, Dell, Mrs. ." The vouni girl threw aside her veil. Rich clus- ters of gold-brown silken rings hung in wavy brightness upon her fair forehead. She extetided: her hand and grasped mine within her own soft palm, and said, while the tears glistened in her eyes: "Can I kiss you?" "The kiss went tingling to my heart.'" This question was asked in such a sweet, earnest, half-doubtful, childish manner that I mentally ex- claimed ; "Too sweet! too pure for corruption or depravity, either by nature or association." There was at that. moment a1 feeling which many, I doubt not have felt, which none can truly des- cribe-a reaching away down into my mother, child-loving, heart-and as the beautiful head rest- ed for a moment upon my bosom    tear mingled- with tear. Then recollecting that my work Was to cheer her I said-  "Sit down upon the sofa, Miss Dell, and let me take -your things; I want you to feel perfectly at home here with me.   Your-brother tells me that you are a musician; I have no instrument, but I was informed to-day by a  lady friend that there was one to let somewhere in town.  A lady who is going home to the States for a few months would, be glad to rent it cheap to any one who will take good care of it, If you make up your mind to have one I will attend to it to-morrow." "'Certainly," said Mr. Dart "Dell must have- the piano, if only to keep in practice." "When do you leave town, Mr. Dart?"I' en- quired, as he was about to take his departur. ' "Day after to-morrow." he answered.  I  will not tire the reader's patience by relating the minute details of all that occurred 4uring- lthe  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7907-00000009"/> 16   DELL DART ; OR, WITHN THE MRSIlP'. first week of Dell's residence with me. Nothing that she said or did gave me the least clue where- by I could begin to unravel the thread to the strange mystery. That she was a sweet, beauti- ful. loving, warm-hearted girl, and just as sane as any human being in the world were facts beyond a doubt. For two weeks we bought and cut and made garment after garment, without the slight- est hint of what became of her former wardrobe. Not one article of clothing save that which I had sent to her ever came into my house except those we had made up. She played and sang charmingly; conversed fluently upon many subjects, but never referred to the past or to any person, place or thing beyond her school days. She had read "extensively and she usually conversed upon something connected with school or characters of which she had read. Never mentioned coming to California-when she came, or how she came. Her brother had left orders at a livery stable in the city to let her have a carriage or saddle horse just when she asked or sent for them, and we rode out two or three times a week. She sewed, and read, and copied for me, and frequently insisted upon doing the kitchen work. She wopld some- times become a little low spirited, and Hfer beauti- ful, expressive blue eyes would seem to look afar off. She would grow impatient and restless if her brother's letters filed to come just when she ex- pected them. One thing a little strange, although she appeared to love me and cling to me, she never permitted me to see her brother's letters, but burned them just as soon as she answered them, and she never gave me an opportunity of reading a superscription on her letter to her broth- er. I was in perfect ignorance of his whereabouts. Two months had passed, and I had become ten- derly attc4ed to this mysterious girl-this strange   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.  17 girl whose maidenhood -was a sealed book, closed so irrevocably that no sudden outhurst of natural, unguarded, youthful pasion ever divulged even the slightest revelation. Her board and the piano rent Ihad been p;aid to me three nlontlhs in ad vnce. Her neat and tastefill wl-rdrobe, every articlp in keeping with the simple style in which we lived had cost about two hundred dollars, including a few presents which she hatd given my children. Yes, during this two montlhs I had learned to love this tirl. I felt a sisterly calre and anxiiety lor her.  onometimes the mystery of the past an d uncertainty of her future became almost painful to me; plarticularly had it been Qofor the last two weeks of the two months.   I thought that. I de- tected a restlessness il all' her actions. I 4had I)e- gun to find  little scraps of paper scribbled upon, torn in two and thrown alside. My  curiosity was aroused, and I watched an opportunity and picked up ,a few pieces unobserved by her and put the bits together, 1hoping to get at the drift of her thoughlts.  The first. that I was able to make out was the. old lilles : "I knolw not, I cartl not if guilt'.s in thy heat, I kno,w tlilt I love thee whiitever llou art." And a repeat.: "Ye.. i)love 1 thpe, whatever thou art!" I  was determined from that moment. to  watch her closely, and also try to get hold of all the bits of paper she nmight scatter ;tround. I  put -the above in a soafe place; it Was in her handwriting, 'nmd  mig'ht lead to some di.-covery. I  asked her one day when she expected her brother back. "His last letter  aid that he might le away ,another month." This was delivered in a tone which plainly said, ,Ask no more." I continued to do all I could to cheer her, and 3  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7907-00000010"/> 18   DELL DART ; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. studied many a little act to dispel that restless- ness which she herself labored hard to conceal. We rode out often; and, one evening I invited i party of friends to spend a few hours with us, and we sang, and Dell and others of the ladies played, and I never saw a sweeter, happier and more con- tented countenance than that of Dell Dart on that evening. She seemed almost wild with happiness. I trembled as I listened to her sweet, silvery laugh and gay repartee, and saw the glowing color upon her cheek and the brilliant sparkle of her deep, loving eyes. "A head and heart gone astray!"I ejaculated. "A blending of the woman and sister's duty, and the soul out-reaching way beyond-a tiny bark on a stormy sea! What devilish fiend! What spirit of darkness has wrought this wreck-this ruin? What imp of Satan has thrown out the net and caught this little struggler within its meshes?" And while these thoughts were passing confus- edly in my mind Dell took a seat at the piano and sang in a low, mournful strain the following lines from Whbittier: !'Oh woman wronged, can cherish hate More deep and dark than manhood may, But when the mockery of fate Hath left revenge its chosen way,' Still lingers something of the spell Which bound her to the traitor's bosom-, Still 'mid the vengleful fires of hell Some flowers of old affection blossom."' As she sang the words of the last line her voice became nervous and almost inaudible, and as the -word "blossom" died away, she burst into tears and pried out: "Oh, take me-take me! I am dying!" I sprang toward her and caught her in my arms. She had fainted. I laid her back upon the floor and hastened to get a restorative. I knew the re. action would bring on hysteria and I used cologne and bay rum to rub her hands and temples ; talked   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESS.   19 to her tenderly, calling her darling and other pet names. Poor heart, it was bruised enough already! In a few moments she showed signs of recover- ing. Her hands clinched, and her lips compressed. It was terrible to be alone with her and I so ner. vous; but this must not be known to my trifling' cold-hearted neighbors, to furnish them with gossip for the next week; so I just worked on and prayed, too, and in a few moments I had the pleasure of seeing her open her eyes and look natural. "Lie still, dear," I said, " while I get you some- thing to take." "What is it '." she asked. "Valerian and ether," I replied; "it will quiet your nerves. I keep it in the house for that pur- pose, and I find it a most excellent remedy for ner- vous attacks-one teaspoonful of each.  See, that is not bad to take," I said as she swallowed it. After a little while I put her to bed. I slept but little that night. My room Was next to her's, and all through the slow, creeping hours I could hear stifled sighs and suppressed groans. She was evi- dently spending a  sleepless nihlt, and when the gray shadows of the early dawn came in through the half-closed blinds I stole into her room. She had fallen into a disturbed sluinmber and was being haunted by troubled dreams. I   heard her mur- tour t' Oh, yes, I am your's, soul and body! Come to me! Oh, let me clasp you once more!" I  slipped out of the door, lest she should awaken and find me apparantly acting the spy upon her, "Will you ride  'With us ?" she sa'd to me that afternoon, as 'the children  dame bounding in from school. "I think not," I   replied. "You and the chil - dlren go and I  will have a nice dinner ready when you return." The sun had disappleared behind the mountains g  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7907-00000011"/> r 20 DELL DART; OP, WITHN THE MESHES. the shades of night had fallen over the earth. F The tvening was a little chilly. I had closed the dodYs .And windows and kindled a fire upon the hearth which was throwing its cheerful, dlanlcinfg shaido*s upon the fllrnliture. The big stick was crowding the small sticks. and they were havingr a littile snap at each other and casting their sparks about the hearth, Which sounded like a young fourth of July. The dinner was done and all readly to be dished up i;till the little family did not return. I sat down by the fire, determineed to waiit patiently, for I had told Pell to take a good long ride. I sat there watching the thusy motions of the iris-hued blaze and listening to the hissillng sap, as it boiled, and bubbled, and sputtered, an-d oozed from the ends of the wood, my thoughts busy with my heroine Dell; and really my thoughts had been oc- cupie'd with little else for weeks. Presently I heard the sound of the merry voices of the chil- dren.  I arose and opened the door. InI they cam4 I nl aglow with pleasure and delight. The drive iand the fresh, cool air had given them rosy cheeks and bright eyes, axid alddled music to their merry Voices. But, poor Dell! How pale and xWorn she 'lobked, and sadder thanu when she kissed me at the gate two hours before. "Yoou look cold, Dell," I s-aid. "Come, sit down in the r-ocking chair by the fire, and I will disli up the dinner." Meanwhile the children, who loved the yoting girl with brotherly af. ection, gathered around her, and one took her gloves, the other her bonnet and shawl; and by this time our dinner was smoking upon the table. I stepped into the sitting-room and said : "Come now, a cup of tea will revive and warm you. "Sister," she said, in sweet, tender tones, (she   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.  21 Ilhad called me by that endearing fraternal epithet from the first day of our acquaintance). I do not feel like eating.  I klow thalt you have everything nice, but I cannot taste a mouthfull; so please ex- cuse me. While you and the children are eating I will go t) the postoffice." "Oh, just take a cup of tea,' I said. "Please excuse me." "Very well, dear,' I answered; "perhaps you will feel better when y-ou come black." She started for the postoffice, and the children and myself proceeded to partake of our evening meal. "Did you have a pleasant time, boys?"I asked. "Oh, yes," they exclatimed silmultaneously, "we had lots of fun. We stoplped for a long time at Mr. Smith's garden, and Aunt Hell let us do just as we pleased tand run where we liked. She stayed in the parlor talking, with a man who came on horseback." "Yes," said the eldest, " and she cried like everything, too." "She didn't cry' wiien I seen her," said the youngrer; " she looked sick and told me to go see the flowers, and gave me this half-dollar to get fiuit, but I knowed mother wanted it, so I kept it. Here, mother, you take it, and don't tell Aunt Dell," he added ill a Whisper. In a few minutes Dell returned looking better and more cheerful, and said in a pleasant tone of voice: "I will take a: cup of tea." That night wte sat and talked long after the usual bed hour, and although my companion said nothing that gave me the slightest idea of what had changed her bright, girl nature into the sad, capricious, half-idild, half-woman, frotn whom all the golden and pink and purple and roseate tints of hope had gone out. Still, she dropped somne  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7907-00000012"/> 22   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MwHTS. few words in the course of the evening which startled me, and brought back the memory of the old, old lines : "I know not, Icare not ifrguilt's in thy heart, I know thll t I love thee, va hatever thou art." She asked me if I had read the elopement case in the 4"Union " of that morning. "I have not," I replied. She then related to me the circumstance. She laughed a bitter, cold laugh and said: "The homely old adage of, 'love will go where it is sent' is true the 'world over. Iln some sordid na- tures pride overcomes love for awhile, but the heart is never reconciled. I believe," she added, "that Miss Boker, the millionaire's daughter of New York, realizes more moments of exquisite bliss with her low-bred husband, Dean, than all else on earth could have afforded her. Those ten- der, delicate fibres of the heart have been touched by some spirit-breathing of his nature. This is love in its purity-love of heart-and although his gives little response, it is sufficient outpouring to keep the delicate taper burning within." "You are Quixotic in your ideas of love," I laughingly remarked. "Do you think so?" she asked eagerly. "Rather extravagant for this practical age--ia little too much inclined to the extreme of romance. You see," I said again laughing, "I have arrived at the age of moderation. I've had the wings up- on which I took my fancy flights clipped; that is, I would not follow a handsome highwayman to his haunts and be willing to share his booty and his isolated life, neither do I think that I could love the incondite savage of the forest." I said these things purposely, hoping to draw from her lips a heart confession. She sat silent for awhile, and then with a ner- vous kind of hand and head gesture she continued:   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.  23 "I believe that love takes many shapes, and dis- tributes its sweets according to the capacity of the individual to receive. My love would be like Othello's grief; it would engulf and swallow all other passions, and still be love." I looked at her for a moment. The temptation was too great! The question was trembling upon my lips. It must give birth in words: "Have You ever loved?" Oh how my heart throbbed as I awaited the answer. She gave me a look almost of wildness as she exclaimed : "Loved-loved! I have worshipped, idolized, adored!" and she laughed a low, half-sobbing hys- terical laugh which made me shudder. She came to me, threw her arms lovingly about my neck and said : "To you, my more than sister, would I make a confession of my past life; but I cannot, even to you, whom I love so much with that calm, beautiful friend-like love. No, J cannot. Oh, no! you would perhaps spurn me-look upon her for whom you now feel so much of kindness and sympathy as a being too mean, too contemptible, to claim even your pity, much less your charity. I never intended to say half what I have said to you to- night to any human being, but my poor, foolish heart must have become overcharged or it never would have given vent to these closely guarded emotions." "You are weak and nervous and will be ill if you overtax your mind with what I am   inclined to believe is partly imaginary troubles. You had better retire and try to get some sleep and you will feel refreshed in the morning. Do not feel annoyed at what you have disclosed. Should you at any time change your mind in regard to the secret of your love which seems to bear so heavily upon your spirits, and should wish to unfold the  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7907-00000013"/> 24   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. secret to me, I will give you such counsel and ad- vice as I am capable of giving. I shall never, if I can possibly .avoid it, say or do ought that will re- vive the unpleasant memories of the past." "The past--past! Oh, if it were only the past! But the future-the terrible future! If I were not a coward I would die by my own .hand, but that I cannot, dare not do. I must live perhaps twenty or thirty ye ars---aye! to be a wrinkled old hag, and never enjoy another day of true joy and happiness! If Go(d would only take me now, to- night! ()h, oh, ol!" ' My dealr Dell," I said, -' you frighten me. Please try to quiet your leelingcs and come up to bed. Shall I sleep with you, to-night?" '"No," ,he said in a -ad,?ublducd tone. 4' No, I shall sleep well; I nam very tired. We will go to bed, you to yours lan(d I to mine, and in the morn- ing you shalll know all." She leaned toward me and kissed my lips gand forehead aind softly whis[pered : * May God bless you and your little ones, jnd if you ever pray, pray for me to-light. Good night!" She picked up the lamp passed into the hall and up the little stafirway. Soon after I retired, and being weary from the night's wa ltching I went to sleep and did not awake until broad daylight. I sprang up and for a moment I listened at the door of' the room  which Dell occupied. All was still. "Oh. that her brother -would come," I sighed, as I hastily put on my wrapper and hurried down to the kitchen. The children soon followed me, and I chargred them to keep very quiet as Aunt Dell was not well and needed sleep. At half-past eight o'clock the boys left for school. I made as little noise as possible until after the clock struck nine. I then ascended the stairs   DELL DART; OR, WITRIN THE MESHES.  25 le adin- to the sleeping apartments. I crept softly towar Is the door of Lell's room and tap led li htlv. No answer. I tried the knob ; it tunrilel,- nd the doorolpelned at the gelltle pressure. I looked to- walrds the bed. To Iny sulrprise it was not occu- pied- I entered the room, thinkingr perhaps she might have gone out on the porch, to which place I hastened. "Not here!"I exclaimee.  Then I thought she must have slipped (down the stairs without attract- Ing my notice and might be in the parlor readlin. T hastened thither and loupd that altartment va- cant, too.  I was surprised(. astoni hedl, friohteledl. What can this mealn?   A thought then sutggested that sle nlmay IFosQilliy have go!pe jor a morning walk or ride, if so it w;as the first tinle that she had ever slipl ed out in that way. I returned to the bed-room ; there stoofl her trulnk with the key in it, Ever3 thing was just as f[saw them thenight prep'ious.  I opened the wat rdrobe ; there hunlg her ,clothing, even the dress she had( pn just before re- tiring,  her gaiters, stockings, morning-wraDper, and night-gown.   I trembled and shook with atgi- tation; emotion  and ta nervous feiar seizel mie. i' (Joultd she have gone fp the river?" At this thought I rulshed wildj!y arpund. the room, shaking out everything shakable hoping to filnd it lote. In so doing my   astonibshment was increalseel, for I found every article of' under-clothing she ppssessed, both'soiled and clean. The mystery thickened. It seemed like it terrible dream;   but I knew that whatever it wats it was a terrible reality and one thalt I must alone realize, flv everything connected with Lell and her advent into my home  had been kept a  secret. I had never given the slightest explanation of' the cir- cuimstances connected with her coming to my most confidential i'iends, consequently I could have no sharer in the surprise and astonishment of her 4  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7907-00000014"/> 96   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. mysterious dislappearance. I must bear all quietly and await the result patiently. I could look to no one for sympa thy; in fact I was not an object of sympathy. I ha-d lost nothing, on the contrary I had been more than paid and had been amply re- warded in a pecuniary sense. Neither could I charge myself with neglect, or of failing in a strict adherence to all the promises I had made to her brother and to all that duty demanded. I had not been requested to watch, her movements, or been warned of any suspicion of her trying to escape. My feelings were anything but pleasant. iI came to the conclusion that I must wait for time to dew velop facts, but thoughts are obstinate little wed: dlers and suggest queer might-have-been's And shouldn't-wQnders and justas-likely-as-nQt's; and, in spite of my better judgment, they were coptin- ually making little suggestions, throwing out hints and interrogations something after this style; "What if I had been imposed upon. Suppose the fellow was an impostor, that he was not her broth- er after all, and all my sympathies had been lav- ished upon an unworthy object, with all of his long face and deep sighs and tearful tones. Some scamp, perhaps, who had won the affections of some other man's young wife and was hiding her away until he could make more suitable and safe arrangements,- and now he had stolen in while I slept and slipped his prize off in the darkness of night in some dis- guise. Yes, he had doubtless passed my bed-room door. "Oh, my!"I exclaimed, as I thought of all this going on in the dead of night. I always had let my heart run away with my head, and I fell to scolding that silly, soft, easily imposed upon organ. I threw myself into a rock- ing-chair and burst into tears. They, were tears of vexation and mortification at the thought of being duped by that handsome, bland, sorrowful-faced man. But these surmises did not make me think   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.    2 7 any the less of the poor woman. I loved and pitied her just the same.  Hapless darling, had she not said to me, "I must live perhaps twenty or thirty years, aye! to be a wrinkled old hao, and never enjoy another day of true joy or happiness." Could I entertain any anger or harsh feeling for such a wretched. soul-sufferinc, child of the human family. With these thoughts tall bitterness and desire to upbraid vanished. With a heavy heart and trembling friamne T re- turned to her room.   I opened the mindows and then proceeded to make the bed and clean up, and leave all to time and circunmstance.   I lifted the. pillow; as I did so a folded bit of paper attracted my eye.  I snatched it eagerly.  Yes. it was a few lines addressed to me.   It was crumple and nd  bore the traces bf tears.  It read as follows: MY DEAR FRIEND AND SISTER:-Forgive me for blip- ping off like a guilty one; I could not stay with you another day without bringitig disgrace upon you. I do not fear either disgrace or ruin; both have come upon me anid crushed me to the very ground. I only live because I .a n afraid to coinmit the dreadful act, self-destruction. The thingsI leave at your house are yours; I have no further need of them. If it is ev'er in my power, I will most surelir befriend you. I may never tmnak  myself known to you; but shall endeavor to never lose sight of you; or, at least a knowledge of your circiumstances and whereabouts. May God bless yoiU and your darlings. May they grow up to honorable tnanhood, and prove the pride and jov of yiur old age. Qh! my dear sister; you cannot even guess the height and depth nhd width of the terrible gulf which forms a barrier between us. , There still are many rainbows in your sky; But mine are all vanished., ,Mine after life! what is mine after life; My day is closed! the gloom of life is comet A hopeless darkness settles o'er my fatei"' I shall remember the few days we have spent together while life and reason shall last. Good-bye, again. May God bless you for the sisterly kindness to the poor, unfortu- nate, though virtuoids,        DELL DART. P. 8i-My brother will be with you in a few days. D. D. "Virtuous!" i Itxclimeid;, "tlh:ik Heaven   foir that!"  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7907-00000015"/> 28   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. -      The mysterv was deeper than ever, for surely I I^      llhallthollht that nothing save lost virtue could nlmake an olltcasts of wornman. For an hour at least I sat wrapt in tholllit. I then roused ms-.Self 'and began to complete my mornillng's work1. This pon-, de'inm over .a n-ystery so deep and dark- would un,; fit'me for my dlailv duties. I must thnk as little abouit it as possible. land wait patiently for Mr. Cheeney Dart to make his appearance. After two weeks of weary watching and waiting and wondering Mr Dart came. Throughrl the half open window blinds I saw him enter the gat,e, and from .the piasannt. almost jovyfil expression of his countenance, I felt certatin that he knew nothing of the disawppelrance of his sister. With a light step he almost hounded upon the porch and gave a qllie k rap. My healrt flutteref anl mv limbs tremn*,led as I approached and opened the door. I felt the color recede from m  ftace. T knoew 'tha t my looks and actions were betraying the feelings of * my hleat. Cheene Dartf was a imhn of quick per- ception, nnd without even Qsa,:inzr "lood morning," he grasped my hand and exdl. aimed : - 'I Go, tl's name what has happened?" "Fit down lipon the kofa," I said, " and don't get excited. I will try and calm my nervous agi- tation and exrltin all to y-ou; and you mnuit en- deavor to concentratte all. of -ollur strength and manhood to bear the blow which has befathen you in voutr ahsence." '"Has Dell left?'i he asked, while his white lips trem ,led. "Yes." I replieid; "t will get a letter which she left for me, annd that Wvill tell all that I know.'" I went up to my room and soon returned with the missive. which I T handet to him. After read- in, it caref'ullv th!rough, apparentlyv weighing every Word, he exclaimed in tohes of bitter despair: "Some fatal passion--stiame fiend! draggiing her   DELL DART ; OR, WITHN TIE MESHES.  29 down to perdition!" and the stronr man wept. '*O! I wish tliLt I caull. have frJll1l her dea l. O! yes; better death at thlsLand times, than this livi;g; disgracel-this death to all that is pure and good." M"Mr. Dart," I said, in as calni and steady a voice as I could command; " whatever your troub. les are, mlake the best of them. Do not let the course which your sister has chosen to pursue in spitei of all. your kind  and brotherly counsel, tdrag you down or blight your manhood, There is a strtange, mysterious contra,!liction of ftiilts and virtues mingled with the circumstances of ,vour sis- ter's lile. Site is the most tender, lovabld, loving, interesting, entertaiiinin woman I ever met; t hatve studied hler closely and almost uncealsingly ever since she enteredl my home. and I finl her an-nigy- ma which would liallt the skill of the most gifted reader of' humantl natture. The only conclusion that I could come to wlas, that her goodl traits are all na;tural-that she naturally has no vicious or ma'- licious traits il hier elharacter. Somne evil influence see ms to be ag grav titthg  and agitaLting her naturally quiet, pllre spiit. Her physical health is gooid; but ilmeltally she is suft-erizl, intense anony. She seemed to be constantly s'ruggling  against -orme unseen evil. I concluded in nly weak judgment that some sudlden misfirtune hil pLartially wrecked her hrain; and I do truly believe her to be a mo- nomanitic upon some sub!ject, anlld that subject is unilmated love; a love which her heart tells liher is unworthy, and still a love whch th;at s;,ne healrt clings to witht uldl\ing r f 1ldness; all (of the better patrt of her nature being a;bsorbedl in the one great l as-ion. This," I adled, " is only surmise on my part. Her lips were closed upon her heaft secret; It was from general observation, not personal eon* versations with her that. I gleaned the information which settled me into the above conclusions."  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7907-00000016"/> 30   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. Mr. Dart had remained silent during myv speech, never uttering a syllable. The last few sentences seemed to arouse him, and he gave me a long, ear- nest look, in which I read his thanks for my char- ity for his .erring, orphaned sister. "Well, Madam," he said, "I thank you, from mny ivery heart, for the favors you have conferred upon ime. I feel certain that you have done all within your power to Win my sister back to a life of tespectability and comnmon sense. I arn satis- fied that I have done all that it is -possible for a brdther to do in kindness fir a sister, and I do not think that I could better the condition of things by Using harsh means. So I must rest content to lihv6 n mn fear of the horrid results which mayv fol- loT in consequence of her strange infatuation of t li' life she has c-iolsen. I will now0- confide to you as jbur just due, all that I know of the strange his- tory bohnected with mry poor, deluded. Wayward, capricious sister. I will go back to the days of her 'Chldtiood, and give you all the facts as briefly as pissriblte" tie intense agony which the sudden hews of hi's sist'er's flight had occasioned had passed off, and i balm loiOk of resignation overspreadl his hand- soAi* :fch'  .          I ' BUt in that instant o'er-his soul, Wtinters of memor'y seem'd to roll, And gather in their drop of time i A life of pain, an. age of crime:-- O'er him who loves, or hates, or fears, Such moments pour the grief of years." "There was just two of us-twelve years differ- ence in our ages. When I left my Eastern home ten years ago she was a golden haired, sunny-faced darling eight years of age; I, a youth! of twenty with the strength and ambition of a 'man. My ambition was to gain wealth for my sweet little sister Dell. Two years after my depa'rture our mother died, leaving us olphans without a near.   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. 31 relative in the world. I hastened back and after settling up all the business I began to think about returning to California; but what would I do with dear little sister Dell. My first impulse was to bring her with me. My judgment tupon second thought told me that it would be next to impossi- ble to have a child of her tender years properly cared for in Califbrnia at that early period. I then thought of placing her in a Convent, but several old ladies, ignorant of' everything outside of their own village, held up their hands in holy horror and asked me if I had ever read ' Mariga Monk.' Yes, I said, and the ' Arabian' Nights also, and many other sensation, catch-penny productions. Still I felt that my sister would be safe and well cared for in such an institution. On the following day when the question was resumed of ' What shall I do with Dell?' the little opne came to me with tears in her eyes and pleading in her voice, threw her white arms about my neck and said : "Please, brother, don't put me in a Nunnery. I don't want to go to one; it makes me feel afraid when I think of it. You won't send me to one, will you, Cheeney?" It was evident'that these narrow-minded women had prejudiced her young mind against the Con- vent and weakened her confidence in my judgment as to what was for her good. "Do you doubt my love and affection. for you, Dell," I asked. "Oh, no; I know you love me, but you don't know how cruelly they treat little girls at those Convents." \ I found that it would be useless for me to urge the case further, at least I felt -that if. I placed her in a Convent she would go with bitter feelings, so I said no more about it. As my business in C ali- fornia was urgent I did the best I couldj I left that sweet little sister, my only relative, with an old  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7907-00000017"/>  32  DELL DART; 0O, WITHN THE MESHES. lady who took her, as shle assured me, just .tQ oblig e me. I m lde tie te st arrnllngelments 1 posIi- bly coahl 1or Vell's Cmllllort; latid ix mnlllllths bJ ird ill adlvalce t and lelt t sufficienllt sulll to lpur chaseclothillg.  I tom^ M rs. Avery, the lady with whol 1 left my sister, that I wolald expect to helar fro htier regularly tylery mollth. Amlid elmbraces, 'kisses anld tears we parted, thalt little si,ster a'd 1. "How We eliti rthi , ng tliln Otlr he: r .s I ave nulrsed,. Every nwlnth, accordinr tqo agreement, the let- ters camthe; eachi speatkiii of' tl!e brigllntess allld bealuty of mly darlulng Dell. Each j ear as it passed along I would promi^e myselt that the tollowing one shoaulc tjl4d 'lle .ack ill lly old bo k hood's 1holne; but as each canite illd u wet I lbund lnmsell' too embarrassed tQ leave. so with a renewal of promi- ses I would go oin. iell wals twelve yeaurs old and much improved in their education as her letters showed, Land Mrs. Avery wrote she wished to send her to ta tashiplltable daj and bor)ding school. ohe must have a piiano, alnd clothing lomlore postly and fiashionable.  i bent ad         thousand doll ars; that was all that I would be able ab to spare out of nlly bubi- ness, so my visit llnuat be pottpoe,ed totloter year. Aye! two years passed and 1 ou;)nd it. almost im- possible to keep up with Vell's increasing ea penses. o3ht was ltow it Oilllimt, betaltitul girl of fifteen. Now I mlust see hter. I wrote to her that I would be att hoale somethe d arill the early Sprilnl. aid should eApect her to return with le. This was mobt agreeable to her. ;ihe wrote inl a lmad, wild tolle iull ot gleetul anticiptthlon of the beautilul "Iiie she expected to enjoy.  ^ Y es, myU darlig ibiter, your life shall be beauti- fulit anlly elrort d11 my ptlit will nlmike it. so. I purchatlsedb lot, put up a neat, handsome cottatge -ald employed uien tu laty oLt and beautify thhe -r(ounds.  Ailter everythllng wats finlihed I had   DELL DART ; 01, W'ITHIN THE 21ESIIES. 3 written to Dell   to btat wrol ov to -rt wit Califbrnia altout tI e ia t o]' Ai).'ii I waitel ner- vously and nl lsiot:!lv I;r ;in ai!swer. On the evl11ing on which ' thel Eastern mait'l was due -I has- tened to the post-office. A letter! Yes, a letter, he sulencr cipilion in my .siter's hanci writing. Biefore I im1 ti'll to op)?;a it s3o.'ll ,t ilesis'n witlh whom  had inmlportant busiIless clnme to me. I put the letter in vy pocket iand sta-rted ofi to the other side of' the town. It was latC whlt'enl, I tid. the parties good night. I then went. to mny roim, and thc first thought which came into my ltlidm was the letter. I dlrew it from nly Iocket and for the first timel noticed that it. was an extremely light letter. Of' course she did not want. to write much, she would see ine soon and  then she could give Ine her thoughts verballly. I opened the little hllf sheet---and  oh, my God! was I awalke, or was this some  terrible nidght-mare? Again and again I read : DEA R BROTITFR :--You llOed nnt conme for ilm. I am lost to you ; ruhilel, undllc a;nd dl (i^,rt i d.  Pray  f,lr nt;  for- give lIl, ianl  fil'ie t InI jif i.,1 1'1;I.  Y1u I I . P(d I11[t ('1lno l rore, you will lot findl me.  I l-hall lea;Iev Ihre l!mnt. 1)ft4re tlh q r.(whPs.%. lm .  01,h I I sfta ell ! wh(  . II 1 e IhI .fl ght "hat I ( could  1;ve  f;ale 1 so} 1,.\ll n st) s Drt  :I tiltlne. QUQD bye, my de..r brother, God Ihelp .'i11 aInd I).rt(ct )ou. Your Wretched Sister, DEr,L. Here, overcome  by his feelinges, his head rested in the palms of his hands and he wept. I  looked up at this strong, lhandsome  man. Dear reader, hlave you ever seen a  sturdy, giant oak ielled by the, axe of the woodmnll?  Oh, it was a pitiful jight. With a   voice half choked with emotion ti said ; "t You can imagine, madam,   what. my feelings wero much better than I  can descri be them to you. My   darling sister ruined, undone, disgraced Obh, where was the villain-the heartless libertine?  I grew almost mad as I   thought that he would re- 5  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7907-00000018"/> 34'  -D , LL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. t      turn to society petted, caressed, fawned and smiled ?5    upon; would marry, somle wealltly beautv, become the holnest father of a1 flllilv, beloved and respect- ed by the good and great. While my poor, little, golden-haired, blue-eyed, ge;tle-voiced sister would be scorned and spurned and shunned-ruineO! Never to hold a position in society. Oh, the thought was burning-malddeninl, to my proud, loving heart. Not go to helr! Not avenge. her wrong! Not take her to mly bosom! Not tell her to look up and be the same pure, darling sister! Not brand her seducer as he had branded her! I know that I was wrought, up to a state of frenzy, for I laughed and cried and cursed all in the same breath. "I will not kill him!"I exclaimed; -' oh, no! I will brand him-disgrace him! Men shall shun him. Yes, if women shun my darling sister, men shall shun -and scorn the viper who poisoned my sister's life!" And I lay awake through all the weary, mad- W   dening hours of that night concocting plans where- by to ruin and disgrace this woman-poisoner. The sweet face of my dear, dead mother and that of Dell were constantly before me urging me in my desperate work, for I did not intend that it should end in mere child's work. I was too impatient to write to Mrs. Avery and await an answer, that would at the shortest possible estimate take eight weeks. No, I would start by the next steamer, I might be able to do something to relieve my sis- ter's misery; the letter was so inexplicit. Her ruin,-or what she deemed her ruin, might not be so utterly without remedy as she in her young haste had conceived it to be; and, ere sleep closed my eyes that night, I had made up my mind to start for the East on the next steamer. I slept but little, and when I arose in the morning I was hot and feverish. I went about like one in a dream.   DELL DART ; ORB, WITHN THE MESHES,  3V This was the first real trial of my life. The death of my darling, Christian manother had caused me many tears; the losses I had sustained byr fire had brought me regrets. My mother was in Heaven away firom  the storms of life. The losses had been easily replaced. But Dell's. darling Dell's trouble was of so different a nature that turn it as I would I could see no bright side. I prepared a cup of coffee and drank it; my heart was too full for food.  I then started to towna, intending to commence makfing arrangements to leave for the Bay the next day.   As I vallked along a friend accosted me with a pleasant " good morning," and added: ' There is a letter in the express office for you from your formier home.* "Indeed!"' I exclaimed, With so much surprise in my voice that my friend looked at me in aston- ishment and said: "Dart, you re not looking wrell this morning. No bad news I hope?" I told him that I had received a  letter through the post-office the night previous which contained rather unpleasant news. "Oh, well, the one in the express will explain away all the disagreeableness of the plrevious one.'  He  then pateed on, and I hastened to the express office, obtained the letter, and then, for fear that it might contain something more startling than the first and cause me to betray mny agitation to the gaping crowd, I  hurried to my hoine on -the out- skirts of the town. Here I  lost no time in break- ing open the envelope and reading the contents. The letter was firom Mrs. Avery. "And here it is," he said. Taking an old, wolrn letter from, his pocket; he read the iollowing; Mum DART:- Dear Sir.- How shall t otihmetco to tell you the sad news I have to communicate. Vour sistor has leftmy house under peculiar circumstances. I had been out spending the day ind evening; I asked Dell to to with  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7907-00000019"/> Jsb     36    DELL DAKT ; OR, ;VITHN THE MESHES, mP. S'lh'e nd he,(-n 1 looking snd :ndl s;rruowful fir wretiln }h,^ ; ^ I tmoughlt it vs1 fgrom oXv(rttx{ir Ih r mintird uwith KPr c'h(vol fil IS. ;,d1 ri rrkvd to) her Il;t .s hp mwirt seek t ;to n'l'-- hIrsr if d,rin t - tl v;ich;i t iol, ;ilud fit thr-elf to look right n1)id pare-vty  Ill ! I u' -,lit 1d ( whe tIo itke her 1tohlf-rieww homeo. I qulitte uracsd hper 11to ncc'mplllmy mife, 1t.1A Ac dlf('lilled, s:yi,  Ilutt sli mllul- I ook itnvor t^r'wa rdr- Snrobe m1r lithtnd to stvpritl iistlra M l;tt't'rs \Wlhiclh tlquiredl illlnjii Init( atfle'im)l. Mily' s'lrvmlllt, til (,only llt lite of llyV hmu.4except Del;r]l lmI ins;lf, lit ( ;.itkcd-l i)pmlli ssil of Iorm I'o visit lhr friptid- 4o silt 1I v, :inr liit- ass^m(eid by Dell ft1.' t?lIe I ()Ul ert aD.ilz ti( ivly, I pte lirtted hIr iof (1f) .o. Orlixiv ierttim abnut tell ,,ik k thait is'ht, 1 wa.,.-surpri.;sle to fin( no ImIim ill tlun Ihptlcf lilt ti- ^If \r-v;ilt\, u lio) lid alrpadV reti'i'Pt. I \vvlnt to 1wr room mdl qie-;(iont-l hir in reivrdrl tothe^  senllep l(1o the omltir iaIdy. KlhP .s-idd sh retirned to tirel fitm:l' a hnnt danrk atid 1fnind phr dotwr ipyv ju-t wlipre siro 'lTPf it, hilt IItt tlPrp s 1 Io liiLrht ill tilehlmu^e, nd he- tiny tlre4l ;inl slp1py she1 l; lid r(t ired ;(hI)Olt (-ilt o'lockandl "pto1iat hour  lik- Dell ):lid not eomm- it. I t'elt ;llrmlld, ft( i'twt:s tl(he irst titip dulring the yiwar sh( li7td lived witD tP ItI'ht Awp lid ld p n ;'ih'ct Irom  t lelsp, llts unlesis I Wm' wit-h ltr. I \vcnt to I li rlront do( r() .it1 Ind lokipd oumt :nd li s- tenpl, No scou rdl Irn Pt I y zl;ir. A qinI I visited e)pll  roomn wilA(c offit ^mme d \wtijl my vmi),. Nothing W-S ;  dlistulrbed. She Hll evidiiiyv wiwrn tlisnime d*ress?.ht(- lim; onit w ilpel I left,Hiirl tl;d a iker schmliol liontill ;nifl c eip: (jverythinil  v1.?se \ASj11s;t a- Althpy wpen" w lic I w COt ;lway. I IIoniper lI ht lhepflowzZ v%%-,-is iDg fl1t ilslv:id of stamdinig 1sga:tah:s tile plwea1 -oard Hs tsut;il. A ilomn )t stiruckl Ime. I haIstpnerd to exiaminr1e, }nd hen(intlh it I found ;i letteir nlId -I smill p-lck- nage hotli sidirtssesd to tirrp. I oplnpl tliP letter, alil to my surlpri{e and liorror re;l fIlivc 'ste fk\ lines I send \-olu : "Dear FIrien7cd)Z{.t a ,nMthefrv-, *Go'od (-, shnd forpver. Do not ;il verti i fo;r Imp-do  not r iv ;lily (exc(ittnent aliout Ile. Seirch would 1ue' v;in, and shioiild you siicct pd iln tra(*- ing nrifp omt, you would only hrhr din - Qgirnrlp? Iled p- rh;lp- ruin 1p1)on myi.\ brothor. I ;tull riflild ;ind dis-racod pa st ;ll re- dlomptifin ; s;o Yfo oin in1 your tI4u ;lJ w:1\iy :;nd le;r';p m. to my bilter faltt. I have writell to m;y  brother ;}indl ( ild enoughl. My clotlhes I 1;ive no th-^ for, (ro witlh them ;n s you plieas-mnetinemy diis()osition of thiemll Iy):}1' m hosep. In the little pwckdazc e with tlis letter you will tinld the Il sft giftof your w relched girl,            D:LL." I hl.-istenc1 to open th- I,1c(k-ip, :in,] to, mn  surprisp two lonf, golden curlk neslet vd in thp I)ioer. () one waS; pinned a Nli)  f pwer mlrmn which vl s written, l* Fr ivv darlinZ lbrother." th  t thr ror mvol1f. I stiippo-4 you will Lret , let- ter from  hpr nt the s1slriml thimlp Ilhit 'you aqt th:. Pje;ife let me hepr if thrp i- ainvthintl. th;lt will throtw?n mynorplight upon the   dreadful mystery, t11tle oblige your friendl and [ympaHthizer;,                 J. AVERY. - After rcading these letters," lie    said. "T felf   DELL DART; OR, WItHN THE MESHES.  37 thlat it would 1)6 useless for me to go in senrch of the truant. I must await in sorrov and silence the cominf events. It wars  eler;allly lknown by ler friends thlat shc cexpected to come to Coalifornia. and  Mrs. Averv left the impression upon the nlinds of all. ilnquirers thail;t she lhad gone rather unexpectetl I . For many weTeks I grieved most bitterly.  AMy friends thought that I was roing ilito a decline and recommended change of climalte; but Nature and Nature's God haIl:ve made a w\\iep rovision I or the sorrow-stricken ; and as time ptasses and the necesities of life call out our energies, anguish and grief settle down into a nature-repining cod- ness; wevc can the the more readily sympathize with others in their afflictiolls, and II thla;t s'm- pathy our own trials lose something of their orir- inal sharpness.  So it wtas with mv terrible trouble. It was about becoming a skeleton in the closet of my  heart. I hald become mnolre palient-nlore chlr- itable in iny thoughts. A spiit seemed to whis- per within me- "Oh give me tp:lrs for other's woe s, Antd ,patien-v foir n, own." The home which I   had built nnd wa-s havinr beautified for the pleaslure of my sister I soldl, mak ing some slight exccuse for doing so. .and leaving the rest to supposition. In fact, I sold out every thing that belonged to me alnd started forth a sort of wanderer, looklin for I knew not what. I read all the newlspapers I coulld get hlold oi' witl a Ort of vague fear, ancd still with a little 1oFe of g-in- ng some clue to the whereabouts of' my sister. While spendingy a. few dtays ill on e of the moun- tain towns of Sierra county, a gentleman said to me one evening  : "Would you not like to visit one of our fashion- able gambling houses?   For," he continued, if I mistake not you are in search of si-htcf n, I .^1  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7907-00000020"/> 38   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MES"RqS. edge." He had evidently supposed me to be a newspaper correspondent. Seeing that I hesitated he said : "Come, there you will see California life in all of its dark and disgusting phases. We wili re- main but a few momelnts." knowing him to be a Man of respectability, and feeling that he hbad no other motive than merely to gratify curiosity, I consented to accompany him. "Ten o'clock." he remarked as we started off'; i' we will be just in time to see the beautiful pan- demonium in all its glory." As we entered, the lights fairly blinded me for a moment, but presently my eyes became accustomed to their brilliancy, and as I gazed I whispered to my companion  "What a motley crew.'" Every- color and shade of color of men and youths. The women, about eight in number, were either Mexicans or Chilenos dressed in bright and gaudy hues, decorated with sparkling jewelry, con- slsting of diamonds and other costly gems. Ave! what. a world of' wealth' in jewelry, watches and coin within that palace of vice and sih. As I looked around the beautiful words of the immor- tal Shakspeafre camne to my mind with all of their painful force ' And many an old man's-sigh, and many a widow's, And many an orphan's Aater-standing eye- Men for their sins, wives for their husbands' fate, And orphans for their parents' timele s death- Shall rue the hour thot. scueh a hell was crreated." ' Can alny one be good or have one spark of manhood or womanhood left who frequents such a vile place of sin?"I asked my friend. "Yes," said he; "even this cannot, it seems, entirely destroy some of the good inherited in some men's natures. You see that neatly dressed youth over there at that corner table-the one with his hat drawn down over his eyes."   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.  89 ( Yes," said I, "Well, that fellow has been in town now for some time. No one knows where be came from or who he is. He is known here as Cleveland. He has the air of a refined young gentleman, is highly .educated, uses no bad language, but he is a perfect expert at cards. Plays an honest game every time, I understand; minds his own business and keeps his own counsel. A widow woman liv- ing in town lost a child with scarlet fever, about two weeks ago, and being in destitute circumstances some of the ladies went out to ask for a collection for the poor woman. Young Cleveland was seen to hand' them half a dollar and then turn and go into the bar-room. That night he'called upon the widow and gave her forty dollars, and did not wait even for thanks." "He looks young," I remarked. "Yes," said my companion; "one of those, too, who will look youthful until quite advanced in years. You have seen such men, have you not?" "Oh, yes, frequently. Have you never learned anything of his history?"I asked. "No, he talks only in monosyllables. We will go around to the table, and if he is not too busily engaged I'll introduce you." Just as these words were uttered the young man arose and came in the direction of the place where we were standing. "Aye, he is coming this way," The next moment he stood before us. "Good evening," he said, taking my companion by the hand; " rather warm in here to-night.," he remarked in a smooth, gentle tone of voice that would entitle him to respect. in any place. "Permit me to introduce you to a friend," said my companion turning to me.   The young man reached out his hand. "Mr. Dart, Mr. Cleveland." "Happy to make your acquaintance, Mr. Cleve- land," I said extending my hand.  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7907-00000021"/> 40   DELL DART j OR, WITHN THE NESHES. He stammered out something, and Esank into a chair. A Get some brandy!" called out my friend; ' young Cleveland Has fainted." "You ,ee, he hns just rcoveredt from ;a bad spell," 4aid the man who broufrhlt the lbrandv. The yomngc mal Mouted enough to take a drinlk, and then arose land said : "Excuse mne."' As hl did so, he gave me one long, strange look. What was it? WaVns it magnetism that fas- tened my eyes to thok deep blue oybs, which seemed to be piercing my v-ery soUI? The neyt moment he approached me and motioned for me to hold my elar dow-n. 1 did so ; when in a low, but distinct whisper, he salid : ': Cheeney, your sister, Dell." Mysister, imy God! I caughtlt her up in my arms and started for the door. My friend, altho' somewhat astonishedl at this sudden movement, turned around ndl salid : "Cleveland is sick, and we are going to take him over to the cabin." That was cxplanation enough for the men and women in the saloon, but what could I say to my friend? As quick as thought I said : '- Mr. Cleveland is my cousin, and he must spend the night with me.'" That was a satisfactory explanation to my friend, who said that le would be obliged to go home. So hle balde nc good night and left us alone-that long-lost, tru;ant sister and myself. The neut daly we ca:me to Sacramento. I Could not find it in iny heart to question her then. $he saw the looks of enquiry I cast upon heor and guessed the state of my mind. "I cannot tell you now." she said, wpeping biUt- Nevrly ermind, dear Del, never mid. Wh "Never mind, dear Dell, never slnd. when   DELL DART ; OR, TEIN THE MMES.   41 you feel like talking upon the subject you ean ex- plain. All I ask is that you exchange this male attire and consent to remain with me for all time to come. I will get you a suitable home for a few days, or it may be for weeks, in the meantime I will go to my former place of residence and try to get possession of the beautiful place which was built for you." While talking with her thus your little story came into my mind. I sought and found you, and now you know as much of the dreadful mystery as I do. "Did she not correspond with you?"I enquired. "I wrote to her a few days after I left; she an- swered, and in that answer she said: ' Brother, I thank and bless you for the kind and brotherly feeling you express for me in providing the hand- some home which you are preparing for me. I will most surely prove myself worthy of your care atnd kindness, and shall explain everything when you come back.'  I wrote to her several times after that, but got no more letters from her." During the recital of the foregoing facts MS Dart had appeared quite calm, but as he sat in si- lence for a few moments his grief broke out afresh, He wept and groaned in agony of mind and ex. claimed : Oh, tell me what to do, madam! Givd me some counsel-some advice. Shall I make come plaint before the city officials and send out detect tives? Or, shall I leave her to what seems to be her fate?" "Of the two suggestions I would prefer the lat ter. In pursuing the former you expose the affair to the whole world. In leaving her to her fatey or to the course she has chosen, but few if Any veept myself will ever know that she is your sistel  that class with which you found her no one will care who she is, where she cafe fr6m, dr what be, 6  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7907-00000022"/> 42   DELL DART ; OR, WITHN THE MVESHRES; comes of her. She has no doubt donned mOale at- tire agatin .s she took no clo)thing with her. You nmight, go to the place where you found her; but as the appears so determinedl to pursue the bent of her strange inclination or infaituation r do not know thalt you could acconplishh anythi!g that would prove a benefit to either of you. As far :s duty is concerned I thilk that you 1:ve fulfilled it to the letter. Of course there re warlmer, tenderer ties binding you to thiis only anid dearly-loved sister than ilerely cold dut y, which must :an1d will ren- der you unhtppy for lifeb, but I feel t ha t exposure will:not lessen the affliction. I would advi;e you to keep quiet, and the tinle may come when shl will see the fully of her w:1vywa rdlno s or infilatua tion--or hallucinatiol, car whatever spell it is thth binds her at recsent to this strange lifl.' '"I1 thiiiik your advice is good and wise," he saidl, "and will be guided by it. I will keep perfectly quiet, but will make one more efibrt to learn the cause of this estrangement i'omln all that is good and pure and womallly. I will write a letter to her asking an explanation. alld also tell her that whenever she elels lile coming to me to do so, no matter how low 'ishe has slnken in the scale of guilt. or crirme-that if neerd be we will' perish to- gether. I will direct-it to the postoffice at A---, imthe name of J. Clevelalll. If she gets it it may do some good, it can do no liarm at least," he said with a bitter heart-bruised sigh. "You can tell her .also, Mr. Dalrt, that she can depen:l upon my frien'lship. antl say that it is my earnest request that she write to ,no or send for me should she ever need nursing or sisterly coun- sel.'" '"I will do so, and thank you, too,"' he said; ! and noow I will leave you for the present, ly 'business is very urgent. I will let you know," he continued, "should I get an answer."   DELL DART; OR. WITHN THE MESHES   43 With this assurance Mr. Dart took lhis leave. Aga;in mnv little home b)ecame quiet, nlld the old : settled routine of' liland and head work went oi. Months passel, and still I had received not even a line firon Mr. Dtht, anl( the whole afia}ir was grad- ually naking its place with other eventfuil ,cenes of my life- -b)ecoming joo:1 for thought--when o'ne day I took up a newspaper and read the followinog announcement t; DIED.--Sdeltnlyy. at hiQi rPsidePneo in Placer county, M1r. Cllerne. Dart, 1 nwiivre (,f BloS-ton, l[;ss. During the two Iours which followed the rend- ing of the above annolncemrnent, I lived those terri- ble ,cenes connected with t'ell Dart and her no doubt heart-broken brother over again anid agrain. Where was poor Cell? Would-- sh e hear of his death? and many other questions of like nnture came up only to be disnmissed unanswered. This new exicitement of min  sted ted a few  days. and took the usual course of events. Three years had passed! Three-years of cha nge and trial and heart-aches, and clouds. with ,an oc- casional gleam  of sunshine, such as comle: only from the natural, sunny nooks of the heart. There were few bright spots for poverty's' children in those diays of gold and ditmonds, especially if those same children hbappened to be women strug- gling between pride and the haggard fice of. ,ant. One day just three years and six months. from the morning upon which I discovered the mysteri- ous disapplearance of' Dell Dart from my comforta- ble little home in Sacramento, I found .myself an inmfte of a pleasant wayside inn,. The true com- forts of a home combined with every accommpa.- ' tion for strangers weary friom: the dust and hlett of -- the day's travel.; the cool, , gentle : bLieezes,.cplnng through the trellis work which supported a tariqty of creeping-vines on the back porch, revived and refreshed my tired body and turned my thoughts  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7907-00000023"/> "  DELL DART ; OR, WITHN THE MESES. into a sort of rosv channel of romance. It was early Spring, and all nature seemed to be serenad- ing the bright, happy-faced queen who had spread her royal mantle of gay colors over the hills and vales,making asoft carpet for the feet of weary mortals to tread upon, and an attractive picture on which the eyke of the lovers of nature might rest. The house and garden attached were situated on the banks of one of the prettiest rivers in the State at that particular season of the year. Its clear waters Vere turbid and rapid from the melt- ing snow in the mountains. At times as it rushed, and labored, and dashed in its wild and reckless fury itseemed to be chanting a low and solemn dirge-a hollow murmuring, mingled with the sul- len roar, and sorrowful, soughing, deep-sighing, mournful sounds, then seeming to die away in the distance. Little weird whisperings, voices min- Mgled with children's mirthful, gleeful laughter formed the music of the water-spirits. Seated in a large easy-chair in the sitting-room, with all silent around me save those voices of Na- ture, I dosed off while repeating a quotation from -Bryant-beautiful lines to a river; ** Amid young flowt ts find tender grass, Thine endless infancy shall pass ; And singing down thy narrowae glen, Shall mark the fadtling race of minen." How long I lingered in this dreamy, half-waking half-sleeping state I do not exactly know, perhaps ten minutes, perhaps a little longer. I awoke with a sudden start, and thought It saw a receding shadow as I looked towards the door leading to another room. The door was ajar and all was still. I looked and listened for a moment, then came to the conclusion that it was an imaginary shadow. While settling the question about the reality of the receding shadow I suddenly recol- lected that some one had just the moment before I raised my head whispered in mtny ear :   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MSTRESS  45 "Come to the- river, to-night." I was an entire stranger at the house, and that was the only habitation within a mile at least. Surelv, no stranger would take the liberty to come whispering about mny ears just for the fun of the thing.  Come to the river, tonight," had just as surely been whispered near my ear-yes as surely as I lived. No dream was ever as plainly im- pressed upon the senses as those mysterious whis- pering. I arose and walked towards the door through which I had seen the shadow flit. I could see a bed neatly spread and other articles of bed- room furniture, that was all. I turned and walked out on the porch, from which I saw the landlord and his wife busily engaged in a garden a short distance from the house. Feeling somewhat ner- vous from the little circumstances which I have just related, I took a sun-bonnet from a nail upon which it hung, put it on my head and sauntered down to the spot where they were planting some early vegetables. Did you get a good nap?" enquired the old lady, smiling pleasantly. "Yes," I replied ; and then asked how long she thought I had been asleep. "Oh, not more than twenty minutes; but," she -continued, "I think short naps in the day time do a person more good than a long sleep.' "Oh, yes," I said, "a little nap is sometimea quite refreshing while a sound day-light sleep causes lassitude and langour. Do you live here alone?"I asked, for I had seen no other human being about the place since my arrival there on horseback about two hours before noon. "Yes, pretty much,'-' was the quiet reply, ex- cept when a traveler comes. Sometimes we have one or two or more every day for a week, and then may-be w6'll be alone a week. Sometimes my daughter comes up and brings her children and  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7907-00000024"/> "  DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESES stays a few days; and our son and llis wife come occasionally when it is pleasant; but they all- live a good bit away and have big famnilies and don't get here ofteii, so pap and I've lcearned to be pretty good company for one another." "Is there no one around the iouse except your- selves?"I asked, with a view of settling the doubt about the shadow and the whisper. 'n Not a soul but we three-you, I and the old man. Why, do you feel lonesome?" "No," I said, "but I had a dream while I was napping, and it seemned so like reality that I thought it could hardly be a dream." "Oh, I've oiten had them direams %when I'.ve been tired and laid down to rest awhile--some- thing like night-mare." "More like a day scare, old lady!" exclaimed the jolly old nlan. We all laughed at this new and original version of a day dream, and after a little more pleasant chat I walked into a little 'piece of meadow and picked a boqiuet oi wild flowers alld grasses, and seeing the old couple leaving the g:arden I hastened to overtake them and go with theln to the house. But, old as they were, they were too nlimble for me, and just as I entered the gate leading into the garden) and through which I had passed out a lit- tle while before, they had reached the porch and disappeared through the dining-rooln door. There was a large rock standing iust outside the gate, it was very large and divided in the middle. I had stopped a few moments when passing it on the -way down to the meadow to admire its gigantic size and peculiar shape. As I turned to fasten the gate my. attention was attracted to a fluttering sound. I looked .up, and to my surprise and .astonishment I saw a small note tied to astring, danglilg from the crevice. Notwithstanding my heart beat with nervous fear and dread, curiosity led me to snatclh   DELL DXRT; OR, WITHN THE MSHJES.   47 it; as I did so I ran with all the speed of' a fright- ened ddeer, never stopping to look'b hehind. I en- tered thie house andi passed quickly into the bed- room whch had been assigned me. On entering I closed the door, -and ifistantly tore open the note. "Great heaLven!"I exclatimed, while drops of perspiration ga;there:l upon my forehead. I trem- bled and shook in every limb while I read : Dear Friend:-Co,n(? 1lwn to tho riwpr to-night just ns soon1 H thSe ,l111 t141Rs iR r. nsleep. Keflp in the shadlw *f the allIk. and d(oin't fil o com(. ,lle. Yol1 l1 Ifmay depenId Iplon your'coiliD! llt'et well tihe warling! D,:LLr, DART. ': Dell Dart! Can it be possible!"I mentally ejaculatedl. I read the note over arnd over. Could it. h:ve I)eeni her voice tha0t lhad whi'pered ill my ear dur- illc the afternoon? I was so bewildered and ner- vous tht [ fet lile gro:lning out in agony. I was not afraid of L'ell Dart; but, oh, what dreadful wLrnfing was she about to give?  Why had I stopped in thalt lollnely place aud with entire stran- gers? Perhaps this old man and woman were con- tederates of some of the nmany bands of despera- does which I ha;l 1heard infested that region of the counltrys. If there was (dangter would it not be best to fly while there wats timle ad light? My horse was fleet ,and fititltftl; I could easily reach the nlext town before (.-dark. Yes, I would fly! Why should I stay and tlice a pending danger?" I was about to rush and order my horse saddled when my eye Hell upon a few fiaintlv written words on the other side of the paper. By close examinar tion I made out the follolwing  P. S.-DI' t 'i ve nI ntlrin, either by word or lok.. The Ie .-t Fllhw of -x,itlenlelt autsiide of Ihe ihouse would per- hiap- nlt oily cotst He my life, but your own, and the' lives of t he old f. lkrs.           D D. Oh, how could I conceal my agitation! I felt like crying out for counsel and succor. Never un- til that moment had I known the true' feeling of  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7907-00000025"/> 18   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE NESUBS. fear. I walked up and down the room wringing my hands in nervous 'agony. I must stay. I must obey the warning given by Dell. I knew the hand- writing, or perhaps I should have doubted the fact of her having anything to do with the affair. In the midst of these horrid fears I was summoned to supper. I had very little appetite for the excellent and bountiful evening meal which had been pre- pared by the host and' hostess. "I believe you feel lonesome and scared here in this out of the way place; but you need not, for we have lived here seven years and have never been disturbed by 'man nor beast," said the old man,-whom I shall call Hall. "I'd be a little scary," said Mrs. Hall, "if I thought anybody knew that we had that eight thousand dollars in gold dust in the house." "Eight thousand dollars!"I exclaimed in uni- feigned surprise. "Yes," said she, "a miner that stops with us sometimes is about to go home. He is in the habit of drinking once in a while, and when he does he is perfectly crazy, and don't remember anything when he gets sober. He didn't want to let the folks in town know how much he had, nor that he Was going home, 'cause he had been fleeced by them three years ago, so he left it with us about two nonths ago for safe keeping.. He starts next Wed- nesday. Thank goodness. then we'll get rid of the dreadful temptation that it would be if any of them stage-robbers and highwaymen knew it was here." With this bit of information the truth flashed across my mind. The stage-robbers and highray- -men had mode the discovery, and Dell Dart, the girl gambler, was here to warn me at the proper time and in the proper way. "You go to bed early, I suppose?"I ventured -to a ky. "Ohj yes ; Mr. Hall goes to bed at dark when   DELL DART -; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.. 49 there are no strangers here, and I follow pretty soon. We are often called up at night by the miri- ers who pass here on their way from town. We keep a little whisky for sale, and sometimes they want a supper of ham and eggs, and then we get up. That's about all the profitable custom we have had since the stage took the new road." "I shall go to bed immediately," I said, arising from the table. "Well, I don't think you'll have nightmare to- night; not front an overloaded stomach, at all events," laughed the old gentleman. I picked up the little lamp which had been pre- pared for me and followed by Mrs. Hall I entered the bed-room. "Now you needn't be the least bit afraid," she began, " for we sleep right in the next room but, one, and if anything happens or you feel lonesome just call out and I will come and lay down with ,you." How good and motherly those words sounded, and with a sudden feeling of weariness and dear- ness I threw my arms about her neck and kissed her wrinkled face. t' Good night," she said, while a tear stood in her eye and tearul sounds almost choked her ut- terance. That darling daughter's form and face, now another's to kiss and caress, was no doubt be- fore her in imagination. d'Good night," I repeated after her. , [heard the aged couple retire. A few :minutes after I heard Mr. Hall' snoring and . Mrs. Hall breathing deeply. I thought now was the time for oae ,to slipout; the moon was shining, -but it would soon disappear. I kept in the shade and :stae Xsftly but tremblingly down to the river. Oh, how ijS waters groaned and sang the dreary song of distress; it seemed like the wailing cries of im- prisoned spirits. Justas I reached the bank I 7  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7907-00000026"/> 50   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. saw a figure in male attire. I started with horror. My heart seemed to stop its pulsations ; I felt faint and dizzy. The figure remained still, while a low but distinct whisper reached my ear: 4* Keep close to the rock. Don't come out into the moonlight, and for heaven's sake keep perfect- ly still."' There was something so ghostly, mysterious and dreamy about the scene that I was completely overcome. Mry strength failed, and I sank down faint and exhausted. With the stillness and fleetness of a cat Dell glided around the rocks and in a moment was bathing my head with water, which she had scooped up in her jaunty little hat. As I revived she caught me in her arms and clasped me fondly to her heart. "Oh, I could have given you all the warning I dare give you in the note, but I could not forego the happiness which I knew this hurried meeting would bring; but we must be very brief. In one hour from now I must be miles away from here. I heard your voice last night in an adjoining room. I heard you say that you expected to stop a day or two at the Mountain View House to rest. I vowed to see you, even though I lost my worthless life in the attempt. Oh, tell me, do you know aught of my poor brother?"' What should I say? I hesitated. "Speak quick! We have but a few moments." "Your poor brother is dead." 4' Deaid! Great God! My brother-my poor brother!" - It was well that the river roared and. moaned, or her pitiful exclamations would have awakened the sleepers at the house. - She sank down at my feet, and wept and moaned in low but bitter wails. '"Oh," she whispered, "I am the same misera- ble coward,or I would this instant plunge into   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.  5 those rapid waters and end my miserable existence." For about five minutes she wept; then with a sudden start she arose, again threw her arms about  my neck, pressed me again and again to her bosom, and then with her tears and grief pushed back in- to her heart out of sight and hearing of mortal eye and ear, she said, hurriedly: "You must quit this place in the morning." Seeing that I was about to question her she placed her hand lightly over my mouth and said: "Listen, there is a pleasant house about ten  miles from here. Take the left hand road after you cross the ravine. It's the Texas House. Be sure and leave here in the morning. Make any excuse you like, but be sure and go. And now I must leave you. You are safe to-night. Good-bye. Pray for poor Dell." As she pressed the last kiss upon my lips she placed a small package in mny hand, and before I could utter a word she was gone. I stood and strained my eyes and ears, but I could neither see nor hear aught of the figure, which but a moment before had clasped me so lovingly. I hastened to the house, slipped into the room with as little noise as possible. I first took off my shoes and dress, then lit the lamp. Upon examining the package-I found one hundred dollars. but not a line to tell me of her strange life or where she could be found. Iretired and strange to say, I slept soundly until called by Mrs. Hall.  About halfpast six the following morning I in- formed them that I had changed my mind. and would leave after breakfast. The old people ex- pressed surprise, and said theey hoped it was not because I was not pleased with their simple ac- commodations. I assured them that I had..been well pleased with the entertainment, but upon re- flection, I had concluded that it would be best for me to go to Forest City. I had written a few days  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7907-00000027"/> 52   DELL DART; OR, WITHN TIIE MESMES. ago to Sacramento to have a package forwarded to, that place (which was true), and perhaps it might get misplaced. This excuse satisfied them, and with many kind wishes for my success, I left them about nine o'clock. As I passed the Texas house I looked all around, thinking perhaps that Dell might possibly be waiting there for me, but seeing no one outside I rode on, and about three o'clock I reached my destination. I remained about that neighborhood attending to my business for several days, and frequently heard of young Cleveland, the female gambler who dressed in male. attire, but not one whisper of Dell Dart. Shortly after these circumstances had occurred' I sailed from California to the Sandwich Islands, and amid new excitements and scenes and cares I seldom thought of poor Dell. She was not entire- ly forgotten, for at times when my thoughts were very foreign to anything connected with her, the whole affair; with herself in the centre, would rush like a sudden whirlwind to my mind, and I would seem to be talking with her. Sometimes I was superstitious enough to think that her thoughts must have been acting in some way upon me, and that perhaps she was sick and suffering, or in trou- ble, and her spirit sought communion with mine, and I would sigh out a little prayer; asking God to help her.; and thus the vision and the memory of the absent one would pass away- for many months, and amid the changing scenes, and passing friend- ships, and defeated aspirations, and future hope- cherishings I had ceased to remember, at least with any interest, the circumstances of my association with Dell Dart, the girl gambler. Five years had passed. Again business made :it necessary that I should visit the mining districts. I was engaged in the sale of - a book, and of course this occupftion brought me face to face with all   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.   58 kinds of people, from the millionaire down to 'the inhabitant of the most humble cabin-from   the holy man professing Christianity and confining himself to the straight and narrow path to the unfor- tunate frequenter of the bar-room; each and all receiving my solicitations with that reverence and respect which every well behaved woman can coIm-i mand from  the most degraded, whisky-besotted American man on God's footstool, if not too much under the influence of the fiery fiend. One day while passing through the streets of a small mining town known as St. Louis, I was ac- costed by a small boy, who said, as he handed me a little note : "Are you the lady that this note is for?" I read the superscription and replied  "This is my name and I suppose the note is for me." "I guess so," said the urchin, "for Mary R told me to hunt up the woman that was selling the books and hand it to her." I thanked the boy and put the note into my pocket. After disposing of what books I had with me I hastened to my room    and lost no time in perusing the npte.  It read as follows DEAR MADAM:-You will please excuse the liberty I take in writing this note to you tor I am a woman outside the pale of society-a stray from the fold. Still, I ami a woman with as warm and tender a heart in my bosom as walks the earth, and I can shed tears of pity for the suffer- ing. I have in my house a poor, unfortunate creature; she is dying from the effects of hard drink and exposure to all kinds of weather. In mmy heart, before my God, I believe her purely virtuous, but a poor victim to man's and wom- an's treachery, and the burning appetite for rum, She is dying slowly. She would die quickly if we should stop giving her all the rum she seems to require. She, -it ap- -pears knew you'in other days. She has talked about,you :many times, and hearing that you were in town -la3t: night she became almost frantic to see you. But how? That was the question. She is too far gone to leave the hous,'a-and We could not dare to ask you to come here in this house of sin and crime., Just as we were talking the matter over and Jessie, as we call her, was saying that she knew "that  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7907-00000028"/> "   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MSATMS. you would come to see her in her dying moments, the doc- torcanme in,and we told him,and asked him what he thought about it, and he said : 61 If she is a true woman she will not refuse to see poor Jessie;" aind then offered to bring you here hitnself, but unfortunately he was obliged to leave town during the-night; and, Jessie lbecame so rest- less and seemed to be sinking so fast that I thought I would venture to ask you to come it the doetor should not happen to get hack to-night in time to see you, if you will consent to do so. I will tell you 'how you can come, and it will never be known by any but the doctor, myself and the per- son who will bring you. Death will soon seal poor Jessie's lips. There is an old lady living just back of my house-a good, kind-hearted, pure woman. She comnes in and talks toJessie quite often. Her name is Shefter. If you will call at her house to-night about dusk while nmost people are eating supper, she will bring you in Ihe back door. Once in, you will never see a soul save the three mtntioned, un- less the doctor should happen in. Will you comne and give a little comfort to this poor dying woma;n? She told me to write the name of Dell Dart in this note, and you would un- derstand what that meant. Do come, and God will bless you.                  MARY R. "Go!" I exclaimed; "why what have the good Christian women of New York and other large cities been doing for the last thirty years? Hun- dreds of them spending their time -and money and pity and sympathy with and for such fallen ones. This sin and corruption is not like small-pox atid other contageous diseases-one cannot carry it awav in their dress. Go to Dell Dart in her dy- ing hour? Yes. let the world scoff! I had no doubt but what the angels would be there with their pure white wings, ready to bear the repentant spirit to the gates of the beautiful hereafter. "What, that outcast's spirit be taken to Heaven!'" I think I hear the selfbrighteous exclaim. Oh, yes, even that poor, weary? sin-sick spirit, if it is truly penitent. "O)h, well; then there's no use trying to be good to get to Heaven -if such characters get there so easy."  Easy! Oh, poor mistaken hi} manity! Easy! Why that poor woman ' had passed through a thousand hells during that seven vears of her life. "Why did she not turn from it, then?" askls the self-righteous again. Because, she   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES.  55 had been caught within the meshes while gliding down the cool, pure stream of innocent maiden- hood.  Thenet-workwas intricate, the threads from which it was woven were strong and unyield- ing, and in the struggle perhaps the fins-the mor- al power and strength-had become impaired and weak, and had the victim of t he meshes contrived to have escaped, she could no longer have glided with pure, innocent freedom down the winding streams with her unimpaired companions. They would have looked at her, gaped at her coldly, and then dashed off, leaving her in her helpless condi- tion. But the Angels, sweet messengers of the meek and lowly Nnzarine, came to fulfill their mis- sion, which was to wash the poor bruised-heart, to whisper of the brightness and beauty beyond the pearly gate. They bore the petition from  the weary-eyed, heart-burdened, erring one to the Higher Power. The petition is read, accepted and recorded, and now the gentle harbingers have re- turned to await the last struggle that shall extri- cate the immortal from the meshes of the mortal and bear it upward amid the hallelujahs of the blessed. At a little past six o'clock on that gloomy De- cember night, while the winds were howling and the snow was drifting, I followed my guide into the chamber of the dying penitent. As my eyes fell upon the wasted form and sunken eyes I started back, for a moment, with astonishment. t: "Come, oh, come!" cried out a feeble voice from the bed. I  approached. Could it be possible that that skeleton was the once beautiful, blooming, graceful Dell Dart. I stooped down  and kissed her then cheek. She put her loving hands and arms- about my neck and held me with all the strength she had left.                 . I knew you would come," she sobbed'; "oh,  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7907-00000029"/> 56   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. how glad I am to see you once more before I go. I have been praying for death for a week, but Mary here won't let me die. She insists on keeping the spark alive, but I cannot last long, and now," she continued, "if Mary and Mrs. Shefter will leave u1 alone foran hour I will try and give you the history of my going astray and the dreadful re- sults." The two women retired and we were left alone. "I fear the exertion will be too much for you, Dell, my dear," I said. Oh, no; I may be obliged to take a little stim- ulant. God will spare me-to tell the story of my *youthful folly and my mad, unnatural love. But ,firsalet me tell you that one of my most damning nibs was inborn-became a part of my nature be- fore I saw the light of day; and, I do most Solemnly believe now on my dying bed and in the fape of Heaven, that our parents through the influ- ence and customs of society, breed within us appe- tites and desires over which our own lives have under control. Those blight spots may be partially oblitered from our natures by early training and example, but let the influence and example be re- mxoved and the crppled twig will fall an easy prey to the wooing breezes. ; My father was a drunkard, one upon whom the appetite was fastened with a vice-like grip. I be- lieve I inherited this even in my mother's womb, for she, poor woman, who had never been under the influence of this fiendish spirit, craved the burning liquid for months-craved it through the Embryo child, the drunkard's offspring-and for i .months after I was born, although my mother ;oagthed and sickened at the smell of whisky, I ,ould only be kept quiet under its baneful influ- ,enc. This was kept up during infancy, but dur- ing the years of childhood I had never been ,per- ,;mitted to taste or smell of alcoholic liquor, and my   DELL DART ; OR, WITHN THE MASHES. 57 father died feeling assured that I bad outgrown the dreadful curse; but alas! it was still- lurking in my system, at least this is my idea of it, for al- though I bad never tasted it and bad no desire for it, and had my mother lived to have watched me into womanhood and from her bands I had passed, all pure and untainted into the arms of a good, true, sober husband, perhaps the appetite never would have returned ; but, when exposed to temp. tation through the arts,-and wiles, and teachings of others I soon fell a victim to the blighting curse. The appetite came back with all of its in.- bred, inborn force. Yes, I was a drunkard when you took me, but once from under its fiendish in. fluence, I felt no desire for it, and could have lived on a lifetime without it, had there been no tempt. ation spread in my quiet path. I haveunbur. dened to you my suffering from my besetting sin, I will now tell you the dreadful secret of my early downfall. You know from brother, I suppose, somethingof my girlhood." I told her that her brother had told me all of her history that he knew with the exception of the natural affliction which she had revealed to me. "Yes, poor fellow, he was spared the pain of knowing all. Here she appeared exhausted and faint, ( I fear," I said, " that it is too much exertion," I gave her a few spoonfulls of brandy, and she proceeded  e  I will have to just give you a brief sketch without going into details. "At the age of twelve I had read at least one hundred sensation romances--those with 'deep laid plots and highly colored. Living as I did with no companions save Mrs. Avery, who never per-       r mitted me to go from  under her eye, except to school, and then she often went with me and came 8  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7907-00000030"/> - 58   DELL DART OR, WITHN THE MESHES. for me. She had a wild passion for novel reading, and always permitted me to read just what I pleased. I, of: course, looked upon myself as. a heroine. Still, this did not appear to interfere with my studies as I kept up with all my classes. Well, I was ignorant of everything but just what I had gleaned from books. I had been taught to feel that I had a, rich, good-natured brother who would and did more than supply my wants, and I thought would be willing to forgive, any folly of which I might be guilty. I am growing weak and I shall be brief. One morning just after my six- teenth birthday as I was on my way to school I noticed a gentleman standing in the. doorway of one of the large saloons by which I passed daily. - He -gave me a look that I never forgot. That look went to my heart. T passed on, but the look and face of the handsome man haunted me all through the school hours, and as I passed home from school that evening I looked in vain for the same face, I paused right in front of the spot where I stood in *the morning. Disappointed, I reached home. I slept but little that night. The next morning as. I was going through the hall to the dining-roomni I met the woman who had been in the habit of wash- ing for Mrs. Avery, standing In a recess just as I tprpe4 to descend the stairs. I had never taken much notice of her before, but she spoke up quite familiarly to we and said;: "This is a pleasant morning." "Yes," I replied, and was about to pass when she laid her band on my curls and said ; "Miss Dell, you have the prettiest hair I ever saw, it is just like perfect threads of gold." Thee were the first words of flattery that had ever fallen upon my ears, and they went right to my silly heart. They left a sweet, tingling, sil- very sound upon my ear, and a leaping, dancing, joyous feeling in my heart, The woman read my   DELL nART; OR. WITHN THE MESHES. 59 thoughts and feelings. She saw that I was sus- ceptible of flattery, and she said: ; Every curl of that shining hair should be hung with a diamond. If I had them on my head and had such a face, no mah should win my heart who was not able to put a circlet of diamonds upon my forehead. We both laughed, and I said: 'KOh, you flatter me! You will make me proud." "You have enough to be proud of in your beau. ty and education." Just then Mrs. Avery canme along, and she slipped Y r arm about my waist and we walked down td breakfast. "What was the washernvoman saying to you, Dell, that made you blush so?" she asked after we were seated at the table. "She said that my hair was handsome." I said shyly. "I think," said Mrs. Avery, " she is a bold kitid of woman, and I don't like her; but she is .-t splendid washer and very prompt, I never tallk with her, and I don't want you to, at least any more than you can -help. There is some talk about her, and I would not employ her only I cannot get one that will suit me as .well." At that moment tile servant came in and the conversation ended. After breakfast I went to my room. I thought of the handsome stranger, and: then of my golden hair and what the woman had said. I put on one of my most becoming dresstes, tied a blue ribbon on my hair, cast several glances at my reflection in the mirror, and then started for school. Mrs; Avery had gone out just ahead of mle to go to the market, and as I approached the front door, school books in hand, I heard my tame called in a half- whisper, and upon looking around I saw thtissame washerwoman with her head just inside of thd back door.  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7907-00000031"/> 60   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MSHES. "Come here, a tninute,' she said. I ran back and remarked: "It is near school time; I must hurry. What do you want?" \ 1 I;only wanted to ask you if you would like to have your fortune told." "Oh, yes!"I said. "Well." continued the wotimaht iIf yIti dWill come out of school an hour before It closes this evening I will meet you and go with you to one i/    who can tell you just who you will nmarry, and everything that is going to happen." We agreed to meet at a certain place at three o'clock, and I hurried off. As I passed the saloon where I had seen the handsome stranger I involE untarily cast my eye towards the door. There he was, and as I passed our eyes met. I Was frights ened at my boldness and resolved never to pass that way again; Poor child! how little I knew of my own heart. (unning3 experienced tuan! how well he understood it. He saw its very pulsation in that blushing glance and exclaimed, 'She is mine if I go slowt' That afternoon I met the Washerwtoman accord. ing to promise, and after going through several dirty, narrow streets we ascended a flight of stairs and knocking at a door, were admitted to a small apartment. "Want your fortunes told?" asked an ugly look- ing old Wotnan.  "6 This young girl does, and nmind you tell her the truth, granny," said my companion; "I alleks do that," said the old crone) as she ushered me into c private room. I was frightened almost to death. I trembled and wished myself safe at home. ' Don't be soared," said the ald hag, with a chuckle. She sat down in a chair opposite me and took my hand and began by saying:   bfLtt DARt OR, WITHbN THE MESHES. 61 "You are very pretty and-- will have many ad; tnirers. Oh, you have one lover already! He is a handsome fellow and a real gentleman, rich as a king and highly connected; he will be your hus. band. Ah, you are a lucky girl for an orphan who was left poor. Let me see! Ah, I see now a brother off ouver the water. He will be married in a few weeks, then your only protector will be gone, It is well that this rich gentleman has fallen in love with you; you can snap your finger at that spiteful sister-in-law-your brother's wife. Oh, how she will hate you and envy you for your beauty. I advise you to get married to this man just as soon as he asks you; he will make you happy." She said many more things and ended by saying, "He will be your husband, that is your fate." How could I help trusting in her-she an entire stranger, to tell me things which no one knew ex- cept myself She certainly must know all things. Little dreaming that the plot had been laid by the Wvasherwoman, the fortune-teller and the handsome stranger, I gave her the fee, and told her that I would send her a piece of my wedding cake, and took my leave. The next morning as I was passing on my way to school, the handsome stranger approached me, and modestly said : "Excuse me Miss, is not this your handkerchief? I tookit. There was my   name, Dell Dart, in one corner. "Yes, sir," I replied. "I thought you dropped it. I should have liked to have kept it, but I thought that would not be honest." This was also a  little maneuvre between the washerwoman and the stranger.  Oh, how pure were my thoughts at that moment! How could I think that my love-my full, heart- gushing, maiden love-could meet with aught but  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7907-00000032"/> 62   DELL DART; OR, lTftIN THE MESHES. purity in return. . It was a case of mutual, lasting love; a love whose fire never died out, never cooled in its ardor-a love that knit our hearts and fates in an indissoluble tie which naught but death could or did sever. No, not even severed in death! we will meet on that shore. He awaits me. We shall spend our eternity together, Eustash, my lover, my husband!" "You are getting nervous," I said, "will you have a little more of the brandy?" "Yes," she gasped. I looked at her; her eyes were glazed and ap- parently set. I was about to calll for help, but she waved her hand. I administered the stimulant and in a few moments she roused again and said: 6 When those spells come upon me I feel that Eustash is holding out his hands just on the other side ready to clasp me." ' You had better rest awhile," I said, "I am afraid that you will exhaust yourself, and make your last moments more painful." Oh, no! I will tell you all and then go to sleep. In two Weeks after I met Eustash Delmora I became his wife-yes, his loyal, lawful Knife. If he was wicked and an outlaw he was good and true and kind to me. It was a clandestine mar- riage. True, he deceived Dell Dart in regard to his wealth and standing in the world, but td Dell Delmora he was true and faithful. He Was half Spanish; the son of a sea-pirate and a beautiful Spanish girl. He had never eaten one mouthful of honest bread in his life. At the time I met him he had only two months prbviouslyr escanp'ed from State prison in Louisiana. The officers were on his track, and before I had been a bride twenty- four hours I was disguised as a youth in male attire and on my way in the steerage of a ship to dali&amp; fornia. Eustash taught me to play every kind of X          game with cards during that voyage. Instead of   DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES,  63 coming direct to California we stopped for a while at Panama and went out into the country. I soon learned to speak Spanish pretty well, and having a good musical education I succeeded in becoming a favorite. I never tried to make it appear that I was a man. It was known that I was the wife of Eustash, and with the company in which we min- gled it made little difference. After tasting the first glass of wine the inborn appetite came back, and I was drunk mIre than half the time, but Eustash used to be very tender and kind to me. After spending our honeymoon among the natives we began to make preparations for the completion of the trip to California. But alas! the day be- fore the ship sailed Eustash was discovered and arrested. The officers were very kind to me. Theyoffered to send me to my friends wherever they might be. I clung to my husband. Poor fellow! He was hand-cuffed, but I was permitted to remain with him until the steamer from Califor- nia should come, and then be would be taken to New Orleans. I should be left alone. We talked till daylight the night before our separation, and it was decided that I should go on to California in male attire, taking a steerage passage, and when- I arrived I should go direct to the place where Iwas found by my brother. Eustash gave me letters of introduc'tion both in Spanish and English. He gave me live hundred dollars, all the money he had. He told me that some of the friends to whom he had written would get me a situation. to play the piano in one of the many saloons and he charged me to keep in practice in gambling. "Oh, Dell, my darling," he said, "be true to me as I swear to be to you. I have but two years more to serve in the prison, and then I will come to you, and I swear to you that I will never commit anoth- er crime that will lay me liable to imprisontment. When I join you in California I will try to honestly  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7907-00000033"/> "  DELL DART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES, obtain a sum sufficient to take us to some part of Mexico, and we will settle down, and I will try, for your dear sake, to be good, honest and true." I promised eternal constancy, and I also prom. ised that I would be just as moderate as possible about drinking, and would take just as good care of myself as possible until he came. We parted! he to go to pay the penalty of his crime, I to Cali. fornia, and it was in that very place where I was waiting for Eustash, that my brother found me under the assumed name of Cleveland. I had drank but little for several weeks previous, and I thought I would try to go and live with my brother and tell him all; and perhaps with his help Euss tash might become a good, honest man. I might get rid of the curse of rum by living entirely away from it. I never wanted it while I was in Sacra. mento. But alas! my fate had to be fulfilled. Just as these pleasant desires were fastening themselves upon me I received a letter from a man who knew the whole secret of Eustash's imprisonment. He said that Eustash was on his way to California, having broken out of prison again. Then I be, came restless. He would come and would need me to cheer him and help him. You know how I left. I went with my beloved that night, and through all the years that followed I clung to him. He joined a band of highwaymen, but swore to me that he would never imbrue his hands in blood; that he would save life whenever he could, The night after I warned you at Mr. Hall's the house was robbed, and but for the good management of Eustash the old folks would have been murdered. Oh, we passed through many, many horrid scenes. I have suffered ten thousand deaths, and as I said to you in that dear, little parlor on N street, in Sacramento, 'I might live to be a wrinkled old hag and never see a day of real happiness.' I never did until one year ago. My mad, blind love for   DELL DABT ; OR, WITHN THE ME*SHFR. 65 my outlaw husband had no real true happiness in it. One year ago Eustash got hurt; we had a few hundred dollars, and I had just recovered from an attack of delirium tremens. I knew that Eustash could not live long. I was weary of life-weary of that bad, wicked life we had been leading. I said to my husband one day, while sitting near his bed- side in a back room of a gambling saloon : A Come, darling, let us leave this kind of life; we have not long to live. The doctor says that I have got the consumption, and he told me last night that you could not possibly live long, at all events-that you could never be well again. Let us leave this life of shame and disgrace and for the little time we do stay on earth let us live alone and try to make ourselves more fit for the hereafter." Poor Eustash drew my face down to his lips and said : "Sweet wife, I fear I have ruined all your pros- pects of a happy hereafter. You have almost con- verted me several times. You have been to me an angel. I have dragged you down oh, so low, I fear there is no pardon for me here or hereafter." And then he wqpt long and bitterly. We both wept, and then and there we vowed to live the rest of our days trying to atone in part for the hateful past. The next day I felt better, and went out and succeeded in getting a miner's cabin, belonging to a mall who was going home to the States. In a few days he gave it to me and said if he never came back it should be mine, and the same afternoon I got a carriage and took Eustash up to our little home. I purchased some articles of comfort, and material for a few suits of female apparel, and that night I sang "Home Sweet Home" to Eus- tash, and we both cried for hours, and slept more sweetly and soundly than we had ever slept dur- ing all -our married life. The doctor came quite 9-  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7907-00000034"/> G6 DsL9ART; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. often to see us, and occasionally an old associate dropped in, but we were alone nmost of the time. I felt that-I was completely weanried from the love -of drink, and, strante ias it 1inay seeni to you, we were really happy for a while. Eust ash began to sink, and two nlonths of our happy days of home life had carely pas,ed when I saw I should soon be alone in the world. Olle night the doctor told me it was-not safe for me to be left alone with Eus- tash, and said hie would send some one. I looked at him for a moment. Hie saw that I wanted to ask for something and dare not. , What is it, Mrs. Delmora?" he kindly asked. "Doctor, Ishould like to have a priest sent in. My husband is-a Catholic by birth and education and I cannot let him die without a prayer. If there is no Catholic priest, please send in some holy man who can pray and speak some words of consolation in his dying moments." "I think," he said, '- that it will be impossible to get a priest, but there is a good old Christian man living about a mile from here. If you like I will bring him and his wifeiup to spend the night with you." "Oh, thank you, doctor," I said, "do bring them. God may yet forgive us." Oh, mly dear friend, the happiness of that night! Those good old folks prayed and sang, and just at daybreak my poor darling passed from this, I trust, to a better world. I think his sins were forgiven, lor, poor fellow, he surely was not responsible for all of his sins, born as he was in sin-never during all of his childhood or boyhood having had the ad- vantage of good examples. Well, he left me. For a long tinie my only companion was an old Mexi- can woman, and I got to drinking a little every day. The doctor said Hrequired it for medicine, (    and so I was just stupified all the time. At last my money was all gone. The old Mexican woman   DELL DART; OR. WITH W THE M1SSERS. 67 left and I was there alone. The doctor would come and bring me a bottle of Bourbon every two or three days, and I should 'have perished there drunk and alone had it not have been for Mar. She heard that I was in a bad condition, and altho; an entire stranger to me she eame and insisted on bringing me here. -She is as kind as she can be and won't allow a loud word to be spoken in the bar-room. The doctor and minister come in al- most evrery daly. I know that I am very near my end, and I wish that I could die while you are here, but I must be patient." I told her that I -would stay with her through  the night if she wished. "Oh no, darling, that would not do. You --must not be disgraced. Why, the whole town would point the finger of scorn at you; no, I must bid you good-by. I hope to meet you in the hereafter." Just at this moment the doctor came in. "This is a dear friend, doctor," said Dell in a faint, pleasant whisper." "You are tired," said the good man. "I was afraid that she would exert herself too much," Irenmarked. "Oh no, madam, not at all. Poor Jessie knows that she cannot live long, andswhen the hope went out the desire very prudently followed it; and, I believe that persons who are passing away should not be debarred the privilege of conversing just when they feel like it. She is now in a quiet slumber an d lmay never awake again to full con- sciousness. Life has been gently ebbing awav since Jyesterday morning, and if she is not closely watched no one will know just when the spark goes out." At that instant the large, blue eyes opened, the lips moved, "Mary," faintly gasped Dell. I stepped to the door and beckoned to the wo- an, who came quickly and hastened to the bedside.  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7907-00000035"/> no   DELL DARt; OR, tWI"THN THE MES=ES. "Good-by, dear good Mary! I hope God wilT' change your heart; don't put it off till a dying moment. Good-by." Mary burst into tears and kissed the sweet, girl- * ish face. I then approached and received a sweet blessing, and then the eyes elosed-the lips faintly murmured, "Eustash I come, God ble-!" and the spirit passed into the unknown land, beyond the power of mortal eye to penetrate. "I will go and bring. my wife," said the- doctor to me. " if you wish to stay." "Very well," I said, I would like tostay a part of thenight. I want to see her neatly robed for the grave." "I have had the house closed up," said Mary,. ' and there will be no one here to-night but Mrs.. Sheffter and myself, and we would be very glad to have yourself and wife present, and also this lady," she said, pointing towards where I stood. The doctor started for his wife, and with the as- sistance of Mrs. Sheffter I washed and laid out the, remains of the once pure and good, but unfortunate woman. All that dreary December night the snow eame silently down! All that night four women worked upon the snowy robe which was to envel- ope the spiritless tenement of clay. Just on the outskirts of the town three men were engaged in constructing a coffin, and the monotonous tack, tack, tack, together with the soughing of the wind throfgh the forest of pines added a tender, touch- ing sorrowfulness to the occasion. Just as daylight greeted the snow-clad hills we laid her all white, silent, cold and beautiful into the crude, unstained box-like coffin. Little rings of golden hair half concealed the delicate wreath of evergreens resting upon her forehead,and a cross of evergreens lay upon her bosom, the symmetri- cal, wax-like hands were clasped lightly upon the emblem of atonement. No millionaires' daughter   DELL DART ; OR, WITHN THE MESHES. 69 ever looked more peaceful, smiling, lovely and angeliclying in her costly tcasket than did this poor, scorned- outcast in that rude box. It was decided by Mary that she should be buried at ten o'clock that morning.  Oh;' 'twas a solemn and a tearful sight to see those rough-handed, shabbily-dressed men one after anther stoop down to look at the cold, white &amp;ace, while they brushed back  their tears and stifling sobs,.and uttered, -"God bless her; she's better off!"Some would burst forth in tears and sob out in lheart-sorrow- ing accents, "Poor girl!" At ten o'clock a few men gathered in the room. The doctor read the 14th Chapter of St. John, and as he pronounced the last clause, "Arise, let uOgo home," a course, rough, but tearful voice, broke forth in the good, old'fashioned Methodist words of the hymn, "Her home is -over Jordan." The doctor, his wife, Mrs. Shaffter and myself joined in and sang amid tears -and penitent .groans. At ten o'clock the remains were followed to the nearest hill-side and let down -in nine feAe of snow. When the warm spring sun had melted the snow a grave was dug and the coffin lowered. A large fallen tree marks the resting place of the once fair maiden, Dell Dart, who fill an early vic- tim to the tangled threads of life's meshes, which the unseen hand of-time cunningly and mysteri- ously weaves, and which, let us hope, the Angelof Death unravels as he bears the world-weary vic- tim across the dark river into the  bright spirit land peopled with the brothers ;and sisters of Char- ity and governed by the Great Teacher, who has said, "Come unto me all ye that are weary ,and I will give you rest." - .THE END, ;  ' " ps'   &#xD;<pb n="70 (Advertisement) -71 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7907-00000036"/> JOHN t. PURGER, 17th Street, Opposite Washington Hall, Merced, WHOLESALE &amp; .RETAIL DEABER IN FAMLY GROCERIES, "QUORS, CIGARS &amp; TOBACCO, And' all other Articles usually found in a Family Groeery Store. ]e^Z Remember tie place--17th St., opposite Washington. Hall. .  MERGCED NURSERY North of Court House Square, MERCED. IFowler &amp; Spafford, Proprietors. CHOICE. ARE OFFERKED' AM THE VERY LOWEST RATES. Fuchias, Cblbus, Geraniums, Strieta Palma, Roses, Evergreens, Ornamental Trees and Shrubs, constantly on hand.   ILiL GEO. E. ISAACS.  THOS. RICARDSON.. ISAACS &amp; RICHARDSON, "UMBER YARD AND South Side of Railroad: Track, MERCED. I&amp;PLUB7 20 ( 9RDO) - do 71; 1^cHn^la Lumber of Every Description Always on hand. Also, a  tEa , :)o  ./OX ilSzB'iOilS) "ATHS, SHNGLES, SHAKES, RUS-TICS, &amp;c., In any quantity. O^k  &#xD;<pb n="72 (Advertisement) -73 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7907-00000037"/> GREEN FRONT STORE. 17th Street, Merced. MCINERNEY   BROS., WHOLESALE AND RETAIL DEALERS IN GENERAL FAMLY GROCERIES, Wines, Liquors and Cigars. J. L. REIDY &amp; CO., Dealers in LADIES DRESS GOODS, BOOTS, SHOES, Etc., Corner 17th and K Sts., Merced, Cal. C. LUANDRAM &amp; CO., VARIETY STORE. Front Street, Merced, Cal. BOOKS, STATIONERY, CONFECTIONERY, TOYS, PICTURE FRAMES, Etc. FINEST BRANDS OF CiGARS &amp; TOBACCO. Constantly on hand and for sale at the lowest prices SIMON, JACOBS k CO., Wholesale and Retail Dealers in BOOTS, SHOES, HATS, GROCERIES, HARDWARE, E, Et Et. ,  Front Street, Merced.   ivi EISB00 c0 o TO iMCTMO      ,2 FASHONABLE DRESSMAKER, 17th Street, Merced.            i Flain Family Sewing Done on Short Notice. Fashionable Dressmakers, 17th Street Corner K, Merced. We Guarantee Perfect Fits in Every Case. AS!"TY STOip          : ,  Font St., Merced. W . M AYER .Proprietor. FRUITS, VEGETABLES, CONFECTIONERY, Cigars &amp; Tobacco, &amp;c., always on hand. JACOB KOCHER, ;Stove, Tinware &amp; Hardware / ESTABLISHMENT. :usflC;iZ^LcOXBXo CAml-"^ Tin and Hardware, Sheet Iron, Stoves of all kinds, Cooking Utensils, &amp;c., constantly on hand aad for sale at Low Prices. .... .  &#xD;<pb n="74 (Advertisement) -75 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7907-00000038"/> V EL CAPITAN HOTEL, MERCED. Point of Departure for Yosemite and Big Trees from the Central Pacific R. R. This house is the largest in the State outside of San Francisco, and is provided with every conven- ience for the pleasure and comfort of its guests, and possesses all the appointments of a first-class hotel. Ladies' Bath-rooms, and Bath-rooms and Barber Shop for gentlemen. H. A. BLOSS.   P. D. WIGGINTON, CHAS. M. BLAIR, MARK HOWELL. WICCINTON, BLAIR &amp; CO-, BANKERS AND REAL ESTATE AGENTS, Merced, Merced County, California. REFER TO Pacific Bank, S. F. Hn. J. W. Bost, S. F. Hon. 0. P. Fitzgerald, S. F. Hon. N. Greene Curtis, Sac. Hon. A. C. Bradford, Fresno. DR. G P. LEE, PHYSICIAN AND SURGEON. MERCED,. OAL. OFFICE-Cook's Drug Store. Residence, 19th -,  . Street) between K. and L, SURGEON VISALIA DIVISION, C. P. B. R   vi   EAGLE HOTEL, FRONT. STREET, OPPOSITE FREIGHT DFPOT, M, ERC ED A. BICK FORD...........................................................Proprietor. Prices Reasonable and fare as good as can be provided at any hotel in the country. Farmers'. Hotel and     Restaurant, 17th Street, near the Corner of M, ,;:  3;:I3nCEI C]BiI3, C'wLi. M . F. M OR A N ......................................................... Proprietor. This house is well and conveniently situated and will be kept with a view to the comfort of guests. Tuolumne Hotel and Restaurant. 17th Street, MERCED. WM. FAHEY..............................................................Proprietor. Travelers and Regular Boarders can be accom- modated at this hotel with as good fare as any hotel in the interior.   t^   UREN'S RESTAURANT. Front Street, MERCED.   SIMON UREN.   Proprieto,.   :BO X.M 3E=or, .;'oz o *0r, . *b-00. MXNCG-3L E:I iElBL. ........... ; ... v  iMealdisitt all hoirs. g  &#xD;<pb n="76 (Advertisement) -77 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7907-00000039"/> vii           I L. D. SEWARD. VII STAR RESTAURANT.                    O sK MCKI 17th :St., between L and M, Merced. ATTO J. M . H ENRY ...................................................  Proprietor. Will practi S9 NOTE THE PRICES. .6a           the State. S aME!^S X., S COtm.  I  MBEXD , 20 O*r.      gation of Lan JOSEPH     LUDESCHER,             P. D. IGGINT( MERCHANT TAILOR,                   WIGG L Street, bet. 16th &amp; 17th, Merced. Office in B PERFECT FITS GUARANTEED.             in all the Sta Millinery and Dressmaking.                   S] lMO Ao OTA 19H.9              . ATTN Front, St., Merced. Orders from the country promptly attended to. FPAsC T   IPOOMD9 1 IS MUIBIB0S i 9 Q 1S9 axx  OFFICE- TOUMG LADIES SEMNERY, MERCED, MERCED CO., CAL. L.12 MRS. E. A. CUNNINGHAM, Principal.         Tacher of This English and Classical School is now opoa for a limited number of young ladies.          Lessons on For. further particulars address,          lar attention MRS. E. A. CUNNINGHAM, Merce4          Residence,   , ..' '.   L D. SEWARD.          D. M. MCKENNBT. MCKENNEY &amp; SEWARD, ATTORNEYS AT LAW, MERGED, GAL. Will practice in any of the Courts of Record in the State. Special attention given to the investi- gation of Land Titles, and Abstracts furnisned. P. D. WIGGINTON.        CHAS. H. MARKS. WIGGINTON &amp; MARKS,   Office in Bank Building, Merced. in all the State and Federal Courts.   Will practice   SILAS W. GEIS, ATTORNEY AT LAW, MERCED, CAL. OFFICE-Front St., next door to the Bank. MUSIC SCHOOL. nEaZo 12 An-G    (DDHM   p79 Teacher of Vocal and Instrumental Music, MERCED, CAL. Lessons on the Piano and Guitar; also, particu- lar attention given to Vocal Music. Residence, 17th St., Merced, &#xD;<pb n="78 (Advertisement) -79 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7907-00000040"/> ix   O. A. R. CASACCIA, FORWARDING AND COMMSSION MERCHANT, And Wholesale and Retail Dealer in GENERAL FAMLY GROCERIES, HARDWARE, CUTLiRY, GLASSWARE, TINWARE, ETC. Opposite Freight Depot, Merced, Cal. SAN JOAQJIN VALLEY STORE! OLCESE &amp; GARIBALDI, Front Street, Merced, Cal. FORWARDING &amp; COMMSSIO N MERCHANTS And Wholesale and Retail Dealers-in Sti^ple Aae :w,n Boy ':Erty Groocdi s, And General Family Groceries, Etc. SCHOENFELD, GOLDMAN &amp; CO., Wholesale and Retail Dealers in   AND COMMSSION MERCHANTS, Merced, Cal. CAPITOL CLOTHNG STORE. ROSENTHAL BROS., 1MERCHANT TAILORS, Front Street, MERCED. Constantly on hand, a large stock of Ready Made Clothing. Also, suits made to order.   KMERCED LIVERY STABLE I7th Street, Merced. WM. J. QUIGLEY............................Proprietor. CARRIAGES,   THORO UGHBRA CES,   BUGGIES, SADDLE HORSES, Etc., Furnished the public at Reasonable Rates. EL CAPITAN STABLE, MERCED. M. McCLENATHAN..................................Proprietor. THOS. HOUSEWORTH &amp; CO., Agents, Office No. 9 Montgomery St., Lick House, San Francisco. Private Teams for Yosemite and Big Trees a ,Specialty. Arrangements made for large or small parties, and satisfaction given, COOK'S PIONEER DRUG STORE, Front Street, Merced, Cal. PURE DRUGS AND     MEDICINES, PAINTS, Oils, Glass, Jewelry, Stationery, Pocket Cutlery, &amp;c. Shirts, Socks, Gloves, Tobacco and Cigars. Physicians' Prescriptions Accurately Compounded. J. J. COOK. DIXON &amp; LEACH, pruggists and Apothecaries, 16th St., Opposite Freight Depot, Merced. Pure Drugs, Paints, Oils, Perfumery, Spices, Cigars Tobacco, Fancy and Toilet Articles always on hand. 4^3  Prescriptions Carefully Compounded.  L   &#xD;<pb n="80 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7907-00000041"/> xi   '.REAL ESTAT REAL ESTATE   AND INSURANCE AGENT. MERCED, CAL.   MERCED MEAT MARKET ltfh St., Merced, Cal. AMOS   HCKS .............................. ........................Proprietor. FRESH BEEF, PORK MUTTON, Etc., Of the Best Quality, onstantly on hand, at the most reasonable rates. Call and see for Yourself.   Front Street Meat Market, Front ,Street, MERCED.   JOSEPH JACOBS.   ......................................    r.......               r.   BEEF, MUTTON, PORK AND SAUSAGES, Fr   sFresh and neatly prepared, sold in the shop or delivered to customers at their homes. EL CAPITAN BARBER SHOP ---AND- BATH HOUSE, EL CAPITAN HOTEL, MERCED. P. RILEY, Proprietor.     PDars ra.-- -     I   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>