<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7377">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Roses and Thornes, or, Recollections of an Artist </title>
            <author>Paine, Susanna.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7377</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1836</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Roses and thornes, or, Recollections of an artist</title>
                  <author>Paine, Susanna.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>ix 204 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>B.T. Albro</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Providence </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1854">1854</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-12-19">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Roses and thornes, or, Recollections of an artist</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7377-00000001"/>OB RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST:  FOR THE GRAVE AND THE GAY. BY SUSANNA PAINE. PROVIDENCE: B. T. ALBRO-PRINTER. 1854.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7377-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1854, BY SUSANNA PAINE, In the Clerk's office of the District Court of Rhode Island.   PREFACE. Having been long before the public as an artist, I will not, now, affect any timidity or reluctance at ap- pearing before them as a writer. I can offer no apology-or definite reason for writing and publish- ing this little volume; except to fill up my remnants of time, and to do away some wrong impressions. Being no more a judge of this--(my first work)- than a mother would be of the beauty of her first babe, I cheerfully submit it to the inspection of all who may honor it with their notice. Trusting in the forbearance of the critic-the generous indulgence of the learned and wise-and the kind considerations of all. If it should meet with the favor and approval of the judicious and pure-minded, (which I hardly dare to hope,) I shall most gratefully and joyfully appre- ciate the blessing. S. P.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7377-00000003"/>  ROSES AND THORNS. "Can you tell me who that is-she that has just passed us?" "What, that tall, large lady, in a drab bonnet, crossing the street yonder?" "Exactly." "Her name and profession are generally known through the medium of the advertising columns, but who or what she really is, is a question that probably few in this part of the city could answer. She is seen going to her studio every morning, and returning about sunset. Neither cold, heat, or even storms prevent her. She always goes on foot, and alone, through all. It is well for the omnibusses that all the ladies are not such pedestrians." "Perhaps poverty makes one of her." "Very likely, for her dress,- though quite decent,  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7377-00000004"/> 6       ROSES AND THORNS, would not lead one to suppose she was one of the upper ten." "How long has she resided here?" "About three years, I believe. It is said that she resided here formerly, and sustains an unblemished character." "Is she, or has she ever been married?" "I do not know; it is pretty evident that she has met with heavy trials of some kind. In the street, she appears in a deep study, and wholly unconscious that there is an individual within a mile of her." "Perhaps it was a matrimonial disappointment?" "Very likely. She is seldom, if ever met at any place of amusement, or public resort; does not ap- pear to move in any society, high or low; or to have any intimacy with any one; but seems to be wholly unconnected. No one seems to know where her residence is: it is probable, however, that she is a boarder in some obscure, private family." "She is certainly a very eccentric person." "No doubt of it, but it has been ascertained that she holds many testimonials, respecting her moral character, and from unquestionable sources." "Will she probably remain long, here?" "It is quite uncertain. She seems to be a bird of   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  passage. She dropped here among us one day, but who she is, to whom related, or where from, still re- mains a mystery to many. Ha, boy, what have you there?" "Books, sir; carryin' 'em to the 'scribers." "What do they read about?" "O I do' no, inside 'll tell. I guess about wim- min folks, and courtin', and all sich." "Let me look at one of them. Written by the very person we were speaking of, as true as I 'm a sinner! That is very singular! I'll have one at any rate. Here boy, take your money and push along. Now we '1 see." (Reads.) CHAPTER I. My birth-place was Rehoboth, (Mass.,) as it was also of my ancestors on. both sides, as far back as my knowledge extends. My father, James Paine, (mar- iner,) descended from a very aristocratic family, and reputed wealthy. They were, however, considerably reduced in their pecuniary circumstances, owing, it is said, to very heavy endorsements made by his father; which he was. eventually obliged to pay; however, it seems they kept up their style of living  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7377-00000005"/> 8       ROSES AND THORNS: to the last, but left nothing for heirs to differ about. They died before my father was twenty years of age. Being thus thrown on his own resources, he chose the sea. It is said of him, that he was all that his most ambitious friends could desire. Being very active and enterprising, he found himself, at the age of twenty-four, in circumstances to warrant his being married to the woman he adored. My mother was Mary Chaffee ; eldest child, and only daughter of the Rev. Jonathan Chaffee, of Rehoboth. The marriage of my parents, 't is said, gave great promise of happiness; being a genuine love-match on both sides. A son, bearing the name of his father, had blessed this union. Their second was a daugh- ter, (named Susanna,) but the days of their union were to be few, on earth, and their happiness to be short-lived. The husband and father, left home, to return no more forever. They never saw him again. He died far from home, or friends. Thus ended the mortal career of my once noble father. I was then too young to know, or even to retain the faintest recollection of him. My mother was left with her two little ones to provide for; and with very slender resources, for she p-id the utmost farthing of debt; trusting in the God   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   9 of the widow and fatherless, for future support. Her parents, with open arms, recalled her back to her pa- ternal home; where we all shared in their deepest affections. And instead of being a burthen, we seemed, rather to be their " crown of rejoicing." It will be seen, in the sequel, that their daughter proved a blessing to them-even to the end of their lives. My mother, strictly speaking, was not handsome; yet she had that in her face, which beauties might well covet. She was extremely fair, with bloom, and it was natural. Her countenance was expres- sive and intellectual. Her good sense, her tenderness, and high moral courage, combined with brilliant wit, and humor, rendered her a general favorite at home and abroad; and a perfect idol in one little heart, at least. Those who knew her, will know that I have not exceeded truth, in this description. Here at our home, we had every indulgence; (no doubt, too much.) Our grand-parents loved us dearly. Our mother doated on her "jewels," as she styled us.- Often on a Sabbath morning-when, arrayed in my "sprig muslin," and my brother in his best suit-she would take a hand of each, and lead us to the house of worship; looking so gratified. Oh, "a mother's love reigns without a rival; and withont an end."  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7377-00000006"/> 10      ROSES AND THORNS: She wholly supported us by her untiring indus- try. I have seen my grandfather's receipts of yearly payments, for our board; which my mother insisted [ on paying, lest we might become burthensome. Be- sides, my grandfather was not wealthy. He would have no regular salary, because his feeble health would not admit of his preaching constantly. He' owned the snug farm where he resided, and my grand-mother was very industrious, and prudent; so that, with their united efforts, they reared a family in comfort and respectability. They were, both, much revered and beloved. My grand-father was esteemed one of the best of men, (I have this from others, be- ing very young when he died;) but remember well, his tender affection for me. My brother would often say, ," O, I wish I had a father." My reply would be, "I do n't wish I had. 'Nampa' is enough for me." Happy days of innocence and simplicity! How bright you appear to me now, looking back through the vista of years! My beautiful brother, well do I remember your dark, pleasant, bright eyes, your fair ruddy face; your unvarying good humor, your mis- chievous wiles, and all your winning ways. How often we sportively rambled the fields, orchards,   OR) RECOLLECTIONi OF AN ARTIST.   1 and meadows, with our constant companion and play-. mate, "Lion," frisking, and gambolling around us. '"How dear to my heart, are the scenes of my childhood, * 'When fond recollection presents them to view." Ah! where are now the busy feet, that then trod those pleasant grounds? Where the eyes that then sparkled with delight? And where the pleasant voic- es, then, and there heard?  Oh! that question might be asked forever? The only answer, until the end of time would be-"Where?" I was a healthy, spirited, romping child, large of my age; but far from being handsome, (my only claim to beauty, was a fair complexion, ruddy cheeks, and glossy, ashen-brown hair, which was abundant, and curled naturally, in large, waving ringlets. I mention these as being able to prove it, by several very respectable old people ; who recollect it perfectly --among the things--" that were.") Neither had I my brother's mild, passive disposition. Mine was sensitive, resolute, and ambitious. Yet all tempers have some redeeming traits. To mine, my partial friends attributed, truthfulness, tenderness, and gen- erosity. A stranger would probably have given it a different version. I was passionately fond of flowers-and that no   &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7377-00000007"/> 12      ROSES AND THORNS: indulgence might be wanting--a flower garden was mine exclusively. I had such a vivid sense of "' mine and thine," that I could not, otherwise, have en- joyed it. My garden, my dolls, my pet kitten, my play-house, and all my play-things, and toys, must be mine. My play-mates were soon obliged to under- stand this; it was selfish, decidedly so; but theirs: were as sacred with me. My brother was the reverse; his property' was- open and free to all; this made him a very great favor- ite. And -if he destroyed theirs in return, why, it was all overlooked, because he was so generous. I was thought to be a selfish, shrewd, little vixen by some, because no one was allowed to plunder me at: discretion. Yet I would freely give. My brother did not give, but they could always take. We see this difference in adults, the passive are beloved, ap- plauded, and befriended, they are called "'good-- hearted, sweet-tempered," &amp;c., while the high-spirit- ed, though firm, truthful, and tender-hearted, com- bined with high moral excellence, it does not avail. They are seldom applauded, except by the few who can appreciate them. My Reverend grand-father was one of the few. It might be said that his being reckoned among the distitnguished few, was owing   6t, REMO0tASCTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  13 so the fact, that he could always find a cause and a reason, fW{ all the sayings and doings of his way- ward darling. 'T is true, he loved the energy and ridependence, that had thus early, begun to mani- fest itself. I will here relate a case in point. He would never get me praised sufficiently it seems, un- less my talents were!" pressed into the service." So, one day, having some brother clergymen at our house, and wishing to obtain a little extra notice for his fa- torite, he called me out to read, handed me the "Pil- grim's Progress." I opened it; courtesied in my best style, and commenced reading. The subject hap- pened to be, where Pilgrim and Faithful were con- fined in "Doubting Castle." Coming to where Pil- grim said, a I have a key in my bosom, that will open this door," so as I read, they escaped, amd "Old Giant Despair "' pursued thewm and was about to catch them, when he was taken with a fit and fell. At this, (I am told, for I do not recollect it) I bounded from the floor, threw the book over my head, and clapped my hands, joyfully shouting, "I 'm glad! I 'n glad!"' wholly regardless of etiquette, or the presence of the worthy divines. This, with the glowing expression of my face on that occasion, 't is said, procured for me notice, to the full and entire satisfaction of my honored grandsire.     B  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7377-00000008"/> "      BossE AND THORIS A CHAPTER II; But my then happy life was doomed to d qSeedy change. Shortly after this, our best of parents ad tenderest of friends, was called to receive his reward in Heaven. He died of the consumption, which had been growing on him, almost imperceptibly, for a long time, His death was my first dep grief. But I was then too young, to realize aM its heaviness, or the change it ToDld make in ox little household, (being then only jug turned of seven years of age.) , There was an eye, whoae partial glauc0, could ne'er my numerous failings see ; Tnhere was an ear, that heard untirea, hvhen others spoke in praise of me. Now closed that eye, and deaf that e atf That lip and voice are mute forever; And colad that heart of tender love, Which death alone, from us could sever My uncles were worthy young men at that tme; two of the eldest were married. They were allgood, -ind brothers to ot  herther; however, she was not nder the slightest pecuniary obligation then, or sub-   O DR , :aEIOLLECTW'i  NO AN ARTIST.. 15 equently, to anyy one of them. My mother young- est brother was about eighteen or nineteen years of age, when his father died.  I well remember his af- fectionate kindness and indulgence, and although so young, he was as a father to us. He and my mother managed the homestead. My grand-mother was, in course, the head of the family; but being feeble in health, my good mother stood between her and weighty cares ; or, indeed, hardships of any kind.- As my, uncle was a minor, the estate remained undi- vided during my grand-mother's life. I will here git  a slight sketch of our residence. "Far sheltered, 'in a glade obscure, The modest mnansion lay." :A few rods in from a by road, a paved lane or ctourt, ran down to it. A high wall, adorned in sum- mer 'with locust flowers, elder blossoms, and red ros- es tan the entire length, on both sides, giving it a very beautiful appearance at that season of the year. The farm abounded with fruit trees and berries of al- most every kind. We had animals and poultry of almost every kind generally kept on a farm, excepting ducks, (I recollect of thinking that, a very important omission.) The dwelling was an old fashioned, long, B2  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7377-00000009"/> 16      ROSES A"D TH0"NeS: brown cottage. The interior was perfectly simple and primitive. I recollect the long, old kitchen, with its oaken floor; at the far end was a Tong, white ta-o ble and "dressers." The latter glistened with long  rows of pewter dishes, of almost every description. The long table often groaned beneath its load, on "baking days," (placed there to cool, where mny own little pie, would stand, conspicuously, waiting to glad- den my return from school, or play.- I had a great fondness for domestic animalsg; was forever feeding, or petting them, in some way-. I had another fondness, which I now deeply deplore, I coveted birds' eggs, and sorry am I to say, that I was aellowed to have the eggs of what they termed "troublesome birds." Thus encouraged, with my own hands I often robbed the poor birds, amid their piercing cries! May God forgive me. Oh, how could I be so selfish and cruel? Those barbarous acts of mine, lie on my heart at this moment, with more galling weight than any other sin I ever com- mitted. I lived on in this quiet and pleasant manner, con- stant at school, always determined to be " at the head." A favorite with the teachers, an object of envy and iealousy with the scholars. Whenever the home   Ult, RECOLZECT-OONS OF A ARTIST.  17 school closed,-I was boarded abroad, to attend some other school; when that school closed for the week, with what rapturous joy I was welcomed home by my fond relatives. But "No morning sun shines all the day." My brother went away from home, to a higher school. My grand-mother's health was rapidly de- clining, when a paralytic stroke prostrated her pow- ers, that she became almost entirely helpless, but re- tained her senses. It was then, that her "dear little daughter," as she styled me, could in part, repay her kind care, by every endearing attention; by reading to her, rocking her, and anticipating all her wishes. O, how many volumes of sermons I read to her, very irksome to me at that time. But what will not love and gratitude do? and for such a friend? Notwithstanding good hired help, my mother's toil and care was incessant; I stood between her and every hardship that she would allow me to. Though then but eleven years of age, I cheerfully left school, and took my stand as my grand-mother's second nurse, and took my turn in watching with her; and though not allowed to do it, often continued my watch throughout the night, and thus cheated my poor, Bm             p o-   &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7377-00000010"/> IS      ROSES ANE THORNS: wearied mother into a good night's rest. I was in- capable of neglecting the dear invalid; or of suffer- ing myselt to fall asleep, save in one instance. One. night, the weather was very sultry, and I felt very weary, but determined to keep awake; so I sat. studying my definitions; while every one, even the patient, slept sundly and sweetly ; but going to light. another candle, and waiting for the last to do its ut- most; whi&amp;e looking steadfastly at it, I fell asleep. I know not how long I dozed, but was aroused to per- fect consciousness, by a heavy stroke of thunder, at- tended by sharp lightning. The candle  out but all -were still sleeping; I ran to the kitchen to lgh it, when to my utter dismay, the fire was out too  and the tinder would not catch. Here was a ease difficult to manage; but after a moment's reflectionp I went back to ascertain if grand-mother still slept. Finding she did, I took a fire-pan, and went to the nearest neighbor's, about one-fourth of a mile distant running at the top of my speed, across fields, and- over fences, amid such peals of thunder and flashes of lighting, as I had scarcely ever seen. Yet my only fear was, that grand-mother would awake, and miss me, and be frightened; and that I might be cen- sured, for deserting my post.   OR , RECOLLECTION$ OF AN ARTIST.  19 I found our kind neighbors up, and a light burn- ing; they were walking the room, greatly alarmed. at the storm. It was then a little past midnight. I took my fire, and flew back, as swiftly as I came; (drenched with the heavy shower, but completely hap- py. I had not been wanted, although my patient was awake, keeping very quiet, fearful of waking me from the nap, she supposed I wasenjoying. Adven- tures, when successful, are applauded: when failures, they are termed rashness and indiscretion. This of mine, as it succeeded, was considered a very smart affair; in the family circle, at least. That dear sufferer often said that I was the best watcher among them alL The recollection of that assertion, is dearer to me now, than any other bequest she could possibly have left me. About this time, I was from home on a visit, when a violent tempest arose, with heavy thunder, and the most piercing lightning. Oh, how piercing! It struck us! Hwas only stunned; but a lady who was standing close to me, never breathed again! The last I knew, I was standing between her and the aperture that admitted the lighting. The house was not struck, at all. I -emember feeling a heavy blow on my head; and of faling one way, as she fell the other. As she was  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7377-00000011"/> 20       RO6E$ AND THORNS: falling, I feel confident that I heard her cry, "Lord, have mercy!"But still, I might be mistaken. During the instant of consciousness, the room seemed enveloped in fame, with a strong, sulphurous smell. I sensed nothing more, until the house was filled with aftrighted people, and physicians, trying every method to restore us. The husband, who had left his wife in perfect health, and excellent spirits, an hour before, had re- turned to see her extended a lifeless corpse! Her tender heart, so true to him, had ceased to beat and lay stamped with the icy seal of death! What devout thanks my tender mother offered at the mercy seat, that her childwas spared. But soon all a mother's fears were aroused. Iwas laid on a sick bed; was given over by my physicians; still getting worse until to all appearances, I died. I have now, a perfect recollection of my fee lifengs at that time; for I fully retained my senses, unti was apparently gone. My sensations were perfect ease and quietness.  felt no fear, though perfectly aware of my situation. aMY limbs, my tongue, and my eyes were perfectly immovable, When any one came within range of   OR, AiECOLLECTIONS OF AN AR TST.  2:1 nmy eyes, I could see them, but not otherwise. My mother wept over me as only a widowed mother can. I tried to look at her, to speak comfort to her, but could not move a muscle. This gave me more sor- row, than the apparent approach of death. (Reader, never mourn visibly, in the presence of a dying friend. You have no idea how trying it is to them, even when their senses seem to be gone.) From this, I felt more and more--vanishing, (I can think of no other word to express the feeling,) until it is said I had apparently been dead nearly an hour-prepara- tions were being made to deck me for my new, and last home; while my poor, weeping parent was in her closet, endeavoring to bring her smitten heart to say, "Father, thy will be done." When lo! it was dis- covered that life was returning! Restored by the same Almighty power, that "  touched the bier," *say- ing to the widow's son, ' Arise." What virtue in that touch! What power in that command! Death, trembling, unloosed his potent grasp. While lying in that state, I felt entirely free from mortality. I seemed to be going forward towards a large group of very young women. They had on white dresses, and looked most beautifully. They seemed to be advanc- * 7th Chapter St. Luke.      Be  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7377-00000012"/> 22      ROSES AND THORNS: ing to meet me; when, suddenly they disappeared; and I was obliged, much against my inclination, to take up my former residence in the body. But it was long before I became reconciled to human life. It has since been ascertained, that young persons who have been lightning-struck and survive, are sub- jects of a disease termed catalepsy; which, at times, has all the appearance of death. Undoubtedly, this was my malady; but being then but twelve years of age, outgrew it, and was saved. Those of adult age, I believe, seldom, if ever, outlive it. About one year subsequent to this, my dear grand- mother died, in the triumphs of faith, though her reason was somewhat impaired, as she advanced to the close of her pious and useful life. She had num- bered sixty-three years; when, like a babe going to sleep, her eyes lovingly fixed on me, until they were glazed in death, she gently departed this life. At the time of her death, my mother's health was much impaired, the homestead was fast running down, and the buildings were getting out of repair; it seemed best for us to leave it. So my mother sold her right, and removed a few miles, in the same town. But never have I found a home, since the sorrowful lay we left that dear sacred spot.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN A STIT.  23 CHAPTER III. About a year after our removal, my mother mar- ried a widower, with four children. A worthy, kind man,and very good cleverchildren--at least, they were all kind to me ; but it was a sad change for me, nev- ertheless. I could have but few exclusive privileges. My mother, desirous of being a "pattern step-moth- er," to her two new daughters, bestowed much care and attention on them, which had formerly flowed in its natural channel; hut I was delighted to see her treat them so kindly-although it materially interfered with my  birth-right." My mother had informed my brother and me, that we were only to have a home with her; but that our clothing, and other ex- penses must be paid from our own funds; she had given us a small sum, each, from the sale of her pat- rimony, for that purpose. However, a door was soon to be opened for me.-.. My step-father purchased a farm, bordering on Con- necticut, about 30 miles frm our native place, where we were then residing, and removed to it soon after their marriage. B6  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7377-00000013"/> 24-      ROSES AND THORNS: Here, being tall, and mature in appearance, my age was not questioned. I was, without hesitation, employed to teach their "district school." Many of my pupils were older, and knew more than their ju- venile teacher; she, being then on the " sunny side " of fifteen years of age. My employers were good, sound, plain people; some of them were not very much polished, but they were of excellent materials. They at first, called me ' dreadful proud,'" but -on further acquaintance, pronounced me a "right smart, clever gal ;" and accordingly shewed me every kind- ness, and not only that, but reverence. Why, bless you, reader! I was " the marm," and nothing less. I was addressed with " will the marmn have thisY' and "will the marm have that?" and " would the mrarm choose to retire?.' etc. When my term of school expired in the Pall, I went, as a scholar, to the best Academy in Rhode Island, where I remained until I was so far advanced in my studies, as to be able to teach any of the com- mon branches of education. On leaving that school, at my final examination, the highest honors were be- stowed on me by the principal and committee; not- withstanding, the most aristocratic and wealthy daughters of the place were my competitors. You   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   25 will exclaim, "What an egotist!" Beit so. I am bound to give you the whole, unsifted. Through all these terms, I paid my board, nearly all by needle work, which I did evenings and Satur- days. (Wrought work, at that time, bore a high price,) but I was obliged to economise in every way, and in every thing; and deny myself of everything that the young are generally so fond of; besides the mortification of knowing that I made a very dowdy and shabby appearance,  ompared with my richly. dressed school-mates, whose parents were, generally, in afluent circumstances. One day, seeing my quills were very poor, a kind- hearted young lady--a daughter of affluence-ob- served to me, ,Eow can you, dear, use such misera- ble quills?, I replied that I could not afford better ones. "Do, pray accept a few of min "said she, extending some half-dozen of the first quality of "barrel " quills. I thanked her in my kindest tone -but declined the proffered aid. I O, I cannot be re- fused ; do, to gratify me , take them," said she.  "Then if you feel so de sirous I will just tae one," Ireplied.  "No," said she; I in si ston your takin g them all."  amafraid you se, "I   am afraid you will be robbing y our- self,I replied.  by no means. T here are ple oThere are plen-  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7377-00000014"/> 26       ROSES AND THORNS, ty of them in Pa's office," said she, and had it all her own way. But I never forgot the kindness, or her last remark. I afterwards thought I wished to feel the same confidence in the distribution of what my Heavenly Father had given me for my use.- Feeling as she did, that what I gave, could, and would be supplied to me, when I really needed it. During the last term of this school, my mind was wrought on, to "Seek the Kingdom of Heaven and its righteousness." But I said in my heart, "Go thy way for this time, a more convenient season I will call for thee." But my spirit was troubled, that I could not rest. Then I promised the Lord, that if He would graciously wait until my studies were completed, that I would thenl seek and serve Him, at the sacrifice of all things else. (How well this prom- ise was kept, the sequel will show.) On leaving this school, I returned to visit my moth- er, and to receive her congratulations. She was de- lighted at the progress I had made, and began to en- tertain some hopes of me, no doubt. I now opened a school, on a little more " elevated scale," a few miles from my mother's residence.- Here I made the acquaintance of a number of re- fined, intelligent, young persons, who were residents   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.    27 in the place; all very gay, though strictly moral.- Parties came off in quick succession. In these gay scenes, if not a belle-I was certainly a "ring-leader' --was " gayest of the gay "-flattered, and caressed --gratified with full success as a teacher--approved by the aged and middle-aged- forgot my vows to the Most High! "Where will those vile affections roll, That let a Savior go?" Although strictly moral, in every sense of the word, yet it might almost be said, that "God was not in all my  thoughts."  But it will shortly be seen that His mercy hedged up my way, and still claimed me. I closed my school the following autumn, (a term of 7  months,) received my wages, about $40,00, (expenses out.) This money I lent to my step-fath- er, as he was still owing something towards his new farm. (I am thus minute in detailing pecuniary af- fairs, for a reason which will manifest itself in the sequel.) I  then went to the town of P. ,in Connecti- cut, and boarded in a quiet, genteel, private family, where I did embroidery, or cut and made garments of any, and all descriptions which ever came to hand,  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7377-00000015"/> '28      ROSES AND THORNS&amp; having learned that, and nearly every other kind of work, by assisting my mother, when at home. This employment, I found pretty profitable, besides it gave me a pleasant recess from the duties and labors of a school-room. In this family, I had opportunity of making the acquaintance of the most respectable families in the place. Went to parties, saw a great deal of young company, and tried to enjoy myself- but impossible. My gourd was blasted, there was a "worm at the root;" for a " still, small voice" was continually saying to my heart, "The summer is past, the harvest is ended, but my soul is not saved!'" this haunted me in all companies, and in all places, The broken vows that " my soul in anguish made," now stared me in the face; I began to fear that I was left in my sins, forever deserted of God! I felt that I had forfeited all claim to his mercy ; and justly deserved such a fate. Oh, I was miserable indeed! . I desired to repent, and be saved; but, like Esau, ,4 found no place of repentance." I could not pray -had no faith, no hope; I was sealed, as I then thought, for everlasting despair and misery. I could not bear to see any of my companions, or indeed, any one else. I thought it best to go home to my mother, as she was a christian, hoping she could do   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  29 something for her poor, lost child-but it was all it vain. She could intercede at a throne of grace- but that was all. She had no power to redeem my soul, not even if she had given her own as a ransom. I soon realized this, and clearly perceived that the case lay entirely between God and my own soul. I writhed under this dreadful agony, until the time had come, that I had engaged to re-commence my school, in the same place I had taught the preced- ing summer. They sent a carriage for me, and I was obliged to go, unfit as I was for anything, es- pecially to have the charge of a school. My mates gave me a most joyful welcome, but I had no ears. Or, like Bunyan's Pilgrim, (figuratively speaking,) I put my fingers in my ears, and ran crying, "Life! Life!! Eternal Life!!!" In this wretched condition, I was obliged to attend my school, for a number of weeks, " and no relief I found." But when I was corrected and humbled enough, before those for whom I turned from a mer- ciful Savior--in that moment of trembling agony, when despair had nearly paralyzed me-He in great mercy manifested himself to my grief-worn soul, say- ing, "It is I, be not afraid." I at once felt my sins  were forgiven-indeed, I knew it. Most lovely pas-  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7377-00000016"/> 30       ROSES AND THORNS: sages of scripture, Iull of sweet promise, came flow- iag into my mind; my fear was gone, I knew not where. Love and thanksgiving filled my heart "To such refined excess, I felt 't would break with any more, Nor couEl I do with less." Ia a short time I received the ordinance of bap- tism, by immersion. I was not daunted in the least, although the only candidate, in presence of a very large assembly of people. O, I was most exquisitely happy. With what sacred joy I was received into the church, to the communion-table, and to all the privileges of the children and servants of God.- (", Ah, but where am I now? And why was it, or how? that I fell from this Heaven of Grace?") I lived through that season and many months after, a very happy and blessed life.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  31 CHAPTER      IV. The following autum, I returned to my winter residence in Connecticut. But my feelings, tastes and pursuits were wholly changed. Some would ex- claim, " Is this, can this be the gay, proud creature we first saw?" I found that I had lost caste with the proud and lofty of this world's height ; how they lamented that "such a young person should be-so deluded!" I continued in Connecticut, winters, sometimes teaching school, at other times, following my other vocations. In summers, I was invariably sought to teach in Rhode Island, near my mother's. I made it a point to go where highest wages could be obtained, without any regard to my own feelings or pleasure. You will now exclaim, "How mercenary!"But you will recall that accusation, when I tell you that this was no inordinate love of gin, or not on my own account, at least; it was to assist, in my small way, my stepfather, who had some fears of being obliged to mortgage his farm, to raise money to liqui- date the amount still due.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7377-00000017"/> 32       ROSES AND THORNS: My mother toiled, early and late, notwithstanding a young son of this second union, a restless, worrying child, who constantly claimed her care and attention, which, all combined, nearly overtaxed her feeble health. Her step-daughters assisted, were kind, obliging and industrious, and very good sisters to me. The step-brothers, I recollect but little of, ex- cept that they were good, easy, comfortable lads.- My mother was a true mother to that family. My step-father was a good kind of a man, and very in- dustrious; but, not possessing a strong constitution, he was too easily discouraged. The fact is, he lacked energy and perseverance, as many a good man has, before him. Thus for several years they received all my earnings, over paying my board, and furnishing my clothing ; which was, in truth, but one remove from actual shabbiness. But, notwithstanding my shabbiness, and other detriments, there was one, (a brother in the church, baptised, a short time after I received that ordinance,) who took great notice of me ; his calls and visits be- came very frequent, and protracted. At length, it became quite apparent, that these vis- its were more than brotherly. He was thought hand- some, industrious and pious. His suit was approbat-   -OH, RECOLLECTIONS OP A1N ARfTgT.  3 ed by the family, with my mother " to the fore."- Because he was so very pious, that he always carried a bible or hymn-book, or both, in his pocket, wherev- er he went; besides his face was always dressed in that fi ed, unmeaning smile, which passes so current with the many, for real good-nature; but with the few, of greater experience, and more knowledge of human nature, it is put down as disgusting, and hy- pocritical. His proposals of marriage were decidedly and firmly rejected by me; having no other love for him, than church love; and that, though good in its place, requires a little additional spice of fancy and fascina- tion, to make it worth wearing a  chain, (often an iron one, for life. (But he did not appear to feel very anxious about winning the heart; that seemed a tri- qe, if he could but get possession of the hand. A lecided proof that he was wholly destitute of deli- Sacy and principle. But no reserve of mine could listance him, while favored by my friends. I could lot treat him with contempt, or even rudeness, be- ause he was brother ----. What would his rela- ires, who were mostly brethren in the church, say, * I slighted him? All this, and much more, trou- led me, until I was weary of life,  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7377-00000018"/> 34      ROSES AND THORNS: My brother, who had now become a young mari- ner, returned about this time, and on seeing my would-be, formed a favorable opinion; said he liked "I the cut of his jib," but thought there need be no haste about his "taking me in tow," that I could i' navigate, and needed no pilot." After my brother's next departure, being so much annoyed with the constant importunity of the be- sieger, and his able advocates, that I determined to make myself an " absentee," (as Judge Meanwell says.) Being acquainted with a family in Connecti- cut, about twelve miles from my former residence, I went there and opened a school, thinking that I had taken a course that would completely evade pursuit; but soon, my persecutor came also. This was the drop that overflowed the cup of my contempt, en- tirely. My resolution was now wrought up to the right pitch. I positively refused to see him, except in the presence of the family; reminded him, that my last answer was decisive. He then left, as I hoped, finally. But now, letters became the " medi- um" of his " communications," but still I remaincd perfectly decided, not taking the trouble to return, or answer them. When a few weeks subsequently, I was greatly sur-   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST,   35 pfised at receiving a letter, marked "haste." It proved to be from my mother, desiring me to come to her without delay, as she wished to see me on business of importances I lost no time in obeying this slummons, thinking my step-father was involved in some pecuniary difficulty, But no; it was my step-tormentor. He had been} to her, and made believe that he was going to die.. His looks did rather warrant the belief, it is true.- So, with his entreaties, he prevailed on her to send for me, that he might " have one more talk with me, before he left the world."  Under the impression that he told the truth, my mother could hardly do other- wise, than to send. But think of my suprise, when my mother, for she was a candid, truthful woman, confessed her object in sending for me; I did not an- ger and storm, as one knowing my hasty tempera- ment, would suppose; my   mother's tears subdued my resentment, but from that moment I felt that I was doomed. Soon, the object of our discussion arrived, (according to their previous agreement, no doubt.)- After the usual forms of civility were got through with, there-was first, a dead, and solemn pause, such as there is in a court, previous to passing sentence.- The silence was broken by mymnother, who remark-  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7377-00000019"/> ed that she had consented for this once only, to be instrumental in bringing us together; that she must confess, that it would be very gratifying to her, if the meeting was fot life; that she was getting in years, that she could not die happy, and leave her dear child unprotected, and unsettled in the world. At the last sentence, the tears rolled down her cheeks-indeed, there was tears on all sides the " booby" wept be- cause he was very miserable, (so he said ) and I wept because I could never see any one weep, no matter for what, without weeping with them for sympathy. With my feelings wrought up in this manner, the tears and entreaties of my dear, deceived mother, backing his, prevailed, Ii an agony of grief and desperation, I frantically cried, "I will marry him! as soon as you like-if to-morrow." They seemed quite surprised-but very much rejoiced at the turn things had taken. Fearing a relapse, an early day was set by them for the ceremony, and sanctioned by me.  But, oh! it was a frenzied sanction, How could that tender mother so sacrifice her only daughter, and thus abuse the influence and control she held over her? Oh, how could she! But yet I know it was not any lack of affection, but rather ex-   OR, t ICOLLECTION5 OP AN ARTtIS.  37 cess of parental solicitude; fearing that a very wrorw thy, honorable young man--of highly respectable family, and connections-a graduate of the University of  - ; but having his own way to carve, and his fortune still to make; not yet having studied his pro- fession, would ultimately succeed in winning the hand and heart of her daughter, and if so, she thought sho could discern nothing in the perspective, but two idolized, spoiled children, commencing an establisih- ment, without present visible means of sustain- ing it-in short, she feared the union of "pride and poverty." This she could not, for a moment, bear to think of, for her daughter, when she should become a wife. Parents, be narned by the sequel. And to avert such a fate-insisted on her bestowing her hand, at once, on one so eminently pious; and though not wealthy; was thought to be doing a very good business; which would ensure a very respectable present establishment; and, probably future wealth. Poor deluded parent! how little she dreamed, that, at that very time, he had become a devoted gambler! It was no fear of being obliged to live in "single blessedness," that caused me to yield to their entrea- ties ;-for, at that time, there were a number of wor- C  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7377-00000020"/> 3S      ROSES AND THOtNS ' thy. pronising young men; either of whom, would, probably, havre taken me " for better or for worse ;"- if they had been pcrsuaded a little. After reflecting about a weelk, on my rash promise-I said mentally -"It will not do!" I wrote, without delay-tomy affianced," informingl him that my leart utterly re- fused to ratify' the mad promise. made under such ex- citement reminded him of the manner in which that promise was extorted; and besoughlt him,--implo1red him to give me backl the fatal promise. But no; he came -with all speed, to see what had changed my mind, as 1ie termed it. Accused me of fickleness, and denolulced the  judgments of Heaven, on nmv perjured soul, if I failed him. "What if I did hilnk that I was sacrificing my happiness? I should find myself mistaken in that respect; and if not, which should a christian hold most sacred, her sol- emn promise, or her girlish fancy?" While ponder- ing--what reply to Inake,-- m y mother being present, -said, during the pause,-;"Has my daughter be- come a coquette?" This was more than I could bear. Reader-that one sentence,--sealed nmy fate! He was able to bind me to another promise, with perfect ease. The fatal day arrived. The guestshad assembled.   (OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST,  39 'They were invited, in order to have the thing come off bright and gay; (not by any agency of mine.)- I should much preferred to have been in a desert; with Bats and Owls; fit witnesses of such a scene. Arrayed by my officious bridesmaids; I was led to the altar-of -sacrifice! My mother seeing the usu- ally florid countenance 'of her daughter pale asu mar- ble, and deluged with 'tears of bitter anguish-she has since said-(I use her own words,) "At that moment, I could have torn the hair from my head by handfulls, if it could have recalled what I had done. I saw, when too late,--that I had wrecked the happi- ness of my dear, confiding child, forever!" I do not recollect any consciousness, while the ,ceremony was being performed.  The evening was s(ad and dull. For they saw, and felt, that all was not right; and notwithstanding the many efforts at "cheerfulness and hiliarty, it proved, in every sense of tthe word a complete failure. i,  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7377-00000021"/> 40       R(OS'ES AND THORNS :: CHAPTER V.. I was removed to nmy new Iomte, in M iode Is'lai' about 25 or 30 miles distance fomumy mother's resi-- dence. My rooms and fulrnitutre lbooked very nice* and comfortable, "But nothing could a charm: inmpa. "' Nevertheless, I had nade up my mind to treat nrmy husband hi-lawi, with the utmost kindness ,;: and withA all the affection I could possibly nmuster ;. determinsd to be a true, and dutiful wife; and to ikme the best of what could not now be remedied ; (not, intcnidiilg to assert, however, that I was erer wraog. ) But allf in vain. I too soon, discovered tha hie. was, at alls points,-a taunting, sneering, surly tyrant--besides; being a consummate hypocrite. But soon he dropped his mask, altogether. Not one' month had passed, before I was'horror-struck at find-. ing him capable of, and in the constant: iha6iti.(in the' dlomestic circle,) of uttering the most horrid'l. cand' re--   t}h, tECOLLECMZ ONS OF AN meaTiSr. 41 v'olting oats! And when his store was closed for tthe day, it .becanme a rendezvous. The business of 9him, and hie fit associates, often continued through ithe " small hours" of the night. I knew this, but ,could not prevent .it. Oh! how miserable and wretched I 'was! holw I envied the veriest beggar that Atrod the earth-free. -h- is impossible to give any ac- ,curate description of my feelings-they were indes- ceribable. I will here relate one circumstance-that will give tthe reader, a true, graphic likeness of the man. I 'had been very sick, with a succession of quinsy in the throat; until I was very nearly famished to death; not having been able to swallow solid food, for nearly two  weeks; and very ;little of liquids. My case seemed hopeless ;  my physician dared not attempt to use the lancet so Jow in the throat ; said it must take its course,-that nothing could be done. I was giv- en up to die; had not been able to speak for many ,days ;  could not raise my hand to my head, but re- tained my senses, perfectly. It was thought best, as I  was so low, to not admit many to my room excepting -those who were inattendance. One day, being more distressed, no one thought I could continue many hours leaager,-when lo!  we heard strains of music, 3  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7377-00000022"/> 42      ROSES AND THYORNS - but it was not celestial. music. It swas in out sore;Y (which opened from the dwelling-house,) and proceed- ed from a violin;-touched by the magic fingers, of the identical young man,-who had been so near dy- ing FOR me, less than one year before I I heard the sounds-but it did not grieve me then ; I hoped all earthly sorrows were nearly at an end. Some hu- mane persons, who thought such c-onduct disgraceful,; rebuked the musician; he then quitted, and came directly to my room. At that moment, there was no one present but my nurse. Under some pretence, (I forget now, what,) he sent her from the room. The door had no sooner closed after her,. than he turned to me, with a most fiendish expression of face, and hissed through his clenched teeth, "D n you; if you aint going to get up soon -I hope to h--1 you 'll stiffen " Reader-this is sacredly true. I should never for- get that; if my mremory was less retentive than it is. Yet the truth of the foregoing statement might be doubted, as I was so very low,-it might be: thought that my senses wandered;-had not the nurse been too prudent,. to go farther than the- outside of the door; where she saw and heard, all She imme- diately entered, and being. a woman of high moral   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  43 courage, bade him leave the room, instantly, if he would avoid exposure. He left, without hesitation; ashamed that he was found out; and glad to get off so easily. How thankful I then felt, that my time was to be so short;-but my hour had not then come. My nurse, subsequently, deposed to the foregoing statement, in the Supreme Rhode Island Court, where probably it still stands recorded; (and much more with it;) should any have doubts of its being au- thentic. He finally carried out the system of abuse he had thus early commenced; not only by constantly using the most obscene and profane language to me; ad- dressing me by the lowest name a female of the vil- est grade could be called; frequently locking me into a room, taking the Holy word of God with him, and putting the key into his pocket, that I might not es- cape; he would then commence reading aloud, with mock solemnity; mingling the revolting language of his own, as though he read it. And by every low and disgusting artifice, too numerous to mention, but by actually endangering-and even attempting my life; which he did more than once. Now, reader, you will probably pause, and say, c4  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7377-00000023"/> "      ROSES AND TIIORNS : i' How severe!" But it is in self-defence; and not more severe than truthful. I have lain under the blame and censure heaped on me, by him, already too long. He had avowed himself a decided deist; a few weeks after I was in his power; and never gave any one reason to doubt the sincerity of the as- sertion; proving his zeal by burning bibles when angry, and could lay hands on them; which Iwas often obliged to prevent by concealing them;-and though threatened with instant death, never would disclose their place of concealment. I was blamed by every candid, just person, who knew the circum- stances for jeopardizing life, by remaining as long as I did. But pride, (that tyrant of our lives,) had kept me, thus far, from revealing to the great world, my wretch- ed situation. But at length, duty prevailed. I urged him to go on a visit with me to my mother's, which he did ; (I did not mean that it should be said, that I left him.) But it was arranged by "Telegraph," (figuratively speaking,--for Magnetic Telegraphs were then un- known,) that I should never return. I had spent one year and two months in cruel bondage. I felt like a   OR, RECOLLECTIONSO WN ARTIST.   43 &amp;"bird released from the snare, that she went into, not knowing it was for her life." About three months after my return to the pater- nal home, I became the nmother of a lovely babe,--a son. He grew to be a beautifal, and stately child)-- an idol that filled my whole heart; all my former trials were nearly forgotten, in the absorbing " deaths less lote? I bore him. But that idolatrous love was temperped, by the fear that his father might, some day- claim him; as he had often sent threatening messages to that effect. To avert this,--when the babe was a few months old: I petitioned, and easily obtained a legal divorce. Previous to this, the inhuman father) who had never been to see the babe, or to defray one farthing of the expenses,--came, post-haste) on hearing what was in progress, declaring he would head, and stop it. But finding I held proofs enough to obtain twenty divorces, had hot tone been sufficient --he then took another tack, and vowed he would take the child. This, I knew he could not do just then; but still I knew it to be a weapon that he could wield over me, at all times; until he could put his threat into execution. This fear blighted all my happiness, and made mie more completely wretched than ever. U5  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7377-00000024"/> "      aOSES AND' THORNS, But at length, a compromise was effected. He would sign away his claim to the babe, on certain conditions ;--which were, that I should not petition for alimony, or support of any kind, for myself or babe; that I should sign deed of real estate--and, in short, be wholly deprived of the means of subsis- tence. To these terms I joyfully agreed. What will a tender mother not part with--to save being parted from her infant? Let every true mother an-  swer this question. When the letter of guardianship was " signed, sealed and delivered"'--and my divorce bill secured, I was almost completely happy. None but those who love as I did, and " fear to lose," can guess my anxious fears, until all this was accomplished. But a heavy damper soon arose on this, as it ever did oin all my joys. The letter of guardianship was held by a tr ustee, until I could letally take it, in my own name. So, after the bill, (without alimony,) was ob- tained-the deed of land signed, and all things ar- ranged, I sent to have the guardianship vested ill me ; when I found, to my agonized surprise, that the per- fidious villian would not change the papers, nor sign to me, (there being no proof of the agreement, al- though the family were about the room at the time,   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.    47 but fearing there might be some objections to these terms on their part, they were discussed in suppressed tones, by my own consent. He sneeringly said, on being applied to,--that he was not obliged to, and he would not, sign to me; tauntingly said I could pro- duce my proofs, if I had any. This piece of bar- barous treachery, nearly goaded me to distraction. co  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7377-00000025"/> 48      ROSES AND THORNS: C HAPTER    VI. It will be asked, why I should confide in the word of one so utterly depraved? Reader, I never thought of such a thing-as its requiring any proof; the mo- ment of such excitement as I then felt, is not the time that we are wary and prudent. My poor, sor- rowful mother took a chaise and carried me to the residence of my trustee,--about ten miles distant.- Esqr.    , after hearing my statement, seemed greatly moved: he said he had not the slightest doubt of its truth, but unless I had proof, there was no redress. At that moment, I suspected him of be- ing an abettor of this base treachery :-but was soon aware that I had grossly wrongled him. He offered; me the paper-calling the signer by an appropriate epithet; said it laid not in his power to legally trans- fer the guardianship to me; but would do every rea- sonable thing in his power, to serve me. He asked me to suggest what I thought best to be done, and what I would desire of him. After a few moments   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  49- reflection, I replied that if he would risk to grant my request, it would be that he would come under a bond to me, in the penal sum of one thousand dollars, to hold the guardianship in his own hands, until claimed by me. To never use his authority, but with my consent; to always interpose at my request; and I would indemnify him against being at any expense, or charge of any kind, for his ward. He willingly, and cheerfully agreed to sign this bond, as soon as it could be drawn up, by my fulfill- ing my part of the conditions. I chose to draw the bond myself-as being able to draw documents in legal form,-besides, I felt that I could make it stronger than any one else; and this was not all-I could save the expense. Reader, do not sneer. I tell you that seventy-five cents is quite an object, and not to be trifled with, by those who are entirely destitute. So, it was decided that I was to draw the bond, and send it for'his sig- nature, together with my own obligation. We start- ed to return home, but the excitement had been too much for me; I became  very ill-my tongue clave to the roof of my mouth; my mother, fearful of be- ing obliged to leave me on the road, drove as fast as she prudently could.  We made out to get home; a  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7377-00000026"/> 50       ROSES AND THORNS: physician was called, who pronounced me very ill, with a settled fever. This fever had run the usual time; the crisis was past, and I was able to be bol- stered up in nmy bed. One day, when she thought I could bear it, my mother brought the beautiful babe--looking sweet as an angel-to the bed, saying, "I dressed him with care for you to see, and love; hoping he will gladden your sorrowful heart." Oh! how the sight of that lovely cherub did gladden me ; can I ever forget it? I felt a rapturous happiness then, that I was never to feel again, on earth. He was taken sick that very night, and lived only a few, short days, (being about one year of age.) No earthly power could save him! Oh, my God! I feel the anguish at this mo- ment, in every nerve--just as when my grief was new! Dear object of the deepest love, A mortal's heart can-feel; Thy sorrowing mother can't forget, And tears of anguish steal. Thou wast. dear babe, my only hope, For all things else were riv'n, The dearest idol of my soul, I sought no other Heaven.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.      51 But God, to save this earth-bound soul, Hath claimed thee, for His own, Humbled in dust, this blighted heart, Now worships HM, alone. But oh! how heavy was the stroke, When he bade me resign! The- anguish! oh! I feel it yet! But, Lord, thy will be mine. But ah! the blank, in this sad heart, A void must still remain;- Although this brow may wear a smile, These lips may not complain: Yet, I am restless, everywhere, Seeking-I know not what; And yet, must ever seek in vainz-- On earth-I find him not. Tho' many weary suns have set- And rose--upon his-dust,-- I still must weep,--my darling's gone I Oh! help! thou good and just. Blest seraph babe, dost thou behold, These sighs and tears, for thee? O, spread thy pinions-hover near, And whisper peace to me.  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7377-00000027"/> 52       ROSES AND THORNS: The cherub replies- "Nay, cease sad soul,-turn to thy GOD, "'T is there, thou shalt find rest; "And find thy loved one, safe in Heaven, "On the dear Savior's breast."   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   53 CHAPTER      VII. With the recovery of my health, I felt a desola- tion, that none but a bereaved -mother can feel.. Childless, and a widow, in its most forlorn sense; I was obliged to begin the world a-new, with a break- ing heart, feeble health, and only my hands, where- with to obtain a support. At that time, I had scarce- ly a decent suit of clothing; having had few addi- tions of apparel for the last two years. I was whol- ly destitute of money; had paid my step-father eve- ry farthing that he would have required of a stran- ger, (so he said.) I did this voluntarily; he was loth to have pay, but I would hear of nothing else-- especially as he was owing me money, lent before the fatal sacrifice. And here let me record the kindness of that fami- ly to me, during my sickness and troubles; and their tender love to the dear, blessed babe. My brother had been absent a long time; we had heard no tid- ings of him for more than a year. (Alas! we have  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7377-00000028"/> 54      ROSES ANE THORNS  never had any intelligence, that could be implicitly relied on.) I mourned for him, as a lost brother. O, my cup of sorrow was filled to overflowing-but "the cup my Heavenly Father giveth me--shall I not drink it?'"While crushed beneath this heavy weight of woe, I looked for sympathy from some relatives of my father's, who had, in former times, (when fortune smiled,) almost idolized me ;-but alas! I looked in vain. One of these families, who had once caressed me most, instead of meeting me as formerly, with every demonstration of affection- exclaiming, "My dear cousin S., how delighted we are to see you! How long you have staid from us," &amp;c. They now received me with stately dignity, and haughty civility; addressing me "Ma'am," and treat- hig me as a stranger. Had my moral character been impaired, or tarnished in the least,-they would have had some plea for their repulsive and unfeeling beha- vior ; but it is well known that they had no suchjplea. But God was my refuge--and a safe one; as,He ever will be, to the desolate and afflicted, who look to Him, and trust Him. There is one thing that I cannot but remark,- those who treated me in that scornful manner, were, in a short time, reduced to poverty. And some of   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   5 them gladly accepted pecuniary aid, even from me, (after I was again in receipt of money)-as their let- ters of thanks, (now in my possession,) will show. This lesson taught me, in after life, to appreciate my winter friends, (for I have found a few,) and to put the summer ones down-at their fill value. Having, in my earlier days, made some attempts at drawing and painting; but without instruction, and entirely for my own anmusement. I thought, in this extremity, to try my hand at painting portraits, having painted several in crayons, which proved to be correct likenesses, I commenced the labors of an artist, (a rather verdant. one, 'tis true,) in connec- i tion with a school I had taken in the vicinity, where my Tragedy of married life was performed. At this time, my step-father, having a favorable opportunity, sold his farm, as he saw little prospect of clearing it, and his business affairs were getting involved. He moved a few miles to a village, and lived in a hired house. They were both getting into years, and their energies began to be on the wane; however, with their united efforts, they managed to keep a comforta- ble home, and to make a respectable appearance abroad. I now   was in receipt of considerable money,  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7377-00000029"/> ROSES AND THORNS : and could frequently send them small sums, as before, my business being pretty profitable. The world now began to brighten before me. My ex-spouse had married, (a short time after the divorce,) to the woman, whose portrait he had suspended in our par- lor, soon after I went there; (telling me that it was a relative of his,) they had gone off, to a great dis- tance, but not before he had abused her shamefuilly in various ways-(if reports from respectable sources, can be relied on.)   CM, REICOLLECTIONS Or AN ARTIST.  57 CHAPTER     VIII, After teaching school in that place for a year or so, and painting in the recesses of school hours, I received an unexpected invitation, from a gentlemanll and wife% to accompany them home; they resided. where the "' Maine Law"' has since sprung up. Be- ing acquainted, and reposing fiull confidence in them; both, I accepted the invitation. They proved them- selves worthy of the high opinion I had formed of their moral and Christian character. At the time ap- pointed, we commenced our pleasant journey to the (now) city of P------ . I did not consult my mother previous to my departure ; well knowing that I should not obtain her consent; so, I wrote a long letter to her, enclosing all the money I could command at that time, (travelling fare excepted,) took my leave in writing, promising to return, " on demand." On my arrival at P---, after paying fares, &amp;c.} I had just eight dollars left, five of which, I found would not pass,so that,three dollars was all my available resource. I was not to board with the family I went with, as  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7377-00000030"/> 58      ROSES AND THORNS: their residence was not central; it was all previously arranged by us. I was to advertise, as an artist; have a good, central room, and--" go a-head." Af- ter resting with them for a few days, I desired them to-procure me a suitable place, which they did, in a genteel, private family; I hired my painting room of them also; and advertised "S. Paine--Portrait Painter," &amp;c., but notwithstanding the efforts and in- fluence of the family I resided with, and also, the one I came with-no orders came. True, I had no specimens, but I had advertised '" full satisfaction or no pay." I thought this sufficient, - besides, I thought such a portrait as I could paint then, would be rather a poor recommendation. Thus, day after day, and week after week, came and went; but they brought no orders for me. It was now, the begin- ning of winter; my three dollars had nearly all melted away, for wood, oil, &amp;c. My landlady was a wid- ow with an expensive family, and by no means, in affluent circumstances. However, she shewed great forbearance to me; never hinting at a payment; but I expected it, every day. I was greatly embarrassed. To stay longer, without candidly telling her my cir- cumstances, would be dishonorable. To go home without money to pay my travelling expenses, (to say     OR, RECOLUIECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  59 nothing of leaving bills unpaid,) was not to be' thought of. There was no one to whom I dared to -confide the secret of my utter destitution. I feared that I should be despised as soon as it was known that I had come to?    a beggar! For the same reason I did not talk confidentially with my landlady upon the subject. Thus, more than a hun- dred miles from home, among strangers-out of mon- ey-out of employment--and, as I feared, near to the small end of my credit,-and the winter, intense- ly cold, I writhed under a mental torture, which none can comprehend, unless they have been placed ex- actly in the same condition. I received very polite attentions from my new acquaintances; and being pretty decently dressed,-no one suspected that I was in such distressing need; or I should, undoubtedly, have been employed. At length, one day, my landlady said to me, ' I linow you are getting discouraged ; but you shall not give up yet. We cannot have you leave us, and cross the water, to your home, until we have given it a far- ther trial. Able or not, I will set you to work. You may begin, and paint my youngest daughter, with Bunny, her pet kitten."  I was in perfect extacy.- It was like a drop of water to one perishing with  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7377-00000031"/> 60       HOSES AND THORNS! thirst; and what lady-like delicacy she displayed!- For, no doubt, she had penetrated my secret, and (as the sailors say,) "found out how the land lay.--- Though she has long been laid in dust, I offer to her memory, the effusions of a grateful heart. I commenced the picture, with all the ardor of hope, sprung up from the ashes of despair. A crack- ling wood fire soon blazed, in my large, cold painting room. It was an awful cold day, and my fingers were benumbed; but my heart was beating a lively air. The first sitting was got over with very smooths ly; except that Bunny was in a disobliging mood; and proved rather refractory. occasionally letting me have the benefit of her nails. I was very diligent; toiling incessantly at my easel, until the picture wtas finished; when I viewed it with great complaceney, (artist like,) and called Mrs. R., my patron and land- lady, to look at it for the first time. She entered, with an anxious, doubting look-but at the first glance, she started back, in surprise--then fell into perfect raptures, declaring it was "}most excellent!'  Not content to enjoy it alone--she first summnoned the family; their praises were-- long and loud.' Then, putting on her cloak, hood, and overshoes, she sallied forth, and invited her friends, and acquaintan-   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   61 ces-to "come and see."   (That beautiful picture, now hangs in the very same room, where it was first placed; a valued and true likeness of the fair origi- nal-who has, for many years, been mouldering in the dust. The next day, the house was " inundated" with eallers. They entered my "sanctum" with eager looks, to see whither-" a woman could paint a like-, ness?" When lo, they all applauded, beyond my ?most sanguine hopes--or expectation. Orders for portraits, followed each other in quick succession; until I was, at length, fairly established. "A prophet hath honor, save in his own country- and among his own kin." I had received a letter from my mother, rather re- ,proving my clandestine departure; but desired me aot to expose my health, by returning before pleasant weather, in the spring.  She little knew how desti- -tute I had been; and what pecuniary straits I had passed through.  I often thought, when under that depression, of some  lines, that had interested me, very much, when a school-girl. They ran thus: '4d No home receives my shivering form, No voice, maternal, sinks to rest  D  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7377-00000032"/> 62       ROgSES  AND THORNS: Alone I brave the midnight storm-- That freezes my unmantled breast." I wrote often to my mother, but never hinted at any thing that could, possibly, give her one moment's anxiety, or regret. The winter wore on; I received a great many callers, and orders; and though fully employed, the days being very short and cold,-couid accomplish but little. However, I had made very valuable ac- quaintances; and had saved my earnings, so, that when I left in the spring,-after paying all bills and expenses, I found myself in possession of about fifty dollars, which I carefully hoarded to bestow on mother. When I left-I had engaged about twenty portraits, to do when I returned fr6m my visit. The tide of fortune, now seemed turned in my favor. A very flattering and affectionate leave was taken of me, on board the boat; one presented a basket of oranges- another a loaf of rich cake-some presented little delicate offerings,--the value of which consisted in what they implied. But not one of them is foi- gotten. I had engaged to return in three months, at farthest; so, after saying " more last words," we were sundered.   S'O1, RECOLLECTIONS :Of AN ARTIST.   r3 The boat -swept majestically over the blue waters, ;as though proud of her blrthen.   My face was turned towards home-- "In search of!'true pleasu res, how vainly we roam, To hold it for life, we must find it at home." I felt it so. None but those who have beenlong absent, and are returning fLome, can have any idea how joyful my feelings were.   It might be said, that those who always remain at home, must be the happier of the two,  I doubt it, very much.  I think, that our highest enjoyments arise more from anticipation, than from actual possession. Because, the former paints her pictures 'in the mostglow'ing colors; but actual possession, seldom, if ever, produ- ces the original, of said pictures. b  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7377-00000033"/> ".      RO5ES AND THORNS:" CH A?T E R   I X.. On my arrival at the city where I last taught a. school, I was most cordially welcomed back by my- former friends, and pupils; but lost no time in has-- tening home.  ' 'T is home, where 'er the heart is ;; where 'er the loved ones dwell." I was joyfully received, on my arrival there, by all. My dear' mother exclaimed "my child!" when sobs and tears prevented her utterance, for along time. When her feelings became more composed-how much joy she expressed, how much thankfulness to Heaven's mer- cy-that she beheld me once more.    But the "golden hours" passed swiftly on; and "all too soon," brought about the time, the dreaded time, that I must return, to meet my engagements in that far off home.  I felt like this- Yes, I must go, how hard to part, There 's none but those who feel it know- Deep-deep regret, now wrings my heart, But stern necessity says "Go."   'ORn RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  J65 My brother, it was still feared, would never aturm. YWe had waited, hoped, and prayed for his safe re- lurn, but so far, all in vain; until hope had nearly giv- en place to despair. My young half-brother had grown a tall, comely lad, very active and enterprising; but as high-spirited as an untamed colt; a little the worse for too great indulgence-as youngest children gen- erally are. My two step-brothers had married, and gone from holme.  When I started on my reluctant journey, my sorrowing mother, and step-father accompanied me to?   , the city from whence I was to take my departure.  When the time came, for the con- veyance to arrive, to take me away from my mother for a year--and perhaps forever f-I could, with dif- ficulty, chase back the tears, that disputed the pas- sage to my eyes.  On seeing the carriage coming round for me, (my baggage stood at the front door,) I pretended to have forgotten something, and rushed out) as if going for it-sprung into -the coach, and was off. Butt as 'the carriage turned, I heard that much loved well-known v6ice, earnestly exclaiming --"God bless my dear child!" she had seen the car- riage a little too soon. I could not bid her farewell -I knew I should weep if I did, and -not be able to 3  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7377-00000034"/> "      ROSES AND THORNS'A stop; thought I would not behave like a chid.--but try to put on a little fortitude.. But all in vain.- Though I shut my eyes, the tears gushed out from their full fountain. Every time I thought of that benediction of my mother's-so fiull of a mother's love! the flood-gates of my grief would open, afresh. O, I would have given much, at that time, to have been where " none but God, was near!" My grief was of a complicated nature; none but the All-see- ing eye, above, could know the depth of my sorrows. On arriving at the boat, that was to convey me to my destination-a new, and unlooked for trial, await- ed me.  The Captain had come to the coach, and very politely escorted me on board. The best, un- occupied berth was selected for me, by the officious cabin maid. (That class of people, always think, that they can tell--" what 's what-and who is who" -by their appearance. But appearances are often deceitful, as the sequel will show..) It so happened, that there was not a passenger on board, that I had ever seen before. A lady and gentleman, (mother and son,) shewed me some civilities, and we con- versed together; on seeing my name dn a hand ker- chief, the lady observed, that she had often heard   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   67 that name in?   -, where we were bound, and where they resided.  They then gave me their names.  I had heard of them, also.  Thus we stood introduced acquaintances ; and were inseparable companions, on deck.  I supposed that the gentle- man would bring me my ticket, when the bell rung for " the fare." So, in order to be " posted up," (as the clerks say,) I went in, and took out my purse to have the five dollars counted to hand to him- when lo, I discovered, to my utter dismay--thaw I had only four dollars and fifty cents left! Here was a dilemma-I lacked fifty cents of the fare, to say nothing of the twenty-five eents, that must be paid to the "Hack-man." I was in a perfect agony, expecting the bell to ring, every instant! What could I do? I thought of writing a line to the Captain, in apology; saying I would send it, imme- diately, on my arrival ;--but that would not do; I feared he would think it a subterfuge, to defraud him of his fare ; and if he should, my character and feel- ings, would, both suffer. I then thought that I would tell the lady, in confidence, and ask her to lend it to me; but this, I also rejected, as not to be thought of.  What would she think of me;--a stranger, and genteelly dressed, to ask her for money! D4  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7377-00000035"/> -68      ROSES AND THORNS: Psha! The idea was preposterous! I threw my- self into my berth-with the cold sweat standing in large drops, on my face. At that moment, my heart felt to murmur against the Most High!   (What mercy he shewed me, in- stead of punishing my sinful rebellion!) That His word of promise, should say-"Give to the poor, and ye shall not lack." "Have I not always done that? and do I not lack'?" were my heart's bitter questioning. The faith in God-had left me! I believed at that moment, the bible had misled me; ten minutes later, I should have been a confirmed deist, or maniac, or both. My pecuniary care was wholly lost,-in the agonizing thought--that the bi- ble was not true, that it had deceived me! When, happening to cast my troubled eyes on the other side, I saw the colored cabin maid, looking with admiring eyes, at my travelling basket, (a late and beautiful pattern;) a hope of relief instantly sprung up in my mind,--(no one was near;) said I, "Do you like my basket?" She replied, O, yes, indeed, Miss, most beautifullest basket I ever saw." Said I, (with assumed indifference,) "You can   - d R, RECOLLECTIONS OP AN ARTIST.  69 have it--if you wish, as I prefer a size smaller.7-- (It was true. I did.) "Would I sell it to her?-and what was the price?" were her eager questions. Said I, "It cost me one dollar; b-l, as I have -used it a few times-you may take it for seventy- five cents." She ran with all speed,-fearing that I might re- cail my offer,--:and brought me three silver quarters, which I tossed on to my berth, with seeming indif- ference; emptied, and delivered -the basket, (much more fearful of a recantation, than herself.) As soon as she had vanished, with her new treas- 'ure, I slipped the money into my purse,--rejoicing, 'and the next instant, the bell sounded for the fare. (It would not have been prudent, under the circum- stances, to let that girl suspect my ntecessity.) As I had anticipated, Mr. W. presented my ticket. Expressing my thanks for his courtesy, and polite 'attentions, I tipped him the five with a careless air.; 'and, no doubt, he thought there was " enough more, where that caame fromn." I believe that I was never considered artful or secretive; but there are occa- sions, where common'prudence will warrant conceal- ment.  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7377-00000036"/> 70      ROSES Ao N TsNff0s . Now, just see, how very singular! I obtained just what I needed, and not one cent, more! How' plainly I saw the merciful hand of God, in this little incident. How deeply I deplored, my momentary apostacy-my faithlessness, and sinful murmuring; How devoutly I adored the merciful forbearance, of a sin-pardoning God! I wept in my berth, and if penetential tears were ever shed, it was in that berth. I then thought-come what will, I shall never dis- trust the providence of my Heavenly Father again, From that hour, my faith was renewed and strength- ened; and it has lasted, from that. to the present hour. Those who watch the hand 'of Divine providence will see it in small-as well as great things. "A sparrow cannot fall to the' ground, without His no- tice." We must not expect, if we are careless, waste- ful, or slothful, that the deficiency will always be supplied. In the case just referred to, I had no just claim on that promise--"Thou shalt not lack."- Because I had not taken good care of my money, be- fore coming to the boat. I had, probably, spent it inadvertantly, or lost it. 1 am certain, howeveTr that no one had stolen it; that was a satisfaction, at least. I had taken enough mon leaving home, to de-   OR, RBCOLLECTIONS OF A ARTIST.   71 fray my travelling, and incidental expenses; and left the rest. We arrived at P--- - the following morning, at sunrise. I was "u Hacked" up, handed my solitary quarter to the driver--and was joyfully received at my boarding place.  There could not have been more respectful courtesy shown to a--a-better artist. They little knew what a cold sweat I had been writhing in. But no matter. I had demands, and in a few days, received all the money I needed;-but have always remembered the lesson I learned at Sea. 106  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7377-00000037"/> 72       ROSES AND THObRSK CHAPTER     X. Time passed on; my first landlady had removed to another part of the city; and I had taken up my residence in another family-equally agreeable, and respectable. It was termed a select boarding housi. They took but four boarders-a young lady of my acquaintance, two young gentletnen-and myself; these, together with their own two sons, and two daughters--(ages, varying from eighteen to thirty)-- made up a pleasant party,--especially, as they were all literary-and very interesting companions, which made it very agreeable at home. My painting-room was thronged with visitors--in deed, it was a fashionable resort. I was enabled, by my constant receipt of money, to dress as I chose, -and for once, in my life, indulged my tastes, how- ever expensive; so that I was richly and fashionably attired; I could not desire more attention than I re- ceived. In this full tide of prosperity- "I of the gift an idol made, The giver quite forgot."   OR, RECOLLEdTIOiS OF AN ARTISt.   73 I had relapsed into my natural element--ife and spirit. Many of the wealthy, and aristocratic ladies, when sad, and low spirited, would come to me.- hoping to imbibe a share of my unvarying cheerful- ness; how little they knew of the deep--under cur- rent of affliction, that still ran beneath the smiling surface. "No comfort or hope, my own heart could elate, Yet comfort and hope, could to others impart." It was my constant endeavor, to put away past troubles-and remember them only as-" things that were ;" and to enjoy the present as much as possible. Being from nature capacitated for much happiness, or misery, as the case might be, I often had the ap- pearance of being perfectly happy. Many declared they never saw so happy a temperament as mine; and they had good reason for thinking so; for though I never tried to deceive them ; or to spread false col- ors ; yet ' never told my grief." My domestic troubles were locked up--and the key -kept in my own pocket.  Hown could I disclose,- farther than it had already reached, my degradation? (for it was degrading in the eyes of many, not to en- dure until death-even if that death were caused by murder.)  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7377-00000038"/> 74      RtOSES AND THORNS' I did not feel bound by any duty--itvil, moral, of religious, to proclaim, among proud strangers, the trying scenes of my past life. I thought it enough for them, to know that my moral character stoodfair, and my conduct such as would be perfectly consist- ent with a virtuous, delicate, wife. It was often conjectured that I was under a matri- monial engagement at home,-from the circumstance of my being so insensible to the very polite atten- tions-which hung within my reach. Thus, time passed on, not deigning to look back, to see who, or how many victims had fallen beneath his wheels. All things were going on brightly--. and smoothly with me, when a sudden cloud dark- ened my fair sky;- and a crushing damper-fell on my short-lived prosperity. A rumor had risen, and spread in every direction, before coming to my knowledge,--that I had ab- sconded from my native place-leaving behind me a husband, (nearly distracted,) and several young help- less children! This came to me like a "clap of thunder, in a clear sky." I had perceived a change of manner in many of my acquaintances-and quite a falling off of profes- sions of regard; this troubled me very much,-I   ORl, hECOLLECTIONS QO AN ARTIST.  75 could not imagine the cause,-I reviewed every word and action of minej since I had been in the placey strictly and faithfully; but was perfectly satisfied, that the whole would bear the strictest scrutiny. Although there had been much in my life, to bring the tear-there had been nothing to call the blush 'of shame to my cheek.  I finally determined to con- suit my landlady,-believing that she could throw light on the subject, if she would. I requested a private audience, told her that I had observed a gradual coldness of manner, towards me ; not only abroad-but at homet-in her family-in her domestic circle. She quickly asked if I had wit- nessed any change in her manner towards me. I admitted that I had not. She then replied-"- Nor do I feel any,-yet I must be candid with you, or I should not be your true friend; as I am, at all points. There is a report- which I know is not true-it cannot--- hope to Heaven -it can not be true."' She then stated the accusation already named; but, said she--c I tell every one, that I know there is not a word of truth in the report-that you came highly recommended-to say nothing of your excel- lent behavior, and praiseworthy. deportment, ever  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7377-00000039"/> 76      RbSES AND THORNS  since you set foot on this soil. Never give youtr self a moment's disquiet, my dear child; you will soon be able to clear off this fog,-thrown on you, no doubt, by jealousy and envy." As soon as I could speak, (for the choking sensa- tion I felt, nearly deprived me of utterance,) I cried -"Oh, no; would to Heaven it was so! "What do you mean?" she cried, looking as if ready to faint-" O, do not tell me it is true!" "I shall not," replied I, "for certainly it is not true, but it is founded on truth.' I then gave her a brief outline of what was actu- ally true. She was greatly surprised, seeming very sorrowful; regretted that it did not come from my- self-originally. Said H"Dear lady, would you have had me lug in my domestic troubles, without any corroborating testimony, to stranger's ears? Of what possible advantage could it have been to myself, or to any one? Besides, you do me the honor to say that my beha- vior has been irreproachable, from the time of my first arrival here, until the present time. What more could any reasonable person require?" Said H "Has there never been any occurrence in your life, not gratifying to your vanity, which you have not   OR, RECOLLECTIONS 01 AN ARTIST.  " communicated to me, or to any stranger, be that stranger ever. so trustworty?" She tearfully replied that I had acted rightly-that her full confidence in me was not, in the least dimin- ished; and that she should prove herself my friend- indeed. I found it a source of consolation, to have one, to sympathise with-and comfort me; for I was much in need-her daughters put on airs," her sons and the boarders, treated me with cool, constrained po- liteness. I felt this severely, and it lessened them in my es- teem.  I soon perceived a great change in the cli- mate of feelings towards me ;-some cast disdainful glances-others treated me with chilling politeness- others, with a patronizing, pitying air; and some with a sort of sorrowful kindness. But this would not do. I never sought their pity -or deserved their contempt; and stubbornly deter- mined, that I would sit down under neither. Here ensued a dead pause ;-my heart was worn almost to a blank, and nearly broken with its fre- quent burthens. My room was nearly deserted ;- and my business, almost entirely down. I resolved  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7377-00000040"/> 78      ROSES AND THORNS: to leave the place, at once, and return to those who knew the whole. But a judicious friend, in whom I had the utmost confidence, said--" nay-do not go now, at any rate. Stay and live it down. Send to where all is well known, and get testimonials respecting this affair, and have them published." This seemed an eligi- ble plan,-and good advice; which I determined to follow, at once, and accordingly, lost no time in writ- ing to a lady of talents, who resided in the vicinity, where all these sorrowful scenes occurred,-to write, in some form, a graphic sketch of the same, only giv- ing fictitious names; that I wished to publish it, and gave her my reasons. While waiting her reply, I left my boarding place ; notwithstanding my landlady's entreaties to the con- trary. I could not enjoy life again, where my feel- ings had been so wounded by the hatuer of her un- feeling daughters.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   79 CHAPTER XI. An elderly gentleman and wife, who had no chil- dren, (they were, formerly, in affluent circumstances,) but Were, at this time reduced, by a succession of misfortunes, to the necessity of repairing their re- sources, by taking a few select boarders. Here I applied-telling the lady all. (I did not intend to be corrected again, on that score,) without hesitation; and apparently much gratified with the proposal, she decided to let me board, and make my home with them; and a very pleasant home it proved for more than two years. They then removed from P to a country residence, some miles distant. I never saw them again, as I left?   myself, shortly after. While with them, I was treated as their own child; was indulged and petted to my full satisfaction. Mrs. G., (my landlady,) on seeing me look sad and dejected, as I sometimes looked and felt,-would say- Don't look so sorrowful, dear; I cannot bear to see it. Why bless you! do you not know that  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7377-00000041"/> 80      ROSES ANE THORNS: you are " a white hen's chicken" all over the house? A favorite with the boarders--and in the kitchen, (where Madam Cook will allow no other boarder,) you can be admitted at all times, and if you turn ev- ery thing 'topsy turvey' it is all right and beautiful, with every one of the help, and it is well known that you are a perfect idol, with one silly old woman here; and as for G., my husband-if you wanted that Market House, (pointing across the street,) turned about,-I have no doubt but he would get hold of one corner--and try." Then I would reply, "I am astonished that you are not jealous of Captain G.; I think you had bet- ter have a watchful eye-it do n't harm honest peo- ple to watch them." Then she would reply,--"I tell you why I am not jealous. I make a point of never feeling the influence of the ' green-eyed monster' unless the lady in question is handsomer than I am." This witty rejoinder would throw me into a laugh ; dissipating all my sadness for that time; and she would rejoice to see me restored to cheerfulness again. In the meantime, my own history-so far as was   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.    81 necessary for the present occasion, was forwarded by the lady referred. to, written under fictitious -names. This, I caused to appear as a story,--in one of the most prominent, and popular papers then and there printed. All recognized in the afflicted Jessey, the artist, then lying under their distrust. Many came forward with professions of sympathy and friend- ship.  Others "Convinced, against their will, Were of the same opinion, still."' However, my business revived, and the affair seemed gradually to be forgotten-at least, all confi- dence in my favor seemed to be fully restored. But with me-the wound left a scar, that never healed, during my residence among them.  The stranger's .heart, oh, wound it not, @ A yearning' anguish is its lot. : I see it all clearly, now; - it was the chastening hand of my Heavenly Father.   I had become a backslider from the Gospel requirements; though strictly moral, my faithless heart had turned agamin to the world; and what did the world give as a reward for my sinful preference? The reader will perceive! that my reward was a bruised and wounded heart.  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7377-00000042"/> 82       ROSES AND THORNS) Doth not disappointment follow, Every step, that leads from God? Have not piercing thorns and briers- Shown their points, through all the road?' It was even so.  I had not denied my Saviour, in words, it is true; neither had I owned him as a pardoned sinner should do,--but like Peter,-"Fol- lowed Him, afar off."   I had made up my mind, that it was best not to own that I had been a pro- fessed christian ;--thought that if I really had any grace-if there was one vestige left, that some watch- fill Christian would discover it, beneath the dross, that obscured it, (then, it was my intention to come forward.)  And so it proved, through all this dis- guise, I'was suspected of privately being a follower of the Lamb. O, how it encouraged and rejoiced my heart, to know that the slightest mark of a Christian was still discernable. Yet I but partly owned to a few friends, the true state of my case; fearing that an open profession) after all that had taken place, would cause them to suspect that I did it, with unworthy motives; so I said-mentally, "Heaven forbid that I should make religion a stepping stone to establish my reputation.'"   oH, RECOLLE9CTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   8 So I said but a little, when interrogated respecting mny religious faith, and belief. I gradually became cheerful and contented, until the year had run its rounds, which again brought about the long anticipated time that I was to set out on a journey to visit my dear mother; when I was taken suddenly ill, that my life was thought to be in great danger; my illness was caused by bathing in new rum, when afflicted with the erysipelas; igno- rant of the danger of such a proceeding, until I felt the effects. It threw me into dreadful spasms. I-had the best medical advice, but, notwithstand- ing, was laid on a sick bed for many weeks, enduring dreadful distress, I was literally covered with blis- ters,-the one on my lungs, doubtless, was God's means to save my life.  I had my senses, and for- bid them to write to my mother.   If I lived, it would be keeeping the trouble from her entirely; if I died, I felt that I could die easier, if she was not present; and she could feel no worse, than if I died with her.  When a cup is full, the rest if poured on, will overflow. No cup can be more than full. I hired a nurse for many weeks. Mrs. G. had never been used to labour or confinement,-and- if the whole truth must be told, she was a better nurse for  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7377-00000043"/> 84      ROSES AND THORNS; the well, than for the sick; which would be the case with many an accomplished lady, if they were put to the test. I received every attention from friends and acquaintances; and though I did not require pe- cuniary assistance, my room looked like a confec- tionery establishment; with jellies, tamarinds, pre- serves, fruit, etc., brought and sent by them. I hal very good watchers, who generally came voluntarily, every night. How God " tempers the wind to the shorn lamb." Thus I was tenderly cared for, and " did not lack," during these weary days and weeks of sickness and confinement. I was paying nurses wages, paying her board; and rent for the furnished parlor, which I was obliged to occupy during my illness; together with the rent of two office rooms, which I had used as painting and exhibition rooms,--which together with other bills, and incidental expenses,-amounted to a pretty round sum.   OR, .lC0LLT Ct01NS oV AN ARTtSTe 83 CHAPTE1   R X  I, After my recovery, I collected all my demands, which just covered it, and no more. Thus, again I stood alone, and penniless. I was now, too fee- ble, and it was too late to go to visit my mother, much as I desired to see her; so I wrote, stating that I had been sick, but was out of danger; that I had intended to come home, but must now, wait un- til Spring. As soon as I was able to paint, I found plenty of employment,-and began anew; I became Very healthy and strong; my cheeks looked like pul- pit cushions, (defaced ones.) Time passed on, and very pleasantly With me; Mrs. G. was very tender to me; so were they all; we had a number of new and very interesting board- ers. Spring soon came bounding in, like a romping child, and received a cordial welcome by all-es- pecially me; for I was again preparing to visit my dear mother; I had written to her often, both before, E  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7377-00000044"/> 86      ROSES AND THORNS: and after my illness, but never hinted that anything had troubled me, since we parted. I could not la: that heavy burden upon her heart. Each letter ha( a small sum in its pocket, that nothing might be un supplied-or lacking, at home. I started from?   in the evening,-there were many prayers put up by my adopted family, fo my safety. I was the bearer of a beautiful lette from Mrs. G., to my mother ; it was a token of re gard for me, which I could not but appreciate.- Many kind friends and acquaintances repaired to th boat, to bestow adieux, and best wishes for my saft ty, and also, for my speedy return. The next morning, at sunrise, it was currently r ported in?  , that the boat I left in, was los and that every soul on board, perished! which,  course, was not true,-respecting that boat; it wz another. On my return to?   ,I was told that Cap and Mrs. G. were almost -distracted; that the mourned for me as an only child. That the boar( ers, and all the household were deeply affected; th my sudden death, (as they took it to be,) was muc lamented in?  .  The certainty of our safe did not reach them until the next evening. (1   OR:, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARtIST, -87 Telegraph wires then.) In the meantime, -holly ignorant of their sorrow and dismay,-I was having a pleasant excursion; and a very happy .time. My heart was again bounding with blissful anticipations of -friends and home. On my arrival, I was greeted with a tender joy- ful welcome,-especially by my mother.; and spent a few-pleasant weeks with her, and in visiting my other friends. My young half-brother, had grown a tall, genteel looking young man-futh of spirit and enterprise, and very interesting; his fondness for me raised -my hopes that he would be a kind, affection- ate brother, and that he would add greatly to my felicity and happiness, in this world. How far I re- alized these hopes, the sequel will show. The time had 1now come to bid them all another adieu; but this was far less painful than formerly; I had become inured to treading the rough path of life; far from kindred and home,--in a word--'"My soul was even as a weaned child." I had ," quieted myself,-and behaved like a child, weaned of its mother."  But to think of another year's absence- and the uncertainty of life, the fear of never seeing home again-caused me deep regret.  But I could 2  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7377-00000045"/> 8s       ROSES AND THORNST see no way, at that time, to provide for myself,---ad assist those, dearer than self,--but by such a sacrifice, At the time appointed, I embarked for?  r taking special care, not to be found " lacking," as the reader will recollect I once was, on board the boat.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST. 89 CHAPTER     XI II. The family at my eastern home, welcomed me with genuine tenderness;-thanking, and blessing the mercy of Heaven, for my safe return. I felt completely at home, rested, and received calls for a day or two; and then re-opened my- painting rooms. I found myself not only liberally patronized-but as highly esteemed, as I could desire to be. (That is saying a great deal, it is true.) Thus my days passed off very rapidly and pleasantly, I reckon that year, among the few sunny spots, of my be- clouded existence. When those who had wounded my spirit, by be- -lieving that false report, and had manifested that be- belief in their deportment to me, saw that their su- periors sought me-why they sought me also--were my "very dear friends," etc., and very amaible of them, too-very. Mrs. G., my landlady, when young, I am told, was styled the "Boston Beauty," and she wA-as still I;3  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7377-00000046"/> 9U      ROSES AND THORNS/ very handsome.  Her husband, in early life, was a. ship master; and she had sailed with him, to many distant cimes and ports; and had visited many for- eign eities,-had increased her knowledge and intel- ligence, until she had become one of the most ac- complished, as well as the most agreeable of women. I often found great amusement in writing verses, addresseed to her, in letter form^--just to get the wit- ty answer, that I was sure to find lying on my table, at my return from the Studio. MErs. G. was a professed christian,--Capt. G.. was. not.  However, being modified by his wite, (for she was, in truth, the better half,.) he used but little of what sailors term--"- Sea language," and was a gootd, easy, passive consort. Mas. G. often ex- pressed her astonishment at. hearing me quote any quantity of scripture, fluently, when conversing, or: arguing upon religious subjects, calling up, readily, any passage I needed, to support my assertions; when. she, nor no one else, had ever seen me reading in the bible; not even on a Sabbath day.  I explained that, by telling her- that I could repeat a great deal of the bible, but it was not obtained by the usual process, of being compelled, when a child, to com- mit a given number of texts of scripture,-or be plun-   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   91 ished; neither was it by having a stated time to read it,-or reading it in the presence of others; but by reading it, when alone, and when I could disencum- ber my mind from worldly thoughts and cares. At such times, it would make a deep impression; then I would read a great many chapters at a time; and retain the substance of the whole. I then referred her to her own observation, for a proof, that my plan had been successful. The boarders here, were mostly pious; one cler- gyman, who was a permament boarder, led in prayer, evening and mornings.  I attended, more to please Mrs. G. than anything else--and frankly told her so. My  reasons were, that they were' often prosy and dull; a thing I never could endure patiently ; for if anything on earth should be done with energy, and spirit, it should be manifested in our intercessions to the Most High God. "Their lifted eyes, salute the skies; Their bended knees, the ground; But God abhors the sacrifice, Where not, the heart is found." It is very true, that a good christian may not al- ways feel spiritual ardour, when he is attempting to E4  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7377-00000047"/> 92      ROSES AND THORNS: pray-if not, he had better "pray in secret," instead of worrying his christian friends, and disgusting all others,-with formal, dull, heartless prayers. I am sincere in saying, that I believe so much dull formali, ty, and so little visible fruit, (for when there is any fruit on a tree, it can generally be seen,) has driven many back-and prevented many more from seeking what has, apparently, done others so little good.- Do n't you think so yourself, reader? I generally attened the Baptist church; but felt no fellowship with what I pettishy called their prim formality; I suppose, however, that I was like the tipsy man, who told his wife, on going home, that he should have -(hic)--enjoyed -(hic)- himself much better, if they had-(hic)-not all been so- so-con-confounded drunk!  (He had been to town meeting.) I did not enjoy gay company; and if solemn and spiritual, I did not feel quite in the right element with them.  At length, I began to reflect seriously, on the subject-something was wrong, that was clear --what that something, was, I now undertook to in- vestigate; when I soon made the discovery, that I might have made long before, (had I paused to re-   'DO, RECOLLECTIONS OF AS ARTIST.  flect,) that my heart, which of right-and by my own voluntary, solemn promise, belonged to God, had turned from its allegiance-and was trying to fix on the world, but the world had lost it charms, it ceased to fill the blank. After making this discovery, I fell into an apathet- ic, uncomfortable feeling; but yet too proud to own that I was unhappy. But one day, happening to be sitting alone, in my studio, these words came to me, with great power--"Choose ye this day, whom ye will serve /" I felt the necessity of making up my mind before Sunset, whether I would serve God or not. I began to feel an earnest assurance, that His mer- cy was no longer to be trifled with ; and though rea- son and conscience both urged me to come out, and to own, and worship God-and Him alone; yet an armed host, held me in their chains, a captive! These chains were thrown about me, so gradually, and so imperceptibly, that I had no idea but that I was free, until I attempted to rise. I was, indeed, a servant of sin, and saw no way to escape. I could not pray-except to say-"Lord have mercy., I would have given much, to have had some good Ea  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7377-00000048"/> ",      ROSES, AND- THONS  Christian intercede at the throne of God's mercy, ia my behalf; but felt ashamed to ask it. I took my, bed, on getting home that night, refused food or drink, and sadly rejected every kindness and- attention offered me. Mrs. G. insisted on my tell-- ing her how I felt; but she could get nothing but "Leave me, leave me." On the following day, Mrs. G. kindly taking my hand, said, "I am going to guess out your malady-- you are under conviction? I did not attempt to de- ny it. She thanked the Lord, that her prayers were- answered; and prayed fervently for me. I then. ownecd: for the first time in P----, that I was, astray from the Fold of God; entreating of them to help me back.  There was much sympathy, and much rejoicing--some cried--"The tall cedars of Lebanon, are beginning to bow." I felt as though. - hung over destruction by a slen- der thread, and feared to go to sleep, lest I should; wake in an eternity of despair! Thus. I continued, day after day, and found no relief,   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  95 CHAPTER      XIV. At length, I concluded to go home to my mother; never expecting to be capable of business again.- My christian friends, were loth to let me go, and un- der such affliction too; but seeing me so much bent on going, they ceased their entreaties-praying the Lord might meet me, on the way. A young lady, of the church accompanied me, as far as the city of B The thoughts of going home, gave me no pleasure, as it had always done before. My feelings were now reduced to calm despair. I felt nothing but complete apathy. When we got on board the boat, I looked on the sea, exclaiming, " how beautiful!"' My friend start- ed in surprise, she looked earnestly into my face--my feelings were so changed, that I could scarcely iden- tify myself, with the miserable creature who had just come on board.  We both attributed this change to the reviving effects of the sea air; when turning gO  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7377-00000049"/> 96      ROSES AND THORNS: from her-these words came to me-"In a little wrath, I hid my face from thee, but with great mer- cy, will I gather thee." I now knew that the Lord had " met me in way" -sure enough; but dared not tell my friend; fear- ing these happy feelings would vanish, if I revealed them.  On arriving at B  , my joyful feelings continued,-so I venturned to reveal them to my friend, as soon as we were alone in our chamber ; she was much rejoiced; said she had mistrusted it, from the time that I exclaimed " how beautiful!" I felt perfectly at home-with my God and Sa- viour. That evening, I wrote to Mrs. G., and my sympa- thizing christian friends in general, a long letter, ex- pressive of my thanksgiving and joyful feelings.- The young lady returned the next day, bearing the letter, which was read in conference meeting; it was expected that I should unite with them, from some expression in the letter ; and I was joyfully received, though not present, save in spirit. I had gc le my way with a joyful heart; had a very harpy visit at home. While there, I made a great hRange in my apparel; I felt that my former expensive, fashionable attire, was the world's uni-   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  97 form, which I had worn too long; that a simple dress would better become a follower of the Lamb. (For I now expected to serve the Lord, with much more zeal and perfectness, than I had done in my first attempt. We shall see whether these expecta- tions were realized or not-as we proceed. After a very pleasant stay of several weeks, I re- turned to P-  , where I was joyfully hailed as "Sister," and requested to unite with them at once --when suddenly, our beloved pastor was taken ill, and lived but a few days. This was a heavy stroke to us all, for there were few such men on earth. It was long before they could find a successor, that they chose to settle; and the pulpit was not regularly sup- plied, during my stay in?.--.  So that I did not choose to become a member under such circum- stances, and remained received, but not united.  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7377-00000050"/> 98      ROSES AND THORNS: CHAPTER     XV. I now lived a very tranquil and happy life.- "Dilligent in business, and fervent in the spirit."'-- The first real sorrow that disturbed the smooth cilr- rent of my life; was giving up my pleasant home at Capt. G.'s, and losing them, and they were as loth to part; but the removal was so much to their advan- tage, that we felt obliged to submit, however reluc- tant. After their departure, I boarded in a small, private family; and they were agreeable enough; but my home was broken up, and I felt desolate and home- sick. My health was getting poor; and I conclud- ed to accept the invitations of some country friends, to visit them, at their homes, and paint the likenesses of their families. This I found very pleasant as well as profitable. One of these families, who resided on the border of N. H., I shall never forget; I spent some weeks with them, most delightfully, to me-(perhaps less   OR, RECOCLLECTIONS OF ANa ARTIST. 99 to, to them.) I visited in this way, being invited- from one place to another, and painting at their residen- ces for more than two months.- But my health was gradually sinking, which admonished me to return to P---- , whieh I did, and made hasty prepara- tions to go home; never expecting to return; as my symptoms were quite alarming. Our leave taking at?   ,was solemn and affecting. The day before I left, I received a letter from an old and valued friend, a widow, who resided in the city of P-   - , (R. I.,) requesting me to come to her immediately, and bring all my trunks; for I tnust not leave her again. She stated that her only daughter was at the point of death, in a consumption. I decided to go directly to her, as I must pass. through the city, on my way home; but thought I could not stop short of my mother. But when I ar- rived at her house, I was so reduaced, that many thought it doubtful, if I outlived the daughter.-- (This was told. me, after my recovery.) I could not then, lift a common parlor chair, and my coughl was quite alarming. My  friend felt full faith, that vith good nursing, I should soon be well, and so it proved.  She left nothing untried, that had any  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7377-00000051"/> 100      ROSES AND THORNS: -hope in it, for my recovery. She said my mother must not see me, until I looked more presentable. In about a week after my arrival, her daughter died.  It was a widow mourning, for her only daughter. It was dreadful to see her cut off in the morning of life, being- but 17 years of age. The widowed mother, though wealthy, was still misera- ble--what can wealth do, towards healing a smitten heart? She had one other child, a son; but still grieved for her lost darling. 'My health was so far restored that I thought of going to see my mother; but my friend entreated me not to leave her; not even to go to my mother.-- She said that if I would bind myself by a promise, to never leave her, while we both lived, that I should inherit her daughter's fortune, (several thousands,) and should do no work, unless for my own amuse- ment, and should have a chaise whenever I chose to ride, etc. But the offer was not accepted, or rather the conditions of it. Would I sell my liberty fcr a few thousands of dollars? I told her that I could not bind myself by any promise ; neither did I wish to heir, what in right belonged to her son; but would spend some time with her, and my own mother-- jointly.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  101 After a visit home, I returned and staid some months with her; which I enjoyed very much.-- She shewed me every affectionate attention; there was nothing too good, or too much to bestow on me; her money presents were very liberal; but I never would accept more than a trifling, sum; I was un- willing to lay myself under a heavy obligation.- Her little keepsakes, such as jewelry, boxes, books, etc., I willingly accepted, and no more. (I eventu- ally found that this was no ill-timed prudence.) At the expiration of this long visit, I was sent for, by an acquintanee, residing in L---- , a manufac- turing town, some 50 or 60 miles distant, to come on a visit, and come prepared to paint a few heads. I went, and spent a few weeks, but was homesick, every day of the time. I might have been liberally patronized; but would stay no longer, when I had done my first set of pictures. I stopped in the city of B---- on my return home, at the very house where I had been so happy, a year or two before. Here, I engaged a room, and board, thinking that I would attempt to locate in B-- as my mother and step-father were getting in years, and my mother had besought me, not to go again, over the waters, and leave them. My  half-brother  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7377-00000052"/> I0'      ROSES AND THORNS: had become a young man, and lived with his parents, but somehow, he had so much business of his own, that the care and burden came upon the aged couple.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  103 CHAPTER     XVI. I returned to B--- , on account of the oppor- tunity of studying my profession, at the Athenaeum, there, which was opened for the benefit of artists.- Here I was presented with tickets, and admitted within the railing. This was very advantageous to me ; but I was troubled with pecuniary cares. My rent and board bills were accumulating, that I felt very low and despondent; few orders came, and I felt heavy cares crushing me down, until it was evi- dent to me, that I could do nothing in B---. At this crisis, an artist, residing in that city, called on me, (I had been introduced to him while at L----,) after first compliments were passed, he asked if I found plenty of business; on being an- swered that I did not--hesaid my location was not favorable; and if I would allow him, that he would aid me in procuring a more central one; this offer was most gratefilllly accepted by me ; and he soon procured me a capital painting room.. He then said  although your boarding place is. very respectable.  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7377-00000053"/> 104      UOSES AND THORNS: yet it is not just the thing for you ; something a lit- tle more stylish and genteel, is requisite, as you are a strayger in B-  , and before the public." He then advised me where to apply; I followed his ad- vice, implicitly, and was received as a boarder, at the house he had recommended.  From that time he remained my friend and adviser. True, I was un- der no pecuniary obligations to him; but shall al- ways remember, with gratitude the unselfish kind- ness of my " brother Chip," as I used to call him.- (For I think he acted upon motives of pure benevo- lence, and no other.) At my new boarding place, all was pleasantness and gayety ; but respectable and select. The terms were very high; but my friend advised me not to flinch; said I should soon discover the advantages of taking such a stand; and I did. The boarders, though otherwise proud, all seemed to take a deep interest inll me, though I could not tell why; for I was care-worn, and made a shabby appearance among those highly accomplished, elegantly attired ladies and gentlemen; but they attributed that to my ar- tistic habits; said that all artists were privileged to look and act as they pleased, and be admired none the less. I knew that these flattering compliments,   OR, RECOMLtECTION9 GP AN At'IST.  l0f were dictated by benevolence and politeness; (but few are proof against flattery, if laid on with a fine brush-and not too thick,) we were on the best of terms. Where now was my zeal and devotedness in the worship of God?  Ah, reader-z-it was in my closets laid up on the shelf, like some good old book, which we value, and lay away very carefully-but think, that the centre-table is not the fitting place for it; although we would not part with it on any account, I had no acquaintance' with any there, exceptfash-' ionable Christians; that class were numerous; but could only help me in the "'broad way.1  I felt the truth of that remark of our Lord and Saviour : 'No man can serve two tnasters." I strove to live as a Christian should; but found the world a heavy clog, which kept me down below the atmosphere of Heavenly life; to which I might have flown, if my wings of faith had been kept in better repair by con-w stant exercise. It was soon discovered by the boarders, that XI painted very true likenesses, and at very low prices; this gave me plenty of business for a tihne,intil an* other door was opened for me.  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7377-00000054"/> 106      ROSES AND THORNS: Reader, remember that you can often do a stran- ger a very great kindness, without putting your hand into your pocket, at all. Your influence, even a word from you, may save them; and will you let them want it? Must you stay until you can find out all about them, before you will lift a finger for their relief? Many an out cast from society, of both sexes, might have been saved by a little timely aid; by a helping hand at some difficult point in their lives. How many in affluent circumstances, and professed ehristians, too-seem to forget this, entirely ; but reader, do not so-"Work while the day lasteth, for the night cometh, wherein no man can work." A family in B-- -, who had liked my painting, were desirous of having their family painted, if I would do them at their own house; and they would remunerate me, for the rent of my own painting room, while I was away. I decided to accept this offer. I went and painted the five, to entire satis- faction, and was not loth to leave when they were finished; notwithstanding, they were very respect- able people, and made " long prayers." Before leaving that place, a married sister of theirs, a haughty, wealthy, purse-proud woman, visited them. from a distant part of the city. She admired   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST;  107 the likenesses, and insisted on my coming to her mansion, to paint all of her family; I hesitated, but she would not be denied; said she, ' board is no object with us-we will give you board and rent, exclusively, and pay you full prices for the pictures; you shall have as many rooms as you wish, and have your choice in the rooms." I thought best to go, as board and rent were ob- jects to me. At the appointed time, the splendid carriage of Madam H. was sent for me, the servant had orders to inform me that I should find a large party, for afternoon and evening on my arrival. On alighting from the carriage, she met me very graciously; but I begged her to excuse me as I was fatigued, and did not feel like -seeing company; but she said that she had invited the company on my ac- count, and should insist on my presence; said she would go with me to my room, where I must lie down a short time, and she would send up a cup of strong tea; and I must brighten up, and go down to be introduced. So she had it all her own way, as I could make no- reasonable objections. I had to pass the ordeal of being introduced to a full drawing-room; but they came to rie, in small  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7377-00000055"/> 108     ROSES AND THORNS'S: groups; and the introductions passed off very smoothly. I found that her company were refined and ele- gant, and people of rank and fashion; I found them very polite and agreeable; and the evening passed off very pleasantly. I have always observed that among the real, highly finished ladies and gentlemen that we poor dowdies, make our way much better than among their apes.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AXtN ARTI9T. lo9 CHAPTER-X      II. After the departure of the guests, said she-.. There did I not tell you that you should not regret coming to us? And you will not; it will be the.' making of you!" I was then shown to a richly furnished sleeping- room-wondering if Madam   would receive the at- tentions of such people as I had met in her drawing- room, that evening-if she was not able to give rich treats? Her husband, though a sensible, plain, pious man, and much respected-was a mere cypher in his own house. After breakfast, the next morning, we were all summoned into the back drawing-room, to attend reading and prayers; this, to me, was a welcome summons. The husband had read a chapter-and commenced a very able, and fervent prayer; when one of the youngest scions was discovered to be impiously scratching some of the splendid furniture with a pin! p  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7377-00000056"/> ItO      ROSES AND THORNS: The enraged mother, not waiting for the " amen, gave the unlucky urchin a goodly number of flat- handed blows; which, together with the screaming of the child, and the trembling voice of the praying father, made such a concert, as I hope never, never to hear again. (How I pitied that rich man.) After this scene was through vith, and the hus- band gone to his counting-room; the servants were nearly all in requisition to prepare the front drawing- room chamber; (as that afforded the best light for the paintings,) and make it as a parlor, (or rather studio,) for me. While this was being done, the lady turned to me, saying, "I think you are highly honored-to have our best front chamber." Said H," No doubt, but 't is an honor that I have been so much accustomed to, that I do not feel exalted by it." I had made up my mind, that I would keep her imperiousness in check; but scarcely a day passed over my head, that I did not receive some covert in- sult; and at the same time, received the utmost at- tention; everything was arranged for my comfort and convenience; but one drop of vinegar will spoil a quart of the sweetest milk.   IOR, RECOLLECTIONS 0t AN ARTIST. -" I had at length, finished my pictures, to their full sattisfaction, and received a handsome sum of money, together with a voluntary diploma for painting by Madam; written, as she expressed it, to give me 4 a start in the world.' Their elegant horses and carriage then took me back to my pleasant boarding place; and there was ymuch apparent rejoicing, at my return. I kept the same painting-room., and found plenty of business, until autumn, when I went home to visit my mother, and to tell her all my wanderings, and to leave her a key that will unlock almost any door. I stopped in the city of? ,to visit my friend, the widow, for she insisted on my making her house tmy home, if I could not abide with her. After a pleasant visit, I returned to B ,and painted until the next spring. When I had an ap pointment to visit Cape A , where I had been in- vrited by a family, for whom Hhad painted, while- in B    , with a guarantee that I should -have plenty of business, to fil up my time while there. I went accordingly; a most beautiful. and pleasant summer I spent there. The scenery was delightful; and F2  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7377-00000057"/> "2      ROSES AND THORNS the people, just to my Eiking. Everything was free, easy and agreeable. I found enough painting, to make my stay profitable; and attended many sq- cial and agreeable parties; the boat parties were de- lightful; and they were constantly kept up, during the warm weather. They would start with a number of sail boats for some pleasant Island or point; carrying all kinds of nice eatables, fruit, etc. A capable man and woman would be engaged to take the care, and set out the dinner, consisting of a variety of nice fish, cooked in various ways, and other "dittos." While the company were amusing themselves in different ways, some fishing, some walking, others swinging- (swinging was a constant practice with them,) until summoned to dinner, when every one acted their ap- proval, to perfection. After dinner, music, singing and sailing, filled the time until tea. Then we were homeward bound; joyous, in the consciousness that we were having a capital time. Cape A--, especially at the Point, (where I spent the summer,) was a singular place. No one was very rich, and no one very poor; they all   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST,  113 seemed on an equality; and nearly all were Uiversa- lists. (Here I learned to judge favorably of that society.) I often told them, that I never saw such fruit, grow on such trees, before. Kindness, be- nevolence and good will, were the most prominent traits of their lives, and characters. "And what doth the Lord, thy God, require of thee-but to do justly, love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God." Brother and sister Orthodox-never differ about naimes, but love the Saviour's image--never mind the frame. I repeat--I love the Universallsts, so far as they are true ones. w3  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7377-00000058"/> 11      IROSES AND THORNS, CHAPTER XVII. Thus pleasantly six months had passed away al- most imperceptibly and brought about the autumn. I then took my leave for a few weeks, to visit home and friends. I had written often to my mother ; no pleasures could make me forget, or neglect that. I also corresponded with my half-brother, I felt san- guine hopes of him; that he would prove a blessing to his aged parents, and, indeed, to us all. I found my home friends in health, and pretty good spirits. My half-brother was about being married. So that I made arrangements to go home in the spring; and returned to Cape A  , but spent the winter in that part called the '"Harbor." This place differed considerably from the "Point,"' and was agreeable, but in another form. The resi- dents here, seemed to claim more aristocratic gentili- ty, and importance, but less of genuine kindness, and hospitality. They were, generally in easy circum- stances, and many of them, wealthy, leisure people.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  115 As there were few places of amusement in this out of the way place ; my painting-room was a place of general resort; I was liberally patronized, and re- ceived some attentions; but it was generally done with an air that seemed to say, "We do this--as you are a stranger, and, therefore, have a claim on our benevolence."' Here I spent a pleasant and profitable winter.-- Early in the spring, I left for home. A polite leave was taken of me at my departure, by my acquaintan- ces; expressing the most cordial friendship; and an earnest desire for my speedy return--which I partly engaged to do; but circumstances prevented-at the time. On my arrival at home, I found the parents alone, and very desolate. The sons and daughters were all married, and removed to their own homes. It seemed left for me to make arrangements, and provide for the aged pair-they were nearly past their labor, and needed the help of younger hands.  I felt much tried-to leave them alone, was not to be thought of; my capital was very small-as I had sent them near- ly all my spare money; at last, after deep reflection, I decided to set up a home for them in the city, and  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7377-00000059"/> "'6     ROSES AND THORNS: remain with them, and trust in the mercy and provi- dence of God for a support for them, and myself. I hired a nice, first-floor tenement-made such im- provement in their furniture as a city residence would require. The parents now came to reside with me; where they seemed much pleased, and perfectly at home. I provided every comfort for them; and un- aided by any of the family-or any one else. This setting up in the city, took all my money, so that, after getting the parents well settled, and pro- vided for, I set out for Cape A---, as I felt sure of full employment there. Feeling the responsibility I had taken, I tasked all my energies to meet bills, and keep the " wheel turn- ing." On my way, while passing through the city of S--, I was desired to stop and paint the like- nesses of a family, with whom I had become ac- quainted, while at Cape A--.   Preferring the 'bird in the hand," I commenced at once-and spent a most agreeable summer; indeed, I think that was one of the sunny spots of my beshadowed life. I was in receipt of plenty of cash-boarded in a private family, and the most lovely and beautiful family I have ever met with, (I can make no excep- -tions. ) Through this family, for whom I was paint-   9O, RECOLLECZTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  I ing a group picture, I was introduced to the first qual- ity of people in the place; from whom I received much cordial politeness; my exhibition-room was constantly thronged with callers; frequently more than one hundred in a day.  This fatigued and gratified me, both together, for that, together with constant employ, kept my energies from rust. O, I enjoyed life completely, and felt that I was blest. I often heard from home ; " alls well," seemed to be the word; and I could remit as much money as they could possibly need, and save a little for a future time. fs  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7377-00000060"/> "8      ROSES' AND THORNS9 CHAPTER     XVIII, Ill the Fall I returned home, for I could not be ab- sent from the parents in the winter; and it was de- cided that I should remain, and paint at home; not leave the parents any more. if possible to meet my expenses, otherwise. But a change was at hand; my half-brother was living a few miles out of the city--and they often Visited us; about this time, my step-father had ob- tained a small annuity, which he disposed of as he chose, I never knew exactly in what way. Shortly after, he received by a bequest of a wealthy relative-a sum sufficient for their entire support, but I requested them to put it at interest, us- ing only the interest; and remain with me, as they had done, when my hands were their whole support. My half-brother and wife were often there-and somehow, my step-father felt as if he must buy a farm with his money, and live in the country; at this intelligence, my feelings were much hurt; but I de-   OR, RBECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTISt. 119 sired them to act out their own choice--without re- gard to me, or my feelings; I said I would like to know, if they had been neglected, or -treated unkind- ly by me?-if not, why so willing to leave me? They both said that they had received the kind- 'est of care; and had been amply provided for, by me.  But they were led to buy- a farm, and a farm, was bought, and they removed to it, a few miles from the city, leaving me alone with the hired house on my hands; and only the furniture I had recently bought. This was a stunning blow to me, a blow that near- ly broke my heart; I felt that the sting of ingrati- tude is indeed, " sharper than a viper's fang." My mother would have remunerated me, had it been in her power. I had wholly provided for them, about two years and a half; they both said they were satisfied and more than satisfied ; but mother must go to the farm if her husband insisted on it. I felt anxious about their living away from any of their children, as they were so much advanced in years: but that trouble- was soon ended, by being informed that my half- brother and his family, were to live with them. I FS  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7377-00000061"/> 120     ROSES AND THORNS: then felt willing that they should enjoy their remnant of life, in their own way, and quieted myself like a "weaned child." I kept the house, and took a little girl, about twelve years old, one that I had known and loved in her infancy; her parents, now reduced in their circum- stances, rejoiced to let me take her; I reared her as tenderly, and gave her as good an education as I pos- sibly could have done, had she been my own child. I kept her about three years ; and kept house for her sake, that she might have a home with me; but finding the expenses and care of house-keeping, was getting too heavy, I sold my furniture and settled my affairs, for a new start. I went to F- R-, taking my protegee with me.  Here I paid our board and room, at five dol- lars per week. I had tried in vain to make a painter of her; so she continued to study the common branches of education. I introduced her as my adopted daughter, and took care to have her treated as such-and not as my servant. We enjoyed life very well in this place; I had plenty of business, and felt relieved from a heavy weight of pecuniary cares. After remaining here a few months, I went to visit my mother, from whom,   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  121 nothing could wean me; and left my little girl in the city of?  , to visit her family. I found my parents living in a sort of out-house- - a kind of back shop, alone, and my half-brother's family occupying the dwelling-house! I asked my mother the meaning of this ;--she sorrowfully re- plied, that unbeknown to her, the deed of the farm was taken in the name of their son-as he bore his father's name it required only the Jr.," to make it his. I went to the record of deeds in that town, and found it even so. My visit was short and sor- rowful. I left them with a heavy heart;-telling them that they could rely on me, in any time of need, as long as I could earn, or get money in any honest way. Oh! how sorrowful I felt! I would have given my life to make that aged couple comfortable and happy.  My little girl, while at her home, had tak- en a sudden cold, which laid her on a sick bed at her mother's- (troubles seldom come singly.) I went to F- R---- with a heavy heart, and made arrangements for leaving finally; as so small a place, probably, would not ensure me business through the winter. I then returned to P---- , and took a boarding place, near the home of the sick girl; ,'  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7377-00000062"/> 132      tOSES AND THORNS  'until she was convalescent; doing all in my power for her there; and doing my best to provide for her future, I left her with her own relatives, and pro- ceeded alone, an entire stranger, with two introduc- tory letters, to W  , (Mass.) It was now late in the fall-the roads were very rough and muddy, (no cars to W   then,) and to make it worse, about noon, the rain began to fall in torrents; and continued until late in the evening. The darkness of night came on early, every female, one after an- other, had got out of the coach, and still we had some miles yet to go, to reach W   , the bad- ness of the roads had retarded--and many times nearly stopped our progress. At length, about 8 o'clock in the evening, we ar- rived at our destinations The rain was still pour- ing like a flood, when a portly looking man, who seethed by his air of authority, to be the agent, asked me where I was to be left?  This was a question that I could not answer very definitely; but after a moment's hesitation and embarrassment, I starmered "That I was an entire stranger in W    , and as it was impossible to deliver my letters that night-that I must, though reluctant, go to a Hotel." He then asked which one I would   oa, 2RECOLtAECtIONS b0 AN- ARTISi, 23 prefer? I replied, "Sir, I will trust your honor, and beg the favor of you to decide that, as I know none of them." He then named one that he thought the best-I had no alternative but to trust him,-and went; he Was very respectful, and shewed me into a genteel look. ing parlor; set me a chair, and asked if there was anything he could do to serve me. I replied that he would oblige me by sending the " keeper." I felt that the occasion required dignity of cars riage, and assumed as much stateliness as an Indian Queen. The bar-keeper entered, with his politest bow, to receive my orders--which were given with an air that old Queen Elizabeth, herself, could not have bettered. (My word for it.) I desired a good room with a fire, to take supper and sleep in the same--baggage sent up, etc. He promised immediate compliance, with such a deferential air, that I felt my assumed pomposity was not lost, by any means. Directly a girl came to show me to my room. which was neat, and handsomely furnished. She then inquired what I would choose for supper? I replied that whatever was on the public table, would  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7377-00000063"/> 124      ROSES AND THORNS' do.  She soon re-appeared with a large waiter, cons taining a very nice and plentiful supper, and placing it on a table before the fire, asked, in a subdued tone, c; any further commands?" Said I, " nothing more at present-come up in half an hour for the tray, and then we will see, what else." After finishing my really comfortable repast, I had leisure to examine the bed,-which proved to be good, clean, and well aired, three things, which, I believe, are seldom found together at a hotel. I had made the discovery that three doors opened into the room, which I determined to investigate, before retiring for the night. AWhen the girl came for the tray, I asked where those doors led? She informed me. I then desired her to go with me, to the outside of said doors, if the rooms were then vacant of their occupants ; she com- plied, but with some apparent reluctance. I then bade her lock the doors, and hand the keys to me; which she did. I then dismissed her for the night. When alone, I inserted each key on the inside, partly turned, to prevent the possible use of duplicate keys, were any disposed to make the attempt. Then com- mitting myself to the protecting care of my Almighty   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OP AN ARTIST.  12, friend, I sought my pillow, and being very weary, soon forgot my desolate condition in refreshing sleep. I had been asleer--as near as I could judge, about two hours, when I was suddenly awakened, by hear- ing some one trying to open one of the doors. I kept perfectly quiet and still; well knowing that no one could enter, unless they broke in. After trying for some time, they left, and nothing more occurred to alarm me; but I found it impossible to close my eyes again that night. Thus passed my first night in W----, (Mass.) I never was certain, even in my own mind, wheth- er that attempt was accident or design. The house, I was afterwards informed, was one of the most re- spectable public houses in that place. It will serve, at any rate, to show that prudence and caution are excellent things in their place,-and that they were not misplaced on that occasion, at least.  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7377-00000064"/> 126      ROSES AND THORNS: CHAPTER     XIX. Early next morning, I dressed, even to my bonnet and shawl, and stepped down to the parlor, rung for the bar-keeper; he soon appeared, with a polite bow ; I said nothing of being deprived of sleep, but de- sired only a cup of coffee, and the amount of my bill, and my baggage taken care of, until I could send for it; and to be shown to the address of one of my letters. This being complied with, the morning being fair, I made my way thither at once, and was most cordially received. They directly sent for my trunks and baggage, and I remained with them, a boarder, through the winter. I began with their portraits, and had full employ- ment afterwards, and formed some very agreeable acquaintances. Towards spring, 1 got a letter from one of my relatives, informing me that my half-brother had sold his farm, and removed to S   K  , (Conn.,)   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  127 where he was keeping Tavern, and had taken the aged parents to live in his family. This was sad tidings to me; I wept over the letter with more bitter tears, than if it had announced their death. I went immediately to S  K  , to see them -I found the poor old people looking sad and de- jected. They seemed to stand in awe---and to feel under great restraint. Oh! it was like break- ing my heart, to leave them there; but what could I do?  I could do nothing but weep. Oh! the anguish of that parting, I shall never forget ! I re- turned to W    , but my comfort was gone; I toiled at my easel, but was often so blinded by my tears, that I could not go on. Among strangers I could have neither sympathy or advice. I could not reveal the "sources of my grief" to them.- Thus for some months I dragged on a tiresome ex- istence ; yet my " brow wore a smile, and my lip did not complain." I could bear this state of feeling no longer; and set out again to visit the parents; at this visit, I felt convinced that it was my duty, as well as my deter- mination, to better their condition; therefore, trust- ing in God for help, I engaged to support them, if  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7377-00000065"/> 128      ROSES AND THORNS: they would remove their furniture into hired rooms; which they gladly accepted; and my half-brother gave his consent, and promised to do something to- wards their support; which promise he kept for sev- eral months ; but gradually, it devolved, almost whol- ly on me ; but I never felt it a burden, although it involved many personal sacrifices on my part. I prayed fervently that I might live to make them comfortable to the end of their lives-being willing to be poor myself, if I could but supply every com- fort to them. My prayer has been granted-to the letter; they had a comfortable support to the end ; and they lived many years after their removal from their son's residence; and I am poor, yet happy in the consciousness of having done all in my power -and "beyond my power," (as St. Paul expresses it,) for their welfare. After they were comfortably settled in their new quarters, and my mind more at rest than -it had been for many months; I agreed with the worthy people of whom the rooms were hired, and who lived in the same house, to do for them, in sickness or health, all they needed, until I could get to them myself. Reader, do you now comprehend the cause of my being poor? I have never received pecuniary aid   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OP AN ARTIST.  1-29 friom any mortal, since I was sixteen years of age-- unless we call hired or borrowed money, aid, but on the contrary, cruel advantages have often been taken of my defenceless condition, and my pecuniary straits --but let those ewho have done it, beware; the great day of reckoning-and retribution is at hand! I now left W---- , and returned to the city of p-----, hoping now, to locate there, because I could more easily get a line from home, should I be needed suddenly. I took a room for my work, on the principal street, where I did pretty well in my profession, and began again, to enjoy life-a thing I had almost done hoping for. Thus, for a number of years, life passed on smoothly ; the parents had good health, of their age; I was able to visit them often; to supply them with all they needed, for a comfortable support; true, it' was like sustaining life by hanging to a rope with one's hands-but I felt thankful for the strength to cling to the rope at that present, and trust in my Heavenly Father, for the  future. My business was sometimes dull, and my faith often severely tried, but thank the Lord, that blessed promise--"Thou shalt not lack," has never yet failed. At the time of the "R-- H- War," not wish-  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7377-00000066"/> 130      ROSES AND THORNS: ing to remain in the city-I went to Connecticut, and spent about three months with the parents, and paint- ed occasionally for the residents of that place, but at reduced prices ; otherwise they would not have drawn their purse-string in such a cause. On my return to P-   in the fall, I soon found that I could do nothing there, at that time; that is, I could not get enough to defray the expenses, that were rapily accu- mulating. Something must be done-but what- or what course to take, I could not tell; but after many a debate, and conflict in my own mind, I de- cided to provide for the parents, with what money I had; and to draw orders (on several groceries, where I felt sure of cheerful trust, if it was needed,) in fa- vor of my mother, to any amount she would order, on my responsibility.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST. 131 CHAPTER      XX. - then went to Cape A---- Harbor, in hopes of finding it as I had left it; but there had been many changes, in the years that had intervened, since I was there before. However, I was cordially received by those who formerly knew me. My room was soon thronged, as before, and I painted quite a num- ber of portraits; but they had learned to croak of "hard times" even there, and it was not profitable to remain-but what was to be done? I began to feel -quite anxious about home, although we corresponded often, and they seemed by their let- ters to be making out very well; but soon as spring opened I hastened home, and spent about three weeks, made all right, and returned to finish what I had commenced, or rather, what I had engaged. This summer I painted a few portraits, but did not make it at all profitable. I then left Cape A--, as I now supposed-forever; and returned to the city of P----- .  Here I found everything changed  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7377-00000067"/> 132      ROSES AND THORNS: since the " rumor of war,5 and the family with whom I had boarded, had removed to a great distance, and left whatever belonged to me, stored in a room of the house they had vacated. I felt homeless and desolate-and like Noah's dove --" found no rest for the sole of my foot." I saw very little prospect of business, and it began to be suspected that I was poor; this was a signal for for- mer friends, many of whom, had been frequent re- cipients of my hospitality, to grow cool and distant. this change of manner grieved me, for I felt con- scious, that if I ever merited their confidence and esteem, it was then. However, I did not despair, but went on and hired a room and boarding, in the principal street of the city, and put out my sign, and put in my coal, and was anxiously waiting for orders-when our precious landlady took a sudden start to give up the house, and gave us all three days notice; that we must then "be found among the missing." This was a severe disappointment to me. I had no home in the city, and was obliged to store my furniture, etc., while I "wandered forlorn, in search of another place that would do for my business. Winter had now set in and the streets were full of snow and mud; I went,   bR, RECOLLECTIONS O A AN ARftST. 1I33 in this dreadful weather, until I was laid up sick, at a house, where I had formerly boarded, with ague and influenza, but rbceived little attention or sympa- thy; being left in ani upper story, without a fire, to recover at my leisure. When I could go out, I paid my bill, (an exhorbiA tant one,) and went with feeble steps to seek again; at length, after a tiresome search, I found a small tenement--in a good locality, and hired it at a very high rent ; but I had no alternative. It i nly be asked-where my friends Were, at this time? Reader--they were at home, for ought I know to the contrary; I did not seek them-well knowing that it was no tlinie to seek earthly friends, *when you need them. I had my furniture and pictures brought, and kept 'house, using my parlor for a painting-room ; but had, not yet commenced a picture, although it. was the middle of winter. My money was entirely gone- but my credit seemed to be very good; so that I could obtain every thing necessary for myself, and for others, at that present time; but the pay day was advancing, with rapid- strides, for that and for my rent; which I saw no. way to meet; this made me, G  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7377-00000068"/> 134      ROSES AND THORNS: perfectly miserable by day-and haunted my dreams: by night. I had no enjoyment of food or rest; I tried then to have faith, that I should u" not lack', but could not feel faith, I wanted sight. I wanted to see with my natural eyes, the workings of Divine Provi- dence; as we see the working of bees, in a glass hive.  This was earthly and wrong. About this time, a relative, who was in affluent circumstances, called on me, one day, to say that he would employ me to paint two full length pictures, if I would paint them at his price-which was one-half my usual price; said he would not give another cent, if they were not done at all. I was not in a situation to -refuse anly honest way of obtaining money, to meet my payments; so I came to his terms, and painted them, so much to their satisfaction, that they have been heard to say, that five hundred dollars could not begin to buy them.- They paid the sum agreed on, and nob more. True, this was legally just, but, under the circumstances, not scripturally so. But even this scanty sum, re- lieved my embarrassments for that time, so that I did not lack,." From this time I had employment enough, to mee t   'OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  135 -all my expenses, at both places. I visited my parents often, every spare dollar was saved to send them, or to pay my fare, to see them. Thus, nearly a year had passed away, since I had taken these rooms, but with very little of enjoyment to me. One day an old friend called to see me, and find- ing me directly beneath a noisy family, who were very annoying, at the best,-said she had plenty of room at her house--though not central, that I had better come to board with them, and use one of their parlors for my studio. To this proposal, I joyfully agreed; in a short time, I was with them. Here I spent about a year, very pleasantly; but being so far from the centre of the city, would not do for a permanent residence; as I needed full em- ployment, to meet my heavy expenses, which were constantly accumulating. I again removed to a more central part of the city. Here I had plenty of bu- siness, and enjoyed a little respite from  pecuniary straits, and embarrassments.  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7377-00000069"/> 36'      OSES AJb tHbftN; . O f A?TE  I8 X  I'. About this time I was taken dangerously ill with billious cholic, while on the way to visit my mother1 about eighteen miles from my residence, and nine Miles from hers, I was left at the house of a family who had frequently visited me. They Sent by my consent, for two physicians; they pronouiced my case a very dangerous one, and gave little hope of my recovery, Here I was sick about four weeks,and very slightingly and unfeel- ingly treated; although it was a case of life and death. I was nursed principally, by neighbors who came in to see me-not by those who were charging me six dollars per week, for occupying a common- sized bed-room, in a back country town. In my greatest agony of distress, I never forgot to charge my callers not to send the news to my moth- er; fearing that she could not come-and would feel distracted, to stay away from me. But some one sent her word that I was lying at the point of death,   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  137 and not taken proper care of. All the mother was aroused at this intelligence; she wasby my bed, in a few hours-not able wholly to nurse .me, but her presence prevented my being neglected. In a few days I was so far recovered, as to be car- ried to my mother's in blankets and pillows; bol- stered up in a close, covered carriage, and though not out of danger, and unable to walk without as- sistance; and could scarcely speak, being in a state of salivation, yet how completely happy I felt, when I was helped into the house here-(my mother's health being good, at the time)-and with kind neighbors, I had every attention, and. the best of nursing-and was soon restored to perfect health. And when about to return to?  , I was joy- fully surprised, to find my mother in possession of quite a good sum of money, which she had laid by, as she said, for just such a a time; I thought she had used all that I had sent her; and had felt anx- ious on their account; this set my heart completely at rest, on that score. She urged me to take a part of it, but I positively refused, deceiving her, respect- ing the state of my funds, for I had not then, money enough on earth, to pay my doctor's bills, to say  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7377-00000070"/> 138      ROSES AND THORNS: nothing of the heavy bill against me at the house where I was carried, when taken sick. These being the only bills against me, I soont earned more money, and in a few weeks had paid the "uttermost farthing" and was in perfect health and prosperity; but had learned a lesson that I shall long remember, viz.: that in this world, we may find many fair weather friends-but let a storm of trouble arise, and their "time is out" at once. At my new place of residence, I hired a few rooms, and provided my own board; I lived in this, way, for some time, often sad and discouraged-and sometimes, hopeful and glad. I took great pleasure in going to visit my mother; and in writing long letters to her-and very often; and in softening her cares and sorrows, by every means in my power; and I made no difference, but treated the parents both alike, until my step-father's death, which oc- curred in about a year and a half, after my illness just referred to. I had occupied these rooms about two years, when the house changed owners; and new arrangements were to be made. I was again obliged to seek a place to lay my head-this was very trying to me, as I liked the place, and it was a good stand for me;   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST. - 139 'but I could not choose; and so followed my destiny. I then hired a tenement, a few doors above, in the same street. Here I spent some months, but not agreeable, by any means, being constantly annoyed by a gang of noisy, ungoverned children, directly over my head.  The parents of these children made " long prayers," but took little pains to prevent their " young hopefuls" from being perfect nuisances, to their near neighbors. At the end of the term for which I had took the tenement, I refused to engage it again,-but felt per- fectly discouraged of ever finding a place of repose, until the grave should rest my weary head. Just before I left that house, I was summoned to attend the funeral of my step-father, who died rather sud- denly, though at an advanced age. At the time of his death, my half-brother was ab- sent on a journey, with his family. The step-broth- er and sister came and took charge of the funeral.- It was arranged for my mother to reside with me, in the city, after her son returned. I was loth to leave her, in her desolate condition, but felt the necessity of returning to my business; so, leaving her to board with the good people in the house, I hastened to prepare for her reception. sG4  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7377-00000071"/> "O      ROSES AND THORNS: CHAPTER     XXII. I had hired a nice, convenient tenement, a few doors above the last; and my mother soon came to live with me; and I now felt almost happy-true, she had entered her second childhood, and almost en- tirely past her usefulness, but she was my mother still; how I strove to gratify and comfort her, every way in my power; but this was to be of short dura- tion. My half-brother had arranged during his journey, to remove with his family, to the city of H-------, (Conn.,) about 80 miles from us. After the lapse of a few months, he -came to P---- in a private carriage, and alone. He thought it would be a good opportunity for mother to go home with him for a visit, and she seemed much pleased with the idea of seeing her grand-children, (for she loved them, as grand-mothers always do.) So, it was arranged that they should   , RECOLLECTEONS OF AN -ARTIST,   141 take an early start in the morning, and be out one night, on the road. I felt no hesitation in placing her under his care; I knew that when he acted singly, there would be no lack of care and tenderness. The next morning, I had a good, warm breakfast ready, before sunrise; my mother arose, bright and cheerful, said I might put clothes in her trunk for several weeks, but thought she should, probably, re- turn sooner, if her son could come 'with her, which he promised to do, if she wished to come then; but alas! she returned no more! My heart sunk, when they drove from the door, I felt a presentiment that it would be so, but could not urge her to forego the pleasure of seeing her darlings once more; yet something seemed to say, " she will never return." I had got every thing arranged for her comfort; and hoped she would live, and enjoy life, to an extreme old age-but her Father in Heaven had a better home prepared; to which, she was shortly to be removed. After their arrival at H---- , my half-brother wrote, to inform me that mother not only stood the journey well, but seemed to enjoy it, and seemed in- G5 '  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7377-00000072"/> "2      ROSES AND THORNS, vigorated by it; but was so anxious to see -ne, that she said she must soon return. He said that they had been persuading her to stay all winter, thinking my hands were more than full with the whole that I had to do; but she would by- no means consent, unless that I would come and spend the winter too; this, he urged by repeated let-c ters, until I gave a reluctant consent to cotne. I did this purely to gratify my mother ; I engaged to go to H    -, and board in the neighborhood with them, that I could come in, every day, to see mother.- This was apparently, satisfactory. They procured me a boarding place, but insisted on my coming to them for a visit, first; and then decide which place- I would prefer. I felt very reluctant to give up my nice rooms, and store my furniture; but it was not to be thought of, to leave such a rent accumulating, in our absence.- Thus, through life, I have been a creature of circum- stance. I started by the route advised, and arrived in H    at the appointed time. Found it a very pleasant city, and having several introductory letters from?   , soon picked up acquaintances.   'OR, RECOLLECTIONS '0F AN ARTIST. 143 A lady, to whom I came recommended, took a decided interest for me, and shewed many polite at- tentions. She said I must take a central and styl- ish room, if I wished to succeed with the public]; that much depended on first appearances, in that place. She then took me to the most stylish boarding liouse in the place, (so said,) and I arranged with 'them for room and board, at a ruinous price; but she :said-" never mind, it will be best, in the end.1"- (At this place, we had everything pleasant-except dplentiful food.) But it did not all avail- my at- tempts were unsuccessful to obtain employment. This kept my mind so troubled, that I could not enjoy the last hours that I was to spend with my -dear mother, on earth; but did not sadden her, by any disclosures of my ill success. True, I did a little-perhaps enough to pay my board bills; but knew that I could not continue long at that rate.- -This thought, made me very unhappy. It was now, mid winters and too cold for mother to go home, and to go and leave her there, pining for me, I could not bear to think of, but was careful -not to let her know the extent of my troubles, that 'she might enjoy herself if possible. G$  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7377-00000073"/> "4     XaOSES AND THOMS e No weather kept me from seeing her every day' and as time advanced, she seemed more and more, loth to part with me, even to go to my work. She' would often seize my dress, saying, "don't pray: go."  And, thank Heaven; I never once, tore: myself away from her, but would re-seat myself again by her side, until she would say-" there, I am too sel- fish--I ought not to detain you from your work-go,. now, my child." I then would depart with heavy! sorrow, that I was obliged to leave her at alL   O1tj RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARttIS  145 CHAPTER XXII,; At one of my visits, she said to me--" if I thought t could get hlome, I should feel anxious to go--I want to go home."  This was enough for me.-- Said I, " motherj if you wish to go, we will set out tt once. I can wrap you up warm; and we will start as soon as I can get ready-say the first plea- sant day, after the morrow." But my half-brother thought that if w9 must go, that I had better go first, as I should have a new home to makej and as soon as I was ready-to write, and he would bring mother, the first suitable day, af- ter getting my letter. This proposal seemed reasonable; and we both consented to it ; but it was like death for me to leave her behind-even for, apparently so short a time.-- 1 went there the evening but one before I was to start for R-- H-, and told her that I hoped to come, as usual, the next morning, to see her; but as it might storm very hard, she had better say any  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7377-00000074"/> -146      IOSES AND THORNS: ' last words"' that evening-alas! how   little I thought-that I was then hearing that beloved voice for the last time  The next morning came, a violent storm-rains sleet and snow ; and she had said, "Do not come out in a bad storm, I shall so soon be at home,"-- And having a considerable to attend to, I did not go --thinking that the separation would be but for a few days-but felt an indiscribable agony of mind, all day. Towards evening, I wrote the following lines, fresh from my heart, and sent them by her messen- ger, who came to me with the last token of a moth- er's love.* Since I must go, then fare the well; I 'll strive to check the falling tear, That swells at thought of leaving thee- My aged, widow'd mother, dear. Affection's tears, in vain must fall- That form, beloved, no more I see, No longer hear a mother's voice- In tones of tender love, to me. A pair of gloves.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  147 Thou God of mercy-guard and keep- My only friend, from harm, or pain; And though we now in sadness part, Oh! grant, we soon may meet again. This token of my affection, she received that eve- hing, and the next morning before daylight, I was on my way to R - - I  -. I had walked my room that night in perfect ago- ny ; the why I could not exactly tell, at that time, I travelled by stage; as I wished to stop at S K    -, (Conn.) The weather came on piercing cold; we were in danger of being frozen, the weath- er was so severe, before night. I stopped that night, in S      , nearly exhausted with sorrow, fatigue and cold. The cold was so intense, that they would not suffer me to proceed on my way for several days. (I staid at the house where my parents had lived.) At length, I took leave of my kind, hospitable en- tertainers, and arrived in? . It was still ex- tremely cold--" no home received my shiv'ring form;" but I took a temporary boarding place, and commenced the arduous task of seeking a tenement, for the one I had vacated, was let to another occu-  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7377-00000075"/> "8      hOSES AND THORNS! pant, I traversed miles in tho city, to find a pleasant place, for a home for my mother and me; but each night, I returned to my lodgings, fatigued, benumbed with cold, and discouraged. Thus, day after day, I sought in vain for a tenement that was at all desi- rable-and that I could afford to hire. At length, a place presented itself, that I thought must do, and engaged it at once. The rent was high, but it was the only one that I thought would do.  I wrote immediately, for mother to come the first comfortable day; and was soon busy putting things in order, and making preparations to receive her. I had planned a place for her easy chair, at a plea- sant window, very near the fire, and thought how much she would enjoy it--the rooms were very plea- santly situated--and I felt so rejoiced that I had ob- tained them- that nothing seemed wanting but mother's presence, to make me feel quite happy. Soon, a very pleasant morning arose. I said, "they will be here to-night," and was joyfully mak- ing little domestic arrangements-gladdened with buoyant hopes of the future. As it grew late in the day, and I in full anticipation of clasping my   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  149 dear mother in my arms--in a few moments-I re- ceived a Telegraphic notice-to set out immediately for H    , that mother was at the point of death! Oh, Heavens! what a crushing blow! and at such a time! how could I bear it! -It paralyzed me-I sat a long time gazing on the fatal letters-trying to make them spell something else-but in vain.  I was alone in the room, and it was some time before I realized that action was required-I ran out into the street, with the letter crushed in my hand-I then thought I would get a friend to help me off-I went in the first cars, that went, after that--but found no mother! she had gone home! Home, to that bless- sed mansion of rest prepared by her dear Redeemer. But oh! how desolate this world has been to me, since the spirit of my mother departed from it. It is in vain to attempt a description of my feelings, at that time; unless to those who have lost an only pa- rent, under just such circumstances-and they know too well, already. She had died in about two days, from her first symptoms of illness; and had no disease-age ex- cepted. I never could clearly understand the cause of her death; and regret that I could not. There  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7377-00000076"/> 150      ROSES AND THORNS: wras no pallor or rigidness-indeed, no appearance of death upon her; she appeared as if tranquilly sleep- ing, so much so, that I could not help thinking it was possible that she mighl aizake. But ah! she *' slept the sleep that knows no walking." The burial service was performed by an Episco- pal clergyman; for I could not think anything about it; although it was left to my choice-I could not decide, and gave back the choice, to my half- brother.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  151 CHAPTER     XXIV. We saw our mother laid in the tomb, under these blessed, and beautiful words:- "I am the resurrec- tion and the life. He that believeth on me, though he were dead, yet shall he live." It was dreadful to me, to leave those dear remains in- that land of strangers; but, as my half-brother had bought a lot in the Cemetery-and was expect- ing to make a permanent- residence in H--- , he was desirous of having the mother buried there; the request seemed very natural, and reasonable; so that I felt obliged to consent ; especially, as I could not remove her, to such a distance, alone, and unaided. On the evening of her death, when they were ex- pecting my arrival, she asked what hour it was-and being told,-said-- I shall never see my poor child again, in this world!" Alas! she never did! There was some unusual delay, on the road, that day-and I arrived too late!-in dying, she had left a tender message, of love, for me-entreating me not  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7377-00000077"/> 152      ROSES AND THORNS to mourn.  That she was willing to die, and was happy; that if she had one wish to stay, it was for us-not herself, and prayed that we might meet in happiness, nevermore to part--and expired without a struggle, although her illness was severely distress- ing, until within an hour of her death. The world was now a wilderness, indeed, to me.  Not one pleasant ray gladdened my grief-worn heart. I could not bear to remain longer in H--- , and immediately set out on my sorrrowful journey, back to my lonesome rooms; O, how desolate! how changed!  I could do nothing but weep, until I was so depressed, and debilitated, that I felt-unable to sit up, for many days. A few friends came to sym- pathize with me, and to offer consolation-but not mnay. "The friends who in our sunshine live, When Winter comes-are flown." None but the great Physician, could heal a wound like this. Myfirst, last and longest loved, of earth, had gone, gone forever! It was a paralyzing grief, that for a time, quite overwhelmed me. My ener- gies were wholly prostrated-gone. In this state, I lived on, for some weeks-not car-   OR, PtEOLLECtIONS OP AN AhitMt.   its ing for food, unlesss some one came in, and insisted on my taking it; then I did, more to prove my grat- itude for their attentions, than anything else. The heavy rent of nily tenement, was daily accu-' mulating-I could riot give it up--I knew of no way -under the circumstancesj but to remain. And td remain, and not Mrake punctual payments; was not to be thought of.  This, first aroused re to exertions for a sense of probity and honor, were' friends that had not deserted Sime. I comtienced pairting, at once, arid godn fiindc that it had a most salutary effect on nmy mind and health. I began to go out, and fouind the truth of that remark-=". the heart may brerak- and still lived on.9, I strove to overcome my itnavailing sorrow; and to feel reconeiied to my lot ; and be socialtand c heer- ful. But perceived that the attenipt whizd plove' unsuccessful, whi-le keeping htous, aidone, in that- se- eluded way; so I decidf-e  6n taking a journey-- Eastward. At the expiration of skx months, from the time of my bereavement, I gave' tip the tenement, and sold off my furniture, (not intending to keep house  any more,) and got ready fgora start. 1 found that btui-  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7377-00000078"/> 154      ROSES AND THORNS: ness cares, and the excitement of preparing for my journey, had a very favorable effect on my spirits.- I became quite cheerful, and my health seemed to be renovated, from the time I commenced the prepara- tions for my departure.   O1t, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST. 155 CHAPTER XXV. With a heart buoyant with hope, that I should find a change of place favorable, I arrived safely, by cars, in the city of?  , (Me.) I had been absent from that place, for quite a: number of years ; and had neglected-through my domestic cares, to keep up the correspondence, that I had promised to many kind /friends, there, and, consequently, was quite uncertain, respecting what had transpired in that place, for the last three years. But entered the' city, expecting to see everything standing just where I had left it. But I had made a wrong calculation,; entirely. I found few of my former friends-as I expected to find them. Some had finished their journey be- low; and passed the " mortal bounds." Others had removed to a great distance. Some had met with reverses of fortune, and (of course) lost caste in fash- ionable society. While others had risen to afflu- ence, and felt all the better for it. Being placed in  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7377-00000079"/> 136      h6SES ANi' T'Mt6R s a positioi, en'tirely new, thby assumed consequential uirs, not formerly practiced by them, of coursei made a bungling affair of it. But we will leave these to enjoy their top-loftiness and seek the unchanged ones. There were a few remriaining, who exhibited nd change, save the track of time, (who will set hig toot in our very faces-and finally, put So ianhy of his pencil touches, And shadows upon us, that our hearest friends, who have been long absent, could scarcely recognize us.) These, 'app'ared rejoiced to see me; others r6ceived me cordially-still there Was an aching void in my heart.  I felt tnyself, comparatively, a stiranger, where I had expected td feel quite at hioine So true it is, that anticipation, always colors her pictures too high. I too, seemed changed to theiti no doubt; for I went to them, lone, sad, and poor; (not a very favorable passport, in the fashionable world. ) I felt that I inust macke an effort at once, to comA mence painting.  That probably I should feel the same in any and all places; for I had learned that our happiness depends not so much on externals as on the furnishing of the mnner temple,   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  157 I hired a room and board in a small private family; but found little encouragement, in the line of my profession. The winter set in, extremely cold; fuel was sold at an exorbitant price; and it required an immense quantity of it, to make my room at all comfortable. I was paying high rent and board; still waiting and hoping for employment. In the mean time, my money was fast melting a- way; and now, pecuniary trouble took the lead.- My mind was on the rack.  What could I do?- Yet something mutst be done. If I removed to some other place, it might, and probably would, in- crease the difficulty, instead of lessening it. Thus I dragged out a very comfortless winter.- True, I had friends; but did not like to put their friendship to so severe a test, as asking their aid, in any way.         -- One very agreeable family,-who were amply a- ble to do so, invited me, and insisted-on my coming to spend the winter, with them, and as much longer as it would be agreeable to me, as their guest; aMd paint for amusement, until I found something more profitable; saying that I ashould be a thousan4d (. Pro                 JM1t  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7377-00000080"/> 158      ROSES AND THORNS: welcome; that it would give them the highest grati- fication, etc. Though I fully appreciated the kindness and deli- cacy of this invitation, I unhesitatingly-but with many thanks, declined accepting it. My pride, so long dormant, now arose, and said- "Will you compromise your independence, to be the humble friend of any family? and perhaps become a 'guest without welcome, and a servant without pay?'"  (It was PRIDE that made this sensible speech,-not .) Shortly after this, my business increased, and I soon found -my way out; without the assistance of any hand-save His, who feedeth the ravens; and "Tempers the wind, to the shorn lamb.' When Spring opened, I took a journey to L Falls, a lovely spot, some thirty or forty miles from P    , with an idea of spending the Summer months if I liked the place; but soon found, that the beauty of its location, and scenery, constituted its chief attractions. Like many other inland places, the inhabitants were fond of display; without pos- sessing too much liberality, or genuine refinement; but there were some exceptions. (Roses grow among thorns.) I found a few in this place, that   OR, RECOLLECTIOS OF AN ARTIST. 19' I shall ever remember with the sincerest feelings of friendship and esteem. And if five righteous per- sons could save a large city, these few, shall save that beautiful little village from many more dashes of my wayward pen. I spent a few months in this place, but found it neither profitable or agreeable. My morning rambles constituted my highest enjoyment. It was perfect- ly delightful to roam " where art, the proud spoiler, had neler laid a finger ;" and view the sublime moun- tains, rearing their lofty heads in the distance-still arrayed in their night caps, of vapor, (which were vastly becoming,) proudly looking down, with a pat- ronizing air, on the lovely wild flowers-that hum- bly nestled at their feet. And then to view the majestic scenery of the Falls; and feel the cool, soft spray-on a warm Summer's morning, ah! it was delightful-perfectly enchanting! But when I returned to the village, I returned to myself, and my own thoughts ; which had not much, it must be confessed, to make them agreeable. I painted a few pictures for just what I could get; in order to meet my expenses; and I found those who were willing to profit by my necessity of doing so. At length, the last picture was finished; and my   &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7377-00000081"/> 160      ROSES AND THORNS  bills all paid; and I joyfully leaving a place endeared to me by few fond recollections.   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  161 CHAPTER     XXVI- On my return to P---- , (Me.,) I was most cor- dially greeted by my friends, and employed at once; a favorable circumstance for me; for I was nearly destitute of money. -(Not a solitary instance-as the reader knows.) After painting here a few weeks; and enjoying myself more than I had done for many months be- fore; I visited in the country, for a few weeks, and had a most delectable time. I then returned to P---  , (Me.,) and took leave of my kind friends there, and received their parting benedictions. (I was presented with severvl beautifal bouquets of flowers, which still remain pressed, as sacred memen- toes of our sorrowful parting.) At evening I took the boat, for the city of B---. We had a very pleasant time, and a most beautiful evening.  The breeze was fresh, and soft. The full moon, rose in all her brightness, and beauty; smiling sweetly, in the face of the glossy waves be- H  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7377-00000082"/> 162      ROSES ANB THORNS: low, which reflected back her pure Ioveliness, to- gether, with the countless gems which adorned the crystal canopy above. O, it was delightful! and, though a homeless wan- derer, my heart throbbed with extacy, at the glorious sight. Nothing material occurTed on our passage. Ar- rived safely in B---- , spent one day, (seeking and seeing the Lions,) and then proceeded, by cars, to the city of P--  , (R. 1.) The change of scene, and air, had done that for me, which nothing else earthly, could have done. It brought back my health and spirits to their natural tone. I had risen above my troubles, but they were not forgotten. I was, again, afloat on the wide world, without a home, and no friend, that would do to lean on. I knew not where to rest the P' sole of my foot.' I often thought of these lines- "Weary and desolate I roam, Without protector, friend or home, My dearest joys, are from me torn, And oft, an absent God, I mourLn." While waiting for the "moving of the waters," I decided to visit the city of H------, (Conn.,) and   OR, RECOI LECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  163 go to my mother's grave, as she remained -entombed, at the time of my departure Eastward. My half-brother, and family received me cordially. He accompanied me to the sacred spot, which con- tained all that was mortal of our earliest, last, best friend; we tarried some time, and were both deeply affected. I spent a few days with them; and when I returned, he took me to the cars, in his carriage; we were alone, many kind and sorrowful words passed between us-but alas! they were the last words we were ever to exchange on earth; I never saw his- face again! I He removed from  H----  , shortly after, to a great distance ; -where he died, after a sholt illness, (by fever) and left a desolate -family, to mourn their bereavement. I now returned to the city of P-----, ( R. I.) al- most wholly destitute of money (reader, you will be- gin to think that I had better have been more pru- dent, and kept my money, when 1 had it. I answer -that money was made to zUse, not to hoard;: That the best time to do without what we need, is when we cannot get it. Besides, : homeless, friendless being--who has everything' to pay for, has little op- portunitv for economising; and you will find it so,- i14  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7377-00000083"/> 164      ROSES AND THORN6 if ever you are placed in the situation,) and knew not what to do next. In seamans' phrase- I was afloat and out to sea, in open boat, Weary and worn, and tempest toss'd My anchor, sail and ballast-lost. In this folorn situation, I waited for the hand of Divine Providence-(which had never yet failed me) -to direct my steps; as we are promised that He will, if we "commit our ways unto Him."  But my faith had a long probation. I had no permanent residence; could find nothing for a painting room that would do; unless such as were too heavy a rent for me to pay; so, doing now and then, a picture, at my temporary abode, I obtained a scanty pittance'; which kept my board bills straight; and no more. I also tried, tending a picture and frame store, for a few weeks-but soon found this, worse than un- profitable, and not fearing any loss by a change, I quit that; after finding that I was selling my liberty, if not my health, at a very low price; considering the immense value of those two blessings. Liberty and health! who would exchange them for the wealth of worlds? Then let no one, enjoying these two greatest of earthly blessings, say-"I am   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   165 poor," or suffer themselves to repine, that a kind Prov- idence has witheld-that which, probably, would prove a snare to them, if obtained. But personal liberty will not give happiness, if the spirit is in bondage. '( Whom Christ makes free--are free indeed. All else are slaves." The Spring had opened, but no suitable place to locate, had opened to me. There was no person that I could 'reasonably ex- pect to take a very deep interest for me. They all had near relatives and friends, to share their kind- ness and attentions. I stood, -sorrowful and alone. Those beautiful words of Burns, in his "lament," often crossed my mind. "Unheard, unpitied, unrelieved, I bear, alone, my load of care; For silent, low, on beds of dust- Lie all that would my sorrows share." At length an office, in an extensive block, and central, was vacated; this was thought by my ac- quaintances, an eligible situation for my business.- I went to get refusal, but found it so very public, and such a heavy rent, that I declined taking it, as not to be thought of. No pecuniary straits had ever a5  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7377-00000084"/> -166     ROSES AND THORNSd yet induced me to take any situation, however profit- able--involving the least impropriety, always deter- mined to respect myself; and to take no step that prudence and delicacy would not approve. This building, though occupied by very respecta- ble gentleman, had no lady occupants-not one.-- It was mostly used for counting rooms--reading rooms, and artist's rooms. I thought if not censu ra- ble, it would be very unpleasant, and unfeminine, to occupy such a situation and gave up all thoughts of it; but after days spent in search of a suitable place, (I wished, now, to make a permanent business place, and board as near as possible,) but could find noth, ing that would do--on every account; and its being urged, that the place I had recently rejected, was highly respectable, and that there was not the least impropriety in my taking it as a painting room, that though no lady then occupied a room there-that the building was the constant resort of ladies and misses, Finding no present alternative, I took a lease for one year; not being allowed to take it, on any other terms. The next thing to be tho-tght of, was the furnish- ing---it required some sixty yards of carpet, to say nothing of the other necessary fixtures, On this   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.  167 occasion, I found that my credit was still in good re- pair, for I had but little of the needful. - The truth is, whenever I happened to get a dollar that I was not obliged to spend for my payments-or needful expenses-I invariably tucked it i nto that Rank, that pays such high interest; and has never failed; and has promised--"Do this, and ye shall not lack."- Reader, I advise you to deposite yours--a portion of it, at least, in this great, strong, Savings Bank. After getting the room fixed, and furnished, and my advertisements and business cards in full circula- tion-I set down to take breath, and wait for orders. But ah! I had time to take many long breaths- and many longs sighs, also, before any orders came; excepting one picture, for the famnily with whom I was boarding. But here I zoas, end nailed for the year, (if I lived so long.) I felt anxious and trou- bled; for the end of the first quarter was-rapidly ad- vancing, and I had received but a few dollars towards paying my rent, but still hoped in the mercy of God, to help me out-not willing to trespass on the for- bearance of mly landlord--and found before it was needed, that I had not trusted ," in vain." Nor will any one, who first does all--aidd the best in his pow- er, and then trusts God with all his heart.  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7377-00000085"/> 168      ROSES AND THORNS: Persons of whose existence on earth, I was before ignorant, came to me and ordered paintings, paying in advance-invariably required-which helped me out completely. No doubt, the hand of our Heavenly Father was in this. "For a sparrow cannot fall to the ground, without his notice." O, let us forever, adore such a tender, merciful, prayer-hearing God!   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST. 169 J CHAPTER XXVII. In this way, I spent a monotonous season, with lit- tie to vary, or improve my situation. Throughout the long, tedious days of Summer, I was, invariably at my post; in that sombre, pent-up room, where I repaired immediately after breakfast, carrying a dry, cold dinner, and remaining until sunset; and then re- turning to my cheerless boarding place-having my supper dealt out with more parsimonious exactness, than courtesy. But here I was; bound for a given time, with fetters, as strong as poverty and necessity could make then. I had but few callers, and but little employment, but must be on hand, or what little patronage came for me, would pass, too readily elsewhere, that was certain. At my boarding place, I found nothing congenial; the heartless conventionalities of the world, appeared to be their creed; and though they were, esxternally,  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7377-00000086"/> 170      ROSES AND THOBNS: genteel and respectable-it was not even an apology for a heome to me. After sitting in sadness, for twelve long tedious hours, nearly suffocated with the heat of the room, and, perhaps not a person to speak to, during the day, and not business enough to occupy me one-half of my time--I would retrace my way to my uncom- fortable abode; and so homesick, that I invariably walked as slow as possible, so great was my reluc- tance to enter it. But my board being already paid in advance, by a painting-I felt obliged to stay; prefering the lesser evil-to the greater one of con- tracting a bill for board, which I saw little prospect of being able to meet, in a reasonable time. My second quarter's rent bill would soon be at. hand; and though I had not forgotten the Provi- dence that had helped me through my former straits  I could not help feeling very anxious and perplexed. I seemed to think that the Lord would grow weary of helping nme-feeling conscious at the same time, that I had done everything in my power, (except exercising faith in God,) a very important item, to those who have lno other refuge in their time of need, and?who has anly other safe, sure refuge? But I found faith a hard thing to exercise. when   oR, Raco LLCTo1Ns or AN ARTIST.    171 one is entirely out of the article. But I strove to obtain it, by every means in my power--and it uwas given. I now without fear, or doubting--    waited on the Lord," assured that I should not lack. O, let my trembling soul be still, While darkness veils this mortal eye; I wait thy wise-thy holy will- Wrapp'd yet in fears, and mystery; I cannot--Lord, thy purpose see- Yet all is well, since ruled by thee."  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7377-00000087"/> 172      hOSES AND THORNS) CHAPTER     XXVIII. At the end of the second quarter, I had received (in the same manner as before) more than enough money to meet my rent bill, and other expenses.- Reader, trust God, and you need never despair. I had removed to another boarding place; where I was to make cash payments. How I was to make it all out,--together with other weekly expenses- was not then quite visible, to the natural eye,-but faith said "advance, you will succeed." So trust- ing in God--I "trod the narrow path of duty on."- There was little occurred throughoutthe first year; to vary the monotony of my life. It was go and paint, or dispose of my time in some way, through the day, and when the toil or ennui of the day was over, to trudge back to my temporary abode, (for I was not stationery at any one boarding place, longer than it suited my pleasure and convenience. But, as a general thing, changing boarding places, is but a change of troubles. If we get rid of one annoy-   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST. 173 ance, or grievance, we commonly have to encounter something in another form-nearly, or quite as bad. True, there are exceptions-as I have most gladly found,-but this does not invalidate the truth of the remark. We can no more have every kind of comfort and enjoyment, at one, and the same time, than we can have every kind of fruit grow upon one tree. If your tree bears apples or pears,-it will not bear peaches or plums-depend on't. I made out to meet my expenses throughout the year, but thought it discouraging to toil through sum- nmer's heat and winter's cold--facing storrris, and dragling through snow and mud,-and make nothing over paying my expenses, while earning it. It might have been otherwise, if all my employers had been honest enough, after ordering and obtaining, an expensive picture, to pay for it. But some, who made great display of wealth, in the street, and in their houses; and great display of benevolence in society, and, in short, on all public occasions; who did not scruple to keep me (notwith- standing, their knowledge of my pecuniary straits,) out of my payment, for many months, and some- times, years; and in some cases, finally; notwith-  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7377-00000088"/> 174      ROSES AND THORNS: standing the acknowledged excellence of the like- nesses. Now, shall persons be highly respected and ad- mired for their attractive appearance-and their pompous display of benevolence,-who can be guilty of such meanness and unrighteousness? while those who are truly upright, and truly benevolent-who bestow unseen, and are just before they are generous -can scarce obtain common civility, because they do not make a genteel appearance? Let every candid, just, pure-minded person, answer this question. My first year had now come to a close, (as all the years before it, had,) and I saw no other way for me, but to plod on, in the same dull, unvarying rounds, and took a lease for another year. Seldom leaving my stand, except on business. Pleasure could not tempt me to leave, for a day, so determined was I to succeed, through my own exertions,-made available by the helping hand of Divine Providence. My business had now begun to increase, and I began to fee hopeful and cheerful; though forced to practice thel most rigid economy, and to make very close calculations in my personal expenses. But board and rent, I found stubborn things to economise in; although some of my boarding-house landladies,   OR, RECOLLECTIONS -OF AN ARTIST.  t75 had both the theory and practice of economy, to perfection. I enjoyed but little comfort at some of these places, -I found few who took an interest in my welfare, -and felt myself an isolated, homeless, friendless being; whom no one loved, or cared for. O, how many desolate, sad hours, I passed in the solitude of my room that year! I could not enjoy the gossip and tattle of the day. I sighed for congeniality and social converse, which would both instruct and please. Not that I assumed an eminence above my daily companions, far from it, it was the reverse, generally; but often felt the truth of the following : "That is not home, where day, by day, I wear the busy hours away; That is not home:, where lonely night Prepares me for the toils of light, 'Tis hope, and joy and mem'ry give- A home, in which, the heart can live." I had always endeavored to preserve as much of the freshness of the heart as possible. I never could bear the idea of my heart's becoming old my per- son was fast fading-or rather, getting "worse and worse," and I tried to submit to it with Christian  &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7377-00000089"/> 176      ROSES AND THORNS: fortitude; but to have my heart become sere and apathetic! I constantly strove to prevent it, by every means in my power. And yet, there seemed to be little prospect of keeping up the life and growth, or even the vegetation of a plant, uprooted, and torn from a genial soil, by rough and careless hands, and cast on the cold way-side to be trampled on, by eve- ry scornful or heedless foot. 1   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST. 1" CHAPTER XXIX. I have passed through many changing scenes, as the reader is, by this time, aware, and have had an opportunity of studying human nature in its every lay dress ; having had access " behind the curtain  of almost every grade of life, and studied character as it appeared and as it was. And though not in- tending to makepersonal remarks,-may I not be allowed to give general description, with the same impunity, as I should say " the Whole world is lying in wickedness P"And no one would think of being offended at that, supposing it had no reference to them, whatever. There is one thing that I cannot pass over in silence : The respect and sympathy due to old age, is almost wholly disregarded. We see this exem- plified in every day life. When the aged poor,who have lived a life of-toil and privation, in order to rear their children in comfort and respectability; until their grey hairs are bowed with sorrow and care, to the  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7377-00000090"/> 178      ROSES AND THORNS: verge of the grave,--should they not be allowed to enjoy an evening of rest, after the burthen of life's tedious day? But no, we more frequently see them the meek drudges and dependent slaves of their children and grand-children, as long as they can trudge one step, or move a limb. Alas! none can write the history of extreme old age.  The aged, themselves,--with their dim eye- sight,-palsied hands, and failing memory, cannot do it. And the young, could form no adequate idea of the sadness and helplessness of decrepid old age.  Only those, to whom age has sent its card, can begin to have any just conceptions of its miseries. And if these persons are childless, and have out-lived their friends-and are destitute, (no matter how re- spectable and useful they have been through life,) they are crammed-indiscriminately-among  the lowest, most abandoned characters, into the alms houses!  Heaven help them! The picture is too revolting; I cannot proceed! And yet, if one could feel a firm faith that they were soon to be admitted to perfect rest and happiness in Heaven, it would not seem so very important--   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST..   179 whether it was an alms-house, or a palace, they quitted;- ("Nor think those beings blest, alone, Vihose days--a peaceful tenor keep- The God who loves our race--has shown A blessing on the eyes that weep." We will now reverse the picture.   The young must be gratified in their various fancies and pur- suits, however hard it may come on their parents.- The darlings mutst have this, and amust have that ; the poor, doating parents are willing to make any sacrifice-their lives, almost, to procure the desired boon, be it what it may. See the daughters of a fashionable, but poor family -while their parents are toiling like slaves, to sup- port them in gentility and idleness,--the mother drudging in the kitchen,--  perhaps washing and ironing the white dresses of her lacdy daughters, for the next party, while they, with long ringlets, and white, soft hands, bedecked with rings, sit, gracefully touching the keys of a piano, or listlessly turning over the pages of the latest novel--while reclining on a sofa. What if there are holes in their stockings? their mother can darn them, as soon as she "'gets the work  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7377-00000091"/> ROSES AND THORNS: done up," and they have left them off, to dress for evening. And thus, a perpetual strife, between show and poverty is kept up.  These fair damsels, cannot think of associating with the " coarse, vulgar girls, who are obliged to work ! not they !" or to come in contact with their spread, rough hands-made so by supporting themselves, instead of being a burthen on their hard-working, care-tired parents.  Now, which of these characters, of young ladies, shall have your favor and applause ?  Many a beau would answer, "0, the parlor ladies, to be sure-I could never en- dure a dowdy."  But does it follow, that she must be a dowdy, because she works ?  No, very far from it.  Industrious labor, and high mental endowments, are perfectly consistent with each other, and often combine in the same individual.  Idleness, is no mark of a genuine lady or gentleman, nor is the hand an index, either of the head or of the heart. But excuse me, reader,-mry headstrong pen had caught the " bitts " and had, well nigh, run into ex- tremes with me.  But if it does not overleap the bounds of truth, I have nothing to regret-unless I have displeased you, "darlint," if so, I do, indeed, repent.   CHAPTER XXY. But I have digressed some distance from my path.   (Let's see  where was I?)  My business was still increasing, and though my rent bill would persist in coming at the end of every quarter, I had become able to meet it,, (as David met Goliah,) and continued on my desolate track, always trudging backward and forward, to and from my studio, and, generally alone, which frequently brought the fol- lowing beautiful lines, to my memory :- " Ie is with thee, whose favor is better than life, Could a human heart, guard tlee, so well ? Then cease the vain wish--hush thy bosom's wild strife, And forbid, but a thought to rebel."' Old Time had passed his annual rounds, and brought about another year.  I had lived below my privileges.  There had been little to arouse my dormant energies, or to encourage and gladden my heart.  True, sometimes my efforts were crowned , &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7377-00000092"/> -182      ROSES AND TlHORNS  with success, and then would follow the long covet- ed meed of approval and unqualified praise ; but more frequently, some affected, self-sufficient person, who, perhaps, had never seen a dozen goodpaintings in their whole lives,-would come in, and with one sweep of their useful, gifted tongues, hurl my air castles to the ground, and my painting talents "into pi," (as the printers say,) with the same feelings that a cow would tread on a pearl necklace.' How any one can be so void of common benevolence, (to say nothing of good breeding,) as to go in where a sort of prisoner, with ke-.r Y pi'rceptions and sensitive feel- ings, has been bending in one position for whole hours, toiling, and stretching every nerve of thought -throwing his life, almost, into the scale--zand make coarse, and unfeeling remarks, to throw a damper on his efforts, and sink his spirits, for the remainder of the day--I cannot comprehend. At the close of the second year, I had about deci- ded not to take another lease, being heartily tired of confinement, and the dull routine of my life. But after nicely weighing and balancing the matter in my own mind, and consulting others, I concluded to re- main, and took a third lease, as I was better estab- ished there, then I could' e elsewhere, for a long   'OR, RECOLLECTTONS OF AN ARTlST.  183 time.  Annoyances ill be found in all places, on earth, there were some, even here; buat a change might not have bettered my condition, all things con- sidered. In reviewing my study -of human life, the follow- ing presents itself-to my mind: "Honor to whom honor is due."  But it must be confessed, that in the present state of society, this injunction of sacred writ, is rot strictly regarded. Is honor due to the untried and unformned character? Or, to those who have only a genteel appearance, and showy accome- plishments, to recommend them?  Or, to persons who have abundant wealth, but hoard it with ;a mi- ser's care, beStowing nothing in charity or hospitality, but have defrauded and oppressed the poor :? Or, to the unrighteous of any grade .? 'urely not, and yet such take the "uppermost seals" in the present day; and the poor-no matter how  well bred, sensible, refined or just,--must sit under the  "foot-stool."- If poverty has set its seal on their dress, they are not Countenanced in fashionable society, or even by the professed followers ofthe Lamb!"  How absurd! And even the churches, built expressly for humility and the worship of God, are scarcely accessible to a shabby coat, an old bonnet, or clumsy, worn-out shoes!        A,  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7377-00000093"/> 184      ROSES AND THORNS: Many a poor person, with sensitive feelings, spend their Sabbaths at home, because they have not the requisite apparel. It might do to appear before Om- nipotence in; but they dare not appear before his worms, unless they are " full-rigged" at all points; not willing to encounter the withering stare, that probably would be leveled at them, by the scornful ; and determine to stay away. Hoping these few hints will serve, instead of a whole sermon, I close the subject. I commenced my third year with good prospects, but being rather crowded with business, I tasked myself too hard, through the long days of summer, which greatly impaired my health for a time, but with good care, and Heaven's blessing on it, I was soon restored to perfect health. In taking another retrospective view of life and its affairs, another text presents itself to my mind :- "The merciful shall obtain mercy"--("if we must err let it be on the side of mercy.") In my wanderings through this " vale of tears," my heart has often been severely pained at the treatment of children, who were bound servants, and had no earthly protectors, but a stern, cruel master and mistress. Such chil- dren. are severely beaten for the most trifling offence.   OR, RECOLLECT1ONS OF AN ARTIST.  18 or accident, and even without any cause. They are made to drudge continually, without the least re- cess or enjoyment. Their food, is, generally, the scrapings of the plates after the family meal is over, and are allowed scarcely time to put that morsel into their hungry mouths. And should hunger tempt them to eat a piece of something, not formally deliv.. ered to them, they are beaten within an inch of their lives! Their clothing (if clothing it can be called) is a mass of filthy rags, put round their skeleton forms.  Their feet and hands, generally, liaked in winter as in summer. Their lodging may be afew tattered spreads on the garret floor; or, perhaps, the cotton from out an old comforter, in the corner of a small, dark closet. The children of the family, are so many extra tyrants, who are allowed to tease, beat and kick the poor trembling, unresisting child, who dares not say that its soul is its own, but sinks meek- ly beneath their abuse, until its senses and energies are completely benumbed, and then the poor child is represented as odd, dull and foolish, to persons who visit the house, but do not see-"behind the curtaii." This description, is not drawn from fiction, as the reader may imagine, but from facts within my own knowledge.  How often have I shed the silent tear, t3  &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7377-00000094"/> 186.      ROSES AND THORNS : and raised the, silent prayer for these poor, defenceless beings, when .my personal interference might be- in- judicious,. and not benefit the poor little wretches,. but rather increase the rigor and hardship of their lives. It was not moral fear, (for that is a stranger to me,) but expediency, that kept me within bounds. But a spirit within me would Veak to their guilty souls, and the cruel tyrants would quail beneath it. But let such beware! for the day of retribution is at, hand!  The All-seeing eye, above, never sleeps,. and has been a witness af the whole.  Remember that! It is to be hoped there are many exceptions to the, foregoing description, and, no doubt, there are; but there are, also, many parallel cases, to my knowledge among what are termed " highly respectable" people. But stay! What finger is that pointing to me- through the vista of ages on ages, and centuries on centuries? It is the finger of Nathan, the Prophet t speaking emphatically to my conscience the truth he uttered verbally and boldly in the ears of that royali sinner.--(Reader, if you do not recollect who, just turn to it, in the bible.) And though not guilty. of crime, I now feel very sorrowful on recollecting a sin, committed, it is true,   OR, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN ARTIST.   187 in early childhood; but, nevertheless, it was sin- for I now have a perfect recollection of the struggle got up, in my heart, between pride and my better knowledge and feelings.  But pride prevailed. I do not recollect a similar case in my whole life; where I trampled (with eyes open,) on the feelings of a poor, friendless orphan child! but I did it to not lose caste in my own little circle, (I do not bring this as a plea in my favor, -no, there is no plea for such cruelty and baseness as I was then guilty of,) but though repented of, and, I trust, forgiven, the scar remains. The subject of this reference was a poor, friendless orphan-she was taken as a servant, by a family that dwelt near us, but the term, slave, would have been far more appropriate. My mother was filled with sympathy and compassion for this miserable child- she was about my own age and size, and when enough of my clothing could be spared to make her a complete suit, (she had a bonnet, old, but still, de- cent,) my mother obtained permission for her to go to meeting-the child was perfectly delighted. There was to be a week-day meeting at a nigh dwelling house.  My mother thought if she could get a grant for the poor girl-to go to that, it would be l4  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7377-00000095"/> 188      ROSES AND THORNS: capital, it would rest her ONE afternoon at least.- She had to promise the mercenary old couple (they had no children at home,) to not let her run, and "tear her dress," and to let her go with us. (She little thought the affair would end so disgracefully to her own petted child.) It did nicely, until within a few rods of the house, my mother and others of the family being a little in the rear, but as we approached the house, 'somehow' I began to feel ashamed of my companion as soon as "somebody better " approached. (Now, was not this worldly wisdom?) I manifested this amiable feeling, by giving short answers to her questions, which I had answered so kindly before. Poor Ra- chael! she looked surprised, as well she might. My mother being still some distance in the rear, did not observe the covert airs of her little saint! going so demurely to meeting. We were all arrived and seated, and the seats all filled; but Rachael- poor child-was standing; my mother observing this, motioned me to give up my seat to her; this I did cheerfully and willingly, because it would not disgrace me as it would to be seen walking with her or speaking to her. A seat was soon found for me, also.   DOR, RECOLLECTIONS  OF AN ARTIST. I 9 I must now leave the meeting, progressing in the usual form, (I heard but little of it, for I. was piously laying plans to evade Rachael when -the meeting closed,) and give a description of the -services, " not spiritual but temporal."7 It was customary on these occasions, for all the "leading members" and their families to be invited to "stay to supper, with which invitation, all tar- ried; and such suppers! very unlike what is now "staying to tea." They would urge and urge their guests to eat more--and when eating had entirely destroyed their appetites, the hospitable entertainers would almost feel hurt, and seem to think they "ought to eat more-it had scarcely paid them -for setting it on the table." When the parents and grown people had evacua- ted the still plentiful board, and passed into the "best room," then we children were ushered in--where we s generally stood, atd were helped, and " coaxed "  to eat, and not to be "' bashful." To this order we were generally, very obedient and docile. I saw Rachael at the far end of the table, for moth- er bade her stay until she went herself. I ' was glad - to see her have a nice, plentiful supper, as it was well known, that she seldom luxuriated in that way, andl 13  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7377-00000096"/> 190      ROSES AND THORNS; if I could prevent her from speaking to me, or expos- ing, in any way, that she was an acquaintance, "my character might still be saved." But nay, the mo- ment we were on the play-ground, Rachael followed me like my shadow-addressing me every instant-- at length it became unbearable-I could stand it no longer,-I cried "go home! we will not have you in the play," declaring that "I would not play, if she did ; "Nor I," nor I," "nor I,"  was echoed "throughout the camp." How I now despise my- self for it, and did then, when she looked on me with, that surprised, reproving, sorrowful look. One word from me would have made her a favor- ite-my feelings were softening with tender pity,. but pride was door-keeper at my heart; and when she went off weeping and alone, to the house, no one followed that desolate orphan! Oh, pride, thoufa- tal destroyer! That evening, I anticipated a deserved reprimand, but my mother, though serious, treated me very kind- ly. I would have given much to have her chide me,. I could have borne it better, than her ill-deserved kindness. She took the course she knew to be the' right one with me--she led me to deeper repentance by it. The next morning, I confessed votimntarily ;   OPt BRECOLLECTtONS OF AN ARTIST.,  19 she then, in the tenderest manner, pointed out the sin and wickedness of my misconduct, desired me, after praying for forgiveness of God, to ask it of the injured orphan, which I did, humbly and cheerfully.  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7377-00000097"/> 192      nOSES AND THOURS ' CHAPTER XXXI. Again.. "The merciful man is merciful to the! beast.' Cruelty to animals, and dumb creatures generally, is so prevalent a sin, that it is scarcely noticed, by some, otherwise, worthy persons; but it is extremely grievous to persons of genuine feelings. How often we see a poor horse most unmercifully and unjustly beaten, because he cannot start a heavy load, which is beyond his strength! How frequent- ly we see a poor dog beaten and kicked, in. a cruel manner, when the creature has done nothing to e-. serve it, only to gratify the malignant temper of hi&amp; tyrannical booby of a master. We see many auii- mals, kept and nearly famished! and by people who are able to feed their own hungry, at least. How any person of any kind feelings, to say nothing of piety, can hear their animals crying with hunger, or thirst, and not relieve them, is past my comprehen- sion, entirely. Parents, if you would train up your sons for a   Olt, RECOLLECTIONS OF AN Ar'lST.  193 prison, and, perhaps, the gallows; and your daugh- ters for a miserable end, let them begin their career, by practising cruelty to animals, in their childhood. I still plodded on, but it had ceased to be a dull and tiresome rounds. I am now having plenty of business, and many pleasant callers and acquaintances, and feel that my efforts have been crowned with success- -but Itis all from the Lord. Blessed be his name,-forever. But then to stand alone, unaided and unconnected in a world like this, is, at times, very desolate, yet our desolation or verdure-our buoyancy or depress- ion-depend much on the cultivation and keeping of that little garden of ours--the heart. No matter how situated in life-whether alone or connected,- whether in wealth or poverty-that garden is our home. it remains for us to have it cheerful and well furnished ;-cheerful by our culture-and furnished by our care,-or the reverse. In this garden, each one must "reap as they have sown;" but the culture must begin early in Life's Spring, to enjoy a rich harvest. "He that goeth forth weeping--bearing precious seed-shall, doubtless, return, rejoicing, bearing his sheeves with him." I am now gliding swiftly down the stream  of 6a  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7377-00000098"/> 194      ROSES AND THORNS Time, which will, ere long convey me to the vast ocean of eternity. "Eternity! thou pleasing, dread- ful thought!" Then, and not before, I hope to find peaceful repose. "Poor wanderer--thy rest Is the rest of the Grave." I build not to this world, and feel but little inter- est in its affairs, more than a traveler does in the inn, where he spends the night, preparatory to reaching his journey's end. But, oh! I hope to rest my weary heart where sorrow never comes, and joys are never ending; and there I hope to meet the loved and lost of earth, (" not lost, blest thought, but gone before.") And there, I hope to find perfect truth; pure, unchanging love; boundless confidence and un. alloyed happiness; with " eternal" inscribed on all. In hope of such blessedness, let us seek the honor "that cometh from God, only."  The God of this world- (Ambition's honor, wealth and pleasure, These sordid THREE in one combined,- The world's Trinity and treasure,- God, of every fallen mind, ) Confers a sort of honor; but will it last? Can you   OR, RECOLLECTIONS: OF' AN ARTIST. 195 take any of it with you, beyond this life? Will it buylife? love? health? happiness? or trute friend- ship?  If not, let us seek it no farther; but " seek for glory, honor, immortality and eternal life." Dear reader.-We have travelled together through the pages of this little volume; if you have found. anything to approve, or that has interested you at all,. I am richly paid for the trip. And, although I must stand justly branded, an egotist of the "first water," O, spare my little book, if it has failed to please you. at all. Bid the archers from your mental armory not to raise a bow against this poor " speckled bird," lone and wild from the forest. Your forbearance is its only refuge. Oh, then, let your motto be mercy, and may it, also, be your reward. We have now arrived at Jan. 1st, 1854-11 o'cl'k P. M., I must close, by wishing you a good night, and A HAPPY NEW YEAR.  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7377-00000099"/>   THE WIDOW'S SON.        197 APPENDIX. THE  WIDOW'S SON. 7TH CHAP. ST. LUKE. In Nain's fair city, the last sad knell had toll'd For one, who lay in the resistless arms of death; The only darling of his widowed mother. The mound of earth, was now to hide-forever, From her fondest gaze-- Her heart's loved treasure, and her earthly hope. With feeble, trembling steps, And grief-too deep for utterance-she slowly moves; By numerous, weeping friends, and relations, attended- When, lo,-they meet a little band;- But ONE, alone, arrests their gaze; And they stand-transfixed, and struck with awe, At all this glorious majesty and beauty Beaming-as when the sun unbars the golden East, And pours a living flood of rosy light on all around, Moved with compassion, for this anguished mother- Saying: "Weep not," he "TOUxHED THE BIER; R  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7377-00000100"/> 198        THE WIDOW'S SON. What virtue in that touch! The cistern wheel begins to move! This Heavenly stranger, then, in sweetest accents, cries "YOUNG MAN, ARISE!" What power in that command! Death, trembling, Unloosed his potent grasp! The young man's pulses beat- Behold, he lives! Has risen up!! All stand aghast,-and petrified with fear, The trembling parent stands, with lab'ring soul,- She strives to speak,-the fainting accents die upon her tongue. Amazement, awe, and most exthtic joy, combined,- Prevent her utterance. Silence was broken first, by him who wore new life, When all, with glowing hearts, beheld So visibly, God's mighty power-they prostrate fell- And weeping-they adored. This blessed Being then passed on- Intent on works of love and mercy. Think'st thou, they e're forgot that man? Or rcmember'd with indifference this deed? And, now, dost thou desire to see him? Thou shalt. For He will meet the gaze of every eye! Not the poor, wayfaring man., as snow; :But in a blaze of daz'ling splendor, heralded by trumpet's loudest blast-   OUR SAVIOUR'S BLRTH.       199 And by the glorious retinue of Heavea attended- He will burst on all sight- THE ADORED SON OF GOD! S. PAINE. OUR SAVIOUR'S BIRTH. Hail, mortals! Hark! bright Seraphs are singing, Notes of joy swell the strain-all heaven is ringing! With love bursts its bonds, and God's angel appears! So refulgent in light, That the Shepherds at night, In amazement stand trembling, transfixed by their fears. "Fear not, sons of earth, my message is love- "Glad tidings I bring you, of peace from above; "A herald of joy, I come in God's name, "On this auspicious morn, "A blest Saviour is borrin- "Free grace and salvation, on earth, to proclaim. i' Be not unbelieving-I give you a sign-- "' By it ye shall know him--go bow at his shrine-  &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7377-00000101"/> 200        THE BURNING LAIMP. "Where yon beaming star, shines brilliantly o'er him, "You'll find the blest stranger, "Your Lord, in a manger! '"Hearts glowing with rapture are bending before him." The hope of all nations, the light of all eyes- By whom all souls live, and the dead shall arise; Yet the world that he made no room could afford! See! his shelter a shed! And coarse hay his bed- Thus lay earth's Creator, Redeemer and Lord! Mem'rable Bethlehem! blest honorable spot, Where sages, rejoicing, have found the long sought; Thev fall down adoring and praising God-then Bright myriads descending, On radiant wings bending- Touch heaven's highest notes, shouting glory! amen! S. PAINE. THE BURNING LAMP. My good old friend, for such thou art: And what is better still--a winter friend; Summer friends, I've had a score- Charming as butterflies, and of as little worth; But thou, in winter lendest more thine aid.   THE BURNING LAMP.        201 And it was thou, that charm'd my earliest gaze, The first pure smile that play'd upon my infant brow Was joy at sight of thee. And all along, through childhood's happy day,- When in the dark, alone, my fertile brain, Had conjur'd up a host of dreadful forms,- Such forms, as nat'ral eyes don't often get a peep at  Thy presence would dispel them in a breath- Not swifter were the rebel angels hurl'd. Through youth's short reign-sure as the night, Whether with needle, pencil, pen or book, Thou wast at once, my servant and my guide, In after life, when illness shut me up, A pris'ner in my room, and sleep forsook me; And pain or sorrow, strew'd with thorns, my pillow; When weary friends, had drown'd their cares in sleep; On duty thou didst stand, by my bed-side; Throughoutthe tedious night, a faithful watcher: And now, at this lone midnight hour, Thy beams fall brightly on this brow of care. Thy source more ancient than the date of man, And both, from the same elements compos'd; The mighty Being, whose all potent breath, Infus'd into thy counterpart a living soul- (And man in life and beauty rose, wearing a crown No monarch since has worn ;) Before had s:id. ".Let there he l'ght"  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7377-00000102"/> 202        THE BURNING LAMP, Quicker than thought, the darkness fled! Countless, commingling rays, flew swiftly Through the vast infinitude of space; Each particle, ill one concentrate blaze, Lights Nature's lamp-which in rich splendor, Day and night, shall burn unquench'd, 'Till weary Time shall drop his scythe. One spark, emitted from this radiant orb, Has made thee what thou art; As useful in thy sphere, more perfect in thy kind, Than the frail beings, thou wast form'd to serve,-- The wretched slave, is doom'd to sweat and toil for thee, Weary and faint, beneath a scorching sun, Writhing with pain, inflicted by the lash / Almighty God, rise in thy might! O, come to their relief-hast thou not heard their cry? The anguished cry of the oppressed Hath never reach'd thine ear, in vain.- Hither, my lamp, straying in sorrow's path- Sometimes, thou'rt prest to serve the legal knave, Who, like the prowling wolf, seeks out his prey ;- His easy victims-the defenceless poor; At night, sits down and counts his gains; Then wants thy light, to read the bible by; Feeling like no small saint; thinks he has Made the balance fair; then sleeps secure; Yet thou hast been in better company.   THE BURNING LAMP.         203 Wo, through a long succession, trace thee back, To where thou first appear'd, design'd by Heaven- In the pure ark of God ; where thou By His all-wise command, did burn; Fed- from the tree, whose far-famed leaf was sent, Borne by the gentle dove, unto the floating ark; A sign from God. We meet thee next, before the 3Iidian camp; Where thou conspicuous shone, (when once The pitcher'd mask was thrown aside)- Aiding thy general, held in his left hand, He, for his valor iamn'd, thou for thine use;- Both, in degree, immortalized their names. In wisdom's courts, built for the Lord; Where dazzling gems, in rich profusion blaze, We find thee there, flashinig hin gold- A brilliantJ, welcome guest. In later times, our modern churches, Do make thee quite their boast ; and oft mistaken, Fondly gaze, and think lthee their best light. And we may trace thee farther still; Thrbugh every street; in every house ; Flrom the proud mansion, to the lowly shed. Again ; thou stand'st a trusty watchman, Upon each dangerous coast; like truth's pure light, Of life's dark, troubled sea ; extending far Thyl welcome rays, to the wrecked mariner;  &#xD;<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC7377-00000103"/> 204       THE BURNING LAMP. In night's dark fog ; his reck'ning lost; he, worn with care, Faint and exhausted-hails thee with delight. My lamp: thou semblance of frail man,- Hurl'd prostrate into darkness, by a stroke,- As thine electric spark, when quench'd in thee, Returns to its own source,--so doth The mortal spirit's intellectual fire; Extinguish'd here, by the fierce blast of death. Thou representative of truth, that priceless gem ; Detecting all diguise. Emblem of grace divine; Which shall sustain the hungry soul it feeds- In Heaven's refulgent, pure, eternal light, The wise, will seek this oil, whatev'er the price; Will strive to obtain it, tho' all else be lost; But those who dare neglect th' important purchase; And think to borrow in the hour of need,- Will find, too late, that none can spare. Now, my old friend, we part awhile,- Like fleeting life, thou'rt spending fast, As grace, blaze pure ; shine clear as truth  And thou wilt ever find a ready welcome-- My valued, honor'd, burning lamp. S. PAINE.      &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
