<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7797">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Joining the Grangers, or, Trying to be a Patron of Husbandry </title>
            <author>Bricktop.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7797</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2246</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Joining the Grangers, or, Trying to be a patron of husbandry</title>
                  <author>Bricktop.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Collin &amp; Small</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1873">1873</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-04-06">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Joining the Grangers, or, Trying to be a patron of husbandry</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (Cover) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000001"/>THE  ILLUSTRATED BY THO'S. WORTH.  PUBLISHED BY 2SX  COLLIN &amp; SMALL, NRE "3 FULTON ST. NEW YORK. l   &#xD;<pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000002"/>  JOINING THE GRANGERS' OB, TRYING TO BE A PATEON OF H"UTONDRY.   PUBLISfiU BY 4 COLLIN &amp; SMALL, 113 FOLTON STREET, NEW POIEKZ.   &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7797-00000003"/>  ENTERED according to Act ot Congress, in the year 1873, by COLLIN &amp; SMALL, In the office of the Librarian Of Congres at Washington.    this o'er true tale. Mr. Sassafras Dodger Lived in St. Louis. Mr. Sassafras Dodger was a professional politician, a man who yearned to serve his country in some fat official capacity. He had been a Democrat and- then a Republican. Both parties had trusted hi, -but being found wanting by both, he had been kicked out, and w as, now on his oars; Not long since he became convinced that the Granger move- Imen was bound to supplant both of the GERisting arties, and be a giant power in the land, and so he resolved to become a Patron o f Husbandry . just follow the initiatory fortunes of the hero Once he had been fooled thinking thas he had found a clue to them. It was a letter-box of the Young Men's Christian Association, put up in one of the leading hoels in St. Louis, to receive dras Dodp-letters of application for membership. ane pu in an urgent wish to join the Grangers, and those good offcioung men had many a hearty laugh over id, and failed to keep the joke toRepublican. the   hadselve been Bu tha failure id no discourae him o  &#xD;<pb n="4-5 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000004"/> 4         JOINING THE GBAGERS,   -  The noblest motives actuated Mr. Sassafras Dodger in this, for he yearned to serve his country-he was a journeyman pat. riot, anxious for a job. For a week he read everything he could find that threw any light upon the subject. At the end of that time he simply knew that they were Patrons of Husbandry; but where were their organizations? At length he concluded that they were to be found among the farmers -of the surrounding country and the mellow West, and he resolved to seek them out without loss of time, and iden. tify himself with the general movement, satisfied that his talents and his patriotism would win for him the honors he sought. Our artist has presented a portrait of- Sassafras Dodger, and a good one it is, too, so the reader can get a pretty fair idea of the man. It now remains for me to give a history of the hardships and comicalities attending his search after avehicle for political power. Bidding his fartmily good-bye without informing them defi- nitely where he was going, or when he intended to return, he started for the agricultural districts in search of the Grangers. He rode for nearly a whole day, and stopped at night at a little town on the road to Jefferson-City. His first search was for a hotel, but the only one the place could boast of was a lit- tle tumble-down tavern that furnished beasts poor provender and man poor liquor.  But Mr. Dodger was accustomed to that, having drank in the slums of St. Louis for political effect, and being on the-same business now he entered the place without any fear or trem- bling worth mentioning.  It was already dark, and a crowd of village blummners were gathered there to learn the news and take chances for getting drinks. The advent of a well-dressed stranger attracted all eyes, of course, and Dodger saw at a glance that he had- chance then to become suddenly popular. '    i         JOING THEE GR7O BANGRSS.      5 VVIN, I\'\\a\ .p s  MBm SASSAFRAS DODGER, THE CANDIDATE FOR THE FOLLOWING HONORS.  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7797-00000005"/> 6         tJOINING THE GFRANGERS. ,Af MR, DODGER MAKESA C-RIOUS MBTAXF WHLE TILYINO TO FIND THE GRANGERS IN ST. Louis. "T'm one of you, bogYS, I am. Trot up and take something said he, slapping the counter with his- fist. "That thar's our lay, that is," was the verdict, and about a dozen of the "boys" trotted up and took adult drinks without a wince. "Nice country out this way," suggested Dodger. "Powerful nice; yer bet," said the landlord, a man with a flushed face and blazing nose. "And that thar's powerful good licker, stranger," said one of the party, smacking his lips. "Kinder sarchin' like2' said another.   JOINING THE GRANGERS.         7 This being a very fair sort of a hint, Dodger didn't attempt to dodge it at all; he threw out a ten dollar bill "Nip again, boys; landlord, spread 'em out again! That cherry-nosed landlord never hesitated. Cash cust6m- ers were a rarity at that tavern, and so he spread out the tum- blers and hoisted the black bottle to the top of the bar once more. "Landlord, can I stay here to-night?" asked Dodger, after he had recovered his breath, for that rye was scorching. "You bet. Stay a week if you want ter." "' Got good fodder?" "Best in these parts, strangers        ! "Well, I'm your man for a week or two, I guess Are there many Grangers in these parts?" he asked. "Right smart lot on 'em--why " "Well, I am very much interested in their movement, and should like to know some- of them." '- Why, stranger, we're all Grangers hereabouts," said one of the party, swaggering up to Dodger. "Course we be; you bet!" said another, "Here comes the Master of our Grange," said another, pointing to a fine looking young farmer who was just entering the door. "What's his name 2 " asked Dodger, in a whisper. "Cal Smith," was the reply. "Mr. Smith, rm happy to see you," said he, going to meet the stranger, and extending his hand. "My name it Sassafras Dodger, from St. Louis; come and have a drink with us!" "No, thank you; I do not drink," replied Mr. Smith, shak- ing his hand calmly. "Don't tear a board off Jibbers' house," said one of the party. No; my friend Jibbers must not suffer. Try something!" said Dodger. "Well, give me a glass of cider, Jib!" said Smith.  &#xD;<pb n="8 (Illustration) -9" xml:id="VAC7797-00000006"/> JOiNING  GRABNGtERS.    JO0INOG THE GRATNOBE         9 The others indulged in "hard stuff," and nudged each other on the strength of it. "They tell me that you are the Master of the Grange here." "I believe I have that honor," replied Smith, bowing. "You are just the man I want to see. I have all along taken a great interest in the Patrons of Husbandry, and my ob- ject in visiting this part,:of the country is to become better ac- quainted with them, and perhaps join the order and buy me a farm out here." "Oh, I see!" mused Smith, with a mischievous twinkle in his eye. "Will you take me under your guidance and see me put through?" "But, my dear sir, if you -wish to become a Granger you must go through a regular course of instruction." "I'll do anything to become thoroughly acquainted with the noble order. When do you meet ." "Well, we have a school for instruction that you can join any time." "I am ready any time-to-morrow." "That will do."- "Will you put me through ," "I will" "Landlord, stand 'em up again! Boys, brace up!" Those "boys " never waited for second invitations, and with- out loss of time they proceeded to brace. Dodger and Smith talked matters over for a while longer, when it was settled that he should enter the school the follow- ing day,- and with this understanding they shook hands and  separated. Smith knew Dodger, having lived in St. Louis for quite a while previous to becoming a farmer, but Dodger was as inno- cent of knowing him as a child could have been. Thereby hangs some fun.  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7797-00000007"/> 10         JrOIINO THE GRANGIERS. "Come, boys," said he, turning again to the crowd, now nearly doubled, " let's licker some more!"  "You're our kind of a hoss, you are, stranger," said one of them, waddling up to the bar. "Jest the man we want fur a sort of a leader, like; got larning, yer see, an' we Grangers kin send you clean ter Wash. ington if we like," put in the landlord, "That's so!. was the chorus. Sassafras Dodger was pleased muchly; he was tickled, so to speak ; it was music in his hungry -ears, and he proceeded to shake each member of the party by the hand and brace up with a serene smile. "a Set out the dishes, landlord, and give my friends all they want. Got some cigars?--trot 'em out." Dodger was happier than he had been for years, and visions of office and power swept over him like a shock of galvanism. For two hours he treated "his friends," and they showed how friendly they were by never once refusing to swallow the whis- key he paid for. One by one they went down upon the sandy floor, or started homeward full of juicy satisfaction, and Dodger was himself shown up to bed by three men, to whom he made a red hot speech on the- political situation. As the time between that and morning was rather cloudy, suppose we pass it over and wait until he has risen the next morning, and settled himself with a cocktail and breakfast. The visions of the night before were still in his mind,. and with as light a heart as his head would admit of, he started out for Cal Smith's farm, some two miles away. A word about Cal. Smith. He was a middle-aged man, genial, well-to-do, fall of saga- city and enterprise, well educated, well posted, and in all re- spects just the man to be Master of a Grange, and conduct its prosperity. He had a vein of humor in his composition and   JON-ING THE GRANGERS.        1I MB. DODGER, AS HE APPEARED AFTER BEING CHANGED INTO A GRANGER, knowing Dodger and his designs, he at once resolved to give him all he wanted of being a practical Patron of Husbandry. He owned a large farm and employed about fifty men, a few of whom he let into the secret regarding the "school" through which he proposed to put Mr. Sassafras Dodger. This, of course, delighted the men, and they promised to second his efforts in giving himn all he wanted of the Grangers. Dodger entered the yard and was escorted out to the barn by a savage looking bull dog, who gave him to understand that he would bear watching, and that that was his especial business. Smith and a few of his men met him at the barn door.  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7797-00000008"/> 12        JOINICNG THE ORANGEERS "Good morning, Mr. Smith!" said he. "Good morning!" "Fine dog you have here!" "Yes; only a trifle suspicious." "By Jove! you have a splendid farm!" he continued, cast- ing his eyes over the well cultivated fields. "Yes, pretty fair. And so you have come to school, eh ." "Certainly; ready and anxious. Where is your Grange 2" "Right here. Here is where the Patrons meet, and it is the Master's duty to examine and instruct all those - who wish to become members of the order;-in short, you are now at head- quarters. I understand you to apply for instruction." "I do; instruction' and admission." '"Very well. These men are all Patrons. They work on my farm and assist in the school Thus you see the first note of harmony in the tune you are about to learn. The way is rough, and if you have any fears, take warning now! ' "Fears! you do not know me, sir I Go on; I'll follow!  "Bravely spoken! Well, the first thing to do is to examine your physical condition. Retire into the barn and strip." "Peel "            '  "To the hide."                  .. With some wonder in his face, Dodger did as requeited while Smith and his men gathered around to note the ^eAect of the peeling. Sassafras Dodger was a well-built ma, anitd a life long intimacy with the fat of the land had left quite :alot of it clinging to his anatomy.          . "Are you healthy in every particular, Mr. Dodger?" asked Smith, approaching him. - "Never was squarely sick in my life." But- in spite of this assurance they tied him to a bench and rubbed him down savagely. "And still your muscle is not what it should be; however, that will harden and develope as you proceed. Now, then, get   -2  MBR. DODGER, IN ATTEMPING TO PUT A HORSE COLLAR OVER AN OX'S HEAD, IS RAISED, SO TO SPEA..K. up and lay by that glossy suit of clothes, and assume a Granger's dress. Here it is." "All right, boys!" he said, still- courageous; ,rll do any- thing!" he said, taking up the rough overalls and getting into them. "Of course you wish to go through while about it ." "Oh, certain; no half way-for me. Howis this? he added, swinging himself round for inspection. "You outwardly resemble a Granger very much, all but your hands and face; but they will color and toughen. Better remove your diamond ring."  &#xD;<pb n="14-15 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000009"/> "-JOmImNr THE GRANGERS. "Oh, certainly; I'll put my toggery all together, and you will see that it is kept safe,l eh?" "I will answer for it, sir," said Smith, taking his clothes. "Good,enough. Now, what next 2 "Mr. Dodger, I may as well inform you that, as you are an apprentice, you must follow what instructions you receive from those above you, and, at the same time, learn from the experi- ence which your own attempts may furnish you   There are the oxen, there are the horses; harness the horses to the harrow there, and the oxen to the plough. Do it in your own way, and . let us observe the result and correct any mistakes." Oh, pshaw! that's only boys' play-anybody can do a little thing like that," said he, starting for the horses. "All right; you do it, and then you will be ready for the next lesson." Smith bundled Dodger's clothes underhis arm and started into the house to put them away, while his men-and fellow con- spirators allowed the solemnity to leak 6ut of their faces, and turned to note Dodger's success. Just before he began, Dodger- wished he hadn't boasted about how easy the task was, for, to tell the truth, he had never done such a thing before in his life, and knew little or nothing about how to go to work. It would be hard to tell just how Dodger went at the task, and how he progressed; He went up to and talked familiarly with the horses a moment, and then, thinking it would be the easiest job to harness them, he concluded to tackle the oxen first. So he seized a horse collar and approached one of them. "Whoa, Dobbin! it's all right, Dob. We only want to get better acquainted to like-each other first-rate. Come up and take something!" The ox shook its head, indicative of not wanting anything, and so Dodger approached nearer and attempted to place the collar -over the horns. It was a sleepy old ox and didn't appear                31   JOINING THE OGRANGERS.   6  &#xD;<pb n="16-17 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000010"/> 16        .JOININmG AE GANGRS. to care what the fashion was, and quietly submitted to the operation of being decked -with a horse-collar. The men laughed and applauded him, so he took heart some more, and went with another collar for the mate. This was not so sudden -a success as in the other instance, for the ox put in an objection and knocked Dodger into the soft barnyard, and then put down its head as though about to charge on him where he lay. But Dodger didn't lay long; he got up and carried some of that barnyard with him to a place of safety. "Whoa I you old idiot!" he said, after he got a .sufficient distance away. "Never give up! never let a critter think you are 'feared " said the laughing Grangers. "Oh, I am not afraid no, no; I'm only calculating," replied Dodger, again approaching the ox.  "Unstrap the collaar at the top 1" said Smith, who had returned. "Certainly. Why didn't I think of that!" said-he. "You are green yet." Dodger opened the collar after pulling off a thumb nail try. ing to get the buckles loosened, and again approaching the ox, he placed it upon his neck without trouble. This made him  - feel proud, and so he proceeded to get them together and adjust the remainder of the harness. This made more sport for his teachers than it did for him,-but, after a fashion, he got them side by side, and hitched them to a plough. "Very good. Now harness the horses to the harrow." "All right; I'm the lad that can do i," he replied, cheer. fully, as he proceeded to the task. I The horses were also patient creatures; that is to say, it took a great deal to get them provoked, and rouse the latent pirit within them. Dodger took the ox yoke, and, backing the horses out of their stalls, he managed to get them side by side, and placed the yoke over their necks   The animals   JOnING THE GANGERE. S. e,; s  '!  ,  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7797-00000011"/> 18         JOINSKG THE RA;NGERS. looked at each other inquiringly, as much as to ask, "is this regular " Then he bridled them and led them forth to the harrow, to with which a chain he attached them. "There! how's that?" he asked, triumphantly, turning to his instructors. "Mr. Dodger, allow me to congratulate you!" said Smith, shaking him by the hand, after which the others also pressed his bleeding thumb. "You promise to graduate early, with all the honors."' "Oh, I'm all- right! What next .?" i"Now to the fields! The harrow shall be your first lesson; come!"  Dodger took up the reins and started the horses. But they didn't appear to like the way they were rigged, and spread themselves all around. ... The harrow was put upon its back, and as that allowed -it to go easier, they managed to drag it to the field near by. But it was easy to see that the animals were getting indignant, and had their. heads together the most of the time, as though planning some mischief. "Now get 'em well together, and start!" Dodger made the attempt with considerable confidence, but .. the horses had- evidently lost what little of the article they had, and, although they started, they made a sorry figure of it, stop. ping every few-steps to send their heels in his direction. "Stand on the harrow, and give 'emvthe gad!  *  Again he obeyed orders; but those horses evidently thought that they had stood nonsense enough without submitting to the indignity of the gad. So they started to run like mad, throw. ing Dlbodger down upon the teeth of the harrow, and in other respects making it lively and somewhat painful for him. "Whoa! whoa! -you idiots! Whoa! stop 'em! stop 'ema!" he yelled, while the- dirt was being scooped up over him and into him and nary a tooth of that harrow was cushioned.   JOINWG THE GBANGERS.        1 THRE BnL OF DAMAGES FOR BRFJAKTNG THE ITARROW AND FONCES IS PRSENED TO MB. DODGER. After going a dozen rods or such a matter, they leaped a fence and wrecked the whole concern, when one of the Grangers cut across the lot and caught the horses. "Thunder and blazes!" howled Dodger, as he struggled to his feet, rubbing his sore spots and spitting out the soil that he had caught in his mouth, " is this what you call harrowing a " ," Well, somewhat harrowing, I should say." "Jamnathan! I should say it was," said he. How is this, sir?" asked Smith, as he approached. "Rather rough, I should say. The- horses don't appear to be used to it," he added, still rubbing his afflictions.  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7797-00000012"/> 20         JOININGS THE GRBANGERS. "But you have broken the harrow." "And the cussed thing came pretty near breaking me." "You must pay' ten dollars for the damage," said Smith. "That is one of the rules of -the order." "All right; but seems to me that its rather rough; some. what harrowing, so to speak." "But you must learn to be more careful." "Well, I'll give ten dollars, but I guess I've had all I want of harrowing. Give me an easier lesson." That evening a little darkey presented him with a bill for damages. "Very well. Go and drive the oxen in here, and try your hand at plowing." "That's the kidney! I never could get along with horses very well, except when they are hitched to a buggy." "Well, go for the oxen!" Dodger limped away as cheerfully as he could towards the barn where the sleepy oxen still stood chewing their cuds of meditation and hay, while one of the farmers released the horses and took them back to the barn. After a deal of trouble he coaxed the oxen into the field, dragging the plough after them. So far as their harness was concerned, it did not bother them quite so much as it did thei horses, but they stopped every few yards to kick at the traces that rubbed against their legs. However, the horse collars were soft, and so were the dispositions of the snailish giants who wore them. "Now take your plough by the handles, and start a furrow straight down to the other end of the field!" said Smith, er Dodger had got his team into position. "All right, Get up, Dob!" After a sufficient amount of prodding, the oxen started, and Dodger followed the plough and the instructions regarding how he must hold it, ,4   JOINING THE GRABGERS.        21  MR. DODGER ATTEMPTS TO MOW, BUT STRIKES -A SNAG, AND COMES TO TEMPORARY GRIEF. "Oh, I've seen people plow lots of times; it's as easy as rolling off a log-! See .?" As he spoke, the plough gave him a larboard yirk that threw him on his beam ends. "Whoa! whoa! you fools!" he yelled, and the oxen didn't have to be told twice on a matter of that kind. "You must brace up! Spread your legs well apart, keep your arms stiff, and accomodate yourself to the motion of the plough," said Smith.  "Oh, I see! It's easy enough after you get your hand in." Dodger was doing his level best th appear cheerful under  &#xD;<pb n="22-23 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000013"/> 22         jomInoG THE OGRBGERS. the trial but his face gave his words the lie direct; he didn't look half so cheerful as his teachers did. Again he started the team, and for about a rod everything went pretty well, only the plough wasn't in the ground any of the time. "Point her down!" yelled one of the Grangers. "She's light in the'bow," replied Dodger. "Never mind; point her down!" Dodger pointed her down, and went over the handles, bark- ing his nose and chin upon the beam. He pointed her down too much. "She takes too much water; she isn't evenly ballasted, or something," moaned Dodger, as he gathered himself out from among that plough. "But you must use your judgment. Don't point it down so much. Now, try again," said Smith. Dodger didn't appear so cheerful as he was. There was more work than romance about being a Granger, after all. But he took the handles and urged the team to motion again. He managed to make something like a furrow for a yard or two, and began to take hope, while his tutors encouraged him along in his initiation. But presently the plough struck a root, -'  and again Dodger went over on his beam end, to the starboard. Then the-oxen began to get tired of the fooling, and turned around to get a square look at the fist-class idiot who was at work with them. He attempted to get them about again, and into the traces, but they shook their heads savagely, and made a concerted charge upon -him with their hookers.- Dodger skipped. He yelled at them to: behave, but they refused to be trifed with any further, and so proceeded to get tangled up in the harness, after which 'they both laid down, as though resolved to rest for the remainder of the day. a "What's to be done now?" he asked, turning to his in- structors.   JONINo TRE GRANOERS.        23 I"* THE GdiAJOERS SET IM TO TREADras DOWN A LOAD OF HAY, VHl..l '.taiE .E PITCH IT ONJ AND PROD UITM WITb THRHlt FOREKS.  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7797-00000014"/> 24        JOINNG  GEBNGERS. "Well, that's all you can do with that team to-day. Don't you see? They have got through." "Seems to me they work on short time." "Why, they are regular Granger oxen, and know to a min- ute when their time is up. Unhitch them from the plough, drive them to the barn, unharness them and give them their hay, after which, return and take the plough back, and then come into the house to dinner." Poor Dodger I The Worst job of- the lot was oefore him now. He got kicked'and hooked and knocked over into the dirt half a dozen times before he succeeded in getting those ex. aspeqrted brutes back to the barn; but he did so at last, and then carefully washed a bushel of potatoes, and gave them their dinner. It was while dragging that plough back to the barn that he entertained the idea of abandoning the school, and allowing the Grangers to go to the old boy without him. But he thought that the best was yet to come nerved him up, and he went to dinner with such an appetite as he never possessed before. After dinner he was again taken to the field with his in. structors, to learn the art of making hay while the sun shines. This had always been- a favorite maxim with him, and, feeling ' a trifle refreshed, he shouldered a scythe, a rake, and two pitch- forks, and followed the lead of the others, each of whom was similarly armed. But the tools got awfully mixed before he got to the field, and gave him lots of bother.  - The Grangers went to mowing in downright earnest, and he was told to grasp his scythe and follow their example. He looked cheerful again. He glanced around for a good chance to begin, and then struck his maiden blow at the waving grass. It was a lusty blow that he struck, for he was bent on making his mark at a jum p. Well, he did! The blow thrust the point of the scythe   JOINING THE GRANGERS.        25 THE LOAD OF HAY IS OVERTURNED, AND MR. DODGER IS DE- POS!Bo UN 1 TDERNFATH IT.- into a stump, and his momentum made him jump over the snathe, and waltz a moment on his head. "Good lick!" said some one. "Point her well up!" said Smith. trying hard to -keep - his face straight. Dodger said something that sounded like "well" with an exclamation point to it. "Brace up, old party, and try it again!? Dodger repeated his consolatory exclamation, and proceeded to pull his scythe out of the stump. Again he struck out, this time " pointing her well up:" but  &#xD;<pb n="26-27 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000015"/> 26        JOININGt THE GRABNERS. - he pointed her so very well up that he clipped off a few clover heads, and swung around two or three times with the momen- tum of his instrument. Then- he struck a stone and left the edge of his scythe on it. Then he cut nearly every finger he had in trying to whet another- edge onto it, and he cussed and swore, and showed plainly enough that he had not attended church lately. After driving everybody outs of reach, and working away for a while, he got so that he struck a middle line between six inches under ground and a foot above it, and with the assistance of his huge cowhide boots, he managed to get quite a lot of grass down. But, oh! how the sweat of his brow did show itself! and how he did wipe it off with his old hat! It was the hardest road he had ever travelled towards an office yet. In the meantime, quite a large field of grass had been mown by the others, and Dodger was given a fork and set to work spreading it. This was comparatively easy business, only he would now and then jab the fork into the ground and attempt to spread that also. After working this way until night, he gladly accepted an invitation to knock off and go- to supper. In fact, he felt that he could lay down almost anywhere and take a sleep without giving supper a thought. Noble tiller of the soil! He had put in a rough day of it, everything considered, and as he dragged -one leg after the other in the direction of the farmhoie, he con- cluded thkt he would rather take a hand in half dozen St. Louis bar-room fights for his country's sake, than to go through such another day. After supper he was initiated into the art of driving home the cows, and then was given a pail anid told to try his hand at milking. His enthusiasm didn't effervesce much at the proposition, but he obeyed orders with as good a show of grace as he could o   O1INING THE GRANGERS. 27  &#xD;<pb n="28-29 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000016"/> 28       ^ JOININGt GE ANGERS. muster. He had learned something by the day's experience, and instead of blindly rushing up to a cow without an intro- duction, he stood around a few moments and observed how the others did it. Then he selected an honest looking cow, and proceeded to say a few encouraging and confidential words to her, after which he placed his stool by the wrong side of her, and began fooling around among her teats. The cow stood it for a few moments, and, finding that he was not relieving her of her lacteal accumulation, she switched him in the eyes with hertail, as a hint for him to begin business; but seeing that he was bent on trifling with her, she raised her leg and knocked him sprawling into the soft -soil, and immedi- ately changed her location with a look of indignation on her brow. Dodger groaned; he was too much exhausted to swear, although he thought of several things, which, if uttered, would have passed for anything but expressions of piety. He prob- ably felt that he was too tired to do the subject justice, and would put it off until the next morning. "What appears to be the trouble, Dodger " asked Smith, who was coming leisurely from the house, and happened to see his pupil's gymastics. "Wal, H just moved, that's all%" replied Dodger, sadly, whereat there was a general laugh. "I see; you -got on the wrong side of her. Always milk on the right hand side of a cow." "Oh! they are that particular, are they 2" t "Very particular, indeed., Now try it!" "All right I But somehow she don't appear to take to me very much," he added, in a low voice. "Oh, she'll take to you, never fear." Smith was right. The cow did take to him when he ap- proached her again. She took to him so earnestly that Dodger   JOnmGo THE aBANomBS.        29 A,'I MR. DODGER IS PUT TO SHELLNGr  CORN S ITH HS TEEH. ROUOHEER ON .TE TEETH THAN IT IS ON THE CORN. b  &#xD;<pb n="30-31 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000017"/> 80-       JONrNG THE GRANGER S. dropped his pail and stool, and meandered over the barnyard fence, just as though he wanted to see somebody over there in a great hurry. a Oh, that cow's a fool I " he muttered, as the boys went on with their laughing. What made him feel worse than all, was, that Mrs. Smith and two or three lady friends came outt, and were enjoying his apprenticeship hugely. Well, try another one," said Smith. Dodger shook his head dubiously, and hesitated. "I say, Smith, is it absolutely necessary that I should learn how to- milk a?" "It is necessary that you should learn everything pertaining to a farmer's life if you hope to become a Granger and share their future honors." Dodger was thoughtful, but gradually, as the visions came before him, his face brightened. "Now, there is an honest, well-meaning cow," said Smith, pointing to an old brindle who stood chewing her cud, and pa- tiently waiting her turn over the paiL "Well, here goes!' said he, getting cautiously over the fence again, and approaching the cow indicated. This .proved to be a very sedate and well-behaved cow, and she stood perfectly quiet while the novice got htmself into po- sition. Then he began to pull at her teats and squeeze them as the other men did, but nary a drop of milk came. In fact, if a young kitten had been depending upon him for support, she would have stood a good chance of starving to death. Smith volunteered a little information, and by following it his heart was made glad at the sight of a tiny stream of milk. Then he felt good, and began to whistle "Paddle your own - Canoe," and to feel that the future looked brighter than it did. But. the cow on whom he had made the first attempt began to move towards him   She went up to her companion who   JOINING THE GRANGoEPS,.      31 ,9' DODGER ATTEMPTS TO FOLLOW INSTRUCTIONS AND LEAD TE PIGS TO WATER BY THE EAR, BUT FINDS THE JOB MORE EASY TO ORDER THA TO EXECUTE.   &#xD;<pb n="32-33 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000018"/> 82         oININGt THE GRNGIES. was now being trifled with, and evidently tried to predjudice her against Dodger, but finding that she took no notice of her, she got indignant, and proceeded to lock horns with her, and to back her back over Dodger, tipping him into the mud, and, by some means or other, jamming the milk pail over his head.. Dodger gathered himself up, and, without attempting to take his head out of that pail, he was kept right busy trying to prevent being run over by the cows, several of whom had now joined in the stampede. But he turned a somersault over the fence at the first opportunity. "That will do for to-night," said Smith, as soon as he could trust himself to speak; "you did very well for a first attempt," he added, consolingly. "Oh, I'd have gotten along beautifully, if it hadn't been for that other cow, confound her I I don't wonder that you laugh, I wish I could," said he. "That is all right. Of course, we can't help laughing at you; we laugh at all the scholars who come here as green as you are.- But you are dismissed now, and may get ready for bed-as soon as you like."            I This was welcome intelligence to Dodger, but he, flt that a good washing was one of his greatest needs, and way shown down to the brook, where there was plenty 1Of water wherewith to do it. One of the Grangers who went down with him kept up the fun on his own account in a quiet way, by assuring him that he was just the man the Grangers wanted in those- parts, and that after he had served a thorough apprenticeship they would dote- on him. This sent him to bed feeling much better. It was, in fact just about the salve he wanted to cure his many bruises, and he sank into a peaceful slumber with the glamour of a Senator. ship before his eyes. The next morning he was routed out bright and early to help feed the hogs, rml]k the' cows, and drive them to pasture,   JOINNG 'TH GRNGEIS .  33 &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7797-00000019"/> t       .TOIINTOnG THE BA B. .G lRS. in all of which he succeeded much better than he did the night before, Then came a substantial breakfast, and it didn't require a cocktail to give him an appetite, either. After this was over with he was tiaken out to the barn, and made to assist in harnessing the horses to a large hay-wagon, into which they all got, and were driven out into the field where they had labored yesterday. The hay had to be spread again, and Dodger worked like a beaver, assisting until the whole -field had been tossed and turned over to the sun. Then they drove to another field where the hay was cured and ready to be gathered in. This initiated him into the mys- terie4 of raking; first into a winrow, and afterwards tumbling it into cocks, in all of which Dodger manifested a great deal of enthusiasm, and got rid of a deal of perspiration. Once or twice he got mixed up with his rake, and tumbled down with it, but on the whole he did very well. Then came the loading. Dodger was told to get into the wagon to tread it down and stow it away, while four others pitched it up to him. For a few moments this was fine sport, but presently his legs got tired, he tripped himself up over his fork handle, and the hay came up to him so fast that he was flooded and soon buried entirely out of sight. Then he yelled, and said they were smothering him, and sticking the tines of their forks into him, but they pretended not to hear, and kept on pitching up and diving from one cock to another in rapid succession. It was altogether too lively, and not until the load had got quite high, and the pitching consequently some slower, did he get a chance to breathe. Then he tried to appear calm and to look pleased, but at the same time he would have given ten dollars to know who it was that had prodded him so often with a fork.   -   DODGER DRIES HMSELF BEFORE THE KITCHEN FIRE, AND BEGIN8 TO ENTERTAIN GRAVE DOUBTS ABOUT ITS PAYING TO BECOME A GRIOGEE.   "Now drive --the load to the barn," said Smith, after the nay had been loaded almost as high as a house, and as badly put together. "All right! hand me up the lines." The reins were thrown up to him, but failing to catch but one of them, the other fell back upon the horses, who at once took fright and started off on a run Dodger yelled for them to stopt and seeing that they paid no attention to him, he pulled on the single rein that he held, bringing the team sharply around, and overturning the load souarely upon him.  &#xD;<pb n="36-37 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000020"/> 16   '    JOINNG TOB GRANGERS. A half a dozen forks were brought into requisition, and he was soon rescued, though not until he had been jabbed several times- with the tines.  "Are you hurt " inquired Smith and the others. "I don't know; I feel prettr ybad. What was it-an earth- quake?" he asked, looking wildly around*    : "He's out of his head," said one of them. "I thought so when he came here," said another. "Take him down ot the house and dress his wounds," said Smith, passing him over to two of his men. Poor Sassafras Dodger I his initiation was making him pretty sore in places. Placesthough, would hardly comprehend the case. He was bleeding from several fresh wounds and bruises, while those of the previous day had been reopened by the ,shock. No wonder he thought an earthquake had overtaken him They took him to the house and began to wash off the blood, and apply salve and court plaster. Submitting to this was easier work than farming. and so he made no qbjection, but allowed the doctor to do just about as he liked with him. In this they appeared to take much delight, and when they were through with him his face looked like a railroad map, and yards of plaster had been used up on his dilapidated mug. But it insured h a day of rest, at all events, for he was excused from further work,- and being left alone to himself, he had a good chance to survey the headway he hadc made, and to figure up in his mind how well he liked it. Secretly he resolved to get away from that active school at the first opportunity, and trust to luck about getting into office in some other way. There was too much seriousness connected with this party to suit him altogether. And so the day wore itself out as well as Dodger, but he made up his mind that he bad taken all the degrees he cared to take. At night his supper was taken to him, but the Grangers ,         &#xD;<pb n="38-39 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000021"/> 38        JOINING THE GRANGERS. had arrangeA the court plaster over his face and about his mouth in such a way as to prevent him from opening that use- ful organ, or making his jaws go in the least. So he was obliged to make his meal of milk, which he sucked through a straw. It wasn't the first suction that he had ever used at the end of a straw, but it was the- first square meal that he had ever parta- keft of in that way. Then Smith and a few of his men came into the room where he lay, and condoled with him, and told him that accidents would happen even among the Grangers, and that he must't get Becouraged, but keep a stiff upper lip and all would come out bright. Assuring him that he would be well enough by the next morning to resume his lessons, they bade him a fond good-night, and then went out to plan new lessons for him to learn the next- day. It took some time to get the -plaster off his face the morning following, and Dodger felt a trifle vexed to find that there was nothing the matter with his face to call for a quarter of what had been put on, but he washed it off the best he could, and limped down stairs to breakfast, where he was greeted with many expressions of delight, which made him feel almost as good as new.  Breakfast over with, he strode out into the barn to see what the day's lay-out was like. "You are hardly well enough, Mr. Dodger, to take into heavy work again to-day. So you may do a few of the Gran- gers' chores, quite as necessary for you to learn as anything else. The first thing for your day's lesson will be shelling corn. This you must do in the good old-fashioned way, by hand or by teeth, as best you can, for not until you are further advanced in the business, will you be allowed to use modern machinery." "All right; bring on your corn! I have never dealt with it in the kernel or on the cob before, but I've handled a deal of it in a liquid state." -,- .  W   JO rIN3  TiE AOANGERS.     39 DODGER IS GREATLY ASTONlSHED- AT THE STYE O THE IST HE HAS LABORED SO: iARD TO BRIING,  &#xD;<pb n="40-41 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000022"/> + JONIING THE GRANOEBS. "I haven't the slightest doubt of it, sir. Now, here is your corn, and there the baskets. By tooth or nail you should shell a bushel an hour, but you'll succeed better with your teeth. We will leave you,: returning now and then to see how you succeed;" saying which, the Grangers withdrew to a con- venient place where they could watch him through the cracks in the barn. Dodger stood a moment looking at the task before him! The ears of corn were hard and tough; the kernels clung to the cob like the bark to a withered tree., Presently he got down and tried one of the ears. The corn refused to leave its fasten- ings. He .pulled at it-; he twisted it through his hands, but not a kernel would shell off. Then he remembered what they told him about using his teeth, and finding that his hands failed, he opened his mouth and went for it. The first twist broke one tooth; then he broke out cussing, and threw the ear at a rooster that stood crowing near by. Then he rnluminated on his prospects; then he howled, and said the Grangers might go to the devil; he: had got all he wanted of them. At this point Smith made his appearance.  "Well, how do you get along?" "Get along-h-1   Got one kernel off andchroke off one tooth! I say, Smith, do you put 'em all through this way?  he asked.                         v "Certainly. We -are very particular about it, as I told you before. But you can change from one thing to another if you desire." "Well, let me try something elsef" he said, sullenly. "But, I say, Dodger, you are not getting discouraged, are you?"  Have you put your foot to the plough and turned back? Is that so, Mr. Dodger ." "No, no; only I don't like to shell corn with my teeth. Give me an axe and let me chop it off, or let me try something else!" -' /    MRIE. DODGER, AFITER BEING TREATED BY THE LMTYBBR TO A RED HOT DRINK; IS ONLY TOO HAPPY TO TAKR A PRESAENT TO TE RAIL- ROAD PRESIDEXNT.   &#xD;<pb n="42-43 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000023"/> 42        JOINING THE OGRANES. "All right. You know where the brook is  Well, lead the pigs down there to water, and return them." "Good enough I I'm hell on pork!" said he, as he started for the hog pen. This'pen was a large -one, a yard, in fact, and he opened the gate and entered it. The hogs started up and grunted their inquiries as to his intentions. He began shooing them towards the open gate, a task that required but little ability to perform. But when they were once out it was not an easy matter to keep them together, or to make them comprehend the idea that they were being driven to water. They went to rooting around in all directions, and gave him heaps of trouble, and again he cussed. "Lead the big one by the ear, and the others will follow," said one of the Grangers.   - Dodger attempted to take that boss hog by his hearing apF paratus, but the porker wheeled around and darted between his legs, throwing the novice upon his back, and nrunning as though possessed of the devil, as did his ancestors on a certain occasion. But the ride was short, for Dodger rolled off and rubbed v his nose in the dirt. Dodger's blood was-up, and again he made a dive for that rooter. The race was long, but being quite fat, the hog was soon run doon and caught. Seizing him firmly by the ear, he attempted to drag -him along towards the brook; but it was no go, for Mr. Porker had different views on the subject, and evidently intended to em- ploy his liberty in a neighboring potatoe field. There was an hour of fun for the Grangers in watching their victim, but not much for the victim. At length they be- gan to saunter towards the brook, and Dodger found a few moments time wheremi to mend his bellows, and wipe the pers piration from his brow. But when the hogs gathered? at the river they did not     &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7797-00000024"/> t4        JoInoING I  GHS OATtoRS. manifest much inclination to take water. On the contrary, they took to the mud along the edges of the stream, and with good-natured grunts they proceeded to adjust themselves to the yielding situation.  Seeing that the animals were not doing what he had driven them there to do, he attempted to rouse them upl, preparatory to a return to their quarters again. In this he 'found more trouble than in executing any other part of the programme. they positively refused to budge, and Answered him back in solemn grunts. Bethtnking himself of the pig's ear, he waded into the watel md seized one- of them, and. attemplted to-drag him from his balmy repose. This wa- strenously, objected to by the animal, while Dodger was just as much in earnest about having his way. The upshot of the seizure was, that Dodger got thrown nto the water, and several hogs took pains to- run over him and crowd him still-deeper into the mire. With great difficulty he rescued himself from drowning, and when he crawled on shore he was mad! The hogs remained there as-long as they wished to, and when night came the returned to their lodgings for supper. But in the meantime Dodger had returned to to the barn, where he found one or two of the Grangers, anudrelated to them is want of complete s;uccess. The men appeared to feel sorry for him, and manifested it by wasming him off with several pails of water, after which- he went to the kitchen to dry himself. Again his heart went down. Again he took a'glance at the situation, and began to entertain doubts as to its paying. If there should a rise result from it, it would certainly be, coming up out of great tribulation. But would there be a rise ' Ah I there was the rub I At night he was -dried, and, thoroughly disgusted. Smith and a few of his men sat down to argue matters with him, and    JOINING THE CGRANGERS.      45 DoDGOB PICKS HMSELF UP AND T'IES- TO COLLECT m 8CAT-  to encourage him onaward in his noble apprenticeship, and with the assistance of a pitcher of real hard cider, they man.- aged to reconcile him to the task of continuing on. The, next day he was told ttake a bag of corn on a wheel barrow  began to grow heavy-the road was awfully rough- and he t E dow  pretty often to take a rest and a thi-nk But he arrived at themill at last and carried the bag in to with the assistance of a pitcher of real hard cider, theg mand aged to reconcile him to the task of continuing on. and he sat down pretty often'to take a rest and a think. But he arrived at the mill at last, and carried the bag in to  &#xD;<pb n="46-47 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000025"/> "        JOINING TEE GRANGERS. the miller, who was familiar with his history and his appren. ticeship. "Glad to see you!" said he. "Glad to hear that you are soon to join our ranks,for we need such men as you are. The fact is, we have too few educated men among us ; men fit for office, and for that reason I am glad that you have progressed so well, as I hear you have." Dodger smiled again and was happy. He even went so far as to say how deeply his heart was in the labor before him, and that he was determined to do all in his power to serve the noble Patrons.  The miller said yes, and then untied and emptied the bag. Dodger started back in surprise; so did the miller. , Why, you must - have taken the wrong bag. These are potatoes; not corn,"'said he. "Thunder I that is too bad! What will they say to me for being so stupid? Oh, pshaw!" " "Well, it is rather laughable; but never mind; I will make it all right with Mr. Smith if you will do me a favor--do the Order a favor, in fact." "Certainly. What is it"  "I have a present here for Mr. Sleeper, the President of the railroad. It is a rare animal, intended for his happy family,? and several members of the Order left it with me with the re- quest that I should see it delivered to him. Now, as it is right on your way^ back to Smith's, if you will deliver it to him I will be very much obliged." "Oh, certainly; anything to oblige you, and especially the noble Order'of Grangers," replied Dodger. "Thanks. Do you drink?" he asked, going to a little closet in the mill. "Well, yes; I would like a pull at something good. Haven't had- anything -but hard cider ever since I went to Smiths. What is this -"  MR. DoDGE FADE TO ENAT TE PART OF SoaREcROW FOR A5 CIscOrar^L.  &#xD;<pb n="48-49 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000026"/> 48         JOINING THE GRANGERS. "-The nicest old Granger rye that you ever saw or dusted your throat with. Brace up!" "Thank you!" and he did brace up, with a long pull, and a strong pull, and a pull that nearly drew up the bottom of the bottle. 7  . "Good enough!" he exclaimed, as he took it away from his lips. "That's right royal." "Glad you like it. It'll kind o0 nerve you up.'  "Yes, indeed; I feel it." "Well, here is the bag containing the animal. Just place-it on your barrow, and deliver it in person to the old man. Yeh know where lives-in that beautiful large house there, on the right as you go home." "All right; -I' find it," said he, taking up the bag and placing it on his barrow. "Kind of a peculiar smell around here somewhere, eh " he queried, as he stirred up the occupant of the bag. "It comes from theerat in the bag-musk rat. See?" Dodger didn't see exactly, but he smelt, and yet he was en- tirely innocent, and getting pretty drunk Taking up his bar. row, he started on his errand. He almost flew, so inspiriting was the draught he had taken at the miller's, and almost before he knew it he had reached the residence of Mr. Sleeper, Presi- dent of the railroad. "This President mus' be a nice ole chap, for ze Grangers don't like 'em as a rule. Guess he's 'bout half Granger 'imself?' Saying which, he started up to the house. Finding the front door open, he wheeled his barrbw right into the --house, but that " musk" became louder every minute, as the "rat" flounced around in the bag. The moment he en tered the house there was an uprising and a nose-clasping among its inmates, while the cry of "skunk 1" was sounded from every room.   JoINIrG THE GRAIGERS.      49 MB. DODOTB BEINGIS DOWN4 TE CEOW A .'TDOOE8 DOWN HM- MR. DODGER BRINGS DOWN Tl  CROW AND COMES DOWN m-  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7797-00000027"/> 50         Jona  THEG GRAD GEES. "I have a present for you from'the Grangers," said the fud- lied Dodger, coming intothe presence of the President. "A present for the devil l" howled the-old man, without . the use of his nose, having it pinched between his thumb and finger. "Where's that skunk " "Donno, boss-; got a musk-rat nere for you," said he, open- ing his bag and allowing the animal to escape, eveni against Sleeper's protestations, for he suspected something wrong. "A skunk I a skunk! by thunder! Git out of here, you infernal idiot! Begone!" But seeing no movement on the part of Dodger to "git," he rushed upon him and hustled him out of the house in short order,/barrow and all, while his ser- vants affixede clothes-pins to their noses, and went for that skunk.         - Dodger began to suspect that there was something wrong going on; that he had somehow made a mistake again, and as he picked up his barrow, a sense of complete woebegoneness overcame him, and he looked'as though he verily wished that he had never heard of such an Order as the Patrons of Husband- ry. So far ms he could see, they were the patrons of deviltry. Slowly, sadly, and with onhsiderable winding and uncer. tainty, did he lift that wheelbarrow and trundle it back to Cal Smith's. By the time he reached home, the liquor he had taken such a pull of was at its height, and he concluded a nap on the haymow was one of the urgent requirements of nature. He awoke from that delightful refreshment just in time for breakfast thasonesixoning.- But the events of yesterday were almost entirely faded from his mind, and a bad headache was about all he remembered of what had been. Yet he felt better after breakfast, and was again taken in hand by his instructors. This lesson consisted in making a scare-crow of himself, to protect the farn. He was dressed up in good scare-crow style, given an old musket, heavily loaded, and placed upon a barrel in the cornfield. with instructions to shoot the first crow that   JOInING THE GRANGERS.      1- 1 '," MB. DODGER TRIES HS HAND AT HOEING POTATOES' WITH, A "ARGE 81ZED HOE. THE POTATOES S UFFE AS WELL AS DODGER. ventured near. His St. Louis friends should have seen him then. He watched for fifteen or twenty minutes, when he espied a crow. He resolved to, show how skilful a shot he was, -and so essayed to bring the corn-thief down on the wing. He fired, but the old musket was one of those articles that kills both ways. It not only burst, but kicked like a mule, and Dodger went to grass over backwards; in fact, he appeared to be spinning around in mid-air for -a moment before he disappeared in the corn, Two or three of the Grangers ran to his rescue, and dosed  &#xD;<pb n="52-53 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000028"/> 5 2        JOMNG THE GORANGES. him well with whiskey before he fairly came to his senses again. This was not -much -more of a success than his other efforts had oeen, but they consoled him by saying that the crow had been blown to atoms by the marvellous accuracy of his aim; in fact, they talked him out of any indignation he might have otherwise indulged in, and they returned to the, barn in pretty good spirits. iThen they put him to hoeing potatoes with one of those huge long-handled hoes used by the negroes in the South. The experiment was not all that could- have been wished, even by the Grangers themselves, for he floundered around among the hills in such a way that nearly every sprout was hoed up and destroyed. They did not keep him at this business long, or not any longer than it required to give him a- good sweat. He was then pronounced a success as a potato hoer, and told to quit, and try something else. All hands shook hands with him and uttered congratulations. This flnished the day, and at night he was told that he had progressed so far that he could now be allowed to sleep on the Grangers' cot, a peculiar affair, on which none but those on the high road to ultimate success were allowed to repose upon. He retired, feeling first-rate. Hope dawned again, and he felt assured that his trials were near an end. Again the bright future flashed before him, and with the Governor's chair dan- cing before his eyes he fell asleep. Dodger slept the sleep of the just that night, and it is not known just how long he would have kept it up, had it not been for that Granger bedstead. At precisely five o'clock it turned over and emptied him out upon the floor, plump. He awoke with a yell of affright, and as he was completely enveloped in the bedding and not able to see light, or to feel anyhing but the inverted bed above him, he was at a loss to account for the situation, unless an earthquake had smashed things and buried him in the general ruin.   &#xD;<pb n="54-55 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000029"/> 54        JORNIN THE GANGEES.  But his cries brought Smith and two or three hers to hi room, when he was dragged out.  "Is everything smashed " was his trst query. "Nothing but your head, I guess," was the reply. "Why, what the devilis it, anyway ' " he asked, still gas ing fromtAie Grangers to the inverted bed. "I am astonished, Mr. Dodger " said Smith, gravely. "So am I. What is it?" "You must know that all good Grangers rise at five o'cloc] in the morning, and when we placed you on this bedstead w, did it to teach you a lesson we hope you will never forget namely, early rising. 1No sluggard can be a Granger. Will yoI remember this?" *1- i^"Be I will!" "Al9eghti . Dress and come down to breakfast." "Thun I! they are coming the moral on me now," sMid he after being left alone; "but I suppose it is all right." "This isSunday, isn't it ' he asked, when he met Smith i] the dining room. "Yes ,-but Sunday, has its labors with the Grangers." "By Jove I there is no let-up with these fellows," though he. After breakfast he was taken to the vegetable garden, ani set to pulling weeds. But in this he gave them almost as muc trouble as he did in hoeing potatoes, for he extracted quite a many vegetables as he did weeds, requiring constant watching This was done-by a local preacher, who watched and exhorte at the same time.  At length he was pronouncel a success as a weedist, an taken before the Master, Cal Smith, who at once shook hit warmly by the hand, and breathed eloquent congratulations i his ear.* It was, indeed, a serio-comic scene ^ . "flow, my friend, you must learn the art of tending cattle All bovines should be carded once a week to make them health-   f   JOINING III IT, GRAWGE S. &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7797-00000030"/> "        JOINING THE GRANGtERS. and their hides tough. Take him to the barn and let him pray tice a while " he said, to his men. Half a dozen Grangers escorted him to the barnyard, and he was thete given a curry-comb and told to-go for a sedate looking bull and rub him down handsomely. With as much confidence- as he had attacked the weeds in the garden did he approach that gentleman cow. He began on his hind-quarters, resolving to go over his "round" before he worked on his " sirloin"' and " chuck." Despite Dodger's good' intentions towards that bull, he did not appear to appreciate the kindness. On the contrary, he wheeled-around to take a look at the person who was treating him to a dry shampoo.: But Dodger hung to his flank, and again began his manipulations. Still the bull acted uneasy, and as though utfused :to such a display of hygienic solicitude on the part of his friends. He began to reason with him, and, in a few words, to explain how much better it would make him feel if he had a good dry rub. But still the bull acted very suspicious. At length Dodgei got provoked at his stubborn studidity, and gave him a kiek on the shin. - Then the bull began to run, and so did Dodger, and he man- aged to leap upon his back, amid the roars of laughter and ap. plause of the lookers on. Dodger, kept up his currying all the while, and when the old bull fetchedp in the corner of the yard, 'his sudden stopping threw his worrier over his head into the mud. This brought matters to a crisis, and before Dodger was aware of it, Mr. Bull caught him on his hornds and threw him over the barnyard fence, where he fell into a soft accumulation- into which he sank- frther than -he wanted to. Dodger gathered himself up and tried to look cheerful, but it was ,a failure. "Are you hurt much?" asked one of them. "Well, there seems to be' a little distance between me and the Styx; but it rather sticks: inay crop to have to put up with such treatment. T don't think I shall stick to this school much longer." "What! are we to lose our future United States Senator " asked one.   JOINING THE GRANGERS.   '1 75 /     -    "Our Governor?" chimed another. "Our -future President, perhaps?" intoned still another of the Grangers.   - "Well, the fact is, I'm being used rather rough," whined Dodger. er Tle road to greatness is always rough." "Per haps you don't wish to be great." "Well, don't you think Im devilish unlucky 1. "No more so than oters who are like you in inexpherience. "What you say may be trqe, but-" "Our fBut are we to un , perstandthat you falter  of"  "rBut are we. fo unaers ana'that you falter a "   &#xD;<pb n="58-59 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000031"/> - 58    -    JOINING THE GRANGERS. '"No; go on!" said he) resolutely, brightening Uip and shaking the mud from his person. "What next e"- "Well, do you think you understand rubbing down cattle?" "There are things I understand better, but I think I com- prehend the idea well enough." "All right. The next thing for you to learn is the economy of weeds. You see hereabout a large number of them. These can all be made available as fodder for milch cows and nursing sows. Take these shears and cut the various specimens into short feed. The bits will be mixed with meal and water, and, thus fixed, will fol the most dainty animal in the farmyard. "Out 'em up with shears?"-he asked, wonderingly. - "To be sure. We use only primitive methods for our initi. ates. iN ow, try your hand, and we will return in a few minutes and see how you progress;" saying which, the Grangers retired to the house and left our hero alone. Dodger held the shears in his hand and fell to meditating. "Now, if this was anywhere but in the country, I should suspect that I was being played with; in fact, I can hardly keep down the thought that these Grangers are having a devil- ish good time at my expense. The devil! If I thought so, how I would meander put of this. And if it is so, and the sell should everi reach St. jouis, it would be too warm for me there ever after. But they look so honest; they are such straight- forward, practical men; I can hardly believe they are up to any trick. It must be regular, so here goes!" He began pulling up a lot of weeds, and for half an hour he patiently cut them up with the shears, until he had about a bushel of this cut-feed. Then the bell rang for dinner, and he gladly answered it. After dinner he was allowed an hour for rest, and then he was led into the potato-bin, and set to work sorting them over, throwing the good ones into one pile and the poor ones into another. This work lasted him all the afternoon. Sunday night passed pleasantly. He was allowed to assume his best clothes, and to walk out around the neighborhood, a treat he very much enjoyed, as he returned to the hotel from whence he set out, and put away rye enough to make up for lost time. But he Was not suffered to go alone, for Cal Smith had not gotten through with him yet, and so- he was allowed to- pay the shot for two of the Grangers who accompanied him. Monday morning he was again emptied out upon the floor by that Grangers' bedstead. After breakfast he was taken in hand   &#xD;<pb n="60-61 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000032"/> 60        JOINI( THE GRANGERS. by Cal Smith, who now informed him that an opportunity would now be given him for practice with a flail. There were oats, wild and tame, to be threshed, and as the art was one veryt necessary to the completion of a farmer's stock of knowledge, he might put in a day's practice at it. Dodger felt rather good. He had given. and received many tihrashings in his life, but this was the first time that he had ever lad a chance at grain with a flail, in fact, he felt triumphant. The barn floor was covered with the unbound bundles of oats, and Dodger was given a flail and told to do as Smith did. Now, Sm'ith was a thresher. He could swing a flail with the best in the lund, and he set his pupil a very good example indeed. -Dodger watched him a moment, and when he ceased he raised his flail to make a beginning. Reader, have you ever attempted to thresh with a flail If you have, you probablyknow how difficult a task it is to make a success of it at first          , The first blow that Dodger struck landed on the back of his head, and then he threw down the flail and went out to find the man who hit,him. Not succeeding in this, he rubbed his philoprogenitiveness, cussed a ifttle, and took up his flail again. Smith and three or four others were concealed where they could see what was going on, and they nearly exploded under the pressure of 'suppressed laughter.   , The next blow was abortive, and the end of the swingle whack- ed him on his knuckles. This did not -make him happy even, and he felt in no hunfor to lead'the exercises of a revival meeting. Again he tried, and managed to kill an old hen that cameIn just then to see if he had got enough threshed out to make her a-dinner. But his next essay was a success beyond a doubt. The swingle, by some hocus-pocus, some boomerang movement, struck him on the nose, and scattered the claret in all directions. Then Dodgerhowled! lIe danced! he got down on the barn floor amongst the straw, and tore around like a freshy caught eel. He called for Smith; he dared him to come and congratulate 'him on his success; in short, he called for the whole Order of Grangers to come and face him! Smith and his companions rolled and laughed, but they con- cluded not to confront him just then. Dodger, went to the well and bathed his damaged smeller with cold water, and for a quarter of-an hour he sozzled itf and cussed himself down to a simmAr. i    JOINnva THE GiRBNGCE8. 61 &#xD;<pb n="62-63 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7797-00000033"/> 62        rOiNIo THE GOANGERS. Then he returned to the thrashing floor again and contem plated the task before him. Would it pay . Then he tried the flail again, anid banged himself and the oats some more. But there was a limit to Dodger's patience as well as to his greenness. He was mad all over now, clean through to his marrow, and giving the flail a fling into another part of the barn, he sat down and resolved to go no further. It was while thus engaged that he heard a snickering in another part of the barn, out of sight, and he: gradually became convinced  ththeGrangers were enjoying his misfortunes al. together too well. In fact, they were having the fun entirely to themselves, and he was receiving all of the rough knocks. Then it occured to him that he had all the while been mak. ing a donkey of himself, and that he was no nearer now to the goal- of his political ambition than he was at the start. What should be done? ;After allowing him to cogitate for a few minutes, Smith approached him. "Well Dodger; got tired " " i Yes; so tired that I guess I won't work any more to-day. Damn that fa1P" he added, energetically. "Does s work well?" he askescheefully. ,Ye-J]oo well-on my head."  "Osuch accidents are common to, every one who learns to thresh with a flail But you will soon get used to it, old man!" iI don't think I shall; I'm sick.  "Well, supposeyou go to the house and lay off for the re. Tainder of the day. You will be all right by morning." "I trust I shall," he moaned. "Well, well; we will excuse you to-day;" saying which, Smith turned away to join the other conspirators. Dodger sat there a long time, and eery now and then, while the Grangers wereabout their work, he could hear a roar of laughter, which convinced him that his apprenticeship was beig commented upon with more hilarity than would probably be the case were he present with them. In short; the whole affair, with all its torments and comicalities, rose up before him, and had it not been for his swollen nose and sore back-head, to say nothing of aozzen or so old scars and sores, he might have laughed too. Had another been the victim, he would have laughed as heartily as they. At all events, he concluded that they had gotten all the - )ort out of him that they would ever get.   JOrNING THE GIRANGIEBS. 63 C4 '.220 y 4  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7797-00000034"/> "        ; oININGm TB"GRAGtEBRS. All day long he brooded over his situation, but it made on difference how indignant he might get, he could not prove that they were not in earnest with his schooling, but if he stayed to graduate, he felt convinced that he should be a dead subject. Late in the afternoon, and while the men on the farm were all away in different directions at work, and talking over his case, Dodger stole minto the house and managed to secure his clothes. Taking them to his room, he put them out of sight, and waited for we approach of night, concluding that he would graduate out of the back door at the first favorable opportunity. It was nearly ten o'clock before that opportunity came, and then, taking his clothes under his arm, he stole out of the house as quietly as he could. Going around behind the barn, he proceeded to put them on, instead of the outlandish toggery he had worn as a Granger's apprentice. Once more he seemed like himself again. He now felt even more than ever that he had learned enough. He would return to his old stumping ground, and work in the old way once more, trusting to luck for crumbs, if a square meal was denied him. Taking, up his farmer's gear, he thought a moment, and then started for a pond not far away. Thrusting a pole into the ground on the shore, he proceeded to adjust his old clothes to it in such! a way as to attract the attention of passers-by, and he didn't care if they really thought that he had committed suicide out of sheer desperation. It would be some satisfaction for him. And at first they did think so. The railroad was but a short distance away, and towards it he now turned his steps, resol-ing to travel on foot until he reached the next station, and from thence take the first train that would carry him back to St. Louis again. Good-bye, Grangers!" he said, waving his hand in the direction of Cal Smith's. "I'm done, and off. Enjoy your- selves at my expense as much as you can, but I'll be even with you yet! ' He turned away into the, darkness, and started down the track, but it was either a realityor a fancy that he could hear shouts of laughter away back behind him,- and as he hurrid on, he seemed to hear, "How ARE YOU, GRBEtor . " tittered forth upon the silent air. Dodger hasn't joined the Order yet. THE END.    &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
