<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7104">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Inflation at the Cross Roads </title>
            <author>Locke, David Ross, (1833-1888)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7104</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1568A</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Inflation at the cross roads :</title>
                  <author>Locke, David Ross, (1833-1888)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>American News Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1875">1875</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-06">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="TechBooks" when="2002-08-23">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-09-02">Finished TEI conversion and final editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7104-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>INFLATION AT THE CROSS ROADS,</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">BEING A HISTORY OF THE RISE AND FALL OF THE ONLIMITED TRUST AND CONFIDENCE COMPANY,  OF CONFEDRIT X ROADS.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">IN A SERIES OF FIVE LETTERS,</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>PETROLEUM V. NASBY.</docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <docEdition>
               <figure>
                  <head>DEACON POGRAM INSPIRING CONFIDENCE.</head>
               </figure>
            </docEdition>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>AMERICAN NEWS COMPANY.</publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1875">1875.</docDate>
            <docEdition>PRICE, TEN CENTS.</docEdition>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="" xml:id="VAC7104-00000002"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered according to Act of Congress in the year 1875, by DAVID R. LOCKE, In the Office of the Librarian of Congress at Washington, D. C.</edition>
               <publisher>Macgowan &amp; Slipper, Printers, 168 Nassau Street, N. Y.</publisher>
            </bibl>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Inflation at the cross roads :</head>
            <head>INFLATION AT THE CROSS ROADS.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE CORNERS DECIDE FOR INFLATION—THE UNLIMITED TRUST AND CONFIDENCE COMPANY.</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>CONFEDRIT X ROADS, (WICH IS IN THE STATE UV KENTUCKY,) Sept. 23d, 1875.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>The Corners hev red the speeches uv Honest Ole Bill Allen and that other gileless patriot, General Samyooel Cary, uv Ohio, ez well ez the Pennsylvany platform, on the momenchus subjick uv More Money, till they hev bin worked up to a state uv absloot madnis. The Corners are jist the same ez all other impecoonius people—they want More Money, and the idee uv Honest Bill Allen, that, to git it, all yoo hed to do wuz to ishoo it, filled our idees uv finanse eggsackly. It's simple and ezily understood.</p>
                  <p>I determined to put the idee into practice, and to that end sejested to my friends the organizashen uv a Bank uv ishoo, under the name and title uv "The Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company uv Confedrit X Roads."</p>
                  <p>I hed some trouble to git the citizens into it, but I finelly succeeded. I explained to the people that more money wood be an advantage to the debtor class, wich, ez nine-tenths uv em is in debt to Bascom, the grosery keeper, settled em. They hailed with joy any movement that wood wipe out their scores and give em new credit at his bar.</p>
                  <p>To Bascom, and them ez I intended to hev in the management, I showed that more money meant increased trade, and ez the money woodent cost anything but the printin we coodent lose anything. So the Bank wuz started. I wuz made President, Issaker Gavitt, Cashier; Bascom, Vice-President; with a Board uv Directors consistin of ourselves, with Kernel McPelter, and the venerable Deekin Pogram. We put the Deekin on becoz he is bald-headed, and therefore respectable. His biznis is to sit in the front window reedin an inflashen paper. It inspires confidence. Yoo have to watch him to keep him from hevin the paper upside down, but in this community that don't matter, ez very few know the difference more 'n he does. Our<pb n="2-3" xml:id="VAC7104-00000003"/> bankin room is lokatid immejitly under the printin-offis, so we kin let the printed notes which we ishoo down to the President's desk by a rope. This saves labor, wich is a great pint in a instooshen like ours.</p>
                  <p>The theory on wich our paper is ishood is very simple. The Company ishoo it and the people take it. We hev no time fixed for redempshun, for the beauty uv the biznis is that we don't never intend to redeem. Our notes reeds:—</p>
                  <p>"The Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company uv Confedrit X Roads (wich is in the State uv Kentucky) promises to pay the bearer One Dollar."</p>
                  <p>We don't say when, where, or how it is to be redeemed, and therein is the strength uv the enterprise.</p>
                  <p>Our first ishoo wuz reseeved with some hesitashen.</p>
                  <p>"Where is our secoority?" demanded one farmer to whom we offered it in payment for a load uv wheat.</p>
                  <p>"Faith in the company!" I ansered, lookin at him pityinly. "Gaze onto that face," I resoomed, pintin at Deekin Pogram, who ruther spiled the effeck by brushin off a fly that hed lited on his nose; "Look at that face and then ask for secoority."</p>
                  <p>"When is it to be redeemed?" askt another.</p>
                  <p>"It never wants to be redeemed," wuz my anser We shel be libral, and when a note wears out we will give yoo another. Wat do you want it redeemed fur? Money ishood on faith needs no redempshun. We buy yoor prodoose with it—yoo yoose it to buy yoor goods, and so it goes round and round in a cirkle, dispensin blessins wherever it lites. Ez long ez yoo take it wat do yoo want uv anything else?"</p>
                  <p>Another remarkt that it wuz his idee that paper money wuz all to be redeemed in gold.</p>
                  <p>"Gold," I promptly replied, "is played out. Gold is merchandise. Our Democratic brethren in Ohio hev desided that money is simply promises to pay, and that it don't matter on wat material that promise is stampt—whether gold, silver, iron, shells, or copper. We shel put ourn on paper, coz it's the cheapest. We shel hev no extravagance about this bank."</p>
                  <p>Pollock, the Illinoy disturber, in the most brootal manner, refoozed to tech it, and consekently his biznis suffered. One shoemaker from Ohio followed soot and undertook to argoo agin so much money. He asserted the heresy that addin to the volum uv currency didn't add nothin to its power. Sed he:</p>
                  <p>"I will illustrate so the Corners will comprehend. Yoo take a gallon uv whiskey and add to it three gallons uv water. Well, yoo hev four gallons in the barl, but there ain't but wun gallon uv square drunk in it, after all."</p>
                  <p>I ansered him by readin copious extrax from Cary's speeches, showin that troo prosperity goes hand in hand with plenty uv money.</p>
                  <p>They finelly wuz convinst and took our money for their grain, tho we hed to pay them at the beginin twenty cents a bushel more for this wheat than other money wood hev got it for. But we didn't care, for we knew we cood make all uv it we wanted.</p>
                  <p>It wuz astonishin wat a era uv prosperity set in on the Corners to wunst. Money became ez plenty ez blackberries, and everybody hed their pockets full uv it. Land went up in valyoo two hundred per cent. in a week, and the price uv the nessaries uv life raised ekally. Bascom put up his new whiskey from 5 to 25 cents per drink, and sich wuz the run uv trade he hed that his wife and his oldest son, Jefferson Davis Bascom, both hed to stand in the bar to wait on customers. The bank bought all the wheat and other produckshuns, and paid for 'em in its own money, and we paid sich prices ez happened, for money wuz with us no objeck. The high prices brot all the trade for twenty miles around to the Corners, and all the dealers who wood take the money, stood up to their middles in it.</p>
                  <p>Then my turn come. Pintin to the crowds uv people in Bascom's, I sed to the doubter:</p>
                  <p>"Wuz trade ez brisk ez that afore inflashun?"</p>
                  <p>Improvements are bein projected every day. We hev organized a company to build a branch road from here to Secessionville, another over to Bloody Fork, and still another to Little Andersonville. Five turnpike companies hev bin organized, and three factries hev bin actooally commenced. The water power on the Run jist above the village is to be improved to-wunst, and Bascom is alreddy at work on a wing to the back part of the grocery. Town lots are doublin in valyoo every day, and new addishuns are bein perpetyooally laid out. Everybody is spekelatin, and everybody is gettin rich. There is flush times here. The people are all inflashionists.</p>
                  <p>I am President uv all these companies, and I see no reason why I can't put em through. It is troo the price of everything hez gone up. The commonest nigger labor is now up to $8 a<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7104-00000004"/> day, and a pair uv pegged boots is wuth $20, but wat difference does that make? So long ez Simpkins, the printer, kin work his press, we kin manufackter all the money we want; and ez long ez we kin manufackter money, there must be prosperity.</p>
                  <p>Pollock and Joe Bigler we hed to git red uv, for they wuz prejoodissen the people agin us. Pollock's stock uv goods and his store wuz wuth, in the old times, before the era uv inflashun, about a thousand dollars, and Bascom and me and Deekin Pogram went to him and offered him that sum for his property.</p>
                  <p>"Things hez raised," sed he, "and I won't sell for less than $2,500."</p>
                  <p>We promptly accepted that price, and I sent a boy back to the bank with a bushel basket to bring the money. When it come Pollock refoosed to take it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>RETURN OF THE BOY WITH CURRENCY.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>"I want greenbax," sed he.</p>
                  <p>"Our money is jest ez good," sez I.</p>
                  <p>"I know it," sez he,"but I hev a prejoodis for other money."</p>
                  <p>There wuz a crowd about, and it wood never do to acknowledge that any money wuz better 'n ours. I took Bascom one side.</p>
                  <p>"G. W.," sez I, "here is a golden opportunity to do two things. First we git rid uv a disturber, and second we give confidence in our ishoos. Rake up greenbax and pay him in em."</p>
                  <p>G. W. consented, and it wuz done in the presence uv the people.</p>
                  <p>"Yoo see," sed I, "my friends, that we'd jest as soon pay greenbax ez our own money."</p>
                  <p>The crowd wuz re-ashoored and took our bills ez readily ez ever. Pollock and Bigler gave up the property, but they didn't leave the village. On the contrary, they went to the tavern to board and jeered at us wuss than ever. They sed they hed made more money by this transackshen than they hed ever made in the Corners since they hed landed there.</p>
                  <p>Deekin Pogram, Capt. McPelter and Issaker Gavitt hev all paid off mortgages on their farms, and I hev bot a farm and am gettin up plans for a manshun befittin my new position. I am happy and contented. I hev struck my gait. Bank Presidentin soots me—I wuz born for it. Ef I wuz relijusly inclined I shood pray for Willyum Allen until I had corns on both knees.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>PETROLEUM V. NASBY.</signed>
                     <signed>President uv the Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>P. S.—There's a triflin, but still embarrasin, trouble okkurred. The onprecedented run on Bascom in consekence uv the plentifulness uv money exhausted his stock uv likkers yesterday, and he sent to Looisville for more. The likker merchants uv that mersenary city, ez a mere matter uv form, generally require Bascom to pay for goods afore they ship em, to avoid mistakes. He sent on a thousand dollars uv our money, AND THEY REFOOZED TO TAKE IT! Ez he paid all the greenbax he hed to Pollock, he can't get supplies, and the Corners is parched. Wat to do we don't know. We don't see why our money shoodent go in Looisville.</p>
                  <p>It will take two weeks to ship enough grain to Looisville to exchange for the likker, and then comes another terrible quondary. Bascom demands the grain uv the Bank and wants to pay for it in the Bank's ishoos! And he insists on hevin it at wat its wuth in Looisville in greenbax! Finanseerin aint the easiest biznis in the world. Our money startid well enuff on the cirkle, but there seems to be a break in it. Ef we let Bascom hev that<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7104-00000005"/> grain and take our own money for it, were is our profits? Ef we don't let him hev the grain the Corners will die uv drouth! And ef he gits it our money must be taken for it, for it's all he's got. I cood cut the Gorjen knot by failin, but then the wheat wood be attached. I shell hold on and see wat a week will bring forth. Providence never deserted me yit.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>P. V. N.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE FURTHER PROGRESS OF THE UNLIMITED TRUST AND CONFIDENCE COMPANY—ITS CONTINUED SUCCESS.</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>CONFEDRIT X ROADS, (WICH IS IN THE STATE UV KENTUCKY.) Sept. 30, 1875.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Ef life ever wuz a rose tinted dream to me at any time doorin my mortle pilgrimage, this is the precise time, I am thoroly happy—so happy, indeed that the privashens and troubles that I hev been thro are fadin out uv my memory entirely. I hev paid Bascom's account wich hez bin runnin for so many years, and hev his receet in my safe—<emph>my</emph> SAFE I say. Proudly I write them words. MY safe! Who—thirty days ago wood hev supposed, that I should ever say MY SAFE! Then I hev two soots uv cloze—good ones—wich is one and a half more than I hev hed sence I was Postmaster under Johnson—Heven rest his sole—I hev two shirts for the first time in my life, and I am wearin stockins! I hev but one pare ez yet, but one can't rise to the summit uv hooman grandjer at wun bound. I shel buy another pare in a week or two. I think every Bank President ought to either hev two pare uv stockins or return to the stern virchoos uv the Republic in its better days, and go barefoot. Goin barefoot or hevin a change, is necessary to the keepin uv a Bank President's office in a sweet smellin condition.</p>
                  <p>But this is a digreshen. Suffice it to say, I am clothed. I pade three dollars and a half a pare for them stockins—they is cotton—wich is three dollars and a quarter more than they wuz worth in the old money, but what difference does it make. That three dollars and a half wuz made by four pulls on Simpson's printin press, and when money kin be made in that way wat difference does it make wat I pay for cotton sox?</p>
                  <p>At the beginnin' we ishood 10, 20, 25 and 50 cent currency, but we hev quit that. Prices hev gone up so, under the general al prosperity, that there aint anything in the Corners that sells for less than a dollar, and the frackshnel currency wuz desided to be yooselis. Besides, it costs jest ez much to print a ten cent note ez it does a dollar, and we bleeve in economizin.</p>
                  <p>Simpson, the printer, is makin us a little trouble. At the beginnin I yoosed to pay him for printin our bills by jest signin enuff uv em ez they come from the press to make his amount, but lately he hez refoozed to take our money, and insists on greenbax. We tried to overawe him, but when he threatened to publish the finanshel condishun uv the President and Direktors, it wuz considered advisable to humor him. It is singler that sich men throw impediments in the way uv progress.</p>
                  <p>The obstacles in the way uv the Bank that hev thus far developed themselves, hev bin happily and easily removed. Bascom demanded wheat uv us to ship to Looisville to git more whiskey, and we hed to let him hev it, and take pay in our own money. And ez he demanded that we take our own money jest the same ez greenbax, that bein the standard in Looisville, we met a heavy loss. The account stands ez follows: <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1,000 bushels uv wheat cost us in our own money, at $4 50 per bushel</cell>
                           <cell>$4,500 00</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sold it to Bascom at Looisville greenbax prices, wich is $1 per bushel, takin pay in the same money we hed paid for it</cell>
                           <cell>1,000 00</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Loss (wich is easily figgered)</cell>
                           <cell>$3,500 00</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>We hed one more trouble, wich we got on easier with. Pugsby, the shoemaker, who took our money, run out uv leather, and when he sent to Looisville for more, the merchants there, ez in the case uv Bascom, refoozed to take our currency. Pugsby knowd uv Bascom's experience and he came up smilin to hev us sell him wheat enuff at greenbax prices to renoo his stock.</p>
                  <p>"Wat kin we do?" I demanded in dire distress, for really I didn't see why Pugsby shoodent hev wheat to renoo his stock ez well ez Bascom, ceptin that whiskey is more necessary to the Corners than leather.</p>
                  <p>"Do!" sed Issaker Gavitt, with a expreshun uv skorn on his classick feechers."Do! and yoo claim to be finanseers! Hez Pugsby a safe? No? Well, wher does he keep the $12,000 uv our money? In his desk? Yes? And that is wooden? And<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7104-00000006"/> his bildin is wood? Very good. Tell Pugsby to come to-morrer and we will give him wheat at a dollar a bushel for all uv our money he hez got. We hev twenty-four hours, and banks, ez well as nashens kin be saved in twenty-four hours."</p>
                  <p>And Issaker put some matches in his vest pocket—about $3 worth. Matches hez gone up $4.50 a box—our money.</p>
                  <p>That nite Pugsby's shop burnt up and the fire broke out jist under his desk, The next mornin that unforchnit man came to us and insisted on hevin the wheat on the score uv the money he ned uv ours.</p>
                  <p>"Bring us the money," said Issaker, beamin sweetly onto him, "and we'll give yoo all the wheat you want."</p>
                  <p>"But yoo know that I hed yoor money, and that it wuz burnt up last nite.'</p>
                  <p>"I <emph>persoom</emph> you hed some uv our money, but I dont <emph>know</emph> it," replied Issaker. "No well regulated bank kin live if they shood take every man's word, ez you want us to. How kin I tell but wat yoo hev that money concealed, and that the burnin of your shop was a skeem to defrod yoor creditors. I am not shoor that it isn't my dooty to investigate the matter."</p>
                  <p>And Issaker looked so stern that Pugsby left the bank with a howl of terror.</p>
                  <p>Issaker is developin so great a genius in financeerin that I'm reely jealus uv him. He is the master-sperit of the institooshun.</p>
                  <p>At the Board meetin last nite we discust wat we shood do in sich cases ez Pugsby's hereafter, but arrived at no definit conclooshun. There is several uv em, and they will hev to be met. Issaker bleeves in the style uv treatment he yoosed in Pugsby's case, but I can't consent to it. Its heroic, I admit, and good enuff for a temprary expedient, but it won't do for a reglar system. Ef our money stimoolates a man's biznis to the pint of his bildin a new house, we hev benefitted him, and the commoonity ez well. But ef to avoid the inconvenience uv redeemin that money we hev to burn the house, wat good hev we accomplished! None. We hev got to find some other way. I don't see any other way, but no doubt it will sejest itself to me in time.</p>
                  <p>It is astonishin how the Corners is boomin, now that it hez money enuff. Five new ralerodes are bein built, twenty new turnpikes, one hundred and twenty-eight cellers for new houses is bein dug, and last week the corner-stuns for eight factrys wuz lade with approprit ceremonies. The gradin is bein dun on the ralerodes and turnpikes, and that part uv the work will be pushed to an early compleshun, for the labrers furnish their own shovels and picks and take our money for wages. The labrers buy their livin uv the farmers along the line with that money, and then the farmers come to the Corners with it, and cheer their soles at Bascom's.</p>
                  <p>So far, all is serene and sweet. So far the money sheds blessins. ez a skunk does perfoom. But at this pint comes worry. Wat is Bascom to do with it? The Looisville merchants refooz to tech it for likker, and we can't afford to give him wheat at Looisville prices agin. We wood bild a distillery, but, alas! we can't pay for the nails, the glass and the stillin apparatus in our money, and we ain't got any other. But, thanks to an overulin Providence, Bascom hez enuff likker to last two weeks, and suthin will turn up afore that is gone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>NASBY PERSUADED TO LEAVE MCPELTER'S WATCH.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prices hev gone up so that it takes a vast volume uv currency to transact the biznis uv the Corners. Simpson's hand-press won't anser the demands made onto it, and he hez purchased a power-press, wich will print 1,000 sheets an hour. And to facilitate biznis, and to make it perfeckly shoor that we shell hev all the currency we want, I hev hed my name and Issaker's engraved,<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7104-00000007"/> so that it kin be printed in, thus saving us the trouble uv signin em with a pen.</p>
                  <p>Prices uv things is still mountin up, and general prosperity prevails. Pugsby gits $40 a pare now for pegged boots a great deal eazier that he yoost to git $4, and Bascom hez put drinks up to 50 cents for new whiskey, and 75 when you take sugar in it. Lots in the corporashun hez quadroopled in valyoo within the week, and reel estate is changin hands lively. I cood wish, however, that the ishoos uv the Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company cood hev a wider circulashen. I took a brief vacashun this week, wuz at the Glauber Salt Springs, and wuz beaten out uv $200 at cut-throat loo. The gamblers refoozed to take my money, and I was compelled to leave my watch with em; that is, Captain McPelter's watch, which I hed borrowed, to make an imposin appearance. But it wuz all the same to me, ez I paid him for it in our own currency. I wuz sorry to lose it, for I had depended on that watch to help us out when we got into a very tite place.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>PETROLEUM V. NASBY.</signed>
                     <signed>President of the Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>P. S.—Another trouble is loomin up on the horizon. Perkins, the blacksmith, is out uv iron, and Sampsell, the carpenter, hez to hev a jack-plain and two augers, all uv wich hez to be got in Looisville, and they demand uv us sich money ez Looisville will take. Then another mortifyin circumstance happened yesterday. The Directers uv the Bank hed determined to lay the corner stun uv our new bankin edifis, wich we hev commenst, but after announsin the ceremony we coodent lay it. A bigger rope than any in the Corners, wuz nessary to lift the massive stun to its place, (we hed it massive ez an emblem uv our solidity,) but we coodent rake up enuff currency that they'd take in Looisville to buy one. So that corner stun ain't laid, and the work on the buildin, I spose, will hev to stop till we kin turn up suthin. Ther's a crisis approachin.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>P. V. N.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE PROGRESS OF INFLATION—THE TROUBLE THAT PERKINS STARTED—THE PRESENT STATUS OF THE GREAT IDEA.</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>CONFEDRIT X ROADS, (WICH IS IN THE STATE UV KENTUCKY,) Oct. 5, 1875.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>I hev hed trouble enough with the unenlitened people uv these Corners, for the past week, to nearly drive me mad. Indeed, I shood hev bin in a loonatic asylum ere this, hed I not bin sustained and soothed by an onlimited faith in the correctnis uv the doctrines uv the Ohio Dimocrisy, ez regards money. And feelin that I wuz assistin, in my humble way, in puttin them doctrines into practis, I determined not to go mad, but to persevere even unto the end.</p>
                  <p>But the perverse people are doin ther level best to drive me crazy, and I am not shoor that they won't succeed. I bought a pare uv horses uv one uv em for $8,000, and paid him in our own money He thot he'd rather not tech it.</p>
                  <p>"When will this be redeemed?" he askt, innocently.</p>
                  <p>"Any time you want it," I replied.</p>
                  <p>"In wat?" he retorted.</p>
                  <p>"In other notes onto the same bank," sez I.</p>
                  <p>"And how will yoo redeem them notes?" sez he.</p>
                  <p>"In jist the same way," sez I.</p>
                  <p>"Then all ther is uv it," sez he, "yoo go on takin up one note by givin another, and all uv em without interest nor nothin."</p>
                  <p>"That's it eggsackly," sed I. "Yoo see, cant yoo, or are yoo an ijeot? that money means faith. Now ef the proud finanshel instooshin in wich I am the hed, ishoos its note, yoo must hev faith that it will pay, and so long ez yoo hev that faith, and everybody else hez that faith, so that they take it for money, yoo never want the money on it. So long ez money is taken, yoo don't want it redeemed, for it is good enuff, yoo see! Our money is made good by faith—and ez long ez it is sustaned by faith it will go. When the notes yoo hev now wears out, come to us and we will redeem em with new ones. But evrybody must hev faith. Cant yoo see it? EVRYBODY MUST HEV FAITH! Faith in the ishoos uv this bank uv ourn is nessary to its success and stability. Faith in our money is, ez it is in Religion, the substance uv things hoped for, and the evidence uv things not seen, only more so. Wait till I git $8,000 from the printin offis, and take em for yoor hosses, and go yoor way. Hev faith."</p>
                  <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7104-00000008"/>
                  <p>Perkins, that wuz the farmer's name, took the money and went his way, ponderin ez he went. He walked down to Bascom's with deep lines uv thot onto his face, wich resolved itself into a expreshun uv stern determinashen ez he went in.</p>
                  <p>"Kin yoo sell me a barl uv whisky to-day—a entire barl?"</p>
                  <p>"Certinly," sed G. W., smilingly, "certinly, Mr. Perkins. It's only worth $40 a gallon, or $1,680.00 per barl this mornin."</p>
                  <p>"I'll take a barl," sed Perkins.</p>
                  <p>"All rite," wuz G. W.'s response. "I'd ez soon sell a barl to-wunst ez by the single drink."</p>
                  <p>So G. W. and his wife, and his oldest son Jefferson Davis, rolled a barl up into Perkinses wagon, and Perkins remarkt that he wanted to pay for that likker on the spot. Bascom smiled pleasantly. There wuz nothin so pleasant, Perkins continyood, ez payin for things wen yoo get em, ez it saves bookkeepin and vexashus troubles uv all kinds.</p>
                  <p>"Give me pen, ink and paper, G. W.," sed this Perkins.</p>
                  <p>Nonplushed, Bascom did so mechanically, and Perkins ran his tongue out, ez people do in the Corners when they attempt writin, and after thirty minits uv intense labor, with swet a rollin from his brow fearful, he handed Bascom this dokeyment:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <opener>
                                 <dateline>CONFEDRIT X ROADS, Sept. 1, 1875.</dateline>
                              </opener>
                              <p>I promise to pay G. W. Bascom sixteen hundred and eighty dollars.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>JEHIAL PERKINS.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>"Wats this?" askt the astonished Bascom, with an expreshen uv intense disgust usurpin the place uv the smile.</p>
                  <p>"Pay for that likker," replied Perkins, calm ez a Joon mornin.</p>
                  <p>"But this ain't pay—it's yoor promise to pay, and yoo ain't got time nor place fixed for payment—yoo ain't got no interest exprest, nor nothin. Wen do yoo perpose to pay it?"</p>
                  <p>"Never, G. W., never. Under the noo dispensashen, promises to pay is money. All you want is faith. So long ez yoo bleeve that that paper is money, wat do yoo want uv money? With faith enuff that paper is money. I hev bin figgerin this matter out in my intellek ever sence I hev bin takin yoor bank money. It's all the same. Ef I hev faith in yoor money yoo must hev faith in mine. Wen this note wears out come to me and I will write yoo a new one. And don't keep it too long—I shel take pleasure in writin yoo notes often, so that they will alluz be new and pleasant to look at. How pleasant it is, Bascom, to pay ez yoo go! How much better I feel to pay on the nale, and how much better yoo must feel to hev yoor cash wen yoo deliver yoor goods."</p>
                  <p>And Perkins drove off with the likker, lite-hearted, leavin Bascom dumfounded in the door uv the grosery, gaspin with astonishment and blind with rage.</p>
                  <p>Perkins didn't stop with a barl uv likker. He bot a pare uv pegged boots for $80, and pade for em in the same way, and a kag uv nails, and two soots uv cloze, and calico dresses for his wife and dawters, and a box uv paper collars, and a neck-tie, things he hed never dreemed uv hevin before, and he got so eggscited at his success in finanseerin that he went home drunk ez a biled owl.</p>
                  <p>But the misery uv all this is, every cuss within five miles, seein Perkinses success, is doin the same thing, and an immense volyoom uv wat I may call indivijjle currency is afloat. And they is seriously thretnin to vote to hev the corprashen take the stuff for taxes! The idee uv takin money for taxes that ain't printed, and that heznt got no President and Casheer and Board uv Direkters! There is sich a thing ez carryin this thing too fur.</p>
                  <p>But prosperity continoos her stimulatin rain. We ishood thirty thousand dollars uv our money last week, and the benefishle effeck is visible. Wheat is now $12 a bushel, likker $1 a drink plain, and $1.50 to them ez take sugar in theirn, pegged boots is $80, cotton sox $4, and town lots—well, any price that one chooses to ask for em. The diggin uv cellars is goin on satisfactorily, ez is evrything else that we kin pay for in our own money. But I tremble with apprehensions. Wat will happen when they come to want the lumber, and nales, and glass, and other things wich hev to come from Looisville! That's the gost that hants me.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>PETROLEUM V. NASBY,</signed>
                     <signed>President uv the Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>P. S.—The most wonderful effeck uv inflashen wuz showd this mornin on Deekin Pogram. The old saint made his appearance at the bank in a noo soot uv cloze wich Mirandy, his dawter, got for him. The old man tried to keep up under it, <unclear>but</unclear> finelly broke down. He refoozed to stay in his seet unless we'd<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7104-00000009"/> take off the coat, pull off his boots, and "them d—d stockins," <figure>
                        <head>DEAKIN POGRAM REDUCED TO HIS NORMAL CONDITION.</head>
                     </figure> ez he expressed it, and drip some tobacker joose over his buzm. He swore that he ruther resine his posishen than to wear boots and stockins in the summer time, and ez for paper collars he'd wear none uv em. He wood hev gone insane ef we hedn't stript him and got him back to his normel style. Wat a difference there is in men! Now I took to stockins when I got to be President uv this bank ez naterally ez tho I hed alluz wore em. But I hev moved in better society than the Deekin hez. He is trooly a child uv Nacher.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>P. V. N.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>FURTHER INFLATION—FOUR NEW BANKS—AND, FINALLY, EVERY MAN HIS OWN BANKER.</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>CONFEDRIT X ROADS, (WICH IS IN THE STATE UV KENTUCKY,) October 12, 1875.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>The man wich undertakes to benefit his fellows loads up a very heavy contrack. Half the citizens ov the Corners are a-goin back in the most ongrateful manner onto the Onlimited Confidence and Trust Company. They are a gettin $19 a bushel for wheat, and about the same for oats and corn, aad men now talk uv thousands wich never before knowd how to pronounce the word, but yet they ain't happy. They hev a hankerin after redempshun uv some sort—they demand to know when this money uv ourn is again to be redeemed in suthin else—some other kind uv money—ez tho our money, backed by faith, wuznt ez good ez any in the world. Ef these malcontents wood only take it and look pleasant, there woodent be any trouble about it.</p>
                  <p>But these men are not the worst we hev to contend with. The citizens wich are the stanchest supporters uv the new money hev determined that, ef we hev the rite to ishoo money, they hev the same rite. And so four noo banks hev bin started this week.</p>
                  <p>Mackey and Burns started one, with Mackey ez President and Burns ez Cashier, with them and a nigger carpenter ez the Board of Direkters. They hev got the drop on us by requirin the officers to give bonds, wich they accomplished by hevin Mackey sign Burn's, Burns sign Mackey's, and both sign the nigger carpenter's. Then they hev another advantage over us, for they bought their own press and print their own notes, wich, ez we hev to pay Simpson, the printer, a profit, enables em to make money cheeper than we kin. They call their institooshun "The Nashnel Benefit Assoshashen," and hev their bankin offis in Mackey's bed-room in the Pogram House.</p>
                  <p>Scarsely wuz this bank histin out money afore Squire Pettus and Gedney the shoemaker started another wich they called "The Blessin Diffusin Bank uv North Ameriky," with the offis in Gedney's shoe shop, and they got ahead uv us by printin their notes in two colors, which, I must say, gives em a solvent look.</p>
                  <p>By this time wheat went up to $25 a bushel, and scase at that.</p>
                  <p>Then Parkins and Barney, the plasterers, who hed made a great deal uv money since inflashen set in, <emph>they</emph> hed to start a bank, wich they called "The Ekitable and Insashable Bankin Company uv the Yoonited States," and they ishood their bills by the bushel.</p>
                  <p>Wheat went up immejitly to $38 per bushel, and a noo era uv prosperity sot in.</p>
                  <p>Before these finanseers hed got fairly under way, Butts and Busterd conclooded they'd go into bankin, and behold one mornin the bills uv the "Labor Stimyoolatin Company—I. Butts, President"—made their appearance. They didn't hev<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7104-00000010"/> any offis, for Buts sed he didnt see no yoose uv an offis. He cood pay out money on the street all he wanted to ef the people wood take it, and ez it never wuznt a goin to be redeemed, wat did he want uv an offis? He wuznt a goin to any sich expense, for he bleeved in economizin. To go to yooselis expenses wuz to show a culpable disregard uv the interests uv the people. Wheat went up to $45 per bushel, and there wuz more prosperity.</p>
                  <p>Then trouble set in in chunks. The people who wuz not interested in bankin refoozed, pint blank, to take any uv their ishoos. Banks wuz a gettin rather too frekent. A reackshen okkured agin our money wich we who wuz interested determined to crush to-wunst.</p>
                  <p>The offiishls uv the five banks in the town met and decided to hold a meetin uv the citizens, at wich steps shood be taken to legalize our ishoos.</p>
                  <p>The meetin wuz held, and uv course we kerried it without any trouble, for seven-tenths uv em hed our money in their pockets, and they wuz very favorable to any ackshen that wood keep it a bilin. To that end we past the follerin resolooshens:</p>
                  <p>WAREAS. The Democrisy uv Ohio and Pennsylvany, with a singerly just appreshiashen uv the wants uv the citizens uv the Cross Roads, hev demanded more money, and</p>
                  <p>WAREAS, Five compinies hev kerried out the idee uv the Democrisy uv Ohio and Pennsylvany by furnishin the people more money, and</p>
                  <p>WAREAS, Notwithstandin the onparalleled prosperity that hez resulted from the increase in currency, certin men in the commoonity, by refoozing to take it, decline to be benefited; therefore, be it</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, That this meetin uv citizens demand uv the Town Council that it to-wunst convene and pass an ordnance makin the ishoos uv the five banks legal tender for everything from drinks down to taxes, and that any citizen who refoozes to take it, or murmurs at it, or in any way discredits it, shel be held ez a public enemy and be immejitly hung.</p>
                  <p>The whereases and the resolooshen wuz passed to-wunst, and I felt easier. With the power to hang all wich refooze to take our money, I rather think I kin make it current. A rope over the limb uv a tree is a persuader of rare merit, and it is the best endorsement uv our paper that we kin possibly hev.</p>
                  <p>So far so good. But jist ez I wuz feelin good over my success cess, that onmitigated cuss, Jehial Perkins, the man wat give his note to Bascom for a barl uv whisky with sich distinguished success, rose and sed he hed a series of whererases and a resolooshen to pass. He went on to say that he hed given this question of finance a great deal uv study. He endorsed fully the posishen uv the Dimocrisy uv Ohio and Pennsylvany. He bleeved in more money—money enuff for everybody. He pinted with pride to the development uv the Corners since the creashun uv more money, and he bleeved that still more money would make still more prosperity. The idee wuz correct. The Government shood ishoo promises to pay and faith shood make em good, without any sich nonsense ez redeemin and if the Government shood do it why shoodnt banks; if banks why not indivijles? That's what he wanted to know. Ef ther wuz any sich thing ez redeemin uv it in gold or anything else the people mite hev the rite to ask if them ez ishoo the money hed gold or anything else to redeem em with, but ez ther ain't no redeemin perposed why that question dont come in. The people hev to hev faith, and that's all the hevin ther is in the transackshen. He wuz a bleever in more money and he perposed to hev more money, and he bleeved that them ez hed the greatest need for money shood hev the privilege uv ishooin it, and so long ez the people took it from each other it ansered all the perposes uv money. Therefore he perposed the yoonanimus adopshun uv the followin wherases and resolooshen:</p>
                  <p>WAREAS, Ef yoo hev a good thing yoo can't hev too much uv it; and</p>
                  <p>WAREAS, The increese uv currency in the Corners hez bin productive uv prosperity sich ez we never dreemed uv; and</p>
                  <p>WAREAS, It is the dooty uv all earthly guvernments to diffoose its blessins ekally, therby imitatin the doos of heaven, wich falls alike on the just and onjust; and</p>
                  <p>WAREAS, The manufakter uv money shood not be confined to the few, but shood be the privilege uv the many; and</p>
                  <p>WAREAS, We rekognize the justis and propriety uv compellin the people to take sich money ez may be ishood; therefore, be it</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, That every man may ishoo his notes uv hand, in sich sums ez may soot his interest or convenience, and that sich notes shel be legal tender fur everything, the same ez the notes ishood by our five bankin institooshuns.</p>
                  <p>And the d—d ideots abslootly passed the resolooshen without a minit's delay, and they demandid that the Council meet that very nite and pass the ordinance, wich it did.</p>
                  <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7104-00000011"/>
                  <p>Ez every last man uv em commenst writin notes to wunst, and buyin all sorts uv things with em, we're liable to hev enuff money at the Corners immejitly—ez much ez our brethren in Ohio and Pennsylvany wood desire, even.</p>
                  <p>Everything in the shape uv labor hez bin abandoned, for everybody hez gone into the manufakter uv currency, that is, everybody who kin write. Thank Heaven that they never favored skools here—the inability to shed ink is the only limit to our inflashen.</p>
                  <p>One singler result hez followed this ordinance, viz: Nobody hez nothin to sell. I went into a shoe store yesterday, thinkin to treat myself to a pare of boots, but the dealer hadn't any to sell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>NASBY WANTS TO INVEST IN BOOTS, BUT FAILS.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>"But I see a hundred pare on the shelves," sed I.</p>
                  <p>"They hev all bin bought by people over in the next county," sed this villin; "they wuz bought for gold. Possibly ef yoo hed gold I cood get one uv em to sell you a pare hisself."</p>
                  <p>And he sed suthin about bringing a horse to water, but yoo coodent make him drink.</p>
                  <p>It is plain to me that more legislashun is a goin to be necessary. Up to a certain pint they took our money, but somehow them ez aint a makin it are a fitin shy uv it.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>PETROLEUM V. NASBY,</signed>
                     <signed>President uv the Onlimited Trust Confidence Company.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>P. S.—More trouble. Bascom sez he's got to hev something to go to Loossville with besides our paper, or he'll have to close. And all the mechanics in the village, who hev to buy things in Looisville, are clamorin for suthin they kin buy with, and threaten, ef they dont get it, to bust things. Wun uv em impudently sed that afore the inflation period they didn't hev much money, but they cood do suthin with wat they hed. And the people applauded the disturber.</p>
                  <p>2d P. S.—Bascom hez jest come in. His likker is neerly gone, and he swears he'll close his bar ef we don't do suthin to-wunst. I hev called a meetin of the Direkters. Ef Bascom closes we are lost for ever. The Corners kin get on with any thing but that. I kin get on awhile, for I hev a jug in reserve, but Heven help them who is not pervided,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>P. V. N.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE END OF THE "ONLIMITED TRUST AND CONFIDENCE COMPANY"—THE FINAL SMASH-UP.</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>CONFEDRIT X ROADS, (WICH IS IN THE STATE UV KENTUCKY,) October 20, 1875.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>There is gloom onto the Corners! Our sun uv prosperity is sot, and my hopes is blasted. The Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company is not eggsackly no more, but it's near enuff dead to make it safe to bury it on a vencher. Its eyes is sot. After a brilyant career uv five weeks, coruscatin along the sky uv finance, sheddin a perfect rain uv blessins at every jump, its lite hez gone, its brilyancy hez departed, and it don't coruscate worth a cent.</p>
                  <p>We hevn't suspended, nor failed, nor closed our doors, nor nothin, for the simple reason that the bank wuz constructed on an ijee that made failin impossible, and the closin uv doors on-necessary. Ez we don't hev to redeem, wat shel we fail for? Ez we don't perpose to pay nothin, wat shel we close our doors for? Ther aint nothin hide-bound about this bank. The people is welcome to come in and discuss finance, and put ther feet up on the benches, and spit terbacker jooce all over the floor, jest as frendly as they choose, and they may do it ez long ez they choose.</p>
                  <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7104-00000012"/>
                  <p>No, the Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company ain't failed, but it's kinder petered out, ez it were. It is expirin uv dry rot. Its notes, wich is its blud, ain't hevin any cirkelashen. The people don't take em with that cheerfulness nessary to a proper bankin bizness. Legislashen don't fetch em. The ordinances, wich made death the penalty for refoosin our ishoos, only workt so far ez takin uv em for taxes. The corporashen did take em for takes in pursooance uv their own legislashen, and here wuz where the trouble begun. The taxes wuz levied on a greenback basis, and the entire levy amounted to $8,000. Well, the taxes for the first time in the histry uv the Corners wuz all pade in full, and with great promptness. A more prompter set uv taxpayers I never seed.</p>
                  <p>The treasurer hed $8,000 uv our ishoos when it becum nessary to buy a plow and four spades to do some work on the roads. In vane he tried to git em. The dealers at home, knowin wat currency he hed to pay in, suddenly got out uv plows and spades, and when he went to Looisville it took $1,000 in our currency to pay his fare, and he offered the hardware dealer the other $7,000 for the implements he wanted, but it woodent go. He hed to come back without em.</p>
                  <p>Then he came and demanded some currency uv us wich he cood yoose, wich uv course we hedn't got none, and he becum an opponent to our system.</p>
                  <p>Two shoemakers, each with $70,000 uv our money, coodent buy a side uv sole leather to continyoo ther bizniss with, and hed to stop, our ralerodes and turnpikes hed to stop, becoz, hevin got to the pint wher we hed to hev iron and nales and sich things, we coodent go on. So all the labrers hed to be discharged, which made a desprit populashen, all howlin agin us.</p>
                  <p>But the wust wuz yet to come. We cood hev wethered all this, but alas! BASCOM FAILED.</p>
                  <p>This wuz the finishin blow—the great staggerer wich the Corners cood not possibly recover from.</p>
                  <p>Bascom made a manly fite, and I must say did all that he cood to stand up for us. He raised the price uv drinks to $2 a drink, and when he saw his barls rapidly failin he tried to keep the Corners agoin, by waterin his likker ez we hed watered the currency.</p>
                  <p>But theze expedient didn't work. The higher the price he put on his likker the more the people seemed to want to drink uv it. It seemed to be a delite to em to pay out our money ef they got anything watever for it. But they woodent do wat Bascom most desired—that is to say, they woodent stand his watered whiskey. They sed to him, "Ef $2 a drink ain't high enuff, charge $4. It's all wun to us. Set em up agin."</p>
                  <p>And the bar-room full wood step up and take suthin, and the man who askt em wood throw down on the bar a peck of our currency and tell Bascom to help himself.</p>
                  <p>Bascom come to us and begged that we shood let him hev suthin that he cood yoose to re-stock his bar. He sed the dealers in Looisville laffed in his face when he offered em our money for likker, and he had but two barls left.</p>
                  <p>And them two barls wuz vizably shrinkin every minit. It seemed ez though the populis got insane for likker at the very time when we didn't want em to hev it. For the first time in my life, I wanted the Corners to be temprit, for every drop drunk from those barls brought our bank that much nearer its end. I sot opposite Bascom's, and saw the crowd go in with a sinkin sensashen that wuz akin to death. Drink by drink it went, and, ez ef they coodent eggsaust it fast enough by the single drink, they got to comin for it in tin dippers.</p>
                  <p>"How does it hold out?" wuz the message I sent him at 10 A. M.</p>
                  <p>The answer come prompt:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>"10.5 A. M. Wun barl untutched, twenty gallons in the other and sinkin every minit.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>B."</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Then I sent this:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>"10.10. Fill her up with water. Keep Jeffson Davis a pourin in. Hold the fort.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>N."</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>And the answer come:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>"10-15. Jeffson Davis is a histin in water ez fast ez he kin carry it. Mrs. Bascom is a rinsin out old barls, to which she adds kyan pepper and camfene. Ef I hed some Scotch snuff it wood help. Will hold out ez long ez it's possible. But it's terrible. A man jist come in and demandid a gallon.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>B."</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Twenty minits thereafter Bascom sent this:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>"Hev jist put a spiggot in the last barl, and the Corners is a howlin. It won't last an hour.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>B."</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Then an expedient segested itself to me. I sent this note:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>"Time is everything. Bust the spiggot.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>N."</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7104-00000013"/>
                  <p>Wich he did, thus keepin the wolves at bay for an hour, while it wuz bein repaired.</p>
                  <p>But why harrow the public buzum with the detales uv this painful story? The end wuz inevitable. Drop by drop, drink by drink, pint by pint, that likker wuz ebbin away, and each drop weakened the bank. That likker wuz our life-blud, and ez it flowed we wilted.</p>
                  <p>Waterin the barl wuz merely a palliative; and it wuz with a feelin uv relief that I saw Geo. W. throw up his hands and exclaim: "It's all gone but a gallon, wich I shel keep for my own yoose. It's all gone, and I can't get another drop in Looisville."</p>
                  <p>And he dropt his head despondinly on a pile uv about $12,000 uv our currency, wich he hedn't taken off the bar, and wept despondinly.</p>
                  <p>"Why can't yoo get more?" demanded the excited populis.</p>
                  <p>"Becoz I ain't got no money but this, and yoo coodent get a barl uv whiskey in Looisville for a car load uv it."</p>
                  <p>I attempted to reason with the people. I told em that one reason uv our wealth wuz that we hed it in a currency that we coodent send away from home, thus keepin our capitul within ourselves, but they refoozed to listen to me. They d—d my bank, they d—d me, and they went for the bank, swearin that ef ther wuz anything there that cood be converted into likker Bascom shood hev it. It is onnessary to remark that they didn't find anything. Antissipatin an onpleasantnis, we hed removed the valyooables to a place uv safety, wich wuz the underside uv my bed at Deekin Pogram's.</p>
                  <p>Then they demanded that the money they held be redeemed into suthin they cood yoose, but uv course we declined to discuss the matter, referrin them to the terms uv the ishoo ez expressed on the notes, ez well ez ther own endorsement uv the skeem.</p>
                  <p>But this didn't satisfy em. They delibrately brought out $675,000 uv the ishoos uv the various banks, and pilin uv it up on the street, sot fire to it, dancin a demoniac danc around it. This amoozed me, for uv course I hed no earthly objeckshen to ther redeemin uv it in that way, but when I seed em riggin ropes to the trees in the visinity, I remarkt to my fellow-officers: "Gentlemen, yoor President hez pressin biznis in yonder forest," and I got out ez rapidly ez my poor wastid lims wood permit. I flatter myself that I made tollable time for a man uv my age, whose strength is mostly in his stumick. Indeed, wen I turned and saw ten or a dozen uv the foremost men uv the Corners clost behind me, and all shoutin "Hang the d—d thief!" no gentle gazelle that I ever heerd uv ever skimmed the plain ez I did. I did not cease runnin till I got into the middle uv the big swamp.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>THE RETREAT OF THE FINANCIER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wat become uv the other drekters I don't know. The last fond look that I turned toards the bank I saw Issaker Gavitt and Deekin Pogram strugglin in the hands uv the mob, wich wuz playfully forcin uv em to sit down on a burnin pile uv ther own currency.</p>
                  <p>I am in a deserted hut in the swamp, wich wuz yoosed by runaway niggers in the old times, and am fed by a nigger farmer, who hez not heerd uv the collapse, and consekently takes his pay in the Onlimited. Ef the nooze ever gets to him uv the reel condishen uv things and he shets off supplies, or reveels my whereabouts, I am a lost man.</p>
                  <p>Wat changes ther is in life? A week ago a successful finanseer, and the pet uv the populis—the Saviour uv the Corners!<pb n="24" xml:id="VAC7104-00000014"/> To-day a hunted fugitive, livin on hoe-cake furnished by a nigger. One needs to be a filosopher.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>PETROLEUM V. NASBY,</signed>
                     <signed>Late President uv the Onlimited Trust and Confidence Company.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>N. B.—I hev heerd from the Corners. The ungrateful people, after half killin the officers uv the bank, passed resolooshens that we wuz all a pack up theeves, and that them ez had sold land and sich for our money shood soo for recovery thereof, and that they'd hang any judge wich woodent deside agin us. Bascom hez gone back onto us, and hez sold back to Pollock and Bigler the store we bot uv em, and hez got greenbax enuff to git a few barls uv likker, and hez re-opened. He hez put the price uv likker down to five cents agin, and refoozes to take anything for it but nickels and postal currency. He sez he ain't gittin ez many cart-loads uv money ez he did in the inflashen period, but he's satisfied. The most uv the citizens is bankrupt, and rooin is evrywhere. Oh why did their faith give out at the wrong time!</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>P. V. N.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>