<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7564">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Peter Gott, the Cape Ann Fisherman </title>
            <author>Reynolds, J. (d. 1872)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7564</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2021</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Peter Gott, the Cape Ann fisherman</title>
                  <author>Reynolds, J. (d. 1872)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xii 280 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Proctor</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Gloucester </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1856">1856</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-02-06">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Peter Gott, the Cape Ann fisherman</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7564-00000001"/>PETER GOTT, THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   BY J. REYNOLDS, M D. GLOUCESTER: PROCTOR &amp; BROTHERS. 1856.  -  &#xD;<pb n="-3 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7564-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress in the year 1856, by JOHN P. JEWETT &amp; COMPANY, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the District of Massachusetts.  AMERICAN STEREOTYE COMPANY, 28 PHOENIX BUILDING, CORNER OF DEVONSHRE STREET AND EXCHANGE PLACE, BOSTON. PRINTED BY D. S. FORD AND COMPANY.    CONTENTS. INTRODUCTION,   .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  7 CHAPTER I. Winter fishing.-Pigeon Cove.-Gloucester Harbor, .  13 CHAPTER II. Mr. Dennis.-Sandy Bay.--An incident of the last war with Great Britain.-Fishermen and their owners.- Settlement of Cape Ann, .  .  .    .  .  26 CHAPTER III. Peter's parents.-His father goes to the Banks.--Bank fishing,                      36 CHAPTER IV' Fishermen's grub.-Fogs.-The Grand Banlis.-Troll fishing,   .  .   .. .  .  .       52 (3)  &#xD;<pb n="iv (Table of Contents) -v (Table of Contents) "
                   xml:id="VAC7564-00000003"/> Iv          aCONTENTS. CHAPTER V. Peter's father lost on the Banks.--The vessel returns to Pigeon Cove.-The news of a man lost, reaches there before her, .   .  .  . .  .         63 CHAPTER VI. Mr. Dennis informs Peter's mother of her sad loss.-  Kind   neighbors.-The afflictions of the poor.-A widow's struggles, ,and her reward, .  .  .  .  75 CHAPTER    VII. Peter's boyhood.-His early education.-Engages in shore fishing.-Visit to the harbor with his mother, .   87 CHAPTER    VIII. Hake fishing.-Making isinglass, .9. 98 CHAPTER IX. Peter's first trip to the Banks.-How the earnings of Bank fishermen are divided.--Peter's care for his family. Second trip.-A  storm, and its consequences, . . 107 CHAPTER X. Pollock fishing.-Lobster catching.-Poiitical troubles, . 120 CHAPTER XI. Peter ships on board a  privateer.-Is taken and carried to Halifax.--Dartmoor prison, . .  .      131   CONTENTS'.            V CHAPTER XII. Return home.-Changes at home, .   .  .  .    144 CHAPTER XIII. Peter becomes skipper of a fishing vessel.-Labrador fishing.-Clannish feeling.-Peter builds a house, and marries a wife, . .  .  .  .  .  . * .  151 CHAPT:ER XIV. Mackerel fishing.--Peter's enterprize.-Bait mills, . 164 CHAPTER XV. Smuggling.-Treaties.-Revenue cutters,  .  .  . 1" CHAPTER XVI.  Peter thinks of quitting fishing.-Goes one trip more.-- A terrible storm,  .  .   ..  .  .  .  189 CHAPTER -XVll. Kindness of the people of Prince Edward's Island.-The stormi ceases.-They repair damages as far as they can, and return home.-The loss of a year's work, . 213 CHAPTER    XtVII. Peter Gott builds a vessel after a hew model.-Goes to the Banks in her, and to the Bay of St. Lawrence again. -Bounty laws, .     .     .  .  .    226 1*  &#xD;<pb n="vi (Table of Contents) -7" xml:id="VAC7564-00000004"/> vi.    -     CONTENTS. \ CHAPTER XIX. Forms a partnership with Mr. Dennis.-His family.- Schools.--A busy life.,-Dissolves partnership.--A new. store and a new firm.-Voyage to the West Indies,  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  242 CHAPTER XX. Mullet fishing.-Clam digging.-Peter Gott gradually withdraws from the business of the firm.-Becomes a cultivator of the soil.-Goes to the legislature.--His character, and the closing scenes of his life, . . 256 *   IN TR O D U C T I O N. THE object of the following pages is to exhibit the every-day life of the fishermen, whether ashore, on the Banks, or at the Bay. The incidents are not fictitious, are not exaggerated, are not too highly colored. They may not have occurred in the exact chronological order in which they are here set down, but hundreds of fishermen can tes- tify to their truth, from their own experience. Very few of his fellow citizens understand any thing of the nature of the employment by which the fisherman is enabled to draw his daily bread from the briny deep. Some may have dozed- over the pages of " gentle Isaak Walton," and enjoyed the pictures of still life, which he has so graphically (7)  &#xD;<pb n="viii-ix" xml:id="VAC7564-00000005"/> Viii     INTRODUCTION. drawn. They see the old man seated under the shade of a decayed willow, in the quiet autumn days, or stretched at length on the grassy brink of some gently flowing stream, watching his baited hook,-and they will think they have some idea of fishing. Others may have whiled away some hours, with a pleasant companion, on a cloudy morning, angling for trout or pickerel, and think they know something about fishing. Some may have visited the shore, in the sultry days of August, to enjoy the cool breezes from the sea;--they may have sailed out into the bay, with a fishing party, under the care of a trusty skipper, furnished with all the fixings necessary to enable them to have a good time, and returned at evening, tired with the- day's -sport,-and this is all they know of the life of the fisherman. Landsmen, I .believe, generally suppose that fishermen pursue their business only in pleasant weather, when the sun shines, and the waves are calm around them. Little do they think of the storms, the howling winds, the heaving billows, the rock-bound coast; the long, dark nights, the   INTRODUCTION.         ix anxious hours and days and weeks, in which they stand their watch, battling with unremitting strife and sleepless eyes, the fiercely assailing waves. They are lying to, on George's Bank, in a stormy night. They must keep their little craft head on to the sea. If they suffer it to broach to for a moment, the coming wave, thundering and roaring. with 'its foaming crest higher than the head of their mast, may bury them many fathoms' deep beneath the green waters. A watchful eye, a steady hand an'd a bold heart needs the, fisherman on such a night as this. He thinks not of him- self alone; his: thoughts are with the loved ones at home; and he knows, too, that they are think- ing of him,--that their prayers are besieging the throne of Mercyin his behalf.  He, too, prays to the God of the orphan and widow, for he - doubts if he shall see his wife and- children again. O, how 'he longs for the morning! And when it comes, it brings him no relief from his life-struggle. He rises upon the crest of a mountain wave, and far as his eye can reachrthe ocean is one white field of foam. lBut he catches, or fancies that he  &#xD;<pb n="x-xi" xml:id="VAC7564-00000006"/> -X       INTRODUCTION. catches, a glimpse of the schooner with which he sailed in company, lying upon her beam ends at no great distance from him, and he thinks of the fate of these playmates of his boyhood and youth;-and then he goes down, down into the green depths of ocean, until he fears that the next moment his keel will strike upon its oozy bed. And now only the master and mate, and one well-tried hand, can be trusted with the helm, and they must be lashed, in turn, to the rudder head. And thus they heave and toss through the livelong day. As the sun is setting, a gleam of light is seen in the west., The wind hauls round in the course of the night, and the wild and. broken clouds disperse, the stars shine out, and the storm is past. The morning sun, as it rises from its ocean bed, shines brightly upon him. O, how glad and thankful is his heart. But he cannot resume his labor. The ocean heaves and swells for two or three days, before it becomes so calm that he can drop his line into its depths. He waits patiently, and at length begins anew his toil. But, perhaps, before ie-as c pleteda his fare of halibut or cod, the wind suddenly   INTRODUCTION.          XI chops round into the north-east, and he has to en- counter a storm  from that quarter. The wind is cold; the sharp sleet cuts like a knife,: whenever he turns his face to the wind. His deck is loaded with snow: his rigging is stiff and immovable-from ice; he stands through his long watch, in the face of the howling wind, noting the sleet and snow as they drift past him upon the surface of the water. No cessation, no, rest does he know.  And thus, for two, three or four days, does this second life-battle last; and at the end of sixteen or twenty days, he returns to port, with half a fare, and with the loss of his boats or of a cable and anchor. In hundreds of instances has this experience been verified in the  winter fishing on George's Bank.  Scarcely a sea- son passes in which two or three crews are not lost in this business. How little do we, who are lying snugly in our beds, know of the matter! Believing that the Life of PETER GOTT would interest landsmen as well as seamen, not only in his simple, brave and affectionate character, but in the class of men which he represents; I have told his  &#xD;<pb n="xii-13" xml:id="VAC7564-00000007"/> xii      INTRODUCTION.  story in a plain, straight-forward style, throwing into the narrative such statistical and explanatory re- marks as will enable my readers to understand something of the nature and importance of our fish- eries, as one of the great industrial pursuits of New England, and of their bearing upon the commerce and navigation of the country. CONCORD, DEC. 20, 1855. /- ;.         . - ..    P E T E-R, -G  OT T PETER GOTT. CHAPTER   I. WINTER FISIIING.-PIGEON COVE.-GLOUCESTER HARBOR. AH, Pete, you are in luck this time! your dory fleets. Well, take in your killick, and kile up the painter; then give my dory a shove; may be you'll want a lift to-morrow. That's good. Heave, yo! There she goes! once more! good! There she fleets. Well, Abe, it looks rather gusty. What'll1 it be to-day? will the wind come up with the sun?  I hope not. It was SQ rough yesterday I did nothing, and I have done but little for a whole month. Now fish brings a good price, I wish we might have a long spell of good weather.  2  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7564-00000008"/> PETER GOTT, Well, we must take it as it comes. Where are you going this time? I think I shall go out back-side .of Sal- vage's. The last time I was there fsh was plenty.  That's a long pull. I thought I would go on to the flat ground. I was there yesterday. Found fish scace. Come, let's pull outside. I should like your company. Well, here she goes! The above dialogue took place just as the day began to dawn in the east, between' Peter Gott and Abraham Tarr, upon the beach at Pigeon Cove. This cove is formed by two ledges of rocks jutting out into Sandy Bay, with a narrow opening between their extremities; thus forming a small basin, in which a number of boats and fish- ing schooners milit lie, in comparatively still water, the force of the sea being broken by the ledges. When severe storms oc- curred, and the wind was east, the sea beat over these ledges in one complete mass of foam, and the fishing craft lying inside were: U          : * '  .    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   15   often driven on to the beach, or pitched and plunged against each other, to their very great damage, and sometimes to their total loss. Often, if the coming storm was foreseen in season, the schooners would run across the bay, and rounding the point of Bearskin Neck, would take shelter in Long Cove. If the wind continued to blow from the north-east or north, they rode, out the gale in safety. But if it blew directly from the east, they were not nmfrequcntly driven on to the beach even here. If it was late in the season, and the storm had been brew- ing for several days, so that they antici- pated a long storm, the larger craft more generally ran round Eastern Point, and laid up in Gloucester Harbor.  This harbor is sheltered on all sides, ex- cept the south-west, and is the safest harbor on the coast; aind here, in former days, all the larger vessels employed in the fishing business, belonging to the smaller aidd more exposed harbors and coves around the C-ape, were accustomed to lay up for the winter. Now that breakwaters and artificial harbors O    &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7564-00000009"/> 16      PETER GOTT, are built at Sandy Bay, Pigeon Cove and Lane's Cove, this is less frequently done than formerly. Butr many of the more val- uable vessels from these places, and most of the vessels from Essex and many from Man- chester, continue to lay up here to the present day, as they lie more quietly and are less exposed to injury, and can be read- ily got out when they are wanted. Many a time, in a cold November night, have these hardy sons of the ocean-turned out of their warm berths, and finding the wind blowing from 'the north-east, in sharp and spiteful gusts, and black masses of- broken clouds tumbling and careering through the sky, and now and then spitting small, dry flakes of snow, or sharp needles of frozen mist, they have hauled on their thick fish-' if gghoots, their Kersey jackets and their woollen neck cloths, and hoisted their sails *  and beat out of the bay, and running through the strait that separates Thatcher's Island from the main, have passed to the windward of Salt Island, rounded Monu- ment Point, and beat into Gloucester Har- ,    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    17 bor in the midst of a thick snow storm, or with the sleet and the rairi driving full into their faces. They are all skilful pilots into this har- bor, and can find their way into it in the darkest night. After passing the Point, they stretch over towards the Stage Rocks; then hauling upon the other tack, they lay the head of the vessel for Ten Pound Island Light; then tacking again, they run for Fort Point; then hauling again, they run between this and Ten Pound Island, stretch- ing over towards Rocky Neck. The next tack lays her head towards Harbor Cove; they run in this direction till they are on a line between Duncan's Point and Fort Point, and the next tack brings them in- side of Harbor Rock; there they drop their anchor, haul down their sails and make all snug. They now go ashore in their little boat, and landing at Pearce's Wharf, or  Duncan's Point, start for home, a distance of six miles, right in the eye of the wind, encumbered with their thick boots and heavy wet jackets. On they go, tr mp, 1  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7564-00000010"/> 18      PETER GOTT, tramp, for three mortal hours, and reach their homes about noon; and this, perhaps, without having had a morsel of food since their supper, the evening before. Usually three, but sometimes only two hands came round with the craft on these occasions. When the wind is boisterous and the night is dark, it is not only an adventure of a toilsome and exhausting nature, but one of great hazard. Few veteran sailors would undertake it unless driven to it by neces- sity. But these men, inured to toil from their childhood, cradled among the rocks, hardy and fearless, when they set foot upon the deck of a favorite-boat, know no dan- ger. Their craft behaves like' a thing of life, and seems obedient to the word of com- mand.- It is sometimes wonderful to see these schooners winding their way between rocks and ledges, doubling the sharpest points, and' shooting up in the very teeth of the wiid, as though conscious of their danger, and aware of the only course by which it could be avoided. These fishing boats were made on purpose to swim, and   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    19 there are no better sea boats in the world, and none that will hold on better when beating against the wind. We shall have opportunity to make their acquaintance and learn their qualities in the course of- our narrative. Peter and Abe pulled on, side by side. Leaving Pigeon Hill to the north-west, they passed to the north of the ledge known by the name of Salvages since the early set- tlement of the country. Our Pilgrim fa- thers spelt the word savages in that way, and it is supposed they gave this name to that dangerous mass of rocks, from the wild and savage aspect which they presented, as they approached the extremity- of the Cape. They continued to pull on till they had reached about a mile to the eastward of the ledge. By this time, the sun began to shoot his golden rays athwart the ocean, and the sheen'from the rippled surface was like the reflection from ten thousand mov- ing mirrors. Pete and Abe now took their berths within speaking distance of each other, un-  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7564-00000011"/> 20      PErTER GOTT, , shipped their oars, threw over their killicks, 7/Y and prepared to engage in the business of the day. -aBut first, each took out from un- der the seat in the stern of his dory, a par- cel wrapped in a brown paper, which he carefully unfolded, and took out a portion of cold meat and bread, which he had brought from his home.  Having eaten this, and drank a draught of cold coffee from the earthen jug which held his daily. supply, and carefully replaced the paper and the jug, the contents of which were reserved for a lunch ini"the middle of the day, each now charged his hook with a clam from a bucket sfanding near the stern, threw over his sinker, and cast off the line from his reel. The day's work was now fairly begun. In about ten minutes -each had -hauled in a fine fish; and thus they continued for about five hours, sometimes taking in three or br. four in rapid succession, then waiting fifteen Oorntwenty minutes for a bite. At the end of this time each had taken from thirty -to forty fish, cod and haddock.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   21 And now they began to think it was time to make for the shore. First, they ate up what remained of Athe :morning meal, then reeled up the line, hauled in the killick, set their bows for Pigeon Cove, and now came the hardest part of the toil of the day. The weight of the fish which they had caught caused their dories to draw more water than they did in the morning. They were fatigued with the labors of the day. The wind had chopped round into the north-west. A short sea was running, but they were used to such a termination of their day's toil, and were no ways discouraged. They pulled away with patience and perseverance, and about three o'clock in the afternoon they reached the mouth of the cove. Here they found a heavy swell; but watching their chance, they shot between the points of the ledges, and run their dories upon the beach. And now, kind reader, you think the day's work is over, and they will go to their homes, and get a warm dinner, and put on some clean clothes, and spend the  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7564-00000012"/> 22      PETER GOTT, evening in comfort. Not quite so fast. There is more work to be done. As they entered the mouth of the cove they noticed three or four wagons standing by the side of a row of small, black, dilapidated build- ings, called fish houses. These wagons be- long to hawkers, who come here to buy the fish, as they are brought in fresh from the water. As soon as- the dories have struck the beach, these men come down to see how many fish they have taken. They will not make an offer yet. They will wait till all the boats get in. There have been a good many out, and they hope they will bring in good fares; then they will be able to get them three or five cents a hundred cheaper. In the meanwhile, the fish are to be dress- ed. So taking his clam bucket and reel, the fisherman goes to the&amp; fish-house where he keeps his gear, and depositing them in their proper places, he takes his handbar- roav, his oil bucket, and a sharp-knife, and returns to his boat. Then placing his bar- row athwart the bows, he takes his stand in the water by its side. Then seizing a fish   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    23 by the head with his left hand, he makes a cut across the throat, just behind the gills; then slitting down the belly with one stroke, he seizes the liver between the edge of his knife and- the thumb of his right hand, and detaching it from its connections drops it into his oil bucket which stands before him, j towards the stern. Now dropping his knife upon a thwart, he seizes the whole mass of entrails in his right hand, and holding the fish firmly in his left, tears out'the whole with a sudden jerk, and throws it into the water. Then he throws the fish into the barrow, and seizing another with his left hand, and his knife with his right, goes through with the same motions. Thus he proceeds with the rapidity and regularity of a machine, until the fish are all transferred from the bottom of the dory into the hand- barrow. He now carries up his oil bucket, and empties the livers into a cask or butt which he keeps for the purpose. He is now ready to dispose of his fish. If the boats are all in, and the fares are not very large, the hawkers will offer seventy-five  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7564-00000013"/> 24     ' PETER GOTT, cents:a hundred. ' After a good deal of haggling, Peter gets eighty cents for his. Taking them to the scale, which stands near the passage leading down to the beach, they are found to weigh 150 pounds. They are now taken to the wagon of the pur- chaser, who pays Peter one dollar and twenty cents. He now returns to his boat, takes out his oars, dips up a bucket of water, washes out the boat, and throwing a bucket of water into it, rolls it over on to its side and lets the water run out. Then carrying up his killick high on to the beach, he gathers up his oars, and carries them to the fish-house. These houses are generally occupied in common by several dory men, each of whom pays rent for the corner in which- he keeps his own gear. Now it is sundown, and his day's work is done. He dips a bucket- of fresh water from the .spring, just back of the fish-house, and washing the gurry from his hands and face, starts for his home, and carries to his pother the dollar and twenty cents which he has earned. She receives him with a smnile and a kind word, and sets before him   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   25 a mug of hot coffee and a plate of bread, baked before the fire, and some bits of dried fish. .If Peter has had good luck for several days, they get a pound-of butter and a .piece of cheese, in addition to the bread and fish. The history of this day, was the history of many of his days during the winter and spring after Peter Gott arrived at the age of fifteen. During at least half the days, the weather was so cold and stormy that he could 'not go out at all; and many times, after pulling out two or three miles on a dark and cold morning, the wind would come up with the sun, and the sea would become so rough that he could not fish, and he would have to pull back, perhaps, against the wind, and thus would return .% having onlyhis labor for his pains. Per- ' haps about one day in three, he'was able to fish. When there were no hawkers on  ^ the ground to take off his fish, he sold' them to Mr. Dennis, who kept the store at  the cove. He allowed seventy-five cents a i/E hundred for them, and paid out of the store.- 13 '   &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7564-00000014"/> 26      PETER GOTT, CHAPTER   II.  MR. DENNIS. --SANDY BAY. AN INCIDENT OF THE LAST WAR WITr GREAT BRITAIN..-FISHERMEN AND THEIR OWNERS.-FIRST ATTEMPT TO SETTLE CAPE ANN. MR. DENNIS was a quiet, easy man. He purchased second and third rate goods, and sold them at a dear rate. But then he took his pay in fish, and this he had to salt and make, and carry to market, and then, perhaps, wait four or six months for his money; and he was obliged to charge a large profit. But he took in his fish at such a lay, that he made a good profit on this, and another large profit on the goods which he sold. He had grown rich in this, business, and owned about half of the small houses which nestled among the rocks and ledges on the eastern declivity of Pigeon -Hill, besides a good two-story house, with green blinds, which stood a little to the northward of the cove, surrounded by a   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    27 pretty enclosure, and a score or two of ap- ple and pear trees. This house stood on an elevated site, and commanded a fine view of the ocean to the east and south. The whole bay was under the eye of Mr. Dennis, together with the little village of Sandy Bay, which lay along its southern shore. This village at that time had but one church, and that stood within gunshot of deep water. During the last war with England, a British cruiser was lying in the bay; and one morning, about daylight, sent a barge ashore, armed with a swivel, to reconnoitre the village. Some fishermen, who had just turned out for their daily task, discovered the barge before it reached the shore, and rang the bell to alarm the inhabitants. The midshipman in command of the barge, said he would silence that tell-tale, and or- dered the gunner to fire at the bell. He charged his gun heavily and lodged a ball in one of the posts that support the bal- cony. There it remains to ;the present time, and is shown to visitors with no small  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7564-00000015"/> 28      PETER GOTT, degree of pride, as proof of the part which the people of that village took in that war, and the dangers to which they were ex- posed. The sequel of the story is never omitted, which was as follows: When the gun was discharged, its recoil caused the barge to spring a leak. The water fast gaining upon them, in spite of their exer- tions, to keep the .barge free, the middy, with his crew of eight men, called out lust- ily for help. Several fishermen, who had now collected -on the shore, seeing their condition, put off in their dories and brought them ashore, and kept them as prisoners. Now it so happened, that James Rowe and David Pool, two fishermen, being out in a wherry two days before, had been picked up by the cruiser, whose officers took a fancy to a meal of fresh cod, with which the wherry was loaded. These men were still detained on board the cruiser. The British sailors immediately proposed :-an exchange of prisoners. But no one be- ing authorized to negotiate an exchange, the affair was managed with true Yankee   , ' .    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    29 shrewdness. The British officer and crew solemnly promised, that if they were fur- nished with a boat to return to the frigate, they would send it back in charge of James and David. Trusting to their honor, their captors, thinking their two townsmen worth more than the nine British seamen, showed them a boat to which they might help. themselves; and one day, when their guard was at dinner, they escaped from the room in which they were confined, seized the boat, and put off to the cruiser. They reached her ini safety, and honorably fulfil- led their promise, sending back Jim and Dave, with the borrowed boat. In addition to the real estate which Mr. Dennis had accumulated on shore, he own- ed a large share of five or six schooners, whose outfits he furnished, and whose proceeds he received and marketed. The crews for these vessels, consisting of eight or ten hands to each, were usually shipped in the winter. From the time they were shipped, Mr.- Dennis supplied them and their families with groceries, shoes, and 3*     &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7564-00000016"/> 30      PETER GOTT, most of their clothing. After the vessels put to sea, he continued to supply the fam- ilies during the spring and summer. If the vessel was doing well, he continued to sup- ply them till she was hauled up, late in the fall; but if she did not make good fares, he refused to supply them at an early day in the fall. It very often happened that strong and active men, after having labored hard through the season, had not a dollar com- ing to them when the voyage was settled, with which to supply the wants of their families through the winter. This was owing, in part, to the want of economy in the families, and in part to the high prices which they had to pay for every thing which he furnished them. Mr. Dennis al- ways considered it an object to bring about this result. Even if they owed him a few dollars at the settlement, it was all the bet- ter, for then he was sure of their services the next year. Thus they were bound to 'him, by a bond which they found it very difficult to break. He had all their earn- ings in his hands, and paid for them in ,4 \.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   31 goods at his own price, and how could he fail to grow rich, or they to remain poor? He had several men who had been in his employment from twenty to thirty years, and had rarely, if ever, been out of his debt. If a man, with a family, once got into his debt, his only hope was, that when his boys got old enough to have their labor of some value, their wages, added to his own, might enable him to pay off hIis debt to Mr. Den- nis, and begin to lay by a little capital for himself. The earnings of the sons of fish- ermen are always claimed by the parents. Hence a father, who has three or four boys, if he can maintain his family by his own earnings, and lay up the wages of his sons from the time they are sixteen till they are twenty-one, amasses enough to buy for him- self a snug house and a part of a schooner, and then he thinks his old age well provided for. Thus a family of sons becomes a for- tune to those who are fortunate enough to have them. Early marriages are almost universal among this class of men, and thus it often happens, that before a man is forty,  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7564-00000017"/> 32      PETER GOTT, he has several sturdy boys, by whose assist. ance he is laying up a competence for his wife and family, during the remainder of their lives. Peter Gott's parents were of the number of those who had married early in life. His father, whose name he bore, was but twenty- two, and his mother but seventeen. His father was a lineal descendant of James Gott, who was one of the first company that established a fishing station at, Cape Ann. This first attempt to make a settle- ment was abandoned; and the men engaged in it returned to Charlestown. They were driven away, not so much by the hardships incident to a new settlement and the re- moteness and desolate character of the place, as by the unearthly and strange noises which were-, heard in various direc- tions, especially at night. At first they supposed these noises were the roaring of lions. But no lions having been seen in 4he day time, they came to the sage con- clusion that it must be the howling of de- vils, who, they supposed, were disturbed by      ,                 .   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    33 their taking possession of this spot, which the devils claimed as peculiarly their own property, and were taking this method to warn them off. The cause of these sounds is now well understood. The whole of the Cape is little else than a bed of granite, thinly covered with gravel and soil. Through this granite, veins of green stone have been forced up, at intervals, by some violent convulsion of nature. These veins are from   one to six feet in width at the surface, and in some instances may be traced nearly or quite across the Cape, and sometimes far out into the adjacent bay. Where these veins of green stone are ex- posed to the action of the sea, they have been worn away by it, leaving chasms ex- tending from one to two hundred feet into the shore. Of these, the Gully, at Nor- wood's Head, and Raves' Crack near Kettle Cove, may be taken as samples. It has often happened that a mass of granite, or some neighboring boulder, has been driven by some  violent storm into one of these chasms, and the chasm being too narrow to  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7564-00000018"/> 34      PETER GOTT, admit of its reaching the bottom, it has re- mained, its sides resting against the per- pendicular walls of granite which constitute the sides of the chasm. Between the lower face of this rock and the bottom of the gully, there would sometimes be left a small opening. Through this opening the air is driven with great force, when a-lofty wave rolls in upon the shore, filling sud- denly a large portion of the chasm, giving rise to sounds that may be compared to a dozen steam whistles of various sizes and keys, from a sharp treble to a heavy pro- longed bass, all sounding together. When these screeches are heard in the darkness of midnight, mingling with the:howling of the winds and the dashing of the waves upon the rocks, and the echoes from the woods, they produce an effect upon the nerves of persons unacquainted with their cause, any thing but agreeable; and a few solitary, and perhaps home-sick persons, strangers in a strange land, may well be excused for considering them supernatural. After a few years, another, attempt to   THE CAPE ANIT FISHERMAN.   35 effect a settlement was more successful. James Gott was among the number who settled on the north side of the Cape. '-They established their village, a little distance from the sea-shore, upon the western de- clivity of a hill, which overlooked Ipswich Bay. Fifteen or twenty log houses were erected. The cellars, over which these - houses were built, may still be seen, though not one of the houses remains, nor is there a single house in the immediate vicinity. The spot is now known all over the Cape by the name of Dog Town.  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7564-00000019"/> 36      PETER. GOTT, CHAPTER III. PETER'S PARENTS.--HS FATHER GOES TO THE BANKS. BANK FISHNG. PETER GOTT'S mother was Patty Tarr, whose ancestors were also among the set- tlers of Dog Town. Peter was their oldest son, and was born before his mother was eighteen years of age. In the course of the next six years, two boys and two girls were added to the family. To supply their wants, from day to day, demanded of the young father the full exercise of all his powers, and the practice of the most rigid economy. Peter loved his wife and chil- dren, and her cheerful smile, and their noisy mirth at his return from the toils of the day, were an ample. reward. But at the close of the seventh winter of his mar- ried life, he found himself deeply in debt to. Mr. Dennis, who had been induced to trust   THE 6APE ANN FISHERMAN.   37 him to a considerable amount, by his well known honesty and industry, although he did not belong to either of his vessels. His fifth child had just been born, and his wife had been sick some-weeks, in consequence of too early exposure. He had been com- pelled to hire a nurse and to call -on the doctor; and his anxiety about his wife, and the care of his children, had kept him at home during seven days of good weather. When the spring opened, his wife had re- gained her health, but was somewhat low spirited and discouraged in view of the prospect before them. Peter felt the sense of oppression that results from the con- sciousness of being in debt, and not seeing very clearly how the obligation was to be discharged. Under the influence of this feeling, he listened the more readily to a suggestion from skipper Tarr, who com- manded the Jane, that he should ship on board his schooner, which was bound to the Grand Bank, and was to sail on the sixth of April. He talked the matter over with Patty; told her his circumstances, and re-  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7564-00000020"/> 38      PETER GOTT, ferred her to several young men of their acquaintance, who had been engaged in Bank fishing, and had' had better success than he had in shore fishing. Patty shed many tears at the idea of Peter's being ab- sent ten or twelve weeks at a time, which is the usual length of trips to the Banks. But at length, confiding in his judgment, and' influenced, by his assuring her that it was much easier than shore fishing, she, - consented, and the next day Peter Gott's name was added to the list of the Jane's crew; and now Patty was fully employed in getting her husband ready for the trip. Two new red flannel shirts must be made; two pairs of socks must be knit, and three or four pairs of woollen nippers. Every  moment that could be spared from the care of her babes, she plied her needle with the utmost diligence, and when they were sleeping quietly, three of them nestled in the trundle-bed and one in the cradle, and the infant in her lap, her knitting-needles- moved, almost without cessation, far into -the night. At length they were all ready,   THE 'CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   39 and Peter, with a new Kersey jacket and his boots well stuffed, was ready for the voyage. On the morning of the sixth, he took leave of his weeping wife, and kissed his little ones, and went on board. The tide was full; the schooner, freshy painted and in perfect order, was afloat. A gentle breeze from the north-westtwas springing tip. Her, jib and mainsail were run up; the warp that held her to the wharf was cast off, and hauled on board; she gradu- ally fell off from the wharf, and soon, tak- ing the breeze, with the skipper at the helm, she made her way gracefully out of the Cove. Little Peter had come down with his r father to see him off. He stood among the few spectators on the wharf, and joined heartily in the cheers which they gave, as the vessel left the harbor. When Peter left his family, he confidently expected to see them again by the Fourth of July at the farthest.             ::; The Cape Ann fishermen have, from the earliest settlement of the Cape, been accus-  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7564-00000021"/> 40      PETER GOTT, tomed, for the most part, to return to the Cape with their fares, and make the fish at their own homes. The owners of the ves- sels have a flake-yard in the vicinity of the landing places, to which the fish are carried on being landed. The flakes consist of three long poles laid upon crotched posts driven into the ground. These poles are placed parallel to each other, about two feet apart, and covered with brush; upon them the fish are spread. At night they are thrown into small heaps, called hakes, with the skin upwards. They are spread in the morning, when the weather is fair, and turned once or twice a day. The making of fish has, in latter years, become a business by itself. Individuals own large flake-yards, and take the fish from the vessels and make them, receiving every fifteenth quintal for their services. The fishermen from Cape Cod, Marblehead, and many other places, were formerly in the habit, when they had loaded their ves- sels, of running for the nearest points of Nova Scotia or Newfoundland, and landing        .      '    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   -41. their fish and piling them in large heaps, where they were left two or three aays-to drain. In the meantime, they erected their flakes and a hut- which they used as- a- dwelling while they were drying their fish, and as a store-house when the process was completed.  After they were sufficiently drained, they were carried to the flakes on hand barrows, and spread and turned and haked up at night until they were suffi- ciently dried. This process, which is called "making," occupies from four to ten days, according to the state of the weather. The utmost care is needed, when the, sky is clear and the weather hot, to prevent their burning, as it is called. If they become too much heated, they are rendered tender and brittle, like fish- tthat is cooked, which, in fact, is the case with burnt fish. To prevent this, the fishermen shaded them with green boughs, or covered them with sails in    d    of their day. In modern days yankee ingenuity has so arranged the flakes, that they can ;be turned from the sun at such an angle asto preven-t-isdirect    &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7564-00000022"/> 42      PETER GOTT, rays from falling upon them. When the fish were sufficiently made, they were stacked up in the hut and left upon shore. The fishermen now scrubbed the vessel's bottom, payed her seams with tar, filled up their water casks, and put off again for the Grand Banks. By the middle of Septem- ber they usually completed the second fare, and returning to the shore, spread their fish upon the flakes. The weather has now become cold on that northern and in- hospitable coast. The nights are frosty, and occasional snow squalls vary the mo- notony of the scene. The process of mak- ing occupies at least a week longer than in July; but the fish are better made,-they 'do not require to be salted so high to pre- serve them. What are called "dun fish" are made in the autumn. The fall fares command a better price than the spring fares. While the fish are making, they clean out the hold of their vessel, and, se- *  lecting a clear day, pack away the first, or spring fare, in the bottom. When the second fare is ready, they stow that upon   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    43 the other; then shutting down the hatches, : they hoist their sails and bear away for their distant homes, having been absent from six to eight months. If they have been lucky, they will have made from ten to twelve hundred quintals of fish, one half of which goes to' the vessel, and the other half to the skipper and crew. Since the last war with England, the fish- ermen from  the States ha-ve not been allowed to make their fish upon the shores of the British Provinces, and have returned home at the close of each fare. ,When Peter sailed, on the sixth of April, he expected to return as soon as they had wet their salt. When vessels are on the Banks, it is usual for them, at the close of each day, to dress off their fish. The heads are cut off, the fish split open, the livers saved in butts provided for the purpose, and the entrails thrown into the sea. The fish are then salted in layers in the hold of  - the'vessel, or in butts.. Wien they have     : taken fish enough to use up all the salt on board, they say they have wet all their ' ..!4  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7564-00000023"/> "     PETER GOTT, salt. It was the custom, at the period of which we are speaking, to save the roe or spawn of the fish, and salt it in barrels for the European market. This was quite an important article of-trade. This is not now preserved on board the American vessels. -The French vessels still continue to pre- serve it. The Jane sailed out of the bay with a brisk wind, and passing between Sal- vage's and Stretchmouth Island, she laid her course for the Grand Banks, and was soon out of sight of the rocky headlands of the Cape. They went on all that day and the following night with a favorable wind. On the second day at 9 o'clock they spoke the good brig David Pearce, from Bilboa, where she had been through the previous  Lent, supplying the inhabitants with fish and salted roe, called by the fishermen, "Pee," which at that period was shipped in considerable quantities to that port. She had made a good voyage. The year was now completed since the Jane, and other bankers, had- sailed on the previous April   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   45 for the Banks; and the David Pearce was bringing back, in salt, olive oil and wine, the returns of the fish which they had taken. Thus commerce distributes the products of the land and the sea over the face of the earth, furnishing employment to thousands, and enriching, or at least sus- taining, those. engaged in it. The vessels passed so near each, other, that the men readily recognized each other upon deck, and saluted one another with a hearty cheer. Fhe crew of the David consisted mostly of fishermen, who; after the close of the fishing, the previous fall, had shipped for a voyage to Bilboa. It is a common thing for fishermen, es- pecially those who are young, and have no hamilies, to ship in November and December or a winter voyage of three or four or five nonths. One is induced to do so by a de- ire to see the world; another, that he may dd something to the gains of the year, and ,e enabled to marry the girl he loves; nother, the head of a family, is driven by' ecessity to ship as a sailor, that he may  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7564-00000024"/> )r      Y 1STSP U'TE'TTI earn bread for his growing flock at home. When he is far away upon mid ocean, in the darkness of midnight, with the storm. howling around him, as he turns in at the close of his watch, to his cold and damp berth, he thinks of the loved ones at home, and sends up his brief prayer to Heaven for a blessing upon them. He feels that earnest prayers are going up for his safety.; and who shall say that any more, acceptable prayers meet and mingle in the presence of our Father above, than the flayers of the rough and hardy sailor, and the wife and children whom    he has left behind. When we leave our warm parlors and soft couches and retire to our downy beds, as we listen to the peltings of the pitiless storm without, to the sleet or the drifting snow as it drives against our closed blinds, or to the wind as it whistles through the trees around our dwellings, we sometimes think of the sailor, and perhaps say, -" God bless him !" But the sailor's wife, as she lies upon her hard bed, with her babe nest- ling in her bosom, as she listens to the    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    47-  howling tempest, and thinks of him tossing upon the heaving billows and buffeting the briny waves, or perhaps lashed to the helm in the pitchy darkness, with the salt spray and -the sharp sleet driving full into his face, with no ray of light but the little twinkle in the binnacle that casts an indis- tinct gleam    upon the compass.    O how sincere, how heartfelt, how earnest are her prayers!, When she falls into a dreamy sleep, she sees him perhaps struggling in the cold, dark waters, or borne upon a green curling billow, about to be dashed upon some ragged, -projecting rock, and awakes with a scream of agony; and again she prays, O how earnestly, to Him who alone can save him. Thus it is, " Out of the abundance of the     heart, the  mouth speaketh." And is it not the heart-speech that is accepted ? Fishermen make excellent seamen. They are faithful, brave and intelligent, and soon learn the terms used on board square-rigged vessels, and the manoeuvres employed in working them. Many    of the most enter.  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7564-00000025"/> 48      PETER GOTT, prising masters and seamen in our mer- chant service, had their first training in fishing vessels. A voyage to Europe, to the West Indies, or to the Coast of South America, is, on the whole, the best employ- ment for the fisherman in the winter. The great evil in the life of the fisherman is, that he is idle through the winter, and eats up, during that portion of the year, what he had earned in the summer. This it is that keeps most of them poor all their lives. Various attempts have been made to furnish them with some mechanical employment on shore during the cold season, as shoe- making, boat-building, coopering, &amp;c.; but they have all failed, from the fact that sea- men have a sovereign contempt for all the occupations of landsmen. They will not be converted into land lubbers. Hence a large proportion of the fishermen spend their winters loafing about in the stores and fish-houses, smoking their pipes and telling stories; :and when their money is gone, running in debt for supplies for their families, on the anticipation of the next   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   49 year's earnings. The result is what might be naturally expected. They are always poor, and always in debt. After speaking the David, the Jane kept on her course, and the following night en- countered la north-east wind, which blew in spiteful gusts. The clouds were broken and black. In the morning the storm burst upon them. The snow fell with great vio- lence, and soon loaded the deck. They laid her to, under a close reefed foresail, and all hands, except the man at the helm, took refuge in the. cuddy. Here they spent the day and the following night, each taking his turn at the helm. The next morning the wind worked to the eastward, and the snow was followed by a cold, driving rain. As the sun was setting on that day, a glin was seen in the west. The wind came round into the north-west, ahd the cold be- 'ame intense. The wet snow upon deck was converted into solid ice. Their run- ling rigging became immovable. The bows nd bowsprit were heavily loaded with ice, nd they were drifting at the mercy of the  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7564-00000026"/> 50     PETER GOTT, wind. They at length succeeded in put- ting her before the wind, and run for the Gulf Stream, hoping to reach warmer water, and thus free themselves from ice. After running and beating about in the latitude of the Gulf Stream, they set their head to the north and east, and on the twenty- fourth of April found themselves sailing in green water, which indicates soundings, and trying the lead, they found sixty fathoms. They were now fairly on the Bank. But they were enveloped in a fog so dense that they could scarcely see the length of the deck. Every thing in the vessel was satu- rated with moisture. Their pea jackets and baize shirts were doubled in weight by the moisture which they had imbibed. The water hung in drops from the ceiling of the cuddy; even the bed and blankets in their berths, when they turned out in the morn- ing, steamed like so many uncovered wash boilers. They had scarcely been dry for the last fifteen days, and their skins were completely parboiled. But they had come to catch fish, and having with much diffi- culty and some peril reached the fishing   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   51 ground, they were not to be frightened at a fog bank, and immediately set about pre- paring for action. They cast anchor in sixty fathoms. Cleared the deck, took off their hatch covers, uncaulked the hatches and un- covered the hold. They fixed their oil butts in their places, and hoisted out some water barrels and a barrel of salted clams. They got out their reels, hung their sink- ers and ganged their hooks. They next got up their buckets and sharpened their splitting knives and overhauled their chests, to find their woollen mittens and nippers. These arrangements occupied the. remain- der of the day. Peter, and two or three others, who had now come upon the Bank for the first time, were anxious to try their luck. So they put a clam upon their hooks, and dropped their sinkers into the green water. After waiting patiently as only a fisherman knows how, they hauled up four or five noble cod, which were soon sputtering in the cook's fry-pan, and furnished them with a hearty supper, to which they set to with right good will.  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7564-00000027"/> 52      PETER GOTT, CHAPTER IV. FISHERMAN'S GRUB. - FOGS. - THE GRAND BANKS.- TROLL FISHNG. FISHERMEN, in those days, ate much more fish on their trips than they do at the pre- sent time. They were fitted out with a good supply of salt pork and molasses, with a plenty of India meal, a little flour and hard bread. Their bread was made of meal and water, with a little salt and molasses: added, and baked upon tin sheets or pieces of barrel-heads, before the fire. Once or twice a week they had tea made, by put- ting tea into a boiler, and adding a quantity of molasses, and boiling it as coffee is boiled. Coffee was seldom used at sea in those days, f  and their sugar was kept to sweeten their grog, .which was duly served out to them twice a day. On Sunday, it was common to have a flour short-cake, which was pre-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERIAN.    53 pared in the following way: The head was broken out of a flour barrel; the flour scooped out of the centre so as to make a basin-like cavity, sufficiently large for the cook's purpose; he then poured into it a pint of pork fat, which he had fried out of slices of salt pork, a quantity of molasses and a little -hot water, and mixed in the flour till it was of the proper consistence. It was then taken out in a mass, and baked in a Dutch oven over the fire. This is no contemptible dish, and contains nearly as many good qualities as Lord Peter's leg of mutton; and many a hearty breakfast of a Sunday morning do the fishermen make of it, with their pot of boiled tea. Those who have never tried a dish of boiled tea, will be surprised to find how good a substitute it is for coffee, especially if a little sweet milk is added just at the close of the boil- ing. In modern times, the fishermen are fitted out with a much greater variety and abundance )of food, than in the days of which we are speaking.  Salt pork and beef, potatoes and cabbages, flour and hard * .               2  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7564-00000028"/> 54      PETER GOTT, bread of a superior quality from Johnson's bakery, and coffee three. times a day, is their cormon fare. Cape Ann fishermen are famous for their good living. I have known men among them who have drank their strong coffee three times a day for forty years, and, as if on purpose to prove the fallacy of all that has been said about the injurious effects of coffee, they have persisted in having good health for the whole of that time. But fish, fresh or corn- ed, was the principal article of food at the time when Peter made his first trip to the Banks. A few years after the time referred to, Capt. Burnham sailed from Essex in a fifty ton schooner, on a fishing trip to the eastr ern shore, victualled for six weeks. After spending four weeks unsuccessfully on the coast of Maine, and having now but two weeks' provision on board, he sailed for the Banks, determined not to return till he, had filled his little craft with fish. On ar- riving at the Bank, they found an abun- dance of fish. But soon their provisions   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    55 were all gone; not a crumb of bread, not a slice of pork, not a drop of molasses had they left. Halibut fins and napes, fried in their own fat, and boiled codfish, consti- tuted their only food for six weeks. Not even a drop of tea or a drink of grog had they left. Fish, fish, fish! was their break- fast, and dinner, and supper. But they wet all their salt, and returned to the Cape at the end of twelve weeks from the time they sailed, all fat and hearty. They had been given up as lost by their friends some weeks before they arrived. An old man, who was one of the crew, on relating this incident of his early life, remarked, that the whole crew were as fat and savage as bears. The next morning, when the sun arose, he was dimly visible through the thick veil that had so long concealed his face. Tak- ing this as an omen of good luck, they com- menced their work in good earnest. For some days they were not very successful, taking only three or four quintals per day. On the third day, their solicitude was re- lieved by a Marblehead schooner, which  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7564-00000029"/> 56      PETER GOTT, had arrived on the ground, and dropped her anchor about a mile from the berth which they occupied. They now felt that they had some neighbors and could enjoy the pleasures of social intercourse with their fellows. If there is any situation in the wide world where men feel solitary and alone, it is on the Banks of Newfoundland, with no object in sight to break the monot- ony of the scene. Neither sun, moon nor stars are seen for many days. They are enveloped in a dense fog, which shuts them up from all the world. In the long, damp, chilly nights, they are enclosed as with a solid wall of darkness. When a lantern is brought on deck, it literally renders the darkness visible. There you lie, rocking to and fro, and rising and falling with the swelling surges, day after day and night after night; your deck slimy and slippery, the, water trickling in streams down the windward face of your mast, and a large drop hangs ready to fall from the loose end of every gasket. Below deck matters are not much better; every thing is wet and   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   57 sticky in the cabin, and in the hold all is chilly and dank, like some deep, dark cav- ern in the mountain side. When fish are plenty, and the crew take from twenty to  thirty quintals a day, the feeling of success enables one to bear the solitude. But when you are doing nothing, or only catch- ing now and then a dog-fish, the feeling of dreariness is sometimes very oppressive. In a voyage at sea, although you are in mid ocean and not a sail in sight, the very motion of the vessel has something inspir- iting and animating in it. She moves through the water as a thing of life. And then the daily routine of labor, in working the ship and keeping her clean and snug, keeps all hands employed. If a storm overtakes you, or a gale comes down upon you, all is life and activity; all your energy and skill are called into requisition. You have a battle to fight with the elements, and your safety depends upon, your skill and endurance. Here is no feeling of tedium or ennui. The sailor, the world- over, prefers the storm to the calm.  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7564-00000030"/> 58      PETER GOTT, A fisherman often spends weeks on the. Banks without seeing a vessel, althoufgh hundreds are on the ground. This is ow- ing partly to the fogs which abound there, and partly to the immense extent of that portion of the Atlantic known as the Grand Bank. The Bank is a range of submarine mountains lying between the eastern shores of North America and Northern Europe. This range runs nearly north and south, and is twelve hundred miles in length. Its width is very variable, as are the heights of its summits. In some places they approach within forty fathoms of the surface, at other points they are one hundred and twenty or fifty fathoms below it; thus resembling mountain ranges upheaved upon the land. A parallel range, lying to the westward of the main bank, is known by the name of the Western Bank, and is preferred by some fishermen to the Great Bank. The cod frequent all this immense portion of the Atlantic, and during the fishing season, vessels are -scattered on every part of it; and it often happens that a vessel will   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    59 be at work for weeks, without a sail in sight. The Jane remained at her first berth about two weeks; during this time they took less than a hundred quintals, and be- coming dissatisfied with their success, they hauled up their anchor, and ran about fifty miles to the north-east, and anchored in seventy fathoms. Here they were more successful, striking immediately a school of large fish. They now made up for lost time, and in the course of four weeks they had four hundred quintals on board, beside several barrels of halibut cut into slices and salted, and two large sword-fish. But now the school was exhausted, or driven from the ground by sharks or some other monsters of the deep, that visit the Banks to prey upon the cod. It often hap- pens that codfish will all at once cease to take the hook, without any known cause. The same thing is true of pollock and mackerel, and indeed all fish that go in schools. They appear to move in a body, and to be actuated by a common impulse.  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7564-00000031"/> 60      PETER GOTT, Their habits and the laws that govern them are little understood, although many facts respecting them have been known for scores of years. After remaining idle some days, waiting for the fish to take the hook, they again 'shifted their berth about thirty miles to the northward. They had now salt enough for a hundred -quintals more, and in the course of a week they had nearly wet it all. The weather had now become warm and- pleasant, and the rising sun generally dissi- pated the fog that enveloped them during the night. One bright morning, about nine o'clock, as the fog;lifted from the water and floated like a cloud- in mid air, one of the men discovered a string of buoys, about half a mile distant. This informed them, that a, French vessel had been fishing in the vicinity, and had lost one of her lines. The French go -upon the Banks with large vessels, commonly high-decked brigs, with numerous crews, and having selected a-berth, put down a couple of anchors, and make arrangements to spend four or six , f    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.     61 months. They are generally furnished with four large boats, with a crew to each. They run out long lines, about half an inch in thickness, made of flax, hard twisted and very strong. These are from sixty to a hundred fathoms long.  They are attached to, buoys, and laid in different directions from the brig. To these lines they attach short fish-lines, at the distance of about a fathom from each other, with a baited hook at the end of each. These long lines are called trolls, and this mode of fishing is called trolling. The boats overhaul these trolls daily, and when fish are plenty, twice a day, and take off the fish that they find upon the hooks, and re-bait the hooks. The fish are then hoisted upon the deck of the brig, and dressed and salted. When the wind is high, or the sea is rough, they are sometimes unable to visit their trolls for several daysin succession, and the fish that are caught are either eaten by other fish, or become spoiled and unfit for use. The Americans never adopt this method, although in good weather it is .easier than 6  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7564-00000032"/> 62      PETER GOTT, that which they pursue. The hauling of fish over the rail of a vessel, with lines sixty or seventy feet long, is by no means an easy task. When a halibut or large cod is attached to the line, it requires the man to put forth his whole strength, and sometimes the aid of another man, with a gaff, which is a pole with an iron hook at the end, is needed, to bring it on board. The Yankees consider thismethod the most expeditious, and they are not so sparing of muscular efforts as the French. Besides, the high-decked vessels of the French ren- ders fishing with long lines much less prac- ticable than it is on board the low-decked schooners of the Americans.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    63 CHAPTER   V. PETER'S FATHER LOST ON THE BANKS. -THE VESSEL RETURNS TO PIGEON COVE.-THE NEWS OF A MAN LOST, REACHES THERE BEFORE HER. THE crew of the Jane on discovering the troll, made all haste to 'get out their boat, to go and pick it up. Peter, who had never before seen a troll line, was eager to be one of the party, and no sooner was the boat alongside than he jumped into ier, and, with two other hands, briskly pushed off in the direction of the buoys. They danced merrily over the green waves. They soon reached the most distant buoy, and heading the boat in the direction of the Jane, began taking in the troll, clearing the hooks of the dead fish as they pro- ceeded. It proved to be a long line. They had hauled in about half of it, when find- ing a large fish attached to a hook, Peter, in his eagerness to clear the hook, lost his  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7564-00000033"/> "     PETER GOTT, balance and fell over the side of the boat. The men being occupied with the line, were unable to seize him as he fell, and being encumbered with his pea jacket and thick boots, he immediately sunk. They prepared to seize him as he rose; but as he rose at some distance from the boat, they failed to do so. After struggling for a moment, he again sank, and this was the last they saw of poor Peter. They laid by an hour, watching for his rising, but he never appeared. They had cut off that portion of the line which they had not taken in, and now slowly and with sad hearts, returned to the vessel. On learn- ing the loss of Peter, the skipper and two fresh hands jumped into the boat and pulled for the buoys; but after searching for half an hour in vain, they returned with heavy hearts to the Jane. A sudden gloom came over them all, and every countenance wore a deep expression of sorrow. Seamen say but little upon the subject of death. Indeed they seem reluctant to speak of it; yet they deeply feel the loss   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   65 of a messmate. Although there is but a plank between them and a watery grave, death, when it comes, seems as unexpected to them as to men on land. Peter was be- loved by all the crew, and a big tear stood in every eye, when it was certain they would see him no more. They thought of his wife and children. . "Poor Patty," said one, who had left his young wife and child at home, "it might have been me, and then what would Mary have done?" and the tears flowed afresh at the thought. They now picked up Peter's lines, and all his traps, and stowed them in his chest and with little appetite sat dowin to their dinner. They had still two or three barrels of salt left; but no one, could think of resum- ing the fishing. They walked the deck in silence, or going into the cabin, stretched themselves upon the lockers. Scarcely a remark was made. About four o'clock, as the skipper emptied the ashes out of his fourth pipe, he quietly remarked, "Well, boys, I don't think ye're inclined to fish 6*  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7564-00000034"/> "     PETER GOTT, any more, and I think we may as well heave up the anchor, and set her head for Cape Ann." This was the very proposition which they all desired, and which, in fact, they had been expecting all the afternoon. Indeed one or two of the men, who kept their dunnage in the forecastle, had for an hour past been overhauling and re-stowing it, preparatory for the run home. They immediately set about making preparation to carry the. skipper's proposal into. execu- tion. They washed their lines and hooks in fresh water, and hung them over the taffrail to dry. They cleaned their knives and buckets, and stowed them in the hold. Covered the oil butts, put on the hatches and barred them down. Then they bailed up salt water and scrubbed down the deck, and by sundown they had all snug, and ready to sail in the morning. After supper, they all turned in; but there was little sleep on board the Jane that night. Their hearts were sad, and their thoughts were far away, busied with their wives and little ones, nestling among   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   67 the rocks of the Cape. Nearly eleven weeks had now expired since they left the wharf in Pigeon Cove, and Patty was look- ing for their speedy return. She had been for some time counting the days that would intervene, before the fourth of July, which was the day set for their return. For a week, she had seen Mr. Dennis every morn- ing, before going down to his store, stand- ing in the scuttle of his house, sweeping the horizon with' his spy-glass, to see if they were in sight; and she had gone down regularly to the cove every day, after giv- ing her children their breakfast, to inquire the news. Here she generally met two or three other women, who had come down on the same errand. On the very morning that the Jane left the Banks, she met her cousin, Jane Tarr. On seeing her, she ex- claimed, "O how glad I shall be when Peter comes. Every morning, when I get back from the cove, little Patty says, 'aint father come? when will father come? O I shall be so glad when he comes!'" Poor girl! her hopes were all bright, and  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7564-00000035"/> 68      PETER GOTT' sunshine was in her loving heart. She little thought of the sad bereavement that awaited her. She little anticipated the bitter feeling of desolation that was so soon to come over her, and which she was to carry with lher, as a heavy-burden, to her grave. The blighted hopes, the burning tears, the cruel anguish that wrings the widow's heart, how little did she imagine she was soon to know them all, in her own bitter experience. She had repaired his summer clothes,-had made him a pair of new striped shirts, and knit two pairs of socks, and had them all washed and ironed, and neatly stowed in a basket, which Peter had made, during a snow-storm, the previ- ous winter. She had some hills of beans and cucumbers and a few cabbages growing in a little patch before her door, which she tended with the skill that love had taught her, because Peter would like them so, after being so long away upon the salt water, without the taste of any green thing. Two nice broods of chickens were peeping and scratching among the rocks, and all was bright and cheerful.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    69 On the morning to which we have refer- red, all hands on board the Jane turned out with the first gleam of day. Each man went silently and quietly to his work. No discordant sound was heard.  They set about weighing the anchor: But the "yeave ho!" as they pulled at the windlass bars, had a faint and mournful sound. They next set the jib and run up the mainsail. The skipper took the helm, and as she felt the breeze that was rising with the sun, put her awTay before it. The cook, in the meanwhile, was preparing breakfast. , After partaking of this, they put on all her can- -vas, and laid her- course for the rocks- of Cape Ann. Nothing of special interest occurred dur- ing the 'homeward passage. The weather was good; but as she was heavily loaded, and the wind blew   from  the westward nearly every morning, their progress was slow. About eleven, A. M., the wind gen- erally hauled to the eastward, when they put on all sail, and made the most of it till it went down with the declining sun. Two  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7564-00000036"/> 70      PETER GOTT, days after leaving the Bank, they fell in with the ship George, bound from London to Boston. They reported their catch, and the loss of a man. The ship reached Bos- ton two days before the Jane arrived at her port. How often is it true, that 1" com- ing events cast their shadows before them." Skipper Norwood was in Boston, and had just discharged his little freighter of her cargo of dry fish, and taken in some stores for Mr. Dennis, and was just ready to sail when the George came up to the wharf. The mate of the George, seeing a Cape Ann jigger at the stern, hailed the skipper and reported the Jane on her passage, with the loss of a man overboard. The jigger reached Pigeon Cove that night, and by sunrise the next morning, the report was circulating among the families at Pigeon Cove, Dog Town and Sandy Bay, that the Jane was coming, and that one of her hands was lost. Great anxiety pervaded all minds, , and every face'wore an expression of sad- ness. The loss of a man at sea, was no new thing in their experience, yet when   THE CAPE ANN FIS'HERMAN.    71 such an event occurred, it was always at- tended with a general feeling of sorrow. I The inhabitants are all connected by inter- marriage, and constitute, as it were, one large family, and when one of their num- ber is lost, it is felt as a general loss. It is with them, as with men on ship board at sea, when one is lost, each one is made to feel that death has come very near to him, and that his turn may be next. When Patty went down to the cove in the morning, she learned the sad news, and oh! how her- heart beat with anxiety and fear.  A sad feeling of depression came over her, as she slowly returned to her cot- tage. But hope still predominated in her bosom; she could not realize that she was to be the principal sufferer, that the stroke was to fall most heavily upon her head. "I hope it is not Jemmy Tarr! Poor Jane, it will kill her if it is! And Mary, she was married but a year ago last Christmas, I hope it is not Tim!"And thus she went over the whole list of the families con- nected with the crew, finding some strong I   ,      .  I  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7564-00000037"/>     72      PETER GOTT, reason in her sympathizing heart, why the loss should not fall upon either of them. The skipper they all felt was safe; but then it might -be his son, who was one of the crew, so that his wife had her full share of anxiety with the rest. How little do the farmers and dwellers in the country know of the anxiety and cruel suspense which the families of sea- men  and fishermen  suffer. . With their friends and children around them, and rare- ly separated from them, if, in the course of * nature, or during the prevalence of some epidemic, they become sick, they have' the privilege of ministering to their wants, and solacing their sufferings by all the kind offices that affection can suggest; and if they are taken from them, they follow them affectionately to the grave, and see them decently interred in some consecrated spot. where their parents or friends have been laid before them, and where they expect ^ themselves at length to repose. But the mother and wife of the sailor, who is lost at sea, have no such consolations. They   THE CA-PE ANN FISHERMAN.   73 think of him struggling in the cold waves, and lying upon the oozy bed of the ocean. Their gentle hands have not been permit- ted to smooth his dying pillow, and no kind words of parting can they treasure up in -their hearts, as precious mementos of the departed. There is nothing to break the force of the blow as it falls upon them, or to mitigate the bitterness of their grief. On the evening of the second of July, the crew of the Jane made the lights on Thatcher's Island. In the course of the night they anchored in the bay, and at day- light hoistedtheir jib and worked into the cove, and made fast to the ring-bolt on the capstan of Dennis's wharf. The sun was just rising as she reached her wharf. The news of her arrival almost instantly spread through the village. But all was still and quiet as a' Sabbath morning. Most of the men were away upon the water. Mr. Den- nis, Skipper Norwood and -his two men, and the few men and boys that were at home, soon collected upon the wharf. But the women, who were so eager the day before [l-  -    ,  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7564-00000038"/> 74      PETER GOTT, to learn the name of the lost one, actuated by a common feeling, remained at their homes, dreading the announcement which must but too soon be made. As soon as they had made all secure, the skipper and all the crew washed their faces, and took their several ways to their homes. Patty was busy with her children, in the expecta- tion of soon seeing Peter coming across the rocky pasture, upon the border of which her cottage stood; !   '   \   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.     75 CHAPTER VI. MR. DENNIS INFORMS PETER'S MOTHER OF HER SAD "OSS.- KIND NEIGHBORS. -THE'AFFLICTIONS OF THE POOR.--A WIDOW S STRUGGLES, AND HER REWARD, MR. DENNIS was a kind-hearted man, and no sooner had he learned from the skipper the circumstances attending Peter's loss, than hen took his way along the footpath that wound its course among the rocks and over the hill to Peter's cottage. The mo- ment Patty's eyes fell upon him, the sad truth flashed into her mind. As he enter- ed her door, her heart fell like lead, and a sense of suffocation came over her.  0h Oh, Mr. Dennis!" she exclaimed, " it's Peter; it's he that is lost!" and she fell upon a seat near the door, as if stunned by the overwhelming blow. She sat for a time speechless. Mr. Den- nis sat down by her side, and tried to speak  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7564-00000039"/> 76      PETER GOTT i some words of consolation. Her children, awed by the expression of her countenance, gathered around her. Little Mary, the youngest, who was sitting upon the floor, crept to her feet and put up her hands im- ploringly.- Mr. Dennis took her upon his knees. Peter and Patty stood by their mother's side, with the feeling that some terrible calamity had befallen them. At length little Patty, with tears stream- ing from her eyes, exclaimed, "Is father drownded? Won't he never come home again?"And now the mother's tears burst out in sympathy with the tears of her child, and catching her in her arms, she cried, c Yes, my child, dear father is drown- ed in the deep, cold sea. You will never see him any more. This is what I was always afraid of. How many times have I dreamed that I saw him struggling in the 'cold waves! But he did it for the best. He went for my sake, and for the sake of the children.'  And mother and child min- gled their streaming tears, as if they gushed from one fountain. After waiting a few   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    " minutes, Mr. Dennis gently placed the child, that had been quietly sitting upon his knee, upon the floor, and uttering at few kind words, withdrew, and left her alone with her sorrow. The poor have no time for sorrowing. The demands of nature require of them unremitting exertion. But the very efforts which their circumstances compel them to make, enable them the better to bear the burden of their griefs. This is one of the ways in which " the wind is tempered to the- shorn lamb." It seems a, severe disci- pline to the broken-hearted widow, to be compelled, even in the first hours of her fresh bereavement, to assume the whole burden of that care which has been hitherto shared by a kind and loving husband, and to be made to feel, in all its overwhelming force, that she is now the only guide and protector of her children; and yet how often, does the destitute widow bear up under the crushing weight of her burden, and nerve herself for the stern conflict of life, better than she who is made a widow i  -  *?*7  .  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7564-00000040"/> t'"     78      PETER GOTT, in circumstances of affluence, without a care for the supply of her future wants, and sur- rounded by  sympathizing friends. She gathers around her every token of his love and every memento of her loss. Scenes of past endearment, words of affection and smiles of love, though perhaps long forgot- ten, come crowding into her memory, and she thinks there never was loss like hers, and refuses-to be comforted. She cherishes her grief, and broods over her sorrow as though it were a duty she owed to the lost, 'until she is unfitted for the high responsi- bilities of a parent, which devolve upon her by the very fact of her being released from the duties of a wife. Not so is it in the cottages of the laboring poor. New cares, new wants and new responsibilities demand of the widowed mother new and redoubled effort; and these newcares and new wants are-present wants and present cares. They cannot be put off to a future day. These new responsibilities must be assumed at -once. There is no time for indulging the "'luxury of grief." Daily bread must be   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    ,79 won by daily toil. The mother's heart makes active the- mother's hands; and, trusting in the widow's God  she finds "strength according to her day." So it was" with Patty. Her children, Peter's children, must be provided for. Af- ter the first burst of grief was over, she set herself at once to encounter the stern realities of life. She relied chiefly upon her needle. Her poor neighbors were able to do but little for her, but that little they did cheerfully and in the kindest possible manner. - Many a thoughtful father, as he was dressing his fish, after his return from his day's work, selected a nice fish and sent- home by little Peter, who had gone down jto the cove, to see fthe, .en and boats as they returned at r' ,u; or when he put his wooden skewer through some nice slices of halibut, to carry home for his supper, remembered to add another generous slice, -and left it at Patty's door, as he passed by. When James Tarr, in the late autumn, had placed his quintal of dry fish upon his wheelbarrow, to carry home for his winter's  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7564-00000041"/> 80      PETER GOTT, store, he thoughtfully added a large armfu to his load, and left them at her cottage, a, he passed by to his own dwelling. ManJ a bowl of warm chowder was sent in, jus at the time when it was most wanted Peter was now in his seventh year, anc often he would take his father's hatchet stroll off into the neighboring thicket, anc cut- a. bundle of bushes and young beeches or 9lders, and bring them home for fuel andi as the cold weather came on, many X back-load of wood was thrown down before her' door by some one who remembered the widow and orphans. Mary's husband took it upon himself to cut-the wood which was thus brought to her door, and when the snow drifted around her house, he al. ways brought his shovel, and made her a wide and clean path. Much of the land in the interior of the Cape belonged 'at that time to the Com- moners, as they were called; that is, it be- longed in common to the proprietors to 'whom it had been first granted by the gov- ernment, and to their descendants; it had   m"   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   81 not passed .into private hands. These rocky hills were mostly covered with wood, which was looked upon by the fishermen as a common stock, from whence they ob- tained fuel for the winter. As there were no roads into the woods, and they had no teams, they brought home' most of their wood, in bundles, upon their shoulders. This practice was continued through seve- ral generations, and has scarcely ceased, even at the present day. The land had all passed into the hands of private owners before my day.  But it was with great difficulty that the fisherment could be made to understand that they had not a perfect claim to young trees wherever they Ed find them. Often, of a cold snowy mor-- ing, have I seen a group of fishermen start- ing for the woods, each with his hatchet/ and two or three yards of cod line. When they had cut as much as they could con- veniently carry, they made up a bundle with the line, and took it, upon their shoul- ders and trudged home, more than a mile, 1perhaps, through the snow. More than  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7564-00000042"/> 82     PETER GOTT, once have I seen a woman staggering under a burden of wood, which it seemed impos- sible for her to carry. This, in the time of the past generation, was no uncommon sight. In those days, the wives and daughters of the fishermen worked out of doors a considerable portion of their time. They cultivated their little patches of land with garden vegetables. They gathered their fuel in the summer. I was for many years acquainted with an excellent woman, who had been left a widow, with a large family of children de- pendent upon her for a living. She has often told me how she used to put on a pair of thick boots, and take her clam fork and go upon the flats, with her little boys, and dig clams, during ebb tide, day after day, in the cold of autumn and winter, to get bread for her children. When I knew her, she was in circumstances of comfort, surrounded by her children and grandchil- dren, who looked upon her grey hairs with reverence, and cheerfully supplied all her wants. For several years, she, with her   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   83 little boys, brought home on a hand-sled, or on their backs, all the wood which they burned through the long cold New England winters. She persevered, trusting in the widow's God, and she has found the promise fulfilled, "Train up a child in the way he should go, and when he is old he will not depart from it." Her three sons and five daughters are now all useful and respect- able members of society. The wives and daughters of the fishermen, in those days, were accustomed to make the fish. They were thrown in heaps upon the flakes by the men, after being properly salted, and left in the care of the women.  They spread them, and turned and tended them, until they were sufficiently cured. Some of the women became very expert in this business, and were employed, at day wages, during the season of making fish. Patty was thus employed for many days every summer by Mr. Dennis, who uni- formly treated her with kindness. He fur- nished her with flannel to make into shirts, and with woollen yarn to knit into socks,  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7564-00000043"/> 84      PETER GOTT, and although he was very strict in his reckoning, yet he allowed her the highest price, and now and-then, in making change, gave her the odd cent, although it was justly his due. Thus, by constant toil, by the practise of the most rigid economy, and by those ingenious shifts which were sug- gested by a mother's love, she managed to feed and clothe her children. At the close of the year, it would have been impossible for her to tell how her daily wants had been supplied, nor could she tell from whence her supplies in future were to be derived. But that Providence that feeds the little birds, and clothes the lilies with beauty, watched over her and never suffer- ed her to want. As years rolled on, though the wants of her children increased, yet they were able to render her more assistance. Many a time, during the long evenings of winter, as she plied her needle far into the night, with aching eyes and weary hands, with the wind howling and the snow drifting around her little cottage, while those dearer   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    85 to her than life were sleepig quietly around her, feelings of desolaton and sadness came over her, and she was almost ready to give up in despair. But she looked up, and behind the dark cloud she saw a gleam of light, and her hope revived and her courage was renewed. No New Eng- land mother will apply to the town for aid, until reduced to absolute despair. A feel- ing of self-reliance, a love of independence, a desire to see her children standing upon a level with those around them, sustain her amidst a world of difficulties and hardships. Call it pride ff you will. It is not that pride, connected with vanity, which is ', founded upon a false estimate of one's char- acter or merits, which prompts one to con- ceal from himself, or from others, his true condition, and which, in the order of Provi- dence, is destined to mortification. It is a feeling founded upon true self-respect, which leads to the formation of habits of industry, economy and integrity,-habits which nat- urally result in elevating the character and condition of those who possess them. Thou- 8 -  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7564-00000044"/> 86   6   PETER G0 TT, sands of the sons of New England have risen from the struggle with toil and pov- erty, to a position of usefulness and respect- ability, and have had cause to bless the pride of the mother, who has directed and encouraged their efforts. Patty, in common with her neighbors, had a full share of this feeling; and this, added to her trust in the widow's God, kept her from yielding to the feelings of despon- dency that sometimes came over her. Thus she struggled on, and with the' lapse of time found her comforts increasing and new sources of supply and of hope opening up before her. Her character for honesty and industry was well established. Her children were comfortably clothed, were affectionate and obedient to their mother, respectful to their superiors, and thankful for the little aids and encouragements which they received from those around them. ,[   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    87 CHAPTER    VII. PETER'S BOYHOOD. --HS EARLY EDUCATION.- EN- GAGES IN SHORE-FISHNG. - VISIT TO THE HARBOR WITH HS MOTHER. PETER, at the commencement of our story, had just completed his sixteenth year, and was able, by his daily labor, to contribute very much towards the support of the fam- ily. As he handed his daily earnings to his mother, it was withi a feeling of thankful- ness that he:'as abl:to cheer her toil, and do so much for her assistance. He felt as much real pleasure, when his brother ex- hibited his. new cap, or his sister her new shoes, that had been purchased by the money which he had earned, as when he put on his own new Kersey jacket, or his new thick boots. He had none of that selfish feeling, that required that the largest share of his earnings should be expended  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7564-00000045"/> 88      PETER GOTT, for himself. Indeed, he looked upon his younger brothers and sisters with no small degree of parental feeling, while, on their part, they looked up to him with feelings that partook of filial affection. He had been their guide and protector in their rambles in the woods and .on the hills, where they often went in the summer for berries. When they set snares in the fall and winter, for partridges and rabbits, he led the way. He was with them when they fished for cunners from the rocks; and when they ventured from the cove, in Mr. Den- nis's wherry, for mackerel, he had always brought them safely back to their mother, to whom he always felt that he was respon- sible for the precious charge entrusted to him. Hence had sprung up the filial feel- ing with which they regarded him, and the parental anxiety which he felt for them. Patty had been taught to read in her childhood, and by the aid of Perry's spel- ling-book, she had taught all her children to read. Peter had obtained Dilworth's Assistant, and by the aid of Jemmy Tarr,   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   89 he had mastered the four first rules of Arithmetic, and was able to multiply and divide with tolerable correctness. The nearest school was at Squam, a mile and a half distant, and the time of Master Riggs was fully occupied in teaching arithmetic and penmanship to the older boys and young men, during the two months in the winter, which were occupied by his school, so that Peter had derived no benefit from the free school. When he was fifteen years of age, he purchased a wherry of Mr. Dennis, for which he paid out of the earnings of the ensuing summer. At first he seldom went more than a mile froi the shore, and never except in company with some of the old men, who followed the shore-fishing. When fishermen become old and somewhat infirm, they seldom ship on board the larger crafts, but confine -themselves to the business of making fish on shore, or to wherry fishing. They go out only in good weather, but being well acquainted with the grounds which are frequented by the fish, they are 8*  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7564-00000046"/> 90      PETER GOTT, often quite successful. Young boys may be often found in company with them, and if they are kind and respectful to them, they will readily impart to them the secrets of the craft. During the first season, Peter generally kept in their company. He had, with the assistance of his mother, manufactured a sail out of a piece of an old schooner's sail. He next cut a sapling pine, and trimmed off the limbs, peeled off the bark, and fitted it for a mast. Old George Saunders showed him how to step-his mast, and assisted him -in bending his sail, so that when the wind was fair, he was saved/in great .measure the labor of rowing. Peter now, when on a bright morning he had pulled his dory out of the cove, and run up his sail, and drawn his sheet taut, and shipped his rudder, and taken his seat in the stern, felt himself quite a man. He was proud of his boat, and of his skill in managing her. A quick eye and a skilful hand are often needed in managing one of these little boats- along shore, even in the pleasant days of summer.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.     91 Sometimes a white squall will come off shore, so unexpectedly, that before the fisherman can let go the sheet, his little craft is lying with her gunwale in the wa- ter, or completely capsized. Many a poor fellow has been, in this way, emptied into the cold water, with all his gear, and unless assistance was at hand, has been lost. In August and September, several schools  of mackerel came into the bay, and Peter was quite successful in taking them, some- times making three or four dollars a day. Mr. Dennis furnished him with barrels and salt; and with the assistance of his brother, he dressed and salt@e   them. When* the mackerel fishbing was over, he Sad ten bar- rels of mackerel, for which Mr. Dennis allowed him five dollars a barrel, which, after paying- for the barrels and. salt, left him forty-four dollars.  He worked dili- gently through the season, and after pay- ing for his dory, his lines and bucket, and his clams for bait, his earnings at the close of the year amounted to eighty dollars, in addition to which he had a piles of nice -r - i  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7564-00000047"/> 92      PETER GOTT, scrods, and as many salted fish for winter as the family needed. His mother ventur- ed, upon the strength of his earnings, to run in debt a little at Mr. Dennis's store; but after -paying off the whole, she had a larger sum of money than she had ever seen at one time since the death of her husband. Peter was anxious that his mo- ther should have some articles of clothing more comfortable than she had been accus- tomed to wear, and that his brothers and sisters should share with him the comforts which might be purchased by the money he had earned. He never once thbught of hoarding any portion of it for his own use, or spending it for his own gratification. At Peter's urgent request, on a pleasant day, the week before Thanksgiving, Patty set out, with him by her side, for the "Har- bor." Gloucester harbor was at that time quite a village, and contained several stores, in which a much larger assortment of goods was to be found than at Mr. Dennis's store at the cove, and where, it was supposed, cash might be laid out to much better ad-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    93 vantage. The women from all the settle- ments around the Cape were in the habit of going once or twice a year to the Har- bor, to lay out the little sums which they had saved, and this excursion was one of the events of the year. They usually went in companies of three or four, and carried home their purchases in large bundles. The young women purchased ribbons and calicoes and morocco shoes. and the ma- trons linen cloth, India cottons, flannels, and muslins for caps, and needles and tapes, and various articles, of which mothers only know the use. Patty had made an excur- sion to the/Harbor eVery year while her husband lived. Peter" had never been to the Harbor, except on one occasion, when he went round with Skipper Norwood, with a deck-load of salted pee, which was to be shipped for Bilboa. Now for the first time he visited the motropolis of the Cape with his mother. They arrived at the Harbor soon 'after the middle of the day, and passing through Middle Street, took a deliberate survey of  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7564-00000048"/> PETER GOTT, the church, which had just been completed, and which was the most magnificent struct- ure Peter had ever seen. Then passing down Centre Street, they came into Front Street, which then, as now, was the princi- pal business street of the village. They went into one of the largest stores, attract- ed by the gay show of goods at the- win- dows. Peter was at first quite bewildered at the variety of articles displayed on the counter and shelves.  His mother, after deliberately looking around the shop, began to inquire the prices of the several articles which she wished toipurchase. The first article which she elected, was a piece of drab-colored  Kersey, to make Peter a jacket. The next was a nice Scotch cap, and then a large cotton- handkerchief. These were for Peter. She then selected some yards of cotton and linen check, for gowns for the girls, and some cotton and wool cloth for the boys, and lastly, a pattern of calico for a gown for herself. Peter had been for some time looking with much at- tention at a pile of nice woollen shawls that   lay upon the counter. Wheni she had com- pleted her selection, he called her attention to one of these, that had struck his fancy, She refused to take it, saying that she could do without it, and that they could not afford it. But Peter was very urgent that she should have it, and the shopkeeper joined him in persuading her to take it. At length, finding that Peter's heart was set upon it, and that he would feel hurt if she did not take it, she consented. Peter next selected a pink ribbon for his sister Patty's hair, a nice piece of calico for an apron for little Maryand a couple of pock- et knives forJemmy ani George. He then insisted that his moth'ershould put on her new shawl. The goods were then paid for, and packed up into a large bundle, which Peter took under his arm, and marched off, by the side of his mother, more highly grat- ified with her respectable appearance in her new and comfortable shawl, than most lads are, when, for the first time, they put on a long-tailed coat and a standing dickey. About sundown they reached their home, &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7564-00000049"/> 96      PETER GOTT, and sat down'to a warm supper, which sis- ter Patty had got ready for them, with thankful hearts. When Peter retired to his humble couch that night; the reflection that he had been able to do so much for the comfort and happiness of his mother and his brothers and sisters, caused his heart to swell with gratitude, and he felt completely repaid for all the labor he had undergone. His joyful feelings kept him awake a long time, as he lay forming plans for the future. At length he fell into a sweet sleep, while pleasant dreams occupied his mind. He fancied himself the skipper of a nice new schooner, while -his brothers and the boys, hisidaily companions, com- posed his crew. They brought in full fares of large, fine fish, which, when spread, cov- ered all the flakes in the yard. A long tier of barrels, filled with fat mackerel, was piled upon the wharf. A neat, new house occupied the place of the old cottage; his mother, dressed in her new  gown, and wrapped in her nice shawl, superintending the affairs of the house, and Patty, with her   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.      97 blooming face, her hair neatly combed and tied with a pretty pink ribbon, and Mary, with a bright-colored apron, assisting in her labors, -were always the most prominent actors in the shifting scenes.  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7564-00000050"/> 98      PETER GOTT, CHAPTER VIII. HAKE FISHNG.-MAKING ISINGLASS. IN the morning, refreshed and happy, Peter was up before the sun, and immedi- ately set about preparing for the work of winter. In the latter part of autumn and the early part of winter, hake abound in the bays and coves around the Cape. This fish is inferior to th--cod... It is about the size of the haddock, is somewhat coarse meated, and covered with large scales. It is taken at certain seasons, in large num- bers, and salted for the West India and South American markets, where it is con- sumed by the negroes on the plantations. The principal article received in exchange for this fish is molasses,-the better quali- ties of which are sold for consumption in families, and the inferior qualities for the use of the distillers. When the large ves-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    99 sels are laid up for the winter, the crews often engage in hake fishing. Hake, at the time of which we are speaking, were plenty in Ipswich Bay. Some of the men at the cove had already caught and salted several butts of these fish. The sounds of the hake are much larger and thicker than those of the cod and haddock, and it is from these, chiefly, that the American isinglass, or fish glue, is manufactured. The sounds are taken out by the fishermen when they dress the fish. They are then washed in fresh water, by the women and boys, and the black cuticl with which they are cov- ered, rubbed 'ff. Thei' are then strung upon twine, like dried apples, or spread upon the flakes and dried in the sun. There has existed for many years at Sandy Bay a factory for the manufacture of isin- glass. More than thirty years ago, a patent was granted for machinery, by which it is manufactured. At this factory one may often see from ten to twenty cords of hake sounds in one heap, ready to undergo the manufacturing process. This' process con-  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7564-00000051"/> 100     PETER GOTT, sists in soaking the dried sounds in warm water until they become soft. Then they are passed between iron rollers, by which the glutinous mass is worked into large cakes, about half an inch thick. These are passed between other rollers, until the whole is wrought into a mass of uniform consistence. This is now passed through a succession of rollers, from the last of which it comes out in ribbons, about four inches wide, and several yards long, of about the thickness of brown paper. These ribbons are then hung upon poles and dried, after which it is screwed into barrels, when it is ready for market.  The rollers by which the sounds are wrought into isinglass, were formerly turned by cranks, two men being attached to each set of rollers. This work was mostly done in the winter, and from forty to fifty fisher- men, chiefly old men, were engaged in this laborious employment. This labor is now performed by a steam engine. The hake, for some unknown reason, more readily take the hook in the night   4 THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   101 than in the day time. Probably their eyes are so formed, that, like the owl, they see better in the night than when the sun is shining. However this may be, it is cus- tomary to fish for them in the night. The men go out in their dories in gangs of from three to six. They go put soon after nightfall on still, pleasant nights, and return before dawn in the morning. It is a cold, hard and dreary business, but it lasts only a few weeks, the hake then leaving the grounds where they have been feeding. Probably, as the water becomes cold, they migrate into deeper and warmer water. Peter determined to join one of these gangs of hakers. His mother, at first, made many objections; but finding him in ear- nest about it, she consented; and putting him in charge of old Saunders, who prom- ised to take good care of him, she clothed him up warm and fitted him off. With his Scotch cap,' and his new cotton handker- chief around his neck, about six o'clock he stepped into his dory, and pulled out with the gang. In about an hour they reached 9*,   &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7564-00000052"/> 102A     PETER GOTT, the fishing ground in Ipswich Bay, when they threw over their killicks and com- menced their night's work. The night was dark and cold; but they lay within a few fathoms of each other, so that they could call to each other and hear each other's movements. They soon began to take in fish. At first Peter pricked his fingers in disengaging the hook from the fish in the dark. But he soon learned how to throw them off with a jerk, without exposing his fingers to the barb. Before midnight, he found it hard to keep awake, and his head would often nod, wlhi he- sat: waiting for abite. But soon :sudden puB upon his line would rouse hi! when he would draw in- his hake., At tinmes his feet were be- numbed, and his fingers ached with the- cold; but the taking of several fish in rapid succession, would quicken his circulation and restore warmth to his extremities. Thus while other -boys of his age were sleeping quietly in their warm beds, Peter was upon the dark waves, with the cold, damp wind blowing in his face, with no   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   103 shelter but the broad canopy of heaven, toiling, with wet and aching fingers, not for himself, but for his dear mother and his brothers and sisters. Let no- one say that warm hearts and strong affections are not found in the bosoms of the laboring poor, or that they are not capable of generous impulses, and great self-sacrifice for others. Because such men have a rough exterior, and a weather-beaten face, shall we, who may have a little more of this world's goods, turn away from them and treat them with disdain? They are our brethren, and not seldom the truesA1$%brothers we have, and entitled to our sym! tand our love, and even tO our revererl e, for the kindness of their hearts and the purity of their lives. About four o'clock in the morning, hav- ing nearly filled their boats, they took in their killicks and pulled for the cove, where they arrived about daylight. Leavingshis boat upon the beach, -Peter went to --his,: :-; home, where his mother was ready to:': ceive him with a nice warm  breakfast.-- After eating his breakfast, and resting a  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7564-00000053"/> 104     PETER GOTT, short time, he returned to the cove and dressed and salted his fish, which took him till almost noon. His brothers carried home the bucket of sounds, and set about washing and cleaining them. Their mother showed them how to string them, and they soon  had them drying in the sun. After Peter had got his dinner, he took off his jacket and boots and threw himself upon the bed and slept soundly for four or five hours. But he was awake and had got his supper and was on 'the ground at the appointed time, ready to commence the labor of the succeeding night. This he continued every pleasant night unil the middle: of Decem- ber, when the fisl becoming scarce, they quit this kind of fishing. By this time he looked worn and weary. Young persons, during the period of their growth, suffer more from the loss of their accustomed sleep, than from almost any amount of labor performed during the day. In truth, Peter's strength was not suffi- ciently matured, to sustain him long under the unnatural labor to which this night   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   105 work subjected him. The loss of sleep, the exposure to cold, and the severe labor at- tending this night fishing, breaks down many of the strong, hardy fishermen, and renders them prematurely old, giving to men of fifty the appearance of seventy. It is well for them that the hake fishing lasts but a few weeks. Soon after the close of this work, Peter commenced the regular business of-winter fishing, in which we found him engaged at the commencement of our story. Abra- ham Pool, and two or three other young- sters, were 3is frequent companions. Some twenty or? thirty fisheien, residing in the vicinity if the cove, r ulary followed the same business. It isla kind of labor that exposes those wh-engage in it to great hardship. They endure severe cold. Their feet become often so benumbed that they can scarcely walk. Their hands are con- stantly wet. They are frequently over- taken, while out on the water, with storms of rain, sleet or snow. Sometimes when they have gone out on a pleasant morping,  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7564-00000054"/> 106     PETER GOTT, they return in a driving snow storm, with their boats loaded with snow. As people in the country sit down to a dinner of nice codfish, they little think of the hardship and even danger to which the fisherman has been exposed in taking it. Many of these men suffer much from rheu- matism and neuralgic pains. Their muscles become contracted and stiffened, and they look and move like men bowed by old age. But, notwithstanding the hardships neces- sarily connected with their business, they pursue it patiently and unrepiningly, and win their bread from the ocen by unre- mitting toil.  # Peter followed th kind of fishing through the winter with tolhrable success, earning from one to two dollars a day in good weather. During the stormy days, he im- proved his time in the study of Daboll's Arithmetic, and in learning to write, and in assisting his brothers and sisters, who were now learning to add and subtract. The family got through the winter more comfortably than ever before, by the aid of Peter's labor.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    107 CHAPTER IX. PETER'S FIRST TRIP TO THE BANKS.-HOW THE EARN- INGS OF BANK FISHERMEN ARE DIVIDED.-PETER'S CARE FOR HS FAMLY. --SECOND TRIP.-A STORM AND ITS CONSEQUENCES. SOME time in March, Mr. Dennis pro- posed to Peter to ship on board one of his vessels, offering him a full share with the men. This was more than any lad of his age received 'ad wa, considered a 'highly advantageous offer. Petr immnediately told his mother, saying, "Ni, mother, you will not have to work, so hdl. Mr. Dennis has offered me a full shriif I will ship in the Polly, and it will not be half so hard as wherry fishing." This proposal brought to Patty's mind the scenes and the feelings connected with her husband's trip to the Banks, as though they had occurred but yesterday, and her eyes filled with tears at the recollection. She promised to think of %  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7564-00000055"/> 108     PETER GOTT, the matter. The next morning she went to Mr. Dennis's store, where she found James Tarr, who had ever been to her a faithful friend. They joined in persuading her that this was an opportunity for Peter which she ought by nomeans to neglect. Especially they urged, that by shipping on board a Banker, he would in a few years be qualified for a skipper, while in the shore fishing he would never be qualified for this office. This situation is the one to which young and. enterprising fishermen looks forward as the height of their ambi- tion; and Patty felt her mother's pride gratified with the praises which they be- stowed upon her rling boy, and with the prospect of soon seeing him in command of a fine schooner. The considerations pre- vailed, and she gave her consent, and im- mediately set about fitting him for the voyage. This was speedily accomplished; and early in April he sailed in the schooner Polly, Capt. Griffin, of sixty tons, for the Grand Bank. This was an important event in Peter's   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   109 life, and her neighbors heartily congratu- lated his mother upon his good fortune. The Polly made her first trip, encountering only the usual amount of wet and foggy weather, and returned the last week in June, with eight hundred quintals of fish. On her next trip, which was completed about the last of October, she brought in seven hundred more. This made her fif- teen hundred quintals. These fish were sold by Mr. Dennis for two dollars and twenty-five cents per quintal, amounting to three thousand three hundred and seventy- five dollars. The oil, amounted to one hundred and twenty dolars. Half of this sum, seventeen hundre? thirty-seven dol- lars, deducting half tha cost of the salt, or forty-three dollars, beonged to the crew. From this also was to be deducted five per cent., which belongs to the skipper, over and above his equal. share with the rest of the crew. There remained then to be di- vided among the nine persons on board, sixteen hundred and fifty dollars, giving to each man one hundred and eighty-three 10  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7564-00000056"/> "O     PETER GOTT, dollars. This sum was more than the aver- age made by the Bankers that season. But Capt. Griffin was resolute and enterprising, and most of the crew were smart, active men. There is much said among fishermen about good and bad luck; and indeed ves- sels do sometimes seem to meet with a Godsend, in the shape of a fine school of fish. But it is generally found that enter- prising, energetic men are more successful in fishing, as well as in all other kinds of business. The Polly was thought to have been re markably lucky, and her good luck was a frequent subject ofinversation in the fam- ilies at the cove through the ensuing win- ter. Peter was now thought to be rich, and many of his neighbors congratulated him upon his success. There were few among them, even those who had earned but little, who envied his good fortune. He was known to be so kind to his mother, and to have worked so hard for the support of his family, that all his neighbors consid- ered it but his just reward.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   1" After paying Mr. Dennis for the articles which he had had by way of outfit, and for what his mother had taken up for the fam- ily during the summer, he had one hundred and ten dollars left. This he put into his mother's hands, with the request that she would use it for-the comfort of herself and the children. The usual excursion to the Harbor was undertaken, and a stock of clothing purchased for the winter. Some articles of comfort were added to their scanty stock of furniture. Peter employed a carpenter to mafke him' a nice sea-chest. When the  carpenter had completed this chest, he engaged him to shingle the cot- tage and repair the windows, and make a 'new door.^i: These relirs, in addition to some othersm'ade beiself, rendered their habitation more comfortable than it had been for several years. He then procured some cheap lumber, and erected a shed to protect their fuel during the storms of winter; then he and his brothers labored diligently for several days in collecting fuel. This they piled up snugly in the  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7564-00000057"/> "2     PETER GOTT, shed which he had built. These various operations occupied the whole of the month of November. Peter was not disposed to engage, this year, in the work of night fishing; but he got out his dory and caulked anew her gap- ing seams, and payed her bottom with tar, and painted her gunwales, and fitted her with a new set of thole-pins, and overhauled his lines, and got ready for winter fishing. Most of, the men who go to the Banks in the summer, refuse altogether to engage in fishing in the winter, especially if. they have had tolerable luck ithe summer. A few of them, as we hae already stated, engage in foreign voyages for the winter, but most of them spend the- time in idleness, from the time the vesselh  ed up until she is fitted out again in the spring, by which time they have generally consumed all they had earned, and run up a considerable bill at the store. But Peter had grown up with habits of industry, and had been ac- customed to, labor in winter, as well as in summer; so he joined the company of win-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.  113 ter fishermen; and every pleasant morning through the winter was one of the first to get his wherry afloat, and put out into the bay for a day's work. The fish which he caught through this winter, amounted to sixty dollars; in addition to which, he car- ried home, for the use of the family, every day a fresh fish, a good mess of cods' heads, or a nice mess of tongues and sounds. So that instead of consuming the earnings of the previous summer, his labors supported the family, and in the spring, they found themselves possessed of even more than they had withfal.- When the spring :ved Peter shipped again for ihe Banks hey sailed the first week in April. Th weather was cold and stormy, a  ide  a boisterous passage to the Banks. They were driven out of their course far to the eastward of the Banks, and it was fourteen days before they found themselves on the fishing ground. They did very well for a few days.; but tle weather was cold and cloudy, and they had frequent snow squalls. At length, after an 10*  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7564-00000058"/> "4     PETER GOTT, unusually pleasant night, the wind began to blow from the east in gusts, accompanied with a peculiar howling sound, and the sea was heaving with a heavy swell. As they were going below to breakfast, the skipper observed, "After we have had our grub, we must make all snug, for we're going to have a snorter." When they returned on deck, the wind was blowing in sharp, spite- ful gusts, and the snow was rapidly falling. They immediately dressed off all the fish that were on deck, gathered up their fish- ing gear and carried it below, barred down the hatches, secured e water cask, and made every thing a fast as possible. X Be- fore noon the stormin:ad fearfully increased. The wind blew a Hurricane; the snow drifted in sheets alon:the surface of the- ocean, and so filled the air that it was im- possible to see to windward the length of the vessel. They payed out all their cable, expecting every moment that it would part, or that the vessel would drag the anchor. But she held -on through the remainder of the day, and until about daylight the next   THE CAPE'ANN FISHERMAN.   115 morning. The night was a fearful one. The vessel hove and rolled the livelong night. About daylight the cable parted. There had been no sleep on board through the long watches of that night. The moment the cable parted, the skip- per sprung to the helm and tried to keep her head to the wind; but finding that in spite of all his efforts she would broach to, he determind to get her before the wind, and scud under bare poles. ' To effect this, he watched his opportunity, and the first time she broached to, he gave her the helm; but as she fell a heavy sea struck her broadside and b:urd her many feet deep undeiA the -green aters., For a mo- ment it seeied as if sheiere settling down into the de ths ofc ean; but in ano- ther moment she came up, trembling in every joint, and freed hErself from the water. The men caught by the stays, and clinging with a'death grasp, saved them- selves from being washed overboard. When the vessel righted, it was found that her windward bulwarks had been carried away,  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7564-00000059"/> ,116     PETER GOTT, her boat stove, and every thing movable had been washed from the deck. Before the succeeding sea reached her, she had come round, and shot forward, like a bound- ing steed, before the wind. She held on her course, pitching and plunging through the foaming waves until past the middle of the day, when the storm began to abate. As soon as she would bear it, they got up a double-reefed fore- sail, and just at night, a small piece of the mainsail, so as to keep her steady, and hold on her course throughf-t-; night. Before morning the wing the wn t into-north-west, and the sky clee  up; butfa high sea continued to rui for two orthree days. As they had los  eir best nchor and cable, and their boavatsto  and their bulwarks badly damaged, the skipper de- cided to run home. The first light they made, was that of Cape Cod. The wind being northerly and the sea rough, they were three days more beating about the bay, before they reached their port. It was about four weeks before the repairs were   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   117; completed, and they were ready for sea again. It was now the first week in June. The first trip, of course, was lost. But they were- successful on the summer trip, and filled the vessel, and reached home by the 10th of September.   On selling the fish and making up the voyage, they divided ninety-two dollars to each man. This was their whole summer's work,-all they had earned during the six best months of the year,-from the first of April to the end of September. The outfits which Peter had taken up I^sthe   g  and the bill for goods whii "his   had taken up dur- ing the s-m n' .  nted to sixty-two dollars, le       dollars for Peter; to receive te:;ment. Most- of the crew were mn ebt to Mr. Dennis, their families having taken up more: than ninety- two dollars. To a man under such circumstances, with a wife and children to feed and clothe, the,  approach of a long and cold winter is any. thing but agreeable. In all our fishing /   &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7564-00000060"/> 18      PETER GOTT, ports, such instances occur nearly every year; and some years, the number is by no means small. Such men are thefi en- tirely dependent upon what they can earn from day to day, during the short, cold days-of winter. Perhaps they have never been accustomed to winter fishing, and own no wherries or fishing gear. They have no money to purchase them. If they run in debt for them, it will take half the win- ter's earning to pay for them. If they should be taken with sickness, in conse- qiuence of their unwo  osure, their failies -are often th:l ei:ums tumstances of real distress, andnent on charity for their d But Peter had'n iscourage- ment. He was acc          the winter, and he expected to do it.  He was now a stout young man of nineteen, :i. and his brother was fourteen. He was not in debt, but had something in the locker, : - and he would not allow his mother to de- prive herself of any of the comforts to which she had been accustomed for the last hoI- as A-  THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   119   - -  wo years. Capt. Griffin determined toi: lake an effort to retrieve the bad luck of  ie year, not so much on his own account,  3 on account of some of the crew, who    . ad large families to support. So, instead'  ' hauling up his vessel, he proposed -to    3 Mr. Dennis that he should fit herout, and t them try their luck at pollocking.   &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7564-00000061"/> 120      P-ETER GOTT, CHAPTER X. -POLLOCK FISHNG.-LOBSTER CATCHNG.-- POLITICAL TROUBLES. THE pollock is a kind'of fish that is found in schools, and is sometimes found in im- mense numbers on- our coasts, late in the autumn, on its return from the north to more southern regions. I, is about the size of the codfish-has a sharper head, and its back is of a dark bluecolor. Its flesh is somewhat coarser and darker than that of the- cod, and contains more gluten. When this fish is preserved with but little salt, and dried in the cool weather of au- tumn, it is a favorite fish for the table. It is eaten raw, stripped into small pieces. But it is generally high salted, and shipped with the hake to the south, for the use of the plantation negroes. The pollock is caught and cured in the   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   121 same way as the cod. The season for tak- ing it lasts but a few weeks. Capt. Griffin was ready about the last of October, and was joined by most of the men who had been' with him to the Banks. Two of them, men who had no families, had gone to Boston, to ship for a voyage to St. Do- mingo. Their places were readily supplied by two other men. They went as -far east as Mount Desert, and in the course of three weeks took - four hundred quintals, worth, when cured, one dollar and a quarter per quintal. This gave to each man about twenty-seven dollars, a matter of no small importance to a destitute family. The Polly was now stripped, and laid up for the winter. Most of the men immedi- ately engaged in winter fishing, and those who were industrious got through the win-' ter without absolute suffering. By the first of December, Peter, was in his wherry, engaged in his usual winter employment. Hte was tolerably successful, although the codfish had mostly left the coast. 'These fish often leave the coast -in-   &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7564-00000062"/> 122     PETER GOTT, the winter almost entirely. When this is the case, the fishermen depend chiefly upon the haddock. These fish are somewhat smaller than the cod, and are esteemed in- ferior to them when codfish are plenty; the haddock do not bring so high a price in the market as the cod. But when cod are not to be had, the haddock sell freely at about the same price that is usually paid for cod. The flesh of the haddock is white and delicate, but drier and less glutinous and oily than the cod. When salted and dried, they become very hard, and will keep well. In this state they are shipped in great quantities, with hake and pollock, to the southern market. About the first of March, Peter engaged in the service of a company, that had set up an establishment for the catching- of lobsters, on Thatcher's Island. These shell fish formerly abounded along the rocky shores of the Cape, and were often taken of very large size. There still exist, among the fishermen, traditions, of a somewhat mythical character indeed, of lobsters hav-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    i23 ing been taken that weighed forty pounds. If there is any truth in these traditions, the Pilgrim Fathers must have found " feasts of fat things among the treasures of the sand." From traditions of the same date we learn that the clams and quohogs of those days corresponded in size to these many-armed, mail-covered monsters. What glorious clam bakes, they must have had! Lobsters are taken in a sort of baskets, called lobster-pots. These are aout three feet long, and two feet wide, of semi-cylin- drical form, that is, the bottom is flat and the sides and top are in the form of an arch. At each end is an opening for the ingress of the lobster; around this opening are placed short flexible pieces of wood, projecting into the basket, so arranged that. they will easily separate and allow the lob- ster to enter, but their points close together after him and prevent his egress. They have a door upon the top, through which the lobster is taken out. A long line is attached to these pots; a heavy stone, sufficient to sink them, is  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7564-00000063"/> 124     PETER GOTT, placed in them, and they are bated with the heads or offal of fresh fish, and sunk to the bottom at about low water mark; the- other end of the line is made fast to a block, of light wood, called a buoy. The fisher- men go out with their wherries, freighted with these pots, and drop them at short intervals along the shore. 'During the sea- son of lobster fishing, which lasts from March to July, hundreds' of these buoys may be seen bobbing up and down like so many seals' heads.  Tile fishermen visit them every morning, draw them up along- -side of their boats, take out the lobsters, replenish the bait, and drop them again into the water. The lobsters, when first taken, are very fierce, and seize with their strong pincers upon whatever may be with- in their reach. When thrown together into the boat, they'will grapple with each other and tear off each other's feelers and legs. Without much care in handling them, the fingers of the fishermen get many a hard bite.  To prevent them from injuring each other, the fishermen provide sharp-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   125 pointed wooden pegs, which they insert into the joint or hinge of their pincers, which prevent them from closing. When they have visited all their pots, they row to their landing-place. If they now wish to preserve them for several days, they put them into a long box or kennel, made of plank and bored full of holes, which is moored in the water at a little distance from the shore. If they wish to prepare them immediately for market, they are taken ashore in hand-barrows and carried to a sort of shed, in which is fixed a large cauldron. This is filled with water. A brisk fire is kindled under this kettle, and when the water boils, the living, crawling, squirming lobsters are thrown into it and covered with a heavy plank cover. Here they are kept boiling until their color, which when taken out of the water was a dark green, becomes a bright scarlet. They are now ready for the market. In this state we see them for sale on the stalls in our cities and hawked about the streets. Peter continued in this  employment "$  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7564-00000064"/> 126     PETER GOTT, through the month of March. It is a busi- ness attended with severe exposure to the weather, and often, when the water is rough and the surf is breaking upon the shore, with considerable danger. He was glad to be freed from it; and about the first of April engaged in fitting out the Polly again for the Banks. She sailed on the tenth, and made two trips during the season with tolerable success. His share of the proceeds, this year, was two hundred and twenty dollars. His brothers and sis- ters were now able to earn their own liv- ing. One of ;his sisters was living as a housemaid in the family of C apt. Saunders, at the Harbor. By her industry, fidelity, and good temper, she had secured the good will and confidence of this family, and re- ceived from them many presents, in addi- tion to the two and sixpence per week which she received as wages. Patty was now in circumstances of much comfort, and wash considered by her neighbors as quite independent. Having studied in the school of affliction, she had a sympathizing heart \ A   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   127 for all who were suffering from bereavement or want, and was ever ready to aid them by her counsels, and to impart to them of her moderate store. She found frequent occa- sion for her services among the sick, and was lookedup to by all her acquaintance with much confidence and respect. But other trials were now preparing for her- trials which she was to undergo in common with her neighbors and countrymen. The  cloud which for years had been gathering over the political horizon, but which had hitherto but little affected these peaceful dwellers upon the shore, was daily growing darker. The difficulties between the colo- nies and the mother country were begin- ning to assume a serious aspect. The trade of Boston was much embarrassed, and its entire extinction threatened. It was be- coming difficult for the fishermen to obtain from Boston the means of fitting out their vessels, and the market for their fish was growing uncertain. The next March,' the owners of fishing vessels in Gloucester sent a vessel to Ports-  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7564-00000065"/> 128      PETER GOTT, mouth, for the first time, to obtain salt, be- cause it could not be obtained in Boston. And it was with difficulty, and at a high cost, that they obtained molasses, pork and meal for their Bankers. Sailcloth, cordage and anchors had hitherto been almost en- tirely imported from England. As the trade with the mother country became in- terrupted, these, and other needful articles, assumed an exorbitant price. The fisher-' men struggled along under these difficul- ties until Boston harbor was actually closed by the presence of a British fleet. \ From that time, owing to the impossibil- ity of obtaining the means of sailing their vessels, to the loss of their market, and to the danger of capture by British cruisers, the Bank fishing was entirely given up. During the seven years that followed, the only branch of the fisheries pursued, was the shore fishing. This was carried on to, some extent, in small sail-boats and wher- ries, especially in, the winter, when cruisers could not remain on the coast. These boats pursued their business between Cape Ann   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    129 and Cape Cod, running out occasionally as far as the middle bank, and carried their fares into Boston arid Salem for a market. A small trade also sprung up between the coast and the interior, the farmers carrying their pork and corn to the coast, and ex- changing them  for fresh or salted: fish. But the Bank fisheries, which just before the? Revolution had become of great value, were completely ruined, and the men en- gaged in them were driven to seek other employments, to obtain a livelihood. Some few, who had acquired sufficient means. removed into the country and purchased land and became farmers. But sailors and fishermen are in general averse to engage in any occupation upon the land. They prefer to linger upon' the shore, and draw a precarious subsistence from the ocean. A sailor, when away from the water, is like a fish out of his proper element.  The mountain and the forest have no charms for him. But the fishermen entered heart- ily into the struggle for the defence of the liberties of their country. Two companies  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7564-00000066"/> 130     PETER GOTT, of militia, from the Cape, under Capts. Warner and Rowe, were in the battle of Bunker Hill. Two men were killed and two wounded in Capt. Warner's company, and three killed and two wounded in Capt. Rowe's, in that battle. Capt. Warner's company continued in the service, under Washington, and was in the famous retreat from Long Island. Upwards of two hun- dred and twenty men voluntarily enlisted from the Cape, during the first campaign of the Revolution.  When Congress re- -,quested every State to furnish its full quota, 137 men were assigned as the proportion from Gloucester. "   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   131 CHAPTER XI. PETER SHPS ON BOARD A PRIVATEER. -IS CARRIED TO HALIFAX. -DARTMOOR PRISON. WHEN letters of marque were issued by the authority of the American Congress, ,and privateers were authorized to be fitted out, many of the seamen and fishermen, who were out of employment in the ports of the Eastern States, eagerly engaged in this business and did much to annoy the commerce of England. The schooner War- ren, lying idle in Gloucester harbor, was immediately fitted out, under the command of Capt. Lane, who had been engaged in the West India trade. He was a good sea- man, and the young fishermen were earnest to enlist under his command. The schooner carried two guns, and had a crew of fifty men. Peter entered heartily into the cause of his country, and as many of his associ-  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7564-00000067"/> 132     PETER GOTT, ates had enrolled their names among the crew of the Warren, it required but little persuasion to induce him to do the same. 'This was a sore trial to his mother, and she shed many tears in view of the hardships and danger to which her son might be ex- posed. But in those days the women of America were not backward in the cause of their country, but were ready to sacri- fice their own ease and comforts to pro- mote that cause that was so dear to their husbands and sons. Many brave-hearted mothers consecrated their sons to the ser- vice of their country. During the darkest periods of that long struggle, when many prudent men became disheartened and de- sponding, the courage of the women never failed. - They felt that their cause was just, and without entering into minute calcula- tions, with regard to the means at their disposal, they confidently believed that the . issue would be in favor of the right. ;inh': een Peter had decided that it was his duf i^ o enlist, his mother, although she did not actually give her consent, immediately   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    133 set about preparing his clothing for the voyage; and when, in a few days, he left her to embark on board the Warren, which was now ready for sea, she/ gave him her hearty blessing. Capt. Lane, who had an eye for a good sailor, no sooner saw the clean and active limbs of Peter, his intelligent eye, and his manly and thoughtful countenance, than he at once set him down for his boatswain. He immediately undertook the duties of his office, and the captain had never occa- sion to regret-his choice. As the Warren left the wharf, she was cheered by the whole population of the harbor, assembled on the. shore. On the fourth day out, they fell in with an English vessel, loaded with lumber, bound from Halifax to' Jamaica. As she had but few men, and was unarmed, she immediately surrendered. They took her crew on board-C their own vessel, put three men on board her and sent her into port, where- she ar- rived in safety. They now laid their course for the West 12  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7564-00000068"/> 134     PETER GOTT, Indies, hoping to fall in with some English merchantman. In a few days they descried a sail, and immediately gave chase, with all the sail they could carry. But they soon discovered that the vessel of which they were in pursuit was no merchantman, but a British sloop of war, that was now bear- ing down upon them. As soon as this dis- covery was made, the schooner was put about, and all sail crowded, to escape the enemy. The sloop made every effort to come up with her. But the Yankee showed a clean pair of heels, and when the sun rose the next morning, her pursuer was nowhere to be seen. In about twenty days from the time they sailed, they were in the neighborhood of Jamaica. Here they cruised for two days, when they fell in with a small brig, with a cargo of sugar, coffee, rum and molasses. They ran across the stem of the brig, and demanded her surrender; 'but, instead of this, the brig crowded all sail, hoping to escape. Capt. Lane now sent a ball through her sails, and ran alongside, with the inten- :t   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    135 ion of boarding her. The captain of the      1 rig finding that the schooner was fully rmed, and that he had no chance of es- ape, hauled down his flag and hove her o. The privateer immediately took pos- ession of her, and removed her officers to lis own vessel. Upon looking at her man- fest, Capt. Lane found her cargo to be very valuable, as West India goods then )ore a high price in the American market. [Ie was very desirous of getting her in safely. So after taking out a box of sugar, i puncheon of ruinm, some bags of coffee and two or three barrels of molasses, for the use of his crew, he selected five of his most efficient men and three of the brig's crew, and ordered her into Boston. Peter was one of the five men whom he selected for this hazardous task. On the fourth day. after they parted company, the privateer fell in with a ship, bound from London to Jamaica. Her crew was well armed. But after a conflict, which lasted about fifteen minutes, during which two of the British seamen were killed, and i      '*,  ,*  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7564-00000069"/> 136     PETER GOTT, the first mate was wounded, and four of the Americans were wounded, they suc- ceeded in boarding and taking possession of her. Capt. Lane took from the ship the remainder of her crew,'and put his mate and eight men on board, and sailed for home in her company.  In eighteen days he moored his prize safely in Salem harbor. But the prize crew, on board the brig, were not equally fortunate. When they had arrived within two days' sail of Boston, they were descried by a British sloop of war, and the brig being a dull sailer, and heavily loaded, was soon cap- tured. The- British captain placed the five Americans in irons, and putting an officer and three men on board, in addition to the three English sailors whom he found in her, sent her to Halifax, where she arrived in six days. As the brig did not arrive in the United States, it was a long time uncertain whether she had foundered at sea, or had been re- captured by the enemy. It was generally supposed that she had been lost at sea, as   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   137 there had been- a somewhat severe gale about the time when she must have been approaching the coast. Of course, Patty, as well as the friends of the other four men, Pqter's companions, was greatly dis- tressed, and held in a state of most anxious suspense. This state of cruel suspense, in which the mind fluctuates between fear and hope, is often worse than the dread certainty of loss. It is often surprising, with what tenacity the friends of the lost sailor will cling to the hope of his return. His vessel has been run down, and he has been saved by leaping on board the vessel which has struck them, or he has taken to the boat, and been picked up by some out- ward bound vessel, and will return in her. Such events, no doubt, sometimes do occur. But they are, "like angel visits, few and far between." But the bare pos- sibility of such an occurrence is sufficient to buoy up the desponding heart of a be- reaved wife or mother. Often have I known such a wife or mother cling to such a for- lorn hope, after all others had arrived at 12 '  .      1  2        &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7564-00000070"/> 138     PETER GOTT, the certain conviction that their friends were lost. Patty could not believe that her beloved son, the joy of her heart, was lost. She chose to cherish the belief that the brig had been recaptured. But her heart was heavy and her countenance sad, and 'night after night, did she wet her pillow with tears, as she thought of the hardships he was suffering as a prisoner in the hands of the enemy. Still more bitterly did they flow, when she admitted the possibility that his fair form was lying upon the oozy bed of the ocean, or had been a prey to the monsters of the deep. Sorrow rapidly per- formed the work of time upon her person, and her hair became prematurely grey. -But hope never entirely forsook the mo- ther's heart. She loved to talk of his vir- tues with her children and neighbors, and to tell of the toils he had endured and the hardships he had undergone, for her sake, even in the tender years of his boyhood. She could not give him up; hope still lin- gered in her heart. Reports began to be ,t   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    139 circulated about this time, respecting the treatment to which American prisoners were subjected in the prison-ship at Halifax. It was said -they were confined in the damp, leaky hulk of a condemned man ofwar and that at every rising tide they were obliged to pump for their lives, to keep down the water, which would otherwise have drown- ed them,-that they were kept in irons, and allowed barely food enough to sustain life, and that, often of so poor a quality that only starving men could eat it. 'These re- ports brought little consolation to the hearts of those who believed their friends were the subjects of such treatment. But they served to exasperate Americans against a nation whose government could be guilty of such barbarous conduct. Alas! for the unholy passions enkindled by the usages of war. More than two generations have passed away since these events occurred, 'but the bitter feelings which they produced in many hearts, are scarcely yet forgotten. About two years after Peter was taken prisoner, he succeeded in sending a letter \  I    '  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7564-00000071"/> "O     PETER GO,TT, to his mother, acquainting her with the circumstances of his capture, and the fact that he was still a prisoner. With a delicacy which can exist only in a loving heart, he made no complaint of the cruelty to which he had been subjected, lest the details should distress his beloved mother. But he told her not to be discouraged; that he should one day be set at liberty, and be returned to his country and his friends. He stated that his four companions were alive and' well. Oh! what a thrill of joy did this short letter send through the hearts of those who had given up -their friends for lost, and how did it reward the faith and hope of Peter's mother. It seemed that her prayers were about to be answered, and her hopes realized. But, thankful as she was that her beloved son was alive, her patience was to have yet a longer trial; her maternal anxieties were- not yet ended. It was soon reported that fever was pre- vailing among the prisoners at Halifax, and that many of them had fallen victims to it, and then it was reported that the Ameri-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    141 can prisoners were to be transferred to England, and there be tried as rebels against their king.  No further news from Peter reached his friends until the expiration of another year, when a letter, dated in England, reached them, informing them that the prisoners had been removed from Halifax to Eng- land, and were now confined in the prison of Dartmoor. .He had been sick, very sick of the fever, but was now- in- tolerable health. Two of the men from Gloucester, his companions, had died of the fever, and they had all suffered severely from it. The prison of Dartmoor had not then the noto- riety which it subsequently attained. In the war of 1812, five thousand American prisoners were at one time confined there. On one occasion, without any provocation, the British soldiers on guard fired upon the unarmed prisoners, and killed seven in cold blood, and woundeda several others. The cruelties to which these prisoners were subjected within its walls, have rendered its very name a disgrace to the British na-  &#xD;<pb n="142 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7564-00000072"/> "2    ' PETER GOTT, tion. This prison is situated in the'middle of a bleak moor, upon a damp, marshy soil, without a tree to shelter it from the scorch- ing sun in the summer or to screen it from the piercing blasts of winter. Its inmates were lodged upon the damp ground, and fed upon the coarsest fare. Many strong and vigorous constitutions were broken down by the hardships which they here suffered. Jail or typhoid fever was almost always present, owing to the idepressing circumstances by which the prisoners were surrounded, and at some seasons was aw- fully fatal. Peter had a kind heart, and after his own recovery, most of his time waS em- ployed in nursing his sick associates. Dur- ing his own sickness, he had felt the want of a kind and sympathizing friend. The offices of such a friend he now supplied to many of his countrymen; many a young man, attacked with disease, and with home- sickness, owed his recovery to his sympa- thizing care, and to his efforts to cheer his spirits and to keep alive the dying embers   &#xD;<pb n="-143" xml:id="VAC7564-00000073"/>   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.  143 of hope. These efforts, no doubt reacted favorably upon himself. They furnished employment to his body and mind, and served to strengthen his own hope of final  deliverance.   &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7564-00000074"/> "4     PETER GOTT, CHAPTER XII. PETER RETURNS HOME.- CHANGES AT HOME. AFTER Peter had been confined two years and a half within the walls of this prison, he was returned to New York on board a cartel, which was sent out by the, British government to effect an exchange of pris- oners. He reached New York in safety, after a passage of forty days, but so chang- ed in appearance, that, when he landed upon the wharf, even the maternal instinct of his own mother would not have known him. Here he was, with the other returned prisoners, delivered to the officer deputed by General Washington to receive them. After being comfortably clothed, partly from the government stores and partly by the charities of the citizens of New York, and remaining a day or two to recruit their wasted strength, Peter and his two com-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   145   , panions from Gloucester started on foot, and travelled from New York to Cape Ann, living upon the charity of the inhabi- tants by the way. Early- one morning, after having walked during the night from Boston, they appeared in the midst of their friends and neighbors; as men risen from the dead.   On entering the village of Gloucester, they stepped into a small shop, which stood nearly opposite to where the Gloucester House now stands. One of the travellers was immediately recognized by the keeper of the shop, with whom he had formerly sailed on a trip to the Banks. The news of their arrival flew through the village. On leaving the shop, they had scarcely passed half the length of the street, before they were surrounded by a crowd of men, women and children, eager to see them, but many of them doubting their identity. A gentleman by the name of Sargent observing the crowd from his win- dow, stepped out to inquire its cause, and immediately invited" them into his house, and gave them a warm and hearty breakfast. i13    &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7564-00000075"/> "6     PE TER GOTT,. The three men belonged in different sec- tions of the town. . On leaving the house of Mr. Sargent, they separated, to find their own homes. Peter, wayworn and foot-sore, started for the home of his childhood, on the eastern declivity of Pigeon Hill. He reached his mother's house a little before noon. The scene that occurred upon his meeting his mother and sister, we will not attempt to describe. It may be better im- agined than described. He found his mother greatly altered in appearance during the five years of his absence. Sorrow and anxiety had rendered her countenance pale, had changed her locks to grey, and planted wrinkles in her brow. But the same loving and trusting heart still throbbed in her bosom. His sister had grown to be a woman. His older sister had married a young man, who had become acquainted with her while living at Capt. Saunders's, and was living at the harbor. His brother, who was now an in- dustrious young man, was absent on a fish- ing trip.- On his labor his mother was now chiefly dependent for support. \  '    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   147 The appearance of the whole neighbor- hood had undergone a marked change. The indications of thrift, which it presented at the breaking out of the war, were no longer visible. The houses presented a dilapidated aspect. The shops and wharves at the cove were falling into decay. Many of the most active and efficient inhabitants were gone. Many women, whom he had' left happy wives, were now clothed in the weeds of widowhood. The whole popula- tion of the town, and especially the male portion of it, was much diminished. It is a historical fact, that the number of tax- payers in five years ending with 1779, di- minished from 1053 to 696. This loss fell chiefly upon the seafaring population. Nearly every family had been bereaved of a husband or a son; and when: the :people were assembled upon the Sabbath, or on any public occasion, they appeared like a com- pany of mourners assembled for a funeral service, The- fishing business, and especially the Bank fishing, which had-been the principal  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7564-00000076"/> "8     PETER GOTT, source of the prosperity of the town,' had almost entirely ceased. Some wherries- and a few sail-boats, from ten to fifteen tons burden, were employed in shore fish- ing. At Gloucester harbor the grass was growing upon the wharves, and many of the larger class of fishing vessels were rot- ting at their moorings. This loss of men, of business and of property, and the heavy taxes which the survivors were called upon to pay for the support of the army, was their share of the price which our fathers paid ,for our national independence. While we are enjoying the blessings which have resulted from this independence, how little do we think of the cost at which our fathers purchased it. Peter's health had been much impaired, and his strength much exhausted by the long confinement and the hardships which he had undergone.  But his youth and good -constitution, after a few weeks' rest, restored him to health and strength, so that when winter came on, he fitted up his dory and engaged with his brother in his old business of winter fishing.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN. ,149 In the meantime, soon after Peter's re- turn, Cornwallis surrendered to General Washington, and hostilities between the colonies and the mother country ceased. Negotiations were entered into between the hostile countries, and our independence was acknowledged. Returning peace gave a new impulse to business. American enterprise showed it- self in various directions.' Notwithstand- ing the currency was in a very embarrassed condition, and the country was staggering under the burden of taxation, the energetic men of New England began to bestir them- selves. Vessels that had been lying for years at the wharves, were overhauled and repaired and refitted, and the flag of the United States began to show itself in for- eign ports. Mr. Dennis still survived, and notwith- standing all his losses, a considerable amount of his property -remained. One of his ves- sels was pronounced seaworthy, and he purchased another, the property of a man who had been killed on board of a privateer. 13*  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7564-00000077"/> 150     PETER GOTT, These were fitted for sea in the best man- ner that his means permitted. Mr. Dennis now invited several old fishermen, who had formerly been in his employment, to en- gage again in his service. Many lads, whose fathers had sailed in his vessels, but who had been lost in- the service of their country, had now grown up to man- hood. For these, it was noticed, he ever had a special regard. Several of them were shipped on board his two vessels. Mr. Dennis had no sooner commenced the work of repairing these vessels, than he offered the command of one of them to Peter, ,who at once accepted it.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   151  CHAPTER   XIII. PETER BECOMES SKIPPER OF A FISHNG VESSEL. - "ABRADOR FISHNG.- CLANNISH FEELINGS.-PETER BUILDS A HOUSE AND MARRIES A WIFE. PETER was a true Yankee.  Although possessed of a large share of prudence, he was fond of new enterprises. So he deter- mined to seek his fortune in a new field. When the vessel was ready for sea, he laid his course for the Bay of St. Lawrence, and entering to the eastward of Cape Bre- ton, he crossed it to the east of Labra- dor. He had heard that codfish were abundant along this shore. He found the report correct. The fish, though smaller than the Bank fish, were very numerous. He anchored a few miles from the shore, and immediately commenced operations, and in a few weeks had his vessel filled  with the shore cod. In the meantime, he  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7564-00000078"/> 152     PETER GOTT, had examined the shore for several miles, in his boat, and having selected a small cove suited to his purpose, when his vessel was filled and the fish salted, he ran into the cove and anchored near the shore. A part of the crew were occupied in landing the fish, and himself, with the remainder, erected fish-flakes and a hut. In a few days the fish were all spread, and the pro- cess of drying was rapidly going on. The weather on this coast during the -short summers of this climate, is delightful. The green grass and the modest violets -spring up along the edge of the melting snow. Summer immediately follows win- ter, and spring is unknown. So at the close of summer, winter immediately sets in, without the intervention of autumn. From the middle of May to the middle of September, the long days push vegetation rapidly forward, and these rugged shores are covered with the richest verdure. The sun shines with such intensity that the ut- most care is necessary in making the fish. They require to be turned two or three   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   153 times a day; but by this process the dry- ing is rapidly accomplished. They had no sooner got their fare upon the flakes, and taken in a fresh supply of water from a sweet spring which they found at a short distance from the shore, than they put off again to the fishing-- ground, leaving one of their most experi- enced men to make and house the fish. In about three weeks they filled the vessel again with fish, and took them to the shore. When they had got their flakes again filled, a part of the crew was occupied in tending them, while the rest cleaned out the hold and prepared it for the reception of the dried fish. As soon as this was done, they began stowing the dry fish on board. By careful stowage, two fares of dry fish: may be stowed in the space occupied by one of fresh fish. In a few days the work was all accomplished, and the hold was packed full of dry fish. The oil-butts and fishing gear were secured upon the deck, and wood and water sufficient for the trip home was taken on board.  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7564-00000079"/> 154'     PETER GOTT, Towards the close of the day, when the dew began to fall and the fish had been thrown into hakes, the younger portion of the crew usually roamed into the surround- ing forest with their guns, or crawled along the shore, concealed by the bushes, in pur- suit of the sea-fowl, that abound at this season in these waters. Many a meal of fresh game from the woods, or of ducks and brandt, was thus obtained. When they were ready to sail for hQme, the skipper' and all the crew spent one whole day in hunting. During the day they shot one deer and several small animals, and got sadly frightened: by a bear, which, after a smart fight, finally escaped them. But they returned to the shore at night heavily loadd. with game, and, carrying it all on board, prepared to sail with the rising sun ofdthe next day. They had a pleasant run home, and reached the Cape on the twentieth of Sep- tember. On landing, and weighing off their fare, it was found to amount to six hundred and fifty quintals. The fish found a ready *           as   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   155 market in Boston, but owing to the depre- ciated state of the currency, a large part-of the pay was received in goods, which Mr. Dennis, after charging them with his com- mission and the expense of carrying the fish to market, fairly divided among the crew. Peter, now having the command of a vessel, was not disposed to. lie idle; so, fit- ting her out again, he engaged, about the middle of October, in the pollock fishery. In this he had good success, and hauled up his schooner the last week in November, just in time to celebrate Thanksgiving with his mother, and brothers and sisters. This was the first time for seven years, that they had been together on this, the annual fsti-  val of New England. They talked. t the happy days of former years, of the separa- tion and trials and hardships they had since endured, and recounted, with swelling hearts, the mercies they were now enjoy- ing. Such united sacrifices upon the altar of gratitude do good to all hearts. May these time-honored gatherings around the  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7564-00000080"/> 156      PETER GOTT, hearth-stones of their childhood never cease among the sons of New England. Peter spent the ensuing winter chiefly at home, making preparations for an early trip the ensuing spring. During the long winter evenings, he became acquainted with Mary Griffin, the daughter of Capt. Griffin, with whom he sailed in the Polly, before the breaking out of the war. Capt. Griffin had sailed from Gloucester as mate of a privateer, which was never heard from after she sailed, and was believed to have been lost at sea. Mary was about twenty years of age. The acquaintance very natu- rally ripened into an attachment, the result of which was their marriage in about two years from this time. Peter's care for his mother, and the vicissitudes and hardships to which he had been exposed, had pre- vented him from forming any- early attach- ment, as was then, and is still common among fishermen. It has ever been a rare thing for a young fisherman to go off the Cape, or out of the circle of his acquaint- ance, for a wife. Hence all old families on    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   157 the Cape are connected by intermarriages, and have become, as it were, one family. This gives rise to a feeling of union, to a common interest in each other's welfare, and perhaps to a degree of clannish feeling. They live in a little world of their own. For a century past, it has been a strange thing for one of their number to go from home, and marry and settle in another town. A natural effect of this attachment to their home has been, that whatever pe- culiarities there might be in their habits of life, in their modes of intercourse with each other, in their language and in their man- ners, has been handed down from genera- tion to generation, and become ingrained into their very constitutions. They feel a degree of jealousy towards all strangers who come among them, and although they exercise the virtue of hospitality in a high degree, they continue to call them stran-  gers, until they have resided fifteen or twenty years among them. Even after a man has been a useful citizen among them during this length of time, if he attempt to "  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7564-00000081"/> 158     PETER GOTT, take an active part in public affairs, he must expect to be. reminded by the older fishermen, that he is a stranger in their midst. This state of feeling is now undergoing a change. The influx of settlers from the country, and especially from Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, has somewhat-enlarg- ed their world. These men are intermar- rying with the daughters of the old fami- lies'of fishermen, and this clannish feeling is dying out. But to return from this di- gression. Peter was ready for sea by the first of April, and sailed for the Banks. Here he met with good success, although he and his crew suffered a good deal from the cold and the snow-storms which they experienced during the month of Apr4. But he returned by the end of June, with a full fare. He landed his fish with all de- spatch, and taking in a full supply of salt, sailed for the Bay of St. Lawrence. Tak- ing a position near the mouth of the Strait of Belle Isle, he commenced operations. By the tenth of August he had filled his vessel,   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   159 and taking possession of his old flakes, he refitted them, and landed his fish. By the tenth of September, he was ready to return home with a full fare of dry fish. The weather had now become quite cold, and rain and squalls of snow indicated the speedy approach of winter. He was glad to leave this inhospitable shore. So taking on board as much wood as he could conveniently carry on deck, he sailed for home, which he reached about the twenty-fourth of the month. Having spent a few weeks in the pollock fishery, in October and November, he run his vessel round to Gloucester har- or, and laid her up in harbor cove for the winter. This winter he spent without labor, liv- ing upon the earnings of the summer, only going out occasionally, on a pleasant day, in his wherry. He now began to think se- riously about getting ready for his conitem- plated marriage with Mary Griffin.' The first step was to build a house. So during the winter he purchased an acre of land, at a short distance 'from his mother's house.  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7564-00000082"/> 160     PETER GOTT, About half of his acre was occupied with a ledge of granite; but at one corner of it was a pleasant little sunny nook, where the soil was good. Here he engaged a laborer to dig him a cellar, 16 feet by 25, and stone it up. He next made a contract with a farmer, who lived about a mile north of the cove, near Halibut Point, to cut and haul the timber for the frame of his house, and to cut the board logs which he needed, and haul them to Dennison's saw-mill to be sawed. He next contracted with a car- penter from Sandy Bay, to erect him a one story'house,during the ensuing season. It was to be completed by the end of October. In the following spring he fitted out again for the Banks, and after having made one trip, he returned to his old fishing ground on the Labrador coast. He had been so successful in his previous trips to the bay, that this year he was accompanied by two schooners from Gloucester harbor, whose skippers anchored in his immediate vicinity, and erected their flakes near his. They were successful in their fishiuig;   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   161 but duping the first week in September they encountered a violent storm, which did them considerable injury, and came near driving them upon the rocks. Such storms are of frequent occurrence on this coast, after the first of September, and ren- der fishing at this season highly dangerous.-  But they repaired damages as well as they were able, and reached home in safety. In the latter part of November, on Thanksgiving week, Peter was married to Mary Griffin, and took possession of his new house, amidst the congratulations of all their friends. He had now a new in- ducement to industry and enterprise ; for he had not only his own family to support,: but he felt bound to render his mother the" same assistance that he had hitherto done. Indeed, in about a year from his marriage, he took his mother into his own house, leaving the old house to his brother, who had then taken to wife his cousin, Margaret Tarr. She remained in his family, the ob- ject of his fond and filial regard, the, re- mainder of her life. Her other children, "*;       bp; ,si- He A  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7564-00000083"/> 162     PETER GOTT, indeed, and their families, shared her care and affection, but Peter's house was her home. Peter now 'seemed settled for life, and to have found a course of business that yielded income sufficient to supply his wants, and support his family in comfort. He continued this course of fishing several years, going to the Banks once, and to the Bay of St. Lawrence once in the season, and fishing more or less during the winter. The- second year after Peter's marriage, Mr. Dennis had a new  vessel of fifty tons built at Essex. Her whole cost, when fitted for ea, was twenty-six hundred and fifty ollUars. The  contract with thie builder :as, that he should receive one third of he pay  upon delivery, one third in one year, and the remainder in two years. Of this new vessel, Peter took one fourth and became her skipper. He had paid for his house, and- saved money enough to pay one third of his portion of the -vessel. This new vessel, which he named for his wife, Mary?  They  fitted out for the Banks, and continued to run her-to the Banks and the Bay for several years. , .    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   163 Peter was now in a thriving way. In' addition- to his share, as one of the- crew, and his commission as, skipper; he had his share of the earnings of the vessel. They usually stocked from thirty-five hundred to four thousand dollars per year. One half of this belonged to the vessel. When their- stock, or the produce of their year's work, amounted to four thousand dollars, two thousand of it belonged to the vessel. After deducting the cost of the outfit, in- surance and repairs, the remainder consti- tuted the profit which the vessel" had made. This, when the vessel met with no extraor- dinary injury, was fromeighlt :hundred to a thousand dollars;- so that Peter's income, from his fourth of his .vessel, was from" two hundred to two, hundred and fifty-dol- lars .per-year,: tt e nd  of twoyears, he had--paid for hisi frurth of the vessel, and  had ciajtinulaed more than H undred dollar s beie s . :Th:ne i :year another new vessel was added to the fleet. Of this, he owned'three- eighths.: At the end of two years more he - a1 had paid for his proportion of this vessel. -  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7564-00000084"/> CHAPTER   XIV.  NACKEREL rFISHERY.-PETER'S ENTERPRISE. -BAIT MLLS. ABOUT this time some attention began to be paid to the mackerel fishery. These fish usually begin to appear in schools along the shores of Massachusetts and Maine, in July. They are then going north. Their principal haunts are in the Bay of St. Lawrence, in the Straits of Belle Isle, along the eastern coast of Lab'rador, and in the Bay of Chaleur, and around the Island of Newfoundland. They feed chiefly upon a minute reddish colored    insect, that abounds in these waters from July to No- vember. When they first came upon the coast, they are lean and tough, and of little value; but they rapidly .accUmulate: -fat when they reach the waters in whih their favorite food abounds.   By the last-of    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    100  August they become fat and tender. The best mackerel are usually taken in October, when the schools are beginning; to return- to the- south. The habits of these fish are very peculiar. And although they have been taken in im- mense numbers for three-quarters of a cen- tury, their habits are not well understood. They often move in immense bodies, ap- parently filling the ocean for miles in ex- tent.  They are found near the surface. Sometimes they will take-the hook with the greatest eagerness.  At other times, not a mackerel will bite for days, although millions of them  are visible in the water. t When they are in the mood for taking the bait, ten, twenty, and even thirty barrels are taken by a single vessel in a few hours. They usually bite' most- freely soon after sunrise in the morning, and towards sunset, at evening. They all' cease to bite-about the same time, as if they were actuated by a common impulse.   They are easily fright- ened, and will then descend into deep water. It has often happened, that a fleet of ves-  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7564-00000085"/> 166     PETER GOTT, sels has been lying off the Cape, a mile or two from the shore, in the midst of a school of mackerel, and taking them rapidly upon their decks, when the firing of a gun. or the blast of a rock would send every mackerel fathoms deep into the water, as suddenly as though they had been converted into so many pigs of lead; and perhaps it would be some hours before they would reappear. They are caught most abundantly near the shore, and very rarely out of sight of land. The commencement of the mackerel fish- ery dates many years back. But since the peace of 1815, it has become a business of great importance to Massachusetts, Maine, and the British Provinces. An immense amount of capital, several thousand men, and some hundreds of vessels are now en- gaged from July to November in this fish- ery. It is much easier than cod fishing, though perhaps less certain in its results. - When- fishermenj can make as- much in a few weeks at mackerelling, as in as many months at codfishing, as is sometimes the case, they prefer to run their chance in the   THE CAPE- ANN FISHERMAN.    167 former, rather than to' work all the season    . laboriously at the latter. But they some- times fail of success in the former, either because the mackerel do not appear in suf- ficient numbers, or, if found, they will not take the hook. But in the cod fishing they more, rarely fail, unless it be from storms or disasters at sea. Mackerelling is often called a lottery. But then there are higher-  prizes in it than in codfishing, if there are more blanks ; so that it has become of late the favorite branch of the fisheries among the men of the line.- Peter;proposed to Mr. Dennis, that when the Mary Gott returned from the Banks, she should be fitted out for the mackerel fishing. This was a new business, and re-- quired considerable preparation. Barrels were to be provided. A new set of lines 6 and hooks were necessary. The deck must be furnished with a different set of fixtures. Mr. Dennis was to provide whatever was necessary for this new business, and have - it ready by the first of July. -Peter had    v led the way in the Labrador fishing, and:-   : ; *            -  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7564-00000086"/> 168     PETER GOTT, he was now ready to commence the mack- erel fishing, and run the risk which attends all new enterprizes. Having made all ne- cessary arrangements, he set sail for the Banks. He met with his usual good suc- cess, and returned on the fourth of July. Tmmediately after landing his codfish, he took on board two hundred barrels and his mackerel gear, and sailed for the coast of Maine. Many of the old fishermen looked upon it as a wild enterprize, and predicted that he would lose his labor. Men who move in a narrow circle are guided by ex- perience and rarely strike out new plans, and are always reluctant to engage in new enterprizes. But Peter had seen -some- thing of the world, and being a true Yan- kee, had some notions of his own. Mr. Dennis had. much confidence in his judg- ment, and although a cautious, man, yet, as he had succeeded so well in his Labrador fishing, he was willing he should make the experiment. He laid his course for Mount Desert Island, and lay for several days in the vicinity of -the island. Soon signs of   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   169 mackerel began to appear. They threw over their baited hooks, and now and then caught a mackerel. They continued in this way for several days, fishing through the whole day, and at the end of a week had taken two barrels of poor, small fish. Some of the crew were getting discouraged, when suddenly, one morning, just as the sun was rising, they found themselves sur- rounded by mackerel ready to take the hook the" instant it touched the water. They would seize the bait, whether large or small, with the greatest avidity. They took them on to the deck with great rapid- ity, jerking them from the hook as soon as they were over the rail, and dropping the hook again instantly into the water. So voracious were the fish, that they would oftentimes seize the bare, unbaited hook, almost before it struck the water. This exciting scene continued about two hours, when, all of a sudden, they ceased to bite, and not another fish could they induce to take evenr the best-baited hook. Finding they could catch no more, they ceased their ' * 15    ;    . '  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7564-00000087"/> 170     PETER GOTT, labor and partook of their breakfast, which the cook had had ready for them more than an hour. After breakfast, they dressed and salted their fish, and found they had taken twenty barrels in two hours. After clean- ing the deck, they again threw over their hooks, but few mackerel were to be seen, and of those which they saw swimming about the vessel, only now and then one would take the hook. The next morning the same scene was repeated. They turned out at daylight, and chopped into small pieces with a hatch- et upon a block, the smallest of the mack- erel which they had caught the preceding- morning, and which they had preserved in a barrel of salt water for this purpose. They thus prepared two or three bushels of bait, that no time might be lost in pre- paring it after the fish began to bite. Just before sunrise they began their-work, and this morning they took fifteen barrels. They could not account for these singular movements of the fish. But they did not -forget them. and learned to be always ready ' I         'I \ "   THE CAPE ANN' FISHERMAN.   171 to try their fortune with the rising of the sun. This accidental discovery, that the mackerel had a habit of feeding early in the morning, contributed greatly to the success of their voyage.  They were     greatly encouraged by the result which -they had obtained in the two days. But the mackerel had now disappeared. So they hoisted their sails, and coasted along until they came into the bay of Castine. Here they lay to among the islands, and in the course of a week caught forty barrels more. They found the fish were growing larger and fatter, and of course more valu- able. This circumstance also greatly en- couraged them. For many years the only method of pre- paring the bait was that which I have mentioned, viz, chopping it upon a block placed on deck for the purpose with hatch- ets. But some years since, Yankee inge- nuity invented a machine for this purpose, called a bait-mill. -'It consists of a box of plank, from the inside of which project short, stout knives, placed about :an: inch  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7564-00000088"/> 172   -  PETER GOTT, apart. Within this box a wooden cylinder, about five inches in'- diameter, is made to revolve'by means of a crank. The peri- phery of this cylinder is studded thickly with similar knives. Above this box is placed a kind of hopper, into which the fish to be cut are thrown. When they have passed through the mill, they fall upon the deck. This mill greatly facilitates the pre- paration of the bait. Small mackerel, alewives, and a short, broad fish,: called hard-heads or pohegan, are chiefly used for bait. This latter fish is sometimes found in immense schools in the small bays and coves near the shore. They are taken in seines. Sometimes two or three hundred barrels are taken at one haul. They are prepared for use in the following way: They are thrown upon a table. The-dresser seizes one by the head, and with a sharp, thin knife shaves off a thick slice from just below the head to the tail. Then turning it, he shaves off a simi- lar slice from the other side, leaving little else than the head, backbone and tail. The   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    173 slices, or slivers as they are called, are then salted in barrels, and sold to the mackerel catchers. Before being used, they are cut into small pieces in the bait mill. But Peter and his crew had none of these conveniences; they had to use the mack- erel which they caught for bait.  They pursued their course to the eastward until they reached the Bay of Passamaquoddy. Here they filled up the remainder o1 their two hundred barrels, and by the twentieth of August, set sail for Cape Ann. Here they arrived and landed their mackerel' amidst the congratulations of their neigh- bors, and much to the surprise of the croakers, who had confidently predicted their failure. The fare consisted mostly of poor and small fish, such as would now be reckoned No. 2 and No. 3. They were worth from $3 to $4.50 per barrel. ' The last they had caught were quite fat and large; and so good had been the result of the trip, that Peter was disposed to repeat it. He took in 250 barrels, and sailed for Eastport.- He 15* '  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7564-00000089"/> 174     PETER GOTT, continued in the bay six weeks, during which time he encountered a severe storm, which made it necessary for him to run into Eastport river for shelter. H ie suffered no material damage, and at the end of that time he had filled his 250 barrels with fat mackerel, with which he reached home in safety. This time the mackerel were nearly all No. 1, and were worth $6.50 per barrel, making the whole fare worth about $1,600. The first fare was worth $700. This, added to the fare of Bank fish, which was worth $1,100, made the year's stock $3,400. This was not a great year's work; but it was quite satisfactory, and Peter had demon- strated that the mackerel fishery was both practicable and profitable, and he antici- pated that with the experience he had gained, the result would be still more satis- factory in time. to come. The skippers of two vessels from Sandy. Bay, resolved to try their fortune in the -same business the next season. Mr. Den- nis, and the owners of the two other ves-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    175 sels, contracted with a cooper to furnish them with five hundred pine barrels each, by the next July. This contract set in motion the music of the cooper's adze, which continued to play a brisk tune through the livelong winter and the fol- lowing spring. When the spring arrived, Peter fitted out, as usual, for the Banks. And after his return, the three mackerel vessels sailed in company for the Bay of Fundy about the first of August, each having 300 barrels on board. About the tenth of August they commenced operations in the Bay. For. the first two or three weeks they found the mackerel rather small. But about the first of September, they fell in with a school of fine, fat mackerel, and by the middle of the month they had filled all their barrels.' More than half of their fares-were No. 1's, and the remainder were mostly No. 2's. After landing their fares, they took on board two hundred barrels each, and fished along the shores of Maine, without much success at first. At length, near Cape   .             \  &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7564-00000090"/> 176     PETER GOTT, Elizabeth, they found plenty of fine mack- erel, and soon filled their barrels. Vessels from Newhuryport and Portsmouth began this season to engage in the business, and met with encouraging success. This was the best year's work Peter had ever made. He and Mr. Dennis made ar- rangements to have all their craft engage in the mackerel business the following year.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   1" CHAPTER   XV. SMUGGLING.-TREATIES. -REVENUE CUTTERS. DURING the winter, Peter purchased a fourth of another schooner. He was now part owner of three vessels. Of one of these, his brother now took command. The next season, quite a little fleet fitted out for the maclerel fishery, and sailed for the Bay of Chaleur. They frequently landed on the coast of Nova Scotia, and purchased wood and potatoes, and milk and eggs, and poultry of the inhabitants. For these pur- chases, they usually paid out of the stores of the vessels, giving tea, coffee, sugar, flour, -or shoes, in return for what they received. This was a profitable trade for both parties, -the Americans obtaining wood and pota- toes much cheaper than they could get them at home, and the British people get- t   &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7564-00000091"/> 178     PETER GOTT,  ting tea and sugar at about half what they paid for- them to British merchants. This was especially true with respect to tea. The East India Company, as is well known, has enjoyed a monopoly of the trade in tea for many years, so that all the tea drank by, the subjects of the British crown, in Europe and America, had to pass through its warehouses, and pay to it a large profit. Until within a short time past, there has been no exemption from this rule. But the Americans, bringing their tea directly from China without the intervention of a monopoly, are able to sell :- %^ it at a much lower rate. The fishermen were not slow to learn that teas, and certain mannufactured articles, in demand among .  the people of the Provinces, would pay a.^ good profit. Hence arose Ma pretty trade in smuggled goods, in which the 'fishing vessels'often took a part. The inhabitants of the British shores encouraged this trade, much to the annoyance of the merchants at Halifax and St. Johns. Self interest led these merchants to exert themselves to pre-s   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   179 vent, by treaty stipulations, the American fishermen from frequenting the coasts of the Provinces. A few years after, when they themselves had become engaged in the mackerel fishery, they induced the British ministers to put such a construction upon the treaties that had been made, as should prohibit fishermen from the States to fish within three miles from any of their shores. As the mackerel abound most near the shore, and within the line of three miles, this prohibition has been a source of great -exation, and of much ill blood be- twein the American fishermen and the 'people of the Provinces. For many years past, individuals from Nova Scotia have by in the habit of shipping on board A-erican fishing vessels, during the fishing season, and returning home during the winter. These people, knowing the value of American goods, and the wants of their neighbors' and friends, and being well ac- quainted with all the bays and inlets of the coast, have been the most active in carry- ing on the smuggling trade, while by Brit-  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7564-00000092"/> 180     PETER GOTT, ish merchants, it has all been charged upon American fishermen. These last, knowing the charge to be unjust, and at the same time finding themselves, on account of it, cut off from the best fishing grounds, have submitted to the prohibition with much re- luctance, and no doubt often caught mack- erel within the prohibited line. After the mackerel fishery had greatly increased, and become a business of much importance to the British colonies, that government annually sent several armed revenue cutters on to the coast during the autumn, to keep off American fishermen. When the fleet was numerous, the fisher- men would often combine together, and defy the cutters; and they seldom attempt- ed to capture a fishing vessel under such circumstances, even if they were within the forbidden limit. But when the captains of the cutters were disappointed of their prey, and irritated by the daring conduct of the Yankees, woe be to any solitary vessel that might be found straggling out of sight of the fleet. It was immediately seized as   THE- CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.  181 lawful prey, even though five or six miles from the shore. When such vessels were not taken in the act of violating the treaty, the captain of the cutter would swear that they had done so at some former time, or that he had good&amp; reason to believe that they intended to do so, on some future oc- casion; and upon the ground of this oath, the court at Halifax issued a libel against the vessel. The case then, after due delay, was examined by the proper authorities. If any defence was attempted, the British lawyers and courts were sure to make the costs equal to the value of the vessel and cargo, even if she got clear, which was sel- dom the case. The Yankees soon learned a more economical way of managing the business. They allowed their vessels to be condemned, without defence, in all 'cases; and when they were sold at auction, they bid them off, and drawing an order on some mercantile house in Boston, took possession of them, and sailed for home. Many hair-breadth escapes and stirring adventures occurred during the period in 16  &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7564-00000093"/> 182     PETER GOTT, which this annoying state of things contin- ued. Sometimes a clipper-built fisherman would lead the. cutter a long chase along shore, and run among shoals and islands for the sake of leading her pursuer into dan- ger. Sometimes she would run out of some cove or harbor under the very guns of the cutter, the men all lying upon deck, and receiving her fire. And sometimes, when there was plenty of sea-room, two or three fishermen would attempt to run into- the cutter. Such daring on the part of the fish- ermen taught the cutters caution in their attacks upon them, and compelled them to wink at many open acts of violation of the law. But they were sure to take their re- venge when they coul do it without dan- ger to themselves. Many a skipper and crew, that had carefully conformed to the requirements of the law, confiding in their innocence, were taken and carried into Halifax, and condemned upon the oath of the captaip of the cutter, in revenge for the bold and daring course-of others, who were guilty.     %;       . .   -THE C-APE ANN FISHERMAN.   183 This was a great source of annoyance to the owners and crews, and led them con-.9 stantly to petition the government for redress. The freedom of the fisheries in British waters was one of the subjects of negotiation between this country and Great Britain for many years. But those to whom the construction of treaties was entrusted, could not be made to understand the nature and importance of the subject. Something was attempted to be done by the Ashbur- ton treaty, which was negotiated by Mr. Webster and Lord Ashburton. But the provision in this treaty respecting the fish- eries, was the least satisfactory part of the treaty, and did not meet the difficulties of the case; and nothing effectual was done for the relief of the fishermen until the reciprocity treaty of 1854, when the privi- leges which they had formerly enjoyed were again restored to them. Peter Gott, and the vessels in which he was concerned, engaged in a   Inal! way in this traffic with the inhabitants, without the least intention of injuring any one, or vio-  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7564-00000094"/> 184      PETER GOTT, lating any international law. It was mere- ly a matter of mutual accommodation. But both parties finding it a profitable business, it insensibly increased. The inhabitants in several places depended upon the fisher- men to bring them an annual supply of certain goods, and contracted with them for a certain amount; and the fishermen in their turn agreed to receive certain articles of produ6e at a fixed price in return. The amount of these articles was soon greater than was wanted for the consumption of the vessels. At first, the excess was shared by the skipper and crews, and consumed in their families. Soon, however, it was re- ceived by the owners as a part of the re- turns of the voyage, and sold for the benefit of all concerned. Mr. Dennis and Peter found it quite convenient, when they were fitting out their vessels in July, to put on board a good assortment of thick shoes, teas, coffee and hard soap, and a few other articles that found a ready sale. These were exchanged for butter, eggs, oats, and peltries. This barter trade sometimes add-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    185 ed two or three hundred dollars to the profit of the trip. Another trade soon grew  out of this, which- Peter was not slow to take advan- tage of. The mackerel fishery required a considerable outlay of capital. The vessels employed in it, at the period of which we are speaking; were worth from fifteen to twenty-four hundred- dollars each, when fitted for sea. From six to eight hands were employed on board.- Much time was consumed in sailing to and from the fishing grounds, and often a great deal of time was wasted in searching for fish, or in waiting for their arrival on the coast. We have already remarked, that these fish are found in the greatest abundance within a line of three miles from the shore. Now it must be obvious, that the inhabitants of the coasts frequented by them, can take them at much less cost of time and money, than those who go from  the ports of Massachusetts. Eight men, in four boats, worth ten or twelve .1ollars each, with no outfit but their lines and hooks and reels, can row out from 16 6* *          .         . ' '   &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7564-00000095"/> 186     PETER GOTT, their own homes, when the fish are on the coast, and take as many mackerel in a day, as the same number of men on the deck of a fishing vessel that is worth two tholu- sand dollars, and has sailed fifteen hundred miles to reach the ground. Barrels and salt are worth no more in the Provinces than in the States. - Hence the people upon the coast could afford to sell the mackerel which they caught, at a much lower rate than the Yankee fishermen; and they were the more ready to do this, as they had but few facilities for getting them to a market, and were compelled io take such prices as the Halifax traders were pleased to give1 them. If they received half what the fish were worth in Boston, they made a greater profit upon them than did the Ameri- can fishermen. When, by the Ashburton treaty, the inhabitants of the Provinces were allowed to export mackerel to the 'States, upon paying one dollar and a half duty, per barrel, they sent them in great quantities, and were'even then able to' undersell-the American fishernien to such degree as almost to ruin their business.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    187 Peter Gott was the first to perceive that it would -be a good operation, both for him and the people on the coast, to employ them to fish for him, or to purchase of them mackerel already caught and packed, es- pecially if he could pay for them in Amer- ican goods.  In this way, he was able to fill his vessel in a few days, and thus make three or four trips in a season, instead of two. But the Halifax traders, who fre- quented the small ports, to purchase the mackerel caught by the inhabitants, soon got wind of his doings. As his traffic inter- fered with theirs, they used strenuous exer- tions to break it up. And as he paid for the fish which he purchased, in whole or in part, by prohibited goods, they had some ground for complaint, notwithstanding the trade was beneficial to the people. Mer- chants have a sharp eye for their own in- terests, and are always ready to make a great noise about national rights, and:the violations of treaties, and the laws of trade, when their own profits are injurously affect- ed. The convenience and the advantage  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7564-00000096"/> 188     PETER GOTT, of the people are of small consideration, when compared with their own. The loss of profit by the Halifax traders has been, in fact, the great source of all the troubles and difficulties which the fishermen have had to encounter during many years on the eastern coast. It was this that led to the new and more stringent construction of treaties, and which subjected the Britishs government to the expense of sending rev- enue cutters on to the coast during the fishing season, and which caused so much tedious and unprofitable negotiation be- tween the two nations. But, in the mean- time, Peter and Mr. Dennis managed to make a considerable sum out of this business.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   189 CHAPTER XVI. PETER THNKS OF QUITTING FISHNG.--GOES ONE TRIP MORE.-A TERRIBLE STORM. PETER GOTT now began to be considered by his neighbors as a wealthy man. He was known over the whole Cape, as a man of enterprize and integrity; and as he had been successful in all his enterprizes, his judgment was much depended upon, and he was often consulted by all who were engaged in the yarious branches of fishing. He was now part owner of six vessels. He had a thriving family, and occupied one of the best houses in the village of Pigeon Cove, which had much increased during the five past years. He began to think seri- ously of quitting the fishing himself and commencing business on shore. His wife and mother were, of course, disposed. to encourage this project, as it would keep t  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7564-00000097"/> 190     PETER GOTT, him at home, and he would no longer be exposed to the perils of the ocean. On proposing the subject to his old friend and early patron, Mr. Dennis, he found that he had a plan in view which he thought would meet the wishes of Peter, and would be of mutual advantage to them both. Mr. Den- nis was beginning to feel the infirmities of age. He had accumulated considerable capital, and he had entire confidence in Peter's honesty and capacity. His plan was, that at the close of the ensuing season, Peter should go into partnership with him- self upon equal shares. This plan was im- mediately agreed upon, to the satisfaction of all parties, and, at once, they set-about preparing the outfit for the ensuing season. Peter went to Boston, under a commission from Mr. Dennis, and purchased a good supply of such articles as he- deemed best suited for the trade upon, the coast. The vessels were all fitted out early in the spring, a part of them for coast fishing, and the largest- of them for the Banks. This spring they were not verySsuccessfuL The   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    191 vessels at the Banks encountered a severe storm. One of them lost two cables and anchors, and had her boat stove, and was obliged to return home with but two thou- sand fish; another carried away her main- sail, and a third sprung her foremast and had her bulwarks stove in. Several ves- sels from Marblehead and. other places were severely injured in this storm. Several men were lost from the fleet, and one ves- sel from Beverly was never afterwards heard from, and was supposed to have sunik at her anchor. The vessels from Pigeon Cove all reach- ed home about the first of July, and re- paired damages as speedily as possible. The losses which they had sustained were nearly equal to the value of all the fish they had taken, so that they had to depend for the profits of the year upon the catch of mackerel during the remainder of the season. The Mary Gott rode out the storm with but slight damage; but one of her men was swept from her deck by a sea that struck her broadside. Peter himself came ,..  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7564-00000098"/> 192-     PETER GOTT, near sharing the same fate. He fortunate- ly caught the leeward mainstay, and hung over the side of the vessel, clinging to the stay until the sea had gone by, when he threw himself on deck. The danger to which he was thus exposed, made a deep impression upon his mind. While he hung suspended over the side of the vessel, the scenes of his past life were all present to his mind. His -venerable mother, his be- loved wife and children stood before him; and notwithstanding all the dangers he had previously passed through, he never thought himself so near to eternity as he did at that moment. When he was safe on deck, his heart swelled with gratitude for his deliv- erance.- The impression made upon him at that time was never forgotten, but con- tributed to the development of those seeds of piety which his mother's instruction had early implanted within him. The danger which he thus escaped afforded an addi- tional reason for quitting the line, and en- gaging in business on shore. In a few days, the damages were all re-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    193 paired, the outfits were received on board, and the whole fleet was ready for sea. Damage to the sails and rigging  of fishing vessels is soon repaired. The fishermen can all work as riggers, upon an emergency. They can bend a sail and set a stay nearly as well as professed riggers, and many of them can use carpenters' tools in a work- manlike manner. Peter now took leave of his wife and children, and went on board his schooner for his last fishing trip. On the twentieth of July the fleet set sail for the Bay of St. Lawrence. They agreed to' rendezvous at Prince Edward's Island. On their arrival at the Gut of Canso, they found that some fifty vessels from Massachusetts and Ports- mouth had passed through before them. They had fine weather while on the pas- sage, but they did not 'find the mackerel abundant. They: run about among the islands, catching a few mackerel daily, and occasionally touching into some bay or cove, and trading with the inhabitants. During the month of August they caught 17 *  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7564-00000099"/> 194     PETER GOTT, but few fish. But the mackerel were daily growing fatter and better. Early in Sep- tember, they found the mackerel more abundant, and by the tenth of the month most of the vessels had taken from seventy to a hundred barrels. The weather was now getting cold; the nights were frosty. Storms in this north- ern latitude are of frequent occurrence at this season, and'are often accompanied by squalls of snow. At the time of the Sep- tember equinox, severe storms usually occur in the bay. The eleventh was a still, mild day. There was a slight haze in the atmosphere, just sufficient to produce that quivering shimmer upon the surface of the water, that is often seen upon the land in the quiet days of October, when the cattle are drowsily chewing the cud, and nature, having perfected the growth of vegetation, is waiting the ripening of the golden corn, and enjoying a Sabbath rest. The wind was in the east, but was scarcely sufficient to produce the slightest ripple upon'the water. In the afternoon a gentle   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   195 swell began to be noticed now and then, which gradually increased as the day wore on. At length a sound, like a distant groan, was heard at first, so low as scary to be noticed by those who did not know what it indicated. Soon it resembled a growl rather than a groan, and seemed to be ut- tered in an angry tone. The older skippers were at once aware that a storm  was approaching. They had taken mackerel freely through the day, and to the inexpe- rienced there appeared no danger. But about three o'clock, Peter ordered his crew to reel up their lines and dress off the fish upon deck, and make all snug as fast as pos- sible. By four this was accomplished, when he immediately hoisted sail and shaped his course for Richmond harbor, which was about eight miles distant to the south-west. Soon after he was under way, he noticed five or six other vessels running up their sails. Their skippers had noticed the indi- cations of the weather, and prepared to seek shelter from the coming storm. Most of the fleet, howey, seemed wholly uncon-  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7564-00000100"/> 196     PETER GOTT, scious that any change was approaching, and remained on the fishing ground, won- dering at the movements of those who were leavinihe fleet. These last moved slowly through the water, there being only now and then a puff of wind sufficient to fill their sails. But the swell increased; and the unearthly sounds, that came booming over the water, became more and more distinct. Towards night a thick, dark line of haze appeared in the east, and the air became damp and chilly. The wind grad-. ually increased, and soon after the sun had disappeared, dark, broken masses of clouds began to be seen in the south-west. Soon after night-fall, Peter and those who had left the fishing ground with him, reached the little port of Richmond, and succeeded in getting within the line of breakers, and anchored their schooners, and reefed their sails, and barred down their hatches, and made all as secure as possible. The wind now rapidly increased, and the darkness became very dense, and those who were on deck noticed now and then a drop of frozen   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   197 rain, or a flake of snow. There was then no light house 'on the island, and it 'was very difficult for even those who were well acquainted with the channel, to run into the harbor in the night. They felt great anxiety for those whom they had left in the bay, many of whom were wholly unac- quainted with the shores of the island, and with the channel which led into the harbor. Soon after Peter and his companions had left the fishing ground, the remainder of the fleet became aware of the cause which induced him to leave it. They saw the in- dications of the coming storm. Several o them attempted to follow him; but the darkness thickened around them, and the violent gusts of wind rendered it almost u impossible for them to carry sufficient sail to keep their vessels on their course, and they were tacking -and beating about the bay for several hours, uncertain of their course and in great anxiety. At length they approached the line of breakers. The roaring and rushing of the waters, as they broke upon the reef, and were thrown up 17*  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7564-00000101"/> 198     PETER GOTT, in m dense- mass of white foam, first showed them their positioni and, at the same time, but too plainly warned them of their dan- ger. They attempted to haul off from the shore, and get an offing in the bay; but, at every tack, they found themselves nearer to the foaming rocks. Two of the vessels, after encountering the greatest hazard, ran along by the edge of the sounding reef, at the immin ent risk, every moment, of being swept on to it, and found the opening that led within it, and shot through it, and came to an anchor near the Mary Gott. Three of the vessels finding themselves near the edge of the reef, dropped their anchors and attempted to hold on till the daylight should enable them to find the channel. They took in all their canvas, and payed out all their cable, and for a time had strong hopes that they should hold on; but towards morning the wind increased in violence, and the snow- and rain drove into their faces with the greatest fury. One of them parted her cables and drove into the midst of the breakers. The other two dragged   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   199 their anchors until the stem of one of them was in the edge of the foam, when her an- chor again held. The other, as she entered the boiling cauldron, parted her second cable and plunged into the foaming waves, and drove clear over the reef into the com- paratively smooth water on the- inside. The one that first drove upon the breakers, struck upon a rock and lay rolling and beating through the night,-the crew ex- pecting every moment she would go to pieces. Finding she held together, they cut away her masts, and commenced throw- ing over-their mackerel. This was a work of great difficulty, owing to the fury of the storm and the violent motion of the vessel; but before morning they had thrown over seventy barrels of mackerel and all their salt. At length a wave lifted her from the rock on which she had been fastened, and she suddenly drove through the boiling waters to the inside of the reef, much to the astonishment of the- crew and of all who had beheld her in her perilous and hopeless situation. Being without an an-  &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7564-00000102"/> :200     PETER GOTT, chor, the crew were unable to -bring her up, and- she- soon drifted on to the' beach; and the men, to their great relief, reached the shore in safety, though greatly ex- hausted by labor, anxiety and exposure to the cold storm. The storm continued three days, the wind blowing most of the time with great fury. Sometimes they were drenched with tor- rents of rain; sometimes the air was filled with sleet and snow, so that it was scarcely -possible to see the length of the deck. The eight vessels at anchor in Richmond Bay, rode out the storm in safety; but the re- mainder of the fleet which Peter left on the fishing ground, when he ran for this port, did not all escape so well. Most of  them ran for Souris, a little port near the other end of Prince Edward's Island. A rocky headland juts out from the shore,- and forms one side of the little harbor. Under shelter of this, the anchorage ground is good. Fishing vessels often take refuge in-this place when the wind is east. Sev- eral of the fleet reached this shelter during   THE CAPE ANN FISHERM AN.   201 the night. Three or four were unable to find it in the darkness; and after driving about the bay most of the night, wnt ashore to the northward of Souris. As it was light before they went ashore, the men all succeeded in escaping to land, When one of the vessels struck, her mainmast was thrown out of her, and fell with the head to the land, and thus formed a bridge, by which the crew  reached the rocks. These men thus fortunately thrown upon the shore, succeeded in hauling a line from one of the other vessels, which drove broad- side on to the shore, and made it fast to a rock, by means of which its crew reached the shore. One of the vessels, when within two hundred feet of the shore, struck broadside upon a rock, which stove a hole in her side and held her fast. She heeled towards the shore, and the sea made a clean breach over her. The men were in the most im- minent danger, expecting the vessel would- instantly break up and go to pieces. The deck was swept clean of every movable thing, and it was with the utmost difficulty  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7564-00000103"/> 202     PETER GQTT,  that the men could hold on by the stays and rigging. At length one of them got the cod lines and tied them together, and tied a fish lead to one end, then coiling the line, he attempted to throw the lead on shore, but, after repeated attempts, he failed. Necessity is said to be the mother of inven- tion. It often leads men to think of means of relief, that they do not think of when not under its stimulating influence. One of the crew, when all were ready to give up in despair, happened to think of a wooden bottle in the cabin, containing West India rum, and although the cabin was nearly filled with water, he contrived to get hold of the bottle, and brought it on deck. Then taking a hearty draught from it, he poured out the remainder, and making a loop around the bottle, with the bite of a fish line, he threw it overboard, holding on to the other end of the line. Finding that the waves carried it towards the shore, he tied on another line, and payed out his line, carefully watching his bottle as it was tossed about by the dashing waves. The   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   203 undertow would sometimes draw it back nearly to the vessel, when it had almost reached the shore. One of the men on shore, who were anxiously watching their proceedings, perceived the floating object in the water, and as the men on board were eagerly pointing towards it, he was at once aware of its purpose. He immedi- ately cut a small sapling with his knife, and wading into the water to his waist, after many attempts, entangled his pole in the line that was attached to the wooden bottle. The men on shore now shouted encouragement to those on board. The man who had bethought himself of. this' messenger to carry a line. ashore, now cut  away the fore sheet, and drawing it through the block, attached one end of it to the line which he had made fast to his wrist. Then, with the assistance of the skipper, who was holding on to the windward main- stay, he cut away the main sheet, and fast- ening the ends of the two sheets together, made signs for those who held the bottle end of the line, to draw it in. They drew  &#xD;<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC7564-00000104"/> 204.     PETER GOTT, it in carefully, but when drawn to its ut- most length, the doubled sheet was found to reach but little more than half way to the shore. There was no more rope on board within reach of the benumbed and exhausted men, by which they could lengthen their line. At length, one of the men on shore be- thought him of the line by which he had been-saved, and taking one of his shipmates with him, he ran to the spot where the wreck of his vessel lay, and leaping upon the rock to which the line was fastened, he seized the line and passed along it into the boiling surge, hand over hand, until he Reached the side of the vessel to which it was attached; then, drawing his knife, he cut the line at a blow, and fell with it into the water. His- shipmate on the rock, the moment he saw him fall, drew in the line, and soon they were both standing safe upon the rock. They now cast off the line from the rock, and, leaping on shore, carried it as fast as they were able to the spot where the men were now all assembled, holding - ,  \   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   205 on to the fish line which had been brought ashore by the bottle. The question now was, how this line should be attached to the end of the sheet, which lay upon the water about half way between the vessel and 'the shore. The wooden bottle was again put in requisition, and made to serve another good turn. A running noose was made in the end of the line which the men had brought from the other vessel. To6 this noose the wokden bottle was attached by a small piece of the fish line, and the noose was passed on to the fish line, and the bottle thrown into the water. Soon the undertow taking it, drew it out toward the vessel, which still heldi'together. Them noose ran along the line, drawn by the ' bottle, in the same way that a messenger runs up the line of a boy's kite. In a short time it worked along the line until it passed over the loop by which the end of the sheet had -been made fast to the fish line. After it had passed some way on to the sheet, the man who held it on shore began to draw upon the line, and soon he perceived that 18  &#xD;<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC7564-00000105"/> 206     PETER GOTT, the noose was tightening upon the line, and in a few moments he had the satisfaction to find that it grasped the sheet firmly just beyond the loop. And now the men on shore shouted to those on board to take courage. The poor fellows were exhaust- ed with fatigue and excitement, and be- numbed with the cold. The cold rain and snow and sleet had been driving full in their faces for some hours. They had been holding on to the rigging, constantly drenched with the cold spray, and every few minutes a wave breaking over them. But when they saw that there was now some chance of their escape, and that a -way had been prepared forFCeir rescue, they took courage and made every exer- tion to avail themselves of the means that had been provided for them. Bailey, the man who had first sent the bottle ashore with the fish line, now seized-the line, and let himself down into the water. He soon succeeded in warping himself ashore. The line being buried several feet under water most of the time, and the surf beating with ,  * z   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   207 great fury, this is a work of much greater difficulty than one would imagine who has never seen it performed. It requires much presence of mind, -and a great deal of mus- cular strength. When a man is caught by the undertow, he is very liable to be torn from his hold on the line. When the line is buried deep by a wave, he may be drowned, holding on to the line, before the wave runs by, or he may be struck by some floating body in the water. All these diffi- culties are much increased, when his hands are benumbed and his limbs- stiffened by the cold. Bailey had exerted himself so much on board, that he had retained the full use of his hands and rapidly reached the shore. One of the men on shore wad- ed into the water to meet himj and seized him by the collar as soon as he came with- in reach, and assisted him to land, where he-was received with a shout. The skipper next followed his example. When he had passed about half way, a tremendous wave came over. him, submerging him many feet deep. Finding himself about to suffocate,  &#xD;<pb n="208-209" xml:id="VAC7564-00000106"/> 208      PETER GOTT, "he let go his hold of the line, and rose to the surface to get breath.; but fortunately, when- the undertow took him down again, it brought him in contact with the line, which he instinctively caught, and again pushed for the shore. This time he came so- near to the shore that his feet found the bottom, where he stood holding on to the line until the next wave had broken, when he was soon helped to land. One after another, the crew let themselves down upon the line; and, after encountering many hazards, they all reached the shore, except one poor fellow, who had lashed himself to the main stay, and his hands had become so benumbed with the cold that he could not untie the cord that bound him. After shouting and beckoning to him some time, and - finding that he remained in the same position, the men on shore believing him to be dead or disabled, the skipper, who first landed, volunteered to go to his rescue. This feat he accomplished at the imminent risk of his life, for when he had reached the side of the vessel, a heavy wave broke over    THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    209 it, lifting it from its bed and rolling it on to its beam, crushing another large hole in its side. This movement of the vessel let him fall into the- water, and it was by means of the utmost exertion that he avoided being drawn under the vessel. But holding on to the line with a death- grasp, he soon brought himself to the' sur- face, and drew himself to the rail, which was now under water. Then, raising him- self over the rail, he caught a cleat near the foot of the mainmast, which was used in tautening the main sheet. Drawing him- self up by this, he got his foot against the mast, and, springing upward, he seized the main stay, to which the poor benumbed lad hung suspended by a cord around his waist. Instantly drawing his knife, he cut the lash- ing  that held him, and let him'fall to the lower edge of the deck. Then letting him- self down  after him, he seized him, and grasping the collar of his jacket with his left hand, and boldly plunging into the icy water, seized the line with his right. The man whom he had thus far rescued, 1-8*           ,   &#xD;<pb n="210-211" xml:id="VAC7564-00000107"/> 210     PETER GOTT, was able to make but little effort, and his strength seemed every moment failing, and it was with great difficulty that he could keep his head out of water sufficiently to prevent his drowning. But he struggled on bravely, throwing himself forward as far  as he was able with one hand, then watch- ing his opportunity, he would let go his hold, and reaching forward seize the line again, drawing after him the helpless sea- man. In this way he slowly worked his way towards the shore. Several of the- men were upon the point of going to his assistance, but they feared the line- would part by their additional weight; indeed, they greatly feared that it would be parted by the weight of the two men that were now supported by it; and stood in almost breathless suspense, watching the move- ments of the two men as they were thrown about by the foaming waves. When they- had passed that part of the line where the : noose that was run out from the- shore grasped the loop of the sheet, the inner end of the line being the strongest, and having   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN..  2" no fear that that portion of it would part, one of the men slipping rapidly out'upon the line, soon came to the skipper, and giv- ing him an encouraging word, passed be- yond him until he came to the noose ;then holding on to the inner portion of the line, he cut the noose with his knife. The men on shore being prepared for this, imme- diately drew in the line with the three men, and lifted them on to hard land. The skip- per was completely exhausted and unable to stand, and it was with great difficulty that they loosed the iron grip of his hand from the collar of the now dying sailor, the muscles of his arm and hand had become so rigid and unyielding from violent contrac- tion and the cold. Some of the men ap- plied themselves to the relief of the man who had thus been brought on shore by the bold and heroic effort of the skipper; but in a few moments after he was laid on  the shore he breathed his last, completely overcome by the cold and  exposure/ Others removed --the brave skipper under ,.  &#xD;<pb n="212-213" xml:id="VAC7564-00000108"/> 212     PETER GOTT, the shelter of a projecting rock, and rub- bed his hands and arms, and rendered him all the assistance in their power under the circumstances. He soon recovered ability to stand and walk, and in a few hours was entirely restored. B   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    213 CHAPTER    XVII. KINDNESS OF THE PEOPLE OF PRINCE EDWARD'S ISLAND. -THE STORM CEASES.--THEY REPAIR DAMAGES, AS FAR AS THEY CAN, AND RETURN HOME.-THE LOSS OF A YEAR'S WORK. BEFORE the events of which we have been speaking had transpired, several of the in- habitants of the island had collected at the scene of the disaster. They were very kind to the shipwrecked fishermen, and offered them   all the assistance in their power. The people of this island, and those who inhabit the coasts of the Provinces, are in general very hospitable and kind to those who are thrown upon their shores, reliev- ing their immediate wants to the extent of their means. They led the dripping and. half frozen men to their houses, which were , situated at the distance of half a mile.  They-kindled large fires, and arranged them  &#xD;<pb n="214-215" xml:id="VAC7564-00000109"/> 214     PETER GOTT,  around them, and the women soon cooked them some warm food, and did all in their. power to make them comfortable. They partook of their hospitality with thankful- ness, and after they had got warmed, and partially dried, their hosts led them to the village of Souris, about four miles distant, although the storm was beating with piti- less fury. They were desirous of reaching this place before dark, hoping to be able to communicate with their friends who had reached that port. Before starting for Souris, they engaged two of the islanders to bring, upon a 'handbarrow, the dead body of their lost shipmate to one of the houses, where it could be kept in safety till the storm was over. They reached Souris about dark, wet and weary, and as it was impossible for them to go on board of the vessels of their comrades in the harbor, even if the danger to which these were exposed had tot been such as to forbid it, i they were kindly received by the villagers, ' who distributed them in their families, and provided them fire and food.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   215 These people, most of whom are engaged in fishing or coasting, are exposed to great danger in navigating their rockbound and stormy shores, and can fully sympathize with the sailor in distress. Our fishermen have often been indebted to their kindness and hospitality. A large number of the fleet had reached this port, and through the day had rode in safety under the pro- tection of the jutting headland, and their crews were indulging the hope that they should ride out the storm, although it beat upon them with great violence. But after nightfall, the wind increased to a perfect hurricane, and lashed the waves into a mass of foam. About midnight the wind hauled two or three points more to the north, and the headland now no longer afforded them protection against the rushing waves. Soon mne of the vessels began to drag her anchor, and drifted against another that was an- -hored a short distance to the leeward, causing her to part her cable, and now the -  ;wo drifted foul of a third. They lay somed:';:--  time pounding and beating against "each i.:   &#xD;<pb n="216-217" xml:id="VAC7564-00000110"/> 216     PETER GOTT, other, and at length drifted all together upon the beach. This was about daylight. The men were all so fortunate as to reach the shore in safety. Before morning, most of the fleet had drifted from their holding ground, and were in imminent hazard of going on to the rocks. Some of them cut away their masts, and paying out all their cable, were enabled to hold on. In the course of the day, six more of them went on shore, two of which beat to pieces upon the rocks. The four others falling upon the beach, held together, and were ultimately got off. The storm continued with great violence through the day, the wind varying from east to north-east. The inhabitants, shel- tered by the rocks and buildings on the shore, watched the vessels and their move- ments with the deepest anxiety, expecting them all to go on shore. About noon, the master of the schooner Atalantis, from New- buryport, finding that his vessel was going adrift, and would soon be upon the rocks, hoisted a double reefed foresail and the   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   217 peak of his jib, and cut away his anchor, and beat out of the harbor in the face of the storm, greatly to the surprise and as- tonishment of the inhabitants. This was  the first time that this feat was ever at- tempted in this harbor in a storm. But he  accomplished it safely, and obtained a suffi- cient offing to enable him to put to sea; and although his bulwarks were torn away and his sails badly, split, he reached home in safety. Towards night the wind hauled to the aorth-west, and a gleam of light in the west, at sunset, indicated that the storm was over. the wind, after its change, continued to blow with great strength through the night,  ind the weather was intensely cold; but no more vessels went ashore. In the morn- ng the sun shone out bright and clear. rhe day was cold; but the men from the 'essels that still rode in the bay, came on, hore to refresh themselves, and were kindly ntertained by the people of Souris. They tow set about repairing damages, as far as hey were able.  &#xD;<pb n="218-219" xml:id="VAC7564-00000111"/> 218     PETER GOTT, The vessels that went ashore to the northward of the harbor were entirely lost. Some sails and rigging, a few fish lines, some articles of clothing, and a few barrels of mackerel, were all that was saved from them. The three vessels that first went ashore in the harbor, were so badly injured that they could not be repaired. Their crews, with the help of those who had lost their vessels, got out the mackerel, and de- posited it on shore, and stripped the ves- sels of their sails and rigging. The vessels which had cut away their masts, needed the masts to replace those which they had lost. When the storm had ceased, and the swell of the ocean had subsided, they man- aged to take out these masts. And placing a dismasted vessel between two others, -whose masts were standing, and rigging a derrick upon her deck, they hoisted out the stumps of the cut masts, and passing a strap around the middle of one of the foremasts, which had been taken from the * vessels on shore, and which had been floated alongside, they weighed it on board and   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   219 soon stepped it into its place in the keel- son. Repeating the same operation with the mainmast, they soon had two masts standing, which, -if a size too small, or too large, yet answered the purpose very well, and enabled' them to reach their home. Three vessels were thus- fitted with masts in a short time.  The stays- were set \up and the sails bent, and they were ready for sea. Four of the nine vessels that went ashore at Souris, were got off, after taking out their mackerel and salt. They were more or less damaged, and considerable time was required to repair them, so as to fit them for the voyage home. Peter Gott, and the vessels that got into the harbor of Rich- mond, rode out the storm without material damage. As soon as -the weather would permit, they took out the cargo of the ves- sel that had gone upon the beach, and fit- ting some skids under her bottom, they threw her upon her side and launched her into her proper element. , Finding her hull tight, they took the cargo again on- board,  &#xD;<pb n="220-221" xml:id="VAC7564-00000112"/> 220     PETER GOTT, and overhauled her rigging, and soon had her ready for sea, though with only a small anchor, which was lent her- by one of the other vessels which had it on board as a su- pernumerary. In the meantime, they had sent one of the skippers across the island to Souris, and learned the fate of the ves- sels that had put into that port. Several of these had been badly injured, and as the season was getting late, and they were likely to encounter more' bad weather, it was not thought best for them to engage agaim in ufishing. They, therefore, agreed to put the mack- erel and sails and rigging which had been saved from the wrecked vessels, on board of these, and despatch them to their re- spective ports. Some ten days had now. been consumed by the, storm and the re- fitting of the vessels, and they were rap- idly approaching the end of September. But those whose vessels were 1ill seawor- thy, determined to make an effort to fill them up. Peter Gott was the more desirous of doing this, as two of the vessels lost at   THE CAPE ANN FHERMAN.   221 Souris belonged to him and Mr. Dennis and they were. but partially insured. As soon as he had come to this decision, he got under way, and was followed by six other vessels from Richmond harbor. The nights were now cold and frosty, and Kersey jackets and woollen mittens were in demand. They found that since the storm, the body of the mackerel had moved to the northward, and they followed them across the bay, taking a few barrels daily., They were now large and fat, one barrel being worth two barrels of those which they caught when they first came into the bay. They continued beating about, and fishing when the weather would permit, for eight days, and had taken from forty to fifty barrels each, when perceiving indications of another storm, they hoisted" all sail and ran through the Gut of Canso and made for Liverpool, which they reached, and got into a safe harbor just as the storm broke upon them. They lay here until the third day, when the weather clearing up, they made all sail for home, which they -9'  &#xD;<pb n="222-223" xml:id="VAC7564-00000113"/> 222     PETER GOTT, reached about the middle of October. The vessels which they had depatched from Souris reached home a few days before them, and reported the sad disaster which they had met with. The Atalantis reached Newhuryport on the fifth of October, and  reported all the vessels at Souris lost. This report had reached Cape Ann, and pro- duced the most intense anxiety among the people, especially the friends of all the crews that had 'sailed from the Cape. About the tenth, the vessels that had es- caped at Souris arrived, and reported the true state of things, and relieved the good people of their worst fears. They reported the men from the Cape all safe. The relief thus afforded them from a state of most distressing suspense was almost indescriba- ble. They congratulated each other upon the good news, and rejoiced with the most heartfelt gratitude that the lives of their friends had been so wonderfully preserved in the midst of the most appalling dangers. On the next day, which was the Sabbath, all the clergymen on 'the Cape offered up   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   223 the most sincere thanksgivings for the pre- servation of the crews, and the most earn- est petitions for their safe restoration to their families and friends; and when, on the fifteenth, Peter arrived at Pigeon Cove, he was received with open arms, almost as one from the dead. In the course of three or four days the vessels all arrived and landed their fares. This storm was the most disastrous which had occurred since the mackerel fishing had been commenced by the fishermen of Cape Ann. There was but little loss of life indeed. In this respect they were wonderfully favored. But the loss of pro- perty was great. Eleven vessels were wholly lost, and many others seriously damaged, and the whole fleet was prevent- ed by it from obtaining full fares. In the early part of the year the fishing had not been as successful as usual; but few of the vessels had made enough to pay for re- pairs and outfits, and the owners were depending mainly upon the results of this trip for the profits of the, year and for the  &#xD;<pb n="224-225" xml:id="VAC7564-00000114"/> 224     PETER GOTT, means of meeting the payments becoming due for the vessels which they had previ- ously purchased. The winter was fast approaching, -and a large number of the families of the fisher- men had already taken up all the wages which they had earned, and some of them had much overdrawn their credit. Fisher- men are generally improvident, and have nothing laid up in store for .the future. They depend for a livelihood upon the la- bors of the present year; when these labors are unsuccessful, they and their families are destitute of their usual comforts, unless they can get credit'with their employers.  But this year most of the employers, owing to the losses which they had made, and the want of the profit which they had not made, were unable to give the needed credit. In this state of things, most of the men were compelled to engage in winter fishing. Several men, who had been able to sustain their families comfortably through the win- ter upon the earnings of the summer, were now obliged to resort to this laborious em-   f  THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   225 ployment to gain their daily bread. Several of the owners were obliged to get an ex- tension of their credit, and some were obliged to sell property at a sacrifice,to meet their payments. There had not been so much distress among the laboring fish- ermen and their families for some years as was experienced during this winter. The spring fishing had been unproductive, and nearly all the fishermen on the Cape had engaged in the mackerel fishing, hoping to make up for the want of success in the spring, and the disastrous result of this branch of their labor had left them disap- pointed and nearly destitute. It had also revealed to them the danger of this fishery, and destroyed their confidence in it to a great extent.  *    &#xD;<pb n="226-227" xml:id="VAC7564-00000115"/> 226      PETER qOTT, CHAPTER XVIII. PETER GOTT BUILDS A VESSEL AFTER A NEW MODEL -GOES TO THE BANKS IN HER, AND TO THE BAY OF ST. LAWRENCE- AGAIN.-BOUNTY LAWS. AFTER settling up with the several ves- sels in which he was interested, selling the. mackerel, and paying up the expenses of the year, Peter found that he had lost dur- ing the year about fifteen hundred dollars. This was to him a heavy loss; but; he was by no means discouraged. He had now seen a good deal of the world, and he had found out that losses- are incident to all kinds of business, especially to such as are carried on extensively. He had reflect- ed upon his business in all its relations, and losses had entered into his calculations. He had also learned something by his ob- servations at the Bay, and during the storm at Prince Edward's Island. He had noticed   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   227 that the largest vessels made the best weather, or in other words, that the men on board the larger vessels were better pro- tected from the weather and -suffered less than those in the smaller craft. He had also noticed that all the vessels that were lost were poorly fitted with ground tackle, while those that had long strings of cable and heavy anchors, rode pout the storm in safety. He was a man to profit by his ob- servations; and as two of the vessels in which he owned a share had been lost, he induced Mr. Dennis to join him in contract- ing for a schooner of seventy-five tons, upon a model somewhat different from that upon which fishing vessels had hitherto been built. She was to hayve a longer beam in proportion to her depth, and be better adapted to the stowage of cargo. Her cabin was to be larger, and to afford better' accommodations to her crew. She was to be fitted with stouter rigging, and larger and longer strings of cable than any fisherman had previously carried. Of course, upon- such a model it would take  &#xD;<pb n="228-229" xml:id="VAC7564-00000116"/> 228     PETER GOTT, more timber to build her, and her hull would cost more per ton, and her rigging would be much more expensive. But he was convinced that she would be safer, and would do more service; and besides, if she should not meet his expectations, she could readily be converted to some other use. Having completed his arrangements, he immediately visited Essex, and contracted with Choate &amp; B nham, two of- the most enterprizing builde of that place, for a vessel upon the proposd model. Her keel was soon laid, and by Christmas her frame timbers were set up. -She attracted much attention as the work progressed, and was visited by many fishermen and owners, and was the subject of much speculation. She was to cost, about a third more, in propor- tion to her tonnage, than any fishing vessel that had ever been built at Essex. Many doubted whether she would answer ,the purpose for which she was intended as well as the old model, and still -more doubted the expediency of employing in this busi- ness vessels of such costly construction. \   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   -229 In every pursuit of life, new ideas work their way -with difficulty. They are op- posed by the cautious and tie conservative. The vain and the self-conceited consider every man who advances a new idea, as tacitly reproaching them for not having had the same idea in their own minds. It is doubtless well that most men are held back by caution from rashy adopting new ideas, and acting upon them before they have been properly tested. Peter was not deficient in caution, but he had also enter- prize and calculation, and his careful obser- vation furnished him a safe basis for his calculation, and he was seldom deceived in the results which he anticipated. He lis- tened with good nature to the remarks of all sorts of critics. The work went vigorously on, and by the first of April he brought round his beautiful new schooner, under full sail, with the stars and stripes at her topmast. This was quite an event at Pigeon Cove, and served greatly to encourage the dispirited 'fishermen, who had struggled through the 20  &#xD;<pb n="230-231" xml:id="VAC7564-00000117"/> 230-     PETER GOTT, winter with great difficulty, many of them being almost exhausted by the severe labor and exposure to which they had been sub- jected. The losses which Peter had made the previous year, and the cost of -his new vessel, one half of which belonged to him, induced him to relinquish his purpose of remaining on shore, and going into part- nership with Mr. Dennis for another year, and determined him to take command of the Dennis, which was the name given to the new vessel. A good skipper can always get a good crew. Before his vessel was off the stocks, Peter had shipped a crew of smart young men; he had his pick among all the ambi- tious young men in Pigeon Cove and San- dy Bay. The crew mustered at Essex, took on board the needful ballast, and as- sisted in navigating the vessel across Ips- wich Bay, around Halibut Point, and into Pigeon Cove, on the first of April.. They now set about fitting her for the Banks, for this was the destination of her first trip. It is no small job to fit a new vessel for   rTHE CAPET ANN FISHERMAN.  -231 sea; the seamen find many things to be done after she has left the hands of the carpenters. ,The first thing is to take on board a sufficienti quantity of ballast, and see that this is properly secured, In a flat bottomed -vessel this is:of the utmost im- portance. When the hil of a boat is heel- ed on to her side by the wind, if the ballast is loose, it will naturally roll into that side that is in the water. When this happens, it will sometimes prevent the boat from righting, in consequence of which it soon fills with water, and founders. Many a small vessel has been lost at sea in conse- quence of the shifting of its ballast. To prevent this, a partition of plank is built on the keelson, dividing the hold lengthwise, and the, ballast is packed one half on one side of this partition, and one half on the other side. Then a chimney is built in the cabin to convey the smoke from the stove, and various fixtures are put up in different parts of the cabin and hold; loops are fitted to the stanchions, to hold harpoons and boat-hooks. The water-cask is mounted on  &#xD;<pb n="232-233" xml:id="VAC7564-00000118"/> 232      PETER GOTT, deck and secured; the harness-cask is fitted in its place. Then provisions, water and salt are taken on board and stowed away. Fishing lines and reels and splitting knives are put in their proper places; lines are rove to the water buckets; oil butts are put in their place; wood is cut and split, and taken on board for -fuel. Mattresses, bedding, and, lastly, sea-chests are taken on board; and when every thing is ready, the skipper carries on board the compass. During the first'voyage of a new vessel, the seamen find many little things to be done, which occupy their leisure hours,- such as whipping the loose ends of the sheets and the ends of the boats' painters; lashing pieces of old canvas around the cables, where they lay in the hauseholes, to prevent chafing; and various things that tend to make the rigging safe and contri- bute to the convenience of its working. Peter and his crew were ambitious that every thing on board their new craft should be ship-shape, and when they returned from the Banks, not a vessel in the whole fleet was in so perfect order as the Dennis. ,  *        '  '   - *THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    233 They sailed about the middle of April., The vessel proved a good sea-boat; she sailed well. But as rapid sailing had not been the leading object with her skipper, he had not fitted her with masts so tall that it was difficult for her to keep on her legs, whenever she met a capful of wind. The crew found themselves more comforta- ble on board her than they had ever been before in a fishing vessel. They reached the fishing ground in safety, and remained on the Banks nine weeks. At the end of this time they had caught six hundred and- fifty quintals of fish. The vessel was found to stow her fare more conveniently than those of shorter model. Her deck was wider,-and it was more convenient to dress the fish upon it than on any of the old. vessels. Soon after they left the Bank for home, she encountered a gale, which tried her strength and qualities as a sea-boat. She stood the trial to the entire satisfac- tion of all on board, although she was load- ed down almost to her water-ways. She reached Pigeon Cove on the sixth of July, . v 20* t  &#xD;<pb n="234-235" xml:id="VAC7564-00000119"/> ,234     PETER GOTT, without damage, discharged her fare, and immediately fitted out for the Bay of St. Lawrence, for a mackerel trip. She took on board her mackerel gear, which is en- tirely different from that required for cod fishing, and six hundred barrels, a suffi- cient supply of salt, and provisions for six months. One of the first acts of the American Congress, after the establishment of Inde- pendence, was to offer a bounty to fisher- men who should be' actually engaged in fishing four months in the year, and who should catch a certain number of quintals of fish per ton of the vessels employed. At the period of which we speak, the fish- ermen pursued such branch of the fisheries as they found convenient or most profita- ble, and at the end of the year received the bounty, provided' they had caught the number of quintals required, without much regard to the time actually employed in cod fishing. For some years past, the law has been more stringently interpreted. 'No vessel now is allowed to receive the bounty   .         z     .   THE CAPE ANN EISHERMAN.    235 which cannot make it appear that she has been actually occupied four months in cod fishing, whatever -number of quintals of codfish she may have taken per ton; and if a vessel is found engaged in mackerel fishing, under a cod fishing license, she for- feits all claim to bounty. Vessels now take a cod fishing license in the spring, and pur- sue this kind of fishing two, three or four months, as they find it convenient, before engaging in the mackerel fishery. If they have not completed the four months when the mackerel season commences, they go to the custom-house of the district in which the vessel belongs, and deposit their license with the, collector, and take out what is called a mackerel license, and' after follow- ling the mackerel fishing as long as they choose, receive their cod fishing license again, and complete their four months, that they may be entitled to the bounty. This is a source of much trouble and an- noyance to the fishermen, and there is no good reason why this distinction should be made between cod fishing and mackerel  /t  &#xD;<pb n="236-237" xml:id="VAC7564-00000120"/> 236     PETER GOTT, fishing by the government' The latter is as profitable to the country. It involves more capital and risk, and contributes quite as much to the training of good seamen as the former. Peter and his associates were not subjected to so much petty annoyance. If they caught the number of quintals per ton required by law, they received their bounty, without being required to make out four months in actual cod fishing. This left them at liberty to devote the re- mainder of the season wholly to the mack- erel fishery, if they chose, and to lay out their voyages as might best suit their con- venience. For many years past the Amer- ican government, instead of fostering the great American interest of the fisheries which was the obvious purpose of those who first framed the laws relating to the subject, has apparently thrown all the ob- stacles in their power in its way, and done what they could to harrass and cripple those engaged in it. Treaty regulations have been made with relation to it, by men who understood little or nothing about it;   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   237 and treasury orders have been issued by  men who, if they knew any thing concern- ing it, were evidently willing to sacrifice it to other and less important interests. It is to be hoped that the American govern- ment will one day be in the hands of men who will consider American interests para- mount to all other interests, and will con- sider the laboring classes as entitled to re- gard and protection. The thousands of  seamen and fishermen, who are annually adding largely to. the wealth of the coun- try by hard labor, and at the risk of their lives, are surely as well entitled to protec- tion in their persons and property, as those who are producing cotton and sugar and iron, at infinitely less risk and hardship. Captain Gott embarked, on the first of August, in the Dennis, and directed his course to Mount Desert, and looked!for mackerel among the islands along the coast of Maine. Finding but few mackerel, he  ran down to the Bay. of Fundy, and having coasted around the bay, put into Yarmouth, on the south-west coast of Nova Scotia.  &#xD;<pb n="238-239" xml:id="VAC7564-00000121"/> 238     PETER GOTT, Learning here all he could respecting the course which the mackerel schools were pursuing, he ran down to Canso, which separates the island of Breton from Nova Scotia, and having passed the Strait, put into Charlotte, the principal town on Prince Edward's Island. Here he landed ninety barrels of mackerel, which he had already taken; and then struck boldly across the Bay of St. Lawrence to the island of Anti- costi, and commenced fishing around its shores. Mackerel fishermen had never be- fore visited this region. Cod ,fishermen had occasionally visited the coast of Labra- dor to the northward of this point, towards the Straits of Belle Isle, but mackerel fish- ermen had never been to the north of the Magdalen Islands. Early in September he found the mackerel passing in great num- bers between the island and the Labrador coast. He met with good success in taking them. In addition to this, he went on shore on the island, and induced several of the French people to engage in his service, furnishing them with a boat and lines, and   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.  239 taking the mackerel which they caught from day to day, paying for them liberally in goods, which he had on board. In the course of two weeks he filled four hundred barrels. The school having now gone by, he left the ground and ran for the Magdalen Islands. The weather was grow- ing cold, and the equinox was near by; but in three days he took another hundred barrels. Indications of a storm now appear- ing, he ran for Charlotte, and arrived just as the equinoctial storm broke upon them. iHere he found but few American fisher- men. The great storm of the previous year, and the severe losses which they had sustained, deterred most of them from visit- ing the Bay of St. Lawrence this year. A few had gone to Mirimachi and the Bay of Chaleur, but most of them had confined their operations to the westward of Nova Scotia and the Bay of Fundy. Those who had gone to the Bay of St. Lawrence had been quite successful, and on visiting Rich- mond and Souris, the scenes of the disaster of the previous year, were received with  &#xD;<pb n="240-241" xml:id="VAC7564-00000122"/> 240     PETER GOTT, great hospitality by the inhabitants, who were quite disposed to encourage them to repeat their annual visit, for the sake of the supply of goods which they were thus able to obtain in payment for the mackerel which they sold them. Peter rode out the storm, which lasted two days, in perfect safety, as did all the others with him, except one. This one dragged her anchor and went on to the beach. As soon as the storm was over, Peter passed through the Gut of Canso and lay along the southern coast of Nova Sch- tia, and by the last of September he took fifty barrels more. He now sailed for home, where he arrived on the twelfth of October with six hundred and forty barrels of fish, the largest fare that had ever been brought into Cape Ann. Four hundred barrels of them were No. Is, worth, that year, seven dollars per barrel. One hun- dred and fifty of the remainder were No. 2, worth five dollars per barrel. The remain- ing ninety barrels of No. 3, were worth three dollars-makingthe fare worth three   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   241 thousand seven hundred and twenty dol- lars. The whole vessel belonged to Mr. Dennis and Peter. The vessel's share was eighteen hundred and sixty dollars, half of which, nine hundred and thirty, belonged to Peter. His share, as one of the crew, was one hundred and seventy-six dollars, and his per centage as skipper ninety-three dollars, making about twelve hundred dol- lars.- This was the most profitable trip he had ever made. His portion of the returns of the trip to the Banks was between five and six hundred dollars. The four other ves- sels in which he was interested, spent the fishing season on the coast of Maine and in the Bay of Fuhdy, and were tolerably suc- cessful. These vessels encountered no se- vere storm this year and suffered but little damage, and Peter's share of their united profits was about fourteen hundred dollars, making his whole income for the year about three thousand dollars. 21  &#xD;<pb n="242-243" xml:id="VAC7564-00000123"/> 242      PETER GOTT, CHAPTER   XIX., FORMS A PARTNERSHP WITH MR. DENNIS.-HS FAM- "Y. SCHOOLS. -A BUSY LIFE.- DISSOLVES PART- NERSHP. - A NEW STORE AND NEW FIRM.---VOYAGE TO THE WEST INDIES. -HE now found himself in a situation to carry out the plan previously agreed upon between him and Mr. Dennis, viz., that he should quit the sea and form a partnership, with Mr, Dennis, and take charge of the  business on shore. After selling off the fish and' mackerel, and settling with the crews, whp had been' in their vessels during the year, this arrangement was carried into effect, and a firnm constituted, under the name of Dennis &amp; Gott. Peter Gott was now forty-six years old. The labors and hardships he had endured- gave him the appearance of being more tkan fifty. He hadfacquired more expel   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   243 rience than most men of his calling of sixty. His character as a, man. of integrity was well established, and his :intelligence and well-known enterprize gave him great in- fluence among all engaged in the fishing business. He had been foremost in explor- ing every new field of labor, and ascertain- ing the feasibility of every new branch of the business. His credit was undoubted among all the furnishing houses of Boston, and they were all eager to enrol him among their customers. His family con- sisted of six children-two sons and four daughters. His eldest son\ was nineteen years old. During the four previous sum- mers, he had been engaged in the mackerel fishery, a part of the time with his father, and a part of the time in one of their other vessels on the coast. During the winters he had diligently improved the advantages afforded by such schools as then existed on the Cape. The beautiful and convenient school- houses that may now be seen all over the Cape, had no existence in those days. The  &#xD;<pb n="244-245" xml:id="VAC7564-00000124"/> Ycxr     PETER GOTT, well-arranged system of schools which the people have recently established, so honor- ably to themselves and with the promise of so much advantage to their children, ex- isted then only in embryo. There were very few school-houses of any kind. One of the first school-houses erected was six- teen feet by twelve, and an old record ex- ists, which shows that in the contract made with the carpenter, he was required to build it so that the school-room should be not more than six feet high. There were seve&amp; ral dame schools, as they were then called, taught chiefly by widows or elderly maid- ens, in which children were taught to read and spell, and to say the mrultiplication ta- ble and the catechism. These schools were generally taught in rooms in private houses, and often in the same room in which the work of the family was carried on. There was one -school, called a grammar school, for the whole Cape. This was kept six months at the Harbor and three months at Sandy Bay, and three months at Squam, the same master going from place to place   '-  *     e-          * ,  ^  THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   245, with the school, which was taught in the best room that could be found for the pur- pose. There were also two or three men who devoted themselves to the office of private instruction, and when the grammar school was not keeping in their neighbor-' bgad, were pretty well patronized. In the history of the schools of the Cape, the names of Riggs, Rogers and Saville de- serve to be commemorated. They were the educational lights of their day, and the good people of the Cape have expressed their respect for their memories by giving their names to schools which have been established in the vicinity of their several residences. In the grammar school, in ad- 'dition to reading and spelling, penmanship, arithmetic and grammar were taught. Peter Gott's family lived within the limits of the parish of Squam. His children at- tended the grammar school when it was taught in that parish, so soon as they be- came old enough to travel a mile and a half through the snows of winter to reach it. But these advantages, such as they 21* '  A            2 1 . (  &#xD;<pb n="246-247" xml:id="VAC7564-00000125"/> -246     PETER GOTT, were, were not lost to the men of those times. Peter Gott, Jr. had acquired a good practical" knowledge of figures, wrote a good hand, and was able to take the place of a clerk- in the establishment of Dennis &amp; Gott. In large fishing establishments, in which twelve or fifteen vessels are fitted out, there is a great deal of work to be done. The vessels average eight hands each, making a -hundred or more. Half of these, perhaps, o have families, containing four souls besides themselves. Here, then, are three hundred - persons to be supplied with the necessaries of life. An account is to be kept with each ,person in the employment of the establish- ment, and a separate settlement made with each one at the close of the year. The bounty also, which each mall receives, gene- rally' passes through the - establishment. This, together with the general accounts of purchases and sales, accounts with freight- ers and with coopers and packers and those who make the codfish, makes the book- keeping of the establishment a laborious and important work. Three or four out-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    247  door laborers are usually employed in the spring and fall-at least. Peter now found himself fully employed. He had to attend to the repairs of the ves-  sels; to the purchase of rigging and outfits?; f for the vessels and goods for the store; to the sales of fish, and the collecting of bills; to the obtaining of insurance and fishing licenses; to the securing of skippers for the several vessels, and the mldtifarious cares of the establishment. He was also chosen one of the directors of the insurance com- pany, at which most- of his insurance was done. As he was now to live on shore, he was expected to take an interest 'in the municipal affairs of the town. Fishermen, who are absent a large part of the .year, even if they are qualified and .disposed to act in public affairs, have little time or op- portunity to do so. Their owners, as the outfitting merchants are called, are expect- ed to represent them and look after their interests. A new man, one who leaves the sea and settles on shore, must take his turn as school committee and surveyor of high-    , " \  &#xD;<pb n="248-249" xml:id="VAC7564-00000126"/> 248     PETER GOTT, ways. In short, he must be willing to serve in all the offices of the town. These offices are not in general sought for by the citi- zens, except occasionally, to secure some local or temporary interest, but are consid- ered a task, which each man who is com- petent must perform in his turn. Peter Gott was chosen school committee man for his neighborhood, and feeling a deep in- terest to secure to his own children the best advantages in his power in the way of education, he attended faithfully to the duties of this office, and procured the best teacher within his power for the two months during which the public school continued. Whatever business or office he undertook for' the public, he brought to it the same good judgment and diligence which had distinguished him in his private business. This soon secured him the confidence of his fellow citizens to such a degree, that it was difficult for him to keep out of the offices which were urged upon him, and which most men in other places are ambitious to obtain. He was not desirous of that influ-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    249 ence which results from official position; he chose rather to devote himself diligently to his own business, and in this he found full occupation for all his energies. After one year, Mr. Dennis left the man- agement of the affairs of the firm almost exclusively to him. Under his direction, and guided by his good judgment, the vari- P ous skippers in their employment engaged in those various branches- of the business which promised the most advantage, and generally with good success: He did not- confine his attention exclusively to any one branch of the fisheries; some of their vessels pursued the  cod fishery  on the Banks, and: the smaller ones nearer home on the coast - Some went one trip to the Banks, and then fitted out for the mackerel fishery. Some of them, in the proper sea- son, pursued the pollock fishing. At the end of three years they had fifteen vessels connected with the establishment.   They were part owners of them all, which secur- ed for them  the buisiness of fitting them out, and the sale of the fish which they  &#xD;<pb n="250-251" xml:id="VAC7564-00000127"/> 250     PETER GOTT, caught, together with the supply of groce- ries and staple dry goods to the families of the men. This miscellaneous business re- quired them to keep a general assortment of goods in their store, making it what is called a variety store. As the general prosperity of the people of the village increased, the demand for a greater variety and better quality of goods increased also. This required that a larger assortment of goods should be kept by the merchant. Peter had shrewdness enough to keep up with the times. In the course of four or five years from the time when he united with Mr. Dennis in business, they not only had the largest fishing establish- ment on the eastern part of the Cape, but by far the largest and best assortment of goods in their store. This had the, natural effect of drawing to them a considerable trade from the inhabitants who were not engaged in the fishing business, and from those who were not in their employment. At the end of five years they were com- pelled to build a new store, and enlarge   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   251. their wharf and packing accommodations. The old store was used as a store-house for salt and fish. The general appearance of the village had much improved. Several new houses had been erected, and instead of the rust- colored moss, which attaches itself to the outer surfaces of buildings near the coast, the houses newly erected were neatly paint- ed. As larger vessels were now employed in the fishing business than formerly, bet- ter wharves were required for their accom- modation, runing out into deeper water. These, instead of being built of timber, ar- ranged cobhouse fashion as formerly, when timber was the cheapest and most abun- dant material, were now constructed of substantial stone walls, connected together by cross timbers, and 'filled in with stones and covered with plank. Evidences of gen-  eral thrift were apparent. They still had to take their vessels around to Gloucester Harbor to winter, as the artificial harbors,  that have since been constructed at great labor and expense, did not then exist. *    , ,    t  &#xD;<pb n="252-253" xml:id="VAC7564-00000128"/> 252-     PETER GOTT, Peter Gott, Jr. had now become an ex- cellent young man, with a character well established for talents and integrity. He - was not only an expert book-keeper, but an accommodating clerk, and well skilled in the purchase afd sale of goods. Mr. Dennis was now more than seventy years old,-and quite disposed to retire from 'll active participation in the affairs of the - firm; -and finding that young Gott had-- set his affections upon his only grand-daughter, Mary Pool, of Sandy Bay, he proposed to withdraw his name from the- firm, remain- ing a silent partner to the amount of ten: thousand dollars. The old sign of Den- nis &amp; Gott was taken down, and a new sign, of more pretension to artistic skill, was established in its place, on the front of the new store, bearing the name of- Peter -Gott &amp; Son. But. with the change in the name of the firm, no change occurred in the principles upon which its business was car- ried, on. Industry, economy and careful attention to every part of the business, were no- less strictly exercised than ibefore.   THE CAPE ANN FIS-HERMAN.   253 The habits of the house, in all these re- spects, were well established. They had a hundred and twenty-five men in their em- ployment as fishermen; most of their ves- sels were of the larger and better class. They had one or two new vessels built every winter. After running them about two years, and before their sails and rigging needed renewing, they often sold them to go into the coasting business, or to fisher- men from other ports. This was one of the advantages resulting from the new and. more convenient model which Mr. Gott had introduced. They could be employed in the summer as fishing vessels, and in the winter as coasters. Vessels of this 'class indeed often made voyages in the winter to the West Indies, freighted with provisions in the hold and lumber on deck, and brought back return cargoes of rum, molasses and sugar. Young Gott, finding that several of these West India voyages from Salem and New- buryport had proved profitable to their owners, and being disposed to see more of 22  &#xD;<pb n="254-255" xml:id="VAC7564-00000129"/> 254     PETER GOTT, the world than he had yet seen, proposed to his father to undertake such a voyage. They had a fine new schooner, which had come from Essex in July, and had been one trip to the Bay for mackerel. This he pro- posed to load with dry fish, and take on E deck-load of boards, which he proposed to bring up from Portsmouth-for the purpose, and take his uncle Gott for captain, and go himself as mate and supercargo. This plan was soon agreed to, and the half of the schooner which did not belong to the firm, was chartered of its owners, and they im- mediately set about fitting her out for the voyage. They sent to Portsmouth, and purchased a sufficient quantity of boards of the quality suitable for that market, and selected four hundred quintals of fish, heav- ily salted, such as are in demand for the use of the negroes on the plantations. These fish are called scale fish; they con- sist of hake and haddock. They take a great deal of salt, and dry harder and bear handling better, and keep better in a warm climate than codfish. They are also of less   THE CAFE ANN FISHERMAN.  255 value than codfish, and the planters, who desire to get provisions for their negroes as cheaply as possible, prefer them to codfish. These fish are shipped in large casks, screw- ed down firmly and stowed in the hold. They soon had the first stowed in this way and took on deck the boards, which had arrived from Portsmouth; and about the first of December young Gott set sail for Jamaica. He returned about the last of March, having made a good voyage. They cleared about twelve hundred dollars, after paying all the expenses of the voyage.  &#xD;<pb n="256-257" xml:id="VAC7564-00000130"/> 256      PETER GOTT, CHAPTER    XX. MULLET FISEIVNG.-CLAM DIGGING.-PETE R GOTT GRAD- UALLY WITHDRAWS FROM THE BUSINESS OF THE FIRM. --BECOMES A CULTIVATOR OF THE SOIL.--GOES TO THE LEGISLATURE. -HS CHARACTER, AND TEE CLOS- ING SCENES Op HS LIFE. SOON after this vessel had sailed for Jamaica, Mr. Gott, who had been for some time making inquiries with regard to the subject, fitted out an expedition for a new branch of fishing. There is a fish called mullet, which abounds on the southern coast of the United States, and especially in the Gulf of Mexico, during the winter. This fish, either fresh or pickled, is in de- mand in the southern market, and is nearly as valuable as mackerel. During the month of December, Mr. Gott and some of his neighbors fitted out two vessels to engage in this fishery. As mullet fishing could not very well be classed under the head of   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    257 cod fishing or mackerel fishing, they found some difficulty at the custom-house in get- ting a license, but finally settled it by taking a general fishing license, without specifying the kind of fish to be taken. They arrived out at Florida in safety, and had every prospect of a successful trip. But after they had been on the coast a few days, a norther came on to blow, and they ran into a -port on the coast. Here a cus tom-house officer demanded- their license. He had never known northern vessels, or-- vessels of such a description, to engage in this fishery, and was probably suspicious that they were wreckers in disguise, or that their purpose was to engage in smuggling, or some other illegal pursuit; and finding that mullet fishing was not specified in their license, he refused to return it to them. - As no vessel is allowed to navigate the waters of the United States without a license of some kind, under penalty of be- ing taken for a piratical vessel, and forfeit-- ed to the government, they found them- Selves in difficulty at once. They could 22*   &#xD;<pb n="258-259" xml:id="VAC7564-00000131"/> 258     PETER GOTT, not pursue their voyage, nor could they return home with their vessels.   - They immediately wrote to their owners for instructions. Mr. Gott, after having been at so much pains and expense to make an experiment in a new branch of fishery, which he hoped would prove bene- ficial to the fishing interest, was highly in- dignant that his people should be charged with being engaged in illegal pursuits, and his plans thus interfered with by an igno- rant and conceited official. After' consult- ing counsel, he -wrote to the masters of the vessels to abandon them to the government, and return home in the best way they could.  Some of the men went to New Or- leans, and shipped from thence to Boston; others shipped on board vessels bound to the West Indies, and thence returned to Boston. In the course of the winter they all reached. home. Mr. Gott immediately entered a protest in due form, and commenced an action against the government for the recovery of his vessels, and damages arising from   THE CAPfE ANN FISHERMAN.   259 their detention. This involved him in a long and tedious lawsuit, and was a source of much expense and anxiety. But at length a hearing was obtained before the proper court, and a verdict was given in his favor. The representative in Congress from the district to which Cape Ann be- longs, rendered essential servicein'the case, and did all in his power to promote the in- terest and security of the fishermen;' and it was owing, in no small degree, to the re- presentations which he made to the court, that a favorable verdict was obtained. Like most other lawsuits, even when a verdict is obtained in favor .f the plaintiff, this lawsuit cost more than it came to. He lost the use of his vessels for more than a year and a half; and the expense of attend- ing court, of witnesses' fees and board, and lawyers' fees, and the whole tissue of ex- penses which courts and lawyers know so well how to spin out, amounted to more than the damages obtained. As the expe- dition had been undertaken at the sugges- tion of Mr. Gott, and he had had the entire-   &#xD;<pb n="260-261" xml:id="VAC7564-00000132"/> 260     PETER GOTT, management of it, so he assumed the man- agement of the lawsuit, and paid the whole expense. There were several men engaged in the expedition, who owned shares in the vessels. These shares were nearly all the property they owned in the world; the loss of the use of their vessels during this period, and. the loss of their own time, and the expenses of the lawsuit would have ruined them.  Mr. Gott took these men into his employment, and paid them the full share of the damage recovered, without charging them any part of the expense. This affair cost him all that had- been made in the trip to Jamaica by his son. But it settled a question of much impor- tance to northern fishermen, and ascertain- ed that under a general fishing license, they might fish any where in the waters of the United States, for any description of fish. The failure of the expedition to make any pecuniary return to the owners, owing to the above cause, discouraged them from renewing the attempt, and nothing more was done in the mullet fishery. This   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   261 branch of the fisheries is still open for some enterprizing Yankee to- engage in, and there can be no doubt that, with proper management, it may be made profitable. The petty restrictions that are still attach- ed to the United States' license system, are a constant source of annoyance to the fish- ing interest, and it is high time that the whole system were thoroughly revised, and its provisions rendered. more liberal. If a man determines, at the beginning -of the season, to apply for the cod fishing bounty, let him conform to the rules under which that bounty is distributed; but if he does not purpose to apply for it, why should he be restricted at all,-why should he not be permitted to fish when and where, and for such fish as he pleases? And with respect to the bounty, if a certain number of quin- tals per ton of the vessel employed, is re- quired to entitle him to the bounty, and if he obtain the required number in two or three months, why should he be required to fish- four months in order to obtain it? It often happens that the required amount  &#xD;<pb n="262-263" xml:id="VAC7564-00000133"/> 262     PETER GOTT, has been made up in three months, and that the mackerel have become plenty on the coast, and it would be much more pro- fitable to the fishermen to engage at once in that branch of business. But the law requires them to make out four months. Many of them continue in the cod fishery and make ;out the four months, before engaging in the mackerel fishery at all; others exchange their papers at the cus- tom-house, and exchange their gear, and when the mackerel season is over, receive their cod fishing papers again, and make up the required time. But this occasions trou- ble and loss of time to the fishermen, and trouble to the custom-house officers, and some of these officers refuse to accommo- date the fishermen in this way. If the laws relating to the fisheries were made by those who understood the subject in all its rela- tions, there would be no difficulty in ar- ranging them to suit the convenience and interests of all parties; but when they are under the supervision of men from Missouri and Illinois, who have never seen a fish-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    263 ing vessel, and know nothing of the nature of the business and the difficulties attend- ing it, what better can be expected? If it is said that the object of the bounty is to make good seamen, and therefore they should be required to be at sea as long as possible, it may be truly replied, that the mackerel fishery, as at present carried on, on the coast of the British Provinces and in the midst of the most difficult and dan- gerous navigation, is the best possible school for seamen, altogether better than the Bank fishery, or the cod fishery upon our own coast ;--so that this argument en- tirely fails. After getting through with the mullet business, and paying the losses they had incurred, Mr. Gott and his son engaged, with renewed vigor, in those branches of the fisheries which they had previously pursued. Sometimes their vessels: secured the bounty on codfish; sometimes they made no attempt to obtain it, but pursued that branch of fishing that seemed the most promising at the time. They employed  &#xD;<pb n="264-265" xml:id="VAC7564-00000134"/> 264      PETER GOOTT, their own freighters to convey their fish to market, and to bring home the goods need- ed in fitting out and repairing their ves- sels. Occasionally they fitted out a cargo of fish and lumber to the West Indies, and brought back in return rum, molasses and salt. They were always ready to engage in any new enterprize that tended to pro- mote the -interests of the fishermen, or to furnish them with- a more profitable em- ployment. They occasionally lost one of their vessels at sea or on the eastern shores, and among the vessels which they fitted out were, every year, some -that failed of' success. But by honesty, careful manage- ment and steady enterprize, they gradually accumulated wealth, and increased their means of extending their business. In a few years they became the most reliable and influential firm connected with the fishing business on the Cape. About this time the business of digging clams was engaged in by a large number of persons. They are salted and preserved in barrels, and used by fishermen as bait   THE CAPE-ANN. FISHERiA.- N. 2-65 for codfish. For many years past, the dig- ging and salting of'clams for Boston market has been an important business.  These shell-fish abound in the extensive fiats at the mouth of SqUam River, Essex River, and Ipswich River. These flats are daily covered by the tidie, and afford the feeding ground which the clams require. They multiply with astonishing rapidity. They are dug in the winter and spring. The bu- siness furnishes employment for men and boys, that in former years were occupied in winter fishing. The work is done, of course, at low tide. When the tide is out, on pleasant winter days, one will often see gangs of ten, twenty or fifty men and boys busily employed in turning up the mud on the flats and picking up the clams into buckets. The implement which they use is a stout forkl wit:h three flat prongs, each about an inch wide and ten or telve inches long. The men go out on to the flats, in wherries, when the tide is retiring, and push an oar into the mud, and make -fast the boat to it, and as soon as the water ,is   &#xD;<pb n="266-267" xml:id="VAC7564-00000135"/> .266 ,    PETER GOTT, has left the boat, commence operations. When a bucket is filled,-it is emptied' into the boat. They continue their work until the tide comes in again sufficiently' to float the boat, when they pull to the wharf. On many places on the shores of these flats, there are groups of small huts, ten or twelve feet square, with stone chimneys- running up on the outside, furnished within with a small stove and twh or three stools for seats. The clams are deposited in these huts, and in -hose parts of the day when  the tide is in, so that the men cannot work out on the flats, and in stormy weather, they are employed in shocking them, as it is called, that is, in opening the shells and taking out the clam, which is done- with a small, stout knife. As the clams are taken from the shell, they are dropped into a bucket; when the bucket 'is filled, it is emptied into a barrel. Around these huts it isiot uncommon to see heaps of clam- shells larger than the huts themselves, the akcq mulations of the winter's labor. The  clam -diggers sell the produce of their labor   THE CAP-E ANN FISHERMAN.  267 to traders, who send their teams around to the huts, weekly or daily, according to the weather, and carry them to their store- houses, and repack and salt them, and head them up in bar:rels, when they are ready for the market. The business is one that exposes the men very much to the weather. As their move- ments in going to and coming from the clam flats must necessarily be governed by the tide, they often go out or return in the night. The weather at this season, too, is very changeable, and ften, when out upon the flats and their boatSaground, a storm of snow or rain is driven in upon them from the ocean with great fury; sometimes they are thus unexpectedly drenched with cold rain or covered with snow or-sleet. The east winds, too,. that blow over these flats, sometimes pierce them to their very bones. They have no shelter but such as they can obtain by cowering down in the mud under the lee of their boats. Here - they must r'emain patiently until the tide comes to float them off. Sometimes they  &#xD;<pb n="268-269" xml:id="VAC7564-00000136"/> 268     PETER GOTT, leave their boats on the flats, and make the best of their way through the pools and creek to the nearest shore. There have been many instances of severe exposure, not only of health, but even of life, among those engaged in this business. In early times, when the fishermen used clams, they- dug them themselves. When purposing to be absent several days, they went to the clam ground, and dug a few buckets of clams, as a preliminary step. They were not in the habit of preserving them with salt. In later times, a division of labor was found more convenient and profitable, and the procuring of clam bait became a busi- - ness by itself, or rather a separate branch of the fishing business. Gott &amp; Son, finding that the supply of bait was not equal to the demand, proposed to those who were in the habit of frequent- ing the flats, to take all they would dig during the winter, and pay them one half in cash, and one half in goods. These men, now finding that they had a ready and sure market, set themselves diligently at work;   TH E CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   269 others also engaged in the business, in pre- ference to winter fishing. By the time the opening spring brought a demand for bait to be carried to the Banks, they had accu- mulated more than five hundred barrels. The purchasers found the barrels and salt, and paid about four dollars per barrel. In the spring they readily sold for six, thus yielding them a profit of about one dollar. This business they carried on for several years, some years purchasing from one to two thousand barrels, thus furnishing em- ployment to quite. a number of families, and deriving a fair profit to themselves. In every new enterprize in which Mr. Gott engaged, he had reference to others as well as to himself. He sought to make pro- fitable employment for the laboring men around him, for he believed that the best way to help others was to furnish them with the means of helping themselves. If all who are charitably disposed would adopt this principle, and invest their money in the establishment of some business that would furnish steady and useful employ- 23*   &#xD;<pb n="270-271" xml:id="VAC7564-00000137"/> 270     PETER GOTT, ment to those who need assistance, how much more real good would be done than by bestowing the same amount in charity. Not only would, the individuals thus em- ployed be benefited in a much greater degree, but the whole community would derive advantage from it also.-- There are doubtless many cases in which almsgiving, or direct acts of charity, are required by every principle of humanity; but where profitable employment is furnished to the necessitous, they are spared the degrada- tion which accompanies the reception of alms. They feel that they render an equiv- alent for what they receive. They acquire habits of industry, if they were wanting in them before, and learn to rely upon their own exertions. The moral good thus con- ferred upon them is, in most cases, of more value than the physical. Mr. Gott, through the whole of his life, felt a deep interest in the class of men from which he sprung, and especially -in the young men who were coming forward into life. He was a careful observer of charac-   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   271 ter. Whenever he saw a young man in- dustrious, diligent and faithful, and disposed to avail himself of every opportunity to advance himself, he was always ready to aid him, and to put him into the situation to which he thought hitn best adapted. He remembered the struggles of his own boyhood, and the kindnesses he had receiv- ed from his old friend Dennis. Not all who were assisted by hint manifested or felt the gratitude which he felt for his benefactor; but there were many who felt their obliga- tions to him, and acknowledged their in- debtedness to his helping hand. 'Very many of the young men in his neighbor- hood owed their success in after life to the encouragement and assistance which they received from him.' His kindness to the people whom he employed, and the confi- dence with which he treated them, gene- rally ensured their fidelity. There is no clags of men more sensible to kindness than seamen, or who will longer remember a favor or more faithfully requite it. Until they have been hardened and brutalized  &#xD;<pb n="272-273" xml:id="VAC7564-00000138"/> 272     PETER GOTT, by severity and harsh treatment there are no hearts more susceptible of tender emo- tions and kind feelings than the hearts of the sons of the ocean. Young Gott had now become extensively known as an intelligent, efficient, and up- right business man. He had a young fam- ily growing up around .him. Mr. Gott, having secured a competence, was disposed gradually to retire from business and leave the management of the affairs of the firm to his son. That he might the more read- ily carry out this purpose, he purchased a few acres of land about half a mile from the Cove, and rented a house and barn upon it, and removed into it with his family, and his mother, who still survived, and whom he ever cared for with most affectionate and filial regard, and gave up his house to his son. Most men, as they become advanced in years, acquire a fond- ness for cultivating the soil. After having tried other occupations with more or less success, they find in this an occupation congenial with their feelings, thus proving   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   273 at this is the most natural employment of man. Mr. Gott was no exception to this law Ee had for several years found much satisfactio in the cultivation of a little  garden, and had gradually come to take much interest in the pursuits and successes of the few farmers in his -neighborhood. The land upon the Cape is generally hard and rocky; but there are patches of fertile soil lying between the hills and ledges. Many of these, by persevering labor, have been brought under cultivation. When cleared of stones and subjected to the plough, they are very productive. The seaweed deposited by the waves on the shore, and the offal of the fish, afford abun- dant means of enriching the soil. There X are many acres thus cultivated, that yield as large crops as any land in the county of Middlesex. Mr. Gott selected about four acres of such soil. He took from the sur- face stones enough to enclose the field with a heavy, substantial wall. In a few years he had -a fertile and beautiful field, and a fine garcen well stocked with apple, pear  &#xD;<pb n="274-275" xml:id="VAC7564-00000139"/> 274     PETER GOTT, and quince trees. In the cultivation of this garden and field, he took great pleas- ure, and spent much time. But he did not wholly withdraw from his business; he daily visited the store and wharf, and kept himself fully acquainted with all their business transactions, and ad- vised with his son in respect to every trip that was to be made, and the men who were to -be employed. He kept himself acquainted with the state of the books and the result of every voyage. In the insur- ance office, of which he had now for many years been a director, his opinion was much relied upon, with regard to the value of vessels and the rates of insurance which each should pay. No man understood bet- ter than he the value of all property in the section of the town in which he resided. He was chosen, though much against his will, one of the assessors of taxes, for many years in succession, and was thus compelled to become acquainted with the affairs of' every citizen in town. This is an office of much. responsibility, requiring a sound   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   275 judgment and great impartiality. Both these qualifications he possessed in a high degree. Tax-payers occasionally grumbled, as indeed some always will, at the taxes  assessed upon them; but no man ever se- cured more fully the confidence of the great majority of his fellow citizens than he. Hence he continued to serve in this capa- city as long as he could be persuaded to undergo the labor. When he withdrew from this office, he was selected by his fellow citizens, without distinction of par- ties, to represent them in the General Court. With great diffidence he accepted this office. It was a field of duty with which he was wholly unacquainted; but he brought to it the good sense and lonesty of purpose which were essential parts of his character, and that knowledge of human nature by which he was enablqd, as by a sort of intu- ition, to judge of the characters of those about him. Although unacquainted with the forms of legislation, he readily perceived the bearing of measures proposed and the motives of those who proposed them. He * ,  t  &#xD;<pb n="276-277" xml:id="VAC7564-00000140"/> 276     PETER GOTT, had been in the legislature but a few weeks, before he had secured the respect of all who had become acquainted with him. His sound judgment, and the modesty with which his opinions were uttered, gave them much weight. The mackerel fishery had now become an extensive and important business, and the vessels were fitted out from various establishments on the Cape, at a distance from each other. Up to this time the in- spector-general of fish, who lived in Boston, had appointed but two or three deputies for the Cape. It often happened that the interest of the owners required that mack- erel should be inspected and packed at nearly all these establishments, at the same time. But the small number of deputy inspectors rendered this impossible. The office was one of considerable emolument, each deputy receiving nine cents for every barrel inspected by him. Hence the depu- ties had always opposed the appointment of a larger number. Mr. Gott, always re- garding the interest and convenience of his   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.    2" constituents, procured an alteration in the law regulating the inspection of fish, requir- ing the inspector to appoint as many dep- uties as the convenience of the business required. This change in the law led to the appointment of some ten additional deputies, which proved a great convenience  to all concerned in the business. Mr. Gott remained in the legislature two years, at the end of which he declined be- ing again a candidate for the office, and retired, carrying with him the respect and confidence of all his constituents- -This was the last public office which he consent- ed to fill. He now purchased a few acres more of land, and confined his attention chiefly to the cultivation -of the soi. His children were all married, and settled in the vicinity. They and their numerous families looked up to him with reverence and affection } they went to him for advice in all their trials, and always found him- ready to impart to them not only the coun- sels of experience, but such assistance as their circumstances required. He cherish- ' 24     !   - "  *  -  , ^ 2 4  "'. '  ';'X   &#xD;<pb n="278-279" xml:id="VAC7564-00000141"/> 278     PETER GOTT, ed to the last a deep interest in all their affairs; and when his children and grand- children assembled around him on Thanks- giving day, as they continued to do till the close of his days, he sat among them like a patriarch, revered and beloved; and as he looked upon them his heart swelled with emotions of gratitude to .Him -who had watched over all his steps, supplied all his wants, and crowned 'his days with loving kindness and tender mercy. His venerable mother had now been dead- some years.. She lived to be seventy- four years old, and retained her faculties and'-her activity to the- last, and her inter- est in her numerous descendants  She was beloved by them all; and when they followed her to the grave, it was with the feeling that her cheerful voice, her ready assistance, her tender sympathy, and her wise and pious counsels would be greatly missed by them  all. -All who were ac- quainted with her felt that they had lost a-true friend, and cherished her memory with affectionate regard.   THE CAPE ANN FISHERMAN.   279 Mr. Gott's family had been seldom vis- ited with sickness. His children were bless- ed with good constitutions. They grew up with habits of industry and diligence, which were followed with the natural reward of cheerfulness and health. Winning their bread by cheerful toil, cherishing mutual love and confidence, and contented with their condition, few families enjoyed a- greater share of happiness.- But man is born to die; and in whatever path he' may walk throg"h life, his steps tend to the grave. 'rC Gtott now approach- ed the close of us/-w:ell-spent life. H., work was done"., ie had for some time withdrawn fromt the business of the firm, and given it up entirely to his oldest son, who had become a highly respectable and useful man, and enjoyed the perfect con- fidence of the community around him. Early in March -he took a cold, which was followed with some inflammation of his lungs, and a slight cough, which gave his friends but little anxiety at first. After a few days, however, his appetite failed, and  &#xD;<pb n="280" xml:id="VAC7564-00000142"/> 280      PETER GOTT. his strength yielded to the progress of the disease, and it became apparent that hie must soon cease to be an actor in the scenes of life. He called his children and friends around him, and gave to each a; kind parting word, and laid himself down for his final repose. In a few days his remains were followed to the tombs by a long procession of his weeping kindred and friends, who were joined by hundreds of his fellow citizens from all parts of the Cape, in this last trib- ute of affection and respect. His example and his virtues are still held in affectionate remembrance by the fishermen of the Cape, and no name is spoken by them with more respect and veneration than the name of PETER GOTT.     &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
