<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7184">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Time, or, The Incidents of a Life </title>
            <author >McMechan, I. V. V.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7184</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Time, or, The incidents of a life</title>
                  <author >McMechan, I. V. V.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >40 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >P. Childs</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Clay [New York?] </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1851">1851</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-25">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Time, or, The incidents of a life</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7184-00000001"/>TIME,   OR   THE INCIDENTS OF A LIFE    BY 1. V. . C M ECHAN,   Author ofr"lwafbella orCastile," ( EIyttwyn o3Blo cue,"Circamiamn, etc. etc. etc.   CLAY: P. CHLDS &amp; C., 1001 gO 3 JOB P0AUTS 1851.  &#xD;<pb n="0-3" xml:id="VAC7184-00000002"/> INTRODUCTION.   On a pleasant September evening in the year 18---in a small village but a few miles east of the Hudson, might be seen, lounging around the door of the best tavern, a group of p-rsons com- posed of that class who usually frequent those places where intoxicating drinks are vended. The leader of the group, a well formed and sinewey son of Nep- tune, was descanting on the prospect of the weather as he stood with arm ex- tended, pointing towards the Kattskill mountains and persisting with the ob- stinacy characteristic of an old sailor in his first assersion, that the lowering of the clouds upon the mountains at sun- set, was a sure forerunner of a storm ere morning. He had assumed that dogged resolution which will yield to no argu- ment and was on the point of reitera- ting his first remark, when a carriage drawn by fourhorses, was seen rapidly advancing up the New York and Albany hig'way, when slackening the rein direct- ly opposite,. the driver with a sudden crack of the whip. bro't them under full t speed in front of 'the hotel. It-is a cus-  tom seldom deviated from by our Amer- J ican postillions when entering a town, a ? of increasing the speed of their beasts ( 2i if possible to a gallop, their motive being I unquestionably, to attract observation, i : even at the risk of every neck in the t v coach. The carriage having halted, yan- 1 kee curiosity was on tiptoe among the i ' bystanders, huddling around the steps L to behold its inmates, ' Room, gentle- 1 X men, room ' exclaims the hostler. as he t Acast open the door i but the command f r was unnecessary, for the first passenger t J alighting with a bound and a growl was g a 'huge Newfoundland dog, of such a I ferocious and formidable an aspect, that h half the loungers without regard to cer- g emony or etiquette, took to their heels. a ' Down, Wolf, down! there is no dan- y ger here my  good fellow 1 The dog o appeared to understand the command at o once, for after wagging his tail and walk- s ing among the spectators, he returned to 8s   n the person who addressed him, a mana, a of a dark and sun-burnt complexion, it evidently of another clime, who had just )f descended the steps. The next and last L- was a person who must have seen from it sixty to seventy winters; his pace was s slow and stately, and there was some- , thing in his appearance that riveted the - attention of all; his scarred face; his sun f burnt brow; together with that lofty step - and eye of fire, seemed to bid defiance  1 to time. He reminded me of the mra- - jestic oak, that has withstood the blast a of centuries, and although by the furs f of the elements, a branch is here and - there riven from its trunk, still its roots e remain firm and immovable. I Leaning one arm on his staff, the oth- - er supported by his servant, he bent his - way towards the house. After gaining , the door and halting a moment, he hast- r ily cast his eyes around upon the strange r faces, then wiping a tear from his cheek - and heaving a sigh involuntarily ex- i claimed as he turned to his servant, ' Oh! time! time! I can recognize no face here my good Selim, all--all are gone!' * Then casting the contents of his purse among the crowd  and followed by his dog, wended his way into the house.- It was amusing to see their eager avid- ity as they hustled against each other in their anxiety to secure its contents. which having accomplished, the inquiry ' Who. is he twas again and again repeated. I'll tell you who he is, shouts the sai-- lor. ' Shiver my timbers! if ever I saw the scar. of a boarding pike,on any man's face that old tar carries it, and bravely too!. ' Did you not observe his swag- gering gait? Take my word for it, the Brilish Lion at the Fngate's mast head, has more than once fallen beneath his ea- gle eye.' Away with your folly,' cries a veteran of '76, he was never one of your water fowls! ' Did you ever hear of a boarding pike taking a man's hand off at the. wrist, and did you .ever, see a sailor with a gait as erect as his 2 he is some old general who has served in the  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7184-00000003"/> e Wars I whatdo you know of the wars?' responds the first speaker. ' What do these land lubbers know of the wars .?- Did you ever know one of them. with a loose purse string? answer me that my hearty!' The warmth of our disputants was in- ereasing rapidly, when' the door of the hotel abruptly opened, and Selirn step- ping forth thus addressed them: ( Gen- tlemen, my master has retired, being much fatigued: he requests Ay^ to take this gold, and 'regale yourselves at the next house.: ' Long life to the old Com- xnodore,' cries the sailor, c and when he leaves this world, may he go with good ballast, all sails trimmed, and colors fly- ing!' ' Aye,' exclaims the soldier, ' and when--  but the shout X which was now raised by the group, as they moved for the next house, drowned all remarks in the confusion. But every thing has its day, and the arrival of our travellers was but one of them. Time gradually performed its annual rounds. All attempts to learn Ihe former residence of the strangers were unsuccessful. With the exception of one old woman,. who was positive he had seen the face of the gentleman yearn gone by when but a youth, but bwhen or where she could not or would -ot say. Urged upon dte subject, with a shake of the head her answer always was, ' Do you not see he is relieving the afflicted wherever he goes V' 'Gener- ous old man! were I to mention your name, there are some here who would 'hide their heads with shame for their ingratitude.' Each Sabbath morn when the weather was fair, might be seen the old gentleman, accompanied by Selim -and followed by his faithful dog, wend- ing his way to the church. The master having taken his accustomed seat, his servant would invariably place himself in the rear, and Wolf occupying his position at the door of the pew, observe ;is every motion with the fidelity of his attendant. The church and the grave yard, were his only resorts; every day would he spend from one to two hours rtrolling among the graves, and read ng theinsoriptionsupon thetomb ' Wu his potstion an erect one, Woll /'        was standing by his side ; did he recline upon the grass the faithful dog lay by him and Selim always in attendance - But time is making its annual rounds; years have passed, and the stranger is ,gathered to his rest. Upon his demise, a paper was handed to the authorities by his servanti defining the spot where he wished to be interred. The poor who looked to him as a protector, followed him to his grave, preceded by his serv- ant anid docile dog. For the space of a week, did he and his lone companion visit his master's tomb, but the true heart- ed Selim, borne down by grief, did not long survive him. He, in a short time, was placed by his side, in the I house appointed for all living.' Poor Wolf- the long tried and constant Wolf-he was alone; his home was the grave yard, his bed the sod that covered his friends; no urgency, no entreaty, could draw him from the spot, The poor, who respected him for his master's sake, and who remembered his dying words ' Be kind to my dog,' daily carried him food. But it was all in vain; soon after the dog was Iound dead upon the head of the grave, and the following day, buried at the feet of the strangers. Upon examining his papers, a will was found, bequeathing his vast prop- erty to benevolent purposes, and at the bottom of an old escrutoire. the succeed- i ing chapters headed ,c TIME, OR THR INCIDENTS OF A LIFE,' was found. CHAPTER I. r Well has it been said by a celebrated i character, that ' resist it as we will, our D destiny must be accomplished.' Oh t i time! time! thou unraveler of all mys-  teries, the past, present, and the future! Patiently have I waited, satisfied that an. I 'ALL SEEING POWER' would, when his F omniscient eye saw fit, sufficiently raise i the veil of the future to a poor, weak, ) deluded mortal, and satisfy him, if in i this world, lasting happiness could be obtained. The search is vain , man is r placed here but to prepare for the future.. s At the age of almost fourscore years r with a debilitated frame; an eye dim'd with age; limbs paralyzed with infirm- f ties; a heart that once feared no dan-   ger, no10  alarmed at the least uunsual palpitation, warning me that the Bands, of my hour glass are almost numbered and with locks once of the raven hue now ' silvered oe'r with age.' Sitting in my great arm chair a few eveninogs past, with my servant Selim ready at imy slightest call, I was inad. vertently drawn into the above reflec- tions. The hour hand stood at half past twelve at night. The candle was burn- ing low in its socket. My Tartan plaid suspended on a nail. My turban placed upon the toilet. My Spanish stiletto safe- ly secured in its sheath. Wolf, my brave Newfoundland dog sleeping at my feet, and the smoke from my German pipe. curling its folds to the ceiling. There I sat, alone with my dog, ta- king a hasty meditative view and com- mitting to paper the striking and change- ful Incidents of my checkered life, mem- ory recurred to by-gone times. It carried me back to the days of my I childhood, when, deprived of all my 1 friends at the early age of fourteen years, I was left houseless, almost penniless ( and driven by adversity from the beau- . tiful tillage of K--compelled to seek t my  fortune in a distant land. I left it ( m  the year 17-and meeting with but e few obstacles, safely arrived in the city l of Now York.            t One day, whilst saunteringupon oe of i it wharves, I was unexpectedly accost- ed by8 a Rusian sea Captain (it is hard- a lr necessary for me to add, he had an r interpreter,) in a rough aristocratic tone s with the inquiry, Are you in search of c Lork my   lad  I eagely answered in tl the affirmative.  With an imperitive n Slance of the eye. he orderedl me on h board his vessel, then ready to sail.- h I soon learned she was bound direct for p St. Petersburg. Immediately on the ar- ol rival ofthe Captain, the anchors were d raised, the sails unfurled, all handspiped cl to quarters and we were gaily scudding m with a heavy sea, main sail doubly reefed w across the broad Atlantic.   or Home! home! sweet home  of my fu childhood, I leave you, perhaps forever! n So young, cast loose upon the broad ti world, with no protector, none to advise, d( -Ime to ahield me from danger, none to ly   Ial guide my feet arighto! None, did I say,  is, But a short tirme had elapsed, when d, standing in the grave yard, surrounded ue by the prying eye of curiosity, sympa- thizing with my sorrows but extending w no arm to relieve ; as I there stood wit- m nessing the clods coverii(r the coffin of d- my, last relative; whenl z:e pious -old c- sexton had put the finishing sod on the st mound(, he turned to me with the tears I- trickling do wn his furrowed cheeks, and id perceiving that we were alone,xextended d his hand -as he whispered in my ear : - ' Somethifrg prophetic tells me, that, y although at timnes youppstar may blazon y ande expand with refulgent light; yet n your days of sorrow will be many. Look my son, when those dark hoursme i- envelop youm to a high and unfailing i- source for consolation.' Did that 0ol i- mart read my future fate aright? Could l- he delve into-But why do I anticipate I On on we go across the broad Atlan. y tic, each prosperous breeze bearing me yfarther from the land of my nativify.- , With boyish frankness, I related allthe ;Y events .of my past life to the Captain, - and this confidence influenced him to k treat me with much indulgence. I not t only received a  fair compensation for t such assistance as I was able to render. r but through his kindness was enabled to obtain from the interpreter, a smatter- F ing of the Russian language. *   After encountering many dangers, we - arrived safely at our destined port. I L remained several days on board the ves- t sel, while she was refitting for another Fcruise, and it was then I first learned that our Commander, was of the most noble descent, with wealth and honors heaped upon him, and. when he might have retired to ease and affluence, he preferred periling his life in the cause of his country. The vessel he comman- ded, was a ship of war of the largest class. I   had been on board several, months, we still remained in port, when word was brought from the capital for our instant embarcation.. All was con- fusion: but amid a   perfect Babel of noise, I  managed to catch enough dis- tinguishable words, to learn that we were destined to attack the Turkish fleet then lying in the Archipeligo. My heart boun. 1     Y   &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7184-00000004"/> ded at the intelligence; theo but a youthi, r it had long been .my desire to witness a e naval battle. 'Pearilea for the issue, for my all was tI at stake, often was I sitting upon the c deck eyeing'.the horizon, and watching s the ripling of the water as our vessel i] was plowing proudly rouough the waves d towards the scene'of action. I was vet t  aboy, but endowed with strength and c agility, before which many of;maturer t years, would have recoiled. My tem- c perament was naturally sanguine, and I my disposition, when aroused to anger, almost uncontrollable; but to counterbal- 1 antce that. weakness, which required 1 years .of trial to overcome, I had a for- I giving temper.          ( One trifling incident, briefly narrated, l wit /-llustrate it :-.One day, whilst ly- { irig:/i'trJfor some small offence, I r gtrjUa Couth of about my own page so , violently, he fell senseless upon the N deck. My Captain was standing in the 1 companion way, and it was the first and 3 last timne hi:csountenance lowered upon , t me with a ger. Iperceived my danger, : but remorse had already seized mo.-; , CharlesI exclaimed, ' forgive me for : I -was in the wrong! The boy, who i Oloved q ea as a brother clasped me me- o-0und the neck. ( Let this blow, be to you a lesson,' said the Captain, as his brow relaxed, ' it is the first offence a I pass it by;recollect sir, .cting upton the impulse of the moment some- timaes places man in a situation that years of penitence and repining cannot atone for it The subsequent day, at the -immin ent peril of my lifO, I rescued * I hbarlesfrom a watery grave. Propitious :gales ifavored us, and one morning web tuneIxpectedly found ourselves in sight ol theTirfkish fleet.   q"Stroiin the/.belief that my courage- ,would 'sustain. me in the dread hour of danger; I watched with the keenest in- tensity, our approach to the enemy On we moved, until we closed. Terrible * Was the, contest. During that bloody day, when our deck lay strewn with the , dead and'Aying; when every broadside , told with the most fatal effect, even when 'ldanger pressed so close that my Com- mander with a smile of satisfaction at the daring of one so young, ordered me "to retire below and I answered ' I would   rather die by the side of my benefactor,' even in that dread hour, I felt no fear.. But suffer me to omit particulars of that bloody victory, where the Turkish crescent was made to succumb before superior skill and courage. After remain- ing in those seas some time, we had or- ders (a treaty having been consumated) to return.- Encountering.: but few obsta- cles in our homeward passage, difficul- ties so insigninicant 1 shall not touch up- on them, we arrived at our destined port in an unprecedented short time.- One day, whilst lounging listlessly before the mast, the steward rang the bell for my appearance iti: the cabin. With my hat, under my arm and an elastic step, I walked down the com- panion way, carrying a heart full of grateful emotions towar }; my  com-. mander, for I loved him ai a parent. I asked his."commands. POinting .to- wards the sofa', Be seated, Ferdinand,' he said, 'I have somethingl ..to say to you.' I observed an unusual cloud upon his brow, and I watched with a palpitating heart as he sat ,several min- utes buried in deep meditation. Is it possible, I thought, that through my inexperience,. I have offended niy4.. n- ly remaining  friend  I involuntarily, my eyes were cast up to seaven in 3 supplication. When I again looked on , my friend, all my foreboding, vaniSh-, ed in a moment. With a look of be-- 'nevolence: and an affectionate smile upon his countenance, he grasped my hand. ' Always put your trust in your God, as ]I see you now do, and the winds of adversity ' may blow around you, the dark adversary may cross your path at every step; yet rest s assured, an ALL SEEING EYE will shield you ' from all harm. My motive fol requesting t your presence, is this; you one iday, in my bearing, expressed a wish Sto become a sol- s'diern' I was about to inteTrupt llhim, but f with a sign he commanded my silence.- ' I have a brother, an officer, now preparing a for a campaign against the Cossacks. Im. mediatelyv on our arrival at' St. Petersburg, I wrote fim, mentioning your wish, and yes- Y terday received his reply. Upon my recomn endation, although so young, he contents to receiie you as his aid. It is at your option a to go or remain.' He perceived I hesitated and continued;' Should you enlist in the It Russian army, where merit receives its re-  ward, I have no doubt you will arrive at dis- d tinction-.' I was unable to reply. ' Permit.   me to advise you,' he said,' join my brother in this expedition, also take this signet ring and purse well filled with gold and should you ever need a friend, remember Captain N.' I could not speak ; such kindness entirely overcame me, but wjth tears of gratitude, threw myself into his arms, ' God will bless you air, for such philanthropy towards an un- protected orph an and stranger.' Almost be- fore I was aware of it, we had ascended to the. deck. and I had placed' myself in the boat which lay alongside, of the ship, and thus I left this noble generous friend. As I looked back to the vessel where I had spent so many happy hours, I saw him standing on the deck, waving a last adieu. It was the last! my God! I never saw him more! But ever shall he live in my heart, the first best friend of the lonely deserted boy. Let me pass hastily over several years of ,this eventful life; years that with most would comprise in its vicissitudes the age of man so burdene'd were they with incidents, But time had dealt with a lenient hand, and for- tune had showered her favors with an open palm. My bird's eye view of the Kremlin that wonderful. work of man, subsequently -nearly annihilated by Napolean and his Eol- diers; the excursion to the bloody field of ;Pqltowa where the rashness of Charles XII lost him the empire of Russia; my circuit- ous route to the river Don; my narrow es- cape from a horde of Cossacks, with the loss of all my baggage' (after fortunately preserv- ing the life of a Russian, serf, then in' their hands.) Yes, Selim, well hast thou repaid me for the danger I then encountered in suc- ,coring thee! My grateful, faithful Selim! Little did I think that in after years, when basely betrayed into the hands of the. enemy, your noble life would be so perilled in pre- serving mine. But I am again wandering ; let me pass over my journey to Circassia, with several ensuing years, and introduce the reader to-a change of incidents so-emark- able, that even now, while occupying my great arm chair, in e solitary apartment, and imperfectly committing them to paper, my brain isat times bewildered, and had I not ex- berienced them, I would almost beinclined -to call it fiction. CHAPTER II. It was an autumnal night in Russia, in the year 17--a young officer apparently about twenty five or thirty years of age, was sit- ting in his tent wrapped in a fur cloak, with his sabre hanging by his side, and his pistols in his Belt, he was evidently preparing for 9m5 sudden emergency. His hand was   upon his brow, and a letter Seemingly just written, lay before him. An observer would at once have perceived, that there was deep despondency upon his countenance. The sun had long sunk behind the western heri- zon, and left all nature to darkness and re- pose; naught save the solitary tread of the sentinel, as he traversed his lonely rounds, would have intimated to the chance traveller if such there should have been, that thou. sands of Russian soldiers lay buried in the most profound slumber. But to the occu- pant of the tent. Care was on uis brow.- Had lie been unsuccessful in the field of bat- tle? No: that eye of fire; those trophiessus- pended from the canvass, showed, that to hint defeat was a stranger. His person decked; with honors, would convince the least obser- ving, that he was a favorite of his general.- The epaulettes upon his shoulders, were suffi- cientlyv conclusive alone, that he stood high as an officer of distinction. Had t!ht stern heart been smitten by a passion stronger still than ambition? Did love now reign triumph. ant where glory once had sway? Had he been made to feel, where the strongest have yielded? Let us see what he has written. My Dear Eliza-But three days since, we. strolled before your father's tent, our thoughts our words, all of hope and joy; when with averted eve, you pledged to me your hand, and withyour hand your heart, you solemnly assured me, that come- what might, they should never be given to another; and when I urged you to name the day that was to seal my happiness, your reply was, "Ferdinand, the consent of my father must be obtained, or I never can be yours. I am his only child, and I cannot meet that stern brow in anger." Thl'ough that det.,i;Wn, Pmight, 1 feared, blast my hopes forever; still, I could not but com- mend it. Perhaps my darest, I was too aspi- ring. Your father ranks high amongst tho nobility of Russia; the proudest might covet an alliance with his house. Aspiring! yes, 1 was sulfish; but in extenuation of ny fault, permit me to repeat, I loved--madly loved. Ah! what was, I to anticipate such bliss!- When I look back to nmy former insignificance, and when I look to where I would have as- pirel, it seems almost hopeless. Then suffer me to repest, I could not but approve your de- cision. Marshall N. has made me what I am , he has shielded me froin the envy of' some; and the vengeance of others, and I would have wronged him, by clandestinely uniting with his family. Oh! forgive me my presumption. When we again meet, I will disclose my pas- sion, and if he refilses, (which I fear) Oh1. Eliza, better-far better for me that we had never met, for I feel that with his refusal, haup pinea ha fled forever. Yours, FfiittDNANID,  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7184-00000005"/> Hope again dawns upon me! I have seen him! But let me go back  1 was upon the point of closing my letter when an unexpect- ed messenger called me to his presence. Up- on entering, I perceived he was unusually ag- itated. There were several dispatches lying around him, evidently perused, and carelessly thrown aside. I stood some minutes, ere he was aware ofrny presence, so engrossed was he with the paper in his hands. Suddenly ri- sing, and casting his eye upon me, he adrs:s- ed me in his usual abrupt manner ." '1 have been waiting sir,-time is precious-read this dispatch." 1 perused it, and soon perceived theie was indeed, cause for alarm. To be brief, a spy, stationed on the Cossack line,has transmitted to us the information, that Abdel Kamish, that terror of the Russian soldiery, the scourgd of our frontier, who, two years ago during an armistice, (which it was hoped would lead to a permanent peace,) had the au- dacity to propose to your father for your hand, and meeting with a rejection left him in anger, vowing you should yet be his, has unexpect- edly joined the enemy, with a heavy force of Tartars. My business was, to carry the intel - ligehce, to the several outposts. On returning Itdechared the secret ot my passion. What washis ainswer? For a short time, that ap. peared to-me an age, he paced the tent in much agitation, his arms folded on his breast. Then abruptly pausing before me, said in a slow voice-.sb blow there was almost a pause between each word, "Ferdinand, a few years ago, I receiveda letter from my brother, sta- ting that he haa under his protection an Amer- ican lad, an orphan, who, during an engage- mentat sea, had preserved that brother's life, at the imminqnt peril ofhis own. That youth desireld to become a soldier. At his reqnest, I received him under my protection. True, he bans served with honor in our army, has risen to distinction, and in many desperate conflicts covered himself with glory 'but has he not been compensated, in receiving the thanks of the Empress, for hiscool consumate courage in the hour of danger--in obtaining the title of Count, with the honors and privileges attend- ant T" and here he again paused, ere he con- tinued, " as if ambition could not be satiated, he now demands the hand of my daughter, the child ofone of the first nobles in Russia; but &amp; few years since, an orphan, a foreigner and a stranger. i. omeless. penniless, he now asks to be allied to' one of the oldest, and gIost illus. trious hopues in Russia." He stopped, and I arose overchome, to leave him, when he laid his hand on my shoulder- "Is this attachment reciprocal 7" "It is my lord." 4t Then you wronged me, young man; you have taken the advantage of my great indul- gence"-- ["Hold," I exclaimed, interrupting him, and pierced to the heart with his reproaches, , con- demn-me not unheard my lord.' I then entered into a brief explanation of our first meeting, with the incidents that have since trnsupired down to the present time. I per-   ceived that he was moved," Ferdinand " b, at lastsaid, " better for me perhaps, had I suspected this before- but it is, now too late ;. still sir, if you would obtain her, you must win her, I am willing to admit you have done much, but it is not enough, 1 require more ; now listen, on one condition, 1 consent." * Namne any thing that is possible." I said "I pledge my life for its accomplishment.'; With a smile of doubt, he said, - Be not to confident young man. The task 1 give you, is not so easy. Abdel Kamish has joined the enemy's camp: besides this, he has insulted me so outrageously, that I can never for- give. Bring him a prisioner alive to this tent, and Eliza shall be yours." 1 was about to throw myself at his feet, bunt he checked me, "No protestations sir, but re member that if you accomplsh your task, you lay me and my country, under obligations, that cannot easily be cancelled. I left him imme- diately, and ere to-morrow's sun shall gill the eastern horizon, I shall be on my way to the allied camp. Fear not for my safety, for with the darling wish of my heart as the prize,. I feel that 1 could dare still more and yet sue- ceede Again, I say, fear not my dearest Eliza, but hope for the beet. Your devoted, FERDINAND. The reader, has ere this, discovered that: Ferdinand the orphan, and the young Ofictr are the. same. It was about two years pro- vious to this', that I received orders from MaY- shal N. to head a small force, designed to pro. tect his daughter, who had expressed a strong * desire to be nearer his person than at the capital. I was at once admitted into her 3 presence, and never before, did I behold such- t loveliness. With a complexion, vieing with- the purest alabaster,; her dark hair hang- ing in clustering ringlets upon her shoulders. of almost dazzling whiteness,; while her fig- ure, rather below the middle stature, was east in so light and graceful a mold, that had a sculptor, designed to copy this most perfect work of nature, even with a supernatural skill he would have fallen far short of the original That was my first meeting swith the beauti- ful and accomplished daughter of Marshal N.- The memory of it is deeply engraven on my heart, for with it was the whole tenor of my life changed. Having sealed, and al. though so late, sent my letter, I returned to, my musings; the subject of them I need not tell. Abdel Kamish a prisioter, and 1 sho'd obtain this inestimable prize; but it wu a   perilons-ye e fearful venture,-to capture this daring man, who moved not but with the strongest escort,. Still, if the tales told of Aim be true, there is something noble about him, so brave, and yet so lawless. I rang the bell for my servant, he entered ;I X desi. red you to select for me two hundred men of tried courage; have you obeyed? ' 1 have, your honor.' ' We Shall march in an hour, and ere two suns shall have set, Abdel Kamish must be a prisoner in this tent.' I shall never forget his shudder, when I mentioned the name of Abdel Kamish;it was not of fear, for he was a stranger to its  but rather of dread-a dread of some impend- c ing evil. { A prisoner in this camp did you say?'  I did; need I repeat it. Come Selim, r ypu have seen this wonderful man, can you giv me a description of him?'  * Abdel Kamish, your honor, I would rather encounter unarmed the lion in his den, h than him.  It was in the winter of 17- y when you lay dangerously ill of the wounds ul *you received in that battle, where owing to m your signal bravery'-.- ' Pass that by Selim.'         re ' Ah ! your honor, you never wish to hear I your own praises. Well, during that time, I n bid orders to bear dispatches'-Just then an unusual noise at the door of my tent attracted my attention, and before I could desire Se. w lim to inquire the occasion of it, Marshal N. to entered, every thing about him denoting a thi high stlate of excitement. Without his mil- hit itary hat, his sword naked in his hand, his bu dress thrown orr with no regard to order, be- an fore I could articulate a word, he had reach. tac ed the centre of the tent and thrown himself into a  seat. He sat for several minutes, me with his face buried in his hands, his whole bel oame racked with the most intense agony, Sel large drops of sweat stood  upon his brow. of I   could endure the suspense no longer, but hal stepping gently towards him, laid my hand the upon his shoulder. General I. tell me the meaning of all   are this .' rith The words wecencd to reanirmlte hie whole old system; springing upon his feet, his eyes o t glaring with fury, tho dccljst vengeance "ng upon his countenance, he cried, I Ferdi:andl, !si- my child! my Eliza! is gone! I fear forever K co  ' Lost sir, gone  when, where?' I repeat- ed.  ' But a few minutes since,a some soldiers vo rushed into my tent exclaiming that she was be lost. Her tent was unexpectedly attacked by a body of Tartars, who under cover of the I darkness, succeeded, after slaying her faith- it ful attendants, in carrying away my poor its child. By the light of a lantern, held by one d- of the savages, he saw her placed in front of a man of herculean proportions, who rode a coal black horse, a fit match in size for his a, master. 'Ferdinand that man is,-- 'u Abdel Karmish,' I shouted, as I ground my teeth with rage. d   .' Listen to me my boy; I told you bring it him alive and the hand of Eliza should be - yours ; I now say rescue her, brinp him dead or alive, and not only that, but the whole of my fortune shall be yours.' ' Say no more sir. rely upon it she shall be re 'fed, and the base capturor punished or r I return no more, I have two hundred men [ now ready to march.' i  Take four hundred, you will need them. He laid his hand upon my shoulder;it was like a  grasp of iron, , Haste, Ferdinand, to her rescue, for Abdel Kamish has sworn that despite her father, my daughter shall be his wife. Gladly would I accompany you but duty to my country, stands paramount' and farthermore, it is possible we may be at- tacked during your abscence.' With a palpitating heart, I sat for a mo. ment after he had left me, and then, rang the bell which was immediately answered by Selim, I Give orders Selim, that. an addition of two hundred men be ready to march in half an hour if possible, in an hour at the far- thest.. I have General N's. orders Xt that effect. Inform Count. Menzikoff f  his com- mauds; awake Abdallah, ud return to  m'  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7184-00000006"/> A dread of being alone prompted me to desire his return. Every moment seemed an life age whilst I sat, racked with a. mental tor- do sure far above any physical pain I had! ever pu ndured. The delicate tender blossom, ;nur- in tured with the most kindly care, that could oa be bestowed, to be startled from her peace- fre ful slumbers by a horde of midnight assassins, OV it was a theme upon which I could not dwell. h The thought was agony. Selim had return' Se ed'and informed me that I had been obeyed- m M worthy servant's face was clouded I well as know with anxiety for me, and wishing to do br away with his seriousness, said,' You are be not afraid, Selim; we shall have with us a'A part of the same soldiers, who in thait san. guinary battle on the plains of when n victory had almost declared against us, broke a through the enemy's van-guard and van- a quished them. You know they have never c hbown their backs to a foe yet,' . ' I believe you commanded them in that at. ( took your honor,' said he with an arch smile. i 'Come, come, no more of that Selim, this , is no time for flattery.'       a , Flattery, do youcall it sir, I say no more of my master, than he of his soldiers.' I You will have it your own wayl I see af tor all:' ' Not exactly your honor, I have advised you not to proceed against Abdel Kamish yet you persist in doing so.' ' Yes, indeed, and we are now wasting our precious time. See that the men are ready assoon as may be and immediately push on to thoeoutskirts of the forest, where I will meet you.' ( Ah!! your honor, I need not but tell them who is to 'command, they will be willing enough to obey; you know full well you are -the- idol of-- ' -Have done with this Selim ; now go and send Abdallah hither.' ' Yes, yes, he too owes you his life, as well as myself*' A hasty and impatient movement convin. cedi him that he had gone far-enough, and he droppod the curtai and retiared   That servant would have lain down his life for me unasked ; always sleeping at the door of my tent, and many a time when in pursuit of an enemy, and obliged to bivouac in the forest with nothing but the majestic oak for a shelter, have I awoke from a're- freshing slumber, to find his cloak thrown over me, and he watching by my side. Still he kneer my vulnerable point, the dislike of self praise, and touch it he would despite of my remonstrances. Noble Selim! as honest, , as grateful, as generous a heart beats in that breast, peasant though thou art! as ever throb- bed in that of a king or emperor. Just then Abdallah entered. As with him are connected some of the most striking incidents of my life, I will for ' a moment deviate. He had been my serv- ' ant for about three years, It was, whilst fr crossing a small mountain in Circassia, with about fifty men, to treat with the Circassian L. commander, on an exchange of prisoners, as 'I was descending the mountain, there was 8 an unexpected cry of alarm in my rear, In- stantly commanding a halt, that I might the more readily discern from whence the noise proceeded, my eye was attracted by an un- - usual commotion on the brow of the moun- tain. I immediately ordered my men to re- h trace their steps; it was evident they were aware of our intentions, for giving one shout which I recognized as that of the Tartars, dy they -put spurs to their horses, and dashed on away. Being on the level, and we on the ill ascent, at first gave them the advantage; but on our arrival at the summit, I could observe Nm something impeding their progress, which soon convinced me the pursuit would not be ng a long one. After following about an hou, they suddenly halted. Presuming they were nd preparing for an attack, I ordered my men to halt and form line, (as we were in some con- fusion owing to the excitement of pursuit,) but the word was scarcely given, ere they in. were again in full flight. Enraged at being so baffled, I struck the rowels into my horse, my men followed my example, but as we   were descending a gradual declivity, my stud shied. I cast my eye over my shoulder, and perceived a human being crawling from the road side into the bushes. I directed them to bring him to me and they quickly return. ed, bearing in their arms a youth of about eighteen years. He was much alarmed, but on my assuring him that he was under the protection of friends, his joy knew no bounds; but throwing himself at my feet, bathed them with tears. I perceived that his dress was saturated with blood, and feeling confident that he must be to weak to bestride a horse, I desired some of my men to prepare a litter, (a piece of mechanism easily accomplished i by a Russian soldier,) and meanwhile I in- quired of him how he happened to be pla- ced in such a situation. He informed me that whilst crossing the mountain, he was suddenly surrounded by the Tartars, and before he could make the I least attempt to escape, they seized and bound him hand and foot and threw him upon a t horse. When we were the nearest, they l took the additional precaution of gagging t him, but on resuming their journey ho had a dexterously slipped the gag, and given the t shout which had alarmed me. He farther a informed me that when they found his pres- i ence impeded their flight, they held a short consultation, which resulted in his wounds,. i Supposing him dead, they resumed their I flight. This was Abdallah the servant then 8 before me. I could never place that confi- d dence in him, nor trust him as I could Sellm. But in the hour of danger, with his lance in its rest, and mounted on his Tartar steed, he feared no foe. Although below the middle ti stature, his agility would more than coun- f. terbalance the strength of his opponent, and C in a hand to hand to fight, I have seen him hurl, almost a giant from his seat, scarcely h himself trembling in his saddle. His hate o towards the Tartars was apparently of the deadliest kind, when I informed him that I b shonld march immediately for the Circassian c camp, new fire shof from his eyes. ' See,' said I,' that Saladin is brought h before my tent. Lieutenant F. is already o   1 pushing on to the rendezvous; we must meet a him there.' 3  He left as I desired, and but a very few i minutes had elapsed, before' I heard the neigh-  ing of my horse, and the servant re-entered, t 'Ready Abdallah?' t ' All ready, your honor.' I stepped into the open air, and perceived ; not only Saladin. but my servant's stood knear him equally caparissoned. ' I concluded my lord,' he remarked, as he saw me smile,' from the sudden entrance ,of General N. into your tent this night, that you would be on horse back ere morning, and when Saladin goes, the black steed fol- lows.' ' But never leads,' said I. He made no reply,but I thought those eyes said as plainly as words can express, The time may come when no man shall lead Abdallah Vaulting upon my beast, it needed but the touch of my spur, and my gallant bay was bounding oe'r the camp ground, almost with the velocity of light'ning. He was a borne of remarkable swiftness of foot, and with those stroong elastic limbs, broad full chest and that proudly curved neck, he never gave in, even during our longest marelies. Pardon me gentle reader, if I again digress in taking this opporrunity of explaining, how I became his purchaser, as it will shew the skill and cunning of a Russian peasant in the disposal of property CHAPTER III. A year previous to this, whilst travelling to our camp ground, with a small recruiting force, 'we were overtaken by a'peasant.- Casting his eyes upon my milk white steed, ' Ah! my  lord,' he cried' I have a horse here, that would serve you better on the field of battle than the one you now ride.' * You?' I asked, ' what that lean, gaunt beast? you may be thankfnl if he lives to carry you to camp.' ' To camp sir! I'll wager my bead, that he distances the best horse in your troop, my ord.'  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7184-00000007"/> 4 Take care, sirrah! how you traduce somse of the finest cavalry horses ia the scryicea ' I said nothing against your horse sir, in Yemarking that he could be beaten by mine, and now I perceive my lord, yours is actual. Iy club footed ; pshaw! he. may do in the pur- suit, but take my word fir it, on a retreat, you would be a prisoner il four and twenty houra.' Oan a retreat, fellow!' I repeated, now getting impatient at his assurance, ' the Rus. sian soldier never practices that maneuver.' ' I don't dispute it sir,' and I colld see the villain grinning all the while,' but retreat or advance, I, should think my neck in greater danger on his back; why look yourself sir, how he throws his feet; your lordship's mov- ing up and down, reminds me of my boyish days, when with a companion, one on each and of a board, we used to play the see-saw.' * Out upon you, base serf,' I shouted, fairly settled at his remarks, (for nothing will soon- or excite the ire of a soldier, than to traduce (he character of his horse,) ' were you not a low born peasant, I would quickly convince yo of the nature of this beast.' * From his moves at present, your honor, r'much fear your safety would be endangered jy increasing his speed.' Tho' from a peasant, I could endure his sarcaams no longer, he saw it and turning to me with a taunting air, ' It is but a mile to the first gap ;horse against horse, who fifrg ieap the ditch; but I beg your pardon my lord, for remarking, this ground is rough and should your beast stumble' '* o more. insulting scoundrel! I take yoB at your offer; you will have to walk to camp, and be flogged for your insolence to a Russian officer into the bargain." ' Horse against horse *' he cried, ' the flog- ging will be an after consideration,' and away we dashed. At the first bound, I left my, companion completely in the rear. We remained so for about half the distance, when fieeling confident ofwiinning the race, I exult- tinglycaat my eyes behind me, and withhin a fewr feet beheld him, actually laughing at my -l- .i 8 D fi ,    ' I was thinking my lord, he said, as with one bound he was at my side,' that but few officers in our good army, could keep the saddle under such a beast, ha! ha! I ha!!! but there is one consideration, you will never stumble, he would clear a five barred gate at cvcrv leap.' To be so baffled, and in presence of my soldiers, was insufferable. 'he speed wag now at the hottest; at every bound, with slackened rein, I plunged my spurs into his sides, but all would not avail. My opponent * sitting carelessly upon his horse, instead of r urging, rather impeded hs progress with the rein. On, on, we dashed; the distended nos- trils of my, beast, convinced me that I was pushing him at the hardest. When having arrived neck to neck within a few rods of the leap, I perceived with horror that instead of a ditch, it was actually a gulf of much greater width than any leap 1 had ever be- fore attempted, and at that very minute, to add to my aggravation, the Russian turned to me, an ironical smile playing upon bis countenance,  'Tis not so broad your honor, as I expect- , ed' (catching my whip which was aimed at I his head) but here we go,' (at the same time suiting the action to the word) and I shouting, ' Saladin for the goal ' he distan- i ced me at once, and with a flying bouad "stood securely on the other side. When t I reached the bank, my horse refused the leap; r I raved; I was actually frantic with rage, as i crowding him hard with the spurs, and 49 termining to dare the venture, I struck him I with the flat of my sword; taking the bit ia ) his teeth, for he had now become furious, he a sprang for the chasm-with that yawning gulf below me, 'twas a desperate leap. *Tim won tis won! safe we stand on the other side. But no, the earth crumbles from under him, I try to escape the stirrup -his strength fails , him--he totters-he reels-when gathering i all his energies, for one desperate effort,' he * tumbles backward and falls headlong to the bottom! When I recovered from the stun- ning effects of the accident, the peasamt stood or me. Perceiving  was not muoI   itnjared, ' Horse against horse!' he cried, 'twas 'fairly won.' My soldiers forgetful of all re- spect, shouted with laughter. I was confu- sed, and feeling that I had been overreached 'bv the peasant, ordered them to retire: Hav- ing obeyed me, I turned to the serf, ' Your paice for that beast.' ' Five hundred Rubles sir, nothing less' ' Five huridred Rubles!' I exclaimed,' I can purchase 'the best horse in the service flr two hundred and fifty, come, I'll give you three hundred. What's his name?' ' Saladin, your honor. He is a Saravian horse from Abyssinia. I would this morning have taken three hundred for him, but being on my way to camp, I need but inform the ;oflicers that my lord has been beaten by a peasant,' w  ' There take five hundreds my good fellow, -and say nothing about it.' ' And the flogging, your lordship?' ' Oh! I had forgotten that; I believe it is best to cry quits, and hark you sirrah! dare -to mention this in camp,'--- ' Never fear, your honor,' said he and de.! parted, Such was Saladin, my favorite steed.- 'On arriving at the outskirts of the forest, t i found awaiting me four hundred as brave de 1 tarmined fellows, as ever drew the tabre. 4 Are you ready to follow me,' I enquired I -. where ever I shall lead?' ' ' To the death,' they shouted with one a voice. I then directed Lieutenant F. to send c out scouts in adivance, with orders, if they a should see any unusual movement, by the en- e emy, to return immediately and inform us.- t I then addressed my soldiers as follows :: I march to the tent of Abdel Kamish; if there is one here who values his safety more than I honor, he is at liberty to return.' ' There is none here,' shouted an old veter. an, we will follow our leader, and if necessa. ry die in his defence.'         8 * Let us push on then,' I said, and instantly ^All was in motion. Confident that Abdel Kamidh could not reach the enemy's camp, v Until the next day, it was my intention to n make as mtuch ground as possible, ere it broke Am  with my men secrete ourselves in one of i   8 the vast caverns which abound in that sec- ,- tion of country. there lie concealed, till dark - ness again set in, when mounting, push on d with the utmost speed; I sending a spy in r- the meantime to discover in which part of the camp Eliza was confined; for, without that information, my efforts would be vain. The course was a desperate one, but there was no I alternative. My men I knew were trues e strangers to fear, and innred to danger. To e form ourselves into a solid column; to advance as silently as possible; to strike down the a sentinel; seize Eliza and place her on one of 7 our fleetest horses must be the work of a mo- ' ment, or we were lost. e  What think you Selim,' I inquired as I t mentioned my plan, ' can you advise a better?' ' Not I your honor, but if I know the man, , Abdel Kamish himself will guard that tent.' ' So much the better, Selim, we must soon- er or later nfeet, and I long to try the strength i of his arm with my own good sword.' ' God grant you may succeed sir, but if I can distinguish correctly in this darkness, you have not your true Milesian in the scab- bard.' ' Not my 'Milesian sword,' I asked, draw- ing out a  blade that well fitted the sheath, but which filled me with astonishment. I True, Selim, there is a traitor somewhere. , I now recollected having left the tent a few minutes, when on returning, Abdallah was standing near my armor; he knew this weap. on had once failed me in a single combat, also of my  contemplated attack on the'ene. emy. Could that servant have exchanged them?  What was his motive? 'Selim, there is a traitor in our camp.' "Evidently your enemy" he replied, " and I strongly suspect Abdallah.' , ' But what could be his motive?' I asked ' He is ambitious, your honor*.'  ' And my prosperity is detrimental' to his success, you would infer.' ' I know of nothing else.' I now recollected the look he gave me, when on first setting out, I remarked,( he might follow, but never lead.' ' Had your honor not better arrent him im. mediately,' Selim inquired.  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7184-00000008"/> 4 No,' I replied,' but observe him ; he now i has his eye upon us; let us watch him, and 1 should we discover any farther treachery, se.  cure him at once ; the proof is not positive, 1 possiblv he may be innocent.' ' Had I my way your honor. he should be hung on the first tree; I always thought him as treacherous as a Greek.' ' Fall back Selim, I fear he suspects us., We had advanced some distance in silence and I was falling into my customary mu- llngs, when I was suddenly startled, by the cry of halt on the front, and a moment after one of the scouts rode up in breathless haste, and informed me that they had captured a soldier, evidently by his dress belonging to} Abdel Kamish's treop. This was indeed for. tunate news, and I immediately ordered him to be brought before me. There was some- thing determined and resolute about the man; an aspect which said, ' you can see me sir, but you cannot read me.' i immediately took my course; a deter- mined resolute spirit, must be met with equal fimnness: ' You are a follower of Abdel Kamish?' ' I am sir.' ' You were with him in his late-aassault on the Russian camp?" ' I was.' ' Do you snow what was the motive of that attack?' % The capture of the daughter 'of General * . s What was the number of'his troops?' ' Sufficient to accomplish his purpose; my master requires but few men to defeat the Russians, he being At their head.' 'Take care sirrah, or harsh means shall bend that stubborn spirit, answer me without trifling, in what part of the camp is Abdel Kamish?' ' In the weakest sir, which then becomes the strongest.' To be so baffled, and time flying, was in. sufierable. ' How numerous are the enemy's forces?' ' Numbers sufficient to drive the foe from our territory.  Selim,' said, I ' draw your sword, and if   he does not answer me at once and to the point, cleave him to the chine. Now sir, life is in the balance, and on your answer turns the scale; Again I ask, in what part of the: camp is Abdel Kamish?' His lip slightly quivered as he said, ' [am a husband and a father; the main- tainance of my children; the sole support of an enfeebled wife, hang on this arm; but I will part with all, lather than peril the safety of my master. Strike sir.' In an instant, the glittering blade flashed like lightning in the air, ' Hold,' I said, and in its half descent, it was stayed, such faith- fulness even in an enemy, 1 could not but ad-. mire. Isthere no remedy I thought, when Selim remarked, ' Perhaps he is the bearer of some correspondence.' Ah! right, his looks denote confiusion-- search him.'     -  A moment after, my servant handed me a sealed package; I tore the envelope-it was from Abdel Kamish to thecommander-in- chief ofthe enelmy's forces-brief but pointed: Sir:--I shall join you by day break, with all my men. - The Russians are now lying in fancied security, imagining you are not within two days march of their camp. Ere night, we will be upon them, and then taken unprepared the day is ours, Should -the enemy become aware of our proximity, I have a trusty fellow in their camp who will inform us. It concluded with this post- script: P. S. I wish the command ofthe van guard.- ABDEL KAMSH,  Who was that traitor, that spy, but Abdal- lab! He watched me as I read, and guilty confusion, I thought, could be traced on his countenance. Calling him to me, I direeted  him to fall back and again addressed the pris- oner. ' This letter, (had your obstinacy contin- ued) has probably saved your life. Your- master's movements I now know, and befor&amp;, another night 1 shall meet him.' ' You,' he cried, doubtingly, You meet Ab; del Kamish! I was- ' Silence sir! What has become of the la. - djr who was captured by him? ' He hesitated vc Answer me correctly, ant?   I liberate you in four and twenty hours ; re- fuse and you rot in the dungeons of Russia.' 'I will answer that sir ; my master has sent her with a few trusty soldiers, to the rear of our camp, with ordersto lie concealed in the Akbar cave, until the decision of the coming battle; he will then fall back, regain posses- sion of the lady- ' Never,' I shouted, never again shall he succeed; but go on sir.' ' He will fall back into the interior, and before he again issues from those fastnesses she will have become his bride.' ' His bride! his bride!' ( I repeated, almost madened by the numerous impediments thrown in my way,) ' never! never! I will reach him yet; he shall first feel the effects of my vengeance.' ' He will not fly you sir.' ' Enough! is it possible to overtake them ere they reach the cave?' ' Utterly impossible sir, they have already gained the rear of the camp.' I was struck speechless with horror, the Cossacks and Tartars within a few hours march of us when we supposed them, as near as we could conjecture, two days on our front. What was to be done? There was but one alternative. To have pushed on with my men would have been an act of madness; for we must have encountered the whole of the enemy, and to break thro' their lines with the ' small troop I had then at my command, was ' not to be thought of. I was sensible from Abdel Kamish' letter, and his known predi. X lection for the field of conflict, that nothing f would withold him from the coming attack; t consequently Eliza was safe until after the termination of the impending battle.  r There was but one course to pursue, and I I adopted it by directing Selim to bring Lieut. F. before me. On his appearing, he was or- dered to place trusty scouts in all directions, to guard against surprise, and then with his c men fall back and unite with the main body. v Having given the necessary directions, and v calling a few trusty fellows around me, we e retraced our steps to the Russian camp. et Riding- immediately to the tent of General al N, I was informed, that feeling indisposed, a   - he had retired,' leaving orders to be called at ' break of day. Feeling competent in every t respect of preparing for the coming action, I f concluded it would not be necessary to dis. e turb his repose, I returned to my tent, and g penned some directions to the different offl- - cers commanding under me, apprising them of the close proximity of the enemy, with or- e ders to let the soldiers rest until day break which was near at hand and at that hour to d arouse them, and prepare for marching. 3  Having given the requisite directions, and Selim returned from executing them, I asked t him if'he had seen Abdallah?' 8 'Ihave your honor, he has been absent I from the camp.' ' Absent from the camp,' I repeated, did I not order you to watch him closely.' ' You did sir, and such was my intention, but in passing through the troop, he eluded me and has this moment returned.' ' He can have effected nothing,' he con- tiuued, on observing my look of disappoint. ; ment, ' unless he has an accomplice.' ' That is what I fear; send him to me di- rectly; I shall unriddle him if possible, and hark you Selim!' I added, as he wks on the point of leaving,' I am expecting a letter from a friend in Moscow, by a courier, should it arrive, bring it to me at once.' ' I will my lord; but whilst I think of it, do you not recollect, Abdallah has been ab- sent from the tent on several occasions?' ' Yes,' I replied,' and his plea was fond- ness for hunting; depend upon it there is something at the bottom; Kamish in his let- ter says he has a trusty spy, who will inform him, should we learn of their close approach, and this night, I fear, during that fellows abscence, it has been effected; but send him to me directly.' On his entrance, I watched him closely, but could observe no embarrassment in his countenance. I  was aware, that in some way, he had received an education which would enable him to carry on a correspond- ence, and consequently there would be great- et difficulty in detecting him. There wa%, at times, something mysterious about the man; n, something which led me to think he , '  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7184-00000009"/> ha. seen better days, but when I introduced the subject, he always evaded my questions in a manner that led me to think it was a painful one. He stood before me several mo- ments ere I addressed him, when suddenly looking up I perceived he was watching me closely. I instantly drew Kamish's letter fro m my pocket and passed it to him. 'Do you recognize that hand writing sir,' I asked. ' Abdel Kamish's,' he replied, after point- ing with a smile to the signature. It is from him, and you observe he writes he has a spy in the camp; what; think you Abdallah, have you any suspicions who that traitor may be-?' ' Who, Imy lord, how could I suspect any one, having but just been informed of it?'  ' You have been absent from the camp this night; 'what was your business?' He started when I put the question, and was, I thought, a little confused, but over- same it directly. ' A friend of mine was ill, your honor, and at his request I visited him. *'How far hence does he lie T? ' About half a mile in rear of the army.' ' Abdallah,' I said,' we have a little time to pare;. hand me my cloak and follow me, it ismy intention to visitithat sick man,' ' You are too late, my lord,' he replied with some embarrassment,' he expired ere I left histhovel.' Again was I frustrated in all attempts to unravel this treachery, for if Abdallah spoke truly, why should I visit that hovel? nauth- ing could be learned from a corpse; if false, I feared, notwithstanding my proposition, that my time was too limited. I once more, addressed him, Abdallah, there is a traitor in our camp, I know it and I *supect the man! if my conjectures prove correct a death awaith Aim so howid, that ere the last agonies rrie, he wiU cry, yes and ery in vain for thS knout to erminate hi miserable exist. ence! ' Nowl retire, but leave not this tent and in to-morrbWzconffict, you will remain at my side.'   d  He hesitated a moment; and I thought s something important would have escaped i his lips, but I was deceived. 'Do you suspect mne, my lord?' I do.' e  ' May I inquire on what grounds?' r  * I have mentioned one, and to enumerate all is unnecessary; on this very night my ,' weapons were exchanged, and contrary to or- ders you have been absent from the camp.* - 'I have explained the last, and as for the change of swords, your servant Selim is a s more frequent occupant of your tent than my- a self.' t ' Couple not Selim's name with treachery. or retribution will fall upon your head. ere t leaving this tent; you sayr you are innocent? f '1 do.', 'Then swear by your prophet, that you p prove true in to-morrows conflict.' He was silent and turned pale, g Swear!' I ,/exclaimed raising my pistol; he saw I would - have fired for my suspicions were partially confirmed by his hesitation, ' Count M. ,o I cried, I swear to remain true in to-morrows' battle.' ' True to the cause of Russia,' I repeated, but he w4s gone. Feeling no inclination to sleep, I sat a , short time ruminating upon the singular ad- ventures of this night and the rapidity with I whi h one incident had followed the other int t such rapid succession. Now that years are passed, and my reveries recur to the same. I it appears almost like magic. But man in D his youthful days, with a determined will,. and an iron constitution, and a mind wholly centered Upon an object, and buoyed up with that never failing source of consolation, Hopea to whichv we cling to- our dying day-ah . yes, that extends even into eternity, can ac- compllsh that, before which, at the thought,. Old Age recoils. My meditations were in. terrupted by the raising of the curtain of my tent,' Well Selim,' I asked as he entered, ' what's the hour?' 'The day is breaking, my lord, aand the troops are all in motion; here is a letter I have this moment received from Abdallah,   he tells me it arrived by a courier from Moscow.' Presuming it came f: gm my cor- respondent, and time pressing, i placed it unopened in my pocket, internding when at ;leisure to peruse it. Nearly fatal procrasli. nation i How often do the most disastrous events connected with our lives, hang o'er us suspended as by a hair, we fancying our- selves in perfect security when the weapon of impending danger is ready to strike the deadly blow.! Had I but torn the envelop- had I but broken the seal of that letter-But let me not anticipate. Stepping out from my tent, I perceived the whole Russian force drawn up, with Gen. eral N. at its head; mounting my horse, I was in a few moments by his side. When- he saw me he grasped my hand, You have done right, this was your only course; your 4 ervant has informed me all; Kamieh join. 1 ing the enemy is confirmed ; we will reach him yet, and if I once cross my sword with t ' Be that task mine my lord; permit me t to day to lead the van guard.'     x ' Your request is granted, but be not rash, E though my deadly enemy, I will do him jus. m tice; he is a stranger to fear, and with the y weapon has few equals, perhaps no superior.' ' Fear not,' I  answered, having every fi thing to nerve this arm in the coming contest; tj but should my anticipations be too sanguine, e and if I  fall, Selim, my lord has orders to b select a sufficient n;.- her of my choicest tc troops, if possible bieaiL through the enemy, p push on in all haste, and gain the Akbar li care; the rest must be left to his own discre. cf lon.                  N 'That must be a father's care,' he repeat. n ed. 'I know Kalnish sufficiently to be aware bt until after to-morrow's conflict, Eliza is safe,' w he replied. At that moment word was given that all th was ready.  General N. immediately gave an the order, and the whole Russian force was TI i" rapid motion. The sun was just lighten- of ing the heavens, and with its morning hues me gaily dancing upon the polished bayonets me Of our soldiers. Should they advance in- ap   ,m tending to attack us, it was evident we ,r- must snon meet. We pushed on rapidly, it the spirits of the soldiers raised Co the high. at est pitch. But the sun had reached its me. ti. ridian and still no enemy. We continued tV us push on until it was again sinking in the er heavens. Our Commander fearing a sur- r- prize, ordered a halt. It was evident the foe mn must have learned our proceedings. At that he moment a scout arrived in haste, who inform- - ed us they were a short distance in advance it and falling back in all directions. We im- mediately commenced the pursuit, and came d in sight of them as darkness was covering t- the horizon. I  Upon reconoitering, we perceived they n- were very advantageously posted, and it be e ing evident that we must be the assailantv r General N, concluded not to commenoe the - battle until next morning. h  I shall omit particulars of that bloody aa- i tion; the fight had been long and terrific, as is always the case if it terminates in a hand e to hand encounter, we were just preparing to repel a desperate charge, wlhen Selim laying , his hand upon my shoulder, and pointing to- - wards the approaching ranks, exclaimed,' Do 3 you see him, my lord?' I looked, and within a few rods in me , front was, as I conjectured, Abdel Kamist ; the black plumes of his turban proudly raus. , ed above all his warriors, his colossal size, I his heroic bearing, instantly riveted my at- tention. At that time both wings of the op- posing armies had been driven in, and ours like a pair of forceps was closing upon their centre ; but he with the van-guard stood firm. Now assailed by our whole force, it seemed no human daring could resist such assaults, but with him .as their leader, each soldier would seize his enemy in a deadly grapple, end release him not until the cry of agony, or the gasp of death, announced his triumphl and bade him pass on for another victim, Their Tartar shout, as every terrific sweep of his weapon, hurled a man to the ground, made him appear something more than bu. man, and always in the front of danger, It appeared as if he coarted death.  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7184-00000010"/> ' selira,' I cried,' with the fall of that man i the Vietory is achieved; follow me closely.' I struck my rowels into my charger: not i a man of my troop would have shrunk from I the'encornter, had escape been possible.-- For myself, I felt reckless of the consequen- ces, determined if I fell, that the soul of Ab-t del Kaimish should attend me to the other world. He saw our advance, and halted to receive it; at the very moment when our swords crossed, I received a blow upon the back of my head, which hurled me senseless to the ground. I could recollect nothing bat aconfusedanoise bofwarriors, and:tramp- ling Of horses, and then all was silent. CHAPTER IV. Upon recovering from my stupor,I found myself in a dark room, which- from its damp- ness convinced me it must be an underground apartment, The pain in my head was severe. I arose immediately, and on attempting to walk, perceived with horror that my feet were confined. - What had been the event of the battle? Where was I now? What was to be my future fate? And Eliza, my promis. ed bride, where was she? My emotions must have been excruciating, for although it was. a cold damp place, I could feel the perspira- tion gushing from every pore.! I experienced on that night, that horrid night, a whole age of misery; would I could blot it from my memory forever! I cast myselfon the damp ground, and bu- ried my face in my hands. How long I re- mained inthat position I know not, but when I arose, Hcould perceive the faint glimmer of morning, penetrating from a small window beyond my reach. Involuntarily placing my hand in my pocket, I drew forth a letter, the onel-had -received from Selim. Anxious for souiething to enliven my thoughts, I hastily tore the envelope; but how was I horror struck v to perceive it was in the hand writing of Alk dallLiantil directed to Abdel Kamish. How is this, I said, throwing myself on a seat, and fearing my reasoning faculties were leaving me. Is it possible? Have I been so duped? Noo no, it cannot be. Again I grasped the   scroll, and there in legible characters stood his name. But how came it in my posses. sion? In a moment light entered my bewil- dered mind. The expected letter from Mos- cow must have arrived, and he, by nhistake, sent me his own. Breaking the seal, I read My Lord:-I have fulfilled my pledge; I have assisted you in the capture of the daugh- ter of General N.; I have been instrumental ia bringing your forces withina few hours march of our camp, when the Russians in their fool- hardiness fancy themselves in perfect secu- rity, and where you can strike a blow from which they will not soon recover; and to close I give you my word, that Count M. dead or alive, shall be in your power. Are you equally willing on your part to fulfill yours? You say I am ambitious; I know it and glory in it;,add if that word which haslnever yet been broken, should cancel your part of the agreement, which'will enable me. to command next your honor in the Tartar troop, I shall consider myself'amply compensated for all I have done. Expect me to join you soon. I know not your motivefor securing the Count alive, but it .depends upon circumstan- ces the unchained lion is not so easily caged without a wound, and sometimes the iadnce probes deeper than we are aware of. Sielf- preservation, you know, "I is the first law of nature'," andmroy first thrust or blow must be . effectual, or there is an end, of Abdallah.--- You will oberve, 1 have good and substantial grounds for saying I am not very particular: about it. Recollect ifatlive, you are to surtender him to me.      I      .t You ask in what way, originated my dislike to the Count, who had once saved my life, and who was alwayd a kind master. .I will tell fyou. Sometime ago in a skirmisli withthe , enemy, it was my' hap to stand b hS ;side when he struck down a foe.- I thought at the time, I recognized that countenance. Qu the same night, when all had retired, curidoi A again drew me to that battle field and inthei man wounded byCount M., I recognized my far- * ther. You are aware we had not mt .for several years. He knew me and extended hAi' r hand, whilst in a faint whisper he spake ;tlh i were his words, "Abdallah, give me you titmi ise, it is a dying parents request that the iidii: , which slew me, shall go down to the gravel;y blood." To be brief I took the oath-itrs-t: r corded onhigh.            '  .    Abdel Kamish, my master knows not who I -am; he knows not I am. more than his equal. My father looks down from above;that oath shall not be broken, the Count must die. At the bottom was a post script in the fol. lowing words: I have but a moment to spare ere closing. Half of our plans are frustrated; one of your scouts is taken. You will perceive it was through no negligence on my part. Your movements are known, the Russian advance will be immediate. -I sent a verbal *message of our pursuit, directly on my return to camp. The Count more than suspects me; I will join you soon as this place is getting quite too hot -for me; he has exacted an oath that I would prove true in the. coming battle. You frown-and well you may, but brave as you are, had you been in my situa- tion,(which Allah forbid) I think you would have done the same; in a word, with all the as- surance imaginable, he gave me my choice of the oath or a small piece of cold lead from a well. charged pistol! Ha! ha! ha! my con- science is not at present sufficiently czear, to relish such a breakfast. He said. something about being" true to Russia,". but my time was too limited to enter into particular when another pledge, might have been requisite. Yours, ABABDALLAH. I perused this letter twice before I could comprehend it; 'twas evident Abdallah had commenced it -previous to the arrest of Kamish's spy, and after our return from the fruitless pursuit, closed the same by repeating the discovery, fearful perhaps that his verbal message had been unsuc- cessful, which unfortunately, could not have been the case. There was something inexplicable in all this-the frequentcon- versations held with Selim in reference to him now recurred .to me. 'He always, suspected him, and I, perhaps, should have, done. the same, had he not invariably manifested such hatred towards the Tar- tars when in my presence-'twas apparent fhe had been plying a lon , deep game, and ',tihat was the pivot on which the whole tur- - -ned. i was interrupted by a slight noise at the 'door of my cell, and a person enter-   ed whom I at once recognized by hissdress as a Mohomedan. But his appearance almost beggars description. His height did not exceed four feet, \heich would, at first sight, intimate there was a want of strength and agility, but a nearer view undeceived me on the first point, for his great length of arms and broad shoulders, was sufficient indication, that there was no want of manual power, and his peculiar X entrance satisfied me on the second. Pla- cing his feet upon the threshold', and rai- sing his hands within reach of the ceiling, he made a sudden spring, and stood at one bound within arms length of me. It was like the leap of the chamois. I do not recollects through all those trying scenes, ever having experienced a sensation like fear, if I did or any thing resembling it, 'twas then. 1 was unarmed. There was a grin of exultation upon his countenance, which extended a mouth naturally too capacious, almost from ear to ear; his fi. ery eyeballs were in constant motion, and the stiiking contrast between them and his teeth, which were a jet black was tru. ly revolting. His forehead was low and receded. with a gradual acclivity to the centre of the, skull. Immediately after assuming his position, he placed his hand  upon an ivory handled poniard and draw- ing it from his bosom,. stood irresolute as if anxious to strike, but deterred by some,- thing incomprehensible to me. , In a word he reminded me whilst we were observ- ing each other in silence of a fiend sent by, his master from the lower regions, to rev- el on the misery of mortals. ' Ha!' I cried, ' am I then a prisoner of ,bdel Kamish f. answer me monster I and relieve this suspense.' Having placed some refreshments bc- fore me, he turned to leave; F .a ' Told Turk! as vou hope to; en le para. d so reply to my qnestion, wher;/ni#  He cast upon me a look of deadly, hate, as he retreated backwards, for I was en. deavoring to break  my fetters. When he reached the door, casting upon me an iro nical smile,' Christian,' he whispered  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7184-00000011"/> ( your die is cast, prepare to meet thy doom,' and darkness again enveloped my prison . Another night of horror passed over me. Once during that age of gloom and mise- ry, I dreamed of tearing Elizh, from the arms of Abdel Kamish, and upon awaken- ing, heard, or thought 1 heard, a female shriek. ' O Godl' I cried,' am I in the same cave with her and yet not able to protect her i' But no, 'tis vain-all my exertions to release myself were ineffectual, and I lay down exhausted with the effort, wait- ing for the break of day. It came at last, and with it four soldiers, armed to the teeth, entered my cell. ' Unlock his fetters and bring him forth,' exclaimed their leader. ' If it is your intention to commit-mur- der, dog of a Turk 1' I said, ' no place so fitting as this dark cell, the very counter- part of your, souls; do your worst, I defy you' '    -. T-hey heeded not my raving, but releas. ing me, I was hastily led through several rooms of an apparently extensive cave, and iuhered into an apartment which contain- ed but one inmate, it was Abdel Kamish. . - Welcome Count,' he said, in a tone of t railery, ' I have been expecting a meeting, ( and rest assured Abdel Kamish feels him- X self honored in receiving such a guest.' 1 ' That assurance wold have come with \ a better grace my lord, had it been previ- b ous to my incarceration in your dungeon i for the last forty eight hours ; you al*  ways practise such humanity to4our pris- oners 1          J  ' Abdel Kamish,' he answerhaughtily - d is answerable to no man for his actions, a and least of all to one who has baffled his a intentions for the last two years. You are sl my prisoner, and when I have done with I you, I may release you.' - I I know it, and how obtained 1 Read p that letter from Abdallah, and own your. self connected with an assassin anda trait- e or'?I He took it, and perused it attentively t   P   hy then folding it examined me closely for ay several moments. ' Young man,' he said,' I have an armn e. strong enough, and a heart bold enough to. e- meet umy enemy in the 'op: n field. You ie suspect Abdallah of attempting your life, r- and your suspicions are correct. I saw le the blow, yet too late to avert it, but I be- lieve he had his deserts, for er- ' : could e recover from its effects, and whilst Iwas :t securing your person, which I wanted ts with your life (he continued with a smile I I could not comprehend) he was ridden. t. over by your soldiers.' t, ' Who was he I' e ' It matters not, at least for the present; suf; ficient for you Count, he was not what he ,' seemed. But enough of this; time press. es. You are aware that the daughter of General N. is in my power, and has been D for some time.' ' Have you dared,' I said, now loosing r all self command, and recalling my dream. 'have you dared sir to insult-- I Fear not,' he replied, interrupting me,. t 'she is too firmly in my grasp to require I rashness; in this cave, known too but few and they all trusty, it is not in the power  of man to rescue her. Her father once. r treated with scorn my proffiered offer, an offer that would have been accepted,' he repeated with warmth, now pacing rapid. ly across the room, with avidity by the proudest Satrap of Persia for his daughter, but'(he added slowly) ' when I again issue from my fastnesses with her as my bride, he shall be proud to call me his son-in-law . ' Chieftain of the Tartar troop,' I said, ' hear me. if not for the father's--for the- daughter's sake, spare her this sacrifice, and with it her life. Name her ransom, and upon her restoration to her friends it shall be paid-I hesitated,' Name the sum' Irfppeated, thinking he wavered, and it- shall be bazle  hould it take the last piece from her father's coffers.' *   Restore her to er friends,' he repeat- ed ironically, an to the arms of Cound M. who hasswfn to bring me a prisoner, to the Russians, ha I Count, you turn pale.'   '"Tis not with fear sir, but that I have been harboring a traitor.' ' I believe you, and when you take Ab- del Kamish a prisoner, believe too, that not a Tartar of my band will be alive. But hate I read you aright my lord, is it that this lady may again be under paren- lal protection, or would Count M. whose philanthropic heart is, I presume, well known, kindly relieve General N. of that great responsibility V? I perceived he had assumed a mildness of demeanor wLich in our relative posi- tions must have been foreign to his nature and that under the mask of duplicity was gathering a storm of passion which with difficulty could be repressed;his attend ants appeared to be aware of the same, as they withdrew to the extreme of the apart- ment. Uncertainty is sometimes worse than the reality,and I determined to bring matters at once to a crisis: 'Abdel  famish,' I said, I stoop not to subterfuge; you have read me aright, and L I glory in it. To be called the son of Gen  eral N. is all I desire, I would aspire no 0 higher.'  ' 'Tis high enough he shouted' (no* C loosing all command of himself) 'tis high tl enough for a base born plebian; one who has usurped the title of nobility; one who ly has villainously inveigled himself into the ' affections of that girl.' ' Liar  1' I exclaimed.     Y  ' ' Stop!' he cried, and stamping on the  door' and listen to me. You offer me wealth--look at this apartment; your Em- su press herselff, cannot show its equal.' For a   moment he eyed me with a smile of exultation, as I hastily scanned my eye over richness and elegance such as I had an never before beheld. ' Recal that offer Count, you see I need ] It not; all that I coveted was beauty, and roc that I   have obtained; now attend to me, id were half the wealth of all the Russia's pa heaped before me, I  would not release her, lr sh  e is mine, mine' he repeated mine for- ac, evI Now listen to my proposition, by OE   Ive which you will learn my motive for your capture. Do yon wish for liberty?, th- 'Explain yourself, sir.' 'at * I will; go to that girl, show her that escape is impossible, tell her of my attach. !t ment, of my honorable intentions, tell her n-. too, that I will permit the ceremony to be nse performed by a Greek Priest, so much do, el1 I love her, foolish as it is, and if you suc- ceed in gaining her voluntary consent to- this union, you may depart.' ss  Rage now took fall possession of me; he' sit saw it, as I was' on the point of refusing, e, and motioned me to silence. as  ' Reflect Count,' he said, ' her fate is th seal'd, I solicit no more; place the alterna- d. tive before her; so strong is the love I is bear her, it rends my very soul to use t- compulsion; but by the Ruler who made e me, and who 'governs heaven and earth g I swear, I solicit this stubborn beauty nh. longer. Your answer.' ,Never,' I   exclaimed, ' I may rot in d thelowestwlest dungeon ofyour cavern, but I  will never become yosur messenger on such an errand; to be bribed with the offer of liberty by a midnight robber, a Captain of Banditti I one who would force t the only child ' Stop,' he cried, and springing furlous- ly towards me and brandishing his weap. on over my heai.    Strike infidel! then enumerate among your other heroic exploits, that you have slain an unarmed man.' For a moment he hesitated, the sword suspended over me. ' Do you refuse my offer y ' Most unequivocally, I do.' ' Even should the alternative be torture- and imprisonment for life?' 'Yes, forever,' He turned from me, and walked'the room   for several minlutes, evidently con- sidering what course to pursue; twice he- paused before He, and again resumed his stride. a' Tis well,' he said, halting, I you have acted as  l, perhaps, should have-done in your situation. Now hear my resolve p  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7184-00000012"/> this day, 'ere the sun reaches its meridian, -a Greek Priest will be in this cave; and immediately upon his arrival, the ceremo- ny shall be performed, and Eliza become my bride. , Count M. you shall witness ,the ceremony' Slaves, bear him hence!' Kamish,' I cried, now -almost distracted, ,hear me:' 'Shall I not give him the bow string, my lord,' said Mahomet.  Peace slave!' then turning to me with a malicious smile,' I have reserved you for another purpose,' and I was again sei- zed and borne back to my cell. I cast my- self upon the ground in utter dispair, and ,directly heard a low chuckling laugh at -the door; on looking up, I could perceive the dwarf figure of Mahomet. ' Count,' he -whispered, ' after to-mor- rpow, I alone become your keeper; ha I ha! ;ha I'tis not the first Christian has fallen into. my hands; my. master away with his bridewe 4he sole inmates of this cave, let it:. console you, 1 have a deeper dungeon than he-wots of.',  "Away fiendX I cried, as, he closed the door. Bu t-let me omit these hours of ag- '.ny-agony so great, thatl I:prayedyes proaygd that ere the meridian hour, : which was now near at hand should arrive, my term of life might cease. I sat list'ning ,to every footfall with the keenest intensity, when all at once there was a shout so long and loud, together with the report of fire- arms. the very cave shook, -from its rever- -berations. CHAPTER V. In an instant all was in commotion.- tcould hear the soldiers rapidly passing from under ground, and the commanding voice of the Persian Satrap, giving his orders. I knew there was an attack, but from what source I could not conjecture. From the loud battle cry 'twas evident it was a serious one. I sprung to the door and found it barred. Throwing my whole force against it, I endeavored to force a Tassng9, but the attempt was vain, Mas , lioiet had too firmly secured it.   I at that moment perceived a low stool in one corner of the room. . Quicker than thought, had I placed it under the win- dow, when leaping upon it, I perceived directly in front of the cave, about one hundred of my tried followers, and Selim at their head. My emotions so, overcame me, I remained several minutes paralyzed unable to attempt an escape. But my at- tention was soon drawn to another quar- fer, for Mohomet suddenly entered my apartment pistol in hand. In a moment, I saw his intention, and aware no time was to be lost, with a desperate effort gain- ed the aperture as a ball grazed my tem- ple. Having effected a passage, I soon saw without a reinforcemeft, the Tartar could not long sustain himself, for we were near- ly three to one; but never did I witness greater heroism than he exhibited, Al- most the sole effort of Selim and his men was directed against him, and as yet to me, not a drop of blood indicated a wound upon hisperson. Braced against the rock, he stood firm and unmoved;his' weapot was asa flashing rod, before which all re- coiled and perished, their blows seemed to be dealt in vain, whilst with every sweep of his sabre, a headless trunk rol- led at his feet. Ten swords were at once 'aimed at his breast, ten swords were at once foiled. Over six feet in heigth, with a frame of iron, and herculean stature, my men at last recoiled so fearfully before his blows, that I feared for the issue, while at the same time I could not but admire the dexterity of the man. Shouting to his followers to lead them on, he would dash upon his victims like a lion on his prey, apparently guarding his own soldiers, equally with himself. His rash impetu- osity made an impression on my men, for they gave ground before him. He saw it, tand collecting his bind closely and quick- ly around, prepared for a last trial of strength. There was a pause. Idared not await the result, bat creeping over a projecting rock that had protected me from ' observation, leaped down among my sol-   diers. Their shout when they perceiv- ed me, seemed to rend the very heavens. I now saw that Abdel Kamish had but about twenty men remaining, and some of them wounded to- contend with fearful odds. He saw me as I was directing Se- lim to prepare for another attack, and his eyes gleamed like burning meteors upon me. Being anxious to avoid any farther effusion of blood, and aware at a glance that the seizure of Abdel Kamish was next to impossible, at The same time fear. lul by pressing matters too far, the safety of Eliza might be endangered, I advanced a little in front of my men. ' latrap,' I said,' your efforts are vain. Just retribution has fallen upon you at last: But there is yet time for safety. I desire not to take advantage of your situ. atioa farther than this ;Surrender the la- dy now confined in that cave into my charge, and you are at liberty to depart.'- ' And the alternative 1' ' Her rescue, and your incarceration in that cave, guarded by my soldiers, and subject to the future disposal of the EKm- press.' 'I will die rather,' he replied. ' Then die tyrant!' I exclaimed, now roused to fury, at the same time directing my men to form themselves into as com- pact a body as possible, with the intention of falling upon the centre. But whilst I was giving the above directions, I observ- ed the Tartar-chief earnestly conversing with one of his followers, which led me to believe, he might yet yield to my offer.- At the very moment I was preparing for a eharge, he checked me with a wave of his sabre. ' Hold Count,' he exclaimed,' and you have my conditions,' and ere I could reply, he had darted like light'ning into the cave, : What means this Selim V' 'I know not my lord, unless there is a passage of egress by which he can escape with the lady; it must be either that, or else the dog of a Turk is preparing for a sally. ' But one thing is certain,' he continued,   rP ' the Prince of Darkness aids him, for  within a rod of him twice have I taken t deliberate aim at his breast, Band twice f have my balls passed him uns:athed.' ! Although the danger w\orso imminent, I could but smile at his superstition, at the s same time directing my men to fall back- L in good order, which by giving us room, r would enable me to prepare Ior any emer. , gency. s  At this moment, Abdel Kamish re-ap.  peared. There was a smile of revenge upon his countenance, which alarmed men forthe safety of Eliza. Could his retreat into that cave, I asked myself with a shud-  der, have been assassination V' t But I was not left long in doubt, for rais- ing his voice to its highest pitch and poin-  ting upwards he shouted, ' Count, behold my condition-I ask r avenged.' Icast my eye in the directionpolnted with alarm and beheld the daughter of i Marshal N. apparently senseless in the I arms of Mahomet. But O! my God!- how shall I write the rest --he stood up- on the very brink of a precipice, from its summit no human eye could trace the bot-  r tom. There he stood the same fiendish grin upon that countenance. ' Abdel Kamish,' I cried,' hear me if i but for one moment.' [' Count,' he said interrupting me with a look of madness and in a voice of thun- der,'these are my conditions; withdraw o your men instantly and she is safe--ad- - vance another step, and by the Holy Proph- r et my minion, at a given signal. well un- f derstood by him, hurls her from that rock, into the abyss below, the bottom of which I noliving person ever reached, a prey to , wolves and vultures.' I was desperate, but knew not what to do. t Eliza,' I cried, ' Eliza.' She heard me, she recognized my voice, r she extend6d her bound arms for aid.-- t Never shall I forget that supplicating ges- ture, or that faini cry in the distance' Oh save me Ferdinand,' as with her dishevy.  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7184-00000013"/> : ellbd locks flying in the wind, I beheld the ;dwarf. the echo of whose horrid laugh revtrberated from rock to rock (whilst ciefsely tyeing liis master) grasp her still :moe firmly in his talons. "The words of her father when we last parted flashed upon my mind, ' Better i exrinand, bring her home a corpse, than alive and dishonored.' In a moment my resolution was taken.  Sooner," I exclaimed, die ten thou- sand deaths, than again fall into the hands ofthat monster. Selim charge.' In an instant, my soldiers were upon them. The dreadful signal is given. 1 saw it as I grasped a rifle. But no, itis too -lat;e, she is already suspended over the yaw- ning gulf, when the fiend to give more impe. tus to the plunge, drew her again towards :himsas if glorying in her agong and repeats the ewing. At the time when he had ad- *ded forcesufficient for the cast, I raised my lde, not a nerve then trembled, I:felt as calm and composed as when firing at a target, fy I neow m, chlnee was a fearful one. .Piril, iem which there i8, apparently, no escape, and -if any, but one coursi to" adopt, will make a coward sometimes brave; and one  t at im naturally of a fearless temperament, Qan c encounter equal danger with the same c ourage; but devoid of his recklessneso, he cam calmly obsero0 the effects of his only aItemative, with a degree of satisfaction, that all that human skill and bravery could , oI, has been done./ It was with the latter , feCeling, I watched the effects of my fire.-- I *I quickly perceived the ball had taken ef- 1 fect, he staggers he reels;--but oh i heav-  -ens! with the tenacity of a dying man, he , clasped her still more firmly in his talons,- They 'tter, they sway upon the awful brink, p at on. time almost suspended over it. Her I bridal dress now of the ensanguined hue, si the blood was ooaing from Mahomet's c wound. In her almost more than mortal 1 efforts to extricate herself, I perceired she e ;had released her hands, which gave mea f fhint hope. During thatmoment which ap-  peared an age. although the whole would k comprise but an instant, I scarcely breathed. Both parties as ifby voluntary consent ceas- y -ed fighting and stood witnessing the strug. Abdel ]amish quickly perceived the advan- e ' tg si8e had gained, and that to secure his fi vctim, both must perish; without a mo- s ments hesitation his thunder toned voice of -rence- could be distinctly heard, even at b ,Imthithe               is *Toether, Mahomet, go togeter or by   e the tomb at Mecca, the time will come, when h you'll wish that yawning gulf had been your st sepulchre. I swear it!' "His slave heard him, and had that com. mand extended to his final doom of everlas- st ting misery, he dared not to have refused, r as summoning all his energies, again they n stand upon the awful brink. But his strength is rapidly failing; sle appeared to be aware I. of it, and as if endowed with superhuman to power, making a desperate effort, released "herself, as he with a shriek, still ringing in my ears, plunged bounding from rock to n rock down the abyss. 1  A shout from my men as they beheld my success, was returned by one of defiance ' by their opponents. 'Come on,' cried their leader,'I am still s nearer, the goal than you.' at the same time  s pointing towards Eliza, who was lying up- ' on the rock to all appearance exhausted r withher'Jast effort. Springing in frontof l my men, I dashed upon him; 'twas a fear. t ful encounter, for never before had I met his e equal. Our men, as if by mutual consent, ; stood inactive, observers of the contest.- Long and desperately we fought. I was, obliged to stand wholly on the defensive, , so rapidly did one blow of his sabre succeed another and even then, I had twice felt i I/ keen edge, Feeling myself growing Wreak from loss of blood, and aware I must adopt another alternative, I quickly assumed tihe offensive, and gathering all my strength for a last desperate effibrt, hurled my weapon at his head, He saw the impending blow, and by a dexterous feat, threw out his guard, mine was instantly shivered at the hilt. Un. armed, I stood defenceless before him. * Now Christian,' he shrouted, raising his sabre,' by. the soul of Mahomet! you are mine.' ' Never,9 I replied, eluding his blow and closing with him. Then came the struggle, long we tfugged closely locked in each others embrace, and grappling with the tenacity of fiends. At last, summoning all his energies, his colossal weight had brought me on my knees. ' Now Count,' he said in fury,' you must yield, and to the victor belongs the spoils' 'Twas then I observed a dagger attached to his belt; quickly drawing it forth, it need. ed but a thrust and he lay prostrate atmy feet. Ordering Selim to secure his men, i slowly ascended the precipice. Eliza,' I said as I clasped her in my em- brace, we meet never to part again with life.'  Ferdinand,' she whispered, and agaht   fainted in rny arms. Gently raising her I safely passed the declivity, and entered the cave which had been evacuated by its for- mer inmates. Iv immediately ordered Selim to make preparations for our departure, intes n ding to convey her to the nearest seat of her father's I was more anxious to depart from information obtained by my servait. Hear- ned that in the late battle with the Cossacks the Russians had been successful, as imme- late/on my seizure, Abdel Kamish had fallen back with his prisoner, successfully re- siting all efforts to retake me. He also in- formed me that by sparing the life of a won. ded soldier, he had been directed bya cir- cuitous route to the Akbar cave. 'But my, lord,' he continued, , Marshal a,. is wounded, I saw him fall from his horse m attempting to follow me, and the great i :rumb ofcombatants that intervened, prevent- X ed my reaching him.'           i ' You know not if he is alive?' t ' I do not.' With a heavy heart, I turned from him r eolving not to mention it to Elizain her a debilitated state. Selim re entered the cavec soonei than I expected, and informed me that tl 'the bdy of Abdel Kamish had disapeared.  'i8 countenance was so ghastly; 1 wras alar. da oad at  me impending danger.    ,  b "Weroyou not directed,' I inquired,'by in me to secure that body t ?       th ' Ah.! my lord I was; lets us leave this ti, Eave, 'twas no mortal we were contending  1 ith. Not a s soldier can account for his dis. sc appearance, and Ifyou retake him not one of - them will again attempt to guard him.' E s Although much chagrined  at such negli- at gene  on the part of my followers, I could fot not but laugh at Selim's fears. me i Netver mind,' I re/lied, , we will secure unl his gold at all events. I presume none of you ing would refuse iaking that und er your prate the ' Not I,' he replied, c rossing himself; and koiing suspiciously upon it, not any ofit tint w'il I touch m y lord.' '.As you will my good fellow, there are Tion som e of your comrades I dourbt not, will prove otht leso sensitive upon that sobject.' is E Oidering some of m   y followers to secure his wealth which was immense, we sooncom- I n menced our  journey.            as 8 CHAPTER VI. teere I had become so weak from loss of blood H 'rben we arrived at Marshal N's. seat, that whe muedical assistanee became indispensable. 1]ut do human skill could protect me from a red,   *'.f ^ ler I languishing bedofsicknew, upon whi.  t.* the lay for the spaceof three monlh s  't "t for- that time, (I wa atrards infored)  t ^hi':(- fterard nfor     ind) .? slim irim tting in, the p"ysieion e xpresecllt. " ten. opinio n that should r revive from a elD,ina her to whic I had fallen, in an insanebin ithms , romn my case was bopeless. But my time. hid ear- not yet closed, Providence spared me to tasta cks the cup of happiness, and afterwards drink ne- that of sorrow to the very dregs. had I learned on my becoming convalescent re- th'at Marshal N's, wound did not prove so in- serious as was at first feared, alnd he was n. soon enabled again to head the army, and 'ir- during my sickness had bten contending with the Cossacks. One day whilst sit- al ting in my room, he abruptly entered. It se was the first I had seen him sines may illness. ,at Hastily approaching and embracing me wee it- remained for several moments closely locked in each others arms, unable to articulate a word. ' Ferdin and,1 ' he said upon reviving, my. m on suffer me to call youf impute not this er abseene  to indifference. The calls of my re countr e are paramount to all others. ut 1t the Coeacks and Tartars who have again  shookthe very throne of Russia, having ben drivAen bac to their fastnees, and a peace  being efcted, I have f lost no time in hasten y ing to return you my heartfelt thanks, for the reutoration of an only child from a cap- s tivity oroe than d eath. to a bereaved parent W he could not have long survived her ab b 8CsenCe t f ' My lord,' I replied, I m erit no thanka. Even were my heart callous to sensations of a tenderer nature, and were*Eliza to be hence. I forth a stranger, I acted only as duty bad e me. Did you not take me when a stranger, under your kind fostering care? Extend. ing the hand otf protector, to shield me from tl, envy of some, and vengeance of others? aand now ' Stop, stop,' he said, smilingly interrap. ting me,' no more of tLis Ferdinand. I se you are determined to remain under obliga. tions, and I verilv believe I must adoplan- other method of cancelling the debt. Where is Eliza?'        X ' I  know not my lord, but fear in some way I m  ust have unintentionally offended her, as sae has been absent ever since my illness. ' Absent!' he repeated, , you must be de- ceived, as she was the first perison I encoun- tered upon alighting from m y carnrage.' He was on the point ofleaving the room, when he suddenly turnled thwards me. ' Isan  y thing the matter my lord tI eanqu- 'ed, obserring him bhi 'te'  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7184-00000014"/> ' Yes,' he replied, J geating himself by my ' You are awsrre that in my last battle with I the Tartars;, I had been nearly defeated.' wh A I am,' I replied ' the papers teemed with "ountrof it, how, when the day was near- it; ly. Woan by some singular coincidence, vie- tra tory had like to have been snatched from your grae.          *      ,wI ' Tis true,' he replied, in a low voice, ' and sei that singular coincidence, was the appear- ance of your arch enemy, Abdel Kamish in m the field. f Abdel Kamish ,' I repeated, interrupting hims; is he not dead?'        m I He is not, he said in a sad serious tone, ' there are various reports about him, soie too D incredible to repeat; but the most probable is, w thait whilst he lay wounded and you were in ci the cave, he was rescued by a Faker, and se- sa creted in one of its dark passages. But as I wits saying, he suddenly appeared upon the k field and casting himself before the vanquish- ed foe, with his small band of warriors, tur. a nedthhe tide of victory, and almost wrenched t it- fdro me; he fought like a mad man, arid nothing but the utter confusion of the foe, i saved us from a total route. Wheni he per- I ceived the day was lost, he bounded towards t me and hurled his javelin at my head; the plunging of my horse saved my life. Taking  it up, I found secured to it this scroll.' 1 r'SAbdelKamish yet lives, and will be aveng- i ed. Widow or wife your daughter shall yet l be mine. 1 have swore it!" ' I now leave you,'- he continued, ' but let ti's pass no farther, we must be on our guard.' He had been absent only a few moments, and I was pondering upon the information received, when he he again entered, followed by his daughter. ' Come, Eliza,' he said,' Ferdinand has been laying heavy charges against you, and upon my word, I should sooner his late delir- ium may not have entirely left him, than it prove true.' 'A charge against me, my dear father! she said, evidently alarmed' pray tell me in' what way I have offended him.' I No, no,' he replied, laughing, ' do not take it so seriously my child. But he informs me that during his whole illness, you have been absent and not visited him at all.' ' Have you been ill too, Eliza?' he asked, now eyeing her closely,' surely those faded cheeks, indicate something I was not before, aware of.' ' Not ill my lord,' she replied blushing but you know the alarm I experienced, pre- vious to my rescue, has partially affected   my health.' We both observed her for several moments,  I felt confident something had transpired which was seriously preying upon her mind. Her father grasped the bell rope,- she saw it and springing forward attempted to frus- trate him. ' Hold, mv dear father, and to. morrow I will explain all,' but the next moment her- servant Catherine entered the room. , Catherine,' he said in a stern voice, ' your- mistress has been ill, why was I not inform. ed of it?' She hesitated,-- Need I repeat the question? Answer me me directly.' I will my lord, but I was not to blame.- , During the Count's illness and delirium, not- , withstanding the remonstrance of the physi-: ician, she was night and day almost his con- stlant attendant, and I told her--- I  There, there, that will do' exclaimed, the e Marshal, interrupting her,' you may retire.' 1 ' Is this possible, Eliza? Forgive me for  a moment thinking that I hdd been foigot- d ten'  d   ' Forgotten, Ferdinand, she repeated,' no e, never. Had it not been for you, what woeld, - have been my fate? Did you not peril all is to save me frog a living death?' le  And is he not amply compensated my. ig child,' interrupted her father, in receiving thils?'the same time placing her hand in g- mine, and turning upon her a look ofparen- et tal pride, he addressed me. Take her Ferdinand, excellent as she is - et I believe you every way worthy of her; ma- dt ny splendid alliances has she refused, baek- ts, edby a long line of illustrious ancestors, but on my dear son remember this, true nobility can edas easily inhabit the cot as lhe palace, for it consists notmn subserviently fawning before Las the vain trappings of royalty, whilst allied to nd rank, but in looking upun all men whose [ir. names are spotless and whose characters it are unimpeachable, as your equals. I shall , now leave you, merely remarking, that busi- er. ness of importance will soon cause my ab- in' scence for several months, and if my Eliza. would do me one favor ere that departure my tke hours of travel would be enlivened with an- me ticipating a still happier return.' een ' Come,' he added smiling' upon ler, ' are you prepared to girant mae a trifling favor? I ed believe I never had much cause to charge you with dsBbedience.' ore. ' Nor shall you now, dear papa,' she re- plied playfully placing her arm around his ting neck,' come tell me what that trifling favor pre- is, which by my granting will confel such :tedinexpressible happiness. Do you wish for   my dull company when far away to cheer those lonely hours, if so, I can assure you it will be most cheerfully given. ' Your company my child, Oh! no, do you not perceive poor Ferdinand's demure look at the very proposition? A relapse is con- sidered by physicians more dangerous than the first stage of disease.' Nay, nay, look not so alarmed Eliza,' he continued,I but your father is soselfish he would exceedingly regret having uninten- tionally exposed his daughter to a severe tri- al, and I much fear if you should leave him now, your gentle skill would again become requisite on our return, What say you. Fer- dinand, shall' I take her with me, or exact the favor she has been so kind to promise me? I was on the-point speaking when she in- terrupted me. ' Recollect,' she said blushing, and look- ing first upon me and then upon her father' ' the favor was was to be a trifling one.' ' Did I say so?' he asked laughing. ' Yes you did and you must place no heavy task upon me,' she answered playfully for , my promise you are aware is conditional.' ' Well I believe you are right Eliza, and compared with Ferdinand it may perhaps, be considered trifling. You understand me do you not? Let me be made haIpy in the union of my children ere my departure, and be my abscence a long or a short one, I shalllbe con- soled with the reflection that the dearest wish of my heart is accomplishd and- 'Oh! Papa,' she said, interrupting him, this is indeed ungenerous and 'permit me to rettact my promise; grant me a short respite if only till your return."' * Come Ferdinand,' she;continued, turning blushingly to me, ' cannot-you intercede? ' In this way only, can I interceder' I re- plied, kneeling before her,' in granting your father's trifling favor, you will makle me in- expressibly happy ; dare I ask, dare I hope it will not be refused?' ' Now, Eliza,' remarked the Marshal laugh ing, you had better not call in any more in- tercebsors.'  * ' If I do, I can assure you they shall be more impartial and less interested, than this selfish Ferdinand.' ' Come, come, my child, you see I must be in Moscow   at the expiration of three days,' ' Three days!' she repeated, ' so soon!' 'Yes, I was in hopes I might have post- poned it, but a letter received from court this morning, makes my departure at this tinme unavoidable.' She stood for several moments hesitating, ' If neither you nor Ferdinand will release   me, I believe t must submit.' I sprang to clasp her in my arms, but elu- ding me she darted from the room. It being settled between us, that as she pre- sented no more objections to our union, the ceremony should be performed before Mar- shal N's departure. That evening we were united, and he left us happy in the assurance of her bliss. After our marriage, I immediate ly threw up my commission, and being of a sed entary habit, and Eliza's taste coinciding with mine, we retired to a country seat of Marshal N*, near Moscow. Years of unalloyed happiness was ours.- My wife, her father and a boy (now three years of age,) comprised my society ; I sought and wished no other. 'One day whilst sitting in my library watching my heir in his childish gambols with his mother ,for his playmate, I involuntarily opened a newspaper and whilst casting my eye over foreign news, my attention was drawn to the land of. my birth-again did the scenes of my childhood return. My bome, my school-mates, my rambles when a boy; how vividly was X re- minded of them all. At that mounent aband was laid upon my shoulder, looking up, X per- ceived Eliza hanging over me. . ' Do you my dear Ferdinand, reserve some of your thoughts from your wife, or, shall I be a partaker of them all.?'   . ' The whole Eliza,' 1 said,' my thoughts reverted to the days of my childhood;..my heart was bleeding over the oppressions of my native land; a land I feel, where true liberty, fre ed from the thraldom of tyranny will yet exist.' ' Ah! Ferdinand, did you not tell me at the altar, that I was the sole possessor of your heart; then 'why do you allow it to play truant?' ' Not truant my dear wife,' I cried, em- bracing her, ' you have, tand shall ever have the whole; but dare I hope, that my Eliza's affections are as wholly, as undividedly pla- ced upon me?' Wholly, wholly, my dear Ferdinand, you know it; why do you ask?' she said, look- ing seriously. I pointed to the little Oscar, now standing by her side. ' Has he no share, Eliza?' ' Oh! our boy,' she said, taking him in her arms and placing him on my knee' I un. derstand you now, he being ours, let our af- fections, there centre and our hearts must re. main undivided. Now promise me certainly lbat you meditate no moreover past incidents which cannot be recalled. Do you promise me Ferdinand?'         1  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7184-00000015"/> ' I do ; from this time let us be to each oth- er, all in all.' Such felicity was ours, when we were again reminded that time was fulfilling its rounds by the death of Eliza's lather, caused by a fall from his horse, when returning to the city. He had been with us but little du- ring the last year, being in active service the most of the time and tnad observed with re- gret my withdrawal from public service-- To enter into a description of our feeling-, at this bereavement would be superfluous,- Those who have not lost near and dear rela- tives might sympathize but hardly realize.- His last words were as he grasped my hand when standing by his side, ' Ferdinand, to you I have consigned all I hold dear; shield her and protect her as you ever have done- I ask no more. But remember my son, war now threatens our land, the land of your adoption; let your affections, if necessary, be sacrificed to your duty. Prize the safety of our country above all else.' These were his dying injunctions. His death was mourned by the whole country.- He had fallen at a time when he could illy be spared, for Russia was indeed again threat- ned with invasion. Obrazoff, our minister to Constantinuple had been confined to the Seven Towers, and the multifarious bands of military assembling themselves out of Asia to the amount of 250,000 marched from Constantinople towards the Danube. To repel this force, the different nations comprising the extensive empire of the Autocrat of all Russia, were pushing on towards the Dnie- ster. For several months, hostilities contin. ued and notwithstanding the remonstrances of some and the intercession of others, I re- mained an idle, but not uninterested specta- tor of the war-but my feelings were chang- ed partially; the, sound of martial music was incapable of reviving that love of the battle-field, which once so fully posessed me. But at times, when news reached me of some impending action, or as I read accounts of the bravery of our soldiers, duty would urge i moe on to the encounter, a love of military I glory would again fire my breast. Eliza, however, was watchful, and being opposed to my joining, would smilingly place our boy upon my lap, and this, together with her look of entreaty, would soon restore me to my former listlessness. One day whilst walking with them in front c of our mansion, my attention was arrested! by. a rapidly advancing horseman, Upon i amrving at the gate, he dismounted and waa, in a short time before u       1n.1   ' Have I the honor to address Cournt M.9  he inquired. That is my name ; what may beyour bu- siness?' I e handed me a letter, and I was just go- ing to break the seal, when Eliza, pale and trembling, laid her hand ubon it, 'Do not open it now, dear Ferdinand.' ' Not open it Eliza?' I asked, at the same - time bidding the courier retire ' I do not un- derstand this.' ' But I do,' she replied, taking it from my extended hand ' I recognize the writing ;  give me half an hours respite, and I will re- store it, but just now 1 do not wish you to  peruse it; come let us retrace our steps to the house ; this is what I have been long ex. pecting.' After being absent sometime, she returned and placed the letter in my hand. ' Ferdinand, that letter is from General ' General R.' I repeated, ' surely you must be mistaken Eliza.' ' No I am not,' she said, with an incredu- - Ious shake of the head, ' the courier wore bi . livery; he calls you, and I feel that we must part. Instantly breaking the seal, I read: Dear Count:-A   fewyears since, I became acquainted with an individual, of such anam- bitious and military spirit, that no induce-- ments, no allurements, not even those of the gentlersex, could turn him from the pathof fame. Let the pinnacle be ever so high, the daring as great, he had a mind willing enough: and an arm strong enough to accomplish all his  wishes. That sword never for a moment wa. vered, even in the hottest of the fight, whilst guided by his arm; that heart inthe pursuit, never relented, unless before a vanquisled foe, and then when the fate of war cast his oppo. nent helpless before him, vengeanciee was stay- ed, and mercy the " darling attribute of heav. en" entertd. At that time I looked upon him as destined to accomplish much, but how have my sanguine expectations been disappointed. Safely esconced ,n his snug little corner, with a lovely Countess by his side, (whom to ad- mire is but to see,) he reads with unconcern of the booming of the cannon. Alas! he hears it not;war has become to him an idle tale, his country, a secondary consideration. With his affections concentrated upon his wife and heir, he forgets his old comrades in arms, or (which I can hardly believe possi- ble) thinks his old friend for being still a-bach. elor, must undergo all the drubbings, I have almost come to the conclusion my dear Count, if you do not join me soon of becoming a Ben, edict myself, and then by followipg your exam. pie. our good Empress will lose (pardon my vanity) two of her most efficient officers. What say you, shall I throw up my commia-   sion, or look for your joining me on the Dan- ube. To be serious, you are needed here very much, Halitza, has been driven back bv the Vizier, and Halil, (the latter's successor,) I must soon meet. Tell the Countess, (as from your indolent spirit, I much fear your having lost all command even at home,) that if she consents to your abscence for one campaign, I pledge my word for your safe restoration to her society, and it it would be any inducement, I might add, that, should we be successful in driving that infidel back, I, as an incumbrance might return with you. Yours ever,   f A. R. t P. S. Need I remind you, my dear M. of the last words of the dying patriot, Marshal N. to stimulate your ardor. Having finished it, I handed it to Eliza, at the same time remarking ' Read it Eliza, and in its answer, I will be guided entirely by your wishes.' Afterperusing it, she returned it saying, Go Ferdinand ; we were forgetting my fa- thers dying injunctions ; go, and if we never I meet again I will try and console myself I With the reflection, that he has been obeyed.' } She shuddered as she added, ' Oh! my dear- t est husband, we part forever!'     a ' Why Eliza,' I asked ' do you allow such n evil forebodings? When I return in safety, e we will laugh over your childish fears.' b ' I feel they are no childish fears,.Ferdi n and ; with your departure ends our happi- n CHA PTER. VII,          b Consoling her as well as I could, I made wi preparations  for our instant departure. I ii must omit our parting interview, but never! a never! shall I forget her farewell, as stand.-  ing in the door with our child by her side fe we gave the last embrace. Directing Selim ria to follow, I instantly mounted and directed Io my course to the theatre of action. We had to prosecuted our journey successfully, until the so evening  of the third day. We were then foy passing through a very mountainous country hiL when my   attention was arrested by an unu. in sual rumbling in the distance. I turned to  Selim to learn the occasion of it, when he an- . i ticipated me by saying, ' Let us hasten my lord, to find some shelter from the coming eel storm ere it bursts upon us. I kno-w it v ell, att and its motions are so rapid, that the fleetest ula horse, to escape it will contend in vain.' not He had hardly finished the sentence, ere it  burst upon us in all its fury. Not a vestige my of any thing in its course could resist. Huge gui trees of the forest, were. instantly torn from at 1 their oote and cattered in every direction..- ho   tan- We were so forunate as to halt in front of a ,ery projecting rock, the overhanging arch of thIe which was sufficient to protect us and our rom horses. There is something grand and aw- ,ing ful in this war of elements; in seeing the she demolition of the Creator's works, by his own n,I mighty arm. The growth of centuries, up. her rooted and leveled with the ground led me t, I into a reverie on the subject, from which my I in mind wandered to my home, and in a mou nce ment all impending danger was forgotten, Elver since my departure, I had felt an unu. Psual depression, a gloomy foreboding at my of heart, for which I could assign no reasona- N. ble cause, except that it might have been the effects of Eli:a's sadness, as her depres- at sion appeared to be on 'my account, while nd my thoughts constantlyv brooded over her and by my boy. 'IThis I knew was absurd; she was protected by faithful servants, who would ig, die, to serve her. fa- As I thought of this the memory of Abdel ,er Kamish crossed my mind and I shuddered. elf Yet why should I? I had not heard fro ' him for several years, and I was aware r- the roving bands of Tartars had been con. stantly contending, and in all probability he Dh must have fallen, or if living, forgotten his y, wrath. Here my reflections were interrupted by a low groan issuing from the rocks be- i- neath us, at the same time Selim moved i- nearer to me and asked, ' Did you hear that groan, my lord?' I replied in the affirmative, and desiried him to be silent. We had been listening some time, the wind still howling around us, e when it was again repeated. Ordering Se- him to strike a light, I at once discovered an * aperture in the rock large enough to admit ' a man with ease. My   servant naturally , fearless, at once leaped into it. I -was secua 1 ring my horse, intending to follow when a loud cry from him, again and again repeated a togetherwith my  name, convinced me that some imminent danger was near. Springing for the aperture, my coursq was arrested by his reappearance and at the same time clasp. ing me around the body. ' ' Hold! hold!! my master,' he exclaimed in the name  of God enter not that cave! ' What mean you,' I asked, releasing my- self with difficulty from his grasp, and again attempting to descend; all he could artia- ulate was, ' Oh! my  master, forbear, enter not that horrid cave P' Surprized at his unmanly cowardice, I drew my sword and   though the light was extin- guished entered the subterranean Fassage at at the same time directing him to secure my horee, he having broken his rein and was now  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7184-00000016"/> Imost unmanageable, as each flash of light- of ning- followed bv repeated crashes of thun. at der in rapid succession, was pealing through e( the forest.               w A flight of steps led to a long narrow pas- G sage ;the ground was smooth, evidently oft- a en trodden by the foot of man; but its sides " were rough as if by some violent shock the rock had been rent asunder. After groping my way a short distance, occasionally halt- ing for the heavens to again illume my path, I came to a halt, concluding it advisable to 0 await the arrival of Selim, whose non-ap. t  pearance I could not account for. It was ev- ident to me that his alarm must have origin- ated in something real, although 1 could not tl divine the cause I had never yet known him a to fly a foe, and he would treat lightly perils, v that threatened momentary destruction. ti Between the peals of thunder, the cavern was as dark and silent as the grave, and the  farther 1 advanced, the less light was deri- s ved from the heavens. Selim's prolonged f abscence was so inexplicable, that I at last resolved to advance alone, when my attention was suddenly arrested by another groan, which made it at once apparent that the per- son must have retreated farther into the cav- ern. , thought at the ..same time I could in the distance detect a quick footstep, as if by come person moving with caution-it was drwlng nearer and not knowing in what mariner, (if r ny)- I rtifght: be assaled, I con- eluded to retcan my position, and if danger threatened, at first, assumethe offensive.- - I had two motves for this; the being advan- cing was not the one that first attracted our attention, therefore should the cavern contain banditti, to advance alone would be prema- ture; and in the second, Selim, who had not yet entered, might lose my direction. As I said, the step was drawing nearer, although what may appear remarkable, the noise was leasning. T could assign but one cause for it the approacher must have been aware of my intrusion, perhaps of my very position, and contemplated terminating my existence at a blow. It appeared to me after listening some time longer, that I could feel his lot breath upon myface!.-imagination will sometimes go far-- but this was not imagination. Again in the distance, I heard tihat groan of pain, and immediately after, a person rustling near me, "Tis an assasainr,' I involuntarily exclaim; ed to myself,' he is flog from hbs victim. But my reverieswer interrupted by a voice so near, thafthe lowest whisper would have been intelligible, "Count M., I hold your deaith warrant!! Years previous, had I stood upon the field   of single combat, within fifteen paces of my adversary, and with calmness, twice receiv- ed his fire. I returned it not, but pointed my weapon towards the heavens, thanking my God for giving me strength to resist the tempt ation ; such a shot, and mine never failed, would have been murder; such a shot would have been insanity. Let'not the duellist incredulously smile at my assersion; but let him ask his own heart as he stands over his prostrate victim, perhaps once his dearest friend, and now-for some trivial offence, prematurely hurried into eter- nity. As that sunken eye is cast upward and he raises his already clammy hand and grasps that of his destroyer, with the smile of for- giveness upon those dying lips, let him I re. peat, ask his own heart what are its sensa- tions? REMORSE. He may, years subsequently, riot in scenes of debauchery; he may revel in palaces of splendor; beauty may subserviently bow be- fore him, and his autumnal sun be bright as that of spring; old age may come upon him ;and find him crowned with honors; the idol of his country; the gazing crowd may envy whilst they love; b it hat dread messenger, death, at last has set h'i seal; wealth, honors, avail him naught; the fiat hath gone forth; r time with him is 1losing;then vividly the i scenes of his youth turn. t  Ah! ask that old man, that paralyzed  frame, what's throbbing at his heart; in a r sepulchral voice, he'll tell you there is an eter- nitv opening to hi-1iew ;he'lltell you its REMORSE ; the canker that unseen, for r years has been preying upon his vitals! Change we the scene-In the melee of the fight, mounted on my powerful courser, have t I broke through the serried pikes of the ene- I my, dealing death with almost every blow of I my weapon, and scorning, the threatened dan- s ger--the wild blast of the bugle; the char- t ging notes of the trumpet; the shout of defi- ance from the one, and the cry of agony d from another, makes man ferocious, more alike the hyena of the forest, than of the hu- e man species. h Once more we change--when but a nov- ice in the art of war, and whilst passing to the river Don, my course was arrested by the cry nof distress. Undeterred, though with but one I attendant, I flew to the rescue, and found a Russian bound: he was in the hands of bra-  voes; there were four, but I heeded Rot the t number, (danger was alleady a pastime,) as a I sprang among them ; their leader was power- ful, but I more skillful, and a short contest d terminated the conflict; his glassy eye of hate was lowered upon me even in death; Id his accomplices fled; 'twas then I rescued Selim from an untimely grave.   Reader, through those scenes and many more had I passed, but there is a striling contrast between them and midnight dssas- sination. The non-appearance of my servant; the stillness, as silent and dark as the tomb ; the peculiar situation ; the low muttering thunder in the distance; the cautious step, and the whisper, "Count M. I hold your death-warrant!" would have startled a nerve of iron. But 1 feared it not. That onnipo- tent power in whom alone I trusted, preser. ved me when upon the threshold of eternity. Scarcely had the words escaped his lips, when there was a vivid flash of lightening, that made every object in that part of the cavern distinguishable. Directly in front of me was a Mohomedan;he was leaning to- wards me in a posture that would enable him to'command all his strength; raised high, and on the point of descending, was my " death warrant," but there was blood upon it; in that glance of a moment, I discovered my danger, that glittering dagger was guided by the hand of Abdallah! those eyes were glaring upon me as if the consumatlon of his deadly purpose was already accomplished. To have swerved in the least, would have been death. Strong, and endowed with re- markable dexterity, without a moments hes- itation, I clasped the blade within my naked hand although it pierced me to the bone, for I already felt the point enter my breast. He endeavored to renew the thrust, but placing my other hand upon his wrist, with a sudden wrench I broke the bone, and cast him on the ground. Not a word as yet had been spoken. Ordering Selim, who now entered, and who hastily informed me he had been detained in order to secure my horse, to take the charge of him, I again struck a light and darted with reckless imi tuosity through the cavern not- withstanding the loud calls of my servant, but I was urged on by repeated groans.  I had not advanced far when 1 discovered the cause of Selim's alarm, in the person of Abdel Kamish, who resting against a pil. lar of a rock, supporting himself upon his sword, stood, as though arrayed for the field of battle. His warrior dress of the richest material was surmounted by the same tow- ering plume floating gracefully above his princely brow; and the same eye of fire flash-. ed upon me, that I encountered at the Akbar cave. But there was a pallor of the counte- nance that mosty, arrested my attention. It wasofthe hue of death. His left hnnd was  placed upon his breast and oozing between I his fingers, I could see the blood, successfully t resisting his efforts to restrain it, trickle down f a gorgeous white scarf embroidered with gold   r which hung suspended from his shoulder. I saw at once that the mighty conqueror Death had placed his irresistable hand upon the ; fearless intrepidWarrior. We stood for some ; moments eyeing each other in silence and I could observe a slight shudder, like that of surprize on his part, a -sensation I also experi- enced. Years had passed since we last met, and although the assertion of Marshal N. had be- come prevalent and report frequently spoke of him, still it was at a great distance con- tending against the prowling bands of his own country. 'Abdel Kamish!' ' Count M.! These were our first words as he be'kon. ed me towards him. I approached. ' Come nearer Count, my time is limited; this voice that could once be distinctly heard bv thousands, is about to be hushed in ever. lasting silence. You have secured that vil- lain.' ' Abdallah?' ' Yes.' I have.' ' Enough, bring him before me.' ' One moment, and I grant your request; explain this singular meeting;is Abdallah again a traitor?' ' A traitor!' he repeated, as his heavy brow lowered in anger, 'a traitor! hell cannot pro- duce his equal, but he shall, ere many min- utes elapse, become its occupant; until then I enter into no explanations; revenge is sweet bring him before ma'  , I obeyed his command. The Tartar chief eyed him for about a minute, as. ifhewould have searched his very soul. The counte- nance of the assassin quailed before that stern yet solemn look. The Satrap saw it and extending his hand, ' Give me that dagger Count, my blood is upon it; you will observe,' he continued, pla- cing his finger near the handle,'it might have gone deeper, when I strike but little steel will be visible ;' ' Abdallah,' he said, (as the latter was up-Cm on the point of speaking) ' utter not a word; I would teli you to prepare for death, but your time is too short; that preparation is lost forever; I gave you wealth and honor, made you second in my 'artan troop ;but 'twas not enough, you aspired higher; secured about your person is wealth, that might a. tiate the most avaricious; but how obtained? purloined from my person when asleep, and then anticipating the chief commnand, and fearful of detection, you have destroyed me. Ihave but one more gift to bestow, it is steel,  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7184-00000017"/> I give it in exchange for gold.' He raised his sti'l powerful arm; not a word escaped the lips of Abdallah ; he knrew his hour had come, and the weapon descen- ded with such velocity, I heard it cracking ing the bone whilst passing deep deep with- in the brain ; his victim made but one struggle as he leaped from the floor and fell; there lay the body, but its soul had fled. ' He retains my last gift,' he said with a ghastly smile, pointing to the blade for he had dexteiously broken it, still leaving the metal buried in his skull; then stooping, he took a package fromn his breast. "There,' he said,' are riches that few ob- tain; take them Count, I stand within my own sepulchre; that last act was one ofjus. tice.' ' Take it,' he repeated, observing me hesi. tate, ' there that is right, the spirit appear- lmg before its God, should leave no enemy behind. I slew him; but Oh! will that God sanction the act? should a brother's hand have done this deed?' "Your brother,' I exclaimed with horror, *ute you wahder my lord.' ' No, no you mistake, I shall sustain my reasoning faculties to the last; Abdallah was my brother, or I should say, my half brother, we are children of one mother; listen for my story must be brief, I can feel that strength is failing arid to enter into particulars is im- poisible. You recollect your rescue of Ab- dallah, and the tale he told?' ' I do.' At was a fabrication; you forced him from the avenger, and that avenger was his faiber! one of Persia's most powerful Sa- traps ; his mother was from Constantinople; if you had not interfered, his career would long ere this have ended. But I must hast- on. He had one sister, her beauty I need not extol, it was the song Ef her native hills.- Abdallah coveted gold and to obtain it was carrying her into captivity, but as I said the avenger followed too closely, she was saved, and the brother arrested. i When you pursued an escape with both was impossible, you know the rest, Long after, Imet him; he manifested the greatest remorse for his past conduct, and besought my forgiveness I granted it on two condilions, the seizure of Eliza and yourself.' ' And that letter.' ' That,' he replied, 'as I afterwards learn. ed from himself, was an error of his own, he gave you the wrong one. His father par- doned him his past offences if he would sac- nfice you and again join our countrymen.--- As he waa uhn the point of cancelling his   'oath, he fell. I supposed he was killed, but fortune favored him.' He pause4 evidently from faintness. ' But how,' I asked, ' did you escape at the Akbar ; cave?' ' Had you examined closely, Count,' he continued with a faint smile' you would have found a small opening near where I fell; that Greek priest preserved my life. I can add but little more; do you see the fiss- ure in that rock, place my body in it and close it up, 'twill secure it from- - Observing him stagger from weakness, I placed my arm about him and he sank gent- ly down. All my enmity had vanished-- I saw before me only a suffering, dying, fellow creature. ' Count,' he added, grasping my hand and speaking with difficulty as the inward bleed- ing almost strangled him,' we were ene- mies, but we were soldiers; /have wronged you, let us part in peace.' ' Would to heaven,' I cried, ' we had al- ways been friends,' and grasping his hand, "Twas not to be.' he faintly articulated, and I felt the pressure of his grasp,' Counts I am going--Eliza! till my dying day, I loved her--even now,' he gasped,' Iwas on my way to your peaceful home to gain the treasure-forgive me-- farewell'--and the man of strife was gone. The intrepid warrior- the savage prince-the firm friend-. the indomitable foe--all, all swallowed up in death. When 1 looked up, Selimr was standing by my side. As he supposed that years gone by Abdel Kamish had bid adieu, to this world, it was sufficient cause for the fear he at first manifested We quickly per- fortned the last sad rites to the departed.-r We wrapped his military cloak around him and gently laid him in his last resting place. Having accomplished our task, we were about to leave, when a low hissing noise ar- rested my attention. Turning towards the corpse of Abdallah, which Ihad left but a moment before, I perceived a huge reptile of a very poisonous nature crawling upon the body. I soon became aware from ob- serving it, that it was of the species said by the iatives to prey upon human flesh in pref- erence to all other food. ' Selim,' said I, 'such is- the end of hu- man ambition, I would not secure it if I could,' and the next moment we had issued from the cave The remainder of my journey, it is need. less to relate. Suffice it to say, I reached the Russian  army at the confluence of the the Pruthand the Danube, at the very time   'that Halil the Tirkish Vizier, owing to the sexcessive eagerness of his soldiers was ob- figed to abandon the posi tion, w here he was 'strongly posted, and offer battle to his oppo- nents. WMen I reached the grotund lhe con- 'flict had commenced; riding instantly to General R. and salutintr him, ' Ah.! Count,' he cried ' this is as I ex- pected; wel:omlle, welcome, the armnies as you perceive, are engaged; I have et present no post to offer you.' ' Yes,' I answered, to-day, I contend as a voltunteer ; htve I your permission?' ' Yes! yes!' he said, ' o on and God 'specd you; these rurliish infidels, have made a fool of their General, and forced 'hill to fight at a disadvantage, consequently, the day must be ours.' His prediction was correct; and on our re. turn from the pursuit, I instaintly directed my steps to hi3 tent. Upon entering, fhe met me smilingly adW said, ' My dear CoAdnt, I have bet a dozen hbt- ties on your head; do we go halves, aye or no?' ' I would first wish to be iznformcd of the nature of' the bet,' answered. ' Nay not until I have your answer, Count; fair play is my inotto, in the Gfld, asalt the -glass and your---.  'Then ale, IS V at once,' interruptiirg him,' now 1or the wagetr By my faith,' he repllied, lau1rhirnr 'tis won; the fickle goddess, fortuno, is sfill oil your side Isee ; but pardon my ffretf1u'n1lss how did you leave the C )untess? whe-n i Ist I saw her, slihe was but a pratling gir J; let nme see, ten-twelve-  thirteen -e;tars agro ; hl,wy time flies! it seems buil ycstcrdy ; 'tis ever ,on the wine, and as we tr'ow older we real- ize it more an I more- I was then --- ' But. my  lord,' I said, ' y,ur cenratu. slatin( upon the fickle goddless still b.:fien- ing me, is, I fear, ill itli:ei as lee but liltle likelihoodof imy learning the nature of this bet-' 'Ah! right/ he replied, ' but Jam such a ,confounded talker well Ihere it :s, I laid a wager witl s)ome brother ofir, ere your t- rival, Chat the militarv ardor which once6. fi- 'red your bosomr was n')t so entirely extinguish ed, but that a  letter from  )ourcommander 'would again ignite it. So you perceive itis won, and by following me  you will secure ,the prize atonce.' Prosorofsky having effected a junction of the districts between the Dniester and the Dnieper, thas facilitating the siege of Bendfer i which was immnediately undertaken by Coun; 'Panin. The place was defended by 16,000 i Turks, and the Pascha, a man of indomitable X rtge, for two 'monU  iuci6sefully rtted   all our efforts. One third of the Ramiats had fa le1, and C(ount Panin fearing for the issue, thought of raising [he siege. 'What thirik you,' he asked, turning to m ' repo-t says that thlese infidtel devil* aro provisionetl folr two years ; is it practiicable to effed an entrance with our hal' starved troops?' * Not only possible but probable,' I replied, ' give 'tle lhe c(mmand of the front gate, and ini a few hours the place is-yours.' 4By my flitl,'  lie rellied laughing* 'C I have heard of your dare d(evil escape from the IAklbar cave,gut A doimblt your climbing those walls as easily, with those ypen mouthed canteon on) their sumnllit.'" 'Nor shall I try' I replied in the same strain,' bt, with your permission I shall enter.' "What permnssi,)n you have,' he replied, anld  .ose no time my dear C'oun I for I would give the conters of mo , piurse, to dine in Ihe  l'aGha's palace. Rumja nznff, bad luck to lhiur, gives us bad fare and hard consatiion.  Th answer to mv cltter com- plainint ot'otr lack of food, he replien pithi- ly enoutlrh, You w,/llflfnd rbeter in Bender.- I  otl1yv wish he had;l 10 sit at nly table, it wOucd be the har'd..t wmeal he ever eat.- B1; g(o o' Count, and if you succeed in this ttempllt, an(1 there is a bott/e of wine in the Paclll 's , 'ce/ar, (which Idoubt not, for they say tine old e-lluws love a glass as well aoa ' cil[isti.1t ) we  wilR drilnk it toge-ther ' 1Having now tli ti toops at the fiont gate un- der ;my  ':ommnanth, I innnlediatly dirrcted tha ".n^iil: lto UH'are a Compressi(on Hall, which I. a :o:lprlica lio) ofnilitnes, bleingr charged with svrll Ilundllll d poods ofi gunp6wdcrJ. T'h' ttl-;k haviw,  l'0,'u c',pleted, rilnd the nmatch applicd.1, tliu effect was astounding, raising the gatLf, anid at the same time tcaring the wdll to atoilS. 'IThl troops now entered I the place by storm, nd ttn a .r it terrible nmassacre, Bender was ta- lle n. S;oon nfterits fill, I received orders from Ficl(Jd-aiaishal Ruinjanzotf to push. on witk :,ione troops, and unlite with a force then con- caentratin,  1t Yassey. I lhad remained there snrlo titl-, when one day, uhIilst sitting in my looe0,  I heard an unusual noise in'the street. Steppinl to the windowS, I  perceived a group of the lower order hastily passing in the ut- lo^,st cnf1asion, and shouting the Plague! the Platue t  DL)cvtlv after Selim entered, 'What's the Caus e oel tohis alarm?' asked. Th pague is in the city my lord, thirteen dead bodies were found in the street this morn. ing.", Throwing on my cloak, I called on the som- mander of the place, ' Would it not be adjisa. ble,' I  askcd, ' to adopt some means by whiek this disease can be staved V' ^Ofar b'     tigrE p air dFll  a  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7184-00000018"/> rilling te,' I have just returned from view- a ing the bodias, and in our present situation,  I consider it not best to create an unnecessa ry panic; it will soon subside.' Vexed at his unyielding obstinacy, I retired. Blind infatuation! The next day at noon, I saw him consigned to the earth without a coffin to nclose his putrid carcase. Butthen tocheck  the pestilence was too late; the, Almighty had sent forth his rmandate, and man could not re- bsist the fiat. If not with the speed of light- ning, yet with much more fatal precision, it tastened on to Chotin. Infbected clothing corn . municated it to the grand army under Generil R. who was obliged to scatter his troops in ev-. cry direction, with the utmost haste. Carlried by the auidiers to the great town of Kiaw, its fWry bore it irresistibly bevond the Dnieper.-- One day whilst witnessing its terrible efects  -upon one of my soldiers, there was a sudden *ry raised of-Moscow--Moscow. Securing the paper which the leader of a band of rioters was carrying, my whole atten- tion was riveted oo a short article. How well I reinether the words:"It can no longer be woncealed. The plague isin our city, convey- ed hither by some infected articles from the Ukrane. Death is among us in itsmost hor- ridform; even the environs do not escape.-- I read no more, but penning a line to Rtumin- janzoff explaining my purpose, immediately directed Selim to prepare for our departure. Ere noon, we were on the way to the city.- How I travelled, I hardly know ; distance was asnothing, buttime waseverv thing. As I passed through that CITY OF THE DEAD my fears were more than realized. Armed mobs paraded the streets, whilst heaps ofcorp- seaslay unburiedin theirmidst. That plaeue, which owing to the fatlselv displayed heroism f one individual, carried 90,000 of the inha.- itants of Moscow ani its environs, into eterni- ty. Hastily passing on,l-sIpeeded towards my own habitation; but as I rode' thro' the gate, hope almost died witlhin the. No servant an, twered to my call; no welcome hand was ex- teaded from the thresholdi to receive me. I da- red not advance, but for soinme time stood ir- Resolute. Su, pense, to me then, was preter- able to reality. Suspense!,yes, would it had been suspen e forever! I could not recede. 4 There.' I exclaimed, I on that door step, with my boy at her side, she bid me farewell.' ' Perhaps,' remarked Selim, observing my despondency,I they have fled.' I Pled,' I repeated in agony,' who ever fled from this plague? No, no,' I cried, leaping from inmy horse and rushing into the house, 'death in all its horrors must have been here.' I shouted through the building, but noan- swer;nothing replied save the echo of my own voice. At that instant, when upon the point -f ascending to the upper apartments, J was suddenly arrested by a cry as if of pain.. Re- tracing my steps, I entered a small apartment, which in my confusion, had escaped my mem- erV; and beheld Eliza lyinr upon the floor.- It needed but one look to explain the cause.-- My God  would the plague had stricken me whilstatYassey. : im^, I mutrOm4,- I ph Wayft her   side, yon too gone! oh! ,why did I *ver "M you?' At that moment she revived. ' Away, dea Ferdinand,' she whispered,' I am -smitten wit the plague.'  ' Never,' I  exclaimed taking her in my armo, we will die together; but why ta4k of dying! you may yet live; may still be spared to me and my'boy.' "Oh!' she murmured, I then you know not all,' at the same time removing the covering, I perceived my child, but he .was dead, the dark plague spot visible upon his forehead. But,' she continued,' Gold in his infinite mercy has heard my prayer, he has spared me once more to behold you. Oh! my hus- band, she cried, clasping me still more close. yIv and firmly,' let mne die in your arms! Fer. dinnnd, dear* Ferdinand, I ainm going! Our Os. car has gone! You will be left alone.' I What,' I exclaimed in frenzy, I have I done to be so afflicted? Is there no arrow in death'* quiver, that cain pierce this broken heart?' No live Ferdinand,' slihe gently said,' oh! repine not; murmur not. The ways of Prov- idence are inscrutable, but they are best.! feel that Iam going to join my boy, whfos lust words still called upon his father.' ' But,' she gasped in her dying struggles to articulate, (and for the last time putting her arms aroundme,) but dear Ferdinand, may tliat God in whom I have always trusted, bear you up under this severe dispensation, for, you will be alone'.' CHAPTER III. Torn by the faithful Selim from that pt- trid corpse, and hurried from my house thro' his unexampled fidelity, (barely reserving time to perform the rights of sepulture,) I was then alone! Once when a boy, driven by necessity from the home of my birth, and now, the last tie being severed, forced by grief forever from thai; of' my adoption, for'years with him as my guide, I traversed heretofore, to me, unknown lands, butI was still alone! Alone in the dense city of London and the licentious one of Paris, when surrounded by thousands and all had a look of'gayety and lilarity, I knew it not, I was alone! Tiile passed over me in the burning climes or Africa, with age premature- ly brought on, but I felt it not, I recked it not, let me repeat, I was alone! One day when crossing one of her deserts, my attention was directed to a dark object in front lying in the sand. Upon gaining the spot, I perceived it to be a human being, apparently dying. and by his side was a large Newfound- land dog licking his hands. Taking a flask from my pocket, I poured a few drops int Ithe ..a.'s mouth; the effect was electrical, as ;e directly revived, when casting his languid eyes around, he motioned me to kneel-by him. ' Stranger,' he said, in a low voice,' I am dying. but ny prayer is granted, my dog,mr ' faithful Wolf, with you as his protector, hw not lost his last friend.' * No, I answered,' I will protect him.  'I know it, I feel it; God will reward you come here Wolf+, (the dog obeyed, ashbe placm r k paw in hi maMterft Irad,)' Iaoe, t mW   Wolf! I mustleave you; but there is your mns ter, you will not be left alone.' (How his last words recalled past incidents, and vibra. rd on my ear--alone.) ' No,' I answered, lie will nut, nor I neither, Wolf shall enliven ,ny dull houirs.' , Stranger 'tis well,' he lisped, I I am going, farewell.' Hastily burying his horly ia the sand Come, Wolf,' I said,' your old arester is gone, but iu me you will find as kind a oe,' The dlog appeared to understand me, for af- ter smelling around the grave a moment, with a drooping head, he obeyed mv call, as we wended our way to the city of the ,Sultain. Upon my arrival, I directed Selim io prep:are me a houqe ill he most retired part ;Tfo, uot- withstanding the many years that hIril Id.-s'r, !feared a racouniiion, and wislied to avoid trenawing my aeclquaintan e with the lRussiall eficcra, (now that poa'iC prevailed) who were visiting Constantinople. I had been there omen tiinw, seldom leaving my habitation, but closely imrnuted with myvdo, ponlriig over past events, yet mal.,iag no calcul:tions for thll future. As I before remarked, a:o was coinlilg prematurely upon me ; but notwithstandiiuir the lapse of time, my ariu hal lost non,: ofi:s strength, my limbs none eof tliir ehisticitv. I eould have guided a ch'lirger with ltie sa!nn ease, and stood the shiock of bttie wit h Wi theI indifference and fortitudo of hi -gonerlav s. One eveninr, after conversing with miy ser- vant until late as ha arose to ielpart, ' I had like to have 6;)rgotten ;w lord,' lie said, I rmeltiolmingl a sin?(iiar a'fitir I leadned jesterday whil-st traversing tle, city.' What is it?' I asked witi iiilifference. It appears,' hl replitpd,' thr,e divs ar) a merchint, one of ollr trafil',r iu'hiam iu flesh, arrived lhere witdi sver:tl Greciatint cat- tivea.  HRe has  ,lispastl ofall liut on](', ail silt' is sotranscondently baautiful, thut h-.lf tile city is in coirotnotion; W(-.trc(: a in Irl y tl mliPet who har seen her. bbut wishs h, ware richl ,\nv t a lord, which they thiuk would en'wltle him to  purchase h-r .' * But how i this/, I enquired, (ow Iaconi-  ing iut::restod,) your story aDpears to t-n eoil-  tralictory.  If this Gt'eRK is so passigrl f :it  Low happans it sh has h-en three d,ty s in tlt eity ai  y,'t not find a ptrchis. r ' S e *ur Pacla's anwl Ag t's hairts are not entrcely in,3enAihle  to ClIP attraction.: of b.'aiity.' I Far lrou it,' ha replied,' hbt th wralhi.-st ( Nabobs ar- uow aDsernt with t113 ;-qiltia ; ais to t*ho e who remaini, sh, i-. fur iyoni rl their mn:icei. HR holds her at sn:h al -normoai,  prite, r. port says, nonrq but th., SUirt;ui or iran Pa(i:ha. Who has gold like a Jew. will o!tain h 'r.' ' "At whiat price do.;s th. inrc:eant hold this u Iarvel?'  I know not, but runior say1 hie a a  wia!/onte 1. of hi-; crita, an-1 awaIrta o(,hle excit!ll ;ut, n)w al ideq hiti o!lmSis vieti u; would y,;i n.,t iito  tee sier, my lord P' 'Iwill think o1 it, prhltp3 ciriosity may in thmpt me to behold this wonl,rfil 'kGreci;,i'. 4ad what tai yoU  Selilm, shall I become her tl   s- purchaser t' sa I iou?' he said with a start, I donubt nt t- yo/ur ability, but surely my lord would not trifle. with- r, ' Nany, aity,' I exclaimed, interrupting him and 'augning at his surprise, I be not alarmed for I have no such intention, 1 was going to rcmtnark,' lihe rei'umed,l ifthe purchase of this fair Grecian, would again re- 1 storj that laugh, the first indieation off'tormer days I have y't seen, I would advise you to F- b,'coinme the purchaser of her ; and now my I lord your pardon for psaving this dull njonoto- e n',us lift will never do for vou. The physi- can in the Levant ssur I I me thalt unless you a. ovr rcmri this sorrowing for the past, these - midnigh-t rovecie, your days would be shoiten- Th'ev   will be long enough at the shorteK I my gool Sefi,' 1 rirnswered, we nmust not al- : wavs credit what the doctor tells u ;but what do, you dcesir niv doitng '?' t ';l'ravel,' he 0replied. *' Iave I not tnraversrd the wide world for ma- ny a year? have wej,not visited every clime?' ' You have,' lie s;id,' but I Iihavt not; in open- ing every laper, is not ,y l()ri's attention, al- wilvs first dir,-'ted to, the land of his birth? Re. turn to-it ut ain.' 'And you .Sclm,' I asked, I would you Icave, Il:3?* ' ar fromti it,' lie alswered, now iruch over- colle" i jhave no conneltions eIrft, no frind but you' Mith vour pernij:--ioi), where VOU go'll roilow; your home as your servant, shall be my' '* 'I'l.,n b, it o,' I answered,' the nited Staftes arc ,i)w rivetin- the , itntion of the world -an cxi'et innt with h,.'r i:istrtions, is, at this tWis abolt theniw: t. ited ;,t it will I return;you shall ncc(m;1U;anyIv I m.3' but not as a ser:-nnt. Rcad ttuis p),!rgriaDl, b)ol(dlv proct)lainiing to the Uni versae," LL, ,MEN A'RrE BOiN FREE AND Ei(U ALt." I .lh! $elimA, Inny not my afflic- tion he a jd,gmcnt upon me,'or notassisting her (iring tl:, I'; rugr o(rdeal, she lias sosticcess ful- ly passeld. 1:,ct it is now too lat-3 to repine; this arrancgemenit h:.s rlivced me of a weight of sorrow.  And to obviate your entire depend- ence upon lt! ,acce5pt th1- g'ift.' I i)ii:ld a valau'blc dihnond, one from the caskct ofAlbdel K(mnish in hjs hnd. 'Oh!"V Iord,' he exclaimed, bathing nmy h:indl \wirth is rars,' Icn accept this, but upon o l,? (.'opdilioni. Nu, Niiut.' * Pet'rit me to retain my situation, and 1 ahall be!h;llppy.' My   !ongtried faidhfil Selim,'I exclaimed with emotion,'r.-sponiibilities have devolved 1]jii)l youl, sinc:e first we mit, anlld been succees- f1illy icco,ilishi: d, thart woul( entitle you to  the iionors (ofl Knilhthood, nnd whut is more, au untaraishcid escutcheon, stiilyou would re, t[l ein  t Set I'Vant.' 'it; hle replied, I can acknowledge a master in C:ou011t I, ftiough, I consent; but shoufd the hand of that master ever be raised ipanger agaiut ejr  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7184-00000019"/> as iervotrd---may enerv sinew in its arm with- or! 'o-morrow we see the tfir captive, and then bend our steps to Lny parent land;yotu may sow retire.' 'It was fite; the house had become silent, al I had resigned themlselves to forgzetfithlnss in rleep, and I had tfillen into a gentVe stumbaer when there was a rap tit thie street door, and quickly repeated; it was nut thl;zt of a mendi- cant entreating alius; nor of thle guest who ex- pects a welcome admtIttacic ;i. was tli, knoeck ofone ho de:Iandls an enltrace Gr;tsip g mny Nword at the same titnme ri,.ilnrthe belIl fi,r Sot * lira, withoullt waiting h is app lin,mt,11, 1 fl \w throo an adjoining pa-:sage,. The moieilt I had slip- pedl the bolt. a p.'rso1n dtlilln;;' llasthy p;sr, rdshed thronlli tihe hal, lbut att its extrelme endI was nlrestlt bI 1y y seIrvanlt. C Sciin t}e d,(,r Iretraced iny stlps, and hnd uadvancad but a short distance, whlm I halted to listeni, attracted by his first question. ' Where is ,ounrt M.' How know you,' asked Selim, I that this is the Co tnt's resilence?' ' Detain me not,' he cried, na:ain en!deavoring to pass ' this is thi,- thouse to wlicil I wJs direc- ted andi 1 illst; ltill sCee him ' I could di tin-uihl liitn sutticiently to per- ceive his dress was in tlme tr.2eci itn F tV,! pt, nd f'rom his counten;inc%, alt-l,o"gh he. n ie- 1 0r.'(d to conceal it, tie could not ia;\e (::c,'F!. ( lthe' age of twentv or lwent on,1, ibut his c5e e di, llo- ted a fixedn-ss of plrlp)ose, a ttil" s:t!l li(is it indicated more of the i-elings of dii;pair, thtii, ven ea nce. 'I am the Counti,' I said ldvancinjr at th- moment Wolf hald escaped t frollm nlY rloolll and wais at the poi:ntof i:ipinlc ;uipon hiill. '  Whyl such intrulsion at this Into hour ;lthink you, niy house is tlja: 'e .-.ort of'; al --l 'Oh!my lur{',' tie exaliimndt, casling hiin.. self at my feet,' save her! save her! ' ;ave her,? I '?rpeat.(d, si've who? .mvo1i rave younpg inttl; collct your tiliot't-lt rnf xplinill yourself 'more tuliy. and .be brief tfr 1 like not this delav.' Oh1! sir,' he said (his emotions, aimost over, coming him) ' if ymu have a n ar 1and (i lr friend, one whoml you lovI I), tthr' tit; i1 lite, lost in all probability to yo)u forev er--Dcrhalps now a wife-- 'Stop,' I criqd, stamping upon the floor, 'touch not that:chord. aitinl.' ' Seilmr,' I continlled, tlurnsin  to my s evant A take cilUrge of him, and when h 1 bhecolmeVs mane, I will listen.' I No, 110,' he exclaeiled, r,-claspfing mv knlera ' hear me now, 1 wili explain al1, fior to no *uie else can I go. He then infi)rmed mne lie wa s a resident of the isiand of Ctan(ina, tihat wh;ilst o()ut whl i part, oi a sailinir esxcUlrin; thlyv ia'l te .u Loarded by an Alg^rine C(ors;;ilr, ail brotinhlt to Constantinrpl.,at whch I)l c,', hie llad dlisl-)os.(i of tall but one. Alh! mv lord, sh ids t vy he- trothedtl;w  are wealthy, buit oti rit:hces tt'a har awy; rescue ltner, a 1d }/,'d3o miy lifl you shtil be ainlJpv cotnpi.-ns letod."  owr happaen it,' 1 asked,} thlat you eecaped'!'   , When we reached the city, the night be*ig very dark, whilst bitt one sentinel paced the. deck ,I sprang into thlla w ater and swam ashori. For tvo day s, in disguise, have I traversed the- city, asking aid, ut lall refused nm.' ' ow knew   ou,' 1 ttskt d that I was in it P, 'I was about to inthrmn you. To-day, air most diiven to dispair, 1 called upon the rich G(reek mrnrchant,. Ivan, but on learning my business, lie turned front me with this remark,. I pity yJou, but I cannot  relieve you ; thfi story goes that Kisia'r Aga, (the chief iu- "u,:lh of the Sultan) designs obtaining her Jut his  atstf'r ; did I aid, you my neck would feel the boow ,tritng in twenty-four dhoulrs. Her fate is sealed-you cannot res. cue lier.  *    'iqen I wi I be sold with her,' I said- ,' .for nmvcr witi lib)ertv will I survive her captivity., I li-id lelt his house when he called upon me to 1ol't'i1I11. ' A thou!ht has jnst struck me,' he remark- iedf1 i csicslr 1-ly learned in a peculiar manner tilat Co(Uit?M. is in tie city ; hs fortune is im- mc.-'c(, tdli ctredit indistpuiable, farthermore, his piper will lbe cance//ed bty nmeto an)- alloun)lilt as I !l a his }tlbakcr (although we have not i;ily ment,) in riclhes tlmat the Sublinia Port;. mlight env;. Tl'h.,t tralficker I know- shI(u'l ,1ot th Kislar Aga be present-hec wilt 1.rdliv'da- Irrle relusesuch an order, with mysig- tli;iiltei u})onll it, (he kfmows it welD as inons ,e'l- [ l;oidhits liie in my gerasp. TakePthit l;itier he' cottinuecd (and the youth hnlned it to n.',) shouii( the Count dare the veniture,let hi:: dtnt;w tite d(raft on ime. luttihat is not all, tile l5.;lt l(is .1n 1)l-n purse, and what perhaps is clt"al:l ,iceqsar),a in yolir Case, a strong r1m  , {5 to liiml, here are the dire;'tionp, for i;auny itman canll gi e you a d it minst be hbm., Stiht iih altdeod aIlter a pause, even then, I fear i tl]e rcjit, for as runmor goas she being of  ler:es s I1uauty, and tie disinterested, the pric. tv. ill b1 enoi rlolus. [ia! ,SMiMt, this ;nust be' the girl you refer-, red tloo,' I si id addressing lhim. ' ' l'lie ,ne.' * '   I)6 you know,' I asked, turning to the yoult ' wl',i s1;11 i:i r qv sitite to efect her liberation T' ' I do lnt; Lbtit it app)[ears the merchant, see- in- ilhe avitditv of soine, has doubled on th lprice, S-nmte hs first l'rrival.' 'l'hl-n it behllooves us to lose' no time, at ; wlat  liour will we be likely to gain adiit- tallt"3 ?' At thr- e o'clo.!q to-morrow, my lord.' , Are ')nI crtain tlat the -Kislar Aga has heard oi it V f   I atil not, hut this I learned, that Sirani Pa- clmi nitrrivcti in t!e city, a few hours since.' , Al- ! 1l kmw him by repute, richl and a&amp;v- i {ic:iio(-, :1s well as cruel, and still they say in Ltw:ithtandil ing his misirly disposition, in thll linrhus ' of' a pretty slave, lie seldom  standi ,lhoult a thlusin;l I I)iastre,; what think you Se- ; lil, it will requtiroe something ieor. than the pisrat. with hil,will it not't i   t wi i sI'f, for he n1ver nloves but with Jaai ismuries sulnfficout to aceoupliah his purpee  1 ' ;'  /'   A-I know it, bua in this affair, have no wish st shun'the encounter * there are now plenty of mercenary Greek soldiers in the city, who, for a full purse, will not ask whether they ,tike for Christian or Turk. Endrage me twelve, with the promise of good pay, whch, it We succeed, shall be d. ub e! ,at thl same time hirea fast sailing vessel, ready by mn  order at a moment's notice, for rest as-uretd if' we accomplish this undertaking, Constanting ple will be no secure asvluim Haste-but Ebalter not 'about the t/ice, and rolemembcr I said, as he was about to leave, the great danger is n our obtaining full possession of the ve ssel, As soon as he was gone, I turned to the Greek, * Take this purse,' f said l; observine him 1hesitate,' this is no'time t;,r idtle cereno- ay; I amn wealthy, and god I Drize not. If we succeed in sect Urin-g this ir i, and rethrn not again, embark in the vessel tthat will be ready for your reception.'  ' Never,' he cri rd, erasping my hand,' Count I leave you not, but, to mo,i row g9o with yo0u.  'Impossible,' I replied,'your d3tection would I defeat our purpose.'            i Observing himi still resolite,' Remain here ( or 1 attempt nOt he: ' liberation.'    t I'Then I obey, but if you fill---- ' It matters not, life to 1 is a Iburthen; the t day is n.)w breaking, pass*not into te stlreet, r and ere night I will see wilat can be etfYect l.' V An(d my happiness or misery settled forev  or,' lie added. Haiing learned the situation of the Imer- I ehant's caravansera, from Alusco, whichl wa s a -the youth's name. I pl acetd a iu'lbnn iuDon my head, in order to (disguise lmyself as m1w:h as  possible, and learning  Selin 1 had b)een suc- g cessful in eno:acinl the Grevek so,lliers I re c quested Ihimr to!psh them on in variois dirc- p tions to hvoid sus)icion, and thenl to coIncel!-. trate in the rear of ii. ,w:wallinff, with stri(ct or- m dl-'s not to Pnter untiil called, uts I wap very a desirous of effc'till Inv pnlrpose without cr,- tting an alarm.  The lhonur had already arri. 1y ved, when he rcLttlred. Arminir nivseif in all hiaste, we imlntdiitt ly pushed on for the Imart. Ii Upon d)r wingl n ar, l')perceived several .ol(diers were guarding it.             '  'DeOtend  uID  it, tltev are Siram Pacha's sI Seiiam,' 1 said,' and it is possible we are al- t ready too late '              tr 'IThey  tre,' le reoplied, and what is still tO worse, they out uinzlllr U ; two to one.'  m Tl'That sirnifines n thinr fitvorail;)e fir hiln,' a I  answered, ' the baildigr is small, and il it nl must this question ba deoitled.      b( Havin- reacheld  the door, i waved my hnnsd tha : for their lead.1r to Inake way, alnd was 'relllut-!ot antlv othyed.   '.They wera all r ;1,d. Piss.  Ing .liractly iito tho, butliinoi, notsvitiistiar!dinll tW Wisr thrintnltgl looks. I t 1 i)jn lmvsif alonet t in a  sn:11 aipartlment  , fir Selim' tId left me bu to h3alz the party (shou!d it bo nrecessarv) fir M Ir reqcun. T'th re was a   smn:ill rIoo' thlat tho lookead iitti an aftlijningr on0, anUi which oCna-- i lled man to B e wit'lout b),in  ) preeived. S3tp- tw plin arftly .tozard d it, my whboie attentiou wall ul   ish at first sight, directed towards a fair Greek.-. ntv BVut once ere this, had I beneld'such lovelinem ho, antd the great similarity between her and my ey lost Eliza, struck me so forcibly, I became me agitatesl, and was obliged to support myPelf Iit against the wall. 'T'he remembrance of one me that was lost to me forever--  1 will save er you fatir Greek,' ] mentally exclaimed, ' or die.' we Her age I judged, not to. exceed sixteen or i- seventeen years. She was sliglit as the Ma- Out ician's wand, and as graceful as an Antelope. cr Her Grecian eves were tfringed with lashes of at the deepest black. Her light fitelre was hab- Of itcd in a blue vest of the richest inatefials, ev- idently intended to entrance the eye of the lie piurchaser. The necklace suspended fi'om her' in throat of the rarest value, was as white as the o- bosom  on which it lested. The sinall feet If were placed tlpon a carpet, that for beauty ot might vie with that of the Sultan's chamber. dy The gold-spangled robe diccovered an ankle of remarkable symmetry. Her beautifully pro-  portioned arins, naked to the shoulders, and i o fbidodt up[on her breat, as the tears were trick. Id ling down her cheeks, would have nmelted a  h^'rt ofstcel. her surptissing b)oauty so riv- re eted nmy attention, I ob)seived nothing else un- til stritled byv a low gruff voice. Casting my eye to anoter part of the room, I perceived e two persons in d(eep conversation It rcqui- t, rert but little disceerimrntnt, to decide who they  were, and if I had tilny doll()ts, thevy were quick-. ly remove"d by what toiowed. ' And the price?' was asked by one ofthem. r- -THe was a  person of ordinary appearance, s about fifty years of age. v7  And the price?' he repeatpd, with one linnd s stroking his heavy l}ard, whilst the otiher wa - grasptintg ighlta i)urse stringf, ut the same tima csitinw his small grey eyes upon his antici- - pated victimn; ' Wlat rshall I say my lord? she alone cost me a fortline, but--and he hesitated, a nmoment  as if weighinrg his words, ' but she is yours.' - ' 'hat is somtetliin/,'  said llhe Pacha, ' sure.: ly, 1ult how mrny ) lpurses did you savtv?' I  ' 'She silgs like a nightingale, and for tel- ling a tille none cln Pe(]ual elr.' ' Allah be praispd!' e(xclainled Sirnm lPPha ' bul alain I ask, whttt is the sum, if the 3slave is mine i?' T')e (T,raning merchant sri, tlthe fame wns in his own hands, nnd like a wary trafficker whi(n drivinig a b)arrain, (continued to extol her merits. ' She moves like a fiwn my lord, and L- Stop,' cie( thie Sntrnp in a louder voice, andr stamlping on the floor, ' by my beard. but i Ihave heard eitough of'tDis-tir bosh-noth incg-once nmore I ask vour price for this Greek?' 'Sixty tlonsnld 'piastres, my lord, I can take no les.' ' Sixty thousan(d ti- astres! one hIiindred aind twentv purses!! is the namle of the Ho ly Prophet, shoutel the star- tted Pacha, ' do yvoi think I nm made ( f gold I but no more of tliis, vile slave, or that short neck  shall he fitted to a i)w string! thirty thoulsan( is  Ino,'e than she is worth.' 'Allal i; gr:t!  bhut I redfrsedl that of(ier fromn Al 1i Ba. two days igo: oIand mv lord the Pachai, may the sul ever light4t? kia path, would not be outdnri,  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7184-00000020"/> y td&amp;' aS'if v I q0, nao, le anuwered, 'le S. but dirt, nay his father's grave be defiled; Ztfil it is-a great sum, she is only a christian after'all; come, I'1 I give you forty thousand, lZere is the wonev,' he added, moving a heavy pnrsa that lay upon the table,' count it. and be quick, my business is of more mnoment, than bantering for a worman.' ' Forty thousand was tendered Ina yesterd'ay,' said thie inexora- ble trafficker, ' and 1 refused it.' ' Cur! dog' ' cried the nowr ,araged Satirap,' bt you are laughing at our beard with vyour offers, every day addingten thousandto her value.7 Sure- ly, mv lordt jests ; three days ogo, I learned that Kialar Aga the light ot the Sultan, mIav his shadow never be less, would vis;it I e to dav,' -nd continued  the lvil rg' merchant loaer- ing his voice and atfecltin a con idential smile, ' his slave offered hiigh to nilain the p)rize for himn.' * Wellaid, my sn,  IulV, th;tt is Illuctl,' said the Satrap,' but sixtv tho usanl! is a great sthll,' he-repeated, p'acing his hland upon the purse and fixing s vis volupl Oyeis  up*on the ilreek, ,but she is lair,"h-' Imlthilredl. '1The quick ear of the merchant hlearld hth. Fair as U oliiti, and if possible still mnre Heanti li, lit for' tl e liareni ofa trn e believer, th sh adow of the Sul- tan, butif my lord thinKs lwr net worth the price.' he saiid, watchingl; tie halnd as it- r laxed upon the purie, ' on.: of less ri'tin .i ' ta^te nmay give, it.' Stepping quickly fiorward,- 'I'raffict- er, I lake you at your otF . r;sixly tloasaH d for this slave, anii Justily DiiciNn i lysvetfi his sid(e, I whistercd thie nalle (tal,Vii whilt pres'nll- In'tthe paper His tace ill?,t4ttly bh"camle livid as that of a cvorp.:e, and Ills fi'[ame .h koS I ike the Aspen leaf. I perceived the Greik was cnrrect, aid i lhat hls sg;,a lure had op;erated like a spell o:'.ichuntlnenlt .' -lo! il()r ot a ehristian,' exelaimled tie SlatraD p, rec,gn izintr me notwithls:;itnd(iag rrl 7 tlrba , aniid sicuing towards the d(oor. iisiting ,Iyse/l bcoire him, I had ibi a momeln  sectired %it wi. ii a heavy bar. Upo-rc hI llyi,: nyl y succnes., wihich p!'eveiiied the tn;rl;inoe f lhis si,- diers, his fury kln w ni, t.) uths, but drawiuvvi his weapon, he sprnlg iouw;ard, mne  Our sword-i had hardly rsse', crc a sinmall pan- el that I had not b;fore perceived was r.:Iniv- ed, and a boy ofa?nt-li'iini ;i ,:/;.'c;/n'e, and richlly atlir6d enteteid. W'lihut h.-c Iti  I uSj. he directed hiis steps t ,w' rits t- ti,';t,.:l;ker; 1 (obtervedt etl'e a w't!p)-rn/. ftir Sil,1 Pacha had dropped I hi- -woid II,)on lit, Hen- tralnce and cnr:.-eq inl!y ' lsij lieb t He ,en us had creasred, aiw when* Issaw the inetlh- ant's cou ntenanve isvilen* i. ti, )oerai e, 'aiticipating ihe result, i laid m!y Iaper p'pon (he t bl". As s    ...  1"- ic',iv',d it. he addriesseed e C Yo I7. I   ooU Kislar Aza ,-eads wtd ihi t h- t ill bte be'e Jium- tialely, anii ,i ri,: s ie - . p, ieril o my heat to r-tlarn!he .l-iv'.'  Y Your prive )h a be,.n fixedl,' sldt,' and til.. i)per which will obtain Uie  ,td I(;ud-rld ; lie ih'ek is mine,  sl id is il more th;t yo..ir   life is worth-, to w oUld her."' aek dea O' I cried, as he' stepped in before me, at the same timne hurling him against the wall. Rushing towards Irena on the in- stant. I had seiied her by the arm, and' whispered,' IBe not afraid, I am your friend ' A rude hand was laid upon my shoulder; all was the wovk ofa momrent. I looked up and beheld the Kislar Aga,. the Sultan's chief eninuch standing by me. * Are you mad?' he asked; 'but I will not dailv words with hm, does the fool resist the orders of the lioht of the worldI ho. sl;ves! bring me the bow string.' But the Janissarieq, willing enough were as yeC unable to effect an entrante;their eries. were tremendous, as with fury I could hlar them driving a heavy bit of timber against the dor, at every shout it shuok 1lpoih itl hinges. ', Yes,' I answered, 'clas--, pinz frena. and placing myself firmly be- tfore it, ' back caitiffs, were he twentyr t m nes tlIe ulilan I wou ld beard him as I do his..lave..' Both the Eunuch and Pacha itler d a cry oi .horor at my audacity, fo(r I had become reckless, the tormer with his p,ninrd, the I:tter with his scimetar, rnshed upon me, but in a mument the Kis. lar Apa ay dead at my feet. ' Now Pa- cha,'I said, at the same tlime supporting Irena, who was becomipg ilnsfenrible, ' let me pss,. or bhy the soul )t1 your false proph- et, eter'nity is vpon. you;' ' Never,' he an swered, thr;ustin. his weapnn towards me r he %was mozee skillfill than I expected, but the n(oise be4hind me added vig'or to my arnm, when raisi!)} my sword I directed it ,owards his hilt, and in il. half downward' cours-e, skillfully swayed the weapen an2f hrouzht it- keen edge with full force upon. hi- ,n aled elbow. T'le dropping of that linb upon lhe ftl or sufficient y acce untct for ihat crv of ngony. I'ut then to escape was ip,lpssible, f or with a shout of tri- uliph, that slookl the very building to its 1,f0}nidatin1. h( dot),' was Iorreqd from its hinp s and dli-rin'into the centre of the r.,rth; ')wa t:len I gave the sign;l, my ment answe ttd me from wilholt, and directly qt'ier entered at an o)pposile oasage. At the. mnment o' giving it. I had faced my ol-p',veqts re-,clved to repel them, until Seil, cnld esc;-pe with Ilena. The pas- sa;^-, be(nz narrow, ave rne much the ad-. v'rnl:-e as ,but one could cro-s weaponh xwi;h me at a time. ' Fiv Selimr!' I cried, and pointing to the Greek who lav insensi- bje npon the floor but instead of .beyino ime. he placed hirn-elf bv mny side. ' SSiim , ever fie,' heo , plied,' whbe. !I,'i t,'lster i- in danger, btut tha! blow has :r ,aytd hitm for the piesent/, he aide4, and   I preelvedl -the -eader of the arailants fall a corpse before me. Irena .had for -a moment drawn my attention, and he laking the advantage, was making a thrust at my breast, when Selim staved his arin forever. ' To you,' I said, I amtn indebied for my life, but I shall -rescue that Greek or perish;'you must ob y me, for her es. ,ape is our preservation.' He appeared now for the first to fullv comprehend me ' I see it tny master, but I shall return again,' raising Irena in his arms, he had in a moment left the room.' Come on my men,' I cried, now for the first alarmed for my own preservation, when I perceived The men apparently stupified with horror whilstgazing at thecorpse ofKisar Aga  I, was a deedof daring thebo!tlest of them 3 would not Ilave tempted. '- To the-rescule,  fools!'I shouted, almost distracted at thir 1 'timidity, and aware 1 was lousing ground ' with mv assailants, do you fear a dead Eut- E 'nuch, more than the Sultan's bow string? for 9 'by heavens! the defeat of his myrmidons, is f your only safety.' . Aroused to their danper t by this assersion, -they rushed to nmy assist-.  ance, and in a short time we hIad repulsed e the foe. ' Let us fly my good fellows,' I ex  claimed, giving them a purse of gold. At "the same time, it being now darlk, I dartel h down a narrow  passage and reached mr s: house in safety. On  entering, I perceiyed n Irena lying upon the floor. ' Irena,' I whis- I pered, as I raised her in my arms. ' Oh!' a she sobbed grasping my  hand,4 you area a '*hristian' yet I know not you; motive in pur t. chasing me, surely the kindness that has 1 already transpired will not be obliterated by- 41 ' I will soon shew you, I said smilingly le interrupting her, ' r main here for a few nilo. 1 ments and fear nothing.' Closing the door, w I passed to another part of the building and ce motioned Alasco, to followr When I again in vntered her room, and they beheld each oth- w r,  '-Alasco!' ' rena  !' This was all cc that'they could utter as they rushed into up each others arms. '- Oh 1 our preserver!' they sa 'both exclaimed, now turning to me. ' how fin -shall we ever cancel this debt?  ' It is al- I ready cancelled,' I replied, in this meeting.' ki I  was interrupted by the appearance of vil "elim, Ha'!' I asked, alarmed at his pale in 'looks, is not the vessel ready?', It was my int lord, half an hour ago.' , Then let'a loose co mo time,' I hastly remarked, ' for the fall of we the Kislar Aga  will arouse the whole city, coi and if we are not off soon, escape is impos. the sible.' ' Then we are. lost,' he exclaimed.- col "ost,' I repeated, 'did you not tell me is  the vessel was ready?' I I did my lord, but der rader having been sent to all the Captains lv t f remain until daylight, the one I engaged   wig  omd  ina 4  *lm , now poidiy m   Its refuses to weigih anebar u snd my . monstrating with him fir such aonduct, h* t threatenecd to put me in irons for my insolene. n d Htas he not remuneration for his antioi- eI pated services?' I rsked. ' He has, and hen ed is the contract. Closing the paper immediF ,e ately, I turned to my guests, ' We have but ed one course to adopt, and .it must' be execu- e ted at once; it is to obtain full possession of ne. that vessel, and if we fail, we are irrevocal- rd Iy lost.' The whole city was now inf corn-' iy motion, -for -the alarm lhad become gen- ,r eral, but by taking a circuitous route, we Id reached the wharf in safety. ' My lads,' I or said, directing my remarks to four' oarsmen a] aboard a small water craft, ' your price for n placing me upon that vesseC?" 'Twould be e, as much as our heads are wort your honor, ir to attempt it .; orders 'are given that no man d embarks to night. The Kislar Aga has been I- slain, 'tis said, and the Sultan haspsworn ven- ,r geance upon his murderer ; may the foul s fiend slay his master too, what right had he {r (o the girl? Had I been there; by the Holy  Prophet! my sword, by the side of her deliv- erer, should have been drawn,' was uttered in a low voice, and in it I recognized a Greek, t ' Nanme your price,' I said, (encouraged o by this discovery) and be quick, (for the. j shouts of the soldiers were evidently drawing u nigh) name your price, and it shall be doub- led.' After whilpering a moment the Greek arose, ' If my lord would pay us 200 piastres, hl e said, ' it should be done, ini defiance of the Sultan, may his shadow soon he less. r nd all1 his cuised Pachas.'  You shall have 400 nmy good fellow,' I exclaimed, as we leaped into the boat, but in 'God's name loose no time,' I added. ' for the Janissariee , ere now upon us.' They had grasped the cable when i severed it with my sword, and in a  moment wo  were scudding ovfr te waves. When I reached the vessel, I pla. ced Irena in the arms of Alasco, and leaped upon the deck  ' Tle Captain ofthis craft,' I said as a sailor accosted me. ' You will find him in the cabin.' Hastily descending I  perceived him lying upon the floor, smo- king his pipe of cherry wood. U pon obser- ving me, he arose at the same time taskirb in a  haaghty tone' what I meant by suili intrusion?' Did you charter this veselei^ convey hence some. persons at a moiaeut warning?' '.I did,' he replied as he again commenced smoking, ' but it is mv opinion that some of them will take a longer and a colder one ere morping;:the Sultnn's mck is well freighted now adays, and the mm. dererof the Kishr Aga' (he looked eospicloW Iv upon me) * will snon take his last jorney%' ' lave done with this tri'fling,' I eai .' I am the pomo wkM *n4gged tWis To4l;  ad4  &#xD;<pb n="40" xml:id="VAC7184-00000021"/> ] wish you to raise your anchors instantly.'  'impossible!' he continued, starrting back,  ' I move not an anchor before daylight.' ' It matters not,' I remarked, coolly drawing a pistol from my breast,' but-if she is not di- rectly got under way, she will need a coin- mander ere morning.' Hold!' he ejaculated, observing me cock my weapon, 'I obey you,' at the same time liewwas moving to- wards the companion way, ' Stop!' I said, placing myself before him, 'I know your inten ion, but 'twill not do; let us understand each other; I am the person who slew the chief Eunuch, but I did it in-self defence.- I see you do not credit it, but that ma;ters little too me. Aware of the daltger that awaits me should I be arrested by the city guard, I have boarded your vessel with the fixed resolution of escaping ;without your aid it is impossible, and we perish. But as sure as there is a God above us, that refusal seals ,your fate, for your soul precedes, not follows mine into eternity. I am willing to admit the risk is something, but to counterbalance it, the amount shall be trebled. Noti swear as you hope to enter paradise, that this con- tract shall be fulfilled,' and I placed the paper before him. The alternative also I con- tinued, raising my weapon--chooFe, but -ahoose quickly.' fie stood for several mo- ments, eyeing me closely when observing my :xed purpose,' Christian, he said,' I swear.' Then follow ine.' We both gained the deck together; hastily giving his orders, the vessel was soon gently moving over the wa. ter. Our passage to the island of Candia, *proved favorable, and with a heart full of joy did I witness the meeting of the parents of Alascoand Irene with their children. But when the particulars were unfolded, their feelings overcame them, they hung upon my shoulders and wept; gratitude, inexpressible gratitude,was theirs. Witnessing at a dis- tance, tje seizure of their children, they knew it was intended as an ignominious captivity to one, and a life of bondage worae than death to the other; and when all expectation of their final restoration had vanished, when clad in mourning, they had resigned them. selves to a life of sorrow and dispair, giving up even that last vestige of solace--Hope and looking to time's raising the veil of the future, and unfolding to them eternity, as the laee of final reeting. At that period, we   entered their minasid.- - t- t a e ahi tsi rest, for tny pen is inadequate to do it jus tice; suffice it,! might there again have. found a home. My visit was long, when af- ter witnessing the union of Alasco and Irbna and, notwithstanding the most urgent re- monstrances made with tears and entreaties which had almost changed my purpose, I placed Irene lainting in the arms of her hus- band and bade them a last and solemn adieu. I cmbaiked on board an American vessel and propitious winds favoring us, we safely ar- rived in the city of New Orleans. For sev- eral years my course had been onward, trav- ersing akhn:st every country and every climef and now returniitn to that of my birth, curi- osity led ime to visit the various states, which having accomplished, I reaedled n2 inative village by an extra conveyance from New York. Oh! inm country! my country! I left you when bat a vol:th, retiurning at an advanced age in coniMi'in^g you with the old world, how stri- king the contrast. Born under the yoke of despotism,; cradled in the lap of aristocra- cy ;sus( rvient to the greatest maritime pow- er upon record, with a giants ehiorti, she has cast her fetters from her, and proclaiming to the astonished world "that all men are born free and equal," mnay now, united as she is proudly (Iety the universe in arms. 'The' n iihy po vers of Europe, are watch- in'g cu ; ihey fear, but they dare not molest; an asylni, for her oppressed plebians, whosa- low intincrings, like the distant thunder, yet portendls a learfl't outhreak ; well may her ar- istoerncv treinble at our unexampled republic- canl gr-t;ntlcp(s:. NoDle iron handed sops of Amlerica! Let the sHae h'earts that throbbed , i the br'asts of vour forefathers,and u hich has tunscathld descenoced( to that of their sons, let it but rremainll pure, fnearlessly opposed to op. presaiion, and the thanded powers of Europe, mllay coalesce ag;inst you. They who have already become so sensitive to yonr colossal grettne-ss, nai view wVitlh alarm allied to fear your rapid expl:insion, may conlcentrate their inrliad hio-ts, may collect such an Armada as as has not been seen since the days of Eliza- beth: no, not then, may cross the broad Atlan- f tic-may assail our sea coasts-land upon our frontier-'tw itl all he in vain;their days of conquest on this continent are over; they will be huoiltd back to their own shores in confu- sion and disgrace, never, never, to return.-- The American itepublic stands proudly preA ' eminent, an example to all the world of the 'capability of the people, without the diaimo4i of govUrning thOUemulvo   TRX END.   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>