<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7116">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Harry Todd, the Deserter, or, The Soldier's Wife </title>
            <author >Long, R. H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7116</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Harry Todd, the deserter, or, The soldier's wife</title>
                  <author >Long, R. H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >58 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >American News Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1864">1864</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-27">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Harry Todd, the deserter, or, The soldier's wife</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7116-00000001"/>HARRY TODD,  THE DESERTER ;,   OR, THE SOLDIER'S WIFE.    WITH   SCENES OF THE PRESENT REBELLION.   BY R. H. LONG.   NEW YORK: AMERICAN NEWS COMPANY, PUBLISHERS' AGENTS. 121 NASSAU STREET. 1864  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7116-00000002"/> Entered, according to A   Ceto gro, 1 the year 1864,-by I/ H. L-O X  In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Western Di1tr of Pem  lvq uK m   Stereotyped by STrra &amp; lODOAa   , 8-2 - 841 Beekman Stree, N. rY. J   Qy HARRY TODD, THBE DESERTER; , '. . * *. 1  THE SQL!IE'R'S WIFE.  /   aA PTE:K L IT was, on a beautiful evening in the,. month of May, 1861, that we are about to introduce the reader to one of those pice  tureaque: towns which are chiefly to be' found in our agricultural districts, and with- out which no American landscape'wodld bo cgmplete.,              , As the following tale, is to"a considerable extent' founded upon facts, which we are. c9pe4led for reasons that will develop them- selves in the course of the narrative, to be-: atow names of our own choice upon-the lead- ing characters, in order, to avoid that identi- fication of persons which would arise from maintaining their real n Omes. For a similar reason we are led to substi tute a dierent name for that of the town to which we have alluded: and we will there- fore denominate it Newport. The time, to, see this picturesque village in the perfection- of its beauty, was in the gay spring season, when frosts haviang taken their flight, every day developed some new feature of loveliness in the rural scene. It was tere that a young man in a laborer's garb was wending his way along the bank of the little streamlet towards the woods through which it flowed.' UHeo was about twenty-two years of age-' tall, remarkably upright, and with nothing of the rolling, slouching gait that generally charncterizes some mechanics. There was a certain elasticity visible in all his mptions; and though his pace was now slow, his man- ner dejected, and his looks desponding, yet was that natural litheness of limb still appa' rent, Though his garb was of the. humblest mate- rial, and, though-he had just ,come from his work .yet was, his person scrupulously, clean, It is, tu, '.that'on leaving thoe shop be had hastened,to his abode to cleanse away the traces of his labor ere he Met out again on his wak along the streamlet's bank: but :t at all gnO sa, d. undper al circumstaned, there was lair ot feaplines. and respocabfity abtii   Harry Nd4 that pewed,  inv wet him'wit7. i a sort of' superiority ai;bove his -fel!owsa H, wa a dclid:dly handsorme; and' thero was nothing cor" noir vulgar ia his' featurred, norI in the expression of his,'couhtenan*o.: Brpowned it 'was wItl the sun: but tis 6cot tributed to tho manly honesty of look chartc C tiziriing the individual who eamedtiiasbadi by his own toil. Xit bai dark haif' adI eyes, good whiskers, and set of teetlh which any aristocrat tnight-have envied. . i:eh,'b. spoke, it' was with, no pecitliar accent'nor. i rusic dr;aw'; and fis 4annguage. ;maiked , by a sihngular aicuracj for; one it' hi'p ititin, !Hii parenta both died whiil ' ie wi ia io infancy,' gnd he was reardI' by a widow named- G^i4'f. A'S H'Arryi,'grw p, tw' e a d ily devoured al1 the bboks at he coiuld p'o sibly obtain: and thus had he mleiatl added to the store of laiowledg . de/;ved from the schoiintter's slender. stock. In this tan^ner hbad' he reached the age of eigh teeni old Mr. 'Grant loving hir a' aiFtion atelj as if he were her oun son, but ji j ^ future':plans 4ppeared to bo-e chalked 'ut for ' the" young roian. Tfb schoolmastr lad thought' o'f taking him for ah 'astant" death, however, interfered with thin arrange merit, aris thO pedagogue was gathered to his f     aher/ bnat the s :hade of the pies 'in the churchyad c   , bhon aftelrwtards a 6to broke out .ii r. Grants- otte onpe ni'git, wheU Harry Todd wat absenri on io etormims- fOmr ni agei benefacties.  Te plac ws biirnttoX' the ground, she hr1elf, iOrthin iln the rim4 S and, on ig retumi, he fouutdiimselfdeprived Of his only friend-ho'meiess 'and penniles As a 'matter of 66urse le exrien'eed, sy^ paty a4nld atenmsorar asrstai i ' i  pth:e aFrt of'the -kibahearer(4 pe,6pl 'of the pace, but his '.spiit ,wa too.. proud p*   'titt',h' . oremain , burden ' 'te o, ,)ce e  . h t therefor at 'once 'rWloledo f! Woki fop hL own li*insg. At'ovtter-te, erhadeee hia owa d   ieoa f  cthI;^o aiiii, o6&amp; q^   ^  m ^^o    l'; t  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7116-00000003"/> cise of Harry's talents in this sphere. There I were plainly two alternatives before him.: I one was to go and seek his fortune elsewhere, ( the other was to remain in the village and I become a mechanic. He would have done 4 the former, Hiad 'nOt there bBen a certain tie "i which bound him .to. Newport: and so he adopted the latter alternative. He bore a most excellent character in the village, although he was generally considered, : to be his own enemy in one respect: name- ly, that he had a spirit somewhat impatient of control, and n ever:cringed' nor played .a fond part towards the' boss or the foreman, both of whom were such high and mighty people in the eyes of the citizens. The reader has now learned as much as it is necessary for us to tell him in respect to Harry Todd, whom we must accompany. in his walk along the bank of the little river. Ho soon reached the wood, and still follow- ing the course of the stream, 1Bah the shaderof the over-arching trees, ina few minutes reached the rude briage 'which. spanned the stream. There he was very shortly joined by a young woman'of whom we must say something. Annie Bell was the daughter of William Bell, the foreman of the shop of Mr. John Thurston, where Harry Todd was employed, She was twenty years  of age, and exceedingly beautiful. Tall'and well-made, there was a certain air of gen- tility about Annie which raised her abovo the ordinary average of the rustic maidens,' as Harry himself was superior to the youths of tie neighborhood. She had dark brown hair of singular richness; her eyes were of the deepest blue, and the brows handsomely arched. Sweeter lips were never seen; and when parting, they displayed a faultless set of teeth. She was dressed neatly and plain- ly; yet did her apparel set off the admirable contour of her shape more attractively than the richest raiment could have done. Though what may ba termed a well-grown young woman, her symmetry was perfect. Budh was Annie BeL . And now. the reader can be no longer at'a loss to under- stand the secret tie which had bound Harry Todd to the town. He and Annie had lopg loved each other. 'But'wherefore have we spoken of the tie binding Harry to Newport as a secret one? ' Because. he had never avowed his love for Annie to her father. Mr. Boil, being in good circumstancebs, had loftier views on behalf of his daughter; iadoed, his'a'mbition had soared so high that ho had flatterjd himself her exceeding beauty might evenaptivate Horatio Thurston, the only son and heir of Mr. BelTis emiployer. Of course, in makIng this' calculation, M. Bell knew pe'rfectl well thiat Mr. Thurston would never willingly consent to. such a match; but as the property was entailed, and when young Hobratio should come of ago he might do' as hbe iked anid snap his finger   at his father. So thought Mr. Bell; and from these simple facts the reader nmy at once gather that he was rather an unscrupu- lous man. Such indeed. he was; and being of so designing a character, was not without aconsummate dissimulation to conceal it. He was a widower--Annie was. hi only child-and he hoped by seeing her become "a lady," he might, with a sort of,borrowed reflection of lustre, rise to the rank of a gen- man.      -  On the evening in question, Harry Todd and Annie Bell met at: the -bridge a little before the sunset hour. Yes--at that bridge where they had often met before, and at that same hour which had likewise so fiequently . marked these past meetings. It was with a light, elastic step and with smilespon her beauteous countnnance, that Annie tripped across the bridge to join her lover; an in the first gush of pleasure at the meeting,e did not perceivo the sadness which sat upon his brow. They had not. proceeded far, however, when Annie, in making some observatior, bent her beautiful eyes upon Harry, and was struck by the sadness of his looks. She suddenly stopped short in what she was. saying-stopped short also on the bank of the stream; and gazing upon him in silent earfestness, said, in tones as liquid as the musical flow of the crystal waters themselves: "Harry, dear Harry, something. has occurred--you are unhappy." "I cannot conceal it from you, beloved Annie," answeried the young mani. "I have. been insulted-almost trampled upon by one whom the accident of birth ilas made what the wtorld calls my superior." "Who has done this?" inquired Annie, suddenly becoming painfully excited. "Horatio Thurston," returnedd  Harry. "When I think of what took pl:co, I am surprised that I restrained my Iand from tearing him off his horse and spurning himat my feet. But it is not the mere sense of ter- rible insult which now oppresses me; it is also the fear of a sad, sad change in my cir- cumstances, poor as they already atrel" "What mean you, dear Harry?" inquired Annie, with a startled look of fresh appre- hension. "I mean," was Harry's excited reply, "that the insolent Thurston, not contented with flinging at me the bitterest taunt,-has threatened to deprive me of my bread.'", He has vowed' that I shall work for his father no longer, and that I he will take suffi- cient measures to prevent me from obtaining employment at the hands of his father. -The excitement of anxiety dying away from Annie's countenance, was succeeded by a look of'deep dejection; and for upwards of a minute there was a pause, during which the lovers walked with the slow pace of sad- ness along the bank of the stream. -At length Annie again stopped short saying   somewhat abruptly, "You have not told me, dear Harry, the nature of this quarrel be- tween yourself and Mr. Thurston." "You know, dear Annie, for we have fre- quently spoken on the subject. before, that I amn no great favorite with Mr. Thurston or his son; and I think} it is because I have been decently educated, and have added as well as I could to my little stock of knowl- edge. People in high life don't like humble peons to have much learning; they think it opens their eyes to the injustice of the sys- tem which keeps the millions poor that the few may be, rich.; and because I have been heard to say so, I have been accused as you know, by Mr. Thurston, of disseminating seditious ideas amgngst the people of the neighborhood." "But - you are such a general favorite, Harry," said Annie, gazing up admiringly in her lover's countenance, "that they would not dare outrage general opinion by any open and unprovoked act of tyranny." "That is the exact truth of the case, dear Annie," exclaimed Harry. "But now I fear an opportunity presents itself, and the ty- ranny will be exercised. I will, however, come to the point. This afternoon I was working in the shop when Mr. Thurston rode by on horseback. I touched my hat\as a matter of course, but lhe took 'no notice of me. Ever since his return from New York * he has treated me in this haughty manner; but I can assure you it gave me not much concern, for I was resolved to avoid as far as possible affording the slightest opportunity tor the visitation of the tyranny whichh I nevertheless apprehended. Well, Horaio Thurston, who was riding unattended, passed the shop, and presently I heard him crying out in his weak, sickly voice, 'I say, you fellow Todd, come here 1' My first thought was to disobey a command so imperiously  given; but curbing my annoyance, and true  to my resolve not to suffer myself to bo easily provoked, I hurried to the spot where he had halted. Pointing with his kid-glorved  finger upon the ground, Horatio Thurston i said, 'Pick up that riding-whip.' I felt the i color mounting to my face, and I recollect that I threw upon him a look of irrepressible indignation. the saw it at once, and flying  into a rage exclaimed, ' You beggarly clod- e hopper, make haste and pick up that whip, ' or 1 shall jump off and- lay it about your shoulder s.' Annie, I could no longer control f myself."                i "No, Harry," said the young damsel, her r cheeks now flushed with the crimson glow t of indignation at the bare idea of the treat- i: ment which her lover had experienced; "I c can well understand that you lost all patience e then, and it would even .have shown a .lack of spirit if you had tamely submitted. But it proceed. What followed?"       'o "Mr. Thurston's rgo, grew ungovernable, h   , hi pale, sickly countenance became livid, - his lips turned ashy white, and he poured forth a volley of abuse. I listened until tlo had filished his tirade, and then I remon- [ strated with him upon the impropriety of his r conduct. But still I allowed his riding whip e to remain on the ground where it had 3 dropped. My words, and my demeanor too,  I suppose, almost maddened him; and find- a ing that I would not stoop to pick up his : whip he gave vent to the threats,which I - have before ,described. Therefore I expect 3to be summarily dismissed from my employ. ment, and it will be your father who will 1 have to pronounce my dlischarge." "Alas, Harry, these are indeed ill tidings," said Annie. "What is to be done? Shall I .throw myself at my father's feet and be- seech him; if he would not plunge you into wretchedness, to listen to my prayer. "I"Not for worlds," responded Harry, "I will keep all my calamities to myself. Hither- to I have cherished the hope that fortune would develop some turn in my favor, so that I might acquire a position that would enable me to claim your hand, but I feel now that there is a time coming when we shall have need of all our fortitude; indeed, the time is come, and we must look our position 'calmly and resolutely in the face." "What do you mean, Harry, your words *terrify mel" and Annie gazed upon him with a half friglitened, half deprecating re- gard. "I mean that it is wrong for me to keep you entangled by pledges which you have given, but which must leAd to nought. In a word, it were better that we should part, that you should study to forget me." "Enough, Harry, enough, I cannot insult you with the suspicion that you are seeking a release from the vows which we have mutually pledged. We have known each other from childhood, and I am too well ac- quaiAied with tho nobility of 'your nature to entertain such an opinion of you. Listen then while I tell you, that happen what may, no matter how far your enemies may succeed in persecuting'you, my love for you shall continue unchanged." "Dearest Annie, what can I say, I will not reject the hope which has hitherto in- spired me, nor suffer my spirit to sink bo. ,reath tihe' weight of despondency." The lovers appeared suddenly to .have forgotten all their cares, and were indulging in a fond embrace, when an ejaculation of mingled astonishment. and rage fell upon their ears, and starting asunder, they stood in a kind of guilty confusion in the presence of Mr. Bell, Annie's. father, who had just emerged firom the depths of the wood. "Vile, deceitful, girl!" he exclaimed. "is it for this that those frequent evening walks 'of yours have been taken? But you villain," he added, turaing his wrathful looais upon  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7116-00000004"/> Harry, "how dare, you 'thus seek -to rob me h1 of my daughter?" ,t "' Mr. Bell," answered Harry, who quickly sE recovered his presence of mind, ",it is an d honest love I bear your daughter, a love h which mutually felt, has ripened. from our 1l childhood."             '  "No more," ejaculated Mr. Bell, "not another word upon the subject," and clutch- J ing his daughter violently by the. arm, he fa drew her towards him. "You will come with me, and I will take care to put an end s to your rambles. As for you, Todd, I have v but a few words to say. I was proceeding v to your lodging to tell you that by Mr. "a Thurston's command you are to seek em- is ployment elsewhere. Here is a month's o wages for you, and the sooner you get out t of the town the better."        a As he thus spoke he tossed a few pieces 1 of silver at the feet of Harry, who was standing about three yards distant, then X suddenly turning round he dragged his,  daughter with him. -  Harry remained riveted to the spot, gazing 1 after the retreating forms of Mr. Bell and his daughter; then as they speedily disappeared J from his view, he turned abruptly round and E plunged into the thickest of the wood, there 2 to give way to the anguish that filled his ( heart. But the money that Mr. Bell had so r contemptuously flung down was left un-' headed upon the bank.          1 1 CHAPTER II. WILLtAM BELL, the fatlihr of the beauti- ful Annie, was a man of about fifty-five yea rs of age, of middle stature-not stout, but very strongly built, and possessed of great physical strength. His voice was 'harsh and disagreeable; his manner was usually cold, reserved,' and conveying the impression of a stern, implacable disposition. When he conducted her away from the spot where the scene with Harry Todd;had taken place, he maintained a stern silence for at least ten minutes. Daring this inter- val the extremity of the wood farthest from the town was reached; and the father and daughter proceeded to thread a path which led to the town. ": And so, Annie," said her father, at longth breaking silence, "you have held clandes- tine meetings with this Harry Todd, and have given him evidently the utmost encour- agement that a young lady can possibly give under such circumstances? Doubtless the usual lovers' vows 'have passed between you?" :: Rather," replied Annie, with a firmness of voice that was inspired by the candor of   her nature and ;the artless purity of her thoughts, "not for a moment longer will I seek to disguise from you -the truth, that I do love Harry Todd-love him with all my heart and with all my soul, and ,eaan never love another Il It is true .also that I have pledged my faith to him." "Annie, have I deserved this of you? Am I not your father, and have I not done a father's duty toward you,?" "I do not seek to justify it," she an- swered, merely to extenuate it. "That I was wrong to meet Harry clandestinely I will not deny; but, oh father, I knew- ' alas I I knew too well-that, situated as he is, it were useless to beseech your assent to our love. And yet often and often have I thought of throwing myself at your feet, and imploring you, as you valued my happi- ness, to yield that assent." "Annie," responded Mr. Bell, "you know as well as I can tell you, that it would be sheer madness for you to throw yourself away upon a poor penniless laborer, who at this very moment is out of work,." "1 And why is he out of work?" exclaimed Annie, warmly. "Do you know the circum- stances? Father, I conjure you, if you have a generous feeling in your soul, that you will exert your influence with Mr. Thurston to ,obtain justice for Harry." By this time they had reached their habti- tation; and Martha, the servant girl, opened the door. Annie hurried up to her -chamber, threw aside her bonnet and hllawl, and, sit- ting down, gave vent to tier feelings in a flood of tears. This outhurst of anguish to a, certain extent relieved her. and in a few moments Martha tapped at the door to itti- mate that her father was waiting for her to descend to supper. The father and daughter sat down "together,; but the former ate tot with his wonted appetite, and the latter par- took of nothing. "It is necessary,". said Mr. Bell. "that we should return to the subject of our recent discourse, even though it is an utpleasant one. But while it is still fresh in our minds, we had better talk :it out to the; cidl. Then I mustche explicit," observed Mr. Bell quick- ly; " for after what has occurred this even- ing, it is :useless to, conceal my views any longer. Annie," he added, bending forward and looking his daughter full in the face, '"which would you rather do-become the wife of a wretched mechanic, and dwell in a beggarly lodgingo, or espouse a young gentleo- man of rank, with a certainty of possessing I a fine fortune and living in a mansion?" Still did Annie gaze upon her father in ) vacant bewilderment. Her suspicions seem- a ed confirmed. a  She fancied that she comprehended him; and yet she dared not say to herself that it s was so. f  -If she. did, her father would s-ddenly ap-   pea to her in a new light; and ie pure soul reeoiled from the idea of regarding him as such. She felt as if she'were in a dream, with her thoughts in confusion, yet a strange sinister light penetrating their cloudiness. The color had forsaken her cheeks. She sat still and motionless, in a sort of fright that was subdued by dismay. "Annie, won't you understand me?" ex- claimed her father, with anger in his tone. "This is too much. If all your thoughts are bent-upon that good-for-nothing fellow, I shall know how to drive them out of you. I don't think you will be disobedient enough to maintain any correspondence with him; and I should be sorry to have to say that I will keep a watch upon you. But this I do tell you-that you must' follow the course I point out. You at length know what I mean, and it is for you to obey. I am sure that when you come to think calmly upon the affair, you will fall into my views. You would be mad if you did not. But it is im. possiblq that you have no ambition. Every handsome and intelligent young woman has. You will get over this sentimental love fit of yours much sooner than you expect- particularly when you see that my scheme begins to work well. and that the fish nib- bles at the bait." "Father, no  more-no morel" almost shrieked forth Annie, as she started from her seat. "Even if my heart 'were not pledged to another, I would not lend-myself to such a scheme as this.  No, I would "But I say that yau shalll" ejaculated her father fiercely; and, seizing her by the wrist with a sudden wrench almost brutal in its violence, he compelled her to sit down again. "There has has been too much non- sense already, and I will put up with it no longer. Instead of covering you with re- proaches for your secret meetings with that fellow Harry, I spoke to you kindly; but if kindness will not do, I shall show you that I know how to use harshness. I tell you that it is in your power to ensnare the heart of that half idiot boy, Horatio Thurston, in so inextricable a maze that to possess you he will consent to anything. Of course I mean marriage, and nothing else. Leave it to me to bring about opportunities aid to throw you together. But it will then be for you to play your part; and, by heaven, it shall be played, and well too, or I will show you- that I am  of a disposition not to be trifled with. So, now you understand me." "Yes, too well, father," replied Annie, with a deep mournfulness of tone and a despairing look. Then again rising from her seat, she took up a candle and hurried from the room. That was the first time since her earliest years that she had ever sought her chamber. without bidding her father good night -and:   kissing his cheek, but on this occasion she could not do it-no, she could not. We must now introduce our readers to Mr. John Thurston, the father of Horatio Thurstdn, and his family. 'Mr. Thurston himself was ,a man of about fifty years of age; we may add that he was a tall, fine looking man. He loved to dress in what he called good style. Mrs. Thurston was about ten years his junior, and was an ex- ceedingly handsome woman.  Mr. Thurston ,owned a very extensive machine shop, and had over five hundred hands in his employ; and Mr. William  Bell was the ,foreman of this shop. Mrs. Thurston, as well as her husband, considered that the working classes were born for the mere purpose of fulfilling the part of serfs and bondsmen to the higher orders; and therefore any one who dared entertain a different opinion, was at once set down as a wicked, seditious and evil dis- posed person. Miss Thurston, the sister of Mr. Thurston, was a lady of very nearly tihe same age as her sister-in-law, Mrs. Thurston. But very different was she in personal ap- pearance; and yet those who had known her many years back represented her to have been a very different being from what those who saw her now might imagine. The change which had led her on to be what we have described her, alike in looks and tem- per, had been gradual, as if some insidious poison had been infused into lher, and had imperceptibly but surely done its all but fatal work, corroding the wholesome essence of physical life, as there was no love in the heart for her suitors. What was the cause thereof? No one knew. As a matter of course, the reader will instantaneously sus- pect that it was disappointment in love. Horatio Thurston was close upon twenty- one years of age. Up to the age of sixteen he had been a promising youth, but a couple of years at college had well nigh sent him into his grave. Here they hoped that the fine bracing air of the country would restore his health. But lie did nbt like to go, as he would rather be at his father's shop or go to the army, as he thought there was not enough of young ladies in the country. Horatio was yawning over a new novel which he had received from New  York a few days previously, and Miss Thurston, or "Aunt Jane," as she was' usually called, was sitting very upright in a high backed chair, listening, with a sort, of sneering smile upon her lip, to the rhodomontade her sister-in-law was delivering, "I see your college chum, Frank Jones, has just been appointed a Colonel in a cav- alry regiment," said Mr. Thurston, lowering the paper upon his knees and looking round towards his son.  "Well, after all, if I was a  young man over again, I think I should prefer the army to any other profession."  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7116-00000005"/> "Now, don't go and put those silly notions into Horatio's head," exclaimed his mother. "I am sure I don't want him to go, for he might be killed in battle. You know, there was my brother, the Colonel, who fell id the battle of Bull Run." "As fine a fellow as our Horatio, per- haps," observed Aunt Jane. L I suppose you meant that in your usual ill-natured way, aunt," said Horatio; "but you mustn't think yourself a beauty. In fact, when the corn in our fields is getting ripe, I mean to ask you to stick, yourself up as a scarecrow to keep the birds off." "No,' you would do better," retorted Aunt Jane, "a because it requires a manikin." "Oh, you be hangedl" cried Horatio. "And now that you have spoken of it, sir," he added, turning to his father,' "I really think I should like to go into the army." "Gracious goodness, boy!" exclaimed his mother, frightened out of her wits at this announcement; " you mustn't think of such a thing. What, an only son, the heir of the title and estates, to stand a chance of getting shot W battle!" "Not he!" said Aunt Jane. "He would  always be in the rear." "Oh 1 pray don't interrupt," exclaimed his mother, petulantly. "Now you see, Mr. Thurston, what you have gone and put into Horatio's head." "No," cried the youth; " for I'put it there myself." "It was lucky," interjected Aunt Jane; "your head wanted something in it." "It's a thing I have been t hinking of for a long time past," continued Horatio. "But I don't want to go in a cavalry regiment, because I don't like the uniform. I prefer the blue coat; and so I fix upon the in- fantry." "Well, after all, I think I should like to see Horatio in a blue coat. How you would astonish all our friends in the country, coming down in your uniform, Horatio and what a favorite you would be with the la- dies I They are so fond of an officer!" "As tall as himself;" observed Aunt Jano. "Woll, I do really think," said Mr. Thurs- ton, " that we have started an idea which is not a bad one. It would be as well if Hora- tio had something to occupy lim for the next three years; and I don't know that he could do anything better than take a com- mission for that time." "There are so many things he ixt for, it is of course difficult to, choose," said Aunt Jane. "Well, I am glad, sir, that you think se- riously of it," cried the youth; "for it suits me uncommonly well. When will you see about it?" said Horatio. "I and your mother will talk it over a little first," replied his father, "and if we still think the same, I will write to the Gov-   ernor, and see if there is any chance to get you a commission as Captain, in a .day or two." "By the by, Horatio, I did as you asked me, and gave Bell orders to turn off that impudent fellow-what's lis name?" "Harry Todd," answered Horatio. "There never was such an impertinent scoundrel in this world; the most outrageously saucy clodhopper I ever knew." "Has he been boxing your ears?" in- quired Aunt Jane, with more bitterness than before. "The idea I Why, if he had only waited a little longer, I should have given him such a thrashing- with. my riding whip as he never had in his life. But when hoe saw I was going to leap off to pick it tip for the pur- pose, he scampered away as if a mad dog was after him. All those mechanics are despicable cowards." "And so are some gentlemen," added Aunt Jane. "ut I hope, sir," resumed Horatio, ad- dressing his father-for he seldom took no- tice of Miss Thurston's bitter and sarcastic interjections-- that you told Bell to take measures to get that scoundrel altogether out of the shop." "To be sure I did. We will have no such impudent fellows in the shop.  The town too will be well rid of him; for I have more than once heard that he dares hold opinions which, if spread among the hands, would demoralize them. The idea of the working classes having rights-it is'really ,too absurd!" "To'be sure," said Aunt Jane; '"they should have nothing but wrongs." "For a long time past," continued his father, "I had intended to get rid of the fel- low; but I couldn't very well manage. it without an opportunity; and now it has pre- sented itself. There will be -no alternative but for him to leave the shop." ----  ---- CHAPTER III. FOR about a week garry wandered about tle country in search of employment; and every evening had he returned unsuccessful to his lodging. He had not emitted to visit the trysting place of love, on the balnk of the stream in the grove, in the hope that Annie perhaps might be there; but not once did she make her appearance; and lie therefore feared that she was kept a close prisoner at liome. Gloomy and dark were his prospects as day after day he beheld his fruitless search for employment. He had loped until the very last that he should perhaps obtain work, but at lefgth he was compelled to     come to the conclusion that this hope exist- ed no longer. Carefully as he had husbanded his little resources, they were now complete- ly exhausted; and on the seventh evening, on his return from the day's weary wander- ings, he found himself without the means of procuring the morrow's breakfast. We must now inform the reader of the scheme by which Horatio Thurston and Mr. Bell contrived, to get Harry away from the town, as they werejafraid he might obtain work and remain  h it. They called upon Mr. David Ottis, informing him that if he would assist them ip getting Ha;rry Todd to enlist in the servide ofthe United States, they would remunerate him for it, which he agreed to do for the sum of twenty-five .dol- lars, and left for the purpose of advising Harry Todd to enlist. It was about nine o'clock at night that he was sitting in his bedroom, reflecting mourn- fully on his position, when Mr. Ottis slowly opened the door, and, looking in, said- "How miserable you seem, Harry. I can't bear to see you in this state. What ails you, man?" "You   know how  I -am  situated, Mr. Ottis," replied Harry, alluding to his unsuc- cessful endeavors to obtain work. "I only ask to eat the bread of honest industry; but even this is denied me. What am    I to do?" "If I were in your situation," replied Mr. 'Ottis, "I know  what I would do.  You were never made for a laborer; you osght to be an officer and a gentleman." "An officer and a gentleman " echoed Harry, with a look of surprise. "' What do you mean?" "I mean that promotion from the ranks is quite common now," replied Ottis. "A recruiting officer told me of a number of cases of that kind which had come to his knowledge. A young fellow like you would soon get made a corporal, and then a ser- geant; and, if you behaved well, you would be  made an officer. Ther 's no doubt of that; and if you were to gQ into the army, in a  few years you would co'me back aston- ishing us all with epaulettes on your shoul- ders and a sash around your waisc." "Mr. Ottis," said Harry, suddenly starting from his chair, "I am decided. I have no mnore money. If I remain another week in ' your house I shall be unable to pay you rent, and I know you cannot afford to be without it. My  mind is therefore male up, , and to-morrow morning I  will go to the re- ' cruiting officer." "  Why not to-night," asked Ottis, resolved to strike while the iron was hot, "I am just going up to the recruiting officer, you can go along and you will find the officer a very agreeable man; quite a gentleman." :'No, I  will not go to the office to-night," replied Harry, "but as my'resolve is taken   - I have not the slightest objection to finish [ the matter this evening." "In that case come along with me, and I will call him out to speak to you." Harry Todd accordingly accompanied Mr. Ottis to the recruiting office, but waited out- side while Mr. Ottis entered, and in a few minutes returned accompanied by the officer. "Mr. Todd, I am rejoiced to make your ac- quaintance," he observed, taking the young mans hand and shaking it with what ap- peared to be a cordial warmth, "' I understand that you have made up your mind, to serve your country. It is a noble resolution, and gallantly taken." . Then placing his hand upon Harry's shoulder, he said in a lower t   e of mysterious confidence, "I am very ch mistaken if there won't be an epaulette re before long," and immediately put the enty-five dollars bounty money into the hand of Harry Todd. "Now what ceremony am    I to go through," inquired the young man. "Nothing more at present, my friend, unless you choose to come and take a glass with me." "I would rather not," rejoined Harry, "and trust you will excuse me. Do not think that I shall retract from the step which I ilave taken. There is no chance of that," he added somewhat bitterly. "You speak like a man," replied the officer; "for the next two days you can di- vert yourself in any way you choose. On Saturday evening I shall serve you with a little notice, a mere matter of form to prove that you have enlisted, and then next Mon- day morning at half-past nine o'clock you will be so kind as to, accompany me to the mustering officer to finish the ceremony." "I shall not fail," replied Harry, "and. now I wish you good night." The young man turned away and hurried home to his lodging, where lie sat down and pondered deeply and painfully upon what he had done. But lie did not repent, for ne had no other alternative. The Saturday evening came, and the no- tice of his enlistment was duly presented to ' him by the recruiting officer in person, and in the presence of Mr. Ottis. Harry, in answer..to the. usual question put, admitted that it was with his own free will and consent he had offered himself as a recruitrin the service of his country. The officer felt his satisfaction to be now com- plete, and took his leave, reminding the re- cruit that he would have to attend him on the following Monday morning at half-past' nine. We must here observe that Harry had visited the grove as usual that evening, but in vain; Annie Bell appeared not at tho wonted place of meeting.  Was she then really a prisoner? Had she heard of the step he had taken? Would she make no  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7116-00000006"/> effort to see him before he left? Such were the questions which Harry asked himself but how could he answer them? He could not. And how was he to see her? He dared not proceed to her father's cottage and there solicit an interview. It would be equally useless to loiter about the vicinity of that dwelling in the hope that she might come forth to meet him. There was one hope. Would she not be permitted to repair to church on Sunday? and if, so, might she not endeavor to elude her father's vigilanoce and fly to the spot where she would be sure to meet him? A prey to varied and conflicting emo- tions of pain/and apprehension, Harry Todd proceeded to church at the morning's ser- vice. It was, as a matter of course, known through the neighborhood that Harry had enlisted, and amongst the, humbler inhabi- tants he thus found himself on his way to church an object of marked sympathy. .On entering the building he took his usual seat up in the gallery, and a glance towards Mr. Bell's pew showed him that neither father nor daughter were there. That service passed over, and Mr. Bell's pew remained unoccupied. But still there was the after- noon service. might they not come to that? Harry hoped that it would prove so, but again he was disappointed. At about seven o'clock he was wending his way slowly along the bank of the stream where he had so often met his beloved Annie, but where they had been so rudely separated by the sudden appearance of her father. This was Harry's last hope. But was it doomed to be disap- pointed? ABh what is that rustling amidst the trees on the opposite bank? Whose form is that crossing the little bridge? Oh I joy, jby! it is Annie, and she sinks half faintingai his arms. "What happiness," exclaimed Harry as he pressed her to his heart, and in the bliss of that moment he almost forgot every ' trouble that he had. been doomed to know. "Tell me, Harry," cried the girl in an excited manner, " is it true that--" "It is true," he responded, knowing full well the nature of the question she was about to put, " but what could I do? Every other hope was dead--" "Harry," she interrupted him, flinging her terrified looks around, "we must not remain here. When my father misses me this is tho first place to which he will fly in search of me1"          I "Let us go further into the grove," said Harry. Through the grove they went in too much haste to renew the discourse, until they reached the tree beneath whose shade the avowals of love had for the first time passed, where there was a seat. Upon this they placed themselves. Their looks mutually   expressed pain and sorrow, for while on the one hand Hiarry observed that Annie was pale and careworn, she on the other hand recognized but too plainly the traces of a corroding grief on the countenance of her lover. "I have been kept a close prisoner at home," said Annie, "but through the kind- ness of poor Martha, the servant girl, I have this evening for the first time been enabled to elude the vigilance of my harsh parent But I must not remain long away, or that poor girl will be made to suffer for the sym- pathy she has shown me. Let us talk about yourself, Harry. Have you gone too far to be enabled to retreat?" "Oh I wherefore should you ask me, dearest Annie  What hope had I? You know not the many weary miles I have -walked in the endeavor to procure work, but all in vain. What then, 1 ask, was I to do?" "Had you no faith in my love, Harry," inquired Annie with a tender look of depre- cation. "Oh I faith the most sublime,." exclaimed Ilarry with a degree of enthusiasm which convinced her that his confidence in her love was as great as that which he himself bore for her. "Yes, I said to myself that we were both young, that we had faith in each other, and that we might wait for better times." "Alas, Harry, I could not console myself with that hope," murmured Annie, her head drooping upon his shoulder, "So many things happen in this world that when once a separation takes place," she continued with a profound mournfulness in her tone, "the worst is to be apprehended; the idea of all this is more than I can bear;" and the tears gushed forth plentifully. '"Dearest girl, I must entreat you to com- pose yourself," cried Harry, covering her cheeks with kisses. "Have I not already anguish sufficient in my heart to be spared the idea that I shall leave you thus terribly afflicted? Tranquilize yourself, therefore, beloved one, for my sake." "I will, I will," responded Annie; but it was in the hysterical accents of despair- and she gazed with an earnest, doting fond- ness upon her lover, all the fervor of her soul giving force and power to that tender ad endearing gaze of her's. "But tell me," she continued, in a calmer voice, " is there nothing to be done? can you not retreat from the step you have taken?" "Again you ask me that question, dearest Annie," said Harry; but were I to recall what I have done, should I not relapse into the same hopeless state as before?" "Listen to me, Harry;" replied Annie, with a firmer as well as a more tranquil de- meanor than she had yet shown during the present interview. "Think not that the   words I am about to address to you are in- consistent with a young maiden's -modesty, or that I am too forward in speech or con- duct, for it is this cruel emergency which has made me resolve to speak as I am about to do. I love you, Harry-full well do you know it. I have pledged my faith to you, and I can never be another's. I look upon ,you as my affianced husband. If, therefore, it be possible for you to retrieve the rash step you have taken, I will not hesitate to accompany you to the altar." "Oh! my beloved Annie, how-deeply and how fervently do I thank you for what you have just saidl" exclaimed Harry, pressing her to his heart. But even were it possible, would you not be wedding poverty? Would you not be rendering yourself an outcast from a comfortable home, to share, perhaps, the wanderings of a laborer in search of work? It is impossible that I dould be so intensely selfish ,as to permit you to make such a sacrifice on my account.'; "Think not, dearest Harry, that what I have just said," replied Annie, speaking firmly and calmly again, "was the unpre- meditated rashness of a loving heart excited by the sense of poignant affliction. I have pondered on the proposal I have just made to you, and again I must entreat 'you to lis- ten. My father has never been sparing with his money towards me, and has taken a po. in seeing me dress well-or at least has urged me to dress even above my position. But I have been frugal and economical with the resources thus placed at my command. In short, I have some forty or fifty dollars of my .own saving." Annie now began' to think that there was a hope of seeing her plan realized, as Harry thus suffered her to proceed without the fatal announcement that it was too late. She said: "Well, I was developing my project to you. In this neighborhood it is but too clear there is no hope for you; but elsewlhere the same tyrannical .ban will not be set upon your name.   With my little savings we might commence the world; and perhaps the education -you have received may war- rant the hope of your finding elsewhere some mtore suitable employment than that to which you have been accustomed. Within the last few days I  have thought much and upon many things; affliction and solitude appear to have given my mind scope for enlarging its experience. I understand now  where- fore it is that you have remained altogether in ;this humble and obscure village, and why you have not endeavored to carve out for yourself some higher career or superior call- ing in a city or town where your talents and your acquirements might be rendered avail- able. I  know that it'was in order to be near me that you have accepted so lowly a. position hitherto; and it is this consideration as well as any other, which has induced me   to make of my own accord the proposal t have set before you." "Annie, you have sketched out a plan of happiness which seems to be almost too bright for realization!" "' Oh I do not tell me I must bid farewell to hope," cried the girl, gazing with the ten- derest anxiety on his countenance. "Surely there are some means for you to retrieve the the step you have taken."  "It is not irrevocable, " replied Harry; and as he thus spoke, a perfect torrent of joy shot forth from the eyes of his beauteous companion, her whole countenance becom- ing radiant with hope. "' Tell me, then," she cried, " what is there to be done to enable you to rescue yourself from the power of the recruiting officer?" "To-morrow, at half-past nine o'clock," replied Harry. "I am to accompany him before Mr. Thurston to complete the formali- ties: Mr. Thurston will ask me whether I am still resolved to become a soldier. I can say no. He will then tell me that if I re- turn the bounty I have received, H may be freed from the'shackles of enlistment." "Then you consent to my proposal," ex- claimed Annie; "yes-I see that you will; and think not," she added, more slowly and -seriously, that because in one sense I shall prove a disobedient daughter, think not on this account that I shall provo a' disobedient wife." "No," replied Harry. "I am now receiv- ing too many proofs of your devotion not to fe% how :great is the treasure I shall possess in you. But," continued Harry, becoming somewhat excited, '"I have spent the bounty; it is all gone. What is to be done?" "Forgive me, dear Harry," she resumed, "if I again touch upon this business matter. This money which is required to procure your release, must be paid by Tuesday morn- ing. I will manage to convey it to you to- morrow evening. If I can not contrive to meet you myself, I will trust Martha in the affair. Therefore, if I come not myself, you may rely upon seeing her. Let us not ap- point our old trysting-place at the,bridge. for fear my father's suspicions might be awakened. But lefthis be the spot, to-mor- row evening withi4n half an hour of sunset. Should it be impossible for either of us to get out to-morroW evening, there is no doubt that Martha can manage to run down into the town between seven and eight o'clock in the morning; the money need not be paid till. ten; and, therefore, in any case, there will be ample time. She will discover that there is no tea, or no bread for the breakfast, or some excuse of that kind, and she will hurry to fetch what is needful. Can she not deliver a little sealed packet for you at Mr. Ottis's?' "Yes," replied Harry. "Ottis is well dis- posed towards me, and he will punctually  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7116-00000007"/> deliver anything that may be entrusted to him for me.. Ah, my dearest Annie, how can I ever sufficiently testify my gratitude to you for all this forethought?" *'Gratitude," murmured Annie, half re- proachfully; " do not I possess something that?is above the comparative coldness of gratitude?" "Yes; my ardent, devoted, unchangeable love," cried Harry. "In two days, dearest Harry," she said, "you will be once more fire-e, and then you must not delay the consummation of my hap- piness. We will away to some town where there is no danger of immediate pursuit, and there our hands shall be united." The lovers embraced each other fondly, and then separated; Annie flitting back to the cottage, which she succeeded in reaching ere her father's return, and Harry retracing his way to his humble lodging at Ottis's house, but in a different condition of mind from what he experienced when he issued forth an hour previously. Harry said not a word to Ottis of what his intention was, nor to the recruiting officer, when at the appointed time he repaired to the office. "Well, my friend," said the officer, "you are indeed punctual. Upon my honor, I think you will become the flower of the regiment. It is quite delightful to see such punctuality." Harry was half inclined to deal frankly at once, and to avow his intentions, but as they had a walk of a mile before them, he did not wish to be exposed to whatever cajolery the officer might adopt to induce him to change his mind and adhere to his. enlistment. He accordingly said nothing; and they set out upon their walk. On their way towards the office, they had to pass within a hundred yards of Mr. Bell's cottage; and Harry riveted his eyes upon the windows in the hope of catching a glimpse of that countenance which was the brightest and most beauteous in the world to him. Nor was he disappointed. He be held an upper window open abruptly, and a white handkerchief was waved for an instant. It was then withdrawn--the window was closed again-but above the muslin blind he recognized the countenance of his well-be- loved. This little incident took place so rapidly that the officer, who was looking straight forward, never noticed it. But how cheered was Harry Todd by this little circumstance. It was a sign to convince him that the meot- ing of the previous evening remained unsus- pected by Mr. Bell, and that nothing was changed in the arrangements between him and his well-beloved. In about a quarter of an hour the office was reached, and the mustering officer soon made his appearance. He suffered no sign   of what he inwardly felt to appear upon his countenance, as he acknowledged the .mili- tary bow of the recruiting officer, and then took his seat at the head of the tab; \. But at hIis heart he experienced a secret pleasure at the idea of Hairy Todd having fallen into the fangs of enlistment. "Now, what is this?" he asked, arrang- ing some papers on the desk before him. "' I suppose it's another recruiting case." "It is, sir," replied the recruiting officer. "Well," he resumed, addressing Todd, "here's the Articles of War; it is my duty to read them to you. I need not-ask your name and condition, because I know them both; but have you voluntarily enlisted?" "I have, sir," replied Harry; "but with your permission "- "Don't interrupt me now;" said the mus- tering officer sternly. "Wait till you. are questioned. I am going to read you the Articles of War in respect to mutiny and desertion; and then you will hlave to take the oath of allegiance, which I shall admin- ister." "But, sir," again interjected Harry, "I think I can save you some trouble." "What!" exclaimed the officer, " are you going to refuse taking the oath?" "Is there not," inquired Harry, ,calmly, "some other clause in the act which you are likewise bound to communicate?" "I will tell you the substance," exclaimed the officer. "The whole tenor of the mat- ter is this-that a person declaring his dis- sent from his enlistment on the ground that lie has been induced to enlist by other par- ties against his own will, by returning the bounty money shall be forthwith discharged.' "And is there no specified delay allowed for the payment of this money?" asked Harry. "MWhy, you are not going to shirk 'off?" exclaimed the officer, becoming as red as a turkey-cock. t"I beg your pardon, sir; I do dissent from this enlistment," exclaimed Harry; "and, moreover, I demand the delay of twenty- four hours to refund the money." "Well; this is the shabbiest,. dirtiest thing 1 ever knew in all my life," said the recruiting officer. "What is the reason you have thus made a fool of yourself? you maye  as well take the oath at once and have done with it. WLat other chance have you but to enlist?" "With all due respect, sir, I have changed my mind," answered Harry. "I am truly sorry that I should have given the recruiting officer any trouble in the matter." "Well. there's enough of it," said the mus- tering officer; " but mind, Harry Todd, if that money is not paid in the presence of a witness by ten o'clock to-morrow morning, you will have to be brought up again; and then if you don't take the oath of allegiance,   I will commit you to prison, where you will stay till you do."  ' Harry made no reply, but passed out of the room, closely 'followed by the recruiting officer, whose countenance wore an awful aspect. "You rascal," said he, "how dare you gammon me in this manner? I have a great mind to knock your head off!" Harry fired up in an instant; his hand was raised 'to strike the bully down; but quick al lightning did a thoulght flash to his mind, if he struck the officer, there was a justice of the peace near by who would re- joice in committing him to jail for the assault. and then how quickly would his hopes and those of his beloved Annie be dashed to tho ground I It nevertheless, cost him a tremendous effort to restrain his indignation ; but he did so, and walked in front. "It's an uncommon lucky thing for you, young fellow, . that you didn't touch me," resumed the officer, who perhaps would have sworn that he had. were it Hot that- the guard was standiing on the sfs, and beheld, everything that passed. 'T this manner they reached the door of Ottis's house; and as Harry was about to enter the dwelling, the officer called out, " stop." "Now," said he, standing in the " first, po- sition," as erect as a statue, "-it is my order that you consider yourself under arrest for the present." Harry was thunderstruck. He had not foreseen this; he was not even aware that, the officer could exercise such an authority over himt; but he instantly perceived that it was so, and that he was thus far at the mer- cy of the blue-coated officer. But how was he to keep his appointment in the wood with Annie or or Martha? An expression of an- guish swept over his countenance, and the officer perceiving it, though, of course, not und3rstanding the particular feeling that conjured it up; gave a malignant grin, very, different indeed from his recruiting smile. "I beg you to observe," said Harry, "that I have not intentionally offered you any offenc3." "Go up to your room, sir, and stay there " vociferated the officer. "I shall come and inquire after you, and if you dare to leave, ,1 shall at once have you apprehended as a deserter." With these words ho turned away and walked with majestic stateliness toward the recruiting office.  ' "You had better do as he orders, Todd," said Mr; Ottis, who stood contemplating this extraordinary scene. Harry, who had lingered for a few mo- ments upon the door-step, was recalled by that recommendation, which he took to be ea friendly oate from the stupor of dismay into which he had been thrown; and he at   once ascended to his chamber. At first he was well nigh reduced to despair, as he saw' the-impossibility of keeping the appointment at the oak tree in the grove; but then he recollected that Annie had spoken of the possibility of neither herself nor Martha being enabled to meet him there in the even- ing, in which case the servant-girl was to find an excuse for coming into tilh village in the morning. 'iis circumstance at once re- lieved his min, and becoming suddenly calm, he said th himself, "Should Annie or Martha keep the appointment this evening and find that I come not, it will be concluded tlhat something has transpired to prevent me; and Martha will come across in the morning." His .reflections wero interrupted by the entrance of Mr. Ottis, exclaiming with a great air of sympathy, "What does aqll this mean, Harry?" "Simply becausoe I changed my mind, Mr. Ottis, and gave notice that I should withdraw from the enlistment, the recruiting officer has heaped upon me the most abom- inable abuse, and has also put me under arrest." "Have you returned the bounty then?" demanded Ottis eagerly. "No, not yet," replied Harry; " and now, my good friend," lie added in a confidential tone, "you could do mo a particular ser- vice." "Anything in the world, Harry," ejacu- lated Ottis. "What is it, my dear fellow?" ".Eitlher to-night or Zo-morroW morning," returned Harry, "a little parcel or letter will be delivered here for me. You must take charge of it and bring it up to me im- mediately, as it is of the highest import- anqe." "I understand," said Ottis; "it is the bounty money you have to return. ' Well, I am heartily glad you haveo found a friend to assist you. Depend upon it, when 'the packet comes I Will bring it tip." "I am truly obliged to you for your kind- ness,". oxclaimed Harry in the most truthful confidence. "If you had seen how that man salowed himself in his true colors just now-but you saw enough to convince you what, he is." "AhlI replied Ottis, shaking his head, "I am afraid I have been deceived in hiLm." "Oh! what an escape I have made," continued Harry. "I shudder at the idea of having stood the chance of falling into his power." "Then you are sure of getting thl money, Harry?" observed Ottis. "Becanse if not," he added with every appearance of the most friendly interest, "I will try and borrow it for you."        I "A thousand thanks for 'your kindness; but I am certain of being able to obtain it4" "So much the  better," rejoined' Ottis.  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7116-00000008"/> '".AInd now keep quiet here;, don't put amr-self any farther into the power of the officer." "Not for worlds " ejaculated Harry with a shudder, as he thought of what poor Annie would suffer if anything should happen through his imprudence to frustrate the' plans which she in her devotedness had frmed, and which had been agreed upon between them. The sun went down. Harry lighted his candle in his little room and began to read. Tea o'clock struck by the village church; and Ottis came up to tell him that no packet had arrived, but that the officer had been down to assure himself that he kept under arrest. '"The parcel will not therefore be deliv- ered to-night," said Harry; " but it is sure to be here in the morning." "I am delighted to hear it," answered Ottis. "By ten therefore to-morrow you will be a free man. And now good night, Harry; and pleasant dreams to you." "Good night," responded Harry; and soon after sought his humble pallet to dream of Annie and happiness. When he awoke in the morning the church clock was striking six. He arose and drewed himself with a light heart. This was to be the 'day of his emancipation frown the power of the officers-free to conlict his Annie to the 'altar-free to bear her away to some large town, where they might set up thoir housekeeping and take nmeasures to earn their livelihood. 'When the marriage was accomplished might not Mr. Bell relent? Did he not love his daughter? and would he not forgive her? Yes, this was to be expected; and, then' their happiness would be complete. The time passed, and the clock struck nine, and Martha-had not yet come. Some one was ascending the stairs; he knew the footsteps; the packet had then arrived? Ottis entered the room; and Harry extended hia hand to receive the expected imissive. Ottis thought, or appeared to think, that the young man meantmto shake hands with him; and when Harry found that the hand he thus clutched contained nothing, he ex- claimed, "Is it not come yet?" "No, not yet," returned Ottis. "I would not come up tdyou before for fear any one jmight bring it in my absence from the Shop; and as I knew it was particular, I resolved to wait and receive it myself. But never fear; I will attend to it. You must how- ever keep close; for the recruiting officer has posted a couple of recruits at the door to see that you don't go out; or to stop you if you do." 'Oh 1. I shall be free of him in a few min- *0a" ejaculated the young man. Ah : but the minutes w'ew4 slipping away;   and they soon swelled into half an hour. Yes: hatf past nine, add i:o :Martha--o; Annie-not a line--not a word of either message or hote I He knew not what to think. Was some vile treachery at work? He tortured ,himw self with conjectures; but amidst them all he never once suspected that Ottis could be playing himr'false. Minute after minute passed, but: n one came. Almost maddened to desperation, he opened the door and listened. Ottis:w'as talking in the shop below; others 'wrbe talking also; and amongst :those voices was  thew well known one of the recruiting officer. "Ohl I am I to be sacrificed:? am I ,to be lost?" murmured Harry to -himself "C (an it be possible? Is it indeed true? or a hid- eous dream?" and leaning against the door. post, he pressed his, hands to his throbbitqg temples, in a state of mind not even to be envied by a wretch. about to be'led forth to the place of execution. The clock struck; it was ten. "Too late I too late!" cried Harry in' a fit of desperation. "Harry Todd, come down!" cried -the voice of the officer; and it sounded upo' the ears of the almost distracted young ima'n as if, having, made, a bargain with Saz tan, the time was up, and the evil one was demanding his surtender. Such a calm was it that now seized upon Harry Todd; -and yielding himself to. his destiny, he slowly descended the stairs. ,And in the room below he beheld the re- cruiting officer, on whose countenance there was an expression which might be likened . unto the malignant triumph of a fiend. There was indeed at'that moment something - truly satanic- in the' man'.s features-a dia. bolic gloating over the fallen conditidn-of his victim. "Really, my dear fellow, I am truly sorry for this," whispered Ottis, clutching Harry's. arm. "You know I ofered last night to go and borrow the money for you." "Yes, you have done everything you could for me," replied Harry, shaking M f Ottis by the hand in his frank and unsus- pecting manner, "Come," said the officer; " we have no time to lose. Tramp-march-be quick- and let me have none of your nonsense." At the doorway two guards, with their guns, were posted; and as Harry 'stepped forth, they gave him to understand by their looks that it was against their will, they had been placed there to. keep guard, upon him.            , . He knew fuill well in which:;direction ,he had to go without being. told, and, he ac- cordingly bent his steps towards the mus- tering officer. As he neared Bells house' ho scarcilys had the courage. to cast a:.look hl that dirtio, Ob t; wa.' must -be iAtlit's   feelings if she knew all. Suddenly the door if the house opened, a fem/ale figu're' came . ibunding forth. It Was Annie heiself. "Harry; Harry," she cried in the freinzy of agonizing suspense, "what means this?, wherefore still with him?" and she flung her frightened glances towards the officer; who was about a dozen yards behind." "Dearest, dearest Annie," replied the young man, "'you did not send-". "Heavens!"' she exclaimed with a wild shriek, "there has been the foulest treach- ery; you camb 'not to the oak troe last evening-" "NNo, I could not, I was a prisoner." "But Martha delivered the packet .with her own hand last night at your lodging." "Ah Ottis," ejaculated Harry, the light- ning of suspicion flashing in upon his SOUl and he seemed thunderstruck. "Yes, into his hand she delivered it" cied the almost frantic girl. "I can believe her, I can rely upon her, I am certain that she has not deceived me." "Heaven will not permit this great in-  iquity to go unpunished," said Harry in a: low deep voice, as he sustained the haft fAinting form of his adored one in his arms. ' Oh 1 it is terrible, terrible." "Now, young man," cried the officer, who had stood as erect as possible gazing on this' "scene, "I can't wait for you any moie. It's a great. kindness on my part after all you have done, to wait at all." Scarcely had he spoken when Mr. Bell himself came rushing forth from the cottage. Furious with rage, he actually tore Annie firon her lover's arms, and with a wild cry of despair, she became insensible. '"Villain l" thundered her father, flinging a diabolical glance of hate and rage upon the hapless young man, and he bore his daughter quickly back' towards the house. Harry's impulse was to follow at all risk, and insist upon a final interview with his beloved. Not for a moment whs he deter- red by the presence of the officer; he would have stricken the officer to the ground, reck- less' of:the consequences, had he interfered to Ftop him. It was anothler consideration j which, flashing to his mind, held him back, for he thought that if he obeyed: that im- pulse, it would only excite the father's fury I into madness, and he might visit his 'age all 1 the more heavily upon his daughter, there-  fore, with one look of unutterable despair i flung upon the inanimate form of her who f was being borne away from  his view, he. sped onwards towards the mustering office. Again his thoughts fell into confusion, and 1 when he awakened to consciousness he was i in the presence of the mustering officer, who , commenced to read to him the Articles of i't War,. and when they were read, roughly thld t hnrm to hold up his hand and take the oath I Q  Aeimdea . ' He obeyea, and tolls a beinag.   r such as might be supposed to take posses- sion of a ddoed man 'when his, death sentence is pronounced, seized upon' the wretched,; wretched Harry. ? ' "Now, my fin' fellow," exclaimed the officer as he followed oitur ero down from the mustering office, "you can't escape me, you are in my power; but now:the 'nail is a clenched, I don't 'ind telling you that I will make you smart for all the trouble you have I given me. I will pay you off for your infer. nal insolence. Talk of you ever rising from the ranks, why, you will never even get to be a corporal. There isn't a shadow of a chance;' yo will see what-a 'wa rsa life ih and if yoii' don't find it hell upon earth." In this manner the officer'went on until the vicinage of Mr. Bell's house was again reached. Harry answered him not a word. His eyes were now upon the house. Would any sign be made? would some indication of the last farewell begin forth? 01 I for one glimpse of' that dearly loved countenance ere he entered upon his dismal career, for - such he felt the irresistiblo presentiment that ' it would prove. All on a sudden the crashing of glass, was heard, arid': Hrry stopped short. A 'Whit handkerchief was waved for a   moment- T- e very way in which it was SI;aken; indicated tihe frantic excitement of. her Who thus shookit. Harry waved hiS.'in respodnso, and then rushed onward with fronzy in his brain. Ohl, too well did he comprehend what all that meant; and that signal n'ot merely conveyed ar adieu, but likewise a - hope and a pledge-the hope that better days might come, and a'plodge that the heart of Annie would remain choistant until the end. And he was taking the direction of hLs lodging. 'At least he would have the 'atis- famtion, poor though it were, of upbraiding that man Ottis for his black treachery. But no, even this was denied him; for in a stern voice the officer commanded him to proceed to the recruiting office. Harry already felt that he had' lost hiS manhood,' that thenceforth he could only move in pursuance of orders. On arriving at the recruiting office he was cominmanded,to put on th6 uniform aAnd theo go to his quarters in the guard-room, and there stay' until the hour'of'departure should arrive. The othier recruits had been per- mitted to visit their'friends and' bid 'them farewell, Harry was seated upon a  bench, with his elbows upon his knees, and his countenance buried in his hands, he gave way to his wretched thoughts.' But language 'has no power to describe ae intensity of theirbitV ",frm , ;Pesently the  door opened, and the oficr tossing in, oa parcel said, in a gruml brutal voice,  "There--.r e .y 't ings. from Otis. He  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7116-00000009"/> has packed them up for you to save you the trouble. And there"-with a mocking laugh--"is what was kept from you till now, so .I could make sure of you; and thanks to Mr. Ottis for itl" exclaimed the officer.  As he uttered these last words, he threw down a little packet and left Harry rushed forward and seized the packet. AhI it was not for the money which it contained, as it was too late, but it was because there might be a note inside; and oh I to possess a few lines in the hand- writing of his well beloved. He tore open the brown paper wrapper; some money fell upon the floor; but his fingers clutched a note addressed to himself. Its contents were as follows: "FIVE O'CLOCE MONDAY BVENING. "I pen these few lines, dearest Harry, to let you know that our interview of last even- ing has remained totally unsuspected by my father; but such is his vigilance over me that I cannot hope to meet you presently at the place of appointment. Martha however will be there. I have made a complete confidante of the kind-hearted girl; and she will do anything she can to serve us. If by any accident you do not make your appear- ance at the oak in the grove-and she will wait half an hour for you-she will repair at once to Mr. Ottis' house and deliver this packet into his hands. Therefore you see, dearest .Harry, that every precaution is taken to insure the success of our arrange- ments. You can of course pay the money at once, and then you will be free. Oh I dearest, dearest Harry, ,how happy shall J be presently I At about ten o'clock I shall say to myself, ' He is free by this time; he is no longer a slavc, bound hand and foot; he is happy once more.' These will be my thoughts; and they will prove the source of ineffable bliss.  "Now, my dear Harry, you must -every evening repair to our place of appointment, until I succeed in joining you there; and then when I do, it will be to part no more. Are you not happy, my beloved Harry? I am so happy--oh 1 so happy-I cannot de- scribe all I feel. Heaven's blessings be upon your head, my own well-beloved!- and I need scarcely add that if the sincerest affection which woman's heart may experi- ence can make man hoppy, then do you pos- segS that devoted love on the part of your The tears rained in torrents down Harry's cheeks as he read this note. The strong tan was convulsed with the bitteqetstogaA - and he wept like a child. A child I, Nfo;. the comparison is ridiculous. No child, even when most poignantly afflicted, ever wept so bitterly as Harry Todd wept then.   - l Ob, God how much happiness had been annihilated in a moment. What fearful rav- ages niad foul treachery made I The desola- tion ofe a ravaging army in a fertile territory was aS naught. in. comparison with the des- olati9n which a monstrous iniquity had brought into tvo fond and faithful hearts. ,Oh I that the happiness which was breathed in thi artless, ingenuous language of the sweet girl's letter should be thus annihilated in a moment. Oh I that a crown of thorns should be placed on that beauteous head and that a dagger should be ruthlessly thrust into that innocent bosom. Heaven I why did thy thunders sleep? Hadst thou then no lightnings to blast and destroy the satanic authors of that foul and hideous wrong? Oh I it was almost sufficient to make the young man mistrust Providence itself, in the contemplation of this ghastly wreck of bliss that had been suffered to take place. But we cannot-we dare not-linger upon the scene. Our soul is smitten with a deep, deep sadness, as we make this feeble attempt to delineate the workings of the utter agony which took possession of our young hero's mind. Presently the door opened; and the order was to be ready for departure. Alll this announcement startled Harry from the hor- rible vortex of his wretchedness. Oh I to write a line to Annie. Writing materials were procured, and a note was soon written. Almost broken-hearted- he summoned a young man, and putting into his hand the gold which had dropped from the packet, he besought and conjured him to deliver it to liss Annie Bell, with the letter, which he likewise gave him. The man knew Harry well and liked him as much; he was deeply moved, too, by the spectacle of his boundless grief, and he promised compliance in terms so sincere. that the yqung man felt assured the. pledge would not be broken. Almost immediately after this incident an order came for the recruits to be ready to leave to join their regiment. There were many persons assembled to witness the de- parture, and many a friendly shake of the hand and kind wish were bestowed upon the heroes. Mr. Ottis did not, however, show himself; for after all his horrible perfidy, it was scarcely to'be supposed that he would ven- ture to meet the indignant looks of the out- raged Harry Todd. Distressing enough was the parting scene betwixt all the other recruits, their relatives and friends. Mothers and sisters clung to them frantically. Harry felt, as each familiar object was left behind, as if he were parting with life itself by a rapid succession of the cruelest blows, as he passed out of the town.   CHAPTER IV. A MXONTH had elapsed since the departure of the recruits from the town; and in the meantime Annie Bell recovered a certain degree of mental composure. She was nat- urally endowed with considerable Strength of mind; and for Harry Todd's sake she saw the' necessity of bearing  up with all her fortitude against the e terrible blow which had annihilated ail their hopes of immediate happiness. She knew: that he had enlisted for t ree years. Three, years l Was not that an age to a heart that fondly loved? Yes; bit love is accompanied by hope, and the confidence that it feels in its streongth naturally irispires a like confidence that its fidelity will be rewarded in the end. She had every reason to hope and anticipatO that many long years of happiness would await themn, when once the period of trial and separation should be passed. The young man at the recruiting office had fulfilled his promise to Harry Todd. and by entrusting the letter to Martha the first time he met her, had thus ensured its conveyance to the'hands of her for whom it was destined. If anything had been required to i convince poor Annie of her Harry's affection,' this let- ter wsould have had the effect. She 'saw that much of the writing was blotted by the tears which had fallen from Harry's oyes as he penned it; she saw, therefore, how truly and tenderly she was beloved ; and although she shed bitter tears over that letter, yet, when the first frantic-paroxysm of mental agony was passed, she derived consolation from the epistle, inasmuch as it served' as a proof of Harry's unalterable love, A  month, we said, had pawed; and now that garry was noo more in the town, during this interval her father' had  never once touched upon that topic which, when he first introduced it to her attention, so much shocked her. Let it not, however, be sup- posed that' he had abandoned his views. No,; he was, if possible, more completely bent upon them   than ever; but with cau- ti6n he waiited until he saw that Annie's mind had regained somewhat of calmness; at length adopting even more than his former fondness, for the designing man meant not only to conciliate, but to'coax and Cajole. All the youthful freshness of a maiden's confiding love towards her sire was there- fore Withered; she was obedient and docile in heir deportment and speechi:but no longer affectionate and endearing  in her ways. And as for the sunny sweetness of her smiles, that had fled as if forever.- One morning, as Mr. Bell was going to Cincinnati, he. met. Horatio Thurston.- This was precisely such an opportunity asFMr. Bell sought, :and he resolved to make the best of it.     :    I   "'So, I understand, Mr. Thurston," said Mr. Bell, after the exchange of a few indif- fererit remarks, " that you are going into the army.             . ' "Yes," replied the youth, with a languid affectation of manner; "the governlor will send me a commission in a few weeks," re- 1 plied Horatio.  * That will be just about the time you come of age, won't it, sir?" added Bell, who had his own reasons for the inquiry, as the reader is at no loss to understand. "But, by the by, if I remember right,' you are fond of cider,"' said fr. Bell': ,and I happen to have some very excellent just 'at present; will you do me the honor to walk:l over to my house and take a glass?" Horatio was about to decline, but recol- leeting that Mr. Bell had a vcery pretty daughter, he accepted the proposal, and ac- compatfied Mr. Bell to his house. So they soon arrived, ,and walked into the parlor, where Annie was at the time occu- pied with her needle; but, upon perceiving the visitor, she immediately rose, and with, a respectful salutation, was' about to quit the room. "Pray, do not let me disturb you?' said Horatio; politelyf for he could be the accom- plished gentle man enough when he chose. ".No; you ;needn't leave us; Annie," im- mediately added Mr. Bell. "On the contrary, you must remain to fnow our master's son that he is fully welcome here." Still Annie hesitated; and something like a flush of indignation flitted across her coun- tenrance, as the idea struck her that this visit was not altogether accidental, but that it had been brought about purposely byi her father, whose ambitious views in respect to herself sho had not forgotten. "If you retire,;'iss Bell," said Horatio, "I shall at once conceive that I am really disturbirig you, and in that case shall take my departure."            ; Anhnie had now no 'alternative but to re- sume her seat, if she did not wish to appear actually rude.  Horatio sat down near her, while the father left the room, as he said, to fetch the cider. The youring-gentleman had always thought Annie Bell. to be a very pretty girl, but he had seldom, spoken to her siace',his return from New York., He had not before thought that she was so lovely as she at present appeared to him, and for a few momerits hbe gazed' dpon her ivith an admiration which he could'oot conceal. Nor, indeed, did he';attempt to conceal,it. She tobserved that his eyes wfre thus fixed upon her, 'and again did that transient flushof in- dignatidn, pass over her countenance. , To escape from the  inteitness of 'his regards, she rose from her seat on the pretext of drawing up the window-blind., "! Are you going to'leave, sir?", irquired A nie, experiencing a sense of relief: at 4he  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7116-00000010"/> announcement; but she spokeqin,^a sold, almost glacial tone. .-   ) '  /, '; Yes; in a little Wile. 1an going ito the army, you know." Aninie l'ad heard something of the kind, but she did not like .it for, fear that Harry might be under his command,. and she gae a: sigh, for Horatio's words had touched a painful chord in her heart. ' "I hope I said nothing to offend?" -he hastened to observe. '! I. am sure I didn't mean it, Why, you and:I, Miss Bell, have k-nown each othler from infancy; and when w e were little children, I. used to call you Annie, and you called me Horatio. "But we are no longer children, sir," re- plied Annie, coldly and pointedly. "' At all events, we have known each other too long for you to take offence at any little ompliment I may pay you." . "I detest flattetries, air, and -mistrust flat- terers," rejoined, Annie, proudly glacial. "'There .are two kinds of flatterers, Miss Bell," he proceeded to 'observe, " those who do not mean what they say, and those who do. In the former case, the objects flattered may not be worthy of the flattery; but in the latter case they are,when,it ceases to be. Battery and becomes a delicate and well- deserved compliment. "Mr. Thurston, I am surprised at -you!" exclaimed Annie. her cheeks nows becoming crimson with indignation; and she moved towards the door. "By heaven, how'touchy you are!" he cried, springing from his beat and catching her by the arm. "I didn't mean to offend YOlL"U "Unhand me, sir!'! cried the damsel proudly.; and she threw upon him a look of aversion and disgust; then, as he fell back astounded, she quitted the room, closing the door behind her. "What's the matter, -Annie?" inquired her father. "The next time that, you fetch Mr. Thurs- ton home," was Annie's firm response, "I shall insist upon retiring to my own cham- ber." "By Heavens! I will show you," muttered Bell with horrible rage, and. speaking through:his teeth, "who is master here." She paused not to make any reply, but hurried up to her own chamber, where she burst into tears., Bell reentered the parlor,!and. as he placed the bottle and glasses upoxn the table he ob- served, "' Annie has left youi then?"  ' Why, to tell. you the truth, .replied the young. gentleman, ":she: flew into' a tiff "at something- I said;, but I am sure I' did not mean to Offend her."   "I am quite certain you did not," inter- jected BelL ' ' * merely paid her -some little compli- aentV;'  i   "It was very kind of' you," said Bell,: "and she ought to have felt herself honored and flattered. It isn't as if you were stran- gers to each other; but you have been ac- quainted from childhood. To be sure. 'How do you like this cider, sir?" "It's excellent. But I really hope that your daughter'won't think I meant to insult her." "Not she, thlle silly puss I It's only her coyness."' "I understand what coyness is. It's al- ways so at first. But what were you going to say, Mr. Bell? Allow me to replenish your glass: I don't care to try another glass," said' Horatio. "'Pon my soul, I hadn't an idea that Miss Annie was half so swee;, a creature. But, by the bye, I sup- pose it is not true that there was anything between Miss Annie and that scoundrel, Harry Todd?" "All utterly false, sir; a scandalous re- port. Annie could not bear the fellow." "Why, I wad told that she came rushing out of the house to rescue him when he was being carried off by the recruiting officer- a deuced good riddance, by the bye." "an excellent riddance, sir. But as for Annie committing herself in such a way, I will tell you how the report arose. It was my servant girl Martha who took a fancy to that Harry Todd, and ran out frantic in the way you have heard." "Well, I am glad to hear this version of the tale-for your sake," added Horatio. "It would indeed be a pity if, such a sweet creature was to throw heorself away on such an ugly lout as that Harry Todd." ".A dreadful drunkard too," added Bell: "and such a rake amongst the women. Since we are talking upon a fi'iendly a foot- ing, Mr, Thurston, I do not mind. telling you that I have rather' high views in respect to my daughter." "That's just what I told Miss Annie here now," interrupted Horatio--" that I should take the liberty of dropping in occasionally for a little friendly chat." "As often as you choose, sir-and the oftener the better. My dear Mr. Thurston, excuse me for the liberty I take, as you know that I am foreman in your father's shop." "No offence, my dear Mr. Bell. Proceed." "I was -on. the point of observing -that i your excellent advice and important: appro- ' val has set the seal of sanction on ,my re- solves:. Annie must marry .a gentleman. And, if I am not too bold, I should. be infi- nitely obliged if you would take. the oppor- tunity of giving her yopr..adv yice on this subject-knowing her as yaou have from childhood,. and being my: employer's son." "'I shall drop, in to-morrow. or next. day, and: have a chat. with Miss Anmtie..'!  "Do so," rejoined Bell, " and I will furnish   you an opportunity to give her a little of your excellent advice. But when I think of it," he added, suddenly assuming a seri. ous look, "your father, and mother pnight not be pleased at your coming to my humble house."' '"Who the deuce -cares?" said Horatio. ":But I forgot--you might; and, of course I wouldn't do anything in the world to injure you. Well,' in future I will come in the evening just about dusk; and so the old people needn't know anything about it. Oh, don't mention it, Mr. Bell; your. daugh- ter is charming, and I'm proud to be taken into your confidence in respect to your views." Horatio now rose from his seat, and shook; hands with Mr. Bell and left. When Horatio was gone, Mr. Bell, on" finding himself once more alone, rubbed his hands gleefully together, muttering, "It is, as good as done I  He has swallowed the bait; hie is already deeply ia love with Annie." The father knew full well what was pass i uing in her mnAd; but he was sternly resolved to break her spirit. and compel her to fall into his views.  He however said nothing till dinner was over; and then, as Annie was about to quit the room, he desired her to resume her seat.. "You know what I told you some little time back?" he said abruptly. "I hope, father, that you are not about to" renew a topic which is alike most disagreea-' ble and improper for my ears. If my poor mother were alive, you would not dare en- tertain such ideas." And Annie began to weep. "A truce to this nonsense," cried Bell sternly. "If your mother were alive, she. would assist me in procuring for you the most eligible match; and, by heaven, I will not be thwarted. I can tell you: that I was nearly mad with rage at the way you treat; ed Horatio Thurston just now." "Father," ejaculated Annie, starting up, ' is it possible that you can address me in those terms? That insolent young man spoke to me   in a way which I could not ,tolerate, and never will put up with; and you, father, instead of resenting the insult which your daughter experienced, now make her, own . propriety a subject of re- proach to her.." "Fool!  do understand me," exclaimed Mr. Bell, with rage in his voice. "'If you listened to the dishonorable proposals of any ma nwere he the proudest noble in the land, I  would kill you; but what you have to expect from Horatio is an offer of mar; riage. And beware, how you conduct your- self toward him ina wray that, shall prevent - aim from making you such a  proposal; and again I  tell you that if your mother was , alive she would approve of my conduct." .   "She would not, father; and it is. a blas. phemy against, her name to. say that she would," exclaimed An ie with vehemence. "Woll,l e will put an end tO this con- versation," interjected Mr. Bell abruptly; "but first understand me well, for my mind is made up. If you do not give such proper encouragement to Horatio Thurstoi' as a young damsel may, I will render. the house unbearable to you; and if my views fail through your cursed stubbornness, I will turn you out of doors--and-what is more, I will bestow my curse upon you, and on my death-bed that curse shall be repeated more witheringly stilL" Having thus spoken, the'brutal father left the room, banging the door with violence behind him, and Annie sunk down in a chair, as it were by the awful words which had thus been thundered forth against her. CHAPTER V. IT was on the third evening after- the visit of Horatio Thurston to Mr. Bell's cottage, that theo young gentleman was one evening, soon after dusk, wending his way from his fathe;'s house in the direction of that dwell- 'ing. He walked slowly, for he was engaged in thought. "Thereijs something about that girl that overawes one; and now I begin to understand what is meant by the natural dignity of a virtuous woman. I always thought until recently that it was something only to be, found in romances, or else in' thie highest class of society; but Annie Bell has taught me quite different.'" Here Horatio Thurston stopped short, as he approached the cottage; and he seemed to be struck with a sudden hesitation whe- ther to proceed. '"But after all," he said to himself " this is very absurd on my part, I think I had better cut the matter short. My father. apd mother, would be shocked at the idea of my marrying' their foreman's daughter." But he had not gone many yards when an irre- sistible feeling compelled him to stop short again, and revert his eyes toward the dwell- ing of her whose beauty had established its emnpire, though so unwillingly on' her 'side, over his heart. Horatio Thurston acordingly: prceeded to the cottage; and the door was opened by Martha, who invariably looked vexed and annoyed when he made his appearance. Duing the two weeks which had elapsed , Annie had endured the visits of the young man for the simple purpose of avoiding any more tferric scenes with her father and because she hoped that the departure of Horatio Thurston from the neighborhood,  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7116-00000011"/> when he obtained his commission, would effectually relieve her from his visits. Horatio Thurston entered the parlor;upon the occasion of which kwe are now specially speaking, with the off-hand familiarity of one who knew himself to be a thoroughly welcome guest to the master of the house. But a old and distant salutation was the greeting he always received from Annie; for it was not merely that she loved another, but because she could never forget the in- dignities which Horatio Thurston had heaped upon Harry, and that it was entirely through him that her lover had lost his employment and had been driven to enlist. "Any news about your commission, Mr. Thurston?" said Bell iuquiringly; for he was always apprehensive of hearing that the young man's departure might be precipi- tated ere his schemes were worked out to complete success. "Not yet," was the welcome response- welcome at least to the father, but quite otherwise to the daughter. "From a letter received this morning, it may be a month before I obtain it. But somehow or other I am not now at all in a hurry to leave home;" and he looked signifi- cantly at Annie, who did not however ap- pear to notice that she was the object of his regards. "Indeedl"  exclaimed Mr. Bell. "I thought that you found a country life very dull after the pleasures of New York." 1 Yes, horribly dull, until recently," re- sponded Horatio; then, thinking that he was going a little too far, he turned away from the topic by observing, "So I understand Ottis has got into difficulty. It is said that there are whisperings in the village about his having lent himself to that recruiting officer who was here some weeks ago, and that he helped him to kidnap some of the young villagers." -"Well, there is a rumor to that effect," ,replied Bell, feeling rather uneasy at the topic.; for he had observed the color in Snnie'scheeks come and go rapidly at an allusion .which so forcibly reminded her of him on whom the father well knew her af- ,fvctions were deeply set. "So Ottis, .then," resumed Horatio, "has got himself into bad odor with the trades- men in the village. But at all events he did one good act; fr 'I understand that he helped somehow or other-but I have never learned sihe particulars-in getting the vil- lage rid of that ill-conditioned lout, Todd."  At lhat moment Annie started visibly, while her countenance became crimson; then she rushed to .the .door and quit the , room. "Is anything the matter?" demanded jHoratio, astounded at this abrupt departure of the young lady. ".I thought," he added, with a look full of annoyanc'e, "that you   had positively assured me there was nothing between her and Harry Todd, but that it was your servant girl?" "I did so; and I informed you correctly, Mr. Thurston," replied the foreman. "The fact is, she has been with us a long time, and Annie has taken a sort of liking to her. Martha is terribly cut up at being separated from her lover, and has made Annie believe that the fellow is a 'very excellent young man; so Annie pities her, and would be in- clined to take her part in the matter. You know from your own experience that young women will stick to each other in all love affairs; and therefore I have no doubt Angie felt annoyed that you should have expressed yourself in sucth strong terms against Mar- tha's lover." "Well, I am glad you hare told me," observed Horatio, "because I will not touch upon that topic another time in Miss Bell's presence." "It would be better to avoid it," replied. the foreman. "Ir don't think, by the bye," obseived Horatio, affecting an indifferent air, "that this coyness on the part of Annie wears oif at all. She seems moro reserved this even- ing than ever." "She occasionally speaks of you, 'Mr. Thurston," returned the wily Bell; " and ia very friendly'terms, too." "I am glad to hear it," said the young gentleman; and for a few moments he be- came thoughtful. "She's a very nice girl," he added, again breaking silence; "and it's no compliment to say that the man is to be envied who will have her for his wife. But," continued Horatio, "is not Miss Annie going to join us again this evening?"' "I have no doubt if you wish it," respon- ded Bell, "I will call her;" and lie quitted the room. Ascending to his daughter's chamber he tried -the door, but found it fasteued; he knocked gently, but she did, not answer, for all her senses were absorbed in the depth of her affliction, and she heard not the sum- mons. He knocked again, and a little louder. The sound, reaching her ears, startled her. "Who is it?" she said in a voice clouded with mournfulness. "Your father, Annie," he responded in -a low whisper; "I desire that you will come down." "I cannot, I am not well." So Mr. Bell, composing his -features as Well as he could, descended to the parlor. "Annie has taken unwell," he said to ; Horatio, "she therefore throws herself upon your kindness to excuse her this evening.'" "I am truly sorry to hear that she is un- [ well," returned Horatio, "and I shall not 3 fail to call to'morrow evening to assure my- , self that she is better." I   He then took leave, and while retracing t   his steps to the mansion he could not help saying to himself, "It is strange, but I am madly in love with that girL" It was about ten o'clock when he entered the mansion, and ascended to the drawing- room, where his father and mother, with Aunt Jane, were seated. "What is it, Horatio, that makes you leave us regularly every evening after cof- fee?" inquired Mrs. Thurston. "No good, I dare say," observed Aunt Jane. "Evil be to those who evil think," ex- claimed Horatio petulantly. "The fact is; I, like a little walk in the cool of the evening.' "But you remain out'so late," rejoined his mother, "and I am sure the dews at this houi cannot be good for you." "They seem to smell very much of bran- dy," remarked Aunt Jane, who had caught a whiff of her nephew's breath as he turned round to address her a moment back. "I hope you don't go down to Bushnell's of an evening?" said Mr. Thurston, look- ing at his son with mingled suspicion and alarm. "I should rather think not," he returned spappishy. "Certainlly not," exclaimed Mrs. Thurston. "You   know that Aunt Jane says sharp things now, and then, but she doesn't mean any harm." Sometimes my   sharp things hit home," observed Aunt Jane.  "'But Horatio hasn't told you yet where he wanders these beauti- ful evenings." "Well, if you must know, I smoke my cigar through the fields." "'And are you not afraid of gypsies and robbers?" said Aunt Jane with something very much like contempt. The young gentleman did not condescend to take aLy notice of this observation, and the discourse speedily Bflowed into another channel. Another fortnight passed, during which - Horatio continued to be a constant evening. visitor at Bell's cottage. Annie, still anxious to avoid as much as possible angering her father, still looked forward to his depar- ture from   the neighborhood as the only i means of releasing  her from  the ordeal 1 through which she was every evening doom- ed to pass, for as he had hitherto made her ] no open declaration  of love, she secretly I hoped that he was too shrewd and worldly. wise to fall into the snare which her lather I had set for him             t Mr. Bell now began to feel somewhat an-  noyed and apprehensive because Horatio did I not bring matters to a crisis. Accordingly c one evening, at the expiration of a month of r incessant visits, Bell, of his own accord, gave ] Anuie some hint to leave the room, a hint a which she was by no means slow in obeying. v "Wel Mr. Thurston," he said after a fuw t   ', remarks on different subjects, and when they were alone together, "I have made up my mind to take Annie to Chicago." "Ahl you have made up your mind," ejaculated the youth, with a start and a look of annoyance. "Well, the fact is, Bell," he said. after a brief pause, "you need not go  there to find a suitable husband for your charming daughter," The foreman affected to stare at Horatio in speechless amazement. "What I say istrue'" continued the young gentleman. "In a word then, I love your daughter, and I will marry her. It's serious, there's no joking about it." "But, my dear Mr.; Thurston," said Bell, still appearing as if he could scarcely con- ouer his surprise, "it is impossible, your father would never consent." ' 'I know he would not, but what is that to me?" "Have I not already told you," exclaimed Horatio petulantly, "1hat I do tot want it. To a certain extent rfam independent of my father. The estates are all entailed. and Cannot be left away from me, and if I elope with Annie he could not blame you, and need never know that you were aware of what was going on." "No,"' replied Bell, " if this alliance should take place it would be my duty to accompa- ny my daughter to the altar, and in i)erson bestow her upon you." "Well, just as you like, I only threw out the hint. But pray give me a decisive answ:er this evening." "And suppose that I yield to your urgent entreaties," resumed  the foreman, what course do you propose?" "Just-to wait till I have got my commis- sion, and join my regiment, then I can easily procure a leave of absence, when you could meet me with Annie at Chicago, and there, with a special license. the ceremony could be accomplished." -  y dear sir," returned the foreman, '.'I cannot possibly refuse to yield to your en- treaties. I therefore give my consent." "Thanks, a  thousand thanks," exclaimed Horatio. "May I  come to-morrow evening with the assurance of being kindly received by Miss Annie?" "Will you take my advice in one thing, Mr. Thurston?" asked Bell, as an idea struck him how to. manage the matter with his daughter. ' Annie, as you are aware, is a girl of very delicate sensibilities, it would, therefore, please me, better that you should continue to visit upon the same terms as at present, and that even when taking your departure from the neighborhood, you should make no formal avowal to my daughter. But so soon as you have,.you can write her a   letter, inclosed in one to myself, and in which you can address her in terms befitting the circumstances." $  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7116-00000012"/> "I have/already said that I will follow your wishe in all things" Then with a cordial shake of the hand, Ho- ratio Thirston took his leave of the foreman. Duri g the fortnight which .now elapsed, Horatio continued his evening visits regular- ly; and Annie could not help observing that Be seemed to place himself on a more familiar i footing with her father than before; while to- wards herself his conduct was marked with as much pointed attention as circumstances would allow him to pay her. Still she main- tained her cold reserve towards "him; but he was now accustomed to it, and felt assureW that it was nothing but what her father had represented-namely, a coyness that would wear off. Still she had her misgivings that some secret treachery was at work, and that there wras a secret understanding between her father and Horatio. She, however, held her peace; and thus the days passed Bn-the evening visits were repeated-until Horatio one night announced joyfully that he was pro- moted to a commission in the army. It seemed as if Annie was stricken with a blow; for she thought of Harry Todd being there, and Thurston might seek some opportunity' of tyrannizing over him, and overpowered by her feelings, was compelled to quit the room abruptly; when the wily Bell said to the young gentleman, "Now you can' have no doubt as to the state of my daughter's feelings towards you. "Is it possible," exclaimed Horatio, "that she is so much affected by this sudden an- nouncement of my immediate departure from the neighborhood. "It. is so," responded Bell; "beneath that apparent reserve on her part, she cherishes a fond affection for you." "I leave with my father to-morrow for Cin- cinnati, to procure my outfit. The regiment is now at Nashville-and, by-the-bye, it hap- pens to be the very same in which that fellow Todd serves." "Ah, indeed i" ejaculated Bell, as if now having the circumstance recalled to his mem- ory for the first time. "Yes-it is so. But never mind him; we have important things to think of. May I not see Annie again this evening?" "Do you not think it would be much bet- ter that you should suffer her to compose the feelings which have been so suddenly exci- ted? I beseech this forbearance on your part." "I am entirely in your hands," responded Horatio; and then after some further conver- sation, he took his departure from the cottage. CHAPTER VL. HARRY TODD, and the other recruits join- ed their regiment at Camp Wood, Ky., about   six weeks after their departure from New- port. They were put into squads for drill His officer was harsh, stern and severe, niore especially to Harry Todd. Harry did his best to give satisfaction; and being naturally quick and intelligent, he really acquitted himself in a manner which ought to have pleased any individual. But firom the very instant of his enlistment, he had become a marked man; for the officer had not'failed to let the non-commissioned of- fiers aund the rest of his comrades know what ,Ae had done. At the expiration of a month the regiment got orders to march, and they took up their line of march for Nashville; on their way had a fight at Bowling Green, and marched to Nash- ville, arriving there on the 23d of Februarjy 1862. Here we may inform the reader that at this place Capt. Horatio Thurston joined the regiment. After remaining here a week, they took their line of march for Pittsburgh Land- ing, where they arrived on the 7th of April, and immediately went into battle, in which ' Harry Todd distinguished himself for his bravery. The army then advanced on Cor- inth, which place was taken on the 29th of May. From here they marched to Steven- son, Alabama, and followed the rebel army to Louisville, Kentucky, arriving here Sept. 20th. We must now transport the' reader back to Newport, where he shall find Mr. Ottis post- master. The writer is at a loss to know how he got ths. Well, Mr. JoneS, who had the post-office, died, and Mr, Ottis applied to Mr. Thurstou to get him appointed, which he did. We must now look into Mr. Ottis's office on the morning after Mr. Thurston had mailed. his letters, and there we shall find Mr. Ottis opening the letter bag which the mail had just brought in. "And so there's a conspiracy against me in the town -eh?" said Ottis to himself. "Well then, I will have a conspiracy against- them, for I don't mean to be postmaster for nothing. If I don't find out all their secrets my name isn't Ottis. I will get them all into my power, and teach them what it is to of- fend a man like me." Ottis took the bag with him into his little back room, shut himself in, and began sort- ing the letters. Next he proceeded very de- liberately and carefully to open the letters ad- dressed to some of the merchants; and hav- ing made himself master of the contents, he sealed them up again in such a manner that it was impossible to discern that their sanc- tity had been violated. "Hah I here's a letter for Bell," he said to himself; " and a good thick letter, too. What's the postmark? Louisville." Thus speaking Mr. Ottis broke the seal of the letter. As he read on, an expression of the utmost surprise to find out how Horatio ; Thurston and. Mr. Bell had planned it for An-   nie and him to be married. "And I have managed to keep Xnnie from getting that Harry Todd's letters, and she thinks that he was killed in battle. Well, I musti write a letter to Harry's officer and let' him know how things is up at Newport." We must return to Louisville. The army had arrived, and it was, preparing to move when Harry met Captain Courtenay, his offi- cer.  "Well, what are you doing helire, moping all by yourself?" exclaimed his Captain. "Well," said Harry, "I would like to get a furlough for ten days, to go up to Newport." "Well," observed his Captain, "you can't have it; and by-the-bye, perhaps you think that Mr. Bell's pretty daughter is pining, and sighing, and moping away after you. But there is nothing or the sort." Harry started and gazed with surprise upon his officer. "Ahl you may well look at me it that manner," resumed the officer.- "I know what's going on at Newport; but of course I am not the man. to let the cat out of the bag. However, I would justgive you' one piece of advice, and that is, you' had better not buoy yourself up with the hlope that Miss 'Annie' means to wait till your three years have ex- pired. ,She was meant- for your betters, I can tell you. And so now you know." With these words his Captain turned away and drew forth his handkerchief; but in so doing a letter fell upon the ground, altogether unperceived by him. He quitted Harry's prep sence.  We repeat that not for an instant did Har. ry believe a, syllable, to the prejudice of the constancy of his beloved; but still he could not help faricying that there must be some- thing going on at Newport which had reach- ed the officer's 'knowledge, and led him to speak in thait manner. Perchance Mr. Bell himself was endeavoring to bring about a marriage between Annie and "some suitor of hisaown selection. . PBrhaps,.to, Annie' had as yet remhained ih ignorance of this design against 'lher happiness; or perhaps, being aware of it, the had forborne from mentioning it ia her letters for feat of augmenting the sorrows of him'whoiim her correspondence was intended to conisle. While the youing soldier was thus 'rumina- ting, fiis ees suddenly fell upon the letter which lay upon the ground.' He proceeded to pick it up; 'the' name of Annie coupled with that of Horatio Thurston, caused the young soldier' to start with amazement; he began to devout with avidity 'the cintents of the document. - They ran as follows'* "POST OFFICE, XNj*POnT September 23d,'1862. "DEAR' CAPT AN COTURKTENAY' : "I am ve ry iuch obliged to you for hav. ing thought of me. I received your welcome   letter, and Aist no tine in replying., Well, r the Post-Office has fallen;,into my hands; but I 'am not the man to give myself any airs on that a'Iount.; I sincerely hope that I shall some day have the pleasure of seeing you again i' and if ever you come to Newport on the same business as befbre; you will, know where to find' a friend to assist, "You ask me whya news there is at News. port, and whether Bet's girl frets after that. good-for-nothing: fellow, Harry Todd. I am going to tell you such a-piece of-business that only came Ito my knoWledge this very morn. ing-but how you will excuse'me for not ex- plaining. i  "Would" you 'believe it I Horatio Thurs- ton, who has Just got his commission in your own rbgiment, is going to marryAnniel It's all settledl I don't mean thatMr; Thursthn has given his consent;iifor the fact is, heo knows nothing about it. It's all private like; and young Horatio has planned everything with Bell as nice as possible., Ah I that fel- low Bell is wide awake;, I can' tell yo .; "But:as I dare say you will be interested, with this little bit of gossip, particularly. as Horatio Thurston now belongsn to your regi. ment, and I suppose meansto take his wife with him when he joins. I will just give you a little insight into what's going on. Young Thurston is at this mbmeft in Louisville wait ing for a leave of absence, %O/n the 27th hb is to be at'Chicago to get the special license and make everything;,right, Mr. Bell and his daughter are to :leave -Newport early on the 29th, adid are to ibeet Horatio at Chicago by noon; and: then the young couple are to be spliced at once. What do yoiu think of this? An  artful dodge, say I. Of course you must keep it all dark, and not mention it to a  soul. In fact, it is' one of the. deepest and best contrived plots I ever knew in all my life. It beats anything I ever read in a romance. No more at present. ; "Yours truly, ' .DAVID OTIS'L" It would be difficult to describe the state of, excitement into which Harry Todd, was astonished by 'the astounding revelation contained in this'letter. There was a feeling like . madness in his brain, and for a few minutes he was utterly incompetent for de, liberate reflection. No,/ it, ias but too true; and he could not doubtthat Annie. was to be made the victim of a  treacherous under. standing' between her. father and . Horatio, Thurston. What on' earth ,was he to do? oh 1, what was he to do? Was he not bound hand, and foot by his position as a soldier? Should he ask. for .prompt leave of absence? No; ,heo recollectedgthat, a furlough had been refused him. ,But still what was he to do? what was he to do? This was the  -morning;of the 27th; on the 29th, in the middle of the: day the cere-  &#xD;<pb n="24 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7116-00000013"/> mony was to take place. He had only two days and a few hours to reach Chicago, and but two dollars  his pocket. It was a hundred and eighty     complished in two days and a few hoursr For an instant he shrunk from the, appar- ent hopelessness of such an undertaking; but the next moment he exclaimed, "By heaven, I will do ith"Yes, he would fly to the deliverance of his Annie. Harry accordingly tarried, no longer. He sped through the town and took the cars as far as his. money lasted, and then proceeded on foot on his way for Chicago. We must now return to Newport. It was in the evening of the 27th, after -supper, and-just as Annie was rising from her seat to retire to her chamber, that her father said to her, "By the bye,: Annie, I forgot to mention that to-morrow morning we are going to Chicago. You may as well accompany me." As a matter of course, Mr. Bell had ;not shown her the letter, which Horatio Thurston had specially addressed to her through him, and in which he made her an offer of his hand. - The father intended to leave every- -thing in the shape of explanation until the last moment. .. Annie retired to rest; and sleep foll upon her eyes. . She. awoke at an early hour, and heard her father moving in his own room, which was next to hers. She attired herself in her best apparel, but it was with a flut- tering heart and trembling hands- that she performed the duties of the toilet., In case of the worst, she took with her whatever amount of money she, possessed, and which consisted of sixty dollars. She . likewise secured about her person some few little trinkets. By this time breakfast was ready; but she could not induce herself to swallow a morsel of food. "I do not feel well to-day," she at length said, " and would much rather you would excuse my accompanying you." "Tho journey will do you good," respond- ed Mr. Bell. "We shall not return home for a week, and. therefore you must take a few necessaries with you. Be quick, Annie, for it is time we should start." "1 My dear miss," said the, faithful servant girl, '" how unhappy, you look I Surely you do not fear that there is something wrong in the sudden journey you are about to take?" "Martha, my dear. girl, I know not what to think," replied Annie, with a sort of hys- terical nervousness. "I am unhappy-very unhappy. It may be. all fancy, on my part; and heaven grant that it is I But I cannot help entertaining some terrible apprehension. Even now it seems to me as if I were taking a last farewell of my little chamber, and of you also!" "Do not go, dear miss--do not go!" said the girl, weeping.   "Annie, are you ready?" exclaimed her father from the, b6ttom of the stairs. "In a moment, father," she replied; then having hurried on her bonnet and shawl, she embraced Martha with a stronger pre- sentiment than ever that it was really a farewell she was thus taking. "Good bye, my dear young mistress," said the good-hearted servant girl, who was frightened as well as grieved at Annie's ap- pearance; for though, it was a fine warm autumn morning, yet Mr. Bell's daughter shivered as if under the influence of an ice wind. Annie sped down stairs with a little parcel of necessaries in her hand, and found her father waiting somewhat impatiently. Shle flung a quick -but melancholy look around the little parlor, still feeling' as if she were bidding a long adieu to her once happy home; and then she issued forth from the cottage. It was not long until they were seated in the cars, and proceeding on their journey. Mr.. Bell discoursed with cheerfulness and kindness, and imperceptibly Annie's spirits rose somewhat. The excitement of travel- ing contributed its effect thus to give a healthier tone to her mind, and by the time Chicago was reached she had almost suc- ceeded in persuading herself that she had been torturing her heart with very foolish and groundless fears. Mr. Bell and his daughter alighted from the cars, and took a hack for the hotel, where they soon arrived. Here the father desired the waiter to -conduct them imme- diately to a private room--a command that, was promptly obeyed. But ere the domestic retired, Bell exchanged with him a few 'words, uttered rapidly aside and in a very low whisper, The fact is, he inquiired whe- ther a gentle   amed Thurston was in the hotel, 1 d on recedhng an answer in the affirmative, he desired th waiter to go with his (Mr. ll's) compliments, and say that he would join Mr. Thurstton in ten minutes. All her suspicions, all her misgivings, came back at once, vividly and with re- newed power, to the mind of the unhappy Annie. This whispering appeared darkly ominous, fand her heart sank within' her. She threw a frightened and inquiring look upon her father; the glance that met her Qwn seemed the strongest confirmation of the truth of her apprehensions; for on her father's countenance there was now an ex- pression of a grave and serious meaning, mingled with the stern resolve of a deter- mined man. "Annie," he said, "the moment is now arrived for explanations." "Ah!" she ejaculated, but in a low and stifled voice; and then, sinking upon a seat, she gazed on her sire with mingled wildness and vacancy.   &#xD;<pb n="-25" xml:id="VAC7116-00000014"/> "Daughter," he resumed, addressing her in a firm and implacable voice, "it is your parent who is about to make known to you his intentions; and I warn you to beware how you prove a disobedient child. Listen. Prepare yourself to hear something that may startle you, but take care how you shriek out, for I am resolved not to endure any love-sick girlish airs, much less to be moved by them.- Within the hour-that is passing you will bestow your hand upon Mr. Horatio Thurston i" "No, father-never!" responded Annie, suddenly acquiring a degree of firmness which astonished even herself as she expe- rienced it; and slowly rising from the chair which she had taken, she stood before her father pale and colorless as a marble statue, but with a strange gleaming in the eyes and a strong compression of the lips. "Annie," said Mr. Bell, staggering for an instant, " will you dare your father's curse? My mind is set upon the accomplishment of this grand and brilliant alliance which I have labored to bring about for you. Do not interrupt me, but listen. Mr. Thursthn has offered you his hand. Here is a letter which he sent me two or three days back, with the idea that I'should deliver it to you at once. You can read it," "LOumVILLg, Ky., Sept. 22d, 1862. '   MY DEAR SIR: "According to promise, I take the first opportunity of writing to Miss Bell and yourself "The letter to your dear Annie I enclose unsealed, that ydo may peruse it ere placing it in her hands. I fervently hope that my suit will prove acceptable to your daughter, and from all that has passed between you and me, as well as from the evidence of feel- ing which she testified on the last occasion I was at your house, I entertain no appre- hension upon the subject. 'And now, my   dear sir, I will proceed to explain the arrangements I propose, and to which I hope and trust you will assent. !" r shall leave Louisville for 'Chicago on the 27th, and H will meet you, on the 29th, at Marsh's hotel; and within an hour then passing, your dear Annie may become my own much-beloved 'wife. "Yours most sincerely, and soon to be your son-in-law, "HORATIO THURSTON." After she had finished reading it, Annie shook her head, and there was something strange and even terrible in the fortitude with which she was armed at this moment. 4' Do not think that I am uttering any idle threat," responded Mr. Bell, still cold,'stern and implacable. " If you refuse to receive Horatio Thurston as your husband, H will   Jv drive you forthi with my bitterest, bitterest curse." "I Merciful God, what will become ofm rel" exclaiimed the wretched Annie, sinking ipon her knees andclasping her hands in bitterest anguish as her father produced a pistol fronm his pocket. , "You now know all," he continued, slowly returning the weapon to- the pocket whence he had taken it; and neither by word nor motion did he bid his daughter rise. fromn the suppliant posture to which she-lad sunk. ' Horatio Tlhgrston 'is here within these walls.' All the requisite arrangements are made; he has the marriage license, andsthe clergyman is no doubt in attendance.' Will you, or will you not, become his wife? Wll you force your countenance to assume at least a look of resignation; will you suffer it to appear that it is With your consent as well as with mine, that this marriage takes place. Or will you fail in all or any one of these details, and ruin everything. If so, deal candidly with me at once. I shall then know whether I have or have not a daugh- ter. If I have, you will see me happy be- yond the power of language to describe, If I have not, then need you only remain/here long enough to reeeive my curse, andt the same instant that yon door closes behind you as I drive you :from my presence, will the report of this weapon sound your father's death-knell in your ear.  "Now, Annie,"' said her father, "your decision-what is it? speak; there is no time to lose. Mr. Thurston must not be tri- fled with." "Fatherf--fther-I  am half mad," ex- claimed Annie, started up to her feet as if suddenly galvanized. "Oh, by the memory of my sainted mother, I beseech you not to accomplish this wickedness'l No, no; you will hot-you can not. It is too terrible I Oh, if you talk of suicide, it is I who shall become the distracted suicide!" "Enough I this must end!" exclaimed Mr. Bell, in a terrible voice; "it has already lasted too long. How is it to be? Say at once.   I will be trifled with no longer. Your decision; quick, quick-'your decision. Talk of madness--it is I who am well nigh driven to it." "Oh God, what am   I to do? what will become of me," and again did Annie sink down into the chair horror-stricken, dismayed, yet frenzied. ;' Father, if I say yes, it will be my death; and not only my death, but that of another--f him whom   I love-to whom my troth is pllghted." "Allude not to that man," ejaculated Bell, more fiercely even than before. "You must say yes-you shall, unless you choose to be- come my murderess I And it will be parri- cide, Annie-parricide--I repeat the unpar- donable crime." The unfortunate young woman felt as if  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7116-00000015"/> her senses were abandoning lher. Her hands relaxed the clasp in which they had held each other; her arms dropped down listlessly by her side, and she gazed, with a sort of maniac vacancy upon her father. He re. peated his question demanding her decision. She heard' th:hat. lie spoke, but understood not the purport of his words. A third time did he speak to her while she was in this coudi- tion,and she thought he required some an- swer; but without knowing to wlhat she was answering, she mechanically murmured i "; yes." -"Then may heaven bless you, dearest Annie!" were the words which now all in a moment plainly and intelligibly smote upon her, ears. Her waking dream vanished; she unlder- stood her position in all its frightful reality, and she stretched out her haiid to hold her father back as lie rushed away from her. The next instant he had quitted the apart- ment, and she found herself alone. It was in the enthusiasm of joy and triumph that he had thus sped away to see Horatio Thurs- ton. Annie comprehended what shhe had done- that she had spoken the fatal yes, and that her father had gone to signify her assent to the loathed and detested object who sought her as his bride. Oh! had she then for a single instant, and even in the unconscious- ness of that moment proved faithless to her plighted love to iHarry Todd. There was anguish in the thought; and every other consideration vanishing from her mind, she rushed from the room. lShe, had not taken off her bonnet and shawl on first entering, and thus there was naught to delay her. - Down the stairs she precipitated herself, dashed past all aston- ished servant, who was ascending at the time, and flitted forth from the hotel. Along the street she hurried, reckless of the atten- tion which her manner excited, and in a few minutes sho gained a more secluded part of the town. There she slackened pace to re- cover breath. All of a sudden an ejacula- tion of joy fell on her ears; and at the instant she raised her eyes in recognition of that well-known voice, she was clasped in the arms of Harry Todd. CHAPTER VIL A QUARTER of an hour after this meeting the lovers might have been observed wend- ing their way through the streets of Chicago, and speeding towards a grove, where they could screen themselves from pursuit and enter into those mutual explanations which were so much longed for.   The reader will perhaps be surprised to learn that Harry appeared most respectably attired in a good suit of clothes, and had also an air of superiority above his condition, which even in the nurry and excitement of her thoughts Annie could not help noticing. In a few minutes they reached the grove, and there, upon the huge trunk of a tree which had been cut down, did they seat themselves. Harry then entered upon his narrative, telling. her how the discovery of Ottis's letter to Captain Courtnay had made him acquainted with the whole plot. Annie now comprehended why it was that Ottis had worn so sardonic a look as lie stood upon his threshold; but. her -thoughts were speedily diverted, and most painfully so, into another channel, wlien Harry proceeded, in melancholy candor, to reveal to hier that he was not absent from his regiment with leave, but that he was a deserter. Fortuiately for, the poor girl she knew not the consequences to' which he had rendered himself liable; yet she was sufficiently acquainted with the subject to perceive that he had taken a most serious step, and one which would draw down upon him at least some punlishment. But all her interest was quickly absorbed in the narrative which Harry gave of the fatigues and the privations he had, suffered during his immense journey of one hundred and[ eighty miles, accomplished in exactly two days and a half. The greater portion of his journey he had performed on foot, until at last he had been compelled, through fear of not reaching Chcago in time, to give all the money he had in his pocket for a ride in the cars as far as it would- take him. i' This morning," he continued, "on alight- ing from the cars, I still found myself many miles from Chicago, without a cent in my pocket, and racked by the terrible apprehen- sion that it would be impossible for me to reach my destination in time to save you. At about nine o'clock, as I was approaching a village, my ears suddenly caught the sound of wheels and horses' hoofs dashing along the road with a celerity that at once convinced me something was wrong. Then I heard the screams of female voices, and almost im- mediately an open carriage, containing a gentleman and two ladies, and drawn by two high spirited horses, came rushing along be- hind me. At a glance I perceived that the horses were running away. The gentleman had dropped the lines and the vehicle was swaying from side to side in a manner which threatened it with an immediate upset. I sprang forward, caught the lines, and al- though dragged along for upwards of a minute, to the imminent danger df my life, I succeeded in stopping the animals. The thanks which I received from the gentleman and two ladies were of the most fervid kind. The gentleman made me a present of fifty dollars, and bidding me farewell, pursued his   way. You may conceive the joy which I experienced. It was an unspeakable relief to obtain the means of prosecuting my journey and purchase a suit of plain clothes. I selected a suit of this kind to disguise my- self the better, for no one would think- of looking for a deserter in such a dress. I walked on, and presently I obtained a ride in a farmer's wagon that was proceeding for several miles in the same direction as myself. Thug there was another long walk, and I alighfted in the very street where a few mo- ments afterwards, to my surprise and joy, I happily encountered you." Having given mutual explanations, they lost no time in discussing the plans which' were naturally suggested by 'the circumstan- ces of their position. Harry entertained not the slightest idea of returning to his .regi- ment. His idea was that they should repair with the least possible delay to some remote place, and there fix their abode till the marriage ceremony should be accomplished, and then, after their union, that they should repair to some other place where, under a feigned name, they might settle down in the hope that he would effectually baffle any search that might be instituted after him as a deserter, and where, by his honest indus- try, a livelihood might be obtained. When their plans were settled they ext amincd their stock of money, and found that they had exactly eighty dollars in their pos- session. a Having rested and conversed for nearly an hour in the grove, they continued their way, not exactly knowing in what direction, but resolved to wander on till they reached some main road, where they meant to take the first public conveyance bound ,for any place sufficiently distant to answer their purposes. In another hour their design was so far carried out that they found themselves seated together in the cars proceeding to Galena. On arriving at Galena they immediately hired two distinct lodgings, and at once took tlhe requisite steps for having the marriage ceremony completed, which was done in about a week.  The marriage ceremony being duly accomplished, the young, pair experienced a sense of happiness which absorbed every apprehension of future sor. row. The day after their union they pro- ceeded to Lyons, where they resolved to settle down. Here they hired a couple of rooms in. a respectable, house, but at a cheap rent, and'lost no time in carrying into exe- cution the plans already laid down. Adopting the fictitious name of Mortimer, I-arry had little circulars printed to thlWef- feet that he sought to establish a school; for boys of a tender age, whom he undertook to instruct in the rudiments of a plain education, while other circulars announced. that Annie would execute needlework, either plain or fancy, on very reasonable terms.   The landlady of the house was a respect- able, kind-hearted Woman, and from the very first moment of her new lodgers' arrival she experienced an interest in them; and Annie's circulars, aided by the strong recosmenda- tions of Mrs. Harrison, the good widow, speedily produced the desired results. Work came in rapidly, aid as she executed it with neatness and punctuality she gained the favor of those who patronized her. Three or four day scholars were likewise ob'tainie for 'Harry, arid the parents of these children were so much pleased with his address and his unassuming manners that they promised to',extend their recommendations to the ut- most of their power. Weeks passed away and grew into months, and Annie had more work thai she could do, for Harry would not permit her to toil to a degree, that should injure her. health, es- pecially as he himself had increased his school to some fifteen or sixteen scholars. Thus time passed on and everything pro- glessed favorably withl the young couple. They were indeed as happy as could be expected. One circumstance only at times brou'ght a chill upon their spiriis, and that was the fear that the present even-flowing tide of happiness was too favorable to last, and that they should prepare for any acci- dent which might lead to the recognition and arrest of Harry. It was a pleasing spectacle to see Harry surrounded by his little pupils patiently and kindly instructing their minds and enlarging their intellectual capacities; while Annie, seated by the firbe-for it was now winte-- occupied herself with her work. Thus did time pass away. The spring ar- rived with its verdure and its flowers, sum- mer came 'with 'its sunny glories, and when the autumn fruits were gathered from the trees, Annie became the mother of a boy, whosoepresence was hailed with rapture 'by the overjoyed and delighted parents. The autumn had passed,- winter had come, the Christmas season was at hand, and little Hairry--for the boy was named after his father-was thriving apace. *Not only was the young couple thus happy, but likewise prosperous. 'The claims of the newacomer upon Annie had neees- sarily absorbed much of the time 'that sho used to devote to needlework, and thus her earnings were much less than they were wont to be, but on thb other hand Harry's school had increased. their income was a comfortable one, and during 'the fifteen months they had been settled at Lyons they had laid up, two hundred dollars. It was Christmas eve, and all Annie's preparations for the 'following day were completed.. -The, parents of one of Harry's pupils had sent iim a fine turlkey as a pres- ent And' Annie, with an arch sniile, had assured her husband that the plum pudding  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7116-00000016"/> would be unexceptionable. They were sit- ting at tea; the babe was slumbering in his cradle; the candles were lighted, and a cheerful fire blazed in the grate, wrhen Mrs. Harrison entered the room somewhat in a hurry, and stated that' the father of one of Harry's scholars had beei thrown out of his buggy and met with a serious accident. Out hero and Annie both .xpressed their un- feigned sorrow; and ,when tea was over, Harry thought that it would be but courte. ous and kind if he were to step found and ,make personal inquiries concerning the suf-, ferer. Annie at 'once coincided with the suggestion, and Harry put on his hat and cloak and sallied forth., Having made the inquiry, and to his satisfaction learned that the injury was not so greatas had been repre- sented ito him, he was wendlag his way home again, when, on turning the corner of  street, he ran somewhat violently against an individual who was coming from an op- posite direction; then, as they both instinc- tively drew back to beg each other's pardon,. Harry, to his horror and" dismay, recognized. David Ottis, the Newport postmaster. The recognition was mutual, and for a few, moments they stood speechless, gazing upon each other-Harry in consternation and Ottis in shame. The latter was, however, the first to regain his composure, or rather his wonted effron- tery; and seizing Harry's. hand, he said, Come, Todd, I hope there's no ill will?" "No, not the slightest," stammered our unhappy hero, who felt as if the fabric of his happiness had' suddenly been shaken by an earthquake. "Well, I am glad to hear you say that," said Ottis; and then there was another pause, while they again -surveyed each other.. "What has brought you to Lyons,?" asked Harry, scarcely knowing What he said; for there was a bewilderment ini his brain. His mental glance reverted to the interior of. the parlor he had so recently quitted; and behold- ing his wife and child there as hSe had left them, one smiling and happy, the other slum- bering in the sweet sleep of innocence, a .hor- rible pang shot through his heart; for he felt as if this unfortunate encounter was the be- ginning of a fresh series of evils. "What's brought me to Lyons? Why, it's all about a letter that's lost. That fel- low Mummery-you recollect him-swears that he put two hundred dollars into a letter directed to his brother-in-law, who lives here in Lyons; but the brother-in-law apears never to have had the letter; and s6 it is hinted that ,the letter never left Newport, but was lost through my carelessness, or self-appropriated, or something of that kind. Now if. I can only make up this amount, it will put me all right, and t shall consider self your debtor i' evey way."   "If t were certain that you would really keep my secret," continued Harry; "that is to say, if when you go back to Newpoit you will carefully abstain from mentioning that you saw me, I will give you the amount yo" require." Mr. Ottis poured forth a volley of the most emphatic assurances, and Harry, hand- ing him the money, said, "I' now give you 'the savings of more than a twelvemonth's toil. May you be moved by my conduct toward- you to keep my secret'l One Angle word, inadvertently' dropped from your lips, will suffice to set upon my track those who would show me no mercy; and if so, it would be ruin-utter ruin-not merely for myself" --but Harry could not finish the sentence. He thought of his wife-he thought, of his child-and the tears started into his eyes. "I suppose you are married to Annie- Miss Bell that was, Mrs. Todd that is?" said Ottis, 'after having joyously conveyed to his pocket the two hundred dollars which he had extorted from the young man. "You will pardon me for not remaining any longer with you," interrupted Harry. "But once more I entreat you not to breathe a word of your having met me." "It will be just the same as if we hadn't met at all," replied Ottis. "Come, give us your hand, Harry, and let uS part good friends."  Our hero gave him his hand, for he dared " not refuse.; but the very touch sent a cold thrill to his heart's core, as if he had sud- denly come in contact with the slimy form of a coiled up serpent. He then left him, and in a few minutes Harry was once more with his wife and child. He told Annie how solemnly Ottis had promised to keep his secret; but they both knew in their hearts that they could trust with but little certainty to the pledges of such a man. The following day was Christmas.' They went to church as usual; and though always accustomed to pray fervently, there was on this occasion a deeper earnestness, if possi. ble, in their devotions-a more yearning prayer for intercession went up fron their hearts, that Heaven would preserve them from those terrible ills which would shatter the entire fabric of their happiness;. There had been a reward of twenty dol- lars offered for Todd's apprehension as a de- serter. Ottis was sure to know of this, as Harry had received the proofs that he was in correspondence with-ACpt. Courtenay. Several- days passed; an' though Annie smiled as sweetly as ever, yet it was impos- sible that the husband and wife c6uld 'con- ceal'from thermselves that a sad change had- entered their dwelling, andi that 4they could no longer Wit down and discourse: with any confidence on the future. Thus at theex-   piration of two weeks Harry was cormpedled to arrive at Mbe conclusion that this state of things could not last, and strainling his wife to his Pre aste, S poke out'frankly, paying that they must remove elsewhere. Annie at once couvinced her husband that he might reckon upon her fortitde,' and keeping back her tears, the. convulsive sobs which madeher heart swell almost to burst- ing, she set about the immediate prepara- tions Arfo the departure.  The preparations for departure were com- pletely made, and in'a few. minuteo a porter would come to Stae the boxes to the depot. When their rent was paid they had exactly twenty dollars left. But Harry had. a watch and Annie had her own articles of jewelry; thus -they were not without the hope of being able to manage for ome, little time to come. The, porter made his appearance for the baggage, the farewells to Mrs. Hrison were said, and our hero .and heroine were issuing forth from the house, the latter with the child in her arms, .when Harry was ap- prehended by an individual who, proved to be one of the detectives, as a deserter. "I am your prisoner, I surrender myself" said Harry, knowing that fe$istance was vain; indeed,k he dreamt not of attempting any. The whole truth now flashed to the com- prehension of Mrs. Harrison. She saw that Harry was a deserter, but deeply sympathiz- ing with him and his young wife, she at once said all she could to console them both. "Come, I have no time for this nonsense,'" exclaimed the detective, " the cos are going and we must be off." "And may: I be allowed to accompany my 'husband?" said Annie in an imploring voice. "If you have got the money to pay your fare I can't prevent ypougoing,"' returned the detective, not daring for shame to speak too brutally to the, afflicted wife. The news of Todd's arrest .as a deserter had spread like wildfire in the Neighborhood of Mrs. Harrison's house,. and reaching, amongst others, the ears. of- the worthy trademan who: had :sent the, turkey as a presenti this individua I wrapped something in a paper, and speeding down to the depot arrived just: i,: time to hand it to. Mrs.. Todd. Annie, mocha niclly; took the little packet which he presented to her, and as she felt that.:it cQontained money she was about to express, her theaBls, but tjhe worthy trades. man was already speeding his w ay from the spot where, be. ad. ,performed this benevolent act... One ,esming the paiket she found  it- ontaWn. ed just-,tweptyive dollar. 'At the end of h'er journey Mrs. Todd found herself in .th c-ity of, Touiisville, It was at  the house ,of. an old couple, in aretired part 1 of the Oj wn, that. he:found. alodging. She 1 had firally, told them her oircumtances, and 1   explained to them the position of her un. i fortunate ' husbanAd" Xil cqmmiunications of a direct nature be- tween herself and her husband was stopped, but the wife of one of his comrades called upon her fromi kind motives, to let her know tlat he was well' in hethlth and bearing up with becoming fortitude against his calamity. 'We need not dwell at any length upon the details of the nilitary trial to which Harry was subjected. The room was cleared for the deliberation of the court-martial, the ballotas taken, anlid the result was, as a matter/of course, guilty, His sentence was to th effect that private Harry Todd should have six months' pay .stopped, three months he was to wear a ball and. chain, two hours a day for two months to be tied up by the thumbs, three hours a day for one month to be bounded and gagged, for the crime of de- sertion.  CHAPTER VII. IT was now  about nine o'clock in the evening, and General Clincher,' who,h being an unmarried man,;resided at 'his quartors, was sitting m one' of his apartments drinking champagne with a copple of' gay ladies of a certain character. He was a man a year or two under forty, tall, rather good looking, and very well made. ep had a oldier-likc appearance, and when not engaged in such questionable recreations as that in the midst of which we now find him, had a stern se- verity of look. Now, however, he'was en- joying himself-if the word enjoyment may be used in such a sense-as fully and with as much self-abandonment as the youngest of his officers could have done.  While,'Gen. Clincher was seated between the two ladies, quaffing champagne and tell- ing them anecdotes,'his servant knocked at the, door, and on being bidden- to enter,iin- formed his master that a young woman de- sired to speak with -him. "Who the deuce is she?" asked the Geneo- ral. "She did not give her name, sir," was the response, "as she 3aidit. was of no use;, but she, begged and etreated a few moments interview.  I think, aij, but X .dont know, that she is the' wife of privat Todd.', "Then I will see her;"ai' the General, rising from his seat; b utiis We proceeded to the room  where Aunie a,.f6 she 8as:the vsltres,'h  e composed 8is countenuap hto its habitual severity o x, .  Th moment he entered the rqom the iiti of Ite cthes beaming upon .Annie'la eouountoape revealed to his eyes an amount of  iovelineihss ici h f transcended all his expectations ;pi  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7116-00000017"/> looks settled upon her, and rapidly scanning her from head to foot, they followed all the outlines of a form modelled to 'the most symmetrical proportions, so that his passion was at once excited. He did not, however, permit his feelings'to be betrayed by his countenance, although the severity of his aspect became somewhat relaxed under the influence of Annie's loveliness. "Who are you, and what do you require of me?" he asked, affecting not to have the -least idea of who she was. "I am the wife, 'sir, of that unfortunate young man, Harry Todd," and as Annie thus spoke in a voice clouded with grief, but still full of the most melting melody, the tears gushed forth from her eyes. "Unfortunate do you call him," said the General "A crime wilfully committed can- not be regarded as a misfortune that over- takes a person in spite of himself." "Ah, sir, if you only knew all the circum- stances," exclaimed Annie, clasping her hands and looking up with tearful entreaty at the General, "I am sure you would pity Harry Todd." "And therefore I supposeoun are come to intercede for him?" observed the General. "Yes, sir; and on my knees do I implore your mercy," cried Annie, sinking down at the General's feet. "I have heard, sir, of the terrible punishment to which he has been condemned; and it is greater than even in my most horrible misgivings I had expect- ed. You behold at your feet, sir, a wife who is almost distracted; and if I had dared, I should have brought my child to place at your feet also, that its innocent presence might plead in unconscious eloquence for its father." "Come, come--rise up," said the General; and taking Annie's hands, he raised her from her suppliant posture. "There now, sit down, and we will talk the matter over." Annie thought there was kindness alike in his words and in his manner. Hope began to warm her heart, and she sat down. "You know," said the General, "what your husband is condemned to receive." Annie groaned in the bitterness of her spirit, and wrung her hands with-hysterical despair. "You are very much attached to your husband?" be said, devouring her with his regards, and yet still so masking his features with a calmness of aspect, that she compre- hended not the real -meaning of his looks. "Oh, sir! Ih' is my chief happiness iri'this world exclaimed Annie with impassioned vehemence. "If he were taken from me I should die." "Then," said the General, "you are re- solved to leave nothing unattempted to pro- oure a mitigation of his sentence?" "Oh 1 sir, is it not my duty to do all I can for that purpose? If by any sacrifice on my   part I can achieve that end, how cheerfully, oh I how cheerfully would I do it." "A'hl you would make any sacrifice?" said the General "Do you not speak some- what rashy? or is your love for your hus- band indeed so strong that---" "Any sacrifice short of dishonor!" ex- claimed Annie;, and she felt a species of shock at the idea that her words had been too literally interpreted. "But what if the only means of obtaining a mitigation of your husband's sentence-" "Enough; General," ejaculated the terri- fled Annie; for it was now no longer possi- ble to mistake the meaning of the- looks which were fastened upon her. ! She rose from her seat, coloring with indig- nation, yet half broken-hearted; and she was moving towards the door, when the General exclaimed, ' Stop a moment, Mrs. Todd. If you really love your husbanid as you say, there ought to be no sacrifice which you are unprepared to make. Come, Mrs. T'odd-do not be so over-particular. I have the power to mitigate your husband's sentence, and I will do so but upon one condition. It rests with you," he said, "entirely with you, to what extent your husband's punishment shall 'reach."  And as he thus spoke he took her hand and pressed it, at the same time gazing upon her in a manner which could no longer leave her in the slightest doubt as to his real meaning. "No, sir-no, neverl" she cried hysteri- cally, as she snatched her hand from his clasp. "One Byrd, Mrs. Todd," said the General "Not another word, sirl This is horrible -horrible " exclaimed,' Annio, becoming deadly pale and staggering against a chair for support. "Gen. Clincher," continued Annie, all her presence of mind being brought back to her aid by the strong flood of indignation that had set in--" my husband is too much in your power for me to provoke you by expressing all I think and feel at your present conduct. Oh I sir, when a wife, in the rending anguish of her heart, comes to throw nerself at your feet and implore mercy for her husband, is it, not a cruel thing--to say nothing worse-that she should have another dagger driven deep down into that already too much lacerated heart Permit me to retire, General Clin- cher." "You are resolved upon leaving md thus?' he exclaimed, in mingled humiliation and indignation. "Yes, sir; I have no farther business here;" and Annie withdrew from the apart- ment, the General no longer endeavoring to detain her. As she descended the stairs, so overpow- ering a sense of anguish Seized upon her, that she was compelled to lean against the wall for support. For some momentd did   she rest there, sobbing bitterly, till amused, or rather startled, by hearing rapid footsteps ascending the stairs. Then she continued to advance, and the next instant found her- self face to face with Horatio Thurston. He was in his uniform, having only just left the mess-table, where he had remained drinking, and his countenalce was flushed. "A-hi Annie," he -exclaimed, half in sur- prise and half with an insolent familiarity, 'is this you? I suppose you have been to the General about your husband?" "Allow me to pass, sir," she said as he barred her way. "Just one word, Annie!" cried Horatio, seizing her by the hand; then,: as she lite- rally tore that hand from his grasp, he said, "Why, what a fool you are to get into such a rage for nothing. Of course the General would do nothing for you; but if I was to intercede, it would be different." "I command youl to let me pass, sir " in- terrupted Annie, resolved to escape from farther insults. "Not without a kiss," ejaculated Thurs- ton; "just one kissl for ir you come, into the officers' quarters---- "Where I expected to find honorable men," exclaimed Annie indignantly; and as Thurston endeavored to throw  his arms around her, she pushed him away with such force that he fell against the balustrades. "I will be revenged on Todd for this P' he exclaimed in spiteful accents; but Annie condescended to give no reply, and hurrying down the stairs, she was speedily outside i the barracks. With an anguish in her heart that tran- scended all the poignancy of any feelingshe had ever yet known, she returned to her I lodging, where the women of the house had taken charge of her child during her absence. 1 Then, ona again finding herself alone in her 1 chamber, with her babe pressed to her bo- ( som, Annie wept bitter, scalding tears over i the little innocent. Her memory reverted f to the happy home which but a few weeks r back she and her husband had possessed at Lyons; and as she thought how suddenly it 1 had been swept away, and how calamity  i upon calamity had been accumulating ever c since, it appeared as if she had been whirled r through the rapid stages of a hideous dream. c In three days a communication was re- F oeived from  the General, to the effect that v the proceedings of the oourt-martial had n been approved.             t The prisoner wasbrought in; his sentence 'o was read to him; and while he bowed to the a decision of the court his lips were com- . presd, for a moment with the bitterness of : a heartfelt anguish and a withering sense of h eoasummate degradation.  He was 'then  taken back to the guard-house, with the i intimation that the sentence ,would be car- i ried out     -    CAAPTER I I AND  now what of poor Ann'm? IShe knew the punishment would be inflicted upon her husband. She had locked the door of her chamber; she had fallen upon her knees by the side of the bed ; and bury- ing her face in her hands, she had put up such prayers to Heaven, as for fervor and sincerity and earnestness of pleading never before ascetided from the human heart  She had besought Omnipotent Providence to in- spire her beloved husband with fortitude to bear his punishment and with physical power to survive it. She had prayed too that this same Providence would move the hearts of those who had the authority to mitigate the amount of the chastisement. Terrible was the anguish endured by Annie Todd. Her own soul was torn, and lacera- ted, and rent - thrills of the most acute ago- ny shot through her from  head to foot Such was her sympathy with him whom nhe loved so tenderly, so adoringly, so fervidly  For three mortal hours did the unhappy young woman pass through this frightful ordeal of mental and imaginative excrucia- tions. Fortunately, during the whole time, the child slept soundly, for she felt that if it had awakened and craved' nourishment, sew would not have had sufficient energy to be- stow it. At length, at the expiration of thoso three hlours, a knock was heard at her room door; she rose from her knees to open it, and the friendly soldier's wife made her appearance. At first the good woman was startled and horrified at Annie's aspect, so ashy pale was her countenance, so despairing her regards. The soldier's wife came to announce that there would be no mitigation of the sentence, but that Harry, trusting in the mercy of Omnipotent Providenco, was resolved to bear it with fortitude. Annie thanked the woman for her kindness, but did not ask her to re- main, for she wished to be alone. Then, when once more alone, Anniao took her babe upon her knees, and weeping over it bitterly, she murmured, half aloud, "poor child, little do you think of the awful hor. rors whiqh your father has this day endured, )r the anguish whi6h your mother has ex- perienced! Pity it is, 'deaf child, that you rill ever exchange this blessed' state of ig- norance for the knowledge that there are in ;he world human beings of so fiend-liko a haracter as to tie up their fellow-creatures and lacerate them  almost to pieces. Ohl when I was a girl I read in booktht this was a  ChriiBtian country, that wB Were a humane people, that wre had a gokd paternal government, and that the spirit f the liwk revolted against acts of bWrbarim and' op) presion; and'I wa taught, too, to regard with horror and loathiog the fanatics of other  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7116-00000018"/> times who inflicted the tortures of the rack, the thumb-screw, the steel boot, and the other horrors perpetrated[ in the inquisition. But oh I how strange it is for books to incul-t cate one set of ideas, while experience of the world stamps thems with all the flagrancy of  ,falsehood. We, a humane and civilized peo- ple, and yet tolerate this horrorwhich cries up to heaven for vengeance I No, no, we are barbarians; our Christianity is a mock- ery, our religion is a pretence, and we have no, right to vauut our own humanity in 'contrast with the fiendish ,cruelty of tile perished inquisition." As Annie gave way to this train of mus- ings, the glow of indignation brought back the,color to her cheeks; she felt the blood ,boiling: in her veins; her eyes flashed fire, and she looked as if .inspired by some spirit which had never existed in her before. Her confidence in human nature had received a shock; she began lo see things in a new light. There were numerous churches in the same town of Louisville where she now dwelt, and from' every pulpit on the Sabbath ,went forth teachings of humanity and for- giveness, but of all the clergymen who thus preached the-divine doctrines of the Saviour,  not one had been found bold and honest enough to. present himself in the barrack-yard that morning and protest against the Satanic deed which was being committed there. But to return tow-the progress of our nar- rative. Some hours had. passed after the visit of the good-natured soldier's wife, when  Annie, with her child in her arms, .repaired to the barracks to inquire if she might be permitted to see her husband. She was told that she could not for the present, but that in a few days' time she would be permitted ,to visit him. She dragged herself back to her lodging in the deepest despondency, and ascending to her chamber, sat down to medi- tate again. She did not hear the heavy footsteps of a man ascending the stairs, nor did she hear that he knocked twice at the door of her room, so completely absorbed were her thoughts in the one .tremendous and terrific topic. But now the door opened, and she half started from her seat on observing a male form appear upon the threshold. It was dusk, a solitary candle burnt dimly upon the table, and as the .visitor advanced slowly into the room the feeble rays meeting his countenance revealed to her eyes the face of her father. An. ejaculation of astonishment, not alto- ,gether unmingled with gratiica;tion escaped her lps a tho thought flashed to Her mind; tha,ftif he .came in a friendly spirit, she wouldj derive at least some consolation from the pa- ternal presence.         , 'iAnd thus. we meet again, Annie,' said her father in-a deep. voice.. "To what have you, brought yourself?"   Am  not sufficiently- unhappy without this taunt from your lips?' she asked, sud denly wiping away her tears, for' shefelt'that her father's words con-veyed a  sort of slur thrown out upon the marriage which' she had contracted, and her indignation was -excited. "I care nothing for poverty, and as for pri- vation, I have not yet known, and'shall not know, as long as I have hands to work, and any remnant of health to enable me to work." "Your husband has this day-" "Father," interrupted Annie with hysteri- cal quickness, "speak not of it. No one must allude in my hearing to that circum- stance unless in the tone of sympathy, and as you feel none, I beseech you to spare my heart any additional tortures." "Now, Annie, do you know wherefore I have sought you out?" resumed Bell. "I heard of your husband's arrest, and that he had been brought back to Louisville. I ,thought to myself that you had perhaps ex- perienced enough of the consequences of  your disobedienceand your marriage, and I have undertaken this long journey to offer you a home again if you choose to accept it." "My home, father, is wherever I can live nearest to my husband, and therefore, while thanking you for your offer, I cannot accept it." "You love your husband, then, better than your father?" Annie made no reply, but she bent her looks upon the child, from whose sweet countenance her parent had studiously kept away his regards. "Surely your dream of happiness must have become dispelled by this time," con- tinued Mr. Bell, "and if you persist in cling ing to that man who is unable to support you, you will assuredly sink down into misery, perhaps into something worse." "Father, you dare not insult me thus," exclaimed Annie, her eyes flashing With in- dignation. "Ohl do not destroy the feeling of affection which I entertain toward you," and there was something exquisitely pathetic in the yoijng woman's appeal. "Affection," echoed Bell with a sneer, "do not talk to me of affection I H Eave I not suffered from your disobedience?'might you not' have f6rmed a brilliant alliance? and had you fllowed my advice, would you not now at this moment be .the wife of a gentleman and an officer, the heir to an immense for- tune? Yes, you would now be the. com- panion of ladies and gentlemen living in I comfort and splendor--" . ' "But, father," said Annie, "al that would ' not liave. constituted my happiness,for I could be happier in the meanest garriet with him :whom I sincerely love, than I could be in gilded saloons with one'whom I loved not    sodsvery fine ithe   ge of "-AM1 this sounds very flne in the page of   a romance," observed Bell sneeringly.,agam, "but. the stern realities of life cannobt be colored by the roseate hues 'of love. "I have now come to offer jyou my for-- giveness, and to entreat, if you will, that you return to the place of your birth, to render the rest of my days as happy as you can. Now, Annie, is this asking too much?" "It is, father, because it is asking me tBi abandon one whom I have sworn at the altar to love and cling to, and towards whom my own heart. prompts me most faithfully to keep those- pledges."  "Then listen well and patiently, Annie, to what I'-have to say," resumed Bell, in a voice that was' bitterly implacable; "I give you {his last chance., You have- dashed to the ground all my fondly-cherished hopes, you have annihilated the brightest' dream  of my existence. Nevertheless, I proffer you my pardon, on condition that you leave this man. If you refuse and disobey me now I throw you off forever. I have already made my will, leaving all I possess away from you. Come home, and the instant you cross the threshold that will shall be burnt before your eyes; but refuse and it shall remain in exis-  tence, that its provisions may be carried out at my death. And now observe well, Annie, the time will come when, if you disobey me, you will be exposed to the direst privations, when you will sink down into the bitterest penury, and then you will seek that home which you now refuse. Once more, there- fore, do I ask you whether you will accept my offer, and accompany me back to New- port?  Take four-and-twentyhours to con- sider of it, if you will." "I require not as many minutes-no, nor a single one," replied Annie. "My mind is made up; and not for worlds, however great: my privations, would I abandon my husband. You have spoken of what my prospects may perchance be; but do you not reflect that the time may come that you will repent your harsh- ness towards your daughter? Oh I if I have indeed offendedyou-if I have been really and truly disobedient; yet if ever there were a time when a daughter might expect to receive her parent's forgiveness, it is now that my heart is bleeding with painful wounds, and my soul is tortured with terrible excruciations." Stern and unmoved by this piteous pathetic appeal, Bell rose slowly from his seat; when Annie, anguished at the idea that her father should leave her thus, fell upon her knees at  his feet, and holding up her child towards him, exclaimed, i"One kind word-oh I but one kind'word, ere you 'leave me--for'this; dear infant's sake " "Annie, it  hs the child of the man that' I hate more than any other man in the world," said Bell sternly. "But it is my child, your daughter's child, it is your' grandchild," exclaimed the half- distracted young woman   "Returan home, and I acknowledgQ my grandchild.': was the foreman's response; built persist in your refusal. and I acknowl. edge it not." "Oh I it is impossible that you can be so harsh," cried Annie. "Look at this dear child-it has 1not offended you; and it is cruel -oh, it is cruel, to visit your wrath upon it i" "For the last time, Annie, will you come?" "No, father, I cannot." "Then I throw you off forever-I discard you-I leave my curse behind me." "Oh I my own father has cursed me," shrieked forth the wretched Annie, and she fell back senseless upon the floor. When she returned to consciousness her father was gone, and the babe was crying--by her side. It was its piteous wail that had brought the mother back to life. Snatching her dear infant to her bosom, Annie wept over it long and plenteously. Her father's curse still rang in her ears, and it lay like a' weight, of lead upon her heart. Early on the following morning the young mother, with the child in her arms, repaired to the barracks to inquire after her husband. She lbeied that he- was doing well, and this was at least some consolation. Day after day for the next fortnight did she present herself regularly at an early hour to make the same inquiry; and it was a source of infinite relief to her wounded feelings to receive good accounts upon each occasion. At length she was admitted to an interview with her husband.    Annie was fearfully shocked when- she saw how altered he wasi and with convulsive sobbing did she sink into his arms. He strained her to his breast; and then he lavished his caresses upon his child; then he embraced his wife again, and then he once more took little Harry in his arms and showered his endearments upon him.   During the two months which had elapsed since their removal from Lyons, she had lived with the utriost economy and frugality: but still -the little store of money they had in their possession at, the time was disappearing, and Annie intimated her intention of seeking nee- dlework, as she had done when they were first at Lyons. We should observe that although accus- tomed to display the most undisguised frank- ness towards her husband, she did not think it right to inform him of the conduct of the General, nor the insulting behavior of Horatio Thurston; for she was alarmed lest his, man- ly spirit should prompt him to resent against those two officers the indignities they had of-. fered to his wife, and thus'inevitably'draw down upon himself some signal manifestations of their vindictiveness. On the day following the conference with Harry, Annie intimated to her landlady that she wished to'procure needlework, and asked her assistance. Very different was' the oon, duct of-this woman from that ef worthy Mr.,  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7116-00000019"/> Harrison, at Lyons. She merely gave Annie a few general hints, without making the slightest proffer to forward her views. The suggestions which the landlady had thrown out were merely to. the-effect that Annie might perhaps, obtain work from certain shops, the addresses of which she named; and the young woman lost no time in applying in those quarters. She finally obtained work from a merchant tailor, and at the end of a week, when she took her work back, she re- oeived two dollars for what she had done. The'tailor was well pleased at the neatness with which it was executed, and offered her some work of a superior character, whichl sho at'once accepted; and the second week her earnings amounted to nearly double thlat of the first week. Thus hope once more glim- mered up in the bosom of poor Annie; and all cares relative to subsistence being thus ,banished--at least for the present-some lit- tle alleviation was experienced for her sor- rows. Still her happiness would have been greater could she have seen that Harry was the same being he formerly was. But still, to her own little son, he was still the same iu all his devoted fondness. Time passed on--months elapsed-and a comparative degree of happiness reigned at the little lodging. The child throve apace, and was now able to toddle about from chair to chair. Annie's earnings averaged three dollars a week, and often she. enjoyed Harry's presence at the neatly spread tea-table. And thus it was Annie's satisfaction and joy to be enabled to provide a comfortable meal for her husband.  It often galled Harry very sadly to think that he should in any way encroach upon his wife's earnings, even for the evening meal which he sometimes shared with her. But If over he alluded to the subject, it caused Anniocso much pain and throw sueo a damp upon herspirits, that he invariably regretted having expressed his feelings upon the topic; and thus he soon,ceased from any allusion thereto. la respect to his position, we need only observe that the was most regular and careful in the performance of his duties, being resolved to afford his enemies no opportunity by any dereliction on his part for direct per- secution. Thus did time pass on; ,aud Christmas eame again. It was the rule in the regiment that those soldiers happening to have friends or relations in the town, who would invite tlaheo to dinner on that day, obtained leave of Absonce after morning service ;. and thus it was agreed, in compliance with Apnie's entreaty, that Harry should avail himself of the permlssion so generally accorded, With mingled feelings did she make the prepara- tions ; I&amp; was in one sense a sort of pleasure that they slwuld dine together on this day of unuzerasl festivity; but, on the other band, zse could not help thinking of tilhe   mournful. apprehensions and misgivings amongstwhich, they had eaten their last Christmas dinner together-the 'extortion of Ottis having taken plaice, as the reader win remember, on the previous evening. This made her reflect that if it had not been for the inauspicious appearance of that man at Lyons, they might still be dwelling in happi- ness there at the present time, and the fearful indignity which he had been called to endure would not have taken place. Nevertheless, Annie was more inclined on the present occasion to yield herself up to hopeful thoughts than to desponding ones; and when Harrj made his appearance at one o'clock on Christmas day, he not only found a nicely spread table awaiting him, but also a beautiful wife welcoming him with the tenderest and fondest ssmiles. Then what- ever was harboring in his soul was for a time forgotten. He embraced Annie; he fondled his child; and they were all happy together. When they parted in, the evenin, tlHarry turned back from the throshold which he had already crossed, and again pressing An- nie in his arms. he said iu a low tender voice, My dearest wifo, I am afraid you have sometimes seen mo distracted and , mournful; but it was no easy task to sur- mount all of a sudden a goading sense of tihe bitter wrongs I had endured. To-day I have experienced such true hlappiness that it eems as if it were the era of a more health- ful change in my feelings.  Good night, dearest!" He departed with the warmth of Annie's kisses upon his cheocks; and the fond, ador- ing wife slept that night the sleep of happi- ness Three months had passed since the happy Christmas they had spoent together, when one morning tho tailor for whom  Annie worked sent a message to her lodging, re- questing that she -would come to him at o;ice. She accordingly hastened thither with her little Harry, now upwards of eigh- teen months old, and found that her employ- er, having an order suddenly sont in for some work requiring great care, wished to place in her hands as much thereof as th could undertake to complete in a given time. Annio accepted the task, and hastened back homeward:. As she entered the street whoer she dwelt, she suddenly found herself face to face with Horatio Thurston. "Ah, Annie!" ho exclaimed, stopping short so as literally to bar er way; "it's a long timo i  -ypc..you and I, met. .JIow w .llU you are looking, to be S'rcl '-Upon my soul, you grow handsomer than everl" Annie was endeavoring to pass by the impudent coxcomb, when hastily glancing around and perceiving that they were unob- served, he caught her by the hand, and hold- ing it fast said, "Come, my dear Annie, you must be tired of that soldier chap of yours   Put yourself under my protection, and I will moake a lady of you." "Unhand me, sir," exclaimed Mrs. Todd indignantly; and she struggled hard to escape from him. "No, we don't part in this way," he cried. "You know I have long loved you. I must and will have a clhat with you." But- Annie succeeded in bursting away from him, and hurried home, the frightened child crying bitterly. - She ascended to her chamber, and for a considerable time was unable to compose her feelings sufficiently to commence the work she had undertaken, and which was required in such a hurry. Her bosom swelled with indignation at the treatment she liad received-a treatment too which she had. no means of resenting; for she dared not communicate it to her husband on account of the motives already specified. At length however she smothered her ex- citement as well as she was able, and set to work. Meanwhile Horatio Thurston--who, wo should observe, had recently obtained by purchase the rank of lieutenant in the regi- ment-had through this little incident ascer- tained Annie's abode, and he resolved to profit by the discovery. Depraved and un- principled as he himself was, he could scarcely believe in the existence of real virtue on the part of a private soldier's wife. He thought that th3 manner in which sho had thus treated him w is the result of the lingering of an embittered feeling on account of the past, and which might be easily over- come by cajolery and coaxing. When parade was over, Horatio Thurston drossed himself in plain clothes and pro. ceeded Jo th3 house where Mis. Todd dwelt. The landlady opened the door to his sum- mons, and a one dollar bill slipped into her hand elicited the information that 'Annie's husband was not with her at the moment. He accordingly ascended the stairs to her chamber; and the landlady, who had hith- erto thought that Atnnie was a most discreet and virtuous young woman, muttered to herself "Well, after all, she's no better than the generality of them." Meanwhile Thurston had reached the door of Annie's chamber, at which he knocked. He had ascended so gently that she had not heard his footsteps; and conceiving it to be the landlady, she said, "Come in." He at once obeyed the invitation; and Annio. flinging down the work, started up amazed and .indignant at the outrageous insolonce of this intrusion. "Now, my dear Mrs. Todd," said Horatio, shutting the door, " pray don't put yourself ia a passion; for I can assure you that I wish to speak with you very seriously." "Understand me   well, Mr. Thurston," said Annie, whose cheeks, from being flushed with indignation, had become ashy pale, at   the cruel sense of her position; but she spoke with accentuated firmness&amp; "I do not wish that a disturbance shall be created in the house. Frankly and firmly I tell you that I would sooner perish than stoop to in- famy. Whatever wild hopa may therefore. have brought you hither may be discarded from your mind at once. And now, sir, that I have restrained myself thus far to make you understand everything, I enjoin you to depart." "Nonsense, Annie, you are too good for a soldier's wife, and as I told you just now, I will make a lady of you." "This is too much," ejaculated Annie, and she sprang towards the door. Thurston, maddened with passion, threw his arms round her waist. She struggled against him, and succeeded in escaping from his hold, then tearing open the door, she screamed for assistance. But at the same instant her husband came rush- ing up the staircase, and bursting into the room comprehended it all at once. "Begone,. sir, depart hence," he exclaimed in a furious passion, "or I will kick you ig- nominiously down the stairs." "Do you know, fellow, to whom you are talking?" demanded Horatio, drawing him- self up with matchless effrontery. "Yes, to an unprincipled scoundrel," re- plied Harry, and clenching his fist, he quickly added, "Begone, sir, or I shall cease to be master of myself." "You shall smart for this, you rascal," ejaculated Thurston, but fearful of summary chastisement, he hastened down the stairs, and by the threats which he kept on mutter- ing as he passed by the landlady, she was made completely to comprehend that her transitory suspicion of Annie's impropriety was utterly unfounded. "O Harry," cried Annie, flinging herself into her husband's arms the moment Horatio had left the room, "what will be the conse- quence of this? Have you laid yourself open to anything he may do?" and there was mortal anguish in her voice and looks "There can be no immediate consequen. ces, dearest Annie," replied Harry, " because he dares not make known what has taken place. Compose yourself." "Oh it is you that must compose your- self; my beloved husband, for I perceive that you are much agitated." "O Annie, is it not sufficient to drive one to despair?" exclaimed Harry, dashing his open palm forcibly against his forehead, " to think that this villain should dare violate tho sanctity of your chamber, and that I am at the mercy of a wretch such as he?" "Harry, dear Harry, you must calm .this terrible excitement," and Annie lavished upon himr her caresses. "There," she sud- denly ejaculated, snatching up their child who had waked up, and bringinig the boy to  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7116-00000020"/> his father, she added, " for the sake of this dear innocent, I beseech you to calm yourself!" "I will; I will, Annie," he responded, sit- ting down and taking his son upon his knees. "But now tell me all that occurred." Annie at once told her husband how she had- met Horatio Thurston at about nine o'clock in the morning, what he ,had said to ier, hdow he had just now penetrated to her chamber, and what had then taken place. 'While she spoke she saw that Harry left off fondling the child, that a dark cloud lowered over his features, that his brows became knit, his lips compressed, and his whole form quivering with a spasmodic sensation. Again did she beseech and implore that he would calm his excitement, both' for her sake and that of his son. Hie promised that he would, but for the rest of the time they were to- gether that day, she could not help noticing that his lips frequently assumed that omi- nous aspect which had been wont to terrify her, and that he likewise relapsed into his old fits of moody abstraction. Several weeks elapsed after this incident without any other worthy of narration. But Harry had lost his good spirits, and Annie grew more and more alarmed, and she re- solved at length to speak to him very se- riously on the subject. "My dearest husband," she said one day, placing herself upon his knee, and throwing her arm round his neck, "i there is somethincg preying upon your mind. Do make me your confidant," "Ohl Annie," he cried with a sudden outhurst of excitement, as if feelings long pent up now forced for themselves an issue, "I have endeavored as much as possible to keep my sorrows from you, but I can conceal them no longer." "What doi you mean, Harry," asked Annie, frightened and dismayed. "I mean, my beloved wife, that I am en- "during inrmy regiment the tortures of per- dition. I. mean that I am subjected to such a series of persecutions from the young fiend Thurston, that my patience is exhausted  After receiving such a frightful punishment my mind became morbid, and I cherished the darkest thoughts of vengeance against the author 'of all our sorrows, that miscreant " Ottisl But gradually, under the influence of your love, your smiles, your bright and beautiful example of Christian resignation, my soul recovered its wonted healthfulness, and I was saved from those dark thoughts. CHAPTER X. SEVERAL weeks glided by, and day after day did Todd's position in his regiment be-   come more intolerable, and our afflicted heroine saw that matters were approaching some dangerous crisis,.which she trembled to think of. At length they mutually felt that they could no longer keep silence upon the subject, although they had endeavored to'do so; and one day their eyes suddenly meeting, when each was steainmg a glance at the other, they read what was passing si- multaneously within their souls. "What must we do, Harlry," said Annie with a shudder ofanguish, "for it is impos- sible that you can exist longer thus. Tyran- ny is killing you by inches." "Ah I that is indeed the fatal truth," he ejaculated with a vehement outhurst of ex- bcitement. "I can endure it no longer, I have gone through more within the last few months than any man living would have put up with. Were I unmarried, and did not your image and that of our beloved child constantly rise up before me, I should long' ago have struck that fiend-like monster Thurston. And what I tremble at,- dear Annie, what I shudder to think of, is that some. day, when goaded to desperation, I shall strike that man, and you know that the punishment for striking an officer is death." Annie gave a quick start, shocked to the utmost confines of her being, by this terrific announcement. "What is to be done, dearest Harry?" she said. '"Something must be done quickly. It is impossible that you could incur this frightful risk any longer." Todd looked hard at his wife for nearly a minute, then with a sudden mustering up of all his courage he responded, in a deep hol- low voice, "Annie, to avoid striking a blow, the penalty of which is death, we must flee -I must desert." Annie started not, neither did she shud- der; for she was prepared for this annouce- ment. She herself saw that it was the only alternative. The crisis was involved in the two words-death or desertion. The husband and wife thereupon began seriously to discuss the plan of their pro- ceedings. Altogether in money they had about sixty dollars, and in case of need they could safely reckon on as much more, by making their personal property available. The means of flight were not therefore want-, ing; and now the question arose whither they should go? Where should they estab. lish themselves? This point was discussed long and seriously, but at length for several reasons it was determined that they should proceed to New York. When their minds were thus made up they both became more tranquil; and Harry soon displayed such an elevation of spirits, and talked so hopefully of the future, that his affectionate wife was speedily led to contem- plate with a real pleasure the intended change in their circumstances.   The next evening was decided upon as the one on which the flight was to be accom. plished  Accordingly on the. following day Annie packed up her luggage, and got it arid little Harry on a wagon to be taken to the forry, where they arrived in a few minutes; and soon after they had the river between them and Louisville. Meanwhile Harry Todd had proceeded along the shore to a very secluded spot, and there he changed his clothes. His uniform he wrapped up in a bundle together with a large stone to sink it; and then threw it into the water. At the appointed time he met Annie at the depot at Jeffersonville, where they took their places in the cars. Our travelers reached New York without any misadventure, and soon after they were installed in a comfortable lodging in a retired part of the city. Thus was successfully accomplished Harry Todd's second de seition from his regiment. They now adopted the fictitious name of: Robinson, under which Ha'rry  pened a little school, while Annie again took in nee- dlework.' :They endured no embarrassmnents in a pecuniary sense, and experienced but a smql amount of Up-hill work in eStablishiug their new position.       : Time wore on; weeks swelled into months, the mouths run up to a year; and thust did 1he time pass away fromr the date of Harry's second desertion. Heo was now twenty- eight; Aaiie wai tweaty-six, anal she ap- peared to be in all the bloomni Of ripe woman- hood's glorious beauty. Little Harry, nlow inarly two years old, was a thriving and beautiful boy, combiuing in his countenance, so rar as a child of that ac3 could, the manly features of his father with the more delicate traits and softly ingenuous loolks of his mother. A finer couple, with a fiier pledg, of their affiction, was not to be fouln[ throughout the whole neighborhood where they lived.             ' Three years had they now been united in matrimonial bonds; but'those bonds were silken; ones, which they were joyful and proud to wear; or thioy might more properly be called links of the choicest and sweetest flowers, festooning around their hearts. Harry had riot failed to'keep an eye upon those newspapeors whijch specially recorded the movements of the army. Tho regiment to which he, belonged' had recently. beenri removed, to Nashville. Gen. Clincher was still in command; and Horatio Thurston had risen to. the rank of captain. In respect to Arinie's father no information had been ob- F Lained, and- it was not therefore known whe  ther he was alive or. dead. .As 'for Otti, and everybody else at Newport with whom  they were .acquainted, the T'odds were equally in the dark concening'them and ltheir affii rs. .   . .  One day, at the expiration of the year   during which our little .familyghad now been settled in New York, Harry had some busFi ness to transact with the father of one of his pupils; at-d on returning from that house, as he was passing the post office, an ejacula- tion of surprise tittered hear him caused him to turn quickly, and to his inrexpressible horror and dismay he found' himself con- frbnted by the very man whom last ou the face of the earth 'he would have chosen-to' encounter. 'This-was Ottis. Ruin appeared to look him in the face at that instant. 'All in an instant had he stepped, from the confi- dence of security to the edge of an abyss, into which he felt a remorseless hand was dragging him down. The images of Annie and his child rose up before him, with despair pictured upon their countenances. Mr. Ottis was but very little altered in any respectl. He was the same thin, misera- ble looking, half starved wretch, in thread- bare apparel, that be had always been in Todd's recollection; and he stood gazing with a sort of half familiar, half astonished leer upon the unfortunate man who had already felt that he was again doomed to be the wretch's victim. "I know-I feel that you desire to speak to me," said Todd, breaking silence' as soon as he had recovered something!kel'presence of mind. "But we cannot steak here. Moreover, it may better suit your own pur- poses," he added bitterly, "if you do not mention my name in this place." "Lead on tlihen," said Ottis, half flippantly, half doggedly, "and I will follow." They passed on, and Harry stopped at the door of the nearest public house.  I "No, this won't do," said Ottis. "I mean to go home with you; so lead the way wherevdr you live."  ".No," replied Todd firmly; "you shall not coerpeo me thus. Whatever may now pass between 'us can a's well 'take place here as elsewhere. Are you not aware, do you not feel that there must be some one at my house who will shrink in horror from your presence '" and 'Todd spoke in, a low, deep voice as he fixed his eyes earnestly upon the sinister countenance ofOttis. "Oh1i I will risk that," he exclaimed; ' "But wherefore plunge a dagger into the heart of an amiable and excellent woman who: never injured 'you? Mr. Ottis, I  be- seech, I implore, I conjuie'you to spare her; if you will rot spare me!" "Now, if we attract a crowd by 'tafiding here in altercation in the broad daylight." said Ottis, "it will be' entirely your 'faults Once more I tell you to lead on, or elge I will knock the thing in the head at once by giving you in charge." ' Harry had indeed received a mortal fright, for it had appeared to him at one moment that the fangs of the law  were about to clutch him in their grasp.  Wretched and  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7116-00000021"/> miserable, with frenzy in his brain and anguish in his heart, almost wishing that the earth would open and swallow him up, he led the way towards his home; that home which he had loft invested with happiness an hour back, but into the bosom of which he was about to return accompanied by the remorseless source of sorrow and desolation I "This meeting with you comes amazing handy," said Ottis, as they proceeded along the street. together. "The fact is, I have got into some more trouble with that post. office at Newpprt, there's a regular dead set there to ruin me, but I'll be hanged if they will prevail as long as I've got such a friend in you;" and Ottis laughed in that sub- dued, chuckling, sardonic manner which sounds upon the ear like tho mockery of fiends. Todd made no observation; his mind was tortured with the direst anguish at the idea of the horrible blow which in a few minutes would be given to his beloved wife's happi- ness. "Well, I won't say no more upon the subject," exclaimed Ottis. "But lead on, the people are already saring at us as they pa&amp;s3" Todd saw that it was so, and composing his excited feelings as well as he was able, ho continued his way homeward, followed by the villain whom  he longed to clutch by the throat, hurl into the gutter, and trample under foot. The instant Annie beheld that man also felt as if struck with a sudden blow of a hammer, and she staggered back a pace or two oro sho could recover herself. Her husband's knock at the front door startled her as it were from this stupor, she felt the blood rushing back to her heart with a'pail- ful stinging sensation, and the thought in- stantaneously occurred to her that this was the crisis demanding the exorcise of all her fortitude. The servant girl whom she kept opened the front door, and Annie issuing out of the school-room bade the girl take care of little Harry while she went up stairs with heor lusband and tho visitor. When the three gained the parlor Ottis sat himself down, and putting his old battered hat upon the floor, he looked about him as if lie were a broker taking stock of a place into which he had just put a seizure. 4"Now, what do you require of me?" said Harry curtly and resolutely. "Of course it is money. N'ame your demand." "Well, I am not prepared to state a par- ticular sum," said Ottis. "This is a six-room house, is well filrnished, and I suppose I must set you down as at least four hundred a year folks. Then reckoning your savings you can't hlave less than a year's income put by. So hand me over four hundred dollars and you may consider yourself as safe as if   I you had got your discharge from the rogi- i ment." Now this sum was just double as much as much as the Toods had really saved. But i even that amount Harry was resolved not to L part with. "In the first place," he said, still cold, firm and resolute, "I only possess one-half of what you demand; and in the second place, I am resolved sooner to risk or en- I counter anything than plunder my wife and child, to minister to your extortions." ," I won't bate one farthing of the four hundred," said Ottis, "but if you like to give me half now and half in a week, I don't care for waiting that long." L"I will do nothing of the sort," replied Todd. "And now perform your worst." "Then what will you do?" asked Ottis, fearful that he had perhaps gone too far. "You ask me what I w1ll do?" repliad Harry; "if you delivered me up to the authorities you would obtain twenty dollars for my apprehension, but were I to give you two hundred or two thousand dollars this moment, you would to-morrow betray me all the same for the sake of the twenty. The Judas Iscariot of private life will not scruple to clutch the silver pieces of blood money. Now then, I tell you what I will do. I will give you once the twenty dollars which you would get by betraying me, and every year so long as I remain undiscovered and unmolested, I will faithfully and punctually remit you twenty dollars, so that it will be your interest to guarantee my safety." "It won't do, Master Todd," exclaimed Ottis, "I will have ihe two hundred you say you have got, and then you can send me the twenty dollars of hush money every year if you like. Themn's my terms." "And I do not agree to them," replied Harry resolutely, for he saw that Ottis had become less arrogant and overbearing than he was when he first entered the house. "Well, if my terms ain't accepted," said Ottis, resolved to see what effect a renewed menace would produce, '"I shall know how to act;" and rising from his seat he ap- proached the door. "For heaven's sake, suffer him not to de- part," whispered Annie, with a look of agony at her husband. "He will not' go, dearest," replied Harry in the same low and hurried voice. "One word more," said Ottis. "It does seem rather hard, perhaps, to take all your money, and if you have only two hundred, why, it's not much. Give me one hundred and let the arrangement for twenty a year stand good." "You had better do it," whispered Annie, "let us be rid of the dreadful man at once." "You wish it and it shall be done," re- joined her husband. Then turning his eyes towards Ottis he said, "since I have sub-   ceeded in rendering you thus comparatively moderate in your terms, I agree to them." Thus speaking, he made a sign for Annie to go and fetch the money, and after she had left the room Ottis observed, "don't you mean to ask me to take a little refreshment, a drop of wine, or spirits, or what not.", "I have none in the house," replied Harry. "You surely can regale yourself to your heart's content in a few minutes, when you take your departure with my money in your pocket." "Oh, yes, I can wait. JI suppose you haven't heard from yonder lately?" and he jerked his thumb over his shoulder. "Do you allude to Newport? You can very well imagine that we lhave no corres- pondence there. Is Mr. Bell still in his former situation?" "What I haven't you heard then?" ejacu- lated Ottis. "Well, I've got a bit of news to tell you. Bell has married again. He has been married this eighteen months and more; and between you and me, I think he already repents it, for he looks uncommon glum. She is so extravagant; scarcely a day passes that the carrier doesn't bring parcels for Mrs. Bell,; and I understand that she doesn't pay her millinery bills very regular." "And so Mr. Bell is married again?" said Harry in a musing manner, and not for the pUrpose of encouraging anythirg, like familiar conversation with Ottis. "Hush my wife is coming." Annie reappeared, and presented to her husband the money which she had been to fetch. Todd counted it down upon the table, and Ottis, with an air of triumph and satisfac- tion, consigned it to his pocket. "I do not ask you," said our hero, "tQ keep your word, because I am well aware that you will only do so if it suits your pur- pose." "You .keep your agreement and I will keep mine. And now good bye"--with which words Ottis took his departure.  When he was gone the husband and wife experienced considerable relief; and Annie, throwing her arms about Harry's neck, said to him, "Now, my dear husband, what aro we to do? Have you still a feeling of con- fidence in your security? Will you trust yourself to this man?" "No, dearest-.ten thousand times no!" returned Todd. "So long as the money of which he has just robbed us lasts, he will leave us unmolested;..for he flatters himself that I was sincere in offering him the annual pension. Heaven pardon me the falsehood and duplicity that -I practiced! IBut still such dissimulation and deceit were not crimes, when brought to bear in self-defence against such a villain." "No, Harry, you cannot reproach your- Self I understand the object you had in   view;: it was to gain time. Our- persecutor will leave us unmolested with the idea that as you offered him the pension, you are cer- tain to remain here in this neighborhood and in this house." "And into that belief I have evidently lulled him; and hoe will leave us unmolested for the present, thinking that he has only got to write or come at any time in order to practice a, fresh extortion. Now, Annio, cheer up your spirits and. gather ulp your courage, for we will take a step that will baffle him and set at defiance all our ene- mies." "Oh I your words fill my heart with joy," exclaimed Annie, the color returning to her cheeks. "What do you propose, Harry?" "Wo will repair to Canada," responded our hero. "You see, dearest, that whenever we are left to the exertions of our own hon- est industry, we invariably thrive. We are not even compelled to surmount difficulties in establishing ourselves. Hecaven prospers us if vilo. man would leave us unmolested. In Canada we shall be safe." Todd now proceeded to inform his wife that her father had married again; but lihe did not choose to pain her by the intelligence which Mr. Ottis had given him respecting thie new Mrs. Bell's extravagant habits, and the hint lie bad thrown out at the foreman's mournful looks. "If this step will conduce to my father's happinesq," said Annie, "I am rejoiced that lie has taken it. When once we are in Canada, dear Harry, and beyond the re ach of danger, you will permit me to write to him and beseech that he will withdraw those dreadful words ho uttered against me more than a year ago at Louisville; for perhaps, now that he feels his home less lonely, and in the possession of a wife, misses not lhis daughter, his heart will relent." "Certainly, dear Annie, you shall write to your father the moment we are settled in Canada. It would rejoice me unfeignedly that lie should be touched by your filial conduct, and be moved to reply to you in a kind spirit." The Todds, having made up their minds to leave New York, set about their prepara- tions at once. They did not enter upon this task with very painful feelings, for there was hope in. their hearts. It necessarily took several days to dispose of their furniture and give up the lease of their house; and as during this interval Harry's safety remained unmolested, they had no  doubt that their calculations were ,correct in respect to the course which Ottis would pursue. As at Lyons, Harry took an affectionate leave of his scholars on breaking up, his establishment; and his neighbors and friends were all' sincerely grieved to part with him and his amiable wife.  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7116-00000022"/> When the hour of departure came, iHary and Annie could not help experiencing some little anxiety lest the terrible scene at Lyons should be enacted over again in New York; but when they entered the cars, and no sin- ister countenance appeared to Startle them, they felt that they were indeed safe. They reached Oswego without any misadventure worth narrating; and when' on the following morning they stood upon the deck of a steam vessel bound for ToroPto, they ex- changed looks of unutterable joy; for they experienced all the luxury of a conscious security beyond the possibility of accident or treachery. Harry Todd had rightly said to his wife that wheq left to the exertions of their own honest industry, heaven prospered their ef- forts. They arrived in Toronto with about four hundred and fifty dollars in their posses- sion, and resolved to remain two or three days at a hotel to ascertain what the chances were for commencing a school, and Todd was informed that a good teacher was then very much needed, and here was an additional chance of success for our hero, who had al- ready acquired, by his own self-teaching, a considerable education. So far as his 'own personal security was concerned, he was as safe in the frontier town of Toronto as he would have been at the other extremity of Canada, and thus there was every reason to induce the Todds to fix themselves where they had first set their feet in Canada A neat, comfortable and convenient'house was taken at a very low rent. It was a happy day for them when they just es- tablished themselves in the domicile they had fitted up, for they had everything to cheer them, and nothing to throw a damp upon their spirits, or make them dread to look into the future. Todd had some circulars printed and dis- tributed, and these soon produced their effect. He retained the name of Robinson, because he naturally wished to destroy, as much as he could, the possibility that his identifica- tion with the deserter Todd should be even suspected, lest it might injure, him in bis professional avocations. Pupils crowded in upon him, and in the course of a few weeks he had as many as he could'accommodate. So soon as they were thus comfortably settled, Annie reminded Harry of his'pro- amise that she should be .allowed to write to her father, and he at once besought her to do so. She asked himsWhether any conceal- ment need be practised in respect to their place of abode, and whether he would advise the letters should be dispatched elsewhere to be posted? Her husband at once de- clared that he saw no reason for any such reserve, as the utmost injury which Mr. Bell could now do him, would be to take measures to spread a report in Toronto who he really was; but he did not for a moment ,   apprehend that Annie's father would' mani- fest any subh petty spite towards him -or even if he still felt bitter, would incur the trouble and expense of such a vindictive proceeding. Annie accordingly penned the following letter:-             . "TO:RONTo, December 1'th, 1862. MY DEAR FATHER. After so longs an interval of silence it may be that a sight of my hand-writing will not prove altogether unwelcome to you. In this hope at least do I take up mypen. You will perceive that we are settled, in Toronto, Canada, where I am happy to inform you that, through the noble industry of my ex- cellent hasband, our prospects are most flat- toering. The intelligence has reached me that you are ,married. my dear father, ,and in the sincere hope that this alliance is con- tributing to :your happiness, do I offer you my congratulations. And now, dear father, may I entreat that you will pen me a few lines in acknowledgment of this letter, and to convince me that with the lapse oftime you have learned to think less harshy, less severely of your daughter.  Can you not, will you not, show that you appreciate the truth of this in respect to my husband? "Trusting, therefore, that you will answer me in a strain which will fill my heart with rejoicing, I subscribe myself, dear father, Your very affectionate daughter, ANNIE." "P. S.-Have the kindness to address me as Mhrs. Robinson, for, on account of reasons to which I need, not more particularly allude, we are known in Toronto by that name.'" Annie showed this letter to her husband, who approved of the tone in which' it was written, and a fond caress testified the grati- tude he felt for the manner in which his be- loved wife had alluded to himself. The letter was duly posted, and Annie, calculat- ing how  many days must elapse ere she would receive a reply, buoyed herself up with the hope that at least by Christmas-day the wished-for response would arrive, and she could sca rcely think so exceedingly ill of her father, notwithstanding his past con- duct, as to suppose that he would refuse to address herin a strain of kindness. CHAPTER XL. CHRISTMAS day passed, the month of De* cember was drawing to a close, conducting with it the year to which it belonged, into the grave of Tinae, and Annie began :to fear   v that her father would not answer her letter. But one morning the postman called at the ,Toddls house, and a letter 'bearing the American post-mark, but the address of ,which was written in a female band, was directed to Mrs. Robinson. She hastened to to tear it open, and found its contents to be as follows:- "UNITED STATES HOTEL, CLEVELAND, 0HIO, December 28th, 1S62. MY DEAR ANNIE, For in this style will you permit me to address you, considering the position -in which we stand relative to each other. Your father received your letter, which was indeed most welcome to him. For some time past he had bey led to the reflection that his conduct might possibly have been too harsh and too severe towards you. I will not altogether take credit to myself for having induced these feelings ih your father's breast, but you will at least give me credit for having 'fostered them, for I assure you that from the very day on which I became your step-mother, I have exerted myself to promote a reconciliation between my hus- band and his daughter; therefore, months and months ago, had he known where to find you, he Wrould have certainly taken up his pen to write you a few lines, and to as- sure you of his desire to bury all the past in oblivion. Thus was it that your letter proved truly welcome both to him and my- self You will therefore have the'pleasure of conveying to Mr. Todd the assurance of Mr. Bell that when next they meet it will be to exchange the warmest and the most cordial pressure of the hand. "You will doubtless be astonished to see that I date this letter from Cleveland, but when I explain the reason yoi will accept it as additional proof of Mr. Bell's anxiety to effect a speedy reconciliation with yourself and your husband. "For some time past your father's health has caused great alarm  to myself and his friends. . Under thiat impression, notwith- standing your father has determined to undertake a journey to Canada that he night embrace you ere hie dies. He   Was well aware that -certain reasons would lead you and Mr. Todd to prefer that this visit 'should be paid to you both in Canada, than that you should be requested to undertake a journey to the United States for the purpose of a meeting. We accordingly set out two days ago, and arrived at Cleveland last night, but the fatigues of traveling operated prejudicially to your father's health, and he was during the night taken very ill. But it, is considered most inexpedient for your father to cross the lake at this"season of the year, and the medical attendant sets his face against -it. Under these circumstances I earnestly conjure both you and your husband   to come across, if it be only, for a single day, :to see your father. I say both 'of you, be. cause my husband declares that he cannot die bappily unless he grasped Mr. Todd's hand, as well, as embrace you, dear Annie, in his arms. Therefore, under all these'cir- cumstances, I have no' doubt that you will, both accede to the urgent request which I thus proffer on behalf of myself and my hus. band.          ' "Believe me to remain, dearest Annie, your affectionate mother-in-law, CORA BELL." As the reader may suppose, Annie was in one sense overjoyed by this letter: It as- sured her of a complete reconciliation with her father, and what was equally delightful, it proffered the same toward 4her husband. She however could not help fearing, on the other hand, that her father's illness was more severe than her step-mother either chose to believe or admit  Having read, the letter, she placed it in Harry's hands and watched; his countenance as he read it. His' features showed bytheir expression that he fully shared in his beloved Annie's joy and de- light in respect to the proffered reconcilia- tion; and when he had finished the perusal, he at once said to her, "'We must go." "You do not apprehend that you are in- curring any risk?" asked Anniei clinging affectionately to his arm. "So little, I conceived lvas her husband's reply, " that it will cause me no uneasiness. But even if I thought it great, I should not shrink from -chancing it under' such circum- stances. No, dear Annie, I am not appre- hensive on that score. The regiment to which I belonged is still stationed at Mur- freesboro, many long miles away from Cleve' land. Yes, we will go. Fortunately it is the Christmas holidays, and therefore we can spare 'a few days without detriment to the school."        v "And little Harry will go with us?" said Annie. "As a matter of course. The dear child will enjoy the little trip; and moreover, uh- der present circumstances, your father will be delighted -to acknowledge and welcome his grandson." The 'preparations they had to make for so short an expedition were necessarilyfew and limited. and they accordingly resolved to answer the letter in person by proceeding to Cleveland on the following day. It was a source of satisfaction that the weather was now very beautiful, considering the season of the year--healthy and bracing, without being bleaklyrcold; and the lake was per- fectly calm. Harry and Annie, with their beloved little boy, stepped accordingly on the deck of the steam  packet at about ton ia the nlorning,- and in about six hours they entered Cleve:  &#xD;<pb n="42 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7116-00000023"/> land harbor. It was perhaps with a mo- mehtary sense of insecurity-or rather we should say, with something like a regret at having been compelled to quit a state of complete security-that Harry stepped forth from the steam packet on the stairs leading to the quay; but this, feeling almost imme- diately vanished as he thought to himself of a million chances to one that there were against his being recognized and taken. Annie experienced a transitory fluttering at the heart, but nothing that might be called serious apprehension; for she saw likewise the incalculable chances in favor of her husband and the few that existed against him. To little Harry the whole scene was full of the novelty and excitement of change, and he skipped up the steps in front of his father and mother. The top of the steps was reached, and the Todds had just planted their feet upon the quay, when a hand was laid on Harry's arm, and on his oars, as well as on those of his wife, fell the ominous words, "You are my prisoner!" A shriek roso up to Annie's lips, but with an almost preterhuman effort she kept it back; for quick as lightning did a sense of duty spring up in her mind-that duty which she, in fer angel-character of a de- voted and virtuous woman, was ever ready to perform--namely, the ministration of solace to her husband. "I will go with you quietly," said Harry to the constable, " and will reward you if you spare me any ignominy in the presence of this crowd." But the voice in which he spoke was the low deep tone of despair. "I don't want to hurl your feelings more than I can help," replied the constable, at the same moment making a sign over his shoulder for two of his comrades who were close at hand to keep back. "So come along quick. I must take your arm, though"--to which of course Harry was compelled to submit. Fortunately the passengers who were landing at the time were so busy in hurrying off to their homes or to hotels, or else to meet the friends assembled to receive them, that the arrest passed unnoticed by those around; and thus the unfortunate Todds were spared the ignominy of becoming a mark for universal observation. Annie-pale as death, but keeping back tears and sobs alike-clung to her husband's arms, which she pressed with even a con- vulsive violence, in mute entreaty that he would bear up against this frightful calamity. With her other hand she led the boy, who was intelligent enough to perceive that something was wrong, but what it was he of course could not possibly understand. The looks of his father and mother struck the poor little fellow with a dismay that prevented him from putting a single ques-   tion; but when Annie saw him glance up- wards, half in fright and half in curiosity, at her own and Harry's countenances, it was with a world of difficulty she could repress a violent outhurst of heart-rending anguish. What Harry's feelings were we must leave the reader to imagine. We candidly confern that we have exhausted whatsoever power of language we may be enabled to wield in describing his emotions on former occasions, wien overtaken by calamity; so that we ha-e no words left to convey an adequate idea of the sense of despair with which he received this withering blight that now fell upon his happiness and his heart. "Where do you choose to be taken to?" asked the constable as they proceeded on their way. "I There will be no cars till the afternoon to Louisville." "Who is at the United States Hotel?" demanded Harry, feeling who the author of this atrocity was, and believing him to be there. "Well," returned the  man evasively, "you may just as well go the United States as anywhere else, for I see that you must be a person that has got money to spend." Harry made no answer. An awful stupor seized upon his brain. He appeared to be walking in a dream. They proceeded to the hotel, and on a word from the constable, a waiter showed them at once to a private room. Almost immediately afterward the other two consta- bles made their appearance, and one of them said to him who had taken Harry into cus- tody, "You must put on the handcuffs. He says that this is a slippery chap." "He? To whom do you allude?" ejacu- lated our .hero, starting up from the chair on which he had sunk down when entering the room. 1' Who is he? where is he? Tell him to come hither, that I may sacrifice him to vengeance." "Oh i my dearest husband," cried Annie, throwing her arms about his neck, and now bursting. into a paroxysm of grief which could no longer be restrained, "I beseech and implo re you to calm yourself." "Calm myself, Annie " echoed Harry, a withering bitterness in his accents and the direst vengeance in his looks. "As well bid the storms of heaven to be at peace! It is for you, my beloved one, that I feel thus deeply. Oh, Godl the anguish, the horror; the excruciation of all thisl" and sinking down again upon the chair from which he had so recently started up, the unhappy man covered his face with his hands and sobbed aloud. The little boy climbed up on his father's lap, imploring him in piteous accents not to cry; and Annie, falling upon her knees by her husband's side, in a broken voice re- newed her supplications that he would be calm. It was a scene of such bitter, burning  &#xD;<pb n="-43" xml:id="VAC7116-00000024"/> anguish that the constables themselves were for. the instant moved, and they exchanged looks as much as to imply that 'they were sorry to be compelled to witness it. "Well, I will be calm I exclaimed Harry with an abruptness that in itself was,terri- ble; for -it appeared as if his reason were suddenly touched. Then in a. moment per- ceiving the horrified dismay that appeared on the countenances of his wife and child, he threw his arms round them both, caught them to his breast and covered them with kisses. His tears pourld out freely, and, he experienced some relief-or, at all events, an abatement of the terrific excite- ment that a :moment before had existed in his mind. The constable who had arrested him now slowly and somewhat hesitatingly produced frorAi his pocket certain objects which sent forth ,an ominous metallic sound, and both Harry and Annie at once too well under- stood what they were. The little boy appeared to have some dim but torrible idea that "the wicked men," as he called them, were about to put chains upon his father, and he looked on in speech- less dismay. His beautiful countenance had lost' its color. The child seemed pale, fright- ened and ill. Oh I what a spectacle, to har- row the minds of his parents. "Twenty dollars," said, Harry, "if: you take :me down to Louisville without those." The officer glanced towards his compan- ions, both of whom had placed their backs against the door; and one of them, making a sign to the effect that he who held the hand- cuffs had better wait a moment, issued from the room. In- a few minutes he returned, saying, "As we have got charge of the prisoner, it's all at our own risk whether he escapes or not; so we can do as we like." The consequence was that, after a little negotiation, the constables agreed that if the sum were doubled they would not put on the handcuffs. Fortunately the Todds had come from Canada well provided with money. The forty dollars were paid down, and thus, for the present at least, was the unihappy man spared that fearful indignity, and his wife and child the anguish of seeing it inflicted. "Will you permit me," asked Harry, " to be alone with my family for a little while? You can keep outside tho door.' This was also agreed to, and, when the f three constables had issued forth there was a repetition -of that anguished scene, of erm- s bracing and sobbing and weeping, which we have just now described, -But when the father and mother . regained sufficient' forti- tude to enable them to look, their hideous calamity in the face and discuss what'was to be done, they began to converse in,whis- 'perng!voices, in such a way that little Harry ,;:rmg!Lt not overhear what they said..   "No dearest Annie,' remarked Harry; "Iisten to, whatI am about to say. What . desire is this--that ybou return to C'an. ada with little Harry to-morrow, and you sell off all that we possess there. You can then return to Nashville. By the time you arri  there my. trial will be commenced. You understand me, dearest? and you will fulfill my wishes?" "Yes, my beloved husband; you have but to express your desire, and it becomes law for me." "No, dearest--I will study to compose my feelings. But you, my beloved, will you promise that .you will endeavor to do tia same?"' "I will, I will; for each other's sake must we do it 1" And then there were more embracings- and, alas I more weepings. But we will - not dwell any longer upon this sad, sad scene. Suffice it to say that the unfortunate family were left entirely to themselves until the departure of the cars, which was night; and then the sadness of that scene became far sadder still in the mo- ment of separation. Annie felt as if the chords of her heart were being torn out of her--as if she were parting with life itself amidst rending agonies; but she suffered not all the extreme bitterness of her anguish to be betrayed by her looks. The poor child wept as if his little heart would break, and again and again werQ those last embraces renewed ere Harry could so far master his fortitude as to tear himself away from the beloved ones 'and rush from the room. Then Annie, snatching up little Harry in her arms, continued to weep over him long and plenteously, in the poignant crucifixion of her feelings. Harry entered, thl cars, and found that he was to be accompanied by two of the con- stables. It was not long till a third person entered, the car and took a seat with them; and with some degree of hesitation asked one of the, constables if he was sure Harry ,would do him no harm? ,." He has pledged himself to be perfectly quiet," was ,the response.' "If he isn't, we must slip the darbies on." It was not long until'the lamp was lighted, and behold! Iwho was it but David Ottis, which struck Harry with horror. But not a word was spoken until long after the cars had started, Mr. Ottis re- markced, "Well, I say this job was done ;neat and cleane wasn't it?" -"Are, you'daddressing yourself to me'?" demanded--Harry, podd,. But as he thus 'd- ; dressed that greatest',of all miscreants, he i felt the fury of a tiger springing up withmin him---, .boiling: rage-a ,terrible thirst for - vengeance, such as-he had never experienced i in his life before.  , . *"Well XI ws 'apeajong t9 anybody. t'at  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7116-00000025"/> chooses to listen," answered Ottia "Come, Harry Todd, you must confess that you de- served this of me." "I When I pledged myself to remain per- fectly quiet," replied Harry, now experi- encing a difficulty amounting almost to an excruciation to prevent himself from flying at Ottis's throat and throttling him, "I at least expected that every cause of irritation would be avoided." "Come, come, Mr. Ottis," said one of the constables, " it isn't exactly fair." "Well, then, I won't address myself to him." And throughout the rest of the Journey Ottis kept his word. CHAPTER XIL IT was a cold, drizzling evening, on the fifth day after the arrest at Cleveland, that the untlppy Harry Todd entered Murfrees- boro in the custody of Ottis and the two constables, who delivered him to Ilis regi. mont. He had how the handcuffs on his wrists, but he was not altogether dispirited. There was a project in Harry's mind which he fancied would, if carried out, and if his conjectures on a certain point were correct, afford him the means of inflicting a terrible punishment upon the author of his calami-. ties. What his project was, and what our hero's conjectures were, will transpire in due course. A  court-martial being duly summoned, Harry Todd was arraigned and was found guilty, and condemned to about the same as the last, and in addition thereto to be brand- ed as a deserter, and to Wntake good the time he had   st. He was to commence his punishment in one week from this time, Which was on the tenth of March, 1863. Anrie and little Harry arrived on the cars, and she was allowed to visit her hus- band. In a few moments our heroes were clasped in each other's arms; little Harry had been previously informed by his mamma that his father was now  a soldier, and therefore the child was not amazed to see his parent in a uniform suit. On the follow- ing day Harry and Annie held a deliberation upon their affairs; the money which they had realized was three hundred dollars. The reader may perhaps wonder why Harry did not make up his mind to leave his regiment again as soon as possible, and flee back to Canada, there to remain for ever, with the fixed determination of allowing no pretext or stratagem to seduce him again to his native land. But no, he had not nowthe energy sufficient for this. His nature was already undergoing  a change; he looked upon the whole world with distrust. He' felt   as if his was an evil destiny, which he must irresistibly fulfil. But lie did not state all this to Annie. He had still a boundless love for her, and also for their child; so that if he did not hint at another desertion, neither did he give his reason for not at- tempting it, and Annie, of course, did not breathe a syllable bordering upon such a suggestion. She reminded Harry that when at Lyons she had comfortably sustained her- self by means of needle-work, and she thought of h4aving recourse to the same pur- suit again. Witti a portion of their ready money:furni- ture might be -bought for two little rooms, and thus a saving in the rental be effected. But on the other hand it was by no means certain that the regimeht would remain long in Murfreesboro, and if it were suddenly or speedily removed Annie had made up her mind to return to Nashville, and if she could not obtain work there she would then go to Louisville, where she was certain of getting work. "And now," he observed, when the dis- cussion of their affairs was over, "I am going to tell you, my dear Annie, what I purpose to do. I intend to write to the Postmaster General and inform him that I have every reason to believe the villain Ottis opens the letters which pass through his hands. How could he have known that we were in Canada unless lhe had opened that letter which you had penned to your father?" "Oh fatal, fatal letter," ejaculated Annie, "would to heaven I had never written it." "Do not blame yourself. my dearest wife," responded her husband, "you have no need to do so. But to return to what I bWas say- ing. That letter which deluded us away from Canada could only have been written by some person who had read the one which you addressed to your father. We  know that Ottis must have tampered with the correspondence between Horatio Thurston and your father two years ago, or else he could not have written that letter to my officer which made me aware of what was going on. Oh I to be revenged on that vil- lain, to be revenged upon him. Oh I it will prove the sweetest moment of my life." "Much as we have suffered, deeply as you have suffered, my  beloved husband," she said at length, giving utterance to her feel- ings, and she spoke in a low tremulous voice as she looked up with plaintive earnestness into his countenance, * yet rreveinge is an evil sentiment to cherish. Oh, Harry, I be- seech you' to banish it from your heart, that heart which is so good, so magnanimous." "That was, you mean, Annie," he ex- claimed, "but it is warped, cruelly warped, towards all the world except yourself and our dear child.", "Harry, I  beseech you not to talk thus" said Annie, unable to restrain the tea  that   were pouring down her cheeks. "What can I, say, what can I do to comfort you  Oh I what can I do?", "My dear child," exclaimed Annie, snatch- ing him up in her arms,"' do not look thus sorrowful." "But papa was scolding you," he said, beginning to cry. -"No, no, your papa never scolded me," and at this assurance the little fellow's face brightened up.' "We must talk this matter over alone; Annie,' said Harry, having caressed his little son. "'Take him to the woman of the  house for a few minutes, and let her buy him a toy.", The child was thus disposed of for a little while, .and when Annie returned ; to the chamber she found her husband pacing to and fro in a moody manner, with his arms folded across his chest. "I will be avenged, I will be avenged;" such were the words Which Annie had thus caught. "Now my dear wife," he continued, taking her hand and pressing it in his own, " you must permit me to have my way in this. I feel that the only solace to my wounded spirit will be the punishment of that re- morseless villain. Surely, surely you, dear Annie; must hate him as I do?" "I will say no Inore, my dear husband," Eho rejoined; but it was with a profound mournfulness alike of tone and voice that she spoke. Harry Todd hastened to take writing ma- terials, and seating himself at the table he penned a letter to the Postmaster General, expressing a conviction, from various cir- cumstinces which had come to his know- ledge, that David Ottis, of the post office at Newport, was accustomed to opening letters that passed through his hands. The letter was folded up and Harry took, it to the post office, and then went over to his regiment, and after his duty was over he went-back to his house, and each and every day after Harry got through with his duty he would spend all of his time at home. It was not a long time until Harry and Annie got word that David Ottis had been arrested, and bhowit had been done. There was a letter posted to Mr. Thurston ; it had been traced as far as Newport post office. That letter contained a fifty dollar note, the number of the note was 1,325. After the mail had been distributed the detective went in and asked for a letter for Mr. Thurston; Mr. Ottis answered none here. The next' day he called and the same answer, and Mr. Thurston and the detective called the next day, and the same answer, and they found out where Mr. Ottis had got a note changed, and it was' the same number and the same note. Mr. David: OttiS Was placed in. the dock charged with stealing a letter containing   t fifty dollars, and addressed to Mr. Thurston. t The evidence was complete against Ottis, and he was sentenced to ten years imprison, ; ment. 3  A few days afterwards Mr., Ottis received the following letter.-- "MURFEESBURO, Tenn, April 20th, 1868. MR. D. OTIS, SIR,-I have read in the newspaper of , your trial and condemnation. I now feel thusavenged for the bitter wrongs you have Itolight against me, for it was I who gave Vthe post-office authorities that information, in pursuance of which they acted. Twice have you been the cause that I was subject. ed to a horrible punishment, and you ruined my first prospects. My punishment is past; your's is about to commence, and it will en- dure for ten years. "Go, monster that you are, go to the place where your misery may teach you of:;the. wrongs you have done to me, and my wife, and my child, whom you were twice the means of snatchilg-firom a happy home. Go, reptile, I can waste no moro words upon you. HARRY TODD. Shortly after Ottis's trial, Capt.' EHbraf Thurston, arrived at homre to pass a few weeks with his parents.      . On the day after Horatio's arrival at homek his father took an opportunity of having some private discourse with his wife. "I tell you what, Mrs. Thurston-Horatio must marry." "Oh, dear met he is but a boy.  Why, you would make me out quite old. For heaven's'sake don't think of his marrying yet 1" "Nonsense!" ejaculated Mr. Thurston. "We must find a wife for Horatio. , He'is home on the present occasion for thirty days . --ample time for him to! become engaged to ,some eligible young lady." Meanwhile Capt. Thurston had gone out smoking a cigar. ' We should hero observe that on the proi vious occasions of his' visits at home since;. he had joined his regiment, he had treated Mr. Bell with the most marked coldness, never speaking to him, on the account of, the marriage scheme in respect to Annie being so cqmpletely frustrated at Chicago. Horatio was walking along the street. He overtook Mr. Bell. UHe:touched his hat and said, "Good day, Mr, Bell. But," Horatio,; 'exclaimed, "stop a moment, Mr. Bell. , It is a long time since you and I said a word to each other." ' It is a long time, sir,", replied, Bell "  thought you bore me ill-will, and so of course , I was not forward. enough, to address you when you hav e been at home." , ,'  :-"Well, Mr. Bell, I understand,yo an d,:v your second wife," observed Horatio, " don't  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7116-00000026"/> got along very well. She is somewhat gay and extravagant--eh, Bell " "She is indeed, sir-and there's no use denying it. 'When she was plain Cora Smith she was all amiability and smiles, but Low she is a she devil in temper." "You sought to do the best you could for your girl, and it was all right and natural. So we will bury the past -in oblivion. I have not forgotten that I used to spend some agreeable evenings with you." "Perhaps, sir, you would do me the honor to walk in and take a glass of my cider?" said Mr. Bell. "With all my heart, Mr. Bell," said Hora- tio. So,he and Bell advanced towards the house together. It was not long till they were at the door. Horatio entered the little parlor. At the first glance he could not help thinking of Annie; and it was not long till Mrs. Bell entered. He extended Lis hand, saying, "I am very glad to see you, Miel, Bell. ' "Uapt. Thurston is truly welcome here," 8ho responded. "Pray sit down, sir," said Mr. Bell, "and I will bring some of that nice cider." "'Cider, Mr. Bell? Order the servant to bring in some wine; and I think I have a few biscuits here," said Mfrs. Bell, turning to the sideboard and producing the cakes froim a drawer. "I thank you," said Horatio; "I would much prefer-cider. It is more refreshing at this time of the day. But if you will permit me to drop in now and then of an evening, I may perhaps be beguiled into something stronger." "You will always be welcome-most welcome," replied Mrs. Bell, perceiving that her husband had just quitted the room to bring the cider. "' Qh, I have not forgotten that you and I are old acquaintances," exclaimed the Cap- a tain.  "But I must not call you Cora any longer, now that you have become a sedate t married woman." &amp;"Oh, very sedate indeed!" she cried with  a merry laugh.  "I beg that you will not stand on any ceremony with me-at least not when such restraint may be thrown off," 1 she added; glancing towards the door. I "I understand Bell is jealous-eh?" ob- served Horatio, in a voice of mysterious F confidence. "What fun it would be to ex- cite the fellow's jealousy."      t "Oh, jealous!" echoed Cora; "he is eve- t rything that is unbearable. I am sure he leads t me such a life I wish I had never seen him." i ' How  you are calumniated," observed a Horatio.                n "And now tell me, how long are you  c going to stay at home?"!       a "About thirty days-unless I  get too thoroughly tired of a town lif before my b leav of absence expires."       e   "Military gentlemen are very clever at compliments--Capt. Thurston especially;" and again she laughed slyly. At this moment Bell, who had been listen- ing at the door, made his appearance with the bottle of cider in his hand, but looking as if he had not overheard a word of what had taken place.  : "Really, Bell," said Mrs. Bell, "you have taken your time to fetch that cider." '"I could not find the key of the cupboard, my dear," responded her husband. The cider was poured out. Mr. Thurston drank two or three glasses; and Bell thought that for the sake of apearances he had better remain present on this occasion. And after they had talked on indifferent topics, and when Horatio rose to depart he pressed Mrs. Bell's hand tenderly in his own, and shaking hands with Mr. Bell, he threw upon him a lo which was as much as to imply that all animosity was at an end-although he pro- mised himself in his heart that he would do his best to foster the wife's ill feeling toward her husband, and call at the house now and then when he knew Bell would be there to witness the results. On the other hand, the unprincipled husband chuckled inwardly, for he had heard enough at the door to con- vince him that his wife and Capt. Thurston were already on very good terms with each other. On the other hand, Capt. Thurston thought to himself what a fine opportunity he had, now to be revenged. upon lMr. Bell for the way he was treated in regard to Annie. Three or four days afterward Mr. and Mrs. Thurston  had ,at last found a good match, as they thought, for Horatio. The young damsel's name was Clara Evans. Sho was about twenty years of age, and was very handsome.  tier hair was raven black, her eyes were dark blue and her complexion fair, and she was of medium height. She was an only daughter, and was well educa- ted; Such was Clara Evans, the beautiful and interesting creature whom it was intend- ed, if practicable, to bestow as a wife upoa Capt. Thurston. Mr. and Mrs. Thurston, in company with the captain, made a call one evening at the house of Mr. Evans, when the captain and Clara soon made up their acquaintance, and passed away the evening very agreeably. In two or three days afterward the cap- tain called to see Clara, and in the afternoon they took a few hours' walk, which seemed to be very agreeable to both. Then return- ing home, and tea being over, between eight and nine o'clock he might have been seen making his way to Mr. Bell's dwelling; and on knocking at the door he was immediately admitted. He learned that Mr. Bell was not at home, but that Mrs. Bell was. He   accordingly entered the parlor, and found Mrs. BeU   seated alone reading a new novel. She rd- ceived Captain Thurston with a remarkable kindness. "Dear me, Captain, you are gallant this evening," and Cora affected to turn away her countenance as if to hide her blushes. "I can not be too gallant towards a pretty woman, such as you," and Horatio fixed his eyes with impudent meaning upon her. "Where is Bell this evening?" asked Ho- ratio, as he took a chair close by the one in which the lady had now seated herself. "Oh I down at the public house, as usual," s1o replied; " but perhaps he is better there than here."  "Then he has taken to drinking lately?" observed the captain. "Oh, yes, terribly He was always fond of his spirits and water of an ovening, but he used to take his glass at home and never went into extremes; but of late he has fre- quented the public house and drinks deeper every day." "What a disgusting sight is a drunken husband!" remarked the captain. "I won- dor any woman of spirit puts up with it." "Oh I you should hear how I sometimes go on against him," exclaimed Cora, "yoll would then see that I really do possess a  spirit." -"I should like to hear you. I told you just now that there is nothing I .love so much as to see a woman of spirit, particularly when her anger is not directed against my- SOelf" "I tell you what," said Mrs. Bell as a thought struck her, "if you would really hke to hear me tell William my mind you could just wait till he comes in." "AIhl but I do not want him to find me here, at least not at such a late hour. But if I did stay, how would you manage it?" "You could conceal yourself behind the window   curtains," replied Mrs. Bell. "He woild not stay long in the room here when once I began to storm at him, and as soon, as he went up stairs I could let you secretly and quietly out of the house." Suddenly there was a  knock at the front door, and Cora exclaimed, "There he is, a good half hour earlier than usual. "Perhaps he is sober," suggested Ho- ratio. "Not a chance of it." "But the servant will tell him I am here," was the captain's next remark. "She will say nothing of the kind, she never speaks unless spoken to." The captain immediately passed behind the curtains, which he drew in such a man- ner as to conceal himself. "A  pretty state you are in, Bell," ex- claimed his wife. "How dare you present yourself in this condition before- me? Oh, what a spectacle you are, what a loathsome object!"   "Now then, enougkL of this," growled Bell, "and get up to bed with. you." "I shall not at your command," retorted Cora. "Be off yourself, I am sure you' must be anxious to lie down, for you can scarcely stand." "And I will show that I am the master. Come, now, go up to bed directly," and Bell spoke in a still firmer voice and in a still more resolute tone of command. Cora was not prepared for this, but she therefore thought that the best plan would be to get her husband up stairs as soon as possible, and adopting a somewhat more ' conciliatory tone and manner she said, "I presume you are coming up at once?" "Yes, directly;" then taking up one of the candles he said, "Sarah will put out the other light when she has seen that all is safe. Go up and I will follow you." Mrs Bell was glad to find that there was this easy escape from thlo trouble into wicdl she had got herself   "Come along, thin," she said. Mr. Bell said not a word, but followed his wife from the parlor. "Now, Sarah, we are going up to bed: see that all's right." Sarah proceeded to the parlor, and Captain Thurston, emerging from behind the curtains, placed his finger on his lips. The woman started, or affected to start, as if in dismay at the sudden appearance of the captain, and he at once, slipping ten dollars into her hand, said in a hurried whisper, "Let me out aS quick as you can, and for heaven's sake doa't say a word to Mr. Bell." The door was opened cautiously and lihe stole out. As he hurried back to his home he said to himself, "It was a deuced deal too foolish of me to go behind those curtains, but I did want to hear Cora blow the fellow up. I think she is devilishy in love with me; but I don't know, perhaps I had better not, and yet it would be taking a fine re- venge on that old Bell for trying to hook mn into marrying his daughter two years ago. Ah, the villainl what lies he did tell me, what tricks he did play, and what a narrow escape I  had, too. How I could ever have been such a  fool I can't make out.' The next morning at breakfast Horatio's mother exclaimed, "How late you stay out. at night, whlere have you b8en?" ';Oh! I  just dropped in at Martin's," he responded, glibly uttering the first excuse that came into his head. "I suppose," said Aunt Jane, "that Mr. Martin was very glad to see you?" "Oh I  very," ejaculated Horatio. "Then Mr. Martin is ubiquitous," observed Aunt Jane with a   sneer, "for he had' been with us the whole evening." "Well, then," said Horatio, bursting out into a   supercilious laugh, "I Suppos IT hayen't-been there at all. And T   tell'you what it is, Aunt Janoe you needn't show  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7116-00000027"/> such anxiety to catch me out in a fib. I am not a boy now." "No, you are a manikin/' she observed quietly.- "And you are a nasty, ill-tempered, sour- looking old maid," ejaculated Horatio, and he flung himnself out of the room in a violent rage. "That was not right of Horatio, very wrong indeed," exclaimed his father,. red with indignation. "But then Aunt Jane should not question him, he is not a child now," observed his mother. "It was you, my dear, who first questioned him," replied Aunt Jane. "As for his im- pertinence, I care nothing about it, it's the way he has been brought up," and with these words she quitted the apartment. As Captain Thurston was wending his way along the streets he overtook Mrs. Evans and her daughter Clara. Mrs Evans said, "You seemed uncertain, Captain Thurston, whether you should join us; I can assure you that if we are not taking you from any moro agreeable occupation, your company would be most welcome. The weather is ;ruly beautiful and inviting for a walk." Horatio offered the ladies each an arm. The young lady was evidently laboring under a deep. depression of spirits, which she, how- ever, strove to conquer, or at least to con- ceal. But she only spoke in monosyllables, or in brief sentences, and as for a smile, none gleamed upon her lips. After they had walked some distance the mother complained of fatigue, and they then started for home, where they soon arrived. Mrs. Evans ob- served " that it is no reason why I should deprive you two of your walk." Thus speaking, she quitted Horatio's arm and entered the mansion, leaving her daugh- ter with him whom she hoped to behold the young lady's bridegroom. "rShall we extend our walk a little, Miss Clara?" inquired Horatio. "I shall be happy to accompany you," was the young lady's reply, but delivered in a somewhat cold tone; for she was still the prey of desponding thoughts. As they were strolling along the street Capt. Thurston's eye caught sight of a gayly dressed female approaching up the street. He had no trouble in recognizing Mrs. Bell, and his first impulse was to turn suddenly. off with Clara in another direction; but he felt that this would be an insult which Mrs. Bell was quite capable of resenting on tho spot; and he naturally dreaded such a scene. Besides, it would appear extraordinary to Miss Clara herself to drag her -across the street; and while he was hesitating what cousre to adopt, it became too late to re- -treat or diverge at all. i' Hiowx do you do, Capt. Thurston?" said Mrm Bell, walking straight up to him and extending her hand.   Horatio was. compelled to stop and take that hand, which was not very agreeable at that time; and raising his hat to make a polite bow, in order to disarm Cora of any ill humor, he led Clara onward. t"How very rude and impertinent some of these mechanics' wives are apt to be," said Horatio. "Who was that lady?" exclaimed Miss Evans. "She is certainly veiry familiar." "That is the wife of Mr. Bell, the foreman of my father's shop." He inwardly cursed his folly in having committed such- an over- sight as to bring Miss Evans for a walk in that direction. But the evil was done. After walking some minutes in-silence, he renewed the conversation by directing his fair companion's attention to some interest- ing piece of scenery, but her replies were cold and distant. Again there was an inter- val of silence, which he broke by asking her if they would return home, to which she replied that they would. After reaching hIome the captain remained a short time, and then left, bidding her good bye. CHAPTER   XIII. IN the evening Horatio Thurston sallied forth from the'mansion with his cigar in his mouth, and bent his steps toward Mr. Bell's. He had two objects in making this call so soon after the occurrence of the forenoon, In the first place, he was anxious to disarm Cora of any animosity slohe might experience on account of the somewhat cold way he had treated her.  On arriving at the house, Capt. Thurston learned from  Sarah, the servant, that Mr. Bell wa   out, as usual, but that Mrs. Bell was aloin   the parlor. Cora had expected this visit, an was prepared. "Whereois Bell this evening?" asked the captain. "At the public hous3 as usual, I suppose. Why, upon my word, you look quite charming  and pleased this evening. Do let mo look at that ring," ho said, as a pretext for taking her hand, which she aban- doned to him with only a slight show of re- sistance. "It is really very pretty-the hand I mean, and not the rind;" and as he spoke Ilhe pressed that hand to iis lips. "Fie, Capt. Thurston," exclaimed Cora, affecting to turn away her head in confusion, "are you not ashamed of yourself?" "You are so bewitchingly beautiful this evening that you must excuse me"-and he pressed his lips to hers without experiencing a repulse on the present occasion. But  that very same instant the door opened, and Sarah the servant mado her ap pearance, bearing the snuffars in her hand.   Mrs.! Bell flew to a seat, and Horatio ran his fingers through his hair. She deposited the sniffers upon the table and quitted the room. "How provoking!" ejaculated Mrs. Bell, who was in reality much. annoyed. '*Oh, she will not say a word," observed Capt. Thurston. "Besides, she must have thought there was something singular the other night, when I was concealed behind the curtains." 'I fear," she   immediately answered, "that I am acting very foolishy. What must she think?  Ohl- I have been very imprudent. Now, Capt. Thurston, I entreat you to do me a service." "What is it?" he asked, still astonished a  e seriousness which she had suddenly putts. "I, wish you would leave me," she replied, rising from her chair, but remaining at a little distance. "And I beseech that if you come here again, it may be in the broad daylight, when people are about." "But are you serious, or is this a part you are playing?" and still Horatio gazed upon her with mingled surprise and incredulity. "I am   serious--perfectly so," she an- swered. "But I can forgive you for asking me if I am playing a part. My conduct has been suffioiefit to warrant you in thinking anything.  Do leave me, Capt. Thurston." "If w e must part, then," said Horatio, "will you grant me one favor? Permit me to send you some little present to-morrow as a token of my esteem and friendship. Now, do not refuse me; it is the only con- dition upon which I will go away at once." "Well, well, have it your own way," murmured   Cora. "Now  pray leave me alone." "One more kiss on that fair hand, and I take my departure." "Now go," she said, having for a moment yielded  him her hand.  "Go, I beseech you." "Good bye," said the captain. "'But re- member, if you wish to see .me again, a note sent to the post-office will bring me, hither." With these words he issued forth from the house, slipping five dollars into Sarah's hand as a bribe to insure her silence in respect to the caress which she had seen him upon her mistress. And  he retraed his way home, where he soon arrived. At breakfast time on the following morn- ing he intimated that lie intended to ride over to Cincinnati to make some purchases 'which he required. He proceeded to that town, where he bought a very handsome 'silk dress. This he ordered to be made up into a parcel and addressed to Mrs. Bell; and after all this being done, he rode backl home. But in a  week after this Horatio received   a note from Mra. Bell, and after he re- ceived it he made arrangements to. go down in the evening, between eight and nine o'clock. At about nine o'clock Capt. Thurston made his appearance, and the moment he was alone with Mrs. Bell he pressed her hand to his lips, which afforded him tho most unfeigned pleasure. She really did look uncommonly well-prettier than he had ever seen her before; and he felt an inward glow of triumph at the idea of approaching success. "You must think very ill of me," she said when they were seated at the table, "to have written to you." "Very ill," he ejaculated, "on the con- trary, it gave me infinite pleasure. How can any one think ill of a pretty woman who suffers him to perceive that he is not an ob- ject of indifference to her?" "Do you really mean me to understand,' she asked with a languishing tenderness, "that you care anything for me?" "How can you ask such a question? Why am I here if I did not? why was I so ready to obey your summons?" "Yes, I think you like me a little," she murmured tremulously, "because you know how unhappy I am at home; you have shown a friendly feeling, but then, perhaps, you dearly love Clara Evans?" "I mean to marry her," rejoined H-oratio, "but as for love, it's quite another thing. I love you, Cora, and if you were single I would marry you." "Do you really think so?" she said, flat. tered by the assurance. ". think so or I should not say it. Why, you look so handsome this evening," said Horatio. ':!"How do you like my silk dress you sent- me tho other day?" exclaimed Cora. "H-ow do you like it?" observed Ioratio, "it is very pretty, I thinkh." "O yes, it is a very pretty present you have sent me." "Cora, you are truly beautiful," interrupt. ed Horatio, passing his arm round her waist and pressing his lips to hers. At- that moment the door opened and Sarah entered the room. A shriek escaped from the lips of Mrs. Bell as she tore herself away from the captain's arms. Sarah, who appeared to have intruded only for the pur- pose of inquiring whether Mrs. Bell chose to have supper served up; and Horatio, hastily drawing her aside, slipped some money into her hand whispering, "you are a discreet and faithful woman." While he was thus endeavoring to put a seal upon the woman's lips, Mrs. Bell rushed from the room. "What the deuce can this mean?" thought Captain Thurston to himself. Mrs. Bell called out for Sarah to come up  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7116-00000028"/> to her, and. she -spoke in a voice that was fill of a nervous trepidation. Sarah having obeyed her mistress's sum- moris, almost immediately came down stairs again, and entering the parlor, she closed the door. "Well, what is it?" demanded Horatio, is your mistress coming down again?" a" ro, sir," responded the servant; "she requests that you will take your departure at once." "Oh I that is the end of it." With these words he put on his hat, snatched up his gloves, and quitted the house. And he said to himself, "I will have nothing more to do with her." On the following day Mr. Thurston and family, with Mrs. Evans and Clara, were seated at the dinner table, when the servant entered, placing several letters and papers by the side of Mr. Thurston, which he put aside for perusal after dinner. The door now opened again, when Mr. Martin entered. "'Well, Mr. Martin, any news?" inquired Mr. Thurston. "Well, there is some  excitement down town."              A "What is it?" demanded   -Mr. Thurston somewhat impatiently. "Well, Mr. Bell turned his wife out of doors last night." Horatio let fiall his knife and fork, but no ,mo appeared to take any notice of it, unless it wore Aunt Jane. "Turned   out of doors," ejaculated Mr. Thurston, "' and what for?" "It is not as yet known," continued Mr. [Martin, " what induced Bell to have recourse to such an extreme measure." "But is there no suspicion afloat?" he in- quired, " as to the cause of this proceeding on Mr. Bell's part." "I have heard of nothing specific," was Mr. Martin's response. "No doubt some levity, or else the discovery of some fresh extravagance in respect to his wife has in- duced Mr. Bell to adopt such a course." Again did the door open, and the servant handed Mrh. Thurston a note, who upon ex- amining thoe address said, "This is for you, i Iforatio. It is from Covington; I should ( know this handwriting. It is :Mr. Foster's, e the attorney. What can he possibly want a with you?"               e "  I am sure I can't think what Mr. Foster t can want with me," observed Horatio care- 1 lessly and indifferently; indeed, he spoke the truth. " Hand over the letter and we'll 1 soothe   what it contains."  .    t "  Should you like me to read it for you?' t asked Aunt Jane as she received the docu- b ment from her brother in order to pass it to a her nephew. "  I am sure I don't mind," responded the captain with an air of disdainful indifference, e for he thought to himself that Aunt Jane v   s fancied it was concerning something he would like kept concealed, and as on this lead he experienced the most overweening s confidence, he thought he might obtain, at a d very cheap rate, a character for frankness and open heartedness in the estimation of , Clara. "Oh, yes, open it and read it aloud by all means," he exclaimed, "I have no 3 secrets, thank God, and so you are welcome a to see what it says." "Very good," said Aunt Jane dryly; then a without any more ado she opened the letter s and read its contents as follows:-       Ad'r T? T ilCOvINGTON, Ky., May 10th, 1863. Wmr. BELL, VS. CAPTAIN HORATIO THURST6N. SIR,--I am instructed by Mr. William Bell to commence legal proceedings against you, ; and enter an action for damages for the se- 3 duction of my client's wife, Cora Bell. I will therefore thank you to acquaint me with the name of your attorney, who will accept the usual process on your behalf. *Yours truly, J. FOSTER, Esq. CAPT. H. TIIURSTON." Not a  word was spoken by any of the listeners while Aunt Jane so calmly and de- liberately read this letter. Mr. Thurston seized the letter from Aunt Jane's hand, and cried out in a passion, "It's all through your cursed malignity." "He told me to read it," was her quiet re- sponse, and she went on eating as if nothing were the matter. And Horatio, availing himself of the con. I fusion slipped from the room, hurried forth [ to his room to reflect upon all that had taken place. When he arrived at his room he said, "Clara is lost to me." CHAPTER XIV. WE   must now return to Harry Todd, whom we left at Murfreesboro. We   should observe that as several weeks had now elapsed since Annie's arrival in Murfreesboro, she had obtained work to help to pay their expenses; and one evening as Annie was taking some work home she was overtaken by Captain Thurston. "Ah, Mrs. Todd!" he exclaimed, "it is a long time since you and I  met," and as he thus spoke he stopped short in the midst of the narrow pavement in such a  manner as to bar her way, without, however, having the appearance of rudeness in the eyes of the passers-by. Annie was for the moment alike bewilder- ed and indignant at the cool effrontery with which Captain Thurston addressed her, but   speedily recovering her presence of mind she said' in a reserved and dignified manner, "May I request, sir, that you will allow me to proceed?" "Oome, what nonsense is this," exclaimed Horatio, "surely you don't bear animosity?" Annie, with little .Harry clinging to her hand, endeavoredl to pass, and as the street was somewhat thronged by soldiers at the time, Captain Thurston dared not attempt to molest her. He accordingly stood aside and she continued her way. But he followed close behind, thinking that it was perhaps only because the boy was with her that she was thus guarded in her conduct. At all events he was determined to ascertain where she lived. Mrs. Todd in this state of mind continued her way; and presently little Harry, after looking round, said, ': Matrna, that gentle. man is following us." But before she had time to answer him the footsteps were again heard rapidly ap- proaching, and in a few minutes Mrs. Todd and little Harry were overtaken by the cap- tain. "One word, Annie-just one word," he said; then in a hurried whisper he added, "The boy won't tell; I will give him some- thing to buy a toy with." "Captain," answered Annie, "it is not manly of you thus to persecute an unpro- tected woman. Indeed, I  must appeal for assistance unless-- " "Where? and to whom?" demanded the captain; for he now saw in a moment that he had much underrated her virtue and her firmness. "'All is dark and silent here. I. t is a place where you might scream iri vain." "Captain," cried Annie, "how dare you address me thus in the presence of this child?" "Well," observed Horatio, fearful that an alarm  might be raised, ," I will not conde- scend to talk to you any further. But recol- lect, Mrs. Todd, that since you treat me in this manner, there is one that I can make smart for it." With these words he turned away, while Annie, dragging along the affrighted Harry, hastened on in the contrary direction. Capt. Thurston was continuing his way, wishing ill his heart that he could devise some scheme to get Annie into his power, when he felt his arm suddenly clutched by a man who emerged from the black shade of an archway close by. "Don't be afraid, Capt. Thurston. I have overheard all, and I can serve you." "Overheard what?" demanded Horatio. "Overheard all that took place betwixt you and Annie Todd," replied this individ- ual. '"I tell you that I can render you as- sistance in that quarter. "If you leave it to me to manage," continued the individual, who, it appeared, chose to be known by the   not very uncommon' name of Smith.  If you receive a letter at your qilarters, stating that on a particular day, at a certain hour, Mrs. Todd may be found at some house, the occupants of which are not over-particular as to what takes place beneath their roof--n "I understand you," interjected Thurston. I I know what you mean. But is it pos- sible?" "Leave it to me," exclaimed Smith. "If ;you receive such a letter, telling you that Annie Todd is there, I suppose you won't hesitate to fly to the appointment?" I "Not I!" exclaimed Thurston; ".and your reward shall be a liberal one., In the meantime, here are five dollars as an earnest of m'y good intentions." ' "I shall take the money," responded the man, "' because there will be fees to pay the people of the house before they will enter into the plot."       . ,\ Thus speaking, he extended his hand to receive the gold which Capt. Thurston had just taken from his purse, and again did the lalter-recoil with an irresistible sensation of loathing and horror; for the hand which the miserable being thus stretched forth was seamed and seared in as frightful a manner as his countenance.       , t "Now, then, I shall take my departure," said the captain; but as he issued fdrth from the room it was with a lingering mis- giving that some treachery might be yet in- tended. However, the human monster who called himself Smith appeared to have no such purpose in view, and Horatio Thurston passed out of the dilapidated building in perfect safety. He felt that he breathed far more freely when once again in the open air; and having threaded the alley, he emerged into the well-lighted and bustling street with a feeling of self-congratulation that he had passed unhurt through an .ad- venture of a most singular and suspicious character. It was about half past nine one evening. Little Harry lay in bed, locked in the slum- ber of innocence, when a gentle tap was heard at Annie's door, and she, thinking: it to be the landlady, bade the person enter. But instead of the woman of the house, it was an elderly female, decently dressed, and of somewhat matronly appearance. She had a red face, the rubicund color of which a close observer would have at once discerned to arise from' drinking, but Annie was too generous in the construction she had put upon outward appearances to form any such conclusion, while at the same time her mind was in too confused a state to allow her,to take particular notice of the personal char- acteristics, of her visitress. A single candle was burning upon the table, and by the light thereof the afflicted wife had been en- deavoring to make up for what' she consid- ered to be the neglect of her work during  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7116-00000029"/> the day. The woman who now made her appearance glanced quickly around, and perceiving that the boy was fast asleep in bed, an air of satisfaction at once took pos- session of her features; but even this Annie failed to observe. "I believe," said the female, "that I am speaking to Mrs. Todd, the daughter of Mr. Bell, who until recently was in the employ of Mr. Thurstonl?" "My poor father!" ejaculated Annie. "What- of him? Has he at length consent- on to forgive his daughter? Does he now need the solace and comfort which I may be enabled to bestow upon him?" "He needs more," responded the woman. "He requires your presence by the side of that sick bed on which care and .trouble -have stretched him." "Oh I he shall not ask in vain," cried the warm-hearted Mrs. Todd. "mWhere is he? Tell me, my good woman-keep me not in suspense;" for she experienced a fond and anxious yearning towards that father whom she had not seen for some years, and all the past, so far as his cruelty towards her had been concerned, was obliterated in a moment. "He is here--in this town," answered the woman.   "He came here to see you, that you might forgive him everything." "Oh I speak not to me thus," interrupted Annie vehemently.  "It is not for a child to forgive a  parent  Where is he? where is he?" "He took lodgings at my house," returned the 'woman, "not being able to find you out immediately. He was ill when he came he has grown worse. ' At length I have discov- s ered your abode, and I have come to conduct i you to him."  "I will go immediately," rejoined Annie, ; full of anxiety and suspense, and totally un- suspicious of any treacherous aim on the 1 part of this woman, whose speech and man- ner were more than friendly-they were a motherly. To put on her bonnet and shawl was but \ the work of a  moment, and this being done, C Annie followed the female from the room. a Stopping on the ground floor to request the i landlady to go up and sit in the chamber c dur'g   her temporary absence, Annie accom- X panied the guide out of the 'house; and as f they hurried along through the streets, tho feeling that still continued uppermost in the tc mind of our heroine was totally apart from misgiving and suspicion-it was the absorb- a ing one of anxiety and suspense -in respect id to her father. Here we may turn to Harry Todd, who to occupied the same room with his comrades. a and who were now all assembled there, and about to get ready for retiring to rest. Pre- of sently there was a  knock at the door and n the individual who answered it said that ir some one wanted to speak to Todd. Harry, do   3r who was just beginning to undress, hastened d out upon the landing to inquire whiat*he n wanted.  s "There's a person just been here and told e me to give you this note;" and as the lad thus explained himself, he thrust a soiled a and dirty letter into Harry's hand. Our r hero tore it open, and read the following lines:-   ' "There's a conspiracy going on against your wife. She is being enticed away to a r certain place, where her ruin will be accom- O plished. It's of no use for you to run off to your lodging, because the people of the  house don't know where she is gone. But rif you choose to come out and join me, I owill take yon to the place. I shall be about fifty yards outside of the camp. You can 3 manage to slip out. A  FRIEND." This note was written in a rude, scrawling manner, but in a hand totally unknown to our hero.  He was instantaneously smitten with dismay, but reckless of all consequen- ces, he speedily resolved upon complying with the terms .of the letter. Dismissing the boy, without thinking of putting to him a single question as to the individual who had sent the letter. Todd rushed back into his tent and caught up his cap.  Two or three of his comrades, perceiving his wild appearance, asked him what was the matter, and one of them considerately reminded him that he had better be cautious what he did. But Harry heeded not the words that were spoken; .there was hurry in his brain, frenzy in his thoughts, burning fire in his heart; and the image of Horatio Thurston was up- permost in his mind as the perpetrator of the atrocity that he was now so mysterious- ly called upon to prevent. He rushed out of the camp; he paid no attention to the question which the sentry put to him; but he rushed onward, only slackening his pace when hhe had cleared the camp. At a  short distance therefrom it was nearly dark, but amidst the gloom Harry perceived a  man loitering about, and imme- diately felt convinced that this was the indi- vidual who was waiting for him. He there- fore accosted hin, demanding hurriedly. "Are you the person who sent me the let- ter? My name is Todd." "  Come with me," answered the stranger, and moving on in front, he led the way rap- idly through the streets. But quickly as the man went, his speed appeared a snail's pace to Todd, who would have flown had he been aware of the proper direction to pursue. He had not caught the slightest glimpse of his guide's countenance; for the place was not only dark where they had met, but the individual's features were thrown into a still deeper shade, by a  wide-brimmed slouching   hat that he wore. Nor did he particularly notice the man's walk as he led the' way, for their course was pursued through streets of a poor description, where there were few lights, and those scartely serving to dispel the gloom that pervaded those thoroughfares. All that Todd now remarked was' that the man seemed to be clad in a coarse, poverty- stricken style; and the only circumstance which he had observed at, first was that he had appeared to speak in a feigned voice. This, however, was a matter of no conse- quence, and one which stayed not a moment --in the soldier's thoughts; for how did it sig- nify to him who the individual was, or what his motive could be, since - it appeared evi- dent it was a friendly part he was playing? Nor indeed had Harrj sufficient command over his feelings for deliberate reflection at all. He followed his guide in a state of frenzy, mingled with a burning, boiling rage against the author of the vile proceeding, whoever he might be. But that this was Capt. Thurston he had very little doubt. The man led on, Todd following close at his heels. They passed through 'several alleys and lanes which our hero had never threaded before, until at length the guide turned into one which was almost complete- ly dark, and seemed to be a court having no egress at the other extremity.  Suddenly the man stopped near the door of a house, the lower shutters of which were closed, but through the loopholes, as well, as from the window above, lights were flickering feebly forth-the only ones that rescued the place from utter gloom. "One word, Mr. Todd," said the stranger, placing his back towards those beamls of light in such a manner as to keep his coun- tenance still as much as possible in the shade. "I need hardly tell you that you will have to act with boldness and prompti- tude. You will knock at that door. In reply to your question, if you stop to put any, the woman of the house is certain to tell you that no person answering the de- scription of your wife is within her walls. Don't believe it. Rush straight up stairs. You see that light in the room on the first floor; you will be able to judge where it is situated. Burst in there; kick down the doqr if you find -it locked; and it may be thath .won't have come too late." Having thus spoken in a low, whispering voice, but which was still evidently dis- guised, the man turned away. In so doing his countenance caught the rays streaming through the holes in the- ground floor shut- ters. Todd, though fearfully excited, and about to rush at the door of that den of in- famy, was for an instant stricken with horror end dismay; for it assuredly was the coun- tenance of a monster, and not of a human being, -of which he had just caught a glimpse. Never was there such a spectacle of loath-   some horrhr. But we need not describe the face again; it has already been depicted to odlr 'eaders. 'The man hurried away,.and the next in- stant Todd, forgetting all about him, having now only one idea predominant over his actions, rushed up to -the front door, at which he knocked violently. Doubtless the woman of the house thought it was one of her usual patrons, and-she hastened to ari swer the summons. As the door thus opened Harry. perceived by a light burning in the passage, that the female was an elderly one 'of respectable appearance, though with a very red face. She looked both astonished and frightened on perceiving that it was a private soldier, and doubtless, judging by the wild rage of his looks, she instantaneously suspected who he was. Speedily, however, assuming an angry air. she exclaimed, "And pray who are you, coming to a respectable house in this unceremonious manner?" Todd rushed past her, and as he reached the landing he tried the handle of the door of that apartment whch had been pointed out to him. He found that the door was locked, he burst it open, and with a wild cry of joy his wife sprang into his arms. A   glance showed Todd that Horatio ThUirston was likewise in that chamber, and tearing himself away from Annie, Harry sprang towards him like an infuriated tiger. Horatio drew his sword from its sheath, cry- ing out, "Keep off, or I will kill you."i, But -larry, snatching away the weapon from him with as =much ease as if it were a conflict between a giant and a dwarf, thrust it through him, and left him stretched upon the floor. "Come, Annie, come," he said, not paus- ing to ascertain whether he had killed the young officer or not; and he hurried his wildly excited wife to her home, and then hastened back to the camp. On reaching the camp he made straight for the colonel's quarters, and on inquiring if, that officer was within, he received a re- ply in the affirmative, and at the same time an invitation to come in. "Well, Harry, what is it?" demanded the colonel. "Sir," was the response, "I seek justice at your hands." -Harry then 'proceeded and told the colonel all that had happened. The colonel replied,' "I will have to put you under arrest, -and forward the papers to the general commanding, who will order a court to be convened for your trial." On the following day charges and specifi- cations were preferred against private Harry Todd, for the killing of Captain 1oratio Thurston. In a few days, by orders from the general, a court was convened for trial, and Harry Todd was of course found guilty, and was accordingly sentenced to be shot.  &#xD;<pb n="54 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7116-00000030"/> He offered no further resistance, and was at once conducted as a prisoner to the jail where he was placed in close confinement. CHAPTER XV. IT was about a week after Harry's trial, Annie was allowed to visit him; he was meditating over his punishment when he heard the key turn in the lock, the huge bolts were drawn back, when Annie and the boy entered the -cell. The door was closed behind them again, the key turned and the bolts were drawn once more. Then ensued a scene which defies all the power of lan- guage to depict-a scene in which a con- science stricken husband, an anguished wife, and a wildly sobbing child were the three actors. For the poor boy knew that some- thng terrible was to happen to his father, although  he had not been suffered to learn the whole tremendous truth. Harry strained his poor wife to hiis breast, then he embraced his son, all amidst convulsions of grief, and theu he turned aside to pour forth the agony of his heart in floods of tears and piteous lamentations. Annie fell upon her knees, took his hand and pressed it to her lips, sob- bing and weeping convulsively, and feeling as if he heart would break. Harry assured her that when left to the solitude of that dungeon cell, he modeled his thoughts as much as he was enabled, towards making his peace with heaven; and when the awful moment came he. should meet his doom with the firmaess of a man. Poor Annie laid her head dpon his shoulder, and Harry clasped her in one arm and his boy in the other. He was smitten with appalling despair as he asked himself what was to be- come  of them?"Oh I my God," he ex- claimed wildly, "what will become of you both, what will become of you?" "Hush, dearest Harry," said the poor wife, straining him still closer to her har- rowed and tortured bosom, "give not way to these dreadful thoughts. Oh1! what can I do to impart consolation to your soul? Tell me, dear Harry, what can I do? what can I say?" But the unhappy Todd was now unable to give any response; he was once more convulsed with anguish. He beheld the careworn, haggard countenance and wasted form of that wife who was once so beautiful in the vigor of health and in the cheerfulness of hw disposition; he beheld, too, the pale face of the once blooming boy. The scene transcended all power of de- scription. There is no language competent to convey an idea of the anguish and mental agony endured within those walls. Oh I for   t whatsoever offence Todd might have comrn i mitted, society and the world were already fearfully avenged. An hour passed, and at the expiration of that interval the door was opened angin, and the soldier who appeared upon the threshold was himself well, nigh overcome with grief on beholding the piteous leave-taking that now ensued. Yes I piteous indeed was it, and yet these were not the last farewells that were spoken. At length the almost 1 heart-broken Annie and the weeping boy issued forth from the cell, and Todd flung himself in despair upon his pallet to pass away the night. On the following day, Tuesday, there was a repetition of the distressing scene which we have endeavored to describe, and daily did she continue her visits till the following :Friday, when Harry Todd was informed that the proceedings of the court martial had been approved of by the general command- ing, and that the sentence would be carried into effect on the 19th of June, 1863, which would be just two weeks from that day. Annie entered  the cell, the door was closed behind her, and the next instant they were clasped in each other's arms. Harry summoned all his fortitude to his aid to whisper something in his wife's ear. "This day two weeks, my own dear An- nie," he said in a voice which, despite all his efforts, was broken and tremulous with the emotions that were rending his heart, " will be the last day for us to meet in this world." Todd stopped short, for he felt his. poor wife's arms tightening convulsively round his neck, and he felt, too, that a strong spas- modic shuddering passed through her entire frame. Ohi how ineffable was her anguish, as her heart was smitten with the fearful import of her husband's words. "For heaven's sake command  yourself, my own dear wife," murmured the miserable man, "for we must exert all our fortitude for the next two weeks, then will be, our last interview, and you and I must be alone to- gether. Then I shall bid farewell, an eternal farewell, to-to--" But he could not finish the broken, mur- mured, whispered sentence as he glanced toward the pale, though beautiful, counte- nance of little Harry, who, with the tears bedewing his cheeks, was gazing up- at him in so sad a  manner that the father's heart was riven with anguish.   But when the moment came for this day's meeting to end, and when that father, on straining the boy to his breast, felt that it was for the last time. Oh I it was crucifixioq, it was impale- ment, it was the agony of agonies that he endured. It seemed as, if life itself were being torn away from him amidst excruciat- ing tortures; it was as if parting from the very cords that held his soul as yet bound to existence. And the child, instinctively  &#xD;<pb n="-55" xml:id="VAC7116-00000031"/> comprehending what it meant,.asked in so. piteous a tone "if he should never see his dear papa-aga nt?" that both Todd and Annie- felt as if they were on the verge of shrieking forth as maniacs, or of dashing their heads against the wall in despair. Indeed for a short space did frenzy so seize upon the brain. of the condemned soldier, that he held both his wife and child to his breast, declaring: that he would not part from them, and they also clung with an equal tenacity to him. But at length Annie withdrew from his arms, and Harry, seized with the sudden numbness of a stupor, fell heavily upon the floor. When he came back to consciousness it all appeared to him a hideous dream, but the conviction of its realty soon fastened upon him again, and then what anguish did he endure; what bitter lamentations came forth from his lips. At length, being overcome, they sat down to meditate upon his doom, when Annie, starting suddenly, said, "Harry, I have thought of a plan by which you may be saved from so dreadful a fate. I will go to-morrow and see the President, and on my knees will I implore him to pardon you; I will tell him all, and when he sees the plot that was laid to accomplish your ruin, I think he will at once grant me my request." A new ray of light now gleamed over Harry. "Dearest Annie," he said, "if you think there is any prospect of it you might go; he may, perhaps, do it for your sake. You have two weeks yet, and if you start in the morning you can be back in ten days." It'was indeed a relief and a solace to the unhappy man to receive such intelligence; but in the most earnest manner did he again and again conjure his wife to make as brief a journey as possible, as he could not think of meeting his doom without seeing her again if she should fail in obtaining his par-, don. At length the moment of separation came. How can'we describe'it? We cannot. We. are lost in the presence of the immensity of that anguish, the illimitable extent of that despairing sorrow. Words are ineffectual; the mightiest power of language sinks into- insignificance when viewed in. comparison with -the fearful eloquence of woe expressed in the looks, the tears, the parting words, and the passionate kisses which 'took place then. Again and again did Annie,. after tearing herself away, rush back .into her husband's arms; again and again did they press each other in an embrace which might be the last. But at length they both felt that it was cruelty to one another to prolong the scene. They separated, and the closinig door 'suddenly became, as it were, an' ada- mantine wall -between the wildly distracted wife and the despair-stricken husbanid. Annib ,went immnediately about making preparations,for the journey, and on the fol-   lowing morning she took her: passage on the. cars for Washington City. I Harry threw himself .down on his little pallet and gave way to his reflections.. On the one hand he was borne up with the hope that the President might be moved from sympathy with his distressed wife, to grant him a reprieve; but again, should she be delayed in reaching Washington, or should she; not succeed in getting an interview with the, President till the time would .expire, he would be executed without seeing his be- loved Annie.. In such anxiety .and rovings, of the imagination did Harry indulge, till-on . the fifth day after Annie's departure, he re. ceived the following letter:- "WASnrNGTON CITY, June 15, 186,-  MY DEAR HARRY. I arrived here only last night, and I have . taken the first opportunity of letting youn know that I got here without any mischance. For some reasons which I cannot explain. the trains were detained at different times, which caused my delay in coming here and, writing to you. I am informed that I can not see the President for a day or two, but I  have the greatest encouragement from the people of the place, who affectionately sym+, pathize with. me, and unite in saying there is no doubt that he will grant your pardon. Therefore, while I beseech heaven to forgive our enemies, I sincerely trust that Omnipo- tent Providence will deliver you from the wretched punishment to which they had determined to bring you. ANNoI TODD." The --time passed, and Harry, burdened with. anxiety, paced, back and forth in his little cell, hoping every moment to see his belbved. Annie, or to hear at least what suc- : cessshe had made in his behalf; but nothing. more was heard from her, and the day ar- rived for his execution. At about eight o'clock on the morning of "this day,. Friday, .the commanding officer proceeded to .Harry's cell and informed him that .at twelve" o'clock on that day he would be executed in the presence of the division. Harry replied. that he wished to see his wife, who had gone to Washington City, and ex- pected to obtain a reprieve for him, and en. treated the officer, in the most lamentable manner to have the sentence postponed till the next day if she did:not arrive.  The officer' merely answered that no one but the President could extend it, and as yet:there was no such order received. When Harry heard this he fell to the floor, , and lay for. some time! unconscious of what , was going on. At length, when be came to ,; himselgf it appeared to him like a dreamt but besoon realized what had taken -plae,-.  !h n he exclaimed, "My God, that I should I Veribhave lostsight-of -them-that I should,  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7116-00000032"/> have let Annie got Oh! if I had Annie and little Harry here in these last moments- oh, how happy I could die!" he exclaimed; and the unfortunate man's courage breaking down, in an instant he was convulsed with anguish.               % When poor Harry had recovered, the offi- cer was there to announce to him that the time had arrived. It was now ten o'clock, and the troops were marching out to the place of execution, which was about a mile from the town, each brigade and each regiment taking their places. The division formed in a square, leaving one side open. Immediately after the troops had taken their places, the firing party commenced marching to the centre to a piece of ground that was higher than the rest of the field, where they took their posi- tion to await the arrival of the unfortunate Todd. It was not long till an ambulance was seen coming, and an escort with it, which drove up into the square that was already formed. On arriving at the place, Harry Todd alighted from the ambulance. His coffin was taken out and carried round to the front of the firing party. Harry was dressed in his uniform. His countenance was as pale as the death he was about to meet; but he walked with his head erect, and with a  firm step. The moment he appeared upon the ground his eyes swept over the scene that met them, which appeared awful and imposing.  He knew that it was his privilege-the last he i could claim on  earth-to address a few 1 words to his fellow-soldiers, and he prepared 1 to avail himself of it. All was still and I silent; but yet there was a terrible amount t , of keenly active and acutely felt sympathy E expressed on the countenances along whose t pale array Todd's eyes slowly traveled. At a length that solemn pause-that dread silence t -was broken.              g "Friends and comrades," said the doomed c man, speaking in a firm voice, "you see be- d fore you one whose eyes in a few brief min- n utes will be closed in death-whosa heart a will have ceased to beat-whose form will be reduced to a  mere lump of clay. I am rc about to appear in the presence of a higher el tribunal than that whose sentence has placed hi ime here to die; and if I tremble at the tc thought of so soon standing before that gl sublime judgment-seat, it is not on account hi of that deed for which the earthly one of al the other day has condemned me. No; it is pl because I  feel that whatever faults I may V have committed have been offences against ar those who provoked them not-who merited ul them not. I allude to the best of wives-to the dearest of children."       th Here his voice faltered for a few moments, ey and the tears dimmed his eyes. Tears, too, de were trickling down the pale cheeksofthose in G0   lie the serried ranks; and the sob which rose up -  into the throat of many a soldier there found ; a similarly half-stifled echo in that of a com- ig rade standing next. But Todd, hastily dash- th ing away his own tears, drew himself sud- denly up, as if to show that, having resolved a- to be firm, he would be; and then his speech ie was continued thus:- "And yet I scarcely tremble at' the s thought of appearing before tha celestial a, judgment seat; for the Almigt  no sit- h teth there can attest that the/on rs of ir my life have been those to which  now ?, alluded, and which redound upon my wife )r and child. That angel-wife of mine has for- g given me in her own name and in that of o our son. Yes, by them I am forgiven, and e my Maker will not show me less mercy than i- I have experienced at their hands. I stand e not here to admit the justice of my sentence: I proclaim it to be unjust I About to appear s in the presence of One at whose footstool no h falsehood may be told, I speak to you now y as if I were already kneeling there-I speak 7 to you now as if I were in the presence of s my God. Did I choose to open the flood. ) gates of animosities and upbraiding, I might pour forth a torrent that would overwhelm 3 the many, many enemies I have had to en- ) counter since the fatal day I became a sol- 3 dier. But if a sense of bitter, bitter wrong will not permit me, even in this supreme 3moment, to say that I forgive those enemies -if human nature asserts its empire even until the last instant, when it is about to dissolve away--yet do I earnestly and eL- treatingly implore heaven to touch their hearts, and lead them, when I am gone, to be more merciful, more forbearing, more Chris- tian-like towards others who shall remain subject to their authority. Imagine not, therefore, my heart will fail me, now that in a few short minutes I shall meet Death face to face. If I only had those here who are so dear to me, to bid them a last farewell, I could die a happy man. I know that Provi- dence will protect them, and will also award my enemies for the wrongs I have to suffer at their hands." Todd ceased. The doomed man, turning round, walked slowly; but with his head erect and firm footsteps did he proceed to his coffin, where he halted. He proceeded to take off his coat, threw it upon the ground, and then sank upon his knees, his hands clasped in silent prayer; and when he arose, the chaplain united with him :in im- ploring the mercy of Heaven in his behalf. When the chaplain concluded they arose, and Harry walked to his coffin and sat down upon it.   + The officer now read the sentence, and then proceeded to fasten a bandage over his eyes. The firing party got orders to shoul- der arms and make ready to fire, when the Geaerals attention was called to a  person   on horseback, galloping at full speed, and hallooing at the same time, "Don't fire " All was silence till the individual rode up to the General and handed him a letter. On opening it he found it to be a dispatch from the President, which read as follows:- WASHNGTON CITY, June th, 1863. TO THS GENERAL COMMANDING AT MUR- FREESBORO, SIR,-This will inform you that I have pardoned Private Harry Todd, who was sentenced to be shot to-day at twelve o'clock, in your command, and that he is to be re- stored to duty. You will cause the same to be read in the presence of your command. By order of A. LINCOLN, President of the United States. The bandage was removed from Harry Todd's eyes, and the above order was read. When Harry heard it he fell on his knees, expressing in the most solemn manner his gratitude to Heaven for the deliverance of himself and family. Harry then returned to the camp, to await the arrival of his wife and boy. Annie did not get an interview with the President till ten o'clock on the last day, when she laid all before him, and the Presi- dent at once sent off the dispatch to which we have alluded. Annie lost no time in getting started to join her husband again.- She took the even- ing train, and as they met with no misad- venture and lost no time by the way, they arrived in Murfreesboro on the 23d. Here Harry, by permission, had. come to meet her. When the train arrived, Harry and Annie, on beholding each other, at the same instant burst into a flood of tears; the next moment they were clasped in each  other's arms, they gazed upon each other long and ten- derly. At length, with each other's hands retained in a  firm clasp, they bent their steps to their lodging. A. few days after Annie returned, the army i got orders to advance on Tullahoma. Harry ] proceeded with his regiment, and passed p safely through that skirmish. And in two' a months and a  few days Harry Todd went I into the battle of Chickamauga, Tennessee, V where he fought like a  hero until he was t killed. Thus ended the career of this unfortunate t man.                  t In a  few days Annie received the sorrow- 1 ful news that Harry was dead; and as the ground remained in the possession of the rebels, this was the last intelligence she re- v ceived from him.            b In a  few days Annie and little Harry left v Murfreesboro and went to Cincinnati.  f   CONCLUSION. THE reader will not be satisfied unless we furnish himwith a few particulars respecting the most prominent characters that, having figured in our narrative, yet remain to be disposed of. And first of all, Annie's father. We have already stated that this man became a confirnhed drunkard. The habit of intem- perance grew upon him with an inveteracy that at length it might be literally said he was never sober. He took no note of what was passing in the world around him, but abandoned himself completely to strong liquor. It was not till nearly a month after his son-in-law's death that the circumstance accidentally reached his ears; for the woman who lived with him as his house e Keeltu- diously concealed the occurrence as long as she was able, for fear lest,his heart should be touched with remorse and melt towards his daughter, in which case her influence over the wretched man might be destroyed. For the same object did she intercept and suppress a touching and affectionate letter which Annie wrote to her father about a week after the battle that deprived her of a husband and her son of- a father. This woman, having first obtained an im- mense influence over him, ultimately en- deavored to induce him to make a will in her favor, and this he agreed to do. But the woman fancied that he might yet live some years, during which a reconciliation with his daughter and a reversal of the will were things quite within the chapter of accidents; so she thought of persuading him to sell out his property and keep it all in money at home. For this she urged various reasons, which were of course unfounded enough, -but quite sufficient to operate as she desired on the attenuated mind of the wretched sot. He accordingly did as she suggested. - But not many days after the whole amount was paid over to the miserable drunkard this wretched woman   endeavored to decamp with it. By a combination of circumstances which we need not pause to describe, she was detected and stopped by some of the neighbors who had found out what was going on. When in prison she manifested an exceeding bitterness against Bell, who had been persuaded to prosecute her, and who even kept himself moderately sober for that purpose. This miserable woman was convicted of the attempt at robbery, and was sentenced to a term of imprisonment, where we now leave her. Annie and her boy still found a home in Cincinnati, and kind friends in those who were so generously interested in their be- half. The death of Mr. Bell shortly after- wards put Annie in possession of all his fortune,. which. amounted to- a little over o  &#xD;<pb n="58" xml:id="VAC7116-00000033"/> eight thousand dollars in ready money. She accordingly took up her abode there to devote herself to the education of her son. We have already stated that legal pro- ceedings were instituted against Captain Horatio Thurston for the seduction of Cora Bell, but as Thurston was killed by Harry   Todd before the time came for the trial, and there being sufficient evidence against her, the Court granted Mr. Bell a divorce, and in consequence she never obtained any of Mr. Bell's property; she was thrown out of doors and is now living with her people in New York.   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>