<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7635">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Twisted Threads </title>
            <author >Nauman, Mary D. (1839-1920)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7635</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Twisted threads</title>
                  <author >Nauman, Mary D. (1839-1920)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >xii 202 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Claxton Remsen &amp; Haffelfinger</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1870">1870</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-02-16">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Twisted threads</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="0-iii (Cover) " xml:id="VAC7635-00000001"/>   TWISTED THREADS.  &#xD;<pb n="iv-v (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7635-00000002"/> TWISTED THREADS. BY M. D. NAUMAN, AUTHOR OF "SIDNEY ELLIOTT." No grand "purpose" in it; no dramatic effects - scarcely even a "story;" but a few pages out of the book of daily life, the outside of which often looks so common and plain; and the inside--but One only reads that. -Miss MULOCH. PHLADELPHA: CLAXTON, REMSEN &amp; HAFFELFINGER, 819 AND 821 MARKET STREET. 1870.  &#xD;<pb n="vi-vii" xml:id="VAC7635-00000003"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1869, by CLAXTON, REMSEN &amp; HAFFELFINGER, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Eastern District of Pennsylvania. J. FAOAN &amp; SON, STEREOTYERS.         MOORE BROS., PRINTERS.   TO A. M. D. AND E. L. M., THS BOOK, AS A SLIGHT TOKEN OF REGARD, IS i  &#xD;<pb n="viii-ix" xml:id="VAC7635-00000004"/>  PREFACE. WHEN, one year ago, I wrote the concluding lines of "Sidney Elliott," and anxiously submitted it to the verdict of those with whom it rested to decide if the book would ever be given to the public, I little thought I would ever write again. But the fascination which that mighty sorcerer of modern days THE PEN- exercises over its votaries, has been too strong for me; and in obedience to that fascination the following pages have been written. For the praise and blame which my first book received, I am equally grateful: for the praise, because it has given me encouragement to go on in the occupation I have chosen; for the blame, because I hope it has enabled me to correct some of the faults which, in "Sidney Elliott," merited censure.  That the following pages are faultless, I am very far from imagining; yet, such as they are, I leave them with regret. If we,leave a mere acquaintance unwillingly, is it to be wondered at if it is hard to bid adieu to charac- ters-even though they are fictitious ones who have ix  &#xD;<pb n="x-xi (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7635-00000005"/> X         PREFA CE. been our companions for months, as the persons pictured in this little story have been to me--more like real- ities than the creations of my own imagination! It will not, I trust, be considered out of place, if I express a hope that this book may be found an improve- ment upon its predecessor, and that it may please its readers. M. D. N.  t i    CONTENTS. CHAPTER I. - '        PAGE INTRODUCTORY Q . . CHtAPTER II. - BERTIIA      .          I8 BERT, A . . . . .  . . .  .H8 CHAPTER III. SoUS LES TOITS . . . .   . .    23 CHAPTER IV. EVENING THOUGHrTS . .  .  . . .  CHAPTER V. BREAKING THE ICE           .  37 CHAPTER VI. MOODS ..    .             45 ... *  '  '  *  *  *  *45 CHAPTER VII. YULE-TIME . .  . .           5 *  .  .  . 51 CHAPTER VIII. FAONS DE PARLER ' . . . .  . . . 6 CHAPTER IX. Miss LETTY . . . . . .  .7 CHAPTER X. ENIGMATICAL .  ..           82 i      , xi  &#xD;<pb n="xii (Table of Contents) -13" xml:id="VAC7635-00000006"/> x-ii        CONTENTS. CHAPTER XI. PAGB OFFERS OF SERVICE               . 96 CHAPTER XII. WHAT A RIDE COST  .  .    . .  .     4 CHAPTER XIII. IN BERTHA'S. PARLOR              . I 5 CHAPTER XIV. WHAT DID IT MEAN? .. 126 CHAPTER XV. A MAN'S WILL  .  .  .35 CHAPTER XVI. IN FAIRY-LAND .  .  .  .  . .  .     44 CHAPTER XVII. FOR FRIENDSHP'S SAKE         .  .  .53 CHAPTER XVIII. AUNT ;JANET'S HOME . .  .  .  . .     68 CHAPTER XIX. IN CALM WATERS .  ..              76 CHAPTER XX. OVER THE FIRE .  .  .  .  .  . .  .   87 CHAPTER XXL THE BEST CHRISTMAS-GIFT .   .  . .     195 CHAPTER XXII. THE LAST NIGHT OF THE YEAR .          201   TWISTED THREADS. CHAPTER I. INTRODUCTORY. I WONDER what it was that induced my parents to give me such a name as mine. Maud Elinor Lennox. There it is, written out in full. I am very fond of writing my name, the only thing about me that is not matter-of-fact and plodding--a poor teacher cannot be otherwise; so I may as well make the most of my pretty name, which would suit the heroine of a novel far better than it does the very insignificant little person who bears it. I know I am insignificant. When I sign the receipt for my quarterly salary, I never write my name as some girls would. I make the signature as curt as possi- ble--- M. E. Lennox. Perhaps Madame Levere thinks my name is Mary, or, perhaps, Margaret- something that will do for common use and com-, mon people. I don't believe she thinks of me at all. Why should she?  2                X3  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7635-00000007"/> "    TWISTEPD THREADS. Well, after all, what am I, that I should be thought about? If I am to sit here scribbling, diary-fashion, I may as well begin by a description of myself; and for that purpose I must lay aside my pen, and go to the looking-glass. It is a sad vanity-trap -'most as good as having one's photograph taken -when the wicked sunlight brings into full view every spot, every defect, and enhances irregularity of feature; so that a face which depends upon coloring and expression, and, having those, is pleasant to look upon, comes out in the carte or vignette almost ugly. I wonder if any one ever will care to have my pho- tograph! It would be an ugly one, if it were taken. That peep into the mirror--does that little square of looking-glass deserve such a name?-was taken critically. What has been the result? My nose would be decidedly comical. I'll be polite to it, and call it retrousse; that sounds better- than pug. Pug! just like a King Charles spaniel! I should not wonder if I looked like one, after all, with those great black eyes of mine, and this trou- blesome hair, which will curl whether or no, brush and braid it as I may. I hate a grown-up woman with a curly head; it's not dignified, either, for a teacher. Then I don't think my mouth would look like "Cupid's bow." It's what I call - large. I don't like to look at it, though they do say a large mouth is a sign of intellect: it's poor consolation for those who, like me, have the one without -the other.' I'm proud of my teeth, though; and if I am slight and   TWrISTED THREADS.        1 small cf stature, I have the comfort of knowing that hand and foot are both small, and look well in a nice shoe and glove. Bien gantee, bien chaussee ; that's one of my weaknesses. I imagine there must be some French blood in my composition some- wheres- there were French Huguenots in this coun- try years ago: who knows? I know I 'm not pretty; but I guess I can survive it. What a night it is! rain, rain, rain. Ain't I glad it kept off till I got home! I do hate to get my feet wet. Till I got home! Is this space, fourteen by twelve, what I call home? Well, it might be worse; and I really am getting attached to my little sky- parlor, though it is a journey up stairs to get to it. If the carpet is faded, the blessed sunshine and the sweet pure air come to me over the' house-tops. Here and there I see a tree-top--a peep at Nature through the brick walls all around; and the busy little sparrows come and sit on my window for crumbs. I al-ways bring a piece of bread from table for them in my pocket. I can sit at this little table, which just holds my desk, and look at them -the prettiest things, in their brown-striped coats, spotted vests, and black-velvet cravats, about here: except one thing-I brought it from home-a head of the Saviour, cr.6owned with thorns: only a picture; yet it seems, with the holy, serene face, to sanctify my little nest under the'eaves; It hangs over the mantel; it is the first thing my waking eyes behold; it used to hang in my father's study;  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7635-00000008"/> I6     TWISTED THREADS. I know it was the text of many a sermon; and now I have it! Piled just under it are his Bible, my mo- ther's Prayer Book, ,and a little, old, and worn Thomas a Kempis-the only devotional books I ever use. I need none others: these three are a whole library in themselves. It used to be different once, when my father was pastor at Lynn, and he, my mother, and I lived in the pretty parsonage there. I don't like to think of those days, when we were all so happy in our pleas- ant home; nor of the time my mother died; nor when my father "fell asleep," and I was left alone, with no relatives--only myself to depend upon. There was an insurance for a thousand dollars on my father's life, and the books and furniture. When they were sold, I had a few hundred dollars more; and that was all. Not enough to keep me: I had to do something. What should it be? I could not write, that was very certain. No publisher would buy any effusion of mine; and even if one had been brave enough to try me, nobody would have read my scribblings. I did not even try. I was a good French scholar, and I determined to trust to that for my daily bread. I could not stay in Lynn to see another in my father's place, to hear another read the familiar ser- vices in the dear old church, to know another set of people were living in our home, where I had no right to be now. - I could not bear it; so I came to New York. That was two years ago, and I have been here   TWISTED THREADS.       I7 ever since; I was very fortunate, I suppose. Ma- dame Levere wanted an assistant French teacher, and she gave me the place and five hundred dollars a-year-very good pay. I have been boarding all this time at Mrs. Wil- son's. A good-hearted woman she is, too--kind to me. I won her heart by sitting up with her little girls when they had scarlet fever, and giving them the run of my room when the mother was busy. I wonder she ever gets through. The house is full- a little world in itself. I keep aloof from the board- ers: the women are too gay and dressy for me- a sober gray moth with a long name, like the high- sounding words with which botanists and entomol- ogists designate tiny plants and insects: the men- vapid, silly clerks, worse than the women in their dressiness; for one, can pardon folly in a woman, while we look for something in a man worthy his manhood. Heigho! is it raining still? 'I verily believe it is. Patter away, raindrops, all through the night, if you please; but remember my long walk to Dame Levere's to-morrow. I believe I'm tired- of scrib- bling. Maud Lennox, wipe your pen, and go to bed. 2' /  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7635-00000009"/> CHAPTER II. BERTHA. MRS. WILSON told me, this morning, she had two new boarders. From what she says, I imagine they must be somewhat different from the others. A  lady and gentleman. I shall take a good look at them when I go to dinner to-day. Well, I have seen the newcomers. She is tall, stately, and handsome-a blonde;--I do admire blondes--perhaps because I am so dark myself;- with such lovely hair, and a perfect figure. Bertha Steiner-it's a pretty name. He is a doctor- come here to be Professor in the Medical College: - a man, Mrs. Wilson tells me, of high repute in oi;s profession -the author of several books. I took a good look at him.  I see so few notabilities, that I felt some curiosity on the subject. I liked his appearance: a firmly knit, well-developed' figure, broad-shouldered and robusthis clothes sitting well on him, almost like a part of himself;, a high fore- head; short, wavy, chestnut- hair: deep, serious, gray eyes; a firm mouth, half hidden by the heavy brown moustache; about thirty-five. There were a few gray hairs on the temples, a few lines on the brow. I think Dr. Forsythe a handsome man. Miss Stei- 18   T WISTED THREADS.      19 ner seems to think so too. She looks at him with undisguised admiration. They would make a splen- did-looking couple. I would not like to be a doctor's wife. I should live in fear of-his trying experiments upon me. What nonsense!  I never expect to be anybody's wife. It seems to me that would be something as com- pletely beyond my reach as is the round, full moon babies sometimes cry for, and which by no manner of means can be given to them. Yet no girl, no woman, rich or poor, young or old, plain or fair, but looks forward to having some time, sooner or later, a home of her own, with some one to love her, and for her to love. That would be the pleas- ant part of it for me: to know there was somebody who would think me, as children say, "just right" --who would bear with my failings, and forgive my faults, with the same consideration I should have for his; for I don't believe that "Love is blind." I interpret that in this way: that we are more chari- table and more willing to make allowance for the faults of those we love than for the same defects in those to whom we are indifferent--more charitable, because I think that charity and love are synony- mous. For I think that true love-the real Eros, to use reverently the words of Paul, who, by the way, in his teachings pleases me more than the stern Peter- "Beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7635-00000010"/> 20     TWISTED THREADS. "'Envieth not; never faileth. "Suffereth long, and is kind." Is not this true love, as well as charity? I do not know how it would be in practice -this is only theory. ' And it seems to me as if it would almost be pleasanter to love than to be loved, as "it is more blessed to give than to receive." But I never expect to know either. the blessed receiving, or the " more blessed" giving. I do not say this repiningly'- far from it; but it seems as though my fate was fixed: to drill my pupils, day after day, year in and year out, in French grammar. I won- der why they always take the verb aimer as the paradigm of the first conjugation. Do they use it in other languages? There's an old Latin gram- mar- it was my father's- among my few books. How is it there? As I live, here it is again! amare, to love. As if those boys and girls would not learn to conjugate it, in all its cases, moods, and tenses, without going through it in this way! Well, as I know the thing itself will not come to me, I'll not cry for it, as I said before, as babies cry for the moon. No; I'll be as philosophical as the Frenchman who said: "When we have not the thing we want, we must be content with what we have." Something on the principle of the old proverb: "If you can't get crumb, you must eat crust." So I am content. And all this grew out of my thinking Dr. For-   TWISTED THREADS.        21 sythe and Miss Steiner would make a handsome couple. I like to look at handsome people. And Bertha Steiner is certainly very handsome. I said she was tall and stately; so she is-almost queenly in her bearing, or rather, her bearing would befit majesty; for crowned heads are not always worthy in appearance of their regal surroundings: witness Victoria of England and Isabella of Spain, two as homely women as you can find. But we forget, in the true womanhood of the English queen, her lack of beauty; while, in the dethroned Spaniard-I cannot think patiently of women who are as she is. But royal ermine and purple would suit Miss Steiner's magnificent figure, a regal crown sit well on that noble brow. Hers is a singular style of beauty; not a trace of color in the, clear com- plexion-- --c call it fai,)hot pale; ;" yet you feel, color would spoil the face. The lips are rich, glowing scarlet-lips like Guinevere's. I could imagine a man might "Waste his whole heart in one kiss Upon her perfect lips." A low, broad brow, crowned with fair hair-true flaxen hair --soft, silky, and abundant, with just a slight wave in its smooth luxuriance. In strange contrast with the Saxon hair is the jetty blackness  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7635-00000011"/> 22,     f TWIS TED THR EADS. of the large, languishing eyes, shaded with long, curved lashes: the eyes of the brunette with the hair of the blonde. Hers is a singular style of beauty. I looked at her to-day till I was almost afraid that she would notice my steady gaze; but, if she did, I could not perceive it. Probably she is accustomed to be looked at and admired. She was like a beautiful picture to me. It must be delightful to be able to give pleasure to others, merely because one is beautiful, and to be conscious that we can give this pleasure; for I do not believe that we are ever ignorant of any advan- tages we may possess, be they physical or mental. Why should we be? I think the very knowledge that we have intellect or beautywould be a pleasure in itself, and there need be no conceit nor vanity in it. It is not a thing we owe to ourselves or hold by any merit of our own; it is a gift to be prized and valued, as we would health or strength. Arid Bertha Steiner's beauty must be a true en- joyment to her! -to know that the world is brighter to others because she is so fair. I know I am always happier for looking on anything beautiful- to see that your mirror reflects only what is lovely; a living picture or an animated poem; for there is nothing in the world equal to a truly beautiful woman. I would give anything to possess such beauty! Am I growing envious? I hope not., Cannot we admire and appreciate what is unattainable, without envy?   CHAPTER III. SOUS LES TOITS. IT is very pleasant certainly, this sitting down after my day's work is ended, to jot down as best pleases me the vagrant, thoughts and fancies that go wandering through my brain. This little parchment-bound volume, with its fair white pages, on which, day by day, I write,'and which will be a record of my life, is becoming very dear tome; something like a dpear friend, of whose silent yet expressive sympathy I can always be secure; with the knowledge that I can say what I please, and that what I say can never be laughed at. I do hate to be ridiculed! Now I can understand why people keep a journal or diary. I know why I keep mine-because, liv- ing alone as I do, with neither mother, sister, nor intimate friend, I must have something to take their place; and that is what my little book does. I won't call it a diary, because that means " daily." I shall call it, as Mistress More did hers, a " libellus" -a " little book." -But I won't use her motto -it would never suit me- "Nulle dies sine linea. " * - ;             .23 I  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7635-00000012"/> 24     TWISTED   HREA D S. because I know there would be many days without a line recorded; for there are times and days and seasons in our lives when we have nothing to write or even to think about-days which pass with nothing to mark them--seasons of which, the mo- notony is never',broken - times when we only live, and nothing more. But I intend that these pages shall be a faithful record of Maud Lennox, with all her faults and im- perfections, her wishes and aspirations, that thereby she may attain to the fulfilment of the desire of the ancient sage, "Know thyself." It is a pity I had not lived in stirring times, such as the days of the Revolutionary fathers, that I might have something to record to make my "Iibellus" valuable. What a prize to the literary world a diary kept by Shakspeare, Mary Stuart, Homer, or any great person, would be! How many points now disputed, - both in history and in literature, would then be set- tled.  While I am at it, I may as well let my brain run riot. But my little book will never be of any value to any one but myself. Why should it be? --only the life of a poor French teacher -only her little hopes, her unfounded fears, her vague desires for the fu- ture-only the ins and outs of a woman's heart, the feeble. thoughts of a woman's mind?- nothing more. But if it pleases me that these matters-some might call them trifles-should be recorded, so let   TWISTED THREADS.        25  it be. If my world is a narrow one, my sphere I  limited, am I to blame if I strive to secure all the enjoyment within my reach? Sitting in my quiet room this evening, I could almost write by the brilliant December moonlight, which pours down on the snow all around me. For from my little room under the eaves sozs les toits -where I live, a sort of feminine "Attic Philoso- pher," I can look out on a vast expanse of house- tops, all to-night wearing but one livery, one color, the virgin whiteness of the December snow. For on these high places alone, in this great city, does the snow preserve its purity-because it is nearer hea- ven: in the streets it is a soiled, polluted mass, to be gotten rid of as rapidly as possible. Only to such as I does the pristine beauty show itself, and I have been feasting my eyes upon it, as it sparkles and gleams in the silvery rays of the moon, white, pure; and unspotted as the fair, white robes we shall wear in heaven, when we come to our eternal rest. I was late coming home from schoolthis morning; so late, that when I did return I found that dinner was over, and the boarders had dispersed. But Mrs. Wilson, kind soul, had not forgotten "Miss Maud" --I am very fortunate in being with 1her-and she soon had a nice little meal for me. I sat at the table, taking my own time, leisurely enjoying the quiet of the great dining-roqm, usually at meal-times a scene of bustle and confusion--forty boarders make-no small amount of either; and Mrs. Wilson 3  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7635-00000013"/> 26     TWISTED TSREADS. sat and talked to me, "for company's sake." I really enjoyed- it. 'Going up stairs, a few minutes later, just on the first turn of the steps: I met Miss Steiner; and would have passed. her, but, to my great amazement, she stopped. "Miss Lennox, I believe? I am surely not mis- taken?" "No," I said, quietly, "my name is Lennox." "Then will you pardon my lack of ceremony, and permit me to introduce myself as Bertha Steiner," a- smile curving her beautiful lips. "I like your face, Miss Lennox; I was anxious to know you, and I thought that with you, for once, I might lay aside the niecessary forms, and break the ice myself." "I am glad you did," I said, shyly. "And yet I have frightened you," her large black eyes seeming to look me through and through. "Don't look so much like a frightened bird, Miss Lennox. I am only a woman like yourself, and I in- tend that you and I shall yet be friends." "Thank you." She laughed--a low, silvery laugh. "I know you want to run away; so, go, if you will. But I warn you that I have taken a fancy to you; you will have to learn to talk to me yet." Friends! Bertha Steiner and Hfriends! It would be as though -the butterfly and the working bee consorted together. * "I am not as gay a personage, nor am I as formid- able as you seem-to consider me," she said, as though   TW}ISTED THREADS.      27 she had read my thoughts. "I can afford to wait till you are less shy, Miss Lennox." "I am not shy," very eagerly. "Indeed, Miss Steiner, I am very glad to know you." "Prove it, then. I will not detain you now, Miss Lennox, but I shall not forget." And with a smile she passed on. I stood watch- ing her as she moved away; going down the stairs, as few women can, gracefully and without losing one particle of her dignity. Her long flowing dress, a deep garnet-colored silk, flowed behind her in a train, and a stray sunbeam, from the window on the landing where I stood, fell on her fair hair, lighting it into golden glory, crowning her as it were with a halo like that around the heads of saints in olden pictures. I could not but-think, as she passed along in her trailing robes, her glorious beauty, her golden hair illumined by the sunbeams--while I, in my deep mourning-robe, my slight, frail figure, my un- attractive face, lingered in the shadow-that this meeting, chance though it was, might be a presage of our lives--the brightness and the light for her; the darkness and the shadow for me. But it was only for a moment. Though some paths lie in the shadow, some in the sunshine, my path might yet be an easier one to my feet than Bertha Steiner's might be to her. Through what- soever paths we might wander, the beginning and the end of all would be alike. Birth and death, and a few short years would comprise it all. And then, what would it matter? And as I turned to my room,  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7635-00000014"/> 28       TWISTED     THR-EADS. after she had passed from   my gaze, I murmured to myself some verses, which, full of faults though they might be, yet expressed my thoughts better than I could have done myself: that our thorny paths, our cloudy skies, the cross we bear, only lead us to, and fit us for our final, rest: "A weary weight laid on feeble shoulders, A burden lasting from sun to sun; A toil ne'er ending, yet still beginning, Never, ceasing and never done! Only o'er rocks go our weary footsteps-- , Ever, dark clouds yet obscure our sky, Till in our blindness we can but wonder If only thorns in our pathway lie. "Pale are the flowers that bloom in our pathway; Through clouds and darkness the sunbeams shine; Trials, like sorrows, are sent to lead us, By slow degrees, to our rest divine. To every hand is some toil appointed, - On every heart is some burden laid; All that we pass through is but to bring us Under the Cross where our hope is stayed! ' Oh! what will matter Earth's fading flowers- What will we care for Life's weary days; More will we prize that Heavenly Kingdom, That we have won it through toilsome ways. When, at the last, freed from sin's dominion, Freed from all stain and all earthly dross, Come we, all humbly, in childlike meekness, To our resting-place - under the Cross! ' What, then, will matter Life's toilsome journey, Our weary hearts - or our bleeding feet? Though over rocks or 'neath storms we wander, Still, at the last, will our rest be sweet-   TTWISTED   THREADS.         29 '       If, at the end, through Life's tribulation - Winning a crown through our earthly loss - I/       All of our trials but surely bring us To our resting-place - under the Cross! - \       f"Why need we faint 'neath Life's dreary burden? Under the Cross that we all must bear, Guided by Faith, we move gladly onward, Wearing the thorn-crown that all must wear. For, at the last, all our toils forgotten - Healed our wounds - cast away our dross - Safe we shall lie, crowned with bliss eternal, In our resting-place - under the Cross!" Murmuring these lines to myself, I sought my room, looking out on the pure snow., Turning from thence to gaze, as was my wont before retiring, on the holy face of the "Ecce    Homo" consecrating my little room--He who on the Cross suffered for us -who, for us, bore the pain and wore the thorn- they came back to me; and when, at last, I sought my bed, shutting out the moonlight and the living whiteness of the snow, they were my last waking, conscious thought. 3- !   &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7635-00000015"/> CHAPTER IV. EVENING THOUGHTS. I DO not know why it is that my thoughts-have gone back, this evening, so vividly to Lynn dear Lynn - my dear old home! Perhaps it was because the sermon I heard to-day was on the text: "For here we have no continuing city." I know that was all I heard of the sermon -just those seven words spoken by the white-surpliced minister. I am so glad that he does not wear the black silk robe -a great, heavy pall. I like the pure white vestments so much better. They seem to me emblematic of the "righteousness" where- with "they-who minister about the altar" should be clothed. But somehow, -it may have been the tone, it may have been the ray of sunlight which, pouring through the rich stained glass of the window over the altar, crowned the beautiful head, majestic in its gray hairs, serene in the calm loveliness of a Chris- tian old age, with a halo of colored light, - I can- not say, but my truant thoughts went -wandering away -away - till I was home once more in Lynn -sitting once more in my accustomed place in our 30   TWISTED THREADS.       31 little church, listening again to my father's low, persuasive voice, as he preached-as he always did at this Advent season-of the love our Saviour showed us in taking our human nature on Him. I know that most clergymen, at-this time, preach to their flocks of the Judgment the Second Com- ing - its terrors - its punishments. He never did, at this season. Over his study-table, just where he could see it, hung the Face I am now looking upon-a face which, despite the suffering, the anguish of which it so plainly tells, wears yet a look of such abiding love, such tender compassion, that no one looking upon it can think of anything but mercy and lov- ing-kindness. I have said it was the inspiration of many a ser- mon. Well, my father read in the Gospel, "good tidings," mercy, love, forgiveness. And as the angel brought " good tidings of great joy," so at the beginning of the Christian year my father strove to preach "peace on earth and good will towards men." I have wandered away from the minister's text - "no continuing city "-and the thoughts those words brought up in this restless brain of mine, which carried me far, far away from the grand church in which I sat, with its gorgeous stained-glass win- dows, the fret and carved work of its ceiling and Gothic arches, to the little church in which I had always worshipped. No "continuing city " - no home! ,  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7635-00000016"/> 32     TWISTED THREADS. Then I did have a home, and such a pleasant one! Every room -every corner of that little parsonage was dear to me, peopled as it was with childish fan- cies, maidenly dreams, and, later, womanly sorrows. It was but a quiet, uneventful life I led there-calm, peaceful in its monotony. But, after all, are not those calms in our life--those days which pass unnoticed -those seasons when the river of Life flows stilly on, the happiest? Time,passes most rapidly when we take no note of his flight. Ah! but-I was happy then! It was such a pretty place where we lived. It might have been called an artist's paradise for its beauty. Not a large town--it had, perhaps, three thousand inhabitants; but so beautifully situated. It was built on a river--a beautiful river--which curved lovingly around the town -the high bluffs which form its banks receding about a mile fr6m the river, just at the point where Lynn stands, as though to make room for the quiet little town, nestled down between the hills on the one side, the river on the other. I used to wonder which was the most beautiful, the living water, flashing, gleaming, dancing in the sunlight, or the everlast- ing hills which look down on the flowing waters they bounded. If I could, I would always live near water. -I do not suppose a critical eye would have seen any architectural beauty in Lynn. Any one, going from this great city, with her magnificent stores and handsome  residences' marble palaces, which   T'WISTED THREADS.       33 are to me like great stone advertisements of the owner's wealth and position -would have thought it, with its quiet streets, modest churches, and cosy, ivy-covered houses, standing, most of them, back from the street, but a humble little place. But the surrounding country was so beautiful, the grand old trees--relics of the "forest primeval," which the good taste of the early settlers had spared to shade their dwellings, and which, in one or two of the streets, formed an arcade of living. verdure--the pleasant houses, built mostly of a dark-gray stone, on the rough surface of which the ivy climbed caress- ingly -houses which you instinctively felt were homes-- homes in every sense of the word - ren- dered more beautiful by the gardens in front, which, during the season, were one mass of bloom; for our people in Lynn were fond of flowers- the poetry of nature. Such was my home. I can lay down my pen, and see it all before me now. If I only could paint it as I see it! The river in all its beauty, glistening in the sunshine, gleaming in the moonlight, a clear, fMining path- way, which, when I was a child--" little Maud," as they called me at home, and read fairy tales, and, what is more, believed in them-I thought was the road by which the fairies came down from their palaces in Cloud-land; its rippling waves washing the roots of the old gnarled trees on its banks; the wood, where I found every year the first May-flow- ers-arbutus, hepatica, and anemone; where the \   &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7635-00000017"/> 34      WIS TED THR EA D S. tallest, plumiest ferns grew. It all comes back to me now, till, realizing that I now live a stranger among strangers, I could almost throw aside my pen, push away my " libellus," and cry. It would do no good if I did. And it was the thought that I had no 14ome now, that carried me so far away from the church this evening, and took me to the old familiar places once more, so that I wholly forgot where I was, till the pealing notes of the organ and the sweet choir-voices uniting in "Jerusalem the golden," our future " continuing city," roused me from my revery, and then I came here to my little chamber. I believe it did me good after all to go back, in spirit, to my old life; and yet, even there, in the calm, unbroken life I led, I felt at times some of the restlessness which comes overme now-something of what I imagine is in every human soul- a long- ing, a vague unrest; aspirations after the Infinite, wishes for something we ngerer can attain, like the images of beauty the painter and sculptor dream of, yet never fix, or the burning, livingwords the poet hears, yet never can make his own. Can we ever attain to our ideal? Whittier knew what I meant when he said of his Maud Miiller--I have always loved my namesake -that there was "A feeling she scarcely dared to own For something better than she had known." I am quoting from memory. But I do not have much time for such thoughts   Tl;'ISTED TlREADS.       35 now. These short winter days my time is so fully taken up that, by the time night comes, I am so tired I fall asleep the minuted my head touches my pillow. So that I do not write much in my little book. Except on Sunday evenings. This, for instance: I can see no harm in it. Why, if I had a sister, as I used. to wish in those days at Lynn; which now seem so far away a past so remote from this present--I think that she and I would sit together in the evening, whether it were week-day or Sunday, and talk together. But, as I , have no sister, I talk through my pen with my little book. After all, there are some reasons for which I am glad I have no sister. Yet, under some circumstances, it would be a very pleasant relationship--to feel there was some one of your own name, your own blood, nearer and dearer to you than any one else in the world - near your years; near your heart: a second self. No. I am not sure that I should like that. Not being a special admirer of'my own self--I am too well aware of my many faults and imperfections for that -a sister who was a shadow of myself would never suit me. And, if we were different, I don't believe I should like that either. She might not sympathize with or feel for me. If I were to talk to her as I do to my "libellus," she might laugh at me. Perhaps she might even tease me. i  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7635-00000018"/> 36     TWISTED THREADS. And I never could stand that. It would make me miserable; for I never could understand what pleas- ure people find in tormenting others-where "The dear delight of giving pain" lay. Why, I think some of those who tease are as cruel and as heartless as the old Spanish inquisitors. They, indeed, tore the quivering flesh, crushed the aching nerves; these agonize the feelings-without touching the body, they hurt the soul. And then they wonder that their victims do not love them. I believe it is better as it is. And then, there is only one of us to struggle for a living; and I, Maud Elinor Lennox, spinster, (and likely to remain so, too!) am used to it. Like Lily Dale, at the end of her story, I will write my name again, with her two letters after it. MAUD ELINOR LENNOX, O. M. s                        /    CHAPTER V. BREAKING THE ICE. DO not know why Bertha Steiner should seek my company; it seems to me that she and I, living, as we do, such different lives,.moving in such --different spheres, would have little or nothing in common. She thinks otherwise: twice, since the evening she introduced herself to me, she has stopped me, and tried to enter into conversation with me. At last, she made me promise that some evening, when there were not too many in the parlor, I would come and sit with her, instead of shutting myself up, like a cloistered, veiled nun, in my little -cell. For in truth it is a nun-like life that I lead-these pages my only confessor, and I speak to them and in them more freely than any nun could to her ghostly father. Miss Steiner seems determined to call me out of the barriers of reserve and shyness which my lonely life, void, as it were, of all human interests, has built up around me. So I am trying to be more like other people; and this evening, feeling really ashamed to think she had met me more than halfway, I got up from my table, where I had been looking over 4        .       ,. 37  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7635-00000019"/> 38     TWISTED THREADS. some exercises brought home to be corrected, and began to smooth my hair. I have a careless, child- ish fashion of pulling at my curls, and disarranging them whenever I am puzzled. And I had just brought the rebellious ringlets into something of the prim, smooth order in the which it pleases me to wear the abundant tresses wherewith nature has gifted me. I had put on a fresh collar, brushed the dust from my dress, when there was a light step in the passage, a tap at my door, and when I opened it, there stood Bertha Steiner. She wore a dress of some soft, shining, yet heavy material, a delicate, misty, rosy gray in color: like the faint tinge I have seen on low-lying clouds near the horizon on a dull, sunless day; one of those lovely, undecided colors, such as soft, sweet lilac- airy, cool gray - fresh, del- icate mauve, which I love to look at, yet which I look at longingly, because I cannot wear them. I thought again, as she stood at my door, of the con- trast between us, dawn and darkness. "I have come to besiege you in your own castle," she said, as, in reply to my invitation to enter, she came in and sat down  in my favorite seat, a low, armless rocking-chair. "And you are to come down stairs with me, too. Maurice, strange to say, has an evening's leisure, and you are to come down and make yourself agreeable." "Who is Maurice?"I asked. "Maurice? Ah, I  had forgotten; you do not know him by that name. Will it give you any more definite ideas, or bring an image of the reality before   TW FISTED THfREADS.      39 your eyes, if I call him, instead of Maurice, Dr. Forsythe?" I hesitated. "Miss Steiner, I never can talk to him." "Miss Lennox," imitating my tone, " suppose he were to say the same of you?" "'Not much fear of that," I said, laughing at her manner; "there is nothing formidable about me, while he is a learned professor." "Only a man, for all that. And you know you used to think you- could not talk to me." "How do you know that?"I asked, in surprise. "Poor child, your face betrayed you. You were as shy with me as though I were some grand prin- cess." "So you are in my estimation," I thought, but I gave the thought no utterance. "May I not be the fairy god-mother, and take Cinderella away with me?" she went on. "Come,  ' Maud." I hesitated still. "Come," She went on. "Will you refuse me still, when I ask your presence as a special favor to my- self, and promise to take godd care of you?" So I yielded, and we went together into the par- lor. Two or three persons were there: one, a lady, whom I recognized as'a Mrs. Bernard, a widow, one of the boarders, Dr. Forsythe, and another, a stranger to me, a tall, fair-haired man, aristocratic-looking and dignified, who I found was Mrs. Bernard's son. I paid but little attention to him, however. In-  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7635-00000020"/> 40     TWISTED THREADS. deed, for the first half-hour or so, I was too much amazed at my own position to do anything but wonder how this little gray moth had gotten into the company of such brilliant butterflies as those among whom she now found herself. I had dressed myself, expecting to spend a short half-hour talking to Miss Steiner, and here I was, unexpectedly, sitting in a circle of her friends. I was very quiet at first, I know.- It was the very first time I had ever been among fashionable people --- men and women of the world; and the dread of committing some trifling gaucherie -the fear of be- ing ridiculed when my back should be turned, drove me into the very mal-a'ise I was so anxious to avoid. Miss Steiner had introduced me to her friends. Dr. Forsythe and Mrs. Bernard were talking together, discussing some new book just out--some poem, over which I had forgotten myself a few days before; and though I would have given much to engage in the conversation, I held my peace and listened- listened, and looked at Maurice Forsythe. I like to look at people, and try to guess, from the expression, from the lines on the brow and around the mouth, what the character may be. But I could learn nothing from Dr. Forsythe's face. I studied it carefully. He was the first man I had ever seen who had won himself a name; and I confess I wished to form some opinion about him. He looked ennmye, tired, and careless- as if nothing could interest him, nothing excite him. I thought him hard, cold, and heartless.   TWISTED THREADS.        41 Bertha Steiner drew me into the conversation be- tween Mr. Bernard and herself. What wonderful tact she possesses!- an enviable gift--the power of always saying the right thing in the right place; the ability to set people at their ease. She actually made me forget myself; and I found I could talk to these people as readily as I did to my pupils. Then she went over to Dr. Forsythe. I could not help hearing him, as she asked Mrs. Bernard to play--she is a fine performer --say: "Who is this new protegee you have picked up, Bertha? An escaped novice?" "Hush! I want you to go and talk to her: it will repay you. She is no protege'e of mine. I can assure you she is not a person one would try that with, and there is not much of the novice about her." He turned lazily, and looked at me. I, wondering if he knew what a very thin paper wall there was between us, talked away to Mr. Bernard as indus- triously as ever. "Do you think it would pay, Bertha?" "Go and see for yourself. Quiet as Maud Lennox looks, there is something in her." "A romantic name, too. Why can't people have names to suit them? She is not my ideal of Maud the Fair, surely. Well, Bertha, to please you, I 'll go and be bored presently." It is a nuisance to have a cat's ears. Sometimes I am quick of hearing--painfully so: a mouse gnaw- ing behind the wall will sometimes awaken me from a sound sleep. I cannot, like Fine-ear, hear the grass /1   &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7635-00000021"/> grow; but my organs of hearing-what quaint, shell-like appendages they are to any one's head -are singularly acute. They bring me words and sentences never destined for me, as in this case, in the which, be it known, I was not sorry; for being "forewarned," I was "forearmed;" and pride com- ing to my aid, I resolved to throw shyness aside, and prove to Dr. Forsy the that Maud Lennox spite of her romantic appellation, her quiet, novice- like mien, had yet, as Bertha Steiner said, "some- thing in her," and, like other women, had a tongue, and knew how to use it. So, when Dr. Forsythe slowly, leisurely, and in- differently-in obedience, as I knew, to Miss Stei- ner's bidding-came to the place where I sat, and stood before me, I was prepared to meet him. I think that if his light, scornful words had not come to my ear, I should have been the simple, silly, silent girl I knew he thought me. But I wanted to take him by surprise. His first remark was. "Miss Lennox, do  you believe in woman's rights?" It was a  queer beginning to a conversation be- :ween strangers. He stood before me, twirling his noustache, looking down  upon me, as I have seen all, powerful men look down upon a child whose rambols or prattlings amuse them. I answered, as coolly as I could: "That depends, Dr. Forsythe, upon what you call roman's rights." He sat down then.    "(It would take a long discussion to settle that, I am afraid. Suppose I change the form of my question: Do you believe in women being inde- pendent?" "To a certain-extent, yes." "Very emphatic! May I ask to what extent?" He evidently wanted to amuse himself at my expense. This I was determined he should not do. "I believe," I said, "in a woman's being suffi- ciently independent to act for herself, if it be neces- sary; doing what is right because it is right-.and through it all, remembering her womanhood." He smiled. "Do you consider your sex wingless angels?" "No," I said; "I try to make' allowances in all cases, for the failings of poor humanity." - Mine among the rest?" "If Dr. Forsythe is conscious of needing my for- bearance." "Which of us does not need forbearance?" he said, as I thought, sadly, in a tone completely changed from the light, careless one in which he had first addressed me. "If our thoughts, and often our actions, could be known, we might not be even as indulgent as we are." I said nothing. I only thought how little indul- gence I should merit did the world know me as this little book of mine knows me. And then the conversation became general. I took my part in it-enjoying it, too: even had I wished to be silent, and listen, Bertha Steiner would  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7635-00000022"/> "     TWISTED THREADS. not -have allowed me to sit there without speaking- she drew me into the gay talk. I begin to understand, after this evening's expe- rience, what fascination society must exercise over her votaries. If this little mingling with people- nothing but the ordinary course of events to them, a great break in my usual routine to me--has given me so much pleasure--so exciting me, that I sit here thinking over the gay talk, so that I cannot sleep- what would it be if I were fairly launched in the vortex, and living the life Bertha Steiner lives! It is not likely I ever will.   CHAPTER VI. ; t0I          MOODS. WONDER how it is that people write novels? 1 Does the whole story, plot and characters, come to them at once, as at one glance we take in a beau- tiful landscape, or see some grand painting? Or does it form itself by degrees, as our human lives unfold themselves, each day adding a little more to the story, till at last it attains its full completeness? Does it tell itself, as I am telling my story-my story! there is no story in my life - day by day, as I write in my libellus? I do not know. What a blessing it is that we cannot read the future- that the paths we must tread are hidden from us -that we only know each step as it comes! If to the cares of to-day were added the knowledge of the to-morrow, could we endure it? I do not believe that we could. Sometimes-I cannot help it--I wonder what I ever was put in this world for. For some good purpose, I presume, if I only could see what it was. But, indeed, I am a very useless sort of a somebody--useless to every one excepting to myself; and that is such a selfish thing to have to live for -only one's self. 45  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7635-00000023"/> "     TWISTED THREADS. Will it always be so, I wonder? Will I always live, feeling that it is nothing to any one if I am in the world or not; that no one will care if Maud Lennox drops, unnoticed, out of the niche, a very insignificant one, which she occupies in this world; and even while I am here, will I always lead the uneventful existence I am leading now? I am almost tempted to envy Bertha Steiner to- night: knowing, as I do, how happy she always must be--young, beautiful, and admired. A But I must not grow envious. Only I would like to have some of the sunshine of life for my share. Well, it will come, I suppose, in its own good time. As it is, I weary of my mo- nrotonous life: day after day the same, each one repeating itself, till I think if only the terrible same- ness could be changed! I will not write any more in this strain. It is never a good plan to give way to a fit of low spirits. But I cannot, cannot help it to-night; to- night, when the winds are howling, shaking my win- dows, and every now and then a  fiercer blast than ever drives the pouring rain-a  miniature torrent --against the panes of glass. I am glad I am not "Maud the Fair." For that name, as spoken by Dr. Forsythe, a few nights since, haunted me, and I wanted to give it a person and a form. I did not care it should only be a  name to me. I  searched through an old cyclopaedia till I found her.   TWISTED THREADS.-       47 ifi :!  Her name was Maud Fitzwalter, known as the Fair, even in those days of fair women: those days when, as it seems to us who live in these later times, i  there were more women gifted with beauty, Maud's X? r   fatal gift, than you find now-a-days. X!H  Yet her beauty,' a luckless gift to her, since it won her a king's love, and brought her death--death by poison-after an imprisonment in a bleak, exposed turret, where, many a night like this, she must have shivered with the told,-was one of the remote causes of the signature of Magna Charta, for it drove her father to fight, in revenge for his daughter's wrongs, against his king. vg ievWPoor Maud! May I hope her namesake, think- ing of her, centuries later, may have a happier fate? i3   I don't appreciate such a day as this has been. A winter's day, such as'we sometimes have them: clear, cold, and sunshiny, when the sky is blue and the air full of a crisp frostiness, so that every breath you inhale seems to strengthen and invigorate you; when, if every roof, every tree is fringed with icicles, they yet glitter and glisten, like pendent diamonds, frost-work jewels, or water-crystals, in the slanting rays of a winter sun: such a day is a day to be enjoy- ed. Such days I go out. and think that it is a pleas- ure only to breathe the bracing, fresh atmosphere. But a day like this, when the clouds have hung '  S through the hours of light close to the earth- angry, gray-looking clouds,--when the air is full  if  of a moist chilliness --a chill which goes through and through you, till you vainly long for but one  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7635-00000024"/> 48     TWISTED TR EA D S. ray of sunlight, one ray to pierce the gloom of what you can scarcely call day, so little does it suit our ideas of what day should be,--when you long for darknes, that it may veil that threatening sky, from which, as you know, the pouring December rain will come in time,-a "long, long, weary day," whose death comes at last, and over whose death the lowering, close heaven sheds its tribute in heavy, pelting rain. Such- a day this has been. It seems to me my scholars were unusually dull to-day, too: or perhaps it was I that was stupid. Any way, teaching was regular drudgery, real task- work, to me this morning. I was glad when it was over. Coming home from my class, walking, as is my wont, rapidly, --I always walk fast, and this after- noon, which was shortened by the murky sky, I did not care to loiter in the streets, partly because in this great city I must not be out of doors after dark, partly because, cat-like, I dislike a drenching- it spoils my clothes,. a serious consideration to my slender purse, - I was at last aware of a firm, quick step behind me, and at last Dr. Forsythe overtook me. And passed me without even looking at me, Would he have passed Bertha Steiner thus? She, I believe, is at the opera to-night'; for, when I came up, later than usual, to my room, to-night, I found a note from her: "I had intended that you should spend this even-   E5Iil        T WISTED   THREADS.         49 ing with me. But Maurice has brought me tickets for Lucia; and', malgre the rain, I am    going. That I did not forget you, let the accompanying book BERTHA." bear witness for It is pleasant to be remembered, certainly.      I am glad she coulgl spare a thought to, me; it soothed me wonderfully. I have been looking over the book--the last new   magazine. And in it I found some verses which seem           the echo of my own thoughts---so much so, that I give them a place in this little book of mine. They qre called  AFTER DAPRK. " Tossed in the wailing, wintry blast, The long dead leaves fall thick and fast; And, sitting in my chamber lone, I listen to the wind's wild moan; While, on the darkened window-pane Patters the cold December rain. " No sound in all the quiet street, Not e'en the tread of passing feet: Only the wind's dull monotone; Only my heart beats; as, alone, I hear against my window-pane The slow, sad patter of the rain. "O'er earth hangs low a misty shroud, The sky is hid by one dark cloud: And from my weary, aching eyes- The sad tears fall-as, through my sighs, I hear, against the window-pane, The ceaseless patter of the rain. 5 &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7635-00000025"/> 50        WIS TED TtHREA D S. "Oh! weary heart! oh! tired feet! To thee the grave's rest will be sweet  To clasp upon a pulseless breast These hands: to lie in dreamless rest. In mournful tones against the pane I hear the sobbing of the rain. "What tears above me would be shed,? What heart would mourn, if I were dead? I need not ask--for to mine ear No answer comes --I only hear, In solemn tones against the pane, The ceaseless dropping of the rain." Ah! will it always    be "after dark"  with me? Just now it seems as though there were a "cease- less dropping" in my life. I believe flowers will not grow, even the hardiest among them, under a drip. I  should be  sorry to think  I would always be as "blue"   as I am  this evening.   But it is unusual for me to be thus low-spirited--these fits- only come over me   such days as this.  To-morrow, when  the sun comes out, and the sky is blue, why, Maud Len- nox, like   Richard, will be herself again.   CHAPTER VII. YULE-TIME. CHRISTMAS has come and gone. Christmas! that one day in the year to which all children look forward as a day above all other days - a day of pleasure and enjoyment. I can remember-it is not so very long since, either--how I used to look forward to it, and wish the whole year were one unbroken Christmas-day, an endless Yule. First, there was the pleasure of preparing for it--the little love-gifts, worked at in secret, so that no one might even suspect their existence and thus fore- stall the pleasant surprise intended; others, made- more openly, for my Sunday-school class. And then, the cookery - of cakes, pies, and other good things; for, so far as we were able, we kept open house, and none of my father's poorer parishioners were ever forgotten on the anniversary of that day when to the Eastern shepherds came the " good tidings of great joy." And then, too, there was the' bringing together of the cedar, the fir, and the box, to " adorn" the "sanctuary;" the fashioning by willing hands of these green tributes into wreaths and garlands, to beautify the little church, and to fill it with their rich, spicy, incense-like odors. 51  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7635-00000026"/> A d  '   TWISTED THRSADS. t  It is all changed now. That day, to which I used to look forward with so many anticipations -tfat season, every moment of which I used to enjoy- has become to me a time, in which, if it were not for the rejoicing with which the Church bids us greet and celebrate its coming, I should like to shut my- self up, away from all sound of merriment and all sight of feasting, as, on each recurring anniversary of her husband's death, a noble lady of olden times was wont to seclude herself in her chamber, shutting out the sunlight, and spending the hours in' prayer and in fasting. For such a day is Christmas to me now--a day of mournfully. looking back upon the past--a day of -memories and associations -a day to be enjoyed by those who have a home and home ties-the sweetest, dearest ties on earth: not a day of enjoy- ment to me. Yet this Christmas, lonely though I was--lone- lier than usual, because I have a fortnight's holiday, and am, consequently, my  own mistress, to do as I  please and, go where I please--was yet more pleasant to me than I had expected; and there are some pleasant recollections lingering with it. It was pleasant -to see the many bright, happy childish faces; to go to the church decked with evergreens; to hear the joyous anthems, the same the angels sang over- the humble manger in Bethlehem. Bit though all this pleased me, I owe most of my enjoyment to Bertha Steiner. It is singular how she and I have learnt to know   TWISTED THREADS.        53 each other in these past few weeks. I can scarcely believe that our acquaintance- ah! it is more than that: our friendship-may as yet be counted by days. It is so short a time since the evening she stopped me on the stair. And still, judging by my feelings, that time is already far away. And yet, if it had not been that on Christmas eve, she, meeting -me by accident on the same stair where we first met, and seeing I looked "a-weary," took me to her room --then the ice was broken for- ever-all barriers swept away; and, before I knew exactly how, I was talking to her as if I had known her all my life. "And since then, it has been "Ber- tha" and "Maud" between us. Such a pretty room as hers is, too! She furnished it herself, she told me. It suited even my fastidious tastes. A soft, thick carpet, of some neutral ground- color-wood, Hthink-with ivy branches and scar- let berries wandering over it; the walls covered with a paper matching the ground-color of the carpet, with just a green ivy border at the ceiling; walnut furniture, unvarnished; the chairs, lounge, and table covered with scarlet rep; pretty little brackets in the corners; one or two paintings-a sad "Bea- trice," a loving, beautiful "Madonna," a rich glowing sunset scene, a cool, dreamy picture, water and ruins by moonlight; a few bright flowers in a vase; and, over it all, that indescribable air of elegance and refinement which only the hands of a woman of taste can give. 5  .   &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7635-00000027"/> 54     TWISTED THREADS. It must be delightful, having wealth, to surround oneself with not only the comforts but the ele- gances of life. And. yet wealth cannot give everything; and 'contentment is better than wealth."  It was a 'gloomy day, that same Christmas eve: snow, in huge white flakes, falling noiselessly from the sky--a sky so gray that you involuntarily won- dered whence the snow falling from it won its pure whiteness. As well ask the white pond-lily by what alchemy-what mysterious chemistry -it draws its golden stamens and stainless petals from the muddy bed in which its roots lie. "I am glad we shall not have a 'green Yule,"' Bertha said, as she seated herself in a low easy- chair, which set off with its scarlet covering the purity of her complexion and her delicate features to advantage; while I occupied its mate. "Christ- mas would not be itself without snow." I shall be glad when the day is over," was my reply. She looked at me, kindly. "Ah! I see how it is: a day of recollection to you. It is the same to me, Maud. I suppose it is the same to all, as they; grow older." "Miss Steiner-"I began. "No, you are not to give me that formal title," she said, with a smile. "I call you 'Maud,' not 'Miss Lennox.' Is it so hard for you to say 'Bertha'?"   TWISTED TREADS.        55 "Is it ever hard to do pleasant things?"I asked. "And 'Bertha' is something pleasant to say." "Then, I hope I shall often hear the name from your lips," was the quick reply. "I shall like it, too: except yourself, Maurice is the only person here who does not call me ' Miss Steiner.'" "Are you, like myself, alone in the world?" "Maurice is the only person upon whom I am aware of having the slightest claim." My eyes asked the question I would not put in "What a tell-tale face you have, Maud Lennox! Never try to keep any secrets from me: your face would betray them. You are wondering what claim I have upon Dr. Forsythe. I will tell you." But it'is too long a story to tell in conversational form; it would fill too many pages in this book of mine; so I will tell it in my own language. or these two, at whose use of one another's given names I had idly wondered-- imagining, as I did, that their acquaintance dated from their meeting in Mrs. Wilson's boarding-house--had known each other for years. There was a connection between them, too: for Colonel Forsythe, a widower, with one son, a boy of fourteen, meeting Mrs. Steiner, married her, and her child, a little girl of two sum- mers, was as his own to him; while Maurice found a mother, in every sense of the word, in the new wife who had come to his father's house. It must have been a happy household, judging from Bertha's account of it, for Colonel and Mrs.   &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7635-00000028"/> 56     T WISTED TIR EA DS. Forsythe were well suited to each other; and the wandering life they led was full of enjoyment to both. They might have changed it, had such been their wish, for Mrs. Steiner was independent, and, her second husband had a competency; but the Colo- nel loved his profession, and was unwilling to leave it, and his wife did not oppose him. So the children, though the same blood did not mingle in their veins, grew up members of the same household, treating each other and thinking of each other as brother and sister. And at last, when first the father of the one, and then the mother of the other, died, Mrs. Forsythe left her daughter, a girl of seventeen, as ward to her step-son. He proved himself worthy of the trust. Bertha's little fortune, carefully invested, nearly doubled itself in his hands; and when she came of age, which would not be till she was twenty-five- she was now, she told me, just twenty-three-she would be quite an heiress. "And I cannot tell you," she said, "all that he has been to me. Brother, guardian, friend, in every one of these relations he has proved himself true, faith- ful, and just. I could not do without him. Maud, I shall be sorry when I come of age." "The relationship of guardian and ward some- times changes into one even nearer," I suggested. Her brow clouded. "Don't! I beg of you. I prefer thinking of Maurice as my brother; he calls himself so. There s  his Christmas gift to me."   TWISTEDD THREADS.       57 She unclasped a bracelet from her arm as she spoke -a quaint, valuable ornament: even my eye, little accustomed to looking on such gauds, could see that. A serpent, of dead gold, with scales of green enamel: its head erect, with tiny, sparkling, ruby eyes; 4n the mouth a heart of green enamel, bear- ing on a scroll in the centre, the delicately carved legend, " ye veux." "Is that motto characteristic of the donor?" "He has a strong will." I knew that beforehand. Bertha went on. "I wish you knew him as I do, Maud. If you did, you would think with me, that there are few like Maurice Forsythe." "It is not likely that I ever shall know him well,;" I said, quietly. "A man with his reputation, his standing and wealth, is not apt to trouble himself about knowing a poor French teacher." "t Maud, excuse me; but is it right for you to talk so?" "Thank you," I said; "but if you choose to -over- look the difference in our social position, I cannot expect others will do as much." "I do not consider the fact that you labor for your own support any derogation to you." "Nor do I," I said. "Only, Bertha, you see how it is with me. Completely al one in the world, with neither wit, wealth, nor beauty, I cannot look for the same kindness from all that you show me." "I am kind to myself," she replied. "Mrs. Ber- nard, who acts as my chaperone, is very good in  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7635-00000029"/> 5T FWISTED TfREADS. -  that capacity, very obliging, and very considerate; but she cannot be to me what you are, my friend. And I intend that you and Maurice shall yet learn to know, one another." "Nous verrons," I said, lightly. "If you. can bring us together, I shall be amazed." "'Ce quefemme veut,' you know the rest. And r generally succeed in my undertakings." And since that afternoon I have really felt I could call Bertha Steiner my friend. It is a very pleasant thing to me, too; for let women's friendship be laughed at and ridiculed, as I know it often is--sometimes, too, deservedly-there are cases in which it-can be a source of pure and unalloyed enjoyment. And I am glad to feel that there is some one to whom I can talk, when I grow weary of my own companionship-not, of course, as I talk to my 'libel- !us,' but as woman to woman, knowing that, of the many flowers which grow along her pathway, she is willing to spare a few to me. And my life is brighter for this human companionship which has come into it. Even if she and I were never to meet again, the recollection of her would be something that would linger with me. In the midst of her Christmas-day festivities-- she was spending the day and evening with some friends. youth, wealth, and beauty win many friends -she found time to think of me. As  I came home from the church, where the   TWISTED THREADS.   59   odors of cedar and evergreen brought back forest days, and the anthems rose in waves of melody-- as I came home, wonderfully refreshed by the ser- vices, which told that some day, joy, joy unbound- ed, unmeasured, would be given to the feeblest, most miserable on earth, I met Dr. Forsythe: "Did you know I had been waiting for you, Miss Lennox? This, with the compliments of the sea- son, Bertha sends you; and this is my 'merry Christmas' to you." And without waiting for me to thank him, he was gone. Her gift to me was 'a ticket to a circulating library, one to which only a favoried few, outside the 'ring,' could obtain tickets, and then only given as a favor - a gift she could male and I receive- a gift which promised me, with my love of reading, endless enjoyment: his, a bouquet of flowers- hot-house flowers. I took them to my room, and cared for them there. They made summer in this little room of mine for days. And all this is why this Christmas-time was to me more full of pleasure than I had expected. But to-night, before I threw away the last re-' mains of my bouquet, I took one leaf from it, and one flower, and, pinning them to a page of my book, I wrote under it Bertha's initials and the date, and under that - Given by Dr. Forsythe. It is a rather sentimental performance for me.- I   &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7635-00000030"/> 60    ,TWISTED THREADS. am twenty-three-.I ought to have outgrown all such, nonsense. Twenty-three! Just Bertha Steiner's age. In all human probability, there are fifty year more -of life before me; a long time to look for ward to. I hope, when my time comes - " the good hour --that it will not be said of me, "over there,' that my life was too long-too ill spent.   Ig  CHAPTER: VIII. FAONS DE PARLER. THE Christmas holidays are over. I cannot say that I am, after all, very sorry for it. At first, as I must confess, it was hard to settle down once more to the old quiet routine -to return to the unvarying regularity, the unchangeable order of school-hours, where every moment has its own set duties; in a word, from being my own mistress for two short weeks, to go back to the old machine for teaching French that I am at Madame Levere's. There is an old proverb, that we should not quar- rel or find fault with the bridge that carries us over the water. And I don't intend to do it. But, after an evening spent with Bertha and her friends-the charming coterie which she always at- tracts around her, and into which I am, every now and then, brought- it is not so agreeable, with the gay, witty conversation which goes on still lingering in my memory, to sit down and hear lesson after les- son, when one would so much rather take it easy, and do nothing. Still, I know that I enjoy these things all the more because they only come at times; and although I  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7635-00000031"/> 62     T WISTED THREADS. very often grumble to myself because I must earn my bread, that same bread is far sweeter, more wholesome to me because I owe it to no one. Bertha is very kind in making me join her and spend my evenings with her in the pleasant little private parlor that she and her chaperone, Mrs. Bernard, have secured for themselves. If I do not choose to talk when there, I can listen: I know I am no restraint upon the others; and often I had rather listen than talk. Mrs. Bernard was at the piano the other evening; she plays well, and is fond of favoring her friends. -What a well-preserved woman she is! One would scarcely think her the mother of the tall, handsome young man of twenty-five whom she so proudly calls "my son." I sat, looking over some new stereo- scopic views Bertha had purchased that afternoon, when, on looking up--induced, as I suppose, by that singular intuition through which we are some- times aware of the proximity of certain persons - I saw Dr. Forsythe. It was the first time I had seen him, to speak to him, since Christmas eve, when he had placed his lovely floral offering in my hands, and gone off without waiting for my thanks. So I took advantage of this opportunity, and, in the best language I could command, began to ex- press my gratitude. "I did not come here to be thanked, Miss Len- nox," he said, sitting down opposite me. "Shall I tell you how you can best express your gratitude?"   TWISTED   rHREADS.      63 "I shall be glad to learn." , Then show it by your silence." I bowed, and with a very sober face, adjusted another picture in the glass, and looked at it--not at him. He watched me for a few moments. "Miss Lennox, did you ever hear the French proverb: II y a des femmes et des femmes ? ' "I have, and never could give it a satisfactory translation." "I can give you an equivalent for it -namely, that some women talk when they have nothing to say; others are silent when conversation would be agree- able." "I thought you had asked for silence." "Ay, but I had no desire, in forbidding one sub- ject, to lay a total embargo upon your lips." "I am accustomed to be silent," I said, quietly. "After the enforced use I have to make of my tongue I when on duty in the mornings, I find silence an agreeable change." "Does that mean I am not to talk to you? "As to that, Dr. Forsythe, you are at liberty to use your own .discretion. But," fearing I had gone too far, and indeed, rather wondering at myself for the free and easy way in which I found I was talk- ing to this man, the mere tip of whose little finger was far better known in the world than my whole body-a gnat (minus, I hope, the sting) beside an elephant--I added, "But you will find I am a good listener."  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7635-00000032"/> "     TWISTED TgHREADS. "That, under some circumstances, would certainly be a very great recommendation. But, as I am par- ticularly lazy this evening, perhaps you will be obliging, and talk to me." His attitude, as he leaned back in the chair, was lazy enough; but the firm mouth and--square chin told he could be active enough when he chose; and besides, there was a sparkle in the gray eye which told of latent fun. I have said before, I dislike to be ridiculed; so, not caring to enter into a war of wits -wondering, indeed, what had brought Dr. For- sythe to, talk to me--I made a very quiet answer: "I thought it was the gentleman's place to enter- tain the lady." "There is no taking you at disadvantage, I see. Mrs. Bernard plays well, does she not?" The notes of one of Chopin's weird mazourkas were at that moment filling the room. "She is certainly mistress of her instrument." "I am fond of music," Dr. Forsythe said; " but there are times when in truth I weary of it. To- night, it serves as a cover to our conversation. Do you play, Miss Lennox?" "No, I early learnt my inability to produce any thing but noise." "Thereby showing your good sense." "Or, may I not say, my respect for music as an art. I could never have attained to excellence, Dr. Forsythe, and I never should have been content with mediocrity." "I wish there were more to agree with you. Peo-   TWISTED THREA DS.       65 ple now-a-days undertake too much. Not content with doing one thing well, they attempt many, and consequently fail in all." "Are you musical?"I asked. "No, I am not. I never had time enough for the study the thing required; and my profession, Miss Lennox, like a jealous woman, is a hard mistress: she will brook no rival; or else, to use Scripture words, 'No man can serve two masters:' so I have never attempted it." "Could you not have taken it up as a recreation?" He shook his head. "Not without neglecting more important duties."  "What, for instance?"Bertha's playful tone in- quired. She had come up quietly, and was leaning on the back of Dr. Forsythe's chair. "Has he been telling you of some visionary plans: such, for in- stance, as a search after happiness?" "That would be a search, ending like that of Ponce de Leon for the fountain of youth, fruit- lessly." "I should be sorry to think so," Miss Steiner said, softly; "sorry to think this world was only a 'vale of tears.'  "Were the truth to be told, Bertha," Dr. Forsythe replied, " there are few who could not count the days of real happiness they had enjoyed in their lives. What does your own experience tell you? or yours, Miss Lennox?" turning abruptly toward me. "My experience would scarcely be a fair crite- rion "I replied. I agree with you thus far, that &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7635-00000033"/> "     T WIS TED THR EA D S. happiness, when it comes at all, 'comes unseen, un- sought,;' the very search after it, I think, would destroy it as completely as a touch destroys the down of the butterfly's wing." "Like the. old story of the pot of gold buried under the rainbow," Bertha said," never yet obtained by mortal man." "No," I said; "for I believe th-at it is sometimes attainable: like the bird in the fairy-tale, it flits be- fore us, evading our grasp; and it is only when we give up the vain pursuit, that the winged thing, fold- ing its pinions, comes at last to rest upon our hand." "And even then, like other fairy gifts, it may turn to dust and ashes in our hands," Dr. Forsythe said, gravely, yet with a merry twinkle in his eye. "Now, I suppose I ought to be very happy to-night, with two' such ladies to talk to me ; yet in the midst of it all, I cannot help thinking what a poor preparation this is for the lecture I am to deliver to-morrow morning." Bertha pulled his hair, playfully. "Always thinking of the morrow, Maurice. Will you never learn " "To be content with what goods the gods send me? You have .shocked Miss Lennox, child: look at her."- "Not at all," I said; "I was only amused." "Well," he said, getting up from his chair, "when- ever you two, Columbus-like, set off on your voyage of discovery, let me know, and I will await your return, anxiously; for you will come back with such   TWISTED THREADS.        7 a rich freight that you doubtless will gladly spare a few trifles to such an unlucky mortal as myself." "A poor comparison," Bertha laughed; "for the Genoese discovered America." Mrs. Bernard engrossed his attention for the rest of the evening. I do not know why I should have taken the trou- ble to record this conversation; still less do I know why Dr. Forsythe should have wasted his time in this way upon me. Yet I know very well that I enjoyed it; although he is a man with whom I never could feel perfectly at ease. I sometimes wonder how it is that Bertha can treat him as unceremoniously as she does. I said as much to her one day: my remark seemed to amuse her. "My dear child, what an idea! Your famous Dr. Forsythe, author and professor, whom you seem to consider a formidable specimen of the genus homo, is no more to me than Maurice, who has romped with me, petted me, and whose thick curly locks I have pulled ever since I was two years old. I can't put him on a pedestal, as you seem to do, to save my life. I believe I will tell him, some day, how terribly afraid you are of him." "Don't!"I pleaded, .earnestly. "You must re- member that I am so little used to being with dis- tinguished people that the mere sight of them daz- zles my eyes." "That would amuse him, I can assure you. But, seriously, with all his ability, he has an humble esti-  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7635-00000034"/> 68     TWISTED THREADS. mate of himself. If you ever learn to know him well, Maud, I venture to say that you will think as highly of him as I do." But I have no desire to know Dr. Forsythe well. I would not tell Bertha this, for the world. I am content to look upon him from a respectful dis- tance. Yet, every evening since then, that I have spent in Bertha's parlor-once or twice on the stairs- Dr. Forsythe has come up to me, talked, sometimes for a moment, sometimes longer, and then I have seen no more of him. I' must confess that the man puzzles me. And still I never listen to him without pleasure -a queer sort of pleasure too, for I never can tell if he is in earnest or not. For instance: hearing Mrs. Wilson's youngest child cry, a few mornings since, as he stood talking for a moment to Bertha and to me, he said he "could not understand how any one ever could take the trouble to'soothe a crying child." i, That very afternoon, coming home, tired and worn out by my toil in school, I saw Dr. Forsythe stop, pick up a little child, a little girl, crying be- cause she was afraid to cross the street, and carry her in his arms to the other side; and, not content with that, turn back out of his own way, and, hold- ing the little thing's hand, walk a whole square with her, so as to leave her at her own door. He need not have been ashamed to say before mel he liked children.   69 TWISTED THREADSE.  And even in ou  r brief acquaintance--it scarce merits even that name -this is  only one case out of many in which Dr. Forsythe's w  ords and actions have proved contradictory. Words cost so little! they com e so easily! and yet what bitter stings they sometimes conceal! I think it is Adelaide Proctor who says: , Every word has its own spirit, True or false, that never dies;" but how few of us ever think how much our thought- less words - a mere breath-- air set in motion- may imply!  We  never think, to finish the quota- tion, ," Every word man's lips have uttered Echoes in God's skies." Somewhere or other--where, I cannot now recol- lect I read a theory to this effect: that every word spoken produced, as a stone thrown into calm water, wave-circles in the atmosphere, which, gradually enlarging, extended through all space, till, finally, they came to the Great White Throne, recording themselves there; so that our words tell our own story, and by the utterance of our own lips shall we be judged. If this were believed, might we not be more guarded as to Atow we speak? , The words we daily speak may lightly drop, And yet, like pebbles in the ocean thrown, May in their widening circles never stop Until they reach the Everlasting Throne." I  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7635-00000035"/> 70     TWISTED THREADS. I heard Dr. Forsythe say, a few evenings since, talking to Mr. Bernard: "How little there is to remember in the conver- sation of society now-a-days! Plenty of words- there is no lack of them---fractional currency in -superabundance; but when it comes to ideas, things to be remembered-gold coin-one finds one's purse very empty." And Mr.'Bernard replied, not flatteringly: "You should have been a poor man, Doctor; the gold coin you fling away unthinkingly, in the shape of witty remarks, or suggestive words, woulid make the fortune of many an essayist-the reputation of many a writer." Well, some people's words are like "apples of gold," others like mere nothingness, empty wind. Mine belong to the latter order. And yet, as they are written in this, my little book, it is sometimes pleasant for me to read them over. It is because they are mine -the children of my brain. But on reading over the pages filled this evening- I never use my pen during the day; it is my evening friend: we can always say more to one another in twilight, I think, when there is no broad sunshine to betray every varying expression, every changing look- on reading them over, I say, I am almost ashamed to see. how much space I have given to Maurice Forsythe. Well, if it had not been filled with him, I should   TWISTED THREADS.        71 have written of myself; and I know too much of Maud Elinor Lennox--being compelled, perforce, to carry her small identity, her insignificant personality, around with me, ever present, whether I will or no- to care to have her likeness and imprint staring at me from every page of this my " libellus."  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7635-00000036"/> CHAPTER IX. MSS LETTY. "AMARTINE-(being a French teacher, I am compelled to read the literature of that tongue; and his books being the least objectionable al- ways, of course, excepting the sickly sensibility that pervades them-I use them among my pupils)- says that in every one's history there is a silent ro- mance, unwritten and unread, often unguessed at. I have not come to the romance in my life" yet. But I often think that a novel-writer, one who ex- celled in delineation of character, would find ample material to work upon, and full employment for his pen, did he but spend a few days in this great house, of which I occupy a little chamber sous les toits. Few of the boarders hold as exalted a position as mine. So, if I chose, I might literally look down upon the pothers. I know very little of them, however. Out of the forty people who, for a certain sum every week, are provided by Mrs. Wilson with bed, board, and lodg- ing, there are only three or four with whom I have even a speaking acquaintance; only one whom I can call a friend: except Mrs. Wilson herself. I "   TWISTED THREADS.       73 really believe that good woman does take some in- terest in me. I had nearly forgotten, among my acquaintances in the establishment, the oldest of them all: by name, Miss Letitia Armstrong. She is a quaint little specimen of humanity; some- thing a la Miss Flite, as Dickens represents her, with short, wiry, gray curls, nodding and bobbing on either side of her face: said curls are usually sur- mounted by a- nondescript "cap"I call it-" head- dress," she would say-under which the little, stiff curls bob and dance with every movement of her head, in a most mirth-provoking way: a pair of small black-eyesthright and piercing, which look you through! and through, in spite of the glasses through which they peer; a mouth, which has been pretty; a neat, trim figure, which, summer or winter, is clad in black dresses, made in the style prevalent twenty years ago, when Miss Letty was younger than she is now- and short enough in front to show the small foot, raised from the ground in a very high-heeled shoe; hands always covered with lace mits; a white Shetland shawl, in delicate knitting, thrown over her shoulders:-such is Miss Letty Armstrong. She moves around, noiselessly as a cat, on those high-heeled shoes of hers: her voice in speaking, is shrill; her words come quickly; her ways are old-maidish-very much so. I got a peep, one day, into her room. People say she is rich. I know she is charitable-and not to herself Her room is as scantily furnished as any in 7  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7635-00000037"/> 74     TWTISTFD THREADS. the house. In one corner there is a huge cage, full of, canary birds, which chirp and sing and flutter in- cessantly, in a way which would nearly set me crazy, were I Miss Armstrong, and nervous; in another, a cushion, occupied by an immense Maltese cat: a large, sleek animal, reminding me, with its soft gray fur, of a magnified mouse. These constitute-her live- stock. I suppose that if she ever had had children of her own to pet and love, she would never have kept her cat and birds. For we women must have something to care for: and if one thing be denied us; we cling to another- as vines, which, deprived of their natural support, and unable to climb upward, cling to anything that comes within their reach. And perhaps, some,of these days, when, like Miss Letty Armstrong, I have the snows of fifty winters upon my head, I may pet my cat, and keep my canary birds. She and I have known each other now for more than a year -if a mere speaking acquaintance can / indeed be called " knowing each other." Lately, how- ever, since I have been so much with Bertha, it seems to me that Miss Letty has taken more notice of me than she ever did before. I sometimes think it is because she disapproves of the acquaintance. "D' ye think 't will do you any good," she said to me, as, not very long since, she and I walked home, under the same umbrella, from church. "There ain't much in common betwixt you and the fashionable woman : take care lest-you find yourself dropped."'   TWISTED THREADS.        75 "I think I can depend upon Bertha Steiner," I said, quietly. I was not going to take offence at Miss Armstrong's manner. " Do you ? I don't: that's the difference between uS." " What have you against her ? " I asked. "You poor little fly," she said, quickly; "has the candle so dazzled you that you will persist in singeing your wings ? Do you know Dr. Forsythe? " " Yes; Bertha has introduced her guardian to me." " Guardian and ward! All nonsense! Don't you get caught in the toils." "I can take care of myself, Miss Letty, thank you.'" "Now she is indignant. I could laugh at you, young lady, if I did not hate to see Mark Lennox's daughter playing with edged tools, and never seeing that they can cut." 'I looked at the prim little woman--prim, in spite of her water-proof covering, and the pelting rain through which we were walking- in surprise. " Did you know my father ?" "Did I know your father? Yes: and for that reason, whether or no, I will warn his daughter, though I see she does not thank me for the warning." And with that -we were by this time at our door -she frisked herself away, muttering to herself: " You 're a goose--an old gray goose, Letty Arm- strong ! The girl is nothing to you-let her 'gang her ain gate;' she '11 never thank you for it." I have tried, once or twice since, to induce her to &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7635-00000038"/> 76     TWISTED THREADS. tell me where she ever met my father; and why she objects to Bertha -,but uselessly. I cannot recollect ever hearing my father speak of her; though it would have been more surprising if I had, for he was unusually reticent, and I do not remember his ever speaking to me of his younger days. Perhaps he was connected with the romance of Miss Letty's youth : the days, far away now, when she was young and pretty -perhaps he was its hero. Who knows? And, for the mere possibility of this -an imagining of my own -that long ago, when Letty Armstrong's youth was bright, she may have loved my father; for this reason, I say, I, Mark Lennox's daughter, will let the lonely old woman say what she will to me--because I know so well what hze was." "Why should I avoid my new friend?"I said to Miss Letty, only this morning. "Let me go, child," very quickly. "Advice offered is never taken; advice asked for, never regarded- unless -" "Unless what?" "It coincides with our own wishes." "My wish is to do right," I said, wearily. "No, you don't; no, you don't. Let me go, Miss Lennox: I've no advice for you." "Will a physician's advice do, Miss Armstrong?" Dr. Forsythe's voice at that moment asked. "If it will, I am at your service." "Yours, even less than mine," Miss Letty snapped. "I only ask her to let some things alone."   TWISTED TzHREADS.       " He laughed. " An easy thing to do, you think ? " " The child is a coward," looking at me; "she is afraid of what would be for her own good." "Is Miss Lennox a coward? " inquiringly. "There is more courage, sometimes, in letting things alone, than there is in handling them;" and he passed on. "H-m! the man has wit. His advice, and mine, were it given, would be the same: let edged tools alone." " Meaning Bertha ?" "My cat is walting for his dinner, child;" and with this very irrelevant reply she went off, her short, quick steps beating a sort of tattoo with her high heels upon the oil-cloth of the passage--a tap-tap whichf I heard even after I lost sight of her. I knew, from that, she was not pleased. Brisk as she always is in all her movements, those same little feet carry her around softly. " More courage in letting things alone," Dr. For- sythe said, as he passed. Ah! there is more truth than poetry in those words. Waiting requires more courage than action; silence than speech; abstinence than indulgence. Would it be brave in me to give up my chief pleas- ure? and why? Because Miss Letty Armstrong, with her musty old proverbs and her old-maid's no- tions, thinks it may do me harm. It is very true that I used to live without it, once upon a time; but after drinking, in a dry land, of the cool, living, shaded spring, wilt any one go back,&#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7635-00000039"/> 78     T WIS TED TIIREA DS. willingly, to the sun-hot, stagnant waters of the pond? I do not think that any of us willingly put affec- tion-the affection of a friend--from us. Yet, if needs were, if it could do her any good, or add to her happiness, I think I could give up anything-- could go away from her--could go through fire and water for her - my friend. Or, if I ever should come, unknowingly, between her and something she ardently desired to possess, so soon as I should learn that I was an unconscious obstacle, I would, let it cost me what it might, stantl aside and let her hand, not mine, clasp the prize. But though I might do this for her, I cannot give up the, one great pleasure of my life. I have just remembered that this is my birthday. Twenty-three years old to-day- not many years to have lived. I have called myself twenty-three for a month past, so that, when the reality should come, I might be all ready for it--might under- stand that "another milestone on life's journey" was passed. It seems to me that those same milestones come very often now-that the distances between them shorten every year-that a year passes away more rapidly than a month did in my childhood. At home, in -Lynn, this used to be one of the family feast-days. I like that custom of keeping anniversaries - days sacred to the family. We kept four--my father's   TWISTED THREADS.       79 and mother's wedding-day, their birthdays, and mine. I do not keep them now. My father used to tell me, when every year this day came round, that I should make some good resolution for the coming twelvemonth; or else, lay aside some besetting habit, some fault which needed cure. What resolution shall I make to- night--what toll shall I lay down? I will make no resolution --give no toll. There is nothing, that I can see, to give up in my life-- my life that is made up of Mondays, Tuesdays, Wednesdays-- working-days - days all alike, one unvarying round, in which, were I to tell the story of one day, I would tell the story of a year. Miss Letty would tell me what I might give up. But I WILL NOT do it. Does the sunbeam hurt the flower? showers the parched earth? As well tell the prisoner in his dungeon to shut out, willingly, the one bright ray of sunshine which may creep in, through ever so small a crevice, to tell him that somewhere, away from the four stone walls which shut him in, there are blue skies, green trees, rippling waters, sunlight and moonlight: that though he may not see them, they yet exist. Will he, of his own free will, shut his ears to this little message Mother Nature sends him along the sunbeam ? will he shut out the bright ray which bears it? Need I ask the question? It brings its own answer: our enjoyments and pleas- ures in this world are so " few and far between," that we hold on to those which fall to our share.  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7635-00000040"/> 80      TTWISTED  THREADS. I used, when I was young, (and yet twenty-three is not old;) I used, then, when this birthday of mine came round-the beginning of a new year to me, the turning of a new leaf in Life's volume- to sit and wonder what the ensuing days and weeks and months, which one by one go to make up the sheaf of Time--the measure of space which we call a year--would bring me: what events would inscribe themselves on the blank page before me; even, as now, I sometimes idly sit and wonder if anything out of the common run will ever be writ- ten on the fair paper of this my little evening friend. If I could only do something wonderful, something to make my name famous; if only something would come into my life so that it need not be matter-of- fact, prosaic, and commonplace! Such marvellous castles in the'air as I built in those days, gorgeous rainbow palaces, all couleuzr de rose, as fleeting, yet as bright as the glorious clouds amid which the sun sinks 'neath the western horizon: chateaux en Espagne that every young girl builds though I believe that I carried that aerial architecture farther than most of my sex --in the days when, "In the old, familiar homestead Many, many years ago, Sat I, musing in the twilight, As all maidens will, you know; And the day's last, lingering glances Fell on all the prospect fair: What cared I for aught around me, Building castles in the air? "June's soft breezes kiss'd my cheek- Earth had donn'd her richest green i   TWISTED   THREADS.         8I Soon the moon her silv'ry lustre Shed o'er all the lovely scene. And the air was full of odors- Breath of roses everywhere: What cared I for all this beauty, Building castles in the air? "Ah! full well do I remember How, beneath the soft June skies, I looked on into the' future-- Fair it seemed to youthful eyes; Not a shadow dimm'd its sunshine, Not a thought of grief nor care: Life seem'd very bright before me - Building castles in the air!" I do not build castles in the air now--no, that is not exactly true; for while then I used to wish for wealth, fame, and distinction, I now wish for what seems to me even more unattainable --things which, to most women, come as The daily round, the common task"- love, home, home duties and cares. These are the fairy-gifts I ask for now, gifts which each succeed- ing birthday, each, recurring year seems to 'place farther away from me. And yet, I do not say this repiningly; it is only that I try to look facts in the face, and meet them unshrinkingly. But, upon the whole, I am not sorry that this birthday of mine is over, this anniversary upon which 'no one has given me even the usual "Many happy returns of the day."  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7635-00000041"/> CHAPTER X. ENIGMATICAL. TMV/ ISS LETTY stopped by me again, a few even- ings since, as, at Bertha's request, I waited for her for a moment on the landing. She is a regular fairy god-mother, with her quick, bruzsque move- ments, her airy ways, her nodding curls. She only needs a wand to complete the picture. And she watches over me (as she thinks, without my knowl- edge,) exactly as said fabulous personages are re- ported to have watched over the mortals to whom they stood in sponsorial relation. A  question, for theologians here suggests itself: Did the fairies believe in Christianity, that they an- swered for mortal babies? I had drawn a little into the corner of the land- ing, to avoid being jostled by the people who pass continually up and down the staircase, when, as I stood half in the shadow, I felt a hand on my shoulder, and, turning in expectation of seeing Ber- tha, there were Miss Letty's black eyes peering into mine. "Who are you waiting for here, child? Not, surely, for me?" "No," I   said quietly, "I am waiting for Miss Steiner." 82   TWISTED -THREADS.       83 "So she's not tired of you yet, though she has a new plaything, in the shape- of Allyn Bernard! I wonder Dr. Forsythe does not put a stop to that flirtation. She must play her cards well." "Miss Armstrong, do you remember she is my friend?" "Pooh! child; you don't know who your real friends are." I made no reply - I was a little provoked; and it was with real relief that I saw Bertha approach me at that moment. "I hope I have not kept you waiting, Maud," she said gayly; "I came just as soon as I could get away. Miss Letty, will not you join us in my parlor?" "You will please excuse me." "I suppose I must not press you- -that would scarcely be polite; but you will pardon me if I take Maud away." "If she can pardon herself." Bertha's eyes dilated. "I am speaking in riddles to you, Miss Steiner; but this child "-her hand on my shoulder - " un- derstands me. Howheit, there is' no putting 'old heads on young shoulders.'" "What comical figures we would present under those circumstances!"I said, smiling. "I would rather retain my present appearance." "So should I," Bertha said, lightly. "Miss Letty-" But Miss Letty was gone; and we two stood there and looked at each other--only for a mo- ,  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7635-00000042"/> 84     TWISTED THREADS. ment; and Bertha turned and looked after Miss Armstrong's receding figure, as she went out of the front door into the fast-coming night, Then, for the first time, I noticed that the trim, upright figure was wrapped in a shawl, the gray curls covered by a hood. "That woman's energy puts us to shame, Maud," Bertha said. "She does more good in one week than either you or I would do in a year; and some- thing of herself-force of will, or brain-work- goes into everything she does. Last night she sat up with a sick child in the house-to-night she will do the same thing for a poor woman." -"How do you know that?"I asked. "Through Maurice. She is a friend of his, but she does not like me. What was she saying to yougas' I came up?"     ' "I had rather not say," very awkwardly. "I can easily guess. A repetition of what she said to me, only a day or so since: that our inter- course-she did not say friendship-was far from beneficial to you. I see I am right." "She is very plain-spoken." "Very; she does not hesitate to speak her mind. I tried to reassure her concerning you, Maud: tried to make her believe that we could only do each other good; but, as it seems, uselessly. Why is it that she takes so much interest in you? Are you a rela- tive, or is there any special tie between you?" "We are not related," I said; "nor did I ever meet her, or hear of her, till I came to this house." I   T WISTED THRERA DS.      85 could not tell Bertha-I could not tell any one-- of my little romance about Miss Letty, all growing out of her one mention of my father's name. I had no foundation for it: and yet it satisfactorily ex- plained to me the evident interest the lonely woman took in me; and if some strange intuition had led mee if by some accident I had guessed at the truth, it was not for me to disclose, even to such a friend as Bertha, Miss Letty's treasured secret: and if it were only an imagining of my own, raison de plus why I should be silent. Yet I was very glad that at this moment we reached the door of Bertha's par- lor, so that she need not question me any longer: very glad that as we entered the cheerful room, bright with the red bed of coals filling the grate, whose reflections crimsoned the walls in spite of the light from the gaselier, that Mr. Bernard ad- vanced to us; and, bringing us chairs, seated him- self very quietly, and began to talk to us. I knew then that I was safe -that Miss Letty's surveillance of me would not be discussed any longer that evening. It was my turn to watch now. I wanted to see for myself if it were possible that Miss Letty was right: if Bertha and Mr. Bernard were really on as intimate terms as her words had seemed to imply. I hoped they were, not: it would havebeen nothing to me if the admiration had all, been on the gentle- man's side- it would have seemed only right and proper that she should win love; but I could not bear that the girl I so loved and admired should be 8  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7635-00000043"/> 86     TW -ISTED THREADS. guilty of flirting. I knew little of Mr. Bernard- our intercourse had always been limited to a few courteous remarks; his manner was gentlemanly; his language well-chosen and refined: beyond that I knew nothing; he was handsome, not the style, however, which best pleased me: though one would have thought that with my dark eyes and hair I would have most admired the Saxon type of beauty; on the principle, I suppose, that our opposites attract us. Nothing would have induced me to say a word to Bertha upon the subject. I would watch them, and draw my own conclusions. But all my inten- tionswere frustrated--all my plans came to naught. Ah! it-is so too often, in this life of ours: this life in which we go along blindly, unknowingly; we are influenced by circumstances which force themselves upon us. We are led by persons, who, whether we will or no, control us: into our lives come thoughts, words, and actions which we never anticipated. The future shapes itself against our will: we are but puppets in the hands of Destiny. And so all my plans for this evening failed-like some of "the best-laid plans of mice and men; " only in this case the men, or rather a man, frustrated- I hope; unintentionally--the deep-laid plan of the mouse. I was going to retreat to my corner and use my eyes. Circumstances seemed to favor me at first- our trio had the parlor to ourselves-when in came Dr. Forsythe. If he only had stayed away!   TWISTED THREADS.       87 If! such a little word as it is; and yet who can say how much it'implies; how much ground it covers; how many events in this life of ours are shaped or might be shaped differently by an "if"? It is a very large word then. But so many of the most expres- sive words in our English tongue are little ones- words which come easily-are quickly spoken: yet they- mean volumes. I said I wished that he had stayed away. I did want to see for myself what I would not ask; to let my eyes discern what my tongue was too cowardly to inquire. Yet it wa's scarcely cowardice, either; it was only that I would not ask of Bertha the in- formation she .had not voluntarily given. And then, too, I was aware of a certain uneasiness, a vague discomfort, which comes over me when in Dr. For- sythe's presence. He does not often speak to me, it is true; yet I know, through some peculiar intui- tion, whenever his eyes are upon me--those deep, serious gray eyes of his, which have a way of look- ing you through and through--till I feel as though he were reading my inmost thoughts, and thinking to himself what an insign ificant little creature this friend of Bertha Steiners is. I can imagine, with that strong will of his;-so evident in every thing, even in his slightest movement--how he could influ- ence and control any one over whom he might choose to exert that peculiar power some people have over others; the power best described in the answer the French queen, accused by some of sor- cery, gave to her accusers: "The only sorcery I  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7635-00000044"/> 81     TWIISTED THREADS. have used is the power of a strong mind, the force of a strong will over a weak one." It must be grand to have a will like that-with its usual concomitants, resolution and firmness, which, when added to ambition and ability, win their possessors reputation and position. It is something of this strong will of Dr. For- sythe's which, exercising, in all probability, uncon- sciously to himself, an influence over me, makes. me, when he chooses to single me out, talk to him, quietly retaining my seat, when, often, I had far rather avoid him, and be silent. But this evening, although I was not to be al- lowed to sit in my corner and look on at the little social drama which, as Miss Letty thinks, is being enacted before me, I was to carry away with me words which have haunted me ever since--they seem so inexplicable. But, then, the whole conversation was an odd one -all my conversations with Dr. Forsythe are odd ones, on queer topics, such, I should think, as are not usually discussed in society: though, truly, I know so very little of society that I ought not to say what is or is not done in it. It had begun by Bertha's asking me why I was so distraite this evening. I wish I could get rid of this habit of mine- though in this case I have only used Bertha's own words--when I am at a loss for an English word to express my meaning, of substituting for it the French equivalent. But when, every day, for six   TWISTED THREA DS.       89 mortal hours, you only hear the incessant chatter of many tongues in that language-English not being allowed in school hours-the expressive French idioms will linger with you; anrid as I study every day-as every faithful teacher, who desires the- improvement and advancement of her pupils, must: for if the fountain flow perpetually, with no influx to replenish its waters, it will soon run dry- every day I become more and more familiar with the language, till at times I even find myself think- ing in it. I don't like to do it, however. After school is over, and my studies ended, I like to put away that part of my life altogether-to separate Miss Len- nox, the teacher, from Maud Lennox, Bertha Stei- ner's friend, who does not care to carry the work- day part of her life into her few hours of recrea- tion. "Miss Lennox is absent"- (Dr. Forsythe is particular in always using his mother-tongue, so that when I am with him, and by chance allow one of my pet words to slip out, I invariably feel as though his nervous, vigorous English was a tacit rebuke to me) -"Miss Lennox is absent to-night. To all appearance she is sitting here, but her thoughts are wandering." "Not very far, I hope," "Bertha said. "It would not be very complimentary to us." "Are we responsible for our thoughts?"I asked, carelessly. "It seems to me enough that we are accountable for our spoken words, without our be- 8*  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7635-00000045"/> 90     TWISTED TIREADS. ing made to answer for the thoughts which come, unbidden, into our minds." "Do they always corne unbidden?" Mr. Bernard questioned. "It seems to me that we can encour- age certaintrains of thought until they come to be ever present in our minds, so that we cannot, if we would, escape from them." "And there is nothing, that I can think of," Ber- tha said, "more disagreeable, than to have one thought haunt you, day and night, to the exclusion of all others -one idea, which, whether you like it or no, forces itself continually upon you, till, at times, you vainly wish that your mind, weary of the continued strain upon it, would cease to think." "Miss Lennox's thoughts were not of that nature, I am sure," Dr. Forsythe observed, "or else her countenance belied her." "Maud's tell-tale face!"Bertha said, gayly. "Don't blush about it, child; it is not a face you need be ashamed of." "It should not tell tales on its mistress," I said, as, knowing that the eyes of the others were bent upon me,'I felt the ready blood rush over cheek and brow; "it ought to be hid under a mask." Dr. Forsythe laughed, cynically. "I never yet saw a woman who did not hide her natural countenance under a mask." "You give the ladies a poor character," Mr. Ber- nard said. "Miss Steiner - Miss Lennox, have neither of you a word to say in defence of your sex?"   TWzISTED THREADS.      9x Dr. Forsythe resumed before either of us could answer: "Don't you know that all women are born act- resses? Lip and look are under their control: the lip smiles, the tongue flatters, while their owner at heart feels that the smile and the words are alike untrue. Bernard, if you trust a woman's words- much less her face -your credulity will be greatly -tried." "Maurice, for shame!"Bertha exclaimed. "You know you do not mean what you say: you know that no one has a higher regard for true woman- hood than yourself." "For :true womanhood--yes! for the hideous mockery of it which your sex of late years have set up for our admiration-no! Instead of the pure- minded, true-hearted, modest girls--the unselfish, womanly matrons who were once the boast of the Anglo-Saxon race--women who were a help, not a hinderalce to us--what do you find now? Young girls who give up, as something out of date, the delicacy and refinement which are their truest orna- ments-women who, forgetful of what is due them- selves, unsex themselves, without gaining anything in return--wives and mothers who neglect the true sphere of woman, the family. Against true womanhood, Bertha, I have not one word to say; against those of whom I have spoken, I lift my voice, as does every right-thinking man. Miss Len- nox, you agree with me--you, I know, are no ad- vocate of the so-called 'rights of women.'"  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7635-00000046"/> 92     TWISTED THREADS. "Only so far," I said, "as they are expressed in the language of one of our prominent women: that 'our rights are comprised in two brief words- Home and Peace.'" "Those are your truest, noblest rights, Miss Len- nox." , Mr. Bernard said, with a pleased smile, "'You ladies have the supremacy at home; and if we de- sire to limit you to that kingdom, it is that we prize you too highly to desire that you should meet the world as we do: we wish to keep our treasures to ourselves." "Some of your 'treasures,"' Bertha said, gayly, "are not contented with the sphere you assign them." "More's the pity,'"Dr. Forsythe went on. "Wom- en do not, or will not see that they only harm themselves by the endeavor to throw off the re- straints which the good of society and public opin- ion have laid upon them: it destroys their power. A  true woman, one who is never forgetful of her womanhood and of what is due herself, will do more for her sisters, through the influence of femi- nine delicacy and modesty, by her silent example, than all the efforts of the advocates of the so-called rights of women. The latter only bring discredit upon the sex." I said, quietly, "It is scarcely fair to blame the many for the errors of the few." "You are always indulgent to my  errors, Mau-   TWISTED THREADS.        93 rice," Bertha said, smilingly; and so her part in the conversation ended. Dr. Forsythe remained with me: the other two went to the piano. At last-- "Do you never rebel against the restrictions soci- ety lays upon you?" I looked up, in surprise. ' Nothey are our great- est safeguards." "Do you never envy us our liberty?" I shook my head.  "There are restrictions upon you, as well as upon us."   f He looked at me questioningly. "You aie right, Miss Lennox: honor and conscience are stronger bonds than any the world can lay upon us -bind- ing alike on man and woman." "There is no excuse for breaking them." "You need not tell me that, Miss Lennox; I re- peat it to myself daily." His tone was bitter-so bitter, that I raised my eyes to his in surprise. He was very pale; yet, before H fearing that by my words, unintentionally spoken, I had given offence-could apologize, he rose to his feet, and, looking down upon-me, his lips, under his mustache, set firmly together, he went on: ^"If it were not for those bonds, invisible, yet strong, do you know what I would do? I would go and say to one-the woman of all women for me--- ' Here, by God's rood, is the one maid for me: Here, by God's grace, is the one voice for me.'  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7635-00000047"/> "    'TWISTED THREADS. It would be a poetical wooing, Miss Lennox," with a bitter laugh, "yet none the less true. But I dare not." "True moral courage--obedience to honor," I said, scarcely knowing what answer to make to this singular speech. "True moral humbug!" very bitterly. "I beg your pardon, Miss Lennox; I had no right to show your quiet eyes (they are full of wonder now) the rebellious thoughts of my mind. Forget them, if you please -they were spoken unawares. We men are fools," he added, under- his breath, as he turned to leave me; but my quick ear caught the words, "We make resolutions, and a woman's smile-the smile she gives to all-makes us break them: a little apparent, unmeaning sympathy, and we speak words which we never cease to regret." Ah! but how many of us do that unthinkingly! how many of us, by our careless words, forgotten as soon as uttered, send a dart to the hearts of others, there to rankle and give pain- -pain which we never dreamed of inflicting! It seems very odd to me that Dr. Forsythe, calm and self-possessed as he generally is, should have spoken thus to me-in words as inexplicable to me as iis their motive, for I understand neither: only it seems to me, that, with everything in his favor, Bertha's guardian might woo and win any one who came up to his ideal of true womanhood. Unless, indeed, there were something which made him feel himself unworthy.   TWISTED THREADS.       95 I wish he had not said anything to me. But he might have spared himself, and me, that implied request for silence - he might have known me better. As if I would betray any one's confi- dence, even though it were placed in me uninten- tionally, and against my wishes! and I have never sought conversation with Dr. Forsythe. And, after all, he knows but little of me. But, of course, I shall never repeat our conversa- tion. Writing it here, in my " libellus," is no more than keeping it in my mind; for these pages are my- self, and, being myself, no eye, save my own, shall ever rest upon them; for they would be no pleasure to me, did others read them: they would cease to be mine - the one thing in this wide world which is wholly my own-in which none beside have share or part. I read somewhere, not long since: "The pleasantest things in the world are pleas- ant thoughts, and the greatest art in life is to have as many of them as possible." So, as my mind and my " libellus " are my king- dom, I am selfish, and want to reign there alone, and keep my thoughts to myself. /  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7635-00000048"/> CHAPTER XI. OFFERS OF SERVICE.  ERTHA has seemed worried, of late. I could almost imagine that there was something preying upon her mind, for she is pale; yet, when I ask her if anything ails her, she only laughs, and tells' me I am imaginative--that no one can in- dulge in gayety as she does without paying for it in some way. I suppose this is partly true; yet I am sure that there is something more than this -what, I cannot say, and it is not likely she will ever tell me; for, even to our nearest, dearest friends, there are things of which we do not care to speak -things which we keep to ourselves. They may be pleasures on which we dwell, sacred to ourselves, which would cease to be pleasures did any one else guess at them. They may be enemies-mental enemies, only known to ourselves, for we are sometimes our own worst enemies-with whom we struggle in secret, fighting a battle of which no one is aware save our own selves; for there are battles fought and victories won on .6ther than terrestrial battle-fields. There are agonies, silent martyrdoms, at which the world never guesses. Each has his cross to bear, 96   TWISTED THREADS.       97 whether others know it or- know it not; and often --even as mental pain is harder to bear than is physical suffering--our own feelings may prove our heaviest cross. Bertha and I were talking of this, not many days since. ' I do not like to dwell upon my own feelings, Maud--analyzing them  always reminds me of Kingsley's words: that 'feelings are like chemicals; the more you stir them up the worse they smell.' They won't bear examination, either. Under their external calm there are so many conflicting ele- ments, that one cannot look under the surface- the fair outside which we show society-without growing disgusted with ourselves." "Ay, that is what makes actresses of us." "Yes, Maurice was right there: we desire to appear as well as we can." "Are we ever satisfied with ourselves?"I asked her. "Is it human nature to be content?" she said, more bitterly than I had ever heard her speak. "Maud, most persons, looking at us, would say my lot, of the two, was the most enviable; yet I would, at this moment, gladly change places with your. I looked at her in surprise. She went on, a moment later: S"If I only could escape from myself! Well, I need not wish for the impossible. Did you know I was going away with Mrs. Bernard next week?" 9  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7635-00000049"/> 98     TWISTED THREADS. "I shall miss you terribly; " and the words came from my heart. Bertha bent over and kissed me. "I shall miss you as much. We have only known one another two months, Maud; can you realize it?" ( Hardly." "I must take you sleighing before I go, if such a thing be practicable. Mr. Bernard will act as our cavalier; and when I go away, I shall commission Maurice to take the same care of you that I do." "He will scarcely thank you for the charge." "He will not let it be a charge." I was --silent --there was no use in my telling Bertha that for the past few days Dr. Forsythe has avoided me as much as he can do consistently with politeness. I do not like to think how very lonely I shall be when she goes - how completely I shall be thrown, once more, upon my own resources -how terribly I shall miss this one congenial companionship which. has come into my life. "Sufficient unto the day " - 1 will not think of "the evil thereof" till it comes; and when it does come, I must e'en try to be content; which resolution reminds me of something Dr. For- sythe, not many days since, said to me: " that the discontent we felt at our surroundings was often a blessing in disguise, for without it we should be satisfied to plod along in the same unvarying rou- tine, never trying to raise ourselves, but living in dull stagnation; while to it we owed the improve- ments we daily witness in the arts and sciences,   TWISTED THREADS.       99 the progress the world is daily making, and the gradual amelioration of the human race." I believe there is a good deal of truth in it; for no sooner do we become discontented with our sur- roundings, than we try to improve them. And it was something, 'I suppose, of this spirit, which, making me feel dissatisfied with the aimless, selfish life I am leading --a life only for myself, doing good to no one-this morning, after my teaching was over, carried me to Miss Letty's door, and brought on the conversation following. I tapped at the door, very gently, yet not so gently but that Miss Letty heard me, and called- she did not open it for me --to " come in!" Which I accordingly did-to be rushed at by the Maltese cat, evidently unaccustomed to having his mistress' sanctum invaded by outsiders-and to be nearly deafened by the shrill singing of the canaries. "Be quiet, Tom!" stopped the cat, and sent him to his cushion, where he lay, blinking at me, and moving his tail slowly to and fro like a gray snake, while a shawl thrown over the cage silenced the birds; and then Miss Letty, pulling her glasses- which had been pushed up on her forehead--to their proper resting-place, her little stiff durls nod- ding and bobbing in her haste, turned to inspect her visitor. "Why, it's Maud Lennox!--come to see the old maid! Of course you want me to do something for you, child: old maids are only put'in this world to  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7635-00000050"/> 100     TWISTED THREA DS. make themselves useful, and to pick up other folks' burdens - it is not likely anything else would have brought you here." I laughed, in spite of myself, at her comical tone. "You've no call to laugh at me, that I can see, child. I'm an old maid-a peculiar one, too; and what's more, I know it, and own up to it. There's nothing like telling the truth; and if you laugh at your own eccentricities, people will be less apt to laugh at you. There's consolation in thinking they laugh with you." "I don't appreciate being laughed at," I said, as soon as I could control my voice. "Very few people do," very quickly. "If others amuse us, it ain't gratifying to ourselves if we amuse them.  None of us are anxious to see ourselves through other folks' glasses." "I think it's as well we can't 'See oursels as others see us.' " "I wonder what you see in me to-day," peering at me with her sharp black eyes. "You wanted something--out with it, and in as few words as possible., 'Least said, soonest mended.' " She brought her hand down on her knee em- phatically, as she spoke., Miss Letty uses a great deal of gesticulation when she speaks; and Tom evidently considering this an invitation to him, got up from his cushion, and, jump!ng into his mistress' lap, curled himself there very composedly. Two hundred years ago," Miss Letty went on. "had I lived in Salem, it is probable that Tom and   TWISTED THREADS.       101 I would have been burned at the stake," stroking the cat, who purred an accompaniment to her words. "Now, the worst that people can say of me is, that I am odd. You have not yet told me what you wanted." "It is something in which you can help me, Miss Letty," I said, quietly. "I am tired of being such a useless individual, and I have come to ask you if, in any way, my experience in teaching can be made of any assistance toyou." "Are you really in earnest?" very cordially. "Indeed I am." "There is work enough, and more than enough. I am glad you are willing to take your share of it, Maud Lennox." "I hope I shall never fail to do my duty, Miss Letty.".  . "Easily said, less easily done. I, can give you plenty to do. When can you begin?" "Whenever you need me." "Well," her curls nodding, "I can give you your choice of two places -at the Mission, or at the Hos- pital. At one, you could have a Bible-class-the only one vacant, by the way; at the other, you would have chiefly to read to the patients." "I think I would rather take the latter." I was wholly unprepared for the effect of my words. Miss Letty jumped- from her chair, dropping the cat, and, coming to me, took my face into her hands, and looked straight into my eyes. 9*  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7635-00000051"/> 102     TWISTD TIIREA-DS. "You will tell me the truth?" I spoke a little angrily: "No one ever asked me that question before." "It is a truthful face," she muttered, half to her- self; "she. would not be a Lennox were she false; it is a good face, too--not pretty, not fair, but I think I can trust the child's word. Did you know," ab- ruptly, "that Maurice Forsythe sometimes comes to the Hospital-is it the wish to meet him that has made you select it?" I released myself--hurt at her tone. "Miss Letty! how can you! Till this moment I did not know that Dr. Forsythe ever practiced .his profession, much less that he ever engaged in such work." She smiled, not discontentedly. "Tut, child! you need not get indignant; you must not mind what I say: my bark is worse than my bite. Dr. Forsythe does not practice his profession. He comes to the Hospital at my request, to look after one or two proteg's of mine, who I thought needed other advice than that the City Physician could give. You and he need not come into'contact." "I am not afraid of him, Miss Letty." "Then you shall go with me on Sunday. Come and sit with me sometimes, Maud Lennox, if you are lot afraid of the old maid, her cat and birds. Friends, you will find, are scarce articles in this world--hold on to them when you have them; and I am disposed to be your friend." I thanked her, and came away. Miss Letty is a queer genius. She reminds me of   TWI STED THREA D S.      I03 a chestnut burr, all harsh, prickly, and forbidding without; within, there is satin smoothness, and sweet, nutritious meat. Like many other people,. she shows her worst side to the world: few give her credit for the real kindness of heart actuating her, and the many little kindnesses "( Which most leave undone, or despise," she does; though unfortunately these little kind- nesses are done in such a way that you see Miss Lety is ashamed of doing them; and indeed, you only recognize them as kindnesses when it is too late to thank her for them. It is not often that people try so hard to show their worst side to the world. But I am sorry Miss Letty should have thought, even for a moment, that in my selection of the Hos- pital I had any reference to Dr. Forsythe -a man whom I am only too willing to avoid. And I am glad she said nothing about Bertha. What a recrea- tion to me that promised sleigh-ride will be! If only the snow will come in time! To-night the sky is clear, unclouded, and starry; the air, though cold, is still; it does not look as if there would be a change of weather. But in this uncertain winter-climate of ours, an hour is sometimes enough to produce a change, and by morning the heavens may be hidden by the soft gray cloud-masses, from which the snow, noiselessly and gently, will descend, flake by flake, to cover the earth. And I hope that it will come.  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7635-00000052"/> CHAPTER XII. WHAT A RIDE COST. I T is some little time since I have used my pen- some ten days since I have written a line in this little book of mine: and yet those ten days have contained within their limits more incident than has been inscribed in all the preceding pages. For, sometimes, one day may be like a year--on so many events in one life does the sun, between its rising and its setting, look; and then, in contrast, there may be long intervals of calm, unruffled and unmarked, when all that one can say is, "I have lived." And yet, those words may and do contain volumes. I am glad that the past ten days are over; they have taught me that uneventful days are the happiest; that those epochs which have, as children would say, a story in them, are not always the pleasantest to live through. There is such a thing as the misery of a granted prayer; an expression which lingers in my mind, as some words do, and although it may seem scarcely applicable to the present case, I cannot help using it, for out of the snow-storm I so anxiously looked for came all the rush and event I shall try to describe. 10o   TWISTED THREADS.       o10 The pleasure I promised myself proved, in the end, false pleasure: as some waters, eagerly desired in our thirst, prove, when attained, bitter to the taste--waters of Marah, that we hurriedly reject: and as some fruits, fair to outward seeming, are as gall and ashes within. The snow, for which I had so impatiently waited, came at last. Over the starry sky, that night - all unseen by the sleeping city: only noticed by the few to whom the darkness brought no repose, to whom, keeping watch, some over earthly treasures, some over frail and suffering humanity, "nature's sweet consoler " might not come - slowly gathered the clouds which would send tribute to the earth, either in the dull, dreary winter-rain, or else in the' soft, feathery crystals of the snow. One by one, slowly and gently, then faster, larger, down came the flying flakes, till, their mission accomplished, their "fiulness" bestowed--even as they had gath- ered, the clouds passed away, and the sun rose to look upon a city decked, as a bride, in white rai- ment. I was so glad, when I rose that bright morning, to know that it was Saturday, the one morning in the week in which I am not bound down to Ma- dame Levere, and the "j'ai, tu as, il a" of the younger classes. Bertha came to my room in high spirits. "Make yourself pretty, Maud -just as pretty as you can. Everything is in our favor-a bright sun, a clear day, and first-rate sleighing; and Mr. Ber-  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7635-00000053"/> 106     T WISTED THfREA DS. nard has just sent me word that he will call for us in half an hour." "I wish I could make myself pretty--as much to please myself as to please you," I said, gayly, as I turned to the glass to smooth my hair. "You are not going about it in the right way," Bertha laughed, as she watched my efforts to smooth the rebellious waves and confine the unruly curls into which my hair will twist itself. "Let me play lady's-maid for once, Maud: let me see what I can do for you." She pulled me, playfully, away from the glass, and, seating me in a chair, bade me look out of the window. Then her deft fingers, loosening my hair from its heavy plaits, began to arrange it in a more fashionable style. "Look at yourself now, Maud," she said, at last, "and then wonder at yourself for concealing, as you try to do, the crowning beauty of a woman's head, her wealth of hair." She had indeed changed my appearance com- pletely. Instead of the compact braids which had covered my head, the soft hair was now coiled in wavy masses, with light, airy curls falling over the knot, something in the style you see in antique statues. "I have not done with you," she went on. "You are pleased with the effect, I see; but I have not finished dressing my doll for her ride. Come to my room, Maud. You may as well be a good girl, and obey me unquestioningly."   TWISTED THREADS.       107 It was so very pleasant for me to feel that there was some one who cared if I looked well or. not, that I followed Bertha, and let her do with me as she would. I knew her good taste could be relied upon--'her own costume is always becoming and comme ilfaut. "You must not object to one scrap of color, as I made this for you," Bertha said, as she placed on my head a delicately knitted combination of soft, fleecy white zephyr, with one scarlet bow trembling in its whiteness. "You will wear it for my sake." And I did not object; and--I may as well own up to the feminine weakness - Bertha's handiwork in the little hood and in my coiffure were decidedly becoming; and we women- deny it as we may- take a pardonable pleasure in looking well. With us, beauty is power. And though I do not possess the gift myself, I can see what it must be to those to whose share and heritage it has fallen to be "a joy forever." A man will pardon a woman, for the sake of her beauty, follies and imperfections which, in an ugly woman, are never forgotten. By the time we were wrapped in shawls and furs, a waiter came to the door to say that Mr. Bernard was ready for' us.  So down we went, to find the gentleman in ques- tion standing on the door-step, while waiting for us was a'beautiful sleigh, drawn -by two magnifi- cent specimens of horse-flesh -a pair of perfectly matched' bays, each wifh a white star on his fore-  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7635-00000054"/> I08     TWISTED THREARDS. head, their coats smooth and shining as satin, their flowing manes and tails soft and glossy, their small, beautifully shaped heads telling of good blood, and in every line of the body, every motion, showing strength, and promising the swiftness for which Mr. Bernard's horses are renowned, and which makes a seat behind them something to be sought after and intrigued for. I have not said it before, but Allyn Bernard has an enviable position in New York so- ciety. He helped me, first, into the sleigh; and as I set- tled myself among the soft, warm buffalo-robes, whose wearers once careered freely, in all the strength of animal life. over our broad Western prairies, he turned to perform the same office for Bertha. And as his hand closed on hers, I heard him-I have said I have a cat's power of hearing --whisper, close to her ear: "Fair as the morn!" And when she took her seat by my side, there was a faint, rosy flush upon her fair cheek, heighten- ing her blonde beauty: she has, generally, no color, but this delicate tint was like a sunset glow on pure marble; a soft, tremulous light in the black eyes, which made me wonder if Bertha Steiner really cared that Allyn Bernard should deem her fair, and if her beautiful toilette had been made '/--glad to find 'herself' so fair, And thinking, This will please him best,' She takes a riband or a rose; For he will see them on-"   TWISTED THREA DS.       log But I drove all thought of sentiment away in a moment, as the rapid motion in the clear, frosty air- the bright sunshine flashing and sparkling every- where--the many vehicles, full of richly-dressed women and gallant men, all like ourselves, enjoying the sleighing, combined to make our trio as gay a party as were out that morning. And as nothing lasts, whether it be pleasant or painful, in this world of ours-this stage, on which we are the actors--so this pleasant morning, with its bracing air, its cloudless sunshine, its bright, witty talk--which I will not repeat here, for much of what is called conversation, owing half its charm to manner and expression, loses it when imprisoned by pen and ink on paper--its rapid, exhilarating mo- tion, came, like all things, to an end, and we were all sorry when the time came for the sleigh to stop once more at Mrs. Wilson's door. I little thought what was to come of this sleigh- ride for me; how, for one morning's pleasure, I was to pay with weeks of pain--a fearful penalty for such a brief enjoyment. Bertha had gotten out of the sleigh, and awaited me on the pavement; I had just extricated myself from the warm nest of furs in which I had been so cosily nestled, and was about to avail myself of Mr. Bernard's proffered assistance, when the horses started at some passing vehicle, and I, standing in the sleigh, unprepared for the unex- pected motion, was thrown on the pavement. Mr. Bernaid caught me, as I fell, in time to save my head from striking the curb, but not in time to  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7635-00000055"/> "O T^ FW IS TED THR EA D S. prevent me from injuring my- ankle-my whole weight coming upon it so severely, that I fainted with the intense, agonizing pain, and at first they could not tell if the bone were broken, or the limb only severely sprained. But my unconsciousness only lasted for a mo- ment: the pain I suffered soon recalled me to my- self, and I recovered my senses just in time to hear Mr. Bernard say to Dr. Forsythe, who had just made his appearance upon the scene: "Will you carry Miss Lennox to her room, For- sythe, while I go for a doctor? Miss Steiner, you will show him the way;" and transferring me, as he would have done a child, to Dr. Forsythe's arms, he was off in a moment. Now this being carried, like a baby, whether I would or no, was something I did not like, and I made some little effort to release myself. "You may as well make a virtue of necessity, Miss Lennox," I was quietly told. "You can't walk, thanks to those horses"-there was an expletive before "horses," which I omit-"you must submit to circumstances.'" Bertha led the way to my room: she would have taken me to her own, but to that I objected; but before we got there, the pain again overcame me. I may have .dreamed it, but I surely heard, as I came to, my bearer murmur, under his breath: "My poor little Maud, if I could only bear this pain for you!"But when he laid me on my bed, and I opened my eyes, his face was cold and impassive as   TWISTED THREADS.       IIl ever; and his tone, as he asked me how I felt, had but little sympathy in it. I was in much pain, and I said so. "I wish Mr. Bernard would come back, with the doctor," Bertha said. "I wish I could help you, Maud," as my brow involuntarily contracted from the suffering. "Maurice, cannot you help her? you are a doctor: why did we not think of that before?" "A very useless doctor, Bertha," he said, care- lessly; "you know I am not in practice just now, and as I am not accustomed," with a sneering laugh, "to carrying young ladies up three flights-of stairs, my hand is scarcely firm enough to perform the neces- sary duties." He held out his hand as he spoke. It was trem- bling, and I noticed that he was pale. A moment more, and he went on: ".I will do what I can for you, however, by going :to see if Bernard and the doctor have arrived." And off he went, without giving me another look. So I concluded that the words which were running in my mind had originated there, and not on Dr. Forsythe's lips. Miss Letty came bustling into the room, a few minutes later. "Dr. Forsythe sent me here to make myself use- ful," she said, as she tenderly removed shoe and stocking, and-she was evidently accustomed to such duties--cared for my injured member. So well was it done, too, that when the physician sum- moned by Mr. Bernard did come, he said, upon a  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7635-00000056"/> "2    T WISTED THREADS. examination, there was nothing for him to do: and condemned me to quiescence and inaction for-not days, but weeks. Now, to any one, who like myself, has never known a day's illness; who has been accustomed to con- stant exercise, going out in all weathers; and who - not least of all considerations-is dependent upon that same health for her daily bread-this was a hard sentence-a penalty even harder to bear than the physical pain my ankle did and would give me. Sickness is a forbidden luxury to the poor-their health is their wealth -they cannot afford to indulge in all the little, petty ailments which those more favored with this world's goods are fond of nursing. My face must have told my mental uneasiness, for Miss Letty said to me, at last: "Can't you trust the 'fairy godmother,' child? I promise to take care of you, and I will see that you don't lose your place at Madame Levere's." Miss Letty is in her element when she has some one to take care of. I believe it gave her as much pleasure to make this promise as it gave me to'hear it. And it was not a vain one, either: that very evening there came a note for me to this effect: "Madame Levere regrets to hear of Miss Lennox's accident. She hopes it will only detain her tempor- arily from her duties. In the mean time, a substi- tute has already been obtained; and as it is by no fault of Miss L.'s, her salary will be paid, as usual." So there was a weight off my mind.   TWISTED THREADS.       113 I always thought Madame Levere considered her subordinates as so many machines: out of whom, for a consideration, she was to get a certain amount of work. I believe I did the woman injustice. And so I will never again--even in my own mind- call her "Dame Severe "- a cant name one of the school- girls one day gave her, and which has become a say- ing among teachers and pupils. She has certainly not been severe to me. We are, all of us, so apt to look for the bad traits in people's dispositions, that when, by some acci- dent, our eyes are opened to the good that is in them, we are surprised, and wonder to ourselves that we never saw it before. I think our dispositions are like those curious fig- ures which, seen from one point of view, are hideous and deformed; while from another, they are all grace and beauty: so that they please or displease us according as we look upon them. This is the first day they have let me use my pen. I have suffered great pain, and cannot walk; per- haps will not be able to walk for a month. If I were really sick, I think it would be more endurable: one might bear the confinement patiently; but to be compelled, because one "member" is not "per- fect," to this enforced, painful inaction, is decidedly hard. Miss Letty, who, by the way, is a first-rate nurse, and whose kindness is fast winning my heart, said to me, only this morning-(I have a new comparison for her: she is like a bee, in that from the least - 10O  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7635-00000057"/> "4     TWISTED THREADS. promising flowers she extracts honey, and from the greatest affliction she can draw consolation) --"This is the best preparation you could possibly have for your hospital reading: you will now be able to un- derstand and enter into the feelings of those who lie, not for a few weeks only, but for years, on beds' of suffering, to which your pain is as nothing." I suppose that, until we have felt ourselves, we cannot enter fully into the feelings of others. Our own sufferings give us a clearer insight into human naturer making us kinder and more considerate, more charitable and more loving to our fellow- creatures. -For it is at such times as this that kindly affec- tions, little services, are most highly prized. These- days, since I have been so helpless, I have longed, no one knows how- ardently, for some one of my own kin -if such a one there were in this wide world -who would care for me, who would say to me -as my father and mother once did, and as I imagined Dr. Forsythe did-"My little Maud." Yet the words on his lips were not pleasant to me. I hope he did not really say them.   CHAPTER XIII. IN BERTHA S PARLOR. IT is one month to-day since my ankle was sprained -one month to-day since that sleigh- ride to which I owe my imprisonment; and I have been anything but a willing captive. I do get so tired of myself under these circumstances- of my own little round of thoughts, and my own identity; and as I never, even in my brightest moods, liked to look in upon Maud Elinor Lennaox as I, and only I, knew her, why, I have had more of her, her little impatiences, her idle thoughts, and her companionship, than has been at all agreeable. Then, living, as I have done, in my little attic cham- ber, I have learned to know every nook and cranny in it as I never did before. I see every crack in the plastered ceiling, every figure in the papered walls. I can see those yellow diamonds even when I close my eyes. I have studied the intricacies of the faded carpet until I know every breadth by heart. I see every cobweb the careless chambermaid neglects to remove. Trifles I never before noticed attain a sud- den importance. A snowy or rainy day is a bless- ing, for it is pleasant in the one to see the fair flakes, white as angels' robes, fall from the sky-- in "I5  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7635-00000058"/> 16     TWISTED THREADS. the other, the patter of the raindrops is like music to my ear. But everybody has been kind to me- far kinder than I deserve. First, Bertha put off her trip with Mrs. Bernard, to take care of me, until that lady would wait no longer, and a week ago the two departed. Next, Mr. Bernard--saying his horses, and through them that he bore the responsibility of my accident--has had sent to me, almost daily, choice fruits, and every now and then a book. Mrs. Wilson prepares and brings my meals up to me each day with her own hands. Her little girls, saying that "Miss Maud ought to have something pretty to look at," put their pocket-money together and bought a daily-rose bush, which stands in my win- dow, and which has always either a pink bud or blos- som to remind me pleasantly of its kind little donors. Miss Letty, in addition to her other kindnesses - not the least of which is that every day she dresses and  bandages my injured ankle - has selected from her cagefull of pets, a bright, - golden singer, which, in a l'ight wire cage, hangs over my rosebush, and whose sweet, clear notes fill my room with melody.  Goldie--so I have named him--is great company for me; and as Miss Letty comes every morning to replenish seed-box and water-cup, I can enjoy my feathered companion without having to attend to him. And--I had nearly forgotten-but when I wished to thank Miss Letty for her kind- ness in seeing Madame Levere, she told me I had nothing to thank her for-that though she had seen my principal, that lady had informed her that,   TWISTED THREADS.       II7 having already heard of Miss Lennox's accident, 4 she had made arrangements which she hoped would prove satisfactory to all parties. They were--very satisfactory --at least to me. Every now and then some one of the boarders --perhaps some one with whom I have barely a speaking acquaintance--will send up to inquire "how Miss Lennox is " -- for which trifling, though gratifying attention, said Miss Lennox is truly grate- ful. Dr. Forsythe is-the only person who, of all' my acquaintance in the house, has totally ignored me and my sprained ankle--a very irportant cir- cumstance to me, yet nothing to him; and he takes this way of showing his indifference to me. If one does consider oneself insignificant, one does not care to be reminded of the fact by others. Bertha left me word--by the way, Allyn Ber- nard escorted his mother and my friend on their journey--that whenever I pleased, I should use her parlor, as though it were my own; .and just so soon as I can get up- and down stairs- -I can just drag myself now from bed to lounge - I intend to vary the monotony of my lame-life- other people have a love-life by way of episode -by spending some of my mornings there. It will be a pleasant change--a little spice of variety in my present insipid helplessness. Ah! I ought to feel bitterly ashamed of myself for writing in this strain, when I should rather be only the more grateful to think that I have escaped with a tempqrary inconvenience, while I might have  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7635-00000059"/> Il8     TWISTED THREADS. been crippled for life, or even have been called upon, all unprepared,. to surrender that life. And when that. thought comes over me, I am so truly thankful for this continued boon of existence, that I think I will never again murmur at my lot, knowing, as I do, that on no one is laid a cross too heavy to be borne-that we are, none of us, tried beyond our powers of endurance; and that the very trials at which we most murmur--the crosses under whose weight we most .rebel-may prove to be the choicest blessings, the tenderest mercies which may be shown us. And yet, thinking and knowing all this as I do, there are times when there comes over me -as it is probable there comes over every one--a feeling of restlessness and discontent, against which - all the time knowing it to be wrong - we vainly strug- gle ; yet which grows upon us, spite of all we can do to throw it off. It has been a dark, dreary day -no rain, but thersky has been cloudy and gray, the air full of a chill mistiness, through which, for brief intervals, now and then have come the rays of the sun, red, angry, and fiery--a day. which irritates and depresses one, and when the damp, chill air brings no refreshment to our lungs, as does generally the air of this season - a day when I feel like sitting closely over my register, and my sole desire and aim is to keep warm. One of the most acceptable attentions I have had paid me since I have been- like the queens of Spain -footless, has been the arrival, every day or   TWISTED THREADS.       119 two, of a bunch of flowers. No name is sent with them: the florist's boy says "they are for Miss Lennox," "Only that, and nothing more." So feminine curiosity has not even a peg on which to hang itself. Some days it is a cluster of white, creamy Lamarque roses; then a fragrant combina- tion of heliotrope and geranium leaves; again, rich scarlet camellias. There are sometimes two, mostly 'but one, kind of flower, in these sweet tributes. To-day it was two or three calla lilies, in an en- closure of their own lance-shaped leaves, telling me, with their pure white flowers--stainless ivory chal- ices enfolding a golden torch--of the rapid ap- proach of the joyous Easter season; and carrying me back to the days when my mother nursed her callas, her favorite flower, watching, day by day, the fair flowers unfold themselves, that in their stainless glory they might serve to adorn the font and altar of our little church-fit emblems of the pure joy we are to take in this blessed season. 'Yet the cold purity of the Easter lilies seemed a little out of place on this dreary day, to which would have been better fitted the scarlet brightness of the camellias which came only a few days since. Repining again! Ah! Maud Lennox, for shame! I had written thus far, when that same undefin- 'able restlessness, of which I before spoke, led me to lay down my pen, push away my book, and, pain-  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7635-00000060"/> 120    ?WISTED THEREADS. fully, slowly-urged by the desire for change-drag myself down, for the first time, to Bertha's parlor. Was it fate that led me? and was it not a pre- sentiment of the TO COME which made this day, with its angry sun, its murky sky, so irritating and de- pressing to me? I got down, at last, to the warm room, still kept warm, still adorned with flowers, for such is Ber- tha's wish; for, as she says, she does not want to return to this abiding-place of hers to find it look- ing dreary and uninhabited. So in it still are scat- tered her books, and the vases are full, ready for their fair mistress to return; while in the room still lingers that faint odor of verbena which, wherever Bertha is or has been, betrays her. So I crept into the room, its warmth feeling inex- pressibly grateful, and ensconced myself, with a book, most comfortably in one of the many loung- ing chairs -Bertha is a true Southerner in her love of ease scattered through the room; and at last the warmth and the perfumed breath of the flowers so ministered to my restlessness that it vanished charmed away by the luxurious surroundings which, could I indulge in them, would become absolutely necessary to me - and I fell asleep. I do not know why I linger over these trifles, if it be not that I cannot bear to go over, even to my- self, what followed. For I was so totally unpre- pared-so completely taken by surprise--so bit- terly pained, that the mere thought of what passed brings the blood to my cheek.   TWISTED THREADS.       121 I do not know how long I slept. The perfect quiet was soothing to me. What roused me was my own name, spoken in low tones. Often a whisper will awaken a sleeper on whose ears a loud call or exclamation will fall unheeded. But the sound of my own name awakened me, and I sat up to see - Dr. Forsythe standing at the win- dow, his back to me, looking out into the street. He turned, abruptly, at my low exclamation of surprise. "I am sorry to have disturbed you, Miss Len- nox; but I am so accustomed to walking in and out of this room of Bertha's, that I did not expect to find it thus tenanted." "It is more my place to apologize-"I said in re- ply. "Your right here is better than mine: I only owe my present occupancy to Bertha's permission." "The room can hold us both, I presume," very coolly. "Unless, indeed, my presence is unwel- come; in which case I can easily relieve you of it." "Why should it be unwelcome?"I began. "I might ask you, with more reason, why you shrink from me. Don't look at me so astonished, with those shy eyes of yours; you cannot silence me any longer. What is it in you, Maud Lennox- you tiny, frail thing -that makes me, strong man that I am, powerless in your presence - that makes me struggle against bonds which, till I knew you, lay lightly upon me-and brings me, whether I will or no, to your side? It is wrong in me to say this." "Then do not say it," I said, scarcely knowing II  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7635-00000061"/> 122  .  T WISTED THR EA D S. what I did say. "Do not let any words pass your lips which you will have, later, reason to regret." "Ay, woman-like, you would try your power," he said, bitterly. "You cannot silence me now: you might as well try to check the tempest with a word--to stop the rush of waters with that little hand. You must listen to me. Maud Lennox, do you know I love you? No; how could you know it? Your surprised eyes tell the truth--you never guessed it. And H have fought against it; though from the first moment I saw you I said to myself that you, and you only, were the one woman in this world for me - that you were the other half of my soul, made for me, and me only -that you were mine, in all your 'womanly completeness,' even as I was yours; and knowing this, to feel my- self so bound, so fettered that I dared not go to you, as any other man would have done, and ask you to be my wife! I do not, even now, ask you that; I cannot - I am not free." "Then," I said, "how dare you-" He interrupted me fiercely. "How dare I? By the supreme law of love; by that within me which tells me - I have never yet failed in anything I attempted--that I shall yet win you--that you will yet be my wife. You do not love me now; but, as surely as there is a heaven above us, Maud Lennox, you will yet love me--yet be mine. Love, to you, will never come suddenly, though its consciousness may. It will entwine itself with the very fibres of your being;   TWISTED THREADS.       123 and when it has become a very part of yourself, then, and not till then, you will acknowledge its existence. Even now you think of me--I influ- ence you, unconsciously to yourself; and you will one day find that Maurice Forsythe is as necessary to you and to your happiness as you are to him." " I hope that day may never dawn!" I said to myself, but he heard me. "You think so now," biting his lip in the en- deavor to keep calm. "This is not, I know, the way you would have your favor sought -my words shock you. Yet I can, and some day will, give you what you in your heart long for with an earnest longing--a home,'where you shall reign, a queen enthroned--a heart, which holds you dearer than aught else. I say no more to you now, Maud. I have patience, and I can wait; and to him who waits, all things in time will come." " It is manly in you to speak in this way!" I said, bitterly - " to force me to listen to you, when you know I cannot leave you." " Poor child! " his voice softening; " as if I would not willingly bear your pain, and think it nothing! Maud- Maud," it was said longingly, "forgive me, if I have hurt you-you whom I would so gladly keep from all shadow of suffering--whose little hands I would so gladly fold in my own, that they might never know toil--you who should never lack anything in my power to give you ! " And before I knew what he was doing, he had come to my side--while I, wondering at these    &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7635-00000062"/> 124     TWISTED lTHREADS. strange words, which, as it were, against his will had come from Dr. Forsythe's lips, sat gazing at him, silenced, as we all are, by the display of strong emotion in those from whom we do not expect it-- and, taking one of my curls in his hand, reverently -I say this advisedly--pressed it to his lips, and was- gone. Then, and not till then, I breathed freely. My first impulse was to return to my own little room, but that was only to be done slowly. There, I sat down to think over Dr. Forsythe's strange words- the agitation the usually calm Professor had dis- played-and then, woman-like, my feelings relieved themselves in a violent burst of tears. For it hum- bled me, it did not please me to think of this strange love, against which he himself rebelled, knowing that honor should, though it did not seal his lips -a wooing against which my whole nature rebelled. Like all girls, I had my own fancies as to the shape in which my fate should come unto me. I do not see it in Maurice Forsythe. His is not the hand to open the woman's kingdom for me. For I think -and between us that can never be-that love knows no fear: it comes "Openly, and free." Yet he was right: he can influence me-he can make me think of him! I will not think of him any longer now! Why should this disturbing influence come into my life, to agitate me as it has done? He had no right to   I TWISTED THREADS.      125 speak as he did; whatever the bonds which check him may be, they should have been strong enough to prevent words being spoken which honor forbade. And from this stormy scene I turn with a feeling of refreshment, from the stern reality of human feel- ing to look on the passionless purity of the Easter lilies--which I have placed under the Ecce Homo on which my- waking eyes first rest; and as I gaze upon them there passes into my soul some of their calm, as they bring to my mind Bertha's pure com- plexion and golden hair, and I idly wonder if in truth our lives are interwoven and our destinies are to depend the one upon the other. Ah! it is vain to anticipate-we may not guess -at the mysteries of the future. And our lives are so interwoven, our deeds so act and re-act, not only on ourselves, but upon others, that to tell the story of one human heart ~vould involve, to a certain ex- tent, the history of many others. II*  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7635-00000063"/> CHAPTER XIV. WHAT DID IT MEAN? HAVE neglected my " libellus " sadly of late; but in truth, though I have had the time, I have had no inclination .to use my pen. Some writer says: "No happy woman ever writes." This may be true of those who have the gift of authorship-. when woman's sorrows lead her to find consolation in depicting imaginary scenes and troubles, and in them forgetting her own; but to any one who, like myself, only records her own thoughts, her own private feelings, there is no relief in giving them expression: no pleasure in dwelling on or record- ing thoughts which give you pain, and which you desire, if possible, to forget. And my life is shaping itself so differently from any- thing I ever anticipated--almost like a story; anad I think that I was foolish to wish for incident and event to come into it: for the very things which most in- terest us in a novel are those which, in real life, are most painful and difficult to live through. My physical pain is, I am thankful to say, over. I am once more able to go about, and have resumed my duties at Madame  Levere's. And Miss Letty calls me her "right hand" at the Hospital, where 126. i   TWISTED THREADS.       127 already some of the patients--poor, suffering crea- tures-have learned to look for and welcome my coming, and be grateful for what little I can do for them. "Small service is true service while it lasts" and it brings its own reward; for this work, which I only undertook from a sense of duty, gives me true pleasure in its performance. Mr. Bernard is here again. Bertha stopped one day to see me, before going elsewheres to visit her friends. She writes to me, but letters are not like companionship-and though these missives seem bright and cheerful, I, who know my friend so well, can see, underlying the surface, a secret uneasiness, some disturbing influence which she is not willing to mention. Mr. Bernard is very quiet. ' He asks me occasion- ally for news of Bertha. I begin to believe Miss Letty was right, and that he loves' her. I have never entered Bertha's parlor since that afternoon. Because must I say it-- I am afraid! afraid of myself. And why? I have no wish to meet Dr. Forsythe again - no wish to come under his influence. For, whether I will or no, his passionate words linger in my ear. I dwell upon them with an unconscious fascination - and I fear to risk their repetition. I said I had no wish to meet him: yet, once -or twice since then, we have Come in contact; once, as he passed me, he murmured, so that the words met my ear:  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7635-00000064"/> 128 T. WISTED THR EADS. "I have not changed my mind, Miss Lennox. I have patience-I can wait." And then I thought, and trembled as I thought, how with patience the sculptor frees, from the im- prisoning stone, the statue hidden in the shapeless- block-as a strong will, surmounting all obstacles, attains at last to its desired end. But even though I avoid Dr. Forsythe, he does not avoid me; he either finds or makes an oppor- tunity for speaking to me. Last Sunday, I went, as usual, to the Hospital. Spring, at last, has come-spring, the youth of the'year; and the poor trees-I pity trees in a great city, with their roots prisoned under the pavements -have put on their new foliage; just as everybody --I mean all woman-kind- is out in new, fresh, and tasty costumes. It had been a hot, close day, no air stirring: and as it. is quite a walk from Mrs. Wilson's to the Hos-. pital, Miss Letty and I concluded that we would wait a little later; and, after sending word to our poor friends, to let them know at what hour they might look for us, when the afternoon was nearly gone we set out together. Miss Letty came to rie about half an hour after we reached our destination, to say to me that she had been sent for, but that she would return as soon as she could, and that I should wait for her, and in the cool of the evening we would return together. I went about my duties, reading to the patients, talking to some, and letting others talk to me--it l\   TWISTED TIREADS.       129 -is such a relief to them to have some one who will listen to them --saw some of Miss Letty's proteges --until the daylight began to fade, and my compan- ion was still absent. I waited and waited, till my patience-I have no very large stock of that virtue--was nearly ex- hausted; and then, afraid to stay longer --I am not very brave-I prepared to go home alone: leaving a message for Miss Letty, in case she should yet come for me. But at the door there stood, waiting 'for me, the very person I was most anxious to avoid, namely, Dr. Forsythe. He smiled at my expression of astonishment, and very coolly came to my side., "You will have to accept of my escort, whether you wish it or no, Miss Lennox. I promised Miss Armstrong that I would supply her place, and see you home as safely as she could have done." "Where did you meet Miss Letty?"I asked, see- ing that my companion was determined to retain his position; and as I have learned that when Dr. For- sythe means to do a thing he does it, I concluded I had best resign myself to circumstances, and trust to my woman's wit to keep aloof from dangerous topics. "In one of the wards, where she would probably remain all night; and as she was uneasy about you, I offered to take care of you. You know how will- ing I am to do what I can for you." I made no reply. "Don't you believe me?" ,'  '      *   &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7635-00000065"/> I 30-    T WISTSED THR EA D S. "No," I said, coldly; "for the only thing you could do for me, which really would please me, you will not do." "And that?"  ' "Would be to let me alone." He laughed. "You don't mean thatg I know. And I have no wish to do unnecessary penance, Miss Lennox. Just now, it would punish you if I were to leave you; for, setting aside the impropriety of the thing, you would be afraid, and with reason, to walk the streets of New York alone after dark." "You are ungenerous." "I am very generous to myself, for I am takirg care of what, some day, will be my own. Things look brighter, fair lady," seriously. "I hope, ere many days, I can ask you to let me care for you for life; and, mark my words, Maud Lennox, you will not refuse me." "I have told you this subject was distasteful, Dr. Forsythe." "Yet, am I not right: I have sometimes been the subject of your thoughts?" Now, this I could not deny, and I would not tell an untruth. I felt the blood rush to my very brow, and I was silent. Dr. Forsythe said no more on the subject; he walked by my side, conversing on ordi- nary topics: yet I was thankful when we reached M rs. Wilson's door. There I bade him a courteous, yet curt good-night, not even thanking him for his escort, and left him. * ' /,   TWISTED THREADS.       13! Only to see a smile curve his firm lip--a light come into the gray eye, which softens inexpressibly when, from his superior height, he looks down upon me; and to hear him say, wonderingly, to himself - -he never guessed I heard him: "The bird is shy; but she will yet come to my lure." But I say: he will prove a false prophet. What can the bonds be against which he- rebels? Such a strange thing has just happened. So many strange things do- happen to me now-a-days that I have ceased to be surprised at any of them. Passing down the long entry, the other day, on my way to school-an entry which is always gloomy and dismal: so that on a murky day one almost has'- to grope through it -some one slipped a letter into my hand, with 'a request that I would mail it. Now, this is nothing unusual; for passing, as I do, three or four letter-boxes on my way to and from school, the lady-hoarders often give me epistles to drop therein, and I am always willing to do what little service I' can. So, without even a glance at the person who accosted me - who, by the way, did not even wait for my assurance that I would comply with the request-I put the letter in my pocket, and - it speaks wejl for my good memory - I for- got it. That was three days ago; and the dress I wore has been hanging up ever since, and might have hung for days longer--as it is a dress I keep for  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7635-00000066"/> 132    TWISTED THREADS. rainy days-but that this morning I missed my porte-monnaie-one don't need a purse in these days of paper-money: and as I have a very bad habit of leaving that same little convenience in my pocket, I searched every dress, one after the other, until I came to this old dread-naught of mine-as I call it-the very last I examined; and plunging my hand rather impatiently-it was but a forlorn hope--into the recesses of the deep pocket, out came, not only the truant pocket-book, but the let- ter, intrusted to my care, as I now remembered, three days before. My first impulse was to go to the person who had given it to me, when I remembered that I did not even know from whom I had received it. Then, I looked--a thing I rarely do: I have such a horror of that petty, prying spirit-at the address. And I could scarcely believe my own' eyes when I saw, staring at me, my own name - Miss MAUD LENNOX- with the full number of the house, and the name ' the street. And in my astonishment I dropped ti, little parallelogram on the floor, as though it had burnt my fingers; and there it lay, and I stood staring at it. At last, laughing at myself for my own folly, I picked it up; and then stood, as we often do when an unexpected letter comes, examining the writing, turning it around for some minutes before I opened it. It was very brief-only a few lines; yet they are perfectly inexplicable to me:   *   TWISTED THREA DS.        33 "Miss Lennox has doubtless--she is a good French scholar-heard the proverb in that tongue which says, 'Chateau qui parle, et femme qui ecoute.' It is needless to quote the rest. It is commended to her consideration by       A FRIEND." But no friend would send me an anonymous let- ter. A friend would speak plainly to me, face to face. I do not know the handwriting, which, though firm and bold, is evidently disguised. Such a cow- ardly thing as it is! - the unknown sender shall not have the satisfaction--if it be a satisfaction--of my taking any notice of it. "A listening woman!"I cannot help it if Dr. Forsythe does talk to me. I cannot deprive him of speech, or myself of hearing; and to think that poor little H-I, who try to keep "The noiseless tenor of my way," never interfering with any one, and asking nothing better than that others should let me alone: the world is wide enough, surely, for me to be allowed to fill my little corner of it peacefully--should have received an anonymous letter! I will burn the hateful thing, with all its insinua- tions. I wish I had done so before I read it. Oh, mother Eve! mother Eve! your fatal legacy of curiosity has come down too faithfully to your daughters. I wish I could efface -the contents of that sheet of I2  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7635-00000067"/> 134    TWISTED THREADS. paper from my memory as easily as I have reduced it to ashes. It seems so strange to me why it should have been sent. It is not Miss Letty's hand-writing: her quaint characters are too feminine -even in their oddity-- prim, and upright-as she is herself, ever to assume this bold disguise; and it is not likely that Dr. For- sythe, if his words to me are true---and I think I know when people mean what they say--would warn me against himself; for with that purpose that letter was written. If I could only find out who gave it to me! It has had this effect: that I have done nothing, ever since I read it, but wonder if it were prompted by jealousy; and then, unconsciously to myself, I fulfil 'Dr. Forsythe's prediction, and think of him, and how he would resent this insult. And I don't want to think of him. I want, not only to keep out of his way, but to keep him out of my thoughts. I used to have such pleasant thoughts! I once could say, and truthfully, "My mind to me a kingdom is;" but now, I want to escape from myself. If Bertha were only here! Vain wish: we must bear our own burdens; and troubles like this one of mine are best borne in secret, untold to others.   CHAPTER XV. A MAN S WILL. \M /ISS LETTY said to me, only a few days since - and coming from her it was high praise - that "any woman might feel honored by Dr. For- sythe's notice." But I don't appreciate it, as directed to me. For, go where I will, those clear gray eyes are upon me, looking me? through and through, exercising a mes- meric power over, me; so that although I say to myself that I never will give to Dr. Forsythe the privileges he desires - even if he ever be in a posi- tion to ask for them--I can only be thus firm and resolute when I am not with him; for in his pres- ence, his calm, masterful manner controls me, and I have no will of my own. Masterful! that word describes him well. And it is a quality, which "TWhat not impossible he, - Who shall control my heart and me," must possess.' But that "he," of whom, like all women, I have drawn a mental portrait, does not wear Maurice Forsythe's form or features. I wonder how many pages of this book of mine 135  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7635-00000068"/> 136     TWIS TED TITREADS. would be filled, if, like the sun-dial, it only recorded my hours of sunshine. If I left blanks for the dark days, I am afraid that the entries would be but "few and far between." They do not come very often, as it is; but looking over them, as I sometimes do - though they have, as yet, told of no real, heart-break- ing sorrow; no trial, through the days of which we can barely live; no bitter distress, crushing and agoni- zing the heart--the dark hours outnumber the bright ones. I think it is far easier to live through and bear one great trouble, than to have to endure many petty trials. One of the worst tortures of the Inqui- sition, in olden times, was "the drop of water;" just one drop, which, at stated intervals, fell on the brow of the condemned, who was chained and un- able to change his position. It was nothing at first -one could almost laugh at the idea of calling it torture--but when hour after hour this drop, unhalt- ing, unresting, fell, and fell, and fell, the sufferer at last realized that he was enduring one of the most fiendish inventions of human cruelty. And in life, very often, little things-so little that, taken one by one, they would never be noticed, yet coming as they do, one after the other, incessantly-grow to be a burden heavier than we can bear; and because they are so little, no one else thinks they can be trials. So that a dangerous illness, when you have all the love and sympathy which kind hearts can give, may cause you less real suffering than an aching tooth or a weary head-t-hings which are so corn-   TWISTED THREADS.       137 mon, of such every-day occurrence, that no one thinks of being sorry for their victim. I wonder if life, real life, is ever the thing fiction represents it. I do not believe a novel ever was or ever will be written which would give a true picture of life: its ins and outs, its ups and downs; the little every-day occurrences ,which bring such vast circumstances in their train: a book in which truth would lead the pen, showing, with the action, its motive; the cause with the result; the contradictions which come into every life: in a word, the true history of a human heart. I believe the thing is simply impossible. I can see how it is, from my own experience in this little chronicle of mine: in which, though I know no eye save my own will ever rest upon it, I am not willing to write every thing: it mirrors me faith- fully enough as it is. For, as in the clearest brook which sparkles and ripples over its pebbly bed, there are certain spots where the water is dark and con- ceals its depth from the eye; so in the purest hu- man life there are times and seasons, thoughts and actions we would willingly conceal, not only from the scrutinizing gaze of others, but from ourselves. What an immense capacity for suffering or for enjoyment is crowded into these few brief years of ours!-years in which some of us know so much sorrow th'at one cannot but think, as did the ancients, that those who die young are most truly blest. I am growing to be a regular moralizer, prosing away in this strain. I2  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7635-00000069"/> 138    TWIS TED THREA D S. But I have just thought that I would not care to live to be old, and ugly, and helpless. v Life would then cease to be a pleasure. Two days ago, I received a little note from Dr. Forsythe; and copy it here: "MAUD-I wish I dared, with your permission, to say my Maud--I am free at last; and the first use I make of that freedom is to renew my bonds, and come to you. Little Maud! I want you: will you say me nay?            M. F." Now, I did not intend answering this note-one would have thought, after all I had said, that any man would have been discouraged, and have let me alone. And I hoped that my disregard of this appeal would prove final. I little knew the resolu- tion of the man with whom I had to deal. He did not have much patience. As I returned from Madame Levere's yesterday morning, I met him on the street, and he joined me. "Why do you never use Bertha's parlor now?" was his first question. I made some silly excuse -the first which came into my mind. "You may as well tell the truth, and give your true reason. You were afraid of meeting me. Well, I confess I have haunted the room, hoping you would come; but for once, a woman did not answer my expectations." I made no reply-I was too angry to speak. Then:   TWISTED THREADS.       139 "Why did you not answer my note? I know you received it." "It needed no answer, Dr. Forsythe." "I beg your pardon, Miss Lennox. And that answer, which you would not write, you shall give me in words, before we part." By this time we had reached Mrs. Wilson's door, had entered the house, and, as Dr. Forsythe spoke, were near Bertha's parlor. A thought struck me. "Yes," I said, "you shall have your answer. Come in here, if you please: we shall not be interrupted; and it may as well be over first as last." I sat down, very composedly, in my favorite chair. Dr. Forsythe, his arms folded, stood directly in front of me. "Do you know how pleasant you are to look at," he said, a smile curving his lip. "So pleasant, that I would be content to stand here and look at you forever." "It is not pleasant for me to sit here, however," I said. "If you can only pay me compliments, Dr. Forsythe, I must beg you to excuse my listening to them." He was serious enough now. As I rose to go, he laid his hand on my arm to detain me. "You read my note: you know that I am free; Maud, what is your apswer?" "It is easily spoken: No." "Say that again, if you please," his lips white. "You do not mean it, Maud--you cannot mean it. The love I offer you is not a thing to be lightly  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7635-00000070"/> i40    vTWISTED THREADS. rejected; it is no slight thing to be laughed at and scorned. And, in your heart, you know that it is true: you know my words are not vain ones; you know that even now, your own heart asks for love-- that you shrink from a lonely life, a solitary old age. Maud! Maud! you, and you only, can be my helper and consoler-and you know it! Unconsciously to yourself--I believe that even now you love me." "No," I said hesitatingly, "I do not love you." "You have not acknowledged it to yourself. Can you not trust yourself to me? Your eyes are an- swering for you: you will not send me from you? For if you do, we two can never meet again." I am almost ashamed to write, in this book of mine, what followed. Dr. Forsythe was silent: he had said his say, and I I seemed to see, unfolded before me, all the lonely, dread future, through which I was to struggle, weak and unprotected. I buried my face in my hands. I could not bear my com- panion's searching eye. I looked, as never before I had looked, into the recesses of my heart. "Why give yourself, as well as me, so much pain?" fell on my ear. "My own darling, give me the care of you: my life shall prove how sacredly I will keep the trust." I looked up; and I think he read in my eyes the answer I could not put into words; for that moment I was enfolded in a strong, yet caressing embrace, and I knew that I had done, what half an hour sooner I would have thought impossible--by my silence. pledged myself to become Maurice Forsythe's wife.   TWISTED THREADS.       141 I do not intend to write the thanks and blessings which were whispered into my ear--they are re- corded on my heart. "Let me go, Dr. Forsythe," I said at last--the first words I did say; "you have gained your end, and had your own way: it is my turn to have mine now." He laughed gayly. "It is'pleasant to think that your way and mine will be the same in future. Maud," very seriously, as he led me to the door, "I cannot thank you for this in words: I can only prove to you, in my life, what it is to me." At the foot of the staircase he paused. "I have one little thing to ask of you." "What is that?" very shyly. "Only to say four words: 'I love you, Maurice.'" My face burned. "You must be content with what you have." And without another word, I left him. I wanted to be alone: to look quietly upon this wonderful thing that I had done -this thing that when the morn- ing dawned I had said to myself was impossible. Ah! we women are strange contradictions. A few pages back, I said I would " not care to live to be old:" now, I think that my life cannot be too long. For I believe that it will be a happy one; and I know now-what I never knew before-what I would not say to him, though I say it here of him -that I love Maurice Forsythe, and I am content to know that he loves me. I asked him, to-day--(I wonder already how I  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7635-00000071"/> "2     T WIS TED THR EA D S. /  ever thought him heartless, or was afraid of him)- how he ever came to care for me, when other and fairer women would have smiled on him. "Can you ask me that, Maud? Does- not the knowledge that I love you answer that: that I know you will be a help, not a burden, to your husband; that your true womanliness, your unassuming good- ness won me? And there is 'no woman fairer to my eyes than you are: no one who can compare with you in my sight." "Ah, I fear there is a glamour' over your eyes." "It rests'with you to keep it there, Maud. I am not afraid I shall ever look differently upon you. I hope every passing year may prove How much the wife is dearer than the bride."' Ah, if he does think me fair, it is only because he loves me: as, in the old fairy-tale, the princess saw beauty equal to her own in the prince, who, to all other eyes, was homely and deformed- so, perhaps, and I am glad to think it, I am fair in his sight; and if I please him-what care I for what any one beside may think? And, as yet, it is all strange to me. I sit and think of my nexw prospects tremblingly-I can scarcely realize the truth. But- so many things--unexpected events, new thoughts, new feelings-have, since I began this "Iibellus " of mine, come crowding into my life - things which it seems so strange should happen to ,ME-that I think hereafter I shall never be aston-   TWISTED THREADS.       143 ished, no matter what may come to pass. And the most strange of all is that H-I, who sit this even- ing, idly writing-I, Maud Elinor Lennox, should have such a great light, such a new day to dawn for me-who so little deserve it, that I can only sit in silence, and wonder; and then, with a sudden im- pulse, fall on my knees in voiceless thanksgiving that the blessed boon of love has come to me. O calm, clear stars!--ye who from your circling orbits have looked, through countless ages, un- changed and unchanging, on this earth and its inhabitants-do 'you think that in any of the hearts, innumerable as they are, which have loved and re- joiced, a gladder Te Deum was ever sung than is echoing in mine? I have so much to be grateful for!  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7635-00000072"/> CHAPTER XVI. IN FAIRY-LAND. I AM growing familiar, at last, with my new posi- tion: beginning to feel that it has some reality about it, and that it is not wholly a dream. If it is a dream, it is such a pleasant one that I would be content to have it last forever. I have no desire to waken from it. I said once--not many days ago--that Dr. For- sythe was best described by the word "masterful." And the more I see of him, the better I learn to know him-the more convinced I am, that in him I have truly found my master. Some women, I know, would rebel against that feeling-which to me is so charming. But to feel that HE is better than I am, and that he can guide me and govern me: I like it. I think I am inclined to be submissive. It is well for me that it is so; for I can see that Dr. Forsythe-he scolds because I cannot say "Maurice"-is a man who will be obeyed, and who requires unquestioning obedience; as I suppose is natural to all men who, like himself, have been placed in authority over others. And I like to think that my future is provided for; "4   TWISTED THREADS.       145 that a stronger, abler hand than mine will hence- forth shape it; that I shall have a home: and not least of all, that I am loved. Only, he will load me with gifts--ornaments and jewels, which I will not wear, for they are not suitable for me now; and I am proud, and-do not like to be under obligations to any one. If I did wear them, I should feel, as Zenobia did, when in her golden chains she graced the triumph of Aurelian, that my master, adorning his captive, desired to show his wealth; and although my captivity is so sweet to me that I have no wish for freedom, I will not give any one reason to say I could be "won by gifts." And there the jewels lie - " rich and rare " - yet unworn. Dr. Forsythe says he is glad I have nothing- that he will be able to give me every thing. He seems to think that a man should provide for his own household; and that'any true-hearted man would scorn the thought of marrying a woman be- cause she has wealth: because a true woman is "far above rubies," a priceless treasure within herself; and it seems a pleasure to him to think I shall owe him everything. I never thought of his wealth, I am sure: it would have been all the same to me had he been poor, in- stead of being blessed with an abundance of this world's goods -though they are not to be despised; and though I confess I value money, it is not so much for the thing itself as for what it can do. "Little Maud,". he said to me one day-he has pet names innumerable for me: of which "little I3  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7635-00000073"/> "6    TWISTED THREA D S. Maud" is the most used (and yet I don't think I am so very little, being just five feet two--the height of the Medician Venus)-"Little Maud, do you know what I think of you, you eerie sprite? That I must put a spell upon you before long-a ring on this finger- give you a new name; else some day I shall find myself minus my little Maud." "She is a very substantial reality just at present," I said, saucily. He pulled my hair: to please him, I wear it in curls now. "Very substantial, in truth. She will make a very stately Mrs. Forsythe. Are you blushing, Maud? you need not: it will be your name before either you or I are many days older." "I may have a word to say about that, O most sage professor." "Little one, hush. You belong to me, not to yourself; and you may as well give up gracefully." "You are-" "I am--going to have my own way. And it pleases me that Miss Le/nnox's existence shall soon terminate. Ah, Maud! let me secure my happiness while it is yet within my grasp: I cannot feel secure till you are really my own." U You do not doubt me, I hope." "God forbid! no. But can you blame me if I wish to make of a happy anticipation a blessed reality -to feel that nothing earthly can part us or come between us." I suppose it will end in my giving up to him- and, although it is an early day; letting him name   TWISTED THR EA DS.      I47 the day-the twelfth of June-four weeks from to- day. It is his birthday: and he says he wants the new year of his life to bring him the welcome gift it is only in my power to bestow. It is no use for me to say him nay. I may as well give up at once; for resolve as I may when away from him, when with him I yield myself wholly to his guidance. I wonder if it will last. It seems as though I were walking in a dream. But, in all human probability, my single life is nearly over. After all, there is not really any neces- sity for delay; there is no one to consult, no one to interfere; I have no preparations-or very few--to make; and, some morning, when Bertha comes home, she and 'Mrs. Wilson will go to the church with me--and when I leave it, it will not be as Maud Lennox. And the only wealth I shall take to my husband will be the wealth of a loving heart; my only wed- ding-gift to him, the will to make him happy. Dr. Forsythe told me, to-day, when he desired me to inform Madame Levere that my duties there were soon to terminate, that he hoped I now understood why, at the time I sprained my ankle, he had refused his services -because, as he said, the sight of my suffering unmanned him, and he was powerless. And that, not. daring even to ask for me, much less see me, he had sent me the flowers which I thought came from Mr. Bernard. "It was so hard, my darling, knowing I loved you, to be silent. Those were weeks of agony--fighting  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7635-00000074"/> "8     TWISTED THREADS. against myself. But do not ask me what silenced me: that part of my past is best forgotten. Trust me that it is nothing of which I need be ashamed. You have the present, Maud: leave me the troubles of the past." I can trust him: knowing, as I do, that it is not want of confidence in me that makes him unwilling to speak of the bonds from which he has escaped: which seem to give him pain only to think of them. And--I am glad to think it-a bright future is opening for Bertha as well as for myself. For, as he tells me, Allyn Bernard came to him, a few days since, to ask his consent, as guardian, to his addresses to Bertha. "What did you say?"I questioned, anxiously. "I have but one reply to such applicants. I refer them to the lady. But in this case, I wish the young man success; and my opinion is, that our wedding will be followed by another, It must be from our house, Maud." "I am so glad!"I said, gayly. "So am I. You can congratulate both when you find opportunity: which will probably not be long in presenting itself." I will make an opportunity. I am so happy my- self that I want everybody else to be happy too. It seems to me that there never was such a lovely May as this one is. The skies are of such a brilliant blue -there never was such sunshine such a fresh- ness in the air--such starlit nights. And my little attic chamber is peopled with so many sweet   TWIST:ED, THREADS. '     149 thoughts; so many blessed anticipations; so many pleasant fancies-that it is like a little' paradise to me. I suppose that in reality there is no change in the world and in my surroundings; that it is only the inner light in my heart which makes every thing so bright, as if I were in an enchanted fairy-land. I met Miss Letty this morning, and -why, I can- not say walked with her to her room. Lately, I have been there several times, so that Tom has found out I am not formidable, and does not arch his back and round his tail at me: but will sometimes con- descend to jump on my knee; where, in response to my hand stroking his soft fur, he purrs away sleepily as long as I choose to let him lie in my lap. And-for very mischief's sake- I asked Miss Letty if she thought Miss Steiner had done me harm. She surveyed me, through her spectacles, from head to foot. "I think it's as well she's not here. You are looking remarkably well." I smiled. "And the old maid, through her glasses, can see that her patient is, or thinks herself, very happy. I don't wonder-one has reason to rejoice when a sprained ankle gets well. No thanks, however, to Dr. Forsythe." The blood rushed to my very temples. Miss Letty shook her head. "Don't you be silly enough to fall in love with I3  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7635-00000075"/> 150    T WIS TED .. THR EA D S. him, child. You will repent it, if you do. I tell you again, that edged tools will cut." "Miss Letty, I thought Dr. Forsythe was a friend of yours." "Well! and if he is, what then? An old woman, like myself, can do things you could not do." Did my face betray me? or how did Miss Letty take my words, simple as I thought them: "Dr. Forsythe is a gentleman." For she came and stood before me, and, very slowly: "So, this is what has brought the light to your eye, the color to your cheek! Poor child, you are walking in a fool's paradise; and I cannot lead you out of it: you can only leave it yourself." I laughed. "Miss Letty, you are very compli- mentary to me this morning." "Child, I was young once, and I have not forgot- ten my youth. Experience is a good teacher; but they who have learned of her cannot impart their knowledge to those to whom she has not yet come. You, whose day has just begun, will never listen to us, who have borne the heat and burden of ours." "If you knew all-"I began. "Tell me nothing" - very hastily. "If you ever need a friend, as you may, before long-little as you seem to think it - come to me: I may be able to help you when you least expect it." I looked at her, in surprise. She went on hur- riedly: "Do you know-  No, I had best not tell you -    TWISTED THREADS.       15I ill news flies fast enough, and I may, after all, be wrong: it may all prove a mistake; and knowing no- thing as yet- Child! enjoy 'love's young dream' while yet you may; the awakening will come; and if the staff you now trust fails you, Letty Armstrong will stand your friend." "Miss Letty! for heaven's sake, explain yourself!" She took me by the hand and led me out of the room. "Ask me no questions, for I cannot answer them. I have no wish to destroy your confidence in human nature -to show you it is but a broken reed. You would not thank me for interfering-no one ever is thanked for meddling in such matters as this; and what is more, I have no right to betray confidence." It, is very strange: and strangest of all, on my table, at my return to my room, lay a folded note. I took it up hastily -once or twice before notes from Dr. Forsythe had been left there' for me - and there, in the same bold hand which I had seen before, were the words: "You' are trusting to a broken reed: see that it does not pierce you." "A broken reed!"  Miss Letty's very words; yet I know it could not have come from her, for ever since I left my room she and I have been together. I cannot understand it. And it is as inexplicable to Dr. Forsythe as it is to me. I have shown him this note, and told him of the preyious letter; and neither he nor I can see any cause for them, nor divine their ^, author.  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7635-00000076"/> 1I52    TWISTED THREADS. But they cannot shake my confidence in the man I have chosen- cannot make me doubt him. His I stainless honor and manliness authorize my trust. Yet I wish Miss Letty had not spoken as she did- wish this note had not come to me. For, struggle against it as I will, it seems a foreboding of evil, a premonition of ill; as though the supreme happi- ness, the perfect rest and content, the halcyon days I have of late enjoyed, were but the lull before the storm  the glimpse vouchsafed to Moses of the promised land, whose borders his feet would never cross. But when I say this to Dr. Forsythe, he laughs, and says I am fanciful, and afraid-woman-like-- of shadows. Yet shadows grow into mists, mists into clouds, and clouds darken the sky, and the sunlight fades, and only a dark, weary day is left. SK. ,   CHAPTER XVII. FOR FRIENDSHP'S SAKE. T is all clear to me now; so clear, that knowing 1 what I now know, seeing what I now see, I can only wonder at myself that I was so, blind-only feel amazed that I could have expected a different ending. For how else could the finale come?-when for weeks past everything has been tending to bring on this result-when, if I only had been true to myself, to my first instincts, so much suffering might have been spared to me and to others. For the shadows deepened into mists, the mists into clouds, and then -the storm burst. I will try to tell it as it all happened, briefly and plainly. Only two days! yet how much was crowded into those brief hours! A week passed, during which I found no oppor- tunity for speaking, as I had intended, to Mr. Ber- nard. But the time came at last, when I least ex- pected it. Such a bright day as it was, too: a day like "A bridal of the earth and sky " - a perfect day - a day in which happy thoughts come into your mind, and pleasant words spring to your 153  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7635-00000077"/> 154   -TWISTED THREADS. lips; and you would like, if you could, to share with every .one the happiness that you feel. Only yesterday! yet it seems ages removed. We cannof -measure such days by hours and minutes and seconds: they are counted in heart-throbs. Maurice and I have been sitting, these evenings, in Bertha's parlor. We are secure from interruption there -and we neither of us like to go to the salon which is common to all the boarders: so, this even- ing, I dressed myself-and with more care than usual-putting on a white dress, because, somehow, my usual sombre draperies seemed incongruous with my feelings, and inconsistent with the day: put one white rosebud in my curls, and then went down to the parlor, to await his coming. To my amazement, I found the room was already tenanted: for there- his arms folded, his brow contracted -stood Allyn Bernard, gazing at Bertha's portrait, which hangs over the piano. It is a lovely picture to look at, so true to nature that you would almost expect the sweet lips to smile upon you, and the fair face to lighten up at your coming: Bertha herself, in all her queen-like loveliness. I was so glad to see Mr. Bernard -could, as I thought, so fully understand the feeling which had brought him to look, and feast his eyes upon the rare beauty of her who henceforth was to walk through life with him: his, and only his--that, with a low exclamation, I came to his side, and laid my hand lightly upon his arm. A violent start was the reply to my light touch: he turned, and I saw that   TWISTED THREADS.       155 he was pale; his lips set firmly together, and a wor- ried expression came over his face. And H-(think- ing this might be only because, man-like, he hated that my eyes should see, ing matter with how much sympathy, how much kindly feeling; the worship - which I believe enters into all true love-- he gave to her who. was the light of his eyes, the desire of his heart)--said to him: "May I not, as a friend, offer with my congratula- tions, my best wishes for your happiness?" He shook off my hand, impatiently. "Both are needless, Miss Lennox." "You are too happy to value them," I said, with a smile. He looked at me in- surprise. "One seldom con- gratulates a discarded lover." It was my turn to be surprised; my turn to start from him, and' to begin, scarce knowing what I said, some expression of regret. He stopped the words upon my lips. "You scarcely believe your own ears, Miss Len- nox; yet I am telling you the solemn truth. You need not pity me, either, though your eyes say you do;, you need not waste sympathy upon me: you will require it yourself ere long-if indeed you do not already know the truth." "I do not understand," I began. "I see you do not--and yet ill news generally flies fast. Miss Lennox, you listened, and the voice of the charmer won you -you are leaning on a reed: it will pierce your heart."  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7635-00000078"/> 156    TWISTED THREADS.     3 "What!"I said, angrily; "you are the author of those two letters. I thought you a gentleman, not a coward!" "Stop!" he said, slowly; "do not condemn me till you know how those warnings came to be writ- ten: how I hoped they would clear your path and mine. The mistake was in sending them to you: they should have gone to Dr. Forsythe." "He has seen them already." "Then," in great surprise, " can you account for this letter - which came to me not half an hour since?" He laid a letter in my hand as he spoke. It was only a few words: "For the compliment shown me in your prefer- ence, I am truly grateful. But my hand is no longer in my power to bestow: it is pledged to Maurice Forsythe." The room grew dark: my heart seemed to stand still; but I did not faint. I caught hold of the man- tel, and stood staring at the letter. "She says nothing about -her heart," Mr. Bernard went on gloomily. "You see, we both suffer, Miss Lennox-the same blow falls on us both: had my letters been regarded, this never could have come. Those letters were written, seeing as I did, that Forsythe hesitated between Bertha and yourself. A word of encouragement from you, and you would have prevailed; and by making you think of him- women love to pluck forbidden fruit-I hoped to t   TWISTED THREADS.       157 make you smile upon him, and then - Bertha would have been mine." "I am truly grateful to you," I said, slowly; " you deserved to fail, after the means you employed." "All stratagems are fair in love or war: and had this one succeeded, Miss Lennox, you would not have blamed me." I made no answer. "It is not pleasant to be caught in one's own trap," he went on, bitterly. "Misery loves company, Miss Lennox: and this is, as I see, a crushing blow to you. I can afford to pity you. When you answer Miss Steiner's letter, which I sent to your room some twenty minutes since, add my congratulations to your own- you will write them feelingly, I know. Don't break your heart over it; think, as I do, that the grapes we cannot reach are sour." I can pardon him his hard words because, poor fellow! he scarcely knew what he did say; and be- cause I know, from the aching at my own heart, how his must feel. "I do not believe it!"I said to myself, as the door closed on his retreating figure. "It cannot- must not - shall not be true!" Then I remembered Bertha's letter -of which he had spoken -and I went to my room to seek for it: to see if in any way it might explain this ttrange story - this truth " stranger than fiction," which was lying in wait for me. Two letters - not only one -lay on the table; the first which I took up was in an unfamiliar hand: the second bore Bertha's well- "     /  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7635-00000079"/> 158    TWISTED THREA DS. -known characters. I laid the first down, unopened and unread; the second I hastily tore open, and as hastily read these words: "Maud, dear Maud, ought I not to be happy? You, dear friend, will rejoice with me when I tell you that I am engaged to Maurice: you know how safe and content I am in his hands. All I want is your ready sympathy in this new life. Will you not congratulate your        BERTHA?" So, it was true. And my part came now -to let Dr. Forsythe know I was aware of the truth. It had come upon me unawares; but I was strong-- strong in my woman's pride: he should not know how this hurt me. In a few cold words, soon spoken, he should hear it all from my lips: and then never again, in this world, should there be any intercourse between us. As I write it all here, I wonder at myself for doing it so calmly. Yet, as it all happened, I was not calm -though writing it down, it is as though I were telling the story of some one else, and not of my- self: I cannot take it home; I am, as it were, be- numbed; perhaps after a while I can realize it all. I remembered at last, dimly -as we remember things in a dream -that Maurice was probably wait- ing for me, and wondering why I did not come. So, after a glance at myself in the glass - my own face frightened me, it was so set, so pale and haggard- I smoothed my hair, bathed my heavy eyes, and   TWISTED THREADS. 1D59 slowly went back to the parlor, nerving myself for the coming interview, as I imagine people nerved themselves to bear the rack and its tortures. But the agony I dreaded, the trial I thought awaited me, were in anticipation as nothing to what they proved in reality. I had not strength, when we first met, to put away the cup from my thirsty lips. I could not at once say the words which would part us. Now, I am glad I was silent: now that I know that Maurice - had he been unworthy I could not have loved him -is, like myself, the victim of circumstances, and that his only fault lay in loving me: a fault I can only too easily forgive. O love! given to us as our greatest blessing, how often dost thou turn to our greatest curse! But at last, with an effort, I began to speak. Ere one sentence had passed my lips, Maurice stopped me. "Before you speak, let me tell my story," he said, pleadingly, his arm around me in a close embrace: from which I could not release myself. "Little one, when I sought you, I thought myself free. I knew of no claims upon me: and now, I stand pledged to two women! Maud, when my step-mother died, leaving Bertha to my care, I promised her that one day I would make the child my wife -it was the best way in which I could care for her; and I. re- solved that if- she should have time to choose for herself-- she was unmarried when she was twenty- three, that day I would offer her what I could, my  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7635-00000080"/> i60    TWISTED THREADS. name and my fortune-it might be- my heart. And as the time came near, I learned to be proud and fond of her--to think she would be mine: till, little one, I met you! -and meeting you, met my fate -and learned that Bertha, with all her beauty, all her grace, was as nothing to- me in comparison with you, my Maud, strong in your very weakness: whom I hold, as I would hold you always, close to my heart! Maud, till I thought myself free, I did not ask you to give yourself to me! True to my promise - sacred, because she to whom it was given was dead--I wrote to Bertha, offering my hand; and saying, that if no answer came within ten days, I would consider silence as denial. I counted each day as it passed: the tenth came, bringing no reply: another and another, and still another. I was free! "Then, Maud, I came to you. And till this day -I speak the solemn, sacred truth --I never knew my true position: never dreamed of Bertha's claim upon me, till her missing letter, mis-sent, was half an hour since laid in my hands. You do not blame me?" "How can I blame you," I said. "Thank God, Maurice, your honor is blameless. I can think of you as I ever did." And then I told him of the scene the room we occupied had witnessed not many minutes before. Then, I added, I saw my own course clear. I could not prove faithless to my friend who trusted me. "And now, Maurice, we must part." He sprang to his feet. "Maud, you are dreaming!"   T WISTED THR EADS.      I6t "No," I said, calmly. "I am not dreaming. Your honor is dearer to me than my own happiness." "What right have you to throw ,my happiness away?" he said, eagerly. "Why -from a mistaken sense of duty -will you trifle with your own heart, and with mine? I do not love Bertha-can never love her. Let me go to her, and tell her: she will soon find consolation in Allyn Bernard's attach- ment." "Stop!"I said, eagerly; "you, I hope, will soon forget me. She has the first claim -mine is nothing. Do not give your future wife the pain of knowing that even for a moment your heart strayed from her; think, rather, of the treasure you have won.  Maurice" -I could call him by that name now - "your honor is at stake: do not make me blush for you." "It is as nothing to me by your love." "Do you care for my happiness?" "Can you ask the question?" "Then do not urge me to what I know is wrong. It will only be a brief pang: and a bright future lies before you. You confess Bertha's claim is first-" "I will never give you up." "And I will never'be your wife." I released myself from his grasp, and, unheeding the pleading "Maud! Maud!" which followed me, I fled to my own room, and sat down to realize what I have done. "*  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7635-00000081"/> 162    .TWI STED THREADS. It is going from calm into storm - from day into night; but I cannot prove false to the friend who trusted me -fail in my duty, hard though it is; and now that I know I must give Maurice up, I love him, if it be possible, more ardently than ever. I can see how this love has become part of my very self. Once, writing in this book of mine-as it now seems, in a prophetic spirit -I said: "If I should ever come, unknowingly, between her and anything she desired to possess, if I proved the obstacle, I would stand aside and let her hand, not mine, clasp the prize." I little thought, when I wrote this, I should ever be called upon, as I now am, to work out the fulfil- ment of my words. But she must never know how, to save her happiness, to preserve his honor, I am going to stand aside and let the golden glory I thought my own pass to another. I cannot stay here to see it --I must go away. Yet, where can I go? Only to-day I notified Madame Levere that I must resign. I have nrot closed my eyes through the live-long night. I have heard every hour strike, one after the other. I have paced my room restlessly--have written, in the vain endeavor to still the aching and fill the empty void in my heart, and in trying to get courage to look fearlessly upon the long, lonely life which lies so plainly before me. It has been such a long nlight; and not one tear have I shed: my eyes are dry and burning, and yet I am calm. Sometimes a mortal wound deadens the nerves of   TWISTED THREADS.         163 sensation, so that there is no pain: it is so with me now. The night is passing, the stars are growing dim, the dawn is coming, "Sad and strange, as in dark summer-dawns," and slowly, yet surely, "( The casement slowly grows a glimmering square." This fearful night is over. Thank God that it is! It seems so much easier to endure in the day-light, when there are things going on all around us to distract us and draw us away from self-contempla- tion; while through the long night-watches- in the darkness that it is so hard to live through, when no rest comes to our wearied bodies, no sleep to our tired eyes, no ease to our aching hearts -we would almost cry, in our agony, "My punishment is greater than I can bear." And to sit, as I have done through this night, looking back mournfully into my past - a thing of yesterday, so near, and yet so far away--and to know that never, by prayers or by weeping, can I -- c" restore me Those days of happiness, forever flown; Or change in aught the d'estiny before me - To pass through life, uncared for and alone!" In these hours I have kept a vigil by the corpse of my dead happiness. With the dawn of this new davI bury it away, never again to rise. I put it  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7635-00000082"/> i64     T WIS TED ZTHREA DS. away from my sight, wishing that, as I do so, I might forget. Yet it might have been worse: there is conso- lation in the thought that I have no reason to blush for the man I love. The day has come--the bright, brilliant day, and with it, my daily duties. One cannot let the little, every-day matters of life pass unheeded, even if one is in distress. Habit and Custom--those stern task-masters-drive us on, and we dare not dis- obey them. The grand routine of the world--its wheel-work and machinery-cannot be stopped because one heart is breaking. ---- I have just spied the letter which came with- Bertha's, and which I had forgotten. Letters, of late, have played such- an important part in the drama of my life--have so twisted its thread with the threads of other lives - that I am almost afraid now to open one: something as one feels on re- ceiving a telegram, dreading the evil tidings that such swift messengers generally impart. But no worse tidings can come to me than have already come. It has brought me good news - cleared my way for me: a loving, womanly letter, whose pleasant words are doubly soothing to me in this dark hour. I never before knew such a person lived: my father's only sister. She, it seems, has just heard of me, and she wishes me to come and share her' home. She refers me to Miss Letty--how much she has,   TWISTED THREADS.       I65 of late, influenced my life--and bids me go to her for information. And the letter is so kindly and lovingly written, that there has sprung up in my heart an earnest longing to go to this Aunt Janet of mine-- she signs herself Janet Wharton-- to be with my own flesh and blood; while, by so doing, I can hide myself, as a wounded animal withdraws from its companions. I have seen Miss Letty, and learnt all she can tell me. It seems that she and Aunt Janet are old friends, and that they have kept up their girlhood's intimacy; and it is through Miss Letty that my aunt-I love her already from Miss Letty's de- scription of her--heard of me. And the reason I never knew anything of her is this: that her hus- band - who is now dead, leaving her a widow, rich, with one child - proved a harsh, unkind man, who 'took her away from home and friends, never letting her see any of them, and intercepting all the letters which came, or which she wrote, so that my father thought her dead. I told Miss Letty of my wish to go to her. "The best thing you can possibly do," was the reply. "It is a pity we did not know all this six months ago: it would have saved you a great deal; but after I found out who you were, it was months before I wrote to Janet." "And when can I go?" "This very day." And Miss Letty has worked hard in my service. She went to the office, sent a dispatch, waited for the  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7635-00000083"/> 166     T WISTED ZTHREADS. reply--and it was a brief one: "Come at once, I will meet her"--came home, gave me, to soothe my restless and agitated nerves, an opiate, which lulled me and rested me, putting me to sleep; and when I did awake, Missy Letty sat by my bed, and my trunk was packed, my little preparations made, and I was informed that in an hour the hack would be at the door, and the next day I would be safe with Aunt Janet. Miss Letty is energetic. "Dr. Forsythe has been to the door several times,"  she said, quietly; "but I told him you were asleep, and could not be disturbed. Then this note was sent up." She handed it to me, then delicately turned away, busying herself. about the room while I read it. It was an earnest, passionate appeal, which nearly broke my heart to read, to think it must be disregarded. I am cruel to myself to be kind to him: what mat- ters it if I suffer, so long as he does right? I have made Miss Letty promise that she will not tell where I have gone-that she will give no clue to my hiding-place. And she will write me. and let me know when they are - No, I cannot write that word. I am all ready-the hack awaits me; I have only to put away this little book of mine, and bid adieu to my little room, where the past two years and a half of my life have been spent. It is hard to do it, for it is like going into exile-- out of the sun- shine into the storm. I have put all his presents, his notes, everything,   TWISTED THREADS.       I67 together-with a line of farewell: they will be given after I am gone. I will bid Miss Letty adieu at the depot, and then -the last link which binds me to the first part of my life will be broken--the first volume closed. And when next I use my pen, it will be at Aunt Janet's. I leave my adieux to Mrs. Wilson with Miss Letty. Little room, dear hopes, sweet dreams- farewell! *.  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7635-00000084"/> CHAPTER XVIII. AUNT JANET'S HOME. I HAVE been at Aunt Janet's for one week. Of the railroad journey, its rapid motion, for twenty-four hours, I remember little: I was almost stupid, scarcely remembering anything, except that I was escaping from danger - doing my duty. Miss Letty got my ticket and check, put me in the cars under the care of some old gentleman, who,-as it appeared, was going my way, and then, with a whis- pered "God bless you,"'and a strange, unusual misti- ness on her glasses, she left me, and the cars were off. It was like all railroad journeys, I suppose-a per- fect rush over hill, dale, and river; a swift-passing panorama of country, nothing distinguishable, a stoppage now and then, a shrill, screaming whistle, and then off again---till, late in the evening of the. second day, just as the sun, in all his June glory, touched the western horizon, my companion touched my arm, and told me that this was my journey's end. I had only time to thank him--I know he found me but a dull compagnon de voyage, for I had been sit- ting, engrossed in my own thoughts the whole way- and for him to see that my trunk was safe, when the whistle sounded&amp; and once more the train was in 168   TWISTED THREA DS.      I69 motion; and for the first time I felt lost and lone, in a strange place. Only for a moment: then a clear, boyish voice said: "Are you my cousin, Maud Lennox? For if you are, mother said I was to bring you home." A handsome, rosy-cheeked boy, with curly chest- nut hair, and great, mischievous brown eyes, of about fourteen, was the speaker, who introduced himself, on my acknowledging my identity, as my cousin, Dick Wharton. And a moment later I was seated in a low buggy, drawn by a shaggy brown pony, and on my way to Aunt Janet's. I am not accustomed to boys, and this specimen of them had a silencing effect upon me: what to say to him I did not know, and he seemed equally puz- zled concerning me; so, after a few commonplace remarks, we were both silent. I was shy and tired, and it was quite a relief when we stopped at last at a pleasant house, at whose door stood, looking for us, some one whom I immediately knew, without Dick's hearty "Mother, here's cousin Maud, and the trunk's coming by-and-by," to be my aunt Janet. And I knew, the moment I looked upon her-even before her kiss met my ready lips, and I was clasped affectionately to her bosom-that I was welcome, and that I should love her, and that she was prepared to love me. "You are Mark's very image, little Maud! I am so glad to see my brother's features in my new daughter. Welcome home, my child; this is your home, and you are mine now." I5  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7635-00000085"/> 17O    - TWISTED THREA D S. I am perfectly at home already, in this pleasant home-nest, where the tired bird may fold her wings and rest. And Aunt Janet is just what I hoped she would be. She is a tall, stately, splendidly developed woman, magnificently proportioned, and carrying herself with unusual dignity and grace. In her youth she must have been beautiful. She is handsome, even now, with her regular features, her smooth, soft com- plexion, and the rich chestnut hair-just beginning to be streaked with gray, Time's silver touches-- which, crowns the broad, intellectual brow, over which you would scarcely think fifty summers had passed. Her hair is too pretty yet to be hidden under the cap she always wears, either of black lace or else of white tarleton. Her dress is always black, mostly soft, lustreless, and heavy silk; her only or- naments her watch-chain and her wedding-ring. And with all her native dignity, there is such a sweet re- pose, a womanly purity, a calm firmness in her man- ner, that you not only love her, but respect her, and think it a pity that there are so few like her. She is, as I think, a perfect woman;-" and the best word I can find to describe her is that which, when given in its full significance, embraces all that is true and lovely and of good report -motherly. A woman of whom it might be said," her children rise up and call her blessed;" with whom you cannot live with- out being the better for it; for the wholesome reality, the true purity of the atmosphere about her, make you feel that you must at least wish to be good, so \  TWISTED TIIREA DS.      171 as to be like her. I cannot bear to think that I have been without her all these years. And yet, in spite of the restfulness -I can use no better word -which is the grand characteristic of Aunt Janet's manner, there is something which, tells you that she has passed through trials, has known trouble, has been made " perfect through suffering." It has not soured or imbittered her:-'it has enlarged her heart, widened her sympathies, and made her what she is, what she only can be -Aunt Janet. And the house over which she presides is just the place you would think she could make it: a HOME in every sense of the word. For it rests with the house-mistress to make the space enclosed within ?: four walls a true home - a little shadow of that Para- dise our first parents forfeited; and some can se- cure a little of that Eden's sunshine to lighten and illuminate their lives and surroundings, and add to' the happiness of those around them. The house - Ivy Lodge it is called --stands at a corner, on the very outskirts of the town. It faces the north-the principal street of R  runs east and west --and in front thereis a tiny grass-plot, with a gravel walk leading to the front door, over which runs a monthly honeysuckle, on which, look when you will,.you can always find a cluster of the fragrant, pink-tinged flowers, which serve as a con- stant banquet for those miniature beauties, the hum-. ming-birds, who, with their dark-emerald bodies and ruby throats, like animated gems, are ever glancing and flashing about the nectar-cups of the flowers.  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7635-00000086"/> -172a    TWIrSTED THREA DS. The west side of the house is covered with ivy, which has crept up the rough gray stone until its caressing fingers have wholly hidden the building, and the windows peep out cosily from a wall of living green. It is a curious-looking old house, dating years back, built with no apparent plan, yet decidedly picturesque with its high, sharp roof, and projecting gables. In- side it is strangely arranged, with quaint, triangular cupboards in the corners of the rooms; low, broad window-seats, some of which are cushioned, so that they are comfortable as any sofa; steps which take you up or down into a new apartment when you least expect it; wainscoted walls-tiled fire-places. The only thing modern about the house are the gas- burners, and they have been carefully selected so as not to appear incongruous with the quaint, old- fashioned appearance of the building. Ivy Lodge-it is well named-has, Aunt Janet tells me, been in the Wharton family since before the Revolution, and it has come down from father to son; and now my boisterous, bright cousin Dick-- the last- of the name--is its possessor. The house has its ghost-story, too; though when Aunt Janet told me the tale she laughed, and said that she had never seen the spirit which was said to haunt the old homestead -the, ghost of one of the daughters of the house, who, loving, as women do, gave her heart, a hundred years back, to a gay, young cavalier, who, like many others of his sex, won the flower only to cast it aside, and left her- to look and wait in vain for his coming - the- com-   WISTEzD   THREADS.       I73 ing of him who came not, till at last, "aweary'" of "her lone watch-keeping," she faded, slowly, slow- ly, into a harmless melancholy, in which she insist- ed'constantly on standing-then, as her, strength failed, sitting--at the window from which she had watched the departure of him who had bidden her look thence for his return: till the frail thread snapped, and the weary, waiting heart was at rest. And, so the story runs, the pale maiden still stands -in spirit-- at her window: still wearily watches for the phantom-bridegroom who will never return. I like these old stories which linger around houses, giving them a sort of human interest. "All houses wherein men have lived and died Are haunted houses. Through the open doors The harmless phantoms on their errands glide, With feet that make no sound upon the floors." I cannot think it improbable that those who have lived in these houses come back to see the old familiar places - that "The spirit-world about this world of sense Floats like an atmosphere "- and that those who have "{gone before " know and enter into our joys and sufferings, kfiowing that ere long we "shall be as they are."    I cannot believe that they who loved us on earth, because they are parted from us for " a little while," are "All forgetful of our sorrow-- Unpmindful of our pain." I So            -  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7635-00000087"/> 174     TWISTED THREADS. I believe that our lost and loved ones, "made per- fect," hover o'er us, as our guardian angels. The whole house is imbued with the spirit of its mistress. Persons of much character put something of themselves into everything they do; and no one could ever think Ivy. Lodge was the home of any one but she who is its presiding spirit. Going over it with Aunt Janet, the moment we came to her own private sitting-room, I knew instinctively -though it is the most plainly furnished room in the house- that it was hers, so strongly does her own individu- ality impress itself upon her surroundings. My own room is a sweet little nest, cool and quiet, with its light cottage furniture, white hang- ings, and fresh matting: its two windows one look- ing on the garden, Aunt Janet's delight -through which the sunshine comes. I cannot bear a room into which a sun-ray never enters: like plants, I pine when away from its life-giving influences; and since I have bestowed, in their proper places, my own little belongings, it is a resting-place in which I take great pleasure. It is such a true, healthy life that I lead here: so different - in the home purity, and calm, Christian atmosphere pervading it-from the rush, noise,and bustle of Mrs. Wilson's establishment, that my life there seems a thing of long ago, and I could almost think that the Maud Lennox who lived that life- stormy and agitated as it was - is a different person from the Maud Lennox who is writing these lines. I could almost believe that I am some one else---   TWISTED THREADS.       175 everything seems, nay, is so changed-if it were not that I cannot forget! Yet, though I have put away from my lips - I dare not think how unwillingly-the sweet cup offered me; though I have chosen a hard path- hard, because it is lonely-instead of one full of pleasure, I hope I may be able to see how many blessings I have left me, and bear my lot unshrink- ingly. I join their names-Maurice and Bertha-every night in my prayers. And, praying for them, I pray that I may learn ' to be content. Time, the great consoler, may heal this dull aching at my heart. O Bertha! Bertha! you little guess at the sacri- fice I have made for you! May the knowledge of it never come to disturb your happiness!  &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7635-00000088"/> CHAPTER XIX. IN CALM WATERS. "' Like the swell of some sweet tune, - Morning rises into noon " N  OONTIDE sinks into evening, evening fades into night, days grow into weeks, and the weeks pass; unnoticed and unmarked. I seldom, if ever, use my pen. In the calm life, like a sum- mer's idyl, that I am now leading, the perfect tran- quillity is such that, though there is nothing to mark them, the hours and days and weeks pass, and I scarcely note their coming before they are gone.. The swiftest current often  underlies the smoothest waters. I am so perfectly at home in Aunt Janet's house --so completely one of the family-that it some- times seems to me impossible that any part of my life could have been spent away from her. And it pleases her that I should feel as I do- gratifies her to think how highly I prize my  present position,. which I  prize as only those can who, tossed about tnd buffeted by the storms of life, come unexpect- edly to a safe haven -- a harbor of rest. I  had wished, after the first few weeks were over ij6 *   T WISTED THREA D S.     1" --after I had grown a little accustomed to the calm regularity of the life we lead, and able to put away some of the pain which at times comes back--to get some pupils in R ; but when I spoke to Aunt Janet on the subject, it was vetoed at once: she had enough and to spare for us both; and in offer- 'ing me a home, she had expected, and in my accept- ance of the offer, I had given her, the right of car- ing for me in every respect, as a mother would for a daughter. "For your father's sake, Maud, if not for mine," were the words which, after all I could say on the subject, silenced me; and when I yielded, she thanked me as if I had conferred a favor upon her. It is a happiness to her to give--and what she does for me is done in such a way that I can see it all comes from the heart--"not grudgingly, nor of necessity," but cheerfully, gladly, and willingly, I do not wonder, seeing her as I do, that she holds the position she does in R : beloved and respected by all, looked up to and consulted; and, even with- out her large-handed hospitality and untiring cheer- fulness, her delicate, unfailing tact, and ready sym- pathy with every one, could not fail to win her the love and friendship of every one with whom she comes in contact. She is "never weary of well- doing," and " whatsoever her hand finds to do, she does it with her might.'" Aunt Janet is not given to speaking of herself: in talking, she seems to forget her own identity - the "Ich"--of which some people are so very  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7635-00000089"/> I78     TWISTED TPREADS. conscious that this "Self" forces itself upon you whether you will or no, and you feel, no matter how agreeable or entertaining the speaker may be, that the words are only for effect, or, as children say, "i all talk," more to please the speaker than the lis- tener, as though a man were speaking to his own image reflected in a glass; but she interests herself in everything and everybody, understanding and making allowance for everything. I have, by slow degrees, "line upon line, here a little and there a little," picked up the story - there is a story in every life- of Aunt Janet's :youth. It P  is an old story, and a common one: a young girl won by honeyed words, a handsome face, and a smooth manner --to find, when it was too late, that this was only the fair outside--that pure gold had been given for dross. She has never said all this in words. Miss Letty's hints gave me a clue, and one day I asked Aunt Janet what sort of a man my uncle Wharton had been. "A very handsome one," was the quiet reply. I -"And your -married life, was it happy?"I went on. "No, Maud," she said calmly, "it was not. But I have ' Let the dead -Past bury its dead.' There are trials in every life. I could not hope to escape." "But your husband - " "'Was- my husband. The faults -of the dead are sacred. Those who are gone should only be spoken   TWISTED THREADS.       179 of in kindness. The shroud covers many faults, the grave buries many bitternesses." "And your children, Aunt Janet?" "I try to think of them as treasured in heaven- safer there than even here in their mother's care." "I cannot understand your being so cheerful!" "Little Maud"- every one gives me that name- "when you go out, do you look most for pleasant, or for disagreeable things? Life is not all made up of sorrows: if you look for flowersyou can find them. Why seek only for the thorns?" "But ( Robins will not build in winter hail, Nor lilacs bloom in February,'  I objected. Aunt Janet laughed. "Does not every season bring its own pleasures, little girl? Winter has its sunny days and cloudless skies as well as summer-time." I. shall be quite a notable housekeeper some of these days, if I only follow Aunt Janet's example. She is initiating me into the mysteries of cookery --a thorough understanding of which is indispen- sable, she thinks, to every woman. Then every morning I have certain things to do: I give Dick lessons in French, dust the parlor, and replenish the flower-vases-which used to be Aunt Janet's work; now delegated me, as I shrewdly suspect, to get me as much as possible into the open air. Aunt Janet is proud of her garden, and with rea- son. It is no trim, set parterre, where the flowers are like ball-room beauties, to be admired at a dis-  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7635-00000090"/> 180     T! WISTED THREAS. tance - regular touch-me-nots -but an old-fash- ioned garden, a perfect wilderness of sweets, full of old-fashioned, fragrant flowers, which, cut them as you may --and Aunt Janet cuts her flowers with no sparing hand -are every day covered with fresh and renewed beauty. Their mistress says: "aOne's chief pleasure in flowers is the giving them away." There is no regular plan in this garden: here and there the masses of flowers glow brilliantly from the emerald setting of the grass, which is kept smoothly cut; roses stand everywhere in rich profusion; the plants are so arranged, that from the early spring, when first crocus and snowdrop come timidly from their long sleep, to the November frosts, which cut off the dahas and last hardy chrysanthemums, there is a constant succession of bloom. The hyacinths and tulips and the lilac-blooms are long since over. Sweet-william has faded; rocket, in her purple cap, which the honey-bee visits, with the white-head, which. I caught as a child, fearless of its sting, the unarmed drone, lingering over her heavy clusters till their honey intoxicates and stupefies him; roses in every variety, from glowing scarlet to stainless white; graceful fuchsia, fragrant mignonette, rich, spicy-odored pinks, great velvet-coated pansies, tall gaudy gladioli, forget-me-not, golden marigolds-- tuch are a few of the flowers blooming in this gar- ten, where bee and bird and butterfly come and go, ndisturbed and welcome. One day I found, hidden away in a rose-bush, a   TWISTED 2THRES DS.         ISl tiny sparrow's nest. The little birds were fledged and gone, yet the nest, their wind-swung cradle, was sweet, fresh, and clean; and, looking at it, wonder- ing at the dainty neatness with which its nature- taught architect had built it, I saw, to soften its lining to the tender skin of the callow young, a few gray hairs woven in with   the other materials--a strange ending for the crown of old aje-its silver hair. Aunt Janet spends much time in her garden, and though to my unpracticed   eye it seems as if every thing was in order, she never goes among her plants without finding somdthing to be pruned, something to be trained: except on Sundays, when she walks in the evening along the paths, her hands folded, singing--her voice   is yet sweet---snatches    of hymns. Last Sunday I sat and listened to her; only a verse came now and then: "Saviour! teach me how to love Thee, Make me cling to Thee alone: Thou who art in heaven above me, Thou! all-good, the Holy One! To Thy Cross my hands are clinging- Strengthen there my trembling hold; To Thy feet as,offering bringing This poor heart-once dull and cold." I lost the next verse. Then the song went on: "C Let me love Thee more, my Saviour! Let me hold Thee all my own: Look to Thee for every favor, Trust in Thee-love Thee alone, i6 %   &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7635-00000091"/> I82      TWISTED THIREADS. I am blind! oh, do Thou guide me! Sick--Thou canst my sorrows cure: Safe beneath Thy Cross now hide me, There, and there alone, secure! "Of my own, I have no merit-- I but lean upon Thy word-- Led by Thy own Holy Spirit, I may dare to call Thee - Lord! I am worthless, weak, and trembling; Yet at Thy dear feet I fall - To the cross that saved me clinging- Hear, O Lord! a sinner's call. "Thou who once, for man's transgression, Bore the cross; endured the shame, On my heart,.in deep impression Place, in love, Thy sacred Name- That, at last, my sins forgiven- Death defeated, cleansed my dross- I may dwell with Thee in heaven - - Bliss eternal! - 'neath Thy Cross." Later that evening, I    asked  her where  she had found these words, unfamiliar to me. She blushed like a girl. "Little one, do   you  not know  that, sometimes, 'out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaketh?' " - and that was all. Aunt   Janet's religion, however, is not   only a thing for Sundays: it enters into her whole life, and influences her every action. Sunday, in her house, is a beautiful day--a holy day and a holi- day- a    day on  whicheven  Dick--true  boy as he is on  all other days-softens    down  in a reverent   TWISTED THREADS.      I83 way that I can see is most gratifying to his mother, whom he looks upon as something better than any one else; and she--I can only describe her love for her boy by using Scripture words, which some- how always suggest themselves when I try to de- scribe her---perhaps because the spirit -of the Holy Book so pervades and is a part of her---and say her love is such as is given to " the only son of his mother, and she a widow." Ah! if to this pure life have come so many trials, as I know they have, how could I ever have hoped --I who am so imperfect, so full of faults--that my lot should have been free from care, my path easy to my feet? I said that Sundays here were beautiful days, days full of rest and peace, which round off the weeks into perfect wholes-days on which no unneces- sary work is done: there is no smell of cooking through the house, all that being prepared, as far as is possible, the day before, when the house is "set in order"--when we three walk through the shady streets to the little church, ivy-mantled and shadowed with trees, where the sunlight falls in quivering glory through the trembling leaves. Then come our Sunday-school duties, I have a class of little girls, whose eyes brighten and whose lips smile at "Miss Maud's" coming. Then the day ends with our sitting, in the evening, on the porch, and talking, reverently, of the Beautiful City- Jerusalem the Fair-of whose joys these earthly pleasures are but a dim foretaste, and where there  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7635-00000092"/> 184    TWISTED THREADS. are "no tears," no sorrow, no pain, nor grief, nor death, but everlasting life, and joy unspeakable; and then I think that, for this glorious Future, we can easily endure "our light afflictions, which are but for a moment," though they seem to us as eternities of suffering. And on other evenings, Dick and I, mounted on the two ponies -who, cared for as everything on Aunt Janet's premises is cared for, inhabit the warm, well-kept stable - go over the country, far and near, returning in time to change our dress in readiness for the pleasant tea, at which all the events of the day are talked over. Visitors drop in, in the even- ings, one of whom- and the one who comes the oftenest -is the young clergyman who officiates at the church we attend: a man who has sense, edu- cation, and refinement, but who spoils it all by the constant parade- he makes of his learning, and his insufferable conceit. He is a slight, short man, with long, fair hair-which is smoothly brushed from his forehead; soft blue eyes, a delicate mous- tache-which he smooths constantly with his very white and well-kept hand; and a manner which, in its cat-like softness, is very unpleasant to me. His conversation is profusely besprinkled with poet- ical quotations, which creep even into his sermons- which, by the way, are unusually good, if only I could separate the man from the minister. He is delicately neat, even to fastidiousness, in his per- sonal appointments - so neat, that one would think him just out of a bandbox, in which he kept him-   TWISTED   THREADS.       I85 self for fear of getting dusty. I imagine he lives in perpetual fear of that traditional "peck of dirt" which destiny has condemned us all to eat, and de- sirous of deferring the evil day as long as possible - or, if the thing must be taken, receiving it in in- finitesimally small quantities -homceopathic doses. "As neat as a new pin, Mr. Dennis always is," I heard one of his parishioners -herself not noted for tidiness- say a few days since: which wickedly made me think that pin and minister alike had heads, and both contained much-brass. Aunt Janet would scold - no, her gentle rebukes are not scolding -and say I was sadly deficient in the charity which "thinketh no evil." I might be very happy here -I ought to be. I would be, if it were not for the past, which, like a huge bleak rock, with the legend "NO MORE" deeply carved upon its surface, still overshadows me, cast- ing its dark reflections over present and future. Though it returns not again, I cannot put it aside: its' memories linger with me--I cannot, if I would, shake them off. I hear from Miss Letty occasion- ally. Bertha is still away-Dr. Forsythe still mak- ing efforts to find me; and every time I see or write his name, the old pain comes back, telling me "Experience is bitter, but its teachings we retain: It has taught me this: who once has loved, loves never on ea th again! No! if you have truly loved, you will still love on, I know, Till the church-yard myrtles blossom above, and you lie mute below." I sit and think over it all, till I fully realize-how I6*  &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7635-00000093"/> i86     TWISTED THREADS. is it that the poet, unless he speaks from his own heart, can express in words what we feel-- "That a sorrow's crown of sorrow is remembering happier things," --till, knowing, as I know,- that my love for Maurice Forsythe is my very self, and that with my own hand I have closed the world of happiness and love to myself- it may be only for a vain idea of my own, my sacrifice of self fruitless--I, in the seclusion of my little room, push my book -my silent confidant - from me, and then-  I seldom weep-those tear-springs -lie too deep to be easily moved; yet, when they come, they are not soft and refreshing, but violent, burning drops, which I cannot control, and which fall until exhaustion dries their source. Ah! Aunt Janet! you little guess what a heavy load I bear--what restless, agonizing pain, what bitter, unavailing regret find expression in the calm, holy refuge you, in your goodness, have given to your brother's child! Some one has said that the book of life that sad volume to which each day, as- it passes, adds a new chapter - should be. called "Illusions Perdzes ;" for oh! how many of our brightest hopes, our early anticipations, prove as "lost" and as "illusory" as do the pictures which the Fata Morgana, in Eastern lands, presents to the weary traveller.   CHAPTER   XX. ,OVER THE, FIRE. T HE brilliant summer has ripened into golden autumn -the autumn is swiftly changing into winter; the trees have lost the gorgeous tints with which of late they have been decked, and stand, save where a few withered leaves cling to the branches, in bare tracery against a frosty, yet clear sky -only the cedars and box preserve their ver- dure. The last flowers are gone; not even in Aunt Janet's garden, where only in one or two sheltered spots the grass is yet green, can I find flowers enough to fill even one small vase for our parlor. The birds are gone, the butterflies dead: even the great, noisy bees, who in their black and orange livery buzzed and hummed merrily among the flow- ers, drinking their honey, or dusting themselves, miller-like, with the pollen, are gone. The summer constellations have passed from the evening sky, to give way to the more brilliant stars of winter. It is too early, as yet, for snow, though every morning the great alchemist, the sun, turns the hoar-frost to glistening jewels--though every night the Ice-king flings over the, brooks a delicate tracery, like lace- work, it is not strong enough as yet to check their 187  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7635-00000094"/> 188      TWISTED   TIIRE ADS. rippling flow, and the clear, dancing waters go on merrily over their pebbly bed, bordered by the soft mosses which even under the deepest snows retain some of their verdure -as some hearts, some lives, through the hardest trials, and in the bitterest afflic- tions, retain their unvarying goodness and their perfect trust. Our evenings on the porch are over; yet-I believe I enjoy sitting in-doors, by the cheerful blaze of the grate, under the soft light of the Argand burner, quite as much. It is all bright and pleasant enough, so long as I am  with the others, where Aunt Janet's womanly talk, and Dick's playful nonsense, never fail; but when I go   to my own  little room, and sit over the  fire-which  is lighted there every day- then I give up, and "Out of the gathering winter-chill, All out of bitter St. Agnes' weather, When the fire is out, and the house is still," :hen I  sit-unable to sleep-and think; and my    tru- nt fancies take  such strange shapes--as  in the words of a poem I! read only a few days since: "When the hours of the day have departed-- Though not yet is the calm night come-- And the toils of the day are all ended, I sit in the gathering gloom. "Not as yet are the glaring lamps lighted- Scarce, as yet, is the twilight o'er; But the moonlight pours in through my windows, And silvers my parlor floor.   -TWISTED     THREADS.       I89 "Then my thoughts all go back from the Present To that wonderful realm, the Past, As I sit here, and muse in the fire-light, Till the, tears fill my eyes at last. "Then I weave, as I gaze in the fire, All my thoughts into simple rhyme; Yet my songs never bear but one burden-- Memories of the olden time. "And I feel gentlest hands, which caress me, Soft kisses, which fall on my cheek; And I know. that loved spirits are near me, Though I never can hear them speak; "For they hover near me in the moonlight, They linger near me, as of yore; And the friends, in those long-past days cherished, Are with me, in spirit, once more. 's Then my mother's soft words come back to me - Though she lies, calm in dreamless rest-- And I once again feel myself folded To her gentle and loving breast: "And my father's kind hands lie in blessing On my weary and aching head: I can scarce, in my evening dreaming, Realize they are with the dead. "For the moonlight, that pours through my windows, And which silvers my lonely room, Falls alike, as a Heaven-sent blessing, On their distant and moss-grown tomb. "And once more, as I sit here in silence, I live o'er the long-vanished years; Till my heart nearly breaks with its longing, And my eyes are all weary with tears.  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7635-00000095"/> Ig90     T WISTED   THREADS. "Oh! all vain are my tears and my longing! Wild prayers, ye may never be heard! By no sound is the silence e'er broken, By no footfalls the echoes stirred. "But the firelight dies out in its embers, The night wanes, in gathering chill; Yet I sit, through the long, lonely hours, Till the house is all calm and still. "It is past-and I turn from my dreaming, With tears which I cannot restrain, From past joys to the cares of the present, To take up life's burdens again." I had just copied  these lines, and was sitting, as I often do, my hair pushed from my brow, wishing I scarce knew what, when my door opened, and Aunt Janet came into the room. "You   up yet, Maud!   You will get no 'beauty sleep' to-night, little girl.   What has kept   you up?" she asked, playfully, laying her hand on my open book.   "Verses! I declare!   I did not know that this curly head   belonged  to a poetess. How is it, Maud?" I laughed, in spite of myself. "No, auntie: they are only mine because I copied them. And this," laying my hand with -hers on the open pages of my    'libellus,' "is my--I cannot call -it diary-my   mirror, in which I see myself, in which my story, such as it is, is recorded." "Well, may I   not hear some  of my Maud's pretty thoughts?"  Aunt Janet asked, with a     smile.  "I was young once, Maud--it would take me back to   TWISTED THREAADS.       19I my own youth to hear any thing you choose to tell me." "I cannot show you this book, dear auntie," I said, moved by a sudden impulse, a sudden longing for the sympathy I instinctively felt she could give me; " but, if you will listen, I will tell you all - all I can." And, sitting at her feet, I began the story. The seal of silence once removed, it was easy to speak. I told it all, concealing nothing--how, through Bertha, I had met Maurice--how, by slow degrees, I had learned to love him-and how, at last, I had laid my own heart, my own happiness, a sacrifice on the altar of my friendship. Aunt Janet listened in silence, and as I finished- it was a relief to tell her -I asked her if I had done right. "Of that you are" the best judge," she said, thoughtfully. "So far as I can see, your course was clear. Maud, I knew part of this story before. Letty told me much, but I wanted to hear it from your own lips. Often --knowing what I knew, see- ing what I saw -I longed to take you in my arms, and give you my ready sympathy, with what con- solation I could offer; but I could not force them upon you: your confidence must be given willingly -my sympathy sought: I could not intrude my- self into that on which you were silent." "It was such a bitter trial," I said, slowly, " that I could scarcely bear to think of it, much less- even though I wished it- speak of it, even to you." *    2  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7635-00000096"/> 9z     TW 1TWISTED TIIREADS. "Ah! little girl, sorrows and trials come into every life, as rain into every summer! Sometimes the drops fall hard and plashing, breaking and destroy- ing every green thing, blighting all the fair promise: again, they come gently and tenderly, softening the soil, refreshing and opening it to all good influences, so that, afterwards, the fruits come forth in rich abundance. I hope the latter will be my Maud's case." I looked up, my eyes dim with tears, to see an answering moisture in Aunt Janet's, as she bent over and kissed me--,one of her rare, yet all the more prized, caresses. "Yet," I said, "it is hard to me to think that I am cut off, as 'it were, from the dearest joys of life- that I must live, with no one to love me, while .my whole heart cries out for love--to sit with my hands idly folded, when I would so gladly take a woman's duties upon me. Aunt Janet, I could some- times almost say, 'I would that I were dead.' " "Maud, for shame!" she said, in reply to these words. "That is not the right spirit for you to take your cross. If you wish for love for work- there is enough in this world of the one to fill your empty heart--of the other, to busy your willing hands. Is the love of your Sunday-school class nothing to you? do you hold it as nothing that you are to me as a daughter--to my boy as an elder sister? Mauaud, ud, you should have more cour- age: you have been brave; be braver yet!" "Then you must teach me, auntie," I said. "I    TWIS TED THR EA D S.    193 was wrong: if one blessing be denied me, I will remember I have many others left me." "Right! dear child, right! And even that bless- ing, which seems now so far away from you, may yet, if it be best for you, be restored to you; yet, not unless it should be best for you. And even if it should not come, and you should live single, your life need not be a lonely or unhappy one: you may live for others, doing your duty faithfully; you may be happier in the future than you now deem it pos- sible : and after all, Maud dear, what will it matter, if, after these few brief years, we are told, 'Well done, good and faithful servant.' I think we make our crosses harder by looking at them and brood- ing over them; while, if we took themn up bravely, they would, after awhile, grow so light and easy that we would at last forget that they were crosses." "I hope it may prove that your words are true," I said, as, with a kiss, we parted for the night. I feel all the better for this conversation -all the better because Aunt Janet knows the great grief of my life. Her sympathy, her loving words, are more than grateful to me: they have given me courage; and I firmly believe that now, and in future, I shall be happier, and more self-controlled. It is so-pleas- ant to be understood, to know Aunt Janet does not think me--as I .am sometimes tempted to think myself- Quixotic and romantic. I once, in this little book of mine, spoke of Mr. Dennis. Through his constant visits at the house, a sort of familiarity -I could not call it friendship 17  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7635-00000097"/> 194     TWISTED THREA DS. -grew up, by degrees, between us. But I was wholly unprepared for what came at last: a- request, in most poetical language, far-fetched and flowery, that I would "become the mistress of his house, even as I was mistress of his affections." There was but one answer I could make: a cour- teous declination of the proffered honor. Aunt Janet says that I have no business to let such a good opportunity for work pass out of my hands; but there is a twinkle in her eye contradict- ing her words. For I cannot, even for a moment, think of giving the hand, once promised to him, to -another. I know that love is, and will be, the one love of my life. Late flowers last longest. Yet, as the days shorten, I wonder at myself that I am so much more cheerful, so much happier. "Who knows, little woman," Aunt Janet said to me, a few days since, "but that the close of the year may brighten -for y6u! Keep a good heart; the clouds may yet pass wholly away from your sky. Only wait, and be patient." Patience -waiting: alike Aunt Janet's and Mau- rice's words. O Maurice! Maurice! if, by patient waiting, I could only, in honor, win you back, I would count myself well paid for years of waiting!   CHAPTER XXI. THE BEST CHRISTMAS-GIFT. THE year is nearly over. One week more- that is all--and this wonderful year of my life will be past. This is Christmas-eve; and as I sit here, alone, in my little chamber, watching the flickering fire, and every now and then writing :a line or two in this little'book of mine-in which there are so few blank pages now left-I can hardly think that I am really myself. And then I push away my pen, and utter a silent thanksgiving for the infinite mercy which has been showed me. This has been a day of all days - such a day as I believe seldom comes even into the lives of those who are the happiest. I woke up this morning so bright and cheerful, as though something sweet - what, I could not say - was to come to me: there was so much peace in my heart, so much joy in my feelings. And such a lovely day as it was, too, with its clear, cloud- less, deep-blue sky! such dazzlingly white snow! such. a bracing freshness in the air! I thought I was so happy because our Christmas preparations were over--church and house alike adorned and 195  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7635-00000098"/> 196    T-WISTED THREADS. set in order for the morrow's festival--that some of the holy joy of this blessed season had entered into my heart. I know now that it was the reflec- tion of the coming joy, which, as the dawn gives promise of the day, was beginning to shine upon me. I was in my room, putting the last touches to my dress-Aunt Janet likes to see me with my hair curled and my dress tastefully arranged - when the little maid-servant came to my door and gave me a card. It was weeks since a line had come to me from Miss Letty, and at first I thought that it was barely possible she might have come to spend the holi- days with us; but I remembered, then, that she would not send a card into Aunt Janet's house, and I looked at it, to see, in surprise, that it bore the name- MRS. BERNARD. Mrs. Bernard! whom I scarcely knew. I went down slowly. What interest could she take in hunting me, Maud Lennox, out-she, with whom I had barely a speaking acquaintance? But when, very hesitatingly, I opened the door, -and the faint verbena-odor saluted me--even now I think how wonderful it was - I was caught in the embrace of my friend - Bertha Steiner. And, for a moment, I forgot everything in the joy of seeing her. But at last I remembered, and then I asked where Mrs. Bernard was.   TWISTED THREADS.       I97 "Mrs. Bernard!"Bertha gayly repeated. "I have news for- you --much news, Maud: first of which is that- I am Mrs. Bernard." I looked at her in utter -amazement. She smiled - her own sweet smile -at my mystified face. "Bertha, I thought - "I managed, at last, to say. She interrupted me. "Yes, Maud, I know what you thought- I know what your sense of honor made you do: sacrifice yourself for others. Ah! could you not think that others might be unwilling to accept that sacrifice - because, in so doing, they perilled their own' happi- ness? Friend, you should have known me better." "How could I know?"I asked; as by degrees the truth began to dawn upon me. "Bertha, is it, can it be possible that you --" "Loved Allyn Bernard all the time? Yes, Maud; the whole secret lies in those few words." "Then," I went on, " how did you ever come to accept Mau - Dr. Forsythe?" ( Because, Maud, I never, for a moment, guessed that there was, or could be, any feeling between you. Mr. Bernard said nothing. , Maurice spoke, and I, scarcely knowing my own feelings-think- ing that if Maurice really loved me,- gratitude for his unfailing care, esteem for his noble qualities, respect for him as a man, were sufficient to insure my happiness as his wife- never for one moment dreaming that honor alone had led him to offer me his hand -what could I do but accept him? "Then, Maud, came Mr. Bernard's offer-came 17  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7635-00000099"/> 198     TWISTED THREADS. one week too late; for, as I read his passionate, ardent words, they found a responsive echo in my own heart. But I was bound: I must try to be con- tent with my lot that I had chosen; and I wrote to Allyn-not as my heart, but as my duty dictated. I heard from Maurice occasionally: his letters gave me no hint of the true state of the case -every day twisted the threads in a more complicated manner. "At last I came back to Mrs. Wilson's. I had wondered at your silence --I wondered still more at your absence. I questioned Maurice, who I thought was gloomy and unlover-like: he knew nothing. Meantime, living, as I did, under Mrs. Bernard's care-you know she is my cousin meeting Allyn every day, I began to rebel, more and more, against my bonds the more so, that when Maurice spoke of our marriage, it was as of some- thing far off; and I, knowing that I did not love him -that there was even less confidence between us than there had been in the past-longing to know where you were, and why the rnere mention of your name was so distasteful to Maurice; and remembering, at last, your intimacy with Miss Letty, I went to her. "I began to speak of you; but before I had said many words,. Miss Letty's evident interest led me on, imperceptibly, to speak of myself, till the whole truth-more even than I had dared to acknowledge to myself-was told. "Then, Maud, Miss Letty began to speak of you. She told me everything; and as she told, it all grew   TWISTED THREADS.       199 clear. We might all yet be happy! Our good friend offered-and I could only thank her for it- to see Maurice, to explain, as only she could, the tangled story. Can you doubt my answer? "How she did it, I cannot say; but that very evening Maurice and I had a long talk, our old bro- ther and sister relations - which should never have been changed-- fully restored, and everything ar- ranged for the future; and, a day or so later, Allyn Bernard, learning from Maurice's lips that I was free, came to me; and, one week ago, we were married. And so, Maud, your generous self-sacrifice has at last brought happiness to all of us; and might have been unnecessary, if only some one of us had had courage to look facts in the face, instead of try- ing, as we all did, to avoid them. But I must go. Maurice gave me an hour to prepare you. I must send him here to plead his own cause." She was gone. And I had listened, in silence, to this strange unravelling of all our difficulties. I did not try to detain her--I could not. I sat in Aunt Janet's pleasant parlor--how long, I do not even now know -till at last I was roused from my revery by feeling a strong clasp of my hands, a warm kiss on my cheek, and I started to my' feet- only to be caught to Maurice's heart. "Little Maud - truant Maud - my Maud - have I found you at last!" And oh! how can I describe that meeting- that interview--its loving reproaches--its tender ex- planations! Even here, on these pages, sacred to  &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7635-00000100"/> 200    1TWISTED THREADS. myself, I cannot record it, though every word is written on my heart. It was a blessed Christmas-eve! Late that evening, as, after Bertha and her hus- band - handsome, happy couple that they are--had left us, and even Maurice's lingering, reluctant adieux had been said, Aunt Janet called me into her room, and we talked it all over. And she has gladdened my heart by saying: "I like him, Maud; and I can give you, willingly, to him. I do not wonder that you love him." But I wonder how I can be so happy. I must not forget that I told Aunt Janet--(I can scarcely regret the past trouble, because through it I have known her, and because it makes me value only the more my present perfect bliss)-- of my old fancy about Miss Letty. Alas for the Romance I had fashioned! She cnew my father, but it was after his marriage, and [ owed the interest she took in me to her love for Runt Janet..,   CHAPTER XXII. THE LAST NIGHT OF THE YEAR. FOR the last time, I take up my pen. It is New- year-eve-near midnight. Ere many minutes the old year will be dead. In a very few lines, now, my book will be filled. f To-morrow is my wedding-day. So, in this happy week, among my best friends - Bertha, Aunt Janet, and Miss Letty -who came, in response to the telegram sent her - has it all been settled. Maurice wished it-he said he wished to secure me before I could again run away--the others thought it advisable, and my own heart could not say nay. One of Maurice's friends, a clergyman from a neighboring town -we could not ask Mr. Dennis- will perform the ceremony. And the only drawhack to my happiness is, that I must leave Aunt Janet; and I believe it is equally hard for her to give me up. I intend to follow, so far as I may, in her footsteps, though. I can never be what she is. We are to live in New York, but every summer, during Maurice's vacation, we shall be here, and Aunt Janet will sometimes be with- me. 201  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7635-00000101"/> 202     T WISTED THREADS. The future is very bright before me. With Mau- rice's hand to lead me, his arm to support me, what need I fear? I linger over these pages, loth to leave them. I can scarcely bear to lay them aside forever. I shall never again keep a diary. For though with the morrow -the New Year- a new life, a changed fate awaits re, that life, that fate will be merged in another: Maud Lennox will be no more. And so, on the threshold of this great change, of this'new life- the last bit of Eden left on earth, the fruition of all true happiness, the crown of man- hood and womanhood - I stand, as on the verge of the coming year, looking forward gladly, yet trem- blingly. Little book, farewell! Some day you may tell Maurice Forsythe what Maud Lennox has never yet found words to tell him: how much she loves him. 'He will take your place--the partner of my joys, consoler of my sorrows--the one doubled, the other lightened, because shared by him. Hark! the last stroke of the clock dies upon the air! The old year is dead, the new year begun! I lay aside my pen: the book is ended-the story of my life is told. THE END.   3   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>