<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7603">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >My Step-mother, or, The Power of Love </title>
            <author >Roberts, Sarah.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7603</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >My step-mother, or, The power of love</title>
                  <author >Roberts, Sarah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >203 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >General Protestant Episcopal Sunday School Union and Church Book Society</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1856">[1856]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-02-15">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>My step-mother, or, The power of love</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7603-00000001"/>After I had breakfasted, and as comfortably seated in my lsy-chair,-PParc 166    MY STEP-MOTHER; OR. HE POWE IT OF LOVE. BY SARAH  ROBERTS, fh AUTHOR OF "MY CHLDHOOD," "OUR OPPOSITE NEIGHBOR," ETO. "A new commandment give I unto you." NEW YORK: GENERAL PROTESTANT EPISCOPAL SUNDAY SCHOOL UNION, AND CHURCH BOOK SOClETY,  713 BROADWAY.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7603-00000002"/>  Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1S56, by DANA AND COIMPANY,    ! In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the UlJited States for the Southern District of New York.    TO MY BELOVED LITTLE NIECES, EMMA AND FANNY PERRY. THE FOLLOWING PAGES ARE MOST AFFECTIONATELY DEDICATED, WITH THE EARNEST PRAYER, THAT THE WORDS OF THEIR MOUTHS AND THE MEDITATIONS OF THEIR HEARTS MAY ALWAY BE ACCEPTABLE IN THE SIGHT OF THE LORD, OUR STRENGTH AND OUR REDEEMER. S. R.  &#xD;<pb n="0Table of Contents" xml:id="VAC7603-00000003"/>  CONITENTS. PTER                      PAGB I.-TIIE NEW MOTHER .......................    5 II.-MY BAPTISM ...........................   . 15 III.--MRS. NELSON'S REMOVING .................. 20 IV.- TIE RAINY DAY .........................   28 V.--THE NEW DRESS ..........................   36  VI.-WIDOW GRAHAMH ......................... 48  VII.-ANOTHER PICTURE OF MYSELF ............... 58 VIII. -THE HOUSE-MOVING .....................    " IX.-AN IMPORTANT CHANGE ...................    86 X. -A NEW FRIEND .......................... 101 XI.-ONE OF MY SUNDAY LESSONS ............... 113 XII.-CONVERSATION BETWEEN MOTHER AND BLANCHE. 117 XIII.-NRW CAUSE OF I)SAGRUEEMENT ............ 124 XIV.-MY DISAPPOINTMENT ....................... 136  XV.-THE SLEIGH-RIDE. ......................... 144 XVI.-MY ILLNESS. ............  ............   154 XVII.-MY CONVALESCENCE.....   .......    . 166  XVII.-MY OLD NUvSE ...    .  ..........   175  XIX.--MATTIE'S IETURN HOM.   .................. 186 XX.--CONFIRMATION AND COMMUNION ............. 196 *,    MY STEP-MOTHER. CHTAPTER I. THE NEW MOTHER. "DEAR me! dear me! Miss Grace, be quiet, please, for only five minutes; you will never be dressed in  time. How could you torment poor nurse so, and keep her running to the window and the door, back- wards and forwards, up stairs and down, for the last hour, until she is quite tired out looking for you? I was afraid you had got into trouble again, with that great bold Matilda, who is always leading you away. She is not fit to hold a candle to you, deary; why, her mother and me has stood side by side at a wash-tub, many a day, and a wild young thing she was, just like her daughter. And she now thinks, because her husband has made some money, nobody knows how, and has built a house big enough for a tavern, that her great bold Matilda must go to school and keep company with all the ladies in the town. But, poor dear, you will have somebody to look after you, soon, who will keep you pretty straight, I guess. Step mothers haven't much mercy, that I know; but -: 4    &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7603-00000004"/> 6        MY STEP-MOTHER.  poor old nurse will always befriend you, Miss Gracey, be sure of that. Come and tell her all your troubles." I mean to do just as I please, nurse, I replied; when nurse Hopkins paused a moment to take breath. I am thirteen years old now, and old enough to take care of myself; she will not be my mother. "Dear me! what a spirit the child has," continued nurse; "she will be your father's wlfe, Miss Grace, and your step-mother; and step-motl ers do not let their step-daughters do as they please. I have seen enough to know that. But it is best for you to set out pretty firm at first. Dear me! what a whiskabout the child is; she must be set on wires i Do be quiet; you will never look fit to be seen, or be ready before they come; and then what will your Pa say, when he wrote word that you must be all ready to receive them? Dear, dear, I will give up. There is, your boot-string broken, and your ruff torn. What a sad child you are'! Well, your step-mother will learn you to be careful, in a short time. Step-mothers are very particular people. She will have you under foot in no time, that's certain. But, oh dear, there is the sound of a carriage; and your best sjlk apron is not even out of the drawer. How could you stay out to play so long, and worry old nurse so? My hand trembles; and I am all of such a fluster I cannot tie a nice bow at all.    MY STEI'-MjO'THER, .  ' 6What a fille day vour Pa' and your stelp-mother have had for their jou:nlevy home. I 'wonder how she will like our quiet town and our plain folks and ways. They say she is a city lady; but there, deary, you are all ready now; and you. look as pretty and fresh as a rose, and the carriage has stopped at the door. Run dowln ,ald meet them;, Miss Grace; and smile and look pleased, and give her a welcome at any rate. That is but manners, you know; and I will just run into the hall and look out of the window, and see how she looks as she leaves the carriage." So saying, nurse iluriied from the room. This was her usual mode of tallking, while she dressed me, every day. I. was so accustomed to hearing it, that I did not always listen. But, to-day she so often repeated, and so purposely, I know, the hated word, step-mother, tihat I listened eagerly. I did not go down stairs, as she bade me, but stood moodily meditating on some of her improper and ill-judged remarks, and busying myself with conjuring up the most unpleasant images of harsh step-mothers, from pictures my friend Matilda Miller, and 'my nurse, and cook had presented to me; determining that I would not present myself as long as I could possibly help it. I know not how long I stood there; but I was quite startled at my nurse's' expressionl of dismay, as she re-entered the roon: "Why, Miss Grace, you  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7603-00000005"/> 8        MY STEP-MOTHER. not go down yet? Now, be ashamed of yourself, when nurse put on your clean white dress, and new silk apron, and curled your hair so beautiful, and al- most hurried herself into fits to get Iyou dressed in time! What sort of manners do you suppose your new mother will think nurse has. taught you? I know your Pa is expecting you every minute, and blaming me for rot sending you down; and it is all your fault. Go down now; do," she added, coaxingly draw- ing me towards the door, "there is a good Gracey." At this moment the parlor door opened, and I heard my father's step in the hall, and immediately his voice calling me. I did not answer his first call, but, hearing his step approaching the stairs as he called again, I answered, Yes, Sir, I am coming; and I slowly and reluctantly descended. My father had returned to the parlor, and with my head hung down and my finger; on my lip, looking as awkward- ly as a great girl, thirteen years old, could look, I made my first appearance before my new mother. "Ah, Lucia, here is my little wild daughter at last," said my father, as he appeared at the door. But, almost before he had begun the speech, my mother had left her seat, and running across thd room to meet me, she clasped me in her arms, and kissed me several- times with great affection, saying, "My dear little daughter!"And then drawing me gently   MY STEP-MOTHER.        9 to a seat on' the sofa, near her, she sat with one arm around me, and holding my hand she looked most kindly upon me from a pair of very sweet blue eyes, and in a soft, low voice, said, "Grace and I will, I am sure, love each other very much, and be the very best of friends."   " I submitted to her caresses, without returning them; but, upon her saying this, I looked up, and meeting her affectionate glance, I thought for the first time, that perhaps I might love her, and that possibly all step-mothers were not like those described by Matilda Miller and Nurse Hopkins. My father took a seat near us, and addressing me, said, "Grace, my child, this sweet lady is now your mother. You must love and obey her. She will make a better child of you than Nurse Hopkins can, or your negligent father. Lucia," he continued, turn- ing to my mother, "I have been sadly negligent of my duty to this poor child. It has been owing, partly, to necessity, as my business necessarily occu- pies so much of my time; and partly from igno- rance on my part as to the proper mode of controlling and instructing her. I have looked upon her merely as a plaything for my moments of leisure, and only of late have I realized-that she was fast approaching womanhood, and needed other than Nurse Hopkins's culture to make her what I desire her to be. But, un.'  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7603-00000006"/> 10       MY STEP-MOTHER. der your kind guidance, I trust, she will become all you wish." My mother replied most sweetly to these remarks; and much conversation passed at this time on this subject, which I will not relate now. Never, in the course of my life, had I sat still for so long a time, as on that night at tea. I usually rushed into the room, hat in hand, after my father was seated, and often when he had nearly completed his meal; and hanging my hat on my chair that it might be all ready to start out with 'again, as soon as possible, I made my repast. My father was gen- erally occupied with the newspaper as he sat at table; but, whenever I had an opportunity, I would enter- tain him with all the news and gossip of the town, which I gathered abundantly from Mattie Miller and my nurse, and which it gave me great pleasure to repeat., Though he often checked me, he would laugh at my stories, and seem amused; which en- couraged rlather than silenced me. This night, to the great surprise of myself, I sat quietly through the whole of tea-time; and, if I rec- ollect right, I behaved with great propriety. But, as soon as tea was over, I took the first opportunity of gliding away unperceived. Nurse was stationed in the hall, very near the door; and she said she had been there for an hour, peeping in to see my   MY STEP-MOTHER.       1  new mother, and to hear her talk. "How do you , like her, Miss Grace?" she inquired, as we ascended the stairs towards the nursery, which room I had always occupied with her.  She is very pretty, I said. "Sure enough, so she is," said nurse.  "And how neat her dark riding-dress and little plain col- lar look! She does not look haughty at all; but we shall soon find out. Handsome is, that handsome does. I never saw you, Miss Gracey, sit so still, in all ny life, as you did to-night, and that was right. Your step-mother will see how much pains old nurse has taken to give you manners. But, dear me, dear me! I suppose we shall all have to sit still, now we have a mistress over us. No more of the good old easy times, when you and I, Miss Grace, and cook, all were' mistresses, and had nobody to suit but our- selves. But, dear me, I hope she won't crush you, deary, that's all; no matter about old nurse." Nurse made me repeat to her all that my father alnd -mother had said, as far as I could remember, while I was in the room, which I was most happy to do. She sat and made her comments, as I went along; and, when the cook came to the nursery, we both repeated all to her, with various additions and touches of imagination. The next morning, as I entered the school-room,  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7603-00000007"/> 12   '   MY STEP-MOTHER. Matilda Miller called out, in her bold rude way, which I now wonder I could endure, "O, there is Grace Williams come, let us go and hear how she likes her new mother. I would not be in her shoes." I was immediately surrounded by half a dozen girls. "Grace," said Mattie, satirically, "I did not ex pect to see you to-day at school: I thought you would be too much taken up with your\ new mother to leave her; though I suppose you were glad to get out of her way; but how do you like her?' Not knowing what to reply, I made the same answer that I gave nurse, She is very pretty. "That is no answer," persisted Mattie: "how do you like her?" I cannot tell yet, I answered, she has been with us so short a time. She was very kind and affectionate to me last evening. "Ask her a year hence," replied Mattie ; " then she will be able to say ;-ask her a year hence, and see if she will say she is kind and affectionate to her." "My mother," said Anna Ashton, a gentle lady-like girl of my own age, who stood near,-- my mother says, that Grace will love her very muchl; that every- body loves her who knows her. My motheri has visited in Boston a good deal with her, and feels very glad she has come to reside here.' "Love a step-mother! What an absurdity!" replied Mattie. "I do not believe in that; but Grace is old   MY STEP-MOTHER.       13 enough now to take care of herself, and keep out of her way. Mother says, she pities Grace, and that she may stay with me just as much as she pleases, and that she shall always be welcome." "I do not doubt that," said Helen Davis, haughtily, with a sneer, which brought a flash into Mattie's eye, and the blood into her cheek. ,' It is lucky you have moved into your new house, Mattie: you could not invite much company to your old one." "For shame, Helen, for shame!" said several girls: "I would not be so proud land haughty as you are, Helen, if I was so rich." The entrance of our teacher, here put a stop to our conversation. CHAPTER II. MY BAPTISM. MY'own mother died when I was a few months old. I had, therefore, never known a mother's care and love. Nurse Hopkins was with my mother at the time of her last illness, and was recommended to my father as a suitable person to take charge of me; I was, accordingly, committed to" her care. Nurse often told me of my mother's last sickness and holy death; and said, when Mr. Shepherd, our  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7603-00000008"/> "  .    MY STEP-'MOTtIN'R. rector, made known to her that she could not recover, she was much surprised, and wept bitterly, sayi'l,, "How can I leave my husband and my sveet taby a" And then she turned away from all around her, anld, concealing her face from view, lay for an hour so quietly that they thought ier, sleeping. But, when she spoke again, she said she had been praying; and that God had taught her to desire only that his will should be done; that she was now ready to leave her beloved ones with Him. She was, nurse said, always a sweet and pious lady, and was certainly prepared for death. She then said, "Nurse, bring me my baby." I was brought to her. At first she wept much, and be- dewed my unconscious face with her tears of love, and clasped me in her dying arms; but, calming her- self, she said to her pastor, who sat near her, "I must see my little feeble one grafted into the body of Christ's Church, my kind pastor, before I depart hence. Please let the ceremony be performed now, as I may not live to behold another day." The necessary preparations were accordingly made; and, as my young and holy mother was about to be- come a member of the Church triumphant, I, a poor, helpless, unconscious infant, was made a member ot the Church militant. My mother's -dying voice re- sponded audibly throughout the service; my pastor   MY STEP'-MOTHE R.      15 received me from her own trembling hand; and I was baptized Grace, in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost." After the service, my mother said, "I can surely now leave my child to God's covenanted mercy in Christ Jesus, my ever blessed Redeemer."  Then, raising her eyes languidly upward, she said, "Grant, O my Saviour, that this precious infant, whom I now leave with thee, may receive the fulness of thy grace, and enjoy the everlasting benediction of thy heavenly washing, and may come to thine eternal kingdom!" Nurse Hopkins often described to me this touch- ing scene; but she told it, as if it was some interests ing piece of news that might amuse me. Its spiritual beauty was quite lost upon her. My mother then received the Holy Communion. She lived but a few days after; and, from that' time until the event mentioned in the preceding chapter, I was left wholly to the care of the old nurse. So far as my bodily wants were concerned, no one could have been more faithfiul than she. In spite of all my screamings and resistance, I was plunged every morn- ing, summer and winter, into a cold bath, nurse all the time coaxing me to be good, and saying, many times over, "It will make you strong and fresh, my -deary, with cheeks like a rose."  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7603-00000009"/> 165      MYs STEP-MOTHER. As I grew older and wiser, I ceased screaming and resisting, and I enjoyed my morning bath much. I ., now feel grateful to my good nurse for the vigor of constitution which I have always enjoyed, and which I attribute, in a great measure, to her plentiful ablu- tions. She endeavored to keep me always neatly dressed, and took the most particular care of my clothes. She taught me to say my prayers, as she called it; and that was, to repeat every night, and in the morning, if she did not forget it, the Lord's Prayer. But, of the nature of prayer, I had, at the age of thirteen years, but a very indistinct idea. When I was old enough, my father took me to church with himn, on Sunday, regularly,.half the day; and I was much pleased at receiving from him, one Christmas, an elegant Prayer-book, bound in velvet, with a gold clasp. This I took with me, on Sundays, to church, and I found my places and looked over when I felt inclined, which was not very often. Mr. Shepherd, our pastor, once spoke to my father, on the subject of my attending the Sunday-school, and my father said that I should attend. I accordingy went for a short time; but, becoming weary of it, I discon- tinued, without consulting my father, as I supposed he would never think of it again, and, if he did, he never mentioned it to me. Mv father was a lawyer, in large practice, and also   MY STEP-MOTHER,-       17 a man of fine literary taste; and he was wholly occu- pied with his profession and his books. He generously and indulgently supplied all my wants and fancies; sent me to the best schools; and sometimes amused himself by playing with me, or listening to my child- ish talk. But he did not seem to know that any thing, filrther than that, was required of him. He early ac- customed me to know that his word was law; and I never ventured openly to disobey him. But when he was absent, or I thought I should escape detection, I never hesitated to consult only my own pleasure. It was a favorite amusement of mine, to listen to - the conversation of cook and nurse, which generally consisted of anecdotes of the various families in which they had served, and of all the petty gossip and tittle-tattle -they heard from day to day, which they would talk over, and relate again and again, : with new additions and imaginings. When a very I  little child, I would sometimes relate to their friends kl. Some piece of neiws I had heard from them, and on these occasions thtey applauded mle so highly, and appeared so amused at my childish way of relating it, that I was encouraged to try again. Thus, at a very earvlly age, i acquired a hlabit of gossiping and sltory- telling. When I began to attend school, I used to treasure. 'iit tSi ;siV&amp;t 171vi  nvi,ivr ;4-nr vi t4 C) ,  Zi w   &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7603-00000010"/> 18      ';MY STEP-MOTHER. when I returned home, to my eager listeners, adding and subtracting, according to my own taste, and mak- ing it as wonderful a story as possible. They extolled me highly, in such terms as these: "O, is not Miss Gracey sharp! Don't she talk like a book! Dear me, what a tongue she has, and what a memory! Why, she is as good company as a woman. Is that all you heard, dear?"  Nurse and cook generally sat in the nursery, in the evening; and after I was put to bed I would lie awake and watch them, as they sat together, plying their needles, and chatting as fast as possible. My ears were always wide open, listening to their idle conver- sation. Sometimes they would lower their voices, which always excited my curiosity much; and I would ask them what they were saying. The answer generally was, "Dear me, Miss Gracey, are you awake yet? We are talking of what little ears should not hear. Go to sleep, that's a good dear." This only made me strain my ears to hear, and kept me wide awake for a long time. It was from. one of these conversations that I first learned, by- hearing a detached sentence now and then, that I was to have a new mother. The idea I  think would have filled me with pleasure, for I had often envied my companions who had affectionate and careful mothers, had I not heard uttered, at the  ..            , ^-   MY STEP'MOTHER.        19 same time, and with ominous groans and sighs, such sentences as these: Poor Miss Grace, our little pet; how I do pity her! dear child! Step-mothers are dreadfill things for a child, I know from what I have seen. Don't you remember Susan Dale?" "Hush, hush, cook," said nurse, "you know walls have ears." I supposed she meant me; but I did not know why I was called a wall. "Miss Grace is asleep, I am sure," said cook, (I know by her heavy breathing. Poor Susan Dale! what a hard time that girl had of it; worked to death, t rampled on, abused, made a slave of!" Here followed-a long story which I forbear to relate. "Yes, and there was poor Mary Lewis," continued nurse; "dear me, you remember poor Mary Lewis, driven from her own father's house, forced to labor in the world, among strangers, for her support, when her father had enough." And here followed a long story of the sufferlings of Mary Lewis. The stories always concluded with the same, "O, poor dear Miss Gracey, I am afraid her best days are over. When will she find such easy times again, and suche friends as you and I, nurse?" "I love her like my own child," nurse would reply. "Was it not me who took her from her mother's arms when she, sweet lady, was dying?  And did not I hear the last prayer she offered for the poor baby after she was  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7603-00000011"/> 20       MY STEP-MOTITER. baptized? And did it not teach me my duty to- wards her, and cause me to bring her up like a Christian child; and learn her the Lord's Prayer as soon as she could speak? And have we not both tried to make her happy always? Well, well, she knows nothing that is before her, poor dear; and there is no use in telling her. Trouble comes fast enough. It may be bad for you and I too-; if we do not suit the new lady, we may lose our good place we have had these dozen years together. Mr Williams is such a generous, nice, easy man, that I should not like to leave him." Many nights, for several weeks previous to my fa- ther's marriage, I listened to conversations similar to this; and, hour after hour, I would -lie awake and ponder over what I heard, wondering what my new mother would be like, and what sad destiny was be- fore me. CHAPTER III. MRS. NELSON S REMOVING, I WAS actually quiet and reserved, for a. short time. after the introduction of my new mother at our home. I felt a shyness in her presence, which was a new sen- sation to me, and which was very uncomfortable. But it soon wore off, and I appeared in my real char-   " MY STEP-MOTHER.       21 acter, a wild, reckless, uncontrollable child, with a Inost abominable habit of gossiping and news-telling, the result of my unfortunate education, and com- pan'onship with nurse and cook. My fitther was so accustomed to hear me chatter away as I pleased, never troubling himself to listen or reply, unless he was in the mood for it, that he was not aware of my evil habit.. Sometimes he would appear anmaed at my idle stories, and sometimes he would say: "Hush, hush, little busy-body; where do you get such stories? From nurse, or from school? Have you nothing better to fill your head with than other people's business?" But he did not know the natural propensity I had for it; nor how it had been fostered and almost forced into action, from my being left to the care and training of uneducated servants. My mother, from the first, showed me great affec- tion, and always spoke to me most gently and kindly. She seemed sttidying my character and disposition. I often met her eye watching my countenance, with a look of deep inquiry. She was lively, and attrac- tive in her manners; and had not my mind been so prejudiced against her, I think I should at once have loved her, and submitted to her guidance. As, I became accustomed to her presence, my re- serve and my good manners both wore off. I rec- ollect her look of amazement one day, as I rushed  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7603-00000012"/> 22       MY STEP-MOTHER. into the dining-room, after dinner had commenced, quite out of breath, with hair and dress disordered, and, hanging my hat on a chair, seated myself, and pushed out my plate to my father, without saying a word. I swallowed my dinner hastily, and, jumping up from the table, seized my hat, and was rushing from the room. "Where are you running so fast, Grace?" asked my father. "What is the hurry?" O, father, I said,  Mrs. Nelson is removing, and it is such fun to see the things brought out of the house. Mattie and I have been standing at the door a long time watching them. We promised to meet there again in a few minutes. Why, father, I continued, advancing to the table, I know almost every thing she has in her house; and, though they look so genteel and nice in the rooms, shaded by the curtains, they are really shabby when brought out to the sunlight. Her crimson plush sofas. are considerably worn, and the rosewood quite scratched; the gilded frames of her large mirrors are dimmed; her tapestried car- pets, that are hanging in the yard, do not look quite as fresh as they did on the floor; and her chamber- furniture is really old-fashioned and' shabby. There is but little that can be called handsome, and that is far from new; yet Bessie and Margaret Nelson hold up their heads so high, and think they are richer and   MY STEP-MOTHER.       23 sinarter than anybody in town. Nurse says, they have no right at all to do so. She says, Mr. Nelson is no richer than you, and they put on airs, because they have been to Europe. O, I forgot, father, they have some splendid paintings and statuary, that they broughlt from Europe, and that is what sets off their house so, I suppose, for their furniture is not much. "Well, well, little puzzle-brain," said my father, "run off or you will craze me." I met my motlter's eye as I turned to leave the room and its expressidn haunted me all the afternoon. I found Mattie Miller, my intimate friend, already at Mrs. Nelson's door waiting for me; and there we stood a long time, watching the interesting operation of bringing out the furiniture, and loading the drays. About the middle of the afternoon, I saw my mother coming down the street towards us. "Why are you not at school, dear Grace?" she inquired of me; and, at the same time, I saw her critically exam- ining Mattie, who, I must say, was a coarse, vulgar, bold-looking girl. For the first time in my life, I felt ashamed of being with her, as I hastily compared her with the refined, feminine, and very lady-like appear- ance of my mother.  O, I replied, we can go to school any day; and Mrs. Nelson does not move every day; and so Mattie and I thought we would stay here and enjoy the moving this afternoon. "As  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7603-00000013"/> 24       MY STEP-MOTHERJ. you are not at school," she replied, "perhaps, my dear, you would be so kind as to go to a few stores with me. I want to purchase some little articles, and you know I am a stranger here i I did not then understand that this was a plan of my mother's, to draw me away from what she consid- ered a very improper position and employment. Her manner was so sweet and wiuning, that I prepared to follow her without resistance, though Mattie gave my arm a violent pinch, which I well understood. I went with my mother to several stores, but left her most unceremoniously las we reached our home, and ran rapidly down street to join Mattie, paying no regard to my mother's voice, as she called after me, "It is almost tea-time, Grace." "So you -are getting afraid )of your new mother already, Grace," was Mattie's salutation, as I joined her at Mrs. Nelson's doolr "You did not dare to re- fuse to go with her, though you know you did not- w nt to; and I will not tell you a single thing that was brought out of the house after you left. It was :: so tame in you to go, and so stupid in you not to un- derstand, that it was all a pretext of your mother's to get you away. I suppose she gave you a good scold- ing, for not being at school. Well, I pity you, Grace, you will havi no liberty at all pretty soon." I have the same liberty I have always had, I re-   MY STEP-MOTHER.       25 plied, and I mean to have it.  "That is right," answered Mattie; "keep to it. A girl tlirteen years old certainly knows what to do; and if you do not know, at any time, Grace, I am two years older than you, and I will tell you." Tea was half over when I returned home; and rushing rudely in, I seated myself, eating and talking together, in my a'ccustomed uncouth way. The inter- esting and absorbing subject of my conversation was Mrs. Nelson's removing. You would hardly believe, fatler, I said, what a lot of furniture Mrs. Nelson's house holds. There have been four drays hauling it all day; and I heard one of the draymen say, there would be several more loads to-morrow; that they had yet all the basement and cellar things to reinove, and they were full. They only took one load from them to-night; and I did not want to see them, so I came home. It is lucky that they are going into a larger house. Father, Mattie says thatt their chamber-maidi is a sister to Mrs. Nelson's cook, and that she told her that Mrs. Nelson's parlors were all newly furnishedk in the new house, green and gold satin damask furniture and curtains, velvet carpets, chandelier, and all. How smart the Nelsons will feel! Father, I wish you would furnish our rooms so. Nurse says, you are as rich as Mr. Nelson. 3  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7603-00000014"/> 26       MY 'STEP-MOTHER. My father was reading a newspaper, and probably heard only the last part of my sentence, when he look- ed at me, and said,; Well, little chatterbox, what are you talking about? You will craze your mother. As rich as Mr. Nelson!-O, no! nurse is quite mis- taken there: he is worth double my property." Well, then, I suppose he can afford to furnish his house so expensively, I answered. It must cost a great deal, first to build so fine a house, and then to furnish it; but it is so much larger than the old one, that, nurse says, he would have to buy some new furniture, and that it is better to new furnish the lower floor, and put the old furniture up-stairs. Do you think so, father? "Pear me," said my father, again looking up from his paper, on being addressed, "what is the child talking about so fast? Run away, run away, Gracey, if you have finished your tea: I want to read, and your tongue never stops; run away." I seized a large piece of cake in each hand, and, taking up my bonnet, said, Well, I will go and take another look at Mrs. Nelson's, and see if they have done work there to-night. I do not want to see the kitchen furniture removed, though nurse and cook wanted me to very much; but I have enough to tell them now of what I have seen all day. I wish some one would remove every day, it gives Mattie and me so much to   rMY STEP-MOTHER.       27 talk about and look at. It makes a variety, to stay out of school once a while and see what is going on. So saying, I rudely ran out of the room. It is with feelings of great shame and mortification, that I call these incidents to remembrance, and re- cord them here for warning and instruction. It is  necessary, that my young readers should fully under- stand what my character was at that time, and what they might also have been, if left, in their tender years, to the care of uneducated servants. They may learn to feel grateful to their Heavenly Father for kind parents, to guide and restrain them, and fill their minds with higher and holier things than those for which my unfortunate situation and education gave me a relish. My young readers, if ever you desire to throw off the restraints of parental authority, and find its gen- tle discipline and wise teachings galling to your un- sanctified and self-relying spirits, contemplate the sad result which my case presents, and esteem  your parents' counsel and experience more. precious to you than thousands of gold and silver. *     d        ' +             11        *  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7603-00000015"/> 28       MY STEP-MOTHER. CHAPTER IV. THE RAINY DAY. IT was my usual habit, not to return home until the hour of dinner or tea; but to pass the time in strolling the streets, stopping at corners, staring in at shop- windows, and gathering up incidents of conversation to amuse my nurse and the cook, who, as I have said, stimulated this taste by their encomiums on my talent for story-telling. Rainy days were a sad interruption to these favor- ite amusements, as they drove me home for occupa- tion; and, alas for my neglected childhood! I had never been taught- that most necessary lesson which wise and careful parents always early teach their chil- dren,-theart of employing themselves, cultivating resources within the domestic circle, that serve to fill up, and beautify, and give a zest to woman's home life. J My father often presented me with books suit- able for my age; and occasionally, on a rainy day, I sought their company. But as I had no natural nor cultivated taste for reading, they were soon thrown aside, and exchanged for the edifying conversation of nurse and cook. Oh, rain, rain; how it pours! how dismal! I   MY STEP-MOTHER.       29 said, one morning after breakfast, looking disconso- lately from the window. What can I do? "You must stay at home to-day, Grace," said my father, "the wind blows so violently, and you could not hold an umbrella open." O no, father, I replied; indeed I cannot stay at home all day alone. I will go as far as Mattie's, to see if she is going to school; and I will stay with her if she is not going. A whole long rainy day at homie!-I could not bear it. "The weather is too stormy, my child," he said, "for you to go out, at plesent, even for a short distance. . You must stay at home." So saying, he left the room to go to his office. I dared not go out against my father's command; so I threw  myself sulkily on the sofa, and began watching my mother, who was arranging some books and fancy articles on a table; When she had done this, she took her work-table, and, placing it near the sofa on which I sat, she took out some: pretty worsted-work'and began to sew up- on it. At length, looking towards me, she held up lher work, and asked, "Is it not pretty, Grace?" Beautiful, I replied: I never saw any quite like it. Bessie Nelson and Helen Wood work it, but it is not like that. It must be very dull, it takes so much time.  "Dull!  O, no," she replied, "it is very amusing and pleasant, especially on a rainy day. It is not best to occupy too much time with it; but,  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7603-00000016"/> 80       MY STEP-MOTHER. for a variety, it is very agreeable. Suppose I teach you, Grace." I could never learn, I replied. Nurse taught me to sew a little, but I never liked it. "I think you Would like this, my daughter," she said kindly; "and it might amuse you a little while this dull morning. I will show you. I do not think you will be a dull scholar." I could no longer resist; and I submitted to be taught. To my great surprise, I quickly learned the stitch, and to my greater surprise, I became pleased and much interested in the occupation of copying the pretty simple pattern she placed before me. When my mother found: I had learned, and could go on without her assistance, she took up a book, and said, "I will read you a story, Grace, while you work;" and she immediately began to read. To my utter surprise, in what appeared to me a very short time, my father 'came home to dinner. Why did you come home so early, father?, I inquired, as he entered. "It is the hour for dinner, my dear," he replied,-" my usual hour for coming homne." Is it possible! I exclaimed. I thought it would be such a long dull morning; and it has been so short and so pleasant, that I forgot the rain. What a lovely story that is, mother; please finish it after dinner; and please look at my work, and see if it is not just like the pattern. My mother praised my work; and, as   MY STEP-MOTHER.       31 dinner was announced, she said that, if I wished it, we would go on with our work and book after dinner. I saw my father bestow upon my mother a look of great kindness and gratitude, which, at the time, I did not quite understand to be in reference to me. I hurried from dinner to my worsted-work; and my mother proposed that I should commence a pair of slippers for my father, and surprise him by presenting them to him, worked by myself, as a Christmas pres- ent. Christmas is a great way off, I said; they will be done long before that time. I do not want to wait until Christmas. "Well, sooner, my dear, if you finish them," said my mother; " but it takes some time to work them nicely; and you may become tired of them, or only work on them on a rainy day. Mother produced a variety of patterns, and a large bundle of worsted, of different colors. I was much amused for a couple of hours in selecting the pattern, and the shades of worsted suitable for working it. Mother assisted, talking to me most pleasantly all the time; andj she then began the slippers, and afterwards resumed her story. When father returned to tea, it seemed to me too soon to be again interrupted, so agreeably had the time been occupied. I noticed father's look of agreeable surprise, as he found me again seated quietly with my mother; but he said nothing.   &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7603-00000017"/> 32       MY STEP-MOTHERI. , Whe re has my darling been all day?" said nurse to me, as I entered the nursery after tea. "Been with Mattie, I suppose, at her hluse." I have not been out to-day, nurse, I said. Father forbade my going out in the rain. I have been sitting with my umother sewing all day. "Sitting sewing all day, Miss Grace!" saidiniurse, with unfeigned surprise. "Who ever heard the lilke of that . But, oh, poor, poor dear! I understand it all. fYour father bade you stay at home all day, poor deri' and your step- mother bade you sit and sew with her all day, ik e a seamstress. Poor dear! it is whalt nurse never used her to, and what-has killed many apoor young thing. Look at Mary Balker! Worked herself to death, sewing from morning till night, making shirts and fine clothes for ladies. Well, step-mothers have no mercy. I never saw one that had yet. Poor dear! sewing -all day, and sitting so still that poor nurse thought she was out of the house. Dear, dear. I shall think it my duty to speak to your step-mother, and tell her about your constitution. To be sure, you never were sick in your life; but you cannot bear to be tied down in that way. Why did you not jump up, and run out of the room, and come to poor nurse. Sloe would have taken your part. But, dear me, step-mothers take all the spirit of a child; dear, - der 1"   MY STEP-MOTHER.        33 I did not want to run away, nurse, I said; or I should have done so. Mother was teaching me how to do worsted-work;  I am going to work a pair of beautifill slippers for faLther. He is inot to know any thiing about it until they are done. Will he not be surprised,- when he sees them, nurse, and hears that they were worked so nicely by his little whisknbout, as lie always calls me? He says I can never sit still ,long enough to eat my dinner, unless my tongue is going on a-quick run. I wish you could have seen low surplised he looked, when  he came home and found me sitting and sewing 'like  a young lady. Besides, nurse, mother read me such a pretty story, that I did not know ]owo the time was flyii)g. "Ah, poor dear, poor dear,"' said nurse; "that is  just the way these step-mothers always do. Try and please them, and then lord it over them.  She is only trying to get a power over you, Miss Grace. Young ifolks cannot see so far ahead as old folks. Now let me tell you, that is all she is after, and--" "Grace, Grace," called my mother at the stairs, i " look here a moment, my dear." "Tell her you are tired, and want to stay with nurse," said my nurse. I did not answer either my rneother or nurse. Nurse had quite dispelled all the kindly feelings that my pleasant rainy day had called forth towards my mnother.  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7603-00000018"/> MY STEP-MOTHER. '"Grace, Grace," again called my mother; and I heard her ascending the stairs. I opened the door; but in no very pleasant humor. "There is a bright, lovely sunset," she said, dear : Gtrace, after our rainy day; anid your father will be at the door to give us a drive in a few minutes. Wll you go?  It will be quite agreeable to be in the fresh air, after being shut up all day, sewing so busily; and the country will look fine after the rain. I consented, for I liked a drive in the country, though nurse, while arr anging my shawl and hat, said, "We, not one minute now to say with poor nurse That is the way step-mothers always do; take children from their old friends. Poor dear, poor dear! hard times are coming for you." I well remember that drive. It was one of sum- "  mer's loveliest sunsets. The rain had ceased several hours; and a fine wind had dried the hard smooth iroad. The- sun was gilding every window, spire, 'i   meadow, hill, and lake, with that peculiar brilliancy "i  ' which we often notice after a day of rain. The way- side flowers and the fields of grain were shaking of i i 'the rain-drops, and sending forth, in the glad sunset, 'i   rich fragrance on the evening air. The cattle were i   . returning homewards; and the birds carolled galy i    their good-night song, after a quiet day in their snug -,   nests.   MY STEP-MOTHER.        35 I thought mother noticed the cloud on my brow, as I entered the carriage. She said nothing; but conversed gayly with my father, who, having thrown aside his law-books for a while, entered heartily into the pleasures of the drive, and took a most agreeable part in the-, conversation. I too Was unconsciously drawn into it, and soon forgot my unkind feelings, As we drove homewards, with a bright moon above us, I felt that I had enjoyed mnyself, even with a step- mother. This rainy day is indelibly impressed on my mind, for two reasons. It was really the first day I had ever passed quietly and happily in my own home; the first day that the idea came to my mind, that it was pleasant to occupy one's self at home, and enjoy reading and sewing. I felt the dawning of a new, power within me. Ratiny days Iad heretofore been very irksome. If forbidden to go out, I would range friom one part of the house to another, teasing the cook, or tormenting my lnurse; now, in the garret at the swing, or chasing my hoop thrlough  the halls, rolling ninepins, orlplaying ball, to ttle gleat annoy- ance of nurse, and the danger of looking-glasses and windows; tired of every amusement, before the day was half over, and hoping that another rainy day would be very far off. Another reason why I remember this day is, that , '   &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7603-00000019"/> 36       MY ST IP-MOTI!a4 it was the commenicemenlit of an influence ovei' me, though I was not at the timne aware of it,--aan influ- ence which gilded my whole life; a blessed influence, fromn a holy and gentle being, who was patient with me through a thousand provocations, unwearied in her love and-forbearance, ever ardent in her labors, with wonderful skill and judgmnent, to win me to duty, to soften nmy cold heart, to instruct my ignorance and wilfulness, to repair the wasted years of child- hood, and to bring nle to the knowledge of my obli- gations as a baptized child of the Church, a member of Christ, and an inheritor of the kingdom  of Heaven. CHAPTER    V. TEE NEW' DRESS. O, how nice and how fine -the ladies -will all look at church to-morrow, I exclailned, as I ran into the dining-room, and seated nmyself in my usual rude manner at the tea-table, one Satulday evening. So many new hats Mrs. Simonds has sent home to- night; and there are some not quite finished, to be -; sent home this evening. Mattie and I went in there, -, just to get a peep at some of them. Mrs. Holmes  - ?'i   MY STEP-MOTHER,       -37 has one of white lace, with a lovely green wreath of flowers round it, on the outside. The Nelsons hare the sweetest white crapes, with buff trimmings inside, so genteel and so neat. The Maurys have pretty lace straws, with delicate lilac linings, and flowers in bunches on the outside. Then, there is no end to the buff crapes, and the blue crapes, and the pink crapes, and silk hats, and every variety of straws, with every variety of trimming.  It seems to me, that the fashions were never so pretty as they are this summer.    Mrs. Simonds says, that in June, she has hardly time to eat her dinner, she is so busy. After we left Mrs. Simonds', Aattie and  I thought we-would go round to Mrs. Atlins'the dressmaker's, and see some    of the new dresses she was sending home.    0, such lovely bahteges, ald lawns, and sum- mer silks!   I wanted them all! Some- "Hush,     hush, magpie," said my  father;   " I  have read the samne paragraph    over several times, and I cannot understand   it et, for your chattering.  What is the child at  ?" I paused a few moments, and then began again, talking, I     presumle, to myself; as my father was reading his paper, and amy mother showed no interest in my  remnarks, and I  addressed no one. Some  of the dresses had four flounces, and some six, and some had only two or three wide ones. Most 4  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7603-00000020"/> 38       MY STEP-MOTHElK. of them were made open in front, and all of them with flowing sleeves. The lawns were ruffled with the same; and the bareges trimmed with ribbons to match; and most of the silks with rich black lace. Almost all of them were'beautiful. I shall have as much as I can do, to-morrow, to look at the people I meet in their new dresses. How gay the church will look! But here comes Miss Adams with my new dress. I was just beginning to think she would disappoint me, and I should have to stay at home, to-morrow, which I certainly should have done, rather than go out in my old suit, when everybody is dressed out new. I ran tothe door, and quickly returned with my new dress. Please give me three dollars, to pay Miss Adams for making this sweet dress, father, I said; as I displayed a dashy new barege, much trimmed, and in every way unsuitable for a girl thirteen years of age. Father handed me the money; but eyed my dress quite unsatisfactorily. "You do not intend to wear that showy, trimmed-up dress, surely," he said, "Grace; why did you get such a one? It is more fit for a woman of forty than a child." It is a splen- did dress, father, I said, rather impertinently. It is Mattie's and my taste; and it is a perfect beauty. There is nothing handsomer in the city. "If that is your taste, my dear,'7 he said, "I beg you will con--   MY STEP-MOTHER.       39 sult your mother's for the future. I shall feel quite ashamed to see you in that theatrical-looking affair." Why, mother has one just like it, father, I said- and nurse and cook said it was a beauty. The Cooks have them, in the same style, and the Blanchards; and I do not see. why I crannot. ' I do not care what other children wear," he said; "I want my child to be dressed modestly. Nor do I want Mattie Miller, or nurse, or cook, to select the dress of my daughter. But I forgot, poor, poor child, she has had no other director. Go, pay for it now, Grace, and wear it if you like; and when you want another, get your mother to choose it for you. I want you to dress like her." "Poor neglected child!" I heard himn say, as I left the room. "Lucia, I fear she will vex you much, and be a great trouble to you, she has had her own way s6 long, and been controlled so little." I paused outside of the door to hear my mother's reply. "Grace will, I hope, soon learn to love me," she said; "and then all will be right, I trust. She will then love to be with me, and desire my guidance; and my influence will be great over her then." 'It will take a long time to effect a change in my poor neglected child," said my father; " but she has her good points. She is warm-hearted, affectionate, and has a  good mind, but it has run sadly to waste. I have done  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7603-00000021"/> 40       MY STEP-MOTHER. wrong, in allowing her to indulge a natural propensity to run about the streets, and talk and gossip. This propensity has been increased, by her associating so much with servants. My business confilnes me so en- tirely, that I have not done my duty by,her. Can you not break up that habit, dear Lucia?" '; It can only be done now," said my mother, "by teaching her to love her home, by giving her here pleasant occupations to make it attractive, and by creating in her a taste for reading or study, which will fill her mind with more important tilings. It must be the work of time; but we will hope to effect it. It shall be my earnest endeavor to do my duty to her. First, I must teach her to love me, and to choose me for her com- panion and friend. Who is this Mattie, with whom she constantly associates?" ' She is a bold, coarse-looking girl," said my father. "Her parents are vulgar, uneducated people, who have made considerable money within a few years, have built a splendid house, and are trying to push themselves into society. She is not, I am sure, a suitable companion for Grace; and I have many times been tempted to forbid her being on such inti- mate terms with her. If you advise it, I will put a stop to their acquaintance at once." "I do not at all fancy her, as a companion for Grace," said my mother; "but as they go to the same   MY STEP-MOTHER.       41 school, and Grace is on such familiar terms with her, it might be injudicious, and perhaps impossible, to put an end to the acquaintance at once. It would make enemies of the family, and would, perhaps, cause Grace to deceive you. We had better wait awhile. I hope, in time, to influence her; but to exert any authority at once, over a child of her disposition, would weaken my power. I must watch, and be pa tient, and make her love me first." "If you can only make her like yourself, my dear Lucia," said my father, " it Will be all I desire. I have not the heart to reprove her, conscious of my own neglect of duty." "God helping me," said my mother, "I will strive to lead her to Himself; and then all kill be well." There was a pause; and I softly ran to the door to pay my dressmaker. I then went to the nursery, where, with many exaggerations, I related to my nurse the conversation I had overheard; and I ended with bursting into tears, and saying, that she should not separate me from Mattie, my best friend. "Miss Grace," said nurse, "there is where your mother is right. I have often told you, that Mattie was not fit to hold a candle to you. As to your being held in tight reins by a step-mother, keep out of it, as long as you can. If your own father abandons you to her, poor child, it is a hard case: but come to nurse, and  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7603-00000022"/> 42       MY STEP-MO'HER. you have one friend in her. Show a proper spirit, and we will hope for the best." I repeated to Mattie all my father had said about ly dashy new dress, and about consulting my mother for the .fture; and I told also part of the conversa- tion which 'I had related to nurse. ' I think you are old enough to dress as you like, Grace," said my   i friend; " and if I were you, I would show her that I intended to, from the beginning. That is the best way." I will never consult her, I said, if I do not like. I intend to dress to suit myself. So, there are two things where my step-mother in- tends to control me, I said to myself, in relation to my dress and to my intimacy with Mattie. Now, 1 will not be put under her. I will do exactly as I please, I am determined, even if it is entirely contrary to her wishes. I will be more intimate with Mattie than ever; to show her, that I feel myself capable of selecting my own friends. I will consult her about my dress, but follow my own taste, if it does not agree with hers.  Mother, I said, the next day, we have a bill at Ar-  nold's, and father always allows me to go there and get what I want. Mattie and I are going shopping this afternoon, for some dresses: I intend to have a  new summer silk, and a lawn. Do you like flounces,  j mother? " Not for young girls of your age," said    MY STEP-MOTHER,       43 my mother. "Were you ten or twelve years older, 1 should not object to them." Many girls of my age. wear them, mother, I said. I am thirteen, fourteel inl the fall, and tall of my age; and I have made up my mind to have both my dresses flounced, a light  summer silk looks so beautifully, flounced. My mother / was silent. I am also going, I continued, to buy two summer hats; one for my best, and one for school. Do you prefer crape or straw for my best hat, mother? "I think nothing so pretty for young girls of your age," said she, "as a straw hat simply trinmed." I cannot agree with you at all, I said, imperti- nently; I like a dressy crape hat much the best. And which do you like best for school, a flat straw, or a lawn bonnet? "I think flats are very pretty," said mny mother, "and a plain lawn bonnet is also very pretty. Either would be suitable for you." If I have a lawn, said I, would you have flowers or ribbons on the inside? "Flowers I think very much out of place, in a lawn school-bonnet," said my mother; "ribbons are t much more suitable trimming." We do not agree there, I said, rudely. I think here is no kind of bonnet that is not prettier and more becoming for having flowers on the inside.   &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7603-00000023"/> "      MMY STEP-MOTHR. Flowers are much more becoming to me. Ribbons have such a stiff look. Father told me to consult you, mother, and so I have; but I do not see any use in it, for we never can agree on the subject, I fear. I determined to suit myself; and I wished to show my mother, from the beginning, as Mattie advised me, that I was my own mistress. I gave orders, accordingly, for both my new dresses to be made with deep flounces; for my best hat to be. made of pea-green crape, with pink roses inside; and my school-hat of lawn, also trimmed with flowers inside. I thought I would not show my dresses and hat to my mother, but put them on and say nothing; conse- quently, the following Sunday, I arrayed myself for church in my new green and white plaid silk dress, flounced almost to the waist, a showy white silk mantilla, and my green crape hat and pink roses,- a very ridiculous and really fantastic dress, it now appears to me, for a child thirteen years of age. My mother made, no remarks upon my appearance, and really appeared as if she did not know what I had on. Here is a lot of parasols Arnold has sent up for me to select from, I said one day to my mother, en- tering her room; what color do you like, mother? Please look at them.   MY SrTEP-MO'I'TIE R.,     45 She put down her work, seemed i!tc'rested in mv purchase, anlld selected two; ole, at ricli gi'eel; and the other, a brown, and said. "I pDefer onle of those colorsi, (G ace.        I O, mother, t s-lid, you have chosen the two ugliest in the whole lot; we never shall agree in matters of taste. Look at this lovely pink and white one ; so delicate, so lovely, so stylish. It will look beautiful with my green hat and pink roses. I must have this one. I should not be satisfied with those plain, dowdy- looking green and brown ones. My mother made no reply ; but seated herself at her work again. Reserving for myself the pink one, I sent back the others. . Though I was very fond of haviing showy and handsome apparel, I was very careless about my every-day appearance, and very impertinent to my mother, when she once or twice, with great gentle- ness and consideration, advised me to come home, tin  enough before dinner, to smooth my hair and improve my appearance before going to the table. I was well accustomed to the kind of reproof I received every day from nurse, about tearing and soiling my dresses; and I did not mind iknor take offence at any thing she said. But I would not receive kindly one word of correction from my mother.   She once gently suggested to me, that I should learn to sew  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7603-00000024"/> "       MY STEP-MOTHER. and to repair my clothes. I saucily replied, Mending is for servants to do, mother. I have no desire nor intention to learn. "It may be a serious discomfort to you, my dear, in after life,' said my mother, "not to understand that important branch of sewing, so as to give di- rections in relation to it, if you are not obliged to do it yourself." I shall always keep a servant, I said, to take care of my clothes. It is not ladies' work. "Suppose," said my mother, "your fortune should change, and you were unable to keep a servant, how helpless you would find yourself! Many young ladies whose parents are very rich, always repair their own clothes, and make many articles for themselves. Every woman should well understand the use of her needle, whatever may be her situation in life." I hate sewing, I answered, and I never mean to learn. If I cannot have some one to mend my clothes for me, I shall throw them away, and have new ones. Nurse says, it makes people sick to sit moping over their sewing, and so she never taught me much; but I know the stitch well enough. I was exceedingly uncouth in, my manners at table. I as often used my knife as my fork, to con- vey food to my mouth; I drew my'chair very closely to the table; I generally rested my elbows upon it a * i   * I    I   1 MY STEP-MOTHER.       47 portion of the time; and I ate very rapidly. My father, whenever he noticed any of these improprie- ties, corrected me; but it did not do much good, as I was so thoughtless and uncivilized. I had contracted these habits from sitting in the kitchen and watching the servants at their meals. It was a favorite amusement of mine, when I was very small, and I thought it was womanly to do as they did.  After my mother had been with us a few weeks, she spoke to me, one day, ,with great gentleness and consideration, on the bad habits I was contracting at table, begging me to correct them before I was older, or they would be a source of great mortification to me. I told her I hated the trouble of coming to the table; that it took so much time from my play; that, if father did not insist upon it, I should not come home half of the time; that I only came to the table to eat as quickly as possible, and not to trouble myself about manners; there was time enough for that, when I was older. I told her I thought I eat full as well as anybody else; and I wished she would not look at me.  She never suggested the slightest change in my habits or manners, without my replying to her in an impertinent or disrespectful way. m        1  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7603-00000025"/> 48       MY STEP-MOTHER. CIAPI  TER  VI. WIDOW GlRAHAM. "WITERE lavc v0on been, Gracen asked my father, one morning, as I ran in fr-o the street quite out of breath, and took my seat at the brcIkfast-tible: "yon h1ave been oult early." O, fitlher, I said, such1 fun Mat tie and I hav\e hadl! We lave been at larket; /and I can tell you what lalf the people in town hIlave for dinner. It is very anusing, to stand by and wlatch the different people selecting aLnd buying their din- nesl. Some are so rich and generous, ald buy so muchl; ;and some are so poor, or mnean, and buy so little. What do you think the old miser, Mr. Blake, bought for, himself and housekeeper? A bone, and two potatoes. Mattie says, they w ill starve on that for a week. I wonder how they live. Such a nice dinner as Mr. Nelson's waiter bought! A variety of fish, lamb, and chickens; a quaitity of fiesh vege- tables, and the finest and most expensive fiuit in the market. Then Mr. Mardin, our next neighbor, bought beef to roast, potatoes, turnips, and spinach. And Mr. Ray bought mutton and Mr. Smith, veal; and Mr. Townsend, beef;. and Mr. Lee, beef; and Mr. Grenville, beef and mutton-no, I mean veal.   MY STE P-MOTHER.      49 "Child, child!" interrupted my father, looking up from his paper, " neither your mother nor myself are interested in knowing what all the town have for din- ner." Why, father, it was very amusing, I said, to see the different people come in, and hear them make their bargains. O, such an ocean of things as the hotel-keepers bought! and the old ladies that keep boarders on the corner, and the- "Well, well, I dard say," said my father; "but do try to fill your head with something better, and do not go to the mar- ket again, unless you go with me. It is no place for girls to be wandering round alone." O, do not say so, father, I said; for I promised to go with Mattie every day, until we were tired of it, it is such fun. "I forbid your going there again, Grace, without me," said my father, in a tone which I feared to disobey; so I changed the subject. Father, I said, Widow Graham is a thief. "A thief! What do you mean, daughter?" he answered. "I have always considered her a most honest and re- spectable woman; and her poor husband was the most faithful, excellent man I ever employed." Well, now, she is a thief, father, I said. Will you send her any more wood next winter? or let Johnny Graham come for a kettle of milk every night any more , It is wrong, I suppose, to help thieves. "Explain yourself, Grace," said my father; "and 5  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7603-00000026"/> MY STEP-MOTHEKR.  do not repeat nor circulate what may prove to be en- tirely false; for, if you injure the poor woman's char- acter, no one will employ her, and that will be hard for her."  Mattie told me she lRas a thief; I re- plied; and that she was taken up yesterday for stealing a rich piece of lace fiom Mr. Hardy's store; and that she was carried before Mr. Bell, the lawyer; and that she was put in jail. Will she be hung, father  " Hung? No. How the child talks!" said my father. "That story must be false, Grace. I would trust poor Widow Graham, or any of her family, with untold gold. Grace," continued my father, seriously, i to whom have you repeated that story ? You will find it is untrue, I am quite sure; and if you have been repeating it, you have borne false witness against your neighbor, and broken God's law." Mattie told me the story, father, I said; and I told some of the girls at school, and only nurse and cook besides. I thought it was true. "I will pledge my word," continued my father, "that it is false. Grace, your tongue will yet bring you into serious trouble; and your love of gossip, if not checked at once, will bring disgrace upon you. If you have told your old nurse, you might as well have the town-crier proclaim it through the streets. Do not mention it again. I am interested in Widow Graham. I will go myself,   MY STEP-MOTHER.    and see in what the story has originated; and, if pos- sible, I will clear her character." At this moment, there was a gentle knock at the dining-room door; then it was softly opened, and poor Widow Graham, the subject of our conversation, entered, and, dropping a low courtesy, she addressed my father. "Pardon me, Sir," she said, for intruding upon you; but I am in great haste, and in great dis-- tress. I am accused of being dishonest." She covered her face with her hands, and burst into tears. "Do not be troubled, good woman," said my father, kindly; and seeing she was unwilling to proceed, he said, "I have just heard from Grace that you were in trouble; and I feel confident there is some mistake, which I shall be able to clear up. I will testify to your strict honesty and good principles; and do not doubt, that I can get you out of your difficulty. Let me hear your story." "I thank you a thousand times, Sir," said the poor woman, a gleam of hope lighting up her sad face., "I went, yesterday morning, into Mr. Hardy's store to buy some trifles; and, while waiting, I looked around at the different things that covered the coun- ters. There were near me some boxes filled with laces and ribbons, which I amused myself with ex- amining for the few minutes I stood there. I made my purchases of a young man,* and then returned &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7603-00000027"/> MY STEP-MOTHER. home. In the afternoon, as I sat at my work, that young man, accompainied by another, who said he was an officer of justice, walked into my house, and accused me of stealing a rich remnant of lace, which, he said, he was sure was in the box before I came into the store; that, directly after I had left, the lady wtlo bought fiomr the piece the day before returned for the remnant, and it was nowhere to be found. He said no one had been near the boxes of lace since I left the store, as it was but a few minutes, and therefore no one but myself could have taken it; and then the young man asked me, in a most insulting tone, how many pieces of ribbon 1 had taken besides, and what a poor woman, who lived in such an old, house, could do with such a rich piece of lace: that the remnant was worth ten dollars. The officer told me, that if I would quietly return what I had stolen, they would let me off, as Mr. Hardy said I had always borne a good character, and had a family of children to sup- port; but, if I would not give up Ithe goods, I must follow them at once to Mr. Bell, the magistrate's; and that if I refused to do either, they would carry me there. I asserted my innocence. It was all I could do. I told them I'remembered seeing the rich remnant of lace; for I wash so many fine things for the ladies in town, that I knew its value, and admired its beauty;   MY STEP-MOTHER.       53 but that I did not take it, nor even desire it. God has not given me wealth, Sir; but he has given me a contented mind, and I covet nothing, and envy no one. I cannot tell you, Sir, how unhappy I felt, as I followed them to the magistrate's. What would my poor husband have said, had he been living, when 1 was suspected of dishonesty, and actually taken, like a thief, before a magistrate ? I was filled with shame, though I knew my innocence. Mr. Bell knew my poor husband, and my good character; and, after ex-. amining me, he told me to go home and wait until to-day, that further search might be made in the store for the lost lace. What can I do, Sir ? or what can you do for me ? Indeed I hiave told you the strict truth. I fear God, and would not tell a lie. You do not think I took the lace " "No, indeed, my good woman," said my father. "I believe your story entirely; and I feel quite cer- tain of your innocence. I think I shall be able to get you out of your difficulty. The lace will prob- ably be found to-day, as I shall go to Mr. Hardy's, and request a thorough search for it. If it is not found, I will pay its value. Your character cannot suffer among those who have known your honest'hus- band and yourself as long as I have." " You are too kind, Sir: may God bless you. I do earnestly hope the lace will be found. They searched 5* &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7603-00000028"/> 54       MY STEP-MOTHEoR. every thing in my house, and saw it was not there; though the clerk said, he supposed I had hidden it. I could bear the disgrace of a bad name better, were it not for my poor children, who will have to make their way in the world; and it will be hard for them to have a stain on their names, when their father could look the whole world in the face. But, God is just; I will put my trust in Him, and, in his own good time, he will make my innocence as clear as the light. While He permits, for my discipline, this shadow to rest upon me, I will pray for grace to bear it meekly. If you will be so kind, Sir, as to go to Mr. Bell's at ten o'clock, and speak a word for my , character, God will reward you." "I will be there," said my father; "and do not dis- tress yourself. I trust we shall be able to make it all clear. Now, sit down, and take some breakfast. I see Mrs. Williams has been preparing some for you;" and my father left the room. Encouraged by my mother, Mrs. Graham seated herself at the table, and partook of some breakfast; and cheered by words of sympathy and kindness from my mother, she left us. I had watched the whole scene with great interest. As she went out, I said'to my mother, I hope they will find the lace. - "I do not doubt that her inno- cence will be proved in some way," said my mother.   MY STEP-MOTHERI.       55 "She puts her trust in O,ne who never deserts his children. Dear Grace," she continued, " we should always try to conceal the faults of others, and not ex- pose them. If you hear any thing against a person's character, never believe it, until it has been proved to be true. Never repeat any thing injurious to another, nor circulate an idle report, nor even any thing that is true and is against another person's character. You did not intend to break God's command, 'Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbor,' when you re- peated the story about Mrs. Graham; and yet you did break it, mnydear child, because she did not take the lace. I feel quite sure that it will be proved. When you repeat vain and idle reports of others, you know not how often you break that command." At dinner, my father told us that the lace had not been found; and that Mr. Hardy had agreed to wait a week, and have a thorough search made; and if it did not appear in that time, he said Mrs. Graham must pay the value of the lace. Mattie and I, with our accustomed idle busy-body ways, went several times to the store in the course of the week, to'inquire whether the lace had been found. Once, as we were entering, we met poor Mrs. Graham coming out. She had probably been, there, on the same errand. She looked so care-worn, and so dejected, that, it touched even my thoughtless heart.  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7603-00000029"/> 56       ]MY STEI'-MOTHER. The week passed, and the lace was not found. My father paid Mr. Hardy the price of it; but a stigmna rested on the hitherto fair name of Mrs. Graham. Oh, how grieved I felt, and how cruel I had been, when Rose Seymour told me, that her mother had given her washing to another woman, because I had told her that Mrs. Graham was a thief. I made all the reparation I could; and, unknown to my mother, I went to Mrs. Seymour's, and told her that my father believed her innocent.. She told me she never em- ployed suspicious characters; that there were honest people enough to do her work; that she would not run the risk of losing her nice laces; and that, more- over, her friend, Mrs. Stone, who had given Mrs. Gra- ham a great deal of work for many months, 1pad1 also withdrawn it, because she had told her, that-I had said Mrs. Graham was a thief. My conscience did not fail bitterly to reproach me; and "Thou shalt not bear false witness," was constantly sounding in my ears. Towards the close of the second week after' the dis- appearance of the lace, as we were one evening sitting at tea, the door was hastily thrown open, and Mrs. Graham stood before us, almost breathless from run- ning. "O, Sir," she said, "O, Mr. Williams; O, Miss Grace," her face beaming with joy, "the lace is found. It is all cleared up. I shall have an honest   MY STEP-MOTHER.       57 name for my poor children. I knew in whom I trusted; for He said, 'Let thy widows trust in me.' I did trust in Him; and, blessed be his name forever, He has proved my innocence, and has been my strong- hold in the day of my adversity. May the widow's God bless you, Sir, for befriending me in my need. Here are the ten dollars you paid for me. Mr. Hardy has returned them to me." She then proceeded to say, that Mr. Hardy had just been to her house, to tell her that a lady who lived ten miles back in the country, and who was in the habit of purchasing goods at his store, had been there and brought the lace, stating that she had found it, when she reached her home, tangled upon the fringe and points of her parasol. She said, she took her parasol up hastily when she left the store, and threw it upon the seat of her carriage; and, as it was behind her, she did not see it until she reached her home, and took out her parasol; that her distance from town and her numerous engagements had made it impossible for her to return it before. She felt much grieved, when she heard the suspicion of steal- ing it had fallen upon a poor and honest wonan. She sent Mrs. Graham five dollars through Mr. Hardy, to which he had added five more. We truly rejoiced with the poor woman in her happiness. My father refused to receive back the ten dollars he had paidl ?   &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7603-00000030"/> 58       MY STEP-MOTHER. and the poor widow left us, saying, "Who ever put his trust in Him and was confounded?" One would have: thought, that such a serious' les- son as this would have made a lasting impression on my mind, and have taught me to govern my toingue, that most unruly member; and to busy myself less with other people's affairs. But it required many lessons, to soften my thoughtless worldly heart. CHAPTER VII. ANOTHER PICTURE OF MYSELF. DEAR Grace," said my mother to me, one day, "'I am afraid I shall vex you; but John has complained to me of you so many times, that I promised him, to- day, that I would speak to you. He says, that, almost every day, your school-mates and you come running into the hall from the street, without cleaning your shoes on the mat, which lies on the steps for that purpose; and that you leave tracks of mud or dust all over his nice floor-cloth, just at calling hours; so that he has to leave his work, and clean the cloth again." John is an impudent cross thing, I interrupted; and it is none of his business if we do.  "But it certainly is some 'of his business, Grace,"    MY STEP-MOTHER.  '      59 said my mother; " because it is a serious interruption to him. He cannot be dressed suitably to attend the door, if he is engaged in cleaning the floor-cloth. Be reasonable, my child; and also desire to do what is right, even in trifles, for, in reality, nothing that in- terferes with another's comfort can be a trifle." He is a lazy old thing, I said, and does not like to work; and so he complains of having it to do; but he is paid for it, it is his business to do it, and I shall not trouble myself about what he likes or dislikes. "And further, Grace," said my mother, "he com- plains sadly of your trampling on the beds in the gar- den, gathering his rarest flowers, and culling them so carelessly that you often pull up the roots. He says, that you and your companions gather the fruit before it is half ripe; that oftentimes when lie has been watching the fruit with great care, expecting to have a nice dish for dessert the next day, you have stripped it all from the trees or bushes; and that your father would think it was from his want of care or skill, that he had no fruit. He did not like to complain to him, of you and your friends." le is an impertinent, insulting fellow, I said, and the only waiter we ever had that dared to complain of me. If he does it again, I will complain of him to my father, and have him turned away. It is my house, and not his; and I shall, every day, bring just  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7603-00000031"/> 60       MY STEP-MOTHER. as many girls through the hall as I like. The garden is mine, tnd not his; and I have told him so, ofter, when he scolds at me. Flowers and fiuit grow to be gathered, and for nothing else; and we shall gather all that we please, green or ripe fruit, rare or common flowers, without consulting Mr. John. "John is very neat, and very faithful," said my mother; "and he fears we may think him otherwise, if the house and garden are not nicely kept. My dear child, do not feel excited nor angry about it. That is wrong. And do not speak of John with in- justice. If we are accused of doing any thing wrong, we should reflect upon it, and ask ourselves whether we are not to blame. If we are, we are to correct ourselves; for every one has faults, and every one is liable to err.' I am not to blame at all, I said. I hate John; and so do Mattie and all the girls, because he scolds us all, and thinks we are going to mind him. My father lets me have my own way; and I always mean to have it; and I do not choose to be controlled by any body. I emphasized the words "any body," inl a very significant manner; and I arose and left the room, slamming the door loudly after me, in a most impertinent manner. I then ran to the nursery, and told nurse that mother had been scolding at me for running through the hall, and for breaking off some   MY STEP-MOTHER.       61 flowers in the garden; and then I burst into a flood of tears. "Poor dear, poor dear," said nurse, "how un- reasonable she is! But what more can one expect of a step-mother? She that has been here so little while, undertaking already to say what you shall do, who has lived here all your life! I suppose she ex- pects you to come in the back door all the time; that is the way Susan Dale's step-mother treated her; not so well as she treated the servants. O no, though she made a servant of her, I can tell you. And I suppose she expects you to come to her, and make a courtesy, and ask permission to break off a rose, or a bunch of currants. Poor dear, I see plain enough how tight she means to keep you. Do not give up to her, deary. I hope you showed your spirit. Now is your time to show her what you are, and how you mean to live with her. Come to old nurse, my pet, and she will comfort you, and tell you how to manage." O, here they come, said I, one half-holiday, as 1 stood at the window; here they come. "Who?" my mother asked, as I was rushing from the room. O, the girls that are coming here to tea, I answered hastily. I had invited half a dozen of my schoolmates to come and take tea with me; and I would not men- 6  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7603-00000032"/> MY STEP-MOTHER. .d tion it to my mother, because I wished to show her, that I considered myself just as much mistress as her- self; and that I intended to invite company, and to do any thing else that I pleased, without consulting her. A wild merry time we always had of it, when my companions visited me; and I was determined we would behave as we always had done, lest imy companions should think I was afraid of my step- mother. We raced up and down stairs, dozens of times, through the halls into the garden and back again, with our soiled shoes over the nice carpets; played hide and seek, from one end of the house to the other. Then we tried the old swing in the garret; we trundled our hoops over the piazza; we played ball and the graces in the hall, to the great danger of hall lamps; we robbed the garden of its fruit and flowers; and we did as many rude and noisy things as my young readers can imagine such a wild lawless set of girls could do. My mother's closets and pantries were invaded, to the .great destruction of cake, cookies, and ginger- bread; to say nothing of figs, nuts, raisins, sweet- meats, and any thing upon which we could lay our hands. John, said I to the waiter, these young ladies are to take tea with me this evening, so set the table ac- cordingly.   : Y STEP-MOTHER.   63   The house was a scene of uproar and confusion, all the afternoon. I expected, every moment, my mother would come from her room, and reprove us as we deserved, for our rudeness and noise, if not for our extremely disrespectful conduct towards her. But she did not. She received my companions, as I awk- wardly enough introduced them to her at tea-time, with great kindness and sweetness. I saw that my fiiends were much struck with the loveliness of her appearance, and the gentleness of her manners.  She talked to them in a lively, pleasant strain; and, after tea, she interested herself to entertain them, by bring- ing out fine engravings, and books, and by playing and singing for them, and encouraging them to assist her. " 0, Grace," said Helen Morton, as she said good night to me in the hall, " I should think you would love your step-mother dearly. I love her already; she is so pretty, and sweet, and kind." "Love a step-mother 1" said Mattie Miller. "Who ever heard of such a thing ? Grace is too wise for  that.  Mother says, no children ever love them." " And why not love them, if they are so good, and kind, and pretty ?" said Helen. " If she were mine, I would love her better than any body. Her voice is sweeter than a bird's; and she reminds me of the lily of the valley, she is so fair and gentle."   &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7603-00000033"/> O4,       MY STEP-MOTHlER. After my companlions had gone, my father said to me, "Grace, did you ask your mother's permission to invite your young friends to visit you to-day?" No, father, I said; I have always invited theill here when I wanted thell, without asking any one. You never forbade me. "That is true, my dear," said my father; "I fear I have allowed you to have your own way too mu(ch. For the future, when you wish to have company, first ask your mother if it is convenient and agreeable to her. She is now the mistress of this-house; and every person in it must consult her wishes, in every particular, and act accordingly. Remember, my dear, what I tell you." My father then left the room. It is too bad, I began, as soon as my father had closed the door, too bad, that I should be put down so. It is just what nurse, and cook, and Mrs. Miller, and Mattie, all told me. I can no longer lhave any more liberty in my own father's house, than if I were a servant; and I plainly see, that even he has turned against me. It is too cruel; and I burst into tears. "Dear Grace," said my mother, gently, "it will always give me pleasure to see your friends here, at any time you wish.  So, consider yourself just as much at liberty to invite them as you always have been. It might sometimes be more convenient, if you wished to invite a number, to let me know in the /   MY STEP-MOTHERE.       6 morning, on account of making some different ar- rangement about tea." I began to feel ashamed of my impertinence and passion, as my mother spoke so kindly; but I would not let her see it, and I continued in the same strain. I think I am too old to be treated like a baby, and to be compelled to ask any body if I may do this thing or that. I never had to do so before; and I do not mean to begin now. Father is growing really cross to me. He never was so before. They all told me I should have a hard time of it; and I think it is beginning now. "My dear Grace," said my mother, soothingly, "I have but one wish in, regard to yourself, and that is, to make you happy. Judge for yourself, my child, what claims your mother has to your regard and affection, and how far your father is reasonable in his demands; and do not allow prejudice to blind you, nor the opinions of others to turn you against your best friends." Nurse and Mattie are my best friends, I said pet- tishy. I do not call any one my friend who wants to rule me like a slave. So saying, I rudely left the room, to pour my sorrows into the eager ears of my nurse. Father did not know it was dancing-school after- noon, I said one day to my mother, after he'had left                     .Q  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7603-00000034"/> 6.6       MY STEP-MOTHER. the table, or he would have forbidden me to go out in the rain. I would not remind him of it, because I wanted so much to go, and I mean to go. "I an  grieved," said my mother, "that my little daughter  should be willing to do what her father disapproves of; when her father is so indulgent to her." Why, it is such nonsense, I answered, for father to think that it will hurt me to go out in the rain: it will not hurt me at all. And then he will never know it, un- less you tell him, mother; for nurse and cook never tell of me, and if you choose to tell him, I shall run the risk of taking a scolding, for I am determined to go to-day. We are to have some new dances, and are practising for the exhibition, and I would not miss it for the world.  John, I said, as the waiter entered, go to the kitchen, and tell nurse to finish her dinner as quickly as pos- sible, and to dress me for dancing-school. "Yes, Miss," said John, "but it rains quite fast." Do as I bid you, I said: do you not suppose I can see the rain? I am  going; and be ready yourself to wall there with me, and to hold the umbrella over me; and if it rains at five o'clock, be sure you are there punctually to take me home.  While nurse was dressing me, my mother came to , the nursery, and kindly suggested the use of a large  k shawl and India-rubber shoes. So soon as she left    I*       '      *   MY STEP-MOTHER.       67 the room, nurse said, "I will not have her interfering with your dress.. I have dressed you thirteen years, and I think it is time I knew, better than a step- miother, what you ought to wear. But they are such leddlesomle, ruling kind of people, that one cannot expect any thing else. I will not give way one inch to her: I know what a nurse's place is, and what a lady's place is." I hate India-rubbers, I said, and I won't wear them; they will soil my nice silk stockings. "Well, go -vithout theml, delary, if you choose," said nurse; " but wrap this large shaw around you, to keep your pretty new dress from the rain, and hold it up all round. -It is such a beauty, it would be a pity to spoil it. You won't get any. more suih handsome ones, when your step-mother begins to buy them for you." She will never buy them for me, nurse, I replied; our tastes are entirely unlike, and I choose to select for my- self. "Poor dear, poor dear," said nurse, "that is right; keep to it as long Is you can. Things is changing here, though you do not see so much of it as I do; and we shall all have to change, too, before long. Step-mothers one cannot hinder from doing what they will; but run along, my darling, and dance bet- ter than all the girls, and don't trouble-your pretty head about it, Time enough for that."  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7603-00000035"/> 6 8      MY STEP-MOTHER. One Sunday afternoon, ,when my father was absent firom town, mother and I were on our way to ch urch together, when, as we passed Mr. Miller's, Mattie call- ed to me from the window, saying, "Grace, do not go moping to church this afternoon, you were there this morning. I am sure that is enough. Come in, and stay with me; I have something to tell you, and we will go out to the summer-house, and sit and have a nice time." I wanted to go in, but at first felt a little afraid to leave my mother, knowing how much she would disapprove of it; but then the thought came to me, now is the time to show that I am my own mistress, and not to be controlled by her; so I said hastily, Good-by, mother, I won't go to church this afternoon, I think: I will go in and stay with Mattie, and be home at tea. "Dear Grace," said my mother, with a pleading look-I did not give her time to proceed; but I ran  i back, and entered Mr. Miller's. "I am glad to see you showing a proper spirit,"  said Mattie: "you will get along, with her by-and-by, and maintain your own freedom of action, too. Just show her that you mean to be your own mistress, and there will be no trouble, mother says." , I knew I had done wrong, and I did not feel happy '  that afternoon. My mother's pleading eye seemed to  follow me; but I excused myself to my conscience,    MY STEP-MOTHER.       69 by telling it, that I was capable of judging for myself, and it was best for me to act for myself, and not sub- mit to the tyranny of a step-mother. As we sat together that evening, she said, "I was much grieved, dear Grace, that you left me this after- noon, and stayed away from church to visit Mattie." It is too dull to go to church all day, I answered. I nevelr did until you came here, unless I had some- tiling new and pretty to wear. Mattie told me I should get a preaching for staying away. "Do not speak so, my dear," said my mother, mildly. "I do not think you would wilfully break one of God's commands, though you might thoughtlessly or ignorantly. Do you remember the ten command- ments?"  Yes, I said, I believe I know them all; and I never studied them. And how do you think I learned them? Why, it has always been my amusement at church, ever since I could read, to try and decipher them over the chancel from our pew; and the Creed and the Lord's Prayer also; and that is the way I learned them. "Do you relember the fourth commandment?" asked my mother.  "Remember the Sabbath-day, and keep it holy," I replied. "And what is it to keep it holy, my child?" asked my mother. Why, to go to church all day, I suppose, I answered; but  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7603-00000036"/> 70       MY STEP-MOTHER. father never forbade me to go and see Mattie on Sun- day, so there is no harm in it. "But we may go to church all day, dear Grace," said my mother, "and yet not keep God's day holy. It; when we are at church, our thoughts are busying themselves about the dress and appearance of those around us, or are occupied with any' thing but the worship of our Creator, following the holy services in prayer or praise, we are insulting our glorious Creator, and desecrating his holy day. It is Our duty to at- tend the services of the sanctuary, aid to ask God's help, that we may offer to him acceptable worship; for we do not keep his day holy, unless our thoughts are occupied with him. Did your father know, my dear, that you visited Mattie on Sundays?" I do not know, I answered: he always took me to church with him in the morning; and, in the after- noon, he sat at home reading, and I did as I liked. Since you have been here, he has been at church all day; and so have I when he has been at home, be- cause he told me to go. But I do not like it; and when he is away, I shall not go all Iay. It is too dull. I almost always go to sleep in the afternoon. "I am sorry to hear that," said my mother. "' If you would try and interest yourself in the services, and ask God's help, on entering church, to enable you to do, it, you would very soon love to go. And the i , .    I   MY STEP-MOTHER.   "  more you attended the services, the more you would enjoy them. Be assured, my dear Grace, there is an unspeakable pleasure in following God's blessed com- mands, and walking before-him in prayer and love." Mattie told me, I said rudely, that I should have a long preaching, for staying with her this afternoon; so I expected it, and made up my mind to bear it patiently. But I think I have had enough of it; so I won't hear any more, or I shall forget what I have heard. But, mother, let me tell you, you do not un- derstand me yet; you must let me do as I please, and you may do as you please, and that is the best way for us to get along together. So saying, I went to the nursery, and told nurse and cook that I was going to deliver to them a ser- mon I had just heard, on keeping the Sabbath; and I hoped they would profit by it as much as I had. "Poor dear, poor dear! plenty of sermons now-a- days," said nurse, i* ^ -k  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7603-00000037"/> 12       MY STEP-MOTHER. CHtAPTER VIII.  THE IO-OUSE-MOVING. O, SUCH a fine time Mattie and I have had, this morning, I said, one day at dinner; I imust hurry, and run back, or I shall lose part of the fun. Did you know they were moving a house, father? I in- quired. He replied in the negative. O, do go and  see it, father, I said; it is worth seeing. It is such a large house, and there are so many oxen and men. They have yet a long distance to carry it ; and Mattie and I are going to follow it all the way. They do not  get along very fast; for, every now and then, the little wheels on which it is set, or the planks, or something, will get out of order, and they have to stop a long time to get it ready to move again. A good many koys and some rude girlsl got into it to take a ride. Mattie wanted me to get!n, but I would not; I was afraid. "Do not allow Mattie to lead you into dangerous and improper places, Grace," said my father; "for if  she does, I shall forbid you to associate with her." O, father, I proceeded, they cut off a great many, large branches from those splendid elm-trees in High-street and Summer-street, to make room for the house to :       i   MY STEP-MOTHER.       73 move along; and the boys took them and fastened them up at the windows of the house, and madeit look very pretty. But, dear me, I must go. The men had gone home to dinner; but they must have returned by this time. So saying, I ran unceremo- niously from the room. I met Mattie near the house; and, instead of going to school, we followed a crowd of idle boys and girls, to see the moving house. My mother looked very sober, as I spoke of our morning's and intended afternoon's occupation; and once she partly opened her mouth, as if to say some- thing on the subject; but she checked herself, and remained silent. Yet her look haunted me, as I ran down street with my wild companion. Two hours after, I was running by our house with the greatest speed, followed by Mattie, when nurse called to me firom the window, saying, Where are you running, Miss Grace, in such haste? Do, child, stop one mo- ment, and tell me if any thing has happened; you are so excited." O, nurse, I said, scarcely stopping, Joe Morton is killed: he fell from the house when it was moving; and I am going to tell his mother. I am in a great hurry, and will tell you the rest when I return. "Grace, Grace,' called a voice from another win- dow. I looked up and saw my mother.. I cannot stop, mother, I said; Joe Morton is killed; and I 7  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7603-00000038"/> 74       MY STEP-MOTHER. down street towards Mrs. Morton's house. I opened the door, rushed in hastily, and exclaimed, loudly and thoughtlessly, O, Mrs. Morton, Joe is killed; ho fell from the moving house, and is dead. The poor widow uttered a loud shriek, of such agony and hor- ror as I can never forget; and she fell senseless on the floor. Then, for the first time, it, rushed into my mind, how dreadful the tidings I was so eager to communicate must be to her. She was a widow, and Joe was her only child. I must warn my young readers, to beware of this news-telling, gossiping spirit. It blunts all the warm and delicate' sensibilities of our nature, renders rude and thoughtless the heart of youth, and crowds from the mind all that is lofty and holy. It fills up life with idleness, folly, and ofttimes wrong; and causes tears of bitterness and shame. Never did the Psalmist of old utter a wiser resolu- tion, than when he exclaimed, "I will take heed to my ways, that I sin not with my tongue." What have I done what have I done I exclaim- ed, with horror, as I saw before me the lifeless form of poor Mrs. Morton. I have killed her! I have killed her! and I rushed wildly firom the house, and up the street, hardly knowing what I did, but with the one desire of calling for help. I felt myself gently stopped, by some one taking my arm, and recognized, th my great surprise, my mother.   MY STEP-MOTHER.       75 Come to Mrs. Morton, mother, I exclaimed. I have killed her! Oh, come to her!"I was on my way there, Grace," she said, very seriously; "I called to you, to prevent you from- taking to her such painful tidings of distress, but you would not stop; and so I hastened after you, to overtake you. Is it a pleasant thing to be -the bearer of such news, my child, that you should hasten to do it, and desire to be the first to communicate it? And are you quite sure it is true"? Suppose it should turn out otherwise? He might have fainted, from some slight blow or injury; and; should that be the case, how much unnecessary suffering you have caused his poor mother!" I was quite overcome by this, and burst into a flood of tears. On entering the house, we found Mrs. Morton where I had left her, stiff and motionless on the floor. Oh, she is dead; I said with great horror; I have killed her. What can I do? . "Run directly for a physician, Grace," said my mother, as she dashed some cold water into her face, and, kneeling by her, chafed her temples. I obeyed; but I had gone only a short distance when I met some men bearing poor Joe Morton on a litter; and, seeing physicians in attend- ance, I returned to the house, which they also reached in a few minutes. "Do not alarm mly mother," I heard Joe say, as they brought him in. "I am  not much hurt, mother.  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7603-00000039"/> '76      MY STEP-MOTHER. Please, Sir, do tell her so; do not fiighten her, it would kill my poor mother. Mother, mother," he said, as they entered the room where she lay; where is my mother?"At seeing her lying still and insensi- ble on the floor, he exclaimed, "Oh, who could be so cruel as to tell my poor mother, and frighten her so? Who has killed my dear mother'?  Oh, mother, mother!" and the poor boy fainted. O that I could, at that moment, have hidden ny- self from the light of day. Joe hadl not been killed; but I should be the cause of, killing them both. Oh, wretched, wretched me! I was seized with feelings of the most unspeakable horror; but all who were present were too busy to think of me. My mother requested the men to lay poor Mrs. Morton on the bed, and it was a long time before she showed any signs of returning life. And then she relap- sed, from one fainting into another. My mother had Joe placed on a cot-bed near his mother, so that, on open- ing her eyes, she might see, at once, that he was still living; for poor Joe, on recovering from his swoon, seemed to forget all his own sufferings, in thinking of his mother. O, how like an angel of mercy my mother then appeared to me, moving gently round in this room of distress, and endeavoring to repair the l misery my thoughtlessness hadi caused. She seated herself on the bed, near Mrs. Morton, and bathed her   MY STEP-MOTHER.       " temples, and tried to rouse her to consciousness, by every usual method. And as sqon as she saw /a symptom of returning animation, she spoke cheerfully to her, saying, "'Your son is living, my poor woman, and is here, and we hope not much injured; try and speak to him." "Here-O no," said Mrs. Morton; here-O no, he was killed to-day. They told me so; do not keep it from me; killed, and he is my all, my only child." Joe now called to her saying, 'l Mother, dear mother, I am not killed. I am not much hurt; do not go into those dreadful swoons again, or I shall die. Who could have told my poor mother that I was killed  O speak to me, my own mother." The woman raised herself in bed, and her eyes falling on her son, she burst into a flood of tears, in which poor Joe mingled his, as she fell upon his neck.     I It was found, on examination, that Joe had broken one of his legs; and as he was stunned by the fall, and was taken up senseless, some of the boys near hiln supposed he was dead. I heard them exclaim, Joe Morton is killed; and, eager to be the first to tell the news, without thinking of its awful nature, and the agony it would cause his mother, I ran off to in- "tiulge my sad propensity for news-telling, regardless of consequences. Never have I forgotten the horror 7* l, ,   &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7603-00000040"/> '18       MY STEP-MOTHER. of that hlour; I thinkl it was almost the first time in my life, tlat ever I thought seriously of any tiling I had done. I kept repeating to myself, O that I had not told herr My mother, seeing my distress, as I sat weeping bitter tears of remorse in a distant part of the roon, calme to rne, and told me it would be better for me to retuln hlome, and th:at she would follow, so soon as she saw that all was comfortable there. 1 obeyed her unhesitatingly; and, an hour afterwards, when she returned, she found me lying weeping on the sofa with my face bulied in the cuslions. She seated herself by me, and, raising me ge'ntly, placed my head on her shoulder, and- said, "Dear Grace, you have had a hard lesson to-day. God grant its teachings may never be forgotten. It has grieved me much, my dear, to see the habit you have ac- quired, of too much talking, of gossiping, ald news- telling. God has given us a command, Thou shalt not bear false witness; which command implies, that the strictest care should be observed in regard to truth. A person who acquires a habit of talking too much, and of reporting and relating every little in- cident or conversation, soon acquires also a habit of making his story as amusing and wonderful as he can, and thus learns to violate the truth, and break the commands of his Maker. You supposed, to-day, that you were telling the truth, when you so hastily   -MY STEP-MOTHER.       79, carried to poor Mrs. Morton such awful tidings of her son. Your love of nlews-telling caused you to lose sigkht of the distress you must occasion her, and the dalger of so suddenly telling her of such an awful calamity, which proved to be false. You were the cause of Mrs. Morton's being thrown into a most dan- gerous state, and of increasing the sufferings of her  son. You would not deliberately have caused them sucht distress; but your love of news-telling may lead even to worse and mlore fatal consequences, if it is in- dulged."' O no, mother, I said, I never will do such a thing again; I shall nelver forget how unhappy I have been to-day. "All, my dear child, it is easier to resolve than to perform our resolutions," she replied. "No one can do right, of himself; no onle can govern his own tongue. The Bible says, The tongue can no man tame. God's power bestowed upon us, by his blessed Spirit, alone can do it. I do not wish to discourage you; but I wish you to know where to seek for power to do what you cannot do of yourself." She took a Bible from the table, and turning to the third chapter of the Epistle of St. James, she read:-"If any man offend not in word, the same is a perfect man, and able also to bridle the whole body. The tongue is a fire, a world of iniquity; so is the tongue among our mem-  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7603-00000041"/> 80       MY STEP-MOTHER. bers, that it defileth the whole body, and setteth on fire the course of nature, and it is set on fire of hell. For every kind of beasts, and of birds, and of serpents, and of things in the sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed of mankind; but the tongue can no man tame; it is an unruly evil, full of deadly poison. Therewith bless we God, even the Father; and therewith curse we men, which are made after the sjmilitude of God. Out of the same mouth proceedeth blessing and curs- ing. Who is a wise, man and endued with knowledge among you? let him shew out of a good conversation his works with meekness of wisdom"' She then explained to me, in a most simple and earnest way, the meaning of these verses; and seeing I was quiet and interested, she said, "Dear Grace, they were given for your instruction, as well as mine. The duties they involve are binding upon you, as well as  me;. for,l my dear child, you are baptized into the  body of Christ's Church, and made a living member I of the same. You have promised to renounce the   i devil and all his works, the vain pomp and glory of i the world, and all sinful lusts of the flesh; to believe all the articles of the Christian faith; and to keep  God's holy will and commandments, and walk in the same all the days of your life.' Have I, mother? I said; I did not know it. Tears filled her lovely eyes, as I said this; and,   MY STEP-MOTHER.       81 looking upon me with inexpressible love and pity, she said- "Yes, my dear daughter, such your baptism has made both your duty and your privilege. You are a member of Christ, and a child of God, and are under solemn obligations to obey the commands of God, and live as a member of Christ should live here, so that you forfeit not your privileges as " an inher- itor of the kingdonm of heaven." Nurse told me I was baptized when I was an in- fant, I said, and I learned part of the Catechism at Sunday-school, but I never understood much about it, and did not like to study it. "My dear child," she replied, "the vows and prom- ises of your baptism are upon you. Your pious mother gave you, on her death-bed, to her covenant God; and with the holy sign of the cross you were sealed to your Saviour's service. God requires of you to keep these vows; and fearful will be the end of all who keep them not. You are now thirteen years old, dear Grace. It is a long time to live and know no- thing of God and your duty. Thirteen years, you have been pledged to God's service and love, by the most solemn promises; and he now calls upon you to understand their nature, and to live no longer un- mindful of your vows. Will you, my dear child, con- sent to study the Catechism of the Church with me,    &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7603-00000042"/> 82       MY STEP-MOTHER. every Sunday, and try to learn your duty, and seek grace to perform it?" Yes, mother, I said; for my heart was softened for the time, and I was willing to do any thing she re- quired. "And this, only this, I ask of you, dear Grace, Will you recollect and repeat often to yourself, I am by baptism made a child of God; how should I be- have as such? And ask God, the Father, who loves you with an everlasting love, though you have thought little of Him; and the dear Redeemer, who said, Suffer little children to come unto nme; and the Holy Spirit, who desireth to fill your mind' with all that is good and holy,-ask them to guide and teach you." My tears flowed abundantly: her manner was so earnest and affectionate, and the truths so new to my ears, as applied to myself; for, though I had listened to them always at Church, I never thought they concerned me personally. "Let us ask God to- gether, my child," she said, "for his help and blessing." She knelt, and, for the first time in my life, I kneeled in prayer at her side, and she prayed; "Almighty God, who showest to them that are in error the light of thy truth, to the intent that they may return into the way of righteousness, grant unto all those who are admitted into the fellowship of Christ's religion, that they may avoid those things that are contrary to their   MY STEP-MOTHER.       83 profession, and follow all such things as are agreeable to the same, through our Lord Jesus Christ. Grant, O Lord, that as we are baptized into the death of thy blessed Son, our Saviour Jesus Christ, so by con- tinual mortifting our corrupt affections we may be b tried with him; and that through the grave, and gate of death, we may pass to our joyful resurrection; for his merits, who died, and was buried, and rose again for us, thy Son Jesus Christ, our Lord. Amen. O God, the strength df all who put their trust in thee, mercifully accept 'our prayers; and because, through the weakness of our mortal nature, we can do no good thing without thee, grant us the help of thy grace, that in keeping thy commandments we may please thee, both in will and deed, through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen." My mother kissed me most affectionately, and said, "We will now go to our rooms, dear daughter, and prepare for tea. Your father will soon be at home." We left the room, and ascended the stairs together. I went 'to the nursery, and my mother to her own room, which was directly opposite. The doors of both were open. Nurse was sitting in the nursery, and did not know that mother came up stairs with me; but I knew, from what followed, that she must -have overheard the conversation. My eyes were red and swollen with weeping. It  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7603-00000043"/> 84       WMY STEP-MOTHER. was a most unusual thing for me to be moved to tears; and nurse looked much surprised as I entered. "Why, what is the matter with my pet?" she said; "who has made her cry? Not old nurse; no, she never made her pet cry. Come and tell nurse what is the cause of my darling's tears. She never cries without a good cause. It is something your step- mother has done or said-to you. You look as if you had been beaten. Well, step-mothers like nothing better than to make their step-children cry and feel unhappy. Poor dear, this is but the beginning of your troubles, I know. It was really cruel in your father to put a step-mother over you; I should never have thought it of such a nice man. What comfort or happiness will you have now, all the rest of your life, poor dear? Well, always remember, you have one friend in nurse. Poor Joe Morton was not killed after all, was he; dear?" On hearing Joe's name, I again burst into a flood of tears. " O, poor dear, now old nurse has found out what is the matter; your step-mother has been scold- ing you for running and telling his mother, and frightening her so; but how could ' you know she would take it so hard; your step-mother ought to be -ashiamed to blame you for it. It was all perfectly natural, dear, for you to run and tell her the news. I should have done it myself. If that is all that's the   MY STEP-MOTHER, matter, deary, dry up your tears, and do not care one penny about it." I am sorry I ran and told her, nurse, I said. It was wrong in me. "O, do hear the poor dear, saying she was wrong," said nurse, who was truly surprised at this first evidence of humility I had ever shown; "' how could you know she was going to take on so, and go into fits, and all such awful things. Folks isn't often taken in that way; and if you had not told her, somebody else would, deary. So do not think or care any more about it; though your step-mother has almost scolded all the spirit out of my darling, and almost made her think she has murdetred the poor woman, or committed some awful crime. You have done nothing at all wrong, my  pet, but perfectlyt right. I am older, by many years, than yor' stetp- mother, and I know, as well as she dloes, your Pa would not liave scolded you so, I am sure." Mother did not scold me, nurse, I said. "Well, preached to you, then, deary; that is worse. I had rather have a   Found scolding, than a long preaching, any day. Now, be good, and forget all about it, and tell me all about Joe and his mother; for I was quite tired out, waiting for you to come home and tell me, as I would not, go out to find out. But, stop, let me call cook to hear, too." I related to my attentive listeners the circumstan- 8  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7603-00000044"/> ces above narrated, and reeived  their warm thanks and praises. "She talks like a book,"  said nurse ;, "don't she, cook? You and I are her friends, ain't we, come what will?"The tea-bell interrupted our conversation. CHAPTER IX. AN IMPORTANT CHANGE. NOTWITHSTANDING the improper and ill-judged re- marks of nurse, and the subsequent conversation, after I retired to bed that night, my thoughts dwelt much on what my mother had said to me; and more se- rious reflections than ever had occupied me before, filled my mind. My baptism, was it really something more than the "pretty story about "me and my mother" which nurse hqd so often called it, in relat- ing it to mte, and to which I had listened from the, earliest dawn of reason, not associating with it a single idea of personal interest or responsibility? It must be something of importance; for mother had said, by it I was made " a child of God.'"I had learned it in my Catechism before; but I thought nothing about it. And, moreover, mother had told me to ask my- self how ought I to behave as a child of God? I must   M i Y I t m a P-, H-vJ A JL L .... be good, I thought; and vnague and indefinite ideas of goodness, and desires and resolves for the same, floated through my mind until I fell asleep. Ah, how highly favored are those children, who are taught, by pious parents, so soon as they can lisp the sacred name of their Maker, what solemn vows and promises have been made for them in their bap- tism; and'who are led, step by step, -in the perform- anlce of Christian duties, so that they imbibe, with the very air they breathe, the blessed teachings and requirements of the Church of which they are made members, and learn to love and rejoice in her holy fellowship, all the days of their lives. Dear children, who are thus favored, learn to value your high privi- leges as you oughlt. Be not weary of the pious teach- ings of your parents, nor consider the sacred services of the Church wecarisome, and turn from them with eagerness to the follies and sins of the world. If you do, heavy and sore judgments hang over you. A fearful recloning is at hand for all such. I said, it was the first time in my life; and I was thirteen years of age before any one had talked to me, directly anti personally, of my religious duties. For that reason, the conversation was impressed deeply on my mind: it was a- new idea to me, that there was another .and a higher life, distinct from the merely animal life I had hitherto led,--the life of the  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7603-00000045"/> soul; that I was pledged, once and forever, to the service of my Maker; that I had no right to follow tlthe promptings and dictates of my own lawless will. I was a member of the Church of Christ, one of a large family, with an All-seeing Father above me; and was bound by solemn promises, "to obey His holy will and commandments, and walk in the same all the days of my life." The story of my Baptism dwelt constantly in my mind; and, for the first timle, its life and spirituality began to dawn upon my awakening spirit. The prayers then offered for me by my dying .mother, were bringing down blessings upon my soul; and the voice of the Church, visible and invisible, was softly wooing me to the life of those who, having been "buried with the Chirst in His death," have "utterly abolished the whole body of sin," and been ' made partakers of his resurrection." I felt a strong desire, the next day, to go to Ms o Morton's; but, at the same time, a great repugnance. I longed to know how they were, and to take them something for their relief; but I feared ,that Mrs. Morton felt unkindly towards me, and so I did not like to see her. I thought my mother understood my feelings exactly; and I felt most grateful to her. She said to me, after breakfast, "Dear Grace, you would like to go to Mrs. Morton's: will you go there with nme after school? I told her, if she should want any   .   My STEP-MOTHER.       89 thing, to send to me; and I cannot conveniently go out now." I gladly consented; and, after school, I told Mattie that I had an engagement, as she was proposing some wild frolic. But she laughed at me, and said she supposed my step-mother had ordered me home. Not finding my mother in the parlor when I reached home, I ran up stairs to her chamber. She was not there; and seeing her door open, that led into the next room, which was unoccupied, I entered, and found her there engaged in arranging the room. It had always been closed, and dark; and I had rarely taken the trouble to go in. But, how cheerful, how pleasant and fresh it looked to me then, as I entered! The windows were thrown open, and showed a pretty view of our garden, and a fine row of trees outside, and they were hung with long white muslin curtains. The bed was nicely made up, and covered with a snow-white quilt; and every thing about the room was arranged with great care and taste. "Is it not a pleasant room, dear Grace?" said my mother, as she saw me; "these windows look so pretty, with the creeper shading them and peeping in, Would you like to have it for your room, daughter? I have been. all the morning preparing it for you: does it please you?" For me I asked. O, I sleep with nurse; I do not 8*  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7603-00000046"/> }P MY STEP-MOTHER.  like to sleep alone. "But, my little daughter is thir- teen yeai's old," answered my mother, "and quite old enough to have a room to herself. She has slept with her nurse quite long enough. Nurse can come here, and dress her, and wait upon her, whenever she wants her. And you will not feel lonely, my dear, because your room opens directly into mine. I have some little arrangements yet to make here, which cannot be completed before to-morrow." I do not want to leave my nurse, I said pettishy. "You will soon become accustomed to it," my dear, she replied; " and then I think you will like the ar- rangement. It is your father's wish, that you should occupy this room; and it is always best for every one to have a separate room, if it is convenient. But we must now hasten, and go to see Mrs. Morton, or we shall not have time before dinner. I thought you would like to take her something; I have filled a basket, with various articles which I thought might be useful to her."  I said nothing more about the room, for I saw, firom mother's manner, it was a settled .thing that I was to occupy it; and so I became resigned to it, and, on second thought, the idea rather pleased me. It gave me a feeling of importance, which I liked. We found Mrs. Morton looking very pale and feeble. She was waiting on her son, who appeared to be in   MY STEP-MOTHER.   great pain, but was endeavoring to bear it as patiently as possible, so that he might not distress his mother. He had been sleepless all night, and his poor mother had watched with him. They seemed much grati- fied to see us, and grateful for the contents of the basket. "It is hard for me to see him suffer," said the wo- man, "such a good son as he is. He never caused me a moments grief in his life. He has been a great help to me, ever since his father died; and many an honest penny he has earned for his widowed mother. I am very poor, and shall miss his small earnings much."  "God will supply all your need, my good woman," said my mother. "Trust Him fully and lovingly, and He will never desert you." "'I do, lady; O, I do," said the poor widow fervently.  "He is my light and my salvation; whom shall I fear? He is the strength of my life; of whom shall I be afraid "' After conversing with them awhile, my mother read from the Prayer-book the Office for the Visita- tion of the Sick, while we all knelt around the bed of the sick boy. On rising to depart, I took my purse from my pocket, and poured its contents into the widow's hand. "O, you are very kind, dear Miss Grace," she said. &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7603-00000047"/> God will bless you. I did not feel hard towards you, my dear; I knew it was only thoughtlessness in you, yesterday, when you terrified me so with such awful news. God-be praised, it was not true. Your nurse was in here, this morning, and she told me you felt very sad about it; but do not distress youiself any more, I am sure you did not intend to alarm me so. Please to come in and cheer us up again; it does me good to see you." On returning home, I ran up to the nurs6rly, and, to my great surprise, I saw nurse sitting there bathed in tears, and uttering deep groans and sighs. What is the matter, dear nurse? I said, running up to her and throwing my arms around her neck. She made me no reply, but rocked herself backwards and forwards, and continued her distress. Nurse, nurse, I said, tell me what is the matter. I never saw you so before; who is' dead? "Dead! nobody, dear child," she at length replied ; "but there are things worse than death. To think I should have lived to be. parted firom my pretty pet, my sweet Gracey, whom I  love as my own child. 0O dear me, dear me, who would have thought it?" Parted?  nurse, I said; where are you going? what do you mean? "' Oh, oh," sobbed nurse, "I cannot bear the thought of it. Did I not take her from her dying mother's alarms,   thirteen years ago? Have I not had all the care of her, ever since, and trained her well? Who ever loved her -as I have? Not even her own father. And nobody ever can love her so. But I have thought it might come to this; yet, not so soon, not so soon. Only three months ago, her step-mother came home. Dear me, how things change in a little while! Oh dear! that it should come to this." "What do you mean, nurse? I said, what has it come to? "That you are taken straight from me by your step- mother, my pet," she answered. "That is what it has come to; and I think it is just the same as telling old nurse, that you do not need her any more, and she had better leave theb house. And so she means it, and so I am going. I cannot stay with a mistress that does not want me. I am too proud for that, even if she does not tell me, in so many words, to' leave. I can understand it; and I shall go, though it will break my heart to leave my child." Did mother tell you she did not want you to stay, nurse? I asked. "(No, dear," she replied; " but actions speak louder than words. She has moved all your clothes to another room, and told me that you were such a large. girl now, that you had better have a room to yourself, and that I could still keep the nursery for my room, and go to your room to dress &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7603-00000048"/> "       MY STEP-MOTHER. you; but I know what she walnts to do, It is to turn  me -out of the house, so that she canl nmanage you all her own way, and have you close by her all the time; and I will not stay whlere nobody watnts me." I told mother, tlihat I did not wnint to sleep awtny fi'om you, or to sleep alone'; but she stid it was fatlher's wish, and that it would bq bettel for me. "Your father's wish, dear?" replied nu'llse. "And1 who told him it must be so but your step-mother? Your father is such a peaceable man, he would liever have thought of it. Didn't we live on here like lambs together, you and I, and cook? Yes, land we should have lived so all 'our :days, if your father llad not brought home a step-mother and put lher over us. Oh, dear! it is time I was gone, I am nobody here any longer." Mother does not want you to go, nurse, I'said; for she told me, you would still wait upon me, and dress me. "Poor, poor child," said nurse," why should I grieve for myself, when I should grieve more for you, who are getting every day more -and more under a step- inother's power. And who will keep you out of it, when old nurse is gone? Oh, dear! oh, dear!" She resumed her sobs and tears; 1 mingled my tears with hers, and begged her not to leave me. But she was resolute.   MY STEP-MO'OTHER.       95 Tears were on .my cheeks when the dinner-bell summoned mne. "What is the matter, Grace?" asked my father; "it is a rare thing to see tears in your eyes, my child." Nurse is going away, I said; my good old nurse, and I do not want her to go. "Nurse going away?" he inquired, looking at my mother; h'low happens that?"  "tI cannot explain it," said my motherl; t' I have not heard of it before. She said nothing of it to me; perhaps Grace can tell us the reason." She says she knows, I replied, that mother wants her to go away, because she has changed my room, atnd so she is going. "O she is not in earnest," said my father; " do not vex yourself, Grace. I do not thinllk old nurse would leave you, and I should be sorry if she did." She is crying, father, and feeling very sad, I said, and quite in earnest; and she says she is going to- day. Please speak to her, and tell her to stay. "It is very foolish in nurse to expect you to sleep in the nursery, and be a baby all your life," said nay father. "You are getting to be quite a young lady, and it is best for you to occupy a room by your- self." Though sorry to be separated firomn nurse, I rather  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7603-00000049"/> 96       MY STEP-MOTHER. liked the idea of being a young lady, and occupying the pretty pleasant chamber by myself; and I began to feel a little pleased at the prospect. But the thought that my old nurse, to whom I was warmly attached, was to leave the house which had sheltered her so many years, and which I had always consid- ered as much her home as my own, filled me with grief; for I was of an affectionate nature, and felt warmly attached to her. "I will speak to nurse about it myself," said my father, "and I will set it all right, unless she is very unreasonable; so dry up your tears, little daughter, and eat your dinner." After dinner my father told the waiter he wished to speak to nurse before he went out; and, with swollen eyes, and a face disturbed with grief and passion, nurse soon appeared. "What is the matter, nurse?" asked my father. "Grace is so much distressed, that I have sent for you. You cannot think seriously of leaving my house?" ' Why yes, Sir," she replied; "I think my business here is done. I have done my best, to bring up that dear child; but another has taken her now, so I had better go ;" and she burst into another flood of tears. "Grace will require your services for a long time yet," said my mother; she has not learned to dress withut assistance."   MY STEP-MOTHER.       97 ' I cannot be happy here any longer as I have been," said nurse; "things are so changed here, and Grace is taken away from me. I cannot stay any longer; I shall leave to-night." ' You may repent of doing so hasty a thing," said my father. "I advise you to wait a few weeks, and then decide; though, of course, we would not desire you to remain, if it is your srlious wish to leave. You have been faithful, I think, to the best of your ability, in the care of my child. She is much at- tached to you; and I shall provide for you, as long as you live. If you will be happier elsewhere than in my house, you can choose your home. If you stay here, nurse, and you can act your own pleasu:e in the matter, you cannot haive the entire care of Grace, as you have had during her childhood. I wish her to be under her mother's supervision and influence, in every particular. And if you stay, you must re- spect and obey Mrs. Williams, as the mistress of this house, and show her the deference due to her. Grace is old enough now, to occupy a room by herself, and we, think it best it should be so." "I thank you, Sir," said nurse, rather more humbly, "for all your kindness to me; but I i nimot be any more here as I have been, so I ani 'deteriiined to leave. I did not expect to have my child takeni'ayv  from me so soon ;" /and, with another burst of te' 9  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7603-00000050"/> 198       MY STEI'-MOTlEit. nurse left the room. I passed the'whole of that afternoon with her, entreating her not to leave me; but all my eloquence and tears were unavailing. That very evening, she left our house and went to a sister's house, to remain there until she formed some plan for the future. "So your step-mother has turned your old nurse out of the hoise?" said Mattie to me, as I met her on my way to school the next day. "How cruel! Mother says, that is just like step-mothers; that it is lucky it was not you she turned out, instead of nurse." Mother did not turn her out of the house, Mattie, I said indignantly; it was her own choice; they would not do it. "Mother said, if she did not actually turn her out, she supposed she made her so unhappy that she had to go; that nurse was too old to be ruled, and would not bear it, in a house, too, where she had always had her own way." I did not know what reply to make, for nurse seemed to feel very unhappy, though I could not fully understand why; so I was silent, and, I suppose, gave a wrong impression of the case to my friend Mattie, who took great trouble to tell, all over the school, that my mother had made my old nurse so unhappy, that she had to leave the house, which made me feel very unhappy.   MY STEP-MOTHER.       99 My mother went with me to my room, at night, and assisted me in undressing, talking cheerfully all the time, as she saw I felt sad at the departure of my old nurse. And after I was in bed, she sat down by the table and read to me from the Bible, in her low musical voice. How often had I lain on my bed, and watched the two figures of nurse and cook, as they bent over their work, and gossiped -away the hours ; listening to their conversation. And now I contrasted them with the graceful form before me, the tfair, sweet, holy face shaded by its soft curls; the delicate hand supporting the- forehead, the blessed, soothing words that fell like dew on my disturbed feelings; and I was transported to a new and heaveu- ly atmosphere of light and purity. I had thought but little, all my life; but I was beginning to think, and I said to myself that a new kind of life was open- ing before me. It is a holier, a happier, a more real life, said an awakened voice within me. It is a life of restraint, of subjection, said, he who goeth about as a roaring lion seeking whom he may devour. Submit, at once, to the wise and holy guidance of that gentle. being, who is now pouring into your ears the words of light and peace, said the good Spirit. Never submit to the control of a step-mother, said the evil voice: a step-mother is always an enemy; look out for your- self; stand on your own rights; you are old enough  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7603-00000051"/> 100       MY STEP-MOTHER. M now to judge for yourself. She will lead you to the fountain of living waters, said the good voice; even now, by those holy words she reads, she invites you to come. I watched her, until she paused, and I then closed my eyes, for sleep. She still sat there, reading to her- self; but I did not sleep. My mind was very busy. After a while, she rose softly and approached the bed. My eyes were closed, and I feigned sleep. I felt that she was looking upon me; and then she knelt by my bedside, and bowed her head; and I knew she was praying for me. I lay perfectly mo- tionless. She kneeled, for some minutes, and then, rising, she bent over me, and softly kissed my fore- head; and, as she turned to leave me, a tear from her gentle eye fell upon my cheek. She weeps, she prays for me, I said to myself. Why does she care for me ? I have never shown her any kindness nor affection. My heart was softened. She wants me to love her, and to be good, I said. But she is a step-mother. The thought, however, of that silent prayer at my bedside, and the tear of love or pity that fell upon my cheek, gave me a feeling of gentleness and gratitude towards her. 0, had not my young heart been so cruelly prejudiced against her before she came to our home, I should at once have loved such a spirit as hers, with all my warm heart   MY STEP-MOTHER. -10  love, and gladly have followed her into whatever paths she might lead. Surely, they who bear false witness against each other, who speak evil of their neighbor, and slander their neighbor, can never dwell in God's tabernacle, nor abide in his holy hill. CHAPTER X. A NEW FRIEND. "GRACE," said my mother one day, to-morrow my sister Blanche is coming here to make us a visit. I love her very much, and I hope you will love her and make her happy here. She is in delicate health, and the physicians have ordered a change of air, and advised her coming to me." How old is she, mother? I asked. "She is nearly fifteen, about two years older than you." She is just as old as Mattie. Will she run around and play with us, or is she still and moping? I blunt- ly inquired. "She has always been of a very delicate constitu- tion," replied 'my ;mother, "and, is not able to take much active exercise. She rides every day, and walks a little, but will not be able to run around with 9*  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7603-00000052"/> 102      MY STEP-MOTHER.  you much. But, perhaps, you may fancy to sit with ler sometimes. All her young friends -deem it a    - pleasure to pass an hour with Blanche. She is a  rreat favorite." I wish she was my sister, I said, I should so like to have a sister.     '  "She will be like a sister to you, dear Grace, if you : will allow her; and I hope to see you love each otherg very much."  I felt quite curious to see Blanche, and hastily re- :urned home the next day, as soon as school was out, ;o see if she had arrived. I ran to my mother's room ; md how vividly appears now before my mind the irst impression and lovely form of Blanche, as I theni saw her. She was reclining on a sofa, a small, deli-  bate, fair little being, with my mother's dove-like eyes,  m skin of alabaster, a profiusion of soft, light, wavy, chestnut hair, parted, and simply confined in a braid At the back of her head. She had a mouth around  which played the sweetest dimples; and such an ex- Cression of child-like and angelic purity sat upon her youthful brow, and beamed forth from her gentle eyes, as I had never seen on mortal face. She was resting  after her journey, and had thrown off her riding-dress; mnd the loose white robe she wore, added to the ex- treme purity and innocence of her aspect.  My mother stood by the sofa, fanning her, for the day i:            . tf      L .^   MY STEP-MOrHER.       103 was warm. And as she stooped over her, and looked tenderly upon her, the picture was a lovely exemplifi- cation of happiness and peace. "It is Grace," she said, as she caught sight of me at the door; and, bounding lightly forward, she threw her arms around me, fondly kissing me, and said, "We will be sisters, dear Grace." I loved her at once, with a feeling quite new to me. O, sweet, sweet Blanche! how, through the lapse of changing years, thy pure image flits before my mind, like a bright vision from another world! thine angelic loveliness and child-like innocence; thy heaven-born piety; thy burning love for the adorable Redeemer; thy brief years of suffering here, purchasing for thee, through the great blood-shedding, ages of inconceiv- able bliss. Thy life was like the early dew of morn- ing,!and as quickly passed away: before -the noon- day sun dawned upon thy young existence, it had exhaled into the pure light of its kindred skies. And here I might pause in my narrative, and com- mence as it were a new epoch in my life; for, though it was long before my proud and stubborn heart bowed to the blessed yoke of Christ, yet, from my first acquaintance with sweet Blanche, there was a weakening of the influence my friend Mattie possessed over mre, which had estranged me from my mother, and had lessened her influence, and created a barrier  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7603-00000053"/> 104      MY' STEP-MOTHER.            between us, which, after the departure of nurse, would,  I am persuaded, soon have fallen to ruins but for my  constant intercourse with Mattie, and my frequent  visits at her house.  On these visits, her ignorant and ill-judging mother never failed to question me, in the most impertinent  manner, about my "step-mother," as she invariably  ; called her; asking, how I could bear to have any one  over me, when I had so long been my own mistress;  how she treated me, and how she managed the family.  She always concluded her catechising, with such re- marks as these: "Beware, Grace, of being too much under her power; I tell you, if she once gets you  there, you will never be yourself again. Step-mothers : are not to be trusted; they are a cruel, hard set, the  best of them. I dare. say yours is one of the best of them; but they are all pretty much alike; take my  advice, I am your friend, and be independent of her; and let her see, that you mean to be. Do not let her coaxing or indulging make any difference; it is all  for one end, to get you into her power"  How little was this woman aware, that she was breaking one of God's express commands, "Thou shalt not bear false witness," in thus cruelly injuring  one whom she did not know, causing me to look upon her with suspicion and distrust, steeling my heart against her blessed influence, and chilling the   MY STEP-MOTHER.       105 affection, blighting the confidence, I should otherwise readily have given her. Blanche was the exact opposite of Mattie, in looks, manners, and character; and a person who could ap- prdciate and admire Blanche, could not entertain the same feelings towards Mattie. From my first appear-  ance at school, Mattie- had been indefatigable in her efforts to mnake herself my friend; and being two yeals older than I, and possessing strong sense and a determined will, she had acquired ovpr me a degree of influence that has since greatly surprised me. She was exceedingly jealous of the affection I ex- pressed for Blanche; and often was angry with me, for leaving her and running home after school. Some- times she would say, "Well, Grace, will you go and walk with me to-day, or did your step-mother order you to come home immediately after school, to nurse her sick sister? I suppose she did; and you are afraid to disobey her; well, I suppose I should be, if I had a step-mother."  Come in and see Blanche, Mattie, I said one day to her, as we reached our door together; you would love her, I am sure, if you knew her.  "I hate sick people, they are so moping," was her coarse reply; "I do not want to see her, I hear enough of her from you." No one could hate sweet, gentle Blanche, I said;  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7603-00000054"/> 106       MY STEP-MOTHER m she is not moping at all, she is as merry and happy as a bird.         i "O, you were glad enough of my company, Grace," she replied, " before your step-mother came; and shel is trying to set you against me, I know."  She never said a word against you, or any one, I  replied. Cannot I love you and Blanche too? "But you won't run around with me," she said; "and have such fun as we used to have, and see what is going on." I am doing some worsted-work now, which I wish  ' :' to finish; and Blanche is doing some, too; and mother  reads to us such delightful books while we sew; and it is so pleasant to sit with them; they are so kind  and so pretty, and speak so gently to me, and try to please me. And Blanche is teaching me music; and: I love so much to learn with her, that I cannot find so much time to run around, as I did when there was no one at home. When Blanche goes away, I shall  have more time; how I wish she would always stay  with us. "I shall be glad when she has gone," she replied; "for, if she does not go soon, I shall find some other friend, and drop you; so good-by." Anna Ashton, one of my school-mates, whom I    , mentioned at the commencement of my narrative, was previously acquainted with Blanche, and was at In wa a   MY STEP-MOTHER.       107 this time often at our house. She was a girl of great loveliness and simplicity of character, with strong Mattie had heretofore rendered her distasteful to me; but, seeing her so often with Blanche, I began to con- ceive a friendship for her, and learned to appreciate and admire her, which seemed to give great offence to Mattie. "Come, Grace," said Mattie, rudely seizing my arm one. day, as we left the school-room, " ou will be glad to go with lme to-day, I know. O, such lovely fall lat s as I have seen! I only peeped at them, and have waited to examine them, and select one with you. Come, now, for a good old-fashioned exploring expedition at all the milliners'." But Blanche and mother will expect me home to- day; and Ann a Ashton is going with me, I said; but I would like to see the hats. "Anna, Anna," called Mattie, "tell Blanche that Grace is going to walk with me to-day, and will not be at home for a long time ;" and taking my arm, she led me, not unwillingr, down the street. And we went from one milliner's to another, ex- amining and trying on various hats, of every color, in our old wild way. I enjoyed it as much as ever, until the lateness of the hour warned us to go home, I en- gaging to search with Mattie, the next day, for dresses.   &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7603-00000055"/> 108       MY STEP-MOTHER.  I rushed rudely in, when I reached home, excited  by my walk, and exclaimed, O Blanehe, such lovely  hats as I have seen! Mattie and I have had such a  fiolic, trying them on, and selecting them. I have  chosen such a lovely pink one, a perfect shade, and so dressy and fashionable. I suppose father will say it is not simple enough for me; he likes to see me  dress like a Quakeress. But I shall get it and wear it before he sees it, and :then he will have to let me i keep it. Mattie is to have one just like it; we are to have them this week, and we are going to put  I them on and walk out with them before Sunday. Sich a lovely, perfect hat, I am sure you will like it, Blanche. But you look sober, do you not like pink for the fall-? "O yes, dear Grace," she said, "pink is very pretty; but you know I am always sick, so I have many sober thoughts which you have not, who are full of health and spirits. 1 have a great deal of time for thinking;  I pass so many hours alone." But not sober thoughts about my pink hat surely, dear Blanche, I said; no one could have sober thoughts about a new pink hat. Now I am quite  curious to know what they were: please tell me.  "But you might not like them, Grace," she replied; "and I am so used to keeping my quiet sober thoughts to myself, that I had rather keep them in my own    MY STEP-MOTHER.      109 mind, for I am not old nor wise enough to teach you any thing," You have taught me much, dear Blanche, I said, since you have been here; and, among other things, you have taught me to love my own home, and to love to employ myself. If you would stay with us always, I might in time become good and wise, as you are; but now for your sober thoughts or medi- tations on my new pink hat, that charming hat. I insist upon hearing them. "Well, if you insist upon it, dear Grace, you shall have them," she replied, " and you must take the risk of their offending you. When you were talking with so much earnestness and interest of the hat, and your strong desire to possess it, even against the approba- tion of your father, this prayer went up involuntarily from my heart: Blessed Saviour, fill the soul of our dear Grace with an earnest desire for the spotless robe of righteousness; for the, adorning of the meek and quiet spirit; grant, that all desires for the vain pomp and glory of the world which she has renounced at her baptism, may be expelled from her heart; and make her thine humble and childlike follower. That was my sober thought, dear Grace; does it offend you?" she asked, lovingly. O, how could it offend me, dear Blanche? I asked, I would like to be good, like you, but I cannot. 10&#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7603-00000056"/> "O      MY STEP-MOTHER. "I am not good, dear Grace," she said, "but I want to be, and I try to be. , And if you want to be, and ask God, he will make you so." You always seem to have in your heart thoughts of the Saviour, I said, but, I must confess, he is very seldom in my thoughts. "We naturally think much of those we love much, dear Grace," she said; "and he is so tender and loving a friend to me, that I could not be so ungrateful, as not to love him and think of him, the chief among ten thousand, and altogether lovely." And her sweet eyes filled with tears of emotion, and the crimson  flushed her pale cheek, as she spoke of her Re- deemer. How is he kind to you, Blanche? I asked; and how do you know it, when you cannot see him? I mean kind to you, individually, for you speak of him as if he were a personal friend. I know that he died for all, and that he is kind to all. I have often heard it read in the lessons at church, and preached about in sermons; but I mean to you alone. "I often lie awake, whole nights," she replied; "and, in the darkness and solitude, and often suffering, he makes himself so near and'so precious to me, that I  feel his presence as much as if I saw him with my  eyes; and he speaks to me such sweet words of com- fort and love, that they could not be more distnct, if I heard them with my outward ears." v              .   MY STEP-MOTHER.      1" How is it, Blanche, I said, much interested? I can- not understand it; tell me what he says. He does not speak to me. "Yes, he does, dear Grace, though you may not hear him. He speaks to all his children, and you are one; you bear his cross on your forehead, and are pledged to, fight under his banner. His lambs ofttimes turn aside and will not hear his voice; but still he calls, and the time will come when they will hear hiim."' But what does he say to you, Blanche? I asked; I do not understand how you can hear him. "Ifeel that he is near to me, and I speak to him. Do you feel the same when you are alone in the room, as you do when I am with you? If one we love very much is with us, we feel his presence; it makes us happier. When I feel sad or in pain, my heart says, Dear Saviour, look upon thy feeble child; and he reads my heart, and answers, Here am I, my daughter, be of good cheer. When tossing on my bed of restless weariness, longing for the break of day, he says to me, Come to me, weary and heavy laden child, and I will refresh you; and. then he fills me with such holy thoughts of his own blessedness, and of that land of pure delight where he dwells, that I forget my pain and weariness; and when the morn- ing sun streams into my room, I feel refieshed with  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7603-00000057"/> "2       MY STPP-MOTHEuR, sweet slumber. When I have days of health and  brightness, I say, All my fresh springs are in Thee, my Saviour; and he says, I have loved thee, with an everlasting love; ' It is better to trust in me, than to put any confidence in man.' But ah, dear Grace, I cannot give you the faintest idea of tihe blessed fellow- ship he vouchsafes to me, or how my love and grati- tude grow by what they feed upon, even the living  bread and the water of life. His blessed presence turns all pain to pleasure, all sorrow to joy, all doubt to trust- ing faith, all loneliness to fulness of blessed company." I wish I could understand it all, I said, and feel so happy, dear Blanche: I think I was happier before  my mother came here ; it was because I never thought,! But, since she has been here, and I have begun to think, I often feel dissatisfied with myself. I know I am old enough to be wiser and better; but I some- times wish I had never begun to think at all, I was happy enough before. "But you cannot always be a child, dear Grace," she said. "It is God's blessed Spirit who has spoken to your conscience, telling you that God demands your love and your service. O do not turn away from his holy teachings; his service will make you a thousand  times happier than ever you have been, and give you n a peace which passeth understanding." Here my  mother entered, and our conversation was interrupted.  A,         '.    MY STEP-MOTHER.      113 CHAPTER XI. ONE OF MY SUNDAY LESSONS. "PLEASE teach Grace and me, sister," said Blanche one Sunday evening as we sat together; "teach us from the Catechism, as you used to do when you were at home." I looked with wonder at the lovely girl, who seemed to me so well instructed in holy things, as she placed herself at my side in the attitude of a pupil and equal; she, truly, the child of God by adoption and grace, but alas for me! the adoption was mine, but grace had never yet been faithfully improved. I know all the Catechism, I said, except part of the ong answers, and those are too hard to learn. "They do seem hard, dear Grace," said my mother, 'until we understand them, and then they seem easy. We will just talk a little about the Catechism, and hen recite it. Can you tell me, forltwhat is the Cate- hism of the Church designed ." Blanche waited for me to answer; but, as I could ot, she said, "To instruct us in our duty, and teach us "we ought to know and to do, before we are con- rmed by the Bishop." 10*        '  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7603-00000058"/> "4       MY STEPP-MOTHEK,. "Into how many parts may the Catechism be di- vided?' asked my mother. Neither of us answering, she said, "Ilto five parts. The first is the Christian's vows, or the promises made by all who are by Bap- tism admitted into Christ's Church. It embraces the first four questions and answers. The second part is the Christian's belief or form of doctrine, embracing the Creed, and the following question and answer. The third is the Christian's duty, embracing the   Commandments, and the three questions following them. The fourth is the Christian's Prayer, and the question and answer following; and the fifth is the Christian's Sacraments, which closes this eloquent and beautiful form of instruction." "Now, dear Grace, can you tell me what is the first part?" The promises and vows, of the baptized child, I  said, to renounce the devil and all his works; the  pomps and vanity of this wicked world, and all the sinful lusts of the flesh; to believe all the articles of the Christian Faith; to keep God's holy will and coihmandments, and walk in the same all the days of my life.  Yes," she said, "being by Baptism made a member of Christ and a child of God, you promise to renounce  every thing that is wrong and sinful, and to take for  your rule of practice and precept the articles of the  * '  '   - .  sh   MY STEP-MOTHER.       115 Christian's Faith, and the holy will and command- ments of God." "And what is the second part, dear Blanche?" asked my mother. "The belief of the baptized child," she replied. Yes," she answered, "one of your vows in baptism is, to believe all the articles of the Christian Faith. These articles are contained in the Apostles' Creed: drawn from the inspired word of God, and summed up by his holy Apostles. The baptized person re- ceives them reverently, and humbly; and gratefully rests upon them his faith and practice, and prays that he may ever be defended from all false doctrine, heresy, and schism, and hold fast the profession of his faith without wavering. What is the third division of the; Catechism ' The Christian's duty, I replied. "And what does it contain, Blanche?" asked my mother. "The Ten Commandments,' she replied, 'which God delivered to Moses." "Yes," replied my mother; "and the substance of them all in the answers, your duty towards God and your duty towards your neighbor.  If bap- tized persons,-if the world at large,-would only remember to love God with all their hearts and their neighbors as themselves, what a world of love  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7603-00000059"/> "6       MY STEP-MOTHER. and good-will this would be. And what is the next part P" "The Christian's prayer," answered Blanche. "Yes," said my mother; "and how beautiful is our being admitted into God's family by Baptism, and having pledged ourselves to believe in him, to love him and serve him, to be permitted to bow rever- ently before him, and cry, with childlike confidence, 'Our Father,' our covenant Father, who art more ready to hear than we are to pray, and art wont to give more thanwe desire or deserve; who knows we cannot keep the solemnn vows. we have made; that we cannot believe the solemn creed we have uttered; that wye cannot keep the great laws he has givenl us, without his special grace; and therefore we are to come to Him for what we cannot otherwise possess, and he will gladly receive us, and fieely bless us. And what is the fifth division of the Catechism, Blanche?" "The Christian's Sacraments," she answered; "Bap- tism and the Supper of the Lord." "Yes; and of the first of these," said my mother, "you both have been the favored recipients; and my beloved Blanche has often, for the last year, been a  devout communicant at the altar of her Lord. We  I can never be sufficiently grateful to our most blessed  Redeemer, for these sacred institutions, through which    MY STEP-MOTHER.      117 he bestows on his welak and faint-hearted, but loving, followels, strength and light, and nourishes our souls with living bread land with the water of life." In this simple and beautiful way, did my mother try to interest my cold and worldly heart in the teachings of the Churchl; and, for a while, the novel- ty interested me in a measure, and the good seed sown by her with many prayers, finally brought forth fruit. I earnestly pray it may be to life eternal. She never seemed weary in teaching me. No indifference, nor inattention, nor even rudeness, on my part, pre- vented her doing what she felt was her duty ; and had I been to her the most dutiful, affectionate, and docile child, her manner could not have been more patient and loving to me. She must have often wept over her useless labors, and strengthened her heart with the promise, "Be not wreay in well-doing, for in due season ye shall reap if ye faint not." CHAPTER    XII. CONVERSATION BETWEEN MY MOTHER AND BLANCHE, ONE afternoon, I ran in from school, aid feeling heated and fatigued, I threw nmyself on the sofa, in my mother's room; where she and Blanche were  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7603-00000060"/> "8       MY STEP-MOTHER. sitting and ounversing together; and I soon fell asleep.  I know not how long I slept; but, when I awoke they still sat there, and were talking in a subdued tone of voice, as if feaiful of disturbing me. They thought I still slept; so I lay with my eyes closed,  and began to amuse myself with listening to the con- versation. The, first words I overheard were these: "Her coldness, her antipathy I might even call it, dear  Blanche, must be evident to yon; and I feel quite   I sure it is as I have told you." "W hat makes you think so, dear sister?" asked Blanche.  ' Because," she replied sadly, ". dear Blanche, it was  never difficult for ine to gain the love of any child be-  fore. -You know well, how my little class all loved  me, and how much your young friends always liked  to be with me; and I feel quite sure, I could have gained the love and confidence of Grace, if she had  not, by some person, been strongly prejudiced against  a step-mother, before I caine herO. You recollect the  conversation I told you that I ovelheard accidentally,  between Grace and her nurse, before I removed her  i from the nursery; and it was in part from her nurse,  and I doubt not from others also of whom Grace has  spoken, that she has imbibed this prejudice. -It will : be very long, I fear, before it can be eradicated from ! her mind. You see how pleasantly and readily she  ,Vj 8       fs4. ^'Ai   MY STEP-MOTHER.      119 yields to your influence; which shows that she-has not a heart insensible to love and sympathy. But how determinately she turns from me, and opposes my will, and spurns my influence. It shows me, that the poison has taken deep root in her heart; and may God forgive those who have borne f4lse witness of me, and turned against me the hearl of the child whom God has given me to guide and love." She spoke with great warmth, and tears flowed down her fair cheek as she spoke. "Dear, sweet sister," said Blanche, her own voice choked with emotion, "I amn quite ceitain she will learn to love you; you, whon every one always loved so much. Do not feel discoulraged and sad about it, nor allow such thoughts to mar your hlappiness." "You recollect," said my mother, " how much we talked of Grace before I was married; how dearly I thought she would love me, and how niuch I loved her, for her father's sake, before I saw her. O, how ear1nestly I prayed God, to give me grace and wisdom to guide the poor little motherless one, in the way of holiness, and to be a true mnothel to her! But there must be a cloud in every b'ight sky; and mine would be too sunny a lot, but for this, which casts a gloom over mry new home, and causes me many a bitter tear.  I often think, that wheunher father notices the gulf there is between us, he will think I have not faithful-  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7603-00000061"/> 120       MY STEP-MOTHER. ly tried to win her love and confidence; for it is so unnatural, for a child of her age to withhold them from one whQ constantly seeks and desires them. If you could stay with us always, dear Blanche, she migoht through you, learn to love me." I am sure," replied Blancle, " she will in time learn to love you, dear sister. Do not grieve about it; it is the cross our blessed Saviour wills you to bear. Bear it patiently, and hopefully; and in his good time he will remove it." "I earnestly pray that I may," answeredlmy mothher. "I thought, after nurse left her, she would soon learn to love me; but I knew not then what other influ- ences were exerted over her. Mrs. Ashton tliinks, that Mrs. Miller and her daughter, with whom Grace passes most of the time she is absent from home, are very unsuitable companions for her, and exercise a bad influence over her. She says, they are vulgar, ignorant persons, who, having made money, are striv- ing to push themselves into a higher circle of society. Mr. Williams is aware of this, and wished to forbid Grace's associating with Mattie; but I told him, as they went to the same school, it would be almost im- possible, and might cause Grace to be disobedient and deceitful; that it would be better to wait, and by throwing other companions in her way, by making her home attractive to her, and by giving her a taste '            ,             .   MY STEP-MOTHER.       121 forl'refined pursuits and higher pleasures, to wean her frolm the companionship we disapproved of. O, dear Billache, I saw not and feared not this cloud in my sky, when I left our pleasant home. But it is not the lot of fidlen man, to 1have perfect bliss here. I have c:arried my sorrow to tohe foot of the cross. I leave it there; and I will wait the workings of His great will whlo appoiiteth our habitations." "Ah, that is the place, dear sister, to carry all our sorrows, said 13lanche. "You will yet see dear Grace all you can desire." "I wanlt her to feel towards me as you do, dear Blanche," said my mother. "I want to be her beloved friend and elder sister. I do not desire from her the obedience I should expect from her, were she three or four years of age; but oh, it grieves me to have her repel my love, to stland aloof from me as she does, and look upon me as an enemy and intruder.* At this poitlt of the conversation, a servant entered, and sumlnnoned my mother and Blanche to the parlor to receive some visitors. My mother, thinking I still slept, approached the sofa, and threw a shacwl lightly over me, saying, "She is fatigued, and may sleep long, and had better be covered a little." The sound of their footsteps died away, as they descended the staircase; and still I lay as motionless W         n"  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7603-00000062"/> 122      MY STEP-MOTHER. as before, beneath the light folds of the silken shawl her gentle hands had thrown over her ungrateful child. I cau hardly defiue my emotions. They were those of surprise, mortification, and remorse. She was unhappy, and I was the sole cause; and yet how lovingly she still spoke of me. She desire my love! Why, step-mothers have no feeling, nurse said; and Mattie and her mother both said so. Why should she care, whether I loved her or not; and how could I make her unhappy? It was she who was to emn- bitter my whole life, and take fioln me my freedom, and rule me like a slave. What had I done to make her unhappy? And what has she done to make you unhappy? asked the voice within. She has regulated your disorderly home, decorated it with feminine taste and beauty, and made it so attractive and pleasant to you, that instead of shunning it as you once did, you are beginning to love its quiet and healthful atmosphere, and to be softened and improved by its sacred influ- ence. You plainly see, after nearly five months under the same roof with your step-mother, that she has been much calumniated and misrepresented; and a heavy account will they have to render, who have borne false witness against her. You see she is every way worthy of your obedience and love, and all that she desires is your highest good; and yet you treat t il'             *   MY STEP-MOTHER.       123 her with coldness, and often with disrespect. While she is constantly studying how to win you to her heart, and make you happy, you are studying how you can escape from her control, and show your independ- ence of her, and your determination to spurn her love and influence. You have made her unhappy; you are the cloud in her summer's sky; then it is in your power to make her happy. Strive to do so, even as she strives to promote your happiness. Many, many serious thoughts occupied my mind for several days after this occurrence; and I felt more desirous to please my mother than heretofore, and less inclination to thwart her wishes. But I could re- late here many circumstances, which now fill me with remorse and humiliation, of my caprice and wayward- ness, my rudeness and coldness towards her. But I forbear. I think I have given my readers a sufficient lnsight into my character and wyay of life, and I there- fore- proceed with my narrative. ,   ,   &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7603-00000063"/> 124       MY STEP-MOTHER. CHAPTER    XIII.  NEW CAUSE OF DISAGREEMENT. IT was not long after, one glorious O(tober morn- ing, that Blanche, much recruited by the change of air, left us, accompanied llome by my mother, who was to pass a few days at her early home. Blanche calne to my room to say farewell to me; and as she kissed me with much affection, she said, "God bless you, dearest Grace: be kind to my beloved sister, and make her happy, if you love me."  How dreary, how desolate seemed the house to me, the first day that I returned from sclool, after their departure! I wandered sadly from room to room; I seated myself at the piano; but my lesson seemed so dull without my gentle teacher, that I could not practise. I took up my still unfinished worsted-work, but that failed to amuse me; and I wandered away into the garden, until I was summoned to dinner. I had become less and less pleased with my friend Mattie, the longer I associated with Blanche; but now that she had gone, Mattie soon resumed her former place in my regard. One day, dulring the absence of my mother, in my old rude way, I rushed into the room at dinner-time; and seating myself, I began, O, father, you must   MY STEP-MOTHE:.      125 not say no, I am soq set upon it: please let me go to boarding-school with Mattie Miller. She is going next month, and she has been talking to me about it, and urging me to go, all the norning. I should like it so 1much, fatther, if you will consent. I will prom- ise to study a great deal, and to be as good as Anna Ashton, and come honme so sedate and so accomplish- ed, that you will hardly know me. Not with Mattie Miller for your friend and com- panion," replied my father : "it will require a different associate to effect that change in you, Grace." O father, Mattie is a good girl, I am sure, I said; and I like her betterl than any girl at school; do please let me go with her. "It is an important subject, my child," said my father, "and one that cannot hastily be decided upon. I am no friend to boarding-schools for children of your age, though there are instances where they have been of great benefit if the school is one of the proper kind." Father, I said, this is a very fine one Mattie is go- ing ito; I am sure it would benefit me. "I would prefer the guidance and companionship of your mother for you, Grace," said my father, "to that of any other being on earth, and should feel that I was doing wrong, to remove you from her influence, unless it should be by her advice." The next few days, I took every opportunity of "*  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7603-00000064"/> 126      MY STEP-MOTHER. coaxing and entreating my father to grant me my desire, which desire was much strengthened by seeing, at Mrs. Miller's, the preparations making for Mattie's departure from home. My father was so in the habit of indulging me in every whim, and yielding to my wishes, that I finally succeeded in inducing him to say, that if my mother consented, I should go., I ran joyously to Mattie, to tell her how far I had succeeded; but she tauntingly said, "Well now, there is an end of it all, Grace, you may depend upon that." "Sure enough," joined in her mother, " poor Gracey, there is an end to it all. , She consent? Your step- mother consent to put you beyond the reach of her power  Poor child, you have not managed well at all. You ought to make your father promise, before she comes home, that you shall go, and make him write to Mrs. Wilson about it, and engage you there at once; and when the business is all done, just tell her, when she returns, that you are going. That is the way to manage step-mothers. Pool child, you have spoiled it all. When is your mother coining home?" The day after to-morrow, I said despondingly. "Well, then, make the best of your time, Grace," she said; "you may yet effect your purpose, thlough I doubt it. But try; if you leave it for your step-mother to   MY STEP-MOTHER.       127 decide, and think to bring her round by coaxing and urging, as you do your father, you are much mis- taken, and she is made of different material from step-mothers in general." I went home quite cast down, but determined to try all my powers, to induce my father to yield to my wishes. "If you still were, Grace," said my father, "a poor motherless child, with only an indulgent careless father to spoil you, I should probably consent to your wishes; but, as I said before, I prefer that you should be under the influence of your mother, than that of any one else. Unless it should be by her advice, or with her approval, I shall never send you from her; so, my dear, it is useless for you to talk any more upon the subject, until we know her opinion." I saw, by my father's manner, that all further coax- ing would effect nothing; and so I looked forward anxiously to my mother's return, to decide my fate; and in the mean time thought over, mrany times, with great satisfaction, the conversation I had heard be- tween Blanche and herself, as I lay on the sofa, hop- ing that as I was the only source of unhappiness to her in her new home, she would be glad of the opportunity of removing me. My readers will at once conclude, that my mother decidedly objected to my going to boarding-school, under the protection of Mattie Miller. I was exceed-  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7603-00000065"/> 128      MY STEP-MOTHER. ingly indignant, and felt that she took upon herself an authority she had no right to exercise. I tried every art of persuasion that I often had so successfully employed with my father; but, finding it was all in vain, I burst into an angry flood of tears, and said, Mattie and her mother both said you would not let me go, because you were my step-mother. A shade of deep sadness passed over her lovely face, and a tear glistened in her eye as I said this;  and putting her arm around me, she drew me gently to her side, saying, "Dear Grace, you will at some fu- ture time better understand the reasons of my refus- ing to comply with your wishes. It grieves me much to disappoint you; but I should do violence to my sense of duty, should I now consent to your leaving home with Mattie Miller, whom I have never thought a suitable guide and companion for you. It is in God's good providence to me and to you, that he is separating you fromn her. The-work which my Father has given me shall I not do it? God appoints to us our sphere in life; and however weighty our duties may be, we must not shrink from them, nor cast them from us, but journey meekly on, trusting him for strength and grace to perform them. God has placed me here, and intrusted to me the guidance of your youtli; and I cannot conscientiously give up the work to another. I trust, by and by you will learn   MY STElT-MOTHER.       1 29 to 7!oe me, dear Grace, as I love you, and then we shall be so happy toethlle." My insensible heatt was untouched by these gentle words, and my angry feelings were unsubdued. I left her, and ran off to Mrls. Miller's, where, as soon as I en- tered, I burst into a passionate flood of tears, and said, She won't let me go, and I am so angry: it is too bad. "That is just what I told you," said Mattie. "That is just what I told you," said her mother. "And now, Grace, I hope you believe all I have told you about step-mothers. She is like the whole set of them, though she is so young and so pretty, and looks so mild; but do not let her break your spirit now; stand her out; I would not speak to her for a month, if I were you. But come, it is all settled, and cannot be helped ; so dry your telas and come up and look at Mattie's new dresses, which have just come home. The girls all dress a great deal at theschool where She is going; and I choose she shalll look as well as the rest of theml. Her father can afford it." With many protestations of eternal friendship, and promises of frequent correspondeence, I said farewell to my friend Mattie, and envied her as she drove away in fine spirits, and turned with feelings of con- tempt and aversion towards my school and home. And now I would gladly pass in silence over the  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7603-00000066"/> 130       MY STEP-MOTHER. next four months of my life; for memory, true to her trust, recalls to my mind so many painful feelings, I shall make as little record of them as will enable me to keep up the thread of my narrative. The coldness, the unkindness, the contempt, in every possible way, which I showed towards my mother, when not in the presence of my father, as to her authority and her wishes, many times acting in direct opposition to whlat I knew she'approved of, to show I would :not be under her control,-the dislike I showed to her society, the entire want of interest in her pursuits, fill me with shame at the recollec- tion. My mother continued to tach me music; and as my father told mle it was his wish I should learn, I feared to give it up. And when I think of my in- gratitude, and the uncourteous manner in which I re ceived her instructions, and the patience and gentle- ness with which she bore my unkindness and ill-hu- mor, and plodded with me through the dull elements of the science; the remembrance of these, even now brings the warm blood to my cheek, in very shaine. My feelings of resentment towards my mother, for thwarting my wishes, would undoubtedly have soon died away, for I was not of a Inalicious disposition, had it not been for my constant intercourse with Mrls. Miller, and my fiequent long epistles from Mattie; for I-   MY STEP-MOTHER.       131 they both always spoke disrespectfully and disparag- ingly of my mother, and of her harshness, as they called it, in keeping me shut up at home. Mattie set forth, in most glowing terms, the "good times," as she called them, that she had at school, which consisted mostly in evading her studies, de- ceiving her teachers, violating the rules of the school, - stealing out at forbidden hours with one or two wild girls, and spending mtore pocket-money in foolish things than any other girl at school; all of which filled my silly head with strong desires to be with her and participate in her follies. As in sad memory I review these few months, it seems to me as if the whole object of my life was to make my mother as uncomfortable as possible, to be as moody, and obstinate, and self-willed as a child could be. Alas, alas, for those who embitter the sweet joys of home, who darken the sunshine of its hallowed joys, and bring a cloud over the pathway of those whom  God has given them to love and cherish. Alas, alas, for those who bring tears to the eye they should brighten, or sadness to the lip they should cause to smile, or anguish to the heart that beats only with love and interest for them. Ah, let my young readers pause and reflect, if these words apply to them. If so, remember how soon death may close that eye, and seal that lip, and silence that throbbing  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7603-00000067"/> 132       MY STEP-MOTHER. heart;, and then what remorse, what unspeakable agony, will be theirs! Look each day upon each be- loved one of your household, as if it were the ]lst you might pass together on earth; and so live, th:.t the relembrance of your devotion, and unselfishness, and love, may fill your future years wittl sweet and peaceful memories. I had many faults, which my mother tried gently and patiently to reform ; and, before this last disap- pointment, I did try in some respects to do as she wished. But now 1 justified lnyself fully, in neglect- ing every desire of hers, saying to myself that I was only treating her as she treated me, forgettilg that all she wished me to do was solely for ny own good. I was exceedingly clareless of my clothes, and knew nothing about mending them, and never kept a drawer nor closet in order, as nurse never had taught me, but followed me round, and put every thing in order after ine. My mother wished me to learn to keep my room  neat, and put my clothes in their places; but now, not from forgetfulness, but to show my contempt of her wishes, I every day left my drawers half open, and every thing in disorder, and my whole room as untidy as possible. I had also the lazy halbit of lying very late in bed, though my mother herself opened my door every morning, and said kindly, "Come, dear Gracey, it is   MY STEP-MOTHER.       133 time to wake up." I waited until breakfast was nearly over, and then saulntered down, hat in hand for school, silently and unceremoniously hurried tlrough my breakfltst, and ran away. I never showed the slightest interest in my motherl' pursuits, nor gave her the slighltest assistance in any household duty. Though for several weeks in the winter we were without a waiter, and though often, during that time, I saw her busily occupied in various wa ys, I never volunteered my services. Once or twice, when she kindly asked me if I would assist her in some trifling thing, I replied, that I hated house- work, and was not brought up to it, for which im- pertinent reply, on relating it to Mrs. Miller, I received -her warmest praises, and the following comment. "Tblat's right, Grace; do you keep to it. I have no doubt, that lhad you assisted her, she would have put all the waiter's wolrk upon you. That is always the * ay with step-mlothers, and just what they always do to their step-daughters; put all the household drudg- ery upon them. 1 have seen girls made almost hunch- backed by their step-mothers. Keep to it, Grace. You know I am your friend; do not lift your finger to housework; if youl begin it, there will be no end to it, I can tell you." But, in retracing the events of tlese four months, there is one thing above all others whichl fills lmy 12  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7603-00000068"/> 134       MY STEP-MOTHER. heart with shame and sorrow. O, that I could blot out the relmnenibrance of it forever from my memory, withl these bitter tears that even now flow as I recall it. My mother had a severe illness of several weeks' duration, and instead of feeling grief and sympathy for her sufferings, I rejoiced at the restraint's being withdrawn, which I felt in her presence. I treated her with entire neglect. Sometimes, for days I would not go near her room; and I never performed ifor her the slightest act of kindness or voluntary at- tention. Mrs. Miller often said to me, "Now, Grace, do not allow yourself to be made a sick-nurse. Be sure your step-mother will make you one if she can, and keep you up watching every night with her, until you are sick yourself. Be sure she does not impose upon you now. Sometimes, after my being absent several days from her room, she would send for me to come in and see her, and drawing me towards her, would kiss me tenderly, and say, I wanted to see my little daughter, I feel lonely without her; and ofttimes I saw the tears fill her sweet eyes, as I coldly received her kindness. While on one of these visits to her room one day, Mrs. Ashton came in to see her; and when she left, I accompanied her down stairs. "Grace," she said to me, pausing in the hall, "I hope you do all in your   MY S'TEP-MO'(1IER.     135 power to cheer your mother, and keep her compafy, and wait upon her. Sickness always has a depressing effect upon the spirits. Do not allow her to be alone more than is necessary; she has always been the idol of her parents' home, most tenderly cared tor, aind fondly loved; and I fear, that in her sickness she may feel lonely. Your father is of necessity absent most of the day, and she has as yet few friends here who feel at liberty to visit her in her sick-room. She is so like your own mother, Grace, in disposition and character, that, had you known your own mother, you would love your new mother for her sake. There are few such lovely spirits in this world. You are a most fortunate clild, to be so blessed as to be in con- stant companionship with one whlose holiness, and purity, and winning simplicity, and loveliness, have ever made her the beloved and admired of all who knew her." Mrs. Ashton bade me fa!ewell; and I stood, I know not how long, in the place she left me, thinking to myself, how differently Mrs. Miller spoke of my mother, wlen she in reality knew nothing of her; and the thought that Mrs. Miller did my mother injustice, and taught me to do the same, made me feel annoyed and dissatisfied, and wish I was under Mrs. Ashton's influence lmore, and Mrs. Miller's less.  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7603-00000069"/> 136       MY STEP-MOTHER. Without hardly knowing it, I found myself again in my motler's rooml; atnd I saw a glealn of pleasure light up her pale face, as I entered and seated myself beside her. CHAPTER XIV. MY DISAPPOINTMENT. "FEBRUARY is almost hlee, Grace," said Mrs. Miller to me one day, as I entered her parlor to have a chlat with her. "Only two weeks more, land Aattie will be here, and her vacation is four weeks. Ben is coillng home, too, and I expect they will have fine times together. Ben writes, that lie means to pass his va- cation in sleigh-riding; and I hope the sleigling will be good, for Mattie also is very fond of it. Wllere did you go the other daly, Giace, when you rode by with your fatler and mother?" We only went out for the ride, I answered. We went as far as Waterford; I believe it is six miles. Mother rides every day since she recovered friom her sickness. The doctor says it is better for her than walking, while the snow is on the ground. O, I am so glad Mattie is coning so soon. How glad I shall be to see her!   MY STEP-MOTHE,      137 "She writes a great (deal about seeingo you, said 1Mr,. Miller, and you must comle in every day, and see ;is much of each other as you ca l; for, four weeks will soon pass away, and then she will return to school, and not come home lagain until Augsht." The tortnight soon passed away, and Mattie and myself were mutually lhappy, in again being togetlher ; but I recollect the first thoughlt I ihad on seeing her, was, Was she always so coarsea and bold in her ap- pearalice, or lias she changedl  All my spare hIouls froml school we were together; and often, unknown to my parents, I passed whole days with her, returning home at the hour of meals, as if I had been at school; and I amll sure that neither of my parents ever suspected the deception I was practising.  One morning, I was hurrying by to school, late as usual, when Mattie called to me from the window, "Grace, Grace, come in, just one moment; I have something very particular to say." I obeyed, and she proceeded: How would you like to o on a sleighing frolic this evening? My brother Ben, and Tom Gray, and Joe Dunham, are getting up a party, and they told me to invite you. There are to be flur or five large sleighs, and we are going to Waterford, to leave here' at six, have a supper and a dance at the public. house, and return home certainly by twelve. It is 12'  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7603-00000070"/> 138       MY STEP-MOTHER. file sleighing, and a bright moonlight; there is a band of musicians to accolnpany us; and it will be charming. Will you go, Grace? They wish to know  decidedly, because, if you decline, they will invite some one else to take your place." O, it will be de- lightful, I said, exactly what I should like. "Then I will tell Ben you will go," said Mattie; "and I am so glad!"Father is out of town, and I fear my mother vvill not consent to Iny going, I said. Q, how I wish father was at homne! I might coax him to consent. "I would not ask your mother'" said Maattie, if I were you, but tell her you are going to ride with' me this evening; that is enough. You will be a goose, if you let your step-mother prevent you from going, and having such a frolic. Just say to her when you go home, that you have 1)romllsedt to go with me ; that is enough ; and do lnot ask her consent. You are j certainly old eiiough to judge for yourself, in such a trifling matter; but I see, plainly enough, you are afiaid of her, and dare not act for yourself." My father, I am sure, I said, would be very much displeased with me, if I should join such a party, when he is absent, without my mother's consent; so I must ask her. "Then you may as well set it down, that you will not go," said Mattie; "for step-mothers never indulge their step-children, my mnother says, but like to   MY STEP-MOTHER.      139 show their power over them, and make them feel it, too." I will try to make her consent, I said: I should like to go of all things. That morning at school was all lost to me, for my thoughts were filled only with visions of the charm- ing sleigh- ride, and devising plans to induce my mother to consent to my wishes. I concluded, finally, that the best way would be to follow Mattie's advice, and say to her that I was going, and afterwards gain her approval. So, on re- turning home, I ran into' her room, and said, O, mother, I am going to such a charming sleighing party this evening; Bel Miller, and Tom Gray, and Joe Dunhlam are getting it up. There are to be four or five large sleighs, a band of musicians, and we are going to Waterford to have' a supper and a dance. We leave here at six, and return certainly by twelve. My dark silk will be the most suitable: thing to wear, and will be quite dressy enough, if I put a handsome lace in the neck and sleeves. My mother made no reply, but continued her sew- ing, without raising her head from her work. I ex- pected that she would at once aid decidedly express her disapprobation of my plan; and I was well armed with eloquent arguments to induce her to consent. But as she said nothing, I knew not what to do next,  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7603-00000071"/> "O      MY STEP-MOTHER. so I went to my room to leave my cloak and hat, and after being absent a few minutes, returned, supposing she would then say something of the party. She sat quietly, however, at her work, as, I left her, and did not raise her head as I entered. I threw myself on the sofa, and took up a book to appear tk be employed, but in reality to think what I should do next. In a short time my mother began talking pleasantly as usual of various things, but made no allusion what- ever to the sleigh-party, and appeared as if she had not heard a word about it. I made several attempts to introduce the subject, but could not succeed, as Inere really seemed nothing more to be said; for I had already given a full description of the party, and said I was going, and she had not objected, and there was nothing more to be done. Thus matters stood when dinner was announced. I had promised to let Mattie know as I went to school. What should I do? I dared not go without my mother's approval, for fear of displeasing my father. I tried, all dinner-time, to introduce the subject, but failed; and my mother left the dining-room directly after dinner. In a few minutes I followed her to her room, and found her preparing to go out. "I am taking an earlj walk to-day, Grace," she said; "I have made an appoint   MY STEP-MOTHER.      141 ment with Mrs. Ashton, to call on some poor families of  the church, and we shall not have time to do all we wish, unless we leave early." I was desperate. I must speak; I dared not go without her consent, not that I felt sorry to displease her, but I feared my father's displeasure.' So I said, I am glad you do not object to the sleigh-party, mother, because I want so much to go. Do you not think it will be delightful?" "Why do you think, dear Grace," she asked, "that I do not object?"Because you did not say so, I replied, when I told you of it. "You did not ask me, my dear," she said; " therefore I supposed you did not wish my opinion on the matter; and so I said nothing." But do you not consent, mother? I asked, quite humbly for me. "Dear Grace," she said, "I shall never interfere with your plans while you have a father to direct you, unless my opinion is desired. If you are willing, in your father's absence, to take upon yourself the responsibility of joining the sleigh-party, and feel sure of his approbation, I shall say nothing to prevent you from doing as you please. If you wish me to take the responsibility, I will do so." Father would not object, if you consented, mother, I said: will you not consent? I have set my heart upon going; it will be so delightful. I cannot tell vou how much I want to go; and Mattie is; very .T  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7603-00000072"/> "2       MY STEP-MOTHER. sirous to have me; but I am afraid father will be dis- ul-ased if I go without your consent, so do please say yes. "If you wish me to decide for you, dear Grace," she said, I must disappoint you; for such parties, unless c nducted by older persons of discretion, I consider very unprofitable for young girls, and indeed decidedly improper. I would not consent to your going, unless you went under the protection of some of your pa- rents' friends; and among those you have mentioned, there is not an individual who visits at your father's house, and they all have the character of being very vild and thoughtless. I should feel very sorry to have my little daughter go on such an excursion, and with no more discreet company. Do you yourself think, dear Grace, that your father wouldapprove of it?" I could not ayv with truth that I did think so; so I pettishy said, If you would consent, he would say nothing against it, I know. I think you might let me go.  Mattie said, she knew you would not, and that I was a goose to ask you. "It grieves me much," she said gently," to disappoint you; but it would be impossible for me to consent for my child to go where Iould be unwilling to go myself, to subject her to influences that I wholly dis- approve of, anld to associates with whom I am wholly unacquainted. Dear Grace," she continued, coming   MY STEP-MOTHER.       143 up to me, and putting her irms coaxingly around me; "do believe that I have at heart your best and highest good. If I want my child to be refined in her manners, modest in her deportment, pure and holy before her God, can I conscientiously consent to her associating with those from whom she can learn nothing that I desire for her? Should I, firom false indulgence, and with the strong wish I have to gratify you, consent to your going, I should feel ashamed to say to your fa- ther, that I had not better guarded his treasure in his absence; and how could I ask my heavenly Fa- ther, ' Lead not my child into temptation, but deliver her from evil,' when I permitted her to go into both telnptation and evil? It is hard for me to disappoint you, mly dear, but as you must see from the nature ,of my lleasons, that it is impossible for me to consent, I mntust now leave you, as I engaged to be at Mrs. Ash- ton's at this hour." "That is just what I told you, Grace," said Mattie, when I related to her what had passed between my mother and myself. "Now do you not wish you had followed my advice, and gone withoutV asking her?  I would go now, if I were you; she won't tie you. If I were in your place, how differently I should act: I would not be afraid of a step-mother." I s;t all the afternoon with Mattie, instead of going to school. And after seeing her gayly attired for the  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7603-00000073"/> "4       MY STEP-MO'T'IEtR. sleighing-party, I returned home moody and dissatis- fied, and with no very cordial feelings towards my mother. I stationed myself at the window, to watch for the sleighs to pass. The bright moonlight and the splark- ling snow but increased my disappointed feelings; and when five large sleighs, with their merry bells, and band of music,a and laughing voices, glided rap- idly by, I burst into tears. I was cross and silent all that evening, whch I well remember to my shame, though my mother made every effort to amuse me, and comnpensate, as far as was in her power, for my disappointment. CHAPTER XV. THE SLEIGH-RIDE. AFTER the disappointment related in the last chap- ter, my mannerg towards my mother becamne more cold, and distant, and unkind than before. When my father was not present, I generally addressed her as Mrs. Williams, instead of mother. Sometimes, a day or two passed without my addressing to her a single word, except merely replying, in as laconic a manner as possible, when she addressed me.  My father   MY STEP-MOTHER.       145 made no remarks on my behavior, and I did irot know at the time that lhe observed it. It was towards, lte close of Mattie's vacation, that ' my mothcer-ole day received a letter from her mother, stating- that Blalchle was alarmingly ill, and begging her to come to ler immlediately. Accompanied bv mry fatler, she left the next 'mo'rning for Boston, rmy father purposing to return homue in a day or two. My motler was- overwhelmed with distress at the news of Blanche's illness, though it was not unex- pected, and I felt truly grieved. She kissed me kinddy at. parting; and, in spite of all m y unkindness, her manner towards me wavs as affectionate and gentle as the day she first received me. My young readers must not think I was happy, or at peace -with myself; while I conducted myself so un- justly and improperly towards my mother; and they will at once see, how cruel and bitter a thing is pre- judice, and how dreadful a tling it is to bear false wit- ness. The opinions expressed by my nurse and cook, and also by Mrs. Miller and Mattie, to a person who was older or capable of judging of character, might have had but little weight; and their influence ceased to work, on learning the character of my estimable and pious mother. Butt shame, shame on those who bias the unformed mind of a child, to fill it with cruel prejudices and false ideas! 13  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7603-00000074"/> "Ot      MY STEP-MOTHER. But I was not wholly without blame; for I was old enough to see tlt they had given me a false impres- sion of one step-mother at least; that they spoke un- truly of her motives towards me, and were in entire ignorance of her character. I often felt, after my nurse left me, that were I away from Mrs. Miller's in- fluence, and not afraid of Mattie's ridicule, I would gladly be guided by such discreet and watchful care, and by such a gentle and loving spirit. O, oftentimes, when her unwavering kindness and forbearance, and her affectionate tones would fill my heart with re- proach, I have longed to throw myself into her arms7 and beg her forgiveness for my cruelty and ingrati- tude; but my proud heart, and the fear of losing my independence, as I called it, prevented me. Ah, what bitter, bitter tears has it since cost me! "The last and gayest of the season, Grace," said Mat- tie to me one day, as I entered her house. "To-mor- row is the finale of my winter's fun, the last and gayest sleighing-party, the largest and grandest of the whole, closes my holidays; and the next day I depart for school, and you will not see me again until August. Now, Grace, I have a last favor to ask of you. Your father and your step-mother both are away. You are consequently your own mistress, and cannot say me nay, if you are disposed to say yea; so will you join the party to-morrow? No one will be the wiser for   MY STEP-MOTHER.      147 it. I will venture to say, that you will not be child enough to say you are sorry after they come home, and ask to be pardoned for enjoying yourself in an innocent way, when they were absent." O, Mattie, I said, do not ask me; you know my parents will dis- approve of my joining you. Thley are not here to approve or disapprove," said Mattie. "You are at last left to choose for yourself; and if you do not use your opportunity and go with us, you will act like a baby, that is all I can say." She then began to give me a glowing descriptionr of the music and dancing, feasting and folly, of the anticipated party, which quite turned my silly head, and gave me a strong desire to go with her; but still I did not consent, and she would not hear ny weak re- fusal. "Tlhink about it, Grace," she said, "and stop in as you pass, in the morning, and letmne know; I am quite sure that, upon reflection, you will not refuse when the opportunity seems made on purpose for you.' When I was absent from Mattie, I found it harder to make up my mind to go, than I expected I should; for conscience plainly pointed to me the right path. And as I tossed at night on my restless couch, two scenes, so adverse, alternately presented themselves to my mind; one, of the wild, thoughtless, noisy party of dancers; and the other, the silent chamber of my  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7603-00000075"/> "8       MY STEP-MOTHER. sweet friend Blanche, her pale and suffering form and heaven-beaming eye, and one gelitle wa:tcher all through the long midnight hour, in the form of my wronged mother, hovering lovingly near her. I was yet undetermined when I entered Mrs. Mil- ler's the following molning; but I needed olly a few words of encouragement from Mattie, to decide me. These words were not wanting. I feel ]ashamed to confess, that the plrincipal thing which decided me to go was, that there seemed to me no chance of my parents' discovering it; and so it would be a pity to lose the opportunity. They were not personally ac- quainted with any of the )party. And even should any of their acquaintance know of my going, they would not think of mentioning it to thleln, supposing, of course, that I acted with their sanction. I added wrong to wrong, by staying away from school that day, and passing it with Mattie. Wthen it was time to dress for the party, I left her, promising to return and go. with he!', as I did not wish the sleighs to be seen stoppingat my father's door. When I had almost reached home, to my great embarrassment I was met by Mrs. Ashton and Anna. Mrs. Ashton kindly accosted me, and said, "Grace, we were on our way to your ]ouse, to invite you to go home with us and take tea.  Helen Morton and Bessie Morrison are coming, and you will have a   MY STEP-MOTHER.       149 pleasant evening together. You must be quile dull, left so alone." nio, I said, I am not. I cam with Mattie, almost all the time, and father returns to-mo'row. ",iWeell, com e  h e ith us now, G-mce, will you not?" asked Anna. I colored, and awkwardly stanm- mered out, Thank you, I amn engaged with Mattie this evening, alnd must decline. "I amn sorry," said Anna; but, before she could say more, I left her, fearful of being questioned as to lmy evening engagement.  After dressing myself suitably for the party, I returned to Mrs. Miller's; and as the large sleighs dashed down the streets, and Mattie and I took our seats, the merry bells and the music and the sound of cheerful voices excited me with pleasant anticipations of a gay evening. The sleighng proved to be very rough, after the filst mile; and there was a good deal of joking among the noisy party, about sleighing over bare ground and stones. But the rough motion and the confined air made me feel very uncomfortable, producing a headache and nausea, which made nme long for the end of the ride. Many complained sadly of the same feelings; but Mattie said, she had enjoyed so many fine sleigh-rides over the smooth snow and under the light of the moon, that she was determined not to 13*  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7603-00000076"/> 150       MY STEP-MOTIIER. cormplain of one over bare ground and stones, with only a few feeble stars to light the way; so she com- menced a lively song, in which many joined her, and, in spite of all obstacles, we arrived in safety, where the brilliant hall and cheerful fire made us soon forget the discomforts of the way. I do not intend to describe the coarse and noisy manners of the rude and vulgar company in which I found myself, nor- the scene of folly and. gayety, of feasting and dancing, which followed. Many a time during the evening, I thought of the relmarks my mother had made, on parties of that description; and, many a time, I wished myself at home, for there was no one present with whom I was acquainted ex- cept Mattie and her brother, and all the company were several years older than myself, and seemed to regard me as a child, though they were not deficient in showing me attention, and I danced until I was very weary, and the hour was very late. I several times begged Mattie to remind her brother of the lateness of the hour; but she said she would not, that it was9 the last frolic she should have for a long time, and she was determined to stay as long as she possibly could. "One more good dance," said Ben Miller, as we left the supper-table, "while the drivers are refreshing themselves with what we have left, and then we will   MY STEP-MOTHER.       151 start for home, though I dread that rough ride so much, I do not feel in any hurry." It was soon found, that but few of the young men were capable of joining in the dance, for wine had been fieely circulated; and I cannot express the deg- radation I felt at being in such company, when I saw some sitting stupidly round the room, others excited to a high degree of noisy merriment and low joking, others making ridiculous attempts to appear sober and join in the dance. There were indeed but a few among them who appeared to be entirely in possession of their senses. It was half past twelve o'clock before we left the house; and as we were entering the sleighs, I cannot describe -the fear and horror I felt, when I saw, by the quarrelling and swearing among the drivers, that they also were intoxicated. O what shall we do, Mattie? I said. How shall we get home? These men cannot drive us safely; the road is so rough, and there is no moon. What can be done? how I wish we were safe at home. "Do not be childish, Grace," she replied. "The young men will see to that; we need not trouble our- selves about it. Any body might see, that you never were out before without some one to take care of you. You must learn to take care of yourself. I fear noth- ing, and care for nobody; we shall get home safe  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7603-00000077"/> toi      3i 1 r MY STEl' IP--OTitER enough." So saying, she turned away, talkingl and lauoghing loudly with a young man near us, who ap- peared to lne like any thing but a person in his sober senses, The sleighs jogged on, and the nausea and le ad ache I had suffered from before, returned, mlluch ; g- gravated by the late supper and the fatigue of ddalcigE). Many of the party were complaining of the samle. Some, overcome with fatigue, slept, solet e lauihed and talked, and some scolded at the rougmllnsess of the way. Thus we proceeded forl about two mIliles, wten one of the sleiglls behind us ca(nle da-hilg flaorward, and the dliver called loudly to otur driver, "IaIllo there, Bill, you are asleep, I believe; you will not reach home until dayliog1t at this r;ite; so I'll just whip up and get before you: if you do not under- stand driving over frozen ground, I will show you how." "That you won't, Jack," answered our (river, wIho was stupefied with dr(Iink. "My horses can1 beat \ours any day, and if you do not. stop and fall back, I'll show you how mine can beat you." "I won't fall back," answel ed Jack. "I'll bet you ten dollars I will reach the town first;" lan, witl tihat lie whipped up his horses, and our driver did the same. They dashed forward' at a fearftul rate, sweaing, and urging the horses to their utmost speed.   MY STEP-MOTHER.       153 We all were greatly excited, and were filled with unspeakable terror. In vain the young rnhen from both sleighs called to the drivers to stop, threatening them severely; in vain the girls screamed and shrieked with tfear. Excited with wine, and desirous of win- ning, they dashed onward, regardless of every thing. They passed and repassed each other, several times, tlheir loud shouts and blasphemous oaths adding to the horror of the scene. I cannot even now think of it, without a shudder. How it would end) we could not tell. "We shall all be killed, I am certain," was said by inany voices; "oh, what will become of us "' Some endeavored to leap from the sleigh, but were prevented; and there we were, poor helpless beings, d:ashed on, ol, on, oand expecting every moment our awtful end would comle. I recollect that there was a sudden crash, as of both sleiigls coming violently together. I recollect a tlrilling sound of sheks and gr'oans, and felt that we were thrown over, and were -till dragged on- ward, at a feariful rate, and then I lost all conscious-  ness.  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7603-00000078"/> 154      MY STEPL'-MOTHER. CHAPTER XVI. MY ILLNESS. WHEN I was again aware of my own existence, I was lying on my bed, in my own room. The stillness of death reigned around me; the room was shaded, and I seemed alone. I attempted to raise my hand; but, to my surprise, I found it almost impossible to do so. I then slightly moved my head and body, but experienced a sensation of pain and sickness. Slightly as I must have moved, from inability to do otherwise, I heard a soft step approach the bed, and saw my mother, looking very wan, pale, and dis- tressed, and clothed in deep mourning, standing by me. I tried to speak; but she put her finger to her lip, and stooping over me, kissed me tenderly, saying, Thank God, the delirium has passed, she knows me. Dear Gracey, the doctor has forbidden your speaking a word , your life depends upon it. You are very ill, dear child, and must lie perfectly still; try and sleep." So saying, she left me, and seated herself as before. Then I began to think how I came to be ill, what had happened to me, and how long I had lain there. Then that awful ride, and the terror I had endured, the swearing drivers, the excited horses, the crash   MY STEP-MOTHER.      155 and overturning of the sleighs, and the groans and shrieks of the company, all came before me; and I knew I was injured by the accident. Exhausted with the effort of thinking, I fell asleep. When I again awoke, it was evening. A bright fire blazed on the hearth, a shaded lamp cast a pleas- ant light round the room, and my father and mother sat by my bedside, conversing together in a low voice. I looked at them for sore minutes before they ob- served I was awake, and I again tried to move myself, but felt the same pain and inability as be- fore. My mother was the first to notice that I was awake, and said, "She is again awake, and knows us. O, thank God, our child will live." My father came ner to mel, but motioned, to me not to speak, and said, kissing me, "O, my child! what joy to see you again in your right mind! But you will injuree yourself if you make the least exertion or speak; lie perfectly quiet, dear Grace, and try to sleep again. It will do you good." Mv mother ap- proached the bed witlh a cup and spoon, and gave me something cooling and pleas:lnt, and then smoothed back my hair from my forehead, and rearranged my pillows, which refreshed me much, and then seated herself again by my father. I lay dreamily looking at them, until sleep again  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7603-00000079"/> 156       MY STEP-MOTHER. overpowered me; and, for several days, a few minutes, at a time was all T had the strlength to lie awake; and then it was just the samne. My mother was ever at my bedside, with a tender caress, an affectionate kiss, and a refreshing cdraught. If it was evenling, my parents sat beside me together. After a few days, I was able to lie awake a little longer; and once the doctor came in while I was awake, and I attempted to speak to him, but he put his finger to his lips, saying, "1 cannot allow you, my dear, to speak one word at present. Your head has been much disor- dered, and your life depends upon your being kept entirely-free from excitement. You are not yet out of danger; but I trust will do well, if you implicitly obey my directions. Your mother will tell you, when it will be safe for you to spealk." In the course of ten days, I felt myself gaining strength; for I could, with a little effort, raise my hands and arms. But I was conscious of acute pain if I attempted to move one of my feet, and experi- enced a bewildered strange sensation if I attempted to raise or move my head. To my great joy, my mother one day said to me, -"You may speak a little, dear Grace, and tell me how you feel." Better, much better, mother, I said; but is my leg broken?   M: STEP-MOTHER.       157 "Your ankle is badly fracturedl, she replied; "you must not try to move it at all, my dear." And what is the matter with my head, mother? I asked. "It was much bruised and injured," she said; "and for a week, you were delirious all the time, and that is the reason the doctor forbids the least noise or ex- citement; and now you must not talk any more at present, my love. You shall talk a little more to- morrow." She kissed me fondly, and seated herself near me with her sewing, occalsionally looking at me, and smiling kindly until I fell asleep. O those dreamny days of quiet thought! I did not suffer when I lay pelrfectly still; and as I gained strength and consequently felt less inclination to sleep, I amused myself with wathing my gentle mother as she glided noiselessly about the room, day after day, doing every thing for me herself, suffering no other person to enter, lest I should be disturbed, no other hand to prepare or administer my medicine or food. O how my thoughts busied themselves with the past, the present, and the future. The past, how painfully its memories came to me. I thought of another sick-room but a short time be- fore, where lay that tnner, watchful mother, in sick- ness and solitude, dependent upon the attention of "  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7603-00000080"/> 158       MY STEP-MOTHER. servants, for all she required, while her cruel, neglect- ful child preferred being any whoere but in her mlloth- er's sick-room, and was fearful of being compelled to perform for her the slightest act of kindness. 0h, how sharper than a two-edged sword did these thoughts pierce my heart; and with wlat agony did the re- collections fill my mind, as I watched her sweet and patient face, and felt cheered and soothed by her ever' ready attentions and skilful care. When I awoke, the first thought was, to see whether my mother was near; and when from necessity she left me for a few minutes, I felt sad and lonely, and the room seemed to have lost its sunlight, until she returned. I had observed my mother's black dress, but was at first unable to fix my thoughts on any thiing. Soon I recollected the illness of Blanche, and said to my mother one day, Mother, why do you wear a black dress? How  is Blanche? Tears filled her eyes; but she said, "Our sweet Blanche is in heaven, Grace, with the Saviour she so loved. You must not weep and distress yourself now, my dear, or serious conse- quences may follow, which twill greatly retard your recovery." Blanche dead I said, and I shall never see her again! O sweet, sweet Blanche, do let me weep, mother. How can I help it? everybody will weep for gentle Blanche. t s   MY STEP-MOTHER.       159 "You must compose yourself, my child, and I will soon tell you all about her last hours," said my mother; "but not now, you cannot bear it. The doctor thinks, that by next week you will be able to converse, and to listen to reading, if you continue to improve. Lie still, my dear, and think of our darling Blanche as one of, the white-robed angel host around the Father's thrbne, freed forever from sickness and death, and rejoicing in the presence of her glorious Redeemer." My mother took her work, and sat-near me; and as I watched her, I saw tear after tear fall from her eyes, at the recollection of her heavy bereavement. But her face was calm and holy as an angel's. Oh, can I ever grieve her again? I said to myself. Could I but throw myself at her feet, ask pardon for the past, beg her to let me love her as Blanche did, and to be all she could desire. Blanche is dead, sweet Blanche is dead, kept sound- ing in my ears, for days after; and the thought often fearfully and powerfully came to my mind, if I had been summoned hence instead of Blanche, how could my soul have met the awful change? Ushered all un- prepared .as it was, into its Maker's presence, where was its refuge? Jesus the Saviour of her soul, I had never besought to save mine; and though my fore- head had received the sign of the cross, and had been \  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7603-00000081"/> 160      iMY STEP-MOTHER. bedewed with the holy water to "tthe mystical wash- ing away of sin," and I had been solemnlly pledged to the service of the Crucified, I had paid no more re- gard to the imposed duties, than if I had been an un- baptized heathen. One day, when the doctor was visiting my mother, I heard hilm say to her, though he spoke in a low voice as if to prevent my hearing, "My dear Mrs. Willians, you look ill; your health is suffering firom your close confinement with Grace; I now consider her as doing well; and I insist upon it, that you must take care of yourself, and walk out every day, or I shall have another patient soon. Your many nights of watching, and your anxiety and care, have changed you very much." He said much more, and very earnestly; and my mother promised to follow his advice. What were my emotions, as I overheard this! Every word fell like a sharp arrow on my accusing heart. I thought of the slight acts of assistance I had refused to give her, when household cares had oppressed her, and sickness had laid its heavy hand upon her; and such bitter tears as remorse alone can shed, my wretched heart poured forth. She was wearing away her life and strength, for a disobedient, unthankful, rebellious child, who had spurned her authority, despised her counsel, and set at defiance her wishes, who had   MY STEP-MOTHER.       161 planted thorns of anguish in her pillow, and brought bitterness and sorrow to a home, where she came trustingly, and hopefully, and full of love and pity for the motherless child. I had often heard, at church, the story of One who walked the earth in the form of man, who was per- secuted, mocked, scourged, and crucified, by the very beings He came to love and bless; who daily received ingratitude and wrong, while he bound up the broken- hearted, preached deliverance to the captive, and gave rest to the weary and heavy-laden; and I thought of Him, as I remembered her life; and then I thought of myself, as of the ungrateful world. She is like the Saviour, I said to myself; and whom am I like? Let him be crucified, let him be crucified, my heart replied. "Dear Grace," said a gentle voice, near me, hold- ing a spoon to my lips, "please take this, little daugh- ter." I could hardly restrain my tears, as I obeyed; for my whole heart seemed bursting with its emotions. And as she turned away, I followed her with my eyes. my heart repeating always, She is like the Saviour My mind seemed at once to awaken to the beauty and loveliness of her character; but oh, could she ever forgive? Could she ever love nie.? And then again came thoughts of that blessed One who for- gave his enemies, and prayed for his murderers; "* I  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7603-00000082"/> 162      MY STEP-MOTHER. and the remembrance of Him  brought hope and comfort. One evening, a few days after, my mother had been reading to me from the Bible, and as she concluded, she said, "Dear Grace, it is now time for you to sleep; and as I have some sewing to finish, I will sit in the next room, lest the sound should disturb you. I will leave the door open; and if you do not sleep soon, speak to me, and I will give you something to com- pose you." I lay listening to the sound of her busy needle, the holy words she had so recently read diffusing calm- ness over my soul, when my father entered, and in- quired, "Is Grace sleeping 2" "She lies so quietly, I think she is," my mother answered. My father ap- proached the bed. My eyes were closed; and I felt too weary to exert myself to move. ".She is sleeping," said my father, returning to my mother's room and seating himself by her; "and she is gaining as rapidly as we could expect. But, my dear Lucia, the doctor has to-day spoken to me of yourself. He says, you have confined yourself too much with Grace, and that your health will seriously suffer, unless you have daily exercise in the open air. Your recent heavy affliction in the loss of your be- loved sister, and your constant care and anxiety with Grace, have been too much for you to bear; and I   MY STEP-MOTHER.      163 cannot allow you to continue your attendance upon her." "Grace will not require such close attention for the future," said my mother; "we will walk or ride every day; and I shall soon be as well as usual." "Dear Lucia,"' said my father, "how can I ever ex- press my great obligations to you, for your kindness and forbearance towards my wayward child? I do not now refer to her illness, the nights of watching, and the wearisome days of confinement you have passed at her couch, a ministering angel to my suf- fering child; but to the patience and gentleness with which you have borne her rude and unfeeling con- duct. I have watched you, and I have watched her most carefully, when you both thought I did not notice you. You have done all that a mother could do to win her to love and to duty, and I feel sure that in time she would become, under your care, all we could desire; but, thirteen years of neglect passed over my unfortunate child, before you came to lighten our home, and it must be the work of time to effect a change. I am not willing that your life should be clouded, and your home made unhappy; and I have decided, as soon as Grace recovers, to send her from home, to some boarding-school that we may deem suitable, where she may remain until her studies are completed,-for five or six years certainly." My father paused, and there was a moment's silence,  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7603-00000083"/> 164      MY STEP-MOTHER when my mother, as if struggling against some strong emotion said, "What you shall think conducive to the highest good of our dear Grace, that you must do. I am not weary of trying; and I feel sure, that God in his good time will answer my prayers and labors. This present illness may be the means he has chosen, to turn her heart to himself. Be sure, my beloved husband, that the last deed and dying prayers of her angel mother are registered above, and that the Redeemer who led her in triumpl through the dark valley of death, then took in charge the help- less infant, and will never desert her." They conversed on this subject a while longer, and then changed the topic; but I could think of nothing else. I was, then, to be separated from my step- mother and be sent to school. My father said he had decided upon it. My young readers may think that I rejoiced, as I had been so anxious to go, a few months before, and felt so indignant at my mother's preventing me; but, weeks of illness and suffering had quite changed my views and feelings, and nothing seemed to me so sad, as to leave the guardian angel of my sick-room, and I wept myself to sleep, that night, at the thought of being separated from my step-mother.   MY STEP-MOTHER.       165 CHAPTER XVII. MY CONVALESCENCE. THE first thought that entered my mind, on awaking the next morning, was the sad one which had closed my eyes in tears the previous night. My mother stood near my bed, and with a bright and cheerful smile inquired how I was, saying that I had passed a very quiet night. I am better, much better, I said, mother; but I cannot recover, I can never feel happy, until I have asked your forgiveness for all my disobedience. She did not reply, but kissed me kindly. O my dear mother, I said, my more than mother, can you ever forgive your cruel, ungrateful, disobedi- ent child? Can you ever love me Can you permit me to love you? I was not prepared for the gush of tears that fell from her gentle eyes, as I said these'words; but quickly recovering herself, she said, "The past is all forgiven and forgotten, dear Grace; I have always loved you." O do not say so, my sweet mother, I said, when I have embittered your whole life here. You have pitied and loved me, as the Saviour loved his enemies.  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7603-00000084"/> 166      MY STEP-MOTHER. It shall be my whlole care, for the future, that you shall love me as an obedient, trusting, loving child. I love you as I might love al angel, far removed from me in holiness. "Say no more, my dear Grace," said my mother. "I see your heart, and am too happy." I must, I will, say more now, my sweet mother, I said. This once I will disobey you, and then never, never again. O if you knew, if you could have read Imy thoughts for the last two months; if you knew how every kind deed of yours, and every loving word, has cut deeply into my once cold and selfish heart; how much I have thought of your neglected sick-room, when you have been the light and joy of mine; of all my un- kindness and thoughtlessness ever sin6e you have been here. "All is forgiven, all forgotten, I repeat, my dear Grace: we will, for the future, love and con- fide in each other; and how happy we shall be. I have lost one sweet sister, but I have found one to take her place, thank God!"O how kind, how good you are, my own mother, I said: you sLall teach me how to be like our lovely Blanche, how I may be worthy of your love. After I had breakfasted, and was comfortably seated in my easy-chair, my mother with her little work-table near me, I begged her to tell me something of the illness and death of Blanche, as she had promised.   MY STEP-MOTHER.      167 "You well know, that our dear Blanche," began my mother, " had always been in very delicate health; and, firom the nature of her disease, we thought we were prepared for her departure to her Heavenly Fa- ther's house. Yet, when the summons came, no one but herself seemed undismayed. Her lamp was trimmed and burning; and she was waiting calmly for the heavenly Bridegroom to bid her to the mar- riage-feast. She lived but two days after I reached Boston; and she was unable to talk much, but wished to have us constantly reading to her from-the Bible or Prayer-book. The day on which she died, we all received with her the Holy Communion; and she baide us all farewell, with perfect composure. Seeing us weeping, she said, 'O do not weep for me, and feel sad: I love you all most dearly, but I love my Saviour more. I hear his gracious voice, saying, Child, come up hither. My earthly home, is sweet and pleasant, but O, I have such bright visions of my heavenly home, where I shall suffer no more, and. sin no more, and shall behold my glorious Redeemer face to face, that I long to be there. Dear sister,' she said to me, 'say farewell to Grace; and tell her I thought of her, and prayed for her at my last hour; and give hei this;' and she drew from beneath her pillow hei Prayer-book, and gave it to me." As my mother spoke, she took from her work  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7603-00000085"/> 168       MY STEP-MOTHER. basket the book, and presented it to me. My tears flowed abundantly. I am not worthy to have it, nor to touch it, it has been in such holy company, I said. But, O, I would like to be as good as Blanche! "The Saviour hears your desire, my child," said my mother. "Form that desire into a prayer, and, be it ever so simple, it will reach his ear of love. "It was the day after the death of Blanche," contin- ued my mother, "that I received a letter from Mrs. Ashton, telling me of your injury, but not of your dangerous state, and urging upon me to remain as long as I wished, saying, she would remain with you until my return. I felt extremely anxious after read- ing her letter; and, as soon as we had consigned the lovely remains of our sweet sister to their last resting- place, I hurried home. I was much shocked, to find you had been delirious ever since your accident, from your head's being injured; and it was a week after my return, before you knew me. Your escape from death was miraculous." I inquired of my mother, whether Mattie was in- jured, for we had never talked the subject over, and I had long felt anxious to know, but dreaded to ask, or to refer to the painful theme. "Very slightly," was her reply; " and 1 was told she returned to school in a few days. But several of those in the sleigh with you were as seriously injured t    MY STEP-MOTHER.      169 as y'ourself; and every person was more or less in- jured, and the unfortunate driver was killed on the spotlj       , 'O how horrible! I said; and he was intoxicated and swearing too! O, mother, how good God was to spare my life, when I was so unprepared to die!"He has been most merciful to us all," said my mother, "in, granting your life to our prayers. For three weeks you were in a most dangerous state. The doc- tor said, humanly speaking, that for that time the chances seemed equal either for life or death." From this day I observed a change in my mother. Her manners towavrds me were warmer and more affetionate than ever. There was a cheerfulness and liveliness, and a beaming of the eye, as she looked upon me, which resulted from the feeling that her love was returned, and that her interest and labors were 'understood and appreciated; and I felt that she had taken me into her heart of hearts, that my waywardness was all forgotten, and that years of love and confidente were in store for us. I now began to gain strength rapidly, though I was not permnitted to put my foot to the floor, my ankle had been so badly fractured; and I was obliged, when sitting up, to have it raised on a level with my body. The bright and merry May had come, and the song of the birds&amp; reached my ears, and the green , F,  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7603-00000086"/> 170       MY STEP-MOTHER. creeper looked in at my window. I fel quite rejoiced, when the doctor said I might go into the next room, if I could go without using my laiie ankle; and mother said I should call it niy plarlor, and we would' sit there together, and it would be a plle sant chanlge for 1me.  How soothingly and hlow pleasantly comes before my mind the memory of the followingo two lolthls! All the pain and weariness are forgotten, and I thilnk only of calm and pleasant days, in the society of ole I had learned to love most dearly, and whose constant endeavor was to make me'comnfortable anld contented, and to instil into my mind some useful; or holy teach- ings. Finding myself in want of occupation, my long- neglected worsted-work was brought forth, and my slippers completed and presented to my fatlher. My mother taught me various kinds of embroidery and fancy work, which interested Ine muchi; and, by hlel advice, I devoted a part of each day to plain sewing, and learning to mend my clothes nea ly. It was a pleasure to me to do every thing she desired, so long as she sat by ine, sewing with me, or leading to me, or teaching me. I also began to love to read, which was to me an unwearying source of amusement; and my kind mother spared no pains in supplying me with suitable and interesting books.   MY STEP-MOTHER.       171 O, how can I learn to be like Blanche, mother? I said one0 day, after she had been telling me some in- cidents of ler life. I never wanted to be good, nor knew what it was to be good, until you came here. I thought I was as good as any body. "By striving, as she did," said my mother, " to follow the life of our most blessed Saviour." IIow can I, nmother? I said. I am im earnest, but so ignorant; I do not know how to learn to be good. "God has given you the desire, my dear child," said my mother; "and now you must ask Him for what you want.  Prayer is the channel through wlich He bestows on us His best gifts. He is more ready to hear than we to pray. Ask Him earnestly for all you want, in that blessed name which is above every name, and you will have all you desire." Mother, I have tried lately to ask God to help me to be good, I said, but I have never yet learned to pray. Nurse taught me "Our Father, who art in Heaven," when I was a little girl; but I left off say-, ing it a long time ago. I thought it was only for little children to say. At church, I never listened much to the prayers. You do not know what a thoughtless child I have been. "Prayer is only asking God for what we want, dear Grace," said my mother.  "What do you want a"  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7603-00000087"/> 172       MY STEP-MOTHER. I want'to be good, and love the Savilou, as Blanche did, I replied. Mother took up a Prayer-book which lay near her, and turning to the following Collect, read it aloud with great solemnity : ' Grant to us, Lord, we beseech the6, the spirit to think and do always such things as are right; that we, who cannot do alny thing that is good without thee, may by thee be enabled to live according to thy will, through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen." "Offer this prayer, many timnes in the day, my dear child," said my mother, L" believing that our Father in Heaven will hear you, and He will guide you into all truth." I followed her advice; and, after reading the col- lect a few times, the words were impressed upon my memory, and many times a day my .heart offered them. The dying gift of sweet Blanche became my constant companion. At night, I placed it under my pillow, and it lay in my work-basket by day; and often, each day, I studied it with deli ght. And, as I studied it, my heai't learned to offer for itself many more of its beautiful collects. The holy; words which had been familiar to my ears from my earliest child- hood, assumed a vitality, and a power so strong and new to my growing soul, that, as I read and pon- dered, I wondered that I had never before been ar-   MY STEP-MOTHER.       173 rested by their thrilling and touching strains and helaven-taught aspirations. My, mother read aloud to me every day the lessons firom the Bible, as appointed by the Church, pausing, as she read, to explain or comment upon Inany pas- sages. And I often interrupted her, to question her as to their inmport. Before reading, my mother always folded her hands reverently, and repeated, with bowed head, "Blessed Lord, who hast caused all holy Scriptures to be writ- ten for our learning, grant that we may in such wise hear them,. read, mark, learn, and inwardly digest them, that by patience and comfort of thy holy Word, we may embrace and ever hold fast the blessed hope of everlasting life, which thou hast given us in, our Saviour Jesus Christ. Amen." My heart soon learned to offer that prayer. And then how full of life and power the Holy Volume seemed; and how mny heart, day by day, learned to love it more and more, and to gain from it wisdom and light. My kind and gentle teacher never aIp- peared mole happy than when we were absorbed in the delightful study of the Word of God; and the hours so appropriated each morning, were, to both of us, the happiest part of the day. Mrs. Ashton and Anna often visited us, and I began to love Anna, for the vsery reasons I had 15*  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7603-00000088"/> 174       MY STEP-MOTHER. disliked her before; because she was so gentle and good. It w;is midsulllner before I was able even to walk. out in the galrden ;* and then the same loving a im supported me, the same gentle face smiled on me, that had watched over me for many molths wi h angel-like patience and love. My fatlher was sitting with us one evening, lwhel I said, Father, when I was sick in bed, I ovellleald you one evening say to my mother, that you intended  to send me away to school. I once did wish to go, but now it grieves me to think of it. If mother is willing, will you allow me to stay with hler? I haive been, father, a very wild, ignorant, and trude child, and have treated my mother with grleat disrespect. I thought mluch of being independent, and I feared the control of mny mother; but it has all passed, father. I can never be a I was before my illness. God sent this suffering to me as a great blessing, to teach me to understand and appreciate my nother, and to make Ine desire to be like her. Do not sepa- rate me fromn her, If you do, I may become as wild and thoughtless as before; if I am with her, I may, by God's help, be a better child. "It makes me too happy, my dear child," said my father, "to hear you speak thus. My only desire for you is, that you may be like your mother. I have i  t            I     .   MY STEP-MOTHER.      175 watched, for many weeks, with great pleasure, the change that has come over you; and if your mother consents, I will never separate yoif from her." It would be a great grief to me," said my mother; "so we will not think of the subject again. I trust we shall enjoy many happy years together." "Made happy by your instrumentality, my beloved Lucia," said my father. "' We will thank the great Giver of all good, for all his mercies," said my mother. CHAPTER    XVIII. MY OLD NURSE. I WISHED' to devote a chapter to speaking of my old nurse, and therefore have omitted introducing her before. Shortly after she left us, she went to visit a brother in a remote town, and did not return until a few weeks before my disastrous sleigh-ride. She then hired a couple of rooms, and occupied them, my father giving her a monthly allowance. My frequent visits to her were productive of much evil; for the time was passed in relating all the gossip I carefully treas- ured up to amuse her, and in relating all the petty  &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7603-00000089"/> 176      MY STEP-MOTHER. occurrences of home, and complaining of mhy step" mother. She would often say such things as these, which only increased my discontent, and nourished my unkind feeliiigs. "'0 dear, Miss Gracey, what a great shame it was, that your father ever brought home your step-nother, when we were living so peaceably and beautifully together. You were as happy as the days were long, with no one to find fault with you, or be cross with you; doing just what you pleased, from morning till night. In a few years, you would have left school, and could have kept your father's house just as you pleased, and had all the company and fine clothes you wanted. But now, poor dear, your faithful old nurse, who loves you bet- ter than anybody, is turned out of the house; and i you have a step-mother to contradict you, and lord it over you, and make you as miserable as she can. You do not look half so gay and happy as you once did; and the worst is yet to come, I plainly see. Old folks see a great way, poor dear, poor dear; it will break poor nurse's heart to see herdarling all crushed to the earth." I was not, as nurse said, so happy as I was be- fore my step-mother came to us; but why was it? Because I rebelled against an authority which God had placed over me, and would not submit to be   MY STEP-MOTHER.       1" led into the path of duty and holiness. I had learn- ed, that the Christian vows were upon me, and I per- sisted in leading the life of a heathen child. The voice of conscience, though still and small, often made me very wretched, because I stifled its wise and salu- tary monitions. After my fearfil acciden my my urse was so anx- ious about me, that she forgot her resolution of never coming to our house again, and Balled every day to inquire concerning me; and as soon as I was able to bear it, my mother allowed me. to sde her. When I had been confined but a few weeks, her visits suddenly ceased, and cook inforlned my mother tlhat she was verl ill with a rheulnatic fever. As soonl as my mothier heard of it, she went to her at once, Cand, found her suffering greatly. But I will relate, in nurse's own words, the account of this first visit, as she related it to me some months after, "I had been lying alone most of the time for several days," she said. "The only person I had seen was Mrs. Brown, who lived in the opposite room, and who came in for a few minutes to see if I wanted any thing, when I heard a gentle rap at the door. When it was opened, and I saw your mother, I was so surprised, that I could not speak. She came to my bed, and took my hand and said, 'Ah, poor nurse, you are iff-; you are  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7603-00000090"/> L io O       iE.11l-MJ T Ul'HiEM. suffering great pain, I see. I only heard of it to-day. Cook says, you have a rheumatic fever, and I know it is attended with much suffering. I am very sorry for you.' Her look was so full of kindness and sym- pathy, and her voice so sweet and soothing, and to me, who had never done for her one kind deed, nor spoken even one kind word in her behalf, that I could have buried my head under the bedclothes for very shame. I could not speak. My tongue refused me utterance. She seemed to understand my feelings, and said, without waiting a reply from me, 'I have something that will soothe your pain, which I have  often seen used with great effect.' "So saying, she rekindled my expiring fire, and after warming some water, she poured into it something from a vial, and then coming to the bed, with her own soft hand she tenderly bathed my swollen limbs. It seemed as if every touch of her gentle hand charmed away some ugly pain. I could only say, Thank you, ma'am, you are very kind. She then prepared something for me to drink, which greatly refreshed me. Her kindness and her condescension filled me with surprise; and as I watched her, moving quietly about my little dark room, with her graceful figure and sweet young face, it seemed to me as if God had sent a holy angel down from heaven to lighten my poor home, and minister to my need.   MY STEP-MOTHER.       179 "She said I must not stay alone; that she would send some one to stay with me that very night, and that she would come in as often as she could leave you, and see if I was rightly taken care of, and had every thing I required. 't Good-by,' she said at parting. 'I know you are suffering much, poor nurse; but there is One above, who will give you patience to bear all that he inflicts. Pray to Him for it, good nurse. He will not turn away from you. In his good time he will raise you up.' I did not 'speak, for I could not utter one word; but she saw the big tears that rolled down my cheeks, and she kn-ew that I thanked and blessed her." My mother went as often as she could leave me, to visit nurse; and when I was so far recovered that she eould leave me and walk out every day, she visited her constantly. Nurse lay for three months in a suf- fering, but tot dangerous, state. When she was not in too much pain, my mother would read to her a chapter from the Bible, or some collects from the Prayer-book. Nurse at first listened from respect  to my mother, but soon began to love to hear them, and would often request my mother to read the same to her several days in succession, that she might remember what she heard, and repeat it to herself. My mother persuaded her to receive the visits of I! I  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7603-00000091"/> 180      MY STEP-MOTHER. Mr. Shepherd, our good rector; and his conversation and instructions were much blessed to her. I felt most anxious to know what were the feelings ot nurse towards my mother, on receiving from her so much attention and kindness, when she had done all she could to injure her, and to prejudice my mind against her; but mother never said a word upon the subject. And though I inquired for nurse every day, I could not question my mother on that point.  It was July before nurse was able to go out again; and it was about that time that I began to walk on my ankle, which had been in a most dangerous state. One day, mother said to me, that sie was going to send a carriage for nurse to pass the day with me, as she was very desirous to visit me, and was unable to walk so far. It was during this visit that she gave me the account of my mother's first visit as above related. I cannot describe the joy I felt, on hearing her speak thus of my beloved mother. "O, dear Miss Grace," she said, "God sent her to us here, in great mercy, to tell us of Him whom we all had forgotten; but we turned away our hearts from her, as the Jews turned away from the blessed Saviour. But she was patient with us, and, like the Saviour, returned good for evil, and served us, though we despised her and   MY STEP-MOTHER.      161 looked upon her as an intruder in our home. She came to show us that there is no true joy nor peace any where, without God.  I thank God for these months of suffering ; for without them I never should have listened to her voice, nor to the ilstructions of oui good rector. I am rejoiced to see, that in spite of all your cruel nurse said to set you against your step- mother, you have learned to love her. May God for- give me, for speaking of her so harshy and so igno- rantly. It is a lesson to me, to teach me to govern my tongue. I shall never forget it. O, if she would only allow me to come here, and live again under the same roof with her, to show, by my poor services, how grateful my heart is for all she has done for me, I would gladly occupy a bed in the garret, so that I miglit watch. over her in sickness, and wait upon her in healtli." It was during this visit, as nurse sat in the room with us at rwork, that she said to my mother, "O dear lady, I have thought much, very much, and deeply, of all you said to me, at your last' visit, on the subject of baptislm; and though, for the last month, owing to your kind and holy teachings, and those of Mr. Shepherd, I have been, led by God's Spirit to see what a sinfutl worldly life I have led, lo'w far my sins have separated between me and my God, and how I need the blood of the, gl'eat RI-'tledeler to save mne, I 'Io '       , * / I  &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7603-00000092"/> 182      MY STEP-MOTHER. dare not, I am so sinful and so weak, take upon me tihe solemn vows the Church enjoins on the baptized. O, should I fall back, what a shame lit would be on the name of my Saviour, though I db now fervently desire to walk henceforth in his holy ways, and to be his disciple." "Then, my good nurse," said my mother, "you dishonor the Saviour, and have not a' strong faith in his promises, because you doubt his power and mercy in keeping you in the right path. You violate one of his commands, Repent and be baptized, are his words. Baptism must follow true repentance, if we want God's favor. The path of a Christian is a difficult one; but it is our duty to strive and walk in it, and grace is promised to all who seek it. I have spoken to Mr. Shepherd on the subject; and he considers that, so far as human judgment can discern, you pos- sess the requisites the Church requires of those who come to Holy Baptism. Therefore, le, no doubts nor misgivings prevent you from using those means of grace which .Christ has established in his Church, as channels whereby he feeds our thirsting souls with the bread and water of life." "I have been carefully studying the baptismal ser- vice,' said nurse, "and I can readily ahd heartily re- spond to the first promise. I most gladly renounce the devil and all his works; and also the vain pomp   i X  MY STEP-MOTHER.      183 and glory of the world, and all covetous desires of the same, and the sinful desires of the flesh. 'What are they, to a poor old woman like me, just snatched by God's mercy from the brink of the grave? Sixty years have I served them, and what did they ever profit me? What comfort were they to me, when death stared me in the face, and the horrors of eternal punishment were revealed to me The second ques- tion, Dost thou believe all the Articles of the Chris- tian Faith as contained in the Apostles' Creed? I can truly answer,-I do, thanks to my holy teachers, and to the Spirit who has enlightened my darkened soul; and gladly will I promise the third question, and be baptized inl this most blessed faith. IBut al, good lady, how c:an If prolnise the last, that I will obediently keep God's hl v will and colmmn ndments, and walk in the same all the days of my life? How can I promise that, when, for sixty years, I leave broken them all? It seems to me presumptuous. I do warmly desire so to do, but I so fear I shall fall out by the way, and disgrace His holy name, that I dare not promise. What shall I do, dear lady? You who have taught me so much that I could not understand, can perhaps help me." ("What is the answer of the Prayer-book to the last question, nurse?" asked my mother. "I will, by God's help," she replied.  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7603-00000093"/> 184      MY STEP-MOTHER. "Are you willing, are you desirous to keep God's holy commandments, and walk in them if he help you?" asked my mother. "I am most willing, most desirous," said nurse. "Do you believe that God call enable you to do it?" asked my mother. "I do believe he can do all things," replied nurse. "And do you believe that he will?" asked my mother. "Ah, dear lady, there is where I doubt," said nurse; that lie should conde- scend to help a poor old sinner lile me, who has so long turned from Him; for, lady, this is not the first time he has spoken to my soul. O no! several times in the course of my sixty years' journey, has he awakened me to a sense of imy sin- Fulness; but I have turned away froio him and not listened to his voice, and thereforte now I doubt his acceptance." "O0 then you limit the Redeemer's power, and the Redeemer's mercy," said my mother. "This may be the last call he will ever extend to you. Had you, when he before aroused you to a knowledge of your danger and sin, steadfastly purposed to walk in his ways, had you humbly leaned upon his glace, had you become a recipient of his holy Sacraments, as one of the duties he enjoins, and as (ppointed-chan- nels for strength and life, le mighlt .ong since have caused you to know the blessedness of His service.   MY STEP-MOTHER.       185  But because you have so long lived without Him, and 1 ;purned His proffers of grace, is it any reason that  you should continue so? Ah no; it is the reason why you should, now that he has in mercy again iroused you to a sense of your duty, go promptly, and humbly, and prayerfully forward, in the path he has appointed, and trust in Him to fulfil his blessed purposes in you; study his holy word with humility, lift up your soul to him in prayer and praise in the closet and in the sanctuary, obey his commands in receiving his Sacraments. And He will preserve you in the hour of temptation, and keep you steadfast unto the end." Nurse, no less than myself, hung upon every one of these words of pious wisdom, as they fell from my mother's lips. They sunk deep into our hearts, and brought forth fruit, I trust, unto everlasting life. &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7603-00000094"/> 186      MY STEP-MOTHER. CHAPTER XIX. M A TTIE'S RETURN HOME. IN Aiugulst, Mattie Miller returned fromn boarding- school. I was as yet able to walk lbut a short dis- tance; yet, every day I took long and deliglitful  'drives in the country, with my lmotlhe and fiat!er, Anna Ashton or somne other of my scthool-mates oc- cupying the vacant seat in the barouche, which my fathelr preferred to drive. O, how Inluch I enjoyed it! I had been so long confined to the house, that every turn of the wheel, every tree and flower tand meadow, filled me with exquisite pleasure. Father would sometimes stop at the entrance of the woods, and we would alight and roam around, and inhale the delicious fiaglrance of the woods, and gather the wild-flowers and berries. Mattie had not been at home nany days, wlgen she came to see me. "Coingratulate me, Grace," she said, "I do not return to boarding-school. I have finished' my education; now I am going to enjoy myself, No more books, no more school; I have nothing to do but run around, and visit, and frolic, from morning till night, and do any thing I please. I suppose you knew father had bought a. carriage and horses. One   MY STEP-MOTHERZ.      187 of them is a saddle-horse; and Ben is going to teach me to ride on horseback. What a fine time I shall have. I have had a nice time at boarding-school, though ; I have not injured my health by study. We have had some capital times. I must tell you all about them some day; pleiity of money and plenty of fun; and I was never detected in breaking any of the rules, by going out in the evening or in any thing else, while I was there. Was I not lucky ? But come, Grace, tell me about yourself. Mother says you have been sick all summer, ever since February. What a disastrous ride that was for you. Was I not fortu- nate to escape ?"  There is tittle to tell, but what you already know, Mattie, I replied. I have been very ill. I was delirious for several weeks, most of the time; it is almost a miracle that I am now living. I have suffiered velry much from my head; and also from my ankle, which was badly fractured, and is still so weak, that it swells badly if I use it much, though it is improving daily. "Why, you have had a hard time, Grace," she an swered. "It is too bad."  0, do not speak so of any affliction God sends upon us, I said. It was sent to me in mercy, to stop me in my career of thoughtless- ness and sin, and to make me, I trust, a wiser child. "Why, Grace, you talk like an old woman," said Mattie. "What is the matter ?"  In the six months &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7603-00000095"/> 188       MY STEP-MOTHER. that have passed, since we parted, Mattie, I replied, I have lived six years. You do not know how rapidly the mind grows, when it is closed to outward occur- rences, and communes only with itself and one or two beloved ones. O Mattie, I have lived long, long, since that awful night of folly and sin we passed to- gether,             How you talk, Grace," said Mattie; "I should not know you, you, have been shut up here so long with your step-mother, that-" Mattie, I interrupted, never again speak to me dis- respectfully of my most tenderly and dearly beloved mother. I am ashamed of myself, when I think of the past; how I allowed myself to be prejudiced against her, and blinded to her true character. But alas! my conscience tells me, that I was not so blinded as I wished to be. May God forgive me, as freely as she has, for all my past disrespect .and misconduct towards her. It will be the study of my future life, to please her, and endeavor to be like her. "Mother said it would be a good chance for her to conquer you," said Mattie; "and so she has at last, I plainly see, poor Grace." Conquered me? Yes, Mattie, I said, subdued me, humbled me before her to the very dust. I would consider any menial office that I could perform for her, too great an honor for me. And how has she   MY STEP-MOTHER.       189  otlquel'ed me? I will tell you; by her unvarying ove and tenderness always extended to me, even when most turned from her; by nights and days of care ind watching, during my long months of illness, Lntil her own health suffered fromn the confinement. Mattie, every drop of medicine, every portion of lourishment for me, was prepared and administered by her own gentle hand. The doctor says, had I not been so blest, as to have just such a nurse, it would have been impossible to have saved my life. I had she been less attentive, less discreet, less tender, I should have been now in my grave. Through God's goodness, this life, then, I owe to her. Is she not, then, truly your own mother? No one ever loved and honored a mother, moore truly than I love and honor her. For six long months, she has been the joy and light of my sick-room, talking with me, read- ing to me, amusing me in a thousand pleasant ways, never weary, always cheerful, always loving to her rebellious child; but rebellious no longer, Mattie. You see that she has conquered me; and if, for noth- ing else, I thank God for this illness, that it has 'brought our hearts together, and taught me to love, and to desire to be guided by, the best and wisest of mothers. "It does well enough for you to talk so now, Grace," said Mattie; "but when you feel strong and  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7603-00000096"/> 190       MY STEP-MOTHER. well, and are around with me again, you will feel very differently. You will see whether I amn right. Yoll have lost all your spirit, sure enough, if you mean to be plodding about with a step-mother afer you all your life. When you are well enough for us to take some of our old walks together, and have some of our wild times again, you will think very differently. I have a thousand pleasant plans for us for the future. As soon. as you are well enough to come, I am going to give a splendid ball, to give things a start here; and mother says, I may have as many balls as I please; and we shall be as gay as larks, Grace." Mattie, I said, I shall never be the silly, thought- less girl I once was; and you must lay no more wild plans for me. My parents disapprove of them, and my taste for them has gone forever. Dear Mattie, I continued, I have been for the last three months guid- ed by my beloved mother, a daily student of God's Holy Word. I have learned there, that this life is not given us to fritter away in folly and trifling pleasures, but to win for ourselves a life of happiness, when these short lives are over. I have learned from the Prayer- book, that there are many solemn duties imposed upon all-upon you and me-at our baptism, which I have entirely neglected, and hardly bestowed one thought upon. Now, Mattie, I have firmly resolved, God being my helper, to understand whlat these duties   MY STEP-MOTHER.       191 ire, and endeavor to fulfil them. O, Mattie, I wish rou would resolve to do the same. "Why, you have feally' turned preacher, Grace," said Mattie. "Who would have thought it of you, wild, gossiping Grace, Is tley used to call you? You have been taking les- oons of your step-mother, I see." Do not talk so, Mattie, I said; I am a poor, igno- rant child ; but God's mnercy aroused me to a sense of my true condition as a member of Christ and a child of God. I need some one to preach to me. You were my most particular friend, and if I did not tell you what I thought, whom should I tell? "Well," said Mattie, "I suppose, then, that you are to do nothing but go to church all day, on Sundays, prayer-d;iys, and saints' days, and to all the Bible- classes :and Sunday-school; that you will visit the sick alndthe poor, and be like Miss Graves and Miss Wilson. If that is your determination, Grace, I fear we shall not imeet very often; for I have planned for myself a very different course, as you may perceive from. what I have told you. But, Grace, believe me, you will soon become tired of such a prosy, moping life, and be glad of a good frolic with me, before six months are gone." Ah, Mattie, I answered, I wish I could persuade you to feel as I[ do, desirous only of doing for the fu- ture what is right, and what our Saviour requires of  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7603-00000097"/> 492      MY STEP-MOTIIER..  us. Depend upon it, you will weary of your course, but I shall never weary of mine. The more I study God's blessed book, the more I love it; the more I learn of holy things, the more my heart desires to know. Mother .says, there is no foundation for true happiness, apart from God and his service; and I be- lieve it. I had long ceased to feel happy, in my wild and thoughtless life, 'lthough you did not know it. Though I spurned my mother's control, and turned my heart from her love, there has been at wolk  around me an influence, both from her and Blanche, which I could not escape, awakening my conscience, and whispering of duty. I feel, that there is over me a higher power than my own will, even God the Holy Spirit, who will lead me into all truth. But, here comes my old nurse; she, too, has learned to love my mother. She, too, has, through my mother's influence, become an humble student of God's Holy Word, and has, like me, determined to follow the commandments of God, and walk from henceforth in his holy ways. "Are you coming back to-day to your old home, good nurse?" inquired my mother, entering the room. "I hope you have made all your arrangements for so, doing: we want to have you quietly settled with us again." "Thank you, dear lady, a thousand tinmes," saia   MY STEP-MOTHER.      193  nurse,"for allowing me to return. I have given up  my room to-day, and am so glad I may again call   i this house my home."  "The old nursery is yours," said my mother, "and is all ready-for you. You will find no change, but a little new paint, and some new curtains." "Thank you, dear lady," said nurse, "a thousand times, for all your kindness. O, who would have thought you could have been so good, as to permit me to live with you again, when I left you in such an angry and disrespectful manner, and when you knew I had often spoken of you wrongfully, and even tried to turn the heart of Grace against you? Who Wiould have thought, that you would have given. shelter again to a poor old woman, who has only tried to injure you? It is, dear lady, because your heart is so filled with God's blessed Spirit, that there is no room in it for hatred, nor revenge, nor any evil thing. Nothing else could make you so loving, so generous, and so forgiving." "Say no more, good nurse," said my mother; "the past is all forgiven, and I trust you will enjoy, under our roof, a happy and comfortable old age. You must never leave us again." "Never. while you will allow me to stay," said nurse. 4"My whole future life. shall be devoted to showing my gratitude by my poor services. If sickness comes to you, dear lady, lr  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7603-00000098"/> 194       MY STEP-MOTHER. be sure of one experienced and patient watcher at your pillow, one faithful overseer of your household." I had watched Mattie's countenance during this conversation, and saw that it expressed much sur- prise. You see, Mattie, I said, my dear old nurse has learned also to love and reverence my mother. "O Mattie," said nurse, "if you have heard me speak disrespectfully of this most pious and excellent lady, you now hear me say how deeply I regret it; andhow humbly I ask her pardon. It was from en- tire ignorance of her character. O, it is a wicked thing to speak lightly of any one, and to bear false witness! May God forgive me! I can never cease  to regret it." Shortly after this, Mattie took her leave. And I will here add, that as Mattie had determined upon a life of folly and worldliness, as resolutely as I had  upon the Christian life, our paths became so widely separate that we seldom met.   MY STEP-MOTHER.      195 CHAPTER XX. THE CONFIRMATION AND COMMUNION. IT was a lovely summer's morning, on Sunday, neai the end of August, that I was for the first time aftet my illness, permitted to attend church. O, how I had longed to go, for many, many weeks; and how the sweet bells seemed calling me to come and wor- ship; how my full heart yearned to pour out its songs of grateful love for the past six months' mercies. The last time I had entered the sacred courts, it was with a reluctant spirit, a careless step, and a heart crowded with folly. I saw n'o beauty in holiness, no solemnity nor duty in worship,.no God -in the heavens, no Sa- viour on the cross. But, light had been mercifully poured upon my darkness'; and now, with ready step and swelling heart and glistening eye, I reverently entered the house of the living God, and bowed my knee in silent prayer. Though years have passed since then, I cannot recall without emotion, this first Lord's day on which, in His sanctuary, I sought to offer him acceptable worship. Our glorious Liturgy, often as I had heard it before, seemed so new with spiritual life and beauty, that it was as if, for the first time, its holy strains fell upon  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7603-00000099"/> 196       MY STEP-MOTHER. my ear. When the organ ceased its music, and, after a moment of death-like silence, the voice of our pastor broke upon my ear, in the impressive words, "The Lord is in his holy temple," I felt the awful presence, and rejoiced as I felt it. O, how deeply my contrite spirit uttered, in the confession, "there is no health in us ;" how I rejoiced in the absolution, and with childlike confidence re- peated, "Our Father who art in heaven." "Come let us sing unto the Lord, let us heartily rejoice in the strength of our salvation," poured forth my soul with deep fervor and joy. The lofty strains of the Te Deum so overpowered me, that my tears came, my voice ceased, and my soul worshipped in silence. Mr. Shepherd gave notice, that day, that on Sun- day, October the ninth, the Bishop of our Diocese would visit the Church, and administer the apostolic rite of Confirmation. He requested all who were de- sirous to receive it, to meet at his house for instruction, on the Wednesday afternoons previous to the Bishop's visit. He earnestly urged upon all who had reached the age recommended, by the Church, for receiving this rite, to give devout attention to the subject, and take upon themselves, as was their bounden duty and their highest privilege, the solemn vows of their Bap- tism. I felt that every word he uttered was expressly for me; and I felt, that I tust be one of the number   MY STEP-MOTHER.       197 who would avail themselves of the present opportunity of receiving Confirmation. Mother, I said, as we sat together in the evening, October ninth, the day of the Bishop's visit, is my birth-day; I shall be fourteen years old. If you are willing, dear mother, I should so love to join the class at Mr. Shepherd's, to prepare for Confirmation. "I cannot express the pleasure it gives me, my dear," fAid my mother, "to know that you feel the desire. I joyfully consent to it." How delightfully comes to my remembrance that confirmation class. There were twenty-five; a few, in mature life, but most of them young. I see the spacious and pleasant study of our beloved Pastor, with its lining of books, and ornaments of painting and statuary; and I see him, with his benign and holy face, sitting in the midst of us, in, his fatherly and gentle way teaching us, poor feeble lambs of his li! ck, the way of eternal life. I cannot here repeat his instructions, but will only say, I became ex- ceedingly interested in them, and more firmly re- solved than ever, that, from henceforth, I would manfully fight under the banner of the cross, and continue Christ's faithful soldier and servant unto my life's end. After teaching us the object and responsibilities of I Confirmation, he instructed us in our duty with re- 17*  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7603-00000100"/> 198      MY STEP-MOTHER. spect to receiving the Holy Communion, and he urged upon us to give the subject earnest and devout consideration. I also conversed much with my mother on the subject, and felt a strong desire to receive also, on that day, my fourteenth birth- day, for the first time, the Blessed Sacrament of the Lord's Supper. My mother said she could not con- scientiously forbid me, nor discourage me, on account of my youth, and she wished Mr. Shepherd to decide for me.  I shall be fourteen on that day, Sir, I said to Mr. Shepherd. My mother fears you may think me too young; but I so strongly desire it, she says, she cannot forbid me, and refers it to you. "If you -are so young, my dear child," he said, "the more need you have of the fostering and shel- tering arms of our holy Mother, to keep you in the path of duty. The young and the feeble are those whom the blessed Saviour will carry in his arms. You are not too young to die, my child; so you are not too young to learn to follow Christ. You and I, and all of us, are poor feeble mortals. We do not say, when we kneel at the altar, ' God, I thank thee that I am not as other men ;' but, ' he remembrance of our sins is grievous unto us; the burden of them is intolerable. Have mercy upon us, have mercy upon us, most merciful Father; for thy Son our Lord f   MY STEP-MOTHER.       199 Jesus Christ's sake, forgive us all that is past; and grant that we may hereafter serve thee in newness of life.' If you are steadfastly purposed to follow him in newness of life, draw near with faith, and take this holy Sacrament to your conmfort; and He whom you desire to serve, will be your strength and your ex- ceeding great reward." And one more Lord's-day morning, calm and beau- tiful, now comies sweetly to my memory, through the lapse of years. The gorgeous drapery of autumn was upon trees-and fields, and the blue and blessed sky, in its intense autumnal blueness, smiiled above us. There was on that ninth of October a baptism at church; not of a fair and lovely infant, just entering life, given for safe keeping into the arms of the Church, but of a way-worn pilgrim of sixty years. My emotions cannot be described, as I saw my old nurse kneeling humbly at the font and receiving the holy water of baptism upon her aged brow. And as I looked from her, to the young and lovely being who stood as witness at her side, even my own beloved mother, and thought of all she had been to us, my tears would not be restrained, and I saw that many of the congregation were much moved at the scene. Side by side, my old nurse and I stood at the chan- cel rails; and our voices blended as we sang the con -firmlation hymn: ]I '     r  &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7603-00000101"/> ZUU       MY STEP-MOTHER. "O happy day that stays my choice On Thee, my Saviour and my God." O, how fervently my heart prayed, as the consecrated hands of the Bishop were upon my sinful head : "De- fend, O Lord, this thy child, with thy heavenly grace; that she may continue thine forever; and daily in- crease in her thy Holy Spirit more and more, until she come unto thine everlasting kingdom. Amen." And then my first communion,-its warm and fiesh emotions return to my heart as I recall it. I was so absorbed in my own feelings, that I did not notice what was passing around me; and when we knelt in  the Confession, I heard close at my side, the deep and manly voice of my father, uttering, in solemn tones, "We acknowledge and bewail our manifold sins and wickedness, which we from time to time most griev- ously have committed, by th6ght, word, and deed, against thy Divine Majesty, provoking most justly thy wrath and indignation against us. We do earnestly repent, and are heartily sorry for these our misdoings." My own voice became choked with emotion; my heart continued to pray, but my lips wefe silent. Yes, it was even so: the blessed influence which that day brought my old nurse and her wayward child to the Communion of the body and blood of Christ, brought there also my beloved father. At the altar of our crucified Lord and Master, we all knelt together,   MY STEP-MOTHER.      201 a small, but an unbroken family. O, what a mighty power can one holy mind exert, trusting in God for strength! What was our home only one year and a half be- fore! And what was it now! Then, my father's noble mind was so entirely engrossed with the cares and business of this life, that he gave but little thought to a preparation for the life to come. My nurse, hur- rying rapidly down the vale of time, with no hope of heaven, no thought of her awful accountability to God who made her, and to the Saviour who died for her; and myself a headstrong, idle, gossiping child, approaching womanhood, in utter ignorance of all that was good and holy, and under influences which would have made my pathway through life that of the heartless worldling. Now, my father's high gifts were consecrated to his God; my old nurse had found a staff whereon to lean, as with weary steps she de- scended to the grave; and I too had found, that life was a golden period of time, not to be idly squander- ed, but to be devoted heartily to the service of the adorable Saviour. O, what a mighty power can one holy mind exert, trusting in God for strength! On the evening of that sacred day, we all knelt, for the first time, around the family altar, where, ever since, the flame has brightly burned, drawing down upon our household unnumbered blessings. From i ' '?"  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7603-00000102"/> 202   "   MY STEP-MOTHER. that blessed day, I have kept my eye ever fixed upon the one great object before me; and, forgetting the things that are behind, I have, pressed toward the. mark for the prize of the high ca:ling of God in Christ Jesus. Many bitter tears, much watchfulness and earnest prayer, have finally conquered my idle and wicked habit of gossiping, thanks to the blessed Spirit of God; but it was a long and; a hard struggle. I have, my young readers, suffered many painful and humiliating feelings, during the recital of my history; but I have written for your warning and in- struction. May the lessons which these pages teach, sink deep into your hearts. You I ave learned the evils resulting from a habit of idle gossiping, and from having the mind imbued with prejudice. O, beware of them, and of the bitter fiuits they bring. You have seen what a waste your childhood might have been, unblessed with a mother's affection. Then prize- her tender care and wise monitions, and rejoice in her restraining and directing love. Submit rever- ently to all whom God places over yon; and, believe me, there is no life of peace, no true and substantial happiness, apart from Christ, apart from taking up our cross daily and following Him. O, solemnly recall to mind, every morning, that the holy waters of Baptism have been upon you, and that the sign of the cross is upon your brow. God sees it   r   T STEP-MOTHER.     203 there. Let not sin efface it. Bear it ever in your heart and in your life; and earnestly pray, that you shall " not be ashamed to confess the faith of Christ crucified, but manfully fight under his banner, against sin, the world, and the devil; and continue Christ's faithful soldier and servant unto your life's end." THE END. a p   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>