<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
   xml:id="VAC7228">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Elinor Johnston, Founded on Facts; and Maurice and Genevieve, or, The Orphan
               Twins of Beauce </title>
            <author>M. L. M.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7228</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1691A</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                  copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction
                  project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                  University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
                  to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                  contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                  educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                  inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University
                  Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
               Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Elinor Johnston, founded on facts, and Maurice and Genevieve, or, The
                     orphan twins of Beauce</title>
                  <author>M. L. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>136 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>P. F. Cunningham</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1868">1868</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
               Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
               website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
               been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
               Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-11-03">Finished OCR, rough
            encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2004-10-17">Finished TEI
            conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Converted document from SGML to TEI
            P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents
            and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7228-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>ELINOR JOHNSTON;</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">FOUNDED ON FACTS.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">AND</titlePart>
               <titlePart>MAURICE AND GENEVIEVE;</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, THE ORPHAN TWINS OF BEAUCE.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">CATHOLIC TALES;</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>EDITED BY THE AUTHOR OF GRACE MORTON, &amp; C.</byline>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>PETER F. CUNNINGHAM, Catholic Bookseller,
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>216 South Third Street,</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1868">1868.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="verso-3" xml:id="VAC7228-00000002"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1868, BY PETER F.
                  CUNNINGHAM, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States, in
                  and for the Eastern District of Pennsylvania.</edition>
               <publisher>STEREOTYPED BY THEO. BROWN,</publisher>
               <pubPlace>720 Sansom St., Phila.</pubPlace>
            </bibl>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Elinor Johnston, founded on facts, and Maurice and Genevieve, or, The orphan twins
               of Beauce</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ELINOR JOHNSTON:</head>
               <head type="sub">FOUNDED ON FACTS.</head>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                  <p>"WELL, Bessie, I suppose by this time you are quite settled with your new
                     governess," said Mrs. Hardcastle to her sister Mrs. Forrest, as they were
                     sitting cosily together over the fire enjoying a long morning's confidential
                     gossip. "One of good Father Gibson's innumerable <foreign xml:lang="FRA"
                        >protegees,</foreign> is she not? I hope she will turn out better than the
                     last,—the Jewish convert, was it not?—that borrowed a five-pound note of you
                     one day, and started off to see her dying mother at Liverpool, and never came
                     back. No, that was the one before the last but she<pb n="4-5"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000003"/> did something bad too. I forget what it was
                     exactly, but—</p>
                  <p>"Dear Cecy, you certainly do love to tease. I scarcely dare to mention any of
                     my little pet projects to you now; for if any of them should fail—as I
                     acknowledge they do sometimes—not only have I the disappointment itself to
                     bear, but a volley of your satire into the bargain, with every other similar
                     vexation raked up and heaped on my already overloaded shoulders," replied Mrs.
                     Forrest, smiling in spite of her annoyance; "but as to the governess, she did
                     not come after all; and I am very sorry about it, for I was greatly pleased
                     with her."</p>
                  <p>"Did not come? but I thought she was so badly off, struggling with starvation
                     in a miserable lodging, and all alone in the world too; it is very odd."</p>
                  <p>"Yes, it is odd, and she is an odd young person too; but I like her certainly,
                     and I see that Father Gibson has a high opinion of her, and that in itself is a
                     recommendation; for though he is one of the most kind and charitable of men, he
                     does not give his esteem lightly."</p>
                  <p>"But why upon earth, then, will she not take your situation?"</p>
                  <p>"I believe the truth is, she has work in Father Gibsons's parish which she does
                     not like to leave. Of course he would not think to preventing her from coming
                     to me, however useful she may be to him; but it is her own free choice: she
                     gives a few lessons in tradesmen's families chiefly, and makes out a living
                     between that and needle work. All her spare time she spends in visiting the
                     poor; and on Sundays she has the principal management of the Patronage; it is
                     called a new sort of—"</p>
                  <p>"O, my dearest Bessie, save me from the infliction of any more of your
                        <emph>new</emph> charitable schemes, or at least make the recital as short
                     as possible."</p>
                  <p>"The Patronage, Cecy, is only a sort of Sunday-club for girls, who meet in the
                     parish church, and are read to, instructed, and generally entertained by
                     various benevolent persons, of whom this Elinor Johnston is one."</p>
                  <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7228-00000004"/>
                  <p>"Johnston! I expected a much prettier name. Where does she come from?"</p>
                  <p>'She comes immediately from some manufacturing town in Yorkshire; but she was
                     born in the south of England, and brought up at a convent near Lyons till
                     within the last twelve months. I can only get scraps of her history from Father
                     Gibson, but I have managed to piece them together pretty well. Here they are,
                     if you care to listen.</p>
                  <p>Her parents seem to have been well-to-do people,—whether quite in our rank or
                     not, I cannot say, but they kept servants and lived comfortably. The father, I
                     suppose, carried on some business, but what I cannot learn. She lost both
                     parents before she was ten years old; and it was then for the first time an
                     uncle appeared on the scene, who took charge of both herself and a sister, a
                     year or two younger. They knew very little of him previously, as there had been
                     some family-quarrel; and they appear to have had no other near relations.</p>
                  <p>He was a manufacturer, and a self-raised man I fancy; fond of money and of
                     making it, not to spend, but to hoard. He sent the girls to a cheap
                     convent-school abroad,—whether he chose it merely because it was cheap, or
                     because he wished to get them out of his way for some time, I will not say; but
                     they remained there for years, never coming over to England, and hearing from
                     him but seldom.</p>
                  <p>"Elinor at that time had no idea whatever that she and her sister were
                     possessed of any property of their own; in fact, their uncle always impressed
                     upon them in his occasional letters the strong probability that they would have
                     to depend upon their own exertions for their support, and urged them to apply
                     themselves to their studies with the utmost diligence on this account. The
                     school seems to have been well conducted: and though the way of living, to our
                     English notions, appears rough and uncomfortable, they were happy there; and in
                     the case of Elinor it has turned out a most fortunate thing that she has been
                     accustomed from childhood to dispense with many things that we are apt to deem
                     essential.</p>
                  <p>"The little sister died of a low fever, I<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7228-00000005"
                     /> think, about two years after they had entered the school. She was received
                     into the Church on her deathbed, at her earnest request (for I forgot to say
                     that the Johnstons were Protestants); and it was not long afterwards that
                     Elinor was also received at her own desire,—after the ceremony had been
                     deferred from time to time by the nuns, who thought her too young—for she was
                     still almost a child—for such an important step. They insisted on her writing
                     to inform her uncle: he did not appear to have been as much moved as might have
                     been expected by the news; but he used her conversion as a pretext for not
                     inviting her to England during any vacation, alleging that his wife, who was
                     more particular than himself upon religious matters, dreaded the influence a
                     Roman Catholic might exert upon their two young children.</p>
                  <p>"Elinor was, as nearly as she could guess, about nineteen when she was summoned
                     to England by her uncle with only a few hours notice. A friend of his who was
                     passing through the little town where she had spent so many years took charge
                     of her as far as Paris; the rest of the journey she made alone. She found her
                     uncle considerably aged, as was natural, and in low spirits, having recently
                     lost his wife and both children. He was living perhaps in consequence, in great
                     retirement as regarded society, spending his days in his house of business; and
                     Elinor, who was at once installed as his housekeeper found her time hang
                     heavily on her hands, after her constant school occupations. But this did not
                     last long: one evening her uncle did not return home from business; nothing was
                     heard of him next morning; in short, he was missing. Strict search was made;
                     and after a while strong reasons were discovered for his absence: he was deeply
                     in debt; in fact, totally ruined.</p>
                  <p>Then it came out that his nieces had inherited some considerable property from
                     their father, and then that he had fraudulently disposed of the whole of it.
                     Nothing was heard of the man from that time; and it was believed that he had
                     gone to Australia or to America. Great commiseration<pb n="10-11"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000006"/> ration was felt for Elinor; and she would have
                     met with much kindness, had it not been for the circumstance of her being a
                     Catholic. She could obtain no remunerative employment in the town in
                     consequence, for the Catholics there are a mere handful, and the poorest of the
                     poor. Her uncle's creditors did make up a little purse for her, and she came up
                     to London, to the house of an old lady who had been her first governess, and
                     who she found out was living in one of the suburbs; but I suppose religious
                     differences again prevented her receiving the hospitality she had expected from
                     her, for Father Gibson, to whom she had a letter of introduction, appears to be
                     the only friend she has.</p>
                  <p>"And now you know as much of Elinor's story as I do. As for Elinor herself, I
                     hope you may see her some day; and I am sure you will be as much taken as I was
                     with her. First, she is so self-possessed, she is more like forty-one than
                     twenty-one; very gentle, and so dignified, she can awe the wildest of our Irish
                     girls with a look; but she is not always grave, her eyes laugh more than her
                     lips do; and such beautiful eyes!—she would not be pretty, hardly nice-looking
                     even, were it not for her eyes: there is a great deal, too, in her which I
                     cannot describe, and which I am only finding out by degrees. Now do hush, you
                     incorrigible Cecy; I know what you are going to say: that perhaps I shall find
                     out something else by degrees. Well, I will not run on any more about Elinor
                     now, though my husband declares I have fairly lost my heart to her; but come up
                     stairs and see baby,—she will just be waking-up now."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7228-00000007"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
                  <p>ALL this while, quite unconscious that she was the subject of such an animated
                     discussion, Elinor Johnston sat in the shabby backroom of an humble City
                     lodging-house, her fingers busily plying their accustomed task, her brain, no
                     less active, weaving a thousand thoughts and fancies which carried her miles
                     away from the scene of her labours, sometimes to spots which she had formerly
                     looked upon, but far oftener to those which existed only as the creatures of
                     her imagination.</p>
                  <p>Her temperament was by no means however, a dreamy and listless one. It was true
                     she was what is called a self-contained character, and found her chief pleasure
                     in herself and in her own resources; but as soon as her energies were
                     practically required, she would rouse herself to action and put her whole being
                     into whatever was required of her, however simple it might be, and thus succeed
                     in all she undertook.</p>
                  <p>Poor as was her little chamber it was exquisitely neat; and she, its mistress,
                     was no less so. The small hands which provided for all her wants were as white
                     as any lady's in the land; and her dark hair was gathered trimly in shining
                     folds round a well-shaped head. A little crimson bow amongst the black tresses
                     relieved the rather sombre character of the rest of her attire, giving a
                     certain piquancy to the whole, which looked, as people said, rather French, and
                     which Mrs. Atkinson, the landlady, much as she liked her lodger in other
                     respects, hardly knew whether she wholly approved.</p>
                  <p>There was no beauty of feature in the young workwoman, and as Mrs. Forrest had
                     truly said, if it were not for her eyes, she might have been called plain; but
                     somehow or other, there was that in Elinor that made almost every one prefer
                     her to<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7228-00000008"/> far prettier girls. Lucy
                     Atkinson, with her golden curls and red cheeks, in all the bravery of her
                     Sunday attire, crowned by her blue-silk bonnet with its pink roses, was not fit
                     to hold a candle to Miss Johnston. So the lodgers at No. 41 unanimously agreed;
                     and they were people of taste too, who knew what they admired though the
                     reasons for this admiration—not having completed their education at that famous
                     school of art assembling at the Brompton boilers, South Kensington, nor under
                     Mr. Ruskin—remained to them obscured in mystery.</p>
                  <p>The days were only just beginning to lengthen, for it was one of the earliest
                     days of spring; and as the cuckoo-clock on the wall struck six, Elinor folded
                     up her long roll of work—making the sign of the Cross as she did so—and putting
                     on her neat bonnet and shawl, prepared to leave the house. She walked quickly,
                     evidently bent upon some special purpose. She stopped at a second-rate looking
                     house, in a street of the same character, and rang the bell.</p>
                  <p>"Is Mr. Gibson in?" she asked, as an elderly woman opened the door.</p>
                  <p>"He is, to be sure, miss," replied the housekeeper; "but busy over his Sunday
                     sermon; and there's others waiting for him already; but if it's any thing very
                     particular, I daresay he would see you."</p>
                  <p>"It is rather particular, Bridget,—about a sick girl; and I am sure he would
                     see me," answered Elinor quietly; but the words were hardly out of her lips
                     before Bridget, whose weak point was curiosity, began such a loud volley of
                     questions—too eager, however, to wait for any answer—that Mr Gibson the
                     parish-priest came out of his study to see what was the matter.</p>
                  <p>He beckoned Elinor into his sanctum, where piles of books and papers lay in
                     what looked to her inextricable confusion, but which presented no difficulties
                     to their master, who possessed the happy knack of being able to lay his hand
                     upon any required article even in the dark.</p>
                  <p>"Well, my child, what are you so eager about to-night? I thought you were
                     generally very busy on Saturday evenings finishing up your week's work."</p>
                  <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7228-00000009"/>
                  <p>"I got up at six this morning, Father, and have done for the day."</p>
                  <p>"Bravo! and Mrs. Hagan?"</p>
                  <p>"I paid her a visit this morning—at my recreation-time, twelve
                     o'clock.—Father."</p>
                  <p>This was a poor blind woman, whom Mr. Gibson had asked Elinor to visit as often
                     as she could.</p>
                  <p>"And Tom Reilly? But you couldn't have got as far to day."</p>
                  <p>"I did though, after I left Mrs Hagan—for I was glad of a quick walk, for her
                     room is rather close, you know—and he is better. And the two little Byrnes came
                     in to say catechism to me at four o'clock."</p>
                  <p>"Well you seem to have done pretty well to-day; and where do you want to be
                     rambling to this time of night, child?"</p>
                  <p>"There's a girl in my class at the Patronage—Esther Withers—I don't think you
                     know, but she's very ill; dying I believe.</p>
                  <p>She's been in a decline this long while, and she's sent word she wants to see
                     me. And you will go too, will you not,—she is not baptised yet; Father Williams
                     was instructing her before he went away. It's down Star Court, River Lane,—some
                     way off, I fancy; but I thought you could tell me the way."</p>
                  <p>"Star Court, River Lane! no, child, you are not going there to night," said Mr.
                     Gibson slowly, and after pausing for some minutes.</p>
                  <p>"O Father!" cried Elinor. And she could say no more, the tears rising to her
                     eyes; for the message brought her, that the girl was crying her eyes out to see
                     her, had touched her feelings to the quick.</p>
                  <p>"No, you will go home quietly now," continued Mr. Gibson. "You can go into the
                     chapel for a quarter of an hour, if you like, but no longer; you've done enough
                     for to-day. We shall have you falling ill next, as if the parish was not full
                     enough of sick people already. There's no sense in knocking oneself up with
                     over-work."</p>
                  <p>Elinor, who boasted of never having been ill in her life, felt considerably
                     aggrieved by the assumption; and in her own mind wished Mr. Gibson would apply
                     his salutary counsels to himself, for it was well known that the parish-priest
                     of St.<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7228-00000010"/> Mary's was in the habit of
                     working till he dropped, as the coachmen say of their horses, but she confined
                     herself to wishing him good-night; and though she felt a little sore at heart,
                     her face wore its usual composed look, and her eyes only shone the brighter for
                     the slight moisture that dimmed them as she knelt at her evening-prayers before
                     the Lady altar in the quiet chapel to which, in obedience to her pastor's
                     injunction, she had betaken herself on leaving him.</p>
                  <p>"A very sensible girl that, and a good one;" muttered Mr. Gibson to himself;
                     "but she's none the worse of a little cross now and then, and she knows how to
                     take it too." He wrote very fast for some minutes: then having brought his work
                     to a rapid conclusion, by some condensing process with which he alone was
                     acquainted, put on his greatcoat and left the house, calling out to his
                     perturbed housekeeper as he did so, "A sick call, Bridget; I may be kept late;"
                     and took his way, as you will easily guess, in the direction of the
                     above-mentioned Star Court.</p>
                  <p>The next morning, as Elinor was leaving the chapel after the earlinet Mass, a
                     paper was put into her hand by one of the altar-boys. It contained these words
                     in Mr. Gibson's writing: "I saw Esther Withers last night; she was sinking
                     rapidly. I therefore baptised her, and administered the other Sacraments
                     immediately afterwards. She may rally, but only for a short time. Go and see
                     her as soon as you can to-day."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7228-00000011"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
                  <p>ELINOR was hardly surprised at Mr. Gibson's prohibition of the night before
                     when she first entered Star Court. It was one of the lowest spots in a low
                     neighborhood; and it was no pleasant thing to make her way through the idle,
                     squallid-looking crowd, that stood at its entrance, or to displace the more
                     elderly portion of its inhabitants, who for the most part appeared to prefer
                     sitting on the door-steps to pursuing their occupations within.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Withers lived at the very top of one of the most neglected-looking of the
                     houses in the court. Elinor tapped, and was admitted, having to stoop under the
                     line of clothes that were hanging across the room to dry, whilst its mistress
                     stood in the middle up to her elbows in soapsuds, only stopping in her work
                     from time to time to cast an anxious glance upon the sick girl who was propped
                     up in a miserable bed, and breathing with great difficulty. Elinor wondered how
                     any one could have the heart to wash in such a place, and augured rightly from
                     the circumstance that its inhabitants were not born and bred under the usual
                     conditions of their neighbors in Star Court. The woman was old, certainly; but
                     it was not easy to be precise as to her age, for it was sorrow as well as time
                     that had streaked her hair with gray and lined her well-featured face. She
                     looked up, apparently not well pleased to see a stranger.</p>
                  <p>"Who sent you?" she asked sharply, and in a strong north-country accent.
                     "Esther was crying all last night for your Father Gibson, as she calls him, so
                     I just let him come to please her, poor thing? but I did not bargain to have
                     visitors in and out all hours.</p>
                  <p>"Mother, mother!" cried the girl; "don't pray; it's Miss Johnson that teaches
                     at the chapel on Sundays. I have told you about<pb n="22-23"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000012"/> her often;" and her whole face lighted up in a
                     manner that made her naturally plain and haggard countenance almost
                     beautiful.</p>
                  <p>"Well, well, if it's so, she's welcome," said the woman, softening a
                     little.</p>
                  <p>Esther put out her small wasted hand, and drew Elinor eagerly towards her.</p>
                  <p>"If I could talk more, I should have such a great deal to say to you!" she
                     whispered. "I've been thinking—O, doing nothing but thinking these two days
                     past, ever since Friday, when Dr. Pearce told mother I should never be about
                     any more, and she"—indicating her mother by a glance—"doesn't like to hear any
                     thing of that, you know. It's so odd; I don't seem to mind about dying now, and
                     I used to mind awfully—that is, I was frightened—about being put into one of
                     those little graveyards in London, with houses choking it all round, and just
                     one tree in it, withered away, perhaps. But since Father Gibson came last
                     night, I feel different somehow."</p>
                  <p>"He baptised you, did he not, dear Esther?" asked Elinor gently.</p>
                  <p>"Yes; and do you know I think I can never have been baptised before, that is,
                     not properly? They said at the convent that a great many of the Protestant
                     parsons did not do it right; and I asked mother, but she didn't remember one
                     bit; but I feel sure in myself that I was never a Christian before, else why
                     should every thing seem so different now? Can you tell me, Miss Johnson?" and
                     she paused, from weariness of body rather than for lack of words.</p>
                  <p>Elinor soothed her almost silently. She hardly knew how to check the dying
                     girl. She was sure it was not well for her to excite herself thus; but she
                     could not help listening to all she said with interest and curiosity.</p>
                  <p>Esther Withers had had very little education, and no great stock of
                     book-learning; but for all that she possessed some of those elements usually
                     called genius. Being sickly and deformed from an infant, she had never been
                     able to occupy herself actively, and had lived in a world of her own, peopled
                     with her own fancies or<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7228-00000013"/> with those
                     gathered from the few works of fiction—happily for the most part of an innocent
                     nature—that had come in her way. It is said that a drowning man, in the brief
                     moments that elapse before he finally sinks, sees all the events of his past
                     life mirrored before him in perfect order. Something of this kind often seems
                     to occur to other dying persons, although they may lack the power to express
                     their thoughts coherently; and this was now evidently the case with Esther. Her
                     mind first wandered away to the distant farm where she had spent her early
                     childhood; and little by little Elinor learnt her whole history, of which she
                     previously had but a very vague notion, for the girl had formerly appeared
                     exceedingly reserved, and held aloof from all her companions at the Patronage.
                     She had left the country still very young in consequence of her father's death,
                     and had come up to town with her mother and brothers; they had sunk every year
                     deeper and deeper into poverty; one of the brothers had turned out badly, and
                     entailed a worse misfortune than disgrace upon them.</p>
                  <p>"Mother never looked like that till our trouble about Charlie came," whispered
                     Esther, who saw the frown upon the woman's face grow every minute darker and
                     darker as her jealousy of the visitor who seemed to steal all her child's
                     attention from her increased. "Poor Charlie! I recollected to ask Father Gibson
                     about him last night, and he seemed to say he must have gone to Purgatory for
                     certain. I used to feel so miserable about him before; for I never could bear
                     to think he was to be punished for ever and ever, though he did break poor
                     mother's heart and took things that didn't belong to him. It was money—money of
                     his master's," she whispered in a still lower tone.</p>
                  <p>"But just as he was lying dying, as I am doing now, he said: 'O, mother, you
                     don't know how I grieve that I've been so bad a son to you; and you must
                     forgive me, and so must Almighty God.' But I should like to know about Phil
                     also. I wonder if I shall see him too, soon?"</p>
                  <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7228-00000014"/>
                  <p>"Your other brother?—is he dead too?" asked Elinor.</p>
                  <p>"I wish I knew; but I think he must be, else he would have written in all these
                     years he has been away, unless he had grown cruel and forgotten us; but that
                     can't be. Phil was always good. Why, the first thing I can recollect is his
                     swinging me by the great pear tree in our garden as long as I asked him in the
                     mornings; and then in the evenings I used to sit on his knee always as he ate
                     his supper, and he would feed me out of his own spoon, and call me his pussy.
                     Phil went away to get money for us all, he said, when Charlie was steady, to
                     the other side of the world—Australia, they call it,—I've seen it many a time
                     on the maps,—and we never heard from him but once, as I told you. Yes, Phil
                     must be dead too; but then at times I think he's alive yet, and will come home
                     to comfort mother, only that would be too much like a story-book, wouldn't it?
                     But some story-books are true, Miss Johnson. You see poor mother'll be lonesome
                     without me. You'll come and see her sometimes, perhaps?" and the girl looked
                     wistfully into Elinor's face.</p>
                  <p>The woman, who seemed to feel she was the subject of conversation, though
                     Esther spoke in too low a tone for her to hear, came up to the bed-side and sat
                     down beside it, fondling one of the girl's hands. Esther was exhausted with
                     talking, and closed her eyes. Elinor took advantage of the opportunity to put
                     the room into some sort of order. Food and wine had been brought at day-break
                     by Bridget, Mr. Gibson's housekeeper; but they had not been taken out of the
                     basket. Her quick purpose-like movements at last attracted Mrs. Wither's
                     notice, and she exclaimed in a sharp surprised tone:</p>
                  <p>"So you're a working woman after all; I was taking you for a lady all the
                     time!"</p>
                  <p>Elinor looked up from the hearth she was sweeping with an amused glance, though
                     the abrupt obversation had heightened her colour a trifle.</p>
                  <p>"You'r right, Mrs. Withers; I do work for my living."</p>
                  <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7228-00000015"/>
                  <p>"It's odd, though," soliloquised the imperturbable woman. "Her hands are as
                     white as table-linen and as soft as wax, all the while looking as if they could
                     run up and down the piano. I'll be bound they can. O, I've seen a many ladies
                     and their hands too before I was brought down to Star Court."</p>
                  <p>"You're right again, Mrs. Withers; I can play a little; but in France, where I
                     have lived chiefly, even great ladies who have money of their own often do as
                     much as I am doing now every day of their lives."</p>
                  <p>"Only hear, now!" exclaimed the woman, half incredulous but interested; "and I
                     always heard tell before those French were poor helpless bodies, living chiefly
                     upon frogs and such-like."</p>
                  <p>Emboldened by her more accessible manner Elinor, still busied about the room,
                     dropped a few pleasant remarks from time to time; but if she ever as much as
                     hinted at any thing bordering on religion, Mrs. Withers's face assumed its
                     former rigid indifferent aspect, and she relapsed lapsed into silence. Once
                     indeed, when Elinor spoke of the goodness of God, she exclaimed angrily:</p>
                  <p>"I ne'er believe folk when they talk to me like that. The Almighty may have
                     been good to some, I grant; but He's been cruel, dreadful cruel to me. First He
                     took my husband from me, a fine tall man, in the flower of his age, and turned
                     us out of the pleasant farm we'd lived in fifty year—that's to say, my
                     husband's father and his father before him, for the matter of that. I've read
                     of Eve being drove out of the Garden of Eden, and that place was like Eden to
                     me, it was. Then there's my two boys both gone—both; one's in his grave, I
                     know; but where the other lies, whether under the grass or at the bottom of the
                     salt sea, none will ever come to tell me.</p>
                  <p>"But after the troubles of this world there is Heaven waiting for us," said
                     Elinor gently, and almost to herself, "else how could we bear life
                     sometimes?"</p>
                  <p>"Heaven!" continued the other angrily. "I want no better Heaven than the home I
                     was telling you of, where I went when I<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7228-00000016"
                     /> was wed, and where my children were born. I see it all day at my work, and
                     at night in my dreams; and yet, though the sight grieves me sore, it's pretty
                     well all the comfort I have."</p>
                  <p>Elinor desisted with a sigh. For all intents and purposes, this woman, a
                     baptised christian, in a land calling itself radiant with the light of the
                     Gospel, was little better than a pagan: honest, upright in her dealings, it is
                     true; a faithful wife, a loving mother; but as yet living without God in the
                     world.</p>
                  <p>Esther woke only the worse for her feverish slumber, if indeed there was any
                     worse for her now who was so near the better land. She sank gradually
                     throughout the day, not suffering greatly apparently, but too far gone to
                     speak. It was so evident that she liked the little services Elinor was able to
                     render, that even her mother gave way and allowed the stranger to do what she
                     would. Once, while arranging the clothes which covered the sick girl's bed, the
                     hands of both met accidentally, and Esther suddenly extending her own held them
                     together in a convulsive clasp. During the whole of her child's long agony, the
                     mother never lost her composure; she showed not the smallest emotion whilst
                     Elinor recited the touching prayers for the dying, and strove to place the
                     crucifix in Esther's failing grasp.</p>
                  <p>Not even when all was over did she give way; she seemed almost to look upon the
                     tears which fell from Elinor's eyes as the youthful weakness of one
                     unaccustomed to such sorrowful scenes. But every thing was done that could be
                     done for Esther now, and when the pale face that had been for so many hours the
                     only object upon which their anxious looks had been fixed was hidden beneath
                     its white covering in the most remote corner of the room, the mother yielded to
                     a burst of passionate grief which it almost alarmed Elinor to witness. She
                     thought for a moment of going to call some of the lodgers in the house; but
                     Mrs. Withers held her dress in a sort of paroxysm, and she could not release
                     herself without disturbing her.</p>
                  <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7228-00000017"/>
                  <p>It seemed to be hours that the poor creature remained in the same position,
                     sobbing violently at longer and longer intervals, till at length she was
                     thoroughly exhausted and fell asleep. Daylight had long faded when she awoke in
                     a bewilderd state, still too weak to resist Elinor's attempts at feeding and
                     soothing her; indeed she obeyed mechanically like a child.</p>
                  <p>Thus a week passed on: Elinor was obliged to leave Mrs. Withers alone at times
                     to pursue her own avocations, but always returned to her at night, for as
                     little as the poor crerture seemed to notice her, she did not like her to be
                     entirely alone. Mr. Gibson gave directions for the funeral; for it was not till
                     the day of the ceremony itself that she roused herself sufficiently to take any
                     part in what was going on around her. To every one's surprise she was up the
                     first that morning, dressed in faded but respectable black, and joined the
                     melancholy procession to the cemetery with the greatest apparent composure.
                     When all was over, she turned away from the grave, and followed Elinor home
                     without a word. Elinor had been most anxious that she should not return to her
                     solitary room, but had not ventured to mention the subject, and was greatly
                     relieved to find the poor woman had taken the initiative of her own accord. And
                     thus, without one word being said between them, Mrs. Withers became her
                     permanent inmate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7228-00000018"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
                  <p>TIME passed on. Elinor and the widow still shared the same room; they were both
                     absent a great part of the day, laboring literally for their daily bread; for
                     Mrs. Withers was still active, and possessed a naturally good constitution,
                     only slightly impaired by the hardships she had endured; and it was her pride
                     and pleasure to boast that she was able to get her own living yet, without
                     being beholden to any one. Their relations were somewhat peculiar; though Mrs.
                     Withers knew in her secret soul that Elinor was an out-and-out lady, as she
                     would have expressed it, they were now on too familiar terms for her to treat
                     her with the respect really her due; her behaviour towards her was rather that
                     of an affectionate, anxious mother, who, whilst admiring her child in secret,
                     thinks it right to administer reproof and admonition from time to time, and
                     keep up a semblance of authority.</p>
                  <p>Poor Elinor, who had almost forgotten what it was to have a mother, took it all
                     in good part; and indeed she would have borne much more if only she could have
                     made any religious impression upon the unfortunate woman, but that she found
                     impossible.</p>
                  <p>"Do not talk that way to me," she would answer impatiently, "about the will of
                     God! Other people keep their riches why should He take mine from me? Other
                     people keep their children; why should He take mine from me? I've not been more
                     wicked than my neighbours for certain—I that was reckoned the best dairy-woman
                     in the parish, and paid rent and taxes eighteen years or more; and what's more,
                     every Sunday I could be spared from the cows, I was at church with the best of
                        them;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7228-00000019"/> and if that's not being a
                     Christian, I don't know what is."</p>
                  <p>However the winter came and with it fresh troubles. Mrs. Withers fell ill, and
                     was unable to go to work as before; she was no very easy person to nurse, and
                     the additional labour entailed on Elinor was almost more than she could bear.
                     By degrees she slowly recovered, but it was evident that she would never again
                     be as strong as she formerly was, or fit to gain her own living.</p>
                  <p>Mr. Gibson amongst his other numerous and benevolent plans, had always been
                     very desirous that a well-known active religious community should establish
                     themselves in his parish. Amongst their other works of mercy, they devoted
                     themselves especially to the care of the aged and infirm, for whom they had
                     built asylums in various parts of the kingdom. There now seemed a prospect of
                     his wishes being realised; he had already in his mind's eye a long list of his
                     old parishioners who would be fit objects for the good nuns' charity; and
                     amongst others he immediately thought of Mrs. Withers. He broached the subject
                     to Elinor, who shook her head.</p>
                  <p>"It would be the same thing to her as entering the workhouse," she said; "and
                     rather than do that she would lie down and die in the streets."</p>
                  <p>"But she forfeits her independence just as much by living upon your charity, as
                     she does at present," objected the priest.</p>
                  <p>"She does not see it in that light, Father, however; indeed, ever since
                     Esther's death I really believe she has taken to me almost as if I were her own
                     daughter whose duty it was to support her."</p>
                  <p>"It can't go on in this way always, though; it is impossible; you will be
                     knocked up before long with work, or falling into consumption child," Mr.
                     Gibson ended by saying, as he buttoned up his coat, and walked away silenced
                     for the time, but not convinced. He was what is called an eminently practical
                     man, and was not altogether pleased at having his little pet scheme for Mrs.
                     Withers benefit knocked on the head in that way.<pb n="38-39"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000020"/> And Elinor, though she said nothing, would have
                     wished matters could have been ordered otherwise.</p>
                  <p>From the first moment—now nearly two years since—the establishment of the nuns
                     in the parish had been a mooted question, she had hoped and almost resolved to
                     join them. There seemed little prospect of this for the present; and though she
                     paused rather sadly over her sewing for a few minutes, she rose none the less
                     cheerfully than usual when roused by the sound of the poor invalid, feeling
                     that to attend on her was the duty of the hour, and that the future, both as
                     regarded herself and her adopted mother, was in the hands of God.</p>
                  <p>Man proposes and God disposes has been often and truly said.</p>
                  <p>It was about a fortnight later that Mr. Gibson came to Elinor's room, not only
                     in a hurry, that was not at all unusual but with a peculiar air of mystery upon
                     his face. He seemed relieved to find that Mrs. Withers, who had been gradually
                     gaining strength during the past week, had crawled out for a little walk, in
                     the noon-day sun. He entered upon his business immediately, by asking if Mrs.
                     Withers had any relations in Australia. Elinor instantly told him of the
                     long-lost son of whom Esther had spoken on her dying-bed.</p>
                  <p>Then there is no doubt that he is the man! cried Mr. Gibson, striking his hand
                     on a letter he drew out of his pocket. "How extraordinarily things are brought
                     about!" he exclaimed; "to think that a few words of mine about a
                     school-examination should be the cause!" He proceeded to explain that more than
                     two years ago, in writing a letter to his brother, a missionary priest in
                     Sydney, he had been speaking of the progress education was making in England,
                     and mentioned an instance of the cultivation of the memory in children, which
                     he had recently witnessed in his parish. The subject of it was Esther Withers,
                     who before she had joined the Patronage had attended the parish day-school, and
                     won prizes and medals without seeming to try for them, over the heads of<pb
                        n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7228-00000021"/> older and more advanced scholars. He
                     had just added that, though the girl in question was a Protestant, she had also
                     gained a special reward for proficiency in religious knowledge; and had then
                     gone to subjects of more general interest.</p>
                  <p>"It seems" continued Mr. Gibson, "that my brother did not get my letter as soon
                     as he ought to have done; it was forwarded to a post-office some way up the
                     country, where he called on his way home from an expedition he had been making
                     in the neighbourhood of the gold-diggings. He was spending the night at a
                     little roadside inn hard by; and as he was looking over his letters in the
                     public room there, a civil-spoken young man, with whom he had had a little
                     previous conversation, asked him what was the news from England. He said he
                     never had letters himself from home, and that, for that reason any little scrap
                     of information was peculiarly grateful. My brother gave him what little
                     information he thought could entertain a stranger, and they continued talking
                     together in a friendly way; it came out that the young man's name was Withers,
                     and that he was a large sheep-owner in a newly-settled spot at some distance.
                     My brother, who has a ready memory for names, and delights in their study, as
                     most men do in that of facts, remarked that he had just come across that name
                     in one of his letters, and read the few lines in which I mentioned Esther. The
                     young man appeared almost overwhelmed with astonishment when he heard the
                     Christian name, which I had also fortunately mentioned. He told my brother in
                     broken accents that he had left his mother, brother, and sister, in poor
                     circumstances in England, and had not been able to learn what had become of
                     them from the time he landed. He had written repeatedly to the house in London
                     where they had been living, but had had no reply. He feared that they had been
                     obliged to remove, through fresh troubles; at times he dreaded that they might
                     all be dead, and he had several times been on the point of returning to England
                     to look for them; but that until the last year he himself had<pb n="42-43"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000022"/> been in such poor circumstances that he would
                     have proved a burden rather than a help. He begged my brother to write to me at
                     once and inquire further particulars, though the latter warned him not to be
                     too sanguine, nor to rely too strongly upon the fact of the girl's name being
                     the same as his sister's. My brother intended to comply with the young man's
                     request at once, but was seized with a severe illness on his return to Sydney,
                     and was afterwards so overwhelmed with an accumulation of work, that he
                     entirely forgot to do so till the last mail. However, it is better late than
                     never, and I am convinced that the young man is right. Let me see; his name is
                     Philip—Philip Withers, Beaverlands, Tudor's Wood, I think it is; but my good
                     brother's writing is none of the clearest;" and Mr. Gibson held the letter up
                     to the light as he spoke.</p>
                  <p>A scream behind him made him turn. Mrs. Withers entered unperceived, and heard
                     her son's name.</p>
                  <p>"It is news—news from Phil!" she exclaimed; "but perhaps he is dead too like
                     the rest of them;" and she fell fainting on the ground.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
                  <p>ABOUT six months later a light steamer was plying gaily up a broad stream, so
                     wide that it might almost be called an arm of the sea, and rapidly nearing its
                     destination—a collection of white houses, dignified by the name of a town.</p>
                  <p>The little band of passengers, many of whom had patiently borne their long
                     voyage across the Pacific, but who, now that it was nearly over, could restrain
                     themselves no longer as they paced the deck with eager footsteps, gazing on the
                     unknown shore with interest and expectation. A few of them, however, were not
                     quite so animated by their future<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7228-00000023"/>
                     prospects, or concealed their feelings under a more subdued demeanour; and
                     among these were a little band of Sisters of Mercy, an aged woman, and a young
                     one her companion. The good nuns, bending over their office-books in the
                     quietest corner of the vessel, seemed as recollected as if they were in their
                     own convent chapel. The elderly woman, who leant upon her stick, her eyes fixed
                     upon the rapidly-advancing land, was too highly wrought up by repressed emotion
                     for words or action; and the girl at her side was equally tranquil, though from
                     a very different cause. Elinor, for it was no other, had no reason to be
                     otherwise than composed: she had no one to meet or welcome her home on her
                     arrival; her self imposed task would be at an end as soon as the vessel touched
                     the quay, and she would be free and alone in the world as before; though her
                     life had been a training in detachment, she could not repress a momentary sigh
                     at the thought. She belonged neither to the cheerful groups who clustered
                     together, full of plans and projects, within a few steps; nor to the peaceful
                     Sisters who sat together a little farther distant; even the old woman, to whom
                     she had been so long as a daughter clung to her no longer; her whole mind was
                     fixed upon her son, her first born child, who had called to her across the sea,
                     to a home of her own once more. Upon receipt of Mr. Gibson's letter, which also
                     enclosed one for his mother, Philip Withers had answered it immediately by a
                     loving, hearty invitation, urging her to come out and join him at once,
                     enclosing money for the purpose. The poor woman, who had never travelled
                     farther than from her Staffordshire farm to London in her life, was half
                     terrified at the prospect, weakened as she then was by fresh illness, and the
                     excitement produced by the unexpected discovery of her long lost son. Philip
                     spoke of Elinor, thanking her gratefully for her tender care, and never seeming
                     to imagine but that she would accompany his mother and fill the place of the
                     sister he had lost. Elinor saw plainly that Mrs. Withers could<pb n="46-47"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000024"/> never make the voyage alone; and after some
                     deliberation resolved to go with her; if she once saw her safely in her son's
                     hands, she should feel that she needed her no longer, and could either return
                     to England or remain in the colonies, as she judged best at the time. She was
                     not tied to one spot more than another; the Sisters' who were just on the point
                     of arriving in the parish, would amply fill her place there, no doubt; there
                     would be convents in the colonies sorely needing postulants, and where at last
                     she might find rest. Mr. Gibson demurred, but at last consented. Strangely
                     enough, a party of Sisters of Mercy came on board the vessel just at the last
                     moment, some of whom were bound for Sidney itself, whilst a smaller party
                     proceeded with them, on leaving the ship, to a newly settled town some miles up
                     an inland river, where Philip Withers had promised to meet them without fail
                     and convey them safely to his farm. Elinor had already made some acquaintance
                     with the Sisters; they had pressed her to visit their convent on landing and
                     she had promised to do so, if possible.</p>
                  <p>Nearer and nearer the steamer approached the shore; it touched the quay, and
                     was greeted by a shout of welcome from the expectant crowd, who had gathered to
                     welcome the new arrivals. Stalwart men sprang on board with a bound; more timid
                     people nodded smilingly to friends they recognised; all was bustle and
                     animation.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Withers peered anxiously into every new-comer's face; but all seemed
                     strange to her. She and Elinor remained on the deck after every one had
                     disembarked. A middle-aged man in a frieze coat, who had been staring at them
                     in silence for some minutes, approached, and asked in a strong Scotch accent,
                     and in a voice of assertion rather than of question if yon were not one
                     Mistress Withers? He proceeded to explain that his master had sent him in his
                     stead, and that the bullock-cart would take them up to Beaver's Farm as soon as
                     the sun had gone down sufficiently to enable them to<pb n="48-49"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000025"/> bear the journey, and that in the mean while
                     they were to rest and refresh themselves at a little inn within sight, which he
                     pointed out to them. Master had fretted sore, the man said because he could not
                     come himself; but he had given himself an ugly sprain the night before, and
                     could neither drive himself nor bear the jolting of being driven. Poor Mrs.
                     Withers, tired out and disappointed, was near bursting into sobs and
                     lamentations; and Elinor had some difficulty in composing her sufficiently for
                     their short walk to the inn. Once there, however, the weary woman fell into a
                     heavy slumber; and Elinor, knowing that they could not start on their journey
                     for some hours, hurried out to pay her promised visit at the convent. Her
                     former travelling companions greeted her most kindly, showed her over the whole
                     of the building, and introduced her to their reverend mother. The community
                     were very poor, few in number, and the work before them was almost beyond their
                     strength.</p>
                  <p>"We want means sadly; but hands more than money," said one of the elder nuns.
                     We cannot count on postulants from the little congregation here at present. Our
                     novices come from home. But we ought not to complain, with the five recruits of
                     to-day. There is plenty of room for you, you see," she continued, smiling at
                     Elinor, and having no idea that she was likely to take her words seriously to
                     heart.</p>
                  <p>Elinor felt as if she could not speak seriously either just then, so she
                     answered in the same strain:</p>
                  <p>"I am going up the bush, you know, in a couple of hours, Sister; but supposing
                     I do not stop there, I shall know where to come;" and as she left the quiet
                     parlor, something told her that she had not bidden St. Joseph's farewell for
                     ever.</p>
                  <p>Their journey in the bullock-wagon was tedious and without adventure. The moon
                     was high in the heavens when the driver told them they were close to Beaver's
                     Farm, wakening Mrs. Withers from a light doze and Elinor from a fit of
                     meditation as did he so. The light shone<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7228-00000026"
                     /> full upon tall trees, and upon the wide path between them; and an advancing
                     figure—that of a tall young man—walking with some difficulty and leaning upon a
                     stick, was coming towards them as rapidly as he could.</p>
                  <p>"It is master himself," said Alick, their driver—the only one who could find
                     words at such a moment.</p>
                  <p>And after so many years, the mother and son were reunited.</p>
                  <p>A week only had passed since the new inmates had established themselves at
                     Beaver's Farm, and it seemed as if they had been there many years, so easily
                     did they fall into their new mode of life.—Mrs. Withers, after the first
                     excitement was over, almost fancied herself again the mistress of her old home,
                     and gave herself little airs of proprietorship, which would have been amusing
                     to any passive bystander, but which only provoked the scorn and anger of the
                     independent colonial servants, over whom she tried to assert her authority. Her
                     son was all that she could have hoped—affectionate, respectful, and mindful of
                     her smallest wishes; but he was a boy no longer—and here lay the widow's only
                     disappointment, but half confessed even to herself. Phil, who had been the
                     scape-grace of the family, the truant from school, the undaunted bird-nester,
                     who had summed up his wild pranks by flying off to the other side of the
                     world—which was the only name given to Australia by his country neighbours—was
                     now a self-reliant and reflective man, whose powers of mind and body had been
                     developed by circumstances. He wanted polish, certainly, but no other quality
                     to fit him for the position he occupied as a thriving wealthy settler. He was
                     known and respected for miles round, from the poor aborigines who came begging
                     to the farm in the cold season to the local magnates who directed the affairs
                     of the colony. If Mrs. Withers felt that her son was no longer the boy who had
                     left her, he on his part found that there was an alteration in her. It was
                     rather that their mutual relations were changed than any thing else. She leant
                     upon him now for protection and<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7228-00000027"/>
                     support; and if she scolded him, it was in the half querulous, half
                     affectionate way in which the aged are prone to address the young, not like the
                     mother whose word was law, and who ruled the little farm with undisputed sway.
                     She could be no companion to him, now her advice or opinion was of no service,
                     but a frail ailing creature, to be gently tended as she gradually declined
                     towards the grave. But Philip was less puzzled by the change in his mother,
                     which was only what a thoughtful person might have naturally expected, than by
                     the companion she brought with her. He had pictured to himself a rough
                     warm-hearted Irish girl, who had taken compassion on the loneliness of the
                     widowed woman, and worked for her as if she had been a parent of her own. He
                     fully intended to act a brother's part towards her. But he had made up his mind
                     that they would not keep her long to themselves—a steady industrious girl is
                     the true nugget of the working-man of Australia, and this good little damsel
                     might have her pick amongst the shepherds and sheep-owners too for miles round.
                     He actually started when he first saw Elinor, and could scarcely believe for a
                     while that she was the young friend of whom his mother had spoken so
                     gratefully. At first he was susceptible of a slight shade of disappointment; a
                     rosy bright-eyed Kathleen or Nora running about the place would have been a
                     pleasant and unusual sight, and here was instead a slight pale girl, as neat as
                     if she had come out of a bandbox, and as quiet and refined as the governor's
                     daughter herself. First he was piqued by what he chose to consider her pride or
                     indifference to his hearty brotherly welcome, and resolved to leave her alone
                     and let her come out of her shell by degrees. Elinor was what is usually called
                     a self-contained character, and at the present time was too much ocupied by her
                     own future to pay much attention to what was going on around her. Beaver's Farm
                     was nothing to her; she was seated in spirit in the novitiate of the convent,
                     or walking through the wards of the attached hospital or the workrooms of the
                     House of Mercy.<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7228-00000028"/> She was almost sorry
                     she had come up the country at all. She should only find it the more difficult
                     to return; for she knew that Mrs. Withers would not part from her without a
                     good deal of noisy vehemence, particularly when she knew of her intention; and
                     long farewells of any kind are always painful. Then the calm peacefulness of
                     all around stole insensibly upon her, and she lingered day after day, as the
                     traveller does after a long journey through a bare desert by some green spot
                     before tempting the strange lands, beautiful though they may be, that lie
                     beyond. Philip Withers by this time had recovered his fit of pique, and was
                     becoming interested. From interest the step is not a wide one to admiration;
                     and he was not long contented even with admiration. The secret of his success
                     had lain in the strength of his will. If he set his heart upon an object, he
                     would obtain it, let it cost him what it may; and now as it gradually dawned
                     upon him that there was one prize that he coveted more than any thing he had
                     ever coveted yet, he bent all his powers to the consideration of how best to
                     gain possession of it. He felt that he must not be too hasty—that the prize was
                     too precious to be won easily; and a strange and very unusual diffidence crept
                     over him, rendering the plain-spoken cheery fellow as awkward and sheepish as
                     an untrained schoolboy. Then there was an impatient phase. He could not bear
                     suspense without one word of sympathy or encouragement from any one. One of two
                     things he must do—go away from home for a little while and work off his
                     restlessness, or speak at once, and perhaps lose the game by his
                     abruptness.</p>
                  <p>One bright afternoon, when the heat of the day was gradually subsiding, Mrs.
                     Withers had brought her chair to the house-door to enjoy the breeze that was
                     springing up, and gazed with excusable pride upon the undulating slopes only
                     half cleared of the trees that a few years ago had covered them, and every rood
                     and acre of which she knew belonged to her son. Elinor was within, near enough
                     for speech, if either were so inclined; but<pb n="56-57"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000029"/> both appeared to prefer their own thoughts. At
                     length Philip's heavy tread broke the silence, as he toiled up the steep path
                     and threw himself down, panting for breath. by his mother's side. She hardly
                     heeded him, for she was making a short sharp answer to something Elinor had
                     said in a low voice, as she left the keeping-room for her own as soon as she
                     found Mrs. Withers would not be left alone.</p>
                  <p>"What is it mother?" asked her son soothingly, for he saw that she was ruffled
                     for some reason or other.</p>
                  <p>"Naught, lad, naught, she answered querulously. "It's but that silly girl, who
                     wants to vex me by talking of going off to yonder port—what is it that they
                     call it?—as if she were not to stop along with us. Why, you said so yourself,
                     Phil, and you'd not be breaking your word. What ever should I do without her?
                     But it's pride, Phil, pride; and I've no patience with it. She don't like to be
                     beholden to us, that's it. She'd rather starve on a crust than live in plenty;
                     and she that calls herself a good christian too!"</p>
                  <p>"But she does not mean it, you think, mother?" said Philip, looking up so
                     grieved and alarmed that his mother, though guessing nothing of the cause, gave
                     way still further to her irritation.</p>
                  <p>"In course she don't mean it. What ever would she do down there alone without a
                     penny to bless herself with? But it's just to show that she thinks herself
                     above us, as if dressmaking and governessing were better than ploughing and
                     sowing; and as for her folk, she's nothing to boast of in them that I can make
                     out. She'd an uncle who took himself off with her fortune somewhere in the
                     North, I heard say—one of the mushroom sort, who made money in the
                     spinning-jenny way—manufacturers they call them—people who are here to-day and
                     gone to-morrow; and to hold her head so high indeed for all that! Why, we
                     Withers have been known, son and father before him, right back three hundred
                     year on the Chase at home, I heard our parson say. I can count on my fingers
                     myself—"</p>
                  <p>"Never mind that now, mother," said<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7228-00000030"/>
                     Philip impatiently, laying his hand on her arm. "You have no reason, I am sure,
                     to call her proud. You would not be here now if it were not for her. I always
                     heard women loved to pick each other to pieces behind their backs, though I
                     didn't think you would do it."</p>
                  <p>"You are main sharp upon me, lad," said Mrs. Withers, looking at him earnestly;
                     "but I was in the wrong, I take it, and spoke hasty like. It's because I love
                     the lass so well—and good cause have I to do so—that I can't bear to hear a
                     word of our parting. But I feared she might not be easy to stop along with us;
                     for she's a spirit of her own, has Elinor, and ways of her own too, that I
                     never could justly fathom, though I have reared young ones myself."</p>
                  <p>Philip was silent for a few moments, looking fixedly before him with knitted
                     brows. When he spoke it was with an effort.</p>
                  <p>"There is <emph>one</emph> way in which she could stop with us for ever,
                     mother; but only one that I can see, feeling as she does; but whether she will
                     or not—"Phil stopped suddenly; then asked abruptly, "You would like to see me
                     married, mother? I know you would, for you said so the first evening you
                     came."</p>
                  <p>"Yes, yes, my lad, I said so," she answered quickly, with only a dim perception
                     of his meaning; "and so I do again, though the wife turns the mother out. It's
                     the way of the world, and the will of God, and I'd never go against it. Only
                     you must look well before you leap, Phil; the bones you break in that fall can
                     never be mended again." She scanned his face with renewed anxiety.</p>
                  <p>"I never saw but one woman I could fancy," said Philip gravely, "and you know
                     her better than I do—Elinor. But would she ever fancy me, mother, think you?
                     She's not like one of us."</p>
                  <p>A momentary doubt struck across Mrs. Withers' heart; but joy would not let her
                     give it entrance there.</p>
                  <p>"Not fancy you, my lad? she must be a queer one to please then. Handsome, rich,
                     good"—she paused between each<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7228-00000031"/>
                     adjective; then she continued after a few instants' reflection: "I'll not
                     deceive you, Phil. I said before, Ellie" (her pet name for Elinor) "had ways of
                     her own, and she'll be shy with you at first maybe; but this I tell ye, she'd
                     never fancied any one else; and I must know, living night and day with her a
                     twelvemonth and more.</p>
                  <p>Why, bless you, in London there away there was no one fit to hold a candle to
                     her. So all the spare time she had, she'd naught to turn to but praying,
                     church-going, tending sick folk and the like—all very comforting, they say, to
                     those that are getting into years, but not to a lass such as she, with her
                     bright eyes, bless her!"</p>
                  <p>Philip was inexpressibly relieved by this opinion of his mother's; he thought
                     it probable that Elinor's distant abstracted manner was due to some
                     preoccupation that must at once prove a barrier to his rising hopes, but he was
                     still far from sanguine, and almost vexed that he had spoken so soon. It was
                     just at this juncture that the unconscious subject of their conversation
                     entered: her eyes sparkled with unusual animation, a faint smile played about
                     her mouth; it was because her mind was made up, her resolution taken. She knelt
                     down by Mrs. Witheres's side and took her hand caressingly.</p>
                  <p>"I have something to say to you, dear mother," she said; and the old woman
                     smoothed her hair with a fondness which she did not often show.</p>
                  <p>"I'll listen and welcome, Ellie, so long as it's nothing more about going away.
                     I was angered as it just now, but you'll forget all about it and stay with
                     us."</p>
                  <p>Elinor shook her head; she could not find voice to speak for a moment, and then
                     all she could say was: "I have stayed too long already. I must go."</p>
                  <p>"Nonsense, girl—girl, nonsense!" cried Mrs. Withers, grasping the hand she held
                     still tighter, and, seizing that of Philip, who stood close by confused and
                     irresolute, would have joined them in her own; but her son snatched his away,
                     and stood with folded arms leaning on the back of the chair. Displeased as he
                     was at her abruptness, he listened with impatience to the torrent she poured
                     forth.</p>
                  <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7228-00000032"/>
                  <p>The poor woman grew more earnest as she continued: "You will be my child then,
                     really, Ellie, and Philip's wife: he is vexed with me for speaking, though I
                     could not help it when you spoke of going away again just now. He would do it
                     much better than I, for all he stands there so red and shame-faced; but it's
                     just as it was when he was a boy—his mother must get him whatever he wanted,
                     even if it was the moon out of the sky. You're startled, child, and no wonder;
                     but you'll turn it over in your mind till you get used to the notion, and Phil
                     will speak to you himself—only you'll talk no more about going away; for you
                     see now there's two that cannot spare you,—both mother and son."</p>
                  <p>Philip watched Elinor's face. It was a shade paler than usual, and her eyes
                     wore a startled, surprised look, but that was all.</p>
                  <p>His heart sank within him.</p>
                  <p>Elinor rose at last. "Dear Mrs. Withers," she said gently and slowly, "I am
                     going to join the Sisters with whom we made the voyage. I almost thought you
                     might have guessed it."</p>
                  <p>"You're going to join the Sisters' girl!" cried Mrs. Withers. "I'll not say a
                     word against them, for they were good creatures as ever was, though they look
                     as if they lived on nothing but fish, and milk, and water; and huddle
                     themselves up in those fearful black trailing gowns till they are a sight to be
                     seen. They must have a hard life in the world to bury themselves like that, to
                     my fancy; but for you that's got a good home, and a good husband already to
                     your hand, it's just folly. What ever can you want to go for?"</p>
                  <p>Elinor felt in no mood for a discussion upon the counsels, so she only ventured
                     to say; "Dear Mrs. Withers, our religions are not alike, but you know that we
                     are bound to serve God above every thing." But her remark only made the other
                     more angry.</p>
                  <p>"As if you could not serve God well enough, here child! I have prayed more in
                     my farm yard than ever I did in a church. How is the poultry to be reared, let
                     alone the calves and such-like, unless there's a blessing on them? And then<pb
                        n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7228-00000033"/> as to giving thanks to the Lord,
                     looking on one's own green fields is enough to make one repeat over and over
                     again, as they do in the Psalm, 'Bless Him and magnify Him for ever.' But you
                     are too fine for us, that's it. Well, well, you'll find your pride taken down
                     perhaps over yonder.—Phil, why dont you speak lad? can't you say any thing to
                     her?" and she turned towards her son.</p>
                  <p>He had gone a little way off, and was leaning against the mantel-piece gazing
                     sadly at them both. He had grown almost as pale as Elinor herself, and his lips
                     were quivering, for he unlike his mother, recognized at once the utter
                     hopelessness of the case. He understood nothing of Elinor's motives; but he
                     felt that they were not to be combated—that they lay in a region which to him
                     was unknown, and for which, even amidst his pain, he was sensible of
                     admiration.</p>
                  <p>Elinor, though she never lost her outward calmness, suffered also. She could
                     not but be touched by Mrs. Withers's passionate pleading, to which she listened
                     in silence, her eyes fixed on the beautiful peaceful landscape before her; it
                     looked so home-like that the thought of leaving it affected her as it had never
                     done before and she had so long pined for a home. Her will was firm, perfectly
                     firm; her emotions alone were stirred. Fortunately for her she had no idea of
                     the pain she had caused to Philip Withers; she believed his offer had
                     originated in generous compassion rather than in affection, and was made to
                     gratify his mother rather than himself. It was of no use to prolong such a
                     painful scene, and Elinor retired from it as soon as she was able, fully
                     resolved that it should not be renewed.</p>
                  <p>It was growing late in the evening; she put her few personal possessions
                     together, wrote a few words of farewell to leave behind her, and made the best
                     of her way out of the house.</p>
                  <p>At a little distance, near some of the farm-buildings, stood the bullocks's
                     cart, which the shepherd Alick was loading with country produce, and just on
                     the point of starting for the town, as during the hot<pb n="66-67"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000034"/> season it was customary to make the journey by
                     night, so as to arrive in time for the early morning.</p>
                  <p>"You can take me with you, Alick, can you?" she asked anxiously as she
                     approached. Alick was too genuine a Scotchman to answer otherwise than by
                     another question.</p>
                  <p>"And what for will you be going down to the town this time o' night then?"</p>
                  <p>But it soon appeared that she could accompany him well enough if she did not
                     mind "the when bundles" which were stowed inside; and Alick, after he had
                     asserted his nationality by one indirect question, did not possess sufficient
                     curiosity to pursue the subject further. A few minutes more and Elinor had left
                     Beaver's Farm for ever; and she felt that a new chapter in her life's history
                     was about to begin.</p>
                  <p>Elinor was warmly welcomed at the convent; and the Reverend Mother in
                     particular, who had been greatly pleased with her at her first interview,
                     expressed her hearty satisfaction. She had entertained fears that the young
                     postulant might not return to them, though she was far from guessing the
                     inducements which had been held out to her during her short absence. The more
                     the community saw of Elinor the better was she liked, or rather the more highly
                     was she appreciated; and they had rendered full justice to the nobility of her
                     character long before the arrival of a letter from Mr. Gibson, which showed the
                     estimation in which he held her. It was unanimously resolved that Elinor should
                     be admitted as a choir-sister; and she was clothed as a novice in the shortest
                     time allowed by the rule of the Order.</p>
                  <p>There is no need to write a history of the novitiate, nor of its trials, its
                     joys, and its sorrows. Elinor passed through her full share of them all; for in
                     spite of the self-control she had so long labored to acquire, her nature was
                     sensitive to a fault. But through it all grace was triumphant, and her vocation
                     confirmed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7228-00000035"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
                  <p>ELINOR had been more than two years at the convent without hearing anything
                     from Beaver Farm. She had written just before her clothing came and again some
                     months afterwards; but as no notice was taken of either letter, she was forced
                     to conclude that her former friends there had either forgotten her or were
                     still displeased at the step she had taken.</p>
                  <p>It was on a fine summer day, only a few days previous to the retreat that she
                     and two other novices were to make preparatory to their profession, that Sister
                     Mary Agnes, as Elinor was now called, was summoned into the parlor from a game
                     of play, over which she was half presiding and half joining, in the piece of
                     ground given up to the school children's use at recreation. The exercise had
                     raised her colour and brought out one of her sweetest expressions, whilst the
                     pure white veil and long trailing habit added to the dignity of her appearance;
                     so that it was no wonder that her unexpected visitor was at first so struck by
                     the happiness which beamed in every feature and the general gracefulness of her
                     bearing that she was unable to say a word. Sister Mary Agnes also, although she
                     recognised the stranger directly, was surprised by the alteration she saw in
                     her. Mrs. Withers for it was she herself—was now so plump, cheerful-looking,
                     and well-dressed that she really seemed a dozen years younger. At her feet
                     stood a basket almost as large as herself, and so full that the lid could
                     hardly be kept shut, but revealed from time to time the treasures within. Her
                     first words were characteristic.</p>
                  <p>"Why, it's never you, Elinor; looking so plump and hearty, too, I can scarce
                     believe my eyes. No need for me to bring this large hamper for fear you should
                        be<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7228-00000036"/> starving for want of food. They
                     give you something better than salt fish and dry bread, I reckon; and you're
                     not kept psalm-singing all day either. I heard children laughing and jumping
                     about as I was waiting here, and your voice too as merry as theirs, and I said
                     to myself, 'She's got the young ones round her; I do believe she's all right
                     after all.' And that nice good-natured creature that showed me in said, 'It's
                     our little orphans at play in the garden;' and then I bethought me of the
                     plum-cake at the bottom of the basket, and hoped it was big enough for a slice
                     for them all."</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Withers was in such spirits that she would hardly let Sister Mary Agnes
                     speak; and as soon as Philip's name was mentioned burst at once into the whole
                     history—which, indeed, she had come chiefly to impart.</p>
                  <p>"I'll not go back to your going away now, because it's no good crying for spilt
                     milk: but I was vexed sorely, I'll not deny. I had only just looked at both
                     your letters and flung them on the fire, spite of all Phil could say; but I
                     could not bide seeing him go about so sad and sorrowful-like, besides missing
                     you sore, as I did every day. Then there was some new folk, the Gahans, came to
                     live beside us and I was glad for the boy's sake. He was always one for
                     neighbours, and he was always going in to help them settle, he said. The old
                     man, he said, was such a sensible sort of a fellow, and had been a sailor long
                     ago and sailed round the world. But, dear me, he'd little notion of managing a
                     farm, and he was in grief about a son too that was drowned out fishing just in
                     sight of them all at home; and that's why he'd come out to a new country—he
                     could'nt bear the sight of the old place afterwards, he said. So I thought it
                     was but kind in Phil to go in as often as he could. Thinks I, he will cheer the
                     poor man up a bit; and dear me! I never found out there was a Miss Katie Gahan
                     to be cheered up too till the wedding-ring was bought and everything settled
                     between them. I was in a passion then for certain; and scolded Phil for<pb
                        n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7228-00000037"/> a changeable weather-cock; and
                     wondered how he could choose a girl that was not fit to be spoke of in the same
                     hour with you after all. Then he lost patience, and said that what I said was
                     true enough, that you were too much above him altogether,—not too genteel
                     exactly, but a sort of statue like, or an angel, I forget which; but young men,
                     do have strange ways of talking you know. Then he said what was the use of his
                     wasting his life away, caring for one that never could fancy him, let alone her
                     being a nun and shut up for all the days of her life, Dear me! I am sorry now
                     for the life I led poor Katie that first summer she was married. She had a
                     spirit of her own too, and her eyes would light up and she would bite her lips;
                     but she never answered me back, never. She is a real good girl, that she is,
                     and a God-fearing one too—one of your sort—a Catholic, I mean; and often after
                     I rated her she would start off to the little church—we've a wooden one now
                     about a mile away only, since all these new settlers came— and come back
                     looking quite pleasant and cheerful. 'Mother' she would say, 'I vexed you a
                     while ago, didn't I? I'm sorry for that; let's see what I can do to help you.'
                     But I never took to her properly, poor dear, till her twins were born. She was
                     ill a long time, and the little things like to die; and I don't believe they'd
                     either of them be here now if I hadn't been beside them. One always gets to
                     love the folk one tends in sickness; and I don't know which I love best now,
                     Katie or the babies, bless their little hearts! They are boy and girl; as like
                     as two peas, Charles and Elinor. Phil, he did want you to stand for them; but
                     Katie, who knows about it, said as how you could'nt being a nun. So he was
                     forced to be content with giving the little lass your name; and the mother was
                     as pleased as he was with it; for, dear, she's heard us talk of you very often.
                     And she sent you a cheese she would make all herself, and a very particular
                     message,—her affectionate respects, I think it was; and you was to pray for her
                     and the little ones—<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7228-00000038"/> Catholics do set
                     store upon people's prayers, you know, above every thing. I reckon you've been
                     praying for Phil and me pretty often already.</p>
                  <p>"Well, I knew you had, so you needn't stop me to tell me so; and what do you
                     think has come of it? Why, Phil has turned these eight months and more. 'The
                     two best women I ever saw are Catholics, and I'll just take to their religion
                     for that reason,' says he. 'I've clean forgotten all I ever learnt at home; and
                     at nine and twenty a man need settle down to something, if it was only to teach
                     his children.' And now he goes on preaching as well as the priest about it all,
                     saying how beautiful it all is, and how true; and now all he is sorry for is
                     that he never learned it sooner; but that's not all. Why, what between Phil and
                     Katie, and you above all, I'm turning too. It's hard to have to go over one's
                     catechism, as one may say, at sixty years of age; and I'm a trial of patience
                     to that poor Father Donovan, there's no doubt. But it would never do for our
                     twins to look down on their granny as if she were a heathen,—and, deary me, I
                     was nothing better pretty well all my life,—staring at me across the table like
                     little Polly Gahan, because I can't bless myself, as they call it. It's a deal
                     easier to serve God when one's happy than in trouble,—at least for them that
                     don't set up to be so particular good; and if any one on earth is bound to turn
                     to God it must be me for certain; for has He not given me back pretty well all
                     He took away from me—a good home, riches and plenty, and even children—in place
                     of those I was grieving for?" and here the good woman stopped, not for want of
                     words, but for want of power to express her feelings.</p>
                  <p>How Sister Mary Agnes rejoiced over the tale she had heard, it is equally
                     impossible to relate. Mrs. Withers promised before parting, if she could
                     possibly be spared, to come down again for Elinor's profession, and also held
                     out hopes that perhaps during the course of the summer her daughter-in-law, and
                     even the little ones, might pay a visit to the convent,<pb n="76-77"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000039"/> evidently considering that the sight of the
                     twins must infallibly give all beholders the highest amount of gratification
                     that human nature could receive.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
                  <p>FEW events occurred after Sister Mary Agnes's profession to diversify the
                     ordinary routine of her conventual life. The population of the town increased,
                     and with it the number of those requiring aid from the community. The Reverend
                     Mother often longed for a house made of Indian-rubber, or of some equally
                     expansive material, to accommodate the hundreds of poor emigrant girls who
                     arrived amongst them friendless and forlorn. But every year land became dearer,
                     and the funds of the community more scanty; so that there seemed little
                     prospect of her being able to add to the building as she wished.</p>
                  <p>One winters' evening Sister Mary Agnes<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7228-00000040"/>
                     was called from recreation by one of the lay sisters, whose place she was to
                     take in the infirmary adjoining the convent; a portion of which was placed
                     under the care of the Sisters.</p>
                  <p>"It is the poor old man in Number 16," said Sister Bridget, a novice born and
                     bred in the colony—"that was knocked down and half murdered somewhere up the
                     country last week. He rambles strangely at times, and is always talking of his
                     home in England, and questioning one about it; and Reverend Mother said she
                     thought you knew the part he came from, and had better go instead of me."</p>
                  <p>Sister Mary Agnes obeyed at once. Her patient's head and face had been greatly
                     disfigured by the injuries he had received; but as she moved the cloths that
                     covered them to moisten them as he required, she felt almost certain that she
                     had seen him before; but the single lamp in the ward burnt so dimly that she
                     was not able to distinguish any thing clearly. She had no idea that he on his
                     side was examining her keenly from beneath his half. closed eyelids; and it was
                     no small trial to her self-command, when he sprung up suddenly, turning full
                     upon her his bruised and swollen face, over which fell a mass of gray hair and
                     beard, and seized her tightly by the wrist, whilst he looked her through and
                     through as if struck by some sudden fancy. She tried to quiet him, and
                     succeeded in making him lie down again; but he still retained his hold upon
                     her.</p>
                  <p>"You are a Sister of Charity, are you not?" he said at last, very slowly and as
                     if puzzled.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, you see my beads, do you not? at least you must feel them, for they are
                     in your hand now," replied Sister Mary Agnes, trying to release herself as
                     quietly as she could.</p>
                  <p>"Then why do you look like Elinor,—Elinor Johnston?" he continued with more
                     vehemence. "Have you come to torment me before the time? Who said that?" he
                     asked sharply; "it is in the Scriptures, I know. Once I could find chapter and
                     verse for every thing,<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7228-00000041"/> and I could say
                     them off by heart too; but my head is mazed, and then you see I am not
                     altogether easy in my mind, and one doesn't care to remember those sort of
                     things then. There's such warnings and threats, and so much against loving
                     money and about the Almighty's hating injustice—not that I cared about money so
                     long as I could pay my way—that was all; and there's no one living who dares
                     say I did him wrong,—no one." Here he changed his rambling tone into a louder
                     one, and struck his hand with force upon the bedclothes as he repeated his last
                     words, "There's no one living, I say, who dares say I did him wrong. There
                        <emph>was</emph> Elinor Johnston to be sure;" and he again sank his voice
                     almost to a whisper. "She might think I had not done well by her, though I
                     meant it for the best—I did indeed; and she's not alive, she can't be, else why
                     should she come and look at me, as she does now, with her great eyes and pale
                     face?"</p>
                  <p>At first Sister Mary Agnes was so confused by hearing her own name so
                     unexpectedly, that she could scarcely collect her scattered thoughts; but as
                     her patient continued, the whole truth flashed upon her at once. The
                     unfortunate man could be no other than the uncle who had so cruelly defrauded
                     her of her inheritance years ago, and still more cruelly fled to a distant
                     country, leaving her destitute and alone. She commanded herself sufficiently to
                     beg him smilingly not to be frightened at her strange dress. People often were,
                     she said, who were not used to seeing nuns; but he would soon find out that she
                     did not wish to hurt him, but had come to take as much care of him as she
                     could. When he was a little more composed, she ventured to say, that while
                     threats and warnings were reserved for the impenitent sinner, Almighty God
                     loved rather to call His children back to Him with words of hope and
                     tenderness. "See," she said, pointing to the crucifix hanging over the bed,
                     "how He died for our love, that we might live for ever; how good He has been to
                     each of us, to you and to me. He watched over you the other day, and kept<pb
                        n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7228-00000042"/> you alive that you might make your
                     peace with Him, if you have not done so. There are no sins so black that He
                     cannot blot out, if we seek Him with true contrition in a good confession."</p>
                  <p>"Confession! that's what Catholics are always talking about," cried the old man
                     suddenly; "and you see I'm not a Catholic; but—I don't know—there is one
                     matter, only one, mind you, that perhaps it might do me good to confess; that
                     is, to the person—Elinor, I mean—you're so like her I am half for telling you
                     instead, sister." Then he seemed to recollect himself. "I'm talking nonsense
                     to-night," he continued apologetically; "you must not believe what I say; I was
                     always an upright, God-fearing man. We are all sinners of course; but I was
                     better, a deal better, than most of my neighbours. I worked early and late. I
                     never cared to go pleasure-hunting, not even when I was a boy. No, no; I read
                     my Bible; I went to Church Sundays; I gave away in charity; and what man in
                     England could do more?"</p>
                  <p>Overcome by so much talking he fell back exhausted, and just then the doctor
                     entered the ward to give his last directions for the night.</p>
                  <p>"It's a serious case, that Number 16, sister," said Dr. Y. aside. "The injuries
                     are very extensive, and the whole system has received a severe shock; he's an
                     old man, and pretty nearly worn out; I doubt if he'll get round very much;
                     rambles a good deal, and talks strangely; that's likely; it wont hurt him one
                     way or the other; perhaps he'll tire himself out, and get a little sleep, and
                     that will be the best thing he can do. But anyhow, I don't think he can get
                     around; so you may let him do what he likes, and take what he fancies;" and
                     with these words the physician summarily dismissed case Number 16 from his
                     mind, and turned his whole attention to the next in rotation.</p>
                  <p>The ward was quiet for the night, and for some time Sister Mary Agnes believed
                     her patient was asleep, so still did he lie. She sat by his side as motionless
                     as himself, fearing to rouse him from slumber,<pb n="84-85"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000043"/> till at last, finding he required no further
                     attention, she began to say her rosary, and had nearly finished, when he turned
                     around almost as suddenly as he had done before, and thus addressed her;</p>
                  <p>"I heard what that doctor said a while since; my ears are sharp enough yet,
                     though may be I <emph>am</emph> old and worn out. He said I shouldn't get
                     round; he's right enough there; and I'm not sorry—I would not like to go over
                     it all again. It's strange when one feels as I do, that the life is all leaving
                     you, as quietly as the moments pass one, and just as fast. I have been ill
                     before now, but never like this. I seem to see all the places I have ever been
                     in, and pretty nigh all the people I ever knew; the little cottage where I
                     lived with my father and mother, and the common where I used to play with my
                     brother Joe, Elinor's father that was; then there's the office where we used to
                     work—good industrious lads old Thompson used to call us; but I was the smartest
                     though, and the first to get rich. Well it would be all pleasant enough, but
                     for the one thing that troubles me yet. I said it was nothing at all a while
                     ago, but it's come back again now the room's got darker. Sister,—but I can't
                     call you sister; you're Elinor for certain; don't I know that girl's face as
                     well as my own?—say you're Elinor; and I'll go on." And he looked at her
                     intently.</p>
                  <p>Sister Mary Agnes bowed her head in assent; she could do no less, but she could
                     do no more; for she feared fresh excitement for the sick man, and besides
                     hardly knew how best to address him.</p>
                  <p>"About that money of yours, Elinor," he continued, pausing for breath; "I did
                     not mean to take it from you, only to use it for a little while. I was never
                     happy after I touched it; those verses used to ring in my ears night and day,
                     night and day. Then, when the crash came, and I ran away from England, I was
                     more frightened of you than of any one else. I used to see you in my dreams
                     holding out your arms to me and asking for your money; you were white and thin,
                     looking as if you were working hard and half starved.<pb n="86-87"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000044"/> O! I could not bear the sight. And you did work
                     hard and were nearly starved—I see it in your face," he repeated so earnestly
                     that Sister Mary Agnes felt obliged to answer in a clear sweet voice only
                     slightly tremulous from agitation:</p>
                  <p>No, dear uncle, I did not suffer as you suppose. When I was forced to labor,
                     God made it sweet to me, gave me kind friends; I told you before how good He is
                     to us all—to you and to me. He has brought me out of a dangerous deceitful
                     world—"</p>
                  <p>"Then you are dead after all," muttered the sick man.</p>
                  <p>"And placed me where He would have me serve Him for the remainder of my life,"
                     continued the nun; "serving Him in the person of the poor, the sick and the
                     afflicted till that happy time when I shall see Him as He is."</p>
                  <p>"You must be rich to do all that; but you don't look as if you were either."
                     And the uncle looked at his niece's coarse habit inquisitively.</p>
                  <p>"Uncle, I have never known what it was to be rich thank God; and now I have
                     nothing of my own. The community to which I belong is very poor also; and our
                     only sorrow is, we cannot help those who come to us in distress as abundantly
                     as we would wish to do."</p>
                  <p>"You do not want money for yourself then I suppose? Can you say that you
                     forgive me from the bottom of your heart? I am getting tired, but I won't get
                     to sleep unless you say that to me," said the sick man speaking more calmly and
                     rationally than he had hitherto done.</p>
                  <p>From the very bottom of my heart I forgive you," answered the nun gently; "do
                     not ask pardon of me, a sinner like yourself, but of—"</p>
                  <p>"True, true," interrupted her uncle; "but there is something else to be done
                     first. Come close; feel underneath the pillow; there is a belt there. I wore it
                     tied round my waist those villains could not get it from me; you can have it.
                     Now you know where it is. You must give me a piece of paper, and let me sit up
                     to write; I can do it quite well. Did you not hear the doctor say I was to
                        do<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7228-00000045"/> what I liked? Make haste—make
                     haste!"</p>
                  <p>Sister Mary Agnes thought it best to comply. She was glad to find that he was
                     quite satisfied with writing two or three lines in pencil, which he gave her to
                     keep for him till the morning as he said.</p>
                  <p>He was evidently fatigued by the exertion, and took a little nourishment
                     passively, but with evident relish. He lay quite still for some little time
                     afterwards; then he said,</p>
                  <p>"I can ask the Lord's forgiveness now I didn't dare before. I was none of your
                     hypocrites; but I can't think of the words just now. Can you Elinor?"</p>
                  <p>"Will you say these after me, uncle?" said Sister Mary Agnes eagerly; and she
                     began the act of contrition. He repeated it slowly and earnstly, each clause
                     two or three times over. "And now," said his niece, "dear uncle you must say
                     one little prayer more, an act of love to that God who is so good to us." She
                     commenced, but he paused at the words, "I love Thee above all things."</p>
                  <p>"No, no; that is not true. I never loved God above all things, and I cannot
                     now."</p>
                  <p>"What! will you not say that—thanks to Him—you are lying there so peacefully?"
                     pleaded the nun.</p>
                  <p>"Yes I ought to say it," said the sick man at length, thoughtfully; "for it is
                     God who makes me lie so easy now, and who has taken away that heavy weight from
                     my heart."</p>
                  <p>His voice turned very faint, but he was able to follow the short and simple
                     words she suggested to the end. At the conclusion he turned quietly upon his
                     pillow, and appeared to fall asleep as tranquilly as an infant. He was still
                     sleeping when Sister Mary Agnes left him for a few hours rest before morning.
                     She was so thoroughly worn out by the agitation of the previous night, that she
                     did not wake for several hours, and when she did so it was with a sudden start,
                     aroused by the sound of unusually loud and eager voices below.</p>
                  <p>"Sister Mary Agnes told the sister who took her place that the poor man was<pb
                        n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7228-00000046"/> sleeping quite naturally," said one of
                     the speakers, in answer of something which had gone before.</p>
                  <p>"O, it was his heart; nothing else," replied the other, whom Sister Mary Agnes
                     recognised at once as the hospital-doctor; "he must have died without a
                     struggle. I knew there was some local affection there, but at any rate I never
                     thought we should have got him through. Poor fellow, he looked as if he had
                     seen better days. Well, there's a sailor-boy wants to come in directly with a
                     broken arm, so you can get No 16 ready for him."</p>
                  <p>It was only too true—the sick man she had so recently left was dead. Sister
                     Mary Agnes's first thought was one of thankfulness that his last words had been
                     as they were expressions of love and thanksgiving. She involuntarily glanced at
                     the paper which she had carried away with her, and still held in her hand. It
                     was directed in a faint but legible hand.</p>
                  <p>"To my niece, Elinor Johntson;" and signed at the conclusion with her uncle's
                     full name, and giving his place of residence in England.</p>
                  <p>Although it could not in law have been considered a legal will, it was in
                     reality nothing else. It bequeathed to her in a few simple words the whole of
                     the property of which he died possessed, contained in the belt of which he had
                     spoken, and amounting to several hundred pounds. It was however considerably
                     less than the sum of which Sister Mary Agnes had been so unjustly defrauded;
                     but it was not without considerable scruples that she was at length prevailed
                     upon to accept it.</p>
                  <p>Sister Mary Agnes did not live very long—few hard working nuns do; but she
                     lived long enough to see the much-wished-for buildings completed, and tenanted
                     by a constant succession of bright young faces, most of whom were as poor and
                     friendless as she was, when years ago she found herself a stranger in London,
                     penniless and unknown.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7228-00000047"/>
               <head>MAURICE AND GENEVIEVE; OR, THE ORPHAN TWINS OF BEAUCE.</head>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                  <p>AS the traveller from Paris wends his way southward through the central part of
                     France towards Orleans and the beauteous river Loire, he has occasion to pass
                     over the great plain of Beauce. This is a wide tract of country, very level in
                     surface, and being generally fertile, it is entirely under culture, and is
                     plenteously dotted over with villages in which reside the farmers and others
                     who are engaged in rural occupations. In France, there are few farm-houses
                     standing by themselves surrounded by fields, as in England; for those who
                     cultivate the soil reside, for the<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7228-00000048"/>
                     greater part, in dwellings clustered together in villages, where an agreeable
                     society is formed among the inhabitants.</p>
                  <p>The villages in the plain of Beauce are of this kind. Each is a little
                     community of an industrious body of agriculturists, and the tradesmen required
                     to supply their various wants. Every village has a church, an old grey edifice,
                     whose turret may be seen for a great distance on the plain; and a number of
                     these church towers, from being so conspicuous, form stations for telegraphs.
                     The traveller, therefore, as he passes along, may occasionally observe the arms
                     of a telegraph busily at work on a steeple, and in that way helping to convey
                     intelligence across the country between Paris on the one hand, and Marseilles,
                     on the borders of the Mediterranean, on the other.</p>
                  <p>Each church in this, as well as in other parts of France, is provided with a
                     cure. These cures are an humble and diligent class of clergymen, laboring in
                     their sacred vocation for a very small salary; and from their kindliness of
                     manner, as well as their serviceableness in giving advice, in cases of
                     emergency, to the members of their flock, they are very generally beloved in
                     their respective neighborhoods.</p>
                  <p>In Artenay, one of these peaceful and industrious villages, not many years ago,
                     there lived a humble artisan, Jules Asselin. Jules was a journeyman wheelright
                     by profession; he made wheels for the cars which were employed by the farmers
                     in carrying their produce to market in Orleans. These carriages would be
                     thought rude in construction by those who are acquainted with the fine large
                     wagons of England; because, besides being clumsy in fabric, they are frequently
                     drawn only by cows or oxen, yoked in pairs by the forehead. Yet they carry
                     large burdens of field produce, and answer very well for the wants of the
                     people. Jules Asselin had regular employment in the making of wheels for these
                     vehicles; and as he was a sober, industrious and tender-hearted man, fond of
                     domestic happiness, it may be supposed that he married, and dwelt in a cottage
                     in the village.</p>
                  <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7228-00000049"/>
                  <p>It was a pleasure to see the small patch of green or meadow at Artenay, on the
                     occasion of any summer or autumn festival. While the elder cottagers sat at
                     their doors, enjoying the sunshine and the scene of gaiety before them, the
                     younger members of the rural community danced in groups on the village green to
                     the merry strains of a violin, played by a native musician. At these scenes of
                     festivity, as is remarked by strangers passing through the country, every thing
                     is conducted with much decorum. The people are happy, and relieve the gloom
                     that might creep upon their existence by a light-hearted gaiety; a portion of
                     every festival day, in fine weather, being devoted to the dance and the
                     gleesome song.</p>
                  <p>At one time mingling in such festivities with neighbors, Jules Asselin and his
                     wife now principally looked on as spectators from the bench at their cottage
                     door; and their pleasure was greatly increased when their two children,
                     Genevieve and Maurice, were old enough to play in the open air around them.
                     These children were regarded garded with more than ordinary affection. They
                     were twins, and though differing in sex, bore a remarkable resemblance to each
                     other in features, and also in dispositions.</p>
                  <p>"How thankful to God should we be," said Jules Asselin one day to his wife
                     Lisette, "that He has given us two such good and healthy children. What a
                     blessing it is to a poor man to be spared seeing his infants pining and sickly,
                     or, what is worse, possessed of bad tempers and dispositions!" "We should
                     indeed be grateful," replied Madam Asselin, I have never seen them a moment ill
                     since they were babies, though I fear Maurice is scarcely robust enough for a
                     working-man, which of course he must be. He, as well as his sister, however,
                     are considered the most orderly children in the village; and Monsieur, the
                     cure, was only the other day observing to me that their mutual attachment was
                     quite charming—But, dear Jules, I think you have suddenly looked melancholy.
                     What is the matter?"</p>
                  <p>"Nothing, Lisette; I was only thinking—"</p>
                  <pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7228-00000050"/>
                  <p>"You were only thinking! Well, tell me your thoughts. You know you should have
                     no secrets from your little wife."</p>
                  <p>"Well, then, dear, a sort of feeling came over me; I felt a little distressed
                     as to what would come of these little creatures should Providence remove us
                     from our present earthly scene."</p>
                  <p>"Oh, Jules, dont talk so! it makes me so very melancholy you know we are both
                     young yet; and I see nothing against our living many years. Let us hope the
                     best at any rate, and in the meantime do our duty. You remember what the good
                     cure said one day in his sermon—what a great thing it is for a man to know, but
                     how much greater to perform, his duty. And if any man does his duty to his
                     family I am sure you do. Come, cheer up, dear Jules."</p>
                  <p>"I will. It was a mere passing notion; but now that the thing occurs to my
                     mind, I will do my best to give Maurice and Genevieve a good education. They
                     shall go to school as soon as they are able to understand instruction, and I
                     will take all the care I can to train them up at home. I will myself teach
                     Maurice drawing and a love of art."</p>
                  <p>"Oh, delightful! and I will teach Genevieve to spin and sew, and be a nice
                     housewife. And how pleasant it will be to be all together in the winter
                     evenings round the stove; and perhaps we shall try to sing in parts the
                     chanson, "When swallows return in early spring," or "The tender Musette,' or
                     some other pretty country song."</p>
                  <p>Thus Jules Asselin and his wife Lisette would picture to themselves visions of
                     domestic felicity; and until the twins were nine years of age everything went
                     on according to their wishes. Who, however, can tell what a day may bring
                     forth? One morning Jules proceeded to his work as usual; in the evening he lay
                     stretched on his bed a lifeless corpse. A scene of joy was suddenly a scene of
                     mourning. Poor Jules was killed by the overturning upon him of a carriers
                     loaded wagon, the wheel of which he had been called on to repair. The accident
                     was universally<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7228-00000051"/> mourned throughout
                     the district. All felt acutely the loss of so worthy a man, and were distressed
                     for the fate of the unhappy Lisette and her interesting twin children.</p>
                  <p>Misfortune, it is said, seldom comes single. Lisette, a naturally impulsive
                     being, was overwhelmed with the blow, and was in a situation which rendered it
                     doubly afflicting. In three days she lay stretched a lifeless form beside her
                     faithful Jules, and both were buried in one grave.</p>
                  <p>This second disaster still more excited the sympathy of the neighbors, in favor
                     of the twins, now orphans in helpless childhood. The master wheelwright who had
                     employed Jules, bound in some respect by duty, but still more by benevolence of
                     disposition, resolved that he would henceforth be a father to the orphans, and
                     take them home to live with his own family—a species of adoption common enough
                     in the villages of France, where the dwellers beneath their thatched roofs
                     consider themselves as the natural guardians of the orphans left among them
                     without home or support.</p>
                  <p>Briefly must five years be passed over, during which Maurice was instructed in
                     his father's trade, and his sister Genevieve made herself useful in all
                     possible ways to the new parent, beneath whose eye they grew up lovingly
                     together. But their protector, too, was taken from them by death; and the son
                     who succeeded him in the work-shop did not alas! inherit with it his father's
                     considerate tenderness for the poor twins. The boy he tasked beyond his
                     strength, and exacted from the girl such humiliating drudgery, that even
                     gratitude to their benefactor could not long reconcile them to slavery with his
                     successor.</p>
                  <p>Abundance of employment could have been found for the orphans separately; but
                     to live apart had become to them a thought more formidable than any extent of
                     privation together. To work for weeks, perhaps, at distant farms, and leave
                     Genevieve to the mercy of strangers, seemed to Maurice deserting both duty and
                     happiness; while, if Genevieve plied her late mother's skill with some villiage
                     seamstress, the idea of who would care for<pb n="102-103"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000052"/> Maurice, make ready his simple meals, and keep
                     in order his rustic wardrobe, would haunt her to a degree which made remaining
                     asunder impossible.</p>
                  <p>Together, then, like two saplings from one parent stem, which the force of the
                     blast entwines more inseparably, did the orphans struggle on through increasing
                     hardships, until a rich farmer, compassionating their condition, and moved by
                     their rare attachment, once more opened to them a joint home, on terms which,
                     since one roof was to shelter them, they were too much overjoyed even to
                     inquire into.</p>
                  <p>Here, for two more happy years, the lad found on the extensive farm ample
                     employment—now in his original vocation, making and mending the agricultural
                     implements of the establishment, now as a willing sharer in the labors of the
                     field; while the care of the poultry, and all the miscellaneous duties of a
                     farm in France, lent robustness to the frame of his cheerful sister. A passing
                     smile or shake of the hand through the day sufficed to lighten its toils to
                     both; and to sit together over the fire, or on some sunny bank at its close,
                     was an extent of happiness they never dreamed of exchanging.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
                  <p>BUT the "course of true love," even as hallowed, as here, by the sweetest ties
                     of nature—seldom long "runs smooth."</p>
                  <p>Harvest—in Beauce a season of particular activity and importance—was
                     progressing amid the most strenuous exertions of old and young; and Maurice,
                     always earliest and latest in the field, though not gifted with a robust, had
                     yet an agile frame, was eagerly engaged on a sultry afternoon, in placing,
                     before an impending storm, the crowning sheaf on an immensely high stack, when
                     one more vivid flash than ordinary of the lightning which had long been playing
                     along the unenclosed cornfields, struck the exposed pinnacles to which the poor
                     lad had clung, and hurled him down, breathless and<pb n="104-105"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000053"/> senseless, among the pile of sheaves collected
                     for a fresh stack below.</p>
                  <p>When the other workmen, many of them stunned by the same shock, gathered round
                     their late fellow-laborer, they at first concluded him to be dead. A faint sigh
                     undeceived them; but his eyes, when they opened, rolled vacantly round, and
                     vainly did he attempt to utter a word. By feeble signs he pointed to his head
                     as the seat of some fatal injury, of which no external trace could however, be
                     descried; but the effects of it were manifest in his limbs, which, on their
                     attempting to raise him, bent utterly powerless beneath his weight, and he
                     again fainted away.</p>
                  <p>It was a sad and sobered group who followed to the farm the wagon containing
                     the well-nigh lifeless body of their light-hearted young comrade. But how
                     powerless are words to describe the state of his sister, when the brother on
                     whom she doted was brought home to her, more dead than alive—how she suppressed
                     the first burst of uncontrollable agony, to sit on the bed to which she had
                     helped to lift him—his poor head resting on her bosom, her eyes fixed on her
                     darling twin, in long and vain expectation of some sign of returning life!</p>
                  <p>Faint tokens came at last to reward her; but the glance of the slowly-reviving
                     one rolled wildly around, without resting on anything, it met the fixed one of
                     Genevieve when a scarce perceptible smile crossed the pale lips of the
                     sufferer.</p>
                  <p>"He knows me!" exclaimed the fond girl. "God has spared him to me, and will yet
                     grant me to be the means of restoring him by my care and kindness. We were born
                     together, and together I feel we must live or die."</p>
                  <p>The well-known voice found its way to the inmost heart of poor Maurice; fain
                     would he have spoken a word of love or comfort in return, but his paralysed
                     tongue refused its office. All he could do was to point, with a feeble hand, to
                     his forehead, and express by faint signs, that there was the seat of his
                     malady. The most skillful physician of the district, after an hour of
                     unremitting attention,<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7228-00000054"/> came to the
                     conclusion that paralysis had for the present affected both the head and lower
                     limbs, but that the favorable sympton of his being able to point to the former
                     gave hopes that consciousness and reason would soon be fully restored.</p>
                  <p>And when, at the end of a week, the poor fellow stammered forth a few broken
                     words, the first of which were "Genevieve" and "sister," who can tell her joy
                     to be thus called on by the companion of her birth. To think he would no longer
                     be a breathing mass, without the power of expressing a thought or feeling,
                     seemed reward enough for all her nights and days of anxious watching by his
                     side. Since he had begun to speak, he would, no doubt, soon regain the use of
                     his limbs. His arms got daily stronger, and to the precious word sister," he
                     would by degrees add the welcome ones "dear girl," "my keep," "my comfort," and
                     the yet more affecting request that she would take pity on him.</p>
                  <p>"Oh, yes, yes!" she would eagerly answer; "God will take pity on me, and let me
                     make you well by dint of care and kindness."</p>
                  <p>But if, as she thus spoke, she inadvertently kissed a little more fervently
                     than usual the sick head which rested on her faithful bosom, the screams of the
                     poor sufferer, and convulsive fits on the slightest pressure, revealed the
                     unchanged cause of his continued helplessness.</p>
                  <p>The doctor, once more summoned, pronounced the debility of the lower limbs all
                     but hopeless; and the severe winter of 1823 was passed by the twins in a state
                     more easily to be imagined than described. Genevieve devoted all its long
                     nights, and every moment she could snatch from her work through the day, to the
                     couch of the unfortunate cripple, who, though resigned to his own condition,
                     yet prayed to be released by death from being a burden to all around him—to the
                     sister especially whose youth and strength he was wasting, and whose every
                     prospect in life he felt blighted by the calamity which had overtaken his own
                     early career.</p>
                  <p>"Do you wish <emph>me</emph> dead when you speak so, Maurice?" she would
                     sobbingly reply to these heart rending lamentations.<pb n="108-109"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000055"/> "Do you think <emph>I</emph> could stay upon
                     earth if you go and leave me? I sometimes think I <emph>am</emph> going too,
                     for my poor head throbs, and my limbs bend under me at times, almost like
                     yours."</p>
                  <p>"I well believe it," the poor cripple would reply; "but it is all fatigue. You
                     take no rest either by night or day"</p>
                  <p>"Oh, never mind that; God has given me strength to work, and the hope of seeing
                     you at work again at your old trade, keeps me up. Never lose heart, brother
                     dear! You've seen the corn beat flat many a time and oft by the wind and rain,
                     yet half a day's breeze and sunshine set it all right again finer than
                     ever!"</p>
                  <p>These encouraging words from the most sensible, as well as the most loving of
                     sisters, had the effect of making the poor lad at times look forward to
                     possible recovery; and to keep np his industrious habits and neatness of hand,
                     he amused himself ere long in his chair with bits of ingenious workmanship;
                     among others, a little model of a four-wheeled wagon on springs, in which it
                     was his utmost ambition to be drawn by some of his comrades to church or the
                     village green on the evening of a holiday, to witness, since he could not share
                     in, the sports of his rustic neighbours.</p>
                  <p>His sister, who was in the secret, and had furnished all that was required for
                     the construction of the pet model of a carriage, had her own views on the
                     subject, which were, that it should be drawn by no one but herself. And,
                     harnessed in what to her was a complete car of triumph, she was able, after
                     repeated trials, to fulfil her brother's darling wish, that he should attend,
                     on Easter Sunday, the parish church of Artenay, about a mile distant from the
                     farm. The only difficulty (at least in the eyes of the delighted girl) was, how
                     to get her brother—unable yet to endure, without agony, the slightest jolt—over
                     the roughly-paved street leading to the church; but so completely had her
                     devoted conduct won on her fellow-servants and their master, that the whole
                     distance (a considerable one) was found by dawn on the eventful day so thickly
                     covered with<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7228-00000056"/> straw as to obviate the
                     slightest injury to the invalid. From nine in the morning the church path was
                     lined with inhabitants of the village thronging to sympathise with the happy
                     girl, who though declining to yield to any one, the honor of drawing her
                     brother—a task which she accomplished with a skill and gentleness none other
                     could have shown—was yet astonished and bewildered by the admiring looks and
                     congratulations pressed on her by her kind hearted neighbors.</p>
                  <p>The part, however, of the whole scene which went straight to her heart, and
                     touched it most deeply, was the distinction publicly conferred on her by the
                     worthy Curé himself, who, pointing her out to his parishioners as a pattern of
                     christian charity and sisterly affection, and bestowing on the intersting pair
                     his warmest benediction, said to her in a voice of paternal kindness. "Take
                     courage my daughter; God approves of and protects you."</p>
                  <p>It was agreeable to poor Genevieve to have these words of commendation and hope
                     addressed to her; not that she required such prompting to do her duty, but
                     because they assured her that her conduct was worthy of esteem. Her sisterly
                     devotion was therefore strengthened by the cure; and she felt herself repaid
                     for the days and nights of toil and anxiety. But how much more, however, was
                     she paid by the tearful glance of the brother for whom she had suffered so
                     much; and by his fervent prayers that she might be rewarded by Him who had put
                     it into her heart to befriend him! One result only she felt could fulfil such a
                     petition, and something whispered to her it would not be denied. But spring had
                     passed away without any marked amendment in the patient's condition. May had
                     come and well-nigh gone, and with it the hope that the fine weather might do
                     something for the invalid; and resigned at length to his fate, the young
                     paralytic bade adieu for life to all idea of regaining the use of his
                     limbs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7228-00000057"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
                  <p>ONE evening when, as usual, his indefatigable sister had drawn him to the scene
                     of rural festivity between the old elms at the entrance to the village, he was
                     accosted by an old soldier lately come on a visit to a relation in the place,
                     who after closely questioning Maurice regarding his infirmity, gave him in
                     return the important information, that, in consequence of a splinter from a
                     shell at the battle of Eylau, he had himself been two years entirely deprived
                     of the use of both his limbs, and subject to spasms in the head, which had
                     nearly bereft him of reason. Of the various remedies prescribed, he added, none
                     had the slightest success till sea-bathing, persevered in for a whole
                     summer—plunging ing in head formost, and allowing the natural <foreign
                        xml:lang="FRA">douche</foreign> afforded by the successive waves to play
                     freely, as long as strength permitted, on the affected parts—had at length
                     effected a cure.</p>
                  <p>"I was carried to the sea-side in a half dying state," said the old corporal,
                     "in a litter lent me by my colonel. At the end of a fortnight strength and
                     appetite began to return, and with them my spirits and hopes of a complete
                     recovery, which took place in the course of three months after. At first I
                     could only walk on two crutches, then I threw one away, and on the third of
                     September (a day I shall never forget) I walked, without as much as a stick, a
                     good half mile from the town to visit a couple of old friends. Back I came,
                     still on foot to finish my course of the baths; and within three weeks after I
                     was on the top of a coach for my own country, as hale and hearty as you see me
                     before you at this moment."</p>
                  <p>"And where on earth, are these precious baths to be had?" asked the cripple
                     with eager interest.</p>
                  <pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7228-00000058"/>
                  <p>"At a place called Boulogne, a seaport on the Pas-de Calais,<ref rend="super"
                        target="#note_001" xml:id="return_001">*</ref>
                        some two hundred and fifty miles from hence."</p>
                  <note place="foot" xml:id="note_001">
                     
                     <p>In France, the British Channel is called the Pas-de-Calais.</p>
                  </note>
                  <p>"Two hundred and fifty miles! If I must go so far to be cured, I am pretty sure
                     of remaining ill to my dying day."</p>
                  <p>"Try and get conveyed there, my good fellow," said the kindly veteran, "and
                     I'll be answerable for your entire recovery."</p>
                  <p>"What! to get back my poor legs, and return to my trade, and be able to gain my
                     own bread and help my sister? No, no!—such happiness is not for me!" exclaimed
                     the desponding lad.</p>
                  <p>"There, now, my young friend, you are losing hope. You are like many people who
                     cannot believe in any cure till they see it performed. Why be so confident in
                     disbelieving the efficacy of sea bathing? I have knowed many a poor sickly
                     being braced up by it besides myself. I am no doctor; but you are young, and I
                     can see no reason why you cannot get rid of this feebleness, which is perhaps
                     only a sort of disorder of the nerves-a thing bad enough, no doubt. Come, come,
                     cheer up, Maurice; I was, I tell you, radically cured at ffity; why give way to
                     despair?"</p>
                  <p>"But you don't consider the impossibility of my going in any sort of carriage,
                     even the smoothest voitures, when I faint dead away, or go into fits with the
                     slightest jolt. No, no! it is the will of God that I should remain a cripple to
                     my life's end, and I only pray He may be pleased to shorten it for my own sake
                     and that of others."</p>
                  <p>During this conversation Genevieve was an attentive listener; and had the
                     speakers not been engrossed, they most have read on her countenance the lines
                     of deep determination. She took aside the old soldier, to obtain from him the
                     minutest particulars about the wonder-working baths, their proper season, and
                     precise distance, and the easiest and least expensive route by which they might
                     be reached; and no sooner was her plan mature than she hastened to put it in
                     execution. The affectionate girl, overlooking<pb n="116-117"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000059"/> looking all possible difficulties, had actually
                     resolved to draw her brother in his little cart all the way from the centre of
                     France to Boulogne. It was while sitting beside Maurice, and beholding his
                     infirmties that she had come to this resolution, and her emotions found vent in
                     tears.</p>
                  <p>"How strangely moved you are, sister," said Maurice to her anxiously; "surely
                     you have something more than usual in your mind?"</p>
                  <p>"Why should I conceal it longer from you, brother?" was the answer. "I have,
                     discovered the means for your cure"</p>
                  <p>"And how do you intend to effect this desirable object?"</p>
                  <p>"By sea bathing; and I shall draw you myself to the sea baths two hundred miles
                     off!"</p>
                  <p>"You can never have strength to do it."</p>
                  <p>"And why not?—what is there one cannot do for their own twin brother?"</p>
                  <p>"But where is the money to come from for such a journey?"</p>
                  <p>"Oh, I've got in an old glove round my neck five gold pieces saved out of my
                     wages, more than enough to carry us to our journey's end."</p>
                  <p>"Ay, but then the getting back again?"</p>
                  <p>"By that time, please God, you will be walking by my side, and that will
                     shorten the way, and He will provide for us.</p>
                  <p>Don't you remember the words He put into the good Cure's mouth, "Be of good
                     cheer; God approves and protects you."</p>
                  <p>"Well, sister, I commit myself to His hands and yours. Fulfil his commission,
                     for such it surely is, since you are not daunted by the length of the way."</p>
                  <p>"Not in the least."</p>
                  <p>"Or the numberless difficulties you must meet with."</p>
                  <p>"We'll get over them."</p>
                  <p>"Or the dreadful fatigue, perhaps beyond your strength."</p>
                  <p>"Never fear for that; I will manage it nicely; I am very strong."</p>
                  <p>"Ah? but when you come to climb the hills?"</p>
                  <p>"Well, 'tis only taking longer time."</p>
                  <p>"They will keep us back so; perhaps a whole month on the road."</p>
                  <pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7228-00000060"/>
                  <p>"Yes, at the very least; so 'tis time we were off."</p>
                  <p>"And you really wish it?"</p>
                  <p>"Do I not?"</p>
                  <p>Both hearts were full, and a long embrace gave vent to feelings unutterable in
                     words.</p>
                  <p>Genevieve, as may be observed from these traits of character, was not a girl to
                     be turned from her purpose. Possessed of a strong and decisive mind—despising
                     all thoughts of self in a case of such emergency, trusting in God and her own
                     good intentions—she hastened, as we have said, to put her plans in
                     practice.</p>
                  <p>Genevieve had made up her mind to start on her toilsome pilgrimage on the third
                     of June, the birthday of the twins, on which they had never missed visiting,
                     for religious exercises, the little chapel of St. Genevieve, situated a league
                     from where they lived, on the road to Tours. Early on the morning of this
                     anniversary—the sun already shining out cheerfully on the plain of Beauce, and
                     the road lined on each side with shady trees—the heroic Genevieve drew her
                     brother along with the apparatus she had prepared for the purpose.</p>
                  <p>Let us pause a moment to describe this remarkable means of conveyance. It was
                     not without such precautions as her simple wisdom could suggest, or her slender
                     purse afford, that Genevieve had arranged her paraphernalia for the journey.
                     The low carriage, somewhat rude in construction, and mounted on four wheels,
                     was sheltered overhead by a species of canopy, under which Maurice, helpless in
                     his lameness, could recline as on a bed. A leathern strap, a gift from the
                     village saddler, was provided as a harness of draught, when the difficulties of
                     the road rendered such an addition to the ordinary hand-rope necessary. A
                     change of light easy shoes replaced on her feet the clumsy <foreign
                        xml:lang="FRA">sabots,</foreign> or wooden shoes of the country, and a
                     gleaner's ample straw-hat served to ward off the scorching rays of the sun.
                     While Maurice was dressed in his Sunday suit, Genevieve prudently retained her
                     working attire; but a small bundle, which<pb n="120-121"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000061"/> otherwise would have told tales, containing her
                     holiday dress, to be assumed on arriving at their place of destination, was
                     disposed as a pillow in the carriage.</p>
                  <p>Thus provided for the journey, they proceeded along the road towards the
                     chapel, Genevieve, in her speed at the outset, finding vent for her
                     highly-excited feelings. "Dear Genevieve, not so fast! not so fast! You'll be
                     out of breath before we reach the chapel; you'll kill yourself with the
                     exertion."</p>
                  <p>"True, dear brother! I was forgetting that we have <emph>some</emph> way to go.
                     I will be more cautious in future; and you must tell me when you would like to
                     rest."</p>
                  <p>Suiting her pace to the words, and looking ever round to inquire if her brother
                     felt the least inconvenience, the twins arrived about seven o'clock in the
                     chapel, Maurice nowise fatigued, and Genevieve, heated and tired as she was,
                     but too happy to find herself thus far on the road. Having drawn her brother's
                     vehicle under the porch of the little rustic shrine, and listened devoutly to
                     the matin-service performed formed by a gray-headed chaplain, Maurice observed
                     his sister to remain prostrate, engaged in praying with extraordinary fervour,
                     while big tears coursed each other down her cheeks. Her feelings being
                     relieved, and her resolution strengthened by these acts of devotion, she
                     addressed herself to her task. The road northward across the plain of Beauce
                     was taken. The journey was begun.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7228-00000062"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
                  <p>FAIN would we follow, in all its interesting details, the itinerary (unexampled
                     perhaps in the world's history) of the twin travellers, from the very centre of
                     France to one of its farthest extremities; but a few only of its leading
                     incidents must suffice to give an idea of the whole.</p>
                  <p>Along the planted sides of the great high roads and the level plains, their
                     progress, though slow, was steady; halting for the heat of the day under the
                     trees at the entrance of some hamlet, which afforded the needful supplies;
                     while at nightfall, the humblest decent shelter their slender means could
                     command was sought and generally obtained. To avoid large paved villages, and
                     yet more formidable populous towns, was often a tax on the maiden's ingenuity,
                     yet never, save once (at Etampes) was she compelled—by the impossibility of
                     elsewhere crossing two intersecting streams—to consign to strangers' hands her
                     precious charge, and have her brother carried on a hand-barrow from one end of
                     the town to the other.</p>
                  <p>From hence her forward path was beset with new and unforeseen obstacles. The
                     district is now opened up by a railway between Paris and Orleans; but there was
                     no such convenience at this time, and if there had been how should the poor
                     twins have been able to pay for its use? They were therefore compelled to take
                     the ordinary route, which abounds in steep hills, up which the strongest horses
                     find difficulty in dragging their customary loads. No wonder, then, if
                     Genevieve well nigh sunk under hers. Her feet had become so blistered that she
                     was forced to leave off shoes, and being constantly obliged to stop and take
                     breath, she made but little way; yet after every such halt, the agony<pb
                        n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7228-00000063"/> of her brother in witnessing her
                     distress would make her resume her task with a cheerful smile.</p>
                  <p>It was not until after twelve days' weary march, during which she had to climb
                     the hills of Arpajou, Long Jumean, and Bourg la Reine, that they arrived at the
                     village of petit Mont Rouge, near Paris, where they found in the hostess, the
                     widow of an artillery officer killed at Waterloo, an almost maternal friend.
                     The good woman burst into tears on witnessing one of her own sex so dutifully
                     yet painfully employed—lavished on both travellers the kindest
                     attention—procured for poor Genevieve (whose chest the strap had begun cruelly
                     to lacerate, a new and more comfortable one—and insisted on her taking a few
                     days' rest; while the misgivings of her brother regarding a delay, the cause of
                     which was carefully concealed from him, were obviated by the kind landlady's
                     positive refusal to make the slightest inroad on their slender stock of coin.
                     On parting, she embraced, with mingled admiration and regard, the recruited
                     wayfarer, and assured her of the ultimate success of her enterprise, which
                     could only, she said, have been dictated by express suggestion from on
                     high.</p>
                  <p>Cheered by this friendly farewell, Genevieve once more donned her
                     harness—avoided, as directed, the city of Paris, by keeping the line of the new
                     boulevard and Champ de Mars—crossed the Seine in a boat, and, late at night,
                     arrived at St. Dennis, where a less hospitable reception, alas! awaited the
                     poor travellers, A party of gay young sporting men from town, dining in the
                     hotel, chose to consider Genevieve as an adventuress, and her brother as an
                     imposter, and insulted them accordingly; and while the innocent child, choking
                     with indignant surprise, was equally unwilling and unable to reply, Maurice
                     writhing on his seat from inability to chastise such insolence, exclaimed.</p>
                  <p>"Miscreants that you are! the best proof that I am a cripple is my not having
                     the power to punish you as you deserve."</p>
                  <pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7228-00000064"/>
                  <p>This burst of honest feeling only provoked fresh insults from the giddy crew,
                     to escape from whom, Genevieve, in spite of her fatigue, insisted on removing
                     her dear invalid from the inhospitable shelter of the inn to one beneath the
                     canopy of heaven, where the timid girl laid heself down at her brother's feet,
                     her head resting on his knees and their hands twined together like the branches
                     of the old plane-tree above them; and the fine serene midsummer night was
                     passed by both in peace and safety.</p>
                  <p>The only other untoward incident which marked the remaining journey was a
                     thunderstorm in the forest of L'Isle Adam, which brought back on the poor
                     sufferer from a similar visitation a return of his frightful convulsion fit.
                     During its continuance the poor girl—holding her brother's head on her bosom,
                     her hand fast held over his eyes to shield them from the lightning, sheltering
                     him from the rain, as best she might, with her own body—put up the most piteous
                     prayers to Heaven that she might not thus far have led him only to fall a
                     victim to a second catastrophe—adding the natural, and in her case almost
                     pardonable wish, that if the blow were again to fall, it might in death unite
                     them!</p>
                  <p>Her fears were not, happily, realized; the storm passed off, leaving the
                     wayfarers unscathed. A three days' fever, however, occasioned by alarm and
                     neglect of her own soaked garments, detained them at their evenings quarters;
                     and Beauvais, the half-way house of their arduous journey, lay yet a good way
                     beyond.</p>
                  <p>It was reached at last, after twenty-two days march, during which three of the
                     five gold pieces so carefully husbanded had melted away. Fresh courage and
                     economy then became necessary to save the high-minded twins the humiliation of
                     asking alms; and volumes might be written on the hardships, and difficulties,
                     and privations of the remaining half of the pilgrimage. The country in the
                     neighborhood of Boulogne being hilly, Genevieve found the draught of the
                     carriage more<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7228-00000065"/> toilsome than it had
                     been for a week before. In England, probably, under such circumstances, she
                     would have received some assistance from empty return vehicles, but in France
                     there is little general traffic on the public road. A heavy diligence under the
                     charge of a heartless conducteur, or a heavy laden carrier's cart, are almost
                     the only vehicles, bound for long journeys which are met with, and from there
                     she had nothing to expect.</p>
                  <p>As the poor girl drew her car up the last ascent towards Boulogne, she became
                     giddy with fatigue and mental emotion. In a few moments more she would see the
                     sea—the Pas-de-Calais—with perhaps the white cliffs of Angleterre in the
                     distance.</p>
                  <p>"Oh, how delightful it will be, Maurice; I will open the canopy of the car to
                     let you have the first glimpse of the sea, which neither of us have ever seen
                     before.</p>
                  <p>And when she reached the brow of the eminence, there surely was the sea
                     stretched out, a vast sheet of water, with the white cliffs of England faintly
                     pictured on the horizon. Boulogne, also, with its lofty church spire was seen
                     in a hollow bay on the coast—the goal of long cherished hopes. The sensation of
                     the pair on beholding the scene mock description. Maurice, though little less
                     delighted at an event which seemed to him scarce short of a miracle, would have
                     urged on his sister, a halt; but, then, to pause within reach of her object was
                     impossible, and with quickened step she gained the gates of the town. Her first
                     inquiry was how to reach the baths, and the way by which she was directed to
                     them lay along the shore; when the grand and novel spectacle of the gently
                     undulating ocean recalled to the twins the wide-waving corn-fields of their
                     native country.</p>
                  <p>Beneath the shade of an overhanging rock they encountered a group of elegant
                     ladies of different nations, awaiting the proper time of tide for repairing to
                     the baths. All gazed with interest on the cripple and his conductress; and
                     when, in answer to their inquiries from what village in the neighborhood the
                     kind girl was bringing him, he took her by the<pb n="130-131"
                        xml:id="VAC7228-00000066"/> hand, and, with the eloquence of gratitude told
                     whence they came: and what she had done for him, the farm-girl of Artenay
                     appeared in their eyes an angel come down from heaven, whom they felt half
                     tempted to worship, and whom they carried in triumph, sounding her praises to
                     all they met, to the bathing establishment.</p>
                  <p>Its worthy proprietor received the orphans with all his native goodness of
                     heart, thanked heaven that they were thrown on his benevolence, and immediately
                     entered on its active exercise by consigning Maurice, with as many
                     recommendations as if he had been a sovereign priuce, to the skill and
                     attention of two of his most experienced bathing-men.</p>
                  <p>The twins were established in commodious lodgings, and loaded by the awakened
                     interest of the bathers with everything necessary for their comfort. After ten
                     or twelve dips a degree of irritability began to be felt in the feet of the
                     patient, which quickly ascending to the knees, called forth the doctor's most
                     favorable prognostics. And how did the heart of Genevieve leap responsive to
                     the happy omen! how thankful she felt for her own courage and perseverance! And
                     how did her fond brother pour out to her his mingled joy and gratitude, when,
                     by degrees, he could move this or that portion of his crippled limbs, and at
                     length happy day for both—was able to mount, like his friend the old sailor, a
                     couple of crutches. His first use of them, it may be believed, was towards his
                     sister; and never did mother more fondly hail the tottering efforts of her
                     first-born than Genevieve, receding playfully to lure him on, and crying,
                     "Courage, brother! a few steps more!" received him at length in her
                     outstretched arms, mingling tears and caresses with fresh thanksgivings for so
                     blissful a consumation.</p>
                  <p>Boulogne is pre-eminent among the seaports of France for its fine stretch of
                     sands, which are the daily resort of bathers, many of whom come from Paris and
                     other parts of the interior, as well as English from the opposite coast. These
                     sands were a favorite resort of the twins. Carrying a seat almost to the edge
                     of the waves<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7228-00000067"/> Genevieve led her
                     brother to it, and here he inhaled every day the refreshing breezes which
                     played along the surface of the ocean. At other times she would move with him
                     to a sheltered spot inland, where he could have the benefit of milk procured
                     from a farm dairy, and a change of atmosphere.</p>
                  <p>With these attentions, and unremitting attendance at the baths, where the
                     saltwater douche continued to prove of the greatest efficacy, Maurice gradually
                     gained strength. At first he could walk on his crutches only a few steps, then
                     a greater distance, and after awhile he accomplished a mile and sometimes two
                     miles. He was now able to perambulate the streets, and be amused with the
                     shops; in these excursions leaning on his sister's arm, and occasionally
                     resting when a seat presented itself. In their walks through the town Maurice
                     and Genevieve found themselves the objects of respect and interest. Their
                     mutual affection had become generally known, and what Genevieve had done for
                     her brother was a theme of universal praise. In their rambles through the town,
                     therefore, they were frequently addressed by name, while many would point them
                     out in passing, and say, "There go the twins of Beauce."</p>
                  <p>When September was passed and the seabathing season over, the cure of Maurice
                     was so far completed that he talked of returning homeward, and for that purpose
                     modestly asked the worthy bath-keeper to advance him a small sum, to be
                     faithfully repaid out of his own and his sister's first earnings. This loan,
                     however, was not necessary. The day before that fixed on their departure, a
                     deputation from the youth of every rank in Boulogne waited on Genevieve
                     Asselin, inviting her to receive on the morrow, at a civic feast, the tribute
                     so richly earned by her sisterly devotion. The poor girl thought it a dream
                     when thus summoned to enjoy honor reserved in her simple ideas for persons of
                     rank alone; and could scarce comprehend when assured that it was the very
                     obscurity of her station which enchanced her merit and made her worthy of being
                     thus honored.</p>
                  <pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7228-00000068"/>
                  <p>Next day six young ladies came in two carriages to conduct the twins to the
                     spot called Tivoli, in the upper town, where preperations had been made for a
                     fete in commemoration of the purest and most persevering virtue. There the
                     simple, timid girl of Beauce, in the garb she had brought from her native
                     village, was crowned with white roses, and at the end of the banquet presented
                     by the spokeswoman of the young woman of Boulogne with a purse containing fifty
                     gold pieces, as a willing contribution from sisters of her own sex, justly
                     proud of one who had reflected upon it such unfading lustre.</p>
                  <p>How the unconscious heroine blushed and resisted; how the sum—one she had never
                     so much as dreamed of possessing—was forced upon her; how she honorably flew to
                     discharge with it her debt at the baths; but thanks to their owner's
                     liberality, brought it undiminished away—may be left to the reader's fancy. He
                     may be pleased, however, to learn, that by the physician's advice Maurice
                     exchanged his intended walk home for an inside seat beside his sister in the
                     diligence, on the top of which he insisted on fastening his beloved wagon; that
                     a few days were spent in seeing Paris, which they had once so painfully passed,
                     and on visiting the kind hostess of Mont Rouge, who had acted towards them the
                     samaritan's part; and that, availing themselves of a return vehicle for
                     Orleans, they reached it late on a Saturday night.</p>
                  <p>About the hour of ten next morning, just as its inhabitants were proceeding to
                     church, Maurice appeared, now drawing in his turn, up the street leading to the
                     church, his blushing sister, half smothered with the flowers showered upon her
                     by the whole closely-following population of her native village.</p>
                  <p>The good priest, apprised of their return, caused the brother to lead his
                     sister to the foot of the altar, and founding on this living text a most
                     affecting exhortation to Christian charity and fraternal love, and again
                     blessing the maid he held out as a pattern to all around, alluded, in a voice
                     faltering with emotion, to his former<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7228-00000069"
                     /> mer words of encouragement, asking, "Said I not truly, daughter, that the
                     God who approved would protect you?"</p>
               </div>
               <closer>THE END.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
