<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7099">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mary Lee </title>
            <author>Livermore, Kate.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7099</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1563</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mary Lee</title>
                  <author>Livermore, Kate.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>161 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Appleton</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1860">1860</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-06">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Mary Lee</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7099-00000001"/>Mary Lee's Birth-Day Party.   MARY LEE. BY KATE LIVERMORE. NEW YORK: D. APPLETON &amp; COMPANY, 346 &amp; 348 BROADWAY. "ONDON: 16 LITTLE BRITAIN. 1860.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7099-00000002"/> ENTERED, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1859, by D. APPLETON &amp; COMPANY, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York.   TO KATY APPLETON. MY DEAR NAMESAKE: While writing this true story of a little girl, whom I love very much, I have often thought of you, and should be delighted to hear that it had amused you. I hope many little boys and girls will find it interesting. We live so far apart that I fear it will be long before we meet; but I shall always think of you with affection as the daughter of dear friends. K. L. BAxTIFA. FOUNrAIs,  July, 1869.  &#xD;<pb n=" (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7099-00000003"/>  CONTENTS. a PAGE CHAPTER I. FIRST HOME-FIRST FRIENDS-COUNTRY AMUSE- MENTS,   -               9  CHAPTER II. OTHER FRIENDS-STREETS,      -   -  17 CHAPTER II. SEA-SIDE-KIND MARGERY MENAGERY-THE SEA- HAPPY HOUSE-AUGUSTUS-NEW FRIENDS- VISITS,  -   -   -        22 CHAPTER IV. CHRISTMAS GIFTS--OHUROH--NEW YEAR, -  -  37 CHAPTER V. THE POOR OAMPBELLS-TOYS, -   -     44  &#xD;<pb n="vi (Table of Contents) -vii (Table of Contents) "
                   xml:id="VAC7099-00000004"/> ni       CONTENTS' PAGE CHAPTER VI. THRD BIRTHDAY-PARTY--HOUSE TOP, -   -  CHAPTER VII. FIRST SIOKNESS-TSLAND-BATHNG,  -   -   69 CHAPTER- Vll. "ONG JOURNEY--UNOLE EDWARD-LITTLE OOUSIS -DANNY-PETS,   -   -   -   -  65 CHAPTER IX. A CHAPTER OF TALES, CONTAINING THE BLUE HOESE-OLD BEAUTIFUL-TOM BROWN--AT AND JiTTEN ' 1'.             80 CHAPTER X. MORE TALES:-THE DOGES VISIT-ENGLISH HARRY ---BRAVE LITTLE GIRLI -   -   -  93 CHAPTER XI. ARS--HORSEBAOK-PINE WOODS-LOG OABIN  -  105 CHAPTER XII. COTTAGE - TART,.E BEDSTEAD ---7ANIMALS-0HRIST- MABS-PUG BOOK,  -      -   -  1   CONTENTS.          Vii rAGR CHAPTER XIII. THE SLAVE-FIRST LESSONS-SUNDAYS-JERRY--- RIDE TO MLES-LTTER,  -   -   -   124 CHAPTER XIV. ELIZAS PITCHER-ROBIN HOOD-MARY S ACTING,  135 CHAPTER XV. FOURTH BIRTH-DAY--lMNX BOOK-CHNA TEA-SET --RAG DOLL-LITTLE PARTY,   -   -  141 CHAPTER XVI. "OST OREEK-NEGROES-PEACOCK-PET RABBIT, -   148 CHAPTER XVll. TAME DOVE-GREAT GRIEF---NAUHT   BELLE- SNAKES-BIRDS-FLOWERS  -   -   -  155 * &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7099-00000005"/>  MARY LEE. CHAPTER I. FIRST HOME-FIRST FRIENDS-COUNTRY AMUSEMENTS. MARY LEE is just four years old; she is the only child her papa and mamma have. Until Mary was two years old, she lived in a village in New Hampshire, amongst the beau- tiful mountains, where the air was sweet and pure, and where Mary's cheeks grew round and rosy. The first person that Mary loved next to her papa and mamma, while she was still a baby, was Eliza, a pretty young colored girl, 1*  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7099-00000006"/> 10      MARY LEE. who lived with Mr. and Mrs. Lee. Eliza loved Mary very dearly; and it was a pretty sight to. see the golden curls and fair cheek of the baby resting fondly against the dark skin and woolly locks of Eliza. These two friends spent much time out of doors, in feeding the chickens and cows, and in playing on the grass under the shade of the trees. But when Mary was a year and a half old, her "dear Ida," as she called her, died. The last timeMary saw Eliza, she was too ill to speak, or to open her eyes; and Mary said, "Dear Ida seep, dear Ida better." Before the morning Eliza had slept her last sleep, and was indeed better, for she was in that happy home where there is no more sickness or sorrow. When Mary was a baby, several little cousins with their papas and mammas, and dear grandma Lee, came to pass a few months at Mary's home in the country; the   MARY LEE.       " house was very large, and there was plenty of room for them all. Mary loved her grandma, her Aunt Louisa, or "Oudy," as she called her, and her Cousin Jamie very much; but when God sent Aunt Louisa a precious little daughter, I think Mary loved her better than all. She called her "cunny baby," and although she could only just walk and talk, she would say, "Oudy, cunny baby, knee knee ;" by which she meant,. she wished to hold her baby cousin. After the death of Eliza, Mary had for seven months a very kind nurse who read "Mother Goose" to her, and when this good Ann went away, and her cousins were also gone, it was a great amusement to Mary to turn over the leaves and repeat the verses, which she knew by the pictures at the top of each page. Mary's only playfellows now were the ani-  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7099-00000007"/> 12      MARY LBEE.  mals. She had a pretty cat, and her papa had a gray horse, which was so gentle that Mary could hold the reins in her tiny hands, and drive, when seated on Mr. Lee's knee,  in the wagon or sleigh, and many pleasant drives the two had together. Mary had a very kind lady friend who used to take her to ride on horseback, but when Mary was brought home, and lifted off the horse, she screamed and cried, and was so naughty, that her papa and mamma used to say she ought not to go again until she could be a better little girl. Mr. Lee had a farm five miles from his house; it was one of Mary's greatest pleas- ures to go with her papa to see the Howland children, and all the animals that lived there; horses, cows, sheep, turkeys, ducks, and geese, such animals as are always to be found on a farm. One cold winter's day, before. Mary was two years old, Mr. Lee said: "I am going '       /"          i   MARY LEE.        13 to take the colt out to the farm; I will put Molly Grey to the sleigh, and Mary and Rostine shall go with me." Rostine was a lovely little boy of three years old, the son of Mrs. Lee's colored cook. The children were warmly wrapped in cloaks and furs; Mary sat by her papa, and Rostine at their feet. Twice*during their very hilly ride, the colt broke loose; then Mr. Lee left good Molly Grey standing in the road, with the little boy at the bottom of the sleigh, while with Mary in his arms he ran after and caught the colt. They all came home in safety, very happy; and glad to find a warm dinner waiting for them. Not long after this Mrs. Lee said: "Mr. and Mrs. Howland are very poor, and cannot give their children any of the pretty things that children always like so much,; I intend to provide a present for each of them; papa shall drive me to the farm in the sleigh, and  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7099-00000008"/> "      MARY LEE. Mary shall go to see how happy the gifts will make them." Mrs. Lee dressed a doll for Lucy, the youngest girl. When Mary saw it with its pretty cloak and bonnet on, she liked it so much better than her own doll, that she threw hers on the floor, and begged and cried for "Lucy dolly;" but mhamma said, "No! Lucy must have it fresh and nice, and Mary would spoil it." There were two work- boxes for the two elder girls; they were not alike, and one was larger than the other, but the things inside each box were exactly alike. There were scissors, a needle-book full of needles, spools of cotton, an emery cushion, and a silver thimble; for George there was a ball, and for Walter some large blocks with letters and pictures on them; for the two large boys a knife each, and for Mrs. Howland and her eldest daughter each a nice dress. These presents were packed in a   MARY LEE.        15 basket, which was fastened to the back of the covered sleigh. As soon as mamma was snugly seated, Mr. Lee jumped in with Mary on his knee; she tool the reins, and Molly Grey soon trotted over the snow and stopped at Mr. Howland's cottage door; but when they went in and asked for the children, they heard all were gone to school but the two youngest; they were delighted with the ball and blocks. Mrs. Lee and Mary had not the pleasure of seeing. the surprise and joy of the others. Mr. Howland, who came to the village a few days after, said the children were so much pleased with the doll and work- boxes, that they begged their teacher to walk home with them to see their treasures, which she kindly did. I suppose they thought them too precious to take to school amongst many rude children. This was the last time Mrs. Lee ever went to the farm; for soon afterwards she and  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7099-00000009"/> i 16       MARY  LEE. Mr. Lee packed up their furniture, bid good- bye to their kind village friends, and left  ; their nice large house, never again to live in it.   MARY LEE.        CHAPTER II. OWTRK FRIENDS-STREETS. "TTLE Mary's next home was in a city, in the State of Massachusetts; she went with her mamma to live for a few months in the house of her dear grandfather and grand- mother; two of Mary's uncles also lived in this pleasant home, and now Mary had many loving friends to spoil her. Uncle Robert spoiled hermore than any of them, and grandma's big niece Ann was almost as bad as her uncle. Mary had lived so much out of doors in the country, that her mamma or Ann used  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7099-00000010"/> 18      MARY LEE. to take her to walk every fine day, lest in the city she should lose her red cheeks; but she was often so naughty in the streets that Mrs. Lee was ashamed of her, and what do you think Mary used to stop on the side- walks and crossings and scream and jump for? You will never guess; I must tell you. Because she wanted to pat all the horses that stood by the railroad station, or that were tied to posts near the houses and shops. She had been accustomed to caress Molly Grey, and the horses of her friends in the country, and she was too young to understand why she could not do the same to all the city horses. Sometimes a kind-hearted man would ask Mrs. Lee what was the matter with the child; and when she told him, he would say, "My horses are very gentle, the little girl may pat them;" he would lift her in his arms, and seem much amused, as he watched the   MARY LEE.        19 little hands stroking the necks and noses of the good, quiet animals. Mary and her mamma thanked the man, and walked on more cheerfully for this great treat. In the city Mary had not so many ani- mals for pets and playthings as she had had in the country; but two little cousins lived near grandma's; their names were Johnny and Ellie. Mary loved them dearly; they were older than Mary, and very kind to her. Dear little Ellie could read very well, and sing many pretty songs and hymns, which Mary never tired of hearing; she was so careful, although she was only seven years old, that she could take Mary to walk. There never was a better or kinder little cousin in the world than Ellie. It was a great delight to Mary to go to her uncle's to see Ellie's doll house, and to hear her aunt Mary play on the piano. Mary had as many pleasures in the city   &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7099-00000011"/> 20      MARY LEE. as in the country, but they were entirely dif- ferent. At this -time, and in this happy home, Mary had but one sorrow, and that was the absence of her papa, who was gone to the West, where he intended some day to take Mary and her mamma to live. Every day Mary cried for her papa, and every night when she knelt by her mamma's knee, and said "God bess dear papa," she would stop and, say, "Oh, I wish I can see dear papa:" and then her lip'would tremble, and the great tears gather in her eyes, and her mamma would take her up and comfort her, and read her papa's letters to his little darling daughter, in which he told her how happy it made him to know that she tried to be good, and never forgot to pray for papa. Sometimes when Mary was tired of her dolls, and it was not fine enough for her to go out, or for Ellie to come to see her, she   MARY LEE.        21 asked for a needle and thread, and tried to sew; she soon learned to put the needle properly into the soft rag, which she called a bag for mamma, or a "hankerwish " for papa; but the stitches were very far apart, and much too deep; they pleased her, however, and she often asked, "What would papa say to see me sewing so nicely?" Early in June Mr. Lee came back; Mary was very glad to see him, he told her of the cottage that was being built in the pine woods for her and mamma to live in; he told her of the pretty deer he had seen, with their short white tails, and of the birds and flowers, till Mary longed to go to the West to see all these wonders with her own eyes. &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7099-00000012"/> 22    MARY  LEES CHAPTER III. SEA-SIDE-KIND MARGERY MENAGERY-THE SEA- HAPPY HOUSE-AUGUSTUS-NEW FRIENDS-VISITS. MR. LEE stayed a few days with Mary and her mamma, and then took them to a pretty seaport town. They rode from the cars to  very pleasant hotel, where after waiting a fe- moments in the parlor, a waiter came in am said hewould show them a bed-room. Whil Mrs. Lee was collecting some things fror the other end of the room to carry up-stairs she was greatly surprised to hear Mar scream, "Oh papa, papa, take me up, and d not let me see that little man; I do not lil him." At first they could not understand he   MARY LEE.       23 but when they looked at the waiter they saw he was very much deformed, that is to say, he had a large hump on his back and another on his chest, and he was not taller thaf'a- boy of eight or nine years old. Mr. and Mrs. Lee took Mary to their room, and quieted her, telling her that Au- gustus was good and kind, and would not hurt her. They went again into the parlor, and in a few minutes this same waiter threw open the door and said that tea was ready. Mary cried and clung to her papa, who took her from the tea-table into the hall; there they met the landlord. When he heard what was the trouble, he asked Mary to go with him, which she gladly did; he gave her her tea in a room where she could not see the little man, and she was happy. After tea, they went to see some friends of Mr. Lee's, who invited them to stay and  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7099-00000013"/> 24      MARY  LEE. make a visit. Mary said, "Do stay, dear mamma; there is no little man here;" so they sent to the hotel for their trunks, and passed three days very pleasantly with these friends. There were some nice little girls for Mary to play with, and they had large dolls and many playthings. They all liked this pretty town so much, that they determined to pass the summer there. Mr. Lee found a very pleasant house in which lived a kind lady, who said they might all three board with her. There was a large and pretty garden behind the house, and the room in which they slept overlooked this garden. Mary played there while her mamma sat and sewed, or read in the deep old- fashioned window seat, looking up very often to see that her little girl was in no mischief. Other people beside Mr. and Mrs. Lee and Mary, passed this summer at Miss Car-   MARY LEE.        25 ter's house. There was a physician, who was very gentle and patient with children; there were two ladies from the South, and Frank, a nephew of Miss Carter's; they were all very kind to Mary, and she was fond of them; but her greatest friend and favorite was good old Margery, a woman who had lived in the Carter family more than fifty years; she had taken care of Miss Carter and her brothers and sisters when they were children, and when they grew up and married, and had children of their own, Margery felt as if the little ones belonged to her too; she loved them and took care of them as she had done of their parents: and now that she was living far away from most of the young peo- ple, they never forgot her; but tall young gentlemen came to see their aunt, Miss Car- ter, and were sure to go into the kitchen with some pretty gifts for their dear old nurse, who would kiss them as if they were 2  &#xD;<pb n="26" xml:id="VAC7099-00000014"/> 26      M A RY .LEE. still the little boys she had so often washed and dressed. Mary ate her supper of bread and milk by herself, for it was almost her ,bed time when the ladies and gentlemen had tea; and if she was in the dining-room when the tea bell rung, Margery would look in at the door, and say, with her sweet voice and smile, "Come with me, dear, and I will show you a bird's nest, or tell you a story," and Mary dearly loved to go with Margery; sometimes for a very great treat, Mary was allowed to sit on the kitchen table, and shell peas by the side of this kind friend. Mary Lee is a very happy little girl, and no wonder, when she has so many kind friends to love her. One beautiful afternoon, when Mrs. Lee was sewing in her room, and Mary was play- ing in the garden, Mr. Lee came in to ask mamma to put on Mary's bonnet and her   Is   -' -  &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-27" xml:id="VAC7099-00000015"/> Mary Lee at the Sea Shore.-p. 27   MARY LEE.        27 own, for he had a horse and chaise at the door to take them to drive. Before Mary was called in, her mamma asked if they could go to the beach, that Mary might see the ocean; papa said they could, and that he should like to hear what his little girl would say, when she saw the great salt sea for the first time. After a pleasant drive of four miles, they came in sight of the ocean. "Look, Mary; what is that beyond the white sand?" said mamma, "Water, mamma--great, big, beautiful blue water. How blue it is-papa, papa, do look." And Mary clapped her hands and shouted with glee. They left the chaise, and Mary played with the sand, shells, and sea.-weed, all so new and pretty to her, and watched the waves rolling up the beach and mmning back again, and tried to catch them. She spent a  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7099-00000016"/> 28      MARY LEE. very happy hour with these new playthings, and then her mamma undressed her, and papa took off his shoes and stockings and turned up his trowsers, and carried little Mary into the cold salt water. She liked it very much, until one wave larger than the rest came dashing over her, and that made her cry alittle, but her mamma took her to the dry sand and dressed her, and Mary said she was very cool, and liked the sea to bathe in. After that day Mary always asked to go to "the big blue water and white sand," whenever she went out with her papa and mamma. One more very great pleasure Mary had while they lived at Miss Carter's: it was when she went with her mamma to see some wild beasts. There was a very fine-lion, that growled, and showed his sharp, white teeth, when his keeper struck him with an iron bar, to make him stand up and show himself.   MARY LEE.       29 Mary, who could never bear to see any thing hurt, cried, and said to the man: "Do not hurt the great, good lion; let him sleep, he is tired." There were tigers, leopards, and many other caged animals, which Mary. thought beautiful, but the monkeys charmed her more than all. A stout rope, held up by many posts, kept the people from going too near the wild beasts; but a man who belonged to the show I took Mary in his arms, stepped over the rope, and held her up to the monkeys' cage. Her eyes sparkled with delight, and she laughed aloud as the queer little animals put their paws (so much like hands), through the bars, to take the nuts and cake that Mary gave them. F?  When Mary and her mamma had lived two months at Miss Carter's, they went to pass a few weeks in the country. Grandma spared her Ann to go with them. She took  ' &amp;,   &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7099-00000017"/> 30      MARY LEE. good care of Mary. When it was too warm to walk, they sat together on the shady piazza, and Ann read the "Jenny book " to Mary. This was not really the name of the book. Mary called it so because she liked the story of Jenny Wren and Cock Robin, the best of all the stories in the book. There was the story of "the three bears," " the old dame and her silver sixpence," and many more, making in all twelve stories with very pretty colored pictures, and Mary learned them all in those few weeks. When Mary and her mamma went back to the sea-side, Mr. Lee had left Miss Car- ter's, and taken a room at the very hotel in which Augustus lived. Mary was nearly six months older than when she first saw the de- formed man, and her mamma said to her a little while before they reached the hotel, "Listen to me, Mary dear, and try to under. stand and remember what I say.   MARY LSEE.       31 "We three friends (as you often call papa, yourself and me) are going to live in the large brick house in which you once saw Augustus, and it will make papa and me very sorry if you cry and scream when you see the little man. "Once Augustus was a straight and tall boy. He was playing with some other boys in an empty wagon, when he slipped and fell to the ground; he hit his back against a stone, and hurt himself so much that he could never be made well again. Augustus did I  not grow any taller after this fall; but his spine, that is his back bone, grew out like a i  bow on his back. He still often suffers great pain, although it is more than twelve years since he was hurt. He can only do such light work as he finds to do at the hotel, and it would grieve him very much if he thought little Mary, or any one else, disliked and i. ,j-            &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7099-00000018"/> 32      MARY LEE. feared him because he had met with this sad accident." "Does Mary understand mamma?" "Yes, dear mamma," she replied, with tears in her eyes, "I am sorry for. Augustus, and will not cry when I see him to-day." Mary kept her promise bravely, and in a few weeks she and Augustus were the best of friends. Mrs. Lee told Mary not to speak to Augustus of his hump-back. She prom- ised, and she kept this promise too. When Mrs. Lee had unpacked her trunks and settled herself in her new room, she went one day with Mary to see their friend Miss Carter, and the other kind inmates of the house. They were glad to see the little sunny face again, and Margery had many kisses, smiles, and kind words for her pet; but when mamma said it was time to go back to the hotel, Mary screamed and jumped, and said she hated the hotel, and she loved Margery,   MARY LEE.        33 Frank and Miss Carter, and she would stay with them. It was right in Mary to love her friends, , but this was a most disagreeable and violent - manner of showing her love. Her mamma I took her away in spite of her screams, and never again allowed her to enter the house until she promised she would come away like a good girl; and although Mary was not -! three years old, she knew that it was a great !: sin to break a promise, and kept hers well. ili  Sometimes Miss Carter asked Mary to Xg' pass a whole day with her. That was a most : delightful invitation, and you may be sure ? it was always accepted. Papa or mamma ?:; would take her soon after breakfast, that she   might have a good long day with those she loved so much. Mary made some new friends this win- ter; one lady in particular she dearly loved; this was Mrs. Pierce, the wife of a clergyman. 2*  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7099-00000019"/> 34      MARY LEE. Dr. and Mrs. Pierce had no children of their own; they had a beautiful house and garden, and spent much time and money in doing good, and making many people happy. There were books, pictures, and pretty things in this house: birds to sing, and kit- tens to play with; a piano, and a young lady always ready to make sweet music for Mary; no wonder that she called it "the happy house," and never went to walk without ask- ing to go there. Mary soon found out that Mrs. Pierce was very indulgent to children. When that good lady asked her little friend if she would come with her papa and mamma and spend a whole day with her, Mary replied, "No, I thank you, I would rather come alone." On being asked why she did not wish papa and mamma to be there too, she honestly replied,   MARY LEE.        35 "Because when I come here alone, I can do just as I please." This answer amused Mrs. Pierce so much that shoe declared Mary should have her way. Hter papa walked to the house with her. When Mary said, "Now go, dear papa," he left her; and when he went to bring her back to mamma, he heard she had been a very good child. There was one curious though not very pretty thing that Mary asked to see when- ever she went to Dr. Pierce's. It was a I  fierce-looking wooden man, with a long nose, ! red cheeks, and a great black beard; he i: opened a very wide mouth and swallowed a small man. The first time Mary saw this toy, she was I . rather shocked at the idea of one man swal- lowing another; but when she saw the little man pop out of a tiny door, near the feet of g     -       'op   &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7099-00000020"/> 36      MARY LEE. the large man, and found that he was safe and sound, she thought it very funny; and Dr. Pierce would turn the handle and make the dwarf go in and out of the giant's mouth very often, while Mary sat by and laughed.   MARY  LEE.      37 CHAPTER IV. CHRISTIIAS GIFTS-CHURCI--NEW YEAR. CHRISTMAS, that pleasant time when gifts and good wishes are exchanged, came this winter, as it does every winter. Mary was much interested in hearing, for the first time, whose birthday was celebrated by all Chris- tians on the twenty-fifth of December. Her mamma read her in the Bible the account of the Saviour's early childhood, and Mary listened with great attention and delight. "jMary went to church with her papa and mamma on Christmas day, and she went sometimes for half a Sunday; but she was  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7099-00000021"/> 38      MARY LE-E. too young to sit very still, and Mrs. Lee was so much afraid that the habit of inattention would become fixed and hard to break, that she generally taught Mary her Sunday les- sons and prayers at home. Once, when Mary was in church, Dr. Pierce baptized some babies; they cried as soon as they felt the cold water on their faces; that distressed Mary very much, and she almost cried too; she told her mamma that Dr. Pierce was very wicked to make the babies cry; they were good she said until he put the water on them, and that made them naughty. On Christmas eve (the day before Christ- mas day) there came a large parcel for Mary, folded in white paper, and fastened with pins. Mrs. Lee called Mary to open it, which she did very carefully, and there were two beautiful dolls, both for Mary, with a sweet note from her good friend Mrs. Pierce.   MARY LEE.        39 One doll was large, and dressed like a boy, in white trowsers, blue jacket and shirt, a cap on his head, and morocco shoes on his feet; his clothes very neatly made, and could -I  all be taken off and put on again very easily, as they were fastened with little buttons, made, Mary thought, on purpose for dolls. Mary said this doll should  be called George, and her mamma said he is so very nice he ought to be called "Gentleman George," and that was his name as long as he kept his head on. The other doll was much smaller than "Gentleman George," and was dressed like a " -little girl. Mary called her Rosa. These two dolls made many hours pass happily to Mary. On Christmas day at breakfast time, Augustus came into the dining-room looking very smiling and happy, and put on the table near Mary's plate, a pretty bright green box,  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7099-00000022"/> 40      MARY LEE. with a pink cover, on which was printed "Little Susy's little library." Mary very quickly forgot her breakfast and opened the box, and there she saw three books with pretty bindings, large letters, and pictures. They were all ajbout a little girl called Susy Miller. There was a note in the box, telling Mary that the books were the gifts of the three little girls, in whose home Mary had made a visit, when she first came to this town. Was it not very kind of these young friends to remember Mary on Christmas day? If you have ever read the Susy books, you will know how charming they are; if you have not, I*advise you to ask your papa or mamma, or some kind aunt or grandma, to buy them for you, and I think you will say you never read any books you liked better than these. /   MARY LEE.        41 Mary's mamma read her "Susy's Six Birth Days," very often that winter; it was her favorite book for many months; she un- derstood every word of it, and often played that she was Susy Miller. One morning as soon as Mar awoke, she asked Mrs. Lee if she was not one of God's lambs; "Susy's mamma said she was, and I should like to be one of God's little lambs, as well as Susy." I Mrs. Lee told her she was one of God's lambs when she tried to be gentle and good, and Mary said she would ask God to make her good. The other two Susy books Mary under- stood better when she was a little older. Besides these delightful books, Mary had a set of tea things for a Christmas gift; and her happiness was perfect, when her mamma told her she was invited to dine at Miss Car- ter's; she went directly after church, and took her tea things with her. At tea-time,  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7099-00000023"/> 42      MARY LEE'. Miss Carter was so kind as to have all the little cups and saucers set on a tray before Mary. She gave her tea in her tea-pot, milk in her cream pitcher, and sugar in her little bowl, and all the gentlemen and ladies were so good as to drink a cup of tea out of these tiny cups, just to please Mary. Grandma's Christmas gift to Mary was a pretty little muff. She was going to walk one day with her hands in the muff, when papa came in with "The History of the Five Little Pigs," a present from a cousin in New York. Mamma could not read it before they went out, but Mary said she must take the new book to walk with her. Some merry little boys were coming out of school, and one said to another, "Look at that little bit of a muff! Did you ever see any thing so small and funny?" "There are five little pigs in it," replied Mary, who did not- like her muff to be   M ARY LEE.        43 laughed at; but this only made them laugh still more, and shout, "Oh! hear her, hear her, she says she has five little pigs in that muff." Mamma laughed too, and explained that Mary had a new book by that name. One week from Christmas day was New Year's day, and again Mary's friends thought of her. One sent her a funny picture book, and another a doll dressed like a Scotch boy. Mary called him Jamie Gordon. Mary sent. little gifts and notes to a few of her many friends, and carried to her dear Margery an apron Mrs. Lee had made for her, all but a few stitches that Mary begged to sew, as it was to be her present. Margery valued that apron-very much, because of those stitches put in by that little hand. F. , t  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7099-00000024"/> "      MARY LEE. CHAPTER V. THE POOR CAMPBELLS--- OYS. VERY early in the New Year, Miss Carter told Mrs. Lee of a poor family, who needed some assistance. The father could seldom find work, and the children had not clothes enough to keep them warm, or to wear to school and church. Mrs. Lee said she would go to see them, and carry some of Mary's clothes for the only little girl. "I will take some of my toys to the poors," said Mary, catching up a pretty horse and wagon from the floor; they were quite "new, and Mary had only played with them two or three times. !    M:ARY LEE.       45 "You may take the toy to the youngest boy if you like," said her mamma; " but you must give it to him for his very own, and not bring it back again if you once let him see it; think a moment, should you really like to part with the horse and wagon? You can never play with it again if you give it to the little boy." "I have many other playthings, dear mamma," replied Mary, "and the little boy may have these." "We will take it then," said Mrs. Lee, "and perhaps you would like me to carry it in this basket of cakes and apples that I have ready for the children, and when we reach the house you shall take it out and give it your- self." Mary liked this plan, and they were soon ready for the walk. A very cold wind was blowing, but Mary did not mind it; she ran behind mamma and took hold of the hem of  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7099-00000025"/> "     MARY LEE. her cloak, playing that mamma was her horse, and that kept the wind nicely out of her face. When they reached the Campbells, they found their room neat, and the children's clothes clean and well patched. Little Flo- rence was older than Mary, but not so stout and rosy; all the children looked as if they had not enough good food to eat. Mrs. Campbell was glad of the clothes, the children liked the cakes and apples; but nothing gave so much pleasure as the horse and wagon, that Mary put into the hand of a little fellow of five years old. "Oh, how pretty!" said he; " look, boys, look, mother, look Florence, what the little girl has given me; don't touch it, you will break it; I mean to keep it ever so long; a whole year!" When Mrs. Lee saw the delight which this toy gave, she said, "We will come again     IMARY LEE.        47 in a few days, and bring Florence a doll, and the boys some books." That very day as soon as dinner was over, Mrs. Lee asked Mary to show her all her dolls, that they might see if one would do for Florence. Mary willingly put them all into her mamma's lap; one was very old and torn; another had a broken head; some were too small; some were quite new, and Mary lovpd them too much to part with them: at last her mamma said, "I must make a rag doll for Florence, and you will give me some of this torn dolly's clothes to dress it in." "Yes," said Mary, "Florence may have them all." The doll was begun on that day, and finished on the next; a young lady in the hotel painted its face and hair, and Mary thought it so nice and pretty, that she begged to play with it. Mrs. Lee said she might if she would be very careful of it. The day after dolly was ready   for  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7099-00000026"/> 48      MA RY LEE. Florence was very stormy, and she had to stay with Mary's dolls; she sat quietly by the side of Gentleman George, or rode in the straw wagon with Jamie Gordon and Rosa, and behaved very well; the next day was fine, and as Mrs. Lee knew that time seems very long to little people when they are expecting any pleasure, she took Mary by the hand, and Mary carried dolly closely wrapped in the large cape of her coat, and they walked briskly, till they came again to the large old wooden house in which the Campbells had one room. I wish all the little girls who read this }I  book could have been there, to see the joy of Florence when Mary put the doll into her arms; it would I am sure have made them as happy as it did Mary and her mamma: and perhaps each little girl would have gone home, and looked over her many toys and bro. "  ken playthings, to find something to delight a 21   MARY LEE.        49 poor child whose parents never can spare money to spend in such things for their little ones. Florence jumped and skipped, her pretty little face lighted up with smiles, and looked as bright as if the sun were shining on it. "Oh my dolly, my dear beautiful dolly," she said, "you shall sleep with me, I love you; now I shall have something to show to father when he comes home." This affection- ate thought of her father gave Mrs. Lee great pleasure, for she felt sure that although they were poor in money and clothes, they were rich in love to each other. The boys, who for a moment looked at the doll, and said it was pretty, soon forgot all about it in their books and pictures, and the little fellow with the horse and cart bus- ied himself in arranging Mr. and Mrs. Noah for a comfortable drive; Mary had brought him these wooden people from her ark. 3  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7099-00000027"/> 50      MARY LEE. Once more, before they left town, they went to see the Campbells, and took them all the toys Mrs. Lee did not think worth packing up. Will my little friends sometimes carry the toys of which they are tired, to those children who never have any, but who may often be seen gazing with longing eyes into the windows of shops where these charming things are sold? ,e , .   MARY LEE zzS t        CHAPTER  VI. THRD BIRTHDAY-PARTY-HOUSE TOP. A faw weeks before Mary was three years old, she went again with her mamma to stay at her grandfather's house while Mr. Lee went to the West. Mrs. Lee asked grandma if it would annoy her to let Mary have- a, party on her birthday; kind grandma said it would be no trouble to her, the children might have the dining-room  to play in, and the nice front kitchen to take tea in. Mary went 'with her mamma to invite the little guests, and early in April, one'fine  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7099-00000028"/> i - 52      MARY  LEE. day soon after dinner, twelve nice little chil dren, boys and girls, were assembled in the large dining-room for a good play. A sweet little girl named Lilly brough a pretty crochet purse for a birthday gift Grandma had given Mary a doll's bedstead and mamma had made a feather bed, pillows sheets and quilt for it; and a young lad whom Mary loved, and called cousin Jenn) had worked the ends and corers of a pai of blankets for the bed. A doll was nicely dressed in a night gown and cap, and laid in the bed when : was given to Mary on her birthday. Elli brought her a pretty scent-bottle; Ann ga her a china mug with "a birthday gift written on itfin letters of gold; one frien sent her a vase of wax flowers under a glal cover, another gave her a doll's fat-iron. Before the children came, Mrs. -Lee ha told Mary that she must be very kind ar   MARY LEE.        53 polite to her company, and lend them all her books and playthings as long as they stayed. Mary said she would; but as she was a little girl, and had no brothers and sisters to teach her forbearance and generosity, Mrs. Lee was rather afraid she might be selfish at her first party.  Her mamma remained in the room with the children to take care of them all, and to watch Mary, and it made her very happy to see her little girlcarry her picture-books to the boys, her beautiful bedstead to one little girl, her dolls to another, her teacups to another. They had a doll's tea-party; and then grandma came in with oranges cut up, and well sweetened with sugar. Ellie, and her:friend Sally, told all the little ones to sit down, and they took th(, saucers as Mrs. Lee filled them, and gav one-to each guest; when these useful chil-   &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7099-00000029"/> 54      MARY LEE. dren had waited on the younger ones, Mrs. Lee thanked them, and gave them each some oranges and sugar. They all thought this very nice refresh- ment, and after it they played all sorts of games till tea-time; the boys were some- times too noisy and rude, but it was a very merry and happy party. By five o'clock they were all hungry, and enjoyed grandma's nice tea; soon after tea the little people went home; Mrs. Lee and Ann put the dining-room in order fo grandma's tea. Mary was ready for bed early, after playing so hard; as her mnamma was un dressing her, she told her little girl how glad it made her to see her kind to others; Mary kissed her mamma and said her prayers, anm was soon in a sweet sleep. One day this Spring Mary went with he mamma to pass the day at the house of i   MARY LEE.       55 friend in Boston. This lady, like Mrs. Lee, had only one little girl; she was nearly five years old; her:name was Minnie. She had many beautiful playthings and a large rock- ing horse; this was something new and de- h lightful to Mary, and the little girls played pleasantly together. Half an hour before dinner time Mrs. Lee curled Mary's hair, and made her neat to go to the table, and then sat down again to talk to Minnie's mamma. When a mes- sage came to say the dinner was ready, the ladies looked into the nursery for the children; they were not there; they went down stairs and stopped at the drawing- room door where Minnie's aunt was playing and singing, and asked for the little ones. Aunt Fanny had not seen them.    They went down another flight of stairs into the dining-room, hoping to find Minnie and Mary there, but they were disappointed; no ! ( &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7099-00000030"/> I56      MARY LEE. one had seen them since they had left the dressing-room ready for dinner. Minnie's nurse ran up stairs into every room, loudly calling the children; David the footman ran into the street; Aunt Fanny said to her sister and Mrs. Lee, "You stay here and I will look for them." At the end of ten minutes Aunt Fanny's voice was heard, say- ing, "They are found, they are safe;" but it was many minutes more before they came to dinner. When at last they did come down to the two anxious mothers, the children looked as if nothing had happened; but poor Aunt Fanny trembled, and looked very pale, and Minnie's mamma said," Tell me, did you not find these little girls on the 1hose-top?" Aunt Fanny said she did: "they were on the outside of the roof of the house, standing on the top of a dormer window." In looking for them, Aunt Fanny had seen their dolls on    'M-A;RY LEE.      57 the scuttle stairs--the stairs that led up to the window in the roof of the house. She saw the window was open, and at once feared the children had climbed the steep stairs and gone out. Hardly able to breathe or move, she crawled up the steps, looked out of the fearfully high window, and there saw two little heads below her! With wonderful calmness and gentleness Aunt Fanny said, "Little girls, dinner is ready ;" come to me, I will help you in." It was very difficult for the little creatures to scramble up the steep roof from the flat place on which they stood to Aunt Fanny's out- stretched hand; she was leaning as far out of the window as she dared. Mary slipped back several times, but at last they were both safe in Aunt Fanny's arms. Minnie, it seems, had once before been on the roof of this very high house, and had forgotten her promise never to go there again, 3*   &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7099-00000031"/> 58      MARY LEE. when she took Mary with her this day. What a terrible thing it would have been if, by this act of disobedience, Minnie or Mary, or both, had been killed! There was no rai'- ing or parapet to" save them, if their feet had slipped; they would have been dead before they reached the ground. Mrs. Lee could not sleep that night for thinking of the great;/ danger these children had been in. Very earnestly she thanked their Heavenly Father, who had saved the lives that they had so carelessly risked. When grandma's Ann heard of Mary's adventure, she said, "Sure ma'am, God was with them."  Minnie's papa told Mrs. Lee afterwards, that he had - a carpeiter the next day to nail up that window. He told the man why he had it done, and he looked out, and said he would not go on that roof ithouit -.a strong rope tied round his body and made-fast to the house.   MARY LEE.        59 CHAPTER VII. FIRST SICKNESS-ISLAND-BATHNG. WHEN the spring had passed away, and the warm summer weather came, Mary was sick for the first time in her life; pain was so new to her, that she did not at first bear it very patiently. Dear grandma held her in her arms, and told her stories, and sang her the songs she used to sing to her mamma when she was a little sick girl. Mrs. Lee soothed her to sleep with sweet hymns, and read her about Susy Miller's ill- ness. Every one was so good to Mary that she tried to be patient and gentle. A kind doctor gave her medicine which made her  .  &#xD;<pb n="60 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7099-00000032"/> D0'      MARY' LEE. better. When she was well enough to ride in the cars, she went to the sea-side with her grandpa and grandma, mamma and Ellie. Uncle Robert was already there. This time they were all going to an island, which is a piece of land with water all round it. There was but one house on this island, and that was the hotel in which they were to board. After leaving the cars, a steam-boat took them to the island.. From -every window of the hotel, from all the piazzas, you -could see the beautiful blue ocean, breaking into snowy white spray against the rocks; or rolling gently up the - pebbly beach. There was plenty of green grass for the children to play on, and  two cows to give them 'good-t sweet mik. tMrs. Lee took Mary to-bathe in the sea every day. The water was- very cold, but her maroma let her walk in a fewsteps-at a time,- first wetting 'her head-with the salt water.    Mary Lee leaving the Steamboat.--p 60.  &#xD;<pb n="-61" xml:id="VAC7099-00000033"/>  MA- Y LEV.       61 Soon she tookher in her arms as far as Ellie and the other children went, and then laid her on the water, and showed her how to spread her hands and feet like a swimrnmer. Mary repaid her mamma for all this care and trouble, by never crying and screaming. The many people who wondered to see this little child go so willingly into' the cold salt water, did not know that Mary could trust to her mamma's promise never to dip her sud- denly, or to allow the water to rush into her mouth and ears. When they came out of the water, Mrs. Lee wrapped Mary in warm shawls, and left her on the beach, while she went to the bath- house to dress. When kind ladies offered to dress the little girl, she would say, "No, .I thank you, H would rather wait for mamma;' and Mrs. Lee always found her waim and' dry, and ready to pop on her clothes in a mo, ment.  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7099-00000034"/> 62      M-ARY LEE. Mary went one day with her grandfather and uncle, and many other gentlemen and ladies, in a sail-boat to fish; but as she went to sleep soon after they left the wharf, and did not awake again until just before they landed, I do not think she caught many fish, or knew much about the frolic. Mary, as usual, made many friends. One gentleman said he would give many thousand dollars for such a dear little girl; another thought her sunny face brightened up the island. The ladies loved and caressed her. One said she reminded her of her own precious little girl, who had gone to live with the an- gels, and who had just such bright dark eyes, fair skin, and golden curls. At last the tiae came for them to leave this cool, pleasant! island. When Mary heard her mamma say the boat would soon come to take them away, she   MARY LIEE.        63 cried bitterly. "Ah," she said, "I shallnever see the beautiful blue water again: I shall never smell and pat the cows; there are no piazzas at grandma's; I hate the city; I love the sea." Mrs. Lee took her little girl on her knee to comfort her. She told her they must go back to the city to prepare for their Western journey; that papa would soon be there to take them away. Mary listened and grew quiet, and kissed all her friends and bid them good-bye. A good old man carried Mary to the boat, and many pleasant people went with them, and made the little voyage very pleas- ant. It was eight o'clock, and long past Mary's bed time, before they reached grandpa's house; the tired child was very cross; but there was Ann ready with bread and milk  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7099-00000035"/> "       MARY  LEE. for her; and-as soon as she had eaten it, mamTma put" her to bed in her wire crib, where she forgot all her sorrows in sleep. f  ^     *     .   MARY  LEE.       65 CHAPTER 'Vil. "ONG JOURNEY-UNCLE EDWARD--LITTLE COUSINS-- DANNY-PETS. FoR a few weeks after they returned from the sea-side, they were all yery busy; at last the travelling dresses were made, the trunks packed, and one fine afternoon in October, Mary with her papa and mamma were in the cars, riding-off very fast and far from all the dear ones at grandpa's.    Mary had two favorite playthings in. the cas; a pretty Scotch terrier belonging to Mrs. Leecalled Belle, and a doll with a new china head called Eva Holmes. This doll had    once been  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7099-00000036"/> "     MARY LEE. Gentleman George, but as he had broken his head and worn out his clothes, he had turned into a little girl! Mary liked the steam-boats better than the cars, for in them she could run about with Belle and the children she met. One night Mary had a little bed on the floor of a state-room, and another night she slept on what she called " a wide shelf," with mamma, while papa slept on a narrower one above them. They travelled far and fast, until they reached Western New York, having only stopped once for a short time to see Aunt Louisa and the little cousins. They had been riding all day in the cars, and were very tired, when Uncle Edward met them with his horse "Dame Trot" and the wagon, to take them to his house, where they were to make a visit. Papa went in another wagon with a man and the trunks.   MARY LEE.       67 The evening was cold, they had nine miles to ride, Mary was very sleepy, and if it had not been for the glorious sunset, the new moon, the comet with his long bright tail, I do not think Uncle Edward and her mamma could have kept her awake; but she was not asleep when Uncle Edward stopped "Dame Trot" at his garden gate, and said, "We are at home now, and Mary shall soon go to bed." Aunty Car came rnning out to meet them. Grandma Lee stood by the door ready to kiss them. Aunt Mary put the baby in his cradle, and left the nursery to say how glad she was to see them at last; there was a cheerful wood fire blazing on the hearth, and a brightlamp burning on the tea- table. All was very delightful, and Mary was soon sleeping as soundly as her little cousins, who had been in bed two hours or more. The next morning, while Mrs. Lee was twisting Mary's last curl round her finger,  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7099-00000037"/> 68      MARY LEE. a gentle tap was heard at the door, and when it was opened there stood Mary's two little cousins, Arthur and Lissie.  Mrs. Lee kissed them and asked them to come in to see Mary, which they did; just then the prayer- bell-rang, and they all went down together. The children were very quiet and atten- tive while Uncle Edward- read the Bible. Arthur and Lissie said the Lord's Prayer with all the grown-up people; but as Mary had not learned it, she was silent.- After breakfast, -Mrs. Lee gave Arthur-a tranparent slate that she had brought for him, and Lissie a doll that she had dressed for her. -Mary brought- down Eva Holmes and her tea set, and the little cousins played very happily. Lissie was a few months younger than Mary, and Arthur a -few months older; they were both very kindto her. At Unlel Edwawrd's they had some very '-. . *.   MARY LEE.        69 good rules for little people; one was, that they should have their bread and, milk at a table by themselves early in the afternoon, and go to bed before the large people had their tea. The first time Mary saw the little table set, she said: "I hope you have not put on a mug for me; I shall not take tea with the children, but with the ladies and gentlemen." Her mamma heard this speech, and not wishing her little daughter to make trouble, went to speak to her; but Aunt Mary, who was always very tender and in- dulgent towards her, said, "Let her take tea with us until she knows and loves her little cousins better, and then I dare say she will like their early tea." For a few evenings Mary went into the nursery to see Arthur and Lissie put to bed, and to hear their prayers; and then had her bread and milk in the parlor; but after that she said she should like her supper with  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7099-00000038"/> 70      MARY LEE. her cousins, and did not again ask to return to the later tea. The children had a very pleasant cousin staying with them, his name-was Danny; he was twelve years old, and went to school every day excepting on Saturday, then tie had a whole holiday, and he always spent a part of it in taking care of, and amusing his little cousins. Mary loved Danny dearly, and you will not be surprised, when I tell you some of the many kind things he did to make Arthur, Lissie, and Mary happy. On a sunny day he would take one after the other on his sled, never throwing them off or hurting them; when the Saturday was wet, and they could not play out of doors, Danny would take the three children into the hay loft, and build snug houses for them, and pretend that he was a giant looking for them to eat them up; but M   MARY LEE.        71 they were always so well hidden, that the giant never found them. Danny took a pleasant walk every morn- ing, to a delightful farm-house, for milk for his Aunt Mary; and on Saturday morning, when he was not obliged to walk as fast as on other days, he would take one or all of the children with him. One day, just as Danny came home from school, a barrel filled with all sorts of trea- sures arrived at Uncle Edward's. It was directed to Danny, and was from his mother and grandmother. Oh! how   excited the children were, as they watched Uncle Edward open the barrel and take out the things. There were Useful things for Aunt Mary, a  frock for the baby; beautiful soft warm socks for all the children, knitted by their good grandma; a whole new suit of warm winter clothes for Danny, and a red ball for  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7099-00000039"/> 72      MARY LEE. Lissie; a ship he had begun to build, his bow and arrows, a great parcel of ginger snaps, and pretty little ears of corn to pop. On the very next Saturday, as soon as dinner was over, kind Danny brought his "popper" and some corn into the parlor, drew some coals forward on the hearth, and popped as much corn as every one wanted to eat. The children laughed aloud and clapped their hands as they saw the little hard grains hop up, and turn inside out, and come pouring out of the popper* like large snow flakes.  Beside her cousins and Danny, Mary had three other playmates at her uncle's; these were two cats and a dog. The cats were very pretty, and so much alike that it was not easy to tell one from the other; the dog was old and lame. Mary gave each of these animals a name. One cat she called   MARY LEE.       73 "'Fectionate," the other "Shy shy," and the dog "Lame lame;' you will guess that the names described the animals. 'Fectionate was soon very fond of Mary, and always slept in the room with her and her mammRa, when she could steal up and hide herself. "Shy shy" did not often come into the house except when very hungry. The old lame dog was a greater pet with Mary than with the rest of the family, who thought him useless and troublesome, until one day when he did some- thing that made them all praise and caress him. Mary had been with her mamma and Aunty Car to make calls, old Lame lame limping along beside them; they were on their way home when a large black dog in rude play persisted in jumping on Aunt Car and leaving the marks of his muddy paws all over her nice cloak. In vain she said-"Down, down " to him; but as soon as Medo (that was the lame dog's 4  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7099-00000040"/> 74      M:AR1Y LLE E real -ame) saw what was .the trouble, he barked in the most furious manner fat the blackbdog, which was almost large enough to hye /eaten the little old fellow up at a mouthiil. Lame lame was too braveto think of that; he flew at and frightened the big dog, and walked home close by Aunt Cat's side, keep- ing carefully between her and the stranger dog, which went allthe way home with them, Good Medo showed that although he was old and lame, he was still courageous and faithful.  While Mrs. Lee was   dressing one morning, and little Mary was still in bed, the cat came out of the orner in which Ishe had passed the-:iaht, and began to pl Mary watched her for some' time in, si- lence, when her mamina was much amused at hearing her say( 'Fectionate, do not eat 9   MXARRY- LEE.      75 mamma's hooped skirt, or you will surely have the 'whdoping-cough.' Another morning when Aunty Car was not well, and did not come dowak fast, Mary went to her room with a S ece of bread she had dried on the hearth of the kitchen stove, and said, "I have brought you a piece of toast, dear Aunt Car, because you are sick, and I thought you would like it." Her aunt was so much pleased by the attention, that she kindly ate the bread, although it could not have been very nice; this delighted Mary, who thought she: had done something useful for her sick aunt. The little cousins passed many happy hours together, after Mrs. Lee had taught Mary how to play with  e; at first she wanted -all her own way; ain would notLyi to the wishes of the thehers.; one when - Lee heard angry words, and thought Mary  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7099-00000041"/> 76      MARY LEE. the most to blame, she sent her to her room to stay by herself for ten minutes. At the end of the ten minutes Mrs. Lee wentiup stairs to talk to her little girl, -whom she foand standing very still and close -to the window; her mamma stood by her and asked her what she was looking at and thinking of. , Oh! mamma, I am watching the snow- flakes so soft and white; they are very beau- tiful, and I call them little angels flying down from Heaven." Her mamma took her on her knee and asked her if she did not want to'grow more like the angels, and they had a long talk about Heaven, and, the children who lived there now, but whohad once lived upon earth, where they tried to keep God's command- ..ts, and to love one another; and Mary ihoghtithat she nwogld try harder than ever to be kind and gentle to her little playmates.   MARY LEE.        " I     On the bright sunny days before the Irez  snow came, Mrs. Lee took long walks with the children; they generally carried little pails and baskets with them, to gather acorns in; these they brought home to. play with; OI ithe large ones they called cows and oxen, the small ones sheep and pigs; they built a barn for the cows, pens for the sheep, and a sty d    for the pigs with Arthur's wooden blocks, and fenced in a large pasture that the cows might not stray away when they came out of the barn to graze. In one of these pleasant walks, when they had nearly reached the top of a long hill, and had sat down on a large horseblock to rest themselves, Aunt Kate (that was Mrs. Leeds name to Arthur and imssie) discovered an echo. The children shouted again and again, and never tired of hearing the ech9 repeat their words.  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7099-00000042"/> 78      MARY LE:E. Uncle Edward Often put ',Dame Trot" to the wagon and gave the little ones a delightfu tride, one or two aunties always going to take care of them. Once they ally i l'- a- long warm afternoon in the woods, taking refreshments with them ; they saw a wasp's nest, and a little harmless striped snipe; they gathered flowers and picked up acorns, and thought their pic nic very. charming.  On anothr day Uncle Edard took the children and their aunts on a lovely lake in a smn s steamboat; there they met some very agreeable ladies, who invited them to join their party at dinner. They landed, and saton the sideiof -a- high: green hill, under shady trees; and all dieaed ite d cold meat, bread and water, cakes ainies, tasted much- better of doors than they could have done in the ho se at a regular: dinner-table; the ladies sang very sweetly as they returned on   MA-RY LEE.       79 the boat, and every one thought and said that it had been a very happy day; but perhaps the greatest and most constant delight of, these little cousins, was in the stories their aunt told them every evening for half an hour before they went to bed, by  the bright wood fire in Uncle Edward's snug parlor; and as all these stories are as new to you as they once were to Arthur, Lissie, and Mary, I will tell you some of them in the next chapters.   - '4,  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7099-00000043"/> 80      MARY LEE. CHAPTER IX. A CHAPTEROF TALES, CONTAINING THE BLUE HORSE- OLD BEAUTIFUL--TOM BROWN-CAT AND KITTEN. "MY stories are all true," said Aunt Kate. "I cannot readily remember those I read to Mary, and I never could invent or make ujp a story; but curious things that have really happened I can tell you. "You shall have a story that Mary likes very much, called' The blue horse.' " "Oh! Aunt Kate," said Arthur, (opening wide his eyes, and smiling till the dimples in his cheek grew very deep,) "I never heard of a blue horse, and you promised us a true story!"   MA-BY -L EE.     .8 "I will tell you a true story, and it shall be about a blue horse," replied his aunt laughing. "When Mary's grandpapa had the charge of a large calico print works, he had horses to draw wagon loads of goods to the rail- road, when they were ready to be sent away to distant places; two horses always worked together min one wagon; horses often grow very fond of each other after working long together.   , "One of these horses was white, and he had a chestnut-colored helpmate. "On Sundays they were allowed to roam about in the large pleasant yard of the print works; there were shady trees for them to lie under, grass to eat, and water to drink, and they ought to have been happy on thei' day of rest without getting into mischief  but youshall hear. - "One Sunday the watchman went as usual g S .P  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7099-00000044"/> 82     MARI Y LE-E. at noon' to see that the fires were safe, and all things right in the many: great buildings in the yard: he had no sooner unlocked the high gate, and shut it behind him than the chestnut horse rah up to him, and- seeamed in the most singular and frightful manner; the man afterwards said he had never heard such -a sound from man; or beast before; then the horse ran to a door that stood open in-one of the buildings, then back again to the watchman, as dogs do sometimes when they want people to fellow them. At first the man did not know what to make of these strange actions; he thought the horse had a fit; but after watching him for a few moments he followed him to the open door. The horse left off screaming when he saw the watch- man unnd  toodhim, and -trotted into the building, stopping hear a deep pit in the floor, filled with blue water; into which his friend the white horse had fallen I! /   X MARY LEE.      83 "The watchman was obliged to leave the poor creatures for a few moments, to find ropes and to call men to help the horse out he could not help himself, for the sides of the pit were steep and slippery, the. water deep and only his white head was he, just able t keep above his uncomfortable bath tub. "He was soon safely lifted out; his kin( and intelligent friend showed his delight by walking round him, rubbing against him anm neighmg. For many months this once whit horse was of a deep, bright, blue color, a] but his head, which looked whiter than eve on his blue body. !"When boys in the street pointed at hir and laughed, and called one another to loo at him, he would hang his head and seer ashamed of his gay dress; when he at las shed his blue coat, a new white one am again; but you know now there really we once a blue horse! I .            r   &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7099-00000045"/> 84      MARY LEE"i. "The building into which the horse had wandered, is called a ' blue dye house,' and the pit into which he fell, ' a blue dye vat.' "The blue color is made from a plant called Indigo, and is used to make blue figures on cotton or woollen cloths; it is a veryfast color, which does not mean that it will run away, but that it will not wash out; and men who dip the cloth in the vats to dye it, have always dark blue hands, and keep a set of clothes which are always blue to work in; so you see poor horsey had no chance of losing his blue coat until it dropped off." The children were delighted with this story, but as they, like all little people, were not satisfied with only one, they next crowded round Aunty Car, and begged for another from her. Kind Aunt Car, ever ready to oblige the little ones, thus began the story of another horse called "Beautiful:"   1s MARY LEES             85 "My father had once a horse to which we gave the name of 'Beautiful,' not that he was beautiful; when we first had him, we thought him a very ugly and awkward ani- mal, and all strangers considered him any thing but handsome. "When we all came really to know him, and to find out how strong, enduring, gentle, and patient he was, and how carefully he drew us in the chaise or wagon, up and down the steep hills amongst which we lived, we forgot his ugly outside appearance, and almost fancied he really was beautiful; but the name was given to him at first in fun and derision. "Old David, who took care of and fed Beautiful, went to the stable as usual one morning to give him his corn and hay, when behold! there was no Beautiful there; the stall was empty, and David in looking for the horse in every direction, discovered that the chaise was gone also.  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7099-00000046"/> 86      MARY LEE. "He hurried into the house as fast as he could, to tell his sad news. "We all ran out to the stable, but: no Beautiful could we see, 'What could have become of our good old Beautiful? Had he broken loose and run away? That could hardly be, for the chaise was -gone too, and surely Beautiful never could or would harness himself into the chaise and take it with him. No, no! Some one must have stolen Beautiful; a wicked thief must have come in -the night and driven off with the horse and chaise. ' My father directly saw the sheriff, and sent him off in search of the horse and the thief. "The sheriff rode -nearly all day without hearing any tidings of Beautiful, although he stopped every one he met to ask 'if such a horse -and chaise: had been seen on that road. At last a maln said -he had seen Beautiful; a stranger to him was dliving him, seated in   MARY LEE.        87 the chaise, beating the poor. horse very cruelly, -and calling him all sorts of bad names, and. using very wicked language. "Now the sheriff felt very hopeful of find- ing good Beautiful, and he drove on quickly and soon came to the next town, where some one told him he had seen 'the horse standing tied to a post not far off, and there the  sheriff found   him with  the chaise, and brought him  home without any trouble, for the thief not finding Beautiful a very rapid traveller, had left him and run off. "Before the sheriff returned with the good old horse, all the men, women, and children in the village had heard of his loss, and the next day before we saw our stolen favorite we heard many voices shouting: 'There he comes; Beautiful is found;' "Is he :hurt?' 'I am glad he is safe;' and other pleasant words like those, for every one knew the horse that my father had had for more than twelve  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7099-00000047"/> 88'      M'ARY LEE a years! David was ready with his manger well filled; we all rushed out as soon as we heard the sound of hoofs and wheels, and Beautiful was caressed, and petted, and made a hero of. "Beautiful was twenty-two years old when he met with this adventure; hle lived with us eight years after that, and fell down dead in the harness at last. Dear good Beautiful! he was thirty years old, faithful to the last, and willing to work when the death summons came. We were very sorry to lose him, and really mourned his death, but our comfort was that he had no lingering suffering, no long sickness. One instant's pain perhaps he felt, and then all was over.  He was buried in the coat he had worn for so many years, and in which he had for twenty-one years been our faithful servant. "The wicked thief was. caught and put into jail for a number of years."   MARY LEE.        89 The children often asked for this story, though it always made them look and feel a little sad. Aunty Car told her nieces and nephews many other interesting tales.    g( Two that she made herself they could not hear too often. One was about "Tom Brown and his ten little Indian boys;" they went hunting and fishing, each killing, and carrying home  something different from the rest; they dried venison, made corn cakes, lived in wigwams, and  did many things new and wonderful to the children. The other story that they made Aunty Car tell until she was very tired of it, was e continuation of the bear story; about the great, huge beart, and the middle-sized bear, and the little wee bear going to gathel blackberries and tofill their jars with honey from the wild bees hive in the old hollow tree.  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7099-00000048"/> 90      M-A RY LEE. These stories are so pretty and, amusing that I want Aunt Car to write them, and have them printed for all children who like pleasant tales, and I shall but spoil them by trying to tell them. I know of one little boy who when he heard the bear story read, exclaimed: "I like it; read it again, read it five hundred times," and that, I think, shows how charming a tale it is. I hope you will all have it in a nice little book some day, and "Tom Brown " too. "This is another of Aunt Kate's stories, called "The cat and kitten." ' Mr. and Mrs. Mason, pleasant neigh- bors of ours, had a cat of which they made a great pet; they had also a- dear little daughter of whom  they were very fond; pussy was notealous of the baby, and never seemed to thinkl herself slighted, or ill used, when she/was put down and Lilly taken up. "While the baby took her daily nap,   MART . L'EE.       91 pussy used- to lie at the foot of her crib, and if she moved or turned, the cat crept to her pillow to see what was the matter. "If Lilly still slept, pussy would lie down again at her feet; if she was awake, the little watcher would find Mrs. Mason, and tell her as well as she could, without words, that she was needed at the crib. "One day when Mrs. Mason was holding her little girl, who was fretting with some teeth she was cutting, and which ached very much, the cat, who had long been watching Lilly, sprang on her knee, and rubbed against her little hands and face, purring and trying to comfort her; but the baby was too un- happy to notice the cat, who soon jumped on the floor, ran to the door and mewed. "Mrs. Mason arose with Lilly in her arms, opened the door, and left it open; pussy went out, but returned in a few moments with her kitten in her mouth, and scrambling  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7099-00000049"/> 92      MARY LEE. upon Lilly's lap, left it there, and sitting upon the rug looked at them, as much as to say:' Only see what I have brought you, my own baby kitty surely; that will make you better.' And good pussy was right; Lilly forgot her pain for a time and played with the kitten."   MARY LEE.        93 CHAPTER X. MORE TALES :--THE DOCGS VISIT-ENGLISH HARRY-- BRAVE LITTLE GIRL ONE evening, when they were all gathered round the fire, as usual, Mary said, "Dear mamnma, do tell us some of the English sto. ries this time;" and Aunt Kate began: "The last time that I was in England, I passed some delightful weeks with dear friends by the name of Hunter. "There was something about Mr. Hunter so benevolent, kind, and good, that all animals, as well as all people, loved him at once. "His two eldest daughters and I were walking home with him from a little party  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7099-00000050"/> "     MARY -L EE*. one night, when a cat came mewing up to us. Mr. Hunter spoke to her; she immediately rubbed against him, and walked closely by him all the way home; he gave her some milk, and a bed in the kitchen. "I was surprised that a cat, an animal that seldom cares for strangers, should thus follow any one, and I said so. 'Oh,' ret- plied one of the young ladies,' all animals love papa.' "Do, papa, tell Cousin Kate about the dog and umbrella.' "Mr. Hunter smiled, and said as it was really a curious thing he would do so. "' One day, as I was coming home to din- ner, walking, as I generally do, instead of riding in the omnibus, a very :handsome spaniel, that seemed to have lost his master, looked up pitifully into my face. "' I said, "Poor fellow;" and patted his head. He wagged histail, jumped upon me,   MARY LEE.       95 and as I moved on, followed me. I neither invited nor forbade him to go with me. "' He went all the way home with me. The children were delighted with a new pet to caress and feed. "' I often reminded them that the dog was not ours, but was only a visitor, lest they should love him too much, and find it hard to part with him if ever his own master should be found. "'The dog had spent three or four days with us, always going in and- out of town with me, which I encouraged, thinking he might be seen and claimed by his owner, who, I was sure, must be sorry to lose so beautiful and pleasant a companion. "' One cloudy morning, I stood at the din- ing-room window looking at the sky, to decide whether I should take an umbrella or not; the dog stood near me; then I went into 'the hall, put on my hat, took an umbrella, and  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7099-00000051"/> 96     1ZMARY LEE. walked as far as the garden gate, when I again stopped, looked at the clouds, and thinking there would be no rain, returned and put the umbrella back into the stand, and set off to town. "'The dog had stopped when I stopped, looked up when I looked up, and at last trotted off with me as usual; but when we had gone half a mile the clouds grew .so thick and black, that I was sure it would rain before I could reach my place of busi- ness, and I turned to go back for my um- brella once more; the dog turned too, and scampered off with the utmost speed; he was soon out of sight, although I walked very quickly, and before I had gone half way home again the creature met me with the umbrella in his mouth  -"'I took it, thanked and stroked him, which seemed to give him great pleasure; and so surprised was Iat what he had done,   MARY LEE.       97 that I went home at once to ask how he had made them understand what he wanted. "' Mrs. Hunter told me that she saw the dog returning alone, and at such a furious rate that she was alarmed, and ran out to see what was the matter; while she stood with the door open looking for me, the dog darted in, seized my umbrella, and darted out again like a flash of lightning. "'Then she thought I had sent him, but wondered greatly at his understanding such an order. We all praised and caressed the dog that was so kind and attentive to his new friend, and concluded that his old master must have taught him some sign by which he directed him to go for his umbrella, and I must, without knowing it, have given him that sign. ( 'The beautiful and intelligent creature stayed with us a few days after this adven- 5  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7099-00000052"/> 98      MARY LEE. ture, and then I returned from town without him, much to the grief of the children. "' I told them how it happened, and tried to reconcile them to their loss. "' When I had almost reached the count- ing house that morning, the dog flew across the street with a bark of delight. I saw him jump up on a gentleman that I am sure was his master, for he looked delighted to see the dog, and called him by his name. So he went to his own home again, and we lost our pet.' "'But,' I inquired, ' did you not ask the gentleman about the clouds and the um- brella?' "' I did not,' replied Mr. Hunter; 'it was "packet day," and I was thinking more of the many letters I had to write, than of the dog; but I was sorry afterwards that I had not spent five minutes in crossing the street, and asking a few questions, for the   MARY LEE.        99 children were much disappointed that I had not brought the explanation. "'We have never seen the dog since that day, nor do we know to whom he belongs.' " "Oh! what a good dog--what a dear, nice dog," exclaimed the children, when the tale was told. "I wish he was mine," said one; "I wish we could know what really made him think that Mr. Hunter wanted the umbrella," said another; and when they were all silent again, Aunt Kate said, "I will tell you one more ' English story,' as Mary calls it, and then you must all go to bed. "During this same visit to England, I was one evening taking tea in the family of a cler- gyman who told this story to his children: "'While I was away from home last week, I passed a day with some friends who have one   only child-a boy of five years old. When he was out of the room, I spoke of his loveliness and beauty. His mother said, I  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7099-00000053"/> 100     MARY  LEE. have the delight of knowing that he is truth- ful and obedient. "I must tell you a case in- which he showed these good qualities. "( " ; I was going'to a party a few weeks ago, when Harry begged to sit up to see me in my evening dress before I went. I said he might for just this once; and when I kissed him as I left'the house, and told his nurse to put him to bed, it was long past his usual bed-time. "After he was undressed, he said, I am very very hungry, nurse; I did not know that it made people hungry to sit up.' "'" 'It often does,' answered nurse; ' you shall have a piece of bread.' "'"Oh! no, nursy,' replied the child; 'don't you remember mamma said I must never eat any thing after my supper, and I had that long since.' "'"'I offer you something to eat now, *    MARY LEE.       101 because it is so loyn since you had your bread and milk,' replied nurse, laughing; 'and I am sure your mamma would have told me to give you a piece of bread if she had known how hungry you were.' C "But mamma did not know I was hun- gry, so I would rather go to bed without the bread.' "The little fellow said his prayers, and laid his head on his pillow, but not to sleep- hunger kept him awake. At the end of an hour, nurse found him still awake. Her kind heart was grieved for her darling boy. She brought a piece of bread to the bed-side, and said, ' Eat it, dear Harry; I will explain it all to your mamma when she comes home, and I am sure she will be glad you ate it and went to sleep.' "'"' Oh! nurse, if mainma could only know how much I want that bread, and would say I might have it, how glad I should be; but  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7099-00000054"/> 102     MARY LEE. she is not here to tell me what to do, and I will not eat it if I can help it. Put it under my pillow, dear nursy, and I will try how long I can do without it.' "'Very long it was before sleep made Harry forget his hunger; but the bread was found under his pillow in the morning just as nurse had left it--not a finger had touched it--not a crumb was broken off."'" Bright eyes were filled with tears when this tale was ended. The little ones spoke in gentle tones and loving words of the brave boy Harry. "I knew of a dear little American girl who was as heroic as English Harry," said Aunt Kate. "Her mother left herewith a party of children, telling her not to eat any thing ; she intended to return with the carriage and horses to take her home by tea-time. The lady was detained until late in the evening, and could not call for her child until all the   MARY LEE.        103 other children had left the house. She found, however, late as it was, that the little girl had refused all the dainties on the tea-table, and would not eat even a piece of dry bread, be- cause her mother had told her to eat nothing. "The lady of the house, pitying the hun- gry child, said, ' I am sure, dear, your mam- ma did not intend you to stay all this time without a morsel of food; there must be some mistake.' "'I don't know what mamma meant,' re- plied the little honest thing: 'I only know she said I must eat nothing.' " This is the last story I shall tell you at present, my dear little readers, as this chap- ter is already very long, and I may weary -ou. Aunt Kate had many stories of animals to tell children, hoping it would teach them to be more gentle and merciful to God's dumb *  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7099-00000055"/> 104      M ARY LEE. creatures, if they knew how much intelligence and love many of them could show, even without being able to speak one word. ,   MARY LEE.       105 CHAPTER XI. CARS-HORSEBACK-PINE WOODS-LOG CABIN. EIGHT pleasant weeks were passed with Uncle Edward, the aunts and cousins, when Mr. Lee, who had gone long before to the West, wrote that the cottage was ready, and he wanted Mary and mamma to join him as soon as possible. The trunks were packed and sent to the station, one cold, stormy afternoon, and on the next morning, which was the first day of December, and the first day of winter, Uncle Edward and Danny took the travellers to the cars.  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7099-00000056"/> 106     MARY LEE. They had to ride a mile to reach the train that left at 7 o'clock; they breakfasted by lamp-light; and when they had kissed all the friends, and had been warmly wrapped in cloaks and furs by Aunty Car, the sun was just up; the moon and stars were still shining; it- was a clear, cold morning, and Mary was delighted with the sleigh-ride, and the jingle of Dame Trot's bells. They were in the cars until late in the afternoon of that day, when they were met at the station by Cousin John, who took them in a carriage to his house, where they passed two days with his charming family; then on again in the cars for another long day, at the end of which they reached Cousin Warren's, in Ohio. There they stayed three days, and as Mary was the only child in the family, she was made a great pet of, and did not wish to go away; but papa was waiting for them,   MARY LEE.       107 and they had several hundred miles to ride before they could meet him. They were to go by a train which left this Western city at one o'clock in the morning, which is really in the middle of the night, when all children, and most papas and mammas are fast asleep. Mary had gone to bed with her clothes on, that she might be quickly and easily pre- pared for her midnight ride; but she awoke when she was having her hood and last shawl put on, and she saw the stars in the cold wintry sky, and liked the ride of two miles to the station. Cousin Warren put them under the care of the conductor, bade them good-bye, and left them for a very long ride that was to take them into the State of Illinois. Mrs. Lee made a bed for Mary on one of the seats, where she slept for a little while, but awoke again before daylight.  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7099-00000057"/> 108     MARY LEE. They saw  the sun rise from the car window, and they saw him set while they were still in the same train. They were crossing a long and wide prairie, upon which not a tree could be seen when the sun set, and it looked as if it sank into the ground, just as at sea it seems to sink into the water. It was eight o'clock when they reached the hotel where they were to pass the night. Poor little Mary was very tired, cross and dirty; the smoke and cinders from the engine had turned her face almost black; her hands and clothes were a sight to behold. Many of the passengers had been very kind to Mary, they had told her stories, and tried to amuse her; she had Eva Holmes and her tea-set to play with (Belle had gone before with Mr. Lee), but twenty hours were a great many for a little girl to spend in riding at one time, and when at last they did stop she was almost too weary to be glad. 4.   MARY LE R.       109 After tea Mary thought her mamma really cruel to wash her before she put her into bed; but mamma laughed, and said she could not sleep with such a little black pig. Mamma said prayers for the little tired child, who was asleep as soon as her head rested on the pillow. Mary awoke in the morning, rested and bright, and ready after breakfast for the six hours' ride that would take her to papa. In full view of the great Mississippi River, the cars stopped, and there stood dear papa ready to receive and welcome them. They crossed the broad noble river in a steam-boat, staid at a hotel long enough to rest, and to buy a few things they needed in their new home, and then once more the three friends travelled together. Five hours took them as far as they could go by railroad, and then they stopped,  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7099-00000058"/> "O     MARY- LEE. not at a station, for there was no station there, but on a pile of boards. They had five miles still to ride, to the place where they were to spend the night; but the mud was so very deep, that the wag- on which usually carried passengers, could not pass over the road to the next town. Papa said they must leave the trunks and go on horseback.  Mamma and Mary sat down on the boards to take a few of the most needful clothes out of the carpet-bag, to put in the saddle-bags, as that was the only way in which they could carry any thing on horse-back. Papa went to find a horse for mamma, and to bring his own Jerry from a house where he had left him, half a mile off; he soon returned with his saddle on Jerry, and a side-saddle on a forlorn olil white horse for mamma. Mary rode in front of her papa, on a   MARY LEE.        1 soft cushion made of a large cloth cloak, lined with fur, and called a shube; the saddle- bags also went on Jerry's back. Mrs. Lee mounted the old white horse, not without some fear, as she had not been on a horse before for more than ten years; she had no riding skirt, but fortunate' ly her hoops were not very large, and she managed pretty well. They all laughed merrily as they looked at each other, and wondered what grandma would say if she could see them. The roads were certainly in a very terri- ble state; in one place the horses sank so deeply into the mud, that they could scarcely struggle out again; mamma's stirrup was much soiled, and the horses in a sad, dirty plight. They picked their way very slowly, and were a long time in riding those five miles; the sun was setting most gloriously when  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7099-00000059"/> "2   :  MARY LEE. they reached the little town, and the three friends were glad to leave their horses, and go to the, inn fire, for it was growing cold by this time. After tea Mary was very angry at finding nothing but a feather bed to sleep on; she had always had a hard mattress, and said she she could not sleep in a deep hole. Mamma laughed, made the bed as hard as she could, and told Mary, that so great a traveller as she should not complain of a bed in which she was to sleep but one night. The- feathers and deep hole were soon forgotten in a sound sleep. The next morn- ing at ten o'clock they were all once more in the saddle. This time Mrs. Lee mounted good gentle Jerry, and found him much more easy and pleasant than the white horse; Mary, her papa, and the saddle-bags, were on a hired horse.   MARY LEE.       113 They had sixteen miles to ride, through a forest of oak and pine, and then they would see the cottage that Papa had built for them to live in. The day was very lovely, sunny and mild, although it was Winter, and they all enjoyed the first eight miles very much. The tall dark pines looked as if they touched the bright blue sky; the brown leaves had not fallen off the oak trees, birds were singing, and gay yellow butterflies seemed to think it was Summer, for they were flying about in the sunshine. At noon they stopped to dine at a log cabin with a great many logmen who board- ed there. On the deep wide hearth blazed a splendid fire, made of the unsplit trunks of trees, chopped into pieces more than a yard long. Mary was delighted with the cabin, the fire, the dinner, and a pretty little dog she found there.  &#xD;<pb n="114 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7099-00000060"/> "4     MARY LEE. She pretended that she could not speak plainly, and would only say "dood bye" when she came away, although she could say "good" long before she was two years old. They spent two hours at the log cabin, hoping to rest Mary so well, that she would not be very tired when she arrived at her new home; but although papa whistled sweet tunes, 'and mamma sang songs, and both told stories to amuse their little girl, the last few miles were very hard and tire- some to her; and when they halted at a log cabin, half a mile from their own cottage, to ask for matches, and to take Belle home, the poor wearied child burst into tears and de- clared she could ride no more. A kind man, named Tom, took her from the horse, and said he would " pack " her to the cottage, and Mary was very glad to be carried in his arms.    Mary bee Tired Out.-p 114.  &#xD;<pb n="-115" xml:id="VAC7099-00000061"/> 'f i t\   MARY LEE.        115 CHAPTER XII. 30TTAGE-TABLE BEDSTEAD--ANIMALS--CHRISTMAS--- PUG BOOK. PEN minutes brought them to the cottage; hey had really come to their new home at ast, and were now more than a thousand niles from  dear grandma and  all their Fiends.                      I I do not think you ever saw such a fun- ly little cottage as this, with its very steep   i oof, a large chimney outside at one end, )uilt from the ground to the roof top, and two vide piazzas (or porches as they are called    j n the West) as long as the cottage. Alto   &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7099-00000062"/> "6     MARY LEE. gether it looked like a bird with its wings spread to fly away. There was a parlor down stairs, a bed- room for the three friends, a clina closet, and a kitchen; up stairs a room for Ann, who came the next day, and a wee chamber for visitors, if ever they should have any in the wilderness. When they unlocked the door, and went from the South porch into the parlor, it felt very damp and cold, for the plaster on the walls was new, and the cottage had been shut up for more than a week.  i Mr. Lee and Tom made a fire, while Mary ran about with Belle, and Mrs. Lee sat down to rest and look at her new parlor. Every thing was in the greatest disorder, and all sorts of things that ought not to be in a parlor were there. A bedstead stood on one side of the room, blankets, pillows, bolsters, sheets, were   MARY LEE.       117 scattered all'over the carpet, which was not nailed down or fitted to the floor; the bookcase was filled with tools, china, glass, boxes, table linen, almost every thing except- ing books. Mrs. Lee looked into her room, which was not papered, and into the chambers, which were not plastered. Mary said it was a very funny home, but mamma thought it was rather desolate. Tom brought a pitcher of milk for Mary; out of the saddle-bags came some bread they had bought where they had spent the night, Mr. Lee made tea for himself and mamma, and this was their first meal in the pine woods. Tom's father sent Mrs. Lee part of a small pig he had killed, they had some broil- ed to eat with their dry bread at breakfast, and a piece'roasted to eat with their dry bread at dinner time.  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7099-00000063"/> "8      MARY LEE. Just after Mrs. Lee had washed and put away the dinner dishes, on the day after their arrival, Ann, their servant, made her appear- ance; she was a treasure in this new house, and her quick hands soon put down carpets, papered walls, unpacked boxes, and helped in every arrangement. - At first the three friends slept in the parlor, and Mary had a funny little bed on the floor by mamma's bed, made in the table turned upside down, with its legs in the air, like high bedposts! but after a while a car- penter made her a neat little bedstead, which was rolled under mmma's in the daytime, and drawn out at night for Mary to sleep in. By the end of four weeks, they had the books, pictures, beds, carpets, all in their places, and were very comfortable in their cottage. They had a bright wood fire in the par- lor, and the warm afternoon sun poured in   MARY LEE.       119 at the long western windows, making it a very cheerful room. Mr. Lee took long rides on Jerry, and never returned without bringing home ap- ples, butter, eggs, or something that was needed at the cottage. Soon they had cows and hens of their own, and then they made sweet yellow but- ter, and had plenty of'eggs. Mary had great pleasure in feeding she animals with ears of corn, which they took from her little hand. Perhaps you would like to know the names that the three friends gave to some of their animals. They had a brown cow which they called Unicorn, because she had lost one horn, and a cow with a white streak on her back was named Frosty, when they bought her, and she looked so much as if white frost had fallen on her that her name was not changed. Unicorn had a brown calf, which Mary  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7099-00000064"/> 120      MARY L&amp;EE.  called Sir Calfy, and Frosty had a pretty little baby calf, to which mamma gave the name of Daisy. There was a large white ox, very handsome and gentle, but always trying to take the corn away from the other animals; his name was Greedy Dick. Mary gave the name of Foxy Foxy to one mule, Polly' Hbpkins to anothker, and to a thirdthis queer name , Al-da-bo-ron-ti-co-fos- co-for-mio! This last long word was a name that Mr. Lee had taught Mary to say when she was only two years old, and she declared she would call- the mule by it, but it was so long and hard for most people to say, that it wasgenerally shortened into Alda. One morning: Mrs. Lee found Mary on * the South porch with the animals around her, thrusting out their noses very anxiously for the corn which was in a basket by-her side. Wlhy do you not feed the poor crea- tures, dear?" said mamma.     MARY L EE,      121 "Oh! mamma, I am 'ranging them for their breakfast," replied Mary. "If I do not make Unicorn come to this side, far away from Greedy Dick, he will take all her share of the corn as well as his own." Mamma laughed, but Mary succeeded in ranging them to her satisfaction. Christmas came to the three friends in their forest home, and from the cottage win- dows they could see evergreens enough; to deck many city parlors, and to make Christ- mas trees for hundreds of happy children; they thought and spoke of all the dear ones far away, and wished them  a merry Christ- mas, although they could not hear the words. When Mary awoke on the morning of Christmas day, she found hanging   on the post of her table-bedstead,  close Jby :her head, a large parcel, wchichshe quly seized and opened; it contained a beautiful little travelling dressing case, filled with pockets 6'  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7099-00000065"/> 122     MARY -LEE. in which were a hair brush and comb, tooth brush, nail scissors, a wee penknife and several other useful things. A book also was in the parcel; such a charming book of fables translated from the German; one hundred sweet little stories in rhyme with a picture on each page at the beginning of each story. Mary had had many books in her short life, but never one that delighted her more than this. In a few weeks she could repeat per- fectly, and with much expression, nearly all the fables; she called it her Pug book, be- cause the fable of the pug dog and Spitz was her great favorite; and Pug book was brought every day for many months to papa and mamma. The wood-cuts or pictures were so very pretty that Mr. and Mrs. Lee liked to look at them as much as Mary did.   MARY LEE.       123 All sorts of animals, birds, men, women and children are to be seen in this grand Pug book. Perhaps you may all wonder as Mary did where these Christmas gifts could come from. There were no stores near the cottage at which they could have been bought, and Mary always spoke of Santa Claus as "a little make-believe old man," so she knew he had not brought them. The truth is, they had been given to Mrs. Lee for Mary by friends in New Eng- land, and she had kept them for a pleasant surprise in the pine woods.  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7099-00000066"/> 124     MARY LEE. CHAPTER XIII. THE SLAVE-FIRST LESSONS-SUNDAYS-JERRY--RIDB WHEN Anna grew tired of forest life, and went to the city, Mrs. Lee took a young slave to live with her. Milly was very sweet tempered and gentle; she and Mary were soon good friends; they used to go together "to hunt eggs," to feed the chickens, and to milk the cows. Milly had been at the cottage but a few days when Mrs. Lee asked her if she should like to hear Mary's prayers and hymns; she said she should. When Mary had finished   MARY LEE.       125 her evening devotions, Milly said she should like to learn to pray and to repeat hymns. Mrs. Lee was much pleased and began at once to teach Milly; she soon learned the Lord's prayer and the evening hymn which begins "Glory to thee, my God, this night;" and every evening in Mrs. Lee's room the three met for prayers and singing. The people who lived near Mrs. Lee in the pine woods, thought it very strange, that a little child should be taught to pray. One young girl who was giving Mary a little ride on horseback, asked her if she really said her prayers night and morning. "I do," replied Mary. "And what words do you use when you pray?"asked the girl. "It is not my butiness to say my prayers on horseback," said Mary very earnestly, "and I will not tell you." Mrs. Lee began to teach Mary and Milly  &#xD;<pb n="126 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7099-00000067"/> 126      MARY LEE. to read and write this winter. Papa brought slates, pencils and a primer when he went to the city, and mamma's two scholars could soon say their alphabet, and make letters on their slates. Milly brought her sewing into the par. lor every afternoon as soon as she had done her other work, and then while Mary tried to sew too, or rocked her doll to sleep, Mrs. Lee read aloud to' her two children. Milly par- ticularly liked the Susy books, and Mary could now understand "The six teachers" and "The little servants." Her eyes filled with tears as mamma read of Susy's sickness and the little Angel's visit; she jumped from her chair and stood before Mrs. Lee with flushed cheeks and eager questions, when she was afraid Susy was going to let the trnk lid fall on the head of Thomas. Every day they had some simple Scripture lessons but on Sundays, the large picture   Mary beel Home..- p. l2G.  &#xD;<pb n="-127" xml:id="VAC7099-00000068"/> /   MARY LEE.       127 Bible, and other books proper for the holy day, gave great delight to Mary and Milly, who always listened very quietly, and gave such answers to Mrs. Lee's questions that she knew they understood and remembered what she taught them. Mary came nmming in great haste to her mamma one day to tell her that Milly had said she could not live without water to drink. Mamma replied that Milly was right, and explained how great a blessing is water, and how needful for man and beast. "Begging your pardon, dear mamma," said Mary, "God could keep me alive with- out water or any thing else to drink, for He can do all things." Then mamma tried to make Mary under- stand, that although God is all-powerful, it might not be His will to keep a person alive, who refused the water or food He mercifully provides.  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7099-00000069"/> 128     M^A R Y LE E. Mrs. Lee told Mary and Milly much about Eliza, how patiently she bore her last long sickness, how much she loved to hear the Bible read, to be prayed with and sung to; and mamma taught them what Mary called "Eliza's hymn," the very one Susy Miller liked and learned, beginning, "I think when I read the sweet story of old." Eliza had a very sweet voice, and often sang this hymn. Mary asked if mamma thought Heaven would fit all the good children, and grown up people who had died. Mrs. Lee said she was sure Heaven would be large enough; for all who loved God; and prayed, for the Sa- viour's sake, to live there when they left this world. In the spring, Mr. Lee had two men to work for him---Joe and Summers. They made a great pet of Mary, often giving her a ride on horseback, or taking her with them   MARY LEE.       129 when they ploughed the, ground or sowed seed. She called them her friends, which amused them very much. Mary had many rides during the winter and early spring, with papa, on Jerry. He was a large and powerful horse, but gentle as a lamb, and would stand perfectly still while Mary took burs out of his long tail. One fine spring morning papa and Mary set cff, on Jerry, with paper and matches, to set fire to some brush on a hill, above the cottage. While mamma was talking, in the porch, to- some neighbors who had come to dine with them, Mary rode up, alone I She had left papa in the woods, a mile off; had guided Jerry a mile below the cottage to a place where the creek was very deep, which she wished to cross that she might call on some children who lived on the other side; but good, sensible Jerry would riot take the bold little rider through the deep water. 6*  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7099-00000070"/> 130     MARY LEE. Mary said, "Jerry just took a drink, but refused to cross the creek, and brought me home when I did not want to come." Mr. and Mrs. Lee thought it was not a very good plan for a little girl not yet four years old, to ride three Wiles alone, even on good steady Jerny; and Mary promised she would not do so again. After Mary had had a great many short rides, Mr. Lee took her with him one day to the mills, where he went every week for let- ters and newspapers. It was eight miles to the mills and eight miles home again, which would make the ride as long as that which brought them through the forest to the cottage, and which tired Mary so very much; but she was a little older now, and a great deal more accustomed to horseback exercise. Mamma put on her thick riding trowsers,   MARY LEE.       131 her plaid tunic, and black felt hat, and she set out very gay and happy. A kind woman invited them to dinner, and they did not returrf until late mn the afternoon. Mary had-been a good girl, and was only a very lttle tired; she brought many lettern for mdenma and one for herself, from a lady who lived near Mary's first home amongst the New Hampshire mountains. It is so very pretty, you may perhaps like to read it. This is it:- "MY DEAR LITTLE MARY: "Do you remember the friend who used to take you to ride on her horse? and who has always loved you very dearly. I am that same friend, Lilly and Philip's own auntie; and now Lilly wants me to write to you, and to send her love, and tell you that she wants to see you very much. I am to tell you, too, that she had two kittens, Spotty and Blackey;  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7099-00000071"/> 132     Ma A R Y L E. and Spotty is dead, but Blackey is alive, and went to sleep this afternoon- all curled up in her hood, and looked so funny, with only his little nose and eyes sticking out of the hood! A very wonderful kitty is Blackey. He runs after balls and feathers- and other things, and when he can find nothing else to run after, goes round and round after his own tail. His mam-ma is a very cross old cat, and boxes poor Blackey's ears every time he goes near her, though he has not done the least harm in the world. Lilly wishes you would come and play with her; she thinks you would not be so naughty as Phil, who is very often in a passion,: and then he throws him- self upon the floor, and kicks and screams and strikes about him like a mad thing. I do not suppose you ever saw a little child so naughty. But sometimes he is a very good boy, and :thenu everybody loves him. One day, when Lilly was sickihe stayed with her,   MARY LEE.       133 and took care of her all day long, and brought her every thing she wanted. Once he went to the head of the stairs, and called, ' Mam- ma, mamma; Tilly is suffa-in, bet (but) you must come and put some mensin on it;' which speech made his mamma laugh very heartily. Another day, their mamma was out skating with a large party of ladies and gen- tlemen, when, all at once, everybody began to laugh. She looked to see what they could be laughing at, and lo! there was Lilly com- ing along the path, tugging and puffing at her little sled, on which sat Phil, showing all his pretty .white teeth, and shouting with de- light. She had dragged him all the way up there to find their mamma. Both children have fine times on the ice. First one skater and then another seizes them in his arms, and flies off with them, oh! so swiftly, it almost takes their breath away, and Phil can hardly keep enough to laugh with. You would like  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7099-00000072"/> 134     MARY- LEE. that, would you not? There are some In- dians in the woods just below where you used to live, and they make pretty baskets for children. They have a little tame fox that plays with the dogs, and runs about with the children, and is as gentle and frolicsome as a pet kitten. These Indians do not live in a house, but have a tent made of cloth, (your papa will show you how it is made,) and for a floor they have straw spread on the ground over the snow. "Give my love to your Uncle H. when you see him; and you, dear little Mary, you must not quite forget or cease to love "Your old friend,  H. G."   MARY LEE.       135 CHAPTER XIV. ]ITAS PITCHER--- ROBIN HOOD-.MARY'S ACTING. WHEN Mrs. Lee's china was unpacked at the cottage, a great deal of it was found to have been broken. One thing, however, was safe and sound, and that Mary's bright eyes soon espied, and she exclaimed, "Mamma, mamma, let me see that beautiful pitcher with the dogs and men on it." Mrs. Lee took it from the shelf, and put it on the table, where Mary could examine it as long and closely as she liked. It was a white pitcher, with raised figures of men on it. They were very gaily dressed  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7099-00000073"/> 136      M-ARY LEE. in bright colors; two had on green tunics, another a blue one, and the fourth was decked in pink and gold; they wore black boots, with yellow tops; black hats, with green, purple, and blue feathers in them; their whiskers and eyes were very black and gave them a fierce expression. Two of these men held bows and arrows' in their hands; two had clubs; one, who ap- peared to be the leader, had a horn hanging at his belt. There were two white dogs with black stars on their backs, sitting by the men in green. They were all under a wide-spreading tree, with large green leaves and golden branches. Mrs. Lee had bought this funny pitcher expressly for Eliza, that she might have some- thing bright to set on her breakfast and tea- table, with milk in it; and when she saw how   MARY LEE.       137 muchkit amused Mary, she gave it to her in remembrance of Eliza. "Who are these men, dear mamma? Why are they dressed so gaily, and what are they going to do with the bows, arrows, and dogs?" were some of the questions that Mary asked mamma, as she turned the pitcher round and round. Mamma said she thought they must be in- tended for Robin Hood and his merry men. "Who are they?" was of course the next inquiry; and Mrs. Lee told her little girl that six hundred years ago there lived in England a famous outlaw, called Robin Hood. He had a friend, a very large and tall man, almost a giant, whose name was John Little, but which, in fun, Robin changed into Little John. Robin Hood and Little John had many followers. They lived in the green wood, and slept on beds of fern and dried rushes; they  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7099-00000074"/> 1838    'MARY LEE. took money from the rich and gave to the poor. When they were hungry they killed the king's deer, and lived careless, merry lives, without a roof over their heads. Mary thought there never was any thing so charming as Robin Hood and his wild, free life. Day after day she talked of her favorite hero. Her friend Summers gave her a cow's horn, which she hung round her waist, and calling the two dogs, Belle and Judy, she said she was Robin Hood, going to shoot a deer. She returned with the saddle-bags over her shoulder, telling mamma she had brought her a deer; but mamma said she did not like to take the deer that Robin had no right to kill. "Oh! yes, I have," said Robin; "the king of Ingledon has more deer than he wants, and he said I might have some of them." One day Mary threw herself on the floor   MARY LEE.       139 and said, "I am Robin Hood asleep; mamma you be the small bird to sing and wake me up;" so mamma was sometimes a bird, and sometimes Little John, to help Mary to act her new play. Although Mary had no brother or sister, and lvery few companions, she had, you see, many amusements, and made much happi- ness for herself. She acted many other characters besides that of Robin Hood. One day she said she would play she was an angel; but mamma told her that would not be right, that angels were too holy to be lightly talked of, or to be brought into a play by a little girl. Then she declared she would be Satan, for he was not holy, and it could not be wrong to play Satan. Mamma answered as gravely as she could, that she would rather Mary did not act Sa-  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7099-00000075"/> "O      MARY LEE. tan, but try to be as little like him as pos- sible; then, I am sorry to say, Mary cried and screamed, and said mamma spoiled all her play, and would not let her be any thing, and after all behaved so much like the evil one, that mamma was shocked and obliged to talk to her little girl very seriously.   M'ARY LBBEE.     141 CHAPTER XV. FOURTH BIRTH DAY-MNX BOOK-CHNA TEA SET- RAG DOLL-LITTLE PARTY. ONE sunny day early in April, just before Mary was four years old, Mrs. Lee said she must go to see some of her neighbors. Jerry was brought to the South porch, mamma mounted, and papa put Mary on bee hind mamma. They went first to the log cabin in which Summers and his wife lived; they called and called, but could make no one hear, for no one was at home. They did not dismount, as they knew it would be impossible to climb into the saddle  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7099-00000076"/> "2      MARY LEE. again; but they turned about and went a mile and a half in another direction, to call on Mrs. Pinson. Mrs. Pinson had two little girls, one as tall as Mary, the other rather taller. -Mrs. Lee asked the age of Lissie, the youngest, and heard she was just two days younger than Mary. Mrs. Lee invited the little girls to pass the afternoon of Mary's birth-day with her, and their mother said they should; some cousins of the Pinsons were also sent for, to make the party larger. Mamma made ginger-snaps for the tea- table, some of them not larger than a dime, for the dolls. Eva Holmes had a new hood and a new pair of shoes for the party, and her clothes all nicely washed and put on clean. When the clear, bright, rather cold morn- ing dawned, the morning of Mary's fourth, birth-day, she opened her eyes, stood up in   IARY LEE.       143 her little bed, and looked at mamma who was hardly awake, but she gave her little darling four kisses, and said she hoped God would spare her precious daughter to see a great many birth-days, and that she would grow better and better every year that she lived. Then Mrs. Lee lifted up the corner of her pillow, and Mary saw a book in a bright yellow cover, with large gaily-colored letters on it, which spelled these words, "The little Minxes." Mary opened it, and found pictures of a little girl who did not like to sew, of another who cried every time her mamma left the house, of another who would no take medi- cine when she was sick, and of many other troublesome little girls, who all met with curious punishments. The history of Lotty the tomboy, charmed her the most, and she soon learned the very droll verses belonging to each picture.  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7099-00000077"/> "4      MARY LEE. This was mammna's birth-day present, and came out of-the same treasure-box in which the Christmas gifts had been hidden. When Mary was washed and dressed, and had asked God to bless her, she went into the parlor, and there under a small table that held her gold and white tea-set, sat Eva Holmes, holding a book of nursery rhymes for Mary; this had been given to her by a friend in Boston, and kept by mamma for a birth-day treat. After breakfast all of the Minx book and, many of the nursery rhymes were read to the happy little girl. Very soon after dinner, Sarah and Lissie Pinson arrived; pretty little shy creatures, who did not often go visiting. They were dressed in long bright yellow calico frocks, put on over their winter woollen ones, nice warm stockings and thick leather shoes.   MARY  LEE.      145 Mrs. Lee had made a large rag-doll for Lissie, and dressed it in a red frock; it had brown- silk for its hair, and Mr. Lee had painted its face, and declared it looked like some fat old man he had seen. Marmma had told Mary while she was making this dolly, that as Lissie's birth-day came so near to hers, they must keep them together on the same day; and as she would have no present unless she received one at the cottage, they must have this doll ready- for her, and Mary should give it to Lissie from herself. The little girl was so much pleased with the gift, that she would not spare it for a moment to ride in the straw wagon with the other dolls ; and even at tea time, could hardly bear to put it down. Lissie's little cousins did not come until late in the afternoon. Milly gave up the afternoon to waiting 7  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7099-00000078"/> "6     MARY LEE. on the children; she spread a white cloth on a large low box for the dolls' tea-table in the neat clean kitchen. Mary put the pewter tea things on this table for the dolls; the china set was to be kept for the visitors' tea time; the tiny gin- ger snaps were put into a plate, real tea, milk and sugar were given to the dolls in their little cups; they were very quiet, well- behaved dolls, and not in the least greedy; their mammas ate all that their children left, so that nothing was wasted. Mrs. Lee heard Mary telling one of the company not to drink tea out of the spout of the tea-pot; it was very improper. At four o'clock they had a nice tea spread on Milly's clean white table. Mary poured out the tea--real tea-for the first time, into the little china cups that mamma had had put away for two years. Robin Hood stood on the table, holding   MARY LEE.       147 the tea, ready to fill the pretty china tea-pot as soon as it was empty. Mary told her dear forester not to stare so hard with his round black eyes; it was very rude, 'specially when he was at a grand tea party. This made mamma laugh; but I do not think the shy little girls understood what Mary said, or to whom she was speaking The children looked at the picture books, and played with the doll's bedstead a little while after tea, and then went home, with their mothers and baby brothers and sisters, who had all come for them. Milly washed the little tea things; mam- ma put the room in order; Mary said she was glad her visitors were gone, for she could now hear her Minx book read, and as she had been attentive to her guests, and waited patiently for a second reading of her new book, mamma was glad to oblige her darling. r^  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7099-00000079"/> "8      MARY LEE. CHAPTER XVI. "OFT CREEK-NEGROES-PEACOCK-PET RABBIT. A VERY great pleasure to these three friends and to Milly was a ride through the pine woods, to pass the day at Lost Creek, where lived Mr. and Mrs. Marks, the owners of Milly. I will tell you of their longest visit, where they all went to pass the night as well as the day. It was on a lovely morning in May that they locked up the cottage and all set out; Mrs. Lee on Jerry, with Mary behind her; Mr. Lee on a borrowed horse, with the sad- dle-bags behind him; Milly on   a mule,   MARY LEE.       149 which, perhaps you know, is smaller than a horse, and has much longer ears. The two dogs, Belle and Judy, went too. Milly, who thought Eva Holmes very pretty, begged that she might be taken to show to the children, black and white. So Milly "packed"Eva and a little puppy that had been given to her; the puppy went nicely into the pocket of Milly's riding skirt, with his nose peeping out, and Eva sat on her knee as still as a mouse. Mary often stretched out her head to look at Milly and her companions, and to ask if Eva behaved well and enjoyed the ride, which made Milly laugh, and answer "Yes, mom.7 It was a ride of five miles to Lost Creek, up and down beautiful green hills covered with wild flowers-purple, yellow, blue, red, white --most of them entirely new to the travellers. In an hour and a half they reached Mr.  &#xD;<pb n="150" xml:id="VAC7099-00000080"/> 150      MARY LEE. Marks' brick house, in safety, but not without a little adventure, for Mrs. Lee, in trying to put aside the branch of a tree under which she was passing, had fallen off Jerry, and dragged Mary to the ground with her. They were not hurt. Good Jerry stood quite still, and turned his head to see what was the matter. Mary was frightened, and began to cry: but seeing- a little blood on Jerry's nose, where it had been scratched by the tree, she was so sorry for him that she forgot her own troubles. Mr. and Mrs. Marks and the young ladies were very kind and pleasant; there were two little girls who took Mary to see the peacock, the white ducks, the black babies, and the many other delightful sights to be seen at this pleasant place. Mrs. Lee took some frocks to Maria for her pretty little black children, and to Aunt *F .    &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-151" xml:id="VAC7099-00000081"/>  Mary Visiting the Happy Negroes.--p 151   IARY LEE.        151 Rose (Milly's mother) for her sweet laughing baby, Buchanan; and some pictures to good old Aunt Veny, to, hang up in her cabin. They received these little gifts with many smiles and thanks. Aunt Veny gave Mrs. Lee a piece of nice hard soap of her own making. Aunt Rose said she would send her some sweet potatoes, for seed; and Maria said, if Mrs. Lee would send her Mary's white frocks, she would wash and iron them at any time for her. Mrs. Lee was delighted with their grateful feelings, 'and she and Mary really enjoyed their visits to the different clean and neat lit- tle cabins of these happy negroes. Mr. Marks took the three friends through his beautiful orchard of five hundred apple trees, which were all in bud; and showed them a great quantity of lead that had been dug out of his ground, and was ready to go to market. r   ...  &#xD;<pb n="152-157" xml:id="VAC7099-00000082"/> 152      MARY LEE. The peacock, with his long- handsome tail, and his bright purple and green feathers, roosted in a tree near the window of the room in which the three friends slept, and screamed whenever he awoke in the night. In the morning Mary was delighted to see him there. He spent a long time in arrang- ing his feathers before he came down, but at last he seemed to think himself handsome enough, and flew down, strutted about, held up and spread out his tail like a huge fan, and made a very fine show. Mary ran into the house to tell mamma of the wonderful bird, and to ask if she had seen it. Never in her life had Mary sat down to such feasts as she saw at Mr. Marks'. There were pies, cakes, sweetmeats, venison, golden syrup, and all sorts of good things, at every meal! Mary's mamma did not allow her to eat   MARY LEE.        157 Mr. and Mrs. Lee both liked the tame gentle dove very much; and it almost made them cry to see their little daughter's great distress, and to hear her touching words of sorrow. Mr. Lee gave Belle a severe whipping, and for many days she was, as Mary said, "in great degrace." The dove had been in the habit of play- ing with the dogs. He would ride on Judy's back, or stand on her when she was asleep, and peck her ear or eye; and it seemed really wicked in Belle to kill so gentle a companion, though I suppose she knew no better. The very day before poor Robin Hood was killed, Mary had received a present of a pretty tortoise-shell kitten, and this was something for her to play with and pet, but she did not love "Tortoise-shell. velvet," as she called her, half as well as the dove that used to eat out of her hand, and sleep in the wood box.  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7099-00000083"/> 158     MARY LEE. Mary had a little black pig given to her, but he dug a hole under his sty, and ran away to his wild companions in the deep forest. The same kind friend who gave her the pig has promised her two tame squirrels, and Mary intends to watch that Belle and Judy do not kill them. One day in June, after the snakes had awakened from their long naps, and come out of the deep holes in which they had been sleeping all the winter, Mr. Lee put Mary on Foxy Foxy, the mule, for a short ride. Foxy Foxy would not allow Mary and her papa to ride him at the same time, so that when they came to a rail-fence, Mr. Lee seated her on it, and told her to remain there out of the reach of snakes, until he went a short distance on the mule. Mary promised to obey her papa, and it was well that she kept her promise, for Mr.   M3 ARY LEE.      159 Lee had only ridden a very little way from the fence, when the dogs, running on in front, started up a large rattle-snake! He was spotted all over with gold, white and black spots, very handsome, but very fearful, as he sounded his rattles and sprang at Judy. The poor dog was bitten on the mouth, which, with her throat, swelled enormously. Judy would not allow Mrs. Lee to wash the wound in spirits and camphor, or even to touch it; she often cried with pain during the night, but in the morning she was bet- ter, and in two days she was quite well. Mary was much afraid Judy would die, and said many loving, pitying words to her. If Mary had not been obedient, she would probably have been bitten by the rattle- snake. Many birds, red, yellow, blue, black and brown, sang in the trees near the cottage,  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7099-00000084"/> 160     MARY LEE. and hopped on the porches to pick' up the crumbs of Mary's bread which she scattered at her lunch or supper time; and Mr. Lee put boxes on the north porch for the mar- tins to build in, and there the pretty little creatures came every day, chattering, sing- ing, and building; it was a great pleasure to watch them so busy and happy. Mary and Milly had many long, pleasant walks together, before the weather was too warm and the snakes came out, and they always returned laden with bright and grace- ful flowers of many colors, for Mrs. Lee; and mamma used to tell them, as she filled five or six vases with their treasures, that she had never, from green-house, or garden, received more beautiful flowers. Mrs. Lee and Mary were walking about on the grass one evening, looking at the tiny green apples and peaches, when Mary's bright   MARY LEE.       161 eyes espied a deep red clover blossom; she exclaimed at once: "Sweet Kitty Clover sits under a tree," In a dress as red, as red can be. She often made such little rhymes, I suppose because she had had a great deal of poetry read to her. And now, my dear little friends, I have told you many things about Mary Lee, and could have told you many more, had I not been afraid of making my story too long. I hope you will like what I have written. Good-bye, darlings. God bless you all. That you may grow up truthful, pure, and holy, is the sincere prayer of one who loves children, because they are children.   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
