<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7515">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prize Papers, Written for the New York Observer </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7515</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1968</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prize papers, written for the New York Observer</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>A.D.F. Randolph</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1865">1865</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-01-26">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Prize papers, written for the New York Observer</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7515-00000001"/>  PRIZE PAPERS, WRITTEN FOR  ESSAY, POEMS, AND TALE. NEW YORK:  A. D. F. RANDOLPH, 770 BROADWAY. 1865.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7515-00000002"/>  CHRISTIAN       CHEERFULNESS. BY REV. FRANCIS J. COLLIER, CANONSBURGH, PA. THE life of many Christians is a life of constant sadness and gloom. They seem to be entire strangers to all the happiness of earth, and all the hopes of heaven. Their faces commonly appear as somber as the stones which mark the dwelling-places of the dead. Their feelings are better ex- pressed in sighs than in songs. Unhappy themselves, they make others unhappy; they come and go like clouds, shut- ting out the sunshine from cheerful hearts, and, for a while, casting upon them shadows, cold and dark. Some suppose that this melancholy is a sure evidence of extraordinary piety. Others imagine that it is the necessary and invariable effect of all religion, to depress the spirits, and make men gloomy and morose; and entertaining this erroneous opinion, they refuse to acquaint themselves with the Holy Scriptures, neglect all private and public acts of devotion, and prefer to mingle with the people of the world rather than to mingle with the people of God. Now, we believe that dejection is neither the necessary result of genuine faith, nor the indication of uncommon grace, but that it is altogether at variance with the spirit of the gospel. The religion of Jesus is essentially consoling  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7515-00000003"/> 4         PRIZE  ESSAY. and exhilaratin'g, and so has a natural 'tendency to produce cheerfulness in the soul. The best and truest Christian ought to be the happiest and most hopeful of men. His features should wreathe themselves into sweet and attractive smiles, instead of forming, as we often see, only forbidding frowns. His words should not be cross, but kind;-expres- sions of comfort rather than of complaint. The cheerfulness of which we speak, is not a momentary mood, but a lasting temper. It has not the noise of mirth, nor the emptiness of levity. It is a serious and abiding joy; a joy resembling the flame of a wax candle, which is so mild, so steady, so bright, so pure. The Christian owes it to himself to be cheerful. Only when he is so, has he attained a state most conducive to the enjoyment of high spiritual pleasures, most suited to en- courage the growth of the heavenly graces, most consistent with the free exercise of the soul's mightiest energies, most adapted to lighten its crosses and cares. "The man who is possessed of this excellent frame of mind," says Addison, "is not only easy in his thoughts, but a perfect master of all the powers and faculties of his soul; his imagination is always clear, and his judgment undisturbed; his temper is even and unruffled, whether in action or solitude. He comes with a relish to all those goods which nature has provided for him, tastes all the pleasures of the creation which are poured about him, and does not feel the full weight of those evils which may befall him." The Christian owes it to his fellow men to be cheerful. Amidst all the trials and disappointments and anxieties and sufferings which pertain to this earthly existence, and which tend to shroud the soul in distressing gloominess, they have need at all times to see " lights " in the world,-to see those whose faces constantly beam with a heavenly glory,--whose   PRIZE ESSAY.          5 looks and words and deeds are a good medicine which never fails to give peace to the troubled spirit. And do you not think that if each one of the Lord's disciples were thus to pass the days of his pilgrimage; if his presence in the social circle, at the bedside of the sick, at the cottage of the poor, in the halls of learning, and at the mart of business, were hailed as a bright sunbeam which diffuses joy and gladness; if, in truth, his path were the path of the just, which, "as the shining light, shineth more and more unto the perfect day," our blessed religion would be well commended to the world, and the triumphs of the cross become glorious! It is the excellent remark of Archbishop Usher--"If good people would but make their goodness agreeable, and smile, instead of frowning, inl their virtue, how many would they win to the good cause! I The Christian owes it to his Lord to be habitually cheer- ful. His example must be copied, his will obeyed. You know the record of the Saviour's life, how that he spake unto , the man sick of the palsy, and to the terrified disciples tem- pest-tossed upon the Sea of Galilee, and to the little band weeping in prospect of their Lord's departure from the world, and to others troubled and sorrowful, and his words were ever the same--"Be of good cheer," "Be of good cheer." Then is it not the duty of every Christian to endeavor to attain that spiritual state in which he will be capable of receiving and doing the greatest amount of good (. We are assured that such is his duty, and we believe that cheerfulness is an exalted frame of mind, arising from and resting upon a firm faith, a strong love, a steadfast hope, and a good conscience-a state well pleasing to our Divine Master. Perhaps nothing has a greater tendency to cast gloom over the spirit than disease. The mind sympathizes with  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7515-00000004"/> 6-         PRIZE ESSAY. the body as much as the body with the mind. Their union -is so intimate, so delicate, so sensitive, that what affects the one necessarily affects the other. Each to a certain degree determines the other's condition. If the mind is joyful, its emotion is betrayed by the expression of the body. "A merry heart maketh a cheerful countenance.  But if the body is injured, or the physical system deranged, the mind at once suffers, and forthwith droops into sadness. It be- comes therefore, your Christian duty, if you have health, to study the laws of your physical being, to compel yourself both to labor and to rest, to avoid unnecessary risks or exposure, to abstain from injurious indulgences, to be pru- dent, temperate, chaste, and by every proper means, to try to preserve what is so essential to your spiritual comfort. ' If you have lost this boon, strive to regain it. Think not, speak not, all the while about your malady. Suppress moans and complaints; they are always disagreeable to ^ others, they can never be beneficial to you. Count your mercies and not your miseries. Try upon your body the stimulus of a cheerful spirit. It may not insure your recov- ery, but it will certainly produce a pleasant alleviation, s A merry heart doeth good like a medicine, but a broken spirit drieth the bones," Another cause of dejection is idleness. Employment is essential to our spiritual as well as our physical well- being. And it is only when we are engaged every day in some useful task, some enterprise of business some sportive recreation, some work of taste, some acquisition of learning, or some deed of charity-something that will call into action the hands, or the head, or the heart;-it is only when so doing that we have any right to expect health or happi- ness. An idle body is Death's easiest prey; an idle brain is either " the Devil's workshop," or "the slough of Dew   -               \\ PRIZE ESSAY.           7 spend." "They that do nothing," says Mason, ' are in the ready way to do worse than nothing. It was not for nothing that we were called out of nothing." Our Blessed Saviour " went about doing good." And you should do like- wisi if you profess to be his follower. If you have nothing to do for yourself, do something for others. When you cease to be idle, you may expect to be cheerful. The want of cheerfulness is often owing to the neglect of duty. A man may be in his counting-room when he ought to be in his closet. He may be looking over his ledger when he ought to be searching the Scriptures. He may be at a political meeting when he ought to be at the meeting for prayer. What he does may be right enough when it is done at a proper time; but when worldly business excludes or interferes with the performance of religious duty, then it becomes wrong; and in such a case, the Christian's spirit is soon prostrated under the severe scourgings of an offended conscience. Again, a man may fulfill one duty and at the same time slight another more important. He may act \ after the manner of the Pharisees, who paid " tithe of mint ^ and anise and cummin," while they " omitted the weightier matters of the law, judgment, mercy, and faith." Matt. 23: 23. The moral effect in this case will be the same as in the other. Conscious of his fault, the man feels depressed, and manifests his feeling by his, moody silence or querulous speech. Doubtless you pray to be kept free from this melancholy and disagreeable state, even though it were to last but for a single day. The rule for your guidance is plain:-Learn your whole duty and perform it well, and a heart filled with cheerfulness will be your sweet reward. When envy pushes out contentment from the soul, cheer- fulness goes with it. We sometimes complain and feel discontented when we see others living in more commodious  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7515-00000005"/> 8         PRIZE ESSAY. and elegant dwellings, better clad, more sumptuously fed, possessed of a higher refinement of mind or manners, or occupying a more exalted position than ourselves; but if we were to reflect that for every one above us, there are hundreds beneath, we would have less occasion, for sighs of regret, and more for songs of rejoicing. "Be content with such things as ye have," says the Apostle. He does not mean that we should be content with our sins, or with our ignorance, or with our imperfect graces, but with our worldly substance, and even concerning that he merely stops our mouths against murmurings, while he leaves our hands free to labor. And why should we not be content with our earthly comforts?  We have far more than we deserve more than many of our fellow-men, more than Christ had; and, if we are faithful, we will have better things by and by. When the soul is perplexed with doubts it is a stranger to cheerfulness. They cause uncertainty as to our change of heart and acceptance with God, or as to our belief in the truths of Divine Revelation. They are cobwebs which Satan weaves to obscure the vision of :iFaith. A breath of the Heavenly Spirit can clear them all away. Prayer sets in motion this invisible power. Sometimes doubts are frightful spectres which haunt the shades of ignorance. A few bright rays fromnt the lamp of God's Word will cause them speedily to disappear. Most frequently, doubts are the vile progeny of disease. The remedy which restores health to the body, will rid the soul of their annoying presence., Memory often causes dejection. It reminds us of our: neglected duties and misimproved privileges, our open arind secret sins, our unkind words and actions, our mistakes and disappointments, our trials and temptations, our disputes y and enmities, our sufferings and losses. We grow cheer- less looking at such a gloomy panorama of our lives. But   PR IZE ESSAY.          9 if we were to revert to our past enjoyments and mercies, and successes, to the good that we have done, to the wisdom which we have gained in the school of misfortune, to the full forgiveness which Christ has bestowed,-if we were to look mnore at the bright side of our experience, and less at the dark, we would rise soon, and completely, out of our de- spondency. Forebodings of evil rob the mind of cheerfulness. "Ills that never happened have mostly made men wretched," says Tupper. Casting our glance ahead, we see " lions " in the way,-difficulties which we are sure we can never over- come;-griefs, under whose heavy weight we shall be utterly crushed! Not satisfied with our present troubles, we borrow misery from the future. The Holy Scripture instructs us to do otherwise. "Thou knowest not what a day may bring forth."-Prov. 27: 1. "Take, therefore, no thought for the morrow; for the morrow shall take thought for the things of itself. Sufficient unto the day is the evil thereof."-Matt. 6: 34. And then it gives us a golden promise, s As thy days, so shall thy strength be." But after all, affZictions are the chief and most unavoida- ble cause of despondency., It may seem very unreasonable, like mockery indeed, to ask him to be cheerful, who has become the victim of disease, or who has seen his ship wrecked, his crops blasted, his cattle perish, his debtors fail, his property consumed or swept away with a flood, and, saddest of all! who has seen his beloved ones sicken and die, and buried in the earth! And yet, if he is a true child of God, it is his right, yea, it is his duty, amidst all these sore troubles, to be of good cheer. He may then regard his afflictions not as punishments for his sins, but only as Fatherly chastisements intended for his good-nmaking him humble, making him sensible of his weakness and unworth- I*  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7515-00000006"/> 10        PRIZE ESSAY. iness, and causing him to look to the Almighty for aid and comfort, and so well fitting him for his heavenly citizenship and his heavenly crown! Surely, God does not delight in lamentations and tears; and to the man himself, such things are useless-they cannot repair his losses, nor lighten his sufferings; and if proof were required, they are evidence enough that his heart was too much wedded to the world, and hence he had need to be afflicted. More pleasing to God is the cheerful and submissive spirit that can sing "songs in the night;"-that can say, "It is good for me that I have been afflicted. The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away; blessed be the name of the Lord! The Christian's worldly losses are his heavenly gains. Like a ship upon the stocks, he is ready, when the last of his earthly supports is knocked away, to launch forth into the widely extended sphere of a new life! The hindrances in the way of cheerfulness seem many; f but-it is encouraging to know that they are not alike to all, v and they are not so great but that they can be overcome. The end to be gained-is worthy of te best means, and the mightiest and most persistint enar. And duty urges every one to make an effort to rid his face of frowns, his manners of crabbedness, his heart of gloom. This obliga- tion rests with peculiar force upon the Lord's fllowers. Truly, O Christian! You above all men have reason to acquire and retain a cheerful disposition. No longer an alien from the commonwealth of Israel, a stranger to the covenants of promise, but redeemed, regenerated, forgiven, made a child of God, protected and nourished by your Almighty Father, trained, instructed, loved, having a man- sion in yonr Father's house, made an heir to h heavenly inheritance, and expecting soon to receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away-O! why should you, why should any -   PRIZE ES8A.          " one in such a case, give way to dejection? God's own tem- ple-purified, strengthened, adorned with beauty, furnished with every goodly and gladsome thing, filled with sacred light and peace, having within the glory of the shekinah- your devotions sweet incense, your heart a burning and acceptable sacrifice-O! have you not great reason for abiding cheerfulness! If in this life only you had hope in Christ, then, indeed, you might be miserable; but having "a hope which is as an anchor of the soul, both sure and steadfast, and,which entereth into that within the vail," how inexcusable does it seem that you should he habitually downcast and sorrowful! Arise, O Desponding One! Quit your tearful abode in the valley of gloom, and come and make your dwelling on the bright hill-top of cheerfulness. Look up! look up! and behold the sun shining through the clouds, and the stars through the darkness! yS , a  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7515-00000007"/>   ON THE MOUNTAIN. BY MISS MARY, E. ATKINSON, NAHANT, MASS,. Beneath the pines they sat that Autumn day, Upon the mountain, where beneath them rolled Unto the broad blue river far away, A sea of tossing gold. A sea of maples, dotted here and there With hemlock green, or oak of russet brown, And in the distance, through the smoky air, Appeared the silent town. No sound, except of bells, could come so far, And they came sweet and low, too musical Upon the whisper of the woods to jar, Or v"oice of waterfall. They saw, beyond the gorgeous Autumn trees, The white-winged vessels on the rivers breast Glide to their place among the city's quays, As sea-birds to their nest.  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7515-00000008"/> "          PRIZE  P-OEM. The pines' low music, like the distant song Of angels, filled the pauses of their words, And farewell chirpings from the gathering throng Of the departing birds. They talked of life and all their former aims, Dwelt on each lofty dream and fair ideal, And then on duty and its urgent claims, The commonplace and real. "How oft," they said, " our projects brave and fair, And full, apparently, of lasting worth, Like rainbow-colored bubbles in the air, Break at the touch of earth. "And oft," they said, "' although we seem so free To choose, to will, to do, or to forbear, We meet resistless pressure, so that we Are baffled everywhere. "A force as real, constant as the weight Of the invisible air, which naught can flee; What shall we call it,? Providence, or fate? God's will, or destiny?" She spoke, with glowing cheek and sparkling eye, Of all that she had hoped to be and do, Her pure ambition and her purpose high, Her earnest strivings too. And then, with trembling lip and gathering tears, She told how she had failed in much she tried, And how the,cherished plans of earlier years Had all been set aside.   PRIZE  POEM.           15 Not by the slackening of a feeble will, Not by dull languor, had the plan been marred ; But, where her eager feet were pressing, still Shei found the pathway barred. Barred by the iron gates of circumstance, Hedged in by duty, till she felt that Himself had closed the door, forbade advance In paths she would have -trod. "Until," she said, " of all I hoped to be, All I was sure I should be, when the chains Which bound my early youth should leave me free, Only the dream remains. "Though then I knew my will could have no scope For action 'neath another's stern control, Yet Christ, I thought, in time will surely ope The prison of my soul. "But still I find my purposes are crossed, My plans are thwarted, and the good I sought To do on earth remains, like ripe seed lost, Only a barren thought. "And so, alas! I have but spent my strength For naught, in vain, in spite of hope and prayer; Have toiled in Life's hard field, to reap at length Only such failure there!" There was no lack of tender sympathy In those calm eyes of his, whose steadfast gaze Dwelt on the mountains as he made reply, Grand in their purple haze.  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7515-00000009"/> 16          PRIZi  POEM. The mountains, which beyond the river stood, With noble curves of outline, tender lights And shades, where knoll, or dell, or wood, Varied their misty heights.           IL "And is it not enough," he said, " for thee To recognize, in circumstance, that Hand? Christ's ways with us are deep; hereafter we Shall know and understand." "Yet Christ," she said, "who gave my higher powers, Would have me dare and do, enjoy, achieve; But petty cares 11fill up Life's fleeting hours. What leisure do they leave. "For aspiration, work for God and man, For scaling heights of knowledge, thence to see Still more of God - I fail in all Life's plan For want of liberty."        j He answered slow, as one whom Christ had taught Slow lessons by the years that came and went; Up from his heart's deep well he drew the thought For her encouragement. "Christ's richest gifts are two-fold, first relief, Then blessing. From our-hearts He takes the thorn And makes the rose of it. Out of our grief Our purest joy is born. "From out the ashes of our pleasures lost Spring up the fragrant, snow-white flowers of peace. When hopes of human rescue all are crossed He brings His own release.   P'RIZE  POEM'.          17 "In His beloved hands dread death became The gate of blessed life;- and thou shalt see Thy bondage, touched by His transformiing flame, Become thy liberty." He paused. "But can this be on earth," she said, "Or only when I tread the heavenly street? Will He take off, before He crowns my head, These fetters friom my feet?" He answered, "Let us hear the Master speak Through those who left the record in His Word. --I walk at liberty, because I seek Thy blessed precepts, Lord. "And,-Where the Spirit of the Iord abides Is liberty,-the glorious liberty Of Sons of God. Who in such words confides He cannot but be free. "Easy the charm which breaks our chain, each day We utter it, and yet the strife is o'er If we 'Thy will be done' can truly say; Then bondage is no more. "And blessed be His will, whose boundless love Hath promised all things. Naught can come of ill, For all, till we are safe in heaven above, Shall work out blessing still. "Yea, every longing of the soul for rest, Each aspiration, all for which we pray, These will He give us when He sees it best,. Or show His better way.  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7515-00000010"/> 18          PRIZE  POEM. "O that my soul had wings! we sighing cry. What wings? The dove's to hover round our nest On sweet love-errands? Eagle-wings to fly To glory's mountain-crest? " Or angel-wings to speed on tasks of heaven I Ah! when God's work demands increase of-powers, The wider range and freer flight is given, If such a task is ours;- "But wings to fly away ana be at rest He giveth not, for whither should we go, Away from duty on an endless quest Across a sea of woe? "The fretting friction of our daily life, Heart-weariness with loving patience borne, The meek endurance of the inward strife,         / The painful crown of thorn. "Prepare the heart for God's own dwelling place, Adorn with sacred loveliness his shrine, And brighten every inconspicuous grace For God alone to shine. "As Druid builders on the ancient plains, Stonehenge's giant circles stretching wide, Smoothed every massive block with toil and pains Upon the inner side, "In honor of the gods who dwelt within, Beside the altar of their sacrifice,           So must our secret souls be purged from sin For Christ's oulniscient eyes. ,    PRIZE POEM.            19 "And He alone, who only knoweth man, And knoweth life, and what its changes teach, Is wise to choose and competent to plan The earthly path of each. "Perhaps, as once to David, so to thee He kindly saith, ' That this was in thine heart To do, is well; and yet it must not be, Beloved though thou art.' "Noble to human eyes appears the dream Of Christian life thy earnest heart hath wrought, But wouldst thou follow Christ's, or thine own scheme? Thine, or His perfect thought?  "I know thy heart gives fullest answer,' His.' Look where the tracings of his finger run Through circumstance, this daily life which is, And which thou, blind, wouldst shun. "What is the fetter which hath galled thee so? See'! it is but the Master's loving hand. Dost thou not welcome it? Wouldst thou forego The dear, though hard command? "If thou art restive, it is but to bless, Its pressure grows so heavy, only yield, And it shall prove thy Saviour's kind caress, And all thy hurt is healed." She bowed her head upon her hands; the tears Fell like the drops of summer's blessed rain; The weariness, the inward strife of years, The dull, heart-aching pain  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7515-00000011"/> 20          PRIZE  POEM. Passed all away as clouds disperse 'and flee At touch of sunshine; and aloud she thought, "Hath Jesus been indeed so long with me, And yet I knew Him not  "Hath he indeed been ordering all my life While I have spurned His plan and sought my own? It never would have been,-this sinful strife, If I His voice had known!" "Yea, He knows that!" he answered. "Earth would be In spite of sorrow, far too sweet a place For discipline, might we but always see The Master's loving face. "O when we look from realms of perfect light Ohn all the path which so perplexed us here, When all the clouds and darkness of our night In glory disappear, "How poor will seem the schemes we blindly made I How wise and good Christ's plan for every soul l Strange that we hesitate and are afraid To yield to His control! "Not only must we learn to do, but bear, Not only act, but suffer; firmly tread The lowly, thorn-strewn, weary pathway where The Man of Sorrows led. "Ah, what are we, poor scholars in Christ's school, Who think to choose our lessons? Let Him teach What pleaseth Him, all-wise to overrule The daily task of each.?'   PRIZE  POEM.          21 "But what," she questioned, "if He takes the books From which He bid us study, all away, And we, with folded hands and puzzled looks Sit idle all the day? 'What if the task He set, when but commenced, Be given to other hands, or laid aside, All paths to other labor closely fenced, Our prayer for work denied?" He answered gently, "Only heaven can show If work- or waiting bring the best reward: Let us not choose; we only need to know The bidding of our Lord. "It may be that He lets our labor cease, And calls us from our active sphere apart, To talk with us in secret, breathe His peace, Console and cheer our heart. "It may be that His only word is, 'Trust ' Be not found wanting, if He try thee so, But answer, ' Lord, I know not what thou dost, Nor do I ask to know.' "A/h, let us sit in silence at His feet, Intent to hear His words of wondrous grace; Rebuked like Martha by those accents sweet, Let us take Mary's place. "Dear friend, thy heart is sad and sorrowful Because the fabric which the slow years weave,- Thy life,-to thee looks narrow, coarse, and dull-; Courage? thou needst not grieve.  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7515-00000012"/> 22         PRIZE  POEM. "When dipped in Jordans wave, and sunned in light That knows no shading on the farther shore, Thy weft will shine all lustrous, pure and white, Unstained forevermore.  "And God, whose wonderful eternity Knows neither past nor future, sees thee now Crowned with the grand perfection that shall be, His glory round thy brow. a Why do we grieve, when neither change nor chance Can work us evil? Let us trust for-time, Heirs of an infinite inheritance, A name and home sublime I " She raised her eyes and smiled, as one who saw Afar the dawn of perfect peace and rest, Of freedom under Christ's most loving law, Of acquiescence blest. "Master," she prayed, increase our faith, that hence We lose not sight of heavenly hills serene, Faith, substance of things hoped, and evidence Of what is yet unseen."   THE SOLDIER AND THE VIOLETS. BY MSS CARRIE A. SPALDING, HAVERHTLL, N. H. The twilight of Virginia skies, Was shedding softened rays Upon a blood-stained battle-field, The last of fearful days. Our valiant men had bravely fought, Nor shrank from shot or shell: The deeds of those terrific days Shall future records tell 1 And mingled there in close embrace Were seen the deadliest foes, The fury of the awful strife Now hushed to calm repose. Dead faces there with their white brows Looked up from grassy beds, And o'er them all the rising moon Its cold pale lustre sheds  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7515-00000013"/> 24         PRIZE  POEM. Amid the gathering of the slain A wounded soldier lies, The life-blood oozing from his sides- The dimness in his eyes. But through the air a perfume steals, Borne on the zephyr's breath, That brings his sinking, fainting soul Back from the gates of death. A bed of sweet blue violets, Not very far away, Had sent its messengers of love Where the poor soldier lay.          " And as the fragrance filled the air, Home memories mingled too; Wounded and bleeding, yet he crept Where those blue violets grew. He filled his hand with the sweet flowers, Then laid his dying head Upon the bank, while to his home His wandering fancies fled;- That peaceful home, far, far away, Which, one short year ago, He left, with all its wealth of love, To fight the rebel foe. Again he hears the robin's song Among the waving trees; Or, where the apple-blossoms fall, The humming of the bees.   P'RIZE  POEM.          25 Fainting, and thirsting, now he sees, Upon the hillside near, The brook come babbling, gushing down, With waters bright and clear. He bathes his wan and bloody brow, He tastes'the healing draught; Never was nectar from the gods With such a pleasure quaffedL Still o'er his dying, sinking frame The violets' odor steals, And every breath of perfume there Some home delight reveals: The rose-tree climbing at the door, And, by the porch, the vine, Which round the grand old shadowing oak, Its tendrils doth entwine. And now his eye grows brighter still; He sees in visions clear The loved ones of the household band, A happy group, appear. Their smiles beam brightly as of old, And then their eyes grow dim: The soldier hears them breathe his name- The tears are shed for him. And still he clasps those precious flowers, As if he held the chain That bound his sinking, fainting soul To all he loved again. 2  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7515-00000014"/> 26 4        PRIZE  POEM. And while he breathes the sweet perfume, His mother's hand seems now, In all its tender soothing, laid Upon his heated brow. The gathering death-damps he heeds not, Nor yet the ghastly wound; Sweet voices whisper in the ear Now closed to earthly sound. And there, on that lone battle-field, Just in the twilight gray, 'Mid dreams of home And cherished ones, His spirit passed away. His hands still clasped the violets blue, But on the pale, cold face, A smile was brightly beaming now, Which death could not efface. And so they laid him down to rest, No tears above him shed; Ah, little dream they, in his home, Of that lone, cheerless bed. So let him rest, and may our God Grant peace and consolation To'those who mourn the loved and lost Who died to save the nation! j   1           ,   PRIZE   POEM.            27 Oh the valiant dead, in -their nameless graves! Where the night winds sigh, and the tall grass waves, With no marble tablet, or sculptured stone, To record the deeds of the brave unknown! With their young brows shaded forevermore By the brown locks steeped in the crimson gore, With only the " army blue " for a shroud, And their "pall " the gloom of the evening cloud. The light has gone out frohi each flashing eye; The hearts that with valor were bounding high Have ceased to thrill at their country's wrongs, But a deathless fame to their name belongs. The hand is now still, that had grasped the brand To stike with its vengeance the rebel band-; The lips now are sealed, that with song and cheer Rallied 'round the " old flag" each brave volunteer. The banner lies stained, and soiled, and torn, Which our heroes have once so proudly borne; These sons of the mountain, fearless and free, The wail of the storm shall their requiem be. Unwept, and alone, in silence they lie; No sorrowing tears from a loved one's eye, Save the drops of dew the eventide sheds On the smooth green turf of their lowly beds. But think ye their names are lost from the earth? That they shed their blood, of such priceless worth, As a useless offering--all in vain? Like waters outpoured on the desert plain.   &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7515-00000015"/> 28          PRIZE   POEM . Think ye they have passed from their homes away, Like the mountain mists in the morning ray?- Like echoes that die on a far distant shore, Leaving sorrow and silence for us evermore? No! these battle fields, henceforth they shall be Our richest, our holiest legacy; For beneath their soil there are buried gems Iore precious than monarch's diadems. And He who sitteth enthroned above, Where all is beauty, and light, and love, Has marked each spot, where the soldiers lie, With the watchful care ef a "Father's" eye. It is hallowed with loyal patriot blood, Tho' the soil was bathed in the crimson flood; But a richer hardest shall upward spring, Than ever the Nile in its course could bring Brave hearts shall thrill, as the story they tell Of the slaughtered comrades here that fell, And a nobler aim shall inspire each breast At the valiant deeds of the heroes at rest. How they marched with a firm, unfaltering tread, Wherever the call of the trumpet led,  Alike through the tempest of shot and shell,  To the cannon's mouth, where the bravest fell. How they lingered wearisome days of pain, On those scorching battle fields yet again, With the palsied lip and the glazing eye, And no word of earthly comforting nigh,   - PRIZE  POEM.          29 How, maimed and helpless, weary and worn, The burden of life was patiently borne, With never a word of repining gloom At hopes that were crushed in their early bloom. Of heroes like these, with triumph we sing- The richest gifts to our country we bring- And offer them up on her holiest shrine, Saying, "Take them, oh land! for the best is thine.".. Oh, these unknown dead!-and yet not unknown: There are homes they have loved, and called their own, Where each morning brought, on its sunlight air, Its cravings of blessings, and earnest prayer, That all through the hours of the coming day, In the wearisome march or the battle's fray, The loved and the cherished might sheltered be By the watchful care of the "One in Three."  Like the "shade of a rock in a dreary land," Or bulwarks that 'round the defenceless stand, So in peril and strife, amid dying and dead, -The ' Eternal arms" nmight around them be spread. That alike in the struggle, and in the repose, 'Mid the snares of the tempter, and conflict with foes, These dear ones beneath His presence might rest Who shields from the tempest the sparrow's nest. And now, when that prayer is turned to woe- To that hopeless grief that no comfort can know- Think ye that their memory passes away, Because they are hidden from sight to-day?  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7515-00000016"/> 30          PRIZE  POEM . Each familiar spot where their footsteps played Has become a shrine, whereon gifts are laid; Each flower that blossoms, and tree that waves, Brings a tearful thought of these nameless graves. In the sunshine of life, amid laughter and song, There is ever a shadow comes stealing along; Amid sweetest strains of music, and mirth, Comes an echo of voices now hushed on the earth. By the hearthstone is ever a vacant chair; In some casket a lock of clustering hair:-- But the noble head, with its dauntless brow, In the " stranger soil " is mouldering now. Henceforth in these homes is a sacred name, An altar that burns with a purer flame: 'Tis perfumed with incense, hallowed by prayer- No shadow- can darken the memories there. Home voices shall thrill with a deeper tone, When 'tis breathed in the twilight hours alone, And the eye shall kindle with a holier light, Recalling a glance that is scaled in night. And when coming years shall see our fair land On a firmer foundation of liberty stand; When freedom, honor, and justice, at length,. Shall be, to her, towers and bulwarks of strength; When her empire stretches from shore to shore, And her glad banners float the wide land o'er, The proudest thing in her record shall be The heroes who fell that she might be free.   PRIZE   POEM.,           31 Who rushed to the conflict, fearless and brave, To lay their young heads in the patriot's grave, To offer themselves for the Nation's life, And heal with their life-blood the " waters of strife." Ah, nobler fai than the sculptured stone Is the deathless fame our soldiers have won  And brighter 'twill grow, as the years pass away, When marbles shall crumble and fall to decay. Then, thanks to our God, in our peril and woe, That such aid was given to ward off the foe. Through tear-bedimmed eyes, still trusting, we gaze On the banner which floated in happier days. And soon may the glittering sword be sheathed, And the standard with olive branches wreathed, The sighs and tears of the weepers be o'er, And the blood-stained land be at peace once more I  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7515-00000017"/> 4              6   -               r- Aid Pqi%! XigS, THE BROTHERS LEINHARDT. v BY MSS FRANCES W. OWSTON, PITTSBURG, PENN. ON the borders of a pretty Swedish lake lies the-,. village of Lundkolping. Lake and yillage are each so tiny I doubt if you would deemn them worthy of the name; but the lake, pure, deep, and cool, is the prettiest and clearest of all lakes. The old forest trees (clustering to the very brink, till the long gray moss from their branches trails in the quiet water) wreathe around it a rich emerald garland, and numberless fishes sport in its calm depths. The huge mountain, sheltering it from boisterous winds, casts its rug- ged shadow on the mirroring surface, and down its steep sides, dashing and foaming-down, down, from the far region where the untrodden snow lies under an ever-cloudless sky, dashes a mountain brooklet, bearing to the lake its tribute of limpid waters, and the lake, taking the sparkling treasure to its deep bosom, sends it forth again in a tiny stream, winding its quiet way through the village to gladden the hearts of weary-footed housewives. On either side of the public road clusters the village, with its quaint little houses 2*   &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7515-00000018"/> 34        PRIZE STORY. of squared pine logs, painted a dull, red, and covered with mossy thatch. The gray old church stands just at the mountain's foot, and many an old legend and strange story will they tell you as you loiter in the sombre twilight of its low massive arches. In the grassy churchyard round, where year after year, year after year, for, ohi! so long, sire and son have lain down side by side, sleeping the same dream- less sleep, is shown a spot where rest, they say, the ashes of a grim old sea king, who spent his lifetime plowing the stormy seas, seizing, with right kingly selfishness, whatever his heart desired, and reaching even the green slopes of Vineland in his wild roamings. "He wandered east, he wandered west," till, weary of his wanderings, he returned to his old boyhood's haunts, and sleeps beneath the turf his childish feet had pressed. Ah! poor old sea king; another king, clad in royal purple, sitting on his lion-garnished throne of gold and ivory, the wisest, the richest, the most powerful of the earth, had published the sad truth long, long before you: "The eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear with hearing." I doubt if it were new even in his day; I fear Tubal Cain read it in the glare of his molten metals, and that the " longing for what is not ' mingled its wailing voice with the harpings of Jabal. Peace be with you, weary old Viking; perchance to Him, all-seeing as all-holy, thy crimes of blood and violence gleam not with deeper crimson than our daintier sins, which scarce call forth a sigh of penitence, or tinge our cheeks with shame. God pity us!, A Sabbath stillness reigns around this little village, broken only by the laugh or shout of children, the voices of women calling to their neighbors, or the ringing of the axe on the sturdy mountain pine; and at evening, echoed and re-echoed by the deep gorges, are heard the plaintive call of   PRIZE STORY.          35 the milkmaids and the lowing of the quiet herds. In this sequestered nook life flows on in a calm, unruffled current. A stranger gazing on the tranquil scene, beholding every- where hale health and peace and plenty, would exclaim: "Surely, here, if anywhere on earth, must dwell pure inno- cence and happiness." Ah, me! the devil is a wondrous wight, and manages to keep his myriad irons glowing hot 'mid all his bustle. Though he doubtless holds his high court in great cities, and finds in potent opportunity a fruit- ful aid, yet there's not on all this great round world a spot so tiny or remote that he'll neglect it if inhabited by man. Traces of his nimble fingers show themselves even here, in this lonely mountain village; and sin and sorrow make the office of the holy man, whose voice from week to week awakes the echoes of that quaint old church, no empty sine- cure. At some distance from this village there stood, many years ago, a little brown house, weather-beaten and old, but strong and sturdy. A goodly heritage of sunny meadow lands and fertile fields stretched out on every side, and huge, substantial barns, that scarce could hold the teeming har- vests, clustered round the little brown house, making its dwarfed proportions seem yet more pigmy. Large flocks grazed in the pastures, and the air was filled with the low- ing of cattle, the cackle of poultry, and all the sounds that -tell of rural abundance. Here, without wife or child, dwelt Hans Andersen, the richest man for miles and miles around. Many times and oft the simple folks would gaze upon his herds broad fields, and bursting barns, and sigh, 'If I were as rich as Hans Andersen," as hopelessly and longingly as i  we would say, "As rich as Rothschild." Perhaps none thought this half so often or so earnestly as Franz Leinhardt, who lived in a cot on the mountain  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7515-00000019"/> 8fi        PRIZE STORY. side, from which he could view his neighbor's smiling fields. He and his brother, many years his junior, followed the the calling of wood-cutters in the neighboring forest. No sooner had the first pale heralds of the day appeared, chas- ing the shadows to their lurking-places, than their sturdy strokes resounded through the forest; and not till the sun was hid, and deep gloom- gathered among the trees, did they wend their weary way homeward. Few merry-mak- ings could boast Franz's presence, but when he did appear at bridal or at Christmas feast, he sat with the old men, listening to their wisdom, and mingled not with the bois- terous rout of younger revelers. To woman's charms, he seemed impervious. No female glance, were it sly or art- less, bright or tender, could. bring a glow to his swart cheek, or quicken a pulse of his cold heart. 'Tis needless to say that while grave heads of families praised him, saying, "'Twould be a lucky girl who got so saving and industrious husband," he was no favorite with the bright-eyed Swedish maidens, on whose ruby lips he was "Old Franz Leinhardt" while his cheek was yet decked with the silken down of early manhood; but, alas! Franz cared as little for their frown or favor as for the linnets that his ringing axe scared from their accustomed perch. Gold was-the idol of his wor- ship. Even in the little world in which he lived he saw that poverty was a reproach no virtue or sense could quite wipe away, and that wealth conferred a dignity that mere good qualities could not command. What wonder then that he longed to close his grasp on the weird necromancer that can make men bow humbly down, calling deformity beauty, vice virtue, fatuity intelligence. Fifty times a day the eager, envious wish, "If I were as rich as Hans Andersen," swelled his heart or found utterance at his lips. He knew the wish was wild and unattainable as the cry of a babe for   PRIZE STORY.          37 a star. Working from earliest dawn to latest twilight, spending but what a bare necessity required, he needs must know, count as he would, that a patriarch's life would. not suffice to gain wealth at that poor plodding rate; but he thirsted for gain, and laid coin to coin. The demons Envy and Love of Gold, which he strove not against, hardened his -heart, and held it closely barred, lest Pity, Love, or Joy should enter; and as the years rolled on his life grew bar- ren of kind words or generous deeds, and in his eyes mis- fortune seemed a crime. Yet he was sober, honest, and industrious; none went more regularly to the church, or bent with deeper reverence in prayer, and this he deemed religion, forgetting, as too many of us do, that "He prayeth well who loveth well both man, and bird, and beast." His brother Flemming, handsome, generous, and good natured, with a ready laugh and readier jest, was of a very different spirit, and wherever fun or good fellowship brought the neighbors together, there was Flemming. Envy was unknown to him. Little cared he how much the heavy- headed harvest of Hans Andersen's fields waved their golden treasures before his eyes, so long as Christina's ringlets of brighter gold shone in the sun-light, or were tossed against his cheek by wanton breezes.  Ilans Andersen's herds might have lowed themselves hoarse without winning a thought, when, with her hand in his, they skimmed over the frozen lake, the rattle of the skates and voices of the skaters making merry music under the laughing stars, while the bright aurora painted the dark vault of heaven with gold. and crimson till the snow-clad earth grew rosy. Perhaps as they gathered fir in the sombre forest to strew upon the floors, and Christina stood holding her apron to receive the fragrant tips, her innocent eyes cast upwards, pure and blue a's dew-moistened field flowers, he may have wished for  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7515-00000020"/> 838        PRIZE STORY. wealth to deck her with a crimson bodice and silken kirtle, and put a ring of gold upon her dimpled hand, but avarice had no place in his heart. A penniless orphan was the fair- haired Christina, and maid of the village inn; but when the weary working day was over, and Flemming received from her hands his mug of home-brewed ale and oaten cake, what prince so blest! Love breathed upon them, the humble cot became an elysium, and each with ecstacy ruled supreme over that boundless empire-a loving heart. Why are ye so fleeting, oh happy days of warm young love! when a look or word has power to swell the heart with joy unspeak- able, and tinge life's weary, rugged road with all hope's rainbow hues! It is needless to say that Franz looked on this wooing with no favoring eyes, and when in due course of time the young people changed courtship's fairy land for the sober realities of matrimony, he heaped many bitter, angry reproaches on his brother. Forgetting that He who said "Thou shalt not steal," said also, "He that loveth not his brother abideth in death," Franz thought himself blame- less because he made a just division of his hoarded gains, though he robbed the young couple of what God had made their due-a brother's love and sympathy; and Flemming, his heart wounded and estranged, went with his bride to the neighboring city to push his fortunes amid- its crowd and bustle. Very soon after, Hans Andersen-the rich Hans Ander- sen-died in a fit, just as any poor man might. It had seemed to the simple folks that even death, "the mighty leveler," must respect so great a man, and a sort of wonder mingled with their lamentations. Many relations whom he had neither known nor loved came mourning to his funeral; 1 but when his will was read, it was found he had bequeathed his whole possessions and effects to his good neighbor Franz,   PRIZE STORY.          39 as one who would not squander or abuse riches. "As rich as Hans Andersen!"Yes, every rood and herd that once were his now called Franz Leinhardt master. He had reached the highest pinnacle of his ambition, and sat in the seat, nay, wore the coat and stood in the shoes of him he had most envied; still I doubt if he were half so happy, with all his wealth and consequence, as his brother, poor and struggling for each day's bread, but crowned with the tender love of wife and children. Year after year had rolled away, till many had joined the ages past, and laid their irre- vocable record of good and evil deeds before the throne of God, and the solemn slow-moving years as they passed had hardened Franz's heart, and marked his face with wrinkles. The little brown house still stood amid the broad smiling fields and huge barns, strong and sturdy as of yore, and it would have puzzled a good guesser to say which was the elder-the dry brown old house, or the brown dry-looking old man who lived in it; both looked as if they might have challenged King Time to a trial of strength, and come off victorious. The great barns and out-houses were full to overflowing with earth's richest harvests, as in the days when Franz Leinhardt, the wood-cutter, gazed enviously at them from his cot on the mountain side. Plenty and to spare Franz had, but there had been little comfort or happiness in the little brown house since he called himself its master. No weary wayfarer blessed his hospitality, nor eager children gleaned the scatterings of his fields; he saved money to make more money-to save more money-not to purchase his own ease or luxury, or to do good to others. Forsaking all other pleasures and affections, he loved Mammon only, and toiled and slaved for gold. 'Twas all he had to love. No wife had gladdened the little brown house with her loving smiles, q(   &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7515-00000021"/> 40        PRIZE STORY. nor children's voices woke its slumbering echoes. "Wom- en," he said, "were extravagant and lazy-they were silly and useless, and he was not rich enough to keep a wife in idleness; ' but I doubt if any of the fair-haired, blue-eyed maids- of Lundkolping would have had him for all his gold. But while wealth flowed into the strong box of Franz, and stuck there as if wedged and welded fast, Flemming's little stock of worldly goods had found-wings and flown away, and turn which way he would he found himself pursued by an overwhelming tide of ill fortune; yet was there many a honey-drop in his bitter cup. Christina, no longer rosy- cheeked and dimple-handed, was as tender and true as in the May-day of their love, and met fate bravely, toiling early and late to help provide for the six sturdy children who made her merry with their laughter. It must be admitted, however, that highly as these heart-treasures are prized by their possessors (and I have heard very poor men say worlds could not buy one of them), they are more likely to drag a man down to the mire of poverty than raise him to the sunny plains of affluence. Through all these years, while Franz was growing richer and richer, Flemming was slipping down the grim descent, till he landed at the bottom sick and penniless. His good wife wept, and prayed, and toiled; but eight mouths are hard to fill, and one cold, bleak winter day found the young Leinhardts keeping a forced fast, with no corresponding feast in prospect. The mother sat beside her sick husband with despair in her face, till the tears and lamentations of her children were unendurable, and throw- ing a shawl over her head, she sallied out in the drifting snow and blustering wind to- try if, after years of estrange- ment, Franz could not be moved to part with some of his hoarded wealth to save his kindred from famine. She toiled along the rough road in the face of a storm that nearly blew   PRIZE STO R Y.         41 her away, without feeling much of its fury, for her heart was in her poverty-stricken home; but when she reached the little brown house she trembled, hesitating to supplicate the pity of a man so hard and unrelenting. - She peeped timidly in at the window. Franz was sitting in a large arm chair, before a great blazing fire, smoking his pipe with dreamy satisfaction. On the mantle before him there stood a quaint old clock, and while she gazed the wheels began to whirr, and out popped a queer little man in a red night-cap, holding a tiny bag ih each hand, which he clanked together three or four times, nodding and rolling his odd little head all the time. Franz took the pipe from his mouth, and nodded gravely to the little manikin, which darted into the clock atgain, and all was silent. Four o'clock! Already night was closing in, the snow fell in thicker flakes, and the wind grew each moment more blustering-the poor woman felt there' was no time to lose. Her timid knock brought Franz to the door, and with a broken voice and sinking heart she began her story; but no sooner did he understand that she wanted help than he motioned her impatiently from the door, saying: "Go, go; am I to blame that my brother is a fool, and has a pack of children? Had he minded me, he would have had no such plagues. 'Tis only worthless, idle people who are poor and need help. I won't encourage imprudence and mismanagement." "But my husband is sick; how can I leave him to work for my children?" sobbed poor Christina. "Let him go to a hospital; be in- dustrious and frugal, and take care of your children: 'tis your business, not mine," returned Franz, roughly. "Ah me!' cried the poor woman, clasping her hands, and rais- ing her tearful eyes to the stormy sky; "it is night and winter; my children are starving; surely I shall go mad ;" and as she turned sadly away, she said, "I pray God the  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7515-00000022"/> 42        PRIZE STORY, gold that has so hardened your heart' may never weigh so heavy on your soul that you cannot mount to glory," and with a bowed head and slow step she disappeared in the storm and darkness. Franz stood looking after her with something like remorse in his heart, till night shrouded her from his view, and then he returned to his bright fire, his arm chair, and his pipe ; but a spell was on him-nothing seemed so cheery and comfortable as it had done before that woman came. If he looked into the fire, he saw faces there that he did not want to see; in the dark corners of the room were shadows of drooping figures; from among the old carvings and mouldings looked out thin famine-worn visages, and the old clock kept ticking over Christina's words: "Pray God the gold that has so hardened your heart may never weigh so heavy on your soul that you cannot mount to glory." He wondered at himself, for he had done no new thing; hard and selfish actions constituted his life, but never before had memory given him one moment's uneasiness. He piled the great logs upon the fire, refilled his pipe, and strove to banish such thoughts, but his efforts were in vain; that heart-broken woman haunted him, and her last words passed and repassed monotonously through his brain, till at length, being unable to forget, Franz suffered his thoughts to dwell upon them patiently. He soon began to calculate how much gold would so weigh down a soul, and he wished- wicked wretch that he was-that some demons would give him a trial; not that he was more willing to lose his soul than another, but being very shrewd, he could think of fifty ways to keep the gold and cheat the devil. In such thoughts as these time slipped away, the fire smouldered down to glowing coals, and shadows crept across the floor. Amid the deep silence the wheels of the clock began to whirr, and   PRIZE STORY.          43 forth from his retreat darted the little man in the red night. cap, clanking his bags together twelve times. This Franz expected, but his astonishment was extreme when, instead of returning modestly to his den in the old clock, as he had done every hour for years, the goblin, demon, or whatever he was, seated himself on the mantle shelf, nodding and winking at Franz as if there was some deep secret between them. Franz rubbed his bewildered eyes, and stared with all his might. There sat the little manikin, knocking his tiny heels together, and eyeing him with a look of malicious intel- ligence. "I can do it for you, Leinhardt," said he at length, with a knowing wink; "look at these," shaking his little bags triumphantly, " they are full of gold." Franz laughed aloud. Ten thousand of such Lilliputian bags would not have been a drop in the great ocean of his avarice. "Don't laugh, Franz Leinhardt," said the goblin, with an angry frown, "I could shake gold enough from these bags to bury you, if I wished; lie down and place your strong box upon your breast, and I will give you gold as long as you can bear its weight; but have a care you don't take more than you call lift, for though I can give, I cannot take away." Franz felt inclined to laugh, but did as he was bid, stretch- ing himself on the floor, with his strong box on his breast, and the little goblin, perching himself upon the side, began to pour a small but glittering stream of gold from his two little bags. The weight increased slowly; at first Franz tried to move it frequently, but as the box grew heavier his exultation knew no bounds, and so loath was he to lose one grain of the precious yellow dust, that it was not till a sense of suffocation oppressed him, and he found his strength barely sufficient to move the box, that he cried, "Stop!" "( Oh! you are not allowing for my weight," said the goblin briskly, and Franz, easily persuaded, permitted him to pour  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7515-00000023"/> "        PRIZE STORY, in a little more. The gold seemed to flow much faster than before, and again he cried, "Stop! stop!" for the weight was crushing him. With a shrill laugh, the goblin disap- peared, yet the box, was not a whit lighter for his absence, and Franz strove in agony to move it, but in vain. Poor Franz! He had now what he hoped, and longed, and toiled for-gold, heavy yellow gold, more than he could lift, though he struggled ever so hard; yet it was with no loving clasp that he wreathed his arms around it. His heart loathed its former idol as he groaned and writhed beneath the weight which pinned him to the perishing earth, and every grain of shining dust would he have given fore the memory of one act of loving charity that might win from the cloud-throned Prince of the poor and needy, the welcome sentence-"In- asmuch as ye have done it unto one of these, my brethren, ye have done it unto me." Days, months, and years rolled on till ages had passed in this unutterable agony, when he perceived a strange commotion all around him, and knew intuitively that the end of all things earthly was at hand. Suddenly a bright light shone around, and a crowd of peo- ple entered the room, and gathered sadly about him. Look- ing from face to face, he recognized friends, acquaintances, and servants, and foremost among them his brother, with his wife and children. Then was heard a voice, saying- "This soul has been suffering for ages, and he has learned to hate the gold he worshipped, therefore any of you his kindred, friends, or servants, whom he has helped, may aid him to remove the awful load that binds -him to the earth." A cry of hopeless despair burst from Franz's lips as his eyes wandered from face to face, and only the memory of harsh words and selfish actions -rose up before him. One person, turning to his brother Fleinming, said--"You were a poor sickly creature, with many children often in need of He   PRIZE STORY.          45 daily bread; surely he has given you of his abundance, and you can help him." But Flemming sadly shook his' head, and Christina, whose heart was always pitiful' wept as she turned away, her face reminding Franz of that stormy win- ter night, long, long ago, when he had driven her from his door, cold, hungry, and sore. One by one they passed away, with sad, regretful looks, and a solemn voice, like a distant echo, was heard- "THE GOLD THAT SO HARDENED HS HEART HAS BOCND HM TO THE EARTH; HE CAN NEVER MOUNT TO GLORY." As his friends departed, the light faded away, and he was left to his doom alone and in darkness; he suffered an eternity of anguish. With all the wild energy of despair he struggled, shrieking for mercy, when suddenly the earth gave way be- neath him, and, oh horrors! he felt himself falling-falling -until his head came down with a dreadful thump on the broad stone hearth, and opening his eyes, he found himself lying among the dead embers. He sat up and rubbed his eyes; daylight was glimmering through the windows; but every trace of box, or gold, or goblin had disap- peared. He looked fearfully and shuddered as the little man in the red nightcap popped out, and nodding his head knowingly, clanked his tiny bags together. Back he darted again as usual, and his master sat down in deep thought. The servants were just up and stirring when Franz appeared among them, not as a hard taskmaster to urge on their labors, but to issue such orders, that they declared to each other there was no saying what would happen next. Such a bustle arose in the little brown house as it had not seen for many a long, long day, and before an hour had passed, old Franz was driving his wagon towards his brother's house, laden with good things for the sick and hungry: It was his first errand of mercy, and very queer and bewildered  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7515-00000024"/> "       ?R I Z E ST O R rY. he felt driving along through the sharp morning air, not to increase his wealth, but to give a part to the poor and needy; and many old-fashioned texts grew bright and fresh in his memory which he had well nigh forgotten, such as- "He that hath pity upon the poor lendeth unto the Lord; and that which he hath given will he pay him again."  "Blessed be the mall that provideth for the sick and needy; M the Lord shall deliver him in time of trouble." When poor Christina was so rudely repulsed from her brother-in-law's door, she betook herself with swift foot and heavy heart to her weary homeward road. The night was dark, the way long and rough, and the wind wild and pierc- ing. Hope, that can lighten theheaviest load, was dead; arid love, man's choicest blessing, seemed a bitter curse since the sufferings of each loved one wrung her heart with anguish. When she reached her home, Flemming raised his languid head and gazed at her with questioning eyes; and the little children seized her gown, and crowded round with their clamorous "What did Uncle Franz give you, mother?' "Nothing, nothing, my children. Ah me! yes, a few hard words." Flemming lay down and closed his eyes, and the eager little questioners went supperless to bed, and wept themselves to sleep. God help the mother who hears her children cry in vain for bread! But where will they find help who hear such cries without pity? -when Christ shall say: 1' I was an hungered, and ye gave me no meat; I was naked, and ye clothed me not."  All - the long sad night Christina sat by her cold hearth, almost too despairing to pray; but when the day broke- its cold, bleak, comfortless light making the desolation of her home seem yet more drear-wonder of all wonders! Franz's wagon drew up at the door, and the little man, nervous and fidgety as one will be in a novel position,   PRIZE STORY.          47 jumped out, shook hands with Flemming and his wife, and hastened to deliver his load of comforts. After yesterday's repulse, Christina could not have been more astonished had a flock of ravens appeared with bread and meat in their beaks to minister to her necessities. Franz would hear none of their thanks or wonderment (which latter feeling greatly predominated in their minds); but, as he lifted out jar after jar, package after package, urging all around to quick despatch, and saw the brightened faces of the poor parents, and the eager enjoyment of 'the half- famished children, a pure happiness that he had never felt before thrilled his heart, and he felt that even in--this life mercy has a rich reward. To Christina, it seemed that heaven had wrought a miracle in answer to her prayers for succor; and many a trouble-tried soul did she cheer with the wondrous story. Though he pondered it long and deeply, Franz never told the strange dream that had roused his slumbering conscience; but from that night he was a dif- ferent man-his hand was now open to the suffering and needy; the wayfaring man no longer trudged wearily past the little brown house; the children of the poor joyfully gathered the droppings of his harvests; and though frugal, he was no longer miserly. His astonished neighbors shook their heads, saying such sudden changes boded death; but the event proved them wrong: Franz lived to a good old age; and what seemed at one time much less likely, when he did. die there were many who sincerely regretted him; for he had learned that " to know the art of alms is greater than to be crowned with the diadem of kings."  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7515-00000025"/> it to        arki bsttrbt.             1  O4: THE design with which this paper was founded, more than forty  years ago, has been faithfully adhered to, viz.: to give an im- partial view of                        - ALL RELIGIOUS DENOMNATIONS from week to week: defending and spreading the great doctrines of the Gospel which all evangelical Christians hold in common, to pro- mote union of heart and action among those who love God, and to hasten the coming of that day when the Church shall be one on earth as it is in heaven. To give this complete view of the WHOLE RELIGIOUS WORLD, CORRESPONDENTS in every quarter of the globe, keep us apprised of the progress of religion in the regions around them  ITS VARIOUS DEPARTMENTS, Commercial, Agricultural, Literary, &amp;c., are in the hands of men thoroughly conversant-with the subjects they discuss, and no pains or expense are spared to make these departments invaluable. The Mis- cellaneous reading, SECULAR AND RELIGIOUS, prepared by the best writers, renders the OBSERVER a useful and en- tertaining family paper for - THE OLD AND THE YOUNG. Many popular "olumes have been compiled from the letters and papers published in years past in these columns. Its Creat Objects are: To diffuse sound religious truth; To sustain the Government of the country; To promote peace and good will among men; To please and instruct the domestic circle with the best family news- paper that can be made. Terms.-$3.80 a year, payable IN ADVANCE; $4.00 a year, AFTER THREE MONTHS. Fifty Cents additional when served by carrier. SIDNEY E. MORSE, Jr. &amp; Co., 37 Park Row, Nezw York.     &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
