<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
   xml:id="VAC7211">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Martyr of the Catacombs </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7211</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1675</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                  copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction
                  project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                  University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
                  to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                  contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                  educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                  inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University
                  Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
               Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The martyr of the catacombs</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>202 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Hunt &amp; Eaton</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date from="1800" to="1899">[18--]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
               Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
               website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
               been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
               Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-29">Finished OCR, rough
            encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2006-01-15">Finished TEI
            conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Converted document from SGML to TEI
            P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents
            and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7211-00000001"/>
         <div type="frontis">
            
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Boy-Martyr See page 179</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE MARTYR OF THE CATACOMBS</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">A TALE OF ANCIENT ROME</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <q>
                     <p>If after the manner of men I have fought with beasts at Ephesus, what
                        advantageth it me, if the dead rise not?</p>
                  </q>
                  <bibl>—ST. PAUL</bibl>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <docEdition>ILLUSTRATED</docEdition>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>HUNT &amp; EATON</publisher>
               <pubPlace>CINCINNATI:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>CRANSTON &amp; CURTS</publisher>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="4-5 (Table of Contents/List of Illustrations) " xml:id="VAC7211-00000002"/>
         <div type="contents">
            
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. THE COLISEUM. <ref target="VAC7211-00000004" rend="right">7</ref>
               </item>
               <item>II. THE PRETORIAN CAMP. <ref target="VAC7211-00000013" rend="right">25</ref>
               </item>
               <item>III. THE APPIAN WAY. <ref target="VAC7211-00000018" rend="right">36</ref>
               </item>
               <item>IV. THE CATACOMBS. <ref target="VAC7211-00000024" rend="right">48</ref>
               </item>
               <item>V. THE CHRISTIAN'S SECRET. <ref target="VAC7211-00000032" rend="right">63</ref>
               </item>
               <item>VI. THE CLOUD OF WITNESSES. <ref target="VAC7211-00000038" rend="right"
                     >75</ref>
               </item>
               <item>VII. THE CONFESSION OF FAITH. <ref target="VAC7211-00000049" rend="right"
                     >97</ref>
               </item>
               <item>VIII. LIFE IN THE CATACOMBS. <ref target="VAC7211-00000055" rend="right"
                     >110</ref>
               </item>
               <item>IX. THE PERSECUTION. <ref target="VAC7211-00000064" rend="right">128</ref>
               </item>
               <item>X. THE ARREST. <ref target="VAC7211-00000071" rend="right">142</ref>
               </item>
               <item>XI. THE OFFER. <ref target="VAC7211-00000076" rend="right">152</ref>
               </item>
               <item>XII. POLLIO'S TRIAL. <ref target="VAC7211-00000082" rend="right">163</ref>
               </item>
               <item>XIII. THE DEATH OF POLLIO. <ref target="VAC7211-00000087" rend="right"
                     >173</ref>
               </item>
               <item>XIV. THE TEMPTATION. <ref target="VAC7211-00000092" rend="right">183</ref>
               </item>
               <item>XV. LUCULLUS. <ref target="VAC7211-00000097" rend="right">193</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <head>Illustrations.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE BOY MARTYR. <ref>2</ref>
               </item>
               <item>PLAN OF THE CATACOMBS. <ref>49</ref>
               </item>
               <item>A PASSAGE IN THE CATACOMBS. <ref>92</ref>
               </item>
               <item>THE COLISEUM. <ref>132</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7211-00000003"/>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The martyr of the catacombs</head>
            
            <head>THE MARTYR OF THE CATACOMBS.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE COLISEUM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"Butchered to make a Roman holiday."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IT was a great festival day in Rome. From all quarters vast numbers of people came
                  pouring forth to one common destination. Over the Capitoline Hill, through the
                  Forum, past the Temple of Peace and the Arch of Titus and the imperial palace; on
                  they went till they reached the Coliseum, where they entered its hundred doors and
                  disappeared within.</p>
               <p>There a wonderful scene presented itself. Below, the vast arena spread out,
                  surrounded by the countless rows of seats which rose to the top of the outer wall,
                  over a hundred feet. The whole extent was covered with human beings of every class
                  and every age. So vast an assemblage<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7211-00000004"/>
                  semblage gathered in such a way, presenting to view long lines of stern faces,
                  ascending far on high, in successive rows, formed a spectacle which has never
                  elsewhere been equaled, and which was calculated beyond all others to awe the soul
                  of the beholder. More than one hundred thousand people were gathered here,
                  animated by one common feeling, and incited by one single passion. It was the
                  thirst for blood which drew them hither, and nowhere can we find a sadder
                  commentary on the boasted civilization of ancient Rome than this her own greatest
                  spectacle.</p>
               <p>Here were warriors who had fought in foreign wars and were familiar with deeds of
                  valor, yet they felt no indignation at the scenes of cowardly oppression displayed
                  before them; nobles of ancient families were here, but they could find in these
                  brutal shows no stain upon their country's honor. Philosophers, poets, priests,
                  rulers, the highest as well as the lowest in the land, crowded these seats; but
                  the applauding shout of the patrician was as loud and as eager as that of the
                  plebeian. What hope was there for Rome when the hearts of her people were
                  universally given up to cruelty and brutal oppression?</p>
               <p>Upon a raised seat in a conspicuous part of the amphitheater was the Emperor
                  Decius, near whom the chief people among the Romans were gathered. Among these
                  there was a group of officers belonging to the Pretorian guards, who criticised
                  the different points in the scene before them with the air of connoisseurs. Their
                  loud laughter, their gayety, and their splendid attire made them the object of
                  much attention from their neighbors.</p>
               <p>Several preliminary spectacles had been introduced, and now the fights began.
                  Several hand-to-hand combats were presented, most of which resulted fatally, and
                  excited different degrees of interest according to the courage or skill of the
                  combatants. Their effect was to whet the appetite of the spectators to a keener
                  relish, and fill them with eager desire for the more exciting events which were to
                  follow.</p>
               <p>One man in particular had drawn down the admiration and applause of the multitude.
                  He was an African from Mauritania, of gigantic strength and stature. But his skill
                     seemed<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7211-00000005"/> equal to his strength. He
                  wielded his short sword with marvelous dexterity, and thus far had slain every
                  opponent.</p>
               <p>He was now matched with a gladiator from Batavia, a man fully equal in stature and
                  strength to himself. The contrast which the two presented was striking. The
                  African was tawny, with glossy curling hair and glittering eyes; the Batavian was
                  light in complexion, with blonde hair and keen gray eyes. It was hard to tell
                  which had the advantage, so nearly were they matched in every respect; but as the
                  former had already fought for some time, it was thought that the odds were rather
                  against him. The contest, however, began with great spirit and eagerness on both
                  sides. The Batavian struck tremendous blows, which were parried by the adroitness
                  of the other. The African was quick and furious, but he could do nothing against
                  the cool and wary defense of his vigilant adversary.</p>
               <p>At length, at a given signal, the combat was suspended, and the gladiators were
                  led away, not through anything like mercy or admiration, but simply through a
                  shrewd understanding of the best mode of satisfying the Roman public. It was well
                  understood that they would return again.</p>
               <p>Now a large number of men were led into the arena. These were still armed with the
                  short sword. In a moment they had begun the attack. It was not a conflict between
                  two sides, but a general fight, in which every man attacked his neighbor. Such
                  scenes were the most bloody, and therefore the most exciting. A conflict of this
                  kind would always destroy the greatest number in the shortest time. The arena
                  presented a scene of dire confusion. Five hundred armed men in the prime of life
                  and strength all struggled confusedly together. Sometimes they would all be
                  interlocked in one dense mass; at other times they would violently separate into
                  widely scattered individuals, with a heap of dead upon the scene of the combat.
                  But these would assail one another again with undiminished fury; separate combats
                  would spring up all around, the victors in these would rush to take part in
                  others, until at last the survivors had once more congregated in one struggling
                  crowd.</p>
               <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7211-00000006"/>
               <p>At length their struggles became weaker. Out of five hundred but one hundred
                  remained, and these were wearied and wounded. Suddenly a signal was given, and two
                  men leaped into the arena and rushed from opposite sides upon this crowd. They
                  were the African and the Batavian. Fresh from their repose, they fell upon the
                  exhausted wretches before them, who had neither the spirit to combine nor the
                  strength to resist. It became a butchery. These two giants slaughtered right and
                  left without mercy, until they alone stood upright upon the arena, and the
                  applause of the innumerable throng came down in thunder to their ears.</p>
               <p>These two again attacked each other, and attracted the attention of the spectators
                  while the bodies of the wounded and slain were being removed. The combat was as
                  fierce as before, and precisely similar. The African was agile, the Batavian
                  cautious. But finally the former made a desperate thrust; the Batavian parried it,
                  and returned a stroke like lightning. The African sprang back and dropped his
                  sword. But he was too late, for the stroke of his foe had pierced his left arm. As
                  he fell a roar of joy arose from one hundred thousand human beings. But this was
                  not to be the end, for even while the conqueror stood over his victim the
                  attendants sprang forward and drew him away. Yet the Romans knew, and the wounded
                  man knew that it was not mercy. He was merely to be reserved for a later but a
                  certain fate.</p>
               <p>"The Batavian is a skillful fighter, Marcellus," said one young officer to a
                  companion among the group which has been alluded to.</p>
               <p>"He is, indeed, Lucullus," replied the other. "I do not think that I ever saw a
                  better gladiator. Indeed, both of them were much better than common."</p>
               <p>"They have a better man than either inside there."</p>
               <p>"Ah! who is he?"</p>
               <p>"The gladiator Macer. I think he is about the best I have ever seen."</p>
               <p>"I have heard of him. Do you think he will be out to-day?"</p>
               <p>"I understood so."</p>
               <p>The short conversation was interrupted by a loud roar which came from the <foreign
                     xml:lang="LAT">vivarium,</foreign> a place where the wild beasts were confined.
                  It was a<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7211-00000007"/> fierce and a terrific roar, such
                  as the most savage beasts give when they are at the extremity of hunger and
                  rage.</p>
               <p>Soon iron gratings were flung open by men from above, and a tiger stalked forth
                  into the arena. He was from Africa, whence he had been brought but a few days
                  previously. He had been kept three days without food, and his furious rage, which
                  hunger and confinement had heightened to a terrible degree, was awful to behold.
                  Lashing his tail, he walked round the arena gazing with bloodshot eyes upward at
                  the spectators. But their attention was soon diverted to another object. From the
                  opposite side a man was thrust out into the arena. He had no armor, but was naked
                  like all gladiators, with the simple exception of a cloth around his loins.
                  Bearing in his hand the customary short sword, he advanced with a firm pace toward
                  the center of the scene.</p>
               <p>All eyes at once were fixed upon this man "Macer, Macer," was called around by the
                  innumerable spectators.</p>
               <p>The tiger soon saw him, and uttered a short savage growl of fearful import. Macer
                  stood still, with his eyes calmly fixed upon the beast, who, lashing his tail more
                  madly than ever, bounded toward him. Finally the tiger crouched, and then, with
                  one terrific spring, leaped directly upon him. But Macer was prepared. Like a
                  flash he darted to the left, and just as the tiger fell to the earth, he dealt a
                  short sharp blow straight to his heart. It was a fatal stroke. The huge beast
                  shuddered from head to foot, and drawing all his limbs together, he uttered a last
                  howl that sounded almost like the scream of a human being, and fell dead upon the
                  sand.</p>
               <p>Again the applause of the multitude rose like a thunder peal all around.</p>
               <p>"Wonderful!" cried Marcellus. "I never saw skill equal to that of Macer!"</p>
               <p>"Without doubt he has been fighting all his life," rejoined his friend.</p>
               <p>But soon the carcass of the tiger was drawn away, and again the creak of a grating
                  as it swung apart attracted attention. This time it was a lion. He came forth
                  slowly, and looked all around upon the scene as if in surprise. He was the largest
                  of his species, a giant in size, and had long been preserved for some superior<pb
                     n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7211-00000008"/> antagonist. He seemed capable of
                  encountering two animals like the tiger that had preceded him. Beside him Macer
                  was like a child.</p>
               <p>The lion had fasted long, but he showed no fury like that of the tiger. He walked
                  across the arena, and then completely around it in a kind of trot, as though
                  searching for escape. Finding every side closed, he finally retreated to the
                  center, and putting his face close to the ground, he uttered a roar so deep, so
                  loud, and so long, that the ponderous stones of the coliseum itself vibrated at
                  the sound.</p>
               <p>Macer stood unmoved. Not a muscle of his face changed. He carried his head erect
                  with the same watchful expression, and held his sword ready. At length the lion
                  turned full upon him. The wild beast and the man stood face to face eyeing one
                  another. But the calm gaze of the man seemed to till the animal with wrath. He
                  started back with his hair and tail erect, and tossing his mane, he crouched for
                  the dreadful spring.</p>
               <p>The vast multitude stood spellbound. Here, indeed, was a sight worthy of their
                  interest.</p>
               <p>The dark form of the lion darted forward, but again the form of the gladiator,
                  with his customary maneuver, leaped aside and struck. This time, however, his
                  sword struck a rib, and fell from his hand. The lion was slightly wounded, but the
                  blow served only to rouse his fury to the highest point.</p>
               <p>Yet Macer lost not one jot of his coolness in that awful moment. Perfectly
                  unarmed, he stood before the beast waiting his attack. Again and again the lion
                  sprang, but each time he was evaded by the nimble gladiator, who by his own adroit
                  movements contrived to reach the spot where his weapon lay and regain possession
                  of it. Armed with his trusty sword, he waited a final spring. The lion came down
                  as before, but this time Macer's aim was true. The sword pierced his heart. The
                  enormous beast fell, writhing in pain. Rising again to his feet, he ran across the
                  arena, and with a last roar he fell dead by the bars at which he had entered.</p>
               <p>Macer was now led away, and the Batavian reappeared. The Romans required variety.
                  A small tiger was let loose upon the Batavian and was vanquished. A lion was then
                  set upon him. He was extremely fierce, although of<pb n="18-19"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000009"/> only ordinary size. It was evident that the
                  Batavian was not at all equal to Macer. The lion made a spring and was wounded,
                  but on making a second attack, he caught his opponent and literally tore him to
                  pieces. Upon this Macer was sent out again, and killed this lion easily.</p>
               <p>And now, while Macer stood there the recipient of unbounded applause, a man
                  entered from the opposite side. It was the African. His arm had not been bound up,
                  but hung down by his side covered with blood. He staggered toward Macer with
                  painful steps. The Romans knew that he had been sent out to be killed. The wretch
                  knew it himself, also, for as he drew near to his antagonist he dropped his sword,
                  and cried out in a kind of desperation,</p>
               <p>"Quick! kill me, and put me out of pain."</p>
               <p>To the amazement of all, Macer stepped back and flung down his sword. The
                  spectators stared and wondered. Still more amazed were they when Macer turned
                  toward the emperor and stretched out his hands.</p>
               <p>"August Emperor," he cried, "I am a Christian. I will fight wild beasts, but I
                  will not raise my hand against a fellow-man. I can die, but I will not kill."</p>
               <p>Whereupon a mighty murmur arose.</p>
               <p>"What does he say?" cried Marcellus. "A Christian! when did that happen?"</p>
               <p>"I heard," said Lucullus, "that he was visited in his cell by some of these
                  wretched Christians, and joined their contemptible sect. They are made up of the
                  offscouring of man kind. It is very probable that he is a Christian."</p>
               <p>"And will he incur death rather than fight?"</p>
               <p>"That is the way with these fanatics."</p>
               <p>Rage took the place of surprise in the fierce multitude. They were indignant that
                  a mere gladiator should dare to disappoint them. The attendants rushed out to
                  interfere. The fight must go on. If Macer would not fight he should take the
                  consequences.</p>
               <p>But he was firm. Unarmed, he advanced toward the African, whom he could have slain
                  even then with a blow of his fist. The face of the African was like that of a
                  fiend. Surprise, joy, and triumph gleamed in his sinister eyes.<pb n="20-21"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000010"/> Seizing his sword in a firm grasp, he struck Macer
                  to the heart.</p>
               <p>"Lord Jesus receive my spirit—" The words were drowned in a torrent of blood, and
                  this humble but bold witness for Christ passed away from earth to join the noble
                  army of martyrs.</p>
               <p>"Are there many such scenes as this?" asked Marcellus.</p>
               <p>"Often. Whenever Christians appear. They will fight any number of beasts. Young
                  girls will come firmly to meet lions and tigers, but not one of the madmen will
                  fight with men. The populace are bitterly disappointed in Macer. He is the very
                  best of all the gladiators, and in becoming a Christian he has acted like a
                  fool"</p>
               <p>"It must be a wonderful religion which could make a common gladiator act thus,"
                  said Marcellus.</p>
               <p>"You'll have a chance to learn more about it."</p>
               <p>"How so?"</p>
               <p>"Haven't you heard? You are appointed to unearth some of these Christians. They
                  have got down in the Catacombs, and they must be hunted up."</p>
               <p>"I should think they have enough already. Fifty were burned this morning."</p>
               <p>"And a hundred were beheaded last week. But that is nothing. The city is swarming
                  with them. The emperor has determined to restore the old religion perfectly. Since
                  these Christians have appeared the empire has been declining. He has made up his
                  mind to annihilate them. They are a curse, and must be dealt with accordingly. You
                  will soon understand."</p>
               <p>"I haven't been in Rome long enough to know," said Marcellus meekly, "and I do not
                  understand what the Christians really believe. I have heard almost every crime
                  imputed to them. However, if it be as you say I will have a chance of
                  learning."</p>
               <p>But now another scene attracted their attention.</p>
               <p>An old man entered upon the scene. His form was bowed, and his hair silver white
                  with extreme old age. His appearance was hailed with shouts of derision, although
                  his majestic<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7211-00000011"/> face and dignified manner
                  were only calculated to excite admiration. As the shouts of laughter and yells of
                  derision came down to his ears he raised his head and uttered a few words.</p>
               <p>"Who is he?" asked Marcellus.</p>
               <p>"Alexander, a teacher of the abominable Christian sect. He is so obstinate that he
                  will not recant—"</p>
               <p>"Hush, he is speaking."</p>
               <p>"Romans!" said the old man, "I am a Christian. My God died for me, and I gladly
                  lay down my life for him—"</p>
               <p>A loud outburst of yells and execrations from the fierce mob drowned his voice.
                  Before it was over three panthers came bounding toward him. He folded his arms,
                  and looking up to heaven, his lips moved as if murmuring prayers. The savage
                  beasts fell upon him as he stood, and in a few minutes he was torn in pieces.</p>
               <p>Other wild animals were now let in. They bounded around the inclosure, they leaped
                  against the barrier, and in their rage assailed one another. It was a hideous
                  scene.</p>
               <p>Into the midst of this a helpless band of prisoners were rudely thrust. They were
                  chiefly young girls, who were thus sacrificed to the bloodthirsty passions of the
                  savage Roman mob. The sight would have moved to pity any heart in which all soft
                  feelings had not been blighted. But pity had no place in Rome. Cowering and
                  fearful, the poor young maidens showed the weakness of human nature when just
                  confronted with death in so terrible a form, but after a few moments faith resumed
                  its power, and raised them above all fear. As the beasts became aware of the
                  presence of their prey and began to draw near, these young maidens joined hands,
                  and raising their eyes to heaven, sang out a solemn chant which rose clear and
                  wondrously sweet upward to heaven: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Unto Him that loved us</l>
                        <l>To Him that washed us from our sins</l>
                        <l>In his own blood;</l>
                        <l>To Him that made us kings and priests,</l>
                        <l>To God and the Father;</l>
                        <l>To Him be glory and dominion</l>
                        <l>Forever and ever.</l>
                        <l>Halleluiah. Amen!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>One by one the voices were hushed in blood, and agony, and death; one by one the
                     shrieks<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7211-00000012"/> of anguish were mingled with
                  the shouts of praise; and these fair young spirits, so heroic under suffering and
                  faithful unto death, had carried their song to join it with the psalm of the
                  redeemed on high.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE PRETORIAN CAMP.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"Cornelius the centurion, a just man, and one that feared God."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>MARCELLUS was born in Gades, and had been brought up in the stern discipline of a
                  Roman army. He had been quartered in Africa, in Syria, and in Britain, where he
                  had distinguished himself not only by bravery in the field but also by skill in
                  the camp. For these reasons he had received honors and promotions, and upon his
                  arrival at Rome, to which place he had come as the bearer of dispatches, he had so
                  pleased the emperor that he had been appointed to an honorable station among the
                  Pretorians.</p>
               <p>Lucullus had never been out of Italy, scarcely indeed out of the city. He belonged
                  to one of the oldest and most noble Roman families, and enjoyed corresponding
                  wealth and influence. He was charmed by the bold and frank nature of Marcellus,
                  and the two young men had become firm friends. The intimate knowledge of<pb
                     n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7211-00000013"/> the capital which Lucullus possessed
                  enabled him also to be of service to his friend, and the scene which has been
                  described in the preceding chapter was one of the first visits which Marcellus had
                  made to the renowned Coliseum.</p>
               <p>The Pretorian camp was situated close to the city wall, to which it was joined by
                  another wall which inclosed it. The soldiers lived in rooms like cells made in the
                  wall itself. They were a numerous and finely appointed body of men, and their
                  situation at the capital gave them a power and an influence so great that for ages
                  they controlled the government of the capital. A command among the Pretorians was
                  a sure road to fortune, and Marcellus could look forward with well-grounded
                  prospects of future honors.</p>
               <p>On the morning of the following day Lucullus entered his room. After the usual
                  salutation he spoke of the fight which they had witnessed.</p>
               <p>"Such scenes are not to my taste," said Marcellus. "They are cowardly. I like to
                  see two well-trained men engage in a fair combat, but such butchery as you have in
                  the Coliseum is detestable. Why should Macer be murdered? He was a brave man, and
                  I honor his courage. And why should old men and young children be handed over to
                  wild beasts?"</p>
               <p>"It is the law. They are Christians."</p>
               <p>"That is always the answer. What have the Christians done? I have seen them in all
                  parts of the world, but have never known them to be engaged in disturbances."</p>
               <p>"They are the worst of mankind."</p>
               <p>"So it is said, but what proof is there?"</p>
               <p>"Proof? It is too well known. Their crime is that they plot in secret against the
                  laws and the religion of the state. So intense is the hatred which they bear
                  toward our institutions that they will die rather than offer sacrifice. They own
                  no king or monarch but the crucified Jew who they believe is alive now. And they
                  show their malevolence to us by asserting that we shall all hereafter be tortured
                  in Hades forever."</p>
               <p>"This may be true. I know not. I know nothing at all about them."</p>
               <p>"The city is swarming with them; the empire is overrun. And mark this. The decline
                  of our empire, which all see and lament; the<pb n="28-29"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000014"/> spread of weakness and insubordination, the
                  contraction of our boundaries, all this increases as the Christians increase. To
                  what else are these evils owing if not to them?"</p>
               <p>"How have they produced this?"</p>
               <p>"By their detestable teachings and practices. They teach that fighting is wrong,
                  that soldiers are the basest of men, that our glorious religion under which we
                  have prospered is a curse, and that the immortal gods are accursed demons. In
                  their teachings they aim to overthrow all morality. In their private practices
                  they perform the darkest and foulest crimes. They always keep by themselves in
                  impenetrable secresy, but sometimes we overhear their evil discourses and lewd
                  songs."</p>
               <p>"All this is indeed serious, and if true they deserve severe punishment. But
                  according to your own statement they keep by themselves, and but little is known
                  of them. Tell me, did those who suffered yesterday seem like this? Did that old
                  man look as though he had passed his life in vicious scenes? Did those fair young
                  girls sing lewd songs as they waited for the lions?"<q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l rend="ti-1">"'Unto Him that loved us;</l>
                        <l>To Him that washed us from our sins:'"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> And Marcellus sang in a soft voice the words which he had heard.</p>
               <p>"I confess, my friend, that I mourned for them."</p>
               <p>"And I," said Marcellus, "could have wept had I not been a Roman soldier. Consider
                  for a moment. You tell me things about these Christians which you confess only to
                  have learned from those who themselves are ignorant. You assert that they are
                  infamous and base, the offscouring of the earth. I see them confronted with a
                  death that tries the highest qualities of the soul. They meet it nobly. They die
                  grandly. In all her history Rome can produce no greater scene of devotion than
                  that of yesterday. You say they detest soldiers, yet they are brave; you tell me
                  that they are traitors, yet they do not resist the laws; you declare that they are
                  impure, yet if purity is on earth it belonged to those maidens who died
                  yesterday."</p>
               <p>"You are enthusiastic for those outcasts."</p>
               <p>"Not so, Lucullus. I wish to know the truth. All my life I have heard these
                  reports. But<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7211-00000015"/> yesterday for the first time
                  I suspected that they might be false. I now question you earnestly, and I find
                  that your knowledge is based upon nothing. I now remember that throughout all the
                  world these Christians are peaceable and honest. They are engaged in no riots or
                  disturbances, and none of these crimes with which they are charged can be proved
                  against them. Why, then, should they die?"</p>
               <p>"The emperor has good reasons no doubt for his course."</p>
               <p>"He may be instigated by ignorant or malicous advisers."</p>
               <p>"I think it is entirely his own design."</p>
               <p>"The number of those that have been put to death is very large."</p>
               <p>"O yes, some thousands; but plenty more remain. These, however, are out of reach,
                  and that reminds me of my errand here. I bring you the imperial commission."</p>
               <p>Lucullus drew from the folds of his military mantle a scroll of parchment, which
                  he handed to Marcellus. The latter eagerly examined its contents. It appointed him
                  to a higher grade, and commissioned him to search out and arrest the Christians in
                  their hiding-places, mentioning particularly the Catacombs.</p>
               <p>Marcellus read it with a clouded brow, and laid it down.</p>
               <p>"You do not seem very glad."</p>
               <p>"I confess the task is unpleasant. I am a soldier, and do not like to hunt out old
                  men and weak children for the executioner; yet, as a soldier, I must obey. Tell me
                  something about these Catacombs."</p>
               <p>"The Catacombs? It is a subterranean district that extends to unknown bounds
                  underneath the city. The Christians fly to the catacombs whenever there is danger,
                  and they also are in the habit of burying their dead there. Once there, they are
                  beyond the reach of the utmost power of the state."</p>
               <p>"Who made the Catacombs?"</p>
               <p>"No one knows exactly. They have existed for ages. I believe that they were
                  excavated for the sake of getting building sand for cement. At present all our
                  cement comes from there, and you may see workmen bringing it into the city along
                  any of the great roads. They have to go far away for it now, for in the<pb
                     n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7211-00000016"/> course of ages they have excavated so
                  much beneath us that this city now rests upon a foundation like a honeycomb."</p>
               <p>"Is there any regular entrance?"</p>
               <p>"There are innumerable entrances. That is the difficulty. If there were but few,
                  then we might catch the fugitives. But we cannot tell from which direction to
                  advance upon them."</p>
               <p>"Is any district suspected?"</p>
               <p>"Yes. About two miles down the Appian Way, near the tomb of Cæcilia Metella, the
                  large round tower, you know, bodies have frequently been discovered. It is
                  conjectured that these are the bodies of the Christians which have been obtained
                  from the amphitheater and carried away for burial. On the approach of the guards,
                  the Christians have dropped the bodies and fled. But, after all, this gives no
                  assistance, for after you enter the Catacombs you are no nearer your aim than
                  before. No human being can penetrate that infinite labyrinth without assistance
                  from those who live there."</p>
               <p>"Who live there?"</p>
               <p>"The fossors, who still excavate sand for the<figure/> builders. They are nearly
                  all Christians, and are always at work cutting out graves for the dead of the
                  Christians. These men have lived there all their lives, and are not only familiar
                  with the passages, but they have a kind of instinct to guide them."</p>
               <p>"Were you ever in the Catacombs?"</p>
               <p>"Once, long ago, a fossor guided me I remained but a short time. My impression
                     was<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7211-00000017"/> that it was the most terrible
                  place in all the world."</p>
               <p>"I have heard of the Catacombs, but never before knew anything about them. It is
                  strange that they are so little known. Could not these fossors be engaged to lead
                  the guards through this labyrinth?"</p>
               <p>"No. They will not betray the Christians."</p>
               <p>"Have they been tried?"</p>
               <p>"Certainly. Some comply, and lead the officers of justice through a network of
                  passages till they get bewildered. Their torches become extinguished, and they
                  grow terrified. Then they ask to be led back. The fossor declares that the
                  Christians must have fled, and so takes back the soldiers to the starting
                  point."</p>
               <p>"Are none resolute enough to continue on till they find the Christians?"</p>
               <p>"If they insist upon continuing the search the fossor will lead them on forever.
                  But he merely leads them through the countless pass ages which intersect some
                  particular district."</p>
               <p>"Are none found who will actually betray the fugitives?"</p>
               <p>"Sometimes; but of what use is it? Upon the first alarm, every Christian vanishes
                  through the side ways, which open everywhere."</p>
               <p>"My prospect of success seems small."</p>
               <p>"Very small, but much is hoped from your boldness and shrewdness. If you succeed
                  in this enterprise it will be your fortune. And now, farewell. Yon have learned
                  from me all that I know. You will find no difficulty in learning more from any one
                  of the fossors."</p>
               <p>So saying, Lucullus departed.</p>
               <p>Marcellus leaned his head on his hands, and lost himself in thought. But ever amid
                  his meditations came floating the strains of that glorious melody which told of
                  triumph over death: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l rend="ti-1">"Unto Him that loved us,</l>
                        <l>To him that washed us from our sins—"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7211-00000018"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE APPIAN WAY.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l rend="ti-1">"Sepulchers in sad array</l>
                        <l>Guard the ashes of the mighty</l>
                        <l>Slumbering on the Appian Way."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>MARCELLUS entered upon the duty that lay before him without delay. Upon the
                  following day he set out upon his investigations. It was merely a journey of
                  inquiry, so he took no soldiers with him. Starting forth from the Pretorian
                  barracks, he walked out of the city and down the Appian Way.</p>
               <p>This famous road was lined oil both sides with magnificent tombs, all of which
                  were carefully preserved by the families to whom they belonged. Further back from
                  the road lay houses and villas as thickly clustered as in the city. The open
                  country was a long distance away.</p>
               <p>At length he reached a huge round tower, which stood about two miles from the
                  gate. It was built with enormous blocks of travertine, and ornamented beautifully
                  yet simply. Its severe style and solid construction gave it an air of bold
                  defiance against the ravages of time.</p>
               <p>At this point Marcellus paused and looked back. A stranger in Rome, every view
                  presented something new and interesting. Most remarkable was the long line of
                  tombs. There were the last resting-places of the great, the noble, and the brave
                  of elder days, whose epitaphs announced their claims to honor on earth, and their
                  dim prospects in the unknown life to come. Art and wealth had reared these
                  sumptuous monuments, and the pious affection of ages had preserved them from
                  decay. Here where he stood was the sublime mausoleum of Cæcilia Metella; further
                  away were the tombs of Calatinus and the Sarvilii. Still further his eye fell upon
                  the resting-place of the Scipios, the classic architecture of which was hallowed
                  by "the dust of its heroic dwellers."</p>
               <p>The words of Cicero recurred to his mind,</p>
               <p>"When you go out of the Porta Capena, and see the tombs of Calatinus, of the
                  Scipios, the Sarvilii, and the Metelli, can you consider that the buried inmates
                  are unhappy?"</p>
               <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7211-00000019"/>
               <p>There was the arch of Drusus spanning the road: on one side was the historic
                  grotto of Egeria, and further on the spot where Hannibal once stood and hurled his
                  javelin at the walls of Rome. The long lines of tombs went on till in the distance
                  it was terminated by the lofty pyramid of Caius Cestius, and the whole presented
                  the grandest scene of sepulchral magnificence that could be found on earth.</p>
               <p>On every side the habitations, of men covered the ground, for the Imperial City
                  had long ago burst the bounds that originally confined it, and sent its houses far
                  away on every side into the country, till the traveler could scarcely tell where
                  the country ended and where the city began.</p>
               <p>From afar the deep hum of the city, the roll of innumerable chariots, and the
                  multitudinous tread of its many feet, greeted his ears Before him rose monuments
                  and temples, the white sheen of the imperial palace, the innumerable domes and
                  columns towering upward like a city in the air, and high above all the lofty
                  Capitoline mount, crowned with the shrine of Jove.</p>
               <p>But more impressive than all the splendor of the home of the living was the
                  solemnity of the city of the dead.</p>
               <p>What an array of architectural glory was displayed around him! There arose the
                  proud monuments of the grand old families of Rome. Heroism, genius, valor, pride,
                  wealth, everything that man esteems or admires, here animated the eloquent stone
                  and awakened emotion. Here were the visible forms of the highest influences of the
                  old pagan religion. Yet their effects upon the soul never corresponded with the
                  splendor of their outward forms, or the pomp of their ritual. The epitaphs of the
                  dead showed not faith, but love of life, triumphant; not the assurance of immortal
                  life, but a sad longing after the pleasures of the world.</p>
               <p>Such were the thoughts of Marcellus as he mused upon the scene and again recalled
                  the words of Cicero, "Can you think that the buried inmates are unhappy?"</p>
               <p>"These Christians," thought he, "whom I am now seeking, seem to have learned more
                  than I can find in all our philosophy. They not only<pb n="40-41"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000020"/> have conquered the fear of death, but have learned
                  to die rejoicing. What secret power have they which can thus inspire even the
                  youngest and the feeblest among them? What is the hidden meaning of their song? My
                  religion can only hope that I may not be unhappy, theirs leads them to death with
                  triumphant songs of joy."</p>
               <p>But how was he to prosecute his search after the Christians? Crowds of people
                  passed by, but he saw none who seemed capable of assisting him. Buildings of all
                  sizes, walls, tombs, and temples were all around, but he saw no place that seemed
                  at all connected with the Catacombs. He was quite at a loss what to do.</p>
               <p>He went down into the street and walked slowly along, carefully scrutinizing every
                  person whom he met, and examining closely every building. Yet no result was
                  obtained from this beyond the discovery that the outward appearance gave no sign
                  of any connection with subterranean abodes. The day passed on, and it grew late;
                  but Marcellus remembered that there were many entrances to the Catacombs, and
                  still he continued his search, hoping before the close of the day to find some
                  clue.</p>
               <p>At length his search was rewarded. He had walked backward and forward and in every
                  direction, often retracing his steps and returning many times to the place of
                  starting. Twilight was coming on, and the sun was near the edge of the horizon,
                  when his quick eye caught sight of a man who was walking in an opposite direction,
                  followed by a boy. The man was dressed in coarse apparel, stained and damp with
                  sand and earth. His complexion was blanched and pallid, like that of one who has
                  long been imprisoned, and his whole appearance at once arrested the glance of the
                  young soldier.</p>
               <p>He stepped up to him, and laying his hand upon his shoulder said,</p>
               <p>"You are a fossor. Come with me."</p>
               <p>The man looked up. He saw a stern face. The sight of the officer's dress terrified
                  him. In an instant he darted away, and before Marcellus could turn to follow he
                  had rushed into a side lane and was out of sight.</p>
               <p>But Marcellus secured the boy.</p>
               <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7211-00000021"/>
               <p>"Come with me," said he.</p>
               <p>The poor lad looked up with such an agony of fear that Marcellus was moved.</p>
               <p>"Have mercy, for my mother's sake; she will die if I am taken."</p>
               <p>The boy fell at his feet murmuring this in broken tones.</p>
               <p>"I will not hurt you. Come," and he led him away toward an open space out of the
                  way of the passers-by.</p>
               <p>"Now," said he, stopping and confronting the boy, "tell me the truth. Who are
                  you?"</p>
               <p>"My name is Pollio," said the boy.</p>
               <p>"Where do you live?"</p>
               <p>"In Rome."</p>
               <p>"What are you doing here?"</p>
               <p>"I was out on an errand."</p>
               <p>"Who was that man?"</p>
               <p>"A fossor."</p>
               <p>"What were you doing with him?"</p>
               <p>"He was carrying a bundle for me."</p>
               <p>"What was in the bundle?"</p>
               <p>"Provisions."</p>
               <p>"To whom were you carrying it?"</p>
               <p>"To a destitute person out here."</p>
               <p>"Where does he live?"</p>
               <p>"Not far from here."</p>
               <p>"Now, boy, tell me the truth. Do you know anything about the Catacombs?"</p>
               <p>"I have heard about them," said the boy quietly.</p>
               <p>"Were you ever in them?"</p>
               <p>"I have been in some of them."</p>
               <p>"Do you know any body who lives in them?"</p>
               <p>"Some people. The fossor stays there."</p>
               <p>"You were going to the Catacombs then with him?"</p>
               <p>"What business would I have there at such a time as this?" said the boy
                  innocently.</p>
               <p>"That is what I want to know. Were you going there?"</p>
               <p>"How would I dare to go there when it is forbidden by the laws?"</p>
               <p>"It is now evening," said Marcellus abruptly, "come with me to the evening service
                  at yonder temple."</p>
               <p>The boy hesitated. "I am in a hurry," said he.</p>
               <p>"But you are my prisoner. I never neglect<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7211-00000022"/>
                  the worship of the gods. You must come and assist me at my devotions."</p>
               <p>"I cannot," said the boy firmly.</p>
               <p>"Why not?"</p>
               <p>"I am a Christian."</p>
               <p>"I knew it. And you have friends in the Catacombs, and you are going there now.
                  They are the destitute people to whom you are carrying provisions, and the errand
                  on which you are is for them."</p>
               <p>The boy held down his head and was silent.</p>
               <p>"I want you now to take me to the entrance of the Catacombs."</p>
               <p>"O, generous soldier, have mercy! Do not ask me that. I cannot do it!"</p>
               <p>"You must."</p>
               <p>"I will not betray my friends."</p>
               <p>"You need not. It is nothing to show the entrance among the many thousands that
                  lead down below. Do you think that the guards do not know every one?"</p>
               <p>The boy thought for a moment, and at length signified his assent.</p>
               <p>Marcellus took his hand and followed his lead. The boy turned away to the right of
                  the Appian Way, when he walked a short distance. Here he came to an uninhabited
                  house. He entered, and went down into the cellar. There was a door which
                  apparently opened into a closet. The boy pointed to this, and stopped.</p>
               <p>"I wish to go down," said Marcellus, firmly.</p>
               <p>"You would not dare to go down alone surely, would you?"</p>
               <p>"The Christians say that they do not commit murder. Why then should I fear? Lead
                  on."</p>
               <p>"I have no torches."</p>
               <p>"But I have some. I came prepared. Go on."</p>
               <p>"I cannot."</p>
               <p>"Do you refuse?"</p>
               <p>"I must refuse," said the boy. "My friends and my relatives are below. Sooner than
                  lead you to them I would die a hundred deaths."</p>
               <p>"You are bold. You do not know what death is."</p>
               <p>"Do I not? What Christian can fear death?<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7211-00000023"/>
                  I have seen many of my friends die in agony, and I have helped to bury them. I
                  will not lead you there. Take me away to prison."</p>
               <p>The boy turned away.</p>
               <p>"But if I take you away what will your friends think? Have you a mother?"</p>
               <p>The boy bowed his head and burst into a passion of tears. The mention of that dear
                  name had overcome him.</p>
               <p>"I see that you have, and that you love her. Lead me down, and you shall join her
                  again."</p>
               <p>"I will never betray them. I will die first. Do with me as you wish."</p>
               <p>"If I had any evil intentions," said Marcellus, "do you think I would go down
                  unaccompanied?"</p>
               <p>"What can a soldier, and a Pretorian, want with the persecuted Christians, if not
                  to destroy them?"</p>
               <p>"Boy, I have no evil intentions. If you guide me down below I swear I will not use
                  my knowledge against your friends. When I am below I will be a prisoner, and they
                  can do with me what they like."</p>
               <p>"Do you swear that you will not betray them?"</p>
               <p>"I do, by the life of Cæsar and the immortal gods," said Marcellus, solemnly.</p>
               <p>"Come along, then," said the boy. "We do not need torches. Follow me
                  carefully."</p>
               <p>And the lad entered the narrow opening.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="48-49 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7211-00000024"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE CATACOMBS.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"No light, but rather darkness visible</l>
                        <l>Served only to discover sights of woe,</l>
                        <l>Regions of sorrow, doleful shades."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THEY went on in utter darkness, until at length the passage widened and they came
                  to steps which led below. Marcellus held the boy's dress and followed him.</p>
               <p>It was certainly a situation that might provoke alarm. He was voluntarily placing
                  himself in the power of men whom his class had driven from the upper air into
                  these drear abodes. To them he could only be known as a persecutor. Yet such was
                  the impression which he had formed of their gentleness and meekness that he had no
                  fear of harm. It was in the power of this boy to lead him to death in the thick
                  darkness of these impenetrable labyrinths, but even of this he did not think. It
                  was a desire to know more of these Christians, to get at their secret, that led
                  him on, and as he had sworn, so<figure>
                     <head>PLAN OF THE CATACOMBS.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7211-00000025"/> had he resolved that this visit should
                  not be made use of to their betrayal or injury.</p>
               <p>After descending for some time the steps ended, and they walked along the level
                  ground. Soon they turned and entered a small vaulted chamber which was lighted
                  from the faint glow of a furnace. The boy had walked on with the unhesitating step
                  of one perfectly familiar with the way. Arriving at the chamber, he lighted a
                  torch which lay on the floor and resumed his journey.</p>
               <p>There is something in the air of a burial place which is unlike that of any other
                  place. It is not altogether the closeness, or the damp, or the sickening smell of
                  earth, but a certain subtle influence which unites with them and intensifies them.
                  The spell of the dead is there, and it rests alike on mind and body. Such was the
                  air of the catacombs. Cold and damp, it struck upon the visitor like the chill
                  atmosphere from the realms of death. The living felt the mysterious power of the
                  dead.</p>
               <p>The boy Pollio went on before and Marcellus followed after. The torch but faintly
                  illumined the intense darkness. No beam of day, no ray<pb n="52-53"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000026"/> however weak, could ever enter here to relieve the
                  thickness of the oppressive gloom. It was literally darkness that might be felt.
                  The torchlight shone out but a few paces and then died in the darkness.</p>
               <p>The path went winding on with innumerable turnings. Suddenly Pollio stopped and
                  pointed downward. Peering through the gloom, Marcellus saw an opening in the path
                  which led further down. It was a pit to which no bottom appeared.</p>
               <p>"Where does this lead to?"</p>
               <p>"Below."</p>
               <p>"Are there more passages below?"</p>
               <p>"O yes. As many as there are here, and still below that again. I have been in
                  three different stories of these paths, and some of the old fossors say that in
                  certain places they go down to a very great depth."</p>
               <p>The passage wound along till all idea of locality was utterly lost. Marcellus
                  could not tell whether he was within a few paces of the entrance or many furlongs
                  off. His bewildered thoughts soon began to turn to other things. The first
                  impressions of gloom departed he looked<figure/> more particularly upon what he
                  passed, and regarded more closely the many wonders of this strange place. All
                  along the walls were tablets which appeared to cover long and narrow excavations.
                  These cellular niches were ranged on both sides so closely that but little space
                  was left between. The inscriptions that were upon the tablets showed that they
                  were Christian tombs. He had not time to stop and read, but he noticed the
                  frequent recurrence of the same expression, such as, <q>
                     <p>HONORIA—SHE SLEEPS IN PEACE.<lb/> FAUSTA—IN PEACE.<lb/>
                        <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7211-00000027"/> GEMELLA DORM INPACE</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>On nearly every tablet he saw the same sweet and gentle word. "PEACE," thought
                  Marcellus; "what wonderful people are these Christians, who even amid such scenes
                  as these can cherish their lofty contempt of death!"</p>
               <p>His eyes grew more and more accustomed to the gloom as he walked along. Now the
                  passage way grew narrower; the roof drooped, the sides approached; they had to
                  stoop and go along more slowly. The walls were rough and rudely cut as the workmen
                  left them when they drew along here their last load of sand for the edifices
                  above. Subterranean damps and fungous growths overspread them in places, deepening
                  their somber color and filling the air with thick moisture, while the smoke of the
                  torches made the atmosphere still more oppressive.</p>
               <p>They passed hundreds of side passages and scores of places where many paths met,
                  all branching off in different directions. These innumerable numerable paths
                  showed Marcellus how hopelessly he was now cut off from the world above. This boy
                  held his life in his hands.</p>
               <p>"Do any ever lose their way?"</p>
               <p>"Often."</p>
               <p>"What becomes of them?"</p>
               <p>"Sometimes they wander till they meet some friends, sometimes they are never heard
                  of again. But at present, most of us know the place so well that if we lose our
                  way we soon wander into familiar paths again."</p>
               <p>One thing particularly struck the young soldier, and that was the immense
                  preponderance of small tombs. Pollio told him that they were the graves of
                  children, and thus opened to him thoughts and emotions unfelt before.</p>
               <p>"Children!" thought he, "what do they here, the young, the pure, the innocent? Why
                  were they not buried above, where the sun might shine kindly and the flowers bloom
                  sweetly over their graves? Did they tread such dark paths as these on their way
                  through life? Did they bear their part in the sufferings of those that lingered
                  here flying from persecution? Did the noxious air and the never-ending gloom of
                     these<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7211-00000028"/> drear abodes shorten their fair
                  young lives, and send their stainless spirits out of life before their time?"</p>
               <p>"We have been a long time on the way," said Marcellus, "will we soon be
                  there?"</p>
               <p>"Very soon," said the boy.</p>
               <p>Whatever ideas Marcellus might have had about hunting out these fugitives before
                  he entered here, he now saw that all attempts to do so must be in vain. An army of
                  men might enter here and never come in sight of the Christians. The further they
                  went, the more hopeless would be their journey. They could be scattered through
                  the innumerable passages and wander about till they died.</p>
               <p>But now a low sound arose from afar which arrested his attention. Sweet beyond all
                  description, low and musical, it came down the long passages and broke upon his
                  charmed senses like a voice from the skies.</p>
               <p>As they went on, a light beamed before them which cast forth its rays into the
                  darkness. The sounds grew louder, now swelling into a magnificent chorus, now
                  dying away into a tender wail of supplication.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>In a few minutes they reached a turn in the path, and then a scene burst upon
                  their sight.</p>
               <p>"Stop," said Pollio, arresting his companion and extinguishing the torch.
                  Marcellus obeyed, and looked earnestly at the spectacle before him. It was a
                  vaulted chamber about fifteen feet in height and thirty feet square. In this place
                  there were crowded about a hundred people.<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7211-00000029"
                  /> men, women, and children. At one side there was a table, behind which stood a
                  venerable man who appeared to be the leader among them. The walls of the room
                  seemed to have been rudely decorated with coarse pictures. The place was
                  illuminated with the glare of torches which threw a lurid glow upon the assembly.
                  The people were careworn and emaciated, and their faces were characterized by the
                  same pallor which Marcellus had observed in the fossor. But the expression which
                  now rested upon them was not of sorrow, or misery, or despair. Hope illumined
                  their eyes, their upturned faces spoke of joy and triumph. The scene moved the
                  soul of the beholder to its inmost depths, for it confirmed all that he had seen
                  of the Christians, their heroism, their hope, their peace, which rested on
                  something hidden from him. As he listened he heard their song, chanted by the
                  whole congregation: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Great and marvelous are thy works</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Lord God Almighty,</l>
                        <l>Just and true are thy ways</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Thou king of saints.</l>
                        <l>Who shall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorify thy name?</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">For thou only art holy.</l>
                        <l>For all nations shall come and worship before thee,</l>
                        <l>For thy judgments are made manifest."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Then there was a pause. The venerable reader read something from a scroll which
                  was new to Marcellus. It was a sublime assertion of the immortality of the soul,
                  and life after death. The congregation seemed to hang upon the words as though
                  they were the words of life. Finally, the reader came to a burst of joyous
                  exclamation which drew murmurs of gratitude and enthusiastic hope from the
                  audience. The words thrilled upon the heart of the listener, though he did not
                  understand their full meaning. "O death, where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy
                  victory? The sting of death is sin, and the strength of sin is the law. But thanks
                  be to God which giveth us the victory, through our Lord Jesus Christ."</p>
               <p>These words seemed to open to his mind a new world with new thoughts.
                  Sin—death—Christ, with all the infinite train of ideas that rested upon them,
                  arose dimly before his awakening soul. The desire for the Christian's secret which
                  he had conceived now burned more eagerly within him.</p>
               <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7211-00000030"/>
               <p>The leader raised his head, and stretching out his hands, uttered a fervent
                  prayer. Addressing the invisible God, he poured forth a confession of sin and
                  guilt. He plead for pardon through the atoning death of Christ. He prayed for the
                  Spirit from on high, so that they might become holy. Then he enumerated all their
                  sorrows, and prayed for deliverance, asking for faith in life, victory in death,
                  and immortality in heaven for the sake of the Redeemer, Jesus.</p>
               <p>After this followed another chant which was sung as before: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Behold, the tabernacle of God is with men,</l>
                        <l>And he will dwell with them,</l>
                        <l>And they shall be his people,</l>
                        <l>And God himself shall be with them</l>
                        <l>And be their God.</l>
                        <l>And God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes,</l>
                        <l>And there shall be no more death, nor sorrow, nor sighing,</l>
                        <l>Neither shall there be any more pain,</l>
                        <l>For the former things are passed away. Amen.</l>
                        <l>Blessing, and glory, and wisdom.</l>
                        <l>And thanksgiving, and honor, and power, and might,</l>
                        <l>Be unto our God</l>
                        <l>For ever and ever. Amen."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now the congregation began to disperse. Pollio walked forward, leading Marcellus.
                  At the sight of his martial figure and glittering armor they all started backward,
                  and would have fled by the different paths. But Marcellus called in a loud
                  voice,</p>
               <p>"Fear not, Christians, I am alone and in your power."</p>
               <p>Upon this they all turned back, and looked at him with anxious curiosity. The aged
                  man who led the meeting advanced and looked earnestly upon him.</p>
               <p>"Who are you, and why do you seek us out in the last resting-place that is left to
                  us on earth?"</p>
               <p>"Do not suspect me of evil. I come alone, unattended. I am at your mercy."</p>
               <p>"But what can a soldier and a Pretorian wish of us? Are you pursued? Are you a
                  criminal? Is your life in danger?"</p>
               <p>"No. I am an officer high in rank and authority. But I have all my life been
                  seeking anxiously after the truth. I have heard much of you Christians, but in
                  these times of persecution it is difficult to find you in Rome. I have sought you
                  here."</p>
               <p>At this the aged man requested the assembly to withdraw, that he might converse
                  with the<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7211-00000031"/> new comer. The others readily
                  did so, and retired by different ways, feeling much relieved. A pale lady advanced
                  eagerly to Pollio and caught him in her arms.</p>
               <p>"How long you were, my son!"</p>
               <p>"I encountered this officer, dear mother, and was detained."</p>
               <p>"Thank God you are safe. But who is he?"</p>
               <p>"I think he is an honest man," said the boy, "see how he confides in us."</p>
               <p>"Cæcilia," said the leader, "do not go away for a little time." The lady remained,
                  and a few others did the same.</p>
               <p>"I am Honorius," said the old man, addressing Marcellus, "a humble elder in the
                  Church of Christ. I believe that you are sincere and earnest. Tell us now what you
                  want with us."</p>
               <p>"My name is Marcellus, and I am a captain in the Pretorian Guard."</p>
               <p>"Alas!" cried Honorius, and clasping his hands he fell back in his seat. The
                  others looked at Marcellus with mournful eyes, and the lady Cæcilia cried out in
                  an agony of grief,</p>
               <p>"O Pollio! how have you betrayed us!"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE CHRISTIAN'S SECRET.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"The mystery of godliness, God manifest in the flesh."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE young soldier stood astonished at the effect which his name produced.</p>
               <p>"Why do you all tremble so?" said he. "Is it on my account?"</p>
               <p>"Alas!" said Honorius, "though we are banished to this place we have constant
                  communication with the city. We have heard that new efforts were making to
                  persecute us more severely, and that Marcellus, a captain in the Pretorians, had
                  been appointed to search us out. We see you here among us, our chief enemy. Have
                  we not cause to fear? Why should you track us here?"</p>
               <p>"You have no cause to fear me," cried Marcellus, "even if I were your worst enemy.
                  Am I not in your power? If you chose to detain me could I escape? If you killed me
                  could I resist? I am helpless among you. My situation<pb n="64-65"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000032"/> tion here, alone among you, is proof that there is
                  no danger from me."</p>
               <p>"True," said Honorius, assuming his calm demeanor, "you are right; you could never
                  return without our assistance."</p>
               <p>"Hear me, then, and I will explain all to you. I am a Roman soldier. I was born in
                  Spain, and was brought up in virtue and morality. I was taught to fear the gods
                  and do my duty.</p>
               <p>"I have been in many lands, and have confined myself chiefly to my profession. Yet
                  I have never neglected religion. In my chamber I have studied all the writings of
                  the philosophers of Greece and Rome. The result is that I have learned from them
                  to despise our gods and goddesses, who are no better, and even worser than
                  myself.</p>
               <p>"From Plato and Cicero I learn that there is one Supreme Deity whom it is my duty
                  to obey. But how can I know him, and how shall I obey him? I learn, too, that I am
                  immortal, and shall become a spirit when I die. How shall I be then? shall I be
                  happy or miserable? How shall I secure happiness in that spiritual life? They
                  describe the glories of that immortal tal life in eloquent language, but they give
                  no directions for common men like me. To learn more of this is the desire of my
                  soul.</p>
               <p>"The priests can tell me nothing. They are wedded to old forms and ceremonies in
                  which they do not believe. The old religion is dead, and men care for it no
                  more.</p>
               <p>"In different lands I have heard much of Christians. Shut up in the camp, I have
                  not had much opportunity to see them. Indeed, I never cared to know them until
                  lately. I have heard all the usual reports about their immorality, their secret
                  vice, their treasonable doctrines. I believed all this until lately.</p>
               <p>"A few days ago I was in the Coliseum. There, first, I learned something about the
                  Christians. I saw the gladiator Macer, a man to whom fear was utterly unknown, lay
                  down his life calmly rather than do what he believed to be wrong. I saw an old man
                  meet death with a peaceful smile; and above all, I saw a band of young girls give
                  themselves up to the wild beasts with a song of triumph on their lips: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"'Unto Him that loved us,</l>
                        <l>That washed us from our sins.'"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7211-00000033"/>
               <p>As Marcellus spoke a wonderful effect was produced. The eyes of his listeners
                  glistened with eagerness and joy. When he mentioned Macer they looked at each
                  other with meaning glances; when he spoke of the old man, Honorius bowed his head;
                  and when he spoke of the children and murmured the words of their song, they
                  turned away their faces and wept.</p>
               <p>"For the first time in my life I saw death conquered. I myself can meet death
                  without terror, and so can every soldier when he comes in the battle-field. It is
                  our profession. But these people rejoiced in death. Here were not soldiers, but
                  children, who carried the same wonderful feeling in their hearts.</p>
               <p>"Since then I have thought of nothing else. Who is he that loved you? Who is he
                  that washes you from your sins? Who is he that causes this sublime courage and
                  hope to arise within you? What is it that supports you here? Who is he to whom you
                  were just now praying?</p>
               <p>"I have a commission to lead soldiers against you and destroy you. But I wish to
                  learn more of you first. And I swear by the Supreme that my present visit shall
                  bring no harm to you. Tell me, then, the Christian's secret."</p>
               <p>"Your words," said Honorius, "are true and sincere. Now I know that you are no spy
                  or enemy, but an inquiring soul sent here by the Spirit to learn that which you
                  have long been seeking. Rejoice, for he that cometh unto Christ shall be in no
                  wise cast out.</p>
               <p>"You see before you men and women who have left friends, and home, and honor, and
                  wealth, to live here in want, and fear, and sorrow, and they count all this as
                  nothing for Christ, yes, they count even their own lives nothing. They give up all
                  for Him who loved them.</p>
               <p>"You are right, Marcellus, in thinking that there is some great power which can do
                  all this. It is not fanaticism, nor delusion, nor excitement. It is the knowledge
                  of the truth and love for the great God.</p>
               <p>"What you have sought for all your life is our dearest possession. Treasured up in
                  our hearts, it is worth far more to us than all that the world can give. It gives
                  us happiness in<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7211-00000034"/> life even in this place
                  of gloom, and in death it makes us victorious.</p>
               <p>"You wish to know the Supreme Being. Our religion is his revelation, and through
                  this he makes himself known. Infinite in greatness and power, he also is infinite
                  in love and mercy. This religion draws us so closely to him that he is our best
                  friend, our guide, our comfort, our hope, our all, our Creator, our Redeemer, and
                  our final Saviour.</p>
               <p>"You wish to know of the immortal life. Our religion tells of this. It shows us
                  that by loving and serving God on earth we shall dwell with him in infinite
                  blessedness in heaven. It shows us how to live so as to please him here, and it
                  makes us know how we shall praise him hereafter. By this we learn that death is no
                  longer a curse, but rather a blessing, since it becomes but the sure passage way
                  unto happiness unspeakable in the presence of Him who loved us."</p>
               <p>"O then," cried Marcellus, "if this be so, make known to me this truth. For this I
                  have looked for years; for this I have prayed to that Supreme Being of whom I have
                  heard. You are the possessor of that which I long to know. The end and aim of my
                  life lies here. The whole night is before us. Do not put me off, but at once tell
                  me all. Has God, indeed, made known all this, and have I been ignorant of it?"</p>
               <p>Tears of joy glistened in the eyes of the Christians. Honorius murmured a few
                  words of silent thankfulness and prayer. After which he drew forth a manuscript,
                  which he handled with tender care.</p>
               <p>"Here," said he, "beloved youth, is the word of life which came from God, which
                  brings such peace and joy to man. In this we can find all that the soul desires.
                  In these divine words we learn that which we can find no where else; and though
                  the mind may brood over it for a lifetime, yet the extent of its glorious truths
                  can never be reached."</p>
               <p>Then Honorius opened the book and began to tell of Jesus. He told him of the long
                  succession of prophets which had heralded his coming, of the chosen people of God
                  who had kept alive the knowledge of the truth for so<pb n="70-71"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000035"/> many ages, and of the marvelous works which they
                  had witnessed.</p>
               <p>He spoke of his birth, his childhood, his first appearance, his miracles, his
                  teachings. All this he read, with a few comments of his own, from the sacred
                  manuscript.</p>
               <p>Then he related the treatment which he received, the scorn, contempt, and
                  persecution which hurried him on to his betrayal.</p>
               <p>Finally, he read the story of his death on Calvary.</p>
               <p>Upon Marcellus the effect of all this was wonderful. Light seemed to burst upon
                  his mind. The holiness of God, which turned with abhorrence from human sin; his
                  justice, which demanded punishment; his patience, which endured so much; his
                  mercy, which contrived a way to save his creatures from the ruin which they drew
                  on themselves; his amazing love, which brought him down to sacrifice himself for
                  their salvation, all were clear. When Honorius reached the end of the mournful
                  story of Calvary, and came to the cry, "My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken
                  me!" he was roused by a sob from Marcellus. Looking Up through the tears which
                  dimmed his own eyes, he saw the form of the strong man bowed, and his frame
                  quivering with emotion.</p>
               <p>"No more, no more now," he murmured. "Let me think of Him: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l rend="ti-1">"'Him who loved us,</l>
                        <l>Who washed us from our sins,</l>
                        <l>In his own blood.'"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> And Marcellus buried his face in his hands.</p>
               <p>Honorius raised his eyes to heaven and prayed. The two were alone, for their
                  companions had long since departed. The light from a lamp in a niche behind
                  Honorius but dimly illumined the scene. Thus they remained in silence for a long
                  time.</p>
               <p>At last Marcellus raised his head.</p>
               <p>"I feel," said he, "that I too had a part in causing the death of the Holy One.
                  Read on, more of that word of life, for my own life hangs upon it."</p>
               <p>Then Honorius read the story of the burial, the resurrection, the appearance again
                  to the disciples, and the ascension. Nor did he end with this. He sought to give
                  peace to the soul of his friend. He read to him all the words of<pb n="72-73"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000036"/> Jesus which invite the sinner, and assure to him a
                  gracious reception and complete forgiveness.</p>
               <p>"It is the word of God," cried Marcellus, "it is a voice from heaven. My heart
                  responds to everything that I have heard, and I know that it must be eternal
                  truth.</p>
               <p>"But how can I be a sharer in these blessings? I am a sinner; I seem now to have
                  my eyes cleared of mist. I know myself at last. Before I thought I was a just and
                  a righteous man. But beside the Holy One of whom I have heard I sink down into the
                  dust, I see that I am a sinner before him."</p>
               <p>"He has atoned for all."</p>
               <p>"But how can I be benefited?"</p>
               <p>"He will pardon everything even to the uttermost."</p>
               <p>"How can he pardon me?"</p>
               <p>"Lift up your soul to him and pray for pardon. If you ask you shall receive."</p>
               <p>"O, then, if I may dare to approach, if it be permitted for me to utter a word to
                  him, teach me the words, tell me the way."</p>
               <p>In the dimness of the gloomy vault, in solitude tude and solemn silence, Honorius
                  knelt down, and Marcellus bowed himself by his side.</p>
               <p>The venerable Christian lifted up his soul in prayer. Marcellus felt as though his
                  own soul was being lifted up to the courts of heaven, to the presence of the
                  Saviour, by the power of that fervent and agonizing prayer. The words seemed to
                  find an echo in his own soul. In his deep abasement he rested his wants upon his
                  companion so that he might present them in a more acceptable manner.</p>
               <p>But finally his own desires grew stronger. Hope came to him, timidly, tremblingly,
                  yet still it was hope, and his soul grew stronger at her presence. At last, when
                  Honorius ended, his feelings burst forth. It was the prayer of the publican: "God
                  be merciful unto me a sinner!"</p>
               <p>Hours passed on. But who can fittingly describe the progress of a soul on its way
                  to its God? Enough, that when morning dawned on the earth above, a better day had
                  dawned over the soul of Marcellus in the vaults below. His longings were
                  completely satisfied; the load was all removed; the Christians' secret was<pb
                     n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7211-00000037"/> his; and with rapture unfelt before, he
                  could now sing the song of the Christian: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l rend="ti-1">"Unto Him that loved us,</l>
                        <l>To Him that washed us from our sins</l>
                        <l>In his own blood,</l>
                        <l>To Him be glory and dominion</l>
                        <l>For ever and ever."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE CLOUD OF WITNESSES.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"These all died in faith."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE new convert soon learned more of the Christians. After a brief repose he rose
                  and was joined by Honorius, who offered to show him the nature of the place where
                  they lived.</p>
               <p>Those whom he had seen at the chapel service formed but a small part of the
                  dwellers in the catacombs. Their numbers rose to many thousands, and they were
                  scattered throughout its wide extent in little communities, each of which had its
                  own means of communication with the city.</p>
               <p>He walked far on, accompanied by Honorius. He was astonished at the numbers of
                  people whom he encountered; and though he knew that the Christians were numerous,
                  yet he did not suppose that so vast a proportion would have the fortitude to
                  choose a life in the catacombs.</p>
               <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7211-00000038"/>
               <p>Nor was he less interested in the dead than in the living. As he passed along he
                  read the inscriptions upon their tombs, and found in them all the same strong
                  faith and lofty hope. These he loved to read, and the fond interest which Honorius
                  took in these pious memorials made him a congenial guide.</p>
               <p>"There," said Honorius, "lies a witness for the truth."</p>
               <p>Marcellus looked where he pointed, and read as follows: <q>
                     <p>PRIMITIUS, IN PEACE, AFTER MANY TORMENTS, A MOST VALIANT MARTYR. HE LIVED
                        ABOUT THIRTY-EIGHT YEARS. HIS WIFE RAISED THIS TO HER DEAREST HUSBAND, THE
                        WELL-DESERVING.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>"These men," said Honorius, "show us how Christians ought to die. Yonder is
                  another who suffered like Primitius."</p>
               <p>PAULUS WAS PUT TO DEATH IN TORTURES, IN ORDER THAT HE MIGHT LIVE IN ETERNAL
                  BLISS.</p>
               <p>"And there," said Honorius, "is the tomb of a noble lady, who showed that
                  fortitude which Christ can always bestow even to the weakest of his followers in
                  the hour of need."</p>
               <p>CLEMENTIA, TORTURED, DEAD, SLEEPS, WILL RISE.</p>
               <p>"We do not die," said Honorius; "we but sleep, and when the last trump shall sound
                  we shall awake to be forever with the Lord. Here," he continued, "lies Constans,
                  doubly constant to his God by a double trial. Poison was given to him first, but
                  it was powerless over him, so he was put to the sword:"</p>
               <p>THE DEADLY DRAUGHT DARED NOT PRESENT TO CONSTANS THE CROWN WHICH THE STEEL WAS
                  PERMITTED TO OFFER.</p>
               <p>Thus they walked along, reading the inscriptions which appeared on every side. New
                  feelings came to Marcellus as he read the glorious catalogue of names. It was to
                  him a history of the Church of Christ. Here were the acts of the martyrs portrayed
                  before him in words that burned. The rude pictures that adorned many of the tombs
                  carried with them a pathos that the finest works of the skillful artist could not
                  produce. The rudely carved letters, the bad spelling and grammatical errors, that
                  characterized many of them, gave a touching proof of the treasure of the Gospel to
                  the poor and lowly. Not many wise, not many mighty are called; but to the poor the
                  Gospel is preached.</p>
               <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7211-00000039"/>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>On many of them there was a monogram, which was formed of the initial letters of
                  the name of Christ, "X" and "P" being joined so as to form one cypher. Some bore a
                  palm branch, the emblem of victory and immortality, the token of that palm of
                  glory which shall hereafter wave in the hands <figure/> of the innumerable throng
                  that are to stand around the throne. Others bore other devices.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>"What is this?" said Marcellus, pointing to a picture of a ship.</p>
               <p>"It shows that the redeemed spirit has sailed from earth to the haven of
                  rest."</p>
               <p>"And what is the meaning of this fish that I see represented so often?"</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>"The fish is used because the letters that form its name in Greek are the initials
                  of words that express the glory and hope of the Christian. 'Ι' stands for 'Jesus,'
                  'Χ' for 'Christ,' 'Θ' and 'Υ' for 'the Son of God,' and 'Σ' for 'Saviour,' so that
                  the fish symbolizes under its name <foreign xml:lang="GRC">ΙΧΘΥΣ</foreign> 'Jesus
                  Christ, the Son of God, the Saviour.'"</p>
               <p>"What means this picture that I see so often—a ship and a huge sea monster?"</p>
               <p>"That is Jonah, a prophet of God, of whom as yet you are ignorant." Honorius then
                  related the story of Jonah, and showed him how the escape from the bowels of the
                  fish reminded the Christian of his deliverance from the darkness of the tomb.
                  "This glorious hope of the resurrection is an unspeakable comfort," said he, "and
                  we love to bring it to our thoughts by different symbols. There, too, is another
                  symbol of the same blessed truth—the dove carrying an olive branch to Noah." He
                  related to his companion the story of the flood, so that Marcellus might see the
                  meaning of the representation. "But of all the symbols which are used," said he,
                  "none is so clear as this," and<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7211-00000040"/>
                  <figure/> he pointed to a picture of the resurrection of Lazarus.</p>
               <p>"There too," said Honorius, "is an anchor, the sign of hope, by which the
                  Christian, while tossing amid the stormy billows of life, holds on to his heavenly
                  home.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>"There you see the cock, the symbol for watchfulness; for our Lord has said,
                  'Watch and pray.' There also is the lamb, the type of<figure>
                     <head>PAX</head>
                  </figure> innocence and gentleness, which also brings to our mind the Lamb of God,
                  who bore our sins, and by whose sacrifice we receive pardon. There again is the
                  dove, which, like the lamb, represents innocence; and yet again you see it bearing
                  the olive branch of peace.</p>
               <p>"There are the letters Alpha and Omega, which represent our Lord; for you know
                  that he said, 'I am Alpha and Omega.' And there is the crown, which reminds of
                  that crown of immortality which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give us. Thus
                  we love to surround ourselves with all that can remind us of the joy that lies
                  before us. Taught by these, we look up from the surrounding gloom and see above us
                  the light of immortal life."</p>
               <p>"Here," said Marcellus, pausing, "is something that seems adapted to my condition.
                  It sounds prophetic. Perhaps I too may be called upon to give my testimony for
                  Christ: may I then be found faithful!"</p>
               <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7211-00000041"/>
               <p>IN CHRIST, IN THE TIME OF THE EMPEROR ADRIAN, MARIUS, A YOUNG MILITARY OFFICER,
                  WHO LIVED LONG ENOUGH, AS HE SHED HIS BLOOD FOR CHRIST, AND DIED IN PEACE. HIS
                  FRIENDS SET UP THIS WITH TEARS AND IN FEAR.</p>
               <p>"'In this world ye shall have tribulation; but be of good cheer, I have overcome
                  the world.' Thus Christ assures us; but while he warns us of evil, he consoles us
                  with his promise of support. In him we can find grace sufficient for us."</p>
               <p>"May the example of this young officer be for me," said Marcellus. "I may shed my
                  blood for Christ like him. May I die as faithfully! To lie here among my brethren
                  with such an epitaph, would be higher honor for me than a mausoleum like that of
                  Cæcilia Metella."</p>
               <p>They walked on as before.</p>
               <p>"How sweet," said Marcellus, "is the death of the Christian! Its horror has fled.
                  To him it is a blessed sleep, and death, instead of awakening terror, is
                  associated with thoughts of rest or of victory."</p>
               <p>THE SLEEPING PLACE OF ELPIS.</p>
               <p>ZOTICUS LAID HERE TO SLEEP.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>ASELUS SLEEPS IN CHRIST.</p>
               <p>MARTYRIA IN PEACE.</p>
               <p>VIDALIA IN THE PEACE OF CHRIST.</p>
               <p>NICEPHORUS, A SWEET SOUL, IN THE PLACE OF REFRESHMENT.</p>
               <p>"Some of those inscriptions tell of the characters of the departed brethren," said
                  Honorius. "Look at these."</p>
               <p>MAXIMIUS, WHO LIVED TWENTY-THREE YEARS, FRIEND OF ALL MEN.</p>
               <p>IN CHRIST, ON THE FIFTH KALENDS OF NOVEMBER, SLEPT GORGONIUS, FRIEND OF ALL, AND
                  ENEMY TO NONE.</p>
               <p>"And here too," he continued, "are others which tell of their private lives and
                  domestic experiences."</p>
               <p>CÆCILIUS THE HUSBAND, TO CÆCILIA PLACIDINA, MY WIFE, OF EXCELLENT MEMORY, WITH
                  WHOM I LIVED TEN YEARS WITHOUT ANY QUARREL, IN JESUS CHRIST, SON OF GOD, THE
                  SAVIOUR.</p>
               <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7211-00000042"/>
               <p>SACRED TO CHRIST THE SUPREME GOD. VITALIS, BURIED ON SATURDAY, KALENDS OF AUGUST,
                  AGED TWENTY-FIVE YEARS AND EIGHT MONTHS. SHE LIVED WITH HER HUSBAND TEN YEARS AND
                  THIRTY DAYS. IN CHRIST THE FIRST AND THE LAST.</p>
               <p>TO DOMNINA, MY SWEETEST AND MOST INNOCENT WIFE, WHO LIVED SIXTEEN YEARS AND FOUR
                  MONTHS, AND WAS MARRIED TWO YEARS FOUR MONTHS AND NINE DAYS: WITH WHOM I WAS NOT
                  ABLE TO LIVE, ON ACCOUNT OF MY TRAVELING, MORE THAN SIX MONTHS, DURING WHICH TIME
                  I SHEWED HER MY LOVE AS I FELT IT. NONE ELSE SO LOVED EACH OTHER. BURIED ON THE
                  FIFTEENTH BEFORE THE KALENDS OF JUNE.</p>
               <p>TO CLAUDIUS, THE WELL-DESERVING AND AFFECTIONATE, WHO LOVED ME. HE LIVED ABOUT
                  TWENTY-FIVE YEARS IN CHRIST.</p>
               <p>"There is the tribute of a loving father," said Marcellus, as he read the
                  following:</p>
               <p>LAURENCE TO HIS SWEETEST SON SEVERUS. BORNE AWAY BY ANGELS ON THE SEVENTH IDES OF
                  JANUARY.</p>
               <p>"And here of a wife."</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Domiti inpace Lea fecit</p>
                  <p>Domitius in peace, Lea erected this.</p>
               </q>
               <p>"Yes," said Honorius, "the religion of Jesus Christ changes the nature of man, and
                  while it awakens within him love to God, it makes him susceptible of more tender
                  affection to his friends and relatives." Passing on, they found many epitaphs
                  which exhibited this tender love of departed relatives.</p>
               <p>CONSTANTIA, OF WONDERFUL BEAUTY AND AMIABILITY, WHO LIVED EIGHTEEN YEARS SIX
                  MONTHS AND SIXTEEN DAYS. CONSTANTIA IN PEACE.</p>
               <p>SIMPLICIUS, OF GOOD AND HAPPY MEMORY, WHO LIVED TWENTY-THREE YEARS AND FORTY-THREE
                  DAYS IN PEACE. HIS BROTHER MADE THIS MONUMENT.</p>
               <p>TO ADSERTOR OUR SON, DEAR, SWEET, MOST INNOCENT, AND INCOMPARABLE, WHO LIVED
                  SEVENTEEN YEARS SIX MONTHS AND EIGHT DAYS. HIS FATHER AND MOTHER SET UP THIS.</p>
               <p>TO JANUARIUS, SWEET AND GOOD SON, HONORED AND BELOVED BY ALL: WHO LIVED
                  TWENTY-THREE YEARS FIVE MONTHS AND TWENTY-TWO DAYS.</p>
               <p>HIS PARENTS LAURINIA, SWEETER THAN HONEY, SLEEPS IN PEACE.</p>
               <p>TO THE HOLY SOUL, INNOCENS, WHO LIVED ABOUT THREE YEARS.</p>
               <p>DOMITIANUS, AN INNOCENT SOUL, SLEEPS IN PEACE.</p>
               <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7211-00000043"/>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>"Farewell, O Sabina; she lived viii years, viii months and xxii days.</p>
                  <p>Mayst thou live sweet in God."</p>
               </q>
               <p>IN CHRIST: DIED ON THE KALENDS OF SEPTEMBER, POMPEIANUS THE INNOCENT, WHO LIVED
                  SIX YEARS NINE MONTHS EIGHT DAYS AND FOUR HOURS. HE SLEEPS IN PEACE.</p>
               <p>TO THEIR DESERVING SON, CALPURNIUS, HIS PARENTS MADE THIS: HE LIVED FIVE YEARS,
                  EIGHT MONTHS AND TEN DAYS, AND DEPARTED IN PEACE ON THE THIRTEENTH OF JUNE.</p>
               <p>"Unto the epitaph of this child," said Marcellus, "they have added the symbols of
                  peace and of glory." He pointed to a child's tomb, upon the slab of which was
                  engraved a dove and a laurel crown, together with the following inscription:</p>
               <p>RESPECTUS, WHO LIVED FIVE YEARS AND EIGHT MONTHS, SLEEPS IN PEACE.</p>
               <p>"And this one," continued Marcellus, "has a palm branch, the symbol of
                  victory."</p>
               <p>"Yes," said Honorius, "the Saviour has said, 'Suffer little children to come unto
                  me,'" and he read the following inscription:</p>
               <p>MACUS, AN INNOCENT BOY. YOU HAVE ALREADY BEGUN TO BE AMONG THE INNOCENT ONES. HOW
                  ENDURING IS SUCH A LIFE TO YOU. HOW GLADLY WILL YOUR MOTHER, THE CHURCH OF GOD,
                  RECEIVE YOU, RETURNING TO THIS WORLD! LET US RESTRAIN OUR GROANS AND CEASE FROM
                  WEEPING.</p>
               <p>Their attention was also attracted by epitaphs over the graves of women who had
                  been wives of Christian ministers.</p>
               <p>MY WIFE LAURENTIA MADE ME THIS TOMB. SHE WAS EVER SUITED TO MY DISPOSITION,
                  VENERABLE AND FAITHFUL. AT LENGTH DISAPPOINTED ENVY LIES CRUSHED. THE BISHOP LEO
                  SURVIVED HIS EIGHTIETH YEAR.</p>
               <p>THE PLACE OF BASIL THE PRESBYTER AND HIS FELICITAS. THEY MADE IT FOR
                  THEMSELVES.</p>
               <p>ONCE THE HAPPY DAUGHTER OF THE PRESBYTER GABINUS, HERE LIES SUSANNA, JOINED WITH
                  HER FATHER IN PEACE.</p>
               <p>CLAUDIUS ATTICIANUS, A LECTOR, AND CLAUDIA FELICISIMA HIS WIFE.</p>
               <p>"I see here," said Marcellus, "a larger tomb. Are two buried here?"</p>
               <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7211-00000044"/>
               <p>"Yes, this is a '<foreign xml:lang="LAT">bisomum,</foreign>' and two occupy that
                  cell. Read the inscription:"</p>
               <p>THE BISOMUM OF SABINUS. HE MADE IT FOR HIMSELF DURING HIS LIFETIME IN THE CEMETERY
                  OF BALBINA IN THE NEW CRYPT.</p>
               <p>"Sometimes," continued Honorius, "three are buried in the same grave. In other
                  places, Marcellus, you will see that large numbers are buried; for when
                  persecution rages it is not always possible to pay to each individual the separate
                  attention that is required. Yonder is a tablet that marks the burial place of many
                  martyrs whose names are unknown, but whose memories are blessed." He pointed to a
                  slab bearing the following inscription:</p>
               <p>MARCELLA AND FIVE HUNDRED AND FIFTY MARTYRS OF CHRIST.</p>
               <p>"Here is a longer one," said Marcellus, "and its words may well find an echo in
                  the hearts of all of us." With deep emotion they read the following:</p>
               <p>IN CHRIST. ALEXANDER IS NOT DEAD, BUT LIVES ABOVE THE STARS, AND HIS BODY RESTS IN
                  THIS TOMB. HE ENDED HIS LIFE UNDER THE EMPEROR ANTONINE, WHO, ALTHOUGH HE MIGHT
                  HAVE FORESEEN THAT GREAT BENEFIT WOULD RESULT FROM HIS SERVICES, RENDERED UNTO HIM
                  HATRED INSTEAD OF FAVOR. FOR WHILE ON HIS KNEES, AND ABOUT TO SACRIFICE UNTO THE
                  TRUE GOD, HE WAS LED AWAY TO EXECUTION. O SAD TIMES! IN WHICH EVEN AMONG SACRED
                  RITES AND PRAYERS, NOT EVEN IN CAVERNS COULD WE BE SAFE. WHAT CAN BE MORE WRETCHED
                  THAN SUCH A LIFE? AND WHAT THAN SUCH A DEATH? WHERE THEY CANNOT BE BURIED BY THEIR
                  FRIENDS AND RELATIONS! AT LENGTH THEY SPARKLE IN HEAVEN. HE HAS SCARCELY LIVED WHO
                  HAS LIVED IN CHRISTIAN TIMES.</p>
               <p>"This," said Honorius, "is the resting place of a well loved brother, whose memory
                  is still cherished in all the Churches. Around this tomb we shall hold the 'Agape'
                  upon the anniversary of his birthday. At this feast the barriers of different
                  classes and ranks, of different kindreds and tribes and tongues and peoples, are
                  all broken down. We are all brethren in Christ Jesus, for we remember that as
                  Christ loved us, so ought we also to love one another."</p>
               <p>In this walk Marcellus had ample opportunity to witness the presence of that
                  fraternal love to which Honorius alluded. He encountered men, women, and children
                  of every rank and of every age. Men who had filled the highest<pb n="90-91"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000045"/> stations in Rome associated in friendly intercourse
                  with those who were scarcely above the level of slaves; those who had once been
                  cruel and relentless persecutors, now associated in pleasant union with the former
                  objects of their hate. The Jewish priest, released from the fetters of bigotry and
                  stubborn pride, walked hand in hand with the once hated Gentile. The Greek had
                  beheld the foolishness of the Gospel transformed into infinite wisdom, and the
                  contempt which he had once felt for the followers of Jesus had given place to
                  tender affection. Selfishness and ambition, haughtiness and envy, all the baser
                  passions of human life, seemed to have fled before the almighty power of Christian
                  love. The religion of Christ dwelt in their hearts in all its fullness, and its
                  blessed influences were seen here as they might not be witnessed elsewhere; not
                  because its nature or its power had been changed for their sakes, but because the
                  universal persecution which pressed on all alike had robbed them of earthly
                  possessions, cut them off from earthly temptations, and by the great sympathy of
                  common suffering had forced them closer to one another.</p>
               <pb n="92 (Illustration) -93" xml:id="VAC7211-00000046"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>A PASSAGE IN THE CATACOMBS.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>"The worship of the true God," said Honorius, "differs in one respect from all
                  false worship. The heathen must enter into his temple, and there through the
                  medium of the priest offer up his prayers and his sacrifice. But for us Christ has
                  made a sacrifice once for all. Every one of his followers can now approach God for
                  himself, for each one is made, through Jesus, a king and a priest unto God. To us,
                  then, it is a matter of no moment, as far as worship is concerned, whether our
                  chapels are left unto us, or whether we are banished from them out of the sight of
                  earth. Heaven is the throne of God and the universe is his temple, and each one of
                  his children can lift up his voice from any place and at any time to worship the
                  Father."</p>
               <p>Marcellus's journey extended for a long time and for a great distance. Prepared as
                  he was to find a great extent, he was still astonished at its vastness. The half
                  had not been told him! and though he had traversed so much, he was told that this
                  was but a fraction of the whole extent.</p>
               <p>The average height of the passage ways was<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7211-00000047"
                  /> about eight feet, but in many places it rose to twelve or fifteen feet. Then
                  the frequent chapels and rooms which had been formed by widening the arches gave
                  greater space to the inhabitants, and made it possible for them to live and move
                  in greater freedom. In some places, also, there were narrow openings in the roof,
                  through which faint rays of light passed from the upper air. These were chosen as
                  places for resort, but not for living. The presence of the blessed light of day,
                  however faint, was pleasant beyond expression, and served in some slight degree to
                  mitigate the surrounding gloom.</p>
               <p>Marcellus saw some places which had been walled up forming a sudden termination to
                  the passage way, but other paths branched off and encircled them and went on as
                  before. "What is this place which is thus inclosed?" he asked.</p>
               <p>"It is a Roman tomb," said Honorius. "On excavating this passage the workmen
                  struck upon it, so they stopped and walled up the place and carried on their
                  excavation around it. It was not from the fear of disturbing the tomb, but because
                  in death, no less than in life, the Christian desires to follow the command of his
                  Lord, and 'come out from among them and be separate.'"</p>
               <p>"Persecution rages around us and shuts us in," said Marcellus. "How long shall the
                  people of God be scattered, how long shall the enemy distress us?"</p>
               <p>"Such are the cries of many among us," said Honorius, "but it is wrong to
                  complain. The Lord has been good to his people. Throughout the empire they have
                  gone on for many generations protected by the laws and unmolested. True, we have
                  had terrible persecutions, in which thousands have died in agony, but these again
                  have passed away and left the Church in peace.</p>
               <p>"All the persecutions which we have yet received have served only to purify the
                  hearts of the people of God and exalt their faith. He knows what is best for us.
                  We are in his hands, and he will give us no more than we can bear. Let us be sober
                  and watch and pray, O Marcellus, for the present storm tells us plainly that the
                  great and terrible day so long expected is at hand."</p>
               <p>Thus Marcellus walked about with Honorius,<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7211-00000048"
                  /> conversing and learning new things every hour about the doctrines of God's
                  truth and the experiences of his people. The sight of their love, their purity,
                  their fortitude, their faith, sank deeply into his soul.</p>
               <p>The experience which he too had felt was not transient. Every new sight but
                  strengthened his desire to unite himself with the faith and fortunes of the people
                  of God. Accordingly, before the following Lord's day he was baptized in the name
                  of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghost.</p>
               <p>On the morning of the Lord's day he sat around the table of the Lord in company
                  with other Christians. There they held that simple and affecting ceremony by which
                  the Christians showed forth the death of Jesus. Honorius offered up the prayer for
                  blessing on the repast. And for the first time Marcellus partook of the wine and
                  the bread, the sacred symbols of the body and blood of his dying Lord.</p>
               <p>"And when they had sung a hymn, they went out."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE CONFESSION OF FAITH.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"Yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer
                        persecution."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>FOUR days had elapsed since the young soldier had left his chamber. Eventful days
                  they had been to him; days full of infinite importance. Endless weal or woe had
                  hung upon their issue. But the search of this earnest soul after the truth had not
                  been in vain.</p>
               <p>His resolution had been taken. On the one side lay fame, honor, and wealth; on the
                  other, poverty, want, and woe; yet he had made his choice, and turned to the
                  latter without a moment's hesitation. He chose rather to suffer affliction with
                  the people of God than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season.</p>
               <p>Upon his return he visited the general and reported himself. He informed him that
                  he had been among the Christians, that he could not execute his commission, and
                  was willing to<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7211-00000049"/> take the consequences. The
                  general sternly ordered him to his quarters.</p>
               <p>Here in the midst of deep meditation, while, conjecturing what might be the issue
                  of all this, he was interrupted by the entrance of Lucullus. His friend greeted
                  him most affectionately, but was evidently full of anxiety.</p>
               <p>"I have just seen the general," said he, "who sent for me to give me a message for
                  you. But first tell me what is this that you have done?"</p>
               <p>Marcellus then related everything from the time he had left until his return,
                  concealing nothing whatever. His deep earnestness showed how strong and true the
                  impression was that had been made upon him. He then related his interview with his
                  general.</p>
               <p>"I entered the room feeling the importance of the step I was taking. I was about
                  to commit an act of virtual treason, a crime which can only be punished with
                  death. Yet I could do nothing else.</p>
               <p>"He received me graciously, for he thought that I had met with some important
                  success in my search. I told him that since I left I had been among the
                  Christians, and from what I had seen of them I had been forced to change my
                  feelings toward them. I had thought that they were enemies of the state and worthy
                  of death, but I found that they were loyal subjects of the emperor and virtuous
                  men. I could never use my sword against such as these, and rather than do so I
                  would give it up.</p>
               <p>"'A soldier's feelings,' said he, 'have no right to interfere with his
                  duties.'</p>
               <p>"'But my duties to the God who made me are stronger than any which I owe to
                  man.'</p>
               <p>"'Has your sympathy with the Christians made you mad?' said he. 'Do you not know
                  that this is treason?'</p>
               <p>"I bowed, and said that I would take the consequences.</p>
               <p>"'Rash youth,' he cried sternly, 'go to your quarters, and I will communicate to
                  you my decision.'</p>
               <p>"And so I came here at once, and have been here ever since then, anxiously
                  awaiting my sentence."</p>
               <p>Lucullus had listened to the whole of Marcellus's recital without a word or even a
                  gesture. An expression of sad surprise upon his<pb n="100-101"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000050"/> face told what his feelings were. He spoke in a
                  mournful tone as Marcellus ended.</p>
               <p>"And what that sentence must be you certainly know as well as I. Roman discipline,
                  even in ordinary times, can never be trifled with, but now the feelings of the
                  government are excited to an unusual degree against these Christians. If you
                  persist in your present course you must fall."</p>
               <p>"I have told you all my reasons."</p>
               <p>"I know, Marcellus, your pure and sincere nature. You have always been of a devout
                  mind. You have loved the noble teachings of philosophy. Can you not satisfy
                  yourself with these as before? Why should you be attracted by the wretched
                  doctrine of a crucified Jew?"</p>
               <p>"I have never been satisfied with the philosophy of which you speak. You yourself
                  know that there is nothing certain in it on which the soul may trust. But the
                  Christian religion is the truth of God, brought down by himself, and sanctified by
                  his own death."</p>
               <p>"You have thoroughly explained the whole Christian creed to me. Your own
                  enthusiasm has made it appear attractive, I will confess; and if all its followers
                  were really like yourself my dear Marcellus, it might be adapted to bless the
                  world. But I come not here to argue upon religion. I come to speak about yourself.
                  You are in danger, my dear friend; your station, your honor, your office, your
                  very life is at stake. Consider what you have done. An important commission was
                  intrusted to you, upon the execution of which you set out. It was expected that
                  you would return bringing important information. But instead of this you come back
                  and inform the general that you have gone over to the enemy, that you are one of
                  them in heart, and that you refuse to bear arms against them. If the soldier is
                  free to choose whom he will fight what becomes of discipline? He must obey orders.
                  Am I right?"</p>
               <p>"You are, Lucullus."</p>
               <p>"The question for you to decide is not whether you will choose philosophy or
                  Christianity, but whether you will be a Christian or a soldier. For as the times
                  are now you see that it is impossible for you to be a soldier and a Christian at
                  the same time. One of the two must be given up. And not only so, but if you<pb
                     n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7211-00000051"/> decide upon being a Christian you must
                  at once share their fate, for no distinction can be made in favor of you. On the
                  other hand, if you continue a soldier you must fight against the Christians."</p>
               <p>"That is no doubt the question."</p>
               <p>"You have warm friends who are willing to forget your great offense, Marcellus. I
                  know your enthusiastic nature, and I have pleaded with the general for you. He too
                  respects you for your soldierly qualities. He is willing to forgive you under
                  certain circumstances."</p>
               <p>"What are they?"</p>
               <p>"The most merciful of all conditions. Let the past four days be forgotten. Banish
                  them from your memory. Resume your commission. Take your soldiers and go at once
                  about your duty in arresting these Christians."</p>
               <p>"Lucullus," said Marcellus, rising from his seat with folded arms, "I love you as
                  a friend, I am grateful for your faithful affection. Never can I forget it. But I
                  have that within me to which you are a stranger, which is stronger than all honors
                  of state. It is the love of God. For this I am ready to give up all, honor, rank,
                  and life itself. My decision is irrevocable. I am a Christian."</p>
               <p>For a moment Lucullus sat in astonishment and grief looking at his friend. He was
                  well acquainted with his resolute soul, and saw with pain how completely his
                  persuasions had failed. At length he spoke again. He used every argument that he
                  could think of. He brought forward every motive that might influence him. He told
                  him of the terrible fate that awaited him, and the peculiar vengeance that would
                  be directed against him. But all his words were completely useless. At length he
                  rose in deep sadness.</p>
               <p>"Marcellus," he said, "you tempt fate. You are rushing madly upon a terrible
                  destiny. Everything that fortune can bestow is before you, but you turn away from
                  all to cast your lot among wretched outcasts. I have done the duty of a friend in
                  trying to turn you from your folly, but all that I can do is of no avail.</p>
               <p>"I have brought you the sentence of the general. You are degraded from office. You
                  are put under arrest as a Christian. To-morrow you will be seized and handed over
                     to<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7211-00000052"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>THE ARCH OF TITUS.</head>
                  </figure> punishment. But many hours are yet before you, and I may still have the
                  mournful satisfaction of assisting you to escape. Fly then at once. Hasten, for
                  there is no time to lose. There is only one place in the world where you can be
                  secure from the vengeance of Cæsar."</p>
               <p>Marcellus heard in silence. Slowly he took off his splendid arms and laid them
                  down, sadly he unfastened his gorgeous armor which he had worn so proudly. He
                  stood in his simple tunic before his friend.</p>
               <p>"Lucullus, again I say that I can never forget your faithful friendship. Would we
                  were flying together, that your prayers might ascend with mine to Him whom I
                  serve. But enough, I will go. Farewell."</p>
               <p>"Farewell, Marcellus. We may never meet in life again. If you are ever in want or
                  peril you know on whom you can rely."</p>
               <p>The two young men embraced, and Marcellus hastily took his departure.</p>
               <p>He walked out of the camp and onward until he reached the Forum. All around him
                  were stately marble temples and columns and monuments. There the arch of Titus
                  spanned the Via Sacra; there the imperial palace reared its gigantic form on high,
                  rich in stately architecture, in glorious adornments of precious marbles, and
                  glowing in golden decorations. On one side the lofty walls of the Coliseum arose;
                  beyond, the stupendous dome of the Temple of Peace; and on the other the
                  Capitoline Hill upraised its historic summit, crowned with a cluster of stately
                  temples that stood out in sharp relief against the sky.</p>
               <p>To this he directed his steps, and ascended<pb n="106-107"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000053"/>
                  <figure/> the steep declivity up to the top of the hill. From the summit he looked
                  around upon the scene. The place itself was a spacious square paved with marble,
                  and surrounded with lordly temples. On one side was the Campus Martius, bounded by
                  the Tiber, whose yellow flood wound afar onward to the Mediterranean. On every
                  other side the city spread its unequaled extent, crowding to the narrow walls, and
                  overleaping them to throw out its radiating streets far away on every side into
                  the country. Temples and columns and monuments reared their lofty heads.
                  Innumerable statues filled the streets with a population of sculptured forms,
                  fountains dashed into the air, chariots rolled through the streets, the legions of
                  Rome marched to and fro in military array, and on every side surged the restless
                  tide of life in the Imperial city.</p>
               <p>Far away the plain extended, dotted with countless villages and houses and
                  palaces, rich in luxuriant verdure, the dwelling-place of peace and plenty. On one
                  side arose the blue outline of the Apennines, crowned with snow; on the other the
                  dark waves of the Mediterranean washed the far distant shore.</p>
               <p>Suddenly Marcellus was startled by a shout. He turned. An old man in scant
                  clothing, with emaciated face and frenzied gesticulation, was shouting out a
                  strain of fearful denunciation. His wild glance and fierce manner showed that he
                  was partly insane. <q>
                     <lg type="para">
                        <l rend="ti-1">"'Babylon the great is fallen, is fallen,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And is become the habitation of devils,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And the hold of every foul spirit,</l>
                        <pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7211-00000054"/>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And a cage of every unclean and hateful bird;</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">For God hath remembered her iniquities.</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Reward her even as she rewarded you,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And double unto her double according to her works.</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">How much hath she glorified herself and lived
                           deliciously,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Therefore shall her plagues come in one day,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Death, and mourning, and famine;</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And she shall be utterly burned with fire;</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">For strong is the Lord God who judgeth her.</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">The kings of the earth</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Shall bewail and lament,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Seeing the smoke of her burning,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Standing afar off for fear of her torment,</l>
                        <l>Crying, Alas, alas, that great city Babylon,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">That mighty city Babylon,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">For in one hour is thy judgment come.</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">The merchants of the earth,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Standing afar off for fear of her torment,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Shall weep and wail.</l>
                        <l>Crying, Alas, alas, that great city Babylon,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">That was clothed in fine linen, and purple, and scarlet,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">And decked with gold, and precious stones, and pearls.</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">For in one hour so great riches is come to naught!</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And every shipmaster, and the company in ships,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And sailors and traders by sea,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Shall cry when they see the smoke of her burning,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Standing afar off for fear of her torment.</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">'What city is like unto that great city!'</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And casting dust on their head they shall cry,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Weeping and wailing,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">Alas, alas, that great city,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">Wherein were made rich all that had ships at sea,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">For in one hour is she brought to naught</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">Rejoice over her thou heaven!</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">And ye holy apostles and prophets,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">For God hath avenged you on her!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>A vast crowd collected around him in amazement, but scarcely had he ceased when
                  some soldiers appeared and led him away.</p>
               <p>"Doubtless it is some poor Christian whose brain has been turned by suffering,"
                  thought Marcellus. As the man was led away he still shouted out his terrific
                  denunciations, and a great crowd followed, yelling and deriding. Soon the noise
                  died away in the distance.</p>
               <p>"There is no time to lose. I must go," said Marcellus; and he turned away.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7211-00000055"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"O dark, dark, dark, amid the blaze of noon.</l>
                        <l>Irrevocably dark, total eclipse,</l>
                        <l>Without all hope of day!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>UPON his return to the Catacombs he was welcomed with tears of joy. Most eagerly
                  they listened to the account of his interview with his superiors; and while they
                  sympathized with his troubles, they rejoiced that he had been found worthy to
                  suffer for Christ.</p>
               <p>Amid these new scenes he learned more of the truth every day, and saw what its
                  followers endured. Life in the Catacombs opened around him with all its wondrous
                  variety.</p>
               <p>The vast numbers who dwelt below were supplied with provisions by constant
                  communication with the city above. This was done at night. The most resolute and
                  daring of the men volunteered for this dangerous task. Sometimes also women, and
                  even boys, went forth upon this errand, and the lad Pollio was the most acute and
                  successful of all these. Amid the vast population of Rome it was not difficult to
                  pass unnoticed, and consequently the supply was well kept up. Yet sometimes the
                  journey met with a fatal termination, and the bold adventurers never returned.</p>
               <p>Of water there was a plentiful supply in the passage ways of the lowermost tier.
                  Wells and fountains here supplied sufficient for all their wants.</p>
               <p>At night, too, were made the most mournful expeditions of all. These were in
                  search of the dead which had been torn by the wild beasts or burned at the stake.
                  These loved remains were obtained at the greatest risk, and brought down amid a
                  thousand dangers. Then the friends of the lost would perform the funeral service
                  and hold the burial feast. After this they would deposit their remains in the
                  narrow cell, and close the place up with a marble tablet graven with the name of
                  the occupant.</p>
               <p>The ancient Christian, inspired by the glorious doctrine of the resurrection,
                  looked forward with ardent hope to the time when corruption should put on
                  incorruption, and the mortal, immortality. He was unwilling that the body<pb
                     n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7211-00000056"/> which so sublime a destiny awaited
                  should be reduced to ashes, and thought that even the sacred funeral flames were a
                  dishonor to that temple of God which had been so highly favored of heaven. So the
                  cherished bodies of the dead were brought here out of the sight of man, where no
                  irreverent hand might disturb the solemn stillness of their last repose, to lie
                  until the last trump should give that summons for which the primitive Church
                  waited so eagerly, in daily expectation. In the city above the Christian religion
                  had been increasing for successive generations, and during all this time the dead
                  had been coming here in ever-increasing numbers, so that now the Catacombs formed
                  a vast city of the dead, whose silent population slumbered in endless ranges, rank
                  above rank, waking till <q>
                     <l>"The wakeful trump of doom should thunder through the deep."</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In many places the arches had been knocked away and the roof heightened so as to
                  form rooms. None of them were of very great size, but they formed areas where the
                  fugitives might meet in larger companies and breathe more freely. Here they passed
                  much of the time, and here, too, they had their religious services.</p>
               <p>The nature of the times in which they lived will explain their situation. The
                  simple virtues of the old republic had passed away, and freedom had taken her
                  everlasting flight. Corruption had moved over the empire and subdued every thing
                  beneath its numbing influence. Plots, rebellions, and treasons cursed the state by
                  turns, but the fallen people stood by in silence. They saw their bravest suffer,
                  their noblest die, all unmoved. The generous heart, the soul of fire, awaked no
                  more. Only the basest passions aroused their degenerate feelings.</p>
               <p>Into such a state as this the truth came boldly, and through such enemies as these
                  it had to fight its way over such obstacles to make its slow but sure progress.
                  They who enlisted under her banner had no life of ease before them. Her trumpet
                  gave forth no uncertain sound. The conflict was stern, and involved name, and
                  fame, and fortune, and friends, and life, all that was most dear to man. Ages
                  rolled on. If the followers of truth increased in number, so also did vice
                  intensify her power and her malignity;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7211-00000057"/>
                  the people sank into deeper corruption, the state drifted on to more certain
                  ruin.</p>
               <p>Then arose those terrible persecutions which aimed to obliterate from the earth
                  the last vestige of Christianity. A terrible ordeal awaited the Christian if he
                  resisted the imperial decree; to those who followed her, the order of Truth was
                  inexorable; and when a decision was made, it was a final one. To make that
                  decision for Christianity was often to accept instant death, or else to be driven
                  from the city, banished from the joys of home and from the light of day.</p>
               <p>The hearts of the Romans were hardened and their eyes blinded. Neither childhood's
                  innocence, nor womanly purity, nor noble manhood, nor the reverend hairs of age,
                  nor faith immovable, nor love triumphant over death, could touch them or move them
                  to pity. They did not see the black cloud of desolation that hovered over the
                  doomed empire, nor know that from its fury those whom they persecuted alone could
                  save them.</p>
               <p>Yet in that reign of terror the Catacombs opened before the Christian like a city
                  of refuge. Here lay the bones of their fathers who from generation to generation
                  had fought for the truth, and their worn bodies waited here for the resurrection
                  morn. Here they brought their relatives, as one by one they had left them and gone
                  on high. Here the son had borne the body of his aged mother, and the parent had
                  seen his child committed to the tomb. Here they had carried the mangled remains of
                  those who had been torn to pieces by the wild beasts of the arena; the blackened
                  corpses of those who had been given to the flames; or the wasted bodies of those
                  most wretched who had sighed out their lives amid the lingering agonies of death
                  by crucifixion. Every Christian had some friend or relative lying here in death.
                  The very ground was sanctified, the very air hallowed. It was not strange that
                  they should seek for safety in such a place.</p>
               <p>Moreover, in these subterranean abodes, they found their only place of refuge from
                  persecution. They could not seek foreign countries nor fly beyond the sea, because
                  for them there were no countries of refuge, and no lands beyond the sea held out a
                  hope. The imperial power of Rome grasped the civilized world in its mighty<pb
                     n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7211-00000058"/> embrace; her tremendous police system
                  extended through all lands, and none might escape her wrath. So resistless was
                  this power, that from the highest noble down to the meanest slave, all were
                  subject to it. The dethroned emperor could not escape her vengeance, nor was such
                  an escape even hoped for. When Nero fell, he could only go and kill himself in a
                  neighboring villa. Yet here, amid these infinite labyrinths, even the power of
                  Rome was unavailing, and her baffled emissaries faltered at the very entrance.</p>
               <p>Here, then, the persecuted Christians tarried, and their great numbers peopled
                  these paths and grottoes, by day assembling to exchange words of cheer and
                  comfort, or to bewail the death of some new martyr; by night sending forth the
                  boldest among them, like a forlorn hope, to learn tidings of the upper world, or
                  to bring down the blood-stained bodies of some new victims. Through the different
                  persecutions, they lived here so secure that although millions perished throughout
                  the empire, the power of Christianity at Rome was but slightly shaken.</p>
               <p>Their safety was secured and life preserved, but on what terms? For what is life
                  without light, or what is the safety of the body in gloom that depresses the soul?
                  The physical nature of man shrinks from such a fate, and his delicate organization
                  is speedily aware of the lack of that subtle renovating principle which is
                  connected with light only. One by one the functions of the body lose their tone
                  and energy. This weakening of the body affects the mind, predisposing it to gloom,
                  apprehension, doubt, and despair. It is greater honor for a man to be true and
                  steadfast under such circumstances than to have died a heroic death in the arena
                  or to have perished unflinchingly at the stake. Here, where there closed around
                  these captives the thickest shades of darkness, they encountered their sorest
                  trial. Fortitude under the persecution itself was admirable; but against the
                  persecution, blended with such horrors as these, it became sublime.</p>
               <p>The cold blast that forever drifted through these labyrinths chilled them, but
                  brought no pure air from above; the floors, the walls, the roofs, were covered
                  over with the foul deposits of damp vapors that forever hung around; the
                  atmosphere was thick with impure exhalations<pb n="118-119"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000059"/> and poisonous miasma; the dense smoke from the
                  ever-burning torches might have mitigated the noxious gases, but it oppressed the
                  dwellers here with its blinding and suffocating influence. Yet amid all these
                  accumulated horrors the soul of the martyr stood up unconquered. The Roman spirit
                  that endured all this rises up to grander proportions than were ever attained in
                  the proudest days of the old republic. The fortitude of Regulus, the devotion of
                  Curtius, the constancy of Brutus, were here surpassed, not by the strong man, but
                  by the tender virgin and the weak child. Thus, scorning to yield to the fiercest
                  power of persecution, these men went forth, the good, the pure in heart, the
                  brave, the noble. For them death had no terrors, nor that appalling life in death
                  which they were compelled to endure here in the dismal regions of the dead. They
                  knew what was before them, and they accepted it all. Willingly they descended
                  here, carrying with them all that was most precious to the soul of man, and they
                  endured all this for the great love wherewith they were loved.</p>
               <p>The constant efforts which they made to diminish minish the gloom of their abodes
                  were visible all around. In the ancient world art was cultivated more universally
                  than in the modern. Wherever any large number of men was collected a large
                  proportion had the taste and the talent for art. When the Christians peopled the
                  Catacombs the artist was here too, and his art was not unemployed. In these
                  chapels, which to the population here were like what public squares are to the
                  inhabitants of a city, every effort was made to lessen the surrounding
                  cheerlessness. So the walls were in some places covered over with white stucco,
                  and in others these again were adorned with pictures, not of deified mortals for
                  idolatrous worship, but of those grand old heroes of the truth who in former
                  generations had "through faith subdued kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained
                  promises, stopped the mouths of lions, quenched the violence of fire, escaped the
                  edge of the sword, out of weakness were made strong, waxed valiant in fight,
                  turned to flight the armies of the aliens." If in the hour of bitter anguish they
                  sought for scenes or thoughts that might relieve their souls and inspire them with
                  fresh strength<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7211-00000060"/> for the future, they
                  could have found no other objects to look upon so strong to encourage, so mighty
                  to console.</p>
               <p>Such were the decorations of the chapels. The only furniture which they contained
                  was a simple wooden table upon which they placed the bread and wine of the
                  sacrament, the symbols of the body and blood of their dying Lord.</p>
               <p>Christianity had struggled long, and it was a struggle with corruption. It will
                  not be thought strange, then, if the Church contracted some marks of a too close
                  contact with her foe, or if she carried some of them down to her place of refuge.
                  Yet if they had some variations from the apostolic model, these were so trifling
                  that they might be overlooked altogether, were it not that they opened the way to
                  greater ones. Still, the essential doctrines of Christianity knew no pollution, no
                  change. The guilt of man, the mercy of the Father, the atonement of the Son, the
                  inspiration of the Holy Spirit, salvation through faith in the Redeemer, all these
                  foundations of truth were cherished with a fervor and an energy to which no
                  language can do justice.</p>
               <p>Theirs was that heavenly hope, the anchor of the soul, so strong and so secure
                  that the storm of an empire's wrath failed to drive them from the Rock of Ages
                  where they were sheltered.</p>
               <p>Theirs was that lofty faith which upheld them through the sorest trials, a sincere
                  trust in God that could not doubt. There was no need here either of discussions
                  about the theological term "faith," or of formal prayers that regarded it as some
                  immaterial essence. Faith with them was everything. It was the very breath of
                  life; so true that it upheld them in the hour of cruel sacrifices; so lasting that
                  even when it seemed that all the followers of Christ had vanished from the earth,
                  they could still look up trustfully and wait.</p>
               <p>Theirs was that love which Christ when on earth defined as comprising all the law
                  and the prophets. Sectarian strife, denominational bitterness, were unknown. They
                  had a great general foe to fight, how could they quarrel with one another? Here
                  arose love to man which knew no distinction of race or class, but embraced all in
                  its immense circumference, so that one could lay down his life for his brother;
                     here<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7211-00000061"/> arose love to God which stopped
                  not at the sacrifice of life itself. The persecutions which raged around them gave
                  them all that zeal, faith, and love which glowed so brightly amid the darkness of
                  the age. It confined their numbers to the true and the sincere. It was the
                  antidote to hypocrisy. It gave to the brave the most daring heroism, and inspired
                  the fainthearted with the courage of despair. They lived in a time when to be a
                  Christian was to risk one's life. They did not shrink, but boldly proclaimed their
                  faith and accepted the consequences. They drew a broad line between themselves and
                  the heathen, and stood manfully on their own side. To utter a few words, to
                  perform a simple act, could often save from death; but the tongue refused to speak
                  the formula, and the stubborn hand refused to pour the libation. The vital
                  doctrines of Christianity met from them far more than a mere intellectual
                  response. Christ himself was not to them an idea, a thought, but a real existence.
                  The life of Jesus upon earth was to them a living truth. They accepted it as a
                  proper example for every man. His gentleness, humility, patience, and meekness
                  they believed were offered for imitation, nor did they ever separate the ideal
                  Christian from the real. They thought that a man's religion consisted as much in
                  the life as in the sentiment, and had not learned to separate experimental from
                  practical Christianity. To them the death of Christ was a great event to which all
                  others were but secondary. That he died in very deed, and for the sons of men,
                  none could understand better than they. Among their own brethren they could think
                  of many a one who had hung upon the cross for his brethren or died at the stake
                  for his God. They took up the cross and followed Christ, bearing the reproach.
                  That cross and that reproach were not figurative. Witness these gloomy labyrinths,
                  fit home for the dead only, which nevertheless for years opened to shelter the
                  living. Witness these names of martyrs, those words of despair. The walls carry
                  down to later ages the words of grief, of lamentation, and of ever-changing
                  feeling which were marked upon them during successive ages by those who were
                  banished to these Catacombs. They carry down their mournful story to future times,
                     and<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7211-00000062"/> bring to imagination the forms,
                  the feelings, and the deeds of those who were imprisoned here. As the forms of
                  life are taken upon the plates of the camera, so has the great voice once forced
                  out by suffering from the very soul of the martyr become stamped upon the
                  wall.</p>
               <p>Humble witnesses of the truth; poor, dispised, forsaken; in vain their calls for
                  mercy went forth to the ears of man; they were stifled in the blood of the
                  slaughtered and the smoke of the sacrifice! Yet where their own race only answered
                  their cry of despair with fresh tortures these rocky walls proved more merciful;
                  they heard their sighs, they took them to their bosoms, and so their cries of
                  suffering lived here, treasured up and graven in the rock forever.</p>
               <p>The conversion of Marcellus to Christianity had been sudden. Yet such quick
                  transitions from error to truth were not unfrequent. He had tried the highest
                  forms of Pagan superstition and heathen philosophy but had found them wanting, and
                  as soon as Christianity appeared before him he beheld all that he desired. It
                  possessed exactly what was needed to satisfy the cravings of his soul and fill his
                  empty heart with the fullness of peace. And if the transition was quick, it was
                  none the less thorough. Having opened his eyes and seen the light of the Sun of
                  Righteousness, he could not close them. Rather than relapse into his former
                  blindness, he gladly welcomed his share in the sufferings of the persecuted.</p>
               <p>Conversions like these distinguished the first preaching of the Gospel. Throughout
                  the heathen world there were countless souls who felt as Marcellus did, and had
                  gone through the same experiences. It needed only the preaching of the truth,
                  accompanied by the power of the Holy Spirit, to open their eyes and bring them to
                  see the light. Apart from divine influence over human reason, we see here a cause
                  for the rapid spread of Christianity.</p>
               <p>Living and moving and conversing with his new brethren, Marcellus soon began to
                  enter into all their hopes and fears and joys. Their faith and trust communicated
                  themselves to his heart, and all the glorious expectations which sustained them
                  became the solace of his own soul. The blessed word of life became his constant
                     study<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7211-00000063"/> and delight, and all its
                  teachings found in him an ardent disciple.</p>
               <p>Meetings for prayer and praise were frequent throughout the Catacombs. Cut off
                  from ordinary occupations of worldly business, they were thrown entirely upon
                  other and higher pursuits. Deprived of the opportunity to make efforts for the
                  support of the body, they were forced to make their chief business the care of the
                  soul. They gained what they sought. Earth with its cares, its allurements, and its
                  thousand attractions, lost its hold upon them. Heaven drew nearer; their thoughts
                  and their language were of the kingdom. They loved to talk of the joy that awaited
                  those who continued faithful unto death; to converse upon those departed brethren
                  who to them were not lost but gone before; to anticipate the moment when their own
                  time should come. Above all, they looked every day for that great final summons
                  which should rouse the quick and dead, and arraign all before the great white
                  throne.</p>
               <p>Thus Marcellus saw these dismal passages not left to the silent slumber of the
                  dead, but filled with thousands of the living. Wan and pale and oppressed, they
                  found even amid this darkness a better fate than that which might await them
                  above. Busy life animated the haunts of the dead; the pathways rang to the sound
                  of human voices. The light of truth and virtue, banished from the upper air,
                  burned anew with a purer radiance amid this subterranean gloom. The tender
                  greetings of affection, of friendship, of kinship, and of love, arose amid the
                  mouldering remains of the departed. Here the tear of grief mingled with the blood
                  of the martyr, and the hand of affection wrapped his pale limbs in the shroud.
                  Here in these grottoes the heroic soul rose up superior to sorrow. Hope and faith
                  smiled exultingly, and pointed to the light of immortal life, and the voice of
                  praise breathed forth from the lips of the mourner.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7211-00000064"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE PERSECUTION.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"Ye have need of patience, that after ye have done the will of God ye might
                        receive the promise."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE persecution raged with greater fury. In the few weeks that passed since
                  Marcellus had lived here, great numbers had sought refuge in this retreat. Never
                  before had so many congregated here. Generally the authorities had been content
                  with the more conspicuous Christians, and the fugitives to the Catacombs were
                  consequently composed of this class; it was a severe persecution indeed which
                  embraced all, and such indiscriminate rage had been shown only under a few
                  emperors. But now there was no distinction of class or station. The humblest
                  follower as well as the highest teacher was hurried away to death.</p>
               <p>Until this time the communication with the city was comparatively easy, for the
                  poor Christians above ground never neglected those below or forgot their wants.
                  Provisions and assistance of all kinds were readily obtained. But now the very
                  ones on whom the fugitives relied for help were themselves driven out, to share
                  their fate and become the partakers instead of the bestowers of charity.</p>
               <p>Still their situation was not desperate. There were many left in Rome who loved
                  them and assisted them, although they were not Christians. In every great movement
                  there will be an immense class composed of neutrals, who either from interest or
                  indifference remain unmoved. These people will invariably join the strongest side,
                  and where danger threatens will evade it by any concessions. Such was the
                  condition of large numbers in Rome. They had friends and relatives among the
                  Christians whom they loved, and for whom they felt sympathy. They were always
                  ready to assist them, but had too much regard for their own safety to cast in
                  their lot with them. They attended the temples and assisted at the worship of the
                  heathen gods as before, and were nominally adherents of the old superstition. Upon
                  these now the Christians were forced to depend for the necessaries of life.</p>
               <pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7211-00000065"/>
               <p>The expeditions to the city were now accompanied with greater danger, and only the
                  boldest dared to venture. Such, however, was the contempt of danger and death with
                  which they were inspired that there was never any scarcity of men for this
                  perilous duty.</p>
               <p>To this task Marcellus offered himself, glad that he could in any way do good to
                  his brethren. His fearlessness and acuteness, which had formerly raised him so
                  high as a soldier, now made him conspicuous for success in this new pursuit.</p>
               <p>Numbers were destroyed every day. Their bodies were sought for and carried away by
                  the Christians for purposes of burial. This was not very difficult to accomplish,
                  since it relieved the authorities of the trouble of burning or burying the
                  corpses.</p>
               <p>One day tidings came to the community beneath the Appian Way that two of their
                  number had been captured and put to death. Marcellus and another Christian went
                  forth to obtain their bodies. The boy Pollio also went with them, to be useful in
                  case of need. It was dusk when they entered the city gate, and darkness<pb
                     n="132 (Illustration) -133" xml:id="VAC7211-00000066"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>THE COLISEUM</head>
                  </figure> came rapidly on. Soon, however, the moon arose and illumined the
                  scene.</p>
               <p>They threaded their way through the dark streets, and at length came to the
                  Coliseum, the place of martyrdom for so many of their companions. Its dark form
                  towered up grandly before them, vast and gloomy and stern as the imperial power
                  that reared it. Crowds of keepers and guards and gladiators were within the iron
                  gates, where the vaulted passage ways were illuminated with the glare of
                  torches.</p>
               <p>The keepers knew their errand, and rudely ordered them to follow. They led them on
                  till they came to the arena. Here lay a number of bodies, the last of those who
                  had been slain that day. They were fearfully mangled; some indeed were scarcely
                  distinguishable as human beings. After a long search they found the two whom they
                  sought. Their bodies were then placed in large sacks, in which they prepared to
                  carry them away.</p>
               <p>Marcellus looked in upon the scene. All around him rose the massive walls,
                  ascending by many terraces back to the outer circle. Its<pb n="134-135"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000067"/> black form seemed to shut him in with a barrier
                  which he could not pass.</p>
               <p>"How long will it be," he thought, "before I too shall take my place here and lay
                  down my life for my Saviour? When that time comes shall I be true? Lord Jesus, in
                  that hour sustain me!"</p>
               <p>The moon had not yet risen high enough to shine into the arena. Within it was dark
                  and forbidding. The search had been made with torches obtained from the
                  keepers.</p>
               <p>At this moment Marcellus heard a deep voice from some of the vaults behind them.
                  Its tones rang out upon the night air with startling distinctness, and were heard
                  high above the rude clamor of the keepers: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Now is come salvation and strength,</l>
                        <l>And the kingdom of our God,</l>
                        <l>And the power of his Christ;</l>
                        <l>For the accuser of our brethren is cast down,</l>
                        <l>Which accused them before our God day and night.</l>
                        <l>And they overcame him by the blood of the Lamb,</l>
                        <l>And by the word of his testimony,</l>
                        <l>And they loved not their lives unto the death."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>"Who is that?" said Marcellus.</p>
               <p>"Do not notice him," said his companion. "It is Brother Cinna. His griefs have
                  made him mad. His only son was burned at the stake at the beginning of the
                  persecution, and since then he has gone about the city denouncing woe. Hitherto
                  they have let him alone; but now at last they have seized him."</p>
               <p>"And is he a prisoner here?"</p>
               <p>"He is."</p>
               <p>Again the voice of Cinna arose, fearfully, menacingly, and terribly,</p>
               <p>"How long, O Lord, holy and true, dost thou not avenge our blood on them that
                  dwell upon the earth?"</p>
               <p>"This, then, is the man that I heard in the Capitol?"</p>
               <p>"Yes. He has been all through the city, and even in the palace, uttering his
                  cry."</p>
               <p>"Let us go."</p>
               <p>They took their sacks and started for the gates. After a short delay they were
                  allowed to pass. As they went out they heard the voice of Cinna in the distance: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Babylon the great is fallen, is fallen,</l>
                        <l>And is become the habitation of devils,</l>
                        <l>And the hold of every foul spirit,</l>
                        <l>And the cage of every unclean and bateful bird:</l>
                        <l>Come ye out of her, my people!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7211-00000068"/>
               <p>None of them spoke until they had reached a safe distance from the Coliseum.</p>
               <p>"I felt afraid," said Marcellus, "that we should be kept in there."</p>
               <p>"Your fears were reasonable," said the other. "Any sudden whim of the keeper might
                  be our doom. But this we must be prepared for. In times like this we must be ready
                  to meet death at any moment. What says our Lord? 'Be ye also ready.' We must be
                  able to say when the time comes, 'I am now ready to be offered.'"</p>
               <p>"Yes," said Marcellus, "our Lord has told us what we will have: 'In this world ye
                  shall have tribulation—"</p>
               <p>"And he says also, 'Be of good cheer, I have overcome the world. Where I am, there
                  ye shall be also.'"</p>
               <p>"Through him," said Marcellus, "we can come off more than conquerors over death.
                  The afflictions of this present time are not worthy to be compared to the glory
                  that shall be revealed to us."</p>
               <p>Thus they solaced themselves with the promises of that blessed Word of life which
                  in all ages and under all circumstances can give such heavenly consolation.
                  Bearing their burdens, they finally reached their destination in safety, thankful
                  that they had been preserved.</p>
               <p>A few days afterward Marcellus went up for provisions. This time he was alone. He
                  went to the house of a man who was friendly to them and had been of much
                  assistance. It was outside of the walls, in the suburb nearest the Appian Way.</p>
               <p>After obtaining the requisite supply, he began to inquire after the news.</p>
               <p>"The news is bad for you," said the man. "One of the Pretorian officers was
                  recently converted to Christianity, and the emperor is enraged. He has appointed
                  another to the office which he held, and has sent him after the Christians. They
                  are catching some every day. No man is too poor to be seized in these days."</p>
               <p>"Ah! Do you know the name of this Pretorian officer who is seeking the
                  Christians?"</p>
               <p>"Lucullus."</p>
               <p>"Lucullus!" cried Marcellus. "How strange!"</p>
               <pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7211-00000069"/>
               <p>"He is said to be a man of great skill and energy."</p>
               <p>"I have heard of him. This is indeed bad news for the Christians."</p>
               <p>"The conversion of the other Pretorian officer has greatly enraged the emperor. A
                  price is now set upon his head. If you chance to see him or to be in his way,
                  friend, you had better let him know. They say he is in the Catacombs."</p>
               <p>"He must be there. There is no other place of safety."</p>
               <p>"These are indeed terrible times. You have need to be cautious."</p>
               <p>"They cannot kill me more than once," said Marcellus.</p>
               <p>"Ah! you Christians have wonderful fortitude. I admire your bravery; yet still I
                  think you might conform outwardly to the emperor's decree. Why should you rush so
                  madly upon death?"</p>
               <p>"Our Redeemer died for us. We are ready to die for him. And since he died for his
                  people, we also are willing to imitate him and lay down our lives for our
                  brethren."</p>
               <p>"You are wonderful people," said the man, raising his hands.</p>
               <p>Marcellus now bade him farewell, and departed with his load. The news which he had
                  just heard filled his mind.</p>
               <p>"So Lucullus has taken my place," thought he. "I wonder if he has turned against
                  me? Does he now think of me as his friend Marcellus, or only as a Christian? I may
                  soon find out. It would be strange indeed if I should fall into his hands; and yet
                  if I am captured it will probably be by him.</p>
               <p>"Yet it is his duty as a soldier, and why should I complain? If he is appointed to
                  that office he can do nothing else than obey. As a soldier he can only treat me as
                  an enemy of the state. He may pity or love me in his heart, yet he must not shrink
                  from his duty.</p>
               <p>"If a price is put on my head they will redouble their efforts for me. My time I
                  believe is at hand. Let me be prepared to meet it."</p>
               <p>With such thoughts as these, he walked down the Appian Way. He was wrapped up in
                  his own meditations, and did not see a crowd of people that had gathered at a
                  corner of a street<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7211-00000070"/> until he was among
                  them. Then he suddenly found himself stopped.</p>
               <p>"Ho, friend!" cried a rude voice, "not so fast. Who are you, and where are you
                  going?"</p>
               <p>"Away," cried Marcellus in a tone of command natural to one who had ruled over
                  men; and he motioned the man aside.</p>
               <p>The crowd were awe-struck by his authoritative tone and imperious manner, but
                  their spokesman showed more courage.</p>
               <p>"Tell us who you are, or you shall not pass."</p>
               <p>"Fellow," cried Marcellus, "stand aside! Do you not know me? I am a
                  Pretorian."</p>
               <p>At that dreaded name the crowd quickly opened, and Marcellus passed through it.
                  But scarcely had he moved five paces away than a voice exclaimed:</p>
               <p>"Seize him! It is the Christian, Marcellus!"</p>
               <p>A shout arose from the crowd. Marcellus needed no further warning. Dropping his
                  load, he started off down a side street toward the Tiber. The whole crowd pursued.
                  It was a race for life and death. But Marcellus had been trained to every athletic
                  sport, and increased the distance between himself and his pursuers. At last he
                  reached the Tiber, and leaping in, he swam to the opposite side.</p>
               <p>The pursuers reached the river's brink, but followed no further.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7211-00000071"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE ARREST.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"The trial of your faith worketh patience."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HONORIUS was seated in the chapel with one or two others, among whom was the lady
                  Cæcilia. The feeble rays of a single lamp but faintly illuminated the scene. They
                  were silent and sad. A deeper melancholy than usual rested upon them. Around them
                  was the sound of footsteps and of voices and a confused murmur of life.</p>
               <p>Suddenly a quick step was heard, and Marcellus entered. The occupants of the
                  chapel sprang up with cries of joy.</p>
               <p>"Where is Pollio?" cried Cæcilia eagerly.</p>
               <p>"I have not seen him," said Marcellus.</p>
               <p>"Not seen him!" said Cæcilia, and she fell back upon her seat.</p>
               <p>"Why? Is he beyond his time?"</p>
               <p>"He ought to have returned six hours ago, and I am sick with anxiety."</p>
               <p>"O there is no danger," said Marcellus soothingly. "He can take care of himself."
                  He tried to pass it off with a careless tone, but his looks belied his words.</p>
               <p>"No danger!" said Cæcilia. "Alas! we know too well what new dangers there are.
                  Never has it been so dangerous as now."</p>
               <p>"What has delayed you, Marcellus? We had begun to give you up."</p>
               <p>"I was stopped near the Via Alba," said Marcellus. "I dropped my load and ran to
                  the river. The crowd followed, but I jumped into the river and swam across. There
                  I took a circuitous route among the streets on the opposite side, after which I
                  came across again and reached this place in safety."</p>
               <p>"You had a narrow escape. A price is on your head."</p>
               <p>"Have you heard it?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, and much more. We have heard of the redoubled efforts which they are making
                  to crush us. All through the day tidings of sorrow have been reaching us. We must
                  rely more than ever on Him who alone can save us."</p>
               <pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7211-00000072"/>
               <p>"We can baffle them still," said Marcellus hopefully.</p>
               <p>"They watch our principal entrances," said Honorius.</p>
               <p>"Then we can make new ones. The openings are numberless."</p>
               <p>"They have offered rewards for all the prominent brethren."</p>
               <p>"What then? We will guard those brethren more carefully than ever."</p>
               <p>"Our means of living are gradually lessening."</p>
               <p>"But there are as many bold and faithful hearts as ever. Who is afraid to risk his
                  life now? There will never cease to be a supply of food so long as we live in the
                  Catacombs. If we escape pursuit we bring help to our brethren; if we die we
                  receive the crown of martyrdom."</p>
               <p>"You are right, Marcellus. Your faith puts my fear to shame. How can those who
                  live in the Catacombs be afraid of death? It is but a momentary gloom and it will
                  pass. But this day we have heard much to distress our hearts and fill our spirits
                  with dismay."</p>
               <p>"Alas," continued Honorius in a mournful voice, "how are the people scattered and
                  the Churches left desolate! But a few months ago and there were fifty Christian
                  churches within this city where the light of truth shone, and the sound of prayer
                  and praise ascended to the Most High. Now they are overthrown, the people
                  dispersed, and driven out of the sight of men."</p>
               <p>He paused, overcome by emotion, and then in a low and plaintive voice he repeated
                  the mournful words of the eightieth psalm: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"How long wilt thou be angry against the prayer of thy people?</l>
                        <l>Thou feedest them with the bread of tears;</l>
                        <l>And givest them tears to drink in great measure.</l>
                        <l>Thou makest us a strife unto our neighbors;</l>
                        <l>And our enemies laugh among themselves.</l>
                        <l>Turn us again, O God of hosts,</l>
                        <l>And cause thy face to shine,</l>
                        <l>And we shall be saved.</l>
                        <l>Thou hast brought a vine out of Egypt;</l>
                        <l>Thou hast cast out the heathen, and planted it.</l>
                        <l>Thou preparedst room before it,</l>
                        <l>And didst cause it to take deep root,</l>
                        <l>And it filled the land.</l>
                        <l>The hills were covered with the shadow of it,</l>
                        <l>And the boughs thereof were like goodly cedars.</l>
                        <l>She sent out her boughs to the sea,</l>
                        <l>And her branches unto the river.</l>
                        <l>Why hast thou broken down her hedges,</l>
                        <pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7211-00000073"/>
                        <l>So that all who pass by the way do pluck her?</l>
                        <l>The boar out of the wood doth waste it,</l>
                        <l>And the wild beast of the field doth devour it,</l>
                        <l>Return, we beseech thee, O God of hosts,</l>
                        <l>Look down from heaven, and behold, and visit this vino.</l>
                        <l>And the vineyard which thy right hand planted,</l>
                        <l>And the branch which thou madest strong for thyself.</l>
                        <l>It is burned with fire, it is cut down;</l>
                        <l>They perish at the rebuke of thy countenance."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>"You are sad, Honorius," said Marcellus. "Our sufferings, it is true, increase
                  upon us; but we can be more than conquerors through Him who loved us. What says
                  he—"</p>
               <p>"'To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the tree of life which is in the
                  midst of the Paradise of God.'</p>
               <p>"'Be thou faithful unto death and I will give thee a crown of life. He that
                  overcometh shall not be hurt of the second death.'</p>
               <p>"'To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the hidden manna, and will give him
                  a white stone, and in the stone a new name written, which no man knoweth saving he
                  that receiveth it.'</p>
               <p>"'He that overcometh and keepeth my words unto the end, to him will I give power
                  over the nations, and I will give him the morning star.'</p>
               <p>"'He that overcometh, the same shall be clothed in white raiment; and I will not
                  blot his name out of the Book of Life, but I will confess his name before my
                  Father, and before his angels.'</p>
               <p>"'Him that overcometh will I make a pillar in the temple of my God, and he shall
                  go no more out, and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the
                  city of my God, which is New Jerusalem, which cometh down out of heaven from my
                  God, and I will write upon him my new name.'</p>
               <p>"To him that overcometh will I grant to sit with me on my throne, even as I also
                  overcame, and am set down with my Father in his throne.'"</p>
               <p>As Marcellus spoke these words his form grew erect, his eye brightened, and his
                  face flushed with enthusiasm. His emotions were transmitted to his companions, and
                  as one by one these glorious promises fell upon their ears they forgot for a while
                  their sorrows in the thought of their approaching blessedness. The New Jerusalem,
                  the golden streets, the palms of glory, the song of the Lamb, the face of Him who
                  sitteth upon the throne; all these were present to their minds.</p>
               <pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7211-00000074"/>
               <p>"Marcellus," said Honorius, "you have driven away my gloom by your words; let us
                  rise superior to earthly troubles. Come, brethren, lay aside your cares. The
                  youngest born into the kingdom puts our faith to shame. Let us look to the joy set
                  before us. 'For we know that if this earthly tabernacle be destroyed we have a
                  house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.'"</p>
               <p>"Death comes nearer," he continued, "our enemies encircle us, and the circle grows
                  narrower. Let us die like Christians—"</p>
               <p>"Why these gloomy forebodings?" said Marcellus. "Is death nearer to us than it was
                  before? Are we not safe in the Catacombs?"</p>
               <p>"Have you not heard, then?"</p>
               <p>"What?"</p>
               <p>"Of the death of Chrysippus?"</p>
               <p>"Chrysippus! dead! No—how? when?"</p>
               <p>"The soldiers of the emperor were led down into the Catacombs by some one who knew
                  the way. They advanced upon the room where service was going on. This was in the
                  Catacombs beyond the Tiber. The brethren gave a hasty alarm and fled. But the
                  venerable Chrysippus, either through extreme old age or else through desire for
                  martyrdom, refused to fly. He threw himself upon his knees and raised his voice in
                  prayer. Two faithful attendants remained with him. The soldiers rushed in, and
                  even while Chrysippus was upon his knees they dashed out his brains. He fell dead
                  at the first blow, and his two attendants were slain by his side."</p>
               <p>"They have gone to join the noble army of martyrs. They have been faithful unto
                  death, and will receive the crown of life," said Marcellus.</p>
               <p>But now they were interrupted by a tumult without. Instantly every one started
                  upright.</p>
               <p>"The soldiers!" exclaimed all.</p>
               <p>But, no; it was not the soldiers. It was a Christian: a messenger from the world
                  above. Pale and trembling, he flung himself upon the floor, and wringing his
                  hands, cried out as he panted for breath,</p>
               <p>"Alas! alas!"</p>
               <p>Upon the lady Cæcilia the sight of this man produced a terrible effect. She
                  staggered back against the wall trembling from head to foot,<pb n="150-151"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000075"/> her hands clenched each other, her eyes stared
                  wildly, her lips moved as though she wished to speak, but no sound escaped.</p>
               <p>"Speak—speak! Tell us all," cried Honorious.</p>
               <p>"Pollio!" gasped the messenger.</p>
               <p>"What of him?" said Marcellus sternly.</p>
               <p>"He is arrested—he is in prison!"</p>
               <p>At that intelligence a shriek burst forth which sounded fearfully amid the
                  surrounding horrors. It came from the Lady Cæcilia. The next moment she fell
                  heavily to the floor.</p>
               <p>The bystanders hurried to attend her. They carried her away to her own quarters.
                  There they applied the customary restoratives and she revived. But the blow had
                  struck heavily, and though sense and feeling returned, yet she seemed like one in
                  a dream.</p>
               <p>Meanwhile the messenger had recovered strength and told all that he knew.</p>
               <p>"Pollio was with you, was he?" asked Marcellus.</p>
               <p>"No, he was alone."</p>
               <p>"On what errand?"</p>
               <p>"Finding out the news. I was on one side of the street a little behind. He was
                  coming home. We walked on until we came to a crowd of men. To my surprise, Pollio
                  was stopped and questioned. I did not hear what passed, but I saw their
                  threatening gestures, and at length saw them seize him. I could do nothing. I kept
                  at a safe distance and watched. In about half an hour a troop of Pretorians came
                  along. Pollio was handed over to them, and they carried him away."</p>
               <p>"Pretorians?" said Marcellus. "Do you know the captain?"</p>
               <p>"Yes; it was Lucullus."</p>
               <p>"It is well," said Marcellus, and he fell into a deep fit of musing.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7211-00000076"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               
               <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE OFFER.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"Greater love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his
                        friends."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IT was evening in the Pretorian camp. Lucullus was in his room seated by a lamp
                  which threw a bright light around. He was roused by a knock at the door. At once
                  rising, he opened it. A man entered and advanced silently to the middle of the
                  room. He then disencumbered himself of the folds of a large mantle in which he was
                  dressed and faced Lucullus.</p>
               <p>"Marcellus!" cried the other in amazement, and springing forward he embraced his
                  visitor with every mark of joy.</p>
               <p>"Dear friend," said he, "to what happy chance do I owe this meeting? I was just
                  thinking of you, and wondering when we should meet again."</p>
               <p>"Our meetings, I fear," said Marcellus sadly, "will not be very frequent now. I
                  make this one at the risk of my life."</p>
               <p>"True," said Lucullus, participating in the sadness of the other. "You are
                  pursued, and there is a price on your head. Yet here you are as safe as you ever
                  were in those happy days before this madness seized you. O, Marcellus why can they
                  not return again?"</p>
               <p>"I cannot change my nature nor undo what is done. Moreover, Lucullus, although my
                  lot may appear to you a hard one, I never was so happy."</p>
               <p>"Happy!" cried the other in deep surprise.</p>
               <p>"Yes, Lucullus, though afflicted I am not cast down; though persecuted I am not in
                  despair."</p>
               <p>"The persecution of the emperor is no slight matter."</p>
               <p>"I know it well. I see my brethren fall before it every day. Every day the circle
                  that surrounds me is lessened. Friends leave me and never appear again. Companions
                  go up to the city, but when they return they are carried back dead to be deposited
                  in their graves."</p>
               <p>"And yet you say you can be happy?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, Lucullus, I have a peace that the world knows nothing of; a peace that
                  cometh from above, that passeth all understanding."</p>
               <pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7211-00000077"/>
               <p>"I know, Marcellus, that you are too brave to fear death; but I never knew that
                  you had sufficient fortitude to endure calmly all that I know you must now suffer.
                  Your courage is superhuman, or rather it is the courage of madness."</p>
               <p>"It comes from above, Lucullus. Once I was incapable of feeling it, but now old
                  things have passed away and all has become new. Sustained by this new power, I can
                  endure the utmost evils that can be dealt upon me. I expect nothing but suffering
                  in life, and know that I shall die in agony; yet the thought cannot overcome the
                  strong faith that is within me."</p>
               <p>"It pains me," said Lucullus sadly, "to see you so determined. If I saw the
                  slightest sign of wavering in you I would hope that time might change or modify
                  your feelings. But you seem to me to be fixed unalterably in your new course."</p>
               <p>"God grant that I may remain steadfast unto the end!" said Marcellus fervently.
                  "But it is not of my feelings that I came to speak. I come, Lucullus, to ask your
                  assistance, to claim your sympathy and help. You promised me once to show me your
                  friendship if I needed it. I come now to claim it."</p>
               <p>"All that is in my power is yours already, Marcellus. Tell what you want."</p>
               <p>"You have a prisoner."</p>
               <p>"Yes, many."</p>
               <p>"This is a boy."</p>
               <p>"I believe my men captured a boy a short time since."</p>
               <p>"This boy is too insignificant to merit capture. He is beneath the wrath of the
                  emperor. He is yet in your power. I come, Lucullus, to implore his delivery."</p>
               <p>"Alas, Marcellus, what is it that you ask? Have you forgotten the discipline of
                  the Roman army, or the military oath? Do you not know that if I did this I would
                  violate that oath and make myself a traitor? If you asked me to fall upon my sword
                  I would do it more readily than this."</p>
               <p>"I have not forgotten the military oath or the discipline of the camp, Lucullus. I
                  thought that this lad, being scarcely more than a child, might not be considered a
                  prisoner. Do the<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7211-00000078"/> commands of the
                  emperor extend to children?"</p>
               <p>"He makes no distinction of age. Have you not seen children as young as this lad
                  suffer death in the Coliseum?"</p>
               <p>"Alas I have," said Marcellus, as his thoughts reverted to those young girls whose
                  death-song once struck so painfully and so sweetly upon his heart. "This young
                  boy, then, must also suffer?"</p>
               <p>"Yes," said Lucullus, "unless he abjures Christianity."</p>
               <p>"And that he will never do."</p>
               <p>"Then he will rush upon his fate. The law does this, not I, Marcellus. I am but
                  the instrument. Do not blame me."</p>
               <p>"I do not blame you. I know well how strongly you are bound to obedience. If you
                  hold your office you must perform its duties. Yet let me make another proposal.
                  Surrender of prisoners is not allowed, but an exchange is lawful."</p>
               <p>"Yes."</p>
               <p>"If I could tell you of a prisoner far more important than this boy, you would
                  exchange, would you not?"</p>
               <p>"But you have taken none of us prisoners?"</p>
               <p>"No, but we have power over our own people. And there are some among us on whose
                  heads the emperor has placed a large reward. For the capture of these a hundred
                  lads like this boy would be gladly given."</p>
               <p>"Is it then a custom among Christians to betray one another?" asked Lucullus in
                  surprise.</p>
               <p>"No, but sometimes one Christian will offer his own life to save that of
                  another."</p>
               <p>"Impossible!"</p>
               <p>"It is so in this instance."</p>
               <p>"Who is it that is offered for this boy?"</p>
               <p>"I—Marcellus!"</p>
               <p>At this astounding declaration Lucullus started back.</p>
               <p>"You!" he cried.</p>
               <p>"Yes, I myself."</p>
               <p>"You are jesting. It is impossible."</p>
               <p>"I am serious. It is for this that I have already exposed my life in coming to
                  you. I have shown the interest that I take in him by this great risk. I will
                  explain.</p>
               <p>"This boy Pollio is the last of an ancient and noble Roman family. He is the only
                  son of his<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7211-00000079"/> mother. His father died in
                  battle. He belongs to the Servilii."</p>
               <p>"The Servilii! Is his mother the Lady Cæcilia?"</p>
               <p>"Yes. She is a refugee in the Catacombs. Her whole life and love is wrapped up in
                  this boy. Every day she lets him go up into the city, a dangerous adventure, and
                  in his absence she suffers indescribable agony. Yet she is afraid to keep him
                  there always for fear that the damp air which is so fatal to children may cut him
                  off. So she exposes him to what she thinks is a smaller danger.</p>
               <p>"This boy you have a prisoner. That mother has heard of it, and now lies hovering
                  between life and death. If you destroy him she too will die, and one of the
                  noblest and purest spirits in Rome will be no more.</p>
               <p>"For these reasons I come to offer myself in exchange. What am I? I am alone in
                  the world. No life is wrapped up in mine. No one depends on me for the present and
                  the future. I fear not death. It may as well come now as at any other time. It
                  must come sooner or later, and I would rather give my life as a ransom for a
                  friend than lay it down uselessly.</p>
               <p>"For these reasons, Lucullus, I implore you, by the sacred ties of friendship, by
                  your pity, by your promise to me, give me your assistance now and take my life in
                  exchange for him."</p>
               <p>Lucullus rose to his feet and paced the room in great agitation.</p>
               <p>"Why, O Marcellus," he cried at last, "do you try me so terribly?"</p>
               <p>"My proposal is easy to receive."</p>
               <p>"You forget that your life is precious to me."</p>
               <p>"But think of this young lad."</p>
               <p>"I pity him deeply. But do you think I can receive your life as a forfeit?"</p>
               <p>"It is forfeited already, and will be surrendered sooner or later. I pray you let
                  it be yielded up while it may be of service."</p>
               <p>"You shall not die as long as I can prevent it. Your life is not yet forfeited. By
                  the im mortal gods, it will be long before you take your place in the arena."</p>
               <p>"No one can save me when once I am taken. You might try your utmost. What could
                     you<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7211-00000080"/> do to save one on whom the
                  emperor's wrath is falling?"</p>
               <p>"I might do much to avert it. You do not know what might be done. But even if I
                  could do nothing, still I would not listen to this proposal now."</p>
               <p>"If I went to the emperor himself he would grant my prayer."</p>
               <p>"He would take you prisoner at once and put both of you to death."</p>
               <p>"I could send a messenger with my proposal."</p>
               <p>"The message would never reach him; or at least not until it would be too
                  late."</p>
               <p>"There is then no hope?" said Marcellus mournfully.</p>
               <p>"None."</p>
               <p>"And you absolutely refuse to grant my request?"</p>
               <p>"Alas, Marcellus, how can I be guilty of the death of my friend? You have no mercy
                  on me. Forgive me if I refuse so unreasonable a proposal."</p>
               <p>"The will of the Lord be done," said Marcellus. "I must hasten back. Alas! how can
                  I carry with me this message of despair?"</p>
               <p>The two friends embraced in silence, and Marcellus departed, leaving Lucullus
                  overcome with amazement at this proposal.</p>
               <p>Marcellus returned to the Catacombs in safety. The brethren there who knew of his
                  errand received him again with mournful joy.</p>
               <p>The lady Cæcilia still lay in a kind of stupor, only half conscious of surrounding
                  events. At times her mind would wander, and in her delirium she would talk of
                  happy scenes in her early life.</p>
               <p>But the life which she had led in the Catacombs, the alternating hope and fear,
                  joy and sorrow, the ever present anxiety, and the oppressive air of the place
                  itself, had overcome both mind and body. Her delicate nature sank beneath the fury
                  of such an ordeal, and this last heavy blow completed her prostration. She could
                  not rally from its effects.</p>
               <p>That night they watched around her couch. Every hour she grew feebler, and life
                  was slowly but surely passing away. From that descent unto death not even the
                  restoration of her son could have saved her.</p>
               <p>But though earthly thoughts had left her and<pb n="162-163"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000081"/> earthly feelings had grown faint, the one master
                  passion of her later years held undiminished power over her. Her lips murmured
                  still the sacred words which had so long been her support and consolation. The
                  name of her darling boy was breathed from her lips though his present danger was
                  forgotten; but it was the blessed name of Jesus that was uttered with the deepest
                  fervor.</p>
               <p>At length the end came. Starting from a long period of stillness, her eyes opened
                  wide, a flush passed over her wan and emaciated face, and she uttered a faint cry,
                  "Come, Lord Jesus!" With the cry life went out, and the pure spirit of the lady
                  Cæcilia had returned unto God who gave it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
               <head type="sub">POLLIO'S TRIAL.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"Out of the mouths of babes and sucklings thou hast ordained praise."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IT was a large room in a building not far from the imperial palace. The pavement
                  was of polished marble, and columns of porphyry supported a paneled dome. An altar
                  with a statue of a heathen deity was at one end of the apartment. Magistrates in
                  their robes occupied raised seats on the opposite end. In front of them were some
                  soldiers guarding a prisoner.</p>
               <p>The prisoner was the boy Pollio.</p>
               <p>His face was pale, but his bearing was erect and firm. The remarkable intelligence
                  which had always characterized him did not fail him now. His quick eye took in
                  everything. He knew the inevitable doom that impended over him. Yet there was no
                  trace of fear or indecision about him.</p>
               <p>He knew that the only tie that bound him to earth had been severed. Early that
                     morning<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7211-00000082"/> the news of his mother's
                  death had reached him. It had been carried to him by a man who thought that the
                  knowledge of this would fortify his resolution. That man was Marcellus. The
                  kindness of Lucullus had gained him an interview. His judgment had been correct.
                  While his mother lived, the thought of her would have weakened his resolution; now
                  that she was dead, he was eager to depart also. In his simple faith he believed
                  that death would unite him at once to the dear mother whom he loved so fondly.</p>
               <p>With these feelings he awaited the examination.</p>
               <p>"Who are you?"</p>
               <p>"Marcus Servilius Pollio."</p>
               <p>"What is your age?"</p>
               <p>"Thirteen years."</p>
               <p>At the mention of his name a murmur of compassion went round the assemblage, for
                  that name was well known in Rome.</p>
               <p>"You are charged with the crime of being a Christian. What have you to say?"</p>
               <p>"I am guilty of no crime," said the boy. "I am a Christian, and I am glad to be
                  able to confess it before men."</p>
               <p>"It is the same with them all," said one of the judges. "They all have the same
                  formula."</p>
               <p>"Do you know the nature of your crime?"</p>
               <p>"I am guilty of no crime," said Pollio.</p>
               <p>"My religion teaches me to fear God and honor the emperor. I have obeyed every
                  just law, and am not a traitor."</p>
               <p>"To be a Christian is to be a traitor."</p>
               <p>"I am a Christian, but I am not a traitor."</p>
               <p>"The law of the state forbids you to be a Christian under pain of death. If you
                  are a Christian you must die."</p>
               <p>"I am a Christian," repeated Pollio firmly.</p>
               <p>"Then you must die."</p>
               <p>"Be it so."</p>
               <p>"Boy, do you know what it is to suffer death?"</p>
               <p>"I have seen much of death during the last few months. I have always expected to
                  lay down my life for my religion when my turn should come."</p>
               <p>"Boy, you are young. We pity your tender age and inexperience. You have been
                  trained so peculiarly that you are scarcely responsible for your present folly.
                  For all this we are willing<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7211-00000083"/> ing to make
                  allowance. This religion which infatuates you is foolishness. You believe that a
                  poor Jew, who was executed a few hundred years ago, is a God. Can anything be more
                  absurd than this! Our religion is the religion of the state. It has enough in
                  itself to satisfy the minds of young and old, ignorant and learned. Leave your
                  foolish superstition and turn to our wiser and older religion."</p>
               <p>"I cannot."</p>
               <p>"You are the last of a noble family. The state recognizes the worth and the
                  nobility of the Servilii. Your ancestors lived in pomp and wealth and power. You
                  are a poor miserable boy and a prisoner. Be wise, Pollio. Think of the glory of
                  your forefathers and throw aside the miserable obstacle that keeps you away from
                  all their illustrious fame."</p>
               <p>"I cannot."</p>
               <p>"You have lived a miserable outcast. The poorest beggar in Rome fares better than
                  you. His food is obtained with less labor and less humiliation. His shelter is in
                  the light of day. Above all he is safe. His life is his own. He need not live in
                  hourly fear of justice. But you have had to drag out a wretched existence in want
                  and danger and darkness. What has your boasted religion given you? What has this
                  deified Jew done for you? Nothing, worse than nothing. Turn, then, from this
                  deceiver. Wealth and comfort and friends and the honors of the state and the favor
                  of the emperor will all be yours."</p>
               <p>"I cannot."</p>
               <p>"Your father was a loyal subject and a brave soldier. He died in battle for his
                  country. He left you an infant, the heir of all his honors, and the last prop of
                  his house. Little did he think of the treacherous influences that surrounded you
                  to lead you astray. Your mother's mind, weakened by sorrow, surrendered to the
                  insidious wiles of false teachers, and she again ignorantly wrought your ruin. Had
                  your noble father lived you would now have been the hope of his ancient line; your
                  mother, too, would have followed the faith of her illustrious ancestors. Do you
                  value your father's memory? Has he no claims on your filial duty? Do you think it
                  no sin to heap dishonor on the proud name that you bear, and throw so foul a blot
                  upon the<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7211-00000084"/> unsullied fame handed down to
                  you from your fathers? Away with this delusion that blinds you. By your father's
                  memory, by the honor of your family, turn from your present course."</p>
               <p>"I can do them no dishonor. My religion is pure and holy. I can die, but I cannot
                  be false to my Saviour."</p>
               <p>"You see that we are merciful to you. Your name and your inexperience excites our
                  pity. Were you but a common prisoner we would offer you in short words the choice
                  between retraction or death. But we are willing to reason with you, for we do not
                  wish to see a noble family become extinct through the ignorance or obstinacy of a
                  degenerate heir."</p>
               <p>"I thank you for your consideration," said Pollio; "but your arguments have no
                  weight with me beside the higher claims of my religion."</p>
               <p>"Rash and thoughtless boy! There is another argument which you will find more
                  powerful. The wrath of the emperor is terrible."</p>
               <p>"Yet still more terrible is the wrath of the Lamb."</p>
               <p>"You speak an unintelligible language. What is the wrath of the Lamb? You do not
                  think on what is before you."</p>
               <p>"My companions and friends have already endured all that you can inflict. I trust
                  that I may have like fortitude."</p>
               <p>"Can you endure the terrors of the arena?"</p>
               <p>"I hope to have more than mortal strength."</p>
               <p>"Can you face the savage lions and tigers that will then rush upon you?"</p>
               <p>"He in whom I trust will not desert me in my time of need."</p>
               <p>"You are confident."</p>
               <p>"I confide in Him who loved me and gave himself for me."</p>
               <p>"Have you thought of the death by fire? Are you ready to meet the flames at the
                  stake?"</p>
               <p>"Alas! If I must bear it I will not shrink. At the worst it will soon be over, and
                  then I shall be forever with the Lord."</p>
               <p>"Fanaticism and superstition have taken complete possession of you. You know not
                  what awaits you. It is easy to face threats, it is easy to utter words and make
                  professions of courage. But how will it be with you when the dread reality comes
                  upon you?"</p>
               <pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7211-00000085"/>
               <p>"I will look to Him who never deserts his own in their hour of need."</p>
               <p>"He has done nothing for you thus far!"</p>
               <p>"He has done all for me. He gave his own life that I might live. Through him I
                  receive a nobler life than this which you take from me."</p>
               <p>"This is but a dream of yours. How is it possible that a miserable Jew can do
                  this?"</p>
               <p>"He was the fullness of the Godhead; God manifest in the flesh. He suffered death
                  of the body that we might receive life for the soul."</p>
               <p>"Can nothing open your eyes? Is it not enough that thus far your mad belief has
                  brought you nothing but misery and woe? Must you still hold on to it? When you see
                  that death is inevitable will you not turn away from your errors?"</p>
               <p>"He gives me strength to overcome death; I fear it not. I look upon death itself
                  as but a change from this life of sorrow to an immortality of bliss. Whether I die
                  by the wild beasts or by the flames it will be all the same. If I continue
                  faithful he will support me and lead my soul at once to immortal life in heaven.
                  The death which you threaten me with has no terrors; but the life to which you
                  invite me is more terrible to me than a thousand deaths."</p>
               <p>"For the last time we give you an opportunity. Rash youth, pause for one moment in
                  your mad career of folly. Forget for an instant the insane counsels of your
                  fanatical teachers. Think of all that has been said to you. Life is before you;
                  life full of joy and pleasure; a life rich in every blessing. Honor, friends,
                  wealth, power, all is yours. A noble name, and the possessions of your family,
                  await you. They are all yours. To gain them you have but to take this goblet and
                  pour the libation on yonder altar. Take it. It is but a simple act. Perform it
                  quickly. Save yourself from a death of agony."</p>
               <p>Every eye was fixed upon Pollio as this last offer was held out to him. Amazement
                  had filled the minds of the spectators to find him thus far so unmoved. They could
                  not account for it.</p>
               <p>But even this last appeal had no effect. Pale but resolute, Pollio motioned away
                  the proffered goblet.</p>
               <pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7211-00000086"/>
               <p>"I will never be false to my Saviour."</p>
               <p>At these words there was a moment's pause. Then the chief magistrate spoke:</p>
               <p>"You have uttered your own doom. Away with him," he continued, addressing the
                  soldiery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE DEATH OF POLLIO.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE sentence of Pollio was swift and sure.</p>
               <p>On the following day there was a spectacle at the Coliseum. Crowded to its topmost
                  terrace of seats with the bloodthirsty Roman multitude, it displayed the same
                  sickening succession of horrors which has been before detailed.</p>
               <p>Gladiators again fought and slew one another singly and in multitudes. There was
                  every different mode of combat known in the arena, and of these the most deadly
                  were sure to find the most favor.</p>
               <p>Again were the ever-recurring scenes of blood and agony presented; the fierce
                  champion of the day received the short-lived congratulations of the fickle
                  spectators. Again man fought with man, or waged a fiercer contest with the tiger.
                  Again the wounded gladiator looked up despairingly<pb n="174-175"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000087"/> ingly for mercy, but received only the signal of
                  death from the pitiless spectators.</p>
               <p>The satiated appetites of the multitude now demanded a larger supply of slaughter.
                  The combats between men who were equally matched had lost their attraction for
                  that day. It was known that Christians were reserved for the concluding spectacle,
                  and the appearance of these was impatiently demanded.</p>
               <p>Lucullus stood among the guards near the emperor's seat. Yet his brow was more
                  thoughtful, and his olden gayety had all departed.</p>
               <p>High up among the loftier seats behind him was a pale stern face, that was
                  conspicuous among all around it for the concentrated gaze which it fixed upon the
                  arena. There was an expression of deep anxiety upon that face which made it far
                  different from all within the vast inclosure.</p>
               <p>Now the harsh sound of the gratings arose, and a tiger leaped forth into the
                  arena. Throwing up its head and lashing its sides with its tail, it stalked about
                  glancing with fiery eyes upon the vast assemblage of human beings which hemmed it
                  in.</p>
               <p>Soon a murmur arose. A boy was thrust into the arena.</p>
               <p>Pale in face and slight in limb, his slender form was nothing before the huge bulk
                  of the furious beast. As if in derision, he was dressed like a gladiator.</p>
               <p>Yet in spite of his youth and his weakness there was nothing in his face or manner
                  that betrayed fear. His glance was calm and abstracted. He moved forward quietly
                  to the center of the arena, and there, in the sight of all, he joined his hands
                  together and lifted up his eyes and prayed.</p>
               <p>Meanwhile, the tiger moved around as before. He had seen the boy, but the sight
                  had no effect. He still raised his bloodshot eyes toward the lofty walls and
                  occasionally uttered a savage growl.</p>
               <p>The man with the stern sad face looked on with all his soul absorbed in that
                  gaze.</p>
               <p>There appeared to be no desire on the part of the tiger to attack the boy, who
                  still continued praying.</p>
               <p>The multitude now grew impatient. Murmurs arose and cries and shouts with the
                     intention<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7211-00000088"/> tion of maddening the
                  tiger and urging him on.</p>
               <p>But now, even in the midst of the tumult, there came forth the sound of a voice
                  deep and terrible:</p>
               <p>"How long, O Lord, holy and true, dost thou not avenge our blood on them that
                  dwell upon the earth?"</p>
               <p>A deep stillness followed. Every one in surprise looked at his neighbor.</p>
               <p>But the silence was soon broken by the same voice, which rang out in terrific
                  emphasis: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Behold, he cometh in the clouds,</l>
                        <l>And every eye shall see him,</l>
                        <l>And they also which pierced him,</l>
                        <l>And all the kindreds of the earth shall wail because of him.</l>
                        <l>Even so. Amen!</l>
                        <l>Thou art righteous, O Lord,</l>
                        <l>Which art, and wast, and shalt be,</l>
                        <l>Because thou hast judged thus.</l>
                        <l>For they have shed the blood of saints and prophets,</l>
                        <l>And thou hast given them blood to drink,</l>
                        <l>For they are worthy.</l>
                        <l>Even so, Lord God Almighty,</l>
                        <l>True and righteous are thy judgments!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But now murmurs and cries and shouts passed around. Soon the cause of the
                  disturbance became known.</p>
               <p>"It is an accursed Christian"—"It is the fanatic Cinna"—"He has been confined four
                  days without food"—"Bring him out"—"Throw him to the tiger!"</p>
               <p>Shouts and execrations arose on high and mingled in one vast roar. The tiger
                  leaped in frenzy around. The keepers within heard the words of the multitude and
                  hurried to obey.</p>
               <p>Soon the gratings opened. The victim was thrust in.</p>
               <p>Fearfully emaciated and ghastly pale, he tottered forward with tremulous steps.
                  His eyes had an unearthly luster, his cheeks a burning flush, and his neglected
                  hair and long beard were matted in a tangled mass.</p>
               <p>The tiger saw him, and came leaping toward him. Then at a little distance away the
                  furious beast crouched. The boy arose from his knees and looked. But Cinna saw no
                  tiger. He fixed his eyes on the multitude, and waving his withered arm on high he
                  shouted in the same tone of menace:</p>
               <p>"Woe! woe! woe to the inhabitants of the earth—"</p>
               <pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7211-00000089"/>
               <p>His voice was hushed in blood. There was a leap, a fall, and all was over.</p>
               <p>And now the tiger turned toward the boy. His thirst for blood was fully aroused;
                  with bristling hair, flaming eyes, and sweeping tail he stood facing his prey.</p>
               <p>The boy saw that the end was coming, and again fell upon his knees. The crowd was
                  hushed to stillness, and awaited in deep excitement the new scene of slaughter.
                  The man who had been gazing so intently now rose upward and stood erect, still
                  watching the scene below. Loud cries arose from behind him which increased still
                  louder, "Down," "down," "sit down," "you obstruct the view!"</p>
               <p>But the man either did not hear or else purposely disregarded it. At length the
                  crowd grew so noisy that the officers below turned to see the cause.</p>
               <p>Lucullus was one of them. Turning round he saw the whole scene. He started and
                  grew pale as death.</p>
               <p>"Marcellus!" he cried. For a moment he staggered back, but soon recovering he
                  hurried away to the scene of the disturbance.</p>
               <p>But now a deep murmur broke forth from the multitude. The tiger, who had been
                  walking round and round the boy, lashing himself to greater fury, now crouched for
                  a spring.</p>
               <p>The boy arose. A seraphic expression was upon his face. His eyes beamed with a
                  lofty enthusiasm. He saw no longer the arena, the high surrounding walls, the
                  far-extending seats with innumerable faces; he saw no more the relentless eyes of
                  the cruel spectators, or the gigantic form of his savage enemy.<ref rend="super"
                     target="#note_001" xml:id="return_001">*</ref>
                  
               </p>
               <note place="foot" xml:id="note_001">
                  
                  <p><ref target="#return_001">*</ref>See Frontispiece.</p>
               </note>
               <p>Already his soaring spirit seemed to enter into the golden gates of the New
                  Jerusalem, and the ineffable glory of the noonday of heaven gleamed upon his
                  sight.</p>
               <p>"Mother, I come to thee! Lord Jesus, receive my spirit!"</p>
               <p>His words sounded clearly and sweetly upon the ears of the multitude. They ceased,
                  and the tiger sprang. The next moment there was nothing but a struggling mass half
                  hidden in clouds of dust.</p>
               <p>The struggle ended. The tiger started back, the sand was red with blood, and upon
                  it lay<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7211-00000090"/> the mangled form of the
                  true-hearted, the noble Pollio.</p>
               <p>Then amid the silence that followed there came forth a shout that sounded like a
                  trumpet peal and startled every one in the assembly:</p>
               <p>"O death, where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy victory? Thanks be to God who
                  giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ."</p>
               <p>A thousand men rose with a simultaneous burst of rage and indignation. Ten
                  thousand hands were outstretched toward the bold intruder.</p>
               <p>"A Christian"—"A Christian"—"To the flames with him"—"Throw him to the
                  tiger"—"Hurl him into the arena!"</p>
               <p>Such were the shouts that answered the cry.</p>
               <p>Lucullus reached the spot just in time to rescue Marcellus from a crowd of
                  infuriated Romans, who were about to tear him in pieces. The tiger below was not
                  more fierce, more bloodthirsty than they. Lucullus rushed among them, dashing them
                  to the right and left as a keeper among wild beasts.</p>
               <p>Overawed by his authority they fell back, and soldiers approached.</p>
               <p>Lucullus gave Marcellus in charge to them, and led the company out of the
                  amphitheater.</p>
               <p>Outside he took charge of the prisoner himself. The soldiers followed them.</p>
               <p>"Alas, Marcellus! was it well to throw away your life?"</p>
               <p>"I spoke from the impulse of the moment. That dear boy whom I loved died before my
                  eyes! I could not restrain myself. Yet I do not repent. I, too, am ready to lay
                  down my life for my King and my God."</p>
               <p>"I cannot reason with you. You are beyond the reach of argument."</p>
               <p>"I did not intend to betray myself, but since it is done I am content. Nay, I am
                  glad, and I rejoice that it is my lot to suffer for my Redeemer."</p>
               <p>"Alas, my friend! Have you no regard for life?"</p>
               <p>"I love my Saviour better than life."</p>
               <p>"See, Marcellus, the road before us is open. You can run quickly. Fly and be
                  saved."</p>
               <p>Lucullus spoke this in a hurried whisper.<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7211-00000091"
                  /> The soldiers were some twenty paces behind. The chances were all in favor of
                  escape.</p>
               <p>Marcellus pressed the hand of his friend.</p>
               <p>"No, Lucullus. I would not gain life by your dishonor. I love the warm heart that
                  prompted it, but you shall not be led into difficulty by your friendship for
                  me."</p>
               <p>Lucullus sighed, and walked on in silence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XIV.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE TEMPTATION.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"All this will I give thee if thou wilt fall down and worship me."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THAT night Lucullus remained in the cell with his friend. He sought by every
                  possible argument to shake his resolution. He appealed to every motive that
                  commonly influences men. He left no means of persuasion unused.</p>
               <p>All in vain. The faith of Marcellus was too firmly fixed. It was founded on the
                  Rock of Ages, and neither the storm of violent threats nor the more tender
                  influences of friendship could weaken his determination.</p>
               <p>"No," said he, "my course is taken and my choice is made. Come weal, come woe, I
                  must follow it out to the end. I know all that is before me. I have weighed all
                  the consequences of my action, but in spite of all I will continue as I have
                  begun."</p>
               <p>"It is but a small thing that I ask," said Lucullus. "I do not wish you to give up
                     this<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7211-00000092"/> religion forever, but only for
                  the present. A terrible persecution is now raging, and before its fury all must
                  fall, whether young or old, high or low. You have seen that no class or age is
                  respected. Pollio would have been saved if it had been possible. There was a
                  strong sympathy in his favor. He was young, and scarcely accountable for his
                  errors; he was also noble, the last of an ancient family. But the law was
                  inexorable, and he suffered its penalty. Cinna, too, might have been overlooked.
                  He was neither more nor less than a madman. But so vehement is the zeal against
                  Christians that even his evident madness was no security whatever for him."</p>
               <p>"I know it well. The Prince of Darkness struggles against the Church of God, but
                  it is founded on a rock, and the gates of hell cannot prevail against it. Have I
                  not seen the good, the pure, the noble, the holy, and the innocent all suffer
                  alike? Do I not know that there is no mercy for the Christian? I knew it well long
                  ago. I have always been prepared for the consequences."</p>
               <p>"Hear me, Marcellus. I have said that I asked but a small thing. This religion
                  which you prize so highly need not be given up. Keep it, if it must be so. But
                  make allowance for circumstances. Since the storm is raging bow before it. Take
                  the course of a wise man, not of a fanatic."</p>
               <p>"What is it that you would have me to do?"</p>
               <p>"It is this. In the course of a few years a change will take place. Either the
                  persecution will wear itself out, or a reaction will take place, or the emperor
                  may die and other rulers with different feelings may succeed. It will then be safe
                  to be a Christian. Then these people who are now afflicted may come back from
                  their hiding-places to occupy their old places, and to rise to dignity and wealth.
                  Remember this. Do not therefore throw away a life which yet may be serviceable to
                  the state and happy to yourself. Cherish it for your own sake. Look about you now.
                  Consider all these things. Leave aside your religion for a time, and return to
                  that of the state. It need only be for a time. Thus you may escape from present
                  danger, and when happier times return you may go back and be a Christian
                  again."</p>
               <pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7211-00000093"/>
               <p>"This is impossible, Lucullus. It is abhorrent to my soul. What, can I thus be
                  doubly a hypocrite? Would you ask me to perjure my immortal soul to the world and
                  to my God? Better to die at once by the severest tortures that can be
                  inflicted."</p>
               <p>"You take such extreme views that I despair of saving you. Will you not look at
                  this subject rationally? It is not perjury, but policy; not hypocrisy, but
                  wisdom."</p>
               <p>"God forbid that I should do this thing and sin against him!"</p>
               <p>"Look further also. You will not only benefit yourself but others. These
                  Christians whom you love will be assisted by you far more than they are now. In
                  their present situation you know well that they are enabled to live by the
                  sympathy and assistance of those who profess the religion of the state but in
                  secret prefer the religion of the Christians. Do you call these men hypocrites and
                  perjurers? Are they not rather your benefactors and friends?"</p>
               <p>"These men have never learned the Christian's faith and hope as I have. They have
                  never felt the new birth of the soul as I have. They have not known the love of
                  God springing up within their hearts to give them new feelings and hopes and
                  desires. For them to sympathize with the Christians and to help them is a good
                  thing; but the Christian who could be base enough to abjure his faith and deny the
                  Saviour that redeemed him, could never have enough generosity in his traitorous
                  soul to assist his forsaken brethren."</p>
               <p>"Then, Marcellus, I have but one more offer to make, and I go. It is a last hope.
                  I do not know whether it will be possible or not. I will try it, however, if I can
                  but gain your consent. It is this. You need not abjure your faith; you need not
                  sacrifice to the gods; you need not do anything whatever of which you disapprove.
                  Let the past be forgotten. Return again, not in heart, but in outward appearance,
                  to what you were before. You were then a gay, light-hearted soldier, devoted to
                  your duties. You never took any part in any religious services. You were seldom
                  present in the temples. You passed your time in the camp, and your devotions were
                  in private. You gathered your instruction from the books of the philosophers
                     and<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7211-00000094"/> not from the priests. Be all
                  this again. Return to your duties. Appear again in public in company with me;
                  again join in pleasant conversation, and devote yourself to your old pursuits.
                  This will be easy and pleasant to do, and it will not require anything that is
                  base or distasteful. The authorities will overlook your absence and your
                  misconduct, and if they are not willing that you should be restored to all your
                  former honors, then you can be placed in your former command in your old legion.
                  All will then be well. A little discretion will be needed, a wise silence, an
                  apparent return to your former round of duties. If you remain in Rome it will be
                  thought that the tidings of your conversion to Christianity was wrong; if you go
                  abroad it will not be known."</p>
               <p>"I do not think, Lucullus, that the plan which you propose would be possible for
                  many reasons. Proclamations have been made about me, rewards have been offered for
                  my apprehension, and above all, my last appearance in the Coliseum before the
                  emperor himself was sufficient to take away all hope of pardon. Yet even if it
                  were possible I could not consent. My Saviour cannot be worshiped in this way. His
                  followers must confess him openly. 'Whosoever,' he says, 'is ashamed to confess me
                  before men, of him will I be ashamed before my Father and the holy angels.' To
                  deny him in my life or in outward appearance is precisely the same as denying him
                  by the formal manner which the law lays down. This I cannot do. I love him who
                  first loved me and gave himself for me. My highest joy is to proclaim him before
                  men; to die for him will be my noblest act, and the martyr's crown my most
                  glorious reward."</p>
               <p>Lucullus said no more, for he found that all persuasion was useless. The remainder
                  of the time was passed in conversation about other things. Marcellus did not waste
                  these last precious hours which he passed with his friend. Filled with gratitude
                  for his noble and generous affection, he sought to recompense him by making him
                  acquainted with the highest treasure that man can possess—the religion of
                  Christ.</p>
               <p>Lucullus listened to him patiently, more through friendship than interest. Yet
                  some, at<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7211-00000095"/> least, of Marcellus's words
                  were impressed upon his memory.</p>
               <p>On the following day the trial took place. It was short and formal. Marcellus was
                  immovable, and received his condemnation with a calm demeanor.</p>
               <p>The afternoon of the same day was the time appointed for him to suffer. He was to
                  die, not by the wild beasts, nor by the hand of the gladiator, but by the keener
                  torments of death by fire.</p>
               <p>It was in that place where so many Christians had already borne their witness to
                  the truth that Marcellus sealed his faith with his life. The stake was placed in
                  the center of the Coliseum, and the fagots were heaped high around it.</p>
               <p>Marcellus entered, led on by the brutal keepers, who added blows and ridicule to
                  the horrors of the approaching punishment. He looked around upon the vast circle
                  of faces, hard, cruel, and pitiless; he looked upon the arena and thought of the
                  thousands of Christians who had preceded him in suffering, and had gone from
                  thence to join the noble army of martyrs who worship forever around the throne. He
                  thought of the children whose death he had witnessed, and recalled once more their
                  triumphant song, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Unto Him that loved us,</l>
                        <l>To Him that washed us from our sins."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now the keepers seized him rudely and led him to the stake, where they bound him
                  with strong chains so that escape was impossible.</p>
               <p>"'I am now ready to be offered,'" murmured he, "'and the time of my departure is
                  at hand. Henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness, which the
                  Lord, the righteous judge, shall give me at that day.'"</p>
               <p>Now the torch was applied, and the flames rose up and dense volumes of smoke
                  concealed the martyr for a while from view. When it passed away he was seen again
                  standing amid the fire with upturned face and clasped hands.</p>
               <p>The flames increased around him. Nearer and nearer they came, devouring the fagots
                  and enveloping him in a circle of fire. Now they threw over him a black vail of
                  smoke, again they dashed forward and licked him with their forked tongues.</p>
               <pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7211-00000096"/>
               <p>But the martyr stood erect, calm amid suffering, serene amid his dreadful agony,
                  by faith clinging to his Saviour. He was there, though they saw him not; his
                  everlasting arm was round about his faithful follower, and his Spirit inspired
                  him.</p>
               <p>Nearer grew the flames and yet nearer. Life, assailed more violently, trembled in
                  her citadel, and the spirit prepared to wing its way to its mansion of rest.</p>
               <p>At last the sufferer gave a convulsive start, as though some sharper pang flashed
                  resistlessly through him. But he conquered his pain with a violent effort. Then he
                  raised his arms on high and feebly waved them. Then, with a last effort of
                  expiring nature, he cried out in a loud voice "Victory!"</p>
               <p>With the cry life seemed to depart, for he fell forward amid the rushing flames,
                  and the soul of Marcellus had ascended to the bosom of the Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XV.</head>
               <head type="sub">LUCULLUS.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>"The memory of the just is blessed."</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>AT the scene of torture and of death there was one spectator whose face, full of
                  agony, was never turned away from Marcellus, whose eyes saw every act and
                  expression, whose ears drank in every word. Long after all had departed he
                  remained in the same place, the only human being in all the vast extent of
                  deserted seats. At length he rose to go.</p>
               <p>The old elasticity of his step had departed. He moved with a slow and feeble gait;
                  his abstracted gaze and expression of pain made him look like a man suddenly
                  struck with disease. He motioned to some of the keepers, who opened for him the
                  gates that led to the arena.</p>
               <p>"Bring me a cinerary urn," said he, and he walked forward to the dying embers.</p>
               <p>A few fragments of crumbled bone, pulverized<pb n="194-195"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000097"/> by the violence of the flames, were all that
                  remained of Marcellus.</p>
               <p>Silently Lucullus took the urn which the keeper brought him, and collecting what
                  human fragments he could find, he carried away the dust.</p>
               <p>As he was leaving he was accosted by an old man. He stopped mechanically.</p>
               <p>"What do you wish of me?" said he courteously.</p>
               <p>"I am Honorius, an elder among the Christians. A dear friend of mine was put to
                  death this day in this place. I have come to see if I could obtain his ashes."</p>
               <p>"It is well that you have addressed yourself to me, venerable man," said Lucullus.
                  "Had you proclaimed your name to others you would have been seized, for there is a
                  price on your head. But I cannot grant your request. Marcellus is dead, and his
                  ashes are here in this urn. They will be deposited in the tomb of my family with
                  the highest ceremonies, for he was my dearest friend, and his loss makes the earth
                  a blank to me and life a burden."</p>
               <p>"You, then," said Honorius, "can be no other than Lucullus, of whom I have so
                  often heard him speak in words of affection?"</p>
               <p>"I am he. Never were there two friends more faithful than we. If it had been
                  possible I would have saved him. He would never have been arrested had he not
                  thrown himself into the hands of the law. O hard fate! At a time when I had made
                  arrangements that he should never be arrested, he came before the emperor himself,
                  and I was compelled with my own hands to lead him whom I loved to prison and to
                  death."</p>
               <p>"What is your loss is to him immeasurable gain. He has entered into the possession
                  of immortal happiness."</p>
               <p>"His death was a triumph," said Lucullus. "The death of Christians I have noticed
                  before, but never before have I been so struck by their hope and confidence.
                  Marcellus died as though death were an unspeakable blessing."</p>
               <p>"It was so to him, but not more so than to many others who lie buried in the
                  gloomy place where we are forced to dwell. To their numbers I wish to add the
                  remains of Marcellus. Would you be willing to part with them?"</p>
               <pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7211-00000098"/>
               <p>"I had hoped, venerable Honorius, that since my dear friend had left me I might
                  have at least the mournful pleasure of giving to his remains the last pious
                  honors, and of weeping at his tomb."</p>
               <p>"But, noble Lucullus, would not your friend have preferred a burial with the
                  sacred ceremonies of his new faith, and a resting-place among those martyrs with
                  whose names his is now associated forever?"</p>
               <p>Lucullus was silent, and thought for some time. At length he spoke:</p>
               <p>"Of his wishes there can be no doubt. I will respect them, and deny myself the
                  honor of performing the funereal rites. Take them, Honoring. But I will,
                  nevertheless, assist at your services. Will you permit the soldier, whom you only
                  know as your enemy, to enter your retreat and to witness your acts?"</p>
               <p>"You shall be welcome, noble Lucullus, even as Marcellus was welcome before you,
                  and perhaps you will receive among us the same blessing that was granted to
                  him."</p>
               <p>"Do not hope for anything like that," said Lucullus. "I am far different from
                  Marcellus in taste and feeling. I might learn to feel kindly toward you, or even
                  to admire you, but never to join you."</p>
               <p>"Come with us, then, whatever you are, and assist at the funeral services of your
                  friend. A messenger will come for you to-morrow."</p>
               <p>Lucullus signified his assent, and after handing over the precious urn to the care
                  of Honoring, he went sadly to his own home.</p>
               <p>On the following day he went with the messenger to the Catacombs. There he saw the
                  Christian community, and beheld the place of their abode. But from the previous
                  accounts of his friend he had gained a clear idea of their life, their sufferings,
                  and their afflictions.</p>
               <p>Again the mournful wail arose in the dim vaults and echoed along the arched
                  passage ways, that wail that spoke of a new brother committed to the grave; but
                  the grief that spoke of mortal sorrow was succeeded by a loftier strain that
                  expressed the faith of the aspiring soul, and a hope full of immortality.</p>
               <p>Honorius took the precious scroll, the word of life, whose promises were so
                  powerful to sustain amid the heaviest burden of grief, and in solemn<pb
                     n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7211-00000099"/> tones read that chapter in the first
                  epistle to the Corinthians which in every age and in every clime has been so dear
                  to the heart that looked beyond the realms of time to seek for refuge in the
                  prospect of the resurrection.</p>
               <p>Then he raised his head and in fervent tones offered up a prayer to the Holy One
                  of heaven, through Christ the divine mediator, by whom death and the grave had
                  been conquered and immortal life secured.</p>
               <p>The pale sad face of Lucullus was conspicuous among the mourners. If he was not a
                  Christian he could still admire such glorious doctrines and listen with pleasure
                  to such exalted hopes. It was he who placed the loved ashes within their final
                  resting-place; he, whose eyes took the last look at the dear remains; and he whose
                  hands lifted to its place the slab whereon the name and the epitaph of Marcellus
                  was engraven.</p>
               <p>Lucullus went to his home, but he was a changed man. The gayety of his nature
                  seemed to have been driven out by the severe afflictions that he had endured.</p>
               <p>He had rightly said that he would not become a Christian. The death of his friend
                  had filled him with sadness, but there was no sorrow for sin, no repentance, no
                  desire for a knowledge of God. He had lost the power of taking pleasure in the
                  world, but had gained no other source of happiness.</p>
               <p>Yet the memory of his friend produced one effect on him. He felt a sympathy for
                  the poor and oppressed people with whom Marcellus had associated. He admired their
                  constancy and pitied their unmerited sufferings. He saw that all the virtue and
                  goodness left in Rome were in the possession of these poor outcasts.</p>
               <p>These feelings led him to give them his assistance. He transferred to them the
                  friendship and the promise of aid which he had once given to Marcellus. His
                  soldiers arrested no more, or if they did arrest any they were sure to escape in
                  some way. His high position, vast wealth, and boundless influence, were all at the
                  service of the Christians. His palace was well known to them as their surest place
                  of refuge or assistance, and his name was honored as that of their most powerful
                  human friend.</p>
               <p>But all things have an end; and so the constant sufferings of the Christians and
                  the friendship<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7211-00000100"/> ship of Lucullus at
                  length were brought to a termination. In about a year after the death of Marcellus
                  the stern emperor Decius was overthrown, and a new ruler entered into the imperial
                  power. The persecution was stayed. Peace returned to the Church, and the
                  Christians came forth from the Catacombs again to dwell within the glad light of
                  day, again to sound in the ears of men the praises of Him who had redeemed them,
                  and again to carry on their never-ending contest with the hosts of evil.</p>
               <p>Years passed on, but no change came to Lucullus. When Honorius came from the
                  Catacombs he was taken by Lucullus to his own palace, and maintained there for the
                  rest of his life. He sought to repay his debt of gratitude to his noble benefactor
                  by making him acquainted with the truth, but he died without seeing his desires
                  gratified.</p>
               <p>The blessing came at last, but not till years had passed away. Far on beyond the
                  prime of manhood, even upon the borders of old age, Lucullus found the Saviour.
                  For years the world had lost all charms. Wealth and honor and power were nothing
                  to him; his life was tinged with sadness that nothing could cure. But the Spirit
                  of God at length entered into his heart, and through his divine power he at last
                  was enabled to rejoice in the love of that Saviour, of whose power over the human
                  heart he had witnessed so many striking proofs.</p>
               <p>Fifteen centuries have rolled over the city of the Cæsars since the persecution of
                  Decius drove the humble followers of Jesus into the gloomy Catacombs. Let us take
                  our stand upon the Appian Way and look around.</p>
               <p>Before us goes the long array of tombs up to the ancient city. Here the mighty men
                  of Rome once found a resting-place, carrying with them even to their graves all
                  the pomp of wealth, of glory, and of power. Beneath our feet are the rude graves
                  of those whom in life they cast out as unworthy to breathe the same air of
                  heaven.</p>
               <p>Now what a change! Around us lie these stately tombs all in ruins, their sanctity
                  desecrated, their doors broken down, their dust scattered to the winds. The names
                  of those who were buried here are unknown; the empire<pb n="202-203"
                     xml:id="VAC7211-00000101"/> which they reared has fallen forever; the legions
                  which they led to conquer have slept the sleep that knows no waking.</p>
               <p>But on the memory of the persecuted ones who rest below a world looks back adoring
                  their sepulcher has become a place of pilgrimage; and the work in which they took
                  such a noble part has been handed down to us to be perpetuated for evermore.</p>
               <p>Humbled, despised, outcast, afflicted, fame may not have written their names upon
                  the scroll of history, yet this much we know, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"These are they which came out of great tribulation</l>
                        <l>And have washed their robes</l>
                        <l>And made them white in the blood of the Lamb.</l>
                        <l>Therefore are they before the throne of God</l>
                        <l>And serve him day and night in his temple;</l>
                        <l>And He that sitteth on the throne shall dwell among them.</l>
                        <l>They shall hunger no more; neither thirst any more;</l>
                        <l>Neither shall the sun light on them, nor any heat;</l>
                        <l>For the Lamb which is in the midst of the throne shall feed them,</l>
                        <l>And shall lead them unto living fountains of waters,</l>
                        <l>And God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>THE END.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
