<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7111">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Good Mr. Bagglethorpe </title>
            <author>Logan, Olive, (1839-1909)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7111</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1575</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good Mr. Bagglethorpe</title>
                  <author>Logan, Olive, (1839-1909)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>American News Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1869">1869</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-08">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5. Inserted OCR text. Linked image files</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The good Mr. Bagglethorpe</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7111-00000001"/>OLIVE LOGAN'S NEW STORY&#xD;
&#xD;
THE GOOD&#xD;
MR. BAGGLETHORPE.&#xD;
BY OLIVE LOGAN.&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER I.-TIlE&#xD;
II.-THE&#xD;
III.-TIlE&#xD;
IV.-TIIE&#xD;
V.-TIIE&#xD;
VI.-TIIE&#xD;
&#xD;
PRINCE.&#xD;
GODDESS.&#xD;
HOUSE WITII A HISTORY.&#xD;
GOOD Mit. BAGGLET1ORPE ALARMED.&#xD;
WATCHER IN TIIE STREET.&#xD;
PRINCE INVADES THE CASTLE.&#xD;
&#xD;
VII.-THE CHARMED CIRCLE.&#xD;
&#xD;
VIII.-TILE&#xD;
IX.-TIHE&#xD;
X.-TIIE&#xD;
XI.-TIIE&#xD;
&#xD;
CARNIVAL.&#xD;
NEW ROMEO.&#xD;
RECKONING WITH THE HOST.&#xD;
ANGRY SEA.&#xD;
&#xD;
XII.-T LIE END.&#xD;
TIE AMERICAN NEWS COMPANY&#xD;
&#xD;
1869.&#xD;
&#xD;
ii&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7111-00000002"/>&#xD;
F&#xD;
&#xD;
Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1868, by&#xD;
OLIVE LOGAN,&#xD;
in the Clerk's Ofice of the District Court of the United. States for the Southern&#xD;
District of New-York.&#xD;
&#xD;
Tim drowsy afternoon of a sunny autumn&#xD;
day, which had found its way into the Christ-&#xD;
mas week of December by mistake.&#xD;
In a quiet house at Number Seventeen,&#xD;
One Thousandth street, iarlynburg, (a sub-&#xD;
urb of New-York,) the drowsy afternoon&#xD;
crept past before the eves of a benign-look-&#xD;
ing middle-aged lady, in spectacles, and with&#xD;
her needlework before her;&#xD;
Mrs. Gentry.&#xD;
The pussy-cat dozed in the corner, the ca-&#xD;
nary slept on its perch, and the dog lay basking&#xD;
in the broad path of sun upon the yellow&#xD;
carpet.&#xD;
Mrs. Gentry's needlework slipped silently&#xD;
to the floor, her eyes closed, and she slept.&#xD;
And -the brawny Ellen snored in accordance&#xD;
mnthe kitchen; and the clock ticked drowsily&#xD;
on the whitewashed wall; and all was som-&#xD;
nolence and silence.&#xD;
Mr. Gentry, tapping away with his little&#xD;
hammer at his little watch-springs and trin-&#xD;
kets of tiny brass, with his crutches erect&#xD;
against the work-bench gravely looking on,&#xD;
in the little back-room up-stairs, was hardly&#xD;
noisier than the clock.&#xD;
There came a click, as of a key turning in&#xD;
a lock, followed immediately by the signal&#xD;
lang ! of a heavy street-door.  The Prince&#xD;
had arrived to blow the bugle-horn and wake&#xD;
the inmates of the enchanted castle. Mrs.&#xD;
Gentry started to her feet ; the pussy-cat&#xD;
mewed lustily, and the dog barked and wag-&#xD;
ged his tail with delight ; and the brawny&#xD;
Ellen ceased snoring, and smiled, and put the&#xD;
tea-kettle on. The canary jumped off its perch&#xD;
and chirped merrily, and the clock fell to&#xD;
ringing its five o'clock bell, and all was joy-&#xD;
&#xD;
ful noise and activity in the house - for Willie&#xD;
Gentry had come home.&#xD;
Ile was a noble-looking youth, with broad&#xD;
shoulders, well thrown back, and a head which&#xD;
lie carried with the ails of a king. His hair&#xD;
clustered in thick masses of soft, dark brown,&#xD;
much the same as his mother's had been he-&#xD;
fore time had increased the value of hers by&#xD;
showering silver there. His hazel eyes were&#xD;
playful and vivacious in expression.  The&#xD;
high, fine forehead was of a mat whiteness,&#xD;
equaled only by the brilliancy and purity of&#xD;
Parian marble; and the deep carmine lips re-&#xD;
minded one of some luscious tropical fruit,&#xD;
whose red ripeness is beautiful to the eye :anl&#xD;
staining to the touch.  his step was light&#xD;
and elastic as that of a young fawn, but in&#xD;
spite of this lie had not time to reach the little&#xD;
drawing-room before his mother had tripped&#xD;
out to meet hiiA, for her step was scarcely&#xD;
heavier than his own&#xD;
It was well the red lips did not stain-&#xD;
for if they had, in what condition would&#xD;
Mrs. -Gentry's cheeks and forehead have&#xD;
been&#xD;
" My darling boy !" she exclaimed. " My&#xD;
true young prince&#xD;
" Mother, you're a trump," said the Prince.&#xD;
Where's Pop ?"&#xD;
" O you dreadful child ! why will you call&#xD;
your father by that frightful title?  lie is in&#xD;
his snuggery.  But don't call him by that.&#xD;
horrid name, will you, dear?"&#xD;
"No, mother, I won't," he answered laugh.&#xD;
ingly ; " I won't, I'll call him Daddy. Where's&#xD;
Daddy ? Ah ! here lie cones I IIere's my an-&#xD;
cestor," as Mr. Gentry entered on his crutch-&#xD;
es. " Here's my Governor 1  My dear old&#xD;
&#xD;
THE GOOD MR. BAGGLETILORPE.&#xD;
CIAPTEIR  I.&#xD;
TIlE lINCE.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7111-00000003"/>&#xD;
7 IE GOOD AJR. BAGGLETHORPE.&#xD;
&#xD;
YOUNG    MIE s  11I L..&#xD;
&#xD;
Pop!   My rampaging old Pop ! My High&#xD;
Daddy!'&#xD;
"I knew you were home, my boy," said&#xD;
Mr. Gentry, seating himself, and laying his&#xD;
crutches on the floor within easy reach,&#xD;
"Something told me you had come. ~&#xD;
What was it told you, father ?" asked&#xD;
Will.&#xD;
"Never mind, my boy. But if by any&#xD;
chance you should think it was love, yoU&#xD;
Won't he far wrong."&#xD;
Will Gentry smoothed the few w hite hairs&#xD;
on his father's forehead, stooping over it&#xD;
fondly, and-again it was well that the red&#xD;
lips did not stain.&#xD;
" Tea's ready," said the brawny Ellen,&#xD;
appearing at the door and laughing wildly&#xD;
in Will's face, for no earthly reason except&#xD;
that she was glad to see him.&#xD;
It was a true American tea. Tiere were&#xD;
slap-jacks, and pie, and molasses, and cake,&#xD;
and tea, and yellow cream, and apple-sauce.&#xD;
And plenty of every thing&#xD;
Pop." said Will-and it Li sad to know&#xD;
that ie spoke with his mouth full-"Pop, I&#xD;
believe I'm getting quite dissipated."&#xD;
Mrs. Gentry looked up in alarm,&#xD;
"Don't frighten your mother, Will," said&#xD;
his father ; "explain yourself."&#xD;
Out till twelve o'clock last night at 31r.&#xD;
Pearson's Christmas dinner--''&#xD;
Oh ! interrupted Mrs. Gentry, " eh/ is&#xD;
not dissipation-to go to a tristnas dinnter&#xD;
at your employer's house-and very proud I&#xD;
ant of his ligh appreciation of you, tny dear.&#xD;
It is not every New-York merehaut would in-&#xD;
vite leis book-keeper to a dinner at his house&#xD;
in Fifth avenue. If that is all you mean by&#xD;
dissipation, I am quite proud of it."&#xD;
But that is not all."&#xD;
"Don't frighten me~c, Willie,"1 pleaded the&#xD;
mother.&#xD;
"Don't frighten us, my son," said Mr.&#xD;
Gentry.  "11onor your father and humor&#xD;
&#xD;
your mother, that your days may be long in&#xD;
the land."&#xD;
You won't let a fellow talk," said the&#xD;
young nan. " All I mean to say is this-I&#xD;
am going out again to-ight."&#xD;
" Where '.&#xD;
" Ah ! that's the secret.  I give it you in&#xD;
a thousand to guess what I have got on the&#xD;
tapis for to-night."&#xD;
"Tpis, dear," repeated Mrs. Gentry, cor-&#xD;
recting the boy's pronunciation of the French&#xD;
word.&#xD;
"Well, tappy then,mother. Pop, what do&#xD;
you think I've got on the tappy for to-night?"&#xD;
-'I couldn't say, my boy. I couldn't pos-&#xD;
sibly say," replied the elder Gentry, rather&#xD;
regretfully, as though it were a matter for&#xD;
lamentt that be could not divine his son's&#xD;
thottghts.&#xD;
Well,my new dissipation is, that we&#xD;
should all go to the theatre to-night.''&#xD;
"The theatre ! What theatre ?"&#xD;
Haven't you heard ?'There is a great&#xD;
moral (dratna to be given at Young Men's&#xD;
Hall to-night.  And as it's Saturday nih r,&#xD;
and we don't often get a chance to go to the&#xD;
theatre here in IIarlynburg, I move we all&#xD;
go. Shouldn't you like to go, mother.?''&#xD;
" Yes, dear, very-tmuch;" answered Mtrs.&#xD;
Gentry ; ''that is, if your father will go.''&#xD;
" Go !  es, inleed ! It's only three blocks&#xD;
ofl. I can      ttldislthat, e-ay ('nought.&#xD;
Ave are all such stay-at-homue blies that it&#xD;
will do us good to go out. And besides,&#xD;
Will, we tntmt have sotme public spirit, you&#xD;
know-we mr-St encourage home institutions&#xD;
-and help to establish the drama in Iarlyn-&#xD;
burg. There's a convincing argument--not&#xD;
that argument is needed. I am old enough&#xD;
to obey orders, ntd this rascal here is my&#xD;
superior officer"  And the old gentleman&#xD;
punched Will's ribs playfully with the end of&#xD;
his crutch.&#xD;
&#xD;
CIIA PTIER         I II.&#xD;
T11? (aODDIESS-&#xD;
YOUNG MEN'S IALL Stood .on the buisiest  The Ilarlynburghers considered this a very&#xD;
street of the populous suburban town.     imposing structure, and all new-comers were&#xD;
&#xD;
expected to pour forth exaggeate1 praises of&#xD;
its architectttrl beauty. Here associations&#xD;
held periodical meetings. Here orators ott&#xD;
temperance,In temperance, t       .ta tysims ct&#xD;
enc', literature, religion, itreligiom, itiefeet&#xD;
setn- itid perfect nonset, were wott to dis-&#xD;
c'ott'su to the assetibled t1tititd-sottte-&#xD;
ti-ueS            -- eeitgre tuttltititul--itt the ctn.&#xD;
ilc a v   o r t griyt  im t i tte  ueha t  t ., s  o n ti sid e .&#xD;
'heteilatutawiasstomelhat of an innovation&#xD;
at Yottg Mc's Ilall.  Not but that theatri-&#xD;
cat ltepresentatio s  -wee  fully  nielcotte  -but&#xD;
those  teatt  eal  r nprectitors  whose  part  in&#xD;
life's setio-comcdy was cast in such untire-&#xD;
munerative etricts as this, xw ece generally&#xD;
too pover). ttie'lctn to permit of' rent-pavitg&#xD;
andlSittulli stern ece-sittes of the show&#xD;
world. Jugglers, gytumtnats, barrel organists,&#xD;
m eecunious mIionkeys, nom1adie hlarpists, and&#xD;
the like disciples of artistic itineratie'y, were&#xD;
tle chief atmiusetncits of the place.  A r-&#xD;
gularly iotel  'atma, with  scenes, and(&#xD;
actors, atd above al aian alience, was alto-&#xD;
gethe'r a tosel aflai.&#xD;
The present hi-triome unillprcemario tempo-&#xD;
rarily enthroned lat te hall w as evidently a&#xD;
esot ilf euotrceS.  Whatever situs of' co-&#xD;
m lsso  r       .'t1e li at his door and that of&#xD;
YountgXll's Hll, of i nissitton the ust surely&#xD;
have een fully ticsltittl. The principal c i&#xD;
trance was huttn with flaming hndhlills, full&#xD;
of high-soundini annuoutceiien ts. ellcideS&#xD;
lie, there were picture, h'longing to the&#xD;
rudest sip-cies of thait rude school of art&#xD;
known as " Colored Phol tography." Oi(ne of&#xD;
tiesi' pictures represented a very fat man,&#xD;
-mthiluetr a vet y fat uIotan, tlan a tlthit'd a very&#xD;
thin little girl. Iliut the triumph lof' the hour&#xD;
was a lut-trip of canvas, sttpeindld across&#xD;
tie street on wlieh was painted mt large let&#xD;
ter:-evidetitly by an amltur-these words&#xD;
" (''NT T II t T DA' 1(1 St W IlOSE L)OW l&#xD;
VIEw - It1t 1x 'T'tt' )t liNt) No WOf'TIEYk&#xD;
ACFIION lON I.&#xD;
O ''TAKE' '1i'.s: W ti  tNT) C'oN5tlA&#xD;
'I'ON,&#xD;
AN) '1COM: TO 'it:i' Goo ) :it. B(S GLE&#xD;
TH;ORPES GEA.T MOIL \L EXIH1IIuTION&#xD;
ENTRANCE ONLY      CENTS.&#xD;
Ott this Saturday evening, when the Gentr'&#xD;
family approaclied theI hill, they observcid&#xD;
standing on the threshold of the street-en&#xD;
&#xD;
trance, a portly gentletmai of a most gool&#xD;
natured and happy aspect, who kept tp a&#xD;
continual stream of words-tnot in the lu-l&#xD;
voice of an auctioneer or a learned pig orator,&#xD;
but in a quiet conversational totte, who&#xD;
every accent was oleaginous with good feeling&#xD;
andt~ cordial greeting.&#xD;
" Welcotte, wse lcottte !" he observed i a&#xD;
totne of the ttnost cheerfulness.  " 'at r&#xD;
right itup to the head of the stairs, kind friend,&#xD;
and the door-keeper will he there to intier&#xD;
dooe yot to theI body of the hall, where yout&#xD;
n ill see myl great moral egzib)ition, enltrance':&#xD;
ontly tuVsiot 'tiie ettsn  w lore you ill s''&#xD;
the good 1r. Baggletliorpe's great tmati'&#xD;
curricttletin oitu lhis great mttord curtii'hun-&#xD;
c-r I.ar 'eteCto Fe1(eeete atl te talettel&#xD;
Mis  lieaglethorle.  W  elco e,  w'el'i  tti' l o&#xD;
riglt up -tairs, u here Lm-1 'eeteete ie e(t''&#xD;
will Sile upon)I you --this cegst rawdinan1.&#xD;
young p    on ated nnt.ly-ixetvat', is&#xD;
eamitl as tetir. Jiagglethorpe is guodi. eIt&#xD;
com1te, wi lhomte ! I  n  tithe good  "l. I  gtigl-&#xD;
trpe, and 1 lid you li'trtily weleonn'tG &#xD;
tigllt itt.  itl,tiy  -on,1Itete11 1 to; 'let&#xD;
l1kitt at mt'.  I have neither beauty ii&#xD;
l1nts, I amt ionly good.'&#xD;
Durin'' fhis speech('1the Gentry family lhad&#xD;
(ii at the doi   ', li' gtrtheMood t N' g&#xD;
tlh(illp' tuctint tig 'WXill's illbow as anI enctoutrage-&#xD;
nttt 4 hitt to continue in the lw ays of well-&#xD;
doitng.&#xD;
'Iiey had to di lieu1t y inl obtatitnin  at&#xD;
Although close upon the hour forhn, nnn&#xD;
the lwrfonn u-e, us. Inm noas nt;1ot 11n(1re lman&#xD;
one tini Al.&#xD;
TIhe piee to b'   i-r'f'trticl w  annonitt itit'i' 1&#xD;
inl the handbill a-1'' oonw, original, atnl tI&#xD;
4 ly  moral dranut ,camled Go  rgeIi  Noandl.&#xD;
.  ainl it na-, fisher set, do(wn  that at the conl&#xD;
chit-ion  of t"the  l((''1'" La  Petie  iM te  ",&#xD;
o1)):r inla l a moud A Heg; y , entitled Clau&#xD;
- ".  ,  liduring. n hich the orestl' ra wx ill play&#xD;
the Natiinal Air of XYankle' Io)w'lle.&#xD;
The piece n aIs a curio,ity. T he tierCe 10&#xD;
faItinatin .ti/,,tittl was  i otattt by aCt&#xD;
happy, lgood-natu(red a l 05)woman1, whom i1the&#xD;
tLill- ttttitttiiteil as M1. Atelia nagnlethorlte&#xD;
a gentle oll ouil, hto it was very eviltt w&#xD;
thorougtly itctpal)l'le of harming a wiortil&#xD;
y     nc les ifit lay ing diabolical plans tfor et-&#xD;
,  ing gutleleiS young tetn to p1etltiot. Oi th&#xD;
." other haul, the credulous and youthful /uriu&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7111-00000004"/>&#xD;
6              TIr OODE looD  I. BAGGLETJIOIPTEE.&#xD;
&#xD;
well found a mis-representative in the person&#xD;
of a dark, savage, ruffianly-looking man of&#xD;
past forty, who was in that highly salubrious&#xD;
state of crockery-ware known as "his cups."&#xD;
" Shall we go, Willie ?" asked Mrs. Gentry,&#xD;
so soon as the curtain fell.&#xD;
Wait for the allegory, mother. It won't&#xD;
be long, probably."&#xD;
The allegory consisted of a solitary female&#xD;
figure, standing alone in the centre of the&#xD;
stage, dressed in the traditional costume of&#xD;
goddesses, and holding in her hand a very&#xD;
large and very unwieldy flag 'and staff  A&#xD;
solitary female figure, with short white skirts&#xD;
and flesh-colored leggings, and an il-propor-&#xD;
tion t and worse-sewn liberty-cap poised un-&#xD;
steadily upon her heal. She was evileintly&#xD;
the original of the thmi little colored photo-&#xD;
graphic girl of the doorway dhsplay, whote&#xD;
form had been rounded by the maturing touch&#xD;
of womanhood, until it was now little short of&#xD;
a perfect model of perfect beauty; She hal&#xD;
long training golden locks, which himng inii n-&#xD;
tdilous waves almost to her knees, and h, &#xD;
childlike blue eyes, that looked straight ip to&#xD;
the clouds of heaven, seeminglyti, frott out&#xD;
their pure and liquid depths.&#xD;
A stage goddess-niervols, evidently, at her&#xD;
position, and the knowledge that the eyes of&#xD;
all present were turned upon her; ad w io&#xD;
experietced, doubtless, a great sense of relief&#xD;
when thit clrtaini fell, as it did soon, on her&#xD;
and the allegory.&#xD;
&#xD;
Two streets back of the street in wlich&#xD;
Young Men's Hall gracefully lifted its proud&#xD;
front, and kept it lifted-two streets back,was&#xD;
a third street, as different from its bustling&#xD;
neighbors which lay in close proximity as&#xD;
though they were further removed than Styx&#xD;
from Euphrates. A street so quiet and order-&#xD;
ly and deathly still, that the air which bore&#xD;
on it the noises of those neighboring streets&#xD;
seemed to hold its breath as it passed. A&#xD;
clean street,with clean sidewalks, clean, clerk-&#xD;
like men, clean, sempstress-like women, clean,&#xD;
school-going children, clean houses with&#xD;
&#xD;
"A very unpleasant spectacle," said Mrs.&#xD;
Gentry.&#xD;
If it was I very unpleasant spectacle, how&#xD;
dil it happen that Will Gentry arose, after&#xD;
the curtain had fallen, with a filmyiy mist before&#xD;
his eyes, and knew nothing until lie found&#xD;
himself walking vacantly along the street with&#xD;
his mother on his arni&#xD;
Arrived at home, lie received in silence his&#xD;
father's "God bless yoi, my hboy," and his&#xD;
mother's kiss, and sped up to his own apart-&#xD;
ment. He sat down silently, on the side of&#xD;
his spotless little bed, and meditated long.&#xD;
"I left this room three hours ago," lie sail,&#xD;
lifting his head at last, " a bov-  I return to&#xD;
it-a man. All the cares-all the pains-of&#xD;
a man who loves arc tuine. 0 mys goddess !"&#xD;
lie cried, stretching out his hands-" my&#xD;
-sweet, beautiful goddess, I love you, I love&#xD;
That night there was an aitdded name n the&#xD;
prayer which went up from    Will Gentry's&#xD;
bedside - and when at last lie composed him-&#xD;
self to sleep, lie dreamed that he was trant-&#xD;
formed into 'a glorious antiliue-a: youthful&#xD;
god of freedom; and that the beautiful godl-&#xD;
dess of freedom, (formerly attached to the&#xD;
great moral exhibition of the good Mr. Bag&#xD;
glethiorpe,) with her white arms twinled lov&#xD;
ingly about his neck, was seated on the hack&#xD;
of an ioutpreath Anerieanm eagh- which was&#xD;
slowly upwafting them both to paradise.&#xD;
&#xD;
freshly-scrubbed wooden step , and, midway&#xD;
of the block, a clean little church with three&#xD;
trees in front of it, clean also.&#xD;
Next door to the church there stood a&#xD;
house which had a history.&#xD;
Years ago, a gentleman doing business in&#xD;
New-York, and whose position in life was&#xD;
financially expressed by that ponderous ad-&#xD;
jective "opulent," had bought some "house.&#xD;
lots" in Ilarlynburg. For a length of time&#xD;
his "house-lots" had remained without other&#xD;
occupants than boys at noon-day playing at&#xD;
ball, girls at sunset trolling hoops, and honje-&#xD;
&#xD;
less nomadic animals at night seeking a spot&#xD;
of shelter and of sleep.&#xD;
nt there caine a change.   A house was&#xD;
built on one of the lots-a fiiie house, a large&#xD;
house, a suboirbailla, and the opulent gen-&#xD;
tlen canseoutand lived there with his&#xD;
opulent family , it they kept servants and&#xD;
a carriage , and trieids visited tieii; and&#xD;
altogether the sulburl) promised to become&#xD;
dinnied-jately fashionable, and landholders'&#xD;
were joyous at the prospect of future pros-&#xD;
perit, aid positively refused to sell at former&#xD;
p~riees.&#xD;
Then there aiie another change.  clouds s&#xD;
gathered on the sunny sky-the too -unniy&#xD;
sky. llurr11 ig mtessengers went alter the&#xD;
dtor - for die opulent wife of the opulent&#xD;
gentle an had been taken ill, and in a shorter&#xD;
space of time than you would think it p'ossi-&#xD;
Ide to die in, -lie died. And the opulent&#xD;
geulteuanhiusielf was down, and it was&#xD;
rumored that -lie also would ,die; atnd ntix&#xD;
opulent but thler bad-teumpered little gi-ls,&#xD;
oI-pringof the  aoxe, uiere hastily remottixed&#xD;
to sonio other llace-nio one knew exacth&#xD;
where, ot they never returned to li arl i-&#xD;
btr g.hill an  1 h ,the opulent genutulemtiani got&#xD;
altit, and tIl pteopcle w Iho saw himii sI that&#xD;
he w is a panible looking being when lhe ap-&#xD;
pearedl That his skit was wrinikled, now&#xD;
blue by turit", now yellow,nowy gha-tly white&#xD;
and thattt inoIe id-ays, wlen the sui was&#xD;
liinini brightly aiid every body else was com-&#xD;
plainiing of tie1 heat,'this strange opulent gen-i&#xD;
tenant would shiver and shak e as if w it d&#xD;
cold. And again, when the cold wind was&#xD;
blowing about the corners, taking all per&#xD;
sOIls w ral ptlt wx armily, antd stamp p their feet on&#xD;
the ground to keep life in thlem, this strange&#xD;
opileint gentleman w ould take oil'his hat and&#xD;
invite thie isid to blow on his temples, and&#xD;
supplicate the snOwilakes to melt on his&#xD;
burning brow aid cool it. And soon after,&#xD;
the opulent gentleman went away, leaving&#xD;
his house to let at a house agent's, for the&#xD;
lowest of " songs ; aiid the price of land&#xD;
went down to the zero of the speculator's&#xD;
thermometer ; for Ilarlynburg, poor Harlyn-&#xD;
burg, paria-like llarlynburg, was now known,&#xD;
and truthfully known, to be infested by that&#xD;
pest of pests, the fever and ague !&#xD;
But all this is now completely a thing ol&#xD;
the past. Valiant drainage stepped in, and&#xD;
&#xD;
friendly sewers laughed miasma to scorn.&#xD;
The hand of reform was soon at work, and&#xD;
at present, lIarlynburg is as healthy as any&#xD;
suburb of New-York. But somebody once&#xD;
gave a highly respectable dog a had name,&#xD;
and it interfered w ith every subsequent&#xD;
business operation of that unfortunate canine.&#xD;
And every body said there was fever and ague&#xD;
in lIarlynburg, and it militated against the&#xD;
house-agents, and kept rents low.&#xD;
And it was well for a certain Mrs. liapp&#xD;
that rents were low, as otherwise how could&#xD;
she have taken the great brick house-prop&#xD;
erty of the opulent gentleman--m the clean&#xD;
street iieet to the church, and opened it in&#xD;
rather an ostentatious manner, n\ itli a little&#xD;
tin sign nailed near the hell-pull, announleing&#xD;
that this was now MRS. Rari's FasIIONAiiii.&#xD;
BoxtaoiNsIlot si ?&#xD;
It caine to' pass, however, when, little by&#xD;
little the house tilled, that the appearance ot&#xD;
the guests at table was not snehi as to inspire&#xD;
any one,eVen Mis. Rapp lier-elf,wili lthe n iet&#xD;
that the distimietive adjective fashionale&#xD;
couibIlhe altogether jist y app lied.  mhat&#xD;
there w: as of fahiioii in llIIarl ibii}g had a&#xD;
house to itself, and did not seek to array it&#xD;
tell' unid,-r the presumoptuous tin signbolard&#xD;
at the Rapplm portal.&#xD;
And the good Mr. Ilagglethorpe, casting&#xD;
about for a haven of rest for himself mid lis&#xD;
faiivilx, deliberated for many minutes before&#xD;
daring to disturb the death like quiet of all&#xD;
about in the clean street, by a pull at the hell&#xD;
of the great brick house. Maiiy wre t'.-hesur&#xD;
nises to which this signi gave rise.  MaNiy&#xD;
were the qiuetion-, selfIdenianded, to which&#xD;
Mr. Bagglethorpe, in his love for truth, in-&#xD;
wardly, regretfully, answered in the negative.&#xD;
Was lie fashionable ? No. Ie was good&#xD;
lie was known far and wide as the good Mr.&#xD;
Jhagglcthorpe; but even his most devoted&#xD;
partisanl had never called him " fashionable."&#xD;
And, indeed, even if no other testimony were&#xD;
procurable, that queer, antediluvian  coat,&#xD;
those giant-like flappy trowsers, built probe&#xD;
bly in some remote day when cloth was as&#xD;
cheap as dirt, and a great deal cheaper than&#xD;
dirt is now in New-York ; that immensely&#xD;
high hat, with a brim as wide as the som.&#xD;
brero of a Spanish muleteer, furnished forth&#xD;
f indubitable proof of goodness, doubtless, but&#xD;
of fashion-no.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
U I1IAI1'E l tIll.&#xD;
'TIlI I()Us t i I'1ui \ AISTORS.&#xD;
&#xD;
3,&#xD;
3&#xD;
t&#xD;
k'          ',&#xD;
&#xD;
71IE Or L'LE r&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7111-00000005"/>&#xD;
rlGO1.BAS. Ar's NATURAL C'io.&#xD;
&#xD;
Was Mrs. Bagglethorpe fashionable ? It&#xD;
is true she often personated fashionable cha-&#xD;
racters. The whole range of the drama,&#xD;
from Lady Macbeth down to' Roxalana, was&#xD;
open, and indeed had been penetrated by&#xD;
her.  And penetrated, Mr. Bagglethorpe&#xD;
thought, in a remarkably effective manner.&#xD;
Therefore, in one sense of the word, she wis&#xD;
fashionable.  A person who played Lady&#xD;
Macbeth-a queen, in fact-must be fash-&#xD;
ionable. But was that the style of fashion&#xD;
which Mrs. Rapp demanded ? And would a&#xD;
red cotton velvet robe, tritimed with tar-&#xD;
iiishel gold lace, he the proper fashionable&#xD;
costuie for Mrs. Rapp's boarding-house han-&#xD;
pIclts ?&#xD;
And Fifine-la petite ?  Alh! less thin&#xD;
either of the others, could ite lay claim to&#xD;
being a votary of the goddess of fashion, or,&#xD;
indeed, of any goddess whatever, except tiat&#xD;
very ill-cladone, that flag-hewrapped goddess,&#xD;
wlomt she nightly pcrsoiatel at the great&#xD;
moral exhibition. Little Fifine-a little, gol-&#xD;
den-haired, blue-eyed baby when this poor&#xD;
wandering couple had received her, with a&#xD;
blessing on them and her, from the arms of&#xD;
an unknown dying mother, departing this&#xD;
life as cheaply as possible at a miserable&#xD;
country inn, in some wretched village where&#xD;
the exhibition was then-even at that remote&#xD;
period-exhibiting with only qualified success.&#xD;
'They had taken the child and cared for her;&#xD;
and, by her own will, she had given then&#xD;
her poor aid in return. Sie was beautiful&#xD;
in form and feature, a model for the gods,&#xD;
if the gods had been sculptors; but in  a&#xD;
fashtiionalble sense, the good Mr. haggle-&#xD;
thorpe felt her deficiency as uitich as liis&#xD;
own.&#xD;
lie had concluded, then, that there was lit-&#xD;
tle o'r io isC in his applying at this forbidden&#xD;
source of fashion, Mrs. Rapp's boarding-&#xD;
house, when, by one of those strange acci-&#xD;
dents which, in various 'forms, sometimes&#xD;
govern the fate of nations themselves, the&#xD;
door opened, and a clean, tidy, but poorly-,&#xD;
clad woman issued forth with a basket on&#xD;
her arm, which seemed to indicate is tenden-&#xD;
ey toward that unfashionable but necessary&#xD;
place of resort-market. Seeing the good&#xD;
Mr. Bagglethorpe quite a fixture before her&#xD;
house, (she had been watching him from in-&#xD;
side for some minutes,) and feeling, in view&#xD;
&#xD;
of his rather shabby raiment, a natural anxi-&#xD;
ety for the safety of a coat and two hats&#xD;
which hung suspended just inside her door,&#xD;
she resolutely planted herself before him,&#xD;
and asked peremptorily:&#xD;
"What do you want?"&#xD;
"I want," answered the good Mr. Baggle-&#xD;
thorpe, rather astonished at her question,&#xD;
but determined to answer it truthfully, " I&#xD;
want a heap o' things. -In the first laceI&#xD;
want a fortin, and a noo dress for Feefy;&#xD;
ditto for Mis Bagglethorpe; though the lat-&#xD;
tei', bei' past the years of indiscretion, don't&#xD;
Leer so nuth for noo"dresses ; but the for'&#xD;
mt'er, betityotntg and remarkable handsome,&#xD;
though I for one never expected her to turn&#xD;
out so, for sht -xvas of a thinness wonderful&#xD;
to behold, andh I miight hiev exhibited her as&#xD;
a lixin' skelitot, though that l ight 'i hurt'&#xD;
her feelings, and she's the best girl ever&#xD;
lived, thouh not fashionerble.  u t wat I&#xD;
wxiht' inrust perticklerly to hey just at pre-&#xD;
senit is rooms. lev you any rooms, Mis Ripi,&#xD;
fer folLs not fashionable ?"'&#xD;
Roon's ?" repeated the landlady, some-&#xD;
what softened 1y the prospect of more lodg-&#xD;
crs, "yes, I-'have a few empty, thought only'&#xD;
a tew. Won't yout walk in, sir?  This way&#xD;
please," conducting the good Mr. Baggle-&#xD;
thorpe into a very large antd very barren&#xD;
parlor. ,"'IT:wo rery fashionable ladies, the&#xD;
Miss Millers, now staying at the Fifth Ave-&#xD;
nue Hotel, wrote to me only yesterday for&#xD;
r'oomus.  And I fully intended to write to&#xD;
them to-day, and say: /)ear Miss Millers--&#xD;
they are sisters, that is, /ilfsister's-same&#xD;
father and two mlothers, both dead, and dress&#xD;
in half-:nuriniuig nowx, liut e-ry fashionable--&#xD;
yes I hat af w."&#xD;
Do you require all your female borders&#xD;
to have one father and two mothers in half-&#xD;
uournin' i'-ry fashioinerble, Mis Rip ?" asked&#xD;
the good Mr, .agglethorpe, feeling that these&#xD;
wxere conditions with which Filine and Mrs.&#xD;
IRagglethiorpe could scarcely comply'.&#xD;
Oh I dear, nox; what ate you talking&#xD;
aount ?  I mean the Miss Millers -but, it&#xD;
you wish to take the rooms, I'll xvrite to&#xD;
them that they can't have them.  Will you&#xD;
go up and see them ?"&#xD;
Very gladly, Mis Rip, very gladly. And&#xD;
ant in much haste to be settled with my&#xD;
family, but, es I remarked before, we are&#xD;
&#xD;
rot fashionerble, and shall be glad to know&#xD;
that that is no objection."&#xD;
The rcoms--although Mr. Bagglethorpe&#xD;
would have preferred their being on the&#xD;
same floor--were both confortalble enough.&#xD;
The reoim which was to be honored Iy the&#xD;
anerliliini) of the worthy couple was situated&#xD;
at he ha-k of the hou1ise, ind gave on a bal-&#xD;
aOii), with   liech it eo 1tntnunicate( 1by a deep,&#xD;
liN, _0petninh  iench window. And Fhiine's&#xD;
nook was a tiny hall-bedroomi on an upper&#xD;
floor. -      -&#xD;
Does the price suit you, sir " asked Mis.&#xD;
Rap, after tiameing, that important item.&#xD;
It do, tatrm, it do. I am glad that it do.&#xD;
But if it hadent, I should hev said so at inlt.&#xD;
Ueeaue, ar' any Hotly ab tout mite, atidi they&#xD;
will tell ou I pay reg'ler'. .if business is&#xD;
had, I live poorer but ipay reg'ler.  My mtiotto&#xD;
is be virtoosi atii pay' reg ler."&#xD;
" Yes," sail Mi:. Rapp vaguely, ''I was&#xD;
just goitig to ask you for your refierene('i. .I&#xD;
never take aiiny liody without them."&#xD;
My referencess" said Mr. Itaggletliorpe&#xD;
solemnly, "is the world. Go arid tar-k the&#xD;
world whi l isDa-hgglethi'Ioe wen  he;''s dtsroed,&#xD;
and the world w ill answer, 'When he's dress-&#xD;
ed or undretsel, sleeping' or wx akin', hie's all&#xD;
&#xD;
the same, lie's good. Ie's virtoos and good.&#xD;
Go ask the rivers and the mountains, the&#xD;
lakes and-and the snakes, and they wili all&#xD;
answer itt one accord, lie is good ! augle&#xD;
thorpe is good.&#xD;
"Any body i iarlynhurg know you&#xD;
asked Mrs. iRapp, seemingly nit struck lv&#xD;
the proniscuuts (iract e  of the good Mr.&#xD;
llagglethoripe s reerences5.&#xD;
Young Men's yi all is a perl ler' tieni&#xD;
of mine. Go ars hi . hu i lie11 knew;' me well.&#xD;
Hin and i' is on a spee together at te pr(&#xD;
sent speakin'. Go arsk liu, and he viii lend&#xD;
lv i\elaimii, ' aeglethorlpi'eeodl&#xD;
"ye," said Mrs. lRap1t.  I suipp ue 'i'&#xD;
just as lief pay inl advance&#xD;
".1ut, Mis  1p, just. Inled, I'd l -ter.&#xD;
Fo' then 1 lin feel that 1 an eat in nxeonn&#xD;
vittles, Inain, and not .orn.&#xD;
Wlhen liihie anid iMrs. I lagglethorp heard&#xD;
that this wyas a fa'hiona l 1utardi ; o1uitti&#xD;
they, too, xwetc alaritied.  Illt wlinithey&#xD;
w ere  tistalled  i their ' r mi ,  a ne1  ar11 1&#xD;
ta e  of a feat at the Rltipjiiat bear ,:&#xD;
viewed the  til e o' guests tJ('teat ast  ,&#xD;
their fears wxere gtr'eatly allayedi, mittd eta tv&#xD;
thling we'nt smloothily.&#xD;
&#xD;
ITm; GOODMl.AVAILARMED&#xD;
&#xD;
AT the Iall, too, the prospects xwere het-&#xD;
ter.  FTrom losing money they had got to&#xD;
paying elpensces, and from that to having IL&#xD;
nightly surplus over. Tn fact, it had hecomo&#xD;
wxidxly rmotored abroad that the prettiest girl&#xD;
any onte ver saw could be seen now by any&#xD;
uone at Young Men's  il. lTtither', their. -&#xD;
fore, the fii i-xtive every one went nii-hit&#xD;
after nilit, andt, wxith the rest, Will i-.ntti y&#xD;
is   tutlter, too delicate to ask of himn  a&#xD;
confidence which lie did not sem di-posed to&#xD;
give sit at  hmiite' in the little parlor at No.&#xD;
7 IOne Thousandth street, ostensibly paying&#xD;
)       nucht attrition to Mr. Gentry's'reading aloud&#xD;
frnm the newspaper, but in reality wondering&#xD;
what had happened to her boy. Where did&#xD;
lhe go now, as soon as the hastily-dispatched&#xD;
&#xD;
teL xxwas over?  \Whter'e diid b' 80stty  'xii y&#xD;
eveunig till pat ten o'e-iiek ?  Wiy iiIlii'&#xD;
not tell her, his muothiwr, trotmt xxhtupt, tilto&#xD;
this  tit wt, elie  th  tevir   hia d a  s eret  ?  Th -&#xD;
were the questmits which itheti lt I trhy' Lept&#xD;
continually aiukmg herself, amdxxhi'l lit-i&#xD;
was totally unable to answer.&#xD;
'le' gos1 Ni1'. ltgghtlthurple conu11 iav'&#xD;
toll her. . It was hardly possibl   ttat hi&#xD;
oil' I he st consent l y on guard at the lior&#xD;
of 'uting Mel"'s 11"l, grieving the  n hu&#xD;
nxith   r hinsti' anti ctlordial welcoeutri,  i utout&#xD;
otbservinig that, as sioon as the (diiotrs e&#xD;
opened, the first tickIt boutuah:t was sillto&#xD;
a handsome   young man wi)hoad conoi thre&#xD;
so early as th very first night with ' rost&#xD;
an elegant" lady on his arnt.&#xD;
&#xD;
S                TIlE GOOD 1 Ili. BAr G r Lr  O&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7111-00000006"/>&#xD;
10            TI11 GOOD .MR. J.A GGLETHORPE.&#xD;
&#xD;
"Yes, Feefy," would this good old soul say,&#xD;
when safely installed at his home quarters&#xD;
with his wife and his ward (as lie grandly&#xD;
called her) sitting near hhn. " That there&#xD;
young man, whose name deponent knoweth&#xD;
not, he cane the very fust night, with most&#xD;
an elegant lady hanging on to his arm, and&#xD;
an aged gent beside them o1 cripples-i&#xD;
mean on crutches. Aid ev'ry night sence,&#xD;
there liev lie been. I know not who he is,&#xD;
nor do I keer. Butt of I ketch hin throwing'&#xD;
sheep's eyes at my little girl, I'll refuse hin&#xD;
admittance to the egzibition."&#xD;
"Cuardy," said the girl, "I have never&#xD;
seen him throw any tiing at all at me, and&#xD;
I'm sttre lie seems a very nice person."&#xD;
"My dear, you i(b not know wat these yere&#xD;
young men will do. Es a root, they air 'wick-&#xD;
ed. A young ladyi pursooint' your perfe s'ion&#xD;
is opm ito reimaik. Folks wonder wat on irth&#xD;
she goes on to the stage fur, and serusly ad.&#xD;
vise her to it )so igntermini ous a pursoot.&#xD;
Et the stie time they do not olter her bread&#xD;
to eat, or better to butter it withIt.  Ef she&#xD;
was to say to thteto, ' Ef I leave t( stage, will&#xD;
yol tale heeritv rw  they woithl aiswsier,&#xD;
Nary.' There n l't a doulit they would an.&#xD;
swer,  Nary.'"&#xD;
" It is tl least I can do, Gi:irdv, to try and&#xD;
aid you a little, after all your goodness to&#xD;
me," said Fitine, nestling up close to the fit&#xD;
old mian and looking fondly in his eyes; for&#xD;
he was the only father she had ever known.&#xD;
" My child, you are the darlingest girl that&#xD;
ever lived. Idbless the day mue and the cgzi-&#xD;
bition went to Pettyville, where I lost money&#xD;
and had to pawn our clothes, for there I found&#xD;
you. Your poor mother! How grateful she&#xD;
wits to Nis Ilagglethorpe, wen Mis . said she&#xD;
wul take the child. We told her wat we wuz,1&#xD;
dear. Poor, strollin' players. She says, you&#xD;
will be good to her, w91't you ? Says I, watt&#xD;
is my name, mtarm ?  Says she, I donst know.&#xD;
Says I, it is the good Mr. iagglethorpe.'&#xD;
Do you know what that-that young&#xD;
gentleman's name -is, Guardy ?" asked1Fifine.&#xD;
"The young man that cones at might with&#xD;
the remarkably fine complexion .,&#xD;
"Yes, and the brown eyes," added the&#xD;
young girl eagerly, "and the beautiful curly&#xD;
hair."&#xD;
itim as come the fust night with most an&#xD;
elegant looking lady on to his arm ?"&#xD;
&#xD;
" Ye-es." But her tone was not so buoy-&#xD;
ant as before.&#xD;
" I do not; nor do I wish to know. Why&#xD;
should I?  Our paths air different. Let me&#xD;
go soy way-him his'n. Above all, let him&#xD;
leave you alone severely. lied better ! Ile&#xD;
will find that you air an ernolaly."&#xD;
"What is that, Guardy, dear? Nothing bad,&#xD;
I hope ?" And the great blue eyes looked up&#xD;
frightened.&#xD;
"No, dear. It means that although you&#xD;
air a goddess, you air virtoos. Most of them&#xD;
goddesses wuzn't ; at least so I've licerd. Let&#xD;
him keep his sheep's eyes to himself.  As I&#xD;
sail afire, he'd better.&#xD;
The door way opene lastily and Mrs. Bag-&#xD;
'glethorpe, fat and breathless, it her head&#xD;
iside.&#xD;
"Why don't you come, you two .   Wel&#xD;
le awfill late. Xotrindg tilt at half past seven&#xD;
lptecisel1y now,11, din it yout PIggle ? It's seven&#xD;
11mw, and smy black velvet hiod' is so tieht,&#xD;
and it takes h11(11 a time to hooli it'."&#xD;
They 'nent at once, for to le late at the&#xD;
theatre was an iie\cisable tliing. They ar-&#xD;
nved at the hall quite breathless. There was&#xD;
no private entrance for the performers, anl&#xD;
at the pulie entrance they found the hand-&#xD;
some10 . tton itatn u aitinig oiuitide. He seemed&#xD;
greatly eliharras-cid as they approached, l)it-&#xD;
stod lsi ground, and Mr. \laggletlhorpe, as lie&#xD;
passed, gave hon a scorching look, nearer an'&#xD;
ger than one would have deemed fiose pudgy&#xD;
old features capable of. - Mrs. iagglethorpe,&#xD;
with the kntnledge that she had now only&#xD;
about a quarter of an hour in which to pass&#xD;
through the various stages which lav between&#xD;
her present self and Quccnshiip, did not notice&#xD;
hiltm, or indeed any thing whatever, except that&#xD;
her good husband was a msonstrotus length of&#xD;
time in scraping his feet on the lower step.&#xD;
Will Gentry, gaming at the queer couple and&#xD;
smiling slightly, did not at first look at Fifine&#xD;
so that the girl had ample opportunity to silr-&#xD;
vey hint at her ease. She felt sure this young&#xD;
mian was not wicked ; that lie did not think&#xD;
ill of her for standing there nightly on her&#xD;
goddess-like throne to be stared at by the&#xD;
gaping crowd.   Ile'knew it was necessity.&#xD;
Do you not know it is necessity ? asked her&#xD;
warm young heart, eagerly yearning to com-&#xD;
mnune with his.&#xD;
He turned his eyes on her now-those soft&#xD;
&#xD;
brown eyes of which his mother was so proud.&#xD;
She had uttered no sound ; he uttered none.&#xD;
And vet her question was answered. He knew&#xD;
it was Iecessity  lie understood lier and her&#xD;
po ition -he respected her, he loved her ;&#xD;
wouldlhe give him her love in return ? And&#xD;
then and there she aid yes, and gave its, and&#xD;
still there was nothing uttered.&#xD;
All this oeeipied but a few seconds of time.&#xD;
'he good Mr. IBagglethorpe, still frowning at&#xD;
&#xD;
the voung mall, turned and, almost roughly,&#xD;
pushed the goddess in. Unknown to line,&#xD;
as she passed lby, the younmllii1:111 gently tulle-&#xD;
ed her dress  ithi his hand ; and(whe1i shite&#xD;
had gone and the 1oor had closed upon him,&#xD;
shutting him oit in the street, Wllie lift id&#xD;
his ingeri to his lips and tenderly k ssed them&#xD;
at their tips where they had coie i contact&#xD;
with his Peri's robe.&#xD;
&#xD;
TI:AT1T1 iV.&#xD;
'IIll I}. SW  .'i'c  I  1.I  IN I llTHE, lit'  VtEl'I.&#xD;
&#xD;
Tlsirtnitht wuas noti tint on wideh Will&#xD;
Gent t'hatl followedl the The-sptiais hoil t&#xD;
lollots -i the II nt early, uoSihle in the i&#xD;
l u-  t  alotste  uin ilin 'st a otste , tryml tg i l&#xD;
tlace s -ftutuet on the  aitvinlill tos,  i N  h11 ith h)lti&#xD;
111+ t d  Th 1  ,'I1is nas m  t the fir~t night hle&#xD;
had i t u t after tith emu  at a dit i tm e, i  ati -ill, inl&#xD;
~ ;, ft t  ll tu   ti tl iii  pats ()' a1, i+i'  liet', iul  tout  s  i it,&#xD;
thi(0ill  u t t lt ut' lis  5t i'nt  i think  li-t ))it u'  i  -&#xD;
-                 bl1;=ft  lHt()1.11,0 0  10did  110t Vi-h1&#xD;
h   - t-intuttifoil lij  \\'What 'isould they&#xD;
it -ntme his  h  'ugs to  i'?  Nt',  l ull ii,&#xD;
hahhe wisihid the girl to set hint. I t'ihal&#xD;
"t ibi-iti1uuserved aiunetar'teularli hI aont ie au it&#xD;
dice t- (whicl he dared scarcelyt hop'e-,) tlictt&#xD;
(wiig  a   nlilt  track ig  her at nIlut h t, i  ita  it -lo&#xD;
1    le  i ns  u -a lnStree t,i snt  - itigl 1tofeelalarmtic  lii'&#xD;
he Saifety'of 1her' purse---lways pre-1miln&#xD;
. she had oneit(, wh ich was doubtful; and if' 6 a&#xD;
/oi obrerved hun Iiiiit waS lighly probable shit&#xD;
would legal-IhIs fl- o llniitg her as al tutju ti&#xD;
fid  a-tctn  debitt ate imthes(  i xtrntil-.&#xD;
SButto ni-ht it was diil'eet. Oh '  sto-ight&#xD;
was removed a thousands years from tithu ight&#xD;
which began twenty four long hours ago&#xD;
To-simghit he knew Tier, and she knew hint.&#xD;
Had not their eyes met-and tenderly met-at&#xD;
the door of the Temple now to hint as sacred&#xD;
as that which was reared by the hands of the&#xD;
gods on Parnassus' Ieighit .&#xD;
To-night, when the moonbeams played on&#xD;
the lonely and ill-paved streets, and threw,&#xD;
besides those three shadows walkmig abreast,&#xD;
another, lengthened and distorted, perhaps to&#xD;
&#xD;
atiusei the 51 as srdi1 LutLna it a lfitfid lmood,&#xD;
W11 G;ntIy 11,(, n11l)unIto "&#xD;
sign or conee1lJ,  m i ll) hog ut \w.11.01on holuldy,&#xD;
tollowingth -t  in-it on ii,1t.&#xD;
The  iti d  Mr..' ittt h rIft itthet.ter-&#xD;
natutredl than \wa, 1L, w out, INwltOnte fat hand1&#xD;
clidi'ih  tightly  11111 the  ptuwlse:, ubic  h ld&#xD;
Ow  n ghes  ga ;1in5,  w aslaughtt;in wlya;)111, and  ,&#xD;
te"lling t1"the u two nonwn  remethlingf aboul1 t on&#xD;
'th   -litine lutw not uhaliit. liiir 1sar. 1&#xD;
.mi     li0t' s ill-li  ,tti1-ttt  ilftn I   ""itl i-i&#xD;
whn I lltin ii heIri itlwiad, ,Willelinitryblew&#xD;
a  i  to  Ilr \w1hi("h1  nau hi1t y  . )1 n1\\; i11d&#xD;
l  1tor 1,i 1 in  a  li1  tonl " th1 yor  1'' l i ,&#xD;
null 1be down t utnl si  tou   os i'f y uiitt 't ltoo&#xD;
r1tt11'  tutu  i'  a "Oinl' t    tih'  MI: o i\O'f  tat&#xD;
ohi1  1 t itt (i f iu ,  tuior   b 1 t a n - , i1.(&#xD;
Aut Idotelngerei, eu-it tor naluiiltti'ii&#xD;
anhey aissced the faliltales nithMr. t A;1)&#xD;
w'm  Mr laggthlthorpe oiwnhd thle diiisr.  ioo&#xD;
t d agle tlier , ftog ed ait los-it' wi-reh&#xD;
xtin ohea    ilte , asi-"r  maltlpil,&#xD;
-,md4l devastated  in anl.a1:lllt.ri n anne11r dilnnll&#xD;
the evening)) wearily trudged up1 the step-&#xD;
but 1' ine11 lin c1red1, east another dans h' e&#xD;
hind, saw again the broad-shouldered forum&#xD;
swin ' ig along in its manly grace, with avr&#xD;
m~oolhnamslancing over the snowy forehea&#xD;
tand dallying on the faultless mouth.  And&#xD;
when Mr. 'BIagglethorp~e shut the door, the&#xD;
gddess, feeling as if hope and love were alko&#xD;
shut ot, began to cry ; and Mr. Uagglethorpe,&#xD;
&#xD;
Ii FIFI- E'S Fo O TSTEFS.           11&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7111-00000007"/>&#xD;
It2           TIlE GOOD Aul?. BA. GLIBtT'OJP.                          1. u(LTIIFJ[l'4IICOS&#xD;
&#xD;
greatly distressed, took her in his arms and&#xD;
carried her up-stairs, erroneously attributing&#xD;
her lowness of spirits to-tight shoes.&#xD;
No, it was not the first night Will Gentry&#xD;
had followed them home. le had done that&#xD;
every night'since-and excepting--that Iirst&#xD;
urie on which he had first seen her.&#xD;
But this was the first night lie had lin-&#xD;
gered about the house after they had entered&#xD;
it-lingered till the mnioon, Which was low&#xD;
when they left the hall, had morunite(l high in&#xD;
the heavens, and was pouring lown streams&#xD;
of glory, silvering the three clean tree ,&#xD;
c'aus:ng their bare branches to appear as it'&#xD;
touched hv a fairy's wand-decoratiog the&#xD;
poor, clean lhoiu'es across the unay-thxrowinig&#xD;
weir I shadois over the great brick'hou:i&#xD;
itself-lauhlig i derision at Mlrs. laipp'a&#xD;
presrrnpt liiuous dooir nlate - inellowm og tihe&#xD;
sharp a 1(1iartistic outlines of the iise&#xD;
of pray r, till the defective edifice  wmiied&#xD;
almost as beautiful as a Grecian fnie- paling&#xD;
the flickering light brnmi  in the waking&#xD;
irl' s rooirim-- ing a saving im the gas&#xD;
bills of the suburban town, and kissing&#xD;
Edyl(lnnilln aleep on a hianik.&#xD;
lfine knew -that he was there.  A. dozen&#xD;
tines -he repressed the dresiie which prompt-&#xD;
ed her to go to the window and look out.&#xD;
She had been too bold with this young ian;&#xD;
she felt it  it was wrong to look at him&#xD;
steadily--she lare(l not say lovingly---as -she&#xD;
had done   to-night at the hall entramice.&#xD;
What mnust he think of her&#xD;
Still he stood below, gazing up at her&#xD;
W ninlow.  Ie had Seen! Mrs. Bagglethorpe&#xD;
m1ov iing about in a lower rooimi, and had&#xD;
waited to Sec a light appear in aln-e. Ther&#xD;
light alippeai-rel, and then he waited to see it&#xD;
extiniguishel ; and, waiting for tlis, the hour&#xD;
waxd 1elate&#xD;
Willie, outside, Said  Al !Oiicome to the&#xD;
window !" and Fliine, ahoi e, anlost as it'&#xD;
she heard lis prayer, said decisively, (to&#xD;
whom( did she speak ?) "I-will not go to&#xD;
the window !"'&#xD;
Anid midnight passed arnl another day&#xD;
w biorn noiscs-.li.&#xD;
I i- hall not go till she  comess' said&#xD;
W illie, out-idc. "' I shall not look out till he&#xD;
is ginie," sail lFitine, above.&#xD;
And the hahy day grew older and strong-&#xD;
cr, and the gre -bsard moon began to die -&#xD;
&#xD;
and a lady in One Thousandth street, waking&#xD;
suddenly from her sleep, crept rip to a room&#xD;
above, and, finding the bed empty, fell on&#xD;
her knees and wept, and lifting her face to&#xD;
heaven, cried, ' 0   my God ! slhieltl my&#xD;
boy !"&#xD;
Fifino cane to the window at last.  Amiid&#xD;
Iet lie tsaw wr nhe i passionately kissed his&#xD;
Ihanls to her; anil what could she do, seeing&#xD;
this, buot touch her ow n lips ligh tly with her&#xD;
rosy fingers, and quickiv pull her- window-&#xD;
curtain down? &#xD;
his soul aglow  with happiness, the young&#xD;
roan liastened1 hou-.m&#xD;
His mother was up, and waiting for hin.&#xD;
Willie !" silie si(l, an(l her hand was&#xD;
cold, like ice, as sie grasped his wartiwrist,~&#xD;
what is the ieinariiig if tis ?"&#xD;
"f f n hat ? 'Of toy berig out-rather-&#xD;
lit ? .\ A! yio 1iaven't liitbeen axions about&#xD;
tie, have toiu, mriother ini dear ? lii' so sorry !&#xD;
Iliit you shouldn't worry ---o  kinowii iiyoi&#xD;
sl   lhin't. I'im always all right, you kiov.&#xD;
Nothing ever hmpci'iii utoi ln e.&#xD;
Anl he stroveto kiss her, 1bnut r te r epudlse i&#xD;
hinii, fr she was deeply worinled.' A&#xD;
greatly as she had bloe:icen alariied four ii&#xD;
safety, so greatly now Was ie aioundeinld ta&#xD;
his has iig caused-I needless pain.&#xD;
" I nve Non reniched tie a1 age," she said,&#xD;
her voice   trebtlinig, as  lid  her frame,&#xD;
when   younrig  iel think it manly to be&#xD;
iete ard lepraved  '&#xD;
"(I shioniuln't telIl nio  of it if .I hal, lie&#xD;
r-1plied, angered at herl ioubting himi, anti&#xD;
yit unwillirng to give her a confidence whih&#xD;
would clear away her doubts.   " You have&#xD;
N 'ringed in', mother-I di1 rot expect it of&#xD;
you."  And turning, le left iier, for the first&#xD;
time in hip life, without a gooi-night kiss.&#xD;
Her ringer vanished instantly ;a great sor~&#xD;
row tusged at her achling-! heart, and nearly&#xD;
dranged her ito her knees. Oi !this she&#xD;
oribl not hear'  IIt r hoe, her beauty - what&#xD;
eve' lend come to Hirim, waes lie not her' dar-&#xD;
linr still?&#xD;
Willie !"-a cry if angruisih in the iiglit&#xD;
and as he heard it, he shuddered, stopped.,&#xD;
and sprang back into her outstretched arms.&#xD;
Ilis good, good other ! Iis own sweet&#xD;
mnno: her! What were new loves compared to&#xD;
hers ?  What, indeed&#xD;
&#xD;
Muclh-very much ! ~ Enough to keep him   late at breakfast, and behindhand with lis&#xD;
awake for almost the remainder of that     entire day's work in the counting-room of&#xD;
nrearly-gone night ; and when at last he fell  Pearson &amp;amp; Co&#xD;
ai-eep, he dreamed again of Fiiue, and was&#xD;
 P CICIAT )     TE&#xD;
&#xD;
hitinaN iHome in the ho.rse-cars late in the&#xD;
afternoon, Will Gentry reviewed the situa-&#xD;
tion. He could not flatter hinnself hlie was&#xD;
beloved by such a beautiful creature-o he&#xD;
said -but every tme he said it there was a&#xD;
tinerntal contradiction of his words.  But&#xD;
whether she loved him or not, one thing was&#xD;
certain, he loved her, ianl he must adopt&#xD;
some plani to forl her acquaintance. Younrg&#xD;
arid romanitie as lie wa, lie nevertheless knew&#xD;
that lie could not be hangign i about her win-&#xD;
mIn x',ixrv  night at the risk of taking a&#xD;
dreadful ll, and worrying his poor mother&#xD;
util her very nature u as change to hitter-&#xD;
SI mist make her acquaintance !     lie&#xD;
,titd.&#xD;
&#xD;
But hoxy           ,&#xD;
Diplomac.y&#xD;
The  (youg lilploimite had evidently ar-&#xD;
raniged is plains before reaching IIar nixihurg;g&#xD;
fr so soonum as lie arrived there, he soumghit the&#xD;
fasihioiialble prneinets favored by the This-&#xD;
liars, arid, walking up boldly to Mr-s. Rapp's&#xD;
miaision, nung that worthy person's bell&#xD;
istily.&#xD;
S 's Mr. Bagglethorpe within l" he asked&#xD;
of the clean servant.&#xD;
"Yes, sir ; walk in, please. Take a seat&#xD;
in the parlor. What tiarn shall I say ''&#xD;
Net en' ind the na ime. Siy a gentleman&#xD;
wiles to ee him."&#xD;
The irl vanished. Will Gentry nervously&#xD;
paced the floor.&#xD;
It's extraordinary how nervous I am !'&#xD;
lie muruniired. " I feel exactly as if I had&#xD;
come to steal somietliing."&#xD;
Mr. llaggletholrpe, who entered Iat the io-&#xD;
intent, looked as if ie antlo thought the young&#xD;
mn1111'i designs were of a nefarious chara-ter.&#xD;
lie remembered Will, and. he thought of&#xD;
&#xD;
itiie, and thet he thought of   ifinr  iiand&#xD;
Will together ; and    then h e thoIglht he&#xD;
didt t like lds thoughts.&#xD;
Will took the bull by the Iuhorns-the good&#xD;
Mr. Bagglethorple by the hands.  Ilis resolu&#xD;
tion rose with the' ermerrgenrv.&#xD;
This is-I know it i-      lie burst out,&#xD;
with a gish of entithuiasni, " the good Mr.&#xD;
Bagglethorpi'e&#xD;
" Viry  busy just now, please,.    What&#xD;
triight be your business  with me, kind sir ?"&#xD;
My business is-is very important," and&#xD;
Will shook the listless hand of the good1 Mn.&#xD;
hiagglethorpe eiordially, and his own he.i&#xD;
myo stcriously.&#xD;
Andil then there was a leadil pae'.&#xD;
'Well," said Mr. 1agglethorpre, with a&#xD;
sly twinkle in ihis eye, " perhaps iou'l tel&#xD;
inn' Nat it is somiiei timtie along toward ,li lat&#xD;
ter part of next week."&#xD;
' 1-iiteinde eI to ti-il you itt !&#xD;
" Well, who's a hriniderirn' oirnu, iiy rash&#xD;
young fr iend---who's a hilderini' on you"&#xD;
Thus encouraged-----prmly errnourglh, it im-ist&#xD;
be c oiessed-the young  dipilomiia In'egain&#xD;
again.&#xD;
I called oiln youti this afterfnon--''&#xD;
Evenini' ," corrected 111r. .&#xD;
 Mr. hagglethoipe, to e xpress-that is to&#xD;
saiy, with a puirpose-"&#xD;
A  porpoise '" repeated   the old man,&#xD;
looking carefully about the room.   I don't&#xD;
sce 11nporpoise.&#xD;
A purpose I say, Mr. Bagglethorpe--not&#xD;
a  oirpoise ; a purpose. In otheii' woniS, -&#xD;
I want to gin on tihe stage."&#xD;
I)ttmanrs of this Linil were freiinently&#xD;
iiade to the iraniagen', geinelly by incor-&#xD;
petentt par tie , and the good MIr. 1i ggle&#xD;
thorpe ha cop)osedt  a   nSpeech to fit thi.&#xD;
emergency, whenever and wherever it tiiouil&#xD;
&#xD;
1  Ii. r ,1  ; r L  Tll( Ii l'I; II:lS   sr-sii ioyl .&#xD;
&#xD;
'&#xD;
t&#xD;
e  Y&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7111-00000008"/>&#xD;
14             THE GOOD 3R. IIGGLETIORPE.&#xD;
&#xD;
arise. This was a proper occasion for the&#xD;
delivery of his speech; and he began de-&#xD;
livering it accordingly, in a graceful attitude,&#xD;
with the thumb of his left hand inserted in&#xD;
the armhole of his waistcoat on that side,&#xD;
and his other hand waving serenely in the&#xD;
"It is a thankless spear of life, my aspirin',,&#xD;
young friend--a thankless spear ! Genus is&#xD;
rarely reco'nised. Look at Mis Bagglethorpe.&#xD;
Talent goes fer naught!    Look   at Lar&#xD;
Peeteete Feefeene." (Ai! thought Will, I&#xD;
have looked at her until I am crazy !)  Be-&#xD;
sides that, the art itself stands low. It hedn't&#xD;
orter. It is a grand art. A noble callin'&#xD;
As high in ev'ry way, ef not higher, than&#xD;
paintin' and sculptoorin' and Iakin' photy-&#xD;
graphs.  But it is not so received. The&#xD;
limited intellergence of the general pubhi-~&#xD;
who is, ef you will pardon the expression, a&#xD;
mule-the limited intellergence of the genial&#xD;
public, I repeat, has put it lower than it orter&#xD;
be put. But what can I do for vou, miy young&#xD;
friend Y  Did you aspire to tread] the imnie&#xD;
boards at Young Men's Hall7"&#xD;
t       l" !no ! No, no !" said Will quickly.&#xD;
Tread the boards at Young Men's Hall, in-&#xD;
deed !iHe would as soon have thought of'&#xD;
walking a plank. What would his mother&#xD;
say to such an act as that ?-what his father ?&#xD;
-what all Iliarlynburg ?&#xD;
" Then wat T' said   Mr. Bagglethorpe&#xD;
sternly.&#xD;
" The truth is," stammered Will, hh ishi ng&#xD;
fearfully at his awkwardness in treading the&#xD;
devious paths of diplomacy, " what I wished&#xD;
just at present was, to-a-take a few les-&#xD;
sons in elocution and-a-that sort of thin,&#xD;
you know. I thought you would-that is,&#xD;
might le-willing to give them   to me,&#xD;
and--"&#xD;
I do not act,' said Mr. Iaggletlhorpe,&#xD;
interrupting, and leaning back in his chair&#xD;
Imajestically, "I manage.&#xD;
" Ye " returned Will, " I am aware of&#xD;
that. But perhaps-that is, I thought per-&#xD;
haps one of the- ladies of your f ainly, both&#xD;
so talented and beautiful," (and Willie, thmik-&#xD;
ing only of Fifine, laid great stress on the&#xD;
last word,) " night perhaps undertake, to in-&#xD;
struct me in this difficult art."&#xD;
Did you?" said Mr. Bagglethorpe stern-&#xD;
ly, all the more sternly because he felt his&#xD;
&#xD;
sympathies going out very strongly toward&#xD;
this good-looking young man, with his kind&#xD;
honest face. "Did you  '&#xD;
"Yes, sir; and believe me, sir, any re-&#xD;
muneration you might name I would cheer-&#xD;
fully give."  And now it was Will's turn to&#xD;
lean back- majestically in his chair, uttering&#xD;
this Rothsehildian speech.&#xD;
" I suppose I might speak to Mis Baggle-&#xD;
thorpe about it," said Mr. B. reflectively.&#xD;
-  Oh! do-! Please do! Speak to them&#xD;
Both! Say that I am most anxious to study&#xD;
handet. I think [ could play him finely.&#xD;
Where hie ru-hes on, you know, and says,&#xD;
A horse ! a horse   Imy kingdom   for a&#xD;
horse!&#xD;
" Ihnulet don't say that nowhere," ob.-&#xD;
served the mamniger'.&#xD;
rell, then, somebody    does, if he&#xD;
doesn't."&#xD;
" You may bet on that,' conceded Mr.&#xD;
Bagglethorpe.&#xD;
''hen you will speak about it to the&#xD;
ladies-to Mrs. Baggletlhorpe, and to your-&#xD;
olIi--''&#xD;
My ward ?"&#xD;
Yes, sir."&#xD;
"I'll see about it."&#xD;
"'T'hank  you," said  Will, with hearty&#xD;
gratitude i his tone.  " And when may 1&#xD;
comle again?"&#xD;
' To-morrow, if you like."&#xD;
And the ladies will be here&#xD;
They'll see atiout it."&#xD;
(1i ! thank you !  ood  'venig  Mi&#xD;
Batglethorpe. Indeed, indeed, I thank you&#xD;
for your goodness. And Will Gentry w rung&#xD;
the o1(1 man's hand until every trace of the&#xD;
original ill-feeling had disappeared, and the.&#xD;
warni old heart glowed to the core.&#xD;
("olod-by, sir; and thank you again and&#xD;
again. I will conic at this hour to-morrow."&#xD;
"\Well, well," soliloquized Mr. Baggle-&#xD;
thorpe, as lie stood at the window and&#xD;
watched young Gentry out of sight. " It's as&#xD;
ea y to see through that young fuller as&#xD;
nothit'.  e take lessons in  ellereution&#xD;
What lie wants is lessons in plavim' R')oo&#xD;
No doubt lie thort lie hed hamboozled the&#xD;
old man quite satisfac rily. I guess not, my&#xD;
bloonmin' young friend ! I guess not l' But&#xD;
the good Mr. Baggletlhorpe is good. le is&#xD;
not the man to stand between the hap-&#xD;
&#xD;
A x IA1PI U[PI.                               1,)&#xD;
Av                               r' .  ,  .                                1,&#xD;
-   pines of his feller-creatures; w'en its hon.  panes, "ef it an't honest, I'll kill von as I&#xD;
est. And of it can't honest,' thundered the  would a snake, my han'some young trouba-&#xD;
4    old man, shaking his fist at the iindow-  dour, for all your good-looks !'&#xD;
CHAPTER VII.&#xD;
TILE ('IIAItDED CIRCLE.&#xD;
&#xD;
V  i GENTY manifested but little dramatic&#xD;
talent.  In vain Mrs. Baggletliorpe enetla-&#xD;
vored to instill into his mind the rudiments&#xD;
of the sacred art. All to no ppt'ilose! Il-e&#xD;
was cont' when lie should have been sad-&#xD;
lugubrious wlien lie should have been ga'.&#xD;
lie could not remember the text of' his&#xD;
author-lie could not forget the fact of Fi-&#xD;
fine's sitting opposite hi in lieu of an audi-&#xD;
ence. It is true the goddess said she thought&#xD;
he had hidii'rfiil talent; and so perhaps le&#xD;
had. lut the wonders of his talent were&#xD;
directed im other channels than  those of&#xD;
Thalia or Melpoimete. Thte wonders of his&#xD;
talent had tmanifested themselves principally&#xD;
in the art by which he had obtained a fiot-&#xD;
hold in the poor hiotie of the Thelspiaiis-the&#xD;
charmed irele where dwelt his beautiful&#xD;
go~ddess.&#xD;
his foothold was firmuu now-firimer perhaps&#xD;
than he lutiaginled, or hua'l at firet dart-i to&#xD;
hope lie could make it.&#xD;
At length the lessons were   abandoned.&#xD;
MIrs , Iigletlorpe assured her pupil that lie&#xD;
had better stick to the bookkeeping, fiir an&#xD;
actor he would never titahe.&#xD;
I  a pity, Mu. (einterv,' said the good&#xD;
t oiaii coiipassionaiitely, " bit I'tm afeard you&#xD;
never woutlt get   eh l  ;;respectable utility&#xD;
"Wat'sl that ? asked Will.&#xD;
"Why, don't son know what respectable&#xD;
.             .  -  .  ,                l&#xD;
utility is .  Dehiverim' messen'mies.&#xD;
'lelcraphie -miessages?'' iputired Will,&#xD;
with a merry twimkle i his ey.&#xD;
F ~     'No, no.  ' My lord, the carriage waits, ' or&#xD;
uluain, a letter.' "&#xD;
Oha, iang te if I'd be a foot-boy for&#xD;
any bodyl," said Will.&#xD;
That's what we call respeetabl' utility,''&#xD;
canmitittiel Mrs. Baggletholpe.  " less  oui&#xD;
But few getsfar beyond it; and half of them&#xD;
&#xD;
which do have into right to.  It's a most une-&#xD;
countal)le thing that peple wliehl t't inl&#xD;
the least fitted for it tvill rush into the per&#xD;
fession itn the iiost extraordinary numbers.&#xD;
Now Idon't call myself fitted for it.-"&#xD;
" hut the public do-the liiihlie d, im-&#xD;
meelver' interrtiited the good lMr. I aiggle&#xD;
thorle admiringly.&#xD;
" Yes, dear, they (1o, I confess 'i. Through&#xD;
the tmoedujtin of the public press I have often&#xD;
received   the intist flattering i  nottimium tls.&#xD;
Still, Iy dear" conttiued the 'Jlly ol soul,&#xD;
aldressiing ier husband puointedly. ' did yo&#xD;
eitr 0bseve that the piper's whlilt spoke&#xD;
highest inl myt1' praise was invariably theit&#xD;
n here w'e not tuu Ihandhills s 'it'ulk os"th'&#xD;
Inuniteelyet !'' said the good Mr. iaggle.&#xD;
thtorp", with more severity iin his tone thtati&#xD;
was usual with himt ; 'do you miie:m to throv&#xD;
a slirti onto the hiess?  Woubl you iu it to in-&#xD;
for that a otnuas could lie iuo nr1"&#xD;
" li', lklggley, wIto said a nol ibot  or.&#xD;
tant ?  t' tie I didn 't.  I w ait't i bi ui '&#xD;
of limit it ill thiuahi I  ni-t say I ihvu:t&#xD;
liked thi' mutic uam il thought l 1' vers'&#xD;
foolish to gruiible at 'em so.  What I mtean&#xD;
is this. Don't ''onyou r eibr' whti F\  was&#xD;
pii mi' il Mulld 11'10 C  th at on of the pa-&#xD;
hpers said they  wisth til' ' uild1per lll&#xD;
the worthy Mis iagglethotp' that tt' , ae&#xD;
was not heri oationi ; itoh the thv-u  i'eryn'\t&#xD;
day after  inu had orled     me"hi-i ig llr&#xD;
posters at their job printiimi-oliiee, how they&#xD;
retmarket1 easually that as (Sph/ l  Mis Bag'&#xD;
glethorpi' was the /oau odred of th i ho4t's&#xD;
fann l "&#xD;
" What a'tonishiniig iu'inconsi'tstency ' Jacl-&#xD;
hated Will Gentry.&#xD;
Who amongst its is not wenlial '" ituiuired&#xD;
the good Mt. lagglethorpe-&#xD;
" Vena1 l, (ad'yhv, " suiggestedl Fitini'.&#xD;
That's what I mean, hdear," "till the old&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7111-00000009"/>&#xD;
16                    THE   GOOD 31R.&#xD;
man, smoothing the girl's curls. "XWho&#xD;
amongst us as disdains to look out for num-&#xD;
her one ?  1 don't. Ef the public wants the&#xD;
legitimate drainy, I gives it to them good-na-&#xD;
tured; ef the public wants the sensational, I&#xD;
gives that to them equally good-natured.&#xD;
That's my policy.&#xD;
If I were the public, I should want noth-&#xD;
ing but allegories," said Will Gentry, looking&#xD;
at Fifine, who blushed.&#xD;
" Because, sir, you have poetic taste. Be-&#xD;
cause, sir, you appreciate high art.  But&#xD;
alas ! sir, there is few like you."&#xD;
"Few   indeed !'' echoed  Mrs. Baggle-&#xD;
thorpe.&#xD;
"There are none !" said Filine, but in so&#xD;
&#xD;
TnE: fun was at its height the next night&#xD;
wx ien they arrived at th' sk ating-pond. Theleaf-&#xD;
less braichies of' the w intry trees were hung&#xD;
With Chinese lanterns ; a small brass band&#xD;
was blowing away lustily at a valse iiove-&#xD;
tent from  (t Buullo, while on the ice, clad&#xD;
in the ctstutmet'S of all civilized  and icivil-&#xD;
ized nations was asseimibled the whole skatiin'-&#xD;
iadl coiimuntihty of Ilarlynburg.&#xD;
") Lor !" said Mrs. Bagglethorpe, " it&#xD;
looks xvonderfullike the green-room of a large&#xD;
theatre, don't it, dear ?"&#xD;
" I ius' say I never sor a green-room with&#xD;
ice on the floor,'' said Mr. lktgglethere.&#xD;
"No-nor with Chinese lanterns hung&#xD;
about," remarked Fitine.&#xD;
Don't youtthink it is a prtty sight ?"&#xD;
asked Will Gentry of the girl.&#xD;
"Well--yes." she answered    with sonic&#xD;
hesitation, " rather pretty. I think any other&#xD;
ptersot would enjoy it more than I.   The&#xD;
truth is, it makes te wretched to see all&#xD;
thtesex shabby costumes. It reminds me of&#xD;
Tyself in the allegory.  How cold they must&#xD;
be, too ! Just as I aitu'hien I stand on the&#xD;
goddess's pedestal, and shiver."d&#xD;
" Ii te to see you standing there," said&#xD;
Will angrily.&#xD;
&#xD;
BAG GL ETIIORr'i;&#xD;
&#xD;
low a tone that no one heard her enthusiastic&#xD;
comment.&#xD;
" To change the subject," said Will gayly,-&#xD;
for the truth is, I never could ear to have&#xD;
compliments poked at me-will you go with&#xD;
me to the skating carnival to-morrow night?&#xD;
A sort of masked ball on the ice, you know&#xD;
they say it will be a jolly afluir."&#xD;
"But our moral dramy '" said Mr. Baggle-&#xD;
thorpe.&#xD;
"And our allegory ?" said Fify.&#xD;
" Time enough to go when they are over.&#xD;
I'll be waiting for you at the door after the&#xD;
performance, if you'll on'y say you'll go."&#xD;
They said they would go ; they all said&#xD;
they would go very gladly.&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
n&#xD;
c&#xD;
L&#xD;
a&#xD;
r'&#xD;
Y&#xD;
t+ s&#xD;
"t&#xD;
\t'"&#xD;
i&#xD;
n      i&#xD;
, := roc&#xD;
&#xD;
-To be sure ! Ilow thoughtless of me to&#xD;
keep you standing in the cold !" said Will.&#xD;
Cole in there, Mrs. iagglethorpe,' leading&#xD;
the way to some covered benches.  ' Wn't&#xD;
you have a glass of souethitng hota&#xD;
No, Mr. Gentry; but thank you ijst the&#xD;
Aid Mt. Bagglethiorpe ': ins uiired Will.&#xD;
"Itm :a ,teetotaler, my son," r-eliid the&#xD;
good gentleinii, with a iparetal air, -' a tee-&#xD;
ttal teectotaler. .&#xD;
"So ai I,' said Will, " but I thought you&#xD;
tigthit be chilled. I am glad yott are not."&#xD;
IIe saw thiemi safely enseOnticet in a t1cornr&#xD;
fthe wooden tlhut, and thet felt tree to le ote&#xD;
linielt exclu-ivl cixto lFiline.&#xD;
What a 1itiy hdn't -aiite !"' li  aid.&#xD;
Yeci, isn't it ? 1 fancy I coniIuld t onlea.rn.&#xD;
Don't think slighltingly of me,01 Mr. Geint ry, be-&#xD;
caine I mn so ii'far lind iid other girls o tt'moy&#xD;
in all accomplishments ant    ac'inirt-&#xD;
mieti.  ltemiitbt'er what a pioort little xxit I&#xD;
am1."&#xD;
there r  gill-,  indeed  I ( ) !ther  g irls  can't&#xD;
liiii a caile to xi."''&#xD;
" 'There'sm ie holdings i hnter t i to '',"&#xD;
said Feefy', latughinug.&#xD;
A1 flining fenude l 'tigmeC, drsseaC  s a nisuan&#xD;
witht Turlki-h1 tron ,er.4 and .a jaun1ty Cap,) lung&#xD;
.froml a l mtern whviich sh-It hl, a gILeamc,1 inl&#xD;
F;iline 's face, and nwas gone.&#xD;
Why, that's-w ihuat-youtmay-call-it !" said&#xD;
W ill, partly recognizing the tace.&#xD;
tWlio ?"&#xD;
" -   n eiit thiik of her l nie now. Are&#xD;
your feet cld ?"&#xD;
\ o," siLiine11.&#xD;
Nell, hi-, I'll tell you  iwat tex cat do.&#xD;
You sit down iii this cihir, ad 1I'll push in&#xD;
over the ice. 1'l skate and pth you. )oi't&#xD;
you set' ?  The chair is ont rmmlers, and yoil&#xD;
antd I will whiz over the ice as though ie&#xD;
were going to market in IHollatid.   Comiie&#xD;
now.   Sit down."&#xD;
Fiine seated herself in the chair, and Will,&#xD;
after a last pull at his skate-straps, darted ofh&#xD;
at a rapid pace.&#xD;
" What fun !" cried Fifine.&#xD;
By and by they paused for breath.&#xD;
It a a beautiful sight !" exclaimed the&#xD;
gil.   " The Costumes don't look half so&#xD;
shabby now as they did at first. Perhaps it's&#xD;
because I'm more in the spirit of the thing&#xD;
&#xD;
T IL1T T VRK&#xD;
&#xD;
Why, sir, you astonish me!" said Mr.&#xD;
13agglethorpe, in an amazed tone ; "I thought&#xD;
you liked allegories.''&#xD;
"And so I do, but I don't like Fifine-that&#xD;
IS, I don't eitain that-I don't lie FI'inie--&#xD;
tut, tuit !-of course you know I don't mean&#xD;
that-but I Can't bfear Fiftine's stituing there&#xD;
to be start'ted at by a lot of iipulident young&#xD;
puppies.''&#xD;
, "I guer o/u at-c about the only toe'--" be'&#xD;
gait Mri. tBagglethorttp.&#xD;
"  W hy, wat are you tlk'in  about, Big.&#xD;
gley '" asked Mrs. B. in muazt-iuuetnwnt, for Will&#xD;
was a prime favorite with all.&#xD;
"I mean to say that I gue-s Mi. Center'&#xD;
is about the only onewholpays such particu-&#xD;
lar attention to the allegory. Without disre-&#xD;
spect to the talens of my dear Fi-efy, I must&#xD;
say that the allegory is looked upon by the&#xD;
general public as no great shakes."&#xD;
"Then the general public is a general dunce,"&#xD;
said Will, wounded at any lack of appreci.&#xD;
ation shown the goddess whom he appre-&#xD;
ciated so highly.&#xD;
O dear ! how cold my feet ate !" said&#xD;
Mrs. Bagglethorpe, stamping upon the ground&#xD;
with as much energy as her e oitunpoint would&#xD;
allow.&#xD;
&#xD;
CITAPIEIt, VIII.&#xD;
TIEI (AR NIVAL.&#xD;
&#xD;
Is   ICI iE RN.                         1 7i&#xD;
than I was. 0 dear ! Mr. Gentry---there's&#xD;
that Turkish person again !"&#xD;
The Turkish person was cutting a rose on&#xD;
the ice; and when this addition to Flora's&#xD;
possessions was fully completed, Ate skated&#xD;
rapidly up1) to Will Gentry and held her lantern&#xD;
in his face.&#xD;
"lood  evening, Mr. Gentry,' said the&#xD;
Turkish person, acconp:u n ing her saltitnat&#xD;
wx ith a terrv laugh.&#xD;
Good evetitng,' returned Will, till unt-&#xD;
decided inl regard to her identity v.&#xD;
"1'. don't pretend you don't know n,&#xD;
said tht 'Iurkish person, again laugh iinhg, w hilt&#xD;
1-ilinie looked on in strpirise. '' Thatt n ondld&#xD;
he ab-urd after tlie desperate tmtanttier in hlieht&#xD;
it flirted with me Christmas evening at 1ir.&#xD;
'le:irson's dinttter."&#xD;
SI flirttel with you ?  I  st next vou.  I&#xD;
ttitrtihter   io nowt-sot are Miss IFa. t hbhit.'&#xD;
- ' T e siue I ai. Ilow long I shall  re&#xD;
main so,   ditn't no.itwx .  Now, dlot't loch.&#xD;
aistonlished . This is 1leap-yeart, i n knowt, :ani&#xD;
more thian that, we areit at a skating tarnival,&#xD;
we l' lut-is are pritiligi-d to iay whx at ithi'&#xD;
like ; ,itl  ai  vi   all, as  I  said  befitre,  i)tII&#xD;
flirted xi ihi mii so outrageouly at .Mr. Pe:i--&#xD;
in's flt  lotr dtay, that Iti warranted it&#xD;
sit ing ainy thing to yoi."&#xD;
littleI" Filite  sat  iii  the  skatinig -clair  ;uii&#xD;
gasedil fori brtath.  low happy shlitlie hail et-i1&#xD;
hut a miiiottent blere ! Sio light-hit-irted, st&#xD;
exhilaratld, so gay !Ant ixnow--ntvx. She&#xD;
Ildh ot to the arms of the chair and listened&#xD;
aga:tin t o tiext ordinary revelatioins of t it&#xD;
Turkish pt-rson.&#xD;
" Yes toit give te tWine so oftn, don't xii&#xD;
remember ? And insiatid-onil imy ha ing all&#xD;
the truflie's oultof the honed 0turk'y,1don't you&#xD;
reminemltr   And the ice-craiti, r. e( nti&#xD;
-surely   1 ou iut recollect nour giving tie&#xD;
the little pink Cupid on the    top of the&#xD;
pedestal."&#xD;
Poor F"iline ! The pink Cupid was the&#xD;
strain' which broke the camel'is back. 'T'h1'&#xD;
wine and the truffles, and even the hiotnid&#xD;
turkey might hav been born, but the pink&#xD;
Cupid was thoroughly crutsling.&#xD;
With hot tears welling to h t'e e'1ts, but&#xD;
with a determined eft)t to keep t bititack,&#xD;
Fifine ptutit her hand and touctd the ski t&#xD;
of Will's overcoat,&#xD;
"Won't you please, Mr. Genttry, take mc&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7111-00000010"/>&#xD;
8                    TIIE  GOOD I.&#xD;
back to Mi'. Raglethorpe ?" she asked in a&#xD;
iupplicating  tone.&#xD;
" () dear ime !" ijaculated the Turkish&#xD;
person. " Excuse me, Mr. Gentry. I thought&#xD;
you were quite alone."&#xD;
The cruel girl ! The cruel flirting girl ! She&#xD;
had    iseen the  young book-keeper paling&#xD;
devoted attention to this pretty blue-el&#xD;
little nohody, and had determined to assert&#xD;
the superiority of lir own charms by bring-&#xD;
ing into her retinue the handsome face aid&#xD;
figure of Will Gentry.&#xD;
''No, I am not alone, Miss Fastbhlle,'' said&#xD;
Will, ending over Fif ine in a kind, protect,&#xD;
in  manner. " I am  not alone.  Will you&#xD;
he good enough to excuse me 7'&#xD;
' Ohl! 1with great please. I'e imore beaux&#xD;
here now tliani I know what to do with.  If,&#xD;
however, you  are0 going 'to take MEili-&#xD;
Miss-"'&#xD;
"c Fiftine,"said Will.&#xD;
" If you are going to tak  e 3Ms Miltlin back&#xD;
to her frictid Mr.-Mr.- "&#xD;
"Unigglethorpie."&#xD;
") dear !" and the 'l'ii  ipers liniekei&#xD;
(lut into a bringing Liu;h." What a funny&#xD;
nae ! I nover shall te able to pronounced&#xD;
that. But I was about to sa!, it V iiare&#xD;
going to take little Mi-u here hack toi iher&#xD;
friend, perhaps -  you'd like  to joiinour&#xD;
party'."&#xD;
"Exeuse me if I decline, and wish yo&#xD;
good eveiin, Miss Fast belle,"0 and Will tonc '&#xD;
ed isa skalting c:1p) and skated off, pusingli the&#xD;
chair before him.&#xD;
"Imphudent book-keepitng  clerk !" aid&#xD;
Miss Fatbtelle, as the two were lost in the&#xD;
crowd of skating   itasquertders.  " As if&#xD;
Kate Fa thelle would stOOp1) II)1/,,, except&#xD;
to ftlit with tyou for a hatf ani hlmr iv1so when&#xD;
he'd iintiin- better to do(&#xD;
"Miss F-itine," said Will to the  es,&#xD;
we must take op for lost tiimiet noW. I shan't&#xD;
stop again. Ilow extraordinary inl that young&#xD;
tila to act in that nanuer ! I at by hier&#xD;
i-ide at Mir. Pearson's grand dinner last month,&#xD;
and that's all. I never 1eipecteid to see her&#xD;
again."&#xD;
"Did y-ii give her a little iced pink thing?"&#xD;
ini1uired -iine anxiously.&#xD;
"Oh ! the Cupid ! Well, I believe I did.&#xD;
YOU sC the servant was handing ice-ereatil&#xD;
about, an of course I gave hei the ibest part&#xD;
&#xD;
B.1 1Y LETITOIPE.&#xD;
&#xD;
of it when hke held it to lme to hielp the lady&#xD;
who Sat next me."&#xD;
If it had lbeeii any thing but a Cupid,"&#xD;
sigled Fifine, thinking of the inferences that&#xD;
eight he drawn from a gift of the naughty&#xD;
little god of hearts.&#xD;
" I'm not sure it was a Cupid," said Will,&#xD;
ending over her from behind and skating&#xD;
gracefully and swiftly on one foot while the&#xD;
uthier was raised in air performing soie ballet~&#xD;
dancers gyrations.  "' IoW do you know i&#xD;
1 ipjidi froni--any oilier iiian-done in ice-&#xD;
iy his wing," said Fifine,&#xD;
" Wellithere, thiMttittl11 caphap none.  I&#xD;
remembuler particularly he luud none."&#xD;
" low w  it vou rieiieimb'er SO particular-&#xD;
I lit-em  I tc1remember lie had his hand to&#xD;
his iminutth, moi I thoughlti of little Jack&#xD;
Ilorniii1r wh1to at ini a corner, and put im l 1&#xD;
thimnhti, tint pulle1 m1it a pht;n1, and obieed-&#xD;
ih ! n hat a iood iotyi ant I" And Will laughed&#xD;
a t his own iionn.    "Now, I sholdnt&#xD;
hixe thouhttit of Jacky Ilorner if lie had had&#xD;
in g , -hould  I&#xD;
"No, I Sup~po"e not," -aid Fifine, whio'e&#xD;
equan)1ity Hadlbecoom fully relatalishted&#xD;
by the Irilliancv of thi exphaition.&#xD;
" What a ve-rv self-possessed young lady&#xD;
lhe is! said Filine..&#xD;
"  iis Ftastbeltle:?"&#xD;
"Ye"."&#xD;
Sl-tot 1).,:.e- ed  mShe's as hold as brass-&#xD;
k hold a  tra.,s!  Aii a flirt too-and&#xD;
what1'1 more, f..st.as lighltning.. That's the&#xD;
-til  tmw.  I  uppiose5 sotime mcnliki e f.t&#xD;
gill, but. for my part I detest them."&#xD;
I lm g-lad the goddess was in her heart that&#xD;
iii cite touild accuti lier of hieing fast ! And yet&#xD;
- the tail felt herself a poor stupid little thing&#xD;
while tthe.sell'possesed1 ; l i1fahilioaibtle ghut&#xD;
ihadt stood before i ticiii and chatted with Will&#xD;
(enitr v.&#xD;
Which wav shall we go ?"&#xD;
I think   e had better go hack to 3I-.&#xD;
aii dMrs. agglethorpe. They imay le getting&#xD;
tired."&#xD;
And so back tthey went to the woiodheni&#xD;
shed-.&#xD;
3r,;. Bagglethorpe said she was so glad&#xD;
they had conic, for it was time for all respect-&#xD;
able people to be it bed.&#xD;
&#xD;
-"It is all very well for a strong yoitgi&#xD;
gentleman like you, Mr. Gdenitry."i sali Mt-.&#xD;
Uagglethiorpe, ' to stay itp till attr iiliidiglit&#xD;
satinn; but it' you was a dellate  iong girl,&#xD;
you'd pirot'ly Ie moii ire keerful of youro' el.&#xD;
NOW, Feefy, itt-ver were Stron, and I ami&#xD;
bliiged to take te'r   precaution for her.&#xD;
Shall we No, Bagglet'&#xD;
&#xD;
Trviii  wer t' -oon at it Iotl( de i1p1.&#xD;
t ood i ght, 1myt't On," -tiiMr.-I a L&#xD;
thor i, t  i -out wi th   j tiiiae   'the t lni&#xD;
"todi-nitoht, and mauy'youeverhe ipp)-."&#xD;
"And hope yon will come 5to ;st;;us olent,&#xD;
thottgh  you i-lt  dicontill t  h -&#xD;
:th d.  ( 1'tt  ii., f klwintt'u herIi it  I suphMr-&#xD;
ia    stia'' ir:t .&#xD;
F iine linget-la  mowniitt it ii m  liway'.&#xD;
"  oo-i  M- r xcii  -' tit,.\it.l'try  il."&#xD;
i  Do 't cal   tI hat!t "  I  nhipetri 1(i-nt r&#xD;
(ar. 111anI11( W ill1t1 on't No'Si  I shl d&#xD;
O lotvetob catir iluld by wm  hrtt tii nta byt&#xD;
lt  gtt1f1i.uth  m -q&#xD;
"I feltwills dt tny  thing  to plef -  t ----&#xD;
WVillie'.-'&#xD;
i              aytim y 't   n i  a '-e  li' t t   imt li&#xD;
have! Ani i sutuch b  i itut, itl el! Thii et&#xD;
ti- t'mt hI tt-I\u x ti   i pli yit n  t th t lrt4'&#xD;
(.f  Libertyt,  Il - -  ll  I tol t el  hm  a  I&#xD;
feltxe&#xD;
She  ii  im ti'1ot s -   b t&#xD;
*heaui adirmati -ywitl h (-wr -o)n  ey"-e,  n'-t&#xD;
full on t. I o hi i s autich   a thtdi th clk ,iti-i&#xD;
(iny  -l ta -ft  hall 1,-. p!)&#xD;
"' I felt as thioit n  my who le life had11 cent r'd&#xD;
in yell.  That  tg u  wre  a (firstwom~n  w hlo&#xD;
leul over center( 11 my heart, and ithat there tiln&#xD;
would  remain  till m21d2 in2 d y. And  I'ift,&#xD;
I have never changed el inee. that night--(n&#xD;
cept that 1I02.0"01 tu'ore nd more."&#xD;
"Love ime, Willie  ? d o oulove nwo'&#xD;
Se e ld to the banisterm of the  stairs for&#xD;
support. It was such a auddenl declaration '.&#xD;
1Thy always-ar e.)&#xD;
&#xD;
Ot1' they started together-this Singiul:a&#xD;
square larty "-the fat old 11:1i manan tutu  In'af&#xD;
(I  w oiian in front, ild tie  letndieitir xmiiioun&#xD;
ian aind the -lender voumin i omian ielorty fot-&#xD;
hmninig behil.&#xD;
&#xD;
"t,  , I lt,'' itm  aiswereI vchemi intly  "I&#xD;
lvut-mititi sit iiw(hi lth  I i-art  thit t'f mitimi&#xD;
'io  t utn  I ont  tlt tu11 thit  I  ti-ti  tlul  Il&#xD;
--'"('11  -tuttuti  ut   t  l t  -,o1 i 7itiui  iii  ii ,'&#xD;
":ii l liY   i i  t i tt I misl t it t- tn   r- i&#xD;
i' 111  t11, 1111iii f I hi  :t  I  t  itium it'i x  i i  t&#xD;
ui   th"-.11 i i s i  i i rttl   l n-n1 ro n&#xD;
h     tlm  t.)  thit  n' , wi hn  in  tt  ii y    ntuit-t&#xD;
filltt -  t tliii :111 tit  i ii 7  itt uc  ii  -tirwt': lii&#xD;
longiiiint toti  i tutu her  trmu  a  uti' the  bi ii- t&#xD;
hit 1m11 hu'  ti-tx.tit,ium ix  i n '" lho  xi   de'1   -   it hI&#xD;
1  11    - 1 It ui t 1 l utittt- t&#xD;
S ine  ," i td W illie, I "I1'' uppo Io t   u1&#xD;
It) om t : l wm  any  amrts  (W '(."&#xD;
-. \\ hv, oh ! ntin  -  m  d 11m,  o l1, sm1v"1mu oh&#xD;
1'ii  it l ( I t,   tlltt hu --i  ii- I ii  i- itiiu iuit uI- tilt.&#xD;
"itt:, t, iii ounti x 1.1ly Itoe'ri-! Ii  1r'  ini&#xD;
ttl'ituthx }1t )l xI ii,   l itsi t il  Au Ii- i-,1 tt  it&#xD;
mant-t hats'11 h-  l tw  mune lt)  lv t ht  l w t I mi e&#xD;
11:  mal i er i w, mun' 1h1lv tlus  a 1(nm1&#xD;
:- t old t wii''  (mall I m i utha  -, ittu  'titti-&#xD;
11.1  -train"  l a  it  ll1&#xD;
'" t    jlli   e  y'ili'  '&#xD;
.\h1' the  bli-fu1 l  "in ,perienco  f'  ii 1'dear&#xD;
fir4-  1m11(' !- tllh,  Soonfold  jy  o Itli s  ir&#xD;
aim w11itt  of  it  M the  nitt  .rl  s h-1   e-nt  it' t&#xD;
,u  111'te  f  love.1's first luoi ous tt su gar phunI.&#xD;
"Well, ' you(11now? ITere! I task ymw&#xD;
" ' F  / r.''  ca:lle1oul(t  A q r  .I: -lth rp&#xD;
f:'om1 otver 'the stor,-r:line "r)lcit's tno1e for you&#xD;
It! (;)1m1e111up l-st r."&#xD;
&#xD;
(II  \1' 1     '   I.&#xD;
I  i it  ti'i it t1:t&#xD;
&#xD;
LA&#xD;
&#xD;
ASA 17-Y(-&#xD;
&#xD;
It,&#xD;
&#xD;
,&#xD;
,6&#xD;
}&#xD;
Y&#xD;
b&#xD;
tl&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7111-00000011"/>&#xD;
OUT LATE AGA~d LY.              1&#xD;
&#xD;
20            TiHE' GOOD .fR. BAGGLETHORPE.&#xD;
&#xD;
Was it not like the scene in Romeo and&#xD;
Juliet?  The old nurse at the head of the&#xD;
stairs, and Romeo below with'his skates slung&#xD;
over his shoulder, and Juliet with her beauti-&#xD;
fl eyes bashfully bent down and shaded by&#xD;
the small rim of her jockey hat !&#xD;
"Well, you won't tell me," said Will, '" and&#xD;
I must go. I see quite well how it is."&#xD;
" How is it ?" she asked.&#xD;
"'You don't care for me, and you don't&#xD;
like to hurt my feelings by telling me so."&#xD;
Willie, I-I-" staimimered Filine.&#xD;
What, swecetlieart ? '1' what, Fify?'"&#xD;
1 (b love you so 'uive," and then cane&#xD;
the hot tears which she had kept restrained&#xD;
all the evening, but which would flow now.&#xD;
'' Dear little Fify !" he iurimured, in a low&#xD;
voice. "You have made mue so happy by&#xD;
this."&#xD;
" You don't think I am immodest to tell&#xD;
you so" she asked, blushing.&#xD;
Iminmiodest ?" he replied indignantly. " Not&#xD;
a bit of it. Immodest, indeed!"&#xD;
Somehow, in his enldeavor to Iprove ti her&#xD;
that lie did not think her iinnid-st, the&#xD;
jockey hat fell to the floor, and the -waving&#xD;
ringlets of 'the sun-tinged hair streamed over&#xD;
the collar of Willie's gray overcoat.&#xD;
" How much do you love miie ' lie asked.&#xD;
A lucid question, this. Very popular with&#xD;
infancy.&#xD;
''Oh ! more than I can tell."&#xD;
Not the proper answer by any means.&#xD;
" Three bushelss,' is the orthodox reply.&#xD;
"o miucl," she continued, in so Imw a voice&#xD;
that Will was obliged to bend down his check,&#xD;
till it almost touched her cherry lips, to catch&#xD;
her words--" so much, that to-night when&#xD;
that young lady skated up to us-the Turkish&#xD;
one, you knon--and said you had flirted with&#xD;
her at Mr. Pearson's dinner, I could scarcely&#xD;
keep from crying. And 0 Willie! when&#xD;
she said you had given her a pink Cupid-I&#xD;
thought-my--heart-would-break !"'&#xD;
Confound her !" said Willie indignantly.&#xD;
" Come, don't erv, Fify, don't ! You know I&#xD;
never can love any onebut you !"&#xD;
" Truly ?"&#xD;
"Truly " said Willie, touching her cheek&#xD;
with his lips. But she was scared at this, and&#xD;
moved away from him as though she were&#xD;
afraid. She need not have been afraid of&#xD;
Willie Gentry. The boy was as innocent as&#xD;
&#xD;
herself, and the love which burned in both&#xD;
their hearts was as pure as any earthly pas-&#xD;
sion can be.&#xD;
Will you always be true to nie ?" asked&#xD;
lie.&#xD;
" Always.'&#xD;
"And always love me&#xD;
" Always-always."   And again the bright&#xD;
locks streamed over the gray overcoat. 'Tlic&#xD;
were both too happy for words.&#xD;
Voice from up-stairs&#xD;
'iTie nurse agam.&#xD;
"ood-iiigit, darling ! said Willie.&#xD;
"c Good-night!"&#xD;
Pirtig nx1as sweet sorrow. They muiighit&#xD;
have said good-night until -thn moi row, but&#xD;
the nurse would not let them. She 'called&#xD;
"c I'/ ne !&#xD;
" Good-night, sweet love."&#xD;
food-niighlt, dear Willie."&#xD;
Did Romeo kiss Juliet?     1'erhaps not.&#xD;
ut Will ( entry did not trouble htimIself about&#xD;
precedent at that iioiienit of parting.&#xD;
Out in the street again, lie  alked over the&#xD;
crisp snow with the proud air of a victorious&#xD;
sovereign. Oh ! how happy Ie was! I.Iow&#xD;
dearly, devotedly lie loved her!  is 1eauti~&#xD;
fuil goddess! lie never could love another&#xD;
woman, lie said to himsel; never.  le would&#xD;
love her, and be true to her, man 1 -hie shulit tl&#xD;
be his owna darling--his 0n eet, sweet little&#xD;
baby -wife.&#xD;
Yes, lie would marry her at once. To~&#xD;
morrow or the next day, peraliills--or the&#xD;
next, iontli. le would limr herI as soon&#xD;
as possihle. Hm  happy he was&#xD;
le was not well-oi' yet, triue. But lie had&#xD;
his salary, and one more 1ersoi makes no&#xD;
difl'erence in a hounseliold, (a sweet and popu-&#xD;
lar lovers' error,) and ie would take his wife&#xD;
to live with his father antd moth er, and they&#xD;
xvould love her as they( lid him. How coult&#xD;
they help loving icie ! His beautiful goddes!&#xD;
Ilis sweet little Fifine !&#xD;
Perhaps he was reckoning without his host&#xD;
Who knows ?   But his own reckoning made&#xD;
him happy, and the host's reckoning had not&#xD;
yet been presented.&#xD;
Reckoning thus, lie walked lightly along&#xD;
over the snow, with his hands in his pockets&#xD;
and his shoulders thrown back, as was his&#xD;
&#xD;
wont, and the skate-steels jingling together  gayly-whistled and walked happier than an&#xD;
with a merry sound which reverberated on    emperor, for in his heart the bliss of first love&#xD;
the still night air. As he walked, lie whistled was swelling.&#xD;
T R C I  WAElTIL X.&#xD;
THE, l- RECK ON I N V1"11 1111: iI E I l'.&#xD;
&#xD;
IE put his key in the night-latch of the&#xD;
door of the house it No. 17 One Thousandtlh&#xD;
street, and entered softly.   le mist not&#xD;
wake his mother.&#xD;
lut to-iight, a - on one ot'ccas'ion before,&#xD;
his lrecaut:ons were needless.  As h passed&#xD;
the parlor door,I le saw that 1both hi aIrenlts&#xD;
were sill up, and     looking  nervous and&#xD;
anxious.  his father called limt im.&#xD;
"Willie,'- said Mr. Gentriy, " xou ar' out&#xD;
late again to-might."&#xD;
"Yes, father," replied the 1ov, "f-I-"&#xD;
lie had iinteinde    tell theIm all in the&#xD;
morning.  Hi slove- It;his projects-hi hopes,&#xD;
-all this lie' ha iicturetd hiiiimclf '  o -m&#xD;
fessing, with some lushes, ptrhaps, buott with&#xD;
a liptly heart n ver-theless, when the three&#xD;
should sit tog-thite the ntxt morning at the&#xD;
cheerful breaktst-talde. hlow was it that&#xD;
now, only a few hours earlier thai le heLd&#xD;
anticipated making his love-avowal, the first&#xD;
words of it faltered on his lips, and li found&#xD;
h1imst-lf bllushimig and stannneriig as if' that&#xD;
love of wiithi in reality heit xau so proud,&#xD;
were a guilty teeling forever to be iCon-&#xD;
cealed?&#xD;
The truth was, le had not exiectetd thi-i&#xD;
meeting. le did not think that whn- lie nwt&#xD;
his parents, they u would he sithug togi-tiher in&#xD;
solemnii silence, with every evidentue of dis-&#xD;
tress, if' inot anige', depicted on their cotnte- .&#xD;
"  es mother," hite -o itned, after Ita  i-&#xD;
ute's a   tarth luste, "c I wn -it to the -hatin-&#xD;
oll and - &#xD;
"Williet!'' -aid ili-i father, "is useless to&#xD;
ievaricate. }-or tsine tilme past ouri mother&#xD;
and myself have observed the marlel change&#xD;
in y o misconduct, and 4have be-tn deliyt dis-&#xD;
tressed by it. Your mother is fairly wasting&#xD;
away through the sorrow which your indlif'er-&#xD;
&#xD;
eee and ileglett almve catlsed i her.  For th&#xD;
first time in your life tom have withht-l x iour&#xD;
coifidenet' from mis."&#xD;
Never id I think," sai Mirs. Gentrx hit&#xD;
toly, " that the day w oull evert cotiex nli&#xD;
myii nlyhx child xxnoulhd treat t' as though I&#xD;
wxerxe1 miimore to i1im thani a strmange-r."&#xD;
O miuother' - Said Willie, wx ith11i- otl alr&#xD;
of  irrei-itiilt' suxtettmts  appiu1roaclunaim  -l'r&#xD;
and polling his :arin11about her wainl. "l low&#xD;
..,,&#xD;
1    t r  w1ro'ig meil'&#xD;
She waitts pottiu tlt-.es urltihet touch nid&#xD;
-imec tth of the situ -hit' htiled so th   lx   I i&#xD;
words bir-oughut tis to her i-yes, and whln&#xD;
- lit hilrw himi to lit trtast antI smilteth, ' ilit-'-&#xD;
oturagiit' Wais itotrtdh; and li liie  that hi-&#xD;
mihit mw hivule' his scr-t.&#xD;
Ishoulhirae told 1Iou hloig ag" ai,''diI hte,&#xD;
i but somii-ow-well, I couldn't.  iuut I thde&#xD;
termuinil to ttll vim uitoim-morrow at ireiahkfist,&#xD;
heteause sometthings h apspeialils-int  to-nmight&#xD;
whith-wxhitch hua ' Ihppm-i tettforti.''&#xD;
"'Well, lar'.-  sail hi., iimother', eour&#xD;
iigiing a moire exted'iitlid conm fiientet.&#xD;
" 'ill, imtothi'e," said li- siplilx tmtly swtt-&#xD;
rI am ml lot'(."&#xD;
"lIn love!" ew1,iinwd'tshe.&#xD;
Silly 1m itmnaum ! lholh 4( hit' inott fortmi-ten th:&#xD;
wouhl happen ?     wItIVas oliy xn onderful it hai&#xD;
not huappe-nt 1e-ftrt.&#xD;
" Inilov \illi- '"&#xD;
"Yes':, father."&#xD;
'Iit'thtdtclaration si-medt to have fallen like&#xD;
a pall  n their spii s.  A nd poriW ill had&#xD;
iuiuagmdti thex nuldt mcixe' twitxxth acehuimia-&#xD;
tions of tlelihit ! I   utow was he to kinow that&#xD;
there is a parental itolatry w which regards all&#xD;
loti, even this other so difhi-renmt from ithir'&#xD;
twn, ;with jialouisy and distrust ? How tdiv it'&#xD;
that his fathicr andl miiother were cast in this&#xD;
selfish loxiigi mould ?&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7111-00000012"/>&#xD;
V4&#xD;
&#xD;
22                    THE' GOOD nMR.&#xD;
" And what is to be the upshot of this love,&#xD;
Willie ?" inquired his mother.&#xD;
" The upshot,mother? Marriage,of course."&#xD;
" Oh ! of course," said MI's. Gentry, moving&#xD;
away from her son. " Marriage ! Upon my&#xD;
word, at what age will children marry next ."&#xD;
" I am past twenty, mother," urged the boy.&#xD;
You are in no position to marry yet,&#xD;
Willie," said his father; "your salary is too&#xD;
small."&#xD;
"It would be if the lady were a different&#xD;
sort of person. But O father! she is so&#xD;
good, and so modest, and content with so lit-&#xD;
tie, I'm sure you would love her dearly if you&#xD;
knew her."&#xD;
"Who is she?'&#xD;
"Yes, by the Way," echoed Mrs. Gentry,&#xD;
who is she ?"&#xD;
" Whv, you've seen her once. Oshite's so&#xD;
pretty and so good ! Dear other, you can't&#xD;
help loving her OWhen vou know her.&#xD;
" Who is she, I ask !"&#xD;
" Why, she is that beautiful creature we&#xD;
saw at Young Men's llall. You know the&#xD;
oe who stood on the pedestal-the Gsoldilss&#xD;
of Iiicrty."&#xD;
" An actress!'"&#xD;
A Ihiallet-d:meer !"&#xD;
lint, mother-"&#xD;
" Don't attempt to justiftv her, Willie ! I&#xD;
won't listen to it. I tell you you shall m/&#xD;
marry her. Alh ! I dare Lay nw you w ill tell&#xD;
me you are your own master, and w ill do as&#xD;
you like.  c Very well! I suppose a itotlers&#xD;
broken heart goes for nothing."  Anid 3r-.&#xD;
Gentry burst into tears.&#xD;
" Dear, dear mother,'' said Willie, kistsing&#xD;
her over and over again, "don't take on so-&#xD;
don't-don't, for iny sake."&#xD;
Why should I do any thing more for your&#xD;
sake ? This is what has kept you away front&#xD;
me-playing the gallaitt at the feet of a co-&#xD;
quette-an actress."&#xD;
" Mother," said Will in a low, angry voice,&#xD;
4 you mustn't cast a slur on her on account&#xD;
of her profession. It's as good and honora-&#xD;
ble a calling as any other, if it's only well and&#xD;
honorably followed."&#xD;
" And I suppose this young miss is highly&#xD;
honorable ?"&#xD;
" Yes, site is ; and if any man dares to say&#xD;
she is not, I-I'll knock him down for it."&#xD;
"Come, Willie." said his father, "let's&#xD;
&#xD;
PAcaj'LLTiIo1 P.&#xD;
&#xD;
have no more words abont it. Have you&#xD;
made up your mind to marry this person ?"&#xD;
" I have, father."-&#xD;
" Then you must choose between her love&#xD;
and mine," said Mrs. Gentry, rising to leave&#xD;
the room.&#xD;
"Won't you kiss me good-night, mother ?"&#xD;
asked the boy tenderly.&#xD;
Keep your kisses," she answered, " for&#xD;
-where, I dtare saye, they are to be had cheap&#xD;
enougih-on the blips of that girl.''&#xD;
Poor little Fifiie ! To think that sie should&#xD;
hie accused of givin her kisses cheap! She,&#xD;
off whose fre- young lips Willie's ow t11had&#xD;
bruslhed the first dew.&#xD;
After his mother was gone, Willie sat on&#xD;
the sofa anmd 1 iiehed his face in his hands.&#xD;
" This is a sad busine s," sdil tie father.&#xD;
"Father, mother is cruel to ime. She has&#xD;
tio ight spoken ill of the dearest girl that&#xD;
ever lived. My blood boiled while she was&#xD;
doing.so. If it had been any one but iy own&#xD;
mother 1-0 father, father ! how can m  y&#xD;
ittother he seo cruel ?  And now  it was&#xD;
W\illie's turn to break down, and cob.&#xD;
ili e is your mother, remember, Will,"&#xD;
said Mr. (Gentry gravely ; " and such a good&#xD;
imiotler she has beeni to you-so loving-so&#xD;
devote" .&#xD;
"I know it," said Willie, soling.&#xD;
It would be a sal thing for nme to see a&#xD;
breaking up1 in our little household, where we&#xD;
have all h    'en so happy.' 'lhre were tears&#xD;
im the eyes of the elder man now.&#xD;
" I ti 't anticipate for a moment any&#xD;
breaking up or divisioni" said Willie. raisin&#xD;
his head. " I thought we could all live here&#xD;
together happily and comfortably."&#xD;
".It appears it can not be."&#xD;
" 0 father what am I to do ?"&#xD;
'Willie, your first duty is to your mother.&#xD;
Think of her."&#xD;
" But 0 father 1" said the boy, grasping&#xD;
his father's hand, "I love my little girl so&#xD;
tiearly "&#xD;
Have you asked her to marry you yet ?"&#xD;
No ; but I have asked her to give me her&#xD;
love, and she has given it."&#xD;
" Well, then, my~ boy, I think you had bet-&#xD;
ter wait a bit before asking her to marry you.&#xD;
You see, my child, it is such a serious obliga-&#xD;
tion-marriage, I mean. Wait a bit, and test&#xD;
yourself. See whether this is true love, or&#xD;
&#xD;
0&#xD;
4&#xD;
-, jrr&#xD;
f _&#xD;
si&#xD;
E, .&#xD;
t1&#xD;
L '&#xD;
r&#xD;
t     '-&#xD;
t    i&#xD;
4&#xD;
k=&#xD;
F-' i&#xD;
'V&#xD;
: , ,&#xD;
a 3i&#xD;
s'&#xD;
=1&#xD;
';&#xD;
r ' ,s&#xD;
;&#xD;
_r&#xD;
3&#xD;
3   '&#xD;
' 1&#xD;
j&#xD;
_{&#xD;
3y'&#xD;
iyg&#xD;
h&#xD;
t&#xD;
-/&#xD;
&#xD;
oily its semblance.  Give yourself and her&#xD;
a fair trial for alength of time-say two&#xD;
rears."&#xD;
Those wretched " two years."   They are&#xD;
invariably proposed to lovers, who almost in-&#xD;
variably decline themo.&#xD;
" It would be the best thing you could&#xD;
possibly do itt 'every way, Willie,' continued&#xD;
the father.  " By that thime, I do not doubt&#xD;
you w itill have a largest' income than you hive&#xD;
just at present.  Very likely, too, bv that&#xD;
time, if your mother sees your heart is still&#xD;
fixed on the girl, all ier scruples and prju-&#xD;
.dices will vanish, and w e shall be the hll v&#xD;
and united faitily vni hoped to CC ui1-x&#xD;
Think of my infirmities. 'intik how, at anl&#xD;
age w hen the generality of' nen are still atle&#xD;
to battle and do for thiemtiselves, I tai toligd&#xD;
to sit down quietly and reci e home ainil&#xD;
sustenance from  your hatndls-oi, scarcely&#xD;
more than a boy.   What will beco e of tt,&#xD;
if you leave us, God onlyit knis.'. The itrifles&#xD;
I earn with my little tinikeriingin lt' m-&#xD;
gory would hardly huy our salt.  Willie, I&#xD;
&#xD;
TILE     ANGItY     E-llA.&#xD;
&#xD;
EARLY next morning a letter was left at,&#xD;
Mrs. Rtapp's door for Filine. Poor Will, uil:&#xD;
able to sleoep, had lwr itteni it the nlight 1 e-&#xD;
on~ttonplac~e but inevitale odailv du1ty&#xD;
required that l  toull ut ifneglect fis ent-&#xD;
pltyer's work, even to hoil an interview with&#xD;
ifiuo~e in the mitornin -g so lie left the ltt &#xD;
and at seven o'clock was in thlLii' hors'.ear&#xD;
on his way to Pearson &amp;amp; t' '.i     '&#xD;
Mrs. Iiapp  t delivered th  letter to F   inn,&#xD;
who raised it ho iher hils as sioon as ishe nia&#xD;
quit e alone. Dear \\illie !\\as it not god&#xD;
of him to write to her so soon ?&#xD;
Asking this tjuestion of nobody but Ier-&#xD;
self; of course the answer was a very enthu-&#xD;
siastic " Yes, indeed ! "&#xD;
And then she read the letter-&#xD;
My oWN Dans~t FiiNu:-&#xD;
I have something very sad to say, and so&#xD;
I hope you a il l prepare yourself for it. I&#xD;
&#xD;
ai iot1t uuith tf a htlft oi iai'. Ift'am'Id ue,&#xD;
iutc("t l1 im wute rii t'lv. i ' ta r  \t'  t lt  Iiis t i'o&#xD;
-hryyu    f((115   otlnritnlI nemt&#xD;
nlot motnedliatel y. The (caSe sitam 3 111 do'a&#xD;
linkg--I aitmnot vy w 'I tel  fI' yet, and I have&#xD;
moi/re on11 my thoulders 1than1younig Inwn of&#xD;
iny ie genealy have ; and when I marry&#xD;
yi, I ati to feel it I cnut give you at least&#xD;
a iititf''j he ii' 11it (t liga~nta t oiltiwhtih&#xD;
you sit richly dt'"serve. And how long i i to&#xD;
fight along only ont a iutnl salary I tltt't&#xD;
w       u and I lutve promtisedIl myt' mother&#xD;
faitd"u y unhat I .will  ot, martiry tundet' two&#xD;
years.  Ant  0 muty beautiful, belovel lify!&#xD;
if I were selfi-h, I wouhl take advantage otf'&#xD;
the iiteresta Iwhic (it makes mite so happy to&#xD;
titk (if it) itave awakened itt your heart,&#xD;
nil should heg vout to give me   tour vow&#xD;
that you would be mtinue at the nd (of that&#xD;
&#xD;
1S 11TH1 HIS .13o1.&#xD;
entreat you to consider your parents-the&#xD;
debt of gratitude you owe your mother espe-&#xD;
ciall --and set her ind at rest at once.&#xD;
Conme, my boy, promise me you will not ask&#xD;
this young ladt y to marry  u for tw  yeats.&#xD;
If' you reft s, I shlthi ikyot. te afraid t'&#xD;
girl will not Ite constant to  a aoti u&#xD;
Shelt wit b    constant to t    -n('ritd&#xD;
W illie, starting   tip  tit laslitg  eve's.  'It'&#xD;
will io constat tome, and I shall1it con-&#xD;
stant to li o-t' -t-o vear or twent-. I   t'&#xD;
the promise, father&#xD;
"What's my b1raveLy!Nog~i1an&#xD;
tt11 yourt mother of your n1ole reslh('.&#xD;
lie wemit tilt to lii' romnt, diitl tlit i:a&#xD;
faIth er  ha  I  1id  1 iti. 11t tlte  h tle&#xD;
hin and kissed hit lt iuiy  -ian lienut-y&#xD;
-ctparated for the til it Mir (.Gentry was&#xD;
hlpjtitr ttam ishe had b'en f'r many mcobs&#xD;
past, atd, sing her happy , 1er liistand&#xD;
w as htapty (t.&#xD;
Neither knew how deeply, mllthe hearllt (&#xD;
the sitnt there lovedIw so ell, the iron tal ,&#xD;
tred, thrust by their ottnt Itatils-&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7111-00000013"/>&#xD;
24                    THE    GOOD AIR. .&#xD;
time; but then I know, with your beauty and&#xD;
sweetness, you stand a chance of making, in&#xD;
a worldly point of view, a far better match.&#xD;
Why, to-morrow or the next day, some man&#xD;
with a fine fortune might come along and&#xD;
ask you to marry him, and then how should&#xD;
I feel, knowing that your guardians would&#xD;
think that I had stood in the way of your&#xD;
advancement-in the way of your advance-&#xD;
ment Fifine-whlen I would be willing to&#xD;
sacrifice my life for that very advancement&#xD;
which I might stand in the way of!&#xD;
" If you will let me, I will still conic to see&#xD;
you, but you must not let me interfere with&#xD;
xour prospects. Let us be friends-dcear,&#xD;
(lear friends, and it, when the two years are&#xD;
past, you are still free, why then, dearc,&#xD;
you will let tme enter the lists for your hand,&#xD;
will you not ?  But if, in the mean tiue, you&#xD;
see any one you like, and lie is a man wor-&#xD;
thy of you, and can give you the wealth&#xD;
which, if I had it, should be lavished at your&#xD;
feet, why, then, Fify, [ suppose I mui-t bear&#xD;
oy faite, and go through the rest of iiiy life&#xD;
with a hrken heart.&#xD;
" Dearest, toy eyes are full of tears, and,&#xD;
i ! I do so love on ! Bit I will not he self-&#xD;
i-. You will not send ue quite away fromti&#xD;
your sweet presence, will you  You will let&#xD;
tile hear your darling voice, often again, w ill&#xD;
youi inot? though I dare not hope to hear&#xD;
it as once I did (shall I ever forget it  ) inac-&#xD;
eents of love.&#xD;
I will come to your house this evening&#xD;
as usual. Then I shall know niv fate. I&#xD;
shall read it in your eyes. If you have any&#xD;
piiy iii ourh earth, you will not keep me&#xD;
away from  you altogether. Only a word oc-&#xD;
caniually-only a look, if a, word is too&#xD;
much-Will make the happiness-the only&#xD;
jov of your almost heart-broken&#xD;
" Wi    tiu-Gx~I,:."&#xD;
She dropped the letter from her banda,&#xD;
and put them ii before her eves to catch&#xD;
the flood of bitter tears which feel upon her&#xD;
cheeks ! Poor Will was right ux hen he said&#xD;
lie did not knoow how to colpose a letter&#xD;
Ile had succeeded very ill im this.&#xD;
What did lie mean ?  I)id lie love her or&#xD;
did lie not ?  )id lie want to marry her, or&#xD;
did lie not ? Was she to wait two years fot&#xD;
hun, or to marry some my tliical maxn with&#xD;
" fine for'tun~e " to-morrow ?2&#xD;
&#xD;
7ITr.,    4y/-        -- r -~T  r _-&#xD;
&#xD;
BAG GLETHORPE.&#xD;
&#xD;
One thing was painfully clear in the letter,'&#xD;
and it was the only thing that was clear,&#xD;
IIe seemed to wish her to understand that&#xD;
she must not love him any longer-must riot&#xD;
play Juliet to his Romeo on any future oc-&#xD;
casion, because henceforth they were to be&#xD;
" friends" only, " dear, lear friends" and&#xD;
nothing more.&#xD;
Friends! Fudge ! Could she be nothing&#xD;
more than a friend to him-the first man&#xD;
who had ever stirred her heart to love? No ,&#xD;
he asked the impossible. She would see him&#xD;
tic iore.&#xD;
But could she stand so severe a. test as&#xD;
this? Could she run the chance of meeting&#xD;
him in the streets, and have courage enough&#xD;
to turn her head away from himx  and shun&#xD;
him?&#xD;
She felt like a child standing on the rocky&#xD;
shore of an angry sea-a sudden gust of&#xD;
wind might sweep her over to be lost. She&#xD;
wasp not iimuch more than a child; but in&#xD;
somie cireum-stances ani instant of time suif-&#xD;
fiees to fully mature such childhood as hers.&#xD;
She grew very eahen now; the tears were&#xD;
dry on her cheeks, and her whole bearing&#xD;
was dignilied and composed. With a steady&#xD;
step, she went down-stairs and opened the&#xD;
door of her guardian's room.&#xD;
Mr. Ihagglethuorpe was glancing through a&#xD;
volume of Shakespeare-his favorite after-&#xD;
breakfast recreation. It " toned hii up," he&#xD;
said. The girl walked up to the old man,&#xD;
andi tlaid hx'er hand in his.&#xD;
My dear," he said, looking at her pale&#xD;
face wxeithi surprise. " What is the matter ?"&#xD;
Only this, Guardy," she answered, "I&#xD;
want to go away."&#xD;
lie gazed at her over his spectacles with&#xD;
blank astonishment, and she repeated the&#xD;
words.&#xD;
I want to go away.'&#xD;
"Away ? Away from where?     Surely not&#xD;
a-away from mei 1"&#xD;
She threw her arms about his neck and&#xD;
. kissed him fondly.&#xD;
"Oh ! no," she exclaimed  not from you&#xD;
--ih ! no. I want to go away from   this&#xD;
place ; miles away from it ! I want to be&#xD;
somewhere where  I shall never lay eyes on&#xD;
r  hin agaix.&#xD;
" On who, child 2"&#xD;
" On Willie Gentry," she answered, crying&#xD;
&#xD;
"What has happened ?" asked the good&#xD;
Mr. Bagglethorpe, with blazing eyes.&#xD;
Guardy, I should have told you long ago,&#xD;
but I scarcely knew it myself until now ; and&#xD;
that is, I-that I love him so dearly-so&#xD;
fondly, and lie-he-"&#xD;
He ?' asked the old man fiercely, and&#xD;
pressing her slight little figure closely in his&#xD;
arms. ''lIe what ?"&#xD;
Ile loves me too, dearly," she answered.&#xD;
But he don't want to marry tire--"&#xD;
"nWI? 2"&#xD;
'o.  lie wants me to be his dear friend&#xD;
only-''&#xD;
Damn   him ! I'll kill him !" shouted&#xD;
the good Mr. Bagglethorpe, dealing a blow on&#xD;
the table which might almost have broken all&#xD;
our of its legs at once.&#xD;
Oh! no, no, Guardy--no, Guardy---don't&#xD;
Don't say such terrible words !Im mex-&#xD;
plaminiig it all wrong.  You shall read his&#xD;
letter, and I will tell you all that has ever&#xD;
happened between us. There is no harm&#xD;
done, Guardy--not the least in the world !"&#xD;
She laid her hand on her heart and sighed,&#xD;
and after they had read the letter, began her&#xD;
story---her simple little story of love-adora-&#xD;
tion-idolatry--lavislied-upon an object, recip-&#xD;
rocated by an object.  It was the A B C&#xD;
of love. Like all primers, it had been easy&#xD;
enough at first, and pleasant study; but then&#xD;
that "hard word " in three syllables, Miu iii&#xD;
Aos: had con ; and very hard it was.&#xD;
The two old people listened to her ;ond&#xD;
listening, their hearts warmed. Not alone to&#xD;
her and to the boy on whom she poured such&#xD;
lavish and wild encomium, but to each other.&#xD;
They too had loved thus ; yes, and thus, spite&#xD;
of age, ad-ersi tv, sorrow, suffering, and pain,&#xD;
thus, thank God, the two old hearts loved each&#xD;
other still.&#xD;
" And so I thought I had better come to&#xD;
you and tell you. I come to you in this as I&#xD;
have come to you for years, moy more than&#xD;
father and mother. I had such. a dreadful&#xD;
moment of temptation. I felt that I must&#xD;
rush away to him and fly from yoi-you who&#xD;
have been all im all to me. And, dear Guardy,&#xD;
I am  young yet, and experienced in the&#xD;
ways of the world ; but I know that I lov,-&#xD;
him and that lhe loves me."&#xD;
There was a moment of silence, and first&#xD;
&#xD;
uviUti'1  (RIOS, .                     25&#xD;
one then the other kissed the girl tenderly.&#xD;
She sobbed as though her heart would break.&#xD;
" I hate myself. I do," she said. "1 am&#xD;
wronging you in loving him so much. And&#xD;
I am going to try to contlter it."&#xD;
You cani not, dear," said Mr. Bagglethorpe&#xD;
gravely.  "You can not conquer it. Love is&#xD;
yoosially lictered as a little boy without an&#xD;
clothess on, much less steel armor-hut he's a&#xD;
tough one to deal with--tougher'n any other&#xD;
of the creeters of mytholergy, to my notion.&#xD;
Ef I hied hed the making oni him, 1 should hev&#xD;
peitered him a six-looter withi a vizier draw red&#xD;
down over his face, and a double-edge scored&#xD;
iii his hiamnd. You ('al't co11quer him, Feefly."&#xD;
" What shall I do, Guardyl x-"&#xD;
"You can't do  anv thin', you pore leetle&#xD;
creatur.' 'I'hiis is a (mitirgency fOr the good&#xD;
Mr. lagglethorpe to rise dkal to.  I shall&#xD;
take this matter in miy own hands."&#xD;
 Don't you go doiin' any thin' rash, Bag-&#xD;
gley," said Mrs. Bagglithorpe.&#xD;
tImmiceelyer,'' Was the dignified reply,&#xD;
fear not. I shall hollur il on th' troubled&#xD;
waters." And he gathered Filtine to his heart&#xD;
in a tender embrace.&#xD;
 OC uardxiy ! ott a're sogood !&#xD;
".s I ndiherstatnd this uifortnit comuplii;a-&#xD;
tiol"irslned Mx'. Ikagglethior-pe, a mlinuuut e&#xD;
later, "the sui anuthb,( distance of the diflihkiltyx&#xD;
is that our'est im xablhe young friend, Mr. Wil.&#xD;
liami Gcutexry,has parrentswhoum it is neceary&#xD;
be should support, onto a limited sal. What&#xD;
Ins sal is, I do iut kxnox ner do I cnre. In&#xD;
this state of aflfirs, I shall find it luy duty to&#xD;
call on the (Gmitetry fai'ly this cvetiin', and&#xD;
make a speech to 'em."&#xD;
S A speech, Baggley?&#xD;
"1A -sp(e(h, hIuniielyer--I shall make a&#xD;
speech to 'emu, which will dror tears from&#xD;
their eyes, and-and    change their views&#xD;
xmuateerully. And as the time fir reeiatio&#xD;
is himuited, I shall now go down to Young&#xD;
Men's lHall andl  gin private rehur-als fo'&#xD;
the speech aforesaid. S(o good-mornin', Imi-&#xD;
ieelyer--ood- h F, eefy. Keep up a god&#xD;
heart, tmy dear, and never  think youx can&#xD;
conquer love. He whipped me and Mrs. I.&#xD;
Years ago, and lie hues kep uxs under tver&#xD;
setce."&#xD;
With this lie iwent awa-.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7111-00000014"/>&#xD;
1l.&#xD;
&#xD;
C)&#xD;
&#xD;
TttoT evening, as the Gentry family sat at&#xD;
tea, the brawny Ellen was summoned to the&#xD;
door by the active ringing of the bell there-&#xD;
of.  And coming back antntouncedt that,&#xD;
"Sure, 'tn, the ;good Mistlier Baggiltharp,'tt,&#xD;
an' ie's in the pairlor a-nwaitin'."&#xD;
" Nay, that is an error, my innercent and&#xD;
guileless Bridget," remarked Mr. Baggle-&#xD;
thorpe, entering the dining-room, with his hat&#xD;
in his hand, and bowing low.&#xD;
Will gentry spran to his feet, napkin in&#xD;
htatnd, tossed between the conflictiig emotions&#xD;
of astonislunent at this apparition and a wild&#xD;
desire to offer it a chair.&#xD;
Mr. Bagglethorpe took his hat affectionately&#xD;
to his breast, and lunched at once into his&#xD;
speech.&#xD;
"i tr. and Mrs. Genterv-sir and madam----&#xD;
set doxwn, 'William, 1 do not wiht to set&#xD;
down myself--my dooty is with your parents,&#xD;
umy son.  I am here, my friends-if you will&#xD;
permit the term-as a unworthy ambassador&#xD;
from the court of love. But excuse mtc.  I&#xD;
ramble.  The pint is this. You Itv ben in-&#xD;
formed that your est little son has contracted&#xD;
a attachment so to speak, for the young lady&#xD;
who is known to the public by the title of Lar&#xD;
Peetette }'efeene.  Es I tinderstadtl, this&#xD;
yere attachment is not es agreeable to you es&#xD;
it is to the young people.  Quite lateral, Mr.&#xD;
and Mrs. Gentery.   This young man, feeling'&#xD;
that his fast ilooty is to his parrensts, has&#xD;
nobly, manly, self-sacrificin'ly, writ a letter to&#xD;
my ward, station' the circumstances, and asking'&#xD;
for time---askin' fir two years of time.  I tin&#xD;
quite es willing , sir and nadlai, to grant that&#xD;
time, es your honerbhle selves. The young&#xD;
iatn's sal is tit seeh as to warrant him in&#xD;
takin' a wife, while his parents liev a -laim&#xD;
which he, in his filyul beauty and loveliness,&#xD;
reco'nizes. What it lies cost his brave young&#xD;
heart to take this step, you may not know,&#xD;
but you can no doubt realize if you make a&#xD;
proper effort so to do. Onet you was yount&#xD;
Mr., and Mrs. Gentery.-oiet you also was a&#xD;
&#xD;
suitor at the court of love, Mr. Gentery--as&#xD;
I was, as Mrs. B. was, as we all was.   The&#xD;
feelix' which anerimates the bosom  of your&#xD;
noble and well-edicated son, is the same feel-&#xD;
in' that we too hey felt.  It is a feeling' in the&#xD;
presence of which no honerble man kan say,&#xD;
I ant better ner thou. But I will not ratnble.&#xD;
The pint is this. Feefeene is as dear to mIle, Mr-&#xD;
and Mrs. Genterv, is the apple of iy eve. I&#xD;
tookt- her forum her dxiin' other's ars-I&#xD;
promnist to be a father to her.  The leetle&#xD;
creature' hes crcp itto iy heart of hearts, and&#xD;
it will cost ie a pang to part xx it lher.  But&#xD;
I shell do my dooty.&#xD;
The good Mr. Bagglethorpe's eyes were&#xD;
filled with tears, and lie no longer looked at&#xD;
his tudieice, but kipt his gaze steadily fixed&#xD;
upon the Ceihin' overhead, till he had con-&#xD;
eltudedl his speech.&#xD;
"  It m   xltut what may be called a mta iof&#xD;
prol'ty.  I at a roamer up and down the&#xD;
earth, in the show bu 'iess, xxlilch is ever&#xD;
prtetaoutis and the receipts variable.  Four&#xD;
Year ago I was flush. I put into bank, that&#xD;
year, the sum of five hundred dollars, es a&#xD;
sinkini' fund for the good of Lar Peeteete&#xD;
Feefeene.   Thar it lies laid  ever sence,&#xD;
draxwrin' interest.  I hed long determined to&#xD;
give Feefcene a edication, feclin' the lack of&#xD;
it myself; but I loved the leetle girl so well&#xD;
that it made my old heart ache to think of&#xD;
parting' from her.  She was yooseful to tile in&#xD;
iy egziition. Es a goddess, she lits few&#xD;
sooperiors and fewer ekals.  I clung to her,&#xD;
ant postponed the edictatin' onher.  The time&#xD;
ies now come fer me to act.  I have resolved&#xD;
to withdraxvr her from  the perfession which&#xD;
she adorns, and put her into a hoardin'-&#xD;
school.  But afore I do that, I Lev  a Oro-&#xD;
posal to offer.  I offer to give my darlin'&#xD;
treasure into your keeping .  I honer your s1On&#xD;
-I honer his parents. I can trust him--I&#xD;
can trust you.  Senee she was ten years old,&#xD;
Feefeene les never ben out of the immejit&#xD;
presence of myself er Mrs. B. We know her&#xD;
&#xD;
711E GOOD 1111. BAL GLETJORPJJ.&#xD;
&#xD;
TJEI)XLG.&#xD;
&#xD;
CJIAVTER XI II.&#xD;
THEEE N I).&#xD;
&#xD;
--we know her well- She is as pure as a&#xD;
rosebud. 11er heart is as unsullied as a an-&#xD;
gel's. She is fit to make your son, er the&#xD;
son of any man on the good Creator's foot-&#xD;
stool, a wife--a levin', trusting , clinging , pure&#xD;
i   and gentle wife. Take her to yortt- lcairts,&#xD;
my friends--I gin her up to you.    The&#xD;
-montey nov  biiank For het, is len to ranr&#xD;
on, when   he  ill;and t1eatitl -e, I'&#xD;
ready to pay her hou a  in this Inease for- rto&#xD;
years, at the end of nhilh time o n cii toed&#xD;
o. speeds to conixnec  ou thia t th  1ill&#xD;
make your sonia worthy ip irdier. I C x 01ai&#xD;
Inmmtan, if your hearts 1'(' pt to ie u 1&#xD;
soft inluences of I   t  i, you1i llv   lix et-, ii  ii&#xD;
y  part with her it wx otil I xx -iiw x out- Iw rtiyo to&#xD;
pat-  nx lilier--a a itcloR tlitiea it&#xD;
mine -'&#xD;
it    Mr  Ji  l-tl p     -      -   -    -&#xD;
-      am , tho'pe hunied lhs fa(ce mn ha&#xD;
'handkerchief.&#xD;
Mrs. Genttry arose nal otehrd htitti hetl ,&#xD;
in silence, with teat's bniitnn iovig (tx01(from itr &#xD;
brown eyes.&#xD;
?,,  cc (j  io s C hintyou,iarm !  h tiht good Mir.-&#xD;
V-  agglethorp u; 'your Iheart is tellheel  -1od&#xD;
, less tou.eAnd your son hortfr Will.&#xD;
was wringng ,,his other hauni, " I ietimmy&#xD;
bl es dinl' n it lhlImyl vtreasm-e1'.  1,I was  is  ritchi&#xD;
as JonJalob-x ;Iaeohi Ator, I coitnilt  -o ayli  t&#xD;
plainerin n hat high e-teet I hold (this hon &#xD;
youth1."&#xD;
Noble fellow.cried Mr. (ci-ntrt, coinititi'&#xD;
5k-&#xD;
&#xD;
it on his crutches, " You shall not lose you-&#xD;
trealanre."'&#xD;
What !" cried Mr. Baggletho1te angrily,&#xD;
"ot won't take her"&#xD;
SWe t'il take het," aidl Mtrs. Gentry.&#xD;
""We n'i/#takle her,"' said 3!r. (Gten tr oni&#xD;
trt't for  yout, 311r. 1lagletho rlw.  She  shall&#xD;
taxe  a  Ioite  x1ith  s.  She  shall  a ettiitil&#xD;
hil( Ia1Ilve  vnh  n a, for  two years.  At&#xD;
-h n( O'ta  ilt nn e  t;e :0h~d  e returned to,&#xD;
iit, tit olitliiI her a tL you have  rightt.'&#xD;
A-! eel  tiul -i gItutV Mh:r  'IOrtui&#xD;
-its  nli  ' t= u -0  . ii  xx wil  live  yere.  'lm-&#xD;
Hlhee tt   \ nd t hent, W illia mr&#xD;
xN ill Ihe-at xx'eulii t--'&#xD;
And there n   -na ( hristno too&#xD;
,tiln not "(oing,-to take ten  page  a lW'itb&#xD;
to tell it.  A  Chrietmlas 'iveddiin  e rem ,4&#xD;
The oo ( ,1 Mr. ltialethorpo egae  t;V ytim&#xD;
bridle---;h1!'how  heauttif'ul Iifine  llo d~  th a,&#xD;
ni'gt !- Iix proud hitr faithittil Willie! And&#xD;
wha t a -lly tiit e tiet x as all roundti&#xD;
Atndi thent thegoodit Mr.t tita-ett iiet-ce-t&#xD;
ed1 hop fat old wife,'uinier Ihi,-; arm, and v~lais&#xD;
ced d101 thme di-tane 'withla)a rtivyheart his;&#xD;
da rling  la'iine surre1"ndered  fo,)e~rm -I hwlilin&#xD;
and peace behind h im, before him it rem-ed(&#xD;
groutnd Of the toil ainl tronhle n i\h11are thet&#xD;
chaie freward of, honest Unlustry faithfully&#xD;
andl persistentlyv nusdircectd. .&#xD;
&#xD;
~4&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
               
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
