<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7150">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Annie Reilly, or, the Fortunes of an Irish Girl in New York </title>
            <author>McElgun, John. </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7150</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1614</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Annie Reilly, or, the fortunes of an Irish girl in New York</title>
                  <author>McElgun, John. </author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>245 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. A. McGee</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1873">1873</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-14">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Annie Reilly, or, the fortunes of an Irish girl in New York</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7150-00000001"/>  ANNIE REILLY; OR, THE FORTUNES OF AN IRISH GIRL IN NEW YORK. A TALE FOUNDED ON FACT. BY JOHN McELGUN. NEW YORK: J. A. McGEE, PUBLISHER, 7 BARCLAY ST. I873.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7150-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1873, by JOHN McELGUN, In the Office of the Librarian of Congress, Washington, D. C.  JOHN ROSS &amp; CO., PRINTERS, 27 ROSE STREET, NEW YORK.    IN SINCERE FRIENDSHP TO  THS VOLUME   IS INSCRIBED BY THE AUTHOR.   &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7150-00000003"/> \ ;,   PREFACE. ALL the sufferings under which the Irish tenant-tfarmers have labored, and still continue to labor, are not entirely owing to the bigotry and rapacity of their foreign and wealthy domestic land- lords. There is to-day another class of land- owners in Ireland who are neither foreign nor wealthy, but who, by some means or other, have acquired sufficient to purchase a townland or two which have dropped off from some decayed estate, and who, in order to follow strictly the example of their exalted brothers, generally excel them in oppression and brutality. So little has been said or written of this class in proportion to the magnitude of their evil-doings that I deemed it quite in place to draw John G. Cary from their number.  &#xD;<pb n="vi-vii" xml:id="VAC7150-00000004"/> vi       Preface. After all the poor emigrants have endured , in their native land, it is very distressing to know the hardships and miseries that await them, almost as soon as they lose sight of the scene of the wrongs and cruelties into which they have been born. Those especi- ally who come to this country by way of Liverpool, and have endured the importunity of the man-catcher, and spent a night in his loathsome den, and afterwards borne the heartless insolence of the shipping-office, must surely enter on the Atlantic voyage burdened with far less hope than they car- -ried across the Irish Sea. The description I have endeavored to give of those English institutions in this volume, so far from being overdrawn, falls short of what I have actual- ly witnessed myself. : Notwithstanding how often public opinion has been directed to the coarse treatment of steerage passengers by the ship officers, lit- l tle or nothing has yet been done towards abating th'e evil. The fault may not lie alto- gether with the ship-owners,' but certainly 9    Preface,       vii they are guilty of criminal carelessness in selecting such men as those to whose care they annually commit hundreds of thousands of lives. To observe the manner, actions, and conversation of some of these officials, a person could not- help imagining that gross, vulgar, brutal ignorance was one of the qualifications on which "they obtained their appointments. Little better can be said of the worthy gentlemen at Castle Garden to whose tender care they are given on their arrival at New York. The latter dignitaries, however, have one very pleasant advantage over the equal- ly mighty. ship officers; that is, they are such fastidious, lively, funny, laughing fel- lows, and enjoy the sufferings, fears, and anxiety of the poor passengers so much, that it is quite delightful to behold them after the philosophic, stolid, British severity of the others. A. great difficulty with which the Irish girl in New York has to contend, is the fanatical bigotry of some of the mushroom employers  &#xD;<pb n="viii (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7150-00000005"/> "i      Preface. of the city, masters and mistresses, whose bright minds are stored with such useful knowledge as they derive from the teachings of pious gentlemen like Rev. Dr. Brassman and others of that ilk. Now, let me re- mark that the mean, ungenerous spirit which prompts such people to take advantage of the dependent station of a Catholic girl, to insult and trample on her most sacred feel- ings, is as far from being American as cowardice is. It is found only amongst those low-bred creatures in whose existence not one spark--of noble feeling can be found. However, sad to say, such wretches are not few, even in free America; and, consequent- ly, it devolves upon every intelligent Irish girl to study thoroughly the truths of her religion, that she may be able to repel the foul slanders against her creed, as Annie Reilly did. THE AUTHOR.   CONTENTS. CHAPTER I.      PAGS FARRELL REILLY'S HOME,  .  . . .  9 CHAPTER II. INTRODUCES AN INTIMATE FRIEND OF ANNIE'S, . 15 CHAPTER III. INTRODUCES A VERY HONEST MAN, . .  20 CHAPTER IV. SHOWS SOME OF THE QUALITIES OF THS VERY HONEST MAN, .            28 CHAPTER V. SOME MORE OF THE DOINGS OF THS VERY HONESTMAN, .  .  . .  . .  . 42 CHAPTER VI. THE CHARGE AGAINST JAMES O'ROURKE EX- PLAINED. -A VISIT TO AN IRISH MAGIS- TRATE, .  . .     O     49  &#xD;<pb n="Table of Contents (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7150-00000006"/> Contents.  CHAPTER VII.      PAGE [NG THE OLD HOME, . ...    . 61 CHAPTER VIII. [NG THE OLD HOME, . .   .   68 CHAPTER IX.  ;D ABOUT ON THE WAVES OF ADVERSITY, . 74 CHAPTER X. NATIVE LAND, GOOD-NIGHT" . . . CHAPTER XI. ,POOL MAN-CATCHERS AND  LODGING- OUSES, .    .   .  .    92 CHAPTER XII. O'ROURKE'S FIRST DAY IN NEW YORK. FRAUD AND A FRIEND, .    .  112 CHAPTER XIII. s'S VOYAGE.--HOW EMGRANTS ARE TREAT- ON SHPBOARD, . . . .     22  CHAPTER XIV.  - E AT CASTLE GARDEN.-HOW PASSENGERS RE TREATED THERE, ,   ,    132   CHAPTER XV.       PAGE ,TING OLD FRIENDS, AGREEABLE AND OTHER- WISE,  . .  . .  .   . . 137 CHAPTER XVI. ES O'ROURKE'S EXPERIENCES IN A NEW YORK MENAGERIE, , .   .     1. 48 CHAPTER XVII. TIE FALLS IN WITH A MOTHER-IN-LAW AND A TARTAR.-BOTH TRY TO CONVERT HER, . 157 CHAPTER XVIII.  ODERN CLERGYMAN.---REV. DR. BRASSMAN'S GREAT ENTERPRISE, .  . .  . . 1" CHAPTER XIX. ES O'ROURKE AT  THE OIL-FIELDS.-A SKETCH OF HS COMPANIONS, . .   179 CHAPTER XX. ANGE OCCURRENCES IN THE "MANSION."- HAPPY LIFE OF A MOTHER-IN-LAW.-ANNIE RECEIVES A LETTER FROM HOME, . . . 186 CHAPTER XXI. OURKE'S FORTUNES BEGIN TO IMPROVE, . 1 I97 CHAPTER XXII. RODUCES A FASHONABLE IRISH-AMERICAN "ADY,  . .  . . .  . .  ..  203  &#xD;<pb n="Table of Contents-9" xml:id="VAC7150-00000007"/> CHAPTER XXIIT.      PAGE KITTY BRADY REVISITS THE OLD LAND, AND IS VISITED BY THE FASHONABLE IRISH-AMERI- CAN LADY,  A   . .   . .  . 213 CHAPTER XXIV. EXPERIENCES OF THE FASHONABLE LADY AND HER HUSBAND IN IRELAND.-ENTERTAINING THE GUESTS AT A HOTEL.-A LECTURE IN A FORGE, AND WHAT CAME OF IT, . . . t 223 CHAPTER XXV. ANNIE AND JAMES HAPPY, . . . .  ( 236 , x    , \    ANNIE REILLY. / CHAPTER   I. FARRELL REILLY'S HOqE. N the brow of a green sloping hill in one of the most pleasant districts in the beautiful province of Munster once stood a small whitewashed cot- tage, shaded by tall poplars and neatly trimmed whitethorns. In front of the cottage lay a tastefully arranged garden; planted with choice flowers, which, in the genial spring and warm summer evenings, filled the little parlor with a delightful fragrance. From the garden a charm- ing view of the surrounding country could be obtained: the high blue mountain in the far distance, towering up till its top seemed lost in the clouds; the dark and green forest stretching out from the mountain base, till it fringed the edge of the calm, majestic river which flowed along ig, quiet grandeur to the Atlantic Ocean. The inmates of the cottage, at the time our story  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7150-00000008"/> Io      A nzie Reilly. commences, were a man considerably advanced in years, his wife, and one son and daughter. Farrell Reilly, for such was the man's name, rented the small farm attached to the cottage from a neighboring magnate at an exorbitant rent; but by honesty, perseverance, and skilful man- agement, he never allowed himself to fall into ar- rears with his landlord, and, besides, contrived to maintain his fa'mily respectably. To his son and daughter he gave as good an education as the neighboring school could impart. Mrs. Reilly, who was a devout woman, of great good sense, carefully instructed her children in the true prin- ciples of religion, in order that they might, as she often said, " never wander from the true path when left to their own guidance." It is, and so well it should be, as we here know, the great object of:every Catholic Irish mother who thinks there is a likelihood of her children coming to America, or going abroad into the world anywhere, to impress upon their minds a thorough knowledge of, and deep reverence for, the teachings of God and His Church. This religious training in the old land is the great reason why the Irish emi- grant girl so far outshines in every virtue those who come to our shores from other countries. When the worthy schoolmaster, Mr. Lacy, satis- fied Farrell Reilly that his son and daughter   Annie Reilly.   Ix were as far advanced 'in the rudiments of educa- . tion as his own ability permitted, the father told them that, owing. to his small means and total absence of any prospect of bettering their worldly condition at home, himself and their mother had resolved on allowing them to seek their fortune in America.        'J "For in that land, my children," said he, " by faithfully practising the lessons your mother and I have endeavored to teach you, you will find for yourselves the means we are unable to supply youi with here. It is very, very hard, my dear chil- dren "-and poor Farrell covered his face with his rough hands to hide the falling tears-- to part from you, God knows, perhaps never to see you again; but our prayers will be heard for you as well when you are far away as near." Annie, then a handsome girl of sixteen, with long, dark hair and pensive blue eyes, who had been standing by the hearth, her hands clasped be- fore her heart, went' gently to her father's side, and, putting her arms around his neck, said, while she vainly tried to prevent her own tears: -"Father, oh! do not let us see you cry; it breaks my heart to see you so distressed. Fran- cis and I have long known we would have to leave you and -mother and seek a distant home one, day. You both have done all you could by  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7150-00000009"/> 12      Annie Reilly. us, working hard to send us to school, and we always pray to God that he may enable us to repay you your great trouble with us." "Yes, father," said Francis, coming to his father's side also, "and sister and I, knowing how much you toiled to do without our help when we could have assisted you, will surely, with God's help and your blessing, yet make a happy home for us all." "God grant it, my children!" said Farrell, clasp- ing the hand of each; "but how can I have the least doubt?"And his face lighted up, and he wiped the mist from his eyes. "You will not fail. You are both good, wise childrenand will, I know, always continue so. Anyway," con- tinued he, disengaging Francis's hand, and softly drawing Annie to him, as he sat down on a low chair, " it was rather soon for me to mention this matter to, you yet. I didn't intend doing so for some time to come, but I felt strangely depressed this evening, and you were both running through my mind so much that I could hardly avoid act ing as I have done. We cannot part for some time yet. - Mr. Lacy tells me that you are both as far advanced now as he can put you." "Oh! there is not a doubt of that, father," said Annie, looking around joyously on her bro- i ther, who, with his face toward them, rested his   { 4z Annie Reilly.          13 elbow on the old oak chest. "Francis and I could have told you that a week ago, but we preferred letting Mr.-Lacy do it, as he promised us he would." "I met him yesterday evening," said Farrell, "returning from his usual walk, and, after bidding him 'Good-evening,' I was about to pass on, when he placed his left hand on his side, and inserted the thumb of the right in the lower button-hole of his waistcoat-the sign by which you can tell he is prepared for a talk. I stopped on the spot, and, after a learned- explanation of the causes that produce heat, and smoke, and wind, he told Me there was no necessity for either of you entering upon another quarter, that both your educations were as complete-to use his own words-' as a full moon.' I thought I would never get home to tell your mother, and I don't think I ever went to bed happier than I did last night. In my joy, I/did not think that what I had heard from Mr. Lacy would hasten our separation." The smile on the father's face faded again, and it was evident to his children something unusual was annoying him. Francis said, after a pause: "Father, nothing has happened to you since last night, when you were so happy? I wish you would be so to-night."  ,       ,  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7150-00000010"/> "      Annie .Reilly. "Not a thing, then," said Farrell, rising and going to the Window; " and still I would give a pound note to feel the same as I did last night. As I said a minute ago, I should not have men- tioned our parting to; you so soon. You must both now assist me in every way, till we have enough to fit you out respectably. Till then, we'll say no more on the subject. Here is your mother coming back from the chapel. Not a word of this to her." And Farrell lit his pipe, and went into the garden for his evening smoke. W&amp;R   CHAPTER II. INTRODUCES AN INTIMATE FRIEND OF ANNIE'S. ILES O'ROURKE was a farmer in pretty much the same circumstances as Reilly. Both farms lay close to- gether, and Reilly and O'Rourke were the best of neighbors, aiding each other in that truly generous spirit which can be met with no- where outside of Ireland. O'Rourke was a wi- dower, his wife having died some years before, leaving one child, James, then a bright, fair- haired little fellow of six or seven summers. James O'Rourke and Reilly's son, Francis, were about the same age, and were playmates, very much attached to each other. When at school, they enjoyed their sport and studied their lessons apart from the other children. Miles O'Rourke, partly from the example set him by his neighbor, was also desirous his son should have a good education, and was very careful he should attend every week as regularly as young Reilly. Annie, who was about three years younger than her brother, at length grew strong enough to be carried to the school. At first, young O'Rourke  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7150-00000011"/> 16      A 4nnie Reilly. left the conducting of the little girl to -and from school to her brother, contenting himself wijth carrying the two satchels and books, and occa- sionally lending Reilly a helping hand with his little sister over some narrow plank or brook by the way. A year and more passed by in this manner, till- at length Annie grew lively enough to skip along the way with her two, companions, and join them in their plays. So much were they together, and so attached did they become, that the neighbors often remarked how much like one -family they seemed. If Francis happened to be absent, and any of the other children offered any injury to- "little Annie," as she was fondly called, James O'Rourke instantly became her champion and defender, and many a time he hotly asserted her rights in the division of fruits or lozenges, or her claim to be the winner of a game at "jacks." Annie, on the other hand, regarded him as a brother, and would seek his protection-and advice almost the same as she would Francis. Time went by, strengthening the affection be- tween them, till at length they found they were lovers. This feeling came on each gradually, steadily, till it ripened into full bloom. The day, or week, or month it became such neither could tell; and, as they looked back-if look back            Annie Reilly.       17 they did--it seemed they had been so from in- fancy. James had never told Annie of his love 1  more than by his manner towards her, and, yet knew full well she was aware of it, and returned it fully. Francis, too, soon discovered their regard for each other. James would sing no song, as they sat on the banks of the river or sailed along its smooth surface in his father's fishing-boat, except Annie first told him it was her choice. He would ' gather no flowers for a nosegay in the garden or on the hillside, except those that Annie loved; and in the long summer evenings, when their duties for the day were over, and he carried his flute to the hill-top, Annie was compelled to call for every tune he played. Mr. Lacy, though not over-clearsighted in that department of knowledge, at length saw that James O'Rourke's and Annie's regard for each other was something out of the common sphere, as he termed it one day to a neighbor. "You see," said the garrulous schoolmaster, "it is very delightful to a'man of my profession, whose first duty it is to study the minds of my young charge, and watch the gradual expansion of the intellect, to be able to do so thoroughly. I have seen boys acquire a regard for each other when at school that they afterwards carried into the world, till one would actually lay down his  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7150-00000012"/> 18   -   4Annie Reilly.' -life for the other. When I see this feeling in two youths, I make it a: point to always encourage that feeling, providing it does not extend to prompting in the class. Then," continued he, with emphasis, "I leave nothing undone, at what- ever cost or pain, toreradicate that evil. I have always," and he nodded 'his head sagely, " given myself, in common with other learned and wise men, credit for my great knowledge of human nature. The slightest iota gives me a clue. I can tell by the manner in which a boy or girl 'keeps his or her hands clean, and his or her hair combed, to what degree he or she may rise or fall on the platform of life. My experience is so long and so varied," continued he, rubbing his ear, " that I did not believe there was a crevice in the heart of any boy or girl I could not ex- plore ; but I find "--this in an injured way-" that I have been deceived; yes, deceived badly, and by a youthful pair who have grown up under my very rod and eye. I allude to the daughter of Farrell Reilly and the son of Miles O'Rourke. That they should be friendly to each other, their parents being such agreeable neighbors, is in no- wise strange-friendly, I mef, in the ordinary way. But 'tis puzzling," and again he rubbed his ear; " the friendship of those children for each other goes beyond my comprehension. Both are   ,A nie Reilly.       19 very lively at their tasks, and I often watch them assisting each other in their preparation; but in class, though they stand side. by side, one will never be found prompting the other. I always find both understand the lessons exactly alike, and, if one happens to be absent, the other will be like a bull in a mist for that day; and I have grown so accustomed to this thing now, that I cannot find it in my heart to punish the de- linquent, because I know the cause so well. Little Annie's brother, I find-and that deepens the mystery-though just as clever as either, un- derstands his lessons altogether differently from them. The most ordinary person," he went on, with a sweep of his arm, " would expect the similarity to exist between the brother and sister, and not between two who have not a drop of each other's blood in their veins; but the thing is just as I say. I have given the matter a good deal of considera- tion, and the only point I can arrive at is that, when those young people grow up, if they do not become one, I was born and will die an unquali- fied lunatic."  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7150-00000013"/> CHAPTER III. INTRODUCES A VERY HONEST MAN. HEN Mrs. Reilly-entered the cottage on her return from the chapel, on the evening her husband and children held the conversation related in the last chapter, Annie, who ran to help her mother remove her shawl, noticed how pale and agitated she was. Annie, greatly alarmed after the signs of trouble in her father a few minutes before, asked, while her hands trembled with apprehen- sion, and a flood of tears came into her eyes: "Mother, for heaven's sake, what is the matter with you?"  Mrs. Reilly hesitated for a moment, her lips quivered, and her look became more ghastly; then she pressed her hand to her forehead, and said  "Nothing, I hope, child; tell your father to come here quickly. I want to speak to him a moment. I have something to tell him. I should not, if I could have prevented it," she added to   Annie Reilly.       2I herself, sitting down in the chair fronm which lier husband had risen, " have exposed my distress to you, and anyway the alarm may be groundless." Annie's frightened look and-manner, when she ran to him, so alarmed Farrell that he dropped his pipe on the garden-wall, and rushed breath- lessly into the house. Mrs. Reilly rose to her feet, and tottered against the wall as she did so. "Farrell," said she, " we can rely on Annie's good sense to keep what I am going to tell you from Francis. Thank God! the poor boy is not here now." "Oh! certainly, mother," said Annie, kissing her fervently; "you know I would tell Francis nothing that would annoy him." "Tell us quick, whatever it is," said her hus- band, throwing his hat on the floor. "It is some- thing dreadful, I know, for my heart is breaking all day." "Well, it is this, Farrell," said his wife: ," When I was leaving the chapel-gate this evening to come home, I saw John Griffin Cary, as he calls him- self, just going past, in company with a tall, big- whiskered, ill-favored-looking man. I was draw- ing the hood of the cloak over my face, for it looked like rain, and turned my head away; for I never like speaking to Cary, he is such a false- hearted hypocrite, and carries such an ugly, deceit-  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7150-00000014"/> 22      Alnnie Reilly. ful leer on his face. The corner of his eye caught me, and he said something quickly to the other man, and both turned round and met me in the niddle of the road. "'A good-evening to you, Mrs. Reilly,' said Cary, stopping my way. "I returned his salutation without raising my head, and moved to get past him. "'Mrs. Reilly,' said he, moving before me again, and, as I looked up, a broad grin covered his big, pasty face, ' this is Mr. Crofton, our new distinguished neighbor. He is thinking of settling permanently amongst us, and wishes me to make him known to some of our best people around, and you are just the first we met since he made the request; and; in truth, a splendid beginning, Mr. Crofton.' -"'I wish the gentleman well,' said I, again trying to get past. "' Mr. Crofton is an English gentleman, Mrs. Reilly, and is a great acquisition to this com- munity,' said Cary. 'We must all try and learn something from him.' "Though coming from the house; of God, I could not keep down my anger, and I said: "' We are not so very backward in everything here that any man, even though he is from Eng- land; can be set up as a model for us to imitate.   Annie Reilly.       23 We are always anxious to learn anything profit- able, but not to utterly disregard the old know- ledge, as you have seen fit to do, Mr. Cary.' "His farce reddened like an oven, and he tried to give one of those vulgar, loud laughs of his, but was not able. t"Oh! you are on your shiarps to-day, Mrs. Reilly,' said he; 'but I can well afford to let you go on. Can't I, Mr. Crofton?' "The other made no reply, but gazed at me in a half-stupid, idiotic manner, with his eyes almost closed, and his mouth open. "' I always make it a rule to be nice and civil, even when doing something very unpleasant to me,' said Cary. '1 always practise that, Mr. Crofton, and I find it never fails. I introduced you to a gentleman this evening, Mrs. Reilly, but that is not all my business. Tell your husband to meet me at my office to-morrow morning at nine o'clock.' "' If you have any business-and really, I don't know how you can-with my husband,' said .I, ' it is just as fitting for you to call on him.' "The same ugly smile came on his face, and I dashed away from them. "I felt so annoyed, after this strange interview, that I was hurrying along as fast as I could, when who did I see coming towards me, running along  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7150-00000015"/> 24      Annie Reilly. like a madman, but Miles O'Rourke. When he saw me, he hastened even quicker; and, as he -approached, I could see he was wringing his hands, and that the heavy perspiration was falling from his brow. "'What is the matter, Miles? Said I, when he came near enough to hear my voice. "No- thing wrong with you, I hope?' "'Wrong with me? O God in heaven! we are all ruined, beggared, driven to the poor-house,' said he, panting for breath; ' look at this-read it.' And he puleled a paper from his breast-pocket, and pushed it into my hand. ," Hardly knowing what I did, I glanced over the paper. It was a notice to quit, signed by Crofton and Cary. A thick mist overspread my eyes, my limbs- grew weak, and I would have fallen, only the heart-broken man caught me. "What can be the meaning of this, Miles?' said I, when I recovered strength to speak. 'Why is Cary's name to this? He has nothing to do with this townland.' "'O heaven help us! He has,' said Miles. 'I heard a rumor a- few days ago, but gave it no- attention, that Crofton and he were seen to- gether about here, and that Saunderson was about to sell them this townland. I thought 'twas only idle talk; but, to our grief, the thing   Annie Reilly.       25 is done now. I am going to Cary to ask an ex- planation; and, if he is determined to ruin us, he will drive me to do something desperate.' ' I begged of him to: come back, and consult with you; but he answered, ' No use, Mrs. Reilly; what can we do for each other now?' and walked swiftly on towards the town." Farrell, who, during this story, had been pacing up and down the floor, his hands clasped behind his back, stopped suddenly, and, turning to his wife and daughter, said4, ("What Miles told you is true. We are ruined. That low, mean, sneaking turncoat, that he may win favor with this Eng- lishman and with the other bigots around, will not leave one Catholic family on the land. You , know 'tis the only way he has got to obtain even a nod from them; for, bad as they are themselves, they despise him, because they know the con- temptible, crawling hound he is." "O heavens! no, Farrell," said Mrs. Reilly, "it cannot be; it will never come to that with us, that he will drive us from our old home. God is good and merciful; nothing so bad as that can happen. It is a way he has taken to let us know we are in his power." "Ah!. no," said Farrell; "I wonder at you, who know Cary so well, to talk in that way. Is there anything too bad or too mean for him to attempt?  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7150-00000016"/> 5     AtAnnie Reilly. -a man who allowed his own father to black the parson's boots, and, when he grew too old for that, permitted him to be taken to the work-house, where he was starved to death and buried in a pauper's grave. Yes, buried in a pauper's grave; and Cary himself that day spent hundreds of pounds purchasing pork for the Liverpool mar- ket."   "Oh! may the Virgin Mary protect us from the power of such a man !" said Annie, falling on her knees beside her mother, who had knelt down to beseech Heaven to avert the dreadful impend- ing catastrophe. Farrell said nothing to interrupt their prayers, but stood, with God knows what anguish of heart, looking out on the beautiful valley below, on which the rich dew was falling plentifully. The corn-crake's loud call from the meadows of tall grass, the sweet notes of the nightingale, the deep bark of the faithful watch-dog, all the plea- sures of the suimmer evening which he, till that night, enjoyed so much, only added to his load of sorrow now, byreminding him they were scenes he could not much longer enjoy. The tall white and. red rose-trees, now in full bloom, peeped sweetly over the garden wall, or in at the little parlor window, as if to softly whisper words of consola- tion and peace. Farrell leaned against the door-   post for some minutes, then raised his eyes, and, glanicing around on the beautiful scene, smote his forehead, and re-entered the cottage. Mrs. Reilly and Annie had just risen from their knees, and began to offer all the consolation in their power to the distressed man. "Now, Farrell," said Mrs. Reilly, "we are not certain yet that any such step as we dread has been taken against us. Remember, we have not been notified as Miles has.' In the name of God, do you prepare in the morning, and go and see Cary. What he wants-to see you about may be to make some satisfactory arrangement with you. If he intended putting us out, he would not, I am sure, send for you. We will place all our hope in God, and not give ourselves up to grief and despair; 'tis time enough to deal with misery when it comes, and not invite it." Farrell shook his head, and, resting his chin on his hands, sat silently till Francis came back from leaving the cattle at their accustomed resting- place, when, after a fervent evening prayer, they retired for the night. &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7150-00000017"/> CHAPTER IV. SHOWS SOME OF THE QUALITIES OF THIS VERY HONEST MAN. OHN GRIFFIN CARY, "Pig-Jobber and Hog-Slaughterer," as the wide, dirty sign over his shop-door, in one of the back streets of the town, pro- claimed to all who run and read, combined so many qualities in one body that our readers must learn a little more about him than they may be able to glean from the remarks of Farrell Reilly and Miles O'Rourke. As to the extremities of his name, very little need be said, "John " and "Cary" being very common- and very familiar names; and there is no reason why they should not look very well, and get along very agreeably when put together. Many a less important man than our subject thrives very well with a far worse name. But why this extraordinary man chose to put those nicely-fitting names apart by inserting another between them requires some little inves- tigation. That John G. Cary was a  thorough man of the world, his worst enemies never dare deny. John boasted of the quality at least   Annie Reilly.       29 twenty-five times every day, and no man had the hardihood to contradict him. John never said he was simply a man of the world-oh! no. He was a literary man besides; but he never chose to cul- tivate that quality. He possessed it ; the mine was there, he knew, but he kept it secure from the vulgar gaze, without parade, further than to strike himself on the breast, and say, "The blood of Gerald Griffin flows there"; but more calm and majestic than in the veins of the great poet himself. Yes, Cary claimed to be a relative of Gerald Griffin's. How or in-what manner, when pressed for an explana- tion, he knew not. / He lived at a safe distance from those who knew the poet's family, and, shrewd man as he was, always took care to avoid the subject when business led him to that part of the province. Well, being a blood relation of Griffin's, John Cary condescended to acknowledge the former so far as to give room for his name between his own-took him to his very heart, as it were, and signed himself in very fat letters, when he learn- ed how, "John Griffin Cary." Cary was a great philosopher. No man, living or dead, knew better than he how people should conduct themselves in adversity. He could lean back in his greasy arm-chair, his fat face, showing every sign of entire satisfaction, and lecture a  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7150-00000018"/> 30      Annie Reilly. poor cripple, or paralyzed beggar, for fully two hours, on how they should bear up against their trials; and in the end, as if to see the fruit his advice bore, dismiss them without a half-penny. Cary was a very great .knave. We have it on no mean authority that his rea- son for changing his creed was, that he might obtain the contracts for supplying pork to the military barrack. This little trick he could not conceal from his neighbors; but whenever he went abroad to any of the neighboring fairs, he always carried a pair of beads in his pockets, and always took care to display them as /if by mistake, when making a bargain. If the town or village happened to contain a chapel, Cary was sure to be seen at Mass on the' fair morning, and always walked from the chapel into the street bare-headed, while his flat gray eye glanced nervously up and down, lest some member of his new creed should see him. This happened once; but Cary's ready wit quickly re- lieved him of all suspicion. The minister, 'whose church Cary attended when in his native town, happened to be driving past and saw him, 'hat in hand, leaving the cha- pel.' The minister pulled up his horse instantly, while a tide of holy horror'mounted up his throat from his, very heart, which was a considerable dis-   Annie Reilly.       31 \ tance. Cary s horror was not much less, though of a different kind. He bowed low to the minis- ter-so low that the crown of the hat which he held in his hand came in contact with the road, and received a very ugly dinge. But Cary heeded -this not. He sprang to the side of his worthy adviser's car, drew his cuff excitedly across his brow, and said: "O Mr. Scollop! your reverence, I have been horrified to-day. The thing is going-too far; they- are actually planning the foundation of a new popish chapel here. I heard so when I came here to-day, but could not believe it -till I have satisfied myself by going in there just now. It makes my blood boil, Mr. Scollop." And he shook the hat downwards, as if it contained some of the hot--liquid, and drew his cuff again across his face. The tide of holy horror at this information was beating around the worthy parson's ears; but Cary's fervor caused it to ebb, and, after a firm grip of the hand, he drove away. Cary turned away, too, and joined a crowd of farmers who were looking on at the scene, and probably told them he was threatening to assault the parson. Cary was gifted with an Indian Ocean-ful of family pride. Although just as convenient to him as Parson Scollop's church, his dignity would never allow him to go. to the church of the parson  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7150-00000019"/> 32      Annie Reilly. whose boots his venerable father was said to black- en. Now, we hold there is nothing at all discred- itable in blacking boots. Many of our own boot- blacks here have grown up to be wealthy and respectable citizens, and would never blush to confess they earned an honest penny with the brush. Cary being a philosopher, as we trust we have established, it is hard to say how he would have felt had his father followed the blacking art in his rising years. He would, we venture to hope, have borne it with stoical fortitude. But in  his, early days, the man to whom the world is indebted for Cary sported the gorgeous livery of a country gentleman's coachman; or, as the case  i most likely happened to be, a country gentle- man's carman. Nothing is more certain than that he occupied one or the other of those daz- zling positions; for numerous old men and women, who distinctly remembered that day, could tes- tify they saw him with the lace hat on, but would not commit themselves by declaring they saw the lace coat; so'-tha-t-whether he wore the latter distinguishing 'garment or not must be left to conjecture. The old gentleman had fallen in the world-a thing his son could not tolerate in any man, much less in his own father; but he called the family pride to his aid, and knew him no more   Annie Reilly.       33 Cary was a very great hypocrite. We do not -use the term in an offensive sense, but merely as one of his manifold traits. There are many hypo- crites to be met with in every part of the world so closely resembling one another that a de- scription of one would serve for all. But Cary possessed all his qualities in an eminent degree; each shone out brilliantly. Cary could commit the most base and grievous wrong on any of his fellow-men, and at the same time shed tears in the fulness of his heart over that man's sufferings; and declare, while his voice grew husky with emo- tion, and his arms swept the air in a paroxysm of Christian charity, that he could lay down his life for that man. Any one who had not the pleasure of an intimate acquaintance-with him, and saw him while he planned the ruin of a neighbor, could not help thinking, or, if he were excitable, exclaiming: "Behold him! there is a true friend to all mankind." Cary was a liar, a great liar, a skilful, cunning, systematic liar. When a stranger entered his employment, and Cary saw a likelihood of his proving useful, he would, before the second day passed by, promise the fortunate adventurer a share in the business; but always prefaced this offer by giving it as his advice that he had better, in the meantime, work for little or,  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7150-00000020"/> 34      Annie Reilly. nothing; and, as few could be found to with- stand this luring temptation, many did take Cary's advice. Time would pass on, and the day for taking in the new partner, who probably by this time would have reached an ad- vanced stage of starvation, would come. At no period of his life would Cary look so innocent, so childlike, and so oblivious of earthly things as on that day. His thoughts were no longer of earth; they had penetrated the clouds, and clustered around the' throne of the Deity. Cary-bless him!-would take off his hat and coat, and, sitting down in his chair, let his head fall sadly on his hand, dilate in soft, low murmurs on the short- ness of, life here below, on the length of eternity, and how little we should care for this world's "vile dross." When the hungry expectant, who probably rose by daybreak, hardly condescending to notice such of his acquaintances as might be abroad at that hour, so much did his dignity rise at the prospect of being John G. Cary's partner, would, seeing John so absorbed in heavenly things, venture to remind him of his promise, Cary would gently tell him to leave him to his meditation that *day. Of course, the following day the subject would be again brought under Cary's notice. His astonishment was unbounded. He never heard of such a thing; did he employ a    Annie Reilly.     35 madman? When or where did he make such a promise? Where was the witness? His indigo nation rose, till he ejected the deceived wretch from the place, with the comforting advice to se- cure his bondsmen, as he, John, intended having him arrested for robbery, or larceny, or some other disgraceful offence. Some minor intellects say it is only needful to tell the truth when a lie will not suit. -But Cary was no compromiser. He never saw the necessity of telling the truth in any of his transactions, and he throve on that deter- mination. Well, there is a prince in every trade. We will not call Cary- a swindler. No. The ex- ample. he made of an intended partner, who modestly ventured to add that quality to the chain, deters us. Cary was sitting in his office, elaborately com- menting on the bright world opened up before a young man who stood before him, and whom he had entrapped the day previous, when Farrell Reilly and Miles O'Rourke entered the establish- ment. He had merely time to dismiss the young man with "God bless you!" when the two men came into the office. Cary rose and extended his hand to Reilly, while he said, with the accus- tomed leer, "Farrell, I am delighted to see you, there is nothing one man could do for another I would not do for you. Take a seat, sir."  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7150-00000021"/> 36      Annie Reilly. Miles stood by the office door, but Cary seemed not to notice him. Farrell sat down on a low form which extended along one side of the office, and Cary wheeled his greasy chair around to get a better view of his face. "I don't really know how I feel this morning; I see you look splendid. My men here are so much attached to me that it overpowers me. There is a young man just gone out there, and he is after telling me he'd rather work for me night and day than get into the Bank of Ireland. Did Phil say that, Ned?"continued he, addressing a long, lean, crooked-eyed, ill-clad youth, who, planted on one knee, was scratching with a quill pen in a greasy book which lay on a low, flat bench bt fore him. "Yes, sir; and more, sir," said the well-trained youth, turning his face towards his master and Farrell, but with his eyes on the opposite wall. "Ah! I am so forgetful. What4 else did he say, Ned? Keep down your head while you're talking." Ned almost struck. his nose against the desk; but, being an inquisitive youth, one of his eyes rested on Miles's face, where it remained, to the great horror of the latter. "Phil said, sir," he went on, " that he never knew what comfort or happiness was till he met   nn ie Reilly.      37 with you, and that his mother thinks he must be in heaven." " Ah ! poor woman," said Cary, rolling his eyes along the ceiling, "she is a widow. I never wronged a widow. Evil tongues may say I have. I would wrong myself, I would wrong myself to help a widow. That is my nature, Farrell. I can't help it; neither do I want to. I am a public nuisance-I mean a public institution, Farrell. Some are grateful, some are not; but whether they are or not does not interfere with my claim beyond the skies. When an injury is done to me, I am always ready to forgive it; that's me, John Griffin Cary." "You sent for me, Mr. Cary," said Farrell, who  had not spoken since he sat down; " may I ask what for?" " Yes, yes; so I did," said Cary, stroking his chin. "I chanced to meet Mrs. Reilly. Farrell, you ought to be proud of that woman, so hand- some, and so clever in her remarks besides. I met her yesterday evening when me and Mr. Crofton were going up the street. I introduced Mr. Crof- ton to her, and I don't think she cared much for the compliment. She is very independent, I tell you. My opinion is this," and his gray eye glis- tened villanously: " it is all very well for some people to be independent. I only say that as&#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7150-00000022"/> 38      ff, Annie Reilly. my opinion; other people may think different- ly." "Well, Mr. Cary," said Farrell, rising, while he bit his lip to restrain his anger, " is this all you want with me?" "No, sir," said Cary, in a loud voice," 'tis not; but, if your time is so precious that you cannot wait till I am done, you may go." "I came here to listen to all you' had to say," said Farrell, his heart sinking. "Do you know, sir," said Cary, "that I am your landlord?" "I have heard so," said Farrell, "but was not certain of it till now." "You may be, certain of it," said Cary pomp- ously.' "-Ned, when did we get the deed of that townland, me and Mr. Crofton?" "Day afore yesterday, sir," replied the youth. "Yes, so it was the day before yesterday," said Cary, nodding his head. "You see, I have so much business to attend to, Farrell, that I cannot remember dates at all. I want to tell you now, Farrell--you know the great wish I always had for you-quietly'and in a Christian way that I have let the whole townland to one man. It is the most profitable way for me, and will give me the least trouble." "O great God-! Mr. Cary," exclaimed Farrell, ,.   Annie Reilly.      39 smiting his forehead, and sinking back on the seat," you would not do that. You would not send adrift an old family whose ancestors have lived on the land for a hundred years." "Mr. Cary," said Miles, in a hoarse voice, burst- ing forward, and speaking for the first time, "surely you are not in earnest. We will pay you any rent you choose, if ourselves and our families starve." Cary's gray eye turned on the last speaker, and he said slowly and emphatically: "You are in the hands of the law, sir; go out from this place. I will give some of your family an opportunity to starve. The diet on Spike Island is very low, and the air very ap- petizing. You can tell your son that." Then, turning to Farrell, he went oti: "You say, Far- rell, your ancestors have lived on this townland of mine for nearly a hundred years?" "I can prove it, sir," said Farrell. "My grand- father was born in the house I live in now." "Don't you know, Farrell," said Cary, in a per- suasive manner, " that this is an age of improve- ments? All the old institutions are giving place to new ones. Mighty changes," continued Cary, / remembering a line he had read that morning in an old newspaper, " are going on around us every day, and we find no man grumbling. I did not 1XJ  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7150-00000023"/> 40      Annie Reilly. think, Farrell, that you, of all men living, would set yourself against the tide. I thought I had only to mention the thing to you, and-you would be delighted to find this revolution coming home, to us. Your wife, I know, wishes things to remain as they are; but I did not think she could influence a man of your sound understanding." "Oh! 'tis nothing new, as you know very well," said Farrell, " for foreigners to drive us from our homes. That is one of the oldest institutions of this country; and surely you, a man brought up in our midst, would not follow their exam- ple." "Let me go a little further," said Cary, with dignity. "Other landlords have taken their hold- ings from people, and, rather than let them live on. the land, preferred to let it he waste. Now, what I am going to do is this: I will rent the hull townland to one good Englishman, who will in- troduce everything English and grand into the parish, and make us thoroughly civilized; for we are in a backward state, Farrell." "How can you talk so?" said the latter, for- getting his danger in the height of his disgust. "Are you not an Irishman yourself?" "I don't know, I don't know," said Cary, -stand- ing up and straightening himself to his full height. "I am not sure about that. My fore-   Annie Reilly.      41 fathers were Normans-the Carews. I may have Irish blood in me by the Griffins, but the Carews were French. Anyway, I wish there was not a drop of Irish blood in my veins." "So do I, from my heart," said Farrell; but, re- membering his family at home, said no more. "Now, the wisest and best thing for you to do, Farrell," said Cary, "is to r re off as soon as you can. How long, Ned, did my attorney say we could give them?" "Three days, sir," answered Ned. "And you are bent on doing this?" said Farrell, wringing his hands. "My dear man,"' said Cary calmly, "I sent for you for a little quiet chat this morning, intending -to mention this matter to you in the course of the conversation; and now you lose your temper." So saying, Cary stepped nimbly into the office, for both were outside at this time, and quickly closed and locked the door. Miles had been wait- ing outside for his neighbor, and both slowly re- turned home, a pair of heart-broken men.  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7150-00000024"/> CHAPTER V. SOME MORE OF THE- DOINGS OF THS VERY HONEST MAN HE evening following the morning of her father's interview with John G. Cary, Annie was sitting alone in the shade of a tall whitethorn which grew near the river's bank, her head bent on her bosom, and the warm tears streaming down her pale cheeks. Herself and her mother had spent a morning of the most intense anxiety, dreading, hoping, and praying for good tidings, and guarding lest Francis would notice anything unusual the matter.; for they were resolved to keep the sad news from him as long as possible. The anguish of the family was intense when Farrell returned with word that their worst fears were realized-in less than three days they would be without a home. Mrs. Reilly fainted in her unhappy husba[nd's arms, and was with great dif- ficulty restored to consciousness. Francis-it was needless to keep the calamity from his know- ledge now-was so oppressed with grief that he cried like a child. Poor Annie bore up the  .     .   Annie Reilly. -     ' 43 best of any, and did all in her power to comfort her father and mother, and insisted on them all joining her in a rosary for assistance to come through this terrible misfortune that had befallen them. After prayers,' they felt considerably re- lieved, and set about the best way of removing their valuables to some temporary place of se- curity. Annie had struggled so hard to repress her feelings during the day that, when evening came, she felt she must give vent to her tears, or her heart would break. So overwhelming was the misfortune that she could not bear up against it all day-the desolation of her own home, and Cary's threat against her lover. When her father and brother were silently engaged, she left the cottage, and betook herself to the spot where James used to sing to her. With what a light, bounding heart she used to ap- proach this cosey place! But this evening how different! James was always there -waiting for her; but this evening the seat was empty. She went up the hillside a little distance, to obtain a better view along the shore; but, no far as her eye could reach, he was nowhere to beiseen. For a little she stood on the hillside in the calm summer air, her eyes strained in the direc- tion from which he approached the seat every  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7150-00000025"/> "      Annie Reilly. evening, till her heart sank with disappointment, and her sight grew dim; then she mechanically sought the spot, and let fall her burning tears. "Oh!" thought she, " if, -in addition to our mis- fortune, Cary has already put his threat into execution against James, and he is dragged away to where I may never see him again, what shall I do? Oh!" exclaimed she, raising her hands to heaven, "if such has happened, may God in His mercy take me!" She then bowed her head and wept, she knew not how long, till she was startled by hearing a well-known voice pronounce her name; but, before she could raise her head, James O'Rourke was seated by her side, her hand clasped firmly in his. Annie turned her streaming face towards him. For a moment neither spoke. O'Rourke's lips quivered, and his whole frame shook, but he heroically kept back the tears rising to his eyes. He had made his appearance so suddenly, and the poor girl's joy was so great, that she could only cry the more and press-the hand that held hers. At length James said: "Annie, it's no use in me asking you the cause of those tears. I already knovW the misfortune that has befallen us all. But it is useless now to pine and give way to sorrow. Better bear up bravely, as I know you will, Annie, when you come to   Annie Reilly.       45 reflect. The calamity is sudden, and we must be quick to meet. it." "Oh! it is-a dreadful thing, James," said Annie. "I struggled with my feelings for my father and mother's sake. It is only since I came here I have showed such-signs of grief." "And Heaven bless you for coming here this evening," said he. "I would have been here long ago, if I could; I have had a busy evening of it." Annie surveyed him more closely, and noticed how soiled and mud-spattered his clothing was, and that his face was torn with thorns and brambles. "James," said she wildly, the recollection of Cary's threat again rushing into her head, "in God's name, tell me what has happened. Has Cary-" "Exactly, Annie," said he. "I see you know it." "'Father told us," said she, "that he made some threat against you; and that has grieved me more than anything else." "God bless you!" said James, placing his arm around her neck. "I feel his villany more for your sake; I knew it would grieve you. He has put his threat into execution. They are after me now."    \  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7150-00000026"/> "      Annie Reilly. Annie's head fell against his shoulder, and she moaned deeply. "Oh! now I am sorry I have told you so much," said her lover, raising her head, and looking into the beautiful, pale, quivering face. "But now let me tell you more. You promise, Anlnie, now, you promise," and he pressed his lips to hers, " that you will be a brave girl, as you always were? This misery will soon be over." "Oh! yes, I do promise," said she; "but I beg of you to tell me quickly whatever it is." "God bless you, my darling," said he; and again he kissed her. '.' I rely on you, Annie; you are as brave as a little lion, now that your resolution is taken. Well, Cary ' the Pig' (John was known -by this nickname amongst the peasantry), not satis- fied with driving us from house and home, has taken it into his head to make a charge to the police against me. What the nature of the accu- sation is I know no more of than you do; but he actually swore something against me; for my poor father-God help him!-saw the warrant. When the police were in our house a few hours ago, I happened by good luck to be absent at the time; and now they are searching the whole neighborhood for me. My father managed to give me word in time to elude them, and requested *t   An ie Reilly.      47 me, if possible, to return to the house as soon as I could, and he would try and procure money enough to send me to America. I did so, and - he gave me those seven sovereigns. He wanted me to take a few more he had, but I would not. He will need all that can be spared." "O James!" said Annie, and her hand trem-, bled violently in his. "And you are going?" "You promised to be a brave little girl, Annie," replied he, kissing her fervently. "Listen to me. They will surely return after nightfall, in the hope of finding me there; and for your sake, Annie, and for the sake of my poor old father, I must disappoint them. Night is closing around now. We have not long to stay; and again I ask you to promise you will bear up bravely and gaily till we meet- again." "Ah, James!" said the poor girl, and her little hand felt as cold as ice, "till we meet again. When will that be, James?" "In God's good time; and that will be very soon, my love," replied he. "I know I shall get on well in America; and how I shall perse- vere, having such an object to work for-to bring you to me, my darling! Nothing shall deter me; and your innocent, sweet prayers will save me from every danger." Both were silent for a moment. The grass  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7150-00000027"/> 48      Annie Reilly. around them was wet with dew; the thick mist began to envelope the bosom of the river; the mountain-top was no longer visible. The eastern horizon was beginning to assume a golden hue, and it was evident the moon would soon rise. "Annie," said James, looking  cautiously around, "the time has come. I thank God I am not bidding you farewell; but I must bid you good-by, my love, for a few weeks. How swiftly our weeks at school fled away! But those few now will look like so many years to me. But'- they, too, will have an end, and then we will be together again."  '         - Annie was a brave littlei girl. When he held both her hands in his, and looked into her face in the dim light, she was ashy pale; but not a tear fell. A sad smile came on her lips; and when he pressed her to his breast, and again and again kissed her, she did not add to the anguish -of that moment by a sob. And when he darted away in the darkness, and left her alone on the strand, she knelt down and besought Heaven to watch over him.   CHAPTER VI. THE CHARGE AGAINST JAMES O'ROURKE EX- PLAINED. A VISIT TO AN   IRISH MAGIS- TRATE. OHN   G. CARY was a very cautious and a very prudent man. When he observed so many of nature's laws so faithfully, it is needless to say he was not unmindful of the first-self-preservation. Miles O'Rourke or his son had never done him an injury, and, prominently as he shone among other men, they hardly ever mentioned his name or bestowed a thought on him. In fact, Miles and his son belonged to that sensible class of people who mind their own business and let the virtues and failings of their neighbors alone. Cary knew he was about to perpetrate a grievous wrong upon them, and James being, a spirited young fellow, he dreaded he might be revenged upon him. This consideration annoyed Cary considerably for a little time, but for a little time only. In the recesses of his cunning brain he soonhit upon a remedy.  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7150-00000028"/> 50      Annie Reilly. He was sitting in his arm-chair in his shirt- sleeves as usual, biting the ends of his chin whisker, and pondering over the vexed question, when a light suddenly shone upon him, and he -jumped up with a loud "By golly, sir!" that made the crooked-eyed youth jump also, and his eyes jump, too, in a ludicrous manner. "I have hit upon it!" exclaimed Cary, sitting down again, and slapping his knee; but as he did not look towards the wondering youth, the latter did not venture to speak. "Ned," said Cary at length, turning to his charming clerk, "I want you to swear something for me." "Anything you like, sir," replied Ned, half standing up. "You're a splendid fellow, Ned," said he; "you and- I will get along smoothly when we lay our names together." The comely youth grinned from ear to ear, and turned a whole battery of blinks on his kind master. "Ned," said Cary, stretching his legs, " do you know Miles O'Rourke's son?" "Yes, sir," replied Ned; "as well as I know myself, sir." "So far, all right," said Cary. "When have you seen him last?"   Annie Reilly.       51 "I met him and three other fellows on the road three or four nights ago," was the answer. "You must be particular as to dates," said Cary, shaking his head: " say three nights ago. Now, I want you-" "Yes, sir," broke in the ardent youth. "Listen to me," said Cary, with a slight frown. "Now, I want you to make an affidavit before a I   magistrate that you were concealed behind a hedge at the time you saw O'Rourke -and those other chaps, and that you heard them planning to rob the police barracks of the arms there. Go back to your writing now, and I'll call you again when I am prepared to -go with you before the magistrate." Ned grinned again and again-something so very unusual for him that the work must have delighted him beyond measure. Cary, having transacted his morning's business, talked, lied, and cheated as usual-in fact, brought into play a great many of his qualities-at length called Ned to accompany him to the office of the dispenser of law and justice. Now, the private office of an Irish country magistrate is such a very private, sacred spot that some of our readers may not object to accompany the mighty John, the proud Ned, and our humble self into the presence of Richard Scruffy, Esq., J P., on this occasion.  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7150-00000029"/> 52       Annie Reilly. Richard Scruffy, Esq., J P., was a very fair type of the Irish J P. some years ago, or, in fact, would not be altogether out of fashion to-day. Short and stout in figure, with an immense red face, small forehead, and very bald head, an ex- pression of haughty contempt, tinged with a shade of profound knowledge, slowly moving in terrible waves across his countenance, he looked the-very picture of stern, unbending justice. He wore a blue body-coat, wide in the skirts, and very tight in the shoulders: wide trowsers, white as snow, save one large discolored spot on one thigh, iche smell of which, taken in conjunc- tion with the high color of his face, might lead a malicious person to imagine something he had no right to; a. long, wide vest, which seemed to be in open rebellion with the rest of his. attire, so fierce, staring, and puckered was it; and an im- mense black neck-cloth. The apartment in which he sat was of very small dimensions-four like Richard Scruffy, Esq., J P., would fill it to overflowing. It con- tained, besides Richard-he always sat there at least half the day, knowing vigilance is one of Justice's handmaids-a little round table with very dirty legs, one gigantic chair, and a row of shelving filled with large law-books, these latter looking so very dry that one wondered how any   Annie Reilly.      53 sensible insurance company could be induced to give a policy on them. The large chair served two purposes: first, it served as a judicial bench; and, secondly, as a bed for the justice; for, not having much business on hand, being supported by a stipend, Richard slept just as often as Justice did, and often she found it no very easy matter to rouse him up. When that impartial goddess, in the double shape of John G. Cary and Ned Buttler, articled clerk of the aforesaid John, came to the office door, and when Cary struck the door thrice with his knuckles and once with his foot, and then put his ear to the keyhole, the only re- sponse was the slow, regular snore of Richard within. Cary scratched his head, and, looking round at Ned, said: "Here's a fix. What am I to do?" "Dunt the door again, sir," was the prompt reply. "I don't know about that," said Cary, looking somewhat in dread; "he has such a bad temper, if we were to rouse him up suddenly, he might get so mad that he'd clear us both out. I'll stand back by the wall there, and do you come here to the door, and give a rap or two." Ned quickly changed places with his master. and gave the door two such knocks that Cary  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7150-00000030"/> 54      Annie Reilly. raised his eyes, hands, and heels at the same time. Ned listened; still no answer. "Try it again," said Cary, in a heavy whisper, which could be heard much further away than his loudest call; " this time with your foot."' Cary's eye caught a glimpse of Ned's heel as it swung behind him. The next moment a loud - crash sounded on his ears, followed by the noise of something falling inside, and then a stifled  voice within the office called out,  "Murder! Housebreaking! Where am I?"  Cary knew the magistrate's voice, and retreated as far as the gate, whe're he stood with his head just inside the entrance, and by numerous excited gestures and heavy whispers directed the equally  alarmed Ned to speak. "Who are you, you scoundrel?" again de-  manded the voice.  "Speak," exclaimed Cary, bending down and- lifting a large paving-stone, " or I'll scatter your brains against the wall."           It's me, sir," said Ned, in a husky voice, and turning his head towards -Cary. "Let him hear you," said the latter, holding the stone in a very threatening attitude. "Say  it's a man to do his duty, according to the law."- I "Where is my vagabond servant? Where are   I Annie Reilly.     55 my pistols? Is there no one to come to -my re- lief? said the voice inside. "It's a man according to the law," said Ned, "and wants to see you badly, sir. We're here this hour."' "You're a nice man to mention the name of the law," said the voice, "and come here and conduct yourself like a burglar, which I have no doubt you are." "Say: Your honor, we only want to speak with you a minute or two," said Cary. "Our honors only want to speak with you a minute or two," said Ned, in his excite- ment. A pause followed, during which John shook the stone ominously at Ned, and pledged him- self to straighten the eyes in his head, if he did nothing else. At length Ned heard a footstep enter the office from some other apartment within the building, and then he could hear the angry voice of the magistrate while he rated his servant for his want of vigilance. At length Richard Scruffy, Esq., told the man, in a very loud voice, to open the door. Ned cast a terrified look on Cary, who gave him such. a savage glance in return that it completely turned him round. The key sounded in the door. Ao   &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7150-00000031"/> 56       Annie Reilly. "Stand your ground," whispered Cary, "or I'll knock--" The door was pulled open, and Ned's eyes danced around the apartment, and, alighting on Mr. Scruffy's indignant face, performed a regular "break-down." "Will I bring him in, sir?" asked the servant,. "Oh! no,') replied the magistrate, shading his face; " let him come no nearer to me. He looks like the devil. Ask him  what he wants.   I wish a few of the police were here now." Ned stood still just outside the door, his cap squeezed into a lump in his hand, and kept up a galling, incessant fire of blinks on the magistrate. "What's your business with his honor?" de- manded the servant, in a very haughty voice, and assuming a very threatening attitude; for Ned, as our readers already know, was anything but a strong man. "'He'll tell you all," said Ned, in desperation, and pointing towards Cary, who had advanced his head a little further, to catch what was being' said. The servant glanced towards him, and Cary, seeing he could delay no longer, began to ap- proach the door.   v               ! "This is another of them, sir," said the ser- vant; " but I think, sir, this last fellow is a trades- man of the town."     .5            .:            .   Anmie Reilly.       57 Richard Scruffy, Esq., stretched his neck to look into the yard, and, seeing Cary, smiled, but quickly made up his mind to be stern, as became the majesty of the law; so he frowned grandly, but not exactly on Cary. "Your honor," said the latter, with such a tre- mendous bow that his foot slipped on the pave- ment, and he fell against the side of the door, and his hat tumbled into the office. Cary's hat was always unfortunate, and gave him so much, trouble that we wonder a man of his wisdom did not conclude to go bareheaded. "P--p-pa- par-pardon me, sir," he stammered, as he re- gained his balance, "H-I--I--" "You overdid the thing," said Richard, with a sore attempt at a smile; but quickly added, while his judicial brow lowered, "Do you know that fellow?" pointing to Ned. "He is a deci- dedly roguish-looking fellow. He'll get the gal- lows yet, or my name is not R. Scruffy. How is it he says you know all about him?" , I took hold of him," said Cary, approaching familiarly.  "Don't dirty the floor with your feet," ex- claimed Richard, stamping one of his own on the boards. "Go outside, sir, and wipe them, sir, and stand by the door while you are talking to me, sir."  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7150-00000032"/> 58      Annie Reilly. "Anything at all your honor plazes," said Cary, bursting outside. "I beg your pardon, sir." "And anothet thing I beg to remind you of," said Richard, in a lofty voice, and fitting on his spectacles: " don't bother me with an'account of your rascals. You are the leader of a dangerous crowd." And offended justice climbed into the big chair, and dipped its pen into a huge inkstand. John, not knowing but that terrible pen would indite some words that might ruin him, mounted the door-step, and exclaimed, while the heavy sweat stood on his brow, "Your honor knows me as a loyal, rebel-hating. man." "Confine yourself to the. case," roared the magistrate, " or "- turning to the servant-" you put him outside the gate." The fellow moved' to John's side. "I will, your honor," said Cary. "I came here to your honor to-day, and-brought my young man, in the interest of her Majesty the Queen." "Go on," said the magistrate. "My boy, yer honor, seen and heerd a crowd of rebels plannin'--" "Stop, sir!" exclaimed the magistrate. "I'll swear the boy ; bring him here." The servant guided Ned into. the office, and planted him in front of the magistrate. "Don't you interrupt, on your peril," said the   Annie Reilly.       59 latter, looking over his spectacles at Cary. Cary backed a little nearer the door. The book being handed to Ned, he instantly kissed it. Mr. Scruffy looked at him for fully a minute, to Ned's great comfort, and then said: "That fellow is a fool; I don't think I can take his evidence. What do you think?"-this to the servant. "More knave nor fool," replied that personage. "He's greedy in the good cause, your honor, said Cary, while something painful struggled in his neck. "Wait, Ned, ye --, till his honor says the word."' Ned did wait this time, and related the story to the magistrate in, as near as he could remem- ber, the words his master had told him. Richard's rage knew no bounds. "They" (the gentry, we suppose) " were stand- ing on a volcano which, if it were not quenched with a flood of law, would burst forth and scorch up society itself. Young man, and you, Cary- though you did dirty 'he floor-the Queen of this realm is indebted to you two," said Richard Scruffy, Esq., as he commenced to make out the warrant for young O'Rourke's arrest, and shall, through me, her servant, hear of your exertions on her behalf." Cary's joy knew no bounds.  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7150-00000033"/> 60       Annie Reilly. "Your honor," said he, scratching his head, "I don't know what to do with myself. I don't know how to express my thanks. I am sure we-- "Put them out; clear the office," said the magistrate, with calm, cold dignity.  89a - . . I Of                 . ' ,   CHAPTER VII. "EAVING THE OLD HOME. HEN Annie, with tired limbs and sad, sick heart, returned to the cottage after parting from her lover, she found her father and brother putting' their valuables in a condition for removal to a friend's house some miles distant. Farrell had resolved that they would not wait till the bailiff came to dispossess them, but would move away before suffering the indignity of being turned out by that obnoxious official. Owing to their un- happy state, they did not notice the deep grief exhibited in Annie's face. She set herself to help them in their work at once, calmly, quietly; and, after a little, no one could tell that any other pain lay at her heart except grief for the desola- tion that had fallen on her poor father's home. Love, when shrouded with sorrow, is often a strange feeling. It lies silently gnawing at the heart, but shows itself not to the world. Al- though Annie's face had grown pale and wasted during that night, in the morning she seemed the  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7150-00000034"/> 62  dAnnie Reilly. happiest one of the family-if we can apply the word Ihpapy to that stricken home. Early in the day, Farrell and his son had every- thing ready. All the neighbors came to their assistance; for no man in the parish was more deservedly popular than Farrell Reilly. His ready help to others in their hour of need was not forgotten when his own trouble came. It was drawing towards the close of summer, and Farrell had as much of his crop as the season permitted gathered- in. A number of men, with horses and carts, and everything available for carrying a load, thronged to the little farm. The cattle Francis had driven in the early part of the day to the friend's farm, and by evening every- thing that could be removed was taken away. Farrell, and his wife, and Annie stood by the old cottage, looking after the last load of furniture: as it lumbered down the hillside. -Mrs. Reilly had been very ill all the day, and the family dreaded very much the effect of the last mbment upon her. Farrell and she had lived happily in the old place for over twenty years. Her own family home stood on the top of an adjoining hill looking down on her husband's cottage. Her father and mother had died some years before,* and bad crops and sickness had swept away every member of the family. One of her brothers died * v   Annie Reilly.       63 from hardships endured by hard work in the cold, wet season. Another had left for America many years before, and the only account she ever heard of him was that he had died of yellow fever in Savannah. Still, it was a melancholy pleasure to Mrs. Reilly-to sit in the little garden during the long summer evenings with her knitting, while the rest of the family were engaged elsewhere, and turn her eyes towards her father's house, now un- tenanted, and gaze on its ivy-covered walls and tall, bare chimneys, which seemed to speak to her of times long gone. Then she would think of her childhood days, when she laughed, and sported, and played on the hill-top. Every tree, bush, or rock called back to her memory some recollection of those days. Then she would think of the time when Farrell, a gay young fellow, with a bright, laughing face, used to come and sit by her as she milked the cows in the little sheltered corner field. How she used to delight in annoying him by calling him names, and mocking his old frieze coat, with one new arm, and his old slouch hat, with the piece of black cloth wrong side out sewed on its front with white thread. How she used to refuse to let him help her in anyway, but rebuff him in every way; and then, when he-was gone, cry till her eyes grew red for saying so much to him, and make a resolution never to torment  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7150-00000035"/> "      Annie Reilly. him again--a resolution which was suie to be broken the following evening. Then of the even- ing when Farrell, in spite of all her efforts, in- sisted on carrying the milk-cans a little way for  her, and how very sheepish and red he looked  when he left them down behind the garden-gate, and, turning his eyes away from hers, began to I' fumble the pockets of his coat, and asked her to  speak a word with him. How, when he asked her would she become his wife, and began telling  her how snug and happy he could keep her, how she ran away from him, and told him she thought  him a bigger fool than ever; that night she cried till her heart was sick. , How poor Farrell came  the following evening, and she would not -speak to him nor look at him for some time. How   I Farrell carried the milk-cans for her that evening  again, and begged of her to let him ask her father and mother for their consent; and how delighted he was when she told him she did not care, till she had to knock the hat off his head, and tell him to keep a proper distance. Even then she  could not help laughing at the awkward embar- rassment of Farrell; and how every word stuck in his throat when he came around the following Sunday night, right gaily clad, with a bottle of whisky staring out- of -each pocket, to make the request. Then she would think of what a good,             .          ..'    Anlie Reilly.      65 kind husband Farrell had always been.. If her thoughts came down to the time when her poor brothers, after every effort, failed to keep the old homestead, the tears would fill her eyes, and she would re-enter the cottage. As we said before, Farrell, -and his son and daughter, seeing her distress of mind, and know- ing how fondly she loved the dear old spot, were in great dread lest the. final moment would prove too much for her. Farrell allowed his son to go on, while he and Annie tried to engage the poor woman's thoughts by talking of the great kind- ness of their neighbors, and how well and neatly everything was prepared for the journey. "You see," said Farrell, raising his hat from his eyes, where he had kept it all the morning, and looking round on his wife and daughter, "the kindness and honest generosity of our neighbors altogether take away the bitterness of this day. Surely it is true 'tis only in adversity we can tell our friends. And," added he, with an attempt at a smile, " in our misfortune, we cannot count our friends. We seem to have no enemies at all." "None but the one, Farrell," said Mrs. Reilly, looking at him with a strange, wan, wild look; "and can all the friends in the world make up what he has done? Heaven forgive me!" she  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7150-00000036"/> "      Annie Reilly. added sorrowfully. 'Sure our best friend is God." "Just think of that, now," saidyarrell. He was going to say more, but a scream from Annie startled him, and, turning round, he saw his wife reclining in her daughter's arms, while a stream of blood poured from her nose and down over her face and breast. Farrell took her in his arms, and, handing Annie the key, bade! her open the door again; for, unobserved by Mrs. Reilly, he had locked the door, never again intending to cross the threshold of the cottage. The alarmed girl did so, and, procuring some water in an old. vessel which had been thrown aside, poured it over the face and hands of the fainting woman. Everything they could do was fruitless to stop the flow of blood; and, terribly alarmed, and almost dead from grief, Farrell told Annie to run for the priest. Her hair flowing in wild disorder, and her cheeks wet from tears, Annie started off to the chapel. She found Father Fitzpatrick walking around the church reading. The clergy- man had raised his eyes from the book when she was entering the gate, and, seeing the wild and- alarmed-looking girl coming towards him, ad- vanced to meet her. Seeing who it was, he asked: "Annie, my child, what is the matter?"   Annie Reilly.       67 She stopped short, and for a second or two could make no reply. "What is wrong with you, my child?" he asked again softly, laying his hand on her shoulder. "O father!" said Annie at length, "I fear mother is dying. Pray, father, come quickly to the house with me." The good priest needed no second request, but, hastening into the chapel, prepared himself for the solemn visit. Annie waited for him at his request, and, his car being quickly harnessed, both dashed away at full speed to-to-where was once the home of Farrell Reilly.  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7150-00000037"/> CHAPTER VIII. "EAVING THE OLD HOME. HEN Father Fitzpatrick and Annie reached the cottage, they found Mrs. Reilly still insensible; but the flow of blood from her nose had been stopped. As they drove up the hillside, the clergyman looked with a serious, troubled face at the cottage, with its bare and desolated appear- ance, broken panes, and closed door; then at the little farmyard, in which little heaps of rubbish were lying here and there; but everything else was gone. He sighed heavily, but made no re- mark to Annie. Mrs. Reilly reclined against her husband's breast as he sat on the ground by the wall. "O father dear!" said Farrell, as the priest entered, "I am afraid she is going from us. I knew this would be too much for her. See how ,deadly pale she is.; and I cannot feel her breath." The clergyman bent down, and lifted one of   Annie Reilly.       69 the suffering woman's hands in his, and felt her pulse. "Her pulse is very low, Farrell," said he. "She is certainly very much exhausted. Let me assist you to bring her to the door. She will recover quicker in the open air than here." Both carried her to the door-step, and Farrell supported her in his arms, while the priest chafed ;her hands and temples. Annie's grief knew no bounds. She could not silence her sobs,- and, as in her present state she could be of no service to her mother, the priest requested her to keep within the house., This poor Annie could not do, but stood apart wring- ing her hands and moaning sadly. At length the clergyman announced that the sufferer's pulse beat more lively, and that she would soon recover. "Oh! thank heaven, father," said Annie, ap- proaching and peering into her mother's face. "IDo you think truly she will recover?" "With God's help, my child," returned he, -"I jthink she will recover sufficiently to-" He stopped suddenly, and Annie and her father looked into his anxious, gentle face. Farrell well knew what the father would have added, and, raising his eyes to heaven, exclaimed, in a voice that went to the kind priest's heart:  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7150-00000038"/> 70      Annie Reilly. "Lord, look down on us to-day! We are in- deed but poor outcasts." Gradually the fingers of the hand Father Fitzpatrick held in his began to move, the white lips parted a little, the poor woman opened her eyes for an instant, and, seeming to notice the priest, she faintly uttered: "Thanks be to God!" After a few moments, her eyes opened again, and she looked around on the little group. Speak to me, Mary.  ne; word to poor me," said Farrell, putting the si of his face tohers- "one word." "Oh! that is yoq, Farrell," said she. "Where are we?" "We are -here in the old home yet," said he. "Yet, Farrell," said she, in a voice so low and weak as to be hardly audible, "I thought Annie and I were on board a very large ship going to America, and that you were beyond waiting for us." "Father Fitzpatrick is here, Mary," said her husband gently. "Oh! and he was in my dream, too," said Mrs. Reilly. , "Thank God and His Holy Mother you have recovered!" said the priest, again lifting her   Annie Reilly.       71 hand; " that your life has been spared this time. You will soon be well again. I will wait a little till you are beyond danger; but I think 'tis not necessary to administer to you." "Oh! thank you a thousand times for that, father," said Annie, in a whisper. "You being here will keep her from thinking of our downfall till we are away from this place." t"Away from this place?" said the priest, with a startled look. "Oh! yes, father; Cary put us out. .But don't mention it now," looking at her mother; "( father will explain all to you. We are moving to my cousin's house, and must leave here to-night. Everything belonging to us is gone." The good priest's heart sank within him. The oldest and most respectable family in his parish banished so ruthlessly. What would follow next? He thought of the blessings of the union, and re- solved to join the National Association as soon as expedient. Mrs. Reilly's strength  continued to return slowly; and the kind, gentle priest entered into a quiet conversation with her on the improve- ments he was making in his new church; told her how beautiful the altar of the Blessed Virgin would look when completed. "Were it not for the devotion of yourself and  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7150-00000039"/> 72      Annie Reilly. some other good ladies of the parish, in decorat- ing it with flowers," he went on, " it would have looked very poorly indeed during the month of May devotions. But now we will soon have a -new altar, with candlesticks from Paris; and the 'Virgin and Child' which we had then will be too small, so I am going up to Dublin in a few days to purchase an elegant one, and you must come and give me your opinion of it before we' set it up; -and then those two windows on each side of the altar are going to be taken out. A wealthy Irish-American gentleman, a namesake of mine, whom I met on his way to the lakes a- few days ago, is going to put in beautiful stained glass in its place;' so that I think, when every- thing is completed, we'll not have much right to feel ashamed of our little chapel." The kind, affectionate -manner and chat of the good pastor soothed so much the anguish the poor woman felt that it almost made her forget her desolation for the time. He continued to engage her thoughts in this manner till he saw she was strong enough to be assisted into his car and taken to her new home. Farrell and Annie thanked him fervently for his kind proposition; the four seated themselves in the car, and, as they did so, the priest began relating a comic incident about one of Ihis parishoners, whom the others   Annie Reilly.        73 knew very well, which he kept up till they were out. of view of the cottage. If he saw any signs of the return of the deep sorrow they had felt in the face of any of his companions, he instantly be- spoke that one's-attention, and talked and laugh- ed incessantly till they reached the house of Maurice Handley, which was their destination. After again receiving their heartfelt thanks, and giving them his blessing, Father Fitzpatrick re- turned home with as sad a heart as those he. had parted from.  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7150-00000040"/> CHAPTER IX. TOSSED ABOUT ON THE WAVES OF ADVERSITY. AURICE  HANDLEY, Farrell's ne- phew, lived in a cosey little cottage a short way from the broad road and close by the demesne wall of Castle- saunderson, the Irish residence of Colonel Saunder- son, the gentleman who had sold the town-land containing Reilly and O'Rourke's farms to Cary and Crofton. He, too, was a tenant of Saunder- son's. Maurice was,a young man of thirty or thereabouts, and only a year married. His wife was a strong, healthy young woman, with an abundance of black hair and a very sharp, rather unfriendly face. A small fruit of their union, in the shape of a pretty little girl about six weeks old, had already appeared, and Maurice was very happy.  But the sudden desolation that had fallen on his uncle had pained him very much. His mother had died a few years before, and Maurice was very much attached to her, and used to listen with pride and pleasure to her stories about the old home. Father Fitzpatrick, before leaving, had caution-   Annie Reilly.       75 ed him and his wife to be careful and mention nothing relating to the misfortune that had be- fallen his uncle's family in the hearing of Mrs. Reilly, but to talk over other matters, and appear as gay as possible. Both thanked the good priest for his advice, and promised to strictly obey his instructions. Francis and Annie, too, entered into the plot, and, hard as the effort was, conduct- ed themselves as they used to do in the old home before sorrow came there. The nephew, in order to carry out the plan to the fullest, resolved to make their first evening one of rejoicing, and procured the necessary articles from the village for that purpose. Mrs. Handley and Annie set out for the shop, together, and, now that she was from the presence of her heart-broken parents, and had one of her own sex to confide in, her tears began to fall, and she lamented bitterly their sad situation. Mrs. Handley's only effort to comfort her was .by re- minding her that she saw no cause for her lament- ing now that she had found a home so quickly, and added that many whom she had known to be "put out " had no friends to open their door to them, but. let them go to the poor-hodse. "Oh!" said Annie, looking surprised through her tears at the cutting words of the other, "I don't think we are so far reduced as to be comrn-  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7150-00000041"/> 76      Annie Reilly: i            % pelled to go to the poor-house. Father has a little left yet." "No danger of him or- you either going there while Maurice has a home. That man thinks more of, his friends than I believe is good for him. Whatever your father has got, he can hold on to it now." Annie's face flushed, and her eye kindled; this cold taunting in the day of her distress she could not be silent under. "Martha," she replied, drying her tears, " had we known how unwelcome we were to you, we could very easily have found a home with some of our neighbors." "Oh! I didn't intend to vex you at all," replied Martha, with a toss of her head. "For my part, you are welcome to stay here as long as you like." "We will not trouble you long," replied Annie. "I shall tell my brother, and he will provide some place for us. You ma3 rely on it." The two then walked on in silence, Martha amusing herself with humming a verse of an old country ballad. Maurice was all kind- ness and hospitality, and succeeded so well in entertaining the old pair that evening that, before they parted for the night, both felt much happier than they had at any time since   Annie Reilly.       " their desolation. When the others were engag- ed, Annie beckoned Francis to follow her, and when he did so, led him to the edge of the grove, and, sitting down on the grass, addressed him thus: "Francis, I have tried- hard to keep my feelings from my father and mother this evening." "That was a great effort on my part, too," re- pliedFrancis. "Oh! but, Francis," she said, "you don't know as much as I do. By Maurice's wife we are heartily unwelcome here. I had a few words with her on our way to the village this evening. She insulted me very badly." And Annie put her apron to her eyes and began to cry. "Oh! nonsense, Annie," said Francis, drying her tears; " tell me what has passed. I could see it in her to-night by the way she looked at father and mother, and kept continually finding an excuse to make one or the other shift their place at the fire, that we were anything but wel- come. But then, Maurice is such a generous- hearted fellow himself I would rather not notice this for awhile, till we can find some little place of our own." "Not for the world," said Annie, " would I let mother know of it. I hope she has not noticed it herself already. She would sooner lie in this \  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7150-00000042"/> 78      Annie Reilly. wood at night than there, if she once thought we were unwelcome." "-I'll tell you, Annie," said Francis, after a short pat, "what I intend doing. Colonel Saunder- son as lately built a number of small cottages, which he intends filling with his workmen; and I am thinking of seeking work at the castle and, if I obtain it and one of those little houses, we will be somewhat independent again." "Ah! Francis, that is a good thought," said Annie; " but I fear it would break poor mother's heart living amongst such people as her neigh- bors then would be. And then, you a workman at the castle." "I have thought, of all that," said Francis. "When mother reflects, I don't think she will take it so bad after all. Along -with what little we have got, I could soon earn enough to bring us to America. I could not think of leaving them, now that they have nothing only my exer- tions to rely on." "' Francis," said Annie earnestly, " what do you think of this? I cannot be of much service to you here--none at all, in fact; only a burden. And now, if you think father could spare enough to send me to America alone, I could earn enough there to be of great help to you." "Ah! I am afraid they would never consent to I" '        ,1 .j -i   Annie Reilly.      79 you crossing the ocean alone," said Francis. "For my part, I know very well you would suc- ceed. I wish you had thought of this when James O'Rourke was going; but," he added, "you couldn't easily have done that. It would not have been very pleasant to be under the pro- tection of a man in the danger poor James was in." Francis felt the hand he held in his tremble, and, looking around, he saw Annie struggling to keep back her tears. "Weir, well, Annie," said he, with a smile, I.1 shouldn't have spoken of James to you now; but you know he succeeded in getting off safely, so that he is now beyond danger, and you and he may meet on the other side of the water some day. I have it now, my girl," and he slapped the back of her hand. "I would bet a sovereign, if I had it, that your whole anxiety to get to America is because James O'Rourke is there." And he laughed and shook her by the hair. "No, indeed, Francis," said she; "you do me wrong there.' I should certainly be glad to meet him or any other friend in a strange country; but my whole anxiety is to be able to assist you at home." "I didn't doubt you, Annie," said he. "You must pardon what I have said. You are a great good girl and a wise girl- "  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7150-00000043"/> 80      A nnie Reilly. "Well, well, now, Francis," said she, interrupt- ing him, ' mother will get alarmed if we stay here much longer; and so let us decide on what to do. After what passed this evening, you would not ask your sister to remain in that woman's house; and I beg of you to help me to make father and mother let me go. Mother will not be so hard to induce as you think. Nancy Brady had a letter from her daughter Kitty a couple of weeks ago, and showed it to mother. It gave a- splendid account of New York, and contained five pounds and a promise of five more before the end of summer. You know mother always liked Kitty, and would not have the least doubt of anything she'd say. Now, if I got along as well as Kitty, I could have you with me before three months, and surely both of us could keep the old pair comfortably at home if they would rather live here.' "Oh! Annie, how can I plead with them to let you go away from us? But sure, I see the truth of every word you say." "God bless you, Francis!" said she. "We will go back and say no more about it to-night; but delay is useless, you know, so we will try them to-morrow evening.' s    -    CHAPTER X. ' MY NATIVE LAND, GOOD-NIGHT!" -Byron. ELL REILLY and his wife were a very common-sense couple; none of those sentimental people who sit down and weep and mourn over mis- fortune, and close their eyes to every effort at overcoming it. They saw something must be done, and done quickly; and, painful and dis- tressing as it was to them, the plan for the future laid down by their son and daughter met their approval much easier than the latter had expect- ed. Mrs. Reilly wept bitterly for some minutes, and poor Farrell wrung his hands and paced up and down the floor a few times; then, turning' to Annie, who tried to wear as cheerful a face as she could, he said: "In' God's name, my child, I'll make no objec- tion." "Nor I, Annie," said her mother. "I will be- seech Heaven, night and day, to watch over you, and the just and merciful God will one day, I hope, allow us to see your face again."  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7150-00000044"/> 82      Annitie Reilly. )It is needless to dwell on the incidents of the few days spent in Annie's preparation for her journey. She went to confession to the good Father Fitzpatrick, and told him of her intention, and received his blessing and a promise that he would say a Mass for her safety while on the wide ocean. The night previous to her departure soon came, and a number of the friends of the family assembled at Maurice Handley's to take farewell of Annie and bid- her Godspeed on her journey. Mrs. Reilly was seated on a chair, on one, side of the room, her head resting on her hand, watching Annie ana Francis packing up the little- trunk, and Farrell stood by the window, looking out on the road, when the first visitor, Nancy Brady, called upon them. She carried a small bundle in her hand containing some linen and worsted, and a bunch of green shamrock, which she intended sending with Annie to her daughter in America. The brother andoister were right glad to see her, and gave her a warm welcome; for they knew all she had to say in praise of America would hefp to console their mother for the evening. Nancy was a poor widow, and lived in a small cabin by the wayside, a little distance from the old home of Reilly. After the death of her hus- band, and when she was left with her little girl .*   Annie Reilly.       83 in extreme poverty, Farrell Reilly had been a good friend to her, often supplying her for months with provisions, when otherwise her child and herself might have perished of want. It grieved the poor old lady sorely, the misfortune that had befallen her benefactor and his family. Her cabin-door commanded a view of the cottage, and, when the family were gone, she built up the door on that side, and opened another on the op- posite end of the cabin. The moment she entered Handley's and saw Mrs. Reilly, she smiled as if she felt quite happy, and, seating herself by her side, began to praise their good wisdom in send- ing Annie to America. "My poor daughter," she went on, " that had -neither education nor much ability of any kind, see how well she is doing. Since she went to I America, I have never known the want of a shil- ling. IAnd your daughter, Mrs. Reilly, the best scholar--as Mr. Lacy often told me-at his school, and so smart in every way, how is she going to get along?" Mrs. Reilly said very little, but let the good- hearted creature talk on in this strain. The effect of what she was saying, however, was not lost on the other, and she soon felt well enough to assist Mrs. Brady and. Annie in completing the trunk.  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7150-00000045"/> 84  '    Annie Reilly. Amongst those who came to bid the girl fare- well were a- number of young men, sons of the neighboring farmers, most of whom one day in- tended taking the same course. These in par- ticular laid themselves out to enliven the party% and spend a pleasant night. Annie's health and \ prosperity we: drunk a hundred times. - Numer- ous songs were sung, mostly patriotic, or bearing on the event which assembled them together. Thus the night passed away, and morning came. None of the family went to sleep; for, by the time the last of those who were going no further than the house had left, it was time for Annie, and those who intended leaving her at the railway station, to depart, too. As the time for her parting from her daughter approached, Mrs. Reilly felt her heart growing doubly sad, and she dreaded she would break down at the last moment. The state of her health did not permit her to leave the house. Nancy tried to engage her attention now more than ever. At length Annie went into the room to put on her hat. Noticing this, her mother's face grew deadly pale, and she nervously clutched Nancy's hand.   "Oh! now, after bearing up so well all night," said the latter, while her own voice quivered,   I          4Annie Reilly.     85 "you would not go to break your heart and your child's, too, at the last moment. In pity to her, don't show such signs of grief. What a happy woman I would have been to see my daughter going as Annie is. The morning she -left, not one was in the cabin but little Francis- he was little then-who called in on his way to I school. And Annie this morning leaves you for a happy land with a thousand blessings on her head." Soon Annie came out from the room, with her neat blatck hat and new cloak on, surrounded by a crowd of friends. How pretty she looked, the paleness of her face only serving to reveal more clearly her finely arched, dark eyebrows! Had James O'Rourke seen her at that, moment, he would have loved her better than ever, if love could be stronger than his. Farrell ran from the cottage like one wild; he could not bear to be present at the parting. "Now is the time for your fortitude and charity, too, Mrs. Reilly," whispered the old lady, as Annie approached. "Just kiss your mother and ask her blessing, and leave at once, Annie," said Mrs. Brady. "The less time you spend here now, the better for both of you." The girl bent over her mother.  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7150-00000046"/> 86      Annie Reilly. "My child! my darling! my own Annie!" ex- claimed Mrs. Reilly, " in this, the saddest hour of my life, I call on God to be just to that man who drove us apart so soon, and sent you out alone on the world to-day. O Annie! if ever an unhappy mother died of a broken, crushed heart, it. will be me if anything befalls you." And mother and daughter were locked in each other's arms. The spectators turned away from the heartrending scene, and a tear came into every eye. My sweet child, my fond Annie, that was always such a loving daughter to us, it has been a source of sorrow to me since I first watched for your footsteps to think I would one day have to part from you ; but I would have lain cold in my grave long ago had I ever known .or thought you would be -left a lone bird far away from father, mother, or brother." She sobbed as she pressed the girl close to her heart. "O mother!" said Annie, " my love for you will be stronger than ever now, and will urge me to make every effort to come to your arms again. Give me-your blessing, your fond blessing, and neither of us need fear anything." "My blessing, and God's choicest blessing, and the blessing of all the saints in heaven for ever be with you, my child," said her mother, raising her hands. "And that blessing I will invoke night   Annie Reilly.       87 and day on your head while God leaves me life." They held their faces together, mingling their tears in silent, inutterable anguish, till Mrs. Brady said softly in the mother's ear, "Mrs. Reilly, you have blessed your child, we have all blessed her; 'tis needless to delay longer. Your next'meeting will be a happy one." And thjrgood woman gently withdrew the arms that embraced the girl, and whispered her to leave at once. After fer- vently kissing the, cold, wet face, Annie ran from the house, and was gone. It was a beautiful morning in the month of August; a drop of dew glistened on every'blade of grass and on every thorn. The webs of the busy spider covered every tree and shrub, and the lark's first note of welcome to the rising sun was heard from the wood -close by. Farrell joined the group that had followed Annie, and the little crowd set out for the neigh- boring station ; Maurice had gone on a little be- fore with the trunk, to have it marked, and ready when the train would arrive. Farrell intended accompanying her as far as Queenstown, but Francis was to- return from the station to his mother. , The morning had passed away so quickly that, just as they came within view of the station,  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7150-00000047"/> 88   '   Annie Reilly. the whistle of the engine sounded shrilly over a hill close by, and the next moment a long line of cars shot out on the plain before them, and swept up to the station. A delay of half an hour, how- ever, would occur, and they reached the platform just as an old priest, with long, white hair and bent figure, was giving his parting blessing to a number of emigrants who knelt on the platform around him. Annie hastily made her way and knelt doown on the edge of the crowd. Amongst them were young men and girls, married men and their wives and children. Even grandfathers and grandmothers, who had bravely struggled for a lifetime to 'live and die in the old land, knelt there to receive the' last blessing from an Irish priest, and then face Athe wild Atlantic, probably to die of hardships by the way, or lay their bones to rest as soon as they reached the new land. Beneath the face of God, there is no sadder sight than to witness those old, helpless, broken-hearted creatures, who love their native land next to their God, when every earthly hope has failed, gather- ed at the foot of the saintly priest, to ask his blessing on their flight. What hope they place in this ldst benediction in, the Isle of Saints God only can tell! A warning whistle announced to Annie and the others that it was time to go aboard. -She   'Annie Reilly.      89 hastily took farewell of her friends, and having affectionately kissed her brothes, and bade him be good and true to their aged parents, and 'have every hope in her, hurried into the car, fol- lowed by her father. Her brother and friends stood together on the platform, replying to the white handkerchief which kept waving to them from the carriage window till the train moved out of sight. It was late in the evening when they arrived in Queenstown, and, as the ship by which Annie in- tended going was not expected in till the following morning, they sought a lodging-house for the night. The lodging-house was within view of the beautiful harbor, and the young girl sat by the window in the dim twilight watching the emigrants clamber- ing on board a vessel which had just arrived from Liverpool. Farrell sat with his elbows resting on a little round table which stood in the middle of the room, eagerly scanning an engraving of New York Bay which hung on the opposite wall. A strange feeling came over Annie. She could not take her eyes from the ship, and she heartily wished she had been in time to sail by it. Why she felt thus she could not tell. Her memory wandered to James O'4ourke. What sort of ship did he cross over in? How did he spend his- time aboard, and what kind of friends did he O    " '           'r F  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7150-00000048"/> 90      Annie Reilly. make? Did he enliven them with his flute, or did he stand silently alone looking out oll the wide waters? This latter she thought more likely. It greqw dark, afnd, though she could no longer see those on board, the tall mast and yard-arms were yet faintly visible through the fading light, and she could hear the voices of the sailors as they called out to each other. A light shone on deck. A man carrying a lantern passed along close by the bulwark, and the reflection fell on the form of a man standing alone with his arms folded, just :': Annie thought a moment before James would stand. She knew the figure. No, it could not be James. He had gone a week ago. The man looked down, the gangway, and held the light before him. God! if he would only turn its light the other way. She leaned from the window, -and strained her eyes almost to bursting. At length the light turned in the coveted direction, and she sa:the figure move slowly away. It could be n:other. Yes; it was no other than James O'Rourke. She knew the form, the clothes, everything. Surely it was he. She had pre- sence of mind enough not to alarm her father, knowing how useless it would be. She waited and watched,\ in hopes to see the light return. But, no; the sky darkened for rain, and she could no   A   nnie Reilly.    g 91 longer see even the main-mast; still her eyes were bent in that directior. Soon the rain began to fall. A flash of lightning filled the room, fol- lowed by a crash of thunder that shook the very walls. Annie seemed not to notice it. Another flood of lightning, more terrible than the first, filled the air outside, and, darting outwards, revealed the ship slowly moving out to sea. Neither Annie nor her father slept much during the night, and both were up early and waiting at the ticket-office for the clerk to open. Farrell paid the passage-money, and gave her besides all he could possibly spare, in case she should need it when she reached New York.  About noon, the noble ship came in sight, and soon anchored in the harbor. The parting be- tween her father and Annie was quite as affect- ing as the morning one. Having her luggage taken aboard, she joined the stream of human cargo scrambling and jostling each other up 'the ship's side.   &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7150-00000049"/> CHAPTER XI. "VERPOOL MAN-CATCHERS AND LODGING- HOUSES. HE shall now return to James O'Rourke, whom we left in the rather unpleasant position of bidding a hasty good-by to his sweetheart, while he dreaded every moment the faithful upholders of justice and fair play in Ireland would be upon him. After parting from Annie, he turned his steps northward, hoping to reach Dublin before the authorities there could be apprised of his flight. He deemed it better to take this direction, as the police would be certain to warn their brothers at Queenstown to look out for him. Neither did he think it prudent to travel by the main roads, but kept to the by-lanes and open country. The short night passed quickly away, but, when morning came, James had left his home a long way behind,.and found himself in a part of the country totally unknown to him. By making enquiries of some laborers who were going to their toil at that early hour, he found the road to Dub- lin; and, as his apprehensions had calmed con-   Annie Reilly.       93 siderably since he left his native county, he struck boldly into the road, and that evening, tired and footsore, reached the city. The Liverpool boat was about to leave in a few minutes after he reached the dock, and, as he did not care to delay in the capital, he took passage, and was soon out on the Irish Sea. James and his fellow-passengers had a pleasant voyage. The night was calm and fine on their departure, and continued so till morning; when, just as tall wreaths of smoke began to curl up from the houses along the Mersey, they reached Liverpool. A motley crowd of ship-runners and lodging-house keepers met the passengers on their landing, and surrounded them like a pack of hungry wolves; some crying out they repre- sented such a ship-" the very best on the ocean " -and beseeching all sensible passengers who valued their health and future prosperity to take no other; some frantically roaring out the nume- rous striking qualities lof their boarding-house: what attention-we don't doubt that-what good meals, what cleanliness was to be found there. It would be much better for those man-catchers, as they are called, not to mention cleanliness, lest some inquisitive emigrant should look at their faces and hands,"and begin to reflect, till, seeing they told one lie, probably doubt all they '   &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7150-00000050"/> 194      A nnie Reilly. had to say'- But shout, and yell, and declaim they will, and, always give their voices a little higher pitch at the word cleanliness. James, not being encumbered with much baggage, escaped pretty well till he reached the dock, where he stood looking at the scramble, and din, and noise going on on the gangway and around him. It looked like a fierce charge on a well-fought field, only more terrible; for, when a man fell here, no, companion in swind-in arms, bore him tothe rear.    . The man-catchers bore down on the passen- gers as they left the boat, the latter slowly but steadily driving them back. Old scoundrels, who had made emigrant-swindling a lifelong business, and were very much attached to it now, were knocked down and walked over every day by their stronger competitors; but, nothing daunted, they would be at their post the following morn- ing as determined as ever. At length, when the strife subsided, and the as- sailants began to carry off their spoils, in the shape of innocent men, women, and children who had probably never seen a city before, James, seeing a man standing with his back towards him, clad in very shiny black, looking out on the river, made up his, mind to .ask him the way to the ticket-office. Thinking he must be some distin-         ,   Annie Reilly.      95 guished personage, James approached respect- fully, and said, "Please, sir, will you be kind enough to direct me to the shipping-office? I am going to America." The man turned towards him, and, if James O'Rourke had been a keen observer, he would have seen at once that a front view of the gentqe- man was hardly in keeping with the appearance he presented from behind. His face was very long and irregular, his mouth very wide-much wider than nature had intended it should be, as a deep, bluish scar on one- side added consider- ably to its proportions. His eyes were very small and round, and seemed determined, through time, on making their way through his brain to the other side. His nose seemed to have -met the same adverse fate as his mouth. It hung down in a heavy red bunch in front, owing, we think, to the part nearest the eyes being completely flattened, probably by some blunt instrument, as the doctors say. His forehead--well, that very important part of his head was concealed from view by an immense wide-brimmed hat, which had once been as shiny as his coat, but was now assuming an auburn hue. He wore his coat buttoned up close, a yellowish necktie, but no collar. "My dear young fellow, hi shall be 'appy to  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7150-00000051"/> 96      Annie Reilly. direct -you," said he, turning to James, on hearing his question. "Step this 'ere way a little." And he led him a few yards further away from the boat. "Hof course, you want to sail by the best line?"        f  "Certainly I do, sir," said James, after a little hesitation, 4" if it does not cost any more; for, to tell you the truth-" "Not ha penny more than the leakiest hold tub as crosses ithe Atlantic. 'Ere his the name hof the ship; she sails to-morrow morning." "Thank God!" thought James, delighted at the prosct of spending so little time in Liverpool. Now, it so happened that the gentleman, in showing the notice to James, flaunted it a little too much, so that it caught the eyes of a number of disappointed man-catchers, who were standing here and there, looking very rapacious and sullen. In a moment they were upon them, pushing bills into James's hand, and each begging of him to put no trust in the others, but be guided by him. , The old gentleman was pushed to the outside of the crowd in a moment, but his frantic warnings could be heard above all. One in his desperation caught him by the hand, and tried to pull it open, that he might leave his card there. "Let me speak, for heaven's sake," said James.   Annie Reilly.      97 "Yes, sir; yes, sir; say whatever you have to say, and come on with me," exclaimed half a dozen voices. "I am going with none of you, blast you!"  shouted James, dashing from their midst. "This gentleman," pointing to the man he had first spoken to, "has kindly consented to do all I want for me." "All right, go with him; I wish you luck. You'll not get skinned. Oh! no," said the same voices. ' What - do they mean by attacking a person in that way?" asked James of the other, who had taken his arm to lead him off. "Ho! that's the way as they do things haround 'ere hin general," replied the other, pulling down his tie, which in the scuffle had got, up around his ears. "You're ha fort'nate man to miss 'em." "Please direct me to the office," said James, looking back at the crowd. "I'll leave Liverpool as soon as I can." "Ho! you must not judge Liverpool by what you see 'ere- this mornin'," said his companion. "When you see the place as I'll take ye to, your hopinion of the Hinglish 'ill change; but we'll go to the hoffice first." They walked a long way along the docks, his piohpanion still holding James by the arm, and  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7150-00000052"/> 98      Annie Reilly. pointing out all the places of interest to stran- gers-which, by the way, were chiefly high, old, dirty-looking stores, with broken doors and windows, outside of which sat groups of ill- clad, ill-favored looking men, black with smoke and grease; and an occasional large dray, pulled by huge, lazy horses-so lazy that you would want to be close by before knowing whether they were moving or not-was also an object of curiosity to James. At length they turned iip a side street, walking over heaps-of half-naked women and chil- dren at every step, till they reached a somewhat neat-looking building-neat only when contrasted with its neighbors-and entered an office on the ground floor. The only furniture of any kind it contained was a triangular desk of very doubtful material, and a fat, dull-eyed, middle-aged man of undoubted Saxon nationality. He was eating a, lump of cheese, which he held in the palm of his hand, and did not seem to notice them as they entered. "The best-'arted man in the world," whris- pered the guide. James thought, if that were so, it had very little control over his manner; but he said nothing. "How d'ye do, Mr. Bluffy?" said the other, ap- proaching the desk. "I 'opes as yer well, sir." } -'Well enough," was the reply. "Have you Jo,   Annie Reilly.      99 done anything to-day? I am afraid you're going in the back of the books here, Lantern." "Why, 'ow is that, Mr. Bluffy? said that gen- tleman, with a rueful look, which was his best look. "Han't hi hout hearly and late a watch- in' and a strivin' for this 'ere company?" "That may all be," said Bluffy, reaching for a pint of ale which a boy had just entered with, but you an't doing anything." Mr. Bluffy put the measure to his mouth and drained it to the last drop, smacked his lips, handed it back to the boy, and added: "There's where the mistake comes in." " Do you call this 'ere nothin'?" said Mr. Lan- tern, pointing to James. "Hi took 'im from thirty on 'em ; hi did that, Mr. Bluffy." "Well, well," said the other, "a bob, and no more about it." "Ho Mr. Bluffy, Mr. Bluffy!" And he put an old, torn red handkerchief, which came-out of his pocket like a rope, to his'eyes. "Hi earns it 'ard as hany man, hand why not "-a sob-" give me the same has hanother man?" "You know the rules," said the other: " one bob for one, three bob for two, and so forth."' "Them 'ere rules is 'ard on a poor man'," blubbered Lantern. But looking ,towards James, and noticing  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7150-00000053"/> IOO      Annie Reilly. he was not so shabbily clad as the majority of emigrants, he brightened up a little, and, approaching near to his patron, whispered a word in his ear. The latter let his heavy eyes fall on James, and said: "All right, if it can be done;" "Come 'ere now, my-young friend," said Lan- tern, " hand get yer ticket," James walked up to the desk. "Give me the money," said the man behind it. "How much is it, sir?" asked James anx- iously.  "5 I5s." was the reply. O'Rourke's face flushed a little. "I thought, sir," he said, "5 Ios. was the highest rate of passage?" Bluffy looked at Lantern, and the latter quickly said : "The hextia vive bob his for hextra accom- modation. Mr. Bluffy, the best-'arted man in Hingland, says as 'ow you'll not be treated like hanother passenger." "Oh! but I am satisfied to -rough it with the rest," said James. "My funds are very low." "All right," grunted Bluffy, " if you want to sleep up by the engine, and have the smoke and dirt blowing over you every night." And he be- gan to make out the ticket.   SBAnnie Reilly.                IoI " Young man, you're ha destroyin' of yourself. You may get blinded," whispered Lantern, clutch- ing James by the arm. " Let me hadvise you, has a honest man as does fair by 'is fellow-man, to change your mind." " I'll pay it, then," said James; " but it seems strange to charge more than the advertised rate." "Your wisdom 'ill make yer fortin', young man," said Lantern, not heeding the latter part of the other's remark. James paid the money, and turned away; but, as he did so, the corner of his eye caught Mr. Lan- tern picking up two of the very half-crowns he had paid, and thrusting them hurriedly into his pocket. He was about to make some remark, but, thinking it might be some money due him by the other, he merely sighed and wished himself out of Liverpool. Mr. Lantern joined him outside the office, and conducted him down to the docks again, and along in the direction from which they had just come, then up a very narrow, dirty street, with high, bare, miserable-looking houses on each side, which had not received a brush of whitewash or paint in half a century, if they ever received one. The greater part of these buildings were eating and lodging-houses, and the smell of bad meat, rotten cabbage, and garbage of every kind  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7150-00000054"/> 102      A nnie Reilly. which they sent into the street made the atmo- sphere well-nigh intolerable. At length Mr. Lan- tern stopped at one of the most ill-looking places they had met, with an old weather-beaten sign over the door, on which was scrawled, in almost unintelligible letters, "Lodging and Entertain- ment." "This is the 'ouse where you'll be comfortable till mornin'," said Lantern. "Come halong, sir." James followed him, and, as he entered the door, the abominable smell that filled the place was ten times worse than that in the street. A small door just inside the entrance opened in a very dark little room which fronted on the street. This room, 'like its brothers in every house in that street, had its window continually closed with half-rotten, whitish shutters; and as these managed  to keep together, the room  was left all day, at any rate, without a single ray of light. Its door was standing ajar as James passed, and, happening to look that way, the thick darkness, with here and there the back of an old'white chair dimly visible, like a shy ghost, made him hurry, after his guide into the room directly behind this one. This latter was the principal apartment of the- establishment. Though small in size, it served as kitchen, din- ing-room, laundry, smoking-room, gambling-room,   :Annie Reilly.      10o3 and, in short, every purpose for which any room could be used. The only persons within when they entered were an old, very ugly woman, with a large, full, iron-gray face studded over Fwith numerous small projections, out of which grew several long hairs corresponding in color with her face, and a young, fat, sullen-looking girl, who sat so close to the fire that her face shone again. The former sat in the window-sill, peeling potatoes with the blade of an old razor set in a piece of wood, and, as she finished a potato, she threw the skins through a broken pane into-God knows where-outside. The other, who looked decidedly lazy, now and then took hold of a long stick, black from grease and dirt, which stood in a large pot, of soup on the fire, and-'tir-red it round and round. The old:*itdy's face we do not think could assume a cheerful expression on any occasion; so that there may not be much in saying she frowned as Mr. Lantern went over to her. But it was such a wicked, scornful frown, and her eyes flashed so, surely he must be no favorite of hers. "'E wants to lodge 'ere to-night, Mrs. Vitles. He brought 'im 'ere." Mrs. Witles turned her head from side to side a few times, and resumed her work without mak-t ing -any reply. Mr. Lantern looked around, and &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7150-00000055"/> I04     Annie Reilly.  the top of his nose grew redder as he saw that James noticed his reception. He turned to Mrs. Witles again, and stood with his knees together, not venturing to say a word. "Veil," said she at length, throwing down the knife, but without raising her eyes. "Vell." "Hi brought a lodger to yer, Mrs. Vitles," said Lantern feebly. "Vell, you know 'e can stay. Vere's yer use in tellin' me? Do yer see any sign on 'im runnin' away? "Hi--yer know the reason I tell ye, Mrs. Vitles," said he, with a mean leer, and backing further away. "Wery well I do," said she, in a loud voice; "but do ye expect me to pay ye afore I knows 'ow much I'm a goin' to make meself?" Lantern cast a wistful look at the soup, which Mrs. Witles at once interpreted; for- she ex- claimed: "Hi'll be blowed if I do. Leave 'ere, now." And she snatched the stick from the soup-pot. "Go, now," continued she, advancing threaten- ingly upon him. "You're more 'arm than good to any place as lets you in on 'em. Make tracks, now." And as the worthy gentleman backed into the hall, she slammed the door so quickly that it was a miracle his nose escaped. S r -   Annie Reilly.      1o5 James sat for a time, oppressed by the heat and smell of the place, and by his own troubled mind ; for, now that he was alone-we may say so, for neither of the women addressed a word to him or even looked towards him-the unhappy state of his father at home, and sorrow and anxiety after Annie, crowded on his mind. So much did these thoughts weigh upon him that he forgot his own unhappy circumstances and un- certain future, and even where he was, till the noise of heavy footsteps outside in the hall roused him. The door was burst open, and a motley crowd of coal-heavers, sailors, old pensioners, browned with the sun of India, thimble-riggers, trick-o'-the-loop men, ballad-singers, and, in short, a sample of all the lower grades of the city crowded into the room. James looked up angsaw dinner was already on the table, and Mrs. Witles busily engaged filling a row of wooden bowls with soup, cabbage, po- tatoes, and loathsome-looking lumps of fat which the young woman was lifting from the bottom of the pot with her fingers. . -The men, such of them as could, climbed over the high form which surrounded the table, and, resting their elbows thereon, began to eat like wolves. Many of the old soldiers and sailors, who were disabled so badly in upholding the majesty  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7150-00000056"/> Io6      Annie Reilly. of England that any future attempt of theirs at stepping over a form must be hopeless, sat down with their backs to the table, and such of them as had two hands held the bowl in one of them; but others, who were not blessed with that num- ber, held it between their knees; and a few who, happened to want hands and knees both, sat down on the floor and ate like animals. James looked on in amazetnent at the hideous sight, and made no attempt to join them, till Mrs. Wittles, when the meal was almost over and some of the guests straggling out, said, looking sharply - at him: ' Fall hin, young man, or you'll be too late." "With your leave, madam," replied he, ' I would rather wait a little." The poor fellow could no more eat with such a party, than he could fly. "Hi wouldn't keep my table set hafter the reg- 'lar-hour for the queen-'erself, if she was 'ere," said Mr Vitles, snatching a lump of meat from before a Hean old pensioner, which the latter had stolen from the pot while her back was turned. James moved over to the table, and, the bowl being set before him, covered his eyes with his hands to shut out the sight of a sailor opposite, who was licking the inside of his bowl like a dog. Mrs. Witles's plan for the dinnershour was a   Annie Reilly.       Io7 very good one for herself. As soon as she saw a boarder had his bowl emptied, she immediately ordered him, with a shake of the soup-stick, to leave, thereby preventing the possibility of giving him a second round. This, too, helped James to get rid of the disgusting fellow across the table much sooner than otherwise might have hap- pened; for Mrs. Witles's quick eye alighting on him, she ordered him, with sundry choice epithets, to go before he'd " eat the bowl." James tasted a little of the soup, but no- thing else. He went into the street, and wan- dered down as far as the docks again, tak- ing a mental note of everything of remark he passed, that he might not lose'his way com- ing back. He sat down on the edge of the quay, and watched the men loading and unload- ing the ships, and saw several going out to sea, some for China and Japan and other far distant places. A number of vessels, too, arrived during the evening, and, as he saw the passengers coming ashore, wondered what kind of country they came C from, what sort of cities and people did it con- tain, or were they as dirty as Liverpool.  He remained there till it began to grow dark and a few of the lamps around him were lighted, when he turned and walked back, to the lodging- lhouse.  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7150-00000057"/> I08      A nnie Reilby. If the streets presented a wretched appear- ance in daytime, they looked doubly so at night. They were literally filled with poverty and vice of the very worst kind. Beggars with awful-looking sores stood or lay in knots around the lamp-posts, frantically telling the wretchec passers-by of their sufferings and pain. A blinc or disabled musician of some kind, clad in rags scraped or thumbed a miserable instrument be fore nearly every door. Drunken men and wo men rushed into the streets with yells, curses, ant V4,  shouts of obscenity, occasionally stopping for a moment to dance to the wretched music, then hurrying on, trampling over the children ane helpless. Bad as his lodging-house was within, it wa: some relief to James to escape from such a scene 'None of the other boarders had returned, and hc rluested to be shown to his bed. Mrs. Witle: handed him a candle, and, pointing up the ding) old- stairs, told him to push open the door of the - first room he met, and lie down on any bed hc chose. Of beds he had a noble choice. The room, which, by the'way, was the entire floor was so closely packed with beds that no one might attempt to walk from one side of the apart men{ to the other, except he stepped from bec to bed. James held the candle down betweer  e-   Annie Reilly.      Io9 two beds, that he might see the floor; this was no easy task either, for it was covered to the depth of a couple of inches with dust and other dirt, all of which did not belong to the inanimate kingdom.  He raised the candler and looked around the room, on the green and black walls, down which the rain had poured for years and years; and from the quantity of cobwebs which covered the ceiling--what of it remained-and the angles of the room, it was' evident Mrs. Wit- les made very little use of her broom. James, being very much exhausted from hard- ship and long want of sleep, selected a bed on the outer row, which looked as if it had not been occupied for some time, lay down on its edge, and soon fell asleep. How long he slept he knew not, till he was aroused by the noise of voices around him-loud, coarse voices-and, looking up, saw the same group he had met at din- ner; some walking over the beds to reach their own on the far side, others crowding in at the door, and one and all in an advanced stage of in- toxication. Some were pale, sick, and sad; others were sentimental, who wept to themselves over past attachments in their own and other lands; a few were belligerent, and, assuming numerous -fight- eing attitudes, boasted they were afraid of no man  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7150-00000058"/> IIo      Annie Reilly. in 1' Hingland, without reference to the present company"; and the old soldier from whom Mrs. Witles snatched the lump of fat stood up on his bed, and screamed in a dismal, broken voice a verse of "Rule, Britannia!"By-and-by, all fell here and there on the beds, in different positions, and went to sleep. But so stifling was the atmo- sphere from the fumes of bad whisky that James went out on the- landing, where he remained till daylight. As soon as Mrs. Witles appeared, he paid her the amount of his bill, and went down to the- docks to wait till the time for going aboard would arrive. Soon other emigrants, with packages and bundles of all kinds, began to assemble at the quay, and James went amongst such of them as he knew were from Ireland, and talked with them till the hour for starting came. About mid-day, the ship weighed anchor, and steamed down the Mersey. James O'Rourke was not much of a philosopher; but, as he stood on deck, looking at the noble buildings which rose here and there on the Cheshire coast, and thought of what he had witnessed in Liverpool, he could not help thinking that a nation composed of two such extremes must one day break in the centre. The passage down the Irish Sea was beautiful. James-waited with great anxiety for their arrival I ,         s    A nnie Reilly.     II at Queenstown, that he might, probably for the last time, feast his eyes on the hills and valleys of his native land. But to his great mortifica- tion, it was almost dark night when they entered the harbor. The day, even at sea, had been very warm, and with evening came lowering clouds on deck, looking at the ran of lights along the harbor, thinking of home and the base villany that had driven him thence; of Annie--what was she doing now? This was about the time they used to meet on the river's bank. Did she go there alone now, and sit and think of him, and remember him in her prayers, as she had promised to do? Was it beyond hope that they would ever meet again? This thought sickened his heart so much that he leaned against the cabin-door, and turned his eyes away from the coast. A gruff officer, carry- ing a light, passed down the deck, and ordered him 'I to stand some place else." He went down to his berth, and, throwing himself on his face, wept til the ship was far out to sea. E . s   &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7150-00000059"/> CHAPTER XII. JAMES O'ROURKE'S FIRST DAY IN NEW YORK. -A FRAUD AND A FRIEND. FTER a comparatively safe and speedy passage, James O'Rourke reached New York.  It was one. of those mellow days in the early fall when e ything looks so serene and calm that the anxious passengers were landed. How beautiful New York Harbor looked! The waters seemed asleep on the bosom of the bay, save where dis- turbed by the lively ferry-boats ploughing their way backwards and forwards in every direction, and the little snorting tugs, puiffing in and out here and there, busy as bees of a June morning. A number of large, majestic-looking ships, that had just come in from all ports of the world, lay out in the stream, looking weary after their long voyage. It being early day, the passengers were -not delayed at Castle Garden overnight, except such as chose to wait for friends who were expecting them. James had no friends, and he walked into the streets and up along Broadway, wondering at j   nn ie Reilly.      113 the size, and beauty, and cheerful look of the buildings along that noble thoroughfare. It was at the time of day when Broadway is at its live- liest, lined with wagons, carriages, carts, and drays, and the sidewalk so crowded with people hurrying along that it is impossible for any of them to make much speed. James walked on-- lhe knew not where-looking on himself as the most lonely and friendless of the great throng. At length he came to what seemed to him a neglected waste of ground, which, having mor- tally offended the city in some way, was left be- hind, forgotten, haggard, and cheerless. Near the centre of this waste stood a large building in a half-finished state, looking so dreary that the ill fate of the neighborhood seemed to have visited it at last. A number of men were standing around the doors or sitting on the steps of the building, and all looking so much like men that had nothing to do, that James thought it might not inconveni- ence any of them   much to tell him where he might find work. So approaching a gentleman with a wide-leafed straw hat, a tight-fitting coat, much too short for him, and very long, wide pantaloons, who stood on the end of a row, pick- ing his teeth, James asked:   &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7150-00000060"/> II4   L   Annie Reilly. '} Please, sir, can you tell me where I may find employment? I am a stranger here." "Most undoubtedly, sir; follow me," said the gentleman, putting his tooth-pick in his vest ;pocket. "Come along, sir." James, delighted beyond measure at this sud- den good luck, hurried after his new friend, but found it no very easy task to keep up with him. He had such a happy method of diving past crowds which jostled against the other that he had once or twice to wait for him on the corner. At length the gentleman swept into a low, narrow door in one of the side streets, and when James rushed in after him, he found him seated behind a neat little desk, looking as composed as if he had been sitting there since morning. ( So you -want employment, do you?" said he, surveying James from head to foot. "Yes, sir," replied the latter. "What kind do you prefer?" said he, opening a book which lay on the desk before him. "We have a variety." "Well, sir," replied James with a smile, "I am not afraid of any kind of work, but would of course prefer whichever pays best." ^    "Let me see," said the other, closing his eyes and resting hischin on his hand, " let me see. You are strong enough to work in a dry-goods store?"   Annie Reilly.      I15 "You mean, sir--"  "I mean what you call a cloth-shop in the Old Country." "Oh! yes; I beg your pardon, sir," said James, greatly elated. "Certainly I am, sir." "You landed this morning, eh?" said the gen- tleman. "This morning, sir?" "Any friends in New York?" "No, sir." "All alone, eh?" "Quite so, sir." "Well, now, sir, I'll tell you what I'll do. You give me three dollars, and I'll send you right up to the establishment." James felt greatly surprised at this, for he really thought the gentleman was an extensive employer himself. He had never heard of an "intelligence office," and was quite at a loss what to think. He couldn't be a swindler, hav- ing such a handsome place. "No; he must be an employer, and probably wants this money as security for a day or two, till he sees how I get on," thought James. And looking at the gentleman again, and see- ing him- busy writing, and apparently utterly oblivious of his .presence, was confirmed in this latter idea.  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7150-00000061"/> n16      Aeztie Reilly, (7 I'll pay the money, sir," said he, taking from his pocket a few shillings and one half-crown, which was his entire store. The gentlemian thought it most remarkable, but nevertheless it was true, that the coins when 'changed into dollars amounted to just the re- quired number and ten cents over. So he swept it into a drawer, and, throwing a ten-cent stamp on the desk, drew a piece of paper to him, and, having written a few words on it with violet ink, handed it to James. The latter glanced at it and said: "What way am I to go there, sir?" "You -see I am so busy, or I would take you up myself. But, anyway, all you have to do is to cross over five blocks to your right, then down a long street you'll see with a marble building on the up-town corner, then one block to your right, then take the cars--you know the street-cars- and ride eleven blocks more, and any one can point out Van Sleuthers &amp; Duckey's dry-goods store to you. Go inside, and show them that ad- dress, and you're all right." James thanked him, left the office, and went in search of Van Sleuthers &amp; Duckey's. That he did not find it, and that there was no such firm in the city, it is needless to say. He had been swindled out of the last penny by an   A nnnie Rtilly.     I 17 "intelligence agent" ; and after travelling up and down the streets, looking at every sign, stop- ping to make enquiries at every clothing estab- lishment, he found himself at nightfall close by the East River, footsore, weary, and dejected. He sat down on a log on one of the docks, and, I   covering his eyes with his hands,-began to think over his forlorn, desolate state. In a large city, without a friend, without one face he had ever known, without a single penny in his pocket. Where to spend the night or get a morsel to eat he knew not; he had spent the ten cents riding up and down in search of Van Sleuthers &amp; Duckey's. He sat a prey to these thoughts for some time, ti 11, raising his head, he saw coming leisurely towards him, from the direction of the street, a man in his shirt-sleeves, smoking a large briar-wood pipe. As he approached, James could see he was of his own race, and made up his mind to speak to him. This was no difficult matter, for the stranger came on, puffing like an engine, and, sitting down beside him, remarked it was a fine night. O'Rourke saw at once, from his large, rough hands, that he belonged to the working-class, and, observing his neat white shirt and black tie, and everything he wore so clean, thought of the  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7150-00000062"/> l 8     Annie Reilly. miserable appearance of the English working- men. "You're not long out from the ould counthry, I think," said he kindly. "No, indeed," said James. ' I came ashore this morning.         i "Wel, Well," said the man, moving close to him, "I am glad to see any one so late from the ould dart. How is things there now; anything better-?" "Oh! much the same as usual," replied James. "Improvements come very slowly in Ireland." "That's so, that's so, me friend," said the other, with a sigh. "But the people an't starv- ing as they wor when I left there?" "Not so bad as that now," said James. "Do you live around here?" asked the stranger, after a pause. "I have no home,' said James, drawing back his head a little. "No home," said the other, "and a greenhorn; why, that's rough. I suppose be that ye mane you haven't got any money neither." "Not a penny," was the reply. Then James told him how he had been cheated by the intelligence- agent., "You're not the first who has been fleeced by thim robbers," said the other in a rage. "They   Annie Reilly.      II9 swindle dozens of poor innocent people every day, and you'll niver hear of one of thim bein' arristed. But," added he, checking himself, "it can't be helped now, and I'll niver see one of my countrymen that desarves it out in the streets at night while I have a room; so you must come wid me to-night. The ould woman 'ill find some place for yolu to sleep." Jmes thanked him again and again, and, after enjoying a smoke from his pipe, they walked up the dock and along the street a little way, till they came to a somewhat neat-looking brick house with a wooden stoop. The man entered, and both wentA. a flight of very clean but carpetless stairs to the third story, and, turning the knob of the door, entered a tidily furnished room of comfortable dimensions. .Over the wooden man- tel-piece hung a handsome engraving of Arch- bishop Hughes, side by side with another of St. Patrick, and on the opposite wall hung a picture of Killarney Lakes. Several other pictures, some of Irish clergy, some of American, were fastened round the walls, all very tastefully arranged. There was no person in the room on their entrance, and the man, seeing James look closely at the. archbishop's likeness, began to tell nu- merous stories of his kindness and benevolence. After some time,-a woman came in, carrying a  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7150-00000063"/> I20      A4nnie Reilly. basket on her arm; and from the appearance of her face, and the trim, cleanly way in which she was clad, James knew at once whose taste had arranged the room. "Well, well, Terence, and what a man you are," said she, laying down the basket, and looking at her husband with a smile, " to leave housekeeping." "Oh! in troth, I was afraid she'd begin to screech whin ye'd be gone, Bridget, so I left her inside with Mrs. Kearney. She stays as quiet wid her as wid yourself," said her husband. "Oh! just so ;. anything to get rid of the job. But keep quiet now; she's asleep in Mrs. Kear- ney's arms, and I'll bring her in and put her in the cradle."  * - The woman- left the room, and soon returned, carrying in her arms a little babe of a few months old, and, shaking her hand at her husband to say nothing, lest he should rouse the infant, went through the passage-way into another room. The man conversed with James for awhile, then, telling him he'd be back in a moment, fol- lowed his wife. Both soon returned, and James could see from the kind, sympathetic look the woman gave him that her husband had been tell- ing his story. "Excuse me," said the man, "but ye haven't tould me yer name."   A nnie Reilly.     I21 James told him. "In troth, and a good name it is. My own is -I- Terence McManus, and this is Mrs. McManus, and that sleepy youngster ye seen a minute ago is Mary McManus. So we Iknow each other all roun' now, and are quite at our aise." The agreeable, honest, good-natured manner of the man did make James feel much easier in mind than he had felt for some time.' Mrs. McManus prepared a good meal, of which all three partook. This over; they sat together, and I  talked over matters in the old and new country. One important point to James came out from this conversation, and that was he learned that his, host, who worked along the docks, being what is commonly called a 'longshoreman, would find him employment at the same business the following day. L *      .  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7150-00000064"/> CHAPTER XIII. ANNIE'S   VOYAGE.-HOW   EMGRANTS ARE TREATED ON SHPBOARD. UR ING the first three days out, Annie was very sea-sick, and unable to come on deck. So much did she suffer from this distressing illness and her own grief of mind that she hardly cared whether the ship sank or not. At times during these days, she thought 'she would surely have died were it not for the kindness and attention shown her by a young woman from Dublin, who was going out to meet her husband in the West. Though greatly burdened with her little son, who con- tinued ill all the way, she spent every moment she could with Annie, getting up at least a dozen times during the night to see how she felt; often going to the doctor to tell him of her state, and beg him to send her some relief, and almost as often getting rudely repulsed. Of all the sinecures on land or sea, that of ship doctor, as far as the poor steerage passengers are , concerned, is the most idle. A ship doctor is : generally a very stylish gentleman-a snob-who   At n ie -Reilly.     123 knows far more about the fashions than about medicine, and thinks all that is required of him is to strut the deck, and laugh and chat with the cabin passengers. Those in the steerage are so much beneath his notice that nothing can induce him to go below, even if a -life depended on the very act. He may, if caught in the humor, conde- scend to order a poor sufferer some medicine on the report of the steward-a gentleman generally as ignorant in cases of sickness as himself. What drug the model M D. on this occasion sent Annie she would not venture to touch, and this probably accounted for her being able to go on deck the following morning in company with her kind friend. It was a beautiful morning at sea. The sun shone bright and soft on the waste'of calm water, and the ship was making rapid headway. Annie and her friend, Mrs. Duffy, sat down on deck close by the bulwark. The deck was literally swarming with men, women, and children from every country in Europe, every nationality keep- ing in little groups by themselves. Englishmen, with long side-whiskers, short coats, and moist eyes, stood or lay together in knots, -sometimes silent and sad, and occasionally talking in low- murmuring accents; Irishmen, stout, hearty, and pleasant, smoked, chatted, laughed together,  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7150-00000065"/> I 24      n n ie Reilly. and seemed to take more notice of what was going on around them than any other peo- ple; Germans, black and greasy, lay in heaps to- gether; men and women, and seemed to occupy their whole time eating. All the other passen- gers, especially the Irish, disliked them; their hands and faces were so dirty, and their old rags smelled so disgustingly, that we pity any company in a close room who would have a German amongst them. A few garrulous and excitable Frenchmen walked up and down on one side of the deck, talking loudly; Italian organ-grinders and beggars had their place, and two or three swarthy Spaniards leaned over the bulwark, look- ing down at the water. At a little distance from and directly in front of Annie and her friend sat a Scotchman alone by himself. Not that he was by any means the only Scotchman on board, but he seemed to be of a  sentimental turn of mind, and probably ;  loved solitude. He  had a very long face and forehead, whitish-colored. hair, a very red beard, and wore a  short frock-coat of heavy, coarse material, with a row of immense buttons on each - side, short, tight trowsers, and, when he chose to 'r *' wear it, a torn glazed cap. One arm rested on a coil pf rope behind him, in the hand of which he heldZa large-sized snuff-box, and the other hand i   Annie Reilly.   ,   i^2 was employed in occasionally carrying the snuff .  to his nose. Whether he was an old man- with a, white head, or a very young man with false whiskers, or a middle-aged one, it would take some person well skilled in those matterto:say. From the time Annie and her friend came on deck, he had not taken his eyes off the formed;  and turn her head in what direction she would to avoid his gaze, he moved so as to watch her face. Whether it was from admiration, or curiosity, or , impertinence, his countenance gave no indication. Annie felt greatly annoyed, and, not wishing ty--: , go below in the damp smell, and seeing no platce ;-,- on deck to escape to, mentioned the matter to her friend. "Oh! I have noticed him,"said Mrs. Duffy, laughing. "He is some stupid lout; don't let him. annoy you." Annie laughed at this remark, and they chatted away lively and soon forgot him; but never for a second did he change his look. At length a number of those- on deck went below, and the two friends rose and went to another place behind the engine, where; they found a more comfortable seat. They had hardly seated themselves, when the Scotchman came and lay down, this time on the deck, about the same distance from them, and turned his eyes on e  .            \   &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7150-00000066"/> I26      Annie Reilly. Annie again. She was so much alarmed that she begged of the other to come below at once. "Oh! nonsense," was the reply, ' are we going down there because of that awkward fellow? Leave him to me, and, if he attempts to speak to you, I'll insult him so badly that, if he was as stupid again, he'll annoy you no more." Annie in her heart thanked Providence she had such a friend. If she were alone, what would she do?  He would frighten her to death.' At length the dinner-hour arrived, and, as they were about to descend the ladder, Annie felt a light tap on her shoulder, and, looking up, her eyes met her tormentor's dull gaze. She clutched her friend's arm, but, before the latter could speak, he was gone in amongst the crowd clam- bering down to the table. Annie's heart throbbed so, and she felt so very much annoyed, that she could not eat any of the choice morsels which her friend took from a little basket in her trunk. It was a hard task to induce her to go on deck that evening, but Mrs. Duffy begged of her so much for her health's sake not to remain.-in that "hole," as she called it, and -promised so fervently to put an end to the Scotchman's annoyance in case he should renew it, that at length she consented to go up again.   -        Ann ie Reilly.     127 They climbed up on the forward deck, the mother taking her little boy, who felt somewhat better, and sat watching the water-fowls flying about and dipping down to the water here and there; wondering where those birds built their nests, or were there any islands near. Annie had not quite recovered from the shock she had received, and was yet very restless, turn- ing her head in the direction of the ladder now and then, and starting at every glazed cap she saw appearing. Mrs. Duffy drew her closer to her side, and, putting her arm around her waist, told her she had nothing to dread. At length both, happening to look round, saw the ungainly figure of the Scotchman looming into view up the ladder. "Heavens! there he is again," exclaimed Annie, clinging to her friend. "He'll frighten me to death." Mrs. Duffy fixed her eyes steadily upon him as he lumbered up the deck. When he came within a few yards of them, he hesitated, stopped, came a little nearer, pulled out his snuff-box, and, com- ing up to them, held it open towards Annie, without saying a word. "We don't want your snuff, thank you," said Mrs. Duffy, shaking her head with a frown. "I ony ware to gie this lassie a pinch," said -.*.  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7150-00000067"/> I28      Annie Reilly. he, thrusting the -box into Annie's face. The poor girl was pale with terror. "You begone, sir!" exclaimed her friend, jump- ing to -her feet, " and annoy this young girl no more with look or word of yours, or I'll com- plain to the captain. She is young, and notlong from home, and not used to looking at such, frights as you."  "Ah wull-" h;e began, moving backwards a step. "Say no more. Leave here, now, or I'll go to the captain directly." And she moved as if to fulfil the threat, when he turned and shambled away down the length of the deck, down the lad- der, and, when he had about time to reach there, they saw hii ,tanding very demure-looking, with his back against the bulwark. Mrs. Duffy laughed so heartily when he was gone- at his :awkward look and manner that Annie could nqt help joining her, and they laughed togetie till the tears rolled down their cheeks. -TheScotchman annoyed them  no further during tpite voyage. Any ti-ne he chanced to see them, he might venture to stea -a look at Annie; but, if Mrs. 'Duffy happened to catch him, he quickly made his way, out of sight. Nothing further worthy of notice occurreid to our heroine during the voyage,   Ant ie Reilly,     129 which may be termed a pleasant one, excepting a few- stormy days crossing the banks of New- foundland, when the face of the ocean changed from its calm aspect, the waves ran high and angry, tossing the ship from side to side, drifting tin cans, kettles, boxes, passengers, and baskets hither and thither in every direction. The storm lulled as they approached the American coast, !  and on a beautiful warm evening Sandy Hook lightship came in view. All crowded to the vessel's side, crushing and climbing over each other, to get a view of the new land in which they intended living. What a moment it is for those kept down with poverty and oppression at home, toiling in hunger ,and exposure to' enrich the very ones to whom they owe their degradation, when their weary eyes first rest on America's shore! Once there, they know tyranny can claim them no more, and that every advantage, every justice allowed an honest people on earth, will be their share. When the ship had sailed up the bay and cast anchor, it was nightfall, and the passengers learn- ed they could not go ashore till morning. What an anxious, busy night it was on board; every one putting in the best order they could what little they possessed, that they might make as good an appearance as possible when they reach-  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7150-00000068"/> 130      Annie Reilly. ed New York. Packing up, bundling up, tying up, loosing and unloosing, washing and shaving, were going on in every quarter below; while those who had none of these things to do lined the ship's side, watching the lights along the river and in the city, till the steward announced all would have to go to bed till morning. Little use in sending them there; for not one passenger on board could sleep that night. Mrs. Duffy, who did not intend staying any length of time in New York, but to hurry on to her husband in Ohio, however promised to remain with Annie till she saw her on the right way to Kitty Brady. Poor Annie felt very sad and timid. A thou- sand disturbing thoughts came into her mind. What if Kitty had left New York, and was not to be found, and that she should be left alone in the streets of the large fiity? And even if Kitty was where she still expected her, she might lose her way, and probably meet the Scotchman or somebody like him. These and numerous other apprehensions she mentioned to Mrs. Duffy, who only laughed at some, and chided her good-aturedly for others. Both were up at break -of day, and sat, and walked, and watched till the tender came out to take the passengers ashore. What a rush was   A nnie Reilly.  i    13I there then! Heaps of trunks and other baggage, piled in every shape, covered the deck; men and women rushed frantically around to discover-their own, and the noise and confusion of tongues must have resembled very much that which put an end to the tower of Babel. At length, passengers and baggage arrived at Castle Garden.  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7150-00000069"/> CHAPTER XIV. ANNIE AT CASTLE GARDEN.-HOW PASSENGERS ARE TREATED THERE. te-g iLL the din and confusion which Annie W3   had experienced since she left home heaped'f together would not equal that which met her at Castle Garden. When the tenders reached the dock, the pas- sengers made a mad rush for the shore, crowding over each otherup the gangway. The trunks and baggage were landed in the most confused manner. A person would imagine it was the first obligation those employed for that purpose owed to the emigrants, to break a4nd smash their articles as much as possible. It seemed to be the rule to throw all the small and frail boxes, ashore first, and then fling the heavier and stronhger ones on top of them. Locks were knocked off, lids and sides broken in, and the contents of several strewn like a wreck along the dock. The pas- sengers tried frantically to save their property, and, in doing so, had to contend with the vulgar abuse and often blows of the officials. Some old and feeble men and women, and young girls, saw   A nnie Reilly.     133 all they possessed in the world trampled under the feet of the excited crowd; and, helpless to prevent the injury, turned away and began to cry. It was only the strong and rugged could save their share in such a place, and that only after desperate exertions. A person looking on at one of these scenes could not help thinking that any strong enough to carry away their effects from such a place were able to get along in America as far as muscle was concerned. Annie's trunk, being made of strong oak, re- ceived no further injury than being thrown bot- tom upwards on a number of small paper ones; so all she had to do was to wait till the confusion would abate, to have it taken inside. That which contained Mrs. Duffy's articles did not escape so fortunately. She found it, after a laborious search, broken open, and a quantity of linen she was taking to her husband gone. The poor woman wrung her hands, and ran here and there relating her misfortune to and asking advice of every man whom she saw looked like an official. Not one of them even made her a reply. So all she could do was to wring her hands again, and gather up what was left behind in a corner of her shawl, f6r the trunk was a total wreck. Annie rendered her good benefactress all the  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7150-00000070"/> 134      Annie Reilly assistance in her power, and Mrs. Duffy, being of such a cheerful disposition, was soon laughing at the figure she cut with the bundle in her shawl. A thick-set, rough, decidedly bad-looking man, seeing Annie standing by her trunk, hurried over and asked her if she wished it taken inside. Annie was about to say yes, when her com- panion hastily interposed, and said, "No, not yet." The fellow, seeing he would have got the "job," as he called it, were it not for her, heaped a volley of foul abuse on the poor woman, and even shook his fist in her face, to the great amuse- ment of two officials who were standing by smok- ing very long cigars. -  At length, when the greater part of the lug-  gage was gone, Mrs. Duffy took hold of one end of the trunk, and, telling Annie to lift the other,  both carried it into a long, wide, dreary-looking structure not unlike the arch of a wooden bridge. They then joined the stream, filing into another part of the building, on through a number of narrow doors, at one of which they were obliged to give  their names, then into a large open space, like an X old-country mwarket-house, filled with emigrants, some walking dreamily to and fro, and others lying on the cold flags to rest their weary  X limbs. A number of licensed boarding-house   t! gI   Annie Reilly.       135 keepers, or "sharks," as they are called in New York, were going amongst them, seeking to entice as many as they could to their establishments for the night. Now, we think it is very right and proper to allow the keepers of respectable lodging- houses to enter Castle Garden; for many poor emigrants, who are weary and anxious to find a bed to rest on, know not where to look for it. But to permit such unscrupulous, heartless vil- lains as are usually found there to lead away innocent, unsuspecting people to their dens is a standing shame to the city. But we are greatly afraid that the first-mentioned class have a slender chance of that privilege- till some change amongst the officials takes place. At length, when the poor creatures were worn out with watching to be let out in the open air, a flashily dressed official mounted a platform, and began to call out the names of such as had letters awaiting them.  The number of letters was not many, but the time he occupied in read- ing the addresses was intolerable. Not that he was by any mneans a slow reader; for he mentioned a name so quickly, driving Christian and surname into one, that few of his listeners could make out what he said. The attention he bestowed on his dress, adjusting his collar,  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7150-00000071"/> 136      Annie Reilly. smoothing down his bosom, and brushing up his hair after every name seemed to be the very object for which he was there. Many of the let- ters were thrown aside, no one claiming them, while the very persons for whom they were in- tended were in a fever of expectation on the floor. This task over, such of the emigrants as chose were permitted to depart. Many availed them- selves of this opportunity; but a few -lonely, dejected creatures remained behind, hoping to find employment through the Free Labor Bureau. Annie, accompanied by Mrs. Duffy and her little boy, went in search of the nearest way to the part of the city where Kitty Brady lived, which, after many enquiries and long tra- velling, they found. It was a long way up the city; and, after an affectionate parting, and each promising to write to the other, Annie went aboard a street-car, and was driven off. Mrs. Duffy stood looking after her till the car was out of sight; then began making her own enquiries, and, being successful in these too, started for the Chambers Street ferry.            i -" "*   CHAPTER XV. MEETING OLD FIIENDS, AGREEABLE AND OTHERWISE. 'HE street-car jingled along merrily, first down a narrow, crowded street, filled with shops, outside and inside of which hung more ready-made clothing than Annie thought would supply half the world, then into a long, wide thoroughfare of much bet- ter appearance. Up this street, past more cloth- ing-houses, with figures of men and women clad in the height of fashion dangling from the awn- ings; and underneath, on the sidewalk, Jews and Jewesses, old and young, some gesticulating frantically at the passers-by to "walk in" and purchase; others, pale and worn out from inces- sant talking, leaned against the windows, looking no more like life than the figures above their heads. Past oyster and beer saloons, with fat, lazy Dutchmen resting on the counters or sitting by the doors, while' a few sat around a table drawn near the entrance, drinking, smoking, and playing cards. Past liquor-stores, looking very shabby and unwashed, with numbers of red-faced,  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7150-00000072"/> 138      Annie Reilly. bloated, stupid-looking, ill-clad men dozing on barrels outside, and a few dandily-dressed fellows smoking cigars or chewing tobacco inside the doors. Occasionally a youth or two, evidently taking the dry-rot, roused up one of the sleep- ers, and engaged him in conversation. Past pea- nut-stands, with Chinamen or Japanese sitting on the flags behind them. Up, up, on, on, till Annie thought she would never reach the end of the street. At length the car-conductor beckoned to her, and told her she was to get off at the next corner. He told her very kindly the way to take from there, and to watch the numbers on the doors. She thanked him, and, the car being stopped, got off, and after a short walk arrived at the house bearing the number she sought.2 She descended to the basement door, and rang the bell. A very cleanly-looking girl opened it, and asked politely whom she wanted to see. "Please tell me is this where Kitty Brady' lives?" asked Annie. "Yes," replied the other, " but she is out to market. Please step inside; she'll be in directly." Annie thanked her,; and walked into the hall. "Come on this way," said the other, going be- fore, " and take a seat; you look tired." Annie followed her into the apartment, and, being handed a chair, sat some time in silence; ! t-  1L   Anrzie Reilly.      139 for the girl seemed to be busy. At length the door-bell jingled loudly. "Here she is pow," said the other; and, going to the door, returned with a neatly-dressed, bright- eyed, intelligent-looking girl, who looked so to- tally unlike the Kitty Brady she remembered that she could not believe it was the same, till the other girl said: "Kitty, this young lady has been waiting to see you." Kitty, who had not the least idea of who Annie might be, and was about to go up-stairs to her duties, turned back, and, coming close to her, looked into her face. Annie's eyes met hers, and for a moment they looked into each other's faces. At length Annie burst into tears, and said sor- rowfully: "You don't remember me, Kitty?" This was the first time Annie had spoken. The voice was enough-the same sweet voice Kitty had heard a thousand times in her mother's cabin.       ' "O little Annie, darling, dear! And can this be you?" exclaimed Kitty, throwing her arms around her neck. They kissed each other again and again, and wept till their faces were wet. Neither could speak a word for some minutes. When Kitty sat  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7150-00000073"/> I40      Annie Reilly. down by her new-found friend, and took her hand in hers, the other girl came and kissed her, too, and hoped they would always be good friends. "I will not ask you anything further about home," said Kitty, when she had wept bitterly over the; misfortune that had befallen Farrell Reilly's family, " till we go to my aunt's. I'll get leave to go with you for this evening." Kitty dried her eyes as ivell as she could, and ran up-sfairs, taking with her the parcel her mother had sent her, and soon returned with word she could spend the evening with her. Both girls started out, Annie feeling much hap- pier than she thought she could in many a day. After a pretty long walk, they reached the house. It was a neat, two-story frame building, with vewy- white walls and very green Venetian blinds, and had a trim little garden in front. On the door was a highly polished brass plate bear- ing the name, Patrick Sweeny. Patrick Sweeny was the husband; of Kitty's aunt, and, being a, very sober, industrious mechanic, had by this time accumulated money enough to purchase the cottage and live comfortably. 'Kitty rang the bell, and the door was opened by a plainly-dressed, good-natured-looking, middle-aged woman, who kissed her niece affectionately, and then began chiding her for staying away so long. Kitty   Annie Reilly,      41 made the best excuse she could, and, turning to; Annie, said:       ' "Aunt, if you were to think for. the length of; a day, I don't believe you would find out who this is."                 ' "I am sure of that, child," said Mrs. Sweeny., ; - "I have never, I think, seen the young lady before." And she looked kindly at Annie. "Well, I'll not keep you waiting, aunt. She is Farrell Reilly's daughter Annie, j!st landed to-day." "Farrell Reilly's daughter!" exclaimed Mrs,. Sweeny, taking her by the hand, and kissing hdr.- .. fondly. "You are a thousand welcomes to my ' house. Ham delighted to see one of your family under my roof." And she pushed the parlor door open, and led the girls inside, hastily removed Annie's hat and- shawl, and sat down by her on the sofa. "And how is your father and mother, my child? 'Tis very strange, but I was dreaming of the old country last night; such a queer, mixed-up dream it was. Cary, or John the Pig, as we used to call him, was in it, and Father Fitzpatrick, and your mother, and a strange young lady, whom I think must be you."' "'Twas, indeed, a very strange dream, aunt,' said Kitty. "Cary is the cause of Annie being in New York to-day." -, -  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7150-00000074"/> "2      Annie Reilly. Mrs. Sweeny raised her hands in alarm, and said: "Tell me, Annie, did you leave your father and mother well?" "As well as could be expected, after what had happened to them," said Annie, her tears begin- ning to fall afresh. Mrs. Sweeny was truly grieved when she heard the poor girl's story. "Poor Farrell Reilly!" she said, putting her handkerchief to her eyes, "that was such a good friend to us all. How heart-sorry I am for his trouble! I never dream of that scoundrel Cary," she went on, "but something is sure to follow-- either some trouble to ourselves, or I'll hear bad news. You may not have heard it, child, but he was the cause of our downfall in the old country. But now, when I look back, I think it may all have been for the best; and you, too, child," drying Annie's tears, "will, I trust in God, live to say the same; so we'll fret no more, and be as merry as we can." "That's just the way to be, aunt," said Kitty. "I couldn't help crying, either, when I heard it; so we'll talk about something else." By-and-by Mrs. Sweeny's daughter, a tall, hand- some girl of about sixteen, came in, and all four spent a pleasant evening till it was time for Kitty   Annie Reilly.      143 to leave. Annie and Miss Swqeny accompanied her the greater part of the way, and, after receiv- ing her word that she would call the following lay, turned back. They had not proceeded far, when Miss Sweeny, happening to look across the street, saw the figure of a man, buttoned up in a long, close-fitting, white duster, with his back to- wards them, leaning against a lamp-post. He was such a long figure, and such an awkward one, that she could not help pointing him out to Annie, and both smiled. As they approached, however, Annie's smile quickly faded; for on the head of the figure she recognized the old glazed, chipped cap of the Scotchman. Not wishing to betray her feelings to her companion, and think- ing after all it might not be he, she merely moved a little closer to the other, and walked on., Try as she might, she could not help cast- ing a look in the direction of the lamp-post when they came opposite to it, and there, sure enough, V stood the graceful Scotchman, with his dull eyes fixed on her as they used to be on board the ship. He moved as if to come towards them, and Annie, her heart throbbing violently, caught her friend by the arm, and begged her to hurry on. "Why, what's the cause of this, Miss Reilly?" asked the other, with a surprised look. "What has happened to alarm you?"  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7150-00000075"/> "4      Anrnie Reidly. Annie cast a furtive glance at the Scotchman,  who began walking along the opposite side, and  said: : "Please don't ask me now. I'll tell you when we reach the house. Please hurry on."  Both girls began to walk quickly; but, when they quickened their pace, the man on the other  side of the street did the same, jolting along,  swaying from side to side, like an ill-built load of $  hay. Annie, thoroughly frightened, glanced at  him occasionally, and at last begged Miss Sweeny  to run. The latter, at length comprehending the cause of Annie's fright, broke into a laugh, and said:      -  "Now, Miss ,Reilly, you must not be so easily alarmed as that, or you cannot well live in New York. You will see more frights than him before a week."  ' At this moment, their annoyer hastened into the street, qind, hurrying across, met them on a corner, despite all their efforts to get past before him.  "Ah,! noo, lassie, you're nae kind to run away from an auld acquaintance," said he, planting himself before Annie. I hae lang been watchin' to see ye." "I don't want to see you," said Annie, her terror giving her courage. "How dare you - t      - *  .         X II   Annie Reilly.      145 annoy me this way! Let me pass now, or I'll calI'the police." "Nae, nae,'noo,' said he coaxingly; "ye wad nae do that." '  \ "I shall, I shall. Miss Sweeny, I beg of you call a policeman," said Annie. That young lady had her face partly turned away, looking in the direction of a number of mechanics who were leaving a building on the opposite corner. She seemed not to hear Annie's entreaty, and still watched the men coming into the street, and scattering in every direction. At length a tall, straight, smart-looking young man came out, putting on his coat as he did so. Miss Sweeny quickly beckoned him, and in a second he was beside them. "Here is a ruffian annoying this young lady," said Miss Sweeny, pointing to the Scotchman. "He has stopped her on the sidewalk." The young man cast a scornful look on him, and, drawing his open hand, slapped him two or three times on each jaw; and, when he turned to run, which was as quickly as he possibly could, gave him such a kick that for the first few yards he never made such speed in his life. Now, whether it were that the blows blinded his eyes, or that his feet were so very clumsy that they could not be trusted in a long race, we don't pre-  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7150-00000076"/> "6      A nn ie Reilly.  sume to know; but, after running a little distance,  he stumbled and fell in a heap on a pile of dirt  which the sweepers had just gathered up. A  i policeman, happening to see the crowd of boys gath- j{ ering around him, hurried up, and, in spite of all his-entreaties and declarations, hauled him off to Ad the station-house for a drunken man. The police- :i man was not much to blame; for'he certainly ': looked as if he had rolled the streets for a mile. All this happened in such rapid succession that Annie and her friend were bewildered. The young man .accompanied them part of the way : towards the house, and, when he turned away, Miss Sweeny told Annie he was Kitty's lover. i Mr. -Sweeny was within, anxiously awaiting their return; for, after all he had heard his wife -i say of Annie's family, he longed to see her. He A was a low-sized, fat, good-humored-looking man, :: with a merry twinkle in his eye, and just as fond i of fun as any Irishman in New York. He told so many amusing stories, and laughed so much -during the evening, that Annie thought that he : must be the happiest man in the world. And he was happy. Strictly temperate from the day he came to New York, he spent none of his money in the grog-shop; never came home cross, peev- ^ ish, or full of bad whisky, but always light- ! hearted, even after the hardest day's toil, to join   Annie Reilly.      I47 his wife in their evening prayers; never lounged around dirty and slovenly on Sunday morning, but could be seen early in his seat at church. Through his industry and good habits, he was now inde- pendent.        ' Annie spent a very pleasant evening, went to rest on a comfortable bed, and slept soundly till the bright rays of the sun, shining through the blinds, told her the morning was far advanced. : '      !.  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7150-00000077"/> CHAPTER XVI.         ?  JAMES O'ROURKE'S EXPERIENCES IN A NEW YORK MENAGERIE. , ng AMES O'ROURKE  continued to ;s l work along shore for several months, saving up all the money he could, and sending it to his father. He had  written to Annie the day after his arrival, but, receiving word from Francis that she had gone ! to New York, tried by every possible means to, learn her whereabouts in the city. He went to a Castle Garden, hoping to receive some informa- tion in that very correct establishment; but no such name had been entered on the books about the time he mentioned. This he gleaned from a if clerk after a day's delay-the very clerk to whom X Annie had given her name. 'He even advertised in some of the daily papers, but without effect. When his hard 'day's work would be over, he went around to the houses of such as he had learned were from that part of Ireland, and re- quested them to make every enquiry; but months went by, and he heard nothing of Annie. The + ',           Xi!   Anxnie Reilly.      I49 only conclusion he could arrive at was that she had gone on to some distant city. This bitter disappointment weighed heavily on his mind. . If she were in Ireland, where he might hear from her now and then, he would not have felt so heart-broken; but to know she had been and probably was in New York, that per- haps he saw the ship that carried her over coming into the harbor, and that every effort of his to see her or hear of her proved in vain, was painfully distressing. Meanwhile, the class of people amongst whom he was thrown were not calculated much to im- prove his spirits. We do not mean by this his fellow-laborers, who were for the most' part honest, hard-working men like Terence McMan- us. The latter had told James, when he first went to work, that he could board with him if he chose; but O'Rourke knowing, from the limited accommodation he possessed, that this offer was prompted only by goodness of heart, sought out another boarding-place--an act which he very soon after regretted. This establishment stood in one of the side - streets, directly over a beer-saloon.. It consisted of three floors, divided into five or six rooms each, and served no fewer than fifty boarders. That these rooms were of small compass need     &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7150-00000078"/> 50-     Annie Reilly. not be told. Those which looked out on the street or into the yard in the rear were the lar- gest, and contained two and three beds each. The middle bedrooms were of such small dimensions, and the doors leading into them were so nar- row, that the beds they contained must have been built there. These were sometimes called the dark bedrooms--a most appropriate name; for, except the door is open or broken down, as sometimes happens, not a ray of light can enter them. We defy any man, even the most unim- aginative, to sleep there one night without think- ing of dungeons, skeletons, and ghosts. All the floors were bare but clean, except s wherle covered with tobacco-juice or the ashes of pipes. The beds--well, one of them would not be the most soothing place in the world for an ill- tempered man with the toothache. The straw or hay, or whatever it might be, had an obstinate habit of getting into hard, round lumps, which, if you tried to smooth down in one spot, instantly burst up in another. The" first night a person sleeps on one of those beds he is sure to start up with the impression that some one is beating him about the ribs; and, to complete the comfort of. the thing, the pillows are hard enough for the head and neck of any patriarch., The kitchen was on the lowest floor in the rear; W^i i *a   Annie Keilly.       5 1 and so hot and fierce did it look from the front room that the most stout-hearted boarder never ventured to enter it during the warm weather. The first evening James came to the establish- ment, the boarders were assembled at supper, and the lamp on the table burned very dimly. A first glance along the row of faces, and his heart sank as he thought of Liverpool ; but when he was seated, and surveyed them more closely, he saw that every man had his hands and face washed. This must have taken considerable time; for James saw but one wash-stand in the hall, and one towel sewed .together at the ends, which turned on a round piece of wood like a weaver's reeling-stick. The boarding-mistress, Mrs. Grady, stood at a small, narrow table by the window, on which were placed two such large dishes of corned beef and soup that James wondered how they main- tained their balance, busily engaged serving out their contents. On the table were pickles, rad- ishes, tomatoes, onions, cheese, butter, and baker's bread in every variety of shape, but all in very small quantities, and so close together in the centre of the table that it must have required ex- traordinary exertions on the part of those at the ends to reach them at all. Mrs. Grady's object in thus placing them may   &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7150-00000079"/> I52     SAnnie Reilly. probably have been a very laudable one. Her  husband, a small, weazen, crabbed-looking fellow,  who was what is commonly called a " curbstone broker," or vagabond real-estate agent, always  sat at. the middle of the table, and she may have been determined to give him sufficient, no matter who wanted. The swarm of flies on and around the table- was something awful. Bread, butter, boarders' hands and arms, meat, soup, eyes, noses, and sometimes mouths- were infested with them; and /'the increased hum they kept up seemed to pre- vent Mrs. Grady hearing any boarder who hap- pened to want his plate replenished. James felt nearly as much disgusted as he had been in Liverpool, and ate very little supper, hurried outside, and went down to the docks to i catch a little fresh air from the river. When he returned, the boarders were about to I go to bed, and Mrs. Grady pointed out to James  his bedfellow while he remained in the house: ' A very nice, clean man," she explained. O'Rourke looked at his hollow, drunken eyes, and old, torn red shirt, and gravely doubted the  good lady's recommendation.        ! James sat for some time at the window, look- ing at a wrangling crowd of Dutchmen outside ; the saloon, one of whom kept continually shout-   Annie Rezlly.      I53 irg, "Vat for you do mit das, ha? Vat for you do, ha? Vat for you, oder any man, in the city of Ni Yorik, dare exult me oder mine olt voomans?" When he had roared himself hoarse, and no one appeared to show cause why himself or his wife should be insulted, he muttered a few drunken curses at a crowd of boys who had gathered around himself and his comrades, and staggered into the saloon again. James left the window and went up-stairs to his room, which, by the way, was one of the dark bedrooms. As he approached the door, a faint light, dimly visible through the keyhole, attracted his attention. He pushed open the door, and there, lying on his back in the middle of the bed, with all his clothing, shoes included, on, was his new comrade, quietly smoking a long white pipe. James thought this a novel place to smoke in, but he merely threw the door open; for, from the close heat of the room and the fumes of the tobacco, the apartment was well-nigh suffocating. He sat down on his trunk-the only seat, ex- cept the bed, in the room-and began taking off his shoes, hoping the smoker would leave the" bed, that he might lie down. But, no; lihe lay there, lamenting the high price of liquor, and predicting the consequent ruin of the country, till his pipe was smoked down, when he turned  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7150-00000080"/> 154      Annie Reilly.  over on his side, and, pulling a paper of tobacco  from underneath the bolster, began to refill it, s which having done, he dived after a match in his  old, torn vest, lighted it on his thigh, and went on smoking as before.            X James's patience was exhausted, and he said:  "Do you intend smoking all night? If you do,  you had better sit outside here, and let me lie down."      .    . "Augh! the divil a bit hurry I am in to go to  bed," said he. "Me and a couple more got a little  bit tight around noon-time, and the boss sacked  every man of us; so I am not goin' to work in  the mornin'." "Well, I am not so," said James. "I want to  go to bed. It wasn't on your account I spoke, I assure you."   - The other kept silent, and smoked away.  "Stand up and leave that pipe away! I won-  der how you can tolerate the smell of it your- self; I am sick half an hour ago." "Arrah! take it aisy, can't ye?" said he. "I'll  be through now in twinty minutes." "Up with you to your feet!-" exclaimed O'Rourke, losing all patience; and, catching him by the shoulder, he lifted him to his feet, and left him standing on the floor. "If I have the mis- fortune to be in the same room with you any   Annie Reilly.       I55 more, I'd recommend you to quit smoking in bed." "All right, I'll get square one of these days, me lad. I'm the ouldest boorther in this house, and ought to have the same privilege as any other man; but I'll get square." And he sat down so heavily on the other's trunk as almost to crack the lid. "If you break my trunk, I'll flatten you," said James, as he searched for a peg to hang his clothes on. "I want me rights," said the other, with a drunkeni- leer, and raising his left shoulder to his ear. "What rights?" asked James. "The same as other men," he shouted, waving nis hand toward the other rooms. James looked out and saw at least a dozen boarders, some outside, some inside the bed- clothes, while the smoke from their pipes was struggling desperately to escape through a broken pane. He threw himself on ,the bed,' and, having worked very hard that day, was soon asleep. Happening to wake up during the night, the first object that met his eyes was the red glare of his companion's pipe close by his face. The next day he made enquiries after a new  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7150-00000081"/> 156      Annie Reilly. boardingjhouse; butit, being told by his fellow- laborers that they were all alike, he made up his I mind, in case every effort to find Annie failed, to leave New York. Every-effort in that direction did fail, as our readers know. So when the demand for work- men at the oil-fields in Pennsylvania came, James 3 and a few others-set out there. CI., : ?  'i .i   CHAPTER XVII. ANNIE FALLS IN WITH A MOTHER-IN-LAW AND A TARTAR.---BOTH TRY TO CONVERT HER. OTWITHSTANDING     that Mr. and Mrs. Sweeny and Kitty Brady did all t in their power to persuade Annie to take a few weeks' rest, she advertised for a situation in one of the morning papers the second day after her arrival in New York. Why she insisted on putting her name to the advertise- ment none of her friends could make out; but Annie had been thinking very much of James O'Rourke, and praying that she might see him, and that may have accounted for it. In reply to the advertisement, a tall, thin- jawed, oldish-looking woman, with a net shawl drawn tightly around her shoulders, called about noon. Mrs. Sweeny happened to be out at the time, otherwise she would not have let Annie engage with her. But the latter was anxious to fulfil the promise she had made to Francis. This was the first answer to her advertisement she had received, so she answered the numerous ques- tions put to her as well as she could, and was not  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7150-00000082"/> 58       nn ie Reilly. a little delighted when the. lady told her to come in the morning. She left a name and address on a card. which she explained were not her own, but that of her mar- I ried daughter, for whose service she had engaged Annie. The latter : looked at the name-Mrs. Derby Granville Phillips--and thought to herself it was a pretty high-sounding name, but not such a strange one after all. The address was Brooklyn, and this confused her a little at first, knowing it was so far from her friends in New York; but that was not to be con- sidered. Accordingly, at the  appointed hour in the morning, Annie appeared at the door of Mrs. D. G. Phillips, looking very pretty and cheerful at the prospect of soon being able to-help her father and mother. The door was opened by the old lady who had hired her in New York, who, in return to Annie's nod of recognition, merely held up her hands very high, and said, as -she pulled out a large watch with- a very heavy chain, which Annie thought looked remarkably like brass: "I  like punctuality. You are just three minutes too soon; but we'll overlook that for this time. Hurry down to your business." Annie, not a  little surprised at this odd recep- tion, went down-stairs to the kitchen, and, seeing no ,   A izinzie Reilly.    159 one there, stood for a moment, not rightly know- ing what to do next. Soon she heard the tread of feet coming down the stairs, and, looking along the hall, saw a young lady, who in thirty years hence would pass very easily for the old one, coming towards her with a little white lap-dog resting on one arm, and a very flashy novel in the hand of the other. She put down the animal as she entered the kitchen, -and began talking to it and fondling it, calling it the most endearing names, and bending down occasionally to kiss it and hug it to her breast. She did not look towards Annie, or seem to know she was present, till she had tired herself caressing the dog, when she turned round sud- denly, and said, with her mother's lofty scorn: "You're the new servant, eh?" "Yes, madam," replied Annie, her voice quiv- ering. "A nice servant you are!" said the other, hold- ing an eye-glass, which only dimmed her sight, to her eye, and, with her mouth drawn very tight, looking at the poor girl. "Why don't you go up- stairs and change your dress, 'm?" "Please, madam," said Annie, " the other lady, your mother I think--" "Go on, go on; don't stand to talk to 'me about what you think. I am mistress here," said she,  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7150-00000083"/> I60      Annie Reilly.  lifting the dog again. "Change your clothes, and  look like work, quick." "Where shall I change my clothes, please, madam?" asked Annie.      -       : "Well, well, my dear," was the reply. "Where ' is she to change her clothes? Have you ever  X been in a first-class house before?"But without  giving Annie time to answer, she added, throwing back her head, and closing her eyes languidly, "Go up to the servant's room on the top floor." Annie went up-stairs, and, as she passed the front door, she was almost tempted to run into   the street and away. The servant's room of the " mansion," as Mrs. Phillips loved to call it, 'was a very miserable apartment; the walls and floor bare,'and the ceil- ing hardly five feet in height. In getting ready for her work, no girl could make greater haste than she did but, on descend- ing to the kitchen again, she was :met by the angry frown of the mother-in-law, who declared she really thought Annie was gone and in New York by this time. The mansion employed but one girl, and as the last one had been gone three or four days, and nei- ther the mother nor daughter offered her the least assistance, Annie spent a very laborious morning. There was no system in the "mansion," which   Annie Reilly.      I61 made the work even harder. Mrs. Phillips would call her from the range to smooth a collar, and from that, before it was finished, to run up-stairs or out to the shop for something she needed "desperately," as she always added, to hurry Annie. Being so very busy did not annoy her, but everything she did was found 'fault with, and when she expected a smile, received only a with- ering frown. Poor little Annie, her heart was almost break- ing; but she thought of the calm evening by the river's bank in far-off Ireland, when James said she was brave as a little lion, and she did not shed a tear now either. During the afternoon, Mrs. Phillips's two little boys came- in from school, and, seeing the new servant, were delighted at the opportunity it gave them to display their polite training. "Halloo!" cried the eldest, a youth of about seven, with a yellowish, unwholesome-looking face, narrow forehead, and very flat nose-" hal- lo! And when did you come?"And he ran up to Annie, who was lifting a large vessel, filled with hot water, from the range, and deliberately walked across her toes. " Beware, beware, Gussy, of the scalding water!" cried his grandmother, who happened  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7150-00000084"/> 6 2      Annie Reilly. to come in at the moment. "What a daring lad you are!" - "None of your business," said the hopeful boy. "She is our servant, not yours." "O Gussy!" said the old lady, who, by the way, was only tolerated in the house. "I mean the risk you have just run of getting the boiling water over you, that's all." "Keep your talk to yourself," said the young- est youth. "Papa told you and mamma told you to interfere with us no more, or you might go some place else." "Say, when -did you come?" asked the eldest again, moving beside Annie. She made no reply, but went on with her work. "Oh! she's stuck up, she is," said the young- est, throwing a smoothing-iron into the water, causing it to splash up on the poor girl's face and arms. Annie- turned to the old lady, and said, while her lips quivered: "Pray, madam, tell them to cease tormenting me this way." "Ha! 'ha!" laughed both. "Her tell us tc stop. She has no more right here than you have yourself," said the oldest. "But come along, Roy; papa will murder us for keeping her idle."   Annie Reilly.      I63 And the two scampered up-stairs, and amused their mother, first by relating to her the tricks which "Gussie had played on the new girl," and again exciting her wrath by telling her that their grandmother had interfered with them. At nightfall, Mr. D I G. Phillips came home. He was a small, thin; cross-grained man, with an immense black mustache and a bald head. Not a bald head of the ordinary kind, however, for we dare say the owner of the "mansion" would scorn that; but a crown dotted over with bare spots here and there, which, if put together, would leave a clear space extending probably to the backs of his ears. Annie opened the door for him, and he shot inside with such force that she peeped through the'glass to see if any person outside pitched him in. When she looked around, he had disappeared into the parlor, and she could hear the ring of Mrs. Phillips's voice as she rated him for not being home sooner. Annie hurried down to her duties, dreading lest she might hear a word not intended for her ears; but as we are not so scrupulous, we will stop a -moment and see the cause of the row. "' A pretty time of night for you to come land- ing home," said Mrs. Phillips, closing the novel she had been reading, as her husband put his head inside the parlor door.  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7150-00000085"/> t64      Annie Reilly. "What are you talking about night for?" said the husband, throwing himself on the worn sofa. "Are you prepared for me this evening again?" - "Yes, sir- -I am prepared for you," said Mrs. Phillips, coming close, and looking down on him with a frown. "I want to know where you were till this time of night--night, I repeat. I know I can't believe a word you say, but I insist on some answer."  "Business in the office delayed me," said he, with an ominous look, at which Mrs. Phillips smiled scornfully. "And don't tell me I am a liar again. It ill becomes you to call any one a liar. Your mother, rot her, is the biggest." 'I'll not tolerate this, sir," exclaimed she, stamping her foot and interrupting him. "If anything is to be said to mother, I'll say it." "But this is my house," said he modestly. "Is it your house? Oh! to be sure it is. I am no better than a servant here," said she, with an hysterical laugh. "And of course you can come in or go out any hour of the night you like..' "Why not?" said he. "Why not!" echoed she with a yell that brought the old lady up-stairs in a second. "Oh! what treatment for me to bear. He openly tells me, mother," continued she, in the same loud voice, "that he'll come home when he likes, and go out   Annie-Reilly.       i65 at night when he likes." Here a flood of tears choked her utterance. "I'd put the seas between me and him," said the mother-in-law, shaking her head furiously at him. "Merciful God, if I only could!" said the son- in-law, in an undertone. I:  Lettie, dear, I'll run for some cold water; I think you're going to faint," said her mother. "Oh! don't leave the room now, I beg of you," exclaimed the sobbing lady. "Oh! dear, oh! dear. Bless my soul, he has a very villanous look on him this evening," said the old lady, turning back and looking at her son-in- law, who certainly did not look very agreeable, with his face, mustache, and forehead puckered up with an expression of deep pain. Oh! my soul and body," continued the kind-hearted old lady, wring- ing her hands, " was it for this I raised and edu- cated-ahem!--my daughter in the best style?" She, seemed to expect an answer to this impor- tant enquiry from some person hidden up in the ceiling; for she walked the floor a dozen times, her eyes turned upwards, repeating the same question. The expression on the husband's face grew worse as he watched her, and his wife's tears fell very plentifully and comfortably, as she sat on a  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7150-00000086"/> 166      Annie Reilly. chair opposite her husband, with her head turned away from him.                I "If I were you, I'd put the ocean between us,"  said the old lady again, improving on her favorite expression. "Let us pack' up now, my dear." Mrs. Phillips dried her tears instantly, and, springing to her feet, ordered her mother to leave the room. "What business have you in the parlor?" taking ,; her by the shoulders. "Go down-stairs, and wait : till you're sent for." As the worthy daughter turned from the door after putting her mother outside, she thought, by the altered look of her husband, that he was ! pleased with what she had done. And as please  him was the very last thing on earth she could think of, she burst into tears again, and called :: him a brute, a wretch with a heart like flint or ( steel, and numerous other choice names. Mr. I Phillips bore all patiently till her voice grew hoarse, when she took the little dog in her arms, ; and went up-stairs.              i At length Sunday morning came, and there was X a great bustle of preparation in the "mansion."  A  celebrated divine of Brooklyn, Rev. Dr. Brass-  man, was to preach in the Academy of Music that i Sabbath.  He was the family pastor, and a great I favorite with Mrs. Phillips. ' X" s  ,        ,   Annie Reilly.      I67 Annie worked very hard during the morning, assisting them, and, when they were just ready to go out, the mother-in-law looked at her watch, and announced they were half an hour too early; and as Mrs. Phillips detested a long delay in church, except her favorite preacher was there to entertain her, they sat down to wait till the proper time. Now, the old lady was one of those very sensi- ble people who -try and make the very best use of every moment. The thought that now might be a favorable opportunity to convert Annie came into her head. She ventured to tell her son-in-law and daughter of it, and was greatly delighted, good soul, to find they did not snub her. The three were seated in the parlor, with the two boys tumbling over each other on the floor beside them. Mrs. Phillips held the little white dog in her arms, and the old lady sat bolt upright, waving an immense black fan. The bell rang, and Annie appeared, looking very pale and beautiful, having just dressed her- self to go out to church. "Ahem! Come nearer us here," said the old lady, putting on her glasses. "We want to talk a little with you, now that we have time." Annie approached, wondering greatly what the cause of this solemn council could be.  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7150-00000087"/> I 68     Annie Reilly. "You're a Romanist, an't you?" began the old lady. "I am a Roman Catholic, madam," said Annie, her face pushing. j "Ah! yes ; the greater part of you Irish are," said the other. "But don't you Iknow you are astray?"  "No, madam, I do not," said Annie. "The Catholic Church was established -by our Lord himself." "Nonsense, nonsense," said the other, with a toss of her head and fan, "impossible-the Cath- olic Church founded by Christ! Have you ever read the Bible?" "Certainly, madam," replied Annie; "it was the first book I learned to read." "Don't tell me  that, girl," said the old lady, looking round on the others. "Your priests for- bid you to read the Bible ; I know it."  "With due respect for your knowledge, ma- dam," said Annie politely, " our priests do no such thing!  They earnestly recommend every Catholic to read the Bible, but it must be the Bible complete and unadulterated."' "This is something new for us," said the mother-in-law. "It is by no means new, madam," replied Annie, " but it is something very new and strange " ,er ne          k ta   Annie Reilly.      I69 to me to hear any one assert that priests forbid the use of the Bible. Our parish priest in Ire- land, so anxious was he every family should have a Bible, that he supplied those himself who were unable to purchase one." 'i "I should think that a very dangerous game for I himself," said Mrs. Phillips, patting the dog's head. "How, madam, may I ask?" said the girl. "Why, then you would all see the folly of his pretensions," was the reply. "The Bible doesn't tell you he can forgive your sins?" "Certainly not," said Annie, " by any power of his own." "And by whose power, then?" put in Phillips, who thought he had been long enough silent. "By the power of God, who- has given them that authority," said Annie. "Oh! they all say that," said the mother-in- law with a sneer. "Listen to me, young woman,"' she added earnestly. "Do you think, because our Lord promised that power to his apostles, whom he saw and conversed with every day, that your priests now, after the lapse of eighteen hundred years, possess the same power?" "I believe," said Annie, with something of a smile on her face, "that our Lord can do now what he did eighteen hundred years ago. Time has not diminished his power."  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7150-00000088"/> 1x70     A nnie Reilly.  "I know that," said the old lady, fidgeting uneasily in her chair; "but what I mean to say is, he gave that authority to his disciples only." "There is no reason for saying or thinking so," said Annie. "Those who lived at that time were not a privileged people, more than that they happened to be on earth at the same time as our Saviour. He came to save all-not one genera- tion--and to grant all salvation through the same means." The mother-in-law was biting her lip and twist- ing her fingers, thinking of what she would say next, when Mrs. Phillips joined in with: "Then that is a very easy way -to reach heaven -act as you like, and then go to your priest and get forgiveness." "Oh! no," said Annie; "there are conditions necessary fqr a good confession." "What are they?" asked the mother-in-law. "The most important are," said the girl, "a sincere sorrow for the faults committed, and a strong resolution to sin no more." "Ah!" said the old lady, pitching her head for- ward, "I have you now. You say our Lord came to save all, and yet you believe all except Catho- lics will be lost." "What I said was," replied Annie, " that our Lord came to redeem all through the same means.   Annie Reilly.       7  I He did not adopt two methods; and I say now that the Catholic Church only preserves the Scrip- tures unchanged " "Oh! yes, indeed," said Mrs. Phillipsspite I fully, " that's more of your priests' slander. I don't believe they do a thing else in their cha- pels on Sunday but abuse other people." it "You do our clergy a great injustice, madam, said the girl warmly, " when you say so. They preach the Gospel to their hearers, pointing out to them the evils they are to avoid and the vir- tues they should practise. Now, slander is a very great vice, and none is more severely con- demned by our priests." "Ha!. but they tell you all Protestants will go to hell, don't they?" asked the old lady, taking up the thread of the argument. "If you were to go to any of our churches on Sunday," said Annie, "you would think there was but one religion in the world; because our priests instruct their people in the doctrines of their own, and never mention the name of Protes- tant or any others :who differ from us." The mother-in-law drew out her broad-faced watch, and, to her great relief, saw it was time to go and hear the Rev. Dr. Brassman; so she told Annie that at some future period she would con- vince her of her error.  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7150-00000089"/> CHAPTER XVIII. A MODERN CLERGYMAN.-REV. DR. BRASSMAN'S GREAT ENTERPRISE. HE Rev. Dr. Brassman was a very in- i defatigable man, not alone in the service, of God, but in his efforts to make a name here on earth. The Rev. Dr. knew as well as, perhaps, any minister that the apostles were poor and lowly men who cared not for this world's fame; but thinking that, as the world grows older, men grow wiser, the same poverty and humility were not expected from him. That the apostles preached to large multitudes he had no -doubt, but saw that the language which gathered large crowds in those days would leave him an empty church now. Of this he was more fully convinced by the ex- ample of a brother divine, who totally ignored Gospel preaching in his pulpit, and delighted his hearers with other and more entertaining infor- mation. In this he was very successful, as the number and respectability of his congregation went to show.  At this, Dr. Brassman, as became a -pious and charitable minister; grew very envi-   Annie Reilly.      173 ous, and resolved, at all hazards, not to be kept in the background. Dr. Brassman was a very eloquent gentleman, and had a powerful voice. Even in his calmest days, before the desire to become notorious laid hold of him, no nervous man or woman who happened to know-his church would venture past while he was in the pulpit. The dogs in that neighborhood had acquired such a habit of barking incessantly on Sunday evenings that every sensible citizen kept his can- ine muzzled on that day. But when the desire to outvie his celebrated brother took possession of his head and lungs, the streets in his vicinity began to depopulate, and what people had nerve enough to remain put their dogs into the cellar before the terrible roar broke upon the air. Now, it may seem strange how any one, except they were born deaf as a stone, could stand their ground inside the church, while the noise affected' men and animals outside so much. Well, to any man or woman who may be disposed to doubt these truthful lines, we say-and he may go and try it, if he chooses-that it is much easier to withstand the yells of a roaring minister inside his temple than without. When Mr. Phillips and his wife and mother-in-  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7150-00000090"/> I74      An nie Reilly. law reached the Academy, they found the worthy minister already in the pulpit. This was a great relief to the old lady; for, after the indifferent suc- cess she had achieved -in the controversy with Annie, she wanted something to distract her thoughts. The doctor had not commenced speak- ing yet, and sat on a low seat within the pulpit,  his chin resting on its edge, looking placidly on the thickening crowd. His head, which was all of him that could be seen, was a very peculiar, one indeed-very short and small behind, bulgeds out alarmingly over each ear, and very narrow on the crown.  His face was very long and straight, eyes large and watery, nose short and turned : down, and forehead surprisingly high and nar-  row.  When he saw every seat filled, he rose slowly and with dignity, pushed his hair up in front till it stood on ends, looked wildly around, and, striking the side of the pulpit heavily with his open hand till the building echoed again, said,  in a heavy undertone:             ; "Brothers, we air here toe-day "-puckers' up his mouth, throws back his chest, and shakes his head-" saints and sinners. The little bird that  tunes its lay toe heaven speaks a lesson of wis- dom toe us all toe-day." A little higher:  , Why  does that little bird sing? Because "-louder- "it is free; free, my brethren, toe hop from branch s0 ,  .          Annie Reilly.       175 to branch "-sorrowfully--" and gather up for its young the tiny little worm. Again "--his very loudest---"I ask, Why does that little bird sing? Becau-au- au-ause it has a free conscience," smiting the pulpit again. ' Becau-au-au--ause it is no thief who steals. Becau-au-au-ause it is no liar who breeds discord. Becau-au-au -ause it is no drunkard who comes home late at night." (Mrs. Phillips nudged her husband) "Becau-au-au-ause that little bird is no mur- derer who shoots, or stabs, or beats out the brains of its fellow-man." (He stops and drinks; the mother-in-law is greatly affected.)- The beau- tiful parable--ahem! I made it myself-which I have told you about the little bird reminds me that in the city of New York, that hot-bed of sin, and crime, and etarnal drunkenness, a man lies condemned toe die. Great efforts, we hear, are being made by that man's friends toe -save him;   - but "-a perfect scream--" what did the old law say?" stamping his foot, and swinging his arms wildly round: "An eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth. My friends, it makes my heart sad when I see hardened sinners going back on the old law in this way. Po-litical co-ruption, my friends, is at the bottom of this and every other evil in the land. In the olden times, the pure old times, the people had no Bill Plunderfoots, no Dick   &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7150-00000091"/> 176   --  Annie Reilly. Bezzlers; and if they had, my brethren, what would they have done with them. Suppose, my brethren, when Moses, that man of God and of decided opinions, was leading the chosen people through the bushes, and he had discerned a Bill Plunderfoot in the camp, what would that up- right, uncompromising man," claspin ghis hands and looking upwards, " have done? I'll tell you what Moses, who knocked the ungodly Egyptian on the head, would have done. He'd have smote," shaking his fist like another Moses, "Bill Plunderfoot down-down intoe perdition straight away i If any man says toe any of you, my brethren, that Moses wouldn't have come out as I say, tell that vile man he lies." Grows fu- rious. "Tell that scurvy man he's in error; tell that man he's on the broad road that leads toe death; tell that blind man he's going toe hell himself." The learned doctor continued in this very edify- ing strain, occasionally varying his subject, for at least two hours, when he stopped as suddenly as if he were deprived of the ipower of speech, sat down in the pulpit so quickly that one might think he had lost the power of his limbs, and drank three glasses of brown water in succession. This was a warning to his flock that he intended making some very important announcement, so   A-nnie- Reilly.     !" they retained their seats. He sat for a few min- utes, his head thrown back, eyes and mouth closed tightly, breathing heavily through his nostrils. "Something staggering must be coming," whispered the mother-in-law to her daughter. At length he rose, straight and slowly, like steam ascending from a bottle, and, when he had gained his full height,- advanced to the edge of the pulpit, and said: "Brethren, speaking toe you of the old law in the commencement of my sermon reminds me now that we should practise a few of the ceremo- nies of the times gone by. That fell destroyer and mad, fierce, unrelenting fiend fire--fire, my friends " (an old, unmarried lady near the pulpit tries to faint, but fails, and three little girls scream) --"fire, my brethren, has destroyed our taber- nacle wherein we used to all mingle our sweet voices in salutation and praise. The old spot was dear toe us all, and we long toe cover it with a sacred roof again. You have all subscribed gen- erously towards that object, but as yet we have far from enough toe complete the task. "Let us again turn our thoughts toe the lit- tle bird, toe all feathered creation, my brethren. They build their nests now as they did a thousand years ago, choose their mates as they  did a  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7150-00000092"/> 178      Anznie Reilly. thousand years ago, and wear the same plumage now as they did a thousand years ago. Now, my friends, let us draw a moral from the feathered in- habitants of the aerial skies-a moral, my friends, that will draw us some funds. From this congre- gation, brethren, I will select the most beautiful lady" (the old maid who had tried to faint now tried to smile) " and the handsomest young gen- tleman, and on to-morrow evening marry them in the good old costume of the seventeenth century, in the presence of as many as choose toe pay one dollar each admission." "Hear! hear! Bravo! Bully for you! Hur- rah," shouted the men, while-the ladies waved their fans and handkerchiefs. "I wish toe add," said the-preacher, smiling, ' that the marriage will not be binding except both are satisfied."- The old maid, who had risen to her feet in the excitement, threw herself back in her seat with a deep sigh, and the Rev. Dr. Brassman retired from the pulpit. *  s    CHAPTER XIX. JAMES O'ROURKE AT THE OIL-FIELDS.-A SKETCH OF HS COMPANIONS. HE Pennsylvania oil-fields were only a i hort time in operation when James O'Rourke and those who accompa- nied him arrived there. A number of rude huts, of rough, unplaned timber, were in course of construction for the accommodation of laborers, and one or two had just been completed. They were not built with much view to comfort, and were but poorly adapted to keep out the cold and storms of winter, which had already set in; but the air was pure, and this, after his experience in a city boarding-house, made James overlook every other disadvantage. The men employed in the fields were from every part of America and Europei, and were for the most part a very reckless set of fellows, who cared for nothing but drinking, carousing, and fighting. But James kept apart from them as much as possible, taking no part in their con- versation during the day, and in the evenings sitting alone by himself, thinking of home.  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7150-00000093"/> I80      Annie Reilly. A source of great trouble to him was, he could hear of no chapel in that part of the country. He made repeated enquiries among the laborers, but none of them knew anything of such a place, or cared, to use the words of one," if there wasn't a chapel on the face of the earth." The man who made this remark was a young Irishman only a few years from the old land. He had heard old vagabonds talk in this way, and thought it very manly to imitate them. "You don't care if there wasn't a chapel in the world?" repeated James, with a look in which were blended scorn and pity. "No; why the divil should I?" replied Dooley -for such was his name-stuffing half a paper of tobacco into his mouth. "You are a Catholic, are you not?" asked James. Yis; they used to call me that in Ireland; but I'm nothin' at all now." "And why have you seen fit to change .o so much here?" asked the other. "Religion, I see, is only a humbug. I had very little sinse in Ireland. Augh, Lord! sure the peopli there know nothin' at all." And he pushed the old cap to the back of his head, and tried to look very knowing. "Am I to believe you are in earnest in what i;'   Annie Reilly,       I8I you say?" asked James, looking at him atten- tively-" believe that you, a young man not long from Ireland, have completely turned your back on the teachings of the Holy Catholic Church?" "In troth, and 'pon me sowl, ye may shwear it that I mane every word I say. I seen the toime H i I thought the ground 'id open and swallow me m  .' "up for even thinkin' the loikes; but I tell ye, a man soon gets brave in America." "Do you call it bravery," asked James, " to jj : dread to acknowledge your creed, the creed of your forefathers, because those around you de- spise religion? Brave! .Why, you are the meanest of all cowards!" "What do I care what me forefathers belaved, l 'i or what me father or mother belaves either. I must look out for meself now. Phat's any one in the world to me but meself?" I "If a dog could speak," said James angrily, "I  dare say he would say the very same thing. He cares for no one but himself." But checking his passion, he went on: ^' Surely you don't think you'll thrive any the better here by turning your back on your religion?" "Divil a much meself cares for money," was the answer, "if I  can get a bit to ate, and a dhrink of whisky while I am in it; that's all I care for."  &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7150-00000094"/> 182      Annie Reilly. "So you're a drunkard, too," said James, nod- ding his head sorrowfully. "I can sthand more gin on a Saturday night than any other man in the diggins," was the an- swer. ", When I began to dhrink first," he went on, with a laugh, "I thought I'd niver be able to keep up to the rest ov the boys; it used to give me a headache-; and thin I'd be thinkin' of phat ould Father Philip used to say about drunkards long ago, and phat me father and mother id think if they only hard it; but I soon got over that; and so will-you too, me boy, come all right in the ind, and be, one of the best fellahs in the fields one ov thes days." And he slapped the other on the shoulder. "Sit down again, and listen to fne for a mo- ment," said James. "Come and have something to dhrink; me throat's dhry afther so much talk," said the other. "You know very well," said James, turning away his head, "I am no drinker. Have patience for a little." "All right, young fellah, but don't say any- thing to make me drier, or I can't sthand it." Jarles did not heed this remark, but went on: "You are a young man yet, and have the world befoc-e you; and just ask yourself the question, Is  \   Annie Reilly.      i83 now not the proper time for you to prepare for old age? In these fields, and in every other work in America where a number of men are em- ployed, how many are able to work? By right, hot one-half. It is pitiful to see so many old, - weakly, worn-out creatures, as I may call them, struggling to do hard labor, with possibly not five years of existence before them ; not one bit bet- ter than old horses. And what makes it sad- der still is that the greater part of them have themselves only to blame for their misery. When they were strong, when work was no burden to them, they took care neither of themselves nor of their earnings; ruining their health with bad whisky, for which they squandered their money." "Ah, phat's life to a man without he has some pleasure?" said the other, interrupting him. "And I don't see anything else there's so much pleasure in as a glass of whisky." ( Pleasure?" said James. "Why, you were lis- tening to that old man, that works in the gang with me, talking last night, were you not?" "Phat old man? Oh! yes-ould Mickey that was saying he's twenty-five years in the country. But he's a mane whinger, anyway." "( He spends all his money the.%ame as you do, at any rate," said James; ', and his shirt is no bet- ter or cleaner than your own."  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7150-00000095"/> 184      Annie Reilly. "Ay, but," said the other, in an injured way, "he takes the whole good out ov the thing by cryin' over it." "He knows," said James, " that in a very short time he'll not be able to clutch the spade, and that there is nothing before him but die of want. The man has become an habitual drunkard, and now is powerless to save himself. To advise or. reason with any one reduced to his state is use- less; but we can learn a lesson from his folly. Drink, he tells us, is no longer a pleasure to him; 'tis a hell from which he cannot escape. It has lowered him from the rank of a human being, and left him nothing better than an animal. The only feeling in his heart is regret." "The divil a bit of me is ivir sorry," said the other, in a careless way. "Whin the money's gone, I say, let it go." "Why, he says he felt in like manner when he took to drink," said O'Rourke; '- or, to use his -own words, ' Was as light-hearted without a penny as when he'd have .fifty dollars in his pocket.' But the man was strong to earn more then; he could not look forward to the day when that strength would fail him." "Augh! I say," replied Dooley, with a twist of his body, "whin a man isn't fit to work, it makes little matther what comes of him. He is   Annie Rtilly.      185 afther havin' his day; I wouldn't mind how I spint the last .few years of me days, if toimes were good up to that." "I little thought, of all people in the world," said James, " that an Irishman could be found to I  use such an expression-to show himself so utter- ly wanting in every honorable feeling. Picture to yourself what you .would then be, and what you will be if you don't take heed-scorned and despised by every one, crawling around, a thing with life in it, no more; a burden to yourself and to the world."              I "Oh! be me sowl, its preachin' a sarmon ye are; and, as I don't care for lecthers, I'll go and have me whisky."  Jame"looked sorrowfully after him, as his man- ly but ragged figure disappeared into the door of * the little rum-shop, and thought to himself what a woful blight to his countrymen in America love of such places proved. In a few days after the foregoing conversation, a native of Pennsylvania State came to work in the fields; and from him O'Rourke learned that a long way off, beyond the blue hills, a chapel -could be found. The following Saturday night,   when the laborers were enjoying themselves as usual, he set off ill the direction -indicated, his heart full of joy at the prospect of hearing Mass in the morning.  &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7150-00000096"/> CHAPTER XX. STRANGE OCCURRENCES IN THE "MANSION.-- IIAPPY LIFE OF A MOTHER-IN-LAW.-ANNIE RECEIVES A LETTER FROM HOME. NNIE lived at the "mansion" a little over a month, bearing patiently with every hardship and insult, but always bravely and intelligently defending her race and creed against the repeated attacks of the mother-in-law and her daughter. She had written to her father and mother the evening before leaving Patrick Sweeny's, giving a long account of her- voyage, and telling them what great friends she met with on her arrival in New York. With what anxiety she waited for an answer, giving the ship which carried her note, and the one that bore the reply, the shortest pos- sible time to cross the ocean. From the hour she expected the letter, till three days later, when Kitty Brady walked in with it, a cheerful smile on her face, Annie was in the height of grief, imagin- ing the most terrible things had caused the delay. It happened, fortunately, she was alone, the old and young lady - having gone out for a walk.   Annie Reilly.      187 Annie caught the letter from Kitty's hand, and, recognizing her brother's writing, kissed the ad- dress fervently. Her hands trembled, and, dread- ing she would tear the letter in opening it, requested the other to open and read it for her. Kitty stood over by the window, and, with Annie's head resting on her shoulder looking down at the words, read as follows: ". AUGUST I5, i86-. i a MY DEAR, DEAR SISTER: ' To-day, the Feast of the Assumption, we be- sought the Queen of heaven to watch over you in a far-off land. This blessed day our prayers were all for you, Annie, at home and before the altar. Since you left us, this is the first time mother has been to the chapel; but to-day I assisted her there, that she might kneel at the Virgin's feet for our darling Annie. Since her return, she has felt much better than at any time since we lost our home. Father goes to the chapel every evening now, to pray for you, Annie. We were greatly delighted to learn from your letter that you reached the end of your long journey safely, and that you met with such friends in New York. God's bless- ing on all who are kind to poor, little, lonely Annie! O Annie dear! I thought my heart would break this morning when the procession  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7150-00000097"/> I88      Annie Reilly. moved down from the altar, and your gentle face was not-amongst the bright throng. Of all your friends here, not one is more sincerely sorry after you than Mr. Lacy. When I meet him, his eyes fill up, and he passes by without saying a word; and yet often when father and I are absent, he comes to see mother, and talks to her of you. Between him'and Nancy Brady, she is recovering quickly from the blow our double misfortune has- been to her. Nancy was extremely delighted to hear your praise of Kitty's goodness to you. She has taken it into her head now that Kitty must come home and see her. "The day after you left us, Annie, I went to the castle, and found employment, and we are now living in one of the little cottages I mentioned to you that night by the pond. Martha's manner towards mother was never worse than the day you went away;- so I determined we should live in her house as short a time as possible. 'Father is greatly changed. He is no longer lively, and walks about with his head down, speaking. to or noticing nobody. He had a habit of going out very early in the morning the first week or so after your departure. What he could be doing abroad at that hour surprised me. So I followed him one morning to the top of the demense hill which you know- overlooks our old home, where   Annie Reilly.       I89 he sat down on a stone, and, turning his eyes in that direction, began to cry. I begged him to tell me what brought him there. He told me he found great consolation in coming there, for he could look down on the old cottage, and picture you to himself walking in the little garden or in the green fields around. And, O Annie! at that moment I could not say he was doing wrong. The old, old, once happy home was before my eyes. I saw you- as you used to stand by the door looking out on the river. The path leading to its banks, along which you and I so often ran, looked so familiar and friendly to me that your figure stood in its every winding. Soon my own eyes filled, and I again begged father to come away, but in vain. He desired me to return to mother, but mention nothing of where I had left him. "Now, Annie, from what I have told you, you must not think we are very miserable here. True, our sorrow that you are gone from us is very great indeed, but your letter helped to calm it very much, now that you have the danger of the ocean over you. "Now, sister, about your sending us help from there, let me tell you, and believe me, Annie, I am able to earn sufficient to keep us comfortably till you have supplied yourself with everything  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7150-00000098"/> Igo      Annie Reilly. you need. And, Annie, when with God's help I have managed to leave father and mother a little something, I will go to you, and both of us will, I trust, be able then to keep them comfortable. I know, dear Annie, it is quite useless to remind you of what you owe to God, but you will pardon a brother's anxiety. I have done now, Annie, and pray the choicest blessings of Heaven may fall upon you. Father and mother send their bless- ings to you, Annie. "Your loving brother, "FRANCIS REILLY." During the reading of the letter, poor Annie's tears fell incessantly; and Kitty, too, was so much affected that she was compelled to stop a few times to clear her eyes. "Now, Annie," said she, handing the letter to her, " is not that much better news -than you expected?" "Oh! but think of their unhappy state with all," said Annie through her tears. "My poor mother, I know, will break her. heart to see Fran- cis working for any one; and my poor father- think of him wandering away to the hill-top at break of day to look down on the old home! When he takes the loss of it so much to heart, I'll soon hear of his death."   Annie Reilly.      I9I u Why, no, Annie," said Kitty; " your mother has better sense than fret over such a thing as Francis earning a living at the castle for a time, when you tell her how well he can do here, and the short time 'twill be till he's here with you. You see, Annie, how your people will do at home in a great measure de-ends upon how you get along here. N ow, what a happiness 'twill be to you to have your brother here with you! Just think of that, and make it an object to be gained. Think how happy 'twill make your fathe) and mother to receive good, cheerful letters from you. And when you are well, let them know; never tell them you are fretting; and if you have one true friend in the world, mention it to them. I say this to you now, Annie, because I know you will not delay in writing again, and 'twill make you so happy yourself to think you are making your people happy." "God bless you," said Annie, kissing her friend, "for that-good advice. I will write as, cheering a letter as I can. But, Kitty, what do you say to your mother being anxious to have you pay her a visit? Do you intend going?" "'I'1 think over that," said the other; "'tis a long time till summer yet. This is the first time mother has mentioned the like since I came to America. You must have said something  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7150-00000099"/> 192      Annie Reilly. about me in your letter that made her take such a notion." Annie smiled, arid was about to make some reply, when a violent ringing of the door-bell, again and again repeated, alarmed them. She ran to the door, and, when she opened it, the mother-in-law, her head very erect, and a tear- in each eye, glided into the hall. Annie drew back into the parlor door; for the look and manner of the old lady was very alarming. She looked wildly up the stairs, ran -to the head of the base- ment ones, held her ear downwards in a listening attitude, ran back, glared at the girl, and asked, as she shook her head fiercely: "Has my' daughter returned yet?" "She has not," -said Annie, moving further into the room. "I hope nothing is wrong, madam?" "Don't question me; I don't tolerate it from a servant," was the kind reply. And she went to the door, and tried to look out through the glass. Annie did not venture to speak again; and, when she saw the old lady peering into the street, ran down and joined Kitty. "I think I had better leave you now, Annie," said that young lady. "Don't neglect coming over on Sunday evening, and Miss Sweeny and you and I will go to Vespers together."   Annie Reilly.      193 "Oh! pray don't leave me alone here yet," said Annie earnestly. "Something is the matter with the old lady. She has just come in, and looks terrible. I would die here if you left me alone." "I'll wait a little while, then," said Kitty, "but not long." Another jingling of the. bell, followed by a sharp kick on the outside of the door; Annie sprang to open it, and in came Mrs. Phillips, her face flushed, her mouth set, and her eyes fiery. "Where is that old-"But catchbing a glimpse of her mother in the parlor, she dashed in, and shouted hoarsely, "How dare you, how dare you, I repeat, come into my 'house when I have expressly forbidden you to do so?" "I'll explain to you, Lettie, if you only have patience, that 'twas all a mistake," said the mother, trembling. "No explanation will do," said the other, stamping furiously, and scratching at her face. "You have done the job, and there's no remedy but prevent you ever getting ' a show ' to do the like again. Oh!" and she wrung her hands, and champed her teeth, "to tell Mrs. Howard Roy Plantagenet that I worked in a factory in Eng- land!" "Ah! let ine say one word, Lettie, just one,"  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7150-00000100"/> I94       n Annie Reilly. and the mother threw up her hands to keep her infuriated daughter back, " and then you'll see that wasn't what I said at all. You're the cause of all the shame yourself, to strike me with your parasol before so many ladies." "You would, if you dare, you old disgrace, like to throw all the blame on me; but I am deter- mined to get rid of you now." And--shall we re- cord it?--catching her by the shoulder, "Here, now, leave my ' mansion' this moment, and go into the streets, where you ought to be. The idea of me thinking to be as good as Mrs. Howard Roy Plantagenet or iany other lady in the city, and keeping the like of you to tell my history to them!" "I beg of you, my child, do not cast me'but in my old days," pleaded the mother, turning her eyes, with a strange white look, on her daughter. ( I don't deserve it of you." "Oh! no," said the other, grinning into her face, "I suppose if anybody was here you'd tell them how you struggled in poverty and hunger to raise me, wouldn't you? Come on, now." "Ah! Lettie, let me alone till your husband comes home, and then I"ll leave all to him; and if- -"    -             . ' What!" exclaimed Lettie, giving her a shake, "Iet him,. too, know I was a factory girl in Eng- '   Annie Reily.       195 land? Then," and she laughed bitterly, "my power over him would soon be gone, along with my pridebefore Mrs. Plantagenet. Ah! no; I'll be rid of you before that." "So you are going to put me from your house?" said the mother, facing her. "This moment, now, you old-" "Before I go," shouted the mother, clutching her by the hair, "I say you haveworked in a fac- tory; and that I worked faere to support you, and starved myself to do so." Mrs. Phillips was mad. She knew Annie heard the shout, and, seizing her mother by the hair, dragged her to the door, and pushed her down the steps. Annie and Kitty were nearly Wild from fright. The desperate, unnatural act seemed to them like a dream.       : Mrs. Phillips hastily closed tl/e door and par- lor-blinds, and rang for Annie. "Tell her," said Kitty, "when you go up, that you are going to leave. Now, mind." "Oh! yes, I shall," said Annie; "but I am afraid to venture near her." "Go on," said the other; "I'll wait at the foot of the stairs here." -Annie, trembling, went up to the room, and, without giving her good mistress time to issue  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7150-00000101"/> i 196       Annie Reilly. any orders, told her she was going to leave im- mediately, and hurried down again. Kitty as- sisted her in getting her articles ready, and both set out for New York.         I '    e   CHAPTER XXI. O'ROURKE'S FORTUNES BEGIN TO IMPROVE. HE journey to the little frame chapel amongst the Pennsylvania hills was so long and tedious that, travel as he would, James could never reach there before Mass had commenced, till at length the good pastor, Father Fitzsimons, noticing his bright, intelligent face and becoming manner in church, resolved-to have a conversation with him, and from thenceforth service was delayed every Sunday morning till he would arrive. Father Fitzsimons became a great friend to him, lending him books to read in the evenings, and allowing his father's letters to come in his care. This kindness from one whom he respected so much was a great consolation to James, and helped him to bear up against the hardships and privations of his position; for although he cared little for the toil of the fields, yet the wild and reckless class amongst whom he lived was a source of great pain to him. During his first few weeks there, when the day's work was over, he would wander away  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7150-00000102"/> 198      Annie Reilly. alone, and sit in some quiet spot where he might not hear the curses, foul language, and drunken shouts of the others, and think of Ireland, with its quiet plains, gentle mountains and rivers, and green hills with tall chapel-spires peeping over their tops -an emblem of its people's devotion to God and the Catholic Church. His mind would wander -away back to the time when Francis Reilly and he used to carry little Annie to the school; to the- delight it caused when she clasped her tiny arms around his neck as he lifted her over some dan- gerous part of the road, and with what caution he used to watch lest Francis would deprive him of the pleasure. Thus his niemory would trace every incident of their happy lives up, to the last evening by the river's bank. Then he would vainly try to shut out the recollection of his trials and fears since then, and hope that one day Annie's face would smile on him again. But the misery of his own present state, and the dread of what may have befallen her, clouded the hope; and, with as sad a heart as ever beat within a breast, O'Rourke would return to his hut; and so much did those bitter thoughts take hold of his -mind 1that he often lay insensible to shouts, and uproar, and fighting around him. But when he began to read the good books supplied him by Father Fitzsimons, these gloomy thoughts   , .Axnnie Reilly       199 gradually brightened somewhat, and a new life seemed to open up before him. Of all the men in the fields, he was the most attentive to his business, and never during the allotted hours for work idled away a moment. This, amongst so many who acted differently, could not escape the notice of the proprietor of the field. This latter, Mr. Lewis, was a very amiable, just, polite American gentleman, who always made it a rule-to reward honesty and in- dustry without regard to creed or nationality. It was his custom to make a round of his men thrice every day: shortly after they went to work in the morning, at noon, and again towards the close of the day. He was not a man to act on an impulse. Before taking a step, he waited and satisfied himself fully that it would- not prove an injudicious one. For some weeks after O'Rourke's arrival at the fields, Mr. Lewis, in his daily rounds, passed him by unnoticed. But by-and-by, James began to observe him letting his eye rest on him a little more than usual. At first he paid no attention to this, thinking probably the gentleman only remarked him as-a stranger. One day, however,' he was standing on the edge of the well, looking -n at the work as usual, and'the others were laboring with might'and main for the time, when  &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7150-00000103"/> 200      Annie Reilly. James happened to raise his eyes in that direc. tion, and saw Mr. Lewis regarding him very at- tentively. James resumed his work, but, in a few minutes, Mr. Lewis came over to him, and said: "Young man, I wish to see you during the evening;'don't be out of the road,"' and turned away without giving the other time to speak. Accordingly, when work was over, instead of hiding himself from sight with his book, he waited within view of the little wooden office, till Mr. Lewis came to the door and beckoned him inside. The- gentleman was alone, and, returning to the chair from which he had risen, crossed his legs as  James entered, and told him to sit down. "Well, young man," were the first words, " how do you like oil-digging?" "Oh! I like the work very well, sir," was the reply. "Yes; but there is something else you don't like quite so well," said the gentleman, with a smile. "They are rough fellows, those diggers." "I can get along with them very well, sir," said James. "Yes; but don't you think you could get along better at something else? You write a  good hand, do you?" "I'll show you a specimen, if you please, sir," said James, greatly delighted.    '   Annie Reilly.      20I "Well," said the other carelessly, drawing a sheet of paper from the drawer at/ his hand, and throwing it on the desk, " move your chair over here, and let me see what you can do. Just make a copy of that card." And'he took one of his own from a large pocket-book on his knee. James did so quickly and very neatly, handed it to Mr. Lewis, who, after one glance, put it in the pocket-book, and said: "You write a very good hand indeed. Now what I want to propose to you is this: My busi- ness has increased so much of late, and I have so many men employed, that I cannot attend to all the duties of this office myself, and, if you think well of coming in here to assist me, I'l pay you a decent salary--something you can live on. Now, what do you say?" No use in us saying what James said. He thanked his kind employer heartily, and, after re- ceiving the keys of the office, retired with a joy- ous heart. Next morning found him seated in the office, dressed in his best clothes, busily en- gaged writing up and arranging the books, which want of time had compelled his employer to leave in a somewhat disordered way. He had every- thing in such good order that, when Mr. Lewis arrived and looked over his accounts, he smiled, and cast a look on James, as much as to say, ' I  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7150-00000104"/> :202      Annie Reilly. have not mistaken my man this time, either," and walked out, as he said to himself, "Thank good- ness! that's so much off my mind." Notwithstanding James differed so widely from the other workmen, and, as the saying is, "Made rio freedom with any of them," they were delight- ed, one and all, at his good luck, and began at- once to show him the respect he was now en- titled to, owing to the change in his position. James did not take advantage of his newly-ac- quired power, as a great many in such cases usu- ally do, to win favor with his employer at the cost of the men. He became more sociable with them than had been his wont, and, now that his advice would be more heeded, used it trying to dissuade such of them as he imagined were not' hopelessly lost to abandon drink and mend their lives in every way; and it was far more delightful to him than the change in his own fortune, when, after a weary conversation, he induced, our friend Dooley to come to church with him on Sunday.   CHAPTER' XXII. INTRODUCES A FASHONABLE IRISH-AMERICAN "ADY. NNIE and her friend hastened as fast as they could to the nearest line of cars, and were soon across the ferry and riding up on the other side to Patrick Sweeny's. Mr. Sweeny and his wife were at home, and, when Kitty told them what had happened at the "mansion," they were greatly amused, and praised Annie's good sense for leav- ing such a'place at once. ' ' Oh! yes," said A inie, " it were useless for me to think of living there any longer; they would frighten me to death. -But the worst of it is, I am now idle." "A very short time you need be," said Kitty. "You couldn't happen on a worse -placeanywhere than that." "Why, bless you, Annie," said Mr. Sweeny, "what a greedy little thing you are! If ever any- body made a. fortune in America, you will. The husband that gets you may take the world easy."    &#xD;<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC7150-00000105"/> 204      A nnie Reilly. All had a laugh at this, and after a few pleasant words all round Kitty went back to her place, and Annie into the little parlor to write a letter to her father and mother. Mr. Sweeny would not hear of her advertising again, but promised to find her a suitable situation himself. This made Annie very happy, and the time was passing along nicely, till a tall, pale, smirking young lady of about twenty-five bounced into the parlor to spend the remainder of the evening. She wore a gray dress, very wide in the skirts, and very long and tight-fitting in the body, with two closely-planted rows of bright buttons in front, like those on, a huzzar's jacket, a white hat drawn over her eyes, and carried in her hand an immense fan, which she continued to wave desperately. That she was not much of a favorite with the family was evident to Annie from the manner of her reception. Mrs. Sweeny, without rising from her seat, merely said, "Good-evening, Miss Talbot ;" and Sweeny did not seem to notice her at all. "Well! well! I do declare," said she, dropping into a chair, "the heat and closeness of this place take the breath from me. Whew! good- ness gracious me!" "'Tis very warm out this evening," said Mrs. Sweeny, raising the window a little, " and, instead   *Annie . Reilly.     205 of being so very hot here, I always find a nice draught in this room." Miss Talbot made no reply, but leaned her head  a little one side, and fanned away. Sweeny and his wife exchanged looks, and the former, with an expression of disgust on his face, rose and went outside on the stoop. "I  I'm pretty well used up," said the charming damsel at length languidly, and letting the fan drop. "I was up the road to-day, and what a charming prospect, I do declare!"  "Oh! you were out carriage-riding," said Mrs. Sweeny, with a slight smile. "( We call it going up the road, and not carriage- 'H1l riding any more," said Miss'Talbot emphatically. i- "That word ' carriage-riding '"-this with scorn- "is in everybody's mouth now; so, of course, we had to go to work and give it a name that we'd com-pre-hend amongst ourselves. You didn't go, as intended, to the country this summer, eh?" "Only for a day or two," said Mrs. Sweeny. :  : Miss Talbot, with a sudden start, picked up her ;.-: fan, and, wheeling herself. around, looked closely into Annie's face, while she hummed a lively air. The poor girl blushed deeply, and, rising, went to another part of the room, Miss Talbot's eyes in quick pursuit. "From Ireland, I'll bet a dollar, come," said she, turning her eyes on Mrs. Sweeny.  &#xD;<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC7150-00000106"/> 206      AXnnie Reilly. "Yes; the lady is just as much Irish as you are yourself," said that lady. "It should not require much penetration on your part to'tell that." "Me Irish!" said she, with a short nod of great. force. "I am no such a thing. Is it because father anhd mother was rose there that I am. Irish?" "Exactly; there could be no better reason," said Mrs. Sweeny., Miss Talbot stood up as if to depart, which would have been a great calamity just then; but after twisting her face a few times like a short- sighted man with a bad razor, she went to the window, and began beating a tune with her fingers on the glass. Annie and Miss Sweeny had a hard task-to restrain their laughter. "Please don't rap the' window that way," said Mrs. Sweeny, a little sharply,: "you will attract the attention of the people outside. See, there is a butcher on the far side thinks you're calling. him," "You wouldn't have received this visitation this evening at all," said the indignant lady, "only Mr. La Bunty is off to Chicago, and Mr. Delblether's niece has the cholera-morbus after all the mushmelons -she ate at Coney Island last Sunday. There wzus three doctors and two nurses up with her night and day since."   Annie Reilly.      207 Mrs. Sweeny expressed her great sorrow for the critical condition of the young lady, and asked how she had been so unfortunate as to imperil her life in such a way. "Oh! Mr: Frank Driggler was telling me all about it," said she, again sitting down and clasp- ing her hands. "I went up the road with him to-day, just because the other gentlemen were * engaged. Well, you know Mr. Delblether, and old Mrs. Delblether, and Miss Delblether went to Coney Island last Sunday. They went down on their knees to me to go ; but, stuff!"And she tossed her head. "When they got there, who does they meet but Mrs. Cyrus Xersus Smot and her daughter, that came home from the boarding- school only a few weeks ago. Well, Mrs. Smot, you know, thinks there's not the like of her daugh- ter in the world; so she thought she'd show off a little, and put on airs. They weren't two minutes -talking, till she began to boast of her daughter's -accomplishments, and how beautiful and healthy she was. Mrs. Delblether made up her mind to not let her have it all her own way; so she says, says Mrs. Delblether, ' My granddaughter here knows more than could be pounded into your daughter's head in forty thousand years. Talk of your daughter's -beauty, and her shoul- ders not the breadth of my hand. Talk of her  &#xD;<pb n="208-209" xml:id="VAC7150-00000107"/> 208      Annie. Reilly. health! Why my granddaughter wasn't a day sick in eleven years, when she had the shakes, and your daughter was home two weeks lying with you last fall. And speak of accomplishments: my granddaughter knows how to- eat like a Christian, and has the best appetite of any young lady in New York. I would put her for fifty dollars against yours, starved and thin as she is, coming from that hungry school.' ' I'll take your bet,' says Mrs. Smot, pulling out her purse. She has plenty-of stamps, no getting out of that. ' It's done,' says Mrs. Delblether, cover- ing the money in a gentleman's hand-a mutual friend. ' My dear Bella, an't you in tune for a good feed after so much sea air, and the credit of our family at stake?' says Mrs. Delblether. ' Rely on me, grandma,' says Bella, opening her stays. 'What's the thing going to be?' ' Mushmelons,' shouted Mrs. Smot. You know they lived in Georgia one time, and were used to melons. ' That's not square,' says Mrs. Delblether. ' Never mind, grandma, I'll go it,' says Bella. ' Let it be mushmelons.' "The mutual friend hailed a vender, and told him to drive round behind a sandbank. He did so. and the wagon-load was purchased, and the young ladies pitched in. Well, to make a long story short, Bella was eating away, nothing the worse,   Annie Reilly.       209 only her eyes rolling a little, when Miss Smot gave a terrible roar, and fell back in a faint in her mother's arms. They had the same number eaten at this time; but Bella never ceased- till i I   she finished three more. Her grandma begged her, with tears in her eyes, to make it five; but the brave girl didn't feel as if she could. .Miss iSmot was carried away by four men, in her mother's shawl, but Bella was able to walk, with the assistance of her uncle and grandmother, to the boat; and, when the excited crowd began to cheer, she begged to be left to herself, and walked ten yards without a hand to her. Coming home on the boat, she drank a quantity of apple-sauce, and, if it hadn't been for that, she'd have been on her feet in two days., But she took on terrible that night; a-yelling and a-twisting herself so that they thought she was gone, sure pop. She is not much better yet; but her grandma is so proud of her that she'll spare no cost to bring her round. And why should she? See how ad- mired Bella 'll be now in society." And Miss Talbot finished with a sigh, as if she wished she could do something to gain renown. Annie thought the story a great joke; but, on being told by Miss Sweeny it was every word true, she laughed till the tears rolled down her cheeks. Mrs. Sweeny was well used to such entertaining  &#xD;<pb n="210-211" xml:id="VAC7150-00000108"/> 2IO      Annie Reilly. accounts of high life from Miss Talbot, and made no remark on the thrilling contest; but,-after a pause, asked her when she intended fulfilling her promise to visit Europe. "Not this. season; 'tis too late now," she re- plied carelessly.         '  "Then next summer?" -said the other. "Oh! I rather guess I shall,' was, the reply. "And when T come to say good-by, 'tis not Miss Talbot you'll see, I reckon."?' "Oh! 'twill be Mrs. Delblether we'll have then,"  said Mrs. Sweeny, with a smile. "Yes," said she carelessly, "the thing is to come off during the holidays."' "I suppose, much as you dislike Ireland, you'll not omit paying it a visit," said Mrs. Sween,y. "I guess I'll make a call there. For my part, I don't care; but Mr. Delblether says we shall. He thinks 'twill be so very amusing. But I have my fears for him;, he's such a man to laugh that he may kill himself when he goes there." "Kitty is thinking of paying a visit to her mother next year.' said Annie, addressing Mrs. Sweeny. "Indeed, then," put in Miss Talbot, before the person spoken :to had time to answer, "Ill call on Kitty if we're in Ireland together, and see what them little villages with the noisy boys and   Annie Reilly.      2" girls look like. I'll bet they keep pretty mum while we're there." "Yes," said Annie, with an arch smile. "I dare say you'll surprise them somewhat. It's not very often they see such an extraordinary lady as you." "Never you mind," said the other, " if we don't make them stare! Are there any gentlemen or ladies, or is. there any society at all in Ireland?" she asked, after a pause. "A few," said Mrs. Sweeny. "Oh! then, I suppose they'll bother the life out of us so much with invitations that we won't know what to do." "I don't think you have much to dread in that way," said Annie. "I'll not put up with it; that's how I'll fix the thing," said she. "If I think any of them worth visiting, why, all right." A long pause followed, which was broken by Mr. Sweeny returning to the parlor, and express- ing his surprise at the lateness of the hour. The young lady, however, dr&amp;. not take the hint, but fiercely assailed him with questions on different public matters, not one of which she allowed him to answer; gave her own views and the opinions of numerous intellectual acquaintances of hers, stood up, went to the door, came back again, till  &#xD;<pb n="212-213" xml:id="VAC7150-00000109"/> CHAPTER XXIII. KITTY BRADY REVISITS THE OLD LAND, AND IS VISITED BY THE FASHONABLE IRISH- AMERICAN LADY. R. SWEENY procured Annie a situa- tion in a very respectable family, whose home was on the banks of the Hudson, where she lived contentedly till an event occurred, of which we shall speak further on, which greatly changed the course, of her life. Our story now moves on one year, and we find Kitty Brady standing on the quay, waiting to go aboard a ship which is about to sail for Queens- town. Annie, Mrs. Sweeny, her husband and daughter, and Francis Reilly are standing around her. Francis had arrived a few months before, and carried such an earnest request to Kitty to visit her mother in the old land that it put an end to her wavering on that point. Kitty is much affected at parting from her friends, and her tears are falling fast. They are talking of the great happiness before her, to visit again the scenes of her childhood, and once more hear the   &#xD;<pb n="214-215" xml:id="VAC7150-00000110"/> 2I4      Annie Reilly.  only voice that sustained her there. Her trunk, which has been taken aboard, is filled with pre- sents, neat and tasteful, sent by Annie and her brother to their parents at home. The moment for parting comes; all bid her an affectionate good-by, and pray a blessing on her journey. Kitty had sent a letter apprising her mother of the day she intended leaving New York. Mrs. Brady hastened to Farrell Reilly's, told them the joyful news, and insisted on their coming to the cabin the day her daughter was expected to arrive. Mrs. Reilly and her husband were greatly delighted at the prospect of speaking to one who had so lately seen their children, and promised the old woman they would be with her on that day. Mrs. Brady could not wait patiently till the arrival of the happy day. She walked along the road in the direction of the railway station, first by the broad road, and then by the narrow lane which ran across the hills, dreading, if she travelled one way only, Kitty might be coming by the other; climbed up with great toil, which she felt not, to the top of the steep hill which overhung the cabin, and looked along the river-bank in every direction. Then, after all this hardship, she would recollect Kitty had not time to reach   Annie Reilly.      215  any of- those places yet; so she would return to the cabin, and weep and pray till another morn- ing came. At length-and it seemed to her she had been watching for it a year-the day, about which there could be no mistake, arrived, and Farrell and his wife were early in the cabin-so early that the first rays of the rising sun were barely visible on the tops of the tallest trees. 'Already Mrs. Brady was standing outside the door waiting for them. "0 Farrell! I am afraid of my life we will be too late. Do you think we will, Mts. Reilly ?" said she, turning from one to the other. "It seems an age since daylight." "We shall be early enough, Nancy," said Far- rell, following his wife into the cabin. " The train from Cork will not arrive for two hours yet, and Mrs. Reilly is very tired, so I think we may rest a little." "Surely, poor dear, she is tired," said Nancy, hastily handing her the best chair in the cabin. " And now, Farrell, while you and her rest your- selves, I'll just run as far as the brae, and see' if there's any sight of her. The train may come early this morning." "I wish it may," said Farrell; "but there is little use in your expecting that. Better give  &#xD;<pb n="216-217" xml:id="VAC7150-00000111"/> Annie Reilly X yourself as little fatigue as you can; you will want all your strength when Kitty comes." "Oh! I feel as lively these days, Farrell," said she, "as I did thirty years ago. Two hours is such a terrible wait. No harm in me trying, any- way." "We'll go with you very soon, Nancy," said Mrs. Reilly. "We can walk along leisurely." Nancy insisted no further, but went out on the lane, and returned with word that the cattle were rising from their resting-places and beginning to feed, and that " Pat the Brock," the apple-man, had just passed by on his way to town. "And look," she added, lifting an old tin lid from a crevice in the wall, and letting in a tiny stream of sunlight, "the sun does not come in here till very late." Farrell and his wife could not dispute those convincing evidences of the lateness of the hour, and stood up to accompany her to the station. When they reached there, the depot looked the most deserted of any building they had passed. An odd, smoke-begrimed car stood on the track here and there, looking as if they had made up their minds to travel no more, and were very sorry for travelling so much. The doors were closed, and no one to be seen except a large, lazy-looking porter in his black   Annie Reilly.           217 corduroys, and smoky hair enough on his head for ten porters, walking slowly along, the echo of his-heavy footfall only adding to the loneliness of the situation.  Mrs. Brady and her friends sat down on a large wooden box at one end of the building, to wait. By-and-by the doors began slowly to open -so slow that they seemed in doubt whether to close again or not-and a few more porters ap- peared, ail differing so much in everything except corduroy that any one not in the secret would think they were born at least a thousand miles apart. Soon a guard showed himself in brass buttons and a yellow band around his cap, look- ing so very important, disdainful, and impolite that'passengers under his care must have looked on themselves as in a jail for the time being. A little later, and an occasional traveller wan- dered into the building; one now, then another, then three orfour together, till the place became lively with people. Commercial travellers, with immense light bags in their hands and short lead- pencils behind their ears, walked to and fro; large, fat, good-humored-looking farmers leaned against the pillars, and discussed the markets; keen-eyed, stylishly-clad gentlemen, some old, others young, and all carrying large umbrellas, bustled in and out of the crowds, not together, but separately, &#xD;<pb n="218-219" xml:id="VAC7150-00000112"/> 18      Annie Reilly. as if they were engaged to count the number of people around, and were determined, at all costs, to do so correctly. It seemed remarkable, the deference shown these gentlemen by every one present, especially the farmers, who gave each berth wide enough for a coach and four, and muttered as he passed, "Damn those attor- neys !" At length the ticket-office was opened, and all gathered around the little window, crushing, scrambling, and scolding; for the train which was to bear them away was moving into the depot. When about half the passengers had received tickets, the train began to move off again, and the uproar at the office became deafening. The nimble clerk, however, -supplied these latter in time to get aboard after an exciting race, and the building settled into another half hour's repose. As the time for the arrival of their train ap- proached, Farrell and his companions were in a fever of anxiety. Mrs. Brady asked every porter she saw at least ten times what the exact min- ute would be. They were standing together at the south end of the depot, looking -along the track, when a cloud of smoke rose over the low hill near by, and the station bell began to ring loudly. "Here it is at last !" exclaimed Farrell. "Oh! thank heaven,' said Nancy, clasping Mrs.   Annie Reilly.   219   Reilly by the hand in her joyous excitement. "Oh! God be praised that I have lived to see this day." The three stood, their eyes fixed on the long line of coaches gliding up.  The train soon stopped, and every window was filled with eager faces looking out on those on the platform, and the doors crowded with men, women, bundles, bags, and children hurrying down on the flags. Farrell and the two women ran wildly from win- dow to window, from door to door, eagerly scan- ning each female face. But the cars were empty, and the crowd beginning to disperse, and they had seen no sign of Kitty. Poor Nancy's heart sank, and a mist stood be- fore her and those around. Neither of her com- panions ventured to speak what they thought. "0 my child!" said the distracted woman faintly, " if she is not here-" " Hush a moment !" exclaimed Farrell. " There is a-young woman dressed in green with her back to us, standing by the trunk down there-" But before he could finish the sentence, the young lady turned and looked towards them, and with a cry of joy ran up, and mother and daugh- ter were folded in each other's arms.  Poor Nahcy was wild with delight. Her tears fell on the face, neck, and hands of her child. Again  &#xD;<pb n="220-221" xml:id="VAC7150-00000113"/> 220      A nnie Reilly. and again she kissed her frantically, and breathed blessings on her, till Mrs. Reilly said : *' Nancy, you must not think of keeping her all to yourself; let me kiss and welcome the darling girl." The old woman said, her face against her daughter's               ' ' Kitty, my loving child, Mrs. Reilly is here to meet you, too, and her husband. Every one must be glad to see you." The greeting between Mrs. Reilly and the girl was hardly less warm, and, after embracing Far- rell, and answering numerous questions about her- self and his children, the happy little party set out for the cabin. The number of callers on Kitty, every one of whom were delighted with her handsome appear- ance and nice manners, was immense.  Poor Nancy was almost wild with joy. The good, truthful account she gave of Francis and Annie made their parents very happy, and, for the first time during its existence, Nancy Brady's cabin was the scene of contentment and happiness. Time, which heretofore hung so heavily on Nancy's hands, swept past quickly now. Every day brought some new enjoyment; some old place of historic interest, about which Kitty had read in America, was to be visited; some far-off i   .      ..    .  '   Annie Reilly.      22I neighbor, whose friend or friends had sent mes- sages to those at home, were to be seen; and, as she always insisted on her mother accompanying her, Nancy saw more strange places and people, and learned more of Ireland's story the first month her daughter spent at home, than she had during her previous life. Invitations from old and new acquaintances were numerous, and even Father Fitzpatrick called one day and took both to his house to spend the evening; and, finding Kitty so well informed and so intelligent, many a chat they had together during the summer. Mrs. Reilly let no day pass without seeing her, and often they went down together by the river's bank, and sat talking, till Nancy, who would insist on staying behind to prepare a feast, would have to go in search of them. On one of these occasions, the old woman had just thrown her shawl about her shoulders to sally out in search of the " pair," as she called them, when, happening to look through the little window, she saw a very stylishy-dressed gentleman and lady standing outside, the former pointing with his cane towards the door, and the latter, with her hand pressed against her side, laughing heartily. This sudden sight alarmed the old woman some- what, and she hesitated a moment, in hopes they might pass on. But to her horror, after apparent-  &#xD;<pb n="222-223" xml:id="VAC7150-00000114"/> 222      AInnie Reilly. ly satisfying themselves by scrutinizing the cabin, both came over to the door, and the lady enquired, in a voice which sounded so high up in her nose that Nancy thought she must be suffering from a severe cold, if that was where Kitty Brady lived. "Oh! yes, yes; please sit down a moment," said the old woman, handing each a chair.' "I'll call her directly." The lady declined the proffered accommodation with -a wave of her hand, and the gentleman went over and looked into the little room, the door of which was open, and began to whistle softly. Nancy looked from one to the other in amaze- ment, not rightly knowing what to do. "Oh! hurry up, and tell her right away, will you?" said the lady, after she had swept the floor with her skirt a few times. Nancy hastened as fast as she could -to the river's bank, and told Kitty in such an excited manner that- two very odd-looking people were waiting in the house to see her that she hurried in as quick as she could, and left her mother and Mrs. Reilly to follow after.               .   CHAPTER XXIV. EXPERIENCES OF THE FASHONABLE LADY AND HER HUSBAND IN IRELAND.-ENTERTAINING THE GUESTS AT A HOTEL.-A LECTURE IN A FORGE, AND WHAT CAME OF IT. HE " odd-looking" pair who had caused Nancy so much alarm were a no less couple than Mr. Delblether and his wife; the once charming Miss Talbot. "The thing did come off during the holidays," and they were now on a pleasure trip to Europe. To say Kitty was delighted to see them might be venturing on an assertion not strictly true; but she gave them a kindly welcome, and offered the hospitalities of her mother's cottage, which was rejected by Mrs. Delblether, who declared, with a frown and shake of her head, that to swallow anything under such a low roof would surely choke her. Kitty thought of the dreadful misfortune this would entail on so many, and pressed her no further. The husband, however, drank a large glassful of pure usquebaugh, and, declaring that, he was something very low and mean if he didn't like it exceedingly, finished another. As Kitty or  &#xD;<pb n="224-225" xml:id="VAC7150-00000115"/> 224      Annie Reilly. her companions did not like to lead the conversa-- tion when two such distinguished people- were present, and as the distinguished people did not show much inclination to talk, a very awkward half-hour was spent, at the end of which Mrs. Delblether said: "Kitty, me and Mr. Delblether wishes to take a look around this location at the fowling and"shooting, and so on; so we've put up at that place you call a hotel in the village, and we want you to pay us a visit there." Kitty promised to do so, and the visitors walked away, each looking peculiarly and unaccountably sad. Now, as our restless thoughts can travel much quicker thari Kitty's feet, we will precede her, and see how her exalted friends are getting on in the village alone. They arrived at the hotel early in the evening, and spent the time till supper in their own apart- merits, planning'the measures they would adopt to let the quiet villagers know they were some- thing the like of which probably had never hon- a oredcthem with a visit before. Mrs. Delblether was' by far the better strate- gist. Her plans were numerous and well laid, while all her husband could-think of was for him to put a long cigar in his mouth, with his hat /              . '   Annie KeiZly.      225 greatly on one side, his wife to hang her gold watch around her neck,.and let it fall down'ex- posed to view on her breast. She derided his want of tact, and commanded his attention to listen to her. "Now, you see," she said, "it's all very good to stagger them in the hotel here; but something must be done outside, otherwise half the people may never hear of us at all. To do the thing square inside here you may rely on me, and when we are out together, too. But you know there are some places where you can do a good deal if you only have the pluck. Now, when,we were coming up-stairs, you remember me stopping be- hind for a little?"He did not forget it. "Well, there were two men talking in the room on the right, and laughing very heartily over something that had happened in the forge. One of them said, I heard the words plainly, and more than. twenty men standing around at the time.' Now, anywhere in such a small ranch as this, where -twenty men can be found together must be the chief place of resort, eh?"He held the same opinion. "So I want you to go there to-morrow evening, and just begin by comparing everything you have seen in Ireland with everything in America. Tell them they hain't nothin' here like New York. Tell them they're darn fools f-.  &#xD;<pb n="226-227" xml:id="VAC7150-00000116"/> 226      An nie Reilly. for living in such a country at all, and even go so far as to despise the forge and blacksmith, too." The gentleman was delighted, and declared he surely would have thought of this himself before morning; whereupon the lady said he would not, and went so far as to say she never knew him- to think of anything he should. Soon after, they descended to the dining-room. A number of jovial-looking men, some standing by the windows, others seated at the board, were in the room. Mrs. Delblether seated herself with a loud "Oh!" as if the act distressed her, sat up very erect, and, gathering her eyebrows into an ex- pression of keen scrutiny, looked from face to face, down one side of the table, then up the other. Her husband took his place by her side, and closed his eyes so as to leave only the pupil visible, and resting an arm on the table, threw the other over the back of his chair, and waited for his accomplished wife to commence. When she had satisfied herself looking at the live faces, she turned her attention to the painted ones on the wall, and, singling out a portrait of O'Connell which hung over the chimney-piece, asked, as she pointed her knife in that direction, and looked at a gentleman opposite, "Whose is that? Tell me, will you?" t6 J    Annie Reilly.      227 He hastily informed her, and she said, letting her head fall back, "Mr. Delblether, that's who the Irish in New York talk so much about. Well, only think; no nice paintings even to be seen in this 'ere-I don't 'zactly know what to call it." Tihe guests, who;'up to this had managed to preserve their decorum, all glanced at her, and a smile overspread every face. She kept silent for a moment, eating away rapidly, her face almost on the plate, then leaned over and whispered in her husband's ear, "Why don't you say something? You look as glum. as a pumpkin." "You're a-staggering them yourself. Go on, I am proud of you," whispered he in 'return. "Leave me toe to-morrow evening.' And she did go on, asking questions about this article and that; what the table was made of, how much it cost; how much difference in the price of the black-handled knives and the white ones; were dishes and salt-cellars sold on time, and, if so, how much discount was allowed for cash payment; and even went so far as to ask an old gentleman at the lower end of the table how long after he purchased his wig did the maker wait till he sent in his bill. On every reply to those questions, she commented at moderate length, and drew numerous parallels between Ire.  &#xD;<pb n="228-229" xml:id="VAC7150-00000117"/> 228      Annie Reilly. land and America, to the great disadvantage of the former. Soon the guests began to perceive they had found a treasure, and employed every means -to make the most of it. All heartily coincided with her remarks, and outwardly thanked Providence for sending such an enlightened angel to tell them of their failings, and point out to them so many remedies. Not one of them, except those whom pressing duty called away, left the hotel that night, and even those latter lingered till the last second, and looked back regretfully as they went from the room. Mrs. Delblether talked till after midnight. There was such a crowd at the breakfast-table the fol- lowing morning that the landlord, in his hurry and excitement, broke a pitcher over a slow waiter's head, and pushed another from the kitchen with such force that he fell on the tray he was carrying with a terrible noise, crushing its contents. One maid inflicted a severe wound on the palm of her hand with a carving-fork, and another fell headlong into the coal-cellar. That evening, Mr. Delblether, dressed in a long black - coat of very cheap material, tight-fitting, short, check pants, a soft, wide-brimmed hat, and a cigar in his mouth, sauntered up the street to the forge, to commence his grand attack on the attention   Annie Reilly.      229 of the villagers. The blacksmith, a big, hearty- looking fellow, with a laugh ringing as his anvil, kindly saluted him as he entered. A number of men and boys were in the forge at the time, sit- ting up on the hearth or standing about the floor, -amongst whom he noticed many of those he had seen at the hotel. He returned the smith's friendly nod with an- other of quiet patronage, and, closing one eye, took a deliberate -survey of those present-the walls,-the roof, and behind the bellows. During this time, he had not spoken a word, but hummed merrily, "Say, young fellar," said he at length, balancing himself on his cane, and looking at the blacksmith, "how do the farmers cultivate the sile in these 'ere diggins?" "They have a number of ways, sir," said the man addressed. "Everything is done by system, sir, in my country, and done co-rectly. We hain't no two ways of doing anything, we haven't," said he. "None but the right way?" said the smith, with a smile. "The right way or no way, sil," said the gen- tleman, shaking his watch-chain, "that's our motto." "I suppose you find things very different here  &#xD;<pb n="230-231" xml:id="VAC7150-00000118"/> 23       4 Annie Reily. from your own country," said a man, coming for. ward and resting his foot on the side of the trough. "Etarnally so," was the reply. "Why, hold on, me friend. -If I ever seed anything to come up to the difference between America and this little island, I am- Why, sir, in the first place, I could find you a squash-field in Jarsey bigger than your whole country. And, again, you have no leading questions that I'd bother with. Look at our tar-and-feather compromise question in the West; why, it's ahead of--of- everything," said he, unable to find a better ex- pression. "Then our rivers-what are ye talking about? Why, one on 'em would flow square round your country ten times. Thinkl of our mountains, and snakes, and muskiters; why, you have nothing here." And he moved his head from side to side in disgust. Those in the forge' gathered closely around, hardly giving him room to swing his coat-tails in, and the blacksmith rested on his sledge, and looked on entranced. Others outside, hearing by some means of what was going on, came crowding in, till the little'place was filled to over- flowing. The door was packed, and even the little window had its two or three rows of heads. Still they kept- coming; men in every variety of   Annie Reilly.      231 dress; women, some with shawls about their shoulders, others with children in their arms has- tily snatched from their cradles; boys with books in their hands, from which they had been study- ing to-morrow's lessons; and even little creatures not long out of their swaddling-clothes were met making. their way along the street, and, when questioned as to their destination, looked up and lisped, "The yantee," and ran on. Dogs, seeing they had the place to themselves, worried each other behind the houses, and pursued stray cats and pigs along the street. Philosophic old cocks who had lived all their lives in the village stretched their necks and tried to think; but, arriving at no satisfactory conclusion, fluttered across the wall into the, chapel-yard, and franti- cally called on their charge to follow them. Never was such uproar and confusion witnessed in the town before. Mr. Delblether was delighted. He could hear those in the rear of the crowd exclaiming, "Where is he? Why don't they put him up -on the hearth, and give us all a chance to see him?," A chance was offered him to " come out strong," and prob- ably to make himself famous. So letting his tongue and arms loose, he commenced a harangue on the disadvantages under which he claimed the village and, in fact, all Ireland labored; be- \'w  &#xD;<pb n="232-233" xml:id="VAC7150-00000119"/> 232      Annie Reidlly. sought his hearers to learn something from the example set them by New York, with its theatres, parks, savings-banks, and steamboats; told them, if he had their village in America, he would bore a canal to the ocean, and have all those institu- tions flourishing in it before three months. The audience 'fairly danced with joy. Since Bell's circus visited them, thirteen years before, they had not had such amusement. The worthy entertainer was asked numerous questions, to which he made prompt replies; asked himself several, and answered them as cleverly; skipped admirably from One topic to another; confounded names, dates, and facts delightfully; wras sarcastic at one. time, pathetic at another, and frequently very humorous. He spoke every word with such a genuine twang that not a few on the edge of the crowd cursed whoever was " dinging" the anvil. How long he might have continued it is hard to say, had he not been somewhat rudely silenced by a prolonged clanging noise outside, followed by a loud, mirthful cheer. He looked wildly at the blacksmith, and asked what the uproar meant. "That's the way," replied that gentleman with great politeness (for a blacksmith), "they have of honoring celebrated personages like your- a self."                      I  i   Annie Reilly.      233 "Oh! by -Jove," thought Mr. Delblether, "they are going to serenade me; but," he added aloud, " your music is very coarse." He turned to look around on his hearers before resuming his discourse, but found the greater part of them had gorie into the street, and what remained were huddled together at the lower end of the forge, like men seeking shelter from a shower.  Thoroughly surprised now, he was about to make some remark; but, before he could do so, the candle disappeared from its place, leav- ing the shop in total darkness, and a heavy thud sounded along the roof, which caused him to look up in terror and in time to have his eyes, nose, and mouth filled with dust. He ran to- wards the door, but a well-directed stream of water from the trough covered him from head to foot before he gained the street. Blind with dust and rage, he knew not what direction to take, but stood rubbing his blackened hands to his blacker face, till a motley crowd of boys, with old tin cans, broken kettles, scraps of iron, and, in short, everything convenient that could make a noise, formed a ring around him. At a signal from the leader, they struck up such a horrible, deafening r-r-r--rip that the recipi- ent of the honor fairly jumped from the ground. In vain he tried to make his voice heard; but the  &#xD;<pb n="234-235" xml:id="VAC7150-00000120"/> 234      Annie Reilly. more excited he became, the more his tormentors banged their instruments. At length they parted on one side to let him out, which, when he saw, he dashed from their midst down the street towards his hotel like a madman. They allowed him to gain a little on them, so as to give effect to the thing, and then started in pursuit with even greater uproar, fol- lowed by the dogs, which had by this time grown reckless, and boldly ran into the street, barking, furiously. Boys heretofore timid in their excite- ment wrenched old lids from others whom they dreaded up to that night. Grown-up lads threw down their. smaller companions, and dragged them: along the pavement till they surrendered whatever engine of noise they carried. Some, ,who could find Clothing else, tore up paving- stones, and, holding one in each hand, rapped them together as they ran. Mr. Delblether having reached the hotel, the serenaders gath- ered around the door, cheered, yelled, laughed, rapped their cans a few times, and then disap- peared as suddenly as they'came. Mrs. Del- blether screamed loud and regularly for ten minutes after her husband's arrival. He was blacker than any charcoal nigger she had ever seen and the dust filled his mouth so that he could not speak. At length, when his face re-    Annie Reilly.       235 sumed its natural color somewhat, which it did after blacking all the water in the room, and five , or six jugfuls carried up by a waiter, she recov- ered sufficiently to ask what had befallen him; and when he told her, she attributed the whole misfortune to his ow#n awkwardness, and "wa- gered," if she had been in his place, the story would be a different one. They left town a few days afterwards, and Mr. Lacy was the only inhabitant who regretted their ever coming there. For two months after their departure, he broke more rods on boys than he had in as many years before. They neglected their books, and took to drawing likenesses of Mr. Delblether as he appeared addressing the crowd in the forge on that eventful night, and as he looked flying down the street during the serenade. /      *            "  &#xD;<pb n="236-237" xml:id="VAC7150-00000121"/> CHAPTER XXV. ANNIE AND JAMES HAPPY. GAIN our tale moves on, this time to the end. A few years have passed by, and Annie yet lives with the good, kind family on the banks of the Hud- son. Francis is in good employment in New York City, Patrick Sweeny and his small family live in the same quiet happiness, and Kitty Brady is married to the young man who put such an abrupt end to the Scotchman's love for Annie. It is a bright, pleasant Sunday morning in April, with a gentle breeze waving the white cur- tains on the raised windows, that Kitty and her husband are standing together in the neat little room, both dressed for church. Mrs. Ryan, for that is Kitty's name now, has been to the win- dow half a dozen times, peeping into the street below. "I wonder what can be keeping her," she says at length. "I thought she'd have been here an hour ago." Mr. Ryan looks at his watch, and says: i "They have twenty minutes yet."   Annie Reilly.     237 "Oh! but think of the journey to Barclay Street -" She had not finished the sentence, when the door was pushed open, and Annie walked into the room.   , - "I thought you would never come, my Annie," said. Mrs. Ryan, kissing her fondly, "My eyes are tired watching for you." "Oh!" said Annie, giving her hand to Mr. Ryan, "I couldn't help it, Kitty. The train was delayed an hour this' morning." Notwithstanding her hurry a few minutes be- fore, Mrs. Ryan sat down, and began asking the girl numerous questions as to how she had spent the time since she saw her last, and compliment her on how well and handsome she looked, till her husband said, with a smile:  Ladies, I think you had better come on now. You will have time enough for the like of that during the evening." The three then hurried out and into a car, and in a short time reached Barclay Street, where they alighted, and entered St. Peter's Church just as High Mass commenced. The church was very crowded, but two gentlemen resigned their seats to Annie and Mrs. Ryan, one of whom moved up towards the altar, and the other knelt down by Ryan's side in the passage.  &#xD;<pb n="238-239" xml:id="VAC7150-00000122"/> 238      Annie Reilly. Had Annie's eyes been raised as the latter gen- tleman passed by her, she would have noticed the surprised look with which he regarded her. The music of the grand organ filled the build- ing, and mounted up heavenwards, carrying with it the homage and adoration of the kneeling mul- titude; and Annie bowed her head low in earnest prayer, and was soon lost to every thought of earth. The gentleman knelt at the end of her seat, and, when Ryan happened to raise his eyes in that direction, he could see him glance at the devout girl with a strange, wild look, then turn his face towards the altar, and pray fervently. Of this, however, Ryan took, no notice, till, during the/ Sermon, he could not help remarking the \i9 strange manner of the man, who seemed to be acting in a way which he himself could not control. His face was suffused with blushes. He knew the -people near by could not avoid noticing him, but still he looked at Annie with a restless gaze, his lips. moving as if to speak, and his feet rubbing the floor nervously. It seemed that, if she turned her face towards him, he would lose- his senses, and spring to her side at once. But Annie's eyes were cast down, and she was utterly unconscious of the anxious, agitated face watching, her. Was one of those gentle prayers breathed for the welfare of its owner-?   Annie Reilly.      239 We know Annie was not unmindful of the pro-' mise she made that evening long ago, with none but the moon and stars for her witness. At length, the ceremony over, the people be- gan to leave the church. The greater part of the congregation, however, had departed, and the altar-lights were extinguished when Annie and Mrs. Ryan rose to leave; the gentleman stood up from his knees at the same moment, and, if Annie felt a hand gently, very gently touch hers, she did not notice it, but went down the aisle with her two companions, followed by the stranger; they were about to descend the steps, when a voice behind her said, "Annie!" She turned around, but seeing it was a young gen- tleman whom she did not know that addressed her, and thinking he mistook her for some other person, turned away quickly, and had reached 'the sidewalk, when he came to her side, and, looking into her face, said mournfully  "Annie, don't you know me? I would have known you at the end of fifty years." She looked at him in surprise. A strange, un- explainable feeling came over her; tears started to her eyes, and her limbs grew weak, James O'Rourke came into her mind, probably because the thought of him was uppermost there. But, no; the richly-clad, wealthy-looking gentleman  &#xD;<pb n="240-241" xml:id="VAC7150-00000123"/> 240 .     Annze Reilly. by her side could not be he. Nonsense! Poor James, who ran away from her that night on the river's bank with worn, patched clothes, and barely sufficient to bring him to America in his pocket! "I do not know you, sir," she replied, in a low, broken voice, and tried to move on. But he caught her by the hand, and exclaimed, "Oh! yes, you do, Annie; don't say you- forget your own James." Poor Annie fell against his shoulder. "Oh! heavens, James, and this really is yourself," she murmured through her tears. He drew her closer to his heart, and said, "Ohl! yes, yes, Annie, my love, it is I at last." "O James! how I have -watched and prayed for this meeting these long years!" sobbed the girl- ' Not more earnestly, at least, than I have, Annie. The. thought of you, my dearest, has not left my mind an hour, day or night, since that misty evening. It surely was the good God, -Who has watched over us both during those weary years, sent me here to-day. I knew your sweet face the- moment I saw you, in church, and it nearly drove me wild that I could not make my- self known on the -spot." "Ah! little I thought," -said Annie, '" when my    Annie Reilly.      241 mind was so full of you leaving the chapel-for I can never look on a crowd of people but some one amongst them reminds me of you-that at that moment you were so near. "Now, Annie," said he, " all our misery and anxiety are melted away, and we shall not run the risk of their returning again byparting any more. Mr. Ryan and his wife being introduced, James was greatly delighted to see the latter, and learn how well she had done. "I will not ask you, Annie, how you have got through this time; it is sufficient for me to see you are alive and well. Oh! what dreadful misgivings I had when every effort to find you failed! One time I thought my dear Annie might have died on the voyage; and again, that, lone and friendless in America, she broke her little heart." Mr. Ryan invited him to accompany them to his house for the evening. James readily agreed, and, hastily telling a fellow-guest at a hotel near by, who had- accompanied him to church, that he would be absent for the evening, hailed a car- riage, and they were soon the little, airy room, with Mrs. Ryan bustling here and there prepar- ing dinner. What a change had come over Annie's life since she left that little room in the morning! Then  &#xD;<pb n="242-243" xml:id="VAC7150-00000124"/> 242      Ann ie Reilly. she was not very unhappy, but the painful sense of something wanting, which distressed her so often during those years, was now banished Now her heart was full, overflowing with joy, and the tears which the "little lion " could keep back in the presence of misfortune and grief fell freely now that she was supremely happy. James had been a good, religious man she could tell during his long absence from her sight. No crime or vice had set their mark on his counte- nance. It was as bright, genial, and intellectual as when she gazed-on it unawares as he played or sang for her on the green hill-top. His up- right life was receiving its reward even here. He was on the high-road to fortune, if he had not already reached its golden gates. His employer, in return for his industry and ability, had made him a partner with himself. And what shall we say of his happiness now? All the fears that embittered his life so long at an end; -the dream of years fulfilled; Annie, whose shadow he traced in the twilight, whose smile the moonbeams re- flected, was now by his side, more beautiful than his imagination had ever painted her, never to leave him again.  Yes, Annie and James were very, very happy that Sunday evening in Kitty's little parlor. By-and-by Francis called to see his sister, and   Annie Reilly.      243 the meeting between the two schoolmates was very cordial. Mr. Sweeny and his wife and daughter dropped in during the evening, and every one felt in such excellent spirits that a happier little party never were together. Mr. Sweeny had a joke on every one. Even-Annie came in for a share of his humor. He told James of her frightened look the day she ran away from the "mansion," and how distressed she felt at the thought of being idle. James laughed heartily at this, and Annie blushed very red, but soon re- covered sufficiently to detail, in a very arch way, too, the annoyances she had experienced from the- Scotchman, and the ill-luck that cavalier met with at the hands of Larry Ryan. This amused James beyond measure, and he requested Annie-just as if she were going to please him!--to show how she looked and frowned when the Scotchman offered her his snuff-box. Thus time passed till midnight, when O'Rourke, who told- Annie to be watching for him at an early hour in the morning, went down to his hotel, and the little party broke up. If we were the most truthful historian in the, world, we would not risk our reputation by as- serting that James or Annie slept; a wink till morning. -The former was waiting, accompanied by the gentleman whom he had spoken to outside-  &#xD;<pb n="244-245" xml:id="VAC7150-00000125"/> 244      Annte Reilly. the church, when Mr. Ryan opened the door, and Annie was more than two-no, we will not tell it on her now--Annie was already dressed, and when Francis came, and all -the others who had been there the previous night, there was a-neat little wedding-party after all. Little Annie! a man a thousand degrees less noble than James O'Rourke might have gone wild with Joy at leading you off to be his bride. You blush so much that your blue eyes sparkle the more. You make so many mistakes, and you- are so forgetful this morning, that it is bewitch- ing to see your little puzzled look. -In short, go on, Annie; everything you do this morning makes you look the prettier. Miss Sweeny is a very handsome bridesmaid, but is greatly afraid of the portly groomsman, who thinks James O'Rourke one of .the luckiest men in America. The party went to the church early in the day, and, the important ceremony being performed, the happy bride and groom left the city that evening for a short tour through the States. When they returned, James purchased a house in a beautiful part of New York City, from which himself and Mrs. O'Rourke, and quite a number of little O'Rourkes, may be seen driving to the Central Park every Sunday even- ing.       . --lng.   Annie Reilly.      245 And now we will turn from our happy hero and heroine, and take leave of those other valuable people who have borne us company through our story. John G. Cary being the most illustrious, of course we must greet him first. He yet con- tinues to thrive in his old path, and his bitterest enemy could not wish him worse; for there is an uplifted Hand sustained by Mercy, but which Justice one day compels to fall heavily on such as he. Farrell Reilly and his wife have long since left the castle cottage, and are now living contentedly with Miles O'Rourke, in a neat little house with ' ivy-covered walls, within view of the beautiful bay of Queenstown. Mr. Lacy teaches school yet, but has grown somewhat deaf, which renders him so cross that he is the terror of all the boys in the neighbor- hood. His evening walks are less frequent now, and always terminate at Nancy Brady's cabin. Nancy, who, to use her own words, " wants for nothing," is always very glad to see him, because their chat is all about their old neighbors whom both loved so well. Miss Sweeny is now Mrs. Somebody, the mistress of a handsome rural homestead. Her father and mother still- live in the little white and green dwelling, happy and contented.   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
