<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7078">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Professor Julius Caesar Hannibal's Scientific Discourses </title>
            <author>Hannibal, Julius Caesar, (1822-1857)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7078</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1544</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Professor Julius Caesar Hannibal's scientific discourses</title>
                  <author>Hannibal, Julius Caesar, (1822-1857)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>128 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Stringer and Townsend</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1852">1852</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-02">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Professor Julius Caesar Hannibal's scientific discourses</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7078-00000001"/>   PROFESSOR JULIUS CJSAR HANNIBAL'S  SCIENTIFIC   DISCOURSES, RIGUINALLY PUBLISHED IN THE NEW-YORK PICAYUNE.  STRINGER AND TOWNSEND, 222 BROADWAY. 1852.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7078-00000002"/> Entered according to an Act of Congress, in the year 1852, BY STRINGER AND TOWNSEND, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the Southern District of New York.   MR. JULIUS CESAR HANNIBAL'S SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES. No.. I. FELLER CITIZANS OF NEW YORK: I hab come from de cantfinds ob de east, de sity ob modern N-a- thens, as it am usealy kalled, to gib a corse ob lectures on sience gineraly an events promiscuously, as dey from time to time occur. lDe letter ob invite I receibed from de komitee from dis moon litened city, was as full ob flattery as a gemman ob my great desernmerft, edication, definement, and research could wish. I 'greed to deliber my fust discourse dis ebening, but de fattig ob trablin in de kars hab jolted all de ideas out ob me, notwistandin' de kornductors was bery sibil to me, an mity perlite to 'Sister Bartole- mew, who trabeled under my 'tection all de way. Dey gib us fuss rate kar, an on de teamboat dey gib us fuss rate bed-sep'rate, ob korse. What you all snikerin 'bout?-d'ont you noe dat to laff rite out in meetin am wulgar? but I spose you don't noe no better. It atm all owin to de brougtens up ob de chile. You got nobody dat noes notin to tell you notin. You tink dat you got a feller hear among you dat noes somefin, an dat am dat Professor Pompey Godolphus Squash, Esq., wat lectures in de milintary and naval argus. 'd like to noe wat he am perfesser ob? It kant bo nateral histry, hydolico- lology, or kimistry. It must be broomstickerics, or some such out- landish stuff. He is de most ignumerant kullered man dat eber set liisself up to splanify de fungus mental principals ob sience in all its' contending glory. Dis feller hab bin goin it for some time back, wid a perfect rush, habin all the town to hisself; but I'll lite on him, like   &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7078-00000003"/> 4       MR. JULIUS CASAR HANNIBAL S my namesake did on dat Pompey wat libed at de same ancient date, an lay him out flat. You see I kome out flat foot and take the 'spon- sibility. I don't want none of my kongregashidn to swashiate wid none ob his kongregashion, for dey must be too low to mix wid, eben at a funeral. You all look sprised to hear a man say jus wat he tink; but I'll show you in two minits dat dis stilish perfessor nose noting 'bout tings in natur. His lass lekture was on de bull-frog, an he 'xclaims, wid all de elumquence dat he kan komand, "' Dat no fool-osopheT hab discibered anyting ob de social existence ob de frog." Now, did you eber hear de like in all your life? I kin prove by de alminick, as fur back as 1849, dat dese bery frogs not only) lib in de 'joyment ob sibilizashun, but hab a great taste for mil- intary skill an ticktacks; for de alminick bez- "' A bull-frog, dressed in soger clothes, Went into a field to drill some crows." Now, if my sertions am not correct, do you tink dat de crows when dey form de " crow guard" to go on target 'scursions would hab gaged Brigadig General Bullfrog to drill dem in full uniform, if he had not been oil fat, as we say in French, in de soger business? No, dey would not. I could tell you de history ob de frog from de time ob de unforti- nate occurrence ob his undertakin to watch de hoe cake dat de snake baked to de time he chased de green Irishman over de Jersey marsh- es, crying "Paddy too, Paddy too," dat would make de learned , Pompey stretch him long ears to hear, but I reserbe my fier for anuder charge; an if you choose to settle me ober dis congrega- shion, and gib me nuff to keep de sole ob my boot and de crown ob hat togedder, I'll stay an swamp all opposition. I kin bring creden- tials from de ancient order of free exceptionable stone masons, an from Fred Douglass, Dan Garrison, an de children ob de Abbey, Kelly. You'll find me as sassy as de reb Sixth ward butcher, if not quite as penimtratin into odder people's buzness. Wid dese konso- lin remarks, I will dismiss you as soon as de collecshun am takin up. Suppress your applause, if you please. I   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.         f me-                No. II. BLUBED SISTER AND BRUDDERS: You will find de words o' my text in de lass claws ob de ninety- furst chapter ob de Pilgrim's Progress, whar it says- An' Simon said unto Peter, Let not thy conscience be made ob injin rubber, lest it struch thv sole into dat lake which bums wid tier an' brimstone, kian pepper an' as- sefedity. You must not spose, in de fust place, dat de Simon an' Peter 'luded to in de text was de Simon an' Peter wat libed in de . time when Jerusa-laem -was a little willage, an' when de possle Noah wore swaddlin clothes, kase it wasn't he at all. It was Simon Smock talkin' to he son Peter, when he lebe he fadder's man- shun, in Tater-pelin alley, one mornin' on a carryin' in wood speck-, 'ilation: Now Pete was a bad feller, an' would lie, and take tings 'casionally wich didn't 'long to him, an' de same 'wice may 'ply to you all, derefor I warn you get de tex by hart.  Dere am a grate many men in dis comunity dat hab injin rubber consciences, an de most prominent ob de class, am considered de lawyer-next de showman, and den de doctorman. De'lawyer's conscience 'Will 'low him to struch it furder den de rest, an' some ob dem hab nearly broke in too by continual struching. One ob dese days, snap it will go, and den good by Mr. Lawyerman, 'way he go to de lake dat burn wid all dem 'grediances 'splaned in de text. Dis lake, my fritened hearers, must be a mighty big one to hold all de lawyers, if nobody else in de world but lawyers go dere, kase dere am seberal lawyers to ebery inhabitant troughout de State. Whar dis lake am sitewated am a puzzler to me an9 all succeeding stroni" mers dat hab libed afore my time. But I find, by wat I cap glean, arter burnin' seberal quantities ob midnight oil in deep an laborus re- sarch, dat it mist be nie de gulph whar de walcanoes montanes am, else whar de debel do de walcanoes get up sich a fire from? Why, de cat-a-kize sez dat de 'rumptions ob Mont Wociferous can be heard fur seberal days, fur several miles off, previus before de fire fly, an'  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7078-00000004"/> 6       MR.' JULIUS C4ESAR HANNIBAL'S previously arterwards. Now do you wish to noe, you poor trembling sinners, wat noise dat am dats heard seeding from the mount? Well, I'll tell yer. It am de grones, de lamontashuns, and de smashing ob teeth ob de wicked .peoples who had let dere conscien- ces struch like injin rubber. 'Dis lake, my frends, am sebrel hundred miles in sarcumference, an' 'bout half dat distance round de edges. It am a hundred miles perpendiclarly, measured, an' no bottom hab been found to it yet, dat we nose on. De Rochester knockin' spirits didn't come from dis place, else we find out all 'bout it. Dere was some wicked sailors got so nie to de top ob de mountain where de 'ruption comes from once, dat next day dey found denseffs broke out wid a 'ruption all ober dere bodies, which de dockter struched him conscience 'fishently to pronounce de measels, and he condend de whole proceedings as' bein' rash. Dis drefull place am for bad colored man, as well as bad wite man, an' no matter how much you 'spize de moon-truck tribe on dis eart, you got to mix up wid dem in dat warm climate, an' no doubt many in dis extremely southern climate will be found to hab northern- principles. An' ole Simon noein dis fact, he spake out to de boy Pete to. warn him from de greezey road ob sin, and pint him out de rite paff to kingdom cuam. An' now, let me tell you dat a man who possesses an injin rubber conscience, and libs only to skin him brudder out ob him eye teeth,- can heber be happy in dis world nor in enny oder country; his sinful follies will fall on him own head, like a slege hammer on a carpet tack, and sooner or later he g t smashed, like rotten egg in egg nog time. De more you tuist and turn dis face, de bigger it git, gis like snow-ball. I see by Prof. Pompey Godolphus Squash, Esq.'s last lecture in de Military and Naval Argus, dat his professorship don't like my 'marks 'bout him in my last discourse. Well, I can't help it. When I see ignumrance in de world I must 'spose it. De large section ob my life dat I pass in college would be trown away, if I leave sich imperts as him ride ruff shod-ober me. He call me a rush lite. I'll let him see dat I'll lite on him wid all de fulsomeness of a camphene lamp. He's got no finish to him edication. He neber trabeled, 'sept it was on Long Iland, 'mong de sand clams. I noe him, like A, B, C-book. He mudder u'sed to take in scrubbin', an' he fadder was a   ecl^.rrc accas h.\ I SaSOIENTIFIO DISCOURSES.  barber's clark assistant in Water street. Oh, he sprung from low 'society, and all who go to hear him leckture, ob corse, will be 'sid. ered de same low likewise. Derefore, I warn you to hab notin to do wid him. While Brudder 'Rastus Putts pass round de hat, de congregashun will please sing de useal Ducksholiday to de same good ole tune. No. III. BLUBED SINNERS: De words ob my text on dis 'portant 'casion you can'nt find in eny ob de books dat hab bin printed, nor in eny ob de noose papers, kose I neber spake from dem afore, but neber de less dey am giss as good as do dey had been sounded from one end ob de world to de odder, trough de tellugraff or Bialam's trumpet. De words am-- "G O TO HEBBEN YOUR OWN RODE." I noe, my 'spected hearers, dat all de different 'nominations will be down on me    for telling you dis, kase dere am none dat will 'low you dat pribalige; dey all tell you dat if you don't belibe jis as dey do, and come into de 'tablished church, you-am lost obberboard in de big gulf ob sin; all de churches am 'tablished churches, and dey all tink de rode dey hab picked out through de miserable thickets ob truble, wexations, and odder grevences ob dis life, am de rite one, and de odders am all rong. Bishep Hughes says dat his creed am de only one dat will popelate hebbin, and de prisbeterians, on hearin dis 'sertion, held a mectin right away at de Tubernicle, an' conta- dicted de hole ting, told some good nany-gotes 'bout ole Giles Crog- gins' hoss and kart, and 'spirsed satified dey wor on de rite rode. De Metodist, de 'piscopalions, de Baptist, de 'Tairrians an 'Worsilest, all tink dey see de golden gates ob hebbin rite afore dem, and feel  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7078-00000005"/> $8 -MR. JULIUS CoSAR HANNIBAL'  sure ob being 'wited in to take a seet as soon as nock at de dore. Dey am gis like a lot of skoolboys playing base, dey all see hunk, but all take a different paff, in order to git in fust. Now, my ungrateful frens, I don't want to say dat eny ob dese 'nominations am rong, but I am goin to take my own rode, and cut cross lots. I am goin to do unto all I meet de same as I'd wish dem to do unto me-treat dem kindly-relieve all de sufferin I kin along de paff, and when I reach de golden gate, I shall strip myself ob all de worldly tings, and 'pear wid de necked truff for my breast plate, and I tink by ilen myself --all ober wid de ointment 'posed ob lub, charity, and faith, dat I will slip while St. Peter am 'zaminin de credentials of Brudder Beecher and Brudder Hughes. If I kin git a chance so say a sly word to St. Peter, I'll ask him if charity am one ob de principal foundations of Christianity? an if he say yes, which I tink he will, den I'll tell -him dat Brudder Beecher show no charity toward de actor people, an I'll take his lectur on de 'bolishin ob theatres in my pocket, and show it to him, wherein he see dat Brudder Beecher sends. all de actors to. hell wedder or no; den St. Peter will say, "dat don't look christin like, but den Brudder Beecher got much charity and lub for de negro race, of which you, as a member, should feel tankful and prowd. It shows 'elusively dat he lubs darkey more dan actor." Yes, I'll 'mark, dats a fac, he does tink colored man better dan actor man, kase de colored man don't interfere wid he bread and butter; but I don't so long as de actor man behaves hisself. My lubed Sisters and Brudders, you can all git to hebbin if you like, and 'woid de big lake dat I spoke 'bout lass week. To do dis, you mus go true de world wid a dare conshuns, kick hipocracy to de ole debil, where it belongs, rong nobody, help one anodder along in de trials ob life; keep out ob debt and all de low rum shops; stop playin bluff; don't steal anyting, not eben a chicken; do as near rite as you noe how, and try to learn to do all de good your limited sphere of life will 'low, and you hab as good a sight for a front seat in hebbin as de loudest brawler among de whole tribes ob mankind; you, ob course, hab got to do your duty jis as well as de rich, influ- enshul man hab got to do his'n, an' one ob your duties am to put all do money, you know, in de plate, when Brudder Gustus Lemonskins hans it round. I wish to state afore closin' the shop, dat de Hannibal G s, de   SClENTIFIC ISCOTSRES.         9 colored company gh sodiers ob dis city, dat paraded todder day, was raised in honor ob myself, and named arter me, for de great 'spect dey hab for 'spected laborer. I recebed invite to be judge on lass target 'scursion, and I beliebe Brudder Beecher was honored de same likewise. Dere will be open house in de seller New Years, and sister Johnson will make de ele chowder on dis 'ticlar 'casion, chowder ready from 8 '( M, A.," till dark, an little arter, an I trust you will all joy yonrselfs and keep sober. Santa Klaus visited seb- rel ob de early risin' gineration ob dis congregation, and left peanuts, baloney sassage, and odder good tings. Ante Cuff hung up her 'tockin, but one of de board ob health happened to "smell a rat," ordered it down, else ders no 'noin what mite hab bin inmit. Pompey Dolphin Squash dont hab a word to say in lass week's Military Ar- gus; I guess I use him up. No. IV. DEAR SISTERS AND BRTDoERN: You will find de words of my text for dis ebenin' in de 'gography written by an .ole gouty gemman, named Peter Parley, de tex reads p dus, "Dis World is round, and, like a ball, -Seems swinging in de air?* Now, my ignorant deciples, you must know dat dere am seberil kinds of worlds; dere's de theatrical world, whare de theatres fust come from; den dere's de literary world, whare all de literary come from; den dere's de world ob fashion, whar all de "bong tong" lib; den dere's de world ob sciance, ob which world I claim to be a na- tive. But none ob dese worlds am de world ment in de tex; de world ment dere am dis sirculambula busitarianwrorld, on which we am at dig minute restin' our enlarged undel-tathdins. But how de *  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7078-00000006"/> 10       MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S  f foolosefers ob old find out dat it am round am a puzler to me. De fust man who said dis world to be round was a schoolmaster dat libed prebiously just arter de flood, by de name ob So-crates, and de peeple all laffed at him, an' ole King Cruso, who rained at de time, seein' dat he node so much pholosphy, cotched him one nite while he was on a coon hunt, and got him into de Tombs, and pizened him wid mixture of padlock bark, and Mr. So-crates drink him down jis like cider spirits, smacked his lips, pulled up his shirt collar, an' laid himself down an' died. He was a 'stonishing perssin, 'cordin to Hoil's 'counts ob him. He libed in a sugar hogshead, and led a sweet existence. De nex man dat 'serted de fac was de ole rheu-' matic genius whose poetry serbes your 'litened laborer wid a tex dis ebenin. De fac ob de world being rouad, like a big pumkin, seems to strike your understandings in a 'circular way, and make all you eyes look big as sassers. I'll e'splain de holl ting to you so you will know hencearter all 'bout it, jis as well as odder peeple. You must noe, in de fust place, dat dis world 'am bounded north by de Pasific Ocain, as fur as longitude North Pole, an' on de east by de Gipsian Piramids, south by de Witneys Railroad' depot, and west by de Rocky Mountains. Dere am a South Pole, as well as a North Pole. De South Pole am made ob a mity big red hot crow-bar, big- ger den 300"Liberty Poles, an' on de top of it de world rests one end ob itself on its axel-trees. De odder end rests on de North Pole, which, 'cordin to Aaron, de younger, am made of icebergs. De odder end ob de big axle-tree dat runs true de middle ob de globe rests on de top ob dis pole, an dat's wat bring new-year's day in de cold season, and you see what keeps de world in proper equolibriam trimmins, and perwents it from upsettin' easterly or westerly, am de mighty Gipsian Pyramids on de one hand, an' de spontaneous Rocky Mountains on de odder. Dis I found out myself! Sometimes dese dsle-trees want greasing, to make it slip round easy, an' how dey go to work to do it remains one ob, de "Misteries of Adolphin." I found out de kind ob grease dat dey use for de purpose. It am a 'culiar kind of soap, called "dil toid" soap, which was discovered in -de rain ob Queen Isabel, by one ob Isabel's most darling subjects, who was a professor ob kimakle apparatus, ob de Medical College. Dat was afore de Battle of Yorktown, and long afore de Cademy ob Mtedison was founded, else the doctor mans find out all de 'greedis,   SOCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.       1'1 ant all make permiscuous use ob de same. I tink dat de arthquakes dat we read so much 'bout in de papers, am caused by de takin' down ob one or odder ob de axel-trees, when dey go to grease de top ob de pole. An' one ob dese days, my stingy hearers, de North or South Pole will give way, an' bust up all creation. De wolca- noes will fall on de icebergs an' melt dem all up into water, which will oberflow dis York, and you will be swamped alive! In sich a case ob 'mergency, I would 'wise you all to rush for de ferry boat, an' git onl Brooklyn Hights, as soon as de will ob Providenc4 and power ob steam will carry you; dar you will find de wicked cease from grumblin, and de lazy am at rest. Dis watery pictur dat I draw afore your distorted wisages may be 'sidered out ob place in dis season ob brandy toddy, gin slings, whiskey punches, hot stuff, an' Jersey lightnin'; but noein' you all got pretty well corned on new-years, I thought a more refreshing subject could not be touched 'pon on dis 'portant 'casion. I myself got a little dizzy in de head an' sick at de stomack, after makin' 437 calls 'mong my flock, which may in a small (horn) measure 'polagise for my disinterestin' discorse dis ebenin. Noin dat, so soon arter de holidays, it would be useless&amp; I fourbear passing round de -hat on dis 'casion    -  No. V. "ADIES AND GIMMEN: My discourses dis ebenin will be drawn from the annals of sci- ance, according to Gunter, and de sciance I 'tend to lite on your una derstandings wid, will be de sciance ob NOSEOLOGY  Noseology, my frens, had a good deal to do wid tings ob .is life for by it you can tell to wat race eveiy man you meet in deo tei b'longs.  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7078-00000007"/> 12      EMR. JULIUS CASAR HANNIABALS Noseology, ob course, means nose ob de face ob wite man, red man, black man, half black man, and monkey. Dere am sebril classes ob noses, which was classed in King Crusoe's time, under de heads of wegatable noses, Hook noses, Roman noses, Pug noses, Grecian noses, and flat and Poke noses, and odder noses dat I nose not ob. De wegatable nose am wulgerly called turnup noses. Dese kind am bery prebilent wid young misses when dey git a new bou. If dey happen to meet dere old bou in de street, anedder we- gatabie nose am de redish; dese am generally found on the faces ob ole bachelors who had patronized de dimajog frequently offen. Some time dese redish noses wegetate and cumulate, one on top. ob de od- der, till dey am piled up like a heap of pabin stones on a load ob red sand, and dis, my ignorant frens, am what Spokeshake means by de tex, On horror's head horrid noses 'cumulate. De redish nose am often called de Roman nose, de hook nose is most frequently met in Chatham street, 'mong de Jews, and wo be to de customer who gets hooked under dere nose. H'es sure to be sold someting better ash new, and sheep as dirt. De hook nose is some 'mong de yankees up East. Joseph Miller, Esq., an elderly gemmon, node one wunbt, dat had sich a big one dat when he went to pick cherries, he used to hang by de limb wid it, and pick wid boff hands: dey made him President ob de hook and ledder company. De Roman nose seems to be a mistery 'mong all de foolosefers, and Mr. Milton, or some odder fur seein' chaps, said dat No one nose What a Roman nose. Derefore I pass on dem kind ob noses, and splain de pug nose. Dis nose seems to be permiscusly sent by human natur to all babies, who seem proud ob dem from the time it am no bigger den a piece ob putty wid two holes in it, till it swell to de size ob de hickory nut. Natur seems, in gibin de finishin touch to babies, to hab hit dem on de end ob de nose and turned it up so it would not be in dar way in gitting dere sebril meals a day from de mudder: dese little noses am none as Greesian, as de child grow up 'specially on cold mornins.   SCIEOTIfIC DISCOURSES.        13 De next nose under 'sideration am de poke nose, dese am de wust noses of all. Dey am ginerally long and pinety, and found 'mong old maids, slip shod married wimming, editors, and now and den it am found 'mong de preecher mans, 'specially in Brooklyn, and on board ob steamboats ginerly. My dear deluded lam's, beware ob de pope nose. You noe dem in a minit by dere sneakingly, downwardly, pintingly 'pearance. If you don't look out for dem, you'll wish you better had, kose day'll find out all your business. Noe, how many sasingers you eat for dinner! Whar you git your close! How much you git for white- washing a day! and sich things, an' den go glab it on de corner an' in de cellar. De flat nose am great mark ob 'stinction 'mong de colored folks, if dey am not too flat. Now, dere's young Sister Cole hab got nose so flat dat she hab to put tar on her finger to make dem stick long enuff to blow it. But you may tink I'm blowin' it. Not de nose, but de fact ob her habin' sich nose, but I only mention it in pint ob 'lustration. De next human being dat hab got flat nose am de monkey. An' although dere am not a race ob men on dis circufering earth dat I so much dispise for dere lazy an' cunnin'perpensitys, still I don't wish to 'radicate no honor from eny section ob de great family ob hu- man natur. Brudder Cate Puggs, who mistook de orango-tang in de Museum for his grandmother, and gib her a Christmas present, has 'plied to me to sew Mr. Barnum in de Sperm City Cort, to recobber de half pound ob broken sandy, big orange and stick ob likerish which she took from him widout eben saying tanky sir. I recline to hab notin' to do wid it, 'case he ought to noe better. Brudder Klem, pass roun' de hat, an' look out for tin sixpances. . p  rn 4     , k  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7078-00000008"/> I         ca       . $ 4       MR. JULIUS CAESAR?ANIfISAL S No. VI. [ARDENED SINNERS: My discourse dis ebenin' will introduce to you one ob yer oldest frens, one who you hab swasheated wid at all times of nite, 'specially dose here dat bord in de seller, an' a chap wat is looked 'pon as de biggest tief in de world, an' derefor are kicked out ob all good 'siety. De chap I 'tend to spoke 'bout you will find marked down in de charts ob sience in de Museum as DE RAT. My dewoted Sams, de rat you all noe to well to need a 'scription of from me at dis 'ticlar time. Burl muss 'splanify to you dat dere am seberil kinds ob rats. De ole rat an' de young rat, de black rat an' de gray rat, de long tale rat an' stump tale rat, de big long rat, an' fat chunky rat, de long hair rat an' de no hair at all on him body rat. De rat, my stingy hearers, am a furiner in dis climate, dey origin- ally originated in Rusha about de time de treety 'twene King Furo- neux an Kount Blubberlipee, de uproarer ob Africa, was farst'rati- fled; in dese days dey were 'solutely found in de ole King's palace, eye in him very bed-chamber, smellin' round whar dey hab no bisness to. Dis made de ole King 'pacified, an' he ordered dem to be turned out. Dis, ob corse, led to bludshed, an' a rebolution was de consequence, in which many suffered deff; ob corse de fite was all on one side, like de handel ob a jug, an' de rats suffered some. Wat dere was leff arter de conquest held a rat-ical meetin' an' 'solved to immigrate to dis land ob liberte, whar dey 'sposed dey coul steel as much ob cheese and odder daintyies as -dey pleased, so dey stole, one by one, in different wessels, an' some landed at Cafarine market, an' odders at de Washington market, ah' all long dem warfs, and dere dey libed in clover among de logs an' grow up almost as big as young jackass. Dere am great many ob dese fellers in de city, but we can't find out de hole till de sencis or de Derectory, I forgot now wich, am fin* ised.    SCOENTFltIC DISOOURSES.        1 Dere am one 'culiarity 'bout de rat dat was not generally none 'mong de ancent foolosefers, an' dat am de fact dat de rat's tale am 'zactly as long as him body, 'sept when he loos part ob it in a steel trap.  Nobody will swashiate wid dese chaps, not'eben polemtishens, but de only reason dey am not ca'rressed by dese people am bekase dey, like de poor klass ob cullered people, aint loud to wote. I'm down on dem myseff, kase dey aint got no 'spect for pussons. Tudder nite I myself was fass asleep at sister Wanrumsuller, whar I was taken wid a dizziness in de hed, an hab to lay down, and one ob dese fellers come and pull my hare fuss, and when I nock him on de flur, he fell jess like a big Tom-cat; he den sneaked 'round by my feets, and bit me rite on de big tow, den I wake up an holler fier, an skeared sister Wanrumsuller, so she almoss turned like de kuller ob meal, an injun pan kake. You muss not 'spose, my ignurrant frens, dat dere am no odder kind ob rats runnin' round 'sept dose menshunned in de tex, kase dere am, an high ole rats dere am, too. See wat a sly, crawlin, ole rat the polemtishun man am, and notus in your "DAILY WALKS ABROAD,5 wat a cunning, shrude, averishus, arogant rat de lawyer am, and dere am sum purty cute :ole rats 'mong de precher mans, an you'll find a few 'mong all klasses in de Eastren states. I noe one ole gray rat dat am arter a beutchifull yaller gal! but he won't get her do, long as your 'spected laborer hab a bresse in xistence on dis earth, kase she 'spress mush affection for de same indiwidual. I aint " ail fat," as we' say in French, in de French diemlect, but from wat little I could transmogrify an infur from de French paper, "De Unis Nited de fene Nus" (which am all ober French) I believe I find dat de French people hab had good deal ob trouble wid rats at de big sitty ob Paris. De iats got 'mong de slewers, or de sewers, I can't make out wich, and de peple not habin any blid spilt to any 'count since de lass reflitution, dey went to work and butchered -tousands, and sent dem in de Seine, dat means a big net, to yung stuck-up Boney-part, fur a holiday present. Lam-ertine led do movement, an Lam-er-more follered klose by de side ob de Duke de Clubbem. Dere muss hab bin  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7078-00000009"/> 160      MR. JtLIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL S "MURDER MOSS RAT," Spokeshare has it " murder moss fowl," but as dere was no fowls in de frokis, and it amrrll confine to de rat popemlation, I alter it, ob korse. Dat's all I noe 'bout de rat, if any ob you tink you kin do bettur, jiss cum up and try It. Brudder Ruxell, will you pass 'round de plait? -Notwidstandin'. my caution to brudder Cole lass week, he got stuck wid two tin six- penses, and if I find out who cum dat ober me, I'll fetch 'em, mind I tell you, No, VII. fBRtiDDRS AND SISTERS: I is glad to parsebe dat a tirst fur noledge had agin 'sembled you togedder, an' I trust you will not go 'way sassagefied dat your ole an' worthy speaker am teaching your idias how to shute. I hope de Anti-gomblin 'Siety wont tink I mean shutin'marbels, kase I'm down on all species ob dat, as well as Perfesser Greely. From pitchin' pennies you git to pitchin' quates, from pitchin' quates you pitch into somebody else, and so on to de end ob de pusselogue. But dis, my stingy hearers, hab notin' to do wid de subjic ob my discoure dis ebenin', an' I shall now indeber to lucidate dat subjic to de hight ob you xasperation, and not hide my lite under a half a peck.- De pictur ob de subjic dis time I found in de Spellin' Book, and in de Gogrophy, and when I went in de wild beast show I find him dare showin' away, jis as if he git dollar a day for doin' de same; dere is no use keepin' you in 'spenders eny longer, so Ill tell you dat de crettur dat I tend to splanify to you am no less a pussenage den DE CAMEL! It seems to me, on lookin' abroad on human nature, human indo- lance, and de rest ob de 'rangements, dat dia beast must hab bin   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        1t made last, for it strikes me wid de force ob a ten strike from Hier, dat dere wasent stuff 'nuff leff to finish him out in a 'spectable style, suteable for de 'siety ob de rest ob mankind; day must had a large supply ob lip leff, kase dey furnish him wid eben more den dey handed out to de coulored race. Dey was putty well off for legs, and bones too, I gess; but dere back stuff must hab bin short and in a good many small pieces, kase it looks as if-he was spliced togedder in sebril places, and put on protniscusly, widout eben smofin down, and dere leff to dry, and it neber be eny better wid him. He carries de rockey mountins on him shoulders, Bunker's hill on him rump, and de walley ob Gee hoss-em fat in de middle. His moff am good deel like black man's oney bigger, and more ob it; but de 'spression, as de goggutotipe man sez, am berry simler; he chaws de cud ob bacco wid de same ese and imperience dat de gemmons on de stoop ob de hotel in Broadway do, oney de camel don't spit on de walk, to be wiped up by de ladies' dresses as dey prumenade dat muddy throughfare. When de camel move along, he looks jis like two wolcanos stuck upon four beanpoles, and kivered ober wid a hoss blanket full ob coal ashes, he head stick up strait as a raw recrute in a soger company, or like Joe Cudgo, when he win twelve shillins in de policy shops. Dese animals was born among de turkeys, in Turkdom, and am ginerly brought up and edicated by de Arabian nites, dey kan karry more burden den any odder man, 'ceptin alway, de Pilgrim Progress man. Dey kin go widout water from Saturday nite till Sunday mornin, an not git dry, but den in de mornin dey want dere bitters like odder peepils. Some peepils will hab bitters if dey hab to drink Hutching's bitters, which bitters are de bess kind I nose on, for culinary complaints ob de stomick, when de bile oberflow, de lump- fatic glands ob de dress coats ob de nostrim and upset de powers of stronglaton. De camel, you black rogues,' am mentioned in de big book, whar it say dat it am harder for a rich man to enter de king. dom ob hebbin, dan it am for a camel to go through de I of a needle. Now if dere am enybody I dispise in dis world, it am a poor man, he'm a disgrace to de community, and or't to be kicked out. I was poor once, myself, and I 'now jis how mean dey lib, an I'm down on dem like sledge hammer, but I am sure you all feel glad you aint rich, kase you tink your chances for hebbin am better off, but look  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7078-00000010"/> 18       MR. 'JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S out for yourseffs, one ob dese days some ob dese leadin' abolishonests gib one ob you inderpendent fortun, and den whar will you be? why, I know whar you'll be, in two hours arter you git de money: down on Coney Island, eatin clam soup, if in de summer time, and if in de winter, ob course you go to de seller and treat all hands to a shillin' bowl. But I hope none ob you will be 'flicted wid a fortune, kase no camel kin git in de I ob a needle, no more den a hog kin play de juce-harp. You will please sing de useal ducksholiday, and wamose as soon as de collecktion am counted, and not afore, kase a good deel ob ,counterfeit bad sixpences and pennies hab bin chiped upon me ob late, and I pass on sich foolin. No, VIII. MY BELUBED HERERS: You hab no dout herd many lexshures on, an many preecher men spoke bout de FALL DOWTVN OB MAN. De poet hab sung elaborately on de subjeck-de painter hab tutch it wid de fairey strokes ob de pencil-de most eminent warriors hab wrote upon it-de newspapers hab talked bout it-an it hhb- beeh a standin puzzler to all debatin societies since de kommencement ob time. But, in my humble' pinion, not one ob dem hab trown de least lite on de subjeck: an, darefore, arter burning sebril quantities ob midnite camphene in de research arter facs in de kase, I hab con- cluded to splain de hole matter, so as to set de questshun at rest for eber arter. You must not spose dat de poet means, wen he sez "de fall ob man," dat de man Adam fell down on de ground by stubbin he toe agin a stump, or a stone in de Garden ob Eden, or dat de apple he   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        19 eat was, komposed .ob sumpting dat opeprated on de nee jints, an made dem so week dat he kudent stand! for dat was not so. You noe, Adam an Ebe was made ob human natur, an placed in de Garden ob Eden, in de land ob paradise. Dis garden was de most luxurious spot de earth eber produced. Wen dey was turned loose in dis pasture, dey war told dat all dis magnificent place war dares, an nobody elses. Dey war shown de big fig tree, war dey kood retrete from de burning rays ob de sun at noon-day, an dey was shown de elegant bower made ob grape wines and honey suck- ers, warein dey kood lay down .at nite anO sleep in peace and blissful innocence. But dey war also told dat all outside de fence belonged to de owner dereof, an dey must not tuch ennything beyond it, or dey would rue it as long as dey libed, an a good wile arterwards. In order to more,fully splain how man kum to fall, I will hab to diskribe de siterwashun ob de garden itself. You see dis garden was on de top ob a high, steep, big green hill, frequently called Mount Zion. Dis hill was surrounded on all sides by a deep gully, an was fenced in at de brink ob dis gully by a slight inklosure. Well, one day Adam and Ebe was takin a walk, an \ I lookin ober de fence, dey spied a must lubly apple tree on de outside, wid apples growin on it dat shone in de sun like a new brass button in a nigger's mouf. Wen Ebe see dem it make her mouf water, an she said to Adam, "My lub, jus git one ob dem apples for me, will you?" "Shan't do it," said Adam, C" kase dey don't belong to us." Jis at dis minnit a debil ob a big snake stuk he hed out ob de branches, an sed- "Look ahear, Mr. Adanms, you must be green to say dat, kase dar aint noboddy else in de world to eat dem but you and Mrs. Adams, an ob korse dey am yours." "Dat's a fack," said Ebe, " so you stop your nonsense, an jus git up on de fence an reach me one ob dem apples!" "I don't like to," said Adam, "an, besides, I don't belebe I kood reach dem, dey am so far off."  "Well," said Ebe, " if you'm no more ob a man dan dat, I'll do it mysef." So she got upon de fence, and de snake gib her one ob de apples, an she in turn gib it to Adam, an coaxed him to eat it. He took a bite an found it so mitey nice dat he jumped upon de fence,  tD              &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7078-00000011"/> 20      MR. JULIUS CaSAR HANNIBAL'S an den dar was a race between him an Ebe to see who kood git de most; an in de struggle dey boff lost dar balance by reachin too fur, an oberboard dey went down in de gully ob sin. Dey must hab slid on der backs, kase dey am kalled de fust backsliders. Dis, my frens, was de "Fail ob Man," luded to, bekase dey was de fust man dat fell arter de kreashun; an dey woodent hab fell if dey had not wanted wat dey oetn't to git. Wat a lesson dis teeches all ob us who am discontented wid our lot, an am grasping for tings beyond our reach. Here was Adam an Ebe, wid all paradise afore dem. an still dey war not satisfied, an jis so it am wid all human natur. Dar am Sambo Bogardus Brown, de boot-black, kan black boots berry well, an now, jis bekase he got -a spectable change ob muslin, he feels so mity big dat he tinks he can make a boot, an he actually plied to me to stand skurity for him rent ob a shop in Orange street, so he kood' set up de bizness. Oh! wat a fool is man, an dat man specially. My belubed herers, de only way to be happy am to be kontent wid doin well. Let well enough alone, an, above all, don't envy de success ob, nor injure your neighbor. De world am big enuff for eberybody, an plenty in it for all, if we only tink so. Hopin you may profit by my hints on happiness, I will bid you all good nite, as soon as de kollecshun's taken up. Mr. Whisker Ando Wiggins, de barber-shop man, will no doubt honor de company by acceptin de intended donashun dis ebenin. j                        "'r. No. IX. MY DEAR IGNORANT HEARERS: De subjeck for 'skushion dis ebenin will be one dat I wish tickler tention pade to, 'kase it am one dat must sooner or before interest you mitey much. You must be 'jis as well 'qwainted Wid de fac dat de French langwage, diemleck, or tongue, am gettin' so mity com- *   s rE1IFTO m18COURSE1S.       21 men here 'mong de "bong tong" dat nobody can swasheate in dat sphere at all widout spoken it like a French book. When a waiter, a chambermade, or servent ob eny kind are wanted, de fust question dey ax you am, "Polly-woo-French-a?"--kin you spoke French; and if you say you don't no what dem dribin at, you will be turned out doors, as de most lowest ob de wulgor. De French am inun- datin' dis hole nation! Go war you will you see de little round-eyed mustachered Frenchman, who are courted by de ladies, and fondled jis like lap-dog. In fac tings are b'comin' so berry mush French here, dat ef I don't hab my sallary raised to a libin' pint soon, I'll set up a frog soupery, and teach de langwage for a libin'. Takin' dese tings into 'sideration, I tort it best to gib yew a few hints on de diamlect to-nite, so you kin' spoke 'nuff to let de people see dat yew wasn't born in de woods. If yew all git out your note books, and put down wat I say in French, to-morrow mornin' yeu kin' suffer it up, and git it by heart. When you meet a lady 'fish- ently edemcated to spoke French (ab coorse yew needn't trow away your larnin' on de mail sex) you will undress her wid "Bone saw?' Dat means good ebenin. Den she will say, "Come o wo port wine,', dat means how do you do? Den you say "Jinny fought for beans," aats "I am pretty well marm." Den she will ax you "Kill novela av a beas?" Dat means "Wat's de news? Den you say "Nous verrons." Dat means Colonel Webb's got home, and looks " distin- geree." Den when yew turn to leabe, you trow lubin glances at her, and bow yourself out, observin' "oh reservoy," dat means "good bye." Wid dese few lessons, I tink yew kin git along, and learn French widout a master. "Trees beans; Allez vous le Diable Cochon Kis. kady de Pompray; E Pluribus Christy. Alle woo de frog chowder." De second claws ob my discorse will, like a good many odder mans lecturs, hab notin to do wid de fust; but in dis claws I 'spectfully beg lebe to draw your 'tention to somfin dat cum to my nollage dis day, and dat am de fac dat Elder Brockus was seen late lass Sunday nite a slinging heself round de corner ob Anthony street wid dat yaller widder wat stole de big spoon out ob deseller, wat dey labile up de clam soup wid. I didn't noe wat de ole darkey wanted wid her, at sich a late hour, or wat he wanted in dat naborhood a tall; so I called on him to-day at de boot blackin 'stablishment in Orange street, and put it to him strate. He say was argufying de case wid  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7078-00000012"/> 22       MM. JULIUS CESAR HANNIBAL S her bout de spoon, and she say dat ant Wan Rumseller put a tin six- ,pence on her, todder nite, and den she swore she didn't, and den dere was a fite, and ole Anty Wan Rumseller went to hit her ober de hed -wid de spoon, and she grabbed it out ob her hand and kept it. All dis may be facs, but I warn all de young collored man to keep away from de yaller widder. She's a scorcher. Brudder Dolfin Smith'will please take up de collecshun, and look out for batter. No. X. "ADIES AND GEMMAx,: By de 'tickler inquest ob sebril ladies 'tached to dis congregation I shall dis ebenin' distort my remarks for your edication on de "ROCHESTER NOCKERS," and I must 'spress my great sassagefaction ob seein' so many ob de fair sex present on dis portant caision. De Rochester Nockers hab claimed de 'tention ob de public mind for a year or two, and so excited de nerves ob Professor Greele, dat he immediately took to eatin' beef-stake and onions, instead ob de saw-dust puddin' ob Mr. Graham to raise his spunk 'fishently to un- westigate de matter in a proper manner, in all its ramifications. De fust de world ebber node ob Rochester Nockers was durin' de rainob King Charles de Second ob England. De fust Rochester Nock- er on record am de Earl ob Rochester, who is sed to nock around more den eny udder man ob his time, specely 'mobg de ladies. Dis gem. man was none to gib sebril nocks on de head ob people who made it dere bisness to attend to his instead ob his own. Dey say he was one ob de nockers when he got in a muss; he could always fite his wait, let him find it war he would. De next notice de public hab ob Rochester ,Nockers was in de village bearin' dat name, sitiwated jis- back ob Albany, war de House ob Kongress sets, in de Kourt ob Sessions. Here a party ob high spirits congregated, an' nocked tables an' chairs about in de. most -misterious and promisquis man-   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        -23 ner, at a dollar a head; and de fun ob it am, none ob dese spirits can be seen; but dey am like de good boys my grandfadder used to tell me 'bout, " dey am heard but not seen." Dis fac set de country in a blaze, an' sebrel preacher mans undertook to sleep in de house war de " spirits" was a cuttin' up, but most ob dem got enough ob it afore mornin', and came to breakfast so agemtated, dat dey could not tell a sassage from a piece ob eel, and dey always left, forgitin' to, pay for dere logins; howeber, as dis last claws is frequently noticed 'mong de clergy, it may not be 'sidered strange in dis case. Dere was a curous case ob Nockin 'curred in a cullered family in dat city one night lass winter, which may be set down as bein' done by bad spirits. De facs ob de case am dese :- Old Tone Smock married a putty, likely lookin' molattogAl, most ten years his junitoe, and went and dwelt in dis same town of Roch- ester, and one nite ol Tone was 'gaged to sit up and watch at de house, war de nockers was a gibin dere eximbishions, and it so hap- pened dat he got frightened, and run home in de middle ob de nite time, and swore he'd neber hab notin to do wid eny spirit, 'septin dose ob de most ardent character. When he reached his house he l   put his hand true de broken pane ob glass and onbolted de dore, and in he went smack dab, as de Yankees say, into his bedroom, which so skared his wife dat she hollar fire. In de 'fusion he tort he hear somebody slip under de bed, but he was so frightened wid de nock- ers, dat he daesent look for fear he fined a bad spirit. So he sliped off he close, and he sliped into bed and covered he head wid de bed (   close, shaken like reputation ob some ob 'de Wall street brokers. Well, he had'nt bin in bed long, and his wife had gis finished sayin she did'nt b'lieve he was at de hunted house a-tall, but had bin arter de gals, when he felt somefin push up from under de bed dat feel jis like de back ob camel, and at de same time he heard a nock on de floor, jis like colored man's heel, and a noise as if somebody rush towards de door, and as he raised his 'head from under de close ho seed a tall dark figar 'slope out ob de house. Dis skart him more dan eber, and he nily turned wite. "Wat's dat 2" he gasped to Mrs. Smock. "Wat?" axed she, as innocent as chile. "' Dat big ting, jis lebe de house."  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7078-00000013"/> 24      MR. JULItS CAISAR HANNIBAL S "I didn't see any big ting; lay down; dees delish lockers ober dere to Foxes set you crazy; lay down; notin bin here." Well, Tone lay down, but not to sleep. He kipt his top eye open till daylite, when to his surprise and wonder he seed a man's hat settin on de table. He sprung to de table, seized de hat, and spelt out de name of Deacon Smellgood on de linein. "Wat de debil brought Deacon Smellgood's hat hear? Tell me quick, or I smash somebody," exclaimed ole Tone, mad as thunder. Mrs. Smock said de deacon left it dere yesterday, to hab her sew de linen in it, and dis petrified ole Tone, and he said no more; but in a day or two he met de deacon, and widout hesemtation nocked him down. A reglar fite come off, and Tone was found to be one ob de best Rochester Nockers in de hole digging. Dat's all I nose about de nockers. I don't want to sinemwate 'notin agin de charac. ter ob Mrs. Smock. I dont noe notin about her. I don't noe whar she git her shiney earrings and brespins, and sich tings; dere's no noin war dat new striped silk dress come from, nudder; but I shan't lucidate no more to nite. Brudder Beecher will please hand round de sasser, and remember dat we neber gib change back on no condishun. No. XI. BELUBED BREDEREN AND SISTERS: De argument dis ebenin' are one ob de brightest subjecs dat can possibly be concebed; an' aldo it are a light one, you will percebe de necessity ob fully understandin' it mid odder more waity articles; and widout furder prelimbinary, I will at once succeed to you on de foolosofy ob de undertakin'. De subjeck, den, for dis ebenin' will be on de manufacture and consumption ob GASS. When I say gass, you musn't 'spose dat I mean de camfene gass   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        25 dat am sold for gin in de tree cent grog shops; nor de gass used by de editors ob de daily papers wen dey speak about 'nexin Kuba an odder inflated planets; but de gass I mean ob de infernal regins wat used to be sitewated in Center street, de gass hotuse. De gass dat am made in de gass house am sent trew ebery street in de city by " der machine," jis like de hart trows de blood trew ebery wane ob de human body, only not haf so pleasant or regular. Dey used to make gass wen I was a student at de free school, out ob tar and rosin; and den de gass was much clearer den now-a-days, as it burned briter and cost less; but now dey got makin' it wid coal and oder chemical commodities, wich make it cost more dan in de olden time; and de Lord nose it am much wusser dan it was den; but dat's notin, as long as it comes higher, an' am fashionable, de people will use it. Dere seems to be a mity big eel ob mistry 'bout de gass bisiness. It burns by de feet, an' at a short meter rate; aldo de company hab a 'ticklar meter ob dere own, wich dey lends to ebery body who burns de gass, an' are willin' to pay a high rent for it. You will not find dis 'ticklar meter in de music book; but it am generally found behind de doyer or de counter ob de storekeepers. Dis article looks little like a small sheet iron stove, an' has a face somefin like a clock, wid a long hand on it. Well, ebery month, a man wid a book an' pencil in him hand comes round, an' arter looking at de size ob de shop, and calculatin' de amount ob bizness done by de owner, he bery misteriously opens de "'tickler meter," an' as misteriously chalks somefin down in he book, an' lebes de store. In a day or two arter dat a bill comes in, statin' dat de company will walk into you so many feet. If you 'spostulate wid dem, an' say you neber burned dat amount afore, dey will tell you " if you didn't you ought to," an' dat if de bill am not lickerdated at once, de gass pipes will be " tuck up" afore nite. Now de queshun am dis-am it rite dat de city fad- ders, de policemen, should 'low dere children to be 'posed on in dis triumfant manner? I answer in de most elefant manner-no! no!! But, says some ob you, who keep oyster and barber's shops, war's de remedy? Must we bur spirit gass an' ile till a man am 'leckted dat will 'liten de city on dat point on him own hook? Again, your 'spected lecturer answers elefantly-no! Wat den? Why make your own gass. I is how comin' to de most skyantific porshur ob 2  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7078-00000014"/> t-6       MR. JULIUS CASAR HANXIBALS my discord, an' I wish dat Mister William Henry Harrison Peters, an' Miss Florinda Jemima Watts, will please stop gabblin' till I 'splain myself to de utmost capacity. I do wish people would do dere coortin' at home. I hab, my frens, been studyin de art ob de manufacture ob gass, to show you how easy it am made. I been reedin' all de gassy writers since de days of Josephus, de ole closeman, down to de days ob Pro- fessor Greely, an' I is fully 'swaded dat I nose all 'bout it, an', dere- fore, widout bein' gassy myseff, I will 'splain how ebery body can make dere own gass in dere own house. In de fuss place, you muss get a big iron pot, an' hab a kiber dat fit it 'zactly, den you put in haff peck ob tar, four quarts ob rossin, an' a peck ob antecrite coal, an' den put on de kiber, an' hang it ober a fier ob forty-two degrees north latitude below zebra, by ninety-four de odder way, an' bile it seben hours in de arternoon; and den, wen it get to ten hundred an' thirty nine below the equinoxial line, nock a hole in de pot kiber, an' stick in your gass pipe; den run to de winder, turn on de gass, any lite it. Dat's de triumph ob genius ober de gass monopoly." Wat's dat Pete Williams axes? "'Spose de gass won't lite, wat's to be done den?" Well, if de gass won't lite, dere must be some fault in de ingre- dency, and not in de manufacture, no how. Your belubed lecturer hab offen been axed by de outsiders wat we lite our lecture-room wid, an' I always tell dem dat we rely on de bright eyes ob de lubly fair sex to trow a hello ob lite round de room 'fishent for ordinary purposes, wide de aid ob a few candles. I shall take up de colleckshun myseff dis week. Brudder Beecher was 'posed on last time wid tin sixpences.    SOIEXTIFIC DISC0ttM8ES. No. XIIS   HARDENED SINNERS: To noe thyself am one ob de fust and most 'portant laws ob de State ob 'Merica, derefore I shall dis ebenin lucidate on le poplar subjick ob A-NATOMBY. Anatomy, my poor ignorant frens, am de bones, muzzles, wains and sinners ob de human body,; and eberybody am human body, colored man an Injin 'eluded. I shall commence at de head ob de subjick, and assendingly go down to de foots, and splain tings as I go 'long. Fustly, den, I 'tack de brane, which lay on top ob de coconfit in a pan furnished for de purpose, called de brane pan. Dis lays alongside ob an odder pan called de tinpanum ob de ear, which am so called, from de fac dat it enables us to hear different kinds ob sounds; dere am nudder pan in de human body, and dat's de neepan, and when all dese pans am shut de human body am ready to go off, specaly if de human body hab got a load on. Me next come to de troat, which am made ob somefin like gutta percha, called lumfatix glands, which terminates at de borax, and runs into de juglers wane. Some feller's troat am bigger den odder fellers, and dey drink more bad rum and eat mbre, which catastrofy am all owein to de size ob de swaller. De hart am de next. Dere am two parts ob de hart, and it works in de human body jis like steam injine. It forces de blood to ebery part ob de ramifica- tion, eben to de hair, and dat am wat makes so many red heads. It lays rite under de lungs, whar de peeples had de culenary consurm- shun; rite below dese am sitewated de diagram, which am full ob holes, jis like a sibe. Dis ting am what keeps de stomack in its proper function, and allows de gastrick jewses to overflow de jube- bus and fall into de pizaringtum, all ober de oilfactory nerbes, and -sometimes deranges de whole apparatus, and de human body git sick, send for de doctor man, and funeral expenses hab to be paid by de poor-house.   &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7078-00000015"/> 28       MR. JULIUS CESAR HANNIBAL'S Dere must be a biler in de human body somewar, kase I hear de doctors talk so much 'bout complaints bein' owin' to de bile, and I'll find it out if I hab to go to de Anatomical Museum to do it, De longest bone in de hole structure am called de spine; dis runs ho- rozontaly, dogmaticaly, and catolicaly long de back bone, as far up as de back-ob-de-neck-a-buss. Dis bone am full ob little jintes, and am de tenderest bone to'fool wid, 'septin' de shin bone, in de whole sistem. De action ob de food will, in all probabilemty, be mite interestin' to you all; dere for I will close my discord by gibin' you a 'scription ob de same. You see sister Mussey eatin' dat apple dar, and trow- in' de skins on de floor. Well, dat apple pass fust true de lumf-at- ox glans' ob de troat, down de borax, to de diagram, into de stom- jack; dere it am diegested into de gastrick juce, and passes into de jubams, thro' de anamaI canal and kiuga akeduck, into de piza- ringtum, and is dere lost among de infernal regions ob de corpora- tion. Ah, my poor darkened hearers, dis am a subjeck dat few un- stand; and I would hab been jis as stoopid as you all if I loafed round de warfs, and suck 'lasses from de barrels, like as I seed Pete Bolus adoin' lass week. Dis runin' round de warf arter de sweets ob life will neber fill de head wid useless knowledge! Brudder Bromfoozle will please hand round de sasser; I didn't git 'nuff lass week to buy me backer wid, so shell out dis time. No. XIII. DARKENED DISCIPLES: Your worthy subscriber will 'lighten your bedimed wisionary or- gans dis ebening on one ob de most 'fulgint subjicks dat man or wo- man kind eber listened to. I shall splanify de great siance ob ASS-TRONOMY. You must not spose, you hardened sinners, dat I is one ob-dem gifted sight seers, or one ob dem wicked fortin tellers, kase I is    ,ID           SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        29 guane to read de stars, for you noe dat ass-tronomy means de si- ance ob how to read de stars in de middle ob de nite time. Dere am sebril kinds ob stars in de furmanend. Some about de size ob de head ob a brass nale, and dey grow larger till dey git as big as a soger's button. It am a most beaufull site, ob a cold nite, to stand out doors, raped up in notin but enthusiasm, and gaze pon de starry sky, studded wid angel's eyes, all lookin down on you, to see what you am a doin on dis arth, and how you fool around de wimon. Dere am some comits (and some come-its, too,) wid long tales, which I shall 'lude to bom buy. De milkey way, which you no doubt hear a good deel 'bout, runs doo nort, west, and souf, clar from away down below de Battery, clar up to Orange county, and dat's de reason it am called de milkey way. Der am anodder kind ob milkey whey, dat I will sometime or odder splanify to you. De fust bright star dat was diskibbered was-found out drue de aid ob a double-barrel'd skyglass, by a Jew ob de antshent times, named Peter, and was named arter him (Jewpeter) in a complimentary benefit at de time. De next was Mercury, but we only see dat shine on Sunday mornin in dis city; it am brite as de britest. Wenus am de star ob lub, and always shine britest in healthy warm climates. Mars am de star dat gides de soger man in de dark rode to glory, hallalujah, and E plurabus union am anodder ob de same family. We hab odder stars here dat am egregious wid de sile. Dere am de star Forrest, a native ob dis sphere, who am lately bin taken in, and am now undergoin a sever rubin, but I hope he will come out all de briter for it. De star Cushman am now hoberin over New Orleans, and thou- sands nightly turn out wid dere spyglasses to gaze at her. De star Burton you can neber look at long widout laffin, 'kase he makes funny faces at his beholders. Dere was a comit seen here last fall, dat was fust diskibbered in Sveeden. Its character was ob the purest and britest, and hundreds ob thousands ob peeple used to rush down to Castle Garden to look at it. Its name am Jenny Lind, and it set the people half crazy. One gemman gib a man named Barnum, who' owned de big telem- &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7078-00000016"/> 30       MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S scope through which she was wisable, two hundred and twenty-five dollars jis to get a peep at her. She's a splendid comit, and car. ries a mity long teil arter her all ober. She is 'spected to shine around dis quarter ob de globe in 'bout a month. Dere am many odder stars dat I could menshun, but oein to de late hour I am 'pelled to'disalude to dem; but afore I close de subjick dere am one pint I wish to dwell on, an dat am de pint ob pea nuts dat Done Luker's oldest boy brought in dis ebening and handed round to de congregashun, till I hear notin but crack, crack, on all sides ob me, all true my discord, and den I seed all your jaws a working like hun- gry niggers, and de louder and faster I talked, de faster your jaws worked. I wish hereafter dat you do your pea nut eating at home. I shall pint Done Luker's eldest boy a committee to sweep out de lectur room, and if he eber come hero again I'll cat akise him. Brudder Hutchins will please pass round de sasser. No. XIV, SUSPECTED HEARERS: I shall 'tinue de sujick of Ass-tronomy dis ebening bekase I was 'rupted last lectur, rite in de middel ob my discoorse by de lateness ob de hour, and de chowin ob peanuts. De fust planit dat'I shall call to your notice on dis 'portant 'casion, will be de moon. You hab, no doubt, all seen dis planit so often dat it needs no 'tickler description from your learned lecturer dis ebening. De moon* is s'posed by meny ignumrent peoples to be made ob green cheese, but dat logick am 'roneus and false. Odders tink it 7 am a big tin pan, hung out ob de inwissable winders ob hebin, wid a  lamp hung in frunt to make it shine, like de Dremmond lite on de top ob Mr. Barnum's Museum, and de reason dat we don't see it all     MR. JULIUS COJSAR HANNIBAL'S    de time am bekase it am taken in ebery now and den to get scow, ered, kase de nite air gits it rusty, and it must be cleaned. Sich stories am also a lie. Dere am no foolosefer dat hab disbib. ered zackly wat de moon am made ob, but de opinion of your litened laborer am dis. I look 'peon de moon as de little crystial palace, in which de god ob lub, little bare faced Cupid, libs, kas6 you all Hno dat de moment a human critter falls in lub dey find de greatest delite- in loafin about mbonlite nites, and gazing on de beufill orb, wid de most intense anxiety, as if dey 'spected to find out somefin dereby condusive to dere happyness. Sometimes dese peoples am called moon struck. De moon struck me one nite as bein berry brite and hansome, but it 'fected Sister Huffermoon very different. She was comin home late from a ball in de moonlite wid de yung cullored, man she danced wid last, and it am s'posed she must hab fell in lub wid him, aldo she complained ob feelin bad rite arter, s'pose. Some ob de gossips dere sez: she et more den haff of a 'possom dat was serbed up on dis tickler 'caision. Well, as dey were walkin 'long home she fainted in de cullored man's arms, gis as dey got to de corner ob de alley dat she honor wid her residence. Dis skared de young he feller, and he draged her in de house, roused all de family, laid her on de floo, sent a half-a-dozen arter as menny docktors, an' den rushed for one hesseff. Dey all got back wid de different doc- tors at about one time, and now de berry debil was to pay; kase not one would 'scribe for her till all de rest was turned away, and at last dey got in a gow. De Alopathist said she must be bleed in both arms, leeched wid 42 leaches in de back ob de neck, and a blister ob Spanish flyes must be put on all ober de abominable regions ob de stumiack, and 12 grains ob calomal ebery hour. De Homopathist said dat she woulden't lib under de operation, and dat all she had to do was take as much ob a little powder dat he hab in he pocket-book as dey could put on de pint ob a needle, an trow it in a sist'rn ob rain water, an' take two drop ebery odder Monday nite, at haff-past 10 presisely, an' let her hab a smell ob camfor ebbery few days in de interum, (I 'spect de interum means de nose). Dis made de water- cure doctor mad. He wished to noe wat rite de homapatiest hab to order a sist'rn ob rain water under enny sarcumstances? De rite to dat, he said was his only. He went on to advise de pashent to hab a rope tied to her heels, an be sowsed in de sistren sebral tipes a days &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7078-00000017"/> 82-      MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S on an emty stumjack, den take a refreshin' shower-bath ebery twenty minits; an' he told dem how to fix up de shower bath, by settin' de pashunt on de front stoop, an' pourin' a barrel ob cold water on her head, from de 3d storey windoes. De Thompsonin doctor said all de woman wanted was two or tree good emitics, and a hot steem bath, a hundred an' eighty-seben 'grees above alongo; an' he told dem neber to send for a Thompsonian doctor till dey put de biler on fust. So de whole ob dem got a-jawin' true owne anodder, an' in de middel ob de muss, de yung womon come two, an' was as mad us blazes to see sich crowd round her, and she clar'd de house in a little less den no time, an' de doctors arter insultin" each odder to- gedder, come to de 'elusion dat sister Hofferman must hab been moon struck, an' notin' else. Ah! my fren's, dis big round moon plays de debel wid weekly headed people, sometimes. Will brudder Thomas Benton Squash please pass round de sasser.   No. XV. DEAR   ISTER AND BRUDDERS: You will find de words ob my tex dis ebenin in New England Primmer, dus:- "And Hezekiah said unto Benjaman, get money, Ben, get money- honestly, if thou can'st, but get money." Yew must not s'pose for a moment dat de Hezakiah mentioned in de tex hab ennyting to do wid de Hezakiah ob old, spoken ob by ole profit Shakspeare in his beaufull poem ob "Ole Tar Riber," kase it wasn't him &amp;t all. De Mr. Hezakiah I mean was an ole Quakerman dat libed jis back ob Pennsilwania in Philemdelphia, and used to bring ebery Wednesday and Saturday to Second street market (dat's mar- ket days) sich tings as butter and cheese, ponhorse, headcheese, apple sass, per turnips, and sich like, and by degrees he got nuff to bild a    SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        83 house, and den ebery body take off dere hat to Hezekiah, and made him feel mity prowd. He was a foolasfer, and he node gis as well as de pepile didda it was his money dat dey bowed to, and not him, kase when he first started in de wegetable line nobody swasherate wid him, and I don't belibe he could hab borrowed a levenpenny bit (dats de Fiiemdelfy name ob a York shillin) in de whole willage, derefore he one day, gis afore he kicked de bucket, call'd he son Ben, and-in do full pride ob parential dignity, 'wised him cordin to de tex. Well, de consequence was, Ben growed up one ob de meanest white men dat eber kept wittels from spilen. He was too mean to eat nuff to keep sole and body togeader, and he got so thin dat people begun to tink he had de pin fever, kase his legs swelled up like broomsticks, and he used to wear a blue cap, so he looked like a long locofoco match. When he used to go down town he used to take a crust ob bread in he pocket, and at meal times he'd walk into an eatin house, and call for a glass ob water, and den steal de man's butter to eat de bread wid. He was neber none to gib away a cent but once, and dat was a bad one, and it am said he used to put a led sixpence in de plate, (jis like some ob my mean, contentable hearers does) and take five cents change. Well, tings went on in dis way, and Ben was perfectly happy; but bor by he did 'cumolate bags ob money, and den he didn't noe what de debil to do wid it. He couldn't lay down comfortable at nite, kase he was a feard ob bein robbed; so he had to set up all nite to be up early in de mornin' to watch his property. Den he put out money on interest, but he worried heseff sick ebery day for fear ob bein' cheated; and when he bilt a house he was on nettels for fear dat it would burn down, and at last he cried in de- spair, "I would redder be poor agin den hab all dis great suspense trouble me wid de nite mare." He tort dat readin de good book would solice his intellect, but no, dere he read dat "It am harder for a rich man to enter de kingdom ob heabin den it am for a camel to pass true de eye ob a needle." Den he was troubled worser nor afore; for he had not only. denied heseff de comforts and needfuls ob dis life, but he was in danger ob loosing he soul into de bargain in de nex world to come. My frens addo, as I said once afore to you. I dispise a poor man abominable; yet I lothe a mean rich man past indurance vile, let him be colored man or not. Aint yow glad dat none ob yow am rich? 2*  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7078-00000018"/> j    34       MR., JULIUS COESAR HANNIBAL S '. But I'm afraid some ob you got a sixpence more den is good for your peace ob mind; derefor I send brudder Woodford round mid de sassar to ease your consciences. Dis money sets some people crazy. I wish when de Dorcus Society sends me socks agin dey'd mend de holes in de toes. I don't mind de heel, kase it am necessary to open dat to get de sock on; but I can't go wid my toes out. Who's a laffin' in meetin'? No. XVI. MY DEAR WOOLEY HMADS: My lectur dis ebenin will be on de Manners an' de Fashions, de' Costumes an' National Character ob de Oderiferous Country, known on de geolomical maps ob de arth as de MUSKEETO KINGDOM. Dis kingdom am siterwated away down souff, below war Dickson's line ob stages run to. It am way down de Missippee, in de logatude 383 97, laffertude 9, under de temperance fluid zone. De best way 'to get dere am to take a canal boat from bar to Buffalo, on to de Hio, den to Chingo Lake, to powanrass; from dere you go to de Ismarass, on to Shagemrass; den you get on a jackemass, and ride into de Calafernia regions, git into a Chinese chunk, and go on to de Gipsin Pyridmids, take a one-hoss wagon ober de plank rode to de side ob de harbor ob de Moskeeter Kingdom; den- you git on board de ferry boat, and cross rite ober into de place, and dere you am, high and dry, like an Irishman biles his potatoes. When yow ribe dere yow will find de park full ob omnibusses to take yow to de king's palace, de high bridge, and odder poor- houses. De king ob dis kingdom am a he coloured man, and a mite big one   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.  :  at dat. He stands ten foot six, or six foot ten, I forgit now wich; baut him a mity great soger man. His unicorn consists ob a second- hand-me-down British ossifers blood red soger coat, a pair ob spurs, and a tall bear-skin cap, .wid a red and white fedder, a yard and seben inches and-a-half long, and a pair ob moustachoes. Him 'seedinly popular jis now 'mong his 'stituents, kase he lately sent out his whole army ob eight colored sogers, and tuck up all de ole wimons, and poor deluded, crippels, who had 'barked in de peanut line; and den he had de wiskers of de dandies cut off, kase dey stuck out an inch or two beyond mark laid down in de proceedin's ob de common scoundrels, and odder laws 'fectin' siety. De war on de peanut stands pleased de big bugs, an' de war on de wiskers pleased de poor poperlation, and hence his great popelarity. De principal wegetation ob de island am 'skeeters, and dats de reason it am calld -'Skeeter kingdom. Dese critters grow to about de side ob our chicker hawks, and dey lib in bee-hibes, and ebery hibe ' hab got a grind stone 'tached to it, where de 'Skeeters sharpen dere bills when dey hear ob de ribal ob a furener in de Selestial Empire. De Skeeters am berry tick at all times here. De natives hab to car- ry a tin horn wid dem to blow dem away, so dey can see when it am dinner time. De people lib principally on sider spirits, skunk's cab- bage, and jerked beef.. I never seed any jerked beef but once, and dat was a shin ob beef Sem Cuggo jerked off a butcher stall in Cofa- rine marked, tudder Saturday nite, De papers say dat de manners ob de people am decidedly gross, derefore I tank a man ob genie, like Cap'n Coggy, would do well dere, if he upset a gross-ery. When yow git in dis kingdom, you can hab jis as many wives as you can afford to keep, and you needn't advertise for a bordin house, widout reference, to lib in, kase any hut takes in lodgers, but dere am bery few sleepers. found in eny ob dese houses. De country, as it stands, aint worth much, else it would hab bin 'nexed to dis long ago. But England habin notin else for her navy to do jis now, am sending wessels dere to scrape acquaintance wid' de 'Skeeter king, and see how de land lays. De compliments dat pass between de British orsi- fers and his 'lustrus highness am 'nuff to sicken all porkdom. I un- derstand dat a committee ob de hole coloured folks ob dis city am pinted to send his 'lustrious highness a inwitation to cum on here and visit de soup house, and odder public substitutions I 'speot to  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7078-00000019"/> s86       MR. JULIUS C^ASAR HANNIBAL'S be on hand on dat 'portant 'caision, and I now send Brudder Bose around wid de sasser, hoping to raise 'ficient money to lay in a five dollar suit in time. No. XVII. MY DEAR INLIGHTIND HEARERS: You hab sembled here dis ebening, 'specting, no doubt, one ob my moral, learned and siantifiick discourses; but, my frens, I hab to disempoint you for once in your lifetime, case I aint got no lecture reddy for dis portant 'caision, and de reasion will be omnibus to you all-as soon as I 'spess myself, and tell yon what hab curred. Since last lecture nite your belubed laborer had been gaged in de colored convention dat hab bin held in dis city for de purpose ob elemwatin de colored race from de lowest pinicall of destotution, prostitution, sub- stitution, institution, and all de odder stutions in de Criminal Calendar, "up to de topmost ladder in de round ob fame." When your belubed laborer walked in de church up de middle ile, all eyes was fixed pon my puson, and I could hear on all sides ob me de greatest curiosity 'spressed as to who I was. Its ole Dickey Allen, ob Fidelfy, come on to preach, said one. No, dat cant be, ansured anodder, Dickey  am bin dead dese six years. All de conwention seemed to stop operation and stare at me. I was beckoned to a frunt seat, in frunt ob de altar, when a colored gemmon in green specks, and short cropped wool, rose and said, "Brudders, 'low me to induce to you de great shining lite in de walks of -siance, Professor Julius Seeaser -Hanabel, ob whom you hab all heard so much about." Three cheers was giben for myseff, and de hand organ struck up dat good old tune ob "Jenny, git your hoe cake done." As soon as de music stopped de presandent rose and welcomed me to a seat in dat lustreous body, and offered me de freedom ob de conwention in a snuff box. I took a pinch ob snuff, and was jis going to return thanks in de most elim- phant manner, when a sneeze got into my nose, and I sneezed rite in -Pt           e- and I sneezed rite in   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.         de presemdent's face, and dat set de niggers in de gallery a laffin, and a general babolation was kicked up for a few minutes.- As soon as de wugler portion ob de niggers had hushed up, I made a speech on 'malgamation, among de most enthusiastic enthusiasm dat eber shook de walls ob a colored conwention. De ladies in-de gallery screeched wid delite when I painted out de beauties ob matrimony wid de oppo- site sex, and showed up de orful propensity ob de 'temtable wite trash to cut around arter de yaller gals, and warned dem to bewar ob de wite trash altogedder. I sat down amid loud cheers in a orful prisparatibn, and I sweat like a nigger in a smoke house. I hear a good deal ob debatin arter dat. One feller, in a high heeled shirt collar, and white crevat, nuff to make a sheet, said dat de reason de niggers was so poor was because dey played wid de policies, and drowd blanks ebery day. Nudder feller said dat he was brout up differently from de last speeker. De folks he was brout up wid neber seed a policy ob no kind, not eben an insurance policy, or a policy shop, too. Den dey all grin, like monkey eatin tuffey. Nudder fellow, in a red hot vest, sed dere ort to be a bank, made up ob colored folks, to spress de cole monopoly, and insted ob a poor ne- gro buying half a peck at a time, dey could lay up nuff by chippin up 6c. ante ebery week tru de summer to by a hole bushel in de winter. Anodder ole feller, wid de wool all combed back, like Gen- eral Jackson, sed de only way to raise de colored poperlation on an 'quality wid de wite folks am to edem-catem in de same schools wid de wite children. I 'gree wid all but de last ole feller. De policy bisness am Awful Gardner, dat's a fac. You must not spose I noe dis fac from 'spe- rence; kase I don't; oney heerd so. De ideea of a coal bank am good!-fuss rate!-and I purpose one to be started by dis congre- gation, and I'll be president, scratchentary, director, all in one, gis to save de substitution de sallaryob dese different ossifers. You kin all gib me sixpence a week, and when winter time comes; each 'scriber kin draw on me for a bushel ob coal. It's a fuss-rate thing for you all; but mite hard work for me it will be, mind I tell you. I'm down on de last idea-dat ob sendin' colored children to wite  children's scools; dat would be too much pork for a shillin'; dat would be a mixin' in a little too much wid de wite trash. Deidee ob habin a lubly colored chile settin' on a scdol bench wid somebody's  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7078-00000020"/> 38       MR. JULIUS COESAR HANNIBAL'S wite young one stuck up along side ob her, imertatin' her graces, and laffin at her heels, is monstrous. Dat ting won't do at all. I'm down on de hole proceedin' ob dis Convention on dis pint; and when I rose wid all my great dignity, and told dem so, a bull-headed, thick lipped, chunkey feller called me-me, your worthy laborer, an old blower, and told me to squat, or he'd set me down. I nose de nigger, and I'll get him licked some nite;- I'll let him and de whole conven- tion noe who am an ole blower. 'You may 'spect a lectur on a popeler subjeck next week, when de coal bank will be opened on dis desk. You will now 'tribute to de general collection for de Flannel Shirt 'Siety, on de Jongo Range Islands, on de coast of de Ifisick Oshun. No. X  III.              i "ADIES AND GEMMONS: De tenor, bass, and tribble ob my discord, dis ebenin, will be on de refulgent siance ob Natereal History ;,for, arter studyin' de ana- mal creation, from de bizzy flea to de ballefent, I find notin' more in- terestin' to de human intellect den a full acquaintance wid de man- ners, customs, and habitob de different insexs, as dey am presented to our optical delusions by human natur; I shall, derefore, pro- nounce a benjamandiction on de PORK-AM-PINE. You hab all heard ob dis beauetful insex, eider by readin' about him in de spellin' book, or true " de evel reports ob malicious pus- sons," and no doubt you got your minds made up dat he am a bad character; but I nose better den dat. De Porkampine may be classed in scool ob fitein animals, de same aa Tom Hyer and Yankee Sullevan am classed among de scool ob   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        89 fitein men; and it seems dat human natur, when he made him, in- tended him as a specimen ob de quill driver fraternity; for Daniel Webster 'spressly says, in him catakize, dat he will, when attacked by an odder feller, roll heseff up in a ball, 'bout de size ob a roll ob carpet rags, and shoot his quills at de " fearful adversary," like de injun fire de arrer at de wite man, when de wite come to fool he time 'round de injun. Dere hab no foolosafer as yet diskibered de true origin ob dis most fortified ob all de beasteses; but your 'spected lecturer hab (arter sebril wain 'tempts to find out de truff, durin' many days ob deep study, ebenins ob hard drinkin, and nites ob fearfull contemplation,) assertained all about de hole ting; and now I am redy to relebe my, seff ob de wast diskibery for de sake ob de wancement ob siance. De Porkmapine, my sleepy hearers, am gis wat its name advo- cates, or indicates, (I forget now wich,) for he am haff pork and haff pirie; and now I'll tell you all how he fuss come in dis land ob political corruption and blue ruin. One day an ole 'spectable sow, belongin' to Mr. Adam and Miss Ebe, had a fine litter ob pigs, and de sow not wishin' him to hab her family pen'd up in de city ob Juceerelum durin' de dog days and cat nites, took dem out a walkin' in de garden ob Edin, and layin' heseff down, hog-like, went to sleep, and let de pigs run 'bout, and take care ob demseffs. Well, one ob de little porkers run aginst a pine tree and got heseff all cubered ober wid de sap, which made him brissels stick out jis like quills, and so changed de whole 'pearance ob de pig dat he mudder didn't noe him when she waked up. Jis at dis junction ole Mr. B. Hog, de fadder ob de pig, come saunterin 'long, and seein dis curious lookin ting, stuck he nose up to him to find out what he was, and got de brissels run in him snout for his imperence. "What kind ob beast am dat?" axed de sow. "I don't noe," answered de he hog, " but I'smelt pitch pine and pork on him jis now. Yes, I would be willin to swar before de al- derman dat I smelt pork and pine, both, when I was near him." "Well, den," replied de sow, looking as wise as de Judge, " he must be de porkampine dat we read ob ;" and dis, my frens, was de origin ob dis much abused porker, and de way it comes he shoot off de quills am dis: When he got de sap ob de pine tree on him  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7078-00000021"/> 40       MR. JtLITS CASAR HANNItAL   . it made he skin so tite dat when he'd go to bend, away would go de brissels, and de pig seein dis fac, laid low, and wheneber he went to fite he would roll heseff up, stretch he skin and fire off his brissels, which, ob course, hab growed to quills by dis time. He am a fussy anamal, but not a fuzzy one. When he'm guain to fite, he makes as much fuss as a bottle ob ginger pop in Au- gust, and am about as effective in he'm battles. He am bout de size ob his near frend and relative de hedgehog. I 'spect de pine sap must hab stunted de pig so- he couldn't grow no bigger. He gits he libin by what he can "pick up long shore," and what he can steel in odder ways. All dese ticklers I find out myseff, and if you am too mean to reward me wid a big collection on dis 'portant 'casion, I hope dat my posterior-ity will be kicked into a snug fortune in preceding years to come by your more generous an- sestors. Brudder Cuff Huffman will please hand round de sasser, and be careful to gib back no change. Small change am a scarce article wid me now, and big change too. No. XIX. FELLOW TRABLERS TREW DIS WHALE OB TEARs: I shall draw my discord dis ebenin from de works ob Mr. Gold- smith on de wild beastises, and shall debber to liteen your intellect on de life, character,and occupation ob DE BUCK. You must noe dat dere am sebral kinds ob bucks-de buck rab- bit, de buck sogar, de buck goat, de buck tom cat, de buck ram; dere am two kind ob buck rams:-one am de sheep, and de odder am found ginerally mong de tailors, for dese peoples use him to make de   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        41 coat collars stiff; den dere am de man buck dat you see swelling down Broadway, buried betuene two yards of shirt coller; den dere's de buck nigger wot swells out Sunday arternoons in he mas- ter's clothes, when he master happens to be out ob town; but I don't mean any ob dese fellers, kase dey got no character or occu- pashun worth speakin bout.  You must not mistake de buck man for de buck goat, aldo dey look berry much alike about de face, kase dey boff got mite long beards. You will noe de buck man -by he's alwer's habing a segar in he mowth, de smoke ob which he puffs in people's faces as dey pass him in de treet. He differs from de buck goat in an nodder spect too, kase de clothes dat de buck goat wear he come honestly by, while de clothes ob de odder anamal de tailor often suffer for, kase he gets cheated out ob de same; but I aint lecturin on de buck de tailors made, but on de buck de Lord ob human nature made in de year 1, and sent him in de woods to be de companion and husband to de doe. De buck, my ignorant hearers, am- bout de size ob a yearling heffer, only much more beautifuller made at all pints. His feet differs immediately from de cullured man's in size and shape, dey being small for dere size and round for der formation. His skin, which am sleek, and shines like a puter dollar in a swill tub, am bout de cullor ob a grizly, gray, brown rat, and is mity nice, soft, and silky to feel ob, but dey wont let you feel em much, less you catch em fast asleep in de middel ob de day time. De buck may be classed, jf he was fit to go to school, between de bull and de race horse, for he can beat all creashun on a long run, which smack ob de race horse, and dat make him a bulley on de track, and hence resembles de bull. He am de only anamel dat has beat de telegraph to any great extent. De inguns use him for carrying de males from one wigwarm to de odder, same as we use de steam loferfotive for de same purpose. Mr. Ingun, as he jump 'pon his back, cotches hold' ob his horns, and stears him strait true de woods, and like Brandreth Pills, dey find dere way out in a short time. He head am de most beautifull part ob de countenance, if he'd only keep his nose clean. He hab horns on he head, wich  begin to grow bout de third month arter marriage wid Miss Doe,  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7078-00000022"/> 42       "R. JUL"US CAESAR HANNIBAL'S and de older he grow-de biggar dey git, untill dey git as long as a dull leader in de noosepapers. Dis kritter, you all know, you ungratefull scamps, am de wensen dat you hear 'bout, and sometimes smell when you go past de fash- ionable eatin' houses! De hind quarters am considered de best part, but " dareby hangs a tail,' as de 'posel Shakespee said 'bout de play-house. Wensen, my friends, am deer meet; it am worth 20c. a pound, and when it am fried in a fryin' pan, it looks for all de world jis like slices ob Ingun rubber biled down in molasses, and smells like de same, specally in dog days time. %De occupation ob de Buck am like odder people's, who hab to ricck up a libin as dey go along trew life, and his character stands A No. 1 among de sportin' gentery; for we often hear ob dese gemmen riding-all day gis to get in company mid one ob em; lhe am, in fact, much sort arter; but, like a Subbern nigger, he don't 'pear to return dere affections in de least, for he no sooner hears or sees dem arter him, den he sticks him nose rite strate afore him, and trowin' his horn on his' back, lifts up he tail, and shows his agility in a most surprising manner. Whllen de gents find dat he don't want to suasheate wid dem, dey generally send a bullet-due arter him, on de reception ob which he merely stops, and allows heseff to be conducted to whereber dey wish to take him. Dis, my friends, is all I can find out 'bout de Buck. It's a skittish subjech, and I tink you ort to be mity proud ob your suspected lecturer dis ebening. Brudder Wose will please pass round de sasser, and look out for de California lumps.   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES,.       43 No. XX, MY DEAR WOOLEY HEADS: For de wancement ob siance on dis 'tickler casibn I shall re-lie on de anamal kingdom for a subjeck to lectur on, and derefore I shall, by 'tickler request, proceed to anatamize an old acquaintance ob you all-namely, DE HOG. De Hog, my deluded wooley heads, am a native ob de Sixth Ward, aldo dey am frequently ofen found in odder inhabited dis- tricts ob dis badly litened city, and no matter war he am found, he am de happyest ob beasteses all de world ober; -be always feel per- fectly at home anywar, and generally makes out to find a libin; he am de happyest feller dat runs in de streets. Take him in his single or matrimonial state, dere am no anamal enjoys heseff better; in fact, de deeper he am in de mud de more he am in de mire ob con- tentment; he lays heseff down, straches heseff out, and gibs heseff up to glory. Sometimes he spirits am edified by bein' de fust to find out de depot of a new pail ob swill from a fashionable boardin' house, and den he am led to be frisky; and den it am dat he " cuts up" as if de debil was in him. Dis lass obserwation am too true to cl  laff at; for de big book says dat dp debil was sent into de swine, (swine am de Hebrewer's name for Hog,) and dat accounts for de debilish shines he sometimes indulges in, shaking he little tail, rolin' i  up he little eye, and smackin he chops for joy. Dere am no use }  for me to describe de 'pearance ob de hog to you, kase you am all "on de most intamate terms wid him," as de politishens always sez, when dey spoke 'bout de President. Dey am thought but little ob in siety%, specaly by all polytishens, kase dey can't wote. If dey could, de Sixth Ward would go Hog ebery 'lection. Dere am sebril kinds ob Hogs : dere ain de Wall street Hog, whose hogish appetite for money would make him steal de wool off ob a dead darkey's head, to stuff he hair cushin; den dere's de Hog landlord, who  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7078-00000023"/> "      MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL S would sell de bed from under a sick child redder dan lose 4 shillin rent, if he could; den dere am de Hog boarder, who nebber quits de table as long as dere am enny ting left to eat, and when butter am dearest piles it- on de thickest, and nebber pays up he board. Ah, my stingy hearers, dere am more Hogs in dis world dan wat run around a grunting on four legs. De Hog am a useful anamal; but, like all odder geniouses, de world ne her diskibers his great watlue till arter hle am dead, and served up, young and roasted, at a Yankee train dinner, or steaked off in a sixpenny eatin' house, or turned into de sassage market, in company wid dog meat and red flannel. His life generally ends- when he don't get run ober by de omnibusters-as a countryman's career in de city commences, viz.-by bein stuck. De Hog am a most anshent anamal; he must hab libed long afore de flood, kase it will be remembered dat Gen. George P. Noah took a Ham wid him into de ark; and you know dere can't be no hams war dere am no hogs. Hams were so plenty at one time in Ger-. many, and so berry big, dat de people made houses ob dem, and bilt up a hole town,. which am called till dis day, in all de 'spectable arif- matics, Ham-burgh. But I am led by de nose to belive dat dese Hams spoken ob must hab bin wooden ones; and, no doubt, some ob de Yankee abolitionists' grandfarders took out a ship load, and sold dem at a slight profit, and den stole a ship-load ob slaves from de coast ob Ginny, jis to save dem from any loss by de trip. You see I noe dere are all Yankee fellers aroun Nantucket. But I must close dis interestin' subjec, or else you may tink I am like a Hog myseff for habin so much jaw. I will feel obliged to Brudder Porgie if he will pass round de sasser, and don't probe your- sefsf pigish by-refusing to reward your worthy laborer for his bril- liant discorse dis ebenin.   SCIENTIIC DISCOmURSES.        48 No. XXI. BELUBED WOOLEY HEADS: I shall dis ebenin obstruct my discord from de anamaI wonders ob creation, and, aldo de subjick ob de discord am blind, you musent tink, you ignoramasses, dat your 'spected laborer dont know how to valuminate it-I know it like a book from de head to de tail. De subjick am DE BAT. De bat I mean am not a brick-bat, (a]do he'm a " perfect brick" in his way,) dat fly about offentimes in de Sixth Ward, and make you see stars in de day time wen he hit you on de shin, nor de bat dat play wid de ball; no ! nor de bat on de nose like dat Samn Cow- lip struck Pete Coles wen he spit on his new shiney hoots at Pete Williams' todder nite. It am no sich fluvenile subjick. Dere am two kinds ob Bats: de ole Bat and de young Bat--and it am de ole Bat your poorly supported laborer will pullucilate on, on dis berry 'portant caision. Whar de Bat come from am none ob your bizness, so I nebber took de trubble to go down to de Museasm to find out, but I is fully sassagefried dat dey war made by human natur like all de odder winged beastesses, an my 'pinion am founded on de riteins ob sebrel ob de Common Scoundrel, which I found in de papers, call'd de "Democratick Lebeler," an de  "Wig Screacher," who all say do case am a fact, an ob course it am. De Bat, my stingy hearers, am a considerable ob a bird; he'm haft inseck and haff anamal, an am 'bout de size ob a haff grown rat. He am like a rat kase it has fur on jis like a thievin' scoundrel], and he am also rat-ified by habin a tail in de 'usual place. He head am like a buck rabbit's, and he re- sembles an editor 'bout dis regin a good deal too, kase it am deftshint berry much in de brains; and he am also like justice-'specially like'de justice Judge Barclo promulgated at Pigipsie-bein stone blind. If justice was stone blind it w ould do; but dis one-sided,  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7078-00000024"/> -d8      MBR. JM LIUXS C-ESAR UA!NIBAL'S cross-eyed way ob doing justice am "awful papers," as we say in French. His toes am fledged wid sharp claws, like a California pickaxe, and his habits am berry unregular, because he will fly 'bout nites, and human natur seemin pleased wid his nocturnal propensi- ties, hab gibben him a pair ob wings, seeminly for no odder arthly purpose; and I would 'vise all ob you fellers to be on de look out for dese chaps in de nite time, for if one bats you side ob de head, you'd labor under a hallelujah ob de mind for two weeks and a fortnight, and jis as like as not git in de lunatick assilam in Centre street. If one ob dem 'tempt to bat me any nite, wen I am comin home late from beein out on charatable purposes, I'll take him afore a alderman on a right ob " heap's-o-corpses," as lawyers call it, and sware salt and bat-tery on him. I hab to 'form dis sieety dat Fredrick Douglass, Esq., R. A. N., (run away nigger,) is 'spected in town in a few days prior to his nominating heseff for de presedency. It am not none yet wedder he will bring a trablin companion wid him or not, but sebreal sisters, boff black and wite, in de East, hab kindly waluntered to act in dat compasity to see dat his morals am not tampered wid in dis wicked city. I tink it wiseable, my dear wooley heads, dat you should take up a collection suffishent to purchase a hundred clams to be made into soup for his special benefit, during his stay among us, as a change ob diet mite play de debbel wid his scrutinary functions; derefore Brudder Fitz will please pass round de sasser, and look out for bad pennies, kase dey will 1" ring em in" on us sometimes, if we aint carefull. I understand dat de Hanabel Black Guards, a compa- ny ob sogers named in honor ob myseff, will turn out on his :rible, and scorch him true de five pints.   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.         4 ' i No. XXII. MY POOR DELUDED WOOLEY HEADS: I shall by tickler inquest from Brudders Garrison, Seaweed, Abby Kelley, and odders ob de same kidney, lectur dis time on de siance ob ABBOLITSHUN. I hab kept dark heretofore on dis portant subjick, jis to "bide my time," as de ole Congress men say, and wait till dem fellers in de Senate house blow off dere steam, and git demseffs and de country at large in such a smarl pucker and tite place dat dey can't extrumcate demseffs, and den I was a gwane to open on dem like de bustin ob a wolcano in Princes Bay-extract de sensable speeches from de pyra- mids ob nonsense, grease de axel trees ob de public weal, set de bul- gine ob cibilization on de track ob contentment, put some extra pickle on de constitution, d  t it may always be preserved, and throw a little on de by-laws for de same purpose. Den, I tended to put my name in big letters in de big book, at de wite house, like Fred Douglass, and nominate myseff for de presemdent. -But, as dis brudder wants my 'pinion now on dis absurding questiin, ob course dem fellers at Washington will hab to git out ob dere muss de bess way dey kan. I shall lucidate dis matter fully, and open your benited eyes, ober which dese wite trash hab bin pullin de wool for all your life-time. Wat you laffin about, Gus Jones? Ah, I see you tink bekase you comb yours hair back on your own forehead, like Gen. Jackson, dat your wool kant be pull'd ober your eyes. Dats a  porkempine idia, and berry foolish, as my argements will splanify. You all ob course noe dat de word " abbolishun" means to bolish somefin, an now, wat am dis somefin? Why, de niggers, ob course, and all dese wite sassy tribe wants am to bolish de he niggers fuss, so dey kin went dere canal appertites on de fairest ob all creation, de colored fair sex. Dis fac am as clar as moonshine, when we take into sideration tow close malgamation hab followed on de footsteps ob abolishun in de East. Dey hab two ways ob distryin de race. One way am by sending dem to de Colonization Siety, war dey bab  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7078-00000025"/> 48      -MR. JULIUS C^ESAR HANNIBAL'S to work dere spassage to some odder State, or git licked wusser den dey do in Alabama. De odder way am to mix de breed so offin dat in a few preseeding years de pure African blood will be tirely distinct. Wat you tink ob dat last claws, sisters? Ain't it nuff to cause a flumification mong de hole ob de sex? I can see de dignation rise in your swellin boosems, specialy dose dat forgot to put de cape to dere dresses on. Dis abbolishun originaly originated and commenced in England. De peopled are arter holdin de colored slabes, (whom dey stole by main force from dere own happy country,) in de most tironical bond- age, working dem thirty-six hours a-day, during which time dey got three lickins and a wooden bowl ob mush, concluded, arter dey had got as rich as dey could by slave labor, (which, howsomdever, occu- pied hundreds and hundreds ob years) to mancipate, and it was not till olp Rule Brittaney was as many hundred years ole as de United States am single years before she showed de least signs of 'pentance, and now dey am down on Merica, case she don't cdmplish in a few years what it took her hundreds to perform. And wat did she do wid her slabes? Why, she nimigrated dem to de Ilands mong de Indias, and dere worked dem till dey become ole and useless, and den a great time was kicked up. British pronounced herseff a free nation, and all de slabes was set free, to die in de streets, like dogs. Dere am more fact den poetry in what I am saying, mind I call you. And now, my stingy hearers, my pinion am dat dese wite trash wants to get de niggers free, and send dem out ob de United States to dat detestable iland dat lays todder side ob de Norf Riber, called Jersey, for I heard ob a farmer obber dar, who magnanamousley offered to take colored children out ob de poorhouse, providing dey war bound to him-de males till dey was fifty, and de shemales till dey war forty-nine. De Lord bless Jersey, kase dey need it. In 'gard to dis slabe question, I hab bin rite mong it-dat is, I trabbled souff till I come to Maryland, and den I got better, and back mity fass. I found out as much ob de manners and customs in my journey as one-haff ob de fellers noe dat am making a wool and cry on de subjick all ober de country. It am' a fact dat bad slabes am punished, and putty hard too, and dat good ones hab to work like steamboat all day on Jese plantations. De little sins dat am mostly   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.         AS punished, am gittin drunk, fitein, stealin and murderin. If a slabe git found out in any ob-dese slight offences, he get a mite bad Fog. gin, but here it am different. If any ob you am caught a steali an your way home to-night, or commitin murder, you only git sent a few years at hard labor in de prison, or git your necks strutched a little, like eny odder spectable gemmon found in de same suckumstances. My sleepy hearers, dis am all well nuff to talk bout, but don't tink it am rite for one man to hold anodder in bondage less he pay him for it, but i tink many am better off now den dey would be free, util somefin am done to really better his conditsion, not batter it. De only way to do dis am to edemcate dam like me, and de only way to gib dem dat am to patronise my lecturs, cause no man can enter w ol- ished siety widout a corse ob dem in him pocket. Brudder Clem Green will hand round de asser; poor collection lass week.         3 No. XXIII    . i FELLOEs DISCIPLES: I is sorry to hab to 'pear afore you in de shape ob an 'pology, blat de fact am I hab bin so bizzy wid one ting and anudder sence I -lass spoke to you, dat I had not hab time to fix up a leeturon any i' - tific subjeck.  Barcumstances hab followed sarcumsnesa in sioh rapid suckseshun, jist like de cars on de railroad track,.dat my niy hab bin 'tirely prostitute. De fast suckemstance dat affect me w as de ribal ob Mass Fo- more, de presemdent ob dis mite nation, kase you see I hab a aittle bizness wid him dat 'quire specific attention. I called on himorme at de wite house 'in Washington; but it happened to be wash day and found  Mrs. Foolmore bizzy washin, and she was cross as blaze be. kase I  cotchad her widout her Sunday dress on, so Mara Foolqro tipped me de wink, and he gib me sixpence to drinkhe hellf jid, d 3  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7078-00000026"/> -0       MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S tole me to call agin. I tanked him soderifously, and promiced to do de same which he 'spress; but my ardent bizness led me to git back to de ndrf by de nex train. So I nebber call on Masga Foolmore arter dat, till he 'ribed hear lass Tuesday, wheni tinkihg it my duty, I went down to de Irwing House and ring de bell. A cullored man, behind a big pair ob mustachoes and a wite apron, opened de do'e, and in a grufly woise ax'd me " wat I wanted at dat do'e," and-" why I didn't go to de kitchen do'e?"I laff at his imperence, and told him I was a friend ob de presemdent, and dat I wished to spoke wid him. "Don't belibe it," sed de dandy nigger, "but you kan send your caird up, and if he sez you kin come up, I'll 'scorch you to de rooms." Well den I was in a fix. I nebber did hab eny cairds wid my name on -in partickilyer, and I was for a minite put to an unblush, ' but all at once I remembered dat I had a pack ob cairds in my coat tail pocket dat I took away from Sam Lipley, Guss Trealms, Joe Sampson and Dave Kinney, when I found dem down by Cafirine 'Market playing bluff on a barrel head lass Sunday nite, in de moon- shine, so takin out de Jack ob Spades I rote my name dus, J. C. Hanner-Bull, and gib it to de collored pusson. He showed his ivo- ries clear 'cross he face, and sauntered up stairs. In a minit I hear Massa Foolmore's woise, wich say, "Show her up." Den I hear de waiter say "It aint a she. It am a he.' "Get out," say de Pres- emdent, "de caird sez it's Hanner Bull, send her up." "Shill I send up de pusson dat rote dat name on de caird?" axed de waiter. Presisely," said Massa Foolmore, and in anudder minnit I .was at de do'e. I gib a Rochester nock wid my fist, and de doe was opened by de Presemdent heseff, who was more den delited to see me. He shook hands wiff me, and 'wited me take a seat. I sot down, and we hab a long conflab togedder 'bout de nation and tings in general, not General Tings. Arter axin me many quisshuns 'bout Brudder Tap- pin, My Coon Smith and odders ob less note, he sed he wished to ax me 'bout a class ob comunity which he alers took a great interest in, and he blibed dad he had a good many frends 'mong dem, and thought I node more 'bout dem den odder people. "To wot class do you lude,' I ax'd wid impatients, seeing how interested he was on de subjeck,   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.         1 "DE NEW6 BoYs," said he, "dey spend dere short existence in spreadin abroad de lite ob siance." "Dat's a fac," said I, " dey work for de confusion ob useful nolage."                   fu "Let me ax you, Mr./ Hannerbul]," again returned he, insultin de caird which he held wid my name on, "Do de newsboys embrace de privilege ob usin de public baths, which de corporation so wisely and so nobly instituted for dere use, and for de use ob de rest ob de poor folks dat hab to lib in submarine sellers and penned up apart- ments?" I told him he must be crazy, kase I neboter har ob dem Baffs, and I didn't blibe from de 'pearance ob de boys dat eny ob dem did edder. He said de boys should be looked arter, kase he 'spected to find a good many ob dea in de "House" in a few years. I ax'd him which house he meant; de House ob Refuge, de Poor House, or de Station House. Neder ob dem, said he; I mean de House ob Congress. I tole him dat news boys was found all ober creation, and I 'spected de House ob C ongress would be-full ob dem. Den he axe me how de Picayune get along; an he was 'stonished wen I tole him dat obber thirty-five thousand copies was sold weekly; he said he got it ebery week at de Wite House; and den he axed me confidenshely if I couldn't stir up de 'Mare to keep de streets clean a little, and remarked dat hie was 'shamed ob de condishun Obde city. I tole him dat a man had inwented a merchene dat would keep de streets perfectly clean for wun third wat it now cost to keep dom in de present filthy state. He wanted to noe why it was not employed, and I tole him de trufF, bekase it can't wote. After a few compli- mentary  'marks on m y great talents, larning, and foolosophy, he 'lowed me to take my deparchure arter exagtin a promise to call on him at home soon. On de fuss ob Slay I bin mobin my quarters. I don't lib in de seller no more; I couldn't stan de clam soup diet all de year 'round; clam now an den am a werry good wegetable to ticken soup wid, but tree times a day and all day Sunday for change, am more dan my gisgustine orgins kan bear. I lib now in Tater Peelin Alley, No. 9 3d floor, b ack room, war I keeps bacheler hall, till I fine a likely wo- man for de marriage state.  Deacon Flatsmeller will please hand 'roundl de sasser, and look out for bad specie.  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7078-00000027"/> 512      hMR. JULIUS C ESAR HANNIBAL ' No, XXIV. SUSPECTED WOOLLY HEADS: I shall dis ebening rebound on the great siance of FREENOLOGY. Freenology amn one ob de moss anshent and beutiful siances in de hole catalog ob learnin, and am twin sister to Mesmerism. Free- nology consists in gittin 'nolage free, like you am dis ebening; it was fust discubered in de free schools, and was always looked 'pon by de larned as bein closely connected wid "E plurabus Unum."' In order to fully 'splain my seff on dis 'portant siance, I went to de slawghter house, up in Christy street, and got dis skull. It was cmposable for me to get de hed ob de human body at the Horse- pital, so I hab to use dis sheep's head, which no doubt will answer de same purpos, 'kase it hab got de wool on. De fust bump in a cullered man's hed-and it taint no use bod- derin 'bout enny odder man's hed--am- siterated on de top, and call- ed by de siantifick de cokanut bump; dis bump lays in a triangular form ober'de bump of don't-care-a-d-nativeness, which ebery black man's hed am fully blessed wid; some ob de lower order ob culler- ed mem  hab got de bump of ori-gin-ality, which renders dem 'septable ob drinkin bad gin made up into slings and todies. But, my stingy frens, I warn you to stop dis sling biziness, or else you will sling yourseffs into de place whar de brimstone matches am made. De bump dat am moss cultiwated in de cullered man bed, am call'd on Fowler &amp; Wells' map ob de brane, "Amativeness." Dis am de bump dat plays de debil wid de fair-sex, bekase dat am whar Kupid springs from;- dis bump lays in de back ob de neck, near de coat collar; it am call'd de bump ob lub! Wat am all de sisters feelin in de back ob deir necks for? Wy! dere am not one in dis hole assemblige dat cood tell it if dey had it as largely enweloped as   I             SCIENTIFIC DISCOUSRES.       53 Professor M1affit! It am dis bump whar all de selfishness and wickedness .ob mankind lays; and, I wood say a word to dem fellers as hab got an ober quantity ob it. Look out how you fool you time 'round de opposite sex, kase wen you fall in lub dis bump swells to such an 'xtent dat it oberwellms de hole brane, common sense am kicked out ob de cranium, and lub rain 'spreme till ebery abenue leadin'to de soul am oberflow'd wid de milk ob human kindness, and it takes an " orfull poletice," as we say in French, to traduce de swell'd bump to its proper size. Wats all de sisters laffin 'bout? You better insult your own kon- shunce and see ef you hadn't better laff de odder side ob your mouffs. Sich imperence in meetin I neber did see! De nex fac dat I will call your 'tention to am dis: De hed ob man, like de foot ob de Hog, am diwided into two parts; de front part am whar de intellectual orgins am, and dis part b'hind de ears am whar de anamal propersishens am; dis part ob de forehed am none as de Horse-frunt-us, or frunt-all-bone, b'kase it am all bone and in de fiont ob de hed, which fully 'counts for de nigger's hed bein hard 'nuff to butt down de stone fence. Sum ob de pretenders to dis si; ance hab 'serted dat de brane lays here, but wen dey probe to me dat de brane am bone den I will side wid dem, and not afore. De bump ob ("Benebolence" am sitewated on de top ob dis, but I don't see dat stickin out werry excrusiatin on enny ob your hbds ; but I may be mistaken, and wen de sasser goes 'round de fac will probe itseff. "Combatavness" am found mity big in de cullered race. It lays 'long side ob "Firmness," which bump am 'lustrated on de map by de jackass, which shows how much easyer it am to coax dan to dribe. Some people hab got bigger pumps dan odders, and dis am de way you will fine it out: 'spose you hab a squarrell wid a man and you call him a liar, and he sez, "Ef you call me dat twice more I'll smack you cross de chops." Dat man hab got combatavness small, but ef at de moment dat you call de man a liar, you find you- seff a rollin in de gutter- wid you nose split open, you may make up your mind dat it sticks out on dat man's head so big you can hang your-hat on it. "Cautiousness" am putty *ell enweloped too in collored'man, and dat de reazin dey lub to hunt dat same ole coon; dey kreep kau- &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7078-00000028"/> + 54      MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S shisly 'long de fence till dey git rite under whar he am " a settin on a rale," and den wid telegrofick quickness he sezes him by de tail and trows him on de ground. Dis fac has 'spired de poets to rite songs 'bout it which you all noe by heart. "Self 'steem" am sum in de race likewise; also, as der horror ob swasheatin wide de wite trash, and de manner in which dey " steem up" 'kashionaily, fully probes. "Imitationn" is consnipcious 'mong dem too, but de monkley beats dem all haller in dat bump, which I 'sider no disgrace to de monkey tribe; but one ob de biggest bumps found in de hole hed ob de de- centers ob de African race, 'cordin to de Iwork ob Brudder Bill Sea- weed on Erective Franchise, am call'd 1"Alamentiveness." Dis am de bump dat enables a feller to tell wat-am good to eat, an how nmch he o'rlt to gormandize at a time; for, incstinck, you go irde. seller by Caferine Market, and you see a man call for a plate ob raw clams , ad a plate ob sassengers. Well, if he eat de clams and leabe -de sassengers, den he got de small bump; but ef he eat em boff, den he got it big. Sum. niggars got it mity big, dat dey not oney eat up de clams and sassengers, but call for a plate ob pork and beans, and want it " most all pork, and a good deal ob beans," to top off wid. I call dat hog eatin hog. And now dat I see I got you all in de noshun ob eatin, I will 'smiss you, so you kin go horne and get a cold bite, and wile Brud- der Lem Clawson passes round de sasser I will remark dat I don't want nobody to ring-in dem new free cent pieces on me for a "fip," as was come on me lass week. I don't take em for sixpence no how.- De coal bank am progressin seedinly. De bank owns haff a ton now. *  La   ' .1 SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.                    5g DAlRKEND': HEARERS:' It gibs me joy to see so menny ob you on hand dis ebening. As de wedder grows warmer it will be empossable for you all to crowd into dis room, unless you hab a 'xtraordinary supply of kalonge wa- ter and essence ob peppermint 'mong your clothes. De subject dat I call upon mryseff to spoke * you about on dis 'tickler 'caisidn am de twin sister to Freenology, which Freenology I used up last week all to nuffin. I shall open on you dis time on de great 'fulgent si- ance of MUSSMERISM. Dis ober powerful siance hab waked up de hole world, notwidstandi it am de sleepiest subjick in de hole wokabulary ob nateral fenomo- nens.  It howebber hab nebber bin found out properly, nor nebber will be, I speck, till some larn'd cullered man take it up and splani- fys de whole ting. Dr. Cods. hab published a pulpit on de subjick, and Professor Greeley hab used it andi heself up at do same time, but no lite worth perservin hab been shed by eder ob dese lunatics. Dr. Cods kontends dat Mussmerism lays in de brane pan, wich pan -lays in de top ob de hed, wich I tink seedingly like de fac, kase wen a man lays down at nite to sleep he head lays down lopsided too, which ob cose upsets de brane pan and spills-de Mussmerism all ober de human system and puts de man to sleep; dat looks nateral, and I tink ole Cods am rite. You musent 'spose, you poor ignumrampusses, dat Mussmerism konsists in you ebber bein reddy to be a kickin up" a muss wharebber you go, jis like M3ose when he runs wid der mer- chene, kase dat kind ob siance am altogedder different from de siance 'spressed in my tex. Mussmerism, my stingy followers, am simply de art of puttin a feller creture to .sleep, an keepin him 'wake at de same time. It am  jis dis-'spose Pompey Augustus Mouldyheel dar, de barber's cleark's 'sistant, should happen to noe-whar dar was a dinner pot  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7078-00000029"/> %b6M    MR. JULIUS COSAR HAH-NIBAL'S full ob Kalifornia gold buried, and den 'spose I got Pompey in a chair, and arter spokin some latin and " lapsus lingo" in he ear to sooff his fears, and den I paw ober his face and trow de telemgrafic or magnitized burnin fluid ober he arms and odder 'xtremities, and I git him fass a sleep-and den when he am a sleep, 'spose ole Fronse Ginger dar, de clam soup merchant, should pull he big toe and ax him whar de dinner pot ob money am, an den Pompey should tell him so he kin git it-dat's Mussmerism. Wat's dat sister Jonson axes?" "'Spose Pompey woodent tell 'bout de money, wat wood dat be?" "Why, I should kall dat de blacker kind ob niggerism." De fungusmental principals ob Mussmerism am foun in large iqwantities in de 'lectric telemgraf, an am konwayed true de human body wid all de liveliness ob a fresh bunch ob eels; it am a scase article 'mong ole maids and ole bachelors, but young galls an boys now an en git a shock dat brings dem togedder like an arthquake an make deir hearts flutter like an newly killed chicken. Wen it 'tacks 'de human body dat way it am kall'd by us larn'd scollers Anamal Magnitism, for de simple reason dat de magnetic sluces t rush true de canals ob de body like de-de-like de-debbil. Now you all noe all 'bout dis 'culiar siance, and you kin hold your heads up proud as a lucifer match merchant. De collecshun lass week,'owin to de introcumdueshun ob de tree cent pieces, was not suffishent to pay my washwoman. Ef you dont chip up enny better, previous to dis forth, I shall be 'pelled to anser a berry loud call from de Souff, dat I recebe lass week. I am 'quested to state to dis congregashun dat dere am gwane to be a ball next Saturday nite at Yeller Cuff's seller, nie ole Bare :Market, and short-heel'd Jake hab learned de dance kall'd de poker; and anodder one dey kall de shotteef, which he 'poses to teach to "some ob de ladies on dat caison. Sam Ticklip will be dar wid he five dollar fiddle. No refreshments sarbed up widout de tree cents 'company each order for de same. Clam soup will be serbed up in tree corses-once widout crackor, once wid crackor, and once wid. out crackor. Dancin commence at early candellite, an' I am ex- pectedly inwited to be present, and if Florinda Jacobes will sustain any company, I shall be dare jis to keep tings all strate. I don't finit dar am enny harm in dancin, so long as you pay de fidelers   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.  prowidin' you don't dance for eels Sunday mornins down by de fish markets. While de hand orgin am playin de useal Ducksholiday, I will pass round de sasser myseff dis time, kase I is mity short, and I jis want to see who puts in de plate and who does not do de same. No. XXV ,   AM  WOOLLY HEDS: I is gwane to spoke to you dis ebenin' 'bout PROVENDENCE. Now, when I say Provendence, you must not 'spose dat I mean a steambote ob dat name, nor de city dat bares dat apperation dat lays a little to de leff ob de Sound, which de trabbler hears in de East ribber, as he assendingly goes down to Boston. De Provendence I mean sends us de bread and butter to eat, de cold water to drink, and now and den de sassengers and root beer, and odder 'freshments. Yes, my frens, de Provendence I mean, am a frend to de hole human race; he makes no extinctshun atwixt 'twene de cullored peeples and de wites, and derefore am to be fully trusted in at all times,-kase he am sure to fetch all tings rite and tite in time. Who sed Hallumlujah, dere? Look here, my suspected frens, I don't want no brudder nor sister to interrupt me by sich spokins out. in meetin as dat, kasg it trous do kar ob thort off de trac ob my diskord, and smashes my idias all to a poultice, or a pumice, its all de same. Spokin ob Provendence fetches to my doddle an ole story dat a ole Verginia darkey tole me wen I was a chile. You must noe, on a plantation at de Souff, whar de possum and do sugar kane grow, dar was an ole lazy nigger dat dey kall Proven- dence, 'kase he come dere in de middle ob de nite time, and none ob de odder niggers node whar he come from, and dey war' told Massa 3* '  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7078-00000030"/> 58       XMR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL S Provendence sent him, derefore dey named him Provendence. Well, dere was anudder nigger on de plantation dat dey kall'd Tune, 'kase he was always wistlin some new tune which he make out ob he own hed, and den he would play dem on de banjo in de ebenin, arter de day's work war ober. Well, Tune and Provendence greate frens togedder, sharein ebery ting dey got ('septin de likins Provendence got for he lazyness.) Well, de ole massa seein' wat a good, faithless nigger Tune was, wanted to gim his freedom; but he found dat sich a sementin fren- ship 'xisted twene dem dat a separation would be likely to probe fatal to boff, so he told dem dat if dey jintly would urn so much obber work in a gibin time, dey boff should be free. Dat make 'em smile berry loud, and kick up dere heels for joy. Well, in order to git de work done in time, Tune 'posed to Proven- dence to steal de march on de old Massa, and work on de Sunday; but Pr6vendence was too lazy to work week days, let alone Sundays, derefore poor Tune had to do all de obber work heseff. Well, one Sunday ole Massa'hadt gone to church, and Tune was workin' in de field by -de rode side, and Provendence was loafin' on a haystack, sunnin' heseff, when an ole wite mishenarey preecher man, who was a passin' horseback, rode up to Tune and axed him "Why he worked on de sabbeff?" "Kase," said Tune, 'ole Massa sed if we git so much obber work done in sich a time he would gib us free, and den you noe we kin raise de debil as much as we like, and stay out arter nine o'clock, too." "Ah," said de preecher man, "freedom am worff workin' fur, sar- tinly; but don't you tink you could 'complish de work by workin' a little longer each day ob de week?" "No, sar-ee," said Tune, " kudent do that no how." "I tink you kood," sed de wite man, " 'spose you try dis week kummin in, and putyour trust in Provendence? Well, when he told him dat, Tune tort he was a foolin' him, and he got mad, and swor'd, and sed, "Provendence be d--d; he'm db ',lazyest nigger on de hole plantation, and if I trust to him we nabber get free in de world. Go long wid yer; you don't noe who you am a-talkin' to." You see by dis fack wat it am to noe which Provendence it am to trust to.   SCIENTIfIC DISCOURSES.         9 I am 'quested to state to dis congregashun dat de row at de ball in de seller lass Saterday nite was not owin' to Sam Fugleson 'sultin Pacilla Emerline Stubbs. It was caisioned by Joe Knothead spitin' on Clem Tuker's new patent ledder shiney shoes. I was dere myseff till some bad nigger put de lites out. If I eber kotch de feller done it I'll make him sweep out de lextur room for a month for notin, and pay me a fine ch haff a dollar. Brudder Bumpton will please hand 'round de sasser. No. XXV1I.  DELUDED SISTREN AND BRUDDERN: Habin receibed a free gratis ticket for notin wid de rest ob do clurgy, to wisit de Tom Thomb cattle show ob bullefants, Barnums and odder queeriosities, I put on my new wite hat which Brudder Knox sent me lass week done up in " a horn" box, and seizin my big cane, which hab got de hed ob a jackass carbed on de top, which Brudder Greeley leff me to member him by wile he went to de Brit- ish John IBull show shop, and puttin on my spicks which I got, it am none ob your bizness whar, I wended my way to de carawan, and wen I got dar I foun myseff in a managery. Sum ob de pepil was complainin, kase dey sed dey cudentjsee Barnum no whar, but I laff'd at dem, kase I cood see him in 'most ebery cage, 'septin ob corse de cages whar de wild beastesses was. Well, I look'd all 'round at de old and young bullefants, de lie'un and de monkeys, wich all surbe food fur reflecshun, ef food fur nobody else, and I foun-almost ebery species ob human natur 'mong dem, 'septin de beufell cfur knone in de anamals ob fame as de krockemdile, and as he was not-dar I will splanify. his life, charakter, and costume to you, so you'll be posted up on de subjick. DE KROCKEMDILE, My frens, am a beast and a fish too, dat means he am anty phebeus anamal. De wise men in de East-dat am on de eastern shore ob  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7078-00000031"/> ; S      MR. JULUS CASAR HANNIIAL S Maryland-belibe him to be de connectin link twixt de Abalishunist nid de Maremaid, and de more I cogitate de matter ober in my own bed, de more I is led to belibe in de same 'xclusive 'pinion, kase de Krockemdile hab got a tale like a fish, so hab de Maremaid, dat makes him'like de fish and de Maremaid; and he likes young and tender niggar, so does de Abalishunist, 'specially the female gender wich makes him like de Abalishunist, and deir lub boff amount to 'bout de same ting. Dese fellers am alike in anudder instink, kase dey boff shed krockemdile tears ober de darkey race. De lub ob de Krockemdile am so strong for de darkey, dat he hab been knone to chase him on a sandy beech for a mile cryin arter him all de time. He am by natur like an alderman, kase he lubs fresh meat amazin, and he am all jaw and nebber sez enyting ob consequence. He am like de darkey too, kase he lub to lay in de sun and sun heseff jis like lazy niggar in fly time. He will lay on him back wid him mouf wide open till he git it full ob flies, muskeetoes, tomattoes, bumblebees and grasshoppers, and den widout ringin a bell or gibin eny warnin to de insec world, all ob a suddin he slaps down he upper jaws shuts he mouf like a sellar door, and wo be to all inside dem jaw. He lays eggs, so does a hen, and he am got claws like a hen, but dat don't make him chicken-hearted. Altogedder, my frens, at full length or kirled up, he am a scaley chap, and I 'wise you as a fren to cut his 'quaintance wenebber you meet him. If you should pitch fite wid him you will fine dat, like de skunk, he can do "much 'xecu- shun," as dey say 'bout de soger man, wid he tail ef he gets a crack at you, derefore, do as I do now, leff him alone. De dafkey dat was so liberal as to put a counterfit dollar bill in de nasser lass Week is knone to me, and ef he don't make instant per- sparashun for de rong committed, I shall 'xpose him to de hole con- gregashun, so Jim Crowlen jis come up here and git your bad dollar, and ef ydocome dat ober me agin, I'll turn you out ob meetin. Bradder Sillyous K. Muffin rites me from Long Island, dat sence he got married lass April he hab bin tendin a protracted "Lub Feast." I should like to tend sich a "Lub Feast" as dat meseff. Brudder James W. Cobb Webb will honor de company by passin 'round deousual sasser.   .  . '   SCIENTIFIC DISCOrRSESI        61 No. XXVIII; MY DEAR WOOLEY HEADS: De subjick dat I is choosed for my tex dis ebening, am one ob great interest to dis community. It am somefin you am all seekin arter, but nebber fine; you offen tink you noe whar de little joker am, but you noe sooner put your fingar on it, dan he arn'ent dar. Darfore I shall draw my discord on de subjick ob-- HAPPYNESS. Happyness, my perspirin frens, am de ting dat all mankine am arter, and human natur made man so different, de one from de odder, dat what am one man's happyness am anudder man's ratsbane; and so it am in de wegetable kingdom and 'mong de insex. De clam am 'puted to be happy on a sand bank at high water, and a bee am sed to fine happyness in a tar barrel, but dat's not to say dat a cullered man would feel happy a rolin in a tar barrel on de beach at Coney Island. De young look for it in de marriage life, and de old look for it in de grabeyard, but I don't look for it in eder ob dese speres ob life. My ignoramt hearers, I is, on dis berry 'portant 'caison, gwane to tell you what I consider constipates happiness. It am a clar con- shence and a full stomach; not too full ob de latter, but de former may be as puore and clar as moonshine. It am a glorious ting to hab a clar conschence so you can lay down at nite and tink dat you hab not injured nor ronged nobody all day. Den it am dat you can roll yourseff up in de sheet ob contentment and de blanket ob-inno- sence, and sleep and snore in your wartuous beds wid all de sas- sagefacshun ob a hog in a mud hole; and den in de mornin wen you wake up, you can walk forth in all your strength ob manhood; (I don't mean smellin strength,) and am not afeard to look you feller man plump in de face. Dat's de happyness I enjoy. But how dif- ferent am it wid sum ob you fellers dat will steal chickens and sich tings'! You lay down at nite wid your hed cubbered wid de bed  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7078-00000032"/> 62       MR. JULIUS OASAR HANNIDAL S close for fear de policeman cotch you, and den all day you keep dogs- gin 'round de corners in dread and fear ob de same anamals. I rec- omlect many years ago how I felt arter I had stole somefin; it was one nite when my fadder and my mudder wus gone to bed, dat I cum home late from a huskin frolic dat old master Wanramseller gib to de darkeys on he plantashun, and wen I lit de candle to go to bed, I foun a baskit ob clams dat fadder had bin and cotched in de arter noon; well, I sot down de candle and went at de clams and put 'em away mitey fass till I eat 'em a, moss all up, and den I go to bed; 'but I cudn't sleep, I role and tumbled all nite like a emty barrel on de brinary osun; I tink wat de debil am de matter? kase I begin to feel suffin queer in de bread basket, when all at wonce I taut I bin eatin a moss a hundred stolen clams, and dey lay like a leaden anker on my -conschence, and did hurt me like beeswax. My groans 'sturbe de ole woman; she ax me wat ails me, I tole her, and she sed it suthed me rite; and wood larn me not to meddle wid odder peepel's clams agin. I got skeard and rushed out ob de house, model artist as I was, and run to Dr. Bunsby's. Dis doctor was an Oila- packest, and he bled me at once, and den gib me a dose or two ob sirrup ob swill and ruebub, and by daylite I got ober it. It was a aw- ful nite, and it lamed me de wallue of a clar conschence. My frens, if you wish to be happy in dis world, do all de good you can to de poor, speak kine to ebery body, ef it am only a dog. Don't decibe, and lie to your frens; put as much as you kan in de sasser every week, and don't eat raw clams to any 'xtent at bed time, wedder dey am stolen or not, and I tink you stan a far chance not only ob bein happy in dis world, but you will occupy a snug place in Abraham's bosom, .providin he takes niggers in dat spacious apartment. I is 'sprised to fine wun or two ob de sisters hab 'dopted de wul- gar new Turkey trowsers and Ingin woman's straw hats, which Missus Hickery Smith hab been lecturin on. I tink it wood do well anuff for de young sisters, but wat ebber put it into de hed ob ole fat Ice Cream Anty Clawson to put on her ole man's trowsers and broad tale soger coat, wat he used to wear wen he blow'd de base drum in de niggar band a year ago, am a mistery to my caletation functions. She look so like a ole obergrown Rang Otang dat she make ebbery body laff rite out in meetin. Ef she cum here agin   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        63 in her "new custume" as she calls it, I'll 'xpose her to de hole con- gregashun. Brudder Slofeel will 'xceed in showin dat new five dollar- suit. he got on, ef he will hab de perlashness to pass round de usual sasser, and let him remember I'm watchin dem thievin irons ob his'n all de time. No. XXIX, DEAR SISTERS AND BRUDDERS: I is berry glad'to find dat a true sirst for-'nolage hab brout sc meny ob you to hear me lectur dis ebenin'. De subjick dat I shall spoke 'bout on dis 'tickler 'caision will be one dat shood kommand I   wide awake listeners, kase I shall- splanify some tings dat no fool- osefer hab yet diskibered in dis 'ligtnined country, and I spect to see my name emblasted on de m'ckutchon ob fame, and handed down to posteirity by my antsisters in preseeding years to come in konsequence dereof. I shall once more 'xtract my diskushan from natral histree, and de fust beast dat I shall 'tack will be DE RINOSSINHOSS. Some folks mou't call it de rinossincow, kase it hab got a horn on him hed; but he am  set down as rinossinhoss in de Comic Almy- nack, and odder elemwated works on siance, and derefor I tink he am considerable ob a hoss, and notin' a tall to do wid de cow speech- es. He am a bery fine lookin' kritter, ranging in sise 'tween de mouse and de elemfant, and he am nie de cullor ob a wheat and Ingin nigger, wid de small pox. He  'sembles de cullored man berry sumtously 'bout de mouf, 'septin de nose, kase de darkeys am flat, broad, and soft, while de odder am notin softer or shorter den a horn, and he finds de utmost difikulty in blowin' he own horn or  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7078-00000033"/> 864      ARM. JtotMR S CASAR IANNIIBAL9S nose, and derefore he differs egrediously from de editor, kase de lat- ter anamal blows he own horn jist as easy as if it was natral to him, and looks upon it'as a luxery dat neber 'pears to tire him. My der ignumrent hearers, de rinossinhoss am a amty phebeious creter, jis like de crockemdile, and he libs more den haff he time-in de water, and hence he am better off den de poorer class ob de rvite and de cullered peeple in dis sitty, kase he kan get a baff during de hot wedder free gratis for notin' wheneber he wants it, wich- shows 'clusibely to my mind dat provemdental natur takes better care ob de beasts ob de feelds den de corporation takes ob de lower classes ob 'siety. I gess I cut somebody's buttons den. One rea- son why he don't stay .on land more'n he dose am kase he got eny quantity ob corns on he tose, which renders he "long marches, , dredful measures," as de posel Shakespur sez. De corns on he toes am jis as hard, as de horn on he nose, which make de E'arned Goldsmith, not de larned blacksmith, class him 'mong. de homey anamals; and what makes it worse for him is de fack dat he don't no how to read de noosepapers, dere nebber habin bin no mishenary siety yet 'tablished to go 'mong dem to upset free schools, to larn dem to reed; else, dey could see at once what sab to use to kure dere korns. Ah, my frends, you hab no idia ob de ignumrance dere am in dis world. De hed ob de rinossinhoss am 'bout de size ob a young flour barrel, and he lips am berry much like cullored man's, 'speshaly when him  smile. He got a bery 'spressive, open countenance, and his food consists of ebery ting good in de market, 'sept in spoon witals and hoe cake, and de only reason he don't lub clams am 'kase he don't noe how to open 'em.  His skin lay on him back wid all de ease ob a bed quilt promuskusly trown ober an -emty barrel ob sider, and it am hard as de hart ob a ole miser. Mus. kit bullits fired into his ribs, insted ob hurtin' him, onla tickel him so dat it set him a laffin', and de balls 'bound back on de shootar, jis like a big lie 'bound back in de face ob de liar and slanderer. De bess way to cotch dese fellers (de rinossin-hosses) am to get be- hind dem and dob molasses on he-little tails, and when dey turn dere heds 'round to lick it off, jis trow a rope ober it, and lasseso him,* as dey do de mad bulls in Mexico, and den you git up foulr. Brudd6r Tom Huskings will please pass 'round de useal isaiser,   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        65 and keep his big blue eyes from peepin' under de bonnets ob de fair sex.  If eny ob de sisters and brudders wish me to lectur on eny par- tickler subjick, I will do so by dere leabin' a note at 122 Fulton street, directed to me. in an anvillup, No. XXX. CHLDREN OB DE JUBALEE: Dis time am de firtiest time dat you hab'sembled togedder to listen to de woise ob your humble lecturer, an' I am berry glad to find dat I hab gibin sich uniwersalist sassagefraction dat I hab been inwited to stay tru de summer in dese diggins. It am gittin' putty hot, and de nabers say dat de 'fluvior arizen from de ober crowded state ob dis rooms on dese hot nites, ort to be bot- tded up, and sent to de mare to see if it am inditable. Notwithstanin' all dis. prosicution I'll stay 'mong you as long as clams is eighteen pense a hundred. As soon as dey rise in price, so soon my sallary must be rised in 'portion,-or I jump aboord de ole ship Zion, and sail down de ribber Jorden till I reach de fair land ob Cannon, which is back side ob Juceelam, and when I is gone what will become ob your manners, your edemcation, your morals, and odder tings? why de ole he debil wid de cow split foot, and crooked horns, and tail like a krockemdile will come an' kotch you. Oh, you needn't trimble an' turn pail yet, kase as long as you keep my sallary up, I aint a guane to lebe. Speakin' ob Juceelam, some ob you no doubt would like to hear somefin 'bout dat inflated city, so derefore my lectur dis ebenin will be on de golden sity ob  JUCEELAM. Juceelam, my poor darken'd sinners, was originally originated and biut up by de Jews, an' it was for a long time as selembrated for de 5  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7078-00000034"/> "      MR. JULIUS C ESAR HANNIBAL'S sale ob ole clo's,pinchback watches, long guns, and paunbrokers, as Cheatum street am now at de present time speakin'. De country people used to eome in from Jursey, and odder furren parts, and git sich beuiful bargans as dey do now a days. When de children ob Isreal (ole Mr. Israel must a bin some pumkins to hab so many children; I don't b'leve dey was all legitamite) took it into dere heds to nimegrate to Juceelam, ober de red hot see, in de year ob de world 1, dere must hab bin a time. Dey all went at one time, and de army reached ober forty-seven miles and a haff long, besides de Bugage wagons. (I found out de exaxt length ob dis army by sebril nites ob uninnitiatcd labor ober de midnite camfene, in de Almack ob dat year.) Dis army, you will reccolect, if you eber noed it afore, was 'posed ob Egyptian Jews, guane to settle de hash for de sity ob Juceelam. It was led by ole King David, a playin' on de harp. It was not sich a harp as you see now a days in de pictur books. It was a Jew's harp, kase David was a Jew, and ob kourse his harp was a Jew's harp. Dese lEgyptian Jews war all cullard people, bekase Egypt am in Africa, and Africans am full blooded niggers, so ob kourse dey was cullered peeples dat swelled de ranks ob dis ober swallerin' army. Oh, my frens, it must hab bin a tremendus sight to see dese darkey sogers all dressed up in brite red and gould soger close, wid dere yeller fedders a yard long a wavein' a too and a fro, like a shirt on a close line on a windey mornin'. Talk 'bout you malishe trainin's 'pared to de gyand march ob dat superfluious army. Well, on de rode dey was met by dere emeny ole King Faro, (ole Kipg Faro am a good menny people's emeny yet,) who stood wid an almity host at de udder end ob de stone brige dat run 'cross de red hot see, and when de children ob Isreal got on de bridge he out wid he ax, cut down de stone bridge, and let 'em all fall in de red hot see and git drownded. Dey was all engolloped up in a moufful, and dere blood smingled wid de waters dat was in de canal, and it turned it red, and from dat time it had been none as de red hot see. I kood stan' here all nite, if it wasn't so warm, an' dwell on de ruin ob de sitty ob Juceelam, but time and de wedder for bid dat luxury. De congregashun am 'quested to bring as much peppermint essense on dere close as posable nex' week. I hab recibed sebrel letters from some ob de bruddren and sistren. One Sam W. wants me to lectur on "De Woolly Hors e  M  etddet   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        67 on 's De Beauties ob Natur;' a third, who'libs in Water street, who's konshunce makes him shake in him shoes, want me to lucidate on "Future Punishment, or de Lass Day." I will do as he inquest week after nex. Sister Florinda M1. Meltem want me to splanify de sub- jeck ob Lub, and as I wish to please de ladies, I will hab dat honor nex time: I 'spect de room will be crowded wid de sisterhood, and some widout hoods. Don't forget de pepermint and colonge water on dat tickler 'caision. Brudder CuffGriffin will please hand round de sasser and keep his eye skin'd for bad pennies. No. XXXI. BLUBED SISTERS: I shall spoke to you in partickelyer dis ebening, habin been in- quested by Sister Florinda M. Meltum, to lectur ok de popular sub- jick ob "UB. But I am rudder fareful dat I is too much unacquainted wid de 'fects ob Lub to fully deamonstrate dis all absurdin pashin. Lub, my shemail hearers, belongs to no ked'entry or climate; it am like genus and talent, sent to us in de middle ob de nite time, when we don't noe notin, nor do we noe dat we got it till, like de small pox, suckemstances brings it out; but de warmer de klimate am de hotter de lub will be, ob korse; Lub am ruff like de meg-mut grater, or de skin ob de pine-apple, and it hab nebber been none to run smoff in its korse sence ole Adam and Ebe was kicked out ob Paradice. De poets sez dat music am de feed ob Lub, but it don't foller dat music dealers am all de time in lub no more dan it dus dat people who sell pork and beans, or clam soup, am always hungry. I nebber was in lub myseff but gis wance, and dat was when I war berry young and foolish 'nuff to 'spose I could hab every ting in dis  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7078-00000035"/> t                             - t dS       MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S  ^    .                  / 7 elestial world gis as I wanted dem, but shad experience hab nocked dat idea out ob my ole head years ago.  You muss noe dat de kustoms ob de peeple in de ked'entry am berry different from dose in de city, kase dey aint got no " kustom house" to regemlate de kustoms for em, and konsequently you often find young girls in de ked'entry as innosent as blazes. Well, it was my lot, in my boyhound days to come across wun ob de kind I 'luded to in de lass claws. It was a moonshiny nite, and I was a settin in de boat on de ribber a bobbin for eels, when I spied her a settin on de bank ob de ribber a washin her feet. Oh, hallemlujah! didn't I feel quare! De eels kept a bitin at my bob while lub kept a nockin at my heart and pluck; she was de lubliest creatur I ebber seed, (present company allers sus- pected;) her eyes shine like two new silber dollars bound round wid black velvet; and her gum elastic lip open and shut on a row ob teef dat shineiike bull dogs in a thunder shower, and her smile was like de sparkle ob de litening bug as he sales tru de florifous air, her form wus graceless and faultful. Oh! I nebber shall forgit dat nite; de hot flushes'shot tru and tru my wains, and de cold swet stood on my forehed like de big rain drops ob de April shower; -wun time I tort she was a gwanw to spoke to me, and I held my breff to cotch de sound, and den she didn't say notin, but kept a danglin her feet in de water, and den all at wunce, when I tort she wus a gwane to sleep, she axed me in de moss elemfant manner, "If I had enny luck?" "Yes, indeed," sed I; "I kotch two mity big eels afore you kim, but from de minit I, seed you I kudent bob no more." "Wat's de reason?" she axed. I told her "I didn't noe, but dat it was a fac wat I say to you." "Well," sed she, Ef you aint agoin to bob no mo', You best put up you line and come asho'." I didn't want a second fnwite, so I skull'd ashore and tide de boat fass, and as I wus gis gwane to pick up my eels to take em home, she put her lubly arms 'round my neck, and lookin me full in de face, like a lion looks at de piece ob raw meat, she whispered- Lutff de edls be, And talk to me."    SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        ..9 Well, den I felt wusser dan ebber, and in an ungarded moment I 'lowed myseff to set down on de bank and make lub to her. Dar am no use ob my tryin to tell you how highfalutin I felt on dat 'tickler 'caison, kase T kudent do it; I tort dar was a flock ob pigeons in my westcoat all a flutterin to git out.  Wat's dat cross-eyed sister ober dar along side long Cudjo a laffin at'? she'd better quit sich goins on in meetin; it's abdomable! Well, we staid dar till a late hour, and den I went home haff crazy arterdat gal; but fate isshued a specific order dat we should not get married, kase it was oney a week arter dat, dat she war taken wid a coal in de hed, mingled wid de yaller janders and de small pox tinged wid de mezles and consumption, and nutwithstandin de doctor man gub her a moss a haff a barrel ob medicine in two or tree doses, she continued to get no better fass, and on de ninf day de ship fever took a round turn in her system, a strong appetite set in, and-and dat nite at 2 o'clock in de morning she died. * * Two days arter dat we berried her on de bank ob de stream, at ebening, while de cool heifers gently wandered tru de trees 'and dus ended my fuss and last lub scrape. Dose ob de sistern dat didn't bring pocket-hanshings wid dem dis evening, not 'spectin so 'fectin a discord, ken hab mine to dry dar tears wid; it am a big one sent to me by de Daucus 'Siety, and hem'd by Sister C. Coal. From yvat little I nose ob lub, I 'warn you all ob boff sexes to be- ware ob its influence. It will upset you kalculashun apparatus quicker dan enny ting in de world; it will make you as pale and flimsey as a wet dish doff; it libs on moonshine and music, and 4de 'mortal posel Shakespare sez dat it- "Fattens 'pon wat it feeds on," in his song book ob "Otheller," and I noe ob ioe 'fecshun dat wil bring a feller down so quick as an ober quantity ob dis lub; but de world kudent git'long widout it, kase it am de mainspring dat regem- lates de works ob allinations, and am found in large and small quan- tities in de bosoms ob ebery body, and you can allers tell who hab got  de most ob it by deir actions to deir nabors. Lub am de noblest -se. timent ob de sole, and I 'gin 'wise you to lub wun ahodder, be kind to Afl 'round you, and wen you get on your Sunday go to meeti close  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7078-00000036"/> 70       MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL 8 don't- turn'up your nose at dem who don't look quite so smart as you do, kase it shows a wicked breast whar lub nebber enters-kindness cost notin, and it am 'culiarly pleasant, 'specially to your worthy lec- turer. Ef de wedder keeps as hot as dis, we'll hab to 'jurn our meetins ober back ob Bohucken in de melisia fields, ef you ken be sure dat we will not git pounded like de poor Dutchmen did todder week. Sam Bucklip will please pass 'round de useal sasser--kullecshun berry slim lass week on account ob you a keepin up forf ob July; ginger cake, clam soup and root beer, am great temtashuns on dat day. No. XXXII. DDLUDED DESIPLES: il In quensiconse ob bein inquested by a brudder, who signs his in- quest "Water st.," to lectur on de subject ob FUTURE'PUNISHMENT, OR DE .LASS DAY., I hab 'eluded to do so on' dis refulgent 'caison. It is not my 'tention or wish to lectur on eny relighus subjicks, but to please dis brudd4er I do so for dis wunce only. Dar am so many different 'nominations dat blibe in sich a contrast ob future punishment, dat it puzzles eben a man ob my deep larnin, expended foolosophy and manure judgment, to gib eny ting like a solid chunk ob an 'pinion ont de matter. One 'nomination blive dat de wicked go to a big lake dat am burnin clonstantly wid fire and brimstone, and runs in streams ob liquid hot lead; dis lake am sed to be surrounded by de' mountains obsi ltand misery, so dar's no 'scape. Anudder sect tink it am a hotter place dan de rest, and" not sas, . sagefried wid de- fire and brimstone, wish to mix in a quantity :: y   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        71 assafidity and kiann pepper, gist to make it distingaree from de place dat de first 'nomination blibe in. A third sect tink dar am two orfull places ob dis kind: wun dey call purgetory, and de odder dey paint out to be as hot as lub in August. Dis lass place am for murderers, tieves, and sich fellers, and de odder am for hipocrits, wite liars, lofers, lawyers and actors. A fourth 'nomination discaird all dis kind ob punishment, and blibe dat, like de man in tite boots, we recibe our punishment as we go along.    Ole Mrn Sweetzenbugger sez dat wen we lebe dis atmostfear we go to annudder and lib wid -kidney spirits, so ob korse cullered pees ple will lib wid cullered people ef dey am good, but ef dey am bad dey got to smingle wid de wite trash gis de same as dey do in dis world ob sin and waccination. My poor ignumrent hearers, all dese 'nominations am perfectly rite, and ef you don't blibe me gis, ax eny wun ob dem and see ef dey don't tell you so-and I blibe dat it am a good ting for all ob us dat tings am as dey am, for ef de masses ob mankind war to blibe dar was no future punishment for de sinner, dey would run riot in sin and sellfishness, and dis selestial airth would be turned into wun wast slawter-house and carwin shop in less dan no time. Man wouldn't stop to oney murder he feller man, but he'd sell de bones to de button factory and de flesh to de sassenger makers de same as dey do dogs in dese days. Insted ob de kanals bern filled wid de blessed waters from de clar and coolin lakes, de kanalbotes would float in de blood ob mankind, and all creation would stan palsied wid a fright.  I tink de more feeble de inteleck obhman am, de more nesessary it am to keep dis -burnin lake in his mind, gis like my ole school massa used to lay his rattanon de front ob he desk and ax de boys wat he done wid it. It 'quires sumfin to keep peeple strate, so look 6ut wat way you am about, keep you eye skinned for future futu- riety, kase you kant swar you sitns on eny body else on de lass day, like: Pete Pifer did de stealin ob dat hundred clams on me. Ebery tub hab -got to stan on it's own bottom den, and- take de 'sponsibility ob deir own axes. Dat will be an orfull day for sum folks dat X nose dis minit. It am sed dat on dat day bone will come to bone and flesh to flesh. *-   *  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7078-00000037"/> 72      MR. JULIUS OSASAL HANNIBAL S I 'Now sposen a man start from here to de Ingen country, and in a muss wid de natives, he loses wun ob -his arms; he den goes to, ar- -lamn and gits one ob his legs cut off by de rale rode; he comes to town on de 4th ob July -and gits his eye nocked out by a sky rocket;  and den he sets sail for Caleforny, gits de feber on de Ismarass, and dar dies-dar he lays till dey dig him up to make de rale rode track, when him bones am used to fill up holler places on de rode; all -dis might easily happin, my stingy hearers. Well, ef ls bone comes to bone" on de lass day ob de world, I tink dtr would be some dodgin ob heds to keep out ob de way ob de limbs, and I also tink dat a cummity on researches would hab to be 'pinted to find de main carcuss. All dis, ob korse, am merely speckemlashun on my part, as de man said wen he offered to swop off his wife. Dar will be an end fo ebberyting dat hab a beginnin, and as de world had a, begun ob korse it will hab a stop'; but, my frightened sinners, you  got noting to fear ef you do your duty here to de best oh your nobil- ityf; letfnot your konschence be seared wid de yaller leaf ob sin, and you ken stan and look on de doins ob de lass day wid kompo- ser.. De brudder dat wished me to lectur on dis sujick I -tink muss be a man berry much trubbled in konschence, and am so much in dread obyre dat he won't lib in eny odder strete dan Water strete; do name hab a coolin influenza on he spirits, and de strete run along de riber, so I 'pect he tink he ken jump in wen tings cum toea crysis, but he'll find it's no use ef he am found rotten at de 'heart; old Jimmy Splitfoot will fork him 'up from de bottom wid de hook- on de end ob he tail. Now, as I hab reached de tail ob sumfin, I tink I better end my ! discord, at de same time tankin you for your airnest 'tention, and for wat small change you will put intode sasser wen Julious Hoeshed hands it round. Dar am a gwane to be a gibbin visit to hmy house nex week, wen I spect you will all tow de mark. I wish to reform dis congregashUn, dat de cullered preacherman Davis, wat was 'rested for steelinig gold watches, finger rings, &amp;c., -is hereby rid out ob -meetin unless he gibs me one ob de watches lnd two ob de rings. You now see how prone niggars am to sieel. r    Io0,XXXKIIt  MrY DEAR WooLEY HEADS: Sebrel ob de bruddern and sistern hab riten Bflly Dackses to met inquestin dat I shood lectur on de  j .    NEW COSTUNE - ob de ladies; but I don't'fine suffishent pint 'bout de hole wardrobe ob de shemale to warrent a man ob my expended larnin, and great resarth in de luminated walks ob siance, to fool his timeo id; I don't look 'pon de Blunim costune as being enyting new or un- derful, kase as long back as de oldest 'habatant ob de world (and dat's ole Cudjo Smock, dat lib in Hog Holler, on Long Island,) kan ecomlect, de w/imin allers did ware de britches, and notwidstandin destruggle, hab bin persecuted-wid so much defucally for so long a  time on boff sides, de- men, somehow or odder, allers-.oaiTd f second best. All dat I  kan, now persibe 'bout it, eben 'by'de: de ob de biggest telimscope ob de 'magination I got, am de faackidat de  wimin wants to put dem on inde 'eet. - Dey iab tilt-:'iibw  contented to only ware dem at home  and luff de men- iabe deh o  in de-highways and by-ways; but sUckcess  bab made dem im eiie , and dey am  willin to sacraface modesty to self pride, 'n-and e bdut de town in trowsers. But none ob de, sisterhoo, dit I  ebber node on, was ,ebber sassagefred wid deir dresses ilonga ag't, a-f kese dey no sooner git one dan dey want anuder, ef it ad onlyfor change.  Ole mudder Ebe was contented wid a   litfle apron matde 6ut 6fiBg le esl, and used to lemonade up and down de terpentine watI Obd garden ob Eden in dat costune as large as  life and'as^niase t -a S ta two ea old baby a  gwane into de baff; -but arter she let - ole apent coax her to taste de forbidden fruit  he-felt shamed ob he,  q. jis. as she' orto, and when she left de goMe  gates bi ^^  diee, and found 'herseff in de full sunshine hi '  -in, she made hAiit  tO amke a areas by pinnin togedder widittle wooden pins  4       : ' "#  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7078-00000038"/> - t.4     MRTLIUS COSAR HANNIZALVS she made wid a jack-knife, a hole lot ob big burdock lebes and pam lebes, and when she got it done she put on a crooked necked squash for a bussel, and tort she wus dressed to deff. Dis wus ob korse afore de kalico factories wus bilt-; but as soon as de kalicos come made de wimin cubbered demseffs up, and dey used to drag nuff stuff behind dem in a trale as would make dem two dresses, and dey used to hab sarvants in dem days to ole- up detaes when dey crossed de gutters. Well, bumby de wimins got tired draggin a dry goods shop behind dem in de 'treets, so dey 'eluded to patron- ize de coopers, and for a long time short frocks wus worn wid a big hoop in de bottom to make em stick out a feet; dis wus in de days ob leg ob mutton slebes and sky scrapin bonnets. Den arter dat delong dresses come in de fashion agin, and de Lord nose how long dey, would hab bin worn had not de corporashun stopped cleanin de 'treets, 'siderin 'in deir wisdom dat de ladies done it for dem, anddus sabed de sitty de 'spense ob feedin two hundred and fifty woters and now, as sin and wickedness keeps pace wid sibi- ,lizashun and roasted chesnuts, de wimin want to show deir ankils" by curtalin de dress at de bottom and puttin de stuff in de slebes, -for dey hnoW ware dese latter 'pendages as wide as de trowsers legs ob Dandy Lambert; and not sassagefried wid de, britches, dey hab, 'dopted de sack coat ob .gemman too. Whar all dis will end am a mistery to me; but I kan laff in my boots at de marriedmen, kase I aint got noboddy as yet to 'spute de pants wid me, and by de ade ob Provendence and de rheumatism I 'speck to keep out ob dat muss for a long time at least. :I hope none ob de sistern here to-nite will ebber make sich fools ob demseffs as ole fat Anty Clawson did de odder day when de cul- lered .sogers turned out, She tort dat ef she put on dat ole soger coat, a short petticoat, a pair ob trowsers and a -man's straw hat, .she'd be rite -in de fashon; but you see dat she cut it too fat, and you al laughed at her so when she come in de room dat she nebber - been-to meetin sense..  fLet de wite trash do, as- dey like, but don't you- ware de "new eotl4ie, as dey fishishy call it, unless you am gwane to a-ball at de M Major's or somfin partickyeler turn up like de 'ribel ob Fred ,  seglas, or Mr. Seeweed, or Mr. Garenson. Ef eny ob dese stin- (pubhed senestorions comes den turn out in all your strength, in   Is '1t C -flo DIsCooases. -    - % 'do -new costune, and welcom dem to your firesides, your bed sdea and your sidebords; dar -am whar dese gents want to be afore-dey will be ,sassagefried, and I nose now, my lubberly sistern, wid .Wat strength you would turn out on sich a 'casion as dat. I aint got no more to say 'bout de wimin's dresses.; LI nose bery little 'bout dem;. I nebber pried into de subjick, and I wants to nose less, kase dey allers get a feller in a muss some how or a nudder. I recebed an inwite to go on de targit 'skurshun wid de Tinker Black Guards lass Wednesday week, but when I found dat Brudder Beecher wusn't gwane, and dat Brudder Greeley didn't come.: back yet from Urope, and quinceconsely he wusn't gwane, I didn't want to walk behind dat sheet iron wite band alone, so I inclined de in- wite; but Sam Cowsnout, de base singer, who am wun ob-de mem- bers, brought me home a tin kittle full ob clam soup, which wus leff from de 'freshment ob de day. De clam soup was all dat I should hab went for, but I got dat and sabed mryseff de trubble ob gwane. Brudder Webb-foot will please hand 'round de sasser-and take all de money he kan lay his hand on; watebber you gib to me de poor gits, dat's sartin.  No. XXXIV. M1   BLnMED BRUDDERN: I  shill edify you dis ebenin on de oddities ob dis life, and odder oddities, inkludin-  ODD  FET,LF,RSH1P and odder, wessels. Do oddities ob dis life konsists in de kotenbila. tion ob ammunition to sustain de human body, and it muss.- bbett Odd,  of dis kongregatibi donit understan' de' fai ob dis diskibetry  id- ut myluteidation more close to de matter; I -shill deretfoe dj -rto  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7078-00000039"/> MR. JWU4w  COAS"HAXiAL S d4tdder seckishun ob de subjeck,.now laid bare afore yow intellectul fetres, and at once attack de Hod-Fellows' Hall. DOe reason why I catl it de Hod-Fellows' Hall am kase dat am de rite name ob de 'siety dat bilt it, as I shill fully probe to you aforel is finished my labors dis swelterin ebenin. I shill hab to 'splain myseff moss 'xcrewsiatingly as I see mrre ignumrent peeple here dis ebenin dan useal- Sum ob dose people lastly mentioned, who lib in de wacinity ob de Hall, ax me offen ef de debbil was not de captin ob dese Odd Fellers, kase dey sed dey seed de horns ob de critter a stickin out de -seller door, as dey go to Center Market a Saturday nite, and, derefore, I hab giben dis subjick my conwulcin 'tention. Ef, my frens, de ole debil hab bin dar your suspected lecturer would hab had a fite or a rassel wid him, kase I bin dar and seed de hole konsarn. I went dar alone, by my- seff, widout nobody wid me, and de Hod-Fellers, who 'peared to be berry'spectable peeples, aldo dey am wite, said dar was no debbil dar, and de anamal wat frightened my frens wus notin but de big he billy goat dat am kept by de 'siety for de use ob he milk fur dressin de sores 'caisioned by de hot gridiron, which dey use during de 'nishea- tion ob de members. I will take dis 'caision to say to dose who don't no de debbitfrom de he goat, to jis run your eye ober Oliver L. Black- smithrs Anamated Natur, and dar you will fine de subjeck sublimated to your repulsive intellects. De 'Siety ob Hod Fellers in olden times, wen Jucelem wus a wil- lage, wus calI'd de Hod Carriers, and wus allers komposed ob de moss s6spectable portion ob de wite generation, and dey carried de hod for de cullered Free (stone) Masons wen dey hilt de -tower ob Babylon and de Gipsey Piramids in de gully ob Gohogemfat. In dese days dey wouldn't hab no wite man to carry de hod for dem widout he hab a sartificate ob good character sined by two cullered master mason gemman-                 -  Who said "good" den? I neber like to be interrupted by nobody nor nothin wile I is spoken, kase it upsets de car ob thought and de hole train ob idias run at once off ob de track, and busts de biler ob de subjick. Don't do it no more; I hab told you all sebrel times 'bout dat -mne trick, and ef you do it agin ' 11 quit lecturin and go b  pri't&amp;e to a: clam butcher--I will. . fe :ia   I e!! era 'Sies-tykIab 0ongeadated sense dat tim,;o oib Ia4M L b adttae d some memnber who hab; no t- rde : M-a rkl yi   SOIENTIFPW DISCOURSES.  bautl see by dere books dat de sartificates hab to be giben as in idder days, and de masons gib dem work in preference to all odde-rkind ob wite men; but I am sorry to see dat dere am so:berry many por darkeys at dls time who wants work, dat de wite man stan but little chance to do wat dey did- "In de days wen we went gipseying," be dey ebber so suspectable.  Dis Hod Fellers Hall am a queeriosity ob itseff. It am bilt ob dark broun stone, sum say in honor ob doir early frens, de cullered popel- ation ob old, wich should duly be considered by us in deir behaff. I shall go all true it one ob dese days and layde hole mistery open; de day I went dar I oney got as fur as de lower regions,and took a sip ob Brudder Perkins' Newark sider, wich I found so mity powerful dat it opened my eyes at once to de hdle ting; I seed ebberyting I wanted to no in a glance widout goin up stairs a tall. Ef my odder duties don't stop me I shill go dar until I is able to 'splain all de hidden mis- teries to you all; but you kan make up your mines dat de debbil am not dar.          , I hab recebed "a kaW/" my frens-don't start, I don't mean a kall to go lecture somewhar else, but a kall from my washwoman, and she sez"ef I don't pay up dat five and atepense I shan't hab a clean shirt next lectur nite. I trust de doenashun dis ebenin will be 'fishent to get me on de odder side ob de see ob trubble. Brudder Erastus Mark Anthony Gibbs will please pass round de sasser, and keep his eye skind fur bad pennies. No. XXXV. SUSPECTED WOOLEY HEADS: I shill not draw my subjiek for dis ebenin's lectur from anybocy's writins, but confine my remarks to my own jurisprudence. -I shl divide my subject into seberal apartments,like de potk butchierdked 5*  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7078-00000040"/> y&amp;       MR. JULIUS COESAR HANNIBAL'S d&amp;ihog, and like dey bild -new bildings whar seberal families lib on Ome:fleor and take boarders. I shil-- ?Firstly, Tel lwat lknow and you don't know. Seconidly, Tell you wat you know and I don't know,' ' Thirdly ind lastly, Tell you wat needer wun ob us nose. Last lectur night, arter I had )abird here for tree long owers to splain away de 'preshun dat de moss nigerent part ob dis congregation had, dat de debil wus in Odd Feller's Hall, until de sweat run in tor- ments down to my boots, on which I kotched a cole in my head and got de toofake, I wus gwane home to my wartuous bed foolosofizing on de hebenly bodies, when jis as I turned into Anthony street a wite woman cum'd up to me and 'debored to swasheate wid me in de street. Well, dey had bin a washin de walk off war I stood and demud on my shoes made it as slippery under my feet as a silber dollar bill in de bhands ob a poor man, and I wus afeerd I should slip into temtashun, kase at diPtime I didn't know de cretur dat,'costed me wus wite, but wen de lite ob de lamp post diwulged de culler ob her komplexion I swulled up to stch a 'xtent wid indigestion or indignashun, I forgit now wich, dat my legs refused to sustain my suspended body and down I fell ker wallop into de gutter, and in de fall dereof, my frens, I busted out de best Sunday go to meeting trouserloons I got. Now dis is wat I nosed, and you didn't, and secondly, wat you nose and I do not, is how much you am gwane to gib me towards gittin anudder pair or gittin dese fixed up agin as good as new, and lastly wat none ob us nose, is how much -Bro. Staats am a gwane to charge fur de same. Dere- am only wun sich case as de fourgoin in all de yearly ana- mrals ob fame sense de year ob de world 1, and dat wus wen ole King Shibberm went up to Jubalee to fite wid de Falistines, for we see it - 'corded in de almynacks ob dat year dat his feelins was rent asunder, or like thunder, I don't know wich; ob corse, dis fack am handed down to:us in de Hebrewerd Greek language, from wich I translate dat de word feelins in dem days must hab ment trouserloons. -Dis fack I fine out -myseff;! De fite here spoken ob wus a fite as wus a fite, none ob your shootin iron bizness, but a fite ob faith wid broadax  and ar owhanr. Dere wus no Sulavens and Hyers in dem days, but dAr:wus fitin men notwidstandin, fur we reed in de piCtur book 'bqut on .big bully dat dey nickname Goliar, b'kase he used to go 'round/in   S-XCNTPIO DISCOUBS.          tot de taverns and tell debiggest lies dat ebber wus heerd, gettia lit'd like blazes by a little feller not haff his size or wait. Deycmet on de inclined plane nie de riber Jorden, and de spunky little feller dared de big lubber to moral kombat, not brick-bat, as sum mite 'spose--and den de big feller cum out and de fife commenced; de big feller struck high, but de little feller struck Hyer, which made ole Goliar so mad dat he tryed to git de little feller's head into his clinches, wen de little feller seeing his game, offered him t sling to make it Up, and de big fool wus green 'nuff to take it, and afore he node whar he was he found he had a brick or stone in him hat, and down he fell mid de shouts ob all Jubalee .a slewed man. De kornorer cum and held an inquisition on de body, and suffered up deir wardick- -  , Dat it sarbed him rite, Kase he haunt orto ite. De little fetler den went home in de land ob Nabbuckcasneezer, and set up a ten-pin alley in order to indulge his nock-down propen- sities. Some db my young frens here to-nite, no doubt indulges deir propensities dat way widout goin to a ten-pin alley. Brudder Ferdinand Romulus Augustus Gough Thompson Butts will honor de company by recebing de donashuns. Remember de trousers.  No. XXXVI. CHLDREN OB DARKNESS' I  hab s'elected my discord dis ebein' from a warm climate, and shall spoke to you in parteycler on de peoples laid down in de map ob de creation as de HOTTENTOTS. I don't no wedder dere ata eny Coldentots or not, but I don't blebe der am, else de noosepapers would get telemgraf 'spatche  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7078-00000041"/> MR. JWLIU S cA  AR RANXNIAL'S ftm dem sure; an' as I neber see eny from dat qwarter, I don't ppect  r am eny ai.eh folks a tll, unless it be 'way up in dem re- giosA T'eong de midnite ieebugs, war Sir Jolih Franklin am bin gone dese five ydars- Well, I got a letter lass weke from de IMland ob Hottentot, stain' dat a mishinary was 'bout to lebe dar for dis region of de hamisfoar, in konsequence ob de noose arriben in de papers dat dat dare was a place 'bout dis qwarter whar de peeple go almoss necked in de middle ob de cold winter, and dat all de houses dey got to lib in am wet sellers, whar dey sleep on de ground, ant all deayhab to lib on- am misery, wice, and crime, a cursin' and a swarin' a.ll de time, and stealin' and dripnkn' runs all de rest of dore days; till dey am tuck up by de policeman, who at once consigns dem to dere tomb, which am placed in de middle ob de distric, whar dey lay down and die like rotten sheeps. De captain ob de ship dat bring de mishinary am told- to sail up de oshun till he spies " five pints" ob land, and den luff go he anker, lour de boat, an' send de p asho6r. :No6, ty frens, I tink dese Hottentots hab hurd ob de "Five Pints" in dis sity, and am comin' here to deform de poor miserable diebls dat ernfist edem, while we, at de same time, am takin' up kol- lectsihun ater kollectshun, to raise funds to send mishinarys ober dere among dem fellers to deform dem. Dis sarcumstance make me recollect how ole master Snukem used to let'de dirt lay in him own yard, so he could stan on de top ob de hopes and see if he na- bors kept dars clean, forgitin all de time what a heep dere was on his own primices to'cart out afore he shood bodder his;hed 'bout his na- bors; but sich am mankind. We ken all see de falts ob odders, an' let our own take car ob demseffs. Accordin' to-dis letter, dere hab bin udder mishinaries sent here from de Fungus I'lands, but I understand from suspectable sorses dat as soon as dey hab ribed here, Mr. Barnum find it out, and by ellin' dem in dere own langwage, kase he spokes all de lapsus lin- gbes tone 'mong de tribes ob man, dat he will tote dem to de biggest' hotel in de sitty, gits dem in a coach, and totes dem to de Museum, and den advertises in de noosepapers dat he eotched a libe canabel by batin a hook wid a live body, and dat he kan be seen at two shillins -head; and it am my 'pinion, 'twixt you and me and de bed post, da dt ole he orang-otang, as he kalls him, wat he's got dar now,   SCIXTXFr O DIScoURSES.                8 am some one sent here by de Frendly I'lands, and no doubt he made a kontract wid Barnum to hold his jaw for so long a time, and den he'll go home and 'buse dd country. De Hottentots am a queer peeples, different from all odders,.kase dey lub money, fun, and music. Spokin' ob music, remind me dat I went to de uproar at Castile Garden todder nite. I smouched in, and got a great way up under de gallary, whar nobody could see me, and dere I hear all de singin'. Der was one feller come outto sing wid hair all ober he face, and I tort de gemmen wood bust dere wite krawats wid delite wen dey seed him. I koodn't make out zactly wat he was singin' 'bout by de bills, kase I arn't all fat, as we say in Frinch, in de Italion dialect, but from what I kood make out, by his actions, I tink he was gibin' illustrations ob de symtems ob de kolera, for he rubbed his hands on he stumock, struck he head wid he fists, tore he bar, and made moss orfull- faces at de peeple. Den be rushed up-and down de stage in a mity lot ob misery, kind a haff a cryin' and haff a singin' all de time. Den'he stop short at de foot lites, and opened he mouf as wide as he kood, and hollered like do debil. I was jist a gwane to rush out arter a doctor mnan to git him out ob de scrape, when all de peeple clapped dere hands and kicked de floor, and sing out " ankore, ankore."  I tort dey wanted him to ankor, or stop; but it seem dat'ankor am de Greek, or Irish word for holler louder, for den he screeched like a bulgine whistle, and de forty fidelers, led on by dat Max Broomsticks, played away like thun- der, till I tort de floor would gib 'way and luff as all afloat in de bay. I got skeered, and rushed out in disorder, disgust, and despair, and as I was a goin' out, de loafers at de gate wanted to stop me, for dey kept a hollerin'  Check, cheek," arter me on all sides till I got to de Battery; but dere was no check to me. I rushed true dem like a rush-lite. Arter all I seed and heard, I must say dat I dont like de Italion uproar musick haff so much as I do Long Cudjo's songs on de ole banjo.  De kolleckshun lass week was jis 'nuff to pay my w\sherwo- man, likein' ateteen pence. and if de 'mount to-nite ain't mores dea it was lass-time, 3Ilgib up lecturin' and turn lawyrt, r fori1Mer omn aich-low oocupashn  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7078-00000042"/> 82       MR. JULIUS CAESAR HAUrBAL 8 No. XXXVII. BRXDDEa S ANM SISTERS: My lectur dis ebenin', iA quinseconse ob seberal reasons, will be on de obsorbin' subjeck ob -'MALGAMATION. De word Amalgamation, 'cordin' to de works ob Dockter Kobel, on de "Anamal Probosus ob de Elemfent,n " was deribed from a ole Dqtch painter man, and semply mean a mixin' up ob de kullers. - De fust instinck ob de mixin' up ob de kullers 'mong men and wimin on record in g'ography was wen ole Massa Moses marrid a kullor'd Wimon, jis to luff he Africins see dat he was not afeerd to mix wid dem, in de fullest sense ob de word, and eber sence 'dat ole Jew matn marrid dat black womin, all de mean, stingy, ole wite fellers, dat aim too miserly to keep a wite womin as she shood be, am tryin' to inflamfe de'heds ob de kullor'd peeple wid dere 'malgamation dock- trin, for ebery now an' den we hear ob some sassy wite feller a run. nin' 'way wid -some lubly kullord gal, an' puttin' off for Boston, whar de folks like sich tings, as fass as de' rale rode kar kan karry dem ; an my frens, dis state ob tings am lookin' more omnibus eb- ery day, for dar am not an Eastern paper dat I lay my hands on but * wat kontains a kall for a meetin' ob de wite trash to konsiderde -queshon ob- abolishon an' ,malgamashon; but, my poor deluded frens, dis am all gass and gammon 'bout dese fellers simfersisin' wid de kullor'd race. All dey want am to sassagefry dere bad char- kole appetites by foolin' round do lublyest ob our fare sec. Ef I had a dartur, and she was as humbly as de rinosinhoss, before one ob dese wite raskals shood lay his purlash hand on her welvet skin, I'd do as - de ole Roman Warginious ob ole did, wen ole King Kruso tried to lay wiolent iands on de pusson ob he darter--Id smash him cros de chops wid a Baloney sassenger. I 'member Weil; wen I seed de actor man in de playhouse play dis good Mr. Warginius. I recum- lect now a young man dat was named Isilous, who was a bow to de   SClfNTXEO IXSC O  t .SS.       88 doctor, told him dat Wirginia, his darter, was dragged frough de streets ob Rum to de forum. Warginius look mite cross, and sed, "Don't you see dis arm, Bub? It am a Rumun's, and has manured de sile." De fac am, my sleepy hearers, dese wite aboliskenists want to swasheate wid de darkey popelation so bad dat-dey will come ebery kind ob queer games ober you to 'complish dere purpose. Dey only want to pull de wool ober de eyes ob your blushin', blumin' damselst jis iike de debil pulls de wool ober de eyes ob de sinner, and it am my private 'pinion, dat dese wite peeples am as far from gittin' into hebin as I am to hab rny sallary raised to a libin' pint, and de Lord nose dat's fur 'nuff off; but, my stingey frens, if dis state ob tings am 'lowed to 'sist miuch longer, it will trow de cogw'weel ob sibili- zation out ob jint, breek. off de axel-trees on wich dis circulombular 'arth goes round, bust de biler ob de nashun, upset de kars ob aris- tockracy, and. spill all society, wich katastrofy wood ob korse smash de ole konstitution, an' we hab to lib on de by-laws for eber arter- wards, wich case am a fac, derefor let it slide into your nolage box's wid all de ese and grace dat you would swaller a fried clam. D e "Hanabel Guards,^ de kullered soger fgnpany, raised in honor ob your poorly supported laborer, an -named arter him, went out on shuttin' iron 'scursion week afore lass. I had a invite to go 'long, but not habin' eny pair ob boots in pertickler, I didn't go. Dey had de darkey band 'long, and one ob de abolitions karrid de target an' I hear dey had a fuss rate time. Dis ain't haff wat de darkeys ob New York kan do. It am only a specemen ob wat dey will do if dey git a chance. I understand from Bill Ticklip, de fifer, dat a new darkey Company am raisin', to be kalled de Beecher Fenceables. Brudder Julious Henry Sturgeon will do de kongregation de honor ob passin' round de sasser, an' he will keep he eye skin'd for kounterv fit gold dollars, I bar dey am berry much in wogue jis now.  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7078-00000043"/> - 84      MR. JULIUS CESAR  AqNIVA!PS No. XXXV III "AWES4 AND GEMMAN,: I slell, dis ebenin', 'tract my subjick from de barn-yrd, and 'luei d&amp;t w4yott de nfraiersa customs and history ob-. DE DUCK,  Dteri am shrel kinds ob ducks; de ole duck and de young duck, de tdrri dtak and de wile duck, de seovey duck, de canwus back, de red heid, de briant, and de web-footed duck, all claim a place in de jgigh ob rtit'-ral juryprudence. - De-uber am offen call'd a duck, for de simple :sason dat de liquid words he pours into de listenin' ear ob he Wie0thiii'tkontaini 'bout as much common sense as de musical ef- fo-ti b dOb Bird ini questian-both am quack-ry. De dueki my darkened ftens, am a bird ob no ordinary dimentions, and de fast ting dat Will ttract your 'tention wen you see him, will be -i b6d, hed ihd legs4 de same. De legs are sitewated 'bout an inch niearer de the dan de bed, with tiakes deit tale jerk fust on one silehii de odder at ebery step dey take, jis likde de ovement ob de hd^dy ladies in Bioadway, It hab puzzled your worthy laborer along tiai to find whar de Broadway ladies git dat 'uthar walkl from, btit liftei sdei due ek prominade de tnistery an solbed, and de ducks ab ide *efletnete.  dify :Del hed ob de duckam a snoof as de lawyer's tongue, and he bill am 13 lohit a as bred as de doctors bill. He am -cdbber'd all obtei Wid 'fedders, weh- like my pocket-book i m ob no use to enny bbdy bit de townher De habits ob de duck am bad, ka6e, like itaty bordin-house keepers I nose wat ob, dey am nebber so happy as wen dey am in filth and dirt; de more mud and muss, de more delited dey am. Dr. Killinger, de linement man, b'kase his linement kured ole Aunty Clawson ob gum biles in de stumjack, dat 'flicted dat lady, boldly 'serts dat he am de only pure speciman ob de ginewine quack now in 'xistence, but I tink ef he cood har de quacking dat am goin on 'mong de ducks wen one ob dem 'finds enny ting good to eat, I   ACtiNTIrIC DISCOUtRSEa.        $5 guess he'd find heseff laid out on de shelf ob obskurity, fur he'd find dat his quackery was noting to be kompared to deir's. 3dly. De duck am web-footed. I don't know wat makes dem call dem kind ob foots webb-foots, 'less it am 'kase, like Webb's karacter, dey am always dirty and well flattened out. 4thly. De duck hab de 'wantage ob de ladies in'de splendor obdeir busts; de simetary ob de duck's neck am bewteful in de 'xtrem, and  de swell ob de bussom am graceful wen deir crop's, full, and hence dey nebber hab to resort to pads and double-breasted skoop net-work (wich am 'xposed in de winders ob a shop in Broadway for saiD to make up deir figor. 5thly. De duck am not a singin bird and nose notin ob music, not- widstandin deir frequent endebbors to imetate a cracked clarionet. I sed in a prewious claws, dat de duck hab bad habits; ef-dey hab dem kind dey got some good ones too, and ef some husbands I nose ob wus to foiler deir zample, de wife's wood uphold boff hands wid joy. De zample hear spoken ob means de good hours dey always keep. As soon as de sun burns a hole in de western regions big 'nuff to go to bed in,de ole hemale duck, Mr. Drake, collecks his scatterin forces, and' in a true milintary stile marches homewards wid all de pump and suckemstance ob a malishy captin on a gineral trainin day ; de ime- tashun ob de cracked clarionet am 'set up by de whole brood, deir tales waggles, deir bodies tottles, and home deycome as happy as a skinned eel, waller round till dey find a mud hole soft 'nuff to sleep in, and den to bed dey go and sleep as sound as a hog on a slidin pond. Dis, wid a few trifles, am all I find out 'bout de duck. You all know how to eat dem wen cooked, and some few nose how to cook dem fit to eat, and mitey few too, also, likewise. De sewin 'siety took dem trowsers wat I tor'd, and spoke to you 'bout tree weeks ago and reseated dem good as new; and I tink by uprite conduct (for I dass'nt bend in dem) dey will lass till de kon- gregashun send in anudder pair. De kollecshun dis ebenin am to raise 'fishent funds to constipate your lecturer a live member ob de Clam Chowder Club, wich. meets de year round at de seller. irudder Green will. please hand round 4. Pssenr   &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7078-00000044"/> 868,      M. tLUIS O JSAR  TANNIBAL'B No. XXXIX. MY IGtMRANT HEARERS: You will find de words ob my tex on de middel page ob de Almy- nafbk, towards de lass klaws ob de page, war it 'spressly sez:- - NOTIN' IN DIS WORLD AM MADE IN WAIN.' De more your poorly supported laborer cogitate dis subjick, do more he tink it am a fac; but it takes a foolasefer wid de moss -ril- lient tinkin' aparatus to find out de use ob all and ebery ting. Dar am few nose wat de ant or pea mire war created for; but I kan tell you. Ittam from de pea mire dat mankind fuss lamed to be indns- trius, and it was dis little insex dat teach de Gipsions ob ole how to bild de piremids. From piremids de peoples got to bilding houses, and derefore you see dat if it hadn't a bin for de pea mire de Astor House nor Graceless Church wood nebber hab bin konstrued. It was from seein' dese chaps bild dere nests in de sand dat Arche Textur was fust found out.  De nex insex dat seems to truble de peeple generaly to find out eny use for am de-'Skeeter; but, my frens, dese little trublesum tings am created for good and suffishent purpose, for instinick, how wood we noe how to walue a good nite's rest, ef it wasn't for dese fellers? Mankind wood regenerate to be de hog ef dey kood jis lay down and sleep at all times, widout an eruption; but human nater seen dis fac atarin' it in de face, inwented de 'skeeter for de peeple in de kedentry, and de bed bug an' flee for sitty life. Darfore you will persibe, wid wun eye shut dat dese fellers was made to bodder mankind so dat dey wood walue an' 'preciate wat de poetizer calls nater's sweet re- storant, clamy sleep. Some ob de 'skeeters am more biggerer den de odders. Wen I was ridin' de sircus dis summer, down on Long I'land, I met some putty big ones. In de barn yard war I put up was a big grindstone, and on do fuss ebenin' I was dere I was 'stonished to hear a buzzin' in de air, jis like unto a thousand locusses all a buzzin' at once. The   -     ;It SItCaNTIFI DISCOURSES.         87 singlet, or I may say in fac plural, noise proseeded from de wacinity ob de grindstone, an' a lowdable desire for siantifick nolage led me to see wat was a gwin' on at de place 'luded to, but I coodn't find de grind-stone, kase it was kubber'd wid 'skeeters, a million ob whom was a turnin' de stone, while a million or too was a sharpenin' dere. bills, preparin' for de bloody kontest ob de nite, an' dose kept up such a tokin in de 'skeeter language as you neber did hear i Some ob dese fellers was 'bout de size ob a two weeks ole chicken wen dere wings war spred out for a flyar. I found dere bills mitey long, an' bery pearcin', but de londlords was full as long an' quite as pearcin' to de pocket. Durin' my sojorin I konkockted dis beauful song 'bout de 'skeeters, as illustrative ob how dey used me. You can sing it to any tune it will go to:- DE SKEETERS. De 'skeeters in de nite, Comes at you for a fite, An' bloody de kontest am sure to be, For ov blood he'll get his fill, If he jis insert his bill, At least I found the case was so wid me. I lay an' kicked all nite, But on me dey sure to lite, An' frequently come cusinin roun' my hed, An' I'd scratch wid all my mite, %I On de place war dey did bite, But I b'lebe de smartin neber stop till I am ded. De sun he skorched my nose, And blister'd all my toes, To try to rest or sleep, I found in vain; For de 'skeeters war delightd, Wen dese bery spots dey bited, And make me almost swar wid stingin' pain. I w1ish de debil had de 'skeeters, An' allsh cursid reeter, Dat am made to bodderan' torment mankind; Let de bedbugs and sde feas Be trauSported o'er de iseas Den pae a  qutetneo w all s haU fin.-.  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7078-00000045"/> 8  -     MUR. JULIUS OESARB HANNIBAL S Itold dis bWuful story kontain'd in de lass klows, to long Cudgo, de SoUff Carolina darkeys who 'sured me, on de honer and suscepta^ bility obi ouller'd man, dat de 'skeeters in his part ob de Souff was ,big 'huff to turn de grindstone alone, an' dat dey went in hurds like de bufflaos do at Buffalo. He also 'formed me, dat dey offten steal a pussin out ob bed at nites, take him off to de odders, and den suck all de blood out ob dere bodies, an' luff em lay to starve, an' meny tavern peeples hab bin hbung in dat distirtck war de bodies hab bin found, missin'-in de mornin', wich body was stole away by de 'skeeters. In order to prewent sich dreful pussastrofy, de londlords got a big breed ob bedbugs, so dat when de 'skeeters 'tempted to steal de body, de beb bugs wood hold on to it, an' keep it safe till mornin, an'- in now a days peeple are most always found in de bed in de mornin' alive an' kickin'-.all nite. Now, I don't want to say notin' agin long Cudgo, but I belibe dat de facks Ire tells 'bout de 'skeeters am a lie; but you can all: b'ibe it for all me. I go in for liberty ob speech and konshuns, but I'll take my dinner dat mine story am true. De Dawcus Siety meets to darn de stockins dat-I bin warin' holes in for de lass tree months, at Sister Silwayer Johnson's, on Tuesday afternoon, wind and wedder permittin'. Sam Highstock will please hand round de useal sasser, and gib -back no change.                    E No   vXL    I  MY   'XPECTED PRENS  It was de 'tention ob your mue 'steeped laborer to lucidate on some 'portant subjick dis Oebeaing but habing recibed a lubin' letter from  Brubder 'astus B. Greedy, ,With I fink mite probe highly sasagefactory to you all .to hear,^ 'po to read de same, briefly 'markin' dat Bruddtref fy.:and me entered Yale College togedder,   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        89 an' kum out togedder menny a time. H;e used to karry in de wood, an' I used to dribe a smart bizness 'mong de stugents. in de boot polishin' line,-an' it was a loafin' rouni dis college was how I git my eddication. Here is war I fuss fell in wid de Greek, de Latin, an' de Hebrew, de Shewhrew, and de ;Raybrick, an' fell out wid de stu- gents. Here am war I fuss larned to lextur from seein' an' hearin' de ole professors do de same likewise. Brudder Greedy was a hard bedded stugent, kase when I fuss noe him he kud only read six lines in de spellin' book, but now he can read haff a page down. You -.will derefor see dat de reason I read dis letter to you an kase it kums from a feller stugent ob mine. De- letter am dated from de kamp meetin' now bein' upheld by de darkey pauperlation ob Long rland, twenty miles -dew Souff from here, runnin' norff ob de quaker, or quater, I forgit now wich. My memory am gittin' mity trecherous ob late times. I forgot to pay for a big bowl ob klam soup lass nite at de seller, till ole Arity Clawson bruffly mentioned it as I rose to go hum. "' Wither goes thou?" sez she. "Home to my wartus bed," said I. "Thou had'st better pay for dem bowl ob klam soup afore you lumber off," return she. "Thou shalt be paid promiskusly, or sooner, ef posable," said 1, an' do you belibe dat wen I put my hand in my pocket, I found dat I forgit to put de sixpence in dere at all. Oh, my recolldetion ap- peratus, like de old English bull's eye Watches, wants overhollin'. Ole Anty am down on me yet 'bout dat soup; but here's de brudder's )   letter:- SKUNKS HQOLLER CAMP MEETIN,I  Sept. the 2.  "BRUDDER   JULIUS CzESAR HANNABELL: "Noin' de intress you take in de Long I'land darkeys, I rite to tell you dat we hab had a great rewibal hear. Sebenteen kuller'd pus- sons hab bin sent home haff crazy 'bout dere latter ends, seberal more am konsidered under de, exemsize ob ardent spiritual tinkin', an' nine brudders an' twenty-two sisters hab bin conwicted. Dis ob course was all brot 'bout by me, and de lasi day I spokened to dem Iliad nineteen sisters laid out stiff On de grouni'. ,Brudder, Rufius  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7078-00000046"/> 90       MfI. JUIUS- CXE;AR HANNIBAL'S Arlington Johnson, from Catchunh, done his best afore I 'ribed, but he didn't noe how to put in de big licks like me. All he done was to git de peeples a snifflin' an' a little oneasy in dere seats; but wen I kum down on dem wid my elemquence, de snifflin' was turned to cryin', an' dey kooden't set still no longer. Dey jumped up an' down, an' screeched like a hog under a gate. One Brudder got so hifalutin dat he klimbed a tree, hollerin' 'Glory! Glory!' all de way. Den de sisters 'gin to git stiff, and fall down on dere backs an' clap dere hands an' roll dere eyes, and sing 'Sams, an' shout in triumfs ober de ole debil. It took me to lay em out. I spoke from dat good ole tex dat I hab so often spoked from, ' Flea from de raft to kum,' an' I tink I made out dat raft to come, some. I told dem dat it was'a raft ob fire an' tribulation, loaded wid trouble, misery, and sulfur for de wicked, an' I dwelt on de fack ob de old debil hab- in kommand ob dat raft, and kood steer it 'ginst ebery sinner he choosed, and dat at ebsry word he spoke, de fire fly out ch he  a yard long, anll' it looked blue an' smelt ob brimstone. One sister sed she seed de raft a kumin', an' fell prostutute from her seat in a mud puddle. Dis fritended seberal ob de sisters, who jumped up and looked all 'roun' for de raft. A little pepperment an' gin brot de sister too, who fell in de mud, and she rose up and went into de tent, altered in heart, an' all mud-outside. I felt sorry for her, 'kase she had sich a big hole in her wite 'tockin', an' she wood kick so like skitish hoss. But hab a grorious time dat arternoon. "All-de Long I'land darkeys was in for ten miles roun'. It was, in ebery sense, a bery strong meetin'. "Wen I was done spoken, de brudders an' sisters crowd roun' me to, shake hands an' sich tings, an' den ob kors I kissed de young sisterns; but I am sorry to say I tink dat some ob de black skor- pians gib me  de itch from de way I feel 'twene my fingers. De only ting dat 'noyed me was dat young Jim Skinkas playin' de fid- die all de time  outside ob de camp groun', It seem'd as if de debil sent him dere, kase some ob de sisters, arter gittin conwicted in de arternoon, would go outside at nite an' dance wid de low nig- gers, anI do belibe dat dat ole fiddel made more backsliders den enny odder nigger on de groun'. "'  We bin 'spectin' big Brudder Clem Green to come up from Communipaw, to hold forth, but we ain't seen him yet; but either   SCIENTIFIO I SCOURSES. .       91 him or some elefent come into dis willage lass nite, kase I seed a almity big foot print in de rode dis mornin'. Can't you come down for a day, an' gib em a turn?           - "Yours, respectable, "ERASTUS B. GREEDY, ESQ. "N. B., P. S., F. R. S.-De colleckshun was putty worth wile, an' some ob de sisterns trowed dere rings in de hat. I told dem dat de laborer was wuth his hire, an' so I raked down de hole pile my- seff. Won't I cut a dash dis winter in your York wid some ob dese jewelries! Ob cors dis claus am priwate." Wat you all tink ob dat, eh? Greedy was undoubtedly dar dat arternoon, but he hab made a 'provement on de tex he took, kase 'stead ob de words -bein' "Flea from de raft to come," dey am "Flee from de wrath to come ;" but he tort, by inducein' a raft wid de debil on it hold ob de Brudder, it wood be'n 'probemen 'pon de hole. Brudder Joe Scofell will please han' roun' de sasser on dis 'por. tant 'caison, an' look -out for bad pennies an' tin sixpences, kase 1   dey will ring dem in ef dey kan. No. XLI 'SPECTED BRUDDERS AN' 'STEEMED SISTERS: De subjick for konsiderashun dis ebenin' am one ob de moss inter. estin', an', in fac, I muss say, ingrocery subjicks dat eber struck de understanin' ob mankind, and it am ob de moss 'portance to de hole ob de human family, an' derefor I hab giben it my excruciatin" 'ten- tion for de lass tree months, an' on one 'tickler 'caision, wen Brudder Lemuel G. Broadsnout foun' me a settin' on a seller door, late in de ebenin' in a drousey mood, I was den foolosifizin' on dis mity suljick, notwidstandin' dat he spoke de slander dat I was drunk. I node dat some day or odder I would hab a chance to 'splain dat suckemisitance  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7078-00000047"/> 9     - MR. JUT-TUs aOSAR RANNIRBAL'S away, an' widicate my honor, an' dis am de time dat 'Irbed; I tink I hab konkluded de subjickfor eber, but widout enny furder diskre shunI will kum to de pint, as de ship sed to de kumpis. De subjick am de origin ob a 'culiar word in de 'Merican dialect, or how de word fuss kum to be used, and dat word am a well known word used on menny 'caisions, and am de word "AM. Professor Graham Greele, in his great work on "Stamina and Erective Franchise," don't say a word on dis sublime subjick, and Polk's essay on Monkeys hab bin insulted by me w;idout de least benefit to mankind, an' to me too. For fear dat I mite be rong in de pronounseation ob de-word, I tort it best to git some ob de lamed dis- siples 'pinion on de same, an' 'kordingly I rote a letter to Mr. Make- creedy, de John Bull tragedy man, an' to Massa Forist, de 'Merican Ball*tragady man, tinkin' ob kourse I wood-fin' out all 'bout it; but here agin I was doomed to dis'pintment, for dese two shinin' gas lites differed on dis 'portant subjick, as well as on all odders. I resibed Mr. Mikecreedy letter by lass steemer, which reeds dus:- No. 9 BUBBLE SQUARE, FRONT PARLOR, , "ONDON, August, 1851. "MY DEAR COLORED FRIEND- "Believe me I deeply sympathize with you in the difficulty you ex- penence in obtaining the true pronunciation of the word you send me, for I myself, my dear respected sir, am at a loss to give you the correct pronunciation, it being a word entirely of Yankee origin, which of course has prevented me from paying the least attention to it, as I never meddle with any thing of Yankee origin; but I may venture to say that it is an abbreviation of the word lamb;' and be- ing such, I would pronounce it on the stage as near like the bleating of a lamb as possible, and render it thus, La-am.' "I have read your Scientific Lectures, reported in the New York Picayune, and consider them great efforts in the cause of the advance- ment of science. ' With love and regard I subscribe myself, "Yours, &amp;c.        MAOI. "To Juatu  C aSA HAmnAL, Esq.    sc nrs n  rbscomR ne.        18 4 P. S w-I would advise you to apply to Father Ric, otetise ealled Daddy Rice. He would at once satisfy you on the sjeitet De nex day I resibe Maes Forist's answer. It reeds dus-- "4 CLUMPED HLt ToWiax, T THE iuRAIY t August, 151.  "BLACaMAN-- "You have written to me, and I answer. You wish to know Phw to pronounce correctly the word 'Lam.' I should add ai9&amp;er m to it to render it more forcible, and pall it LAMM, "N. B,-.Shanty Mose is the man to apply to for cprert ,infprra- tion on thispoint." . Well, I rite to Mose an' to Fadder Rice, de grato Jim Crow ;ma and Mose sent me dis anser:- "WEDNESDAY NITE  ' DAUKEY PREECHER FET R T.R-  "D De word 'Lam' in corse is Lam. If yer want any furder 'lus- tration ov it, jis poke yer black mug in de theatre when I'm a playin' enny time, an' ill giv yet one on the side ov yer cocanut dat wil show yer de meanin ob it.  N. B.-Say! why don't you cart yerself to Eplagla d? ur'd git in Parleyment in no time! They love Nigars thiere--" While- was a readin dis note, in comes one from Dt)dy jice. S SIXTH AVENUE, ARTER DARK, 1 "Wensdy. "SAR :-As soon as I recebe your inquirin' letter, I walked into my library, and I tuck down de ' oldest edition ob Shakeumspeare" and I hunted all ober it, but couldn't find de word in de hole book; but, Sar, my opinion is dat Lam am Sheepish, and am doribed from. Mutton-buck Mutton-ob course. "Yours entirely, \Ia .crJ -C '4         ow." - ,?  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7078-00000048"/> "      MR. JULIUS C AsARt HWr sBAL'S Well, my sleepy hearers, you will percibe wid your eyes haff shet, dat I was as fur from de truff as eber; so I had to find it all out my- seff-which I did 'xclusimly. You will find in de almynack, dat when ole Massa Noah went into de Ark, at de time ob de flood, he tuck wid him a "Ham." Well, you'll 'member dat in a lecture todder nite, I told you dat ole Massa Noah was a Jew; which bein' de kase, ob cose he darsent eat de Ham, for de Legislator ob dat day meet up in Albany, and dey pass'd a law dat if enny Jew was seen eben to handle Pork in enny shape watsoeebber, he shoud be biled in hot lard till he- am dead and de lard hab marcy on de sole. Well, dis Ham was a kickin' roun' de Ark, bb no use to enny body, and wen dey had been out to sea 'bout a week or too, some ob de- darkies on bord got a cuttin' up wid de beests and anemals, and got plagin' de monkeys all de time. Ole Massa Noah see dis, and he told dem to be kwiet, but dey wouldn't mindhAim; so he found it necessary to flog some ob dem, and not habin enny ting on board to do it wid, in a moment ob passhun, he grabbed up de Ham by de shank, and sed, "You crazy Niggars, eff you don't be still, I take dis leg ob Lamb and Lam you all, a side ob de bed." You see he darsent call it Ham, kase it was deff by de laws to tutch pork, and enny fool nose dat Ham am Pork fried or odderwise. Well, my igrumrent frens, from dat day to dis, it hab bin a by word 'mong de B'hoys, wet dey got nocked side ob de bed, to say dey got Lam'd. You now see wat grate research it 'quired to find out 'bout de origin ob dis little word, and I tink you ort to feel mighty proud ob your poorly paid laberer dis ebenin'. Will Mr. Icilius Brutiss Torqueen Lutts hand round de sasser, and be kereful to gib back no change? - -   SCZIEITI}IC DISCOWSSo .        95 No. XLII. B'LUBED SINNERS: As. dere am now some 'perence dat we am gwane to hab some fall dis year, I 'cluded to spoke to you on de influance de fall ob de year am s'posed to hab on mankind ginerly, an' cullerd peeple in partickler. You will fin' my tex in any ob de ole catakisms, war it sez- "N ADAM'S FALL WE SINNED ALL." Now, wen dis 'spressive line was written, it wus in de oleden times wen King David was in him babydom, an' Goliah was gis a raisin' mustaches. It was so hot true de summer dat de peeple wus to lazy to commit much sin, but as-soon as de fall kum, all kinds ob debiltree was started to intice de young an' wartus into de paffs ob sin. All de theatres opened den in de fall, jis as dey do now, an' you noe as well as me dat de theatres am de debit's meetin' houses, 'kase Brudder Beecher sez so, an' ef enny man nose wat debil's meetin' houses am, he am de man. He nose more den moss men, 'kase he nose dat all de actor men an' wimin, go's rite to de buttonless pit as soon as dey shiivel off dis mortail sail. De only reeson dat I eber go dere, or to de sarcus, am to study karackter, an' see ef IUcan kotch. Bruddor Beecher dere some nite a laffin' at de fool on de stage, an' I 'speck I kotch him yet. - I 'speck de reeson why de tex sez in "Adam's fall" am kase de fall ob de year was fuss foun' out by ole Mr. Adsamo, an' derefore it was named arter him in consequence dereof. De fall sea- son am a propishus season. Denit am dat de harves am geddered, de grapes am ripe, wine an' good tings flow throughout de world, a' sin an' licenceousness am de nateral konsequence; but den de fall does some good to, 'specailly to de fair sex, kase all summer long de infirmed or confirmed bachelor am glad, nuff to sleep alone, wid- no oder bedfeller dan de bed bugs and fleas, concompetent to de bachb elor's room; but whenfall comes, de nites am cold an' he shiversall ober, an' den it am dat he sets his eye on a sister, an' in de korse ob  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7078-00000049"/> 6s       MR. jlUS - CSSAR A AttIMAL'S human pevents dey git marrid, an' de next year de sensus man put down one: extra poperlation. So yew see dat ef we am prone to sit more in de fall, it am good ting for some peeples. In de fall de fashonable (brandy and) watering places close d season wid a hoe-down, when all de boarders ashamed ob de menn3 intrigs ob de seeson, an' for spendin' so much more money dan 'der! incum, dress demseffs up in disgise in -de theatre peeple's close, an false faces, an' den dey "dance all nite till broad daylite" an' go homf wid de headake in de mornin'. Brudder Sam Flatsmeller was dowr to Bai'Tto one ob dese shin digs, an' in a priwate letter to me dus gib an account ob de affair. I want you all to understan' dat I don't tin! dancin' no sin perwidin' you always pay de fidler. But hear de pistle:-   - "Mr. Juleus Ceasar Hannabul---As you wish to be posted up it t Il qpgs ob note, I tort I'd send you a few notes Itook wid a hasty plate ob I cream todder nite at de gran' fancy ball 4 Bath, L. I Here dey am all-                  - Went down there, refused admittance on .account ob culler, joine George's forces, got in, went under orkester stand, changed dress came 'out, saw a looking glass, in it Othello, all right, spoke to a purt] ,girl all dressed in wite, trimmed with red ribbons, asked her to dance up curm a navy man, cut me out, neber min', try agin, -saw Mrs. an -Miss Blomlier there, Mr. Greek was there, also Mr. Romeo, -Mr. Dal    -Kyser, de Baboon, Mr, Hamlet, Mr. Brigand, Mr. Debardeur, (who 'looked:-de bess dresed gemman in de room, unfortunately he war Obliged to'retire early on account ob de fateegasob de day,) an' a grea n- nnyoder selembrated carackters. Among de ladies I no0iced firss - she Who wS de belle ob de room, dey interdaced me to her as Mrs F-Pf*, but I d1 n t bhbedat -was her -name, kase- wh n Barker, de imlenmsibted hair dresser man .was dressi.^ her hair, Iwas kin his roon waitring to .hal my hair straitened, I herd her say she wanted t .lool like -a Bergee, ;an when she went out ob de room I askedde hbai d   Ssri mana what ^ramckter that was, -an' he told me it was aBere &amp;  wmpagne,; it was mrather a hard name to remember, $o ILgot him, tC [     rite It gown for wme, o I didn't midn. the interducin' .part, buti jivs spok' ut:n'l:ed,t k ari 4tis indiwidual hab de plesur ob dancin? widl M ., Berge ;?' She smiled so sweet took my arm, an' we wer on d L .f    SCIENTIFIC DI6SCCltSES.        97 floor; den her dancin', oh, de grace an bewty ob her ackshun dere is notin' I can compare her to, for as de poetry man sez-- She doth outstrip all praise. Wen de dance was ended we marched into supper, de table was loaded wid de good tings ob life, an -'shampain floed like Kroten, an' a good menny got drunk." Now see, my frens, what am a goin' on in de fall. De-same rag baby show hab bin held at Sarahtogy, Newsport, Nigerie, Cape May, an' at Anty Clauson's seller. I could go on an' pint out de sin'. an' wickedness which de fall fetches wid it, but I is sufferin' wid one ob de miseries dat de fall -bring, none as de rumatism, an'-don't feel jis 'like prolongin' df dis- kord for which you will all be truly tankful dis week I noe. I 'spect to git better by nex lectur nite, an' make up for all defishences. Brudder Huchins will please han' roun' him hat on dis 'tickler 'caision, kase his hat am a Knox hat, an' de crown am put in strong, so dere's noafeer ob de pennies a bustin' it out, like am -de kase wid de common hats; but aldo it will stan' pennies, I want you to-keep not forgitin' dat it will hold silver too likewise also. No. XLMII. BAUDDERN BrT F.B7RS: I bin so sick for de lass two weeks and a fortnight dat I airhoss konkluded to gib up lecturin' and foller sum more useless occepashuxn, but noing as I do dat de cog weeis ob cibilizashun wood git out ob Jint, and de world coodn't wag its tale widoui dam, I 'cluded to fifiish out my present corse and- den except sum kind ob orfiCe undef-'ga 'ernment-like odder grate men. I don't feel like trowin 'off enyo:ib 'doie solid chunks ob -'wisdom dis ebenin', dat cum-r agin your:ilAol ag  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7078-00000050"/> 98       MR. JUJ4fI  CAEAR HANITBAL'S box wid sich force dat you feel it-for tree days arter. In fact, I feel as grave and as out ob place as a herse at a horse race, but nebber. deless, nor nebber de more, I will try and splanify to you de siance ob- FIZ-A-OGNOMY. Fizaognomy am a twin sister siance to Freenology, and brudder tc "E Pluribus Unum." Mr. E. P. Unum am de man dat makes de base drums, as his name on de drum abecate or indikate, forgit now wich, and simply means, as eny fool can tell you, de fetures ob de face. Bill Hardpate dere nose dat heseff. v Dis siance am a berry useful one, and its study gibs infinite delite to de mind and body, 'specially boff. Fizaognomy, I mean de word, am deribed from de Latin, de Greek and Webster's spellin' book. "Phiz" am de Latin for face, and "og" am an abreviashun ob de Greek or Irish for hog-aldo de cockneys use itunsparingly-and de rest ob de word am so simple dat I wood consider it as insultin' your enlarged understandin's to 'tempt to splanify it. Dis siance will became more aparent to you, when I tell you dat, ef you understand it as well as I do, you kan tell a rascal gis by lookin' him in de face, as I kan. What's Mr. Godolphus Lutts holdin' down he hed fur? I wasn't lookin down at him in pertickelyer. A large mouf am a sign-post ob a ginerous heart. Wat de debil you all about, a grinnin' dat way? You needn't try to smile and stretch your mouf from ear to ear gis look as human nature made you, and you kan beat de world on big moufs.  A recedin' forhed, or ' horse fruntis," as we say in de book of 'natomy, shows a person to be highly gifted wid de siance ob imeta- shun, wich our race am superbly honored wid. De monkey tribe hab dis siance to a remarkable quantity; but notwidstandin' dar am no tribe ob beins on dis sarclarumlular arth dat I do so oncondishunly dispise as dis same monkey breed. Dey am too lazy to work to help de cullered man, and gis nose 'nuff to hold deir tongue. High cheek bones, protrudin' out on a lebel wid de nose, am one ob de urest marks ob anamtl 'pensities. De man dat hab dis feture mucm lnbsa meat to extortion. He don't kare wat kind ob meat it am, O lg it am mat and dar m 'nuff ob it. His grate desire fur de \A   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        s9 article so opperates on dis bump ob confidence dat he will eben eat sassengers, skins andall. Dis fact ort to be kept in 'membrance by all bordin' house keepers, as dey kan 'stinguish dereby a big meat eater from de feller dat is sassagefried wid mackerel and week kaughphy, and charge 'cordingly. Big front teeff denote a great lubber ob butter, and here agin am an instince worthy ob de 'tenshun ob eatin' house keepers, for a look at de front teeff ob deir customers will at once tell dem who it am dat eats up all de butter; and now as I got to de greasy part ob my sub- jick, I tink it de best time to slip off till next week, when, ef I am gittin' putty better a good deal, I'll wake up de wezels. Somebody put a bad shillin' in de hat lass week and I gub it to Aunty Clawson for clam soup, and I is afraid she mite pass it off on sum cullerd posson, derefore, ef I kotch Jake Somendike puttin' anudder bad shillin' in de hat, I keep his hat till he dereems it; so look out who you fool wid tin shillin's arter dis. I'll pass round de sasser myseff dis time. - Some ob you fellers wanted to 'pear mitey big lass week when you put dem dollar bills in de hat; you wood hab been ef dey'd bin worth de wool on a dead darkey's hed, but you node de banks war busted gis as well as I noe clam soup from currin jelly; de Pepil's Bank ob Patterson, Amboy stuff and Plainfield am all alike-perfect robbery to de poor man. I nose who put dem in de hat, and is gwane to pur- secute dem afore de tombs fur passin bad bills on dis kotgregashun. No. sLIV. MY D ARKEN'D HEARERS': De subjick ob my discord for dis ebenin will be "GHT  We. have sebreal kind ob light-de light ob day, wich am de bes ob all; de gass lite, de camfene lite, de taller candel lite, de drum. mond lite, de rush lite, and we wus to hab de pain lite, but-dat turn-  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7078-00000051"/> Q100'     MR. JULUWS CiESAR HANMOBAL'S ed out a sham, derefore it am a shampain lite, wich am no lite a tall. De wabes ob public 'pinion am much agemtated gis now 'bout de different 'lites, and sumbody has offered a partishun to de common '  scoundrels to prewent de use ob camfene as a burnin fluid trewout de willage, but notin am sed aginst it bein sold under de name ob gin in de tree cent rum holes 'round de corners. Ob corse de gass house monoponly compeny hab got notin to do wid presentin dis partishun; dey woodn't squat to sich a ting, kase de- burnin ob twenty tousand camfene lamps a nite in dis city don't 'fect dere in- tress not a bit; but de kine-harted indiwidual wat got up de par- tishun wus akewated by de spirit ob gass an filantrofy to hab cam- fene 'bolished, kase some green Irish shemale servants, who wus too lazy to fill de lamps in de day time, got burned wen dey under- took to fill dem whilst dey was a burnin. You nebber har ob a cul- lered pusson eben gittin deir finger skorched wid one ob dem; kase why? dey nose 'nuff to fill 'em by de daylite. I 'splained to you sum time ago how de gass wus made, wat de gass compeny wus detarmined to make de peepil burn at gis such rates as dey 'chuse to charge, wedder dey will or no'; derefore you git no furder nolage on dat hed dis ebenin. As to de camfene fluids, I don't noe 'zactly how dat's made, but it's some kind ob stued up alkehol, turkentime, sederberrys and skat-(miD-dam gin, wich am clarafied and fotyfied for use. Eny ob de'bar-tenders nose how to make camfene, and to dem I muss defer dose dat am- curious on de subjick. Sum ob my contemtable- aries call me a rush lite in consekence ob de lite ob my understand- in, and de way I rush tings trew. I don't noe who fuss diskibered de rush lite, de gass lite, or de camfene lite. But I is prowd to say i dat I nose who fust inwented de drummond lite. Dis wast brilliant luminary am made by mixin up lime and sum odder tings togedder and settin it a fire; and Prof. Gassy, in his History obRumun Despots, instinctly sez dat it was cullered man fuss diskibered de art ob slack-- in lime. Well, ef de cullered man foun out by his own free will and a cord how to slack de lime, wat's de reson he didn't fine out de drummond lite? Dat's wat I ax you, you brack skorpions. I wunce herd all 'bout how dat lite wus diskibered, an I blebe it am a fac. You see, de diskiberer ob dis lite wus not named Drum-. mond a tall; he, wus a cullered man, a drummer in de darkey   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        101 band-a base drummer ;and wun day, meny years long time ago, de band wus a cumin down de Bowery, and he wus a cuttin up sum ob his monkey shines, as de nigger base drummers use to- do, trowin up de drum sticks in de air, and a foolin his time for de ed- dyfication ob de side walk kummity, wen all at wunce he hit he own hed a terabel crak instid ob de drum, wich make de fire fly out ob he eyes. "Wat's de matter wid you?" axed Bill Ticklip, de fifer. "I seed a lite," sed de drummer, and dat wus de fuss drummin lite eber seen by eny body, and dat's de way it fuss got into eny    body's hed-it wus beat in. Well, de darkey went home and laid down, had a kind ob dream, and in two or tree day arter dat Mister Barnum 'nounced a drummond lite on de top ob de Museum. Which fully probes dat it was diskibered by de darkey, or else I don't no possum fat when I see it. I hab bin axed wat we lite de lectur room wid by sum wite peepils; I allers tell dem dat de lite ob de ladies eyes am suffishent to 'luminate de hall. But, 'mong ourseffs, I wish to hab a word to say 'bout litein up here nites. De penny taller candels run so and git into de brudders' hair in sich quantities, and run trew de sisters' bonnets, dat no lady kan set near dem; derefore I move, second, and carry de resolution, dat we git camfene lamps in spite ob de frowns or retreaties ob de gass-house menopoly; derefore dere muss be a kollecshun taken up to portray de 'spences ob de same. Dar also muss be 'nuff ober to by me sum red flannil, kase de Daucus 'Siety aint got none on hand; it wus all sent to de poor African childrin on de coast ob de Tongo Kongo Islands, wid fore dozen fine tooff kombs. Dar muss be a stobe got too, and we muss call on de Cole Bank afore long. Brudder Sam Goathead will hand round de useal sasser.  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7078-00000052"/> 102       R. JULIV COAAR HANNIBAL'S No. XLV. 'SPECTED BRUDDERN AND 'STEEMED SISTERS: I hab recebed a inquest, sined by sebril ob. dis kongregashun, to lecture on de BANK PANICK, and, derfor, 'corin to Gunter, as I is bound to please my consticke- wents, I will do de same on dis:'portant 'caision. I will fuss splain de origin ob de word Bank, and nex de word PAnick. Bank, you noe, means bank; dere am a good many banks; dere's do sand bank, de clam bank, de mossy bank, de money bank, and 'Coon Smith's cole bank, wat he started at de time ob de cur- lered pepil's Conwenshun, dat conwened lass spring. So now you all noe 'zackly wat de meanin ob de word bank am. Panick am deribed from two words-fuss, pan am taken from stew-pan, and ick am taken from de word ipacackuanna, which am a nasty drug used by de qwack doctor man's to make pepil sick to de stum- jack; derefore, I tink de hole am, dat a Bank Panick am a sick- enin stew. De bank panick jis now am all 'caisoned by one bank called de Metrowpolatin Sand Bank, who took it into its hed to cause a run on all de Clam Banks and make dem shell out' so 'cordingly one -day it broke loose and oberflowed de clam banks, and dat's de rea- son de clams hab bin so mity scarce in Anty Clawson's clam soup fur de lass two weeks, kase she told me so herseff, and she orto noe. Well, wen clams become scarce money become scarce, kase a scarcety ob clams allers 'duces a titeness in de money market, den all de pepil git in a stew 'bout de same, and dat wat am mont by de panick. De wite pepil say dat dis present panick am caused by a "run on de country banks ;"I allers tort a run on de banks in do country wus healfy exemcise, ef you don't fall off in de riber. De bank panick don't 'fect me none, kase I nebber git a hole dol- lar at a time; de lowness ob my sallary don't 'low it, and it nebber   SCIENTIFIC DISCOtRSES.       103 cums in de sasser widout it's broke afore it goes in, and ob corse it kan't broke agin. Blessed am de poor, kase dey got no bank bills to git broke in deir pockets. De brokers am de chaps dat make de money out ob de panicks. May be you don't noe who de brokers am. Well, den, I tell you; dey am a set ob kind a leff han gamblers what hold big pewes in de big fashionable churches jis to make dem 'spectable; well, dese fellers buy'd vp all de clams in market afore de -Metrowpolitin Sand Bank oberflowed the Clam Banks, and den dey git heaby profit on de clams. Dese fellers got no konshunce, and dey go on in sin from day to day till dey am too old to tell a V from a saw- buck, and wen dey lebe dis tecelestial speer dey tink dey will fool ole Jimmy Squar Foot by takin one ob Phillips' fire anahighlators wid dem; but I warn dem in time to let sich torts as dat waft down de wabes ob obscurity, kase Massa Barnum will nebber in- went one big 'nuff to put out de 'fernal regions, aldo he will put out a block ob bildins. Dese fellers allers git rich, and you noe it am as hard fur a rich man to enter de kingdum ob hebin as it is fur-me to git my sallary raised to a libin pint. I 'spect dar'll be a run on 'Coon's cole bank soon, kase it am a gittin cold wedder, and de cullered peepil muss hab haff a peck a piece soon to keep deir shin warm and de heel comfortable--but here agin de brokers hab bin to work and broke all de cole up in lit- tle pieces, so dat haff a peck won't be mor'n a qwart. Ef you had all chipped up and raised a cole bank for me, I'd a lumped de job wid you. I recebed a letter lass week from Brudder "Squash," ob New Orleahs, wharin he say he hab good time readin my lecturs to de brudders and sisters in dat qwarter. He must hab had a bad time wid ole Jake fur not shoutin at de rite time; I don't wunder he pull de wool, and den to try to pass a tree cent piece in de haul top'd de shylaps intirely. Brudder Sqwash" muss rite agin soon. Brudder Hyatt, in Fulton street, nie to de Broadway, de clean shirt man, sent me a role ob flanel fur de little children on de Kongo Won- go Islands. Dar isn't eny sich islands as dem, so ob corse I take it fur myseff. I only wun a gammonin 'bout dem children. Brudder Scribner will please hand round de sasser.  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7078-00000053"/> 4  .4    MR. JULIUS CBSAR HANNIBAL'S No. XLVI. DELlTDED BRUDDERS: Widout wishin to be personal to enybody in dis congregashun, I will lectur dis ebenin on dat long eared anamal whose perlite cog. onomy am  I "JOHN HOSS." Ole Mr. Adams, when he called ober de names ob de different crit- turs to old Mudder Ebe in de garden ob Eben, he called dis one by he surname, de Ass, out ob true respect, no doubt; but de ole Nigger- buckerYankeys, becomin more famelyear wid him, gib him a cristian name. I cood neber fine out who it wus dat fust called him John, but dese ole Niggerbuckers, wid de same pertinashusness dat dey call Mr. Webster "Dan," Mr. Forrest "Ned," and Brudder Seward "Bill," called dis anamal "Jack," as soon as dey foun dat dey cood be do least famelyear wid him. I don't noe whar de fuss John Hoss cum from, but we read 'bout him in anchent days in anchent history, dat sum ob dese long ear chaps went on fore legs and sum on two den as in now a days, 'cord- ing to Joe Sefus, George Liphard, Puffer Hetskins, and odder grate heds. I tried to fine out de oragin ob de donkey by goin to de Mu- seasm, but not findin one in de hole show, not eben in de Happy Family, I 'eluded I was- a Jack myseff and so gib up de sarch; but dis I is sassagefried ob, dat he am de oldest beast libin, or else his 'countenance and his mobements greatly belie him. I hab offin tort in deep moments ob reflexshun dat de "John Hoss" and de cullered man am berry much alike, and wid all dew respect to ,boff I say it; and why am you boff alike? I will tell you: it am bekase you am boff de moss neglected and hard workin critturs alive, ef you git beat long 'nuff to git you at it. De master ob dis anamal nebber tinks'bout curryin' him down like de odder bosses ob de same specie, derefore, he go long so shamed dat he wont hold up he hed up, and so it am wid de darkey. Who cars how he goes, and who, I ax you, cars how I go? Ef it wasent for de Dawcus'Siety I'd go lookin   SOIENSTMO DISCOXRSEM.        105 wus dan de Jack for all you'd car. History sez dat dis Johnny Hoss hab got a grate inclinashun to roll in de dirt; here's whar he 'sembles de brack man, kase I fine a great meny laid out on de sellur doors and on cotton bales long de warfs, in de sunshine, and sum I fine eben on de pabement fass asleep. Dis am all berry muley, my frens. 2dly. Dis anamal hab de longest hed ob eny odder beast ob his size, septin de polytishun, and in meny instances de former hab got de moss branes, still de latter should not be 'sidered below de former but 'bout on a lebil. His ears am long like de rabbits, and and am berry good for making baccy pouches on de plantashuns. His hed am shaped sumfin like a flour barrel wid a skin drawn ober it, and his eyes look like de two bung holes. His mouff am shaped a good deel like de darky's only he got radder de moss lip ob de two, septin wen de darkey gits a jawin. In deir diet too dey boff 'semble each odder prodigious, fur it am a 'stablished fac dat de darky will eat possum fat, hoe cake, raw clams, hominy, and salt junk, (not Chinese junks,) and sich korse kine ob feed, and Mr. John Donkey will eat skunk's cabbage, thistles, burdock, gum umphrey root and bilberries,lderefore, whar's de difference? But in de drinkin bizness I tink de Jack hab got de bess ob us, kase natrul history 'spressly sez dat he will not. drink water dat is de least riled or dirty, but will trabel a grate dis- tance to drink out ob sum pure bubblin brook whar he drink before; it is not so wid de darkey, he will drink enyting from camfene gin up to brandy smashers. In dis 'spect I tink de donkey nose de moss. I nebber seed a fore legged John Donkey drunk, but I hab met, meny on two legit and dat is de way I node de two legged ones from de fore legged ones. Dese same smashes hab smashed meny a man's karacter. History riso sez dat dis anamal hab got 'markable instinct ob its home. Ef it hab got a good stable you may ship him off for tousands ob miles and ef his foot touches de ert he will fine his way home agin widout a pair ob kumpusses, chart or map ob de state in he pocket.  How like a darky he am here agin, kase ef you gib one ob de latter a good bed to sleep on and plenty to eat he am ginerally found dar sebeir days in de week and Sundays too. To sum it all up into one claws, dar am no two anamals so alike and unlike as de donkey and de darkey in de crystalized kingdom ob de ert. Dar is one 'culiar ting 'bout de beast dat I hab not yet told you 'bout; dat is de fac ob hiU 8" .    .6  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7078-00000054"/> 106      MR. JTLIUS CiESAR 'UHANNIBAL'S alwers habin a cross on de back-one streak runnin down debaclk, 'pine bone to de tale, and de odder run cross he back by he fore shol- gers: no foolosefer hab 'counted fur dis finominum, but I tink it means to show de warld dat he a cross breed ob sum kine, and dat he am a mitey cross and stubborn chap, jis like de darkey wen lie am a mind to be, wich we all noe am a fac. Dat's all I nose 'bout de John Hoss pro or con, and I 'spect to hear ob dis lectur bein read afore de New York Historical 'Siety, and myseff made a berry orninary member. Prebious before de kollecshun am taken up, I wish to state, by de inquest of Sister Lukresia Notts, dat de 1"Cullered Woman's Rights Conwenshun" will be held at de seller on Tuesday arternoon and ebening wedder permittin, nex night, wedder or no. Sebrel extin- guished sisters will be dar sure, in de Blumer kustom, and distresses am'spected from Sister Nucles, and Sister Pine, Esqress, Lukresia Nott, Lucy Brick, Abby Felly and Old Aunty Clawson. Brudder Greedy hab 'cluded to be presumdent, purvided de biggest bowl ob clam soup be sarved to him, and I 'spect to be dar myseff. Lastly, Will Brudder Nox please to pass roun he hat dis time. No. XLVII. BENITEP FELLER SITTYZANS:  I shel draw de subjick ob my lectur dis evenin once more frum de anamal kingdum kum, and I 'tend to interduce to you one ob you Oldest frens whose name, when you har it, will make you blud tingle wid delite, and you lips smack wid joy. You will no dout recomlect seenes in you past life, wile huntin dis crittur, dat will sharpen you  appetite like de grinestone; you muss all noe by dis time dat I mean to 'lucidate de manners and kustoms ob DE POSSUM. De possum am a animal de same as man, and he hab a grate maxny ob de tricks ob man; one ob de tricks dat dey lamed frum man am o If   BCIENTI'FI DISCUOU1SISS.       UV I de trick ob stayin out all nite, fur you muss noe dat Mr. Possum sleeps moss all day and den loafs 'bout in de nite time, derefore dat am de reason dat dey am hunted in de middle ob de nite time jis like de ole coon. De possum am a kurious kind ob crittur, 'bout de size obt a kobn only not haff so sassy. His skin fits him wid 'bout de same titeness and grace as a bed quilt would fit a emty barrel ob flower. He hab got pockets under each arm in he fur skin obercoat, whar he carries his young children, and it am a beuful site to see de ole one pretendin to be asleep and de little ones all playin 'round, sum wid deir heds jis out ob de pockets and odders climbin all ober him; den ef you want to see fun, jis wissel fur a 'maginary dog, and see de way dese little rat lookin fellers will scrambel in de pockets, and see de ole one make tracks fur de tallest tree he can find whar he sure ob safety. De possum aint got no feet, de hole four extremities am hans; he back foots am hans and so am he fore foots; wich enable him to crawl up a small twine wid de same ease and quickness dat he clime up a tree. His tale am ob de gratest use to him, jis like Boz's tales amuto him, fur he kan hang by it and sleep all dey- way out on de end ob a limb, whar de han ob de sarchin darky kant noless him. You hab all herd, no dout, ob de long Yankee, Who hab sich a big nose he cood hang by it to de limb ob a cherry tree and pick wid boff hans, but my stingy hearers, de possum kan do more, he kan hang by his tale, eat and fife wid all fore ob his hans, derefore de possum hab de 'wantage ob de Yankee. Dar am a kurious ting conneckted wid de mouf ob dis anamal. It am shaped a good deel like de little pigs, but dat aint nuffin; he got ears too like de pig, dat aint nuffin; but de kurious part ob de mouf am dis: on he lower jaw he got jis twenty-five teef and on he upper one he only got two dozen and one, wich I tink fully 'counts fur he bitin and scratchin 'pensities. De possum 'semble de darky in sum tings. He lubs young chickens jis like darkey, and in order to 'dulge de appetite he will steel dem jis like darkey. In size dis anamal am 'twene de rackcoon and de tom, cat, in color Don Dorety Gray, in specy possum, in disposition old womany. I hab dus fur spoked only ob de crittur wile he am alibe, but he is one ob dem anamals dat de deaderer he am de more usefl am ?  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7078-00000055"/> 108      MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S to mankine. De poet and de author am more 'preciatld arter dey am ded, and so am a hen, a hog, a bullock, and de possum. Who in dis wast assemblege hab not luxcurated on de fat ob dis chap till he face shine all ober like glass botttle, and de nose git so greesy dat it coodn't be blowed widout de aid ob ashes on de fingers? Who, I ax you, in dis crowd, hab not rose wid de moon in de nite and went out to hunt dese beuful critturs and brot 'em home and cook 'em fur brakefass long wid de hoe cake and jonny cake. I see by your smiles dat meny ob de older pussons har present hab 'dulged in dat lucretive sport, and kan fooly testify to my 'stounding nolage ob de crittur in debait. Darfor I lebe de subjick wid pride and pomposity. De cullerd Wimin's Rite Con-wench-on wus held at de seller on Tuseday nite 'cordin to 'nouncement, but some he darkys got in and none ob de sisters cood put 'em out and dey kicked up a-row. Anty Clawson led off in de speachifyin. She sed dat she marrid ole Jake Clawson fur lub, dat wen she marrid him he hadn't a second shirt to he back, but she went to work a takin in washin and irunin and soon got him two good ones. Dey war pieces leff ober, and dat, notwid- standin her goodness to him, he would " nock down" money on her whenebber he cood git a chance., She sed. he sawd a lode ob wood dat day and only brot home ten pense out ob de two shillins and swore he loss de ress. Now I don't want to say nuffin agin Anty Clawson, but I nebber node a washwoman ebber had eny shirts leff ober; dat looks like "nockin down" to me. Abbe Felly dtn rose in de bloomer kostum, and was in de middle ob her speach wen sum malishe niggar put de lites out and hollard fire, den sum ob dem went a huggin de wimin wich led to a gineral fite. Anty Clawson's big biler ob clam soup was up set and spilt on de flore, and Sister Lukresia Notts, in tryin' togit out, slipped up on a big Cow Bay clam and fell down and split her nose on one side. Long Cudjo picked her up, and she tort wen he took hold ob her dat he nocked her down, and, I is sorry to say, she forgot her standin in siety while she wus down, and hit him blim in de eye. Cudjo hab to ware his eye in a sling eber sence, kase it am brack. Brudder Greedy leff his ole white coat and a shoe behind, but he made tracks home mity suple. Sister Hickory Smith had her Bloomer kostum torn berry much, and so did all de sisters. I am shamed ob myseff to tink de boys wont let de gals alone, and deA   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.       o10 agin I tink it am sarbin dem bout rite, kase dey better be home tendin to deir bizness a good deel. Will Brudder Mark Anthony Seazar Jonsing hab de perliteness to pass round de useal sasser and look out fur bad pennies. No. XLVIIl BRUDDERN AND SISTERN: You will fine de words from wich I xtrac my lectur dis ebenin in de catakism, whar it 'spressly sez dat ; Uriah's beauteous wife Made David seek his life." Now, you brack scorpions, you must not spose dat de Uriah, wich is 'fered to by de grate poet, wus de Uriah Heap wich Boz show up in de teatres in conjuncshun wid David Copperhead, nor you musn't 'spose dat de David 'fered to am dat David neder. De David and Uriah spoken ob in de tex wus two brVdders dat lib in de olden time; sum mite tink him de David dat got Goliah slued, wich I tole you 'bout two monfs ago, but it wusn't him too. De David 'fered to wus ole David King or King David, I furget wich, who ruled in de Muskeeto kingdom, or some odder fur aff places todder side ob de equinoxtail lime, nie to Jerucelam. David wus de fust musishuner, and played upon de jewsharp, but history don't say wedder Uriah had eny taste dat way a tall. Boff ob dese brudders wus Jews, and derefore ob corse was a fitin wid de Filis- tines or sum odder kine ob low pepil. Well, ole King David made his brudder Uriah a great gineral in him army, and ebery body wus saying wat a good brudder Uriah hab got. But dey dident noe do secret wy David put him in brig-a-dig gineral ob his confined forces. But I foun it out like a book-you see Uriah had bin a gittin mar- rid, jis afore de war broke out, to one ob de hansumest she Jewesses -"  '    '        ;  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7078-00000056"/> "O      MR. JULIUS CAESAR HANNIBAL'S in de hole naborhood, and, David pretended to hab grate pie-tonic 'fection fur her. I 'spose, afore I go eny furder, I better 'splain de difference 'tween pie-tonic and hair-tonic, as you mite tink one wus. deoder; one tonic am a stuff fur takin kinks out ob de wool, and de oder am a nodder word fur frendship. But, my stingy harers, dar am a mity deel ob sin kummitted 'mong de sexes under de name ob pie-tonic 'fection, and so it wus wid ole David. He fell in lub wid Uri's wife one fine arternoon, wen she was takin a baff in de ribber Jordan on de banks ob -Cannion, and den he tort a plan how to git Uriah kild dead so he cood marry de widder, notwidstandin at de same time he had forty oder wibes; so den he went home and sent out de trumpeter to blow it 'mong de fokes dat Uriah was pur- moted a Brig-a-dig gineral ob de fust diwision ob his army, wich wus den reddy to start on a war agin de Ottomites and de Filistines. All dis. time David King or King David was purtendin to hab grate pie-tonic 'fection fur he sister-in-law. Well,. de day 'ribed fur Uriah to go off wid de sogers, and, puttin on a new red soger coat wid gowld applelets, got-he dogeartype taken, mounted he fiery charger, braced he wife, tole her ef enyting curred he'd telemgraf, put two ob Colt's rebolushun hoss pistils and a nudder kine ob pistil made ob glass well loded (wich am in use till dis day 'mong de so- gers) in he saddle-bags, and gib de word ob kummand, and way he went. His wife cry a little, but David pulled out he jewsharp and played a good ole tune wich set her a laffin, and she soon furgit her husban. In de mean time Uriah went on as proud as Lucyfur at de head ob de sogers, but de second day on he trabdel he met wid a slight incounter in de shape ob an oberflowin army, wich stood on de forks ob two rodes and woodn't let him pass eder one ob dem; he draw'd his sward frum de cubberd and tole de enemys to ad- wance backrbut dey dident mine him a bit; den he tole de band to charge bagenets on de Filistines. At dis junction one ob he sogers, named Sam Tomson, (some called him Tom Samson, odders jis Samson, but de rite name is Sam Tomson,) cum up to Uriah and tole him he had no mustick, but de jaw-bone ob an ass, wid wich he wood 'gage to slew six- thousand Filistines ef he let him go at 'em; Uriah tole him to go in and win, wich he did. He went at 'em rite and leff, and laid 'em out cold. De planes ob Abraham wus strewed wid ded sogers; but sad to tell, in de hite o dde fite de   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        ." Filistines fired off a butterin ram at Uriah dat nock him so far into kingdum kum dat he breff nebber kum back agin. He body wus carried back in state; but wich state he kum home in history dusn't state. Wen David seed de body kum back, he wus mity glad, and gib a grate funeral bankuit, as wus de kustom in dem days. Den he tole de widder he lubed her all to pieces, and dey dey git marrid. Now, my frens, you see wat pie-tonic lub am, an I say to you, be- ware ob de man who pertend to hab grate pie-tonic 'fection fur your wife, and fink ob David King and he brudder Uriah. Wat's dat Sister Cathed axes: "Wat am a butterin ram 7" Well, I aint got time to fully splain it to-nite, but I'll tell you it aint sich a buttin ram as butted fat Brudder Eelley off ob de brig into de ribber at Hackumsack lass summer, wen he wus a fishin in a red flannel shirt. In anshent times de sogers used to ketch a big horned ram and tie his feet fass togedder, and den swing him 'tween two poles like de syings or soups ob our day; den wen de enemys kum in range ob de ram de sogers draw him back as fur as dey possably ken, and den luff him butt agin de enemy wid he horns and wid all he wait; and a moss orfull butter dey wus, al- moss as strong and orfull as bordin house butter. Dat's a butterin ram as near as I ken make out by de almacks ob dat year. Will Brudder Bigway please to pass round de sasser? Do kulb leeshun dis ebenin is fur cole and wood. No. XLIX. MY 'SPECTED FRENS: You will fine de words ob de tex ob my lectur in de ' Snortin Song Book," in de 4th werse ob de 19th song-4th werse! 19th song!-whar it 'spressly sez: "Solemon bilt de tower, And it war him dat fix, Dat ebery mechanic, young and old, Should work from six to Six."  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7078-00000057"/> "2      MR. JULIUS CESAB HANNIBAL S De poet, in his 'scripshun bout ole Soleman and de Tower, hab luff us all in de dark as to who Soleman wus, and wat kind ob tower he bilt; but I shood like to see enyting in anshent and moderant history dat I coodn't fine out, and -now I is jis gwane to tell you all bout de Solemans and de Tower. Mr. Soleman's rite name wus Saleman Gundy, he wus a big high g soger man and fit in sebrel fites, and was 'lected king fur he wisdum. He wus de Bunsby 6b his age, and carried, sich a cargo ob wisdom dat he kum nie being swamped by de wait twice. He wus a grate chap fur makin ole saws; not sich kine ob ole saws as you saw wood wid, but sich ole saws as "Time is money," "All flesh am grass," "Kum day, go day, sends sum day," and sich wise sayins as dese. He wus a good man fur de time in wich he libed, but ef I, or eny ob you, my brudders, wus to keep half as meny wibes as he did, we'd hab de wurtus police down on us mity sharp. History sez he had forty wibes and two hundred konkebines. I don't noe zackly wat konkebines am, but I 'speck dey wus sum kine ob loose kattle. Well, Mr. Saleman Gundy, arter he wus stigmatized to de orfice ob king, he took it into he hed to bild a tower so high dat he cood stan on de top and see whar de sun goes to when he goes down at nite, a ting dat puzzled him berry much. Well, so he advertized fur pro- posals to git it bilt, and in tree monfs from date -more den five hun- dred Arabs wus to work a diggin de sellar. De reason he hired de Arabs wus bekase he libed in Araba, and ob korse everybody wus Arab. Well, tings went on berry welD de men a workin from sun- rise till sun-set, and in dat country de sun rise at 3 o'clock in de mornin and set 10 o'clock in de ebening. Well, one day a Yankee pedler kum dar, and in tree days arter dar wus a strike for de ten hour system.  Well, Mr. Saleman gub in to dem 'pearently, but he fool dem arter all, and in dis way-you must noe dat at dis time de Duch hadn't found out de art ob keepin time, in fac de watch hadn't been diskibbered, so all de way dey tole how late it wus, wus by de sun, and as soon as de sun rose, Mr. Soleman says, " 6 o'clock, boys, go to work;" and den wen it wus jis sinkin he say, "6 o'clock, kum agin."     .              - De tower wus called de '"Tower ob Babler," bekase ob de follerin suckemstance. Wen de workmen reached de 87th story--so de story goes-dey war all seized wid an all-overishness, and one begin dAll   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        113 to talk to de odder in a different language, so one coodn't understand de odder.-"Anda pronto con la mercla!" (Hurry up dem morter,) sung out one feller in Spanish. "Trote vit avec ses brics!" (Trot up wid dat brick,) sang out anudder in French. "' Ich mal dival himer ker swallock mit der rote stine!" (More brick and morter,) hollered a third in Dutch; "Ching ching, a ring ching, ki kum ke ka kow!"' (ring in dem hod ob morter,) bellowed a fourth in Chinese. "Kink a wankee, kWlushum, ri hi kawoo!" yelled a fifth in de Injin tongue. Ob korse, de (alwers) poor Irishmen dat carry de hod didn't noe wat dem fellers meant, and dey tole dem in plane Irish to "Go to de debil." De Arabs undertook to speak Spanish, Duch, French, and Inglish, altogedder, and sum ob dem got de lockjaw and odders broke out all dere teef, so dey hab to gum Arabic fur ebber arter, and dat de fust we bar ob '"Gum Arabic." Wen one spoke to de odder dey all laff fur a short time, and-den sum ob dem got mad and went to fitin, and den dar was a regelar row, de police wus called out, and good meny wus 'rested and put in de cala- boose, and alwers arter dat dese pepils coodn't talk notin else, sum wus struck Spanish, sum wus struck French, sum Duch, and de hod-carriers wus all struck Irish- and wen dey 'peared afore de court, 5Mr. Solemans ax dem wat dey hab to say fur demseffs; dey all begin to spoke at once, and dey set de ole man almoss crazy, and he tole dem to luff de tower be aAd go home. Dis ended de bildin ob de tower, wich had taken dem morn fifty years to 'com- plish. Now you noe all 'bout it as well as odder fokes. Sister Clawson wishes me to say to Brudder Seecole dat he had better fotch de change ob dat qwarter she send him out ob de seller to git changed lass Tuesday nite; sich conduct am- berry niggery, and am unwordy de man ob colar. Brudder Cato will hand round de zasser. No bad pennies taken;  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7078-00000058"/> "4      MR. JULIUS CESAR HANNIBAL'S No. L. MY DEAR WOOLLY HEDS: I recibe lass week a inquest from Brudder Clem Green and sebrel odders ob dis 'Siety to lectur on POLLYTICKS AND POLLYTISHUNS, and how Clem and de rest cood do sich a ting, am a misery to me, kase you all noe how mush I dispise em boff. Dar am notin in life dat I so abdomnably dispise as dese fellers, septin it be poor pepil. Pollytishuns ob all sexes, creeds, and parties, am all alike on boff sides ob de fence, and ef you shake up a big bag full ob dimecrats, loco foofoos, hunckers, burn barners, whigs' silwer greys, abbylish- unists, and woolly heds, de one jis as likely to fall out fuss as de odder. Ob corse, dese 'marks don't hab noe leaniri on Brudders Fred Douglass and Bill'Seawees or eny odder culerdc man. Dese lass named pollytishuns am gwane to run togedder fur Presumdent and Wise Presumdent, and den I gwane to nomenate myseff fur a can- didate fur alderman. Seaweed 'spects to 'skure de furrin wote and Fred will git de cullered wote in the State, and ef I can't fetch do sitty den I gib up de ghost, and I'll tell you how I'll do it. I'll use deir own weapons-I'll tell de wigs dat I'll hab De Wit Clintun's ditch widened, and den I'll hab a canal boat named arter me-den I'll tell 'em dat I'll lay out a big park like de " fields Elisha" ob Paris, and put a high tariff on wool and cotton, and I'll walk up Broadway arm in arm wid Horace Greedy, M. C., (dat means Muss'd Coat,) and de man dat hab courage to do dat ort to be an alderman- ;den I'll tell de loco foofoos dat I'll bild out de Battery to Staten Isl- and and Jersey City, to make all de teretory I ken fur de county, and I'll keep all de rum shops open on a Sunday-I'll 'nax Nigger- auger, lick Austria, and bild new sewers in ebery treet and gib dem de contract fur de hole job. Dat will skure dem fellers wotes )   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        115 sartin. Den I'll write an edick to de Temperance Alliegence and 'form dem dat de rum holes ort to be shut up moss all de week and all day Sunday, and promise ef dey wote for me dat I'll probe as pure as "Snow" to dem, and ef I can't shut up de rum holes I'll shut up myself, wich am all de same in Duch; den de temperance fellers will wote fur me. I'll promise de burn barners dat dar shan't be a barn stanin in de State a monf arter my 'lecshun--I'll burn 'em all down. Den I'll say to de firemen, ef you'll see me lectrified to orfice, I'll see dat ebery ingine am painted red afore she lebes de korporashun yard, so she'll be reddy fur use from de jump-'1ll prom- ise to hab all de fire bells streaked down wid red de year round, and I'll go fur gibbing ebery man a shirt made out ob de 'Merican flag, and I'll be down on de fire 'nihilator; dat'll fetch dem fellers. De abbylishunist wote I got shure, but, my poor and kneedy hearers, none ob you brack men ken wote widout you own two hundred and fifty dollars, but dat small amount am so easily raised dat it wont trouble eny ob you long; ef eny ob you don't happen to hab de trifle 'bout you doze on 'lecshun day, all you got to do is to call on some ob de leadin Abbylishunists ob de day, and jes tell dem you am short ob de amount, and eny ob dem will gib it to you; deir sym- phonies fur de race woodn't luff dem 'fuse. Dey may gib it to you in speshie, derefore you mite take a holler horn to git it in. Ebery ting am fair in pollyticks, and ef you'll wote for me I'll lower de price ob clams to eighteen -pence a hundred, eels to six pence a bunch, pork and beans to three cents a plate, wid a good eel ob pork and a moss all beans. - Second hand boots shell kum down, and 'sted ob fibe dollar suits ob cloze you shell hab tree dollar suits; brackin shell fall to tree cents a box, and brushes in 'portion; sassengers will sell ip winter at ten cents and in dog days at fibe cents a pound; sturgeon shell fall too, and you shell hab as much dancin fur eels on Sunday mornin at Cafrine market as you ken stagger under. Wid dis happiness in store fur you we'll shut up de shop for to-nite. Suppress your applause ef you please, de nabors mite tink it am a pollytickical meetin. I is sorry to fine dat some pussons hab made objections to my two last lecturs, and gib as deir resons dat dey am to scriptural; now I wish to say dat in pleasin one part I hab offended de odder, kase I lectured from subjicks dat wus sent me by note, inquestin me to lee-  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7078-00000059"/> - I l     MR. JULIUS CASAR HANNIBAL'S  tur from. Henceforth I shell nebber allude to enyting i:rsi But Htink dat some peepil am two-cents-ative on sum piitesto la long.                        a Long Island Jake will please pass round de sasser, and keep a sharp look out for tin sixpences and bad coppers. No. LI. "ADIES AND GEMMEN: During de lass two weeks and a fortnite I hab recebed sebril iLil- lyducks inwitein me to lectur on INTEMPERENCE; and as I wish to please everybody and offend none 'sept de wite trash, I 'eluded to do so; darfor, 'cordinly I bin out late ob nites dese two lass weeks to pick up subjics, and aldo I was 'faticly told. by Gus Lemington dat I cood nebber lectur on de schjick till I got 'tos- ticated a cupple ob times myseff, I wus nebber near dat state but once, and notwidstandin dey toted me home on a seller door, I neb- ber cood 'swade myseff dat I ribed at de happy state 'scribed by de boys ob de town. Durin my woyage de 'skibery, as we say in French, I foun sebril cullered women dat corfessed dat dey coodent lib widout gin no mor'n I cood do widout my clam soup.; Ole Ge- mima Jonson, de mudder of Sam, tole me dat de lub ob gin wus not refined to de cullered peepil no mor'n dan to de wites, kase she said she libed wid an ole lady wunst dat used to send her ebbery two or three days for a quart ob de bess "Be dam" gin fur de mince pizes, but dey seldom had dem kind ob pizes, and 'twus no matter ef dey didn't she got de gin jis de same. Well, dis ole lady complaned berry much ob a corntinual sinkin in her stumjack, and she use to drink cold tea fur to kure it; she kept de cole tea in de bess chine teapot in de cubbard, and dar she go to r    :;, : , :.O1 SIENTIFXi DISCOtURSS. 127 dt:riItqute often. Well, one day mudder Jonson wus struck wid i; deitofakei and went to dis cubbard to fine some megnut to put in t,    iwhet: she smelt gin; she picked up de teapot, took a drink, and foun  it wtiude- same "Be dam" gin she fotch home.  Hguess, and I'm Yankee nuff fur dat, dis story cut some ob your thuttons, kase odder peepil 'sides ole wimin keep a priwate teapot! I foun one deformed drunkard, and de only reason he stopped drinkin wus kase he han shook so dat he coodn't raise de tumbler to he mouf no' longer, and nobody wood do it fur him, darfor he deformed. In Shin-blister alley I found a cullered man who absoletely signed de pledge. He sed he wus one ob de oldest bruzers off de iland. I ax'd him fur his 'sperence and he gub it to me on paper, as a great temperence orator had put it down fur 'livery, but I kum fust arter it and he gub it to me, and now I read it to you: "My name is Pete Crookleg. I wus born at a bery early period ob my life, so young dat de 'currence luff my nolege box. I hab bin a grate drunkard all my life till a monf ago, wen I signed de pledge by de- help ob de Lord. I lamed de taste ob rum from my mudder, kase she wus a gin bibber. My fadder nebber bibbed, he alwers poured it down. I growed up a drunkard, and I nebber done nuffin all my life but drink wen I could git it. I went from crime to crime, a cussin and swarin, fuss stealin a tater and den a grater. Men'ys de nite I hab no place to sleep 'septin in de ole worn out omonibusses, and I hadn't no doze to my back 'sept ole carpet and rags ob dat kine. I went on a drinkin, swarin, and stealin, till de police cotched me, and Justis Merit (aldo I didn't see eny merit in wat he did to me) sentenced me to tree years to Howl Howl State prisin. I kum out a bigger loafer dan wen I went in, and so continued till I signed de pledge and got a meddel fore blessed weeks ago, and since den I habn't stolen nuffin ob eny consekence, and I aint bin in prisin wunst worth noticin; and I warn you all to beware ob gin coxtail, brandy smashers, and odder low drinks.' I'm gittin long orful wid de Temperence 'Siety, and speck to be made de presumdent soon." My frens, you hear wat Mr. Crookleg sez. Now listen to me. You must not tink dat you am 'quired to be temperence only in-de drinkin line, kase you will suffer almoss as much ef you 'dulge too  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7078-00000060"/> -18      MR. JULIUS CASAR  ANNNIBAL 8 much in de eatin bizness. I nebber node a man dat eat a harty sup- per ob turkle soup and fixins dat didn't fine de ole turkle on he stumjack afore mornin tryin to swim down he mouf, and ef a man obeylodes he bread-basket wid pork and beans, jis a gwan to bed, he is sure to sleep wid a hog dat nite for sartin; I noe dat from 'spe- rence. But ef a man eats a little and drinks a little, it won't hurt him; but you all hab such oberflown idees ob wat a little am, dat I fear dat my warnin will go fur nuffin to de highes bidder, darfor I luff it go fur wat it will fetch. Ef you ken make enyting out ob dis lectur you am welcum to it fur all me. I hab hard, during de week, dat my lectur on de Tower ob Babel wus not de true cause ob Brudder "Amicus" gittin offended, but he did not like de one on de "Jonny Hoss" tree or fore weeks ago. I kin assure him dat I didn't mean him in partickeyler. I shood-tink dat any man who hab de imperence to write sich sultin letters to strangers, ort to hab independence nuff to sine he proper name to it. Brudder Erastus Gedolphus Butts will please pass dq sasser, as he am got de moss colone on he cloze. No. LII. "AIES AND GEMMEN: I shell agin call on de anamle kingdum fur a subjick to interess and amuse you din stormy nite, and as an ackt ob justis and filan- thropy, I will tell you all I foun out bout dat beauful modestic cretur-- DE COW. I spose moss ob you hab seen dese cretures eider male or female, kase we offen fine dem runnin loose and wild in de treets buckin down wimin in red shalls and men wid red heds; but fur de edifica- tion obhdose whose trables hab not extended as fur in de country as dey am found, I will 'scribe him. De cow am bout de size ob de bull,   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.       1X9 oney a little smaller; he got horns when dey'm a mine to grow, jis like de lass named Bdll; dey am short in de leg like Pompey, Duck- shanks, and dey am bery mischievous sumtimes, kase dey often pull down fences wid deir horns and steel green corn and sich tings. He hab bin brought up about de house so much dat he offen copies sum ob de moss wishus wices ob mankine, and one ob de wices wich dey all' seem to have lamed from de ole farmers am de wice ob chawin. I don't noe wedder .ey use 'backer, but dey always got a cud in deir mouf and keep a chawin on it all de time. He hab got ears dat flop back and forward as regler as de clock tick, and he got a beauful tale a hanging down ahind, wich fly bout like polytishuns in 'lexshun times. De cow am deribed from caff; fust he am caff, nex he am hieflyer, and den cow. As soon as he ribes at dis latter pint ob 'xistence den his trubble begins, dat am ef he happens to be owned by one ob de milk factory men, dat ride round in luxury ebery mornin pretendin to sell de pure milk. Human natur intended wen de cow wus mate dat it shood be a blessin to de poor and a comfort to de rich; but my 'noledge seekin harers, I tell you dat dar um not anudder cretur dat am 'posed on so much and used so badly as dis. Dar am not a cretur so lied about eider, for dar am not a milk can in dis city but wat kontains a libil on him, wich libil ort to be 'dited and put in de post orfice. I spose you tink dat de wite fluid sold round de town am milk, but it am. nuffin but a mixter ob chalk and water wid jis honey nuff in it to gib it a sweet taste. Dar am anudder kine ob milk called 'stillery milk. Ole Anty Claw. son hab some ob dis kine and she set some ob it by fur to raise de cream on, she waited tree week and no cream come, and den she gub it to de poor kase nobody cood eat it; she berry charitable allers to de poor. Maby ome ob you would like to noe how dis 'stillery milk am made. Well, I liten you, as de pock picket sed to de gemman wen he stole he pocket book. You muss noe dat nature 'tended de cow to eat de green grass ob de fields in de summer and hay in de winter, wich to him am wat corn beef, pork and beans, clam soup, roast clams, punkin pies and kusterds am to us; but de 'stillery man takes de cow from he natrel feed and puts dem in a stall whar dey can't mobe a foot, and den feed him de slops from de brewery wich \  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7078-00000061"/> 120      MR. JULIUS CESAR HANNIBAL'S keeps him drunk all de time and in a fevor till he drop down ded and rotten;, dat, ob korse, makes de milk poisonous and bad. Dis milk am giben to de childrin ob dis stity, and dat 'counts fur dar being so meny puny and pale childrin,'specially 'mong de cullered popelashun. Dar am more truff dan poultry'bout dis, and de facs hab bin laid afore de common scoundrels, but dey am so bizzy a layin out big parks dat dey nebber inwestigate em. It's a shame to treat de poor cow so kase he am de moss useful anamile dat libs; he not only sustains de libes ob hundreds wile he lib by gibin good fresh milk ebety day, but wen he am dead, ef he dies in de nateral way and gits killed, he am all good; we eat his flesh, make glue ob his feet, and he tale make de best clam soup you ebber tasted. In de cow's younger days he is berry susseptable to lub, and wen in dat state she goes round a bellerin jis like de young fokes wid a face as long as a flour barrel, and lookin as sulky as a dlsappinted lubber. All dis I 1ie out myseff bout de cow. Brudder Lemuel Gustus Jinkson will do de honors ob passin round de sasser dis ebening. Dar'll be a meetin ob de Boot Polishin Siety, who am on a strike since de snow storm, on Wednesday, at Pete's sellar in Baiard street, at tree o'clock, to take into 'sideration wedder an extra cent shant be raised on high heel boots. No. LIII. FELLER SITYZINS: You will find de sublick for 'sideration dis ebenin in almoss ebery house in de sity, and de poorer de peepil you look 'mong am, de more you will find. De subjick am de PUSSY TOM CAT. Dar am sebril kines ob cats, 'mong wich we fine de gray cat, do turkle shell cat, de black and do wite cat, do famomine cat and de   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        121 master!ne cat, and de ole Thomas cat, to which lass gem. an I shell call your 'tenshun-to wid all de force and power ob a lofermotive bul- gine. De catam foun all ober creashun, but more 'specially in de laps ob ole maids, in de arms ob little girls, and sometimes im de closit a stealin sumfin. He am a berry modestic anamile in de day time, but at nite he'm de biggest lofer and .peace-breaker out ob de stashun house. Ef you cood see him a settin in front ob de fire wid his four feet stuck close togedder, and his tail curled round dem as ef he wus ashamed bo em, and watch his yaller eyes wink and blink as inacent as a lam, you woodent tink he wus gilty ob de tricks he am wen he am out ob a nite on a lark. He hab got .um enemys in de world like odder peepil, and de formost ob dese am :brick-bats, ole Boots, ole bottles, and misa-lam-eous matter. I hab frequent seen dese tings fly at him from all directions in de moss spiteful manner, reddy to nock him down wen he wus doin his best on a sarah-nade on de wood-shed. Now I offin hear de Dodgewoth Band sarah-nade in de nite time, and I nebber see enyting frown at dem septin a bokay frqm de young la- dies room winder, darfore I tink de cat am bused. De music ob de P. T. cat is not furoughly depreciated by mankine. Here we fine him settin up all dese cole nites, and cumin under your winder and sarah-nadin you widout price or reward, and so long as he gibs us a fine imetashun ob de prima donnyat de uproar house, seeI se o reason dat, his efforts shood be looked 'pon as pussylanamus. -I recumlect wen I wus an assistant to de proprietor ob a hotel,:dat aole he Thomas cat used to come in our back-yard ebery nite and call our cat put; our cat's name was Pinkey and wus a lady cat, and dat ole Tom nued to come and say "P-i-n-k-y, w-h-y d-o-n-t y-o-u .com-e o-u-t?" jis as plain as Inglish; he used to sarah-nade Pinky ebery nite. I. wun- dered wat he wus arter a comin dar so offin, and one nite I watched dem and found out, it was wittles! We had a mite lot ob scraps ebery day to frow in de swill bar'l, and dis ole feller smelt it out, and bom by he tole all he frens, and den we had a koncart by a dozen; but one nite dey met wid a cat-astrophy, kase de cook put arsnick on de scrap and dey come and eat it, wen dey swell up like an editer readin a louditory notice ob himseff, and busted. a De cat am oh little use in dis world 'sept it am to kotph rats and mouses and 'xtend deir specie, wich dey do semi 'caisionally. Do kitten am born berry young, and fur de fuss nine days am as blind as 6  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7078-00000062"/> 122      MR. JULIUS CSASAR HANIBAL'S your political deponent, but arter dat dey git deir eyes open, and den dey romp and play, scratch and bite, like young lubbers. It am a beufiful site to see de kittens roll and tumble ober one anudder like a tumble beatle ober a hors-chesnut, and den ef dey am interupted sud- denly at deir sports dey stick deir fore claws in de flo', deir back rises to an arch wid passhun and looks as ef it wus broke, deir tale swells up wid indignashun till you'd tink she borrowed all de odder cat tales and put dem in one, and den she spit out like Sam Ticklip's wife did wen he staid all nite on Long Band to a lub feast. - As de cat grows older he gits more lazy, and you may trow him round jis as you like, he don't mind it, he alwers lands on he foots; no matter wat hight you trow him, ef he am from off de house top, he gits up, licks he paws, washes he face, stretches heseff out one leg arter de odder jis to see ef dey am all rite, and den off he goes as ef notin happened. He am a tuff feller, end foolosofers say dat he got nine libes, and dat to make dem stay ded you hab got to kill him nine times. I seed one drowned ate times and den run home to de kitchen fire to dry heseff off. Fbolosefers also likewise say dat de cat skin, in winter, contains electricity, and dis I noe from 'sperence; ef you take a black cat in de dark on a cold nite and rub her back upwards, you will see de sparks fly like tinder box. In cornclusion, I hand him ober to de Siety ob Moral Reform, hopin dey will look into de habits ob Thomas fur he'm an immoral character, as I could probe ef I dared; eberybody nose he will steel when eber he git a chance. But he am a privileged character, and I spose it am none o1 my business how he spends his lazy hours. Will Brudder Simon Snowflake please pass de sasser to de ladies, and dat'll gib him fuss rate chance'to show off dem rings and watch chain, and odder fixins.         "   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.        128 No. LIV. B'LUBED DESCIPLES: I shall 'debber dis ebenin to splain to you de life and karacter ob dat beufiful inseck none mong de anshents as de Hopious Toadabuss, but de common order ob mankine call it- DE TOAD. No foolosefer yit fully skihbered from whar bout dese fellers cum from in de fuss place, and some tink one ting and some anudder, bout dar fuss come. Some tink dey come down in showers, kase we al- ways see arter a summer rain tousands ob dem, some not bigger dan a mouse's conscience and odders bout haff grown. Odders agin tink dat dey am deribed from some anshent circus company wich some ole fairy turned' into toads out ob spite, and made dem perform jimnastic \    . feets all deir life time, and dis am de reason we see dem take sich orful leaps. My fiens, neider ob dese am rite, kase I nose whar dey cum from; dey come from de holler tree, kase I seed one come from dar myseff.  Do toad am blessed wid de same beauties as de frog, dat am in cemetary ob limb; but he aint so green as de frog no how. It hab bin a long standin question in all de old debatin sieties as to wat do toad lib on. Some 'serts dat he libs on promices and moonshine, and I am 'cliped to blebe de last part ob de. 'sertion, kase I hab offen seed dem out on moonshiney nites lookin fur sumfin. A little suckem- stance happened to occur wid me and an ole flame ob mine named Florinda. It wus a good while ago on a plantashun way down souf. It wus in de ebenin ob a hot day in July and arter ole massa and missus go to bed, me and Florinda steeled out ob our cabin and go to de summer house in de garden; we hadn't bin long dar, and I hadn't eben offered to set near her nor nuffin, when all at wunst she sung out, "O Julius!" de reason she called me Julius wus kase dat am my name. "Oh, Julius!" said she, "how mity cold your hand am on my neck." I laffed, kase I hadn't my hands on her at all, and I  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7078-00000063"/> 124      MR. JULIUS CASAR HANNJiBAL S hole em up fur her to see dem. "'Well, den," she muttered, trimblin wid frite, "dar's a wiper on me fur sartin." I jumped up, grabbed a klub, and stole round to de odder side ob Florinda from whar I wus settin, and sure anuT, on her bare neck set a orful big toad lookin in de moonshine like a piece ob brown soap haff used up. I gib de feller fits, and I tort Florinda wood hab dem too de way she went on and slung herseff round, and eber arter dat I hab to keep my arms round her welwet neck wen settin togedder, jis to keep do toads off, and I laffed way down in my heels ebery time she wus Yfraid ob de toads; but I am transgression from my subjick. De diet ob de toad muss be berry lite, almoss as lite as bordin-house diet. De pos'le Julius Seasar Shakespeare, in his grand play 'bout de darkey gineral sez--- ---"I'd rudder be a toad, And' lib 'pon de wapor ob a dunghill, Dan keep a corner grocery." .%, So you see dat Shakespere noe jis wat he lib on afore you and your highly 'spected lecturer wus born. I don't wunder dat Shakespere wus down on keepin a corner grocery, aldo he coodn't hab kept a corner grocery in dis sity ef he'd wished to, kase he aint a Dutchman, and nobody but Dutchmen am lowed to keep dese depots ob cart wheel butter, spiled hams, red herrin, bad rum and larger bier. Nobody kan tell how old Mr. Toad am, not eben de oldest inhab- itant, kase he lib for ebber. In de winter, like de rest ob de toadies, he goes souff, and as soon as spring comes he comes back, full ob abbylishunism and jimnasticks. Like de ress ob mankine he gits he- seff in a mity tite place sumtimes. De titest place I eber heard ob his getin in wus in de middle ob a rock dat wus dug up de odder day to carry on de lexshun wid-and liar let me tell you dat it takes a orful lot ob rocks to carry on dis bizness successfully, kase I hard a alderman say so, and who, I ax you, you ignorampusses, nose more dan a alderman? Well, in de centre ob dis big rock dey found a toad who had bin dar widout de leass particle ob air or a bit to eat, eber since de day dat King Faro blowed his nose fur de fust time and 'ston- ished de court-house; and de toad wus alibe all de time, and as soon as he seb day lite he rubbed his eyes, complaned ob de long nites, and off he went wid a leap dat wood set de circus fellers crazy.   SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.       125 I can't call do toad a berry fine singin bird, but still he makes heseff heard from out ob de holler stumps jis afore a shower, to gib warnin to de wimin to git de close in off de close line. I tink from de way de political toads am now singin round, dat some ob dem ole tirants in Austria and odder hot places may expect a shower soon. Ef de elements ob war does git up a shower in dat sexshun it will be a mity hard one; insted ob de drops bein ob de bountiful rain from hebbin, bullets will form de rain drops and canqpn balls will be de hail. I'm afeard dat de hurrykane will nock down some ob de trones dat am now rotten at de base and totterin. De litenin wisible on dat caision will be de flash ob steel and ob dauntless eyes, and de thunder will be loud 'nuff to echo from dis land ob pet banks, wooden nutmags and liberty, way off dar in de cantfines ob Yourope, and I would 'wise do king ob Austria to look out fur he close-as I come to de word close agin, I'll stop spoken on dat pint. Ef de "Hannibal Guard" (cullerd) don't turn out but nine men, captin and all, dey needn't send me no inwite to targitize wid dem, kase I tink it am a disgrace to my name. Wen dey named de kum- peny arter me, I tort dat'it wus 'spectable and resented,'but now dat de captin luffs dem come de darkey ober him and luffs dem loaf home trainin days I don't want nuffin to do wid dem. Longfoot Jake! pass round de sasser, I'm indigent. No. LV. BLUBED- CORNSYICKEWENTS: I is berry sorry to 'form you dat I hab not bin able to study out a lectur on eny sientifick subjick for dis 'portant caision, and de reson will be omnibus to you as soon as I'splain myseff. You all noe berry well dat de Hungry'uns hab ribed har from Turkey, whar dey made sad havoc in grease. Well, eberybody bar 'bout dese Hungry fellers comin, and de common scoundrels, arter saddlin de toun wi4  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7078-00000064"/> e 126     MR. JULIUS CESAR HANNIBAL'S de gas monoponly kontrack fuir de next 17 years, 'greed to hab a soger holler day wen de grate and good Cowsuthe ribed. Well, dat wiis all well 'nuff, but you hab no idea wat work and trubble it trow'd 'pbn y-our suspected laborer. As 'so6n as our felleis liar dat Cowsuithe wis to bc turned into a lion bar, dey-called a mieetih ob all de cullered popelation, and, ob korrse, I den had my hans full, kase I wus 'nmediately accumolated preslimdent ob de iieetin, and we had great dteal excursion 'bout de hole ting. Briidder Lem Worttiingtori tort dat de cullered peepil had as good a rite to turn out and tcelembrate de friend ob friedom as eiiy ob de wite trrash, darfore he 'posed dat de Hannibal Guard be 'piiited to deceibe him wen he come, and dat de Tinkers' Guard, from Caftinii Markit, allow demseffS to ack as de guard ob honor on dat 'pOftaht ciisio. . trudder Erastus C. J. M. Puckins said he Wood 'gree to dat ef iBrigadig Gen. Sandford wdluff dd Hanitibal Guard hab de rite i&amp;and cornier b de fuss divishon, so de pinlets chbd show off to dis- adVantage. Ole1 Uncle Pete Clawson here rise and wanthd to nde wart de cUilerd soigrs wus a tinkin 'bodt to want to swasheate Wid de wites, fui his part he'd rudder die a thdwin gum in a ingin rub- ber factory dan be seeh 'mong dem, (chebrs and hurras,) and if he mite be 'lowed to digest sumfin dat would be a honor to de darkey all ober Creashun, he wood-(har sumbody sed "Go on! digest!") Well den, sed Uncle Pete, I 'pose dat a kummity ob two hundred 'pint demseff to call on de great Magull and gib him an address jis like de odder peepil's do, 'surin him ob our great sympathy for Hun- gry peepil, kase we noe ourseffs wat it am to be hungry frequently offin. [Cheers, wid wich he squatted.] Brudder Sam Jonson axed for inflammation-whar 'bout dey 'spected to get de 'Dress from? Who wus to rite it? He wus 'formed by a brudder in a high heel'd shirt collar, dat dar wood be no diffukilty 'bout dat, kase Brudder Greeley or Bridder Seaveied wood fix one up in les 'dain no time fur dem. Bat, aied Brudder Snowflake, will de gemmnan recebe us wen we go dar to die tavern? Jim, fdb 'dandy vaiter, sd he had dat all fixed; he cood slip 'em in d'e cTde d-oo:r ob de hotel wen Mr. Irving was out, and den dey cood ifiad   Ae' dloor db Cowsuthe's room, den -gib a nook, and as ho i  a  ri   oor 7  o'ihl    SCIENTIFIC DISCOURSES.      -  12 come out dey coed hand him de paper in wich de 'dress am done up and lebe. I tort it high time fur me to say sumfin, and as I rose dey gib me six cheers and a bench to stan 'pon. I tole dem dat de Hannibal Guard hab only got nine sogers in it, and darfor, I injected to dar turnin out. I -was sassagefried wid de dress 'rangement, but I axed dem ef it wus notpur duty to feed dese Hungry people as well as de wite hurd. Darfor I 'posed to gib dem a banquit de same as de press gang did, but not like dem refuse legitamate peepil and den sell de tickets to Tom, Dick, and Harry. De lawyers, dq- sogers, and de corporation hab fed dem, and why not de cullerd folks? Darfor I 'posed to git up a banquit fur de Hungry'uns at Aunty Clawson's seller, to come off as soon us it kin be kooked. Tickets on dis great 'caision one shilling. I noe it's high-but de obgick! I noe dat money am bery scarce, and dat hundreds ob poor peepil hab to go widout food and close haff de time, but wat ob dat, ef we gib dis feast and gib Massa Cowsuthe de 'dress, we'll git our name in de papers, wich we cood nebber do in any odder way, 'ceptin, ob korse, in de police reports. I hab ranged de bill ob fair dus: -  BtBANQUET TO ALL HUNGRY'UNS, AT AUNTY CLAWSON'S SELLER.  1. Clams in de shell. t  2. Clam soup, widout-cracker. 3. Clams fried, wid gravy. 4;, Clam chowder.  5. Clam soup, wid cracker. 6. Pickled clams. 7. Roast clams. 8. Stewed clams. 9. Clam pot pie. 10. Clam frickazee. ". Clam scolluped. 12. Clami. m  uMqenaore clams, if wanted.  I used all my elemquence to hab de banquit '1opted, but a brudder  &#xD;<pb n="128-129 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7078-00000065"/> 128      MR. JULIUS CMSAR HANNIBAL'S dat keeps a oyster seller 'posed de moshun toof and nail; but it may be got up yet, darfor de kollecshun dis ebenin will be to raise money fur de clams. Brudder Icilaus Nincomfoo will please pass round de sasser. THE END.   THE COUNTERPART OF "COUTT XONTE CISTO." TIME GREATBT OF MODBER FICTIONs COUNT MONTE-LEONE; OR, THE SPY IN SOCIETY. A ROMANCE OF TIE CAREONARI OF FRANCE AND ITALY; ifrorm the Jfrenct of i, 3^ ^t Ceorges, WITH ELEGANT ILLUSTRATIONS. Complete in one rolume, Price 50 Cents. COUNT MONTE-LEONiE is one of the most graphic and piquant romances In any language. Its scene is laid in the exciting events which followed the second re- storation, and in that wild cabal which came so near reproducing another French Revolution, and which, excited as the popular mind then was, could not but have been bloody as the first. The various secret societies, especially that of the CAR- BONARI, legitimate descendants of TmE ILLUMNATI, the schemes of their vente, or lodges, the vast purposes they meditated, are unfolded with an ability which, places M. de Saint Georges among the greatest of the romance writers of the day. It is not difficult to foretell for this book a popularity as great as that of the "Count of Monte-Cristo," witi the headlong exciting interest of which its story may le compared to no disadvantage. -- ---- *-* --- [0titmd nt theT Dres. "This powerfully written and admirably conceived tale may stand comparison ith the famous "Monte-Cristo " of Dumas, or the renowned "WanderingJew," by Sue, for it partakes of the deeply thrilling political character of the one, and the vivid and brilliant writing of the other. The scenes are alternately laid in ' Naples and in Paris, and the story is one of intense and varied interest, chiefly growing out of the adventures of Count Monte-Leone, who is a chief of the Car- bonari. The work originally appeared as a serial in the pages of the International Magazine, and its piopularity induced the publishers to reproduce it in pamphlet form, It will become one of the most successful books of the season."--fome Jour. "This spirited romance has appeared serially in the International Magazine. It is now published in separate form, with the addition of numerous illustrations. It has been carefully translated from the French, and will be found equal if not superior in interest to Dumas's most popular productions."-Commercia Adfver. "The scene of this exciting romance*is laid in France and Italy, and in the stirring times that immediately succeeded, or- rather witnessed, the downfall of the Bonaparte dynasty in France, Spain, Naples, and wherever else Napoleon had thought fit to place upon the head of a member of his family a despot's crown. Intrigue and martial adventure, love, conspiracy, crime and vengeance, all accord- ant, however, in their main features with historical fact, crowd the pages of this highly dramatic and powerfully written work. It will compare, we think, with the most popular stories and legends of Dumas, and may well be termed the 'counterpart-of Monte-Cristo.' The translation is admirable, and we have no doubt that the book will have a tremendous run."-Morning Star. "This thrilling tale is intended as a counterpart to the ' Count Monte-Cristo.' The object of the story is to illustrate the secret societies which at one time, un- der the title of Ventas and Carbonari, pervaded the Monarchies of Europe. The story is kept up with startling and nflagging interest to theend."-Sunay Die STRINGER &amp; TOWNSEND, 222 Broadway. , .   &#xD;<pb n="130 (Advertisement) -131 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7078-00000066"/> "THE BEST ESSAYS SINCE ADDISON'S SPECTATOR. Sixth Edition, Just Published THE -LORGNETTE; BY IK MARVEL, AUTHOR OF "REVERIES OF A BACHELOR," ETC, sZt Aoft Sfb Jim tt ^ iEarXlts' tsijns Complete inr Two Volwnes.-Price $1 25 cents each This is a work for the express entertainment of all Spinsters who wish tins. bands; all Belles who admire their own Charms; allBeaux who are captivated with their own Portraits; all Old Ladies who wish to Se young; all Authors stu- dious of their own Works; all Fashionists in love with their own Position; all Misses eager to be seen; all Rich Men wlho are lovers of their own Money; all Bachelors looking for a Fortune; all Poets infatuated with their own Powers; all Critics confident of their Taste; and all sensible Men who are content to be honest., , ILLUSTRATIONS: :first errfes,           econX $mri, I.-TIIE LTON.            I.-PORTRAIT OF THE AUTHOR. IT.--TiE FASHONABLE GENTLEMAN.   II.-TowN DRESSING-ROOM. "I.-THE HUNGARIANS.         Ill.-BOSTON STREETS. IV.-TIiE TOWN BEAU.         IV.-JNO. TIMON AT SARATOGA. V.-THE LADY IN SOCIETY.       V.-OLD BUCK AT TIIE SPRINGS. VI.-TmE BOSTONIAN.          VI.-MAIN ABOUT TowN. FIRST SERTES.--The Anthor's Purpose-Lodgings in Town-Classification of Belles--The Fashionable hMan-Introductory-Totvn Celebrities-Introductory-  Ways of Getting into Society-Diary of a Fashion IIunter-Correspondence- Respectables-Old Beaux-Correspondence-Introductory-Lions-A   sly chat with his Publisher--Hints for a great Literary Monument-The Opera-People in Society--Journal of a Lady in Society-Correspondence-Introductory-The Fashionable Lady-Talk with the Ladies-Correspondence-The Bostonian- Country Strangers-Family and Ancestors-Authors and Authorlings. SECOND SERIES.-Timon's New Progamme-May Mornings-A Moral about the Polka and Polkists-A Mob-A Chapter on Belles-The Public in the Dark- A Salon Picture-An Eve at the Capitol-Letters of Correspondents-A Boost f'or Bostonians-The Wall Street Brokers--A Taste for the Springs-Letter from Kitty--Death of the President-Habit of our Amusements-Watering-Place Peo- ple-Sir Robert Peel-The Cockney in the Country--Letter from a Cockney- Letter from Senex on a Young Wife-A Lady Revelation-A trip to Saratoga-A Few Portraits in the Country-Country Churches and Preachers-Advice to a Son-Dr. Webster and Jenny Lind-The Young Man About Town-Louis Philippe, his Life and Death--The Return to Town-A Cavatina-Timon's last, a Review--Town Society-Valedictory. --  ptnialrn if the re\m. "The Lorgnette is to New-York society what Shakspeare made the stage to the world. It fairly holds the mirror up to nature. The follies, vices, and amuse- ments of the great metropolis are portrayed, not caricatured, with an acute hand. Of the sparkling, brilliant style of the work, its vivid pictures of real life, and its keen sarcasm, our praise cannot but seem impertinent. We hope not to be thought extravagant in ranking it at the head of its department in literature."- Forom the Courier aand Enquirer's Review of "L Ik Murvel's8 Works. t"The work is destined to take its place in our libraries by the side of the Spec. tator and Salmagundi. The designs of Darley are really gems of their kind; they are unique, too, as specimens of their class."--Eening Mirror. STRINGER &amp; TOWNSEND,      222 Broadway, New-Tork.   BRAITHWAITE'S RETROSPECT; A HALF-YEARLY JOURNAL OF PRACTICAL .MEDICINE AND STRGERY, Part XXiV., January, -1852, Now Ready. CHAN-GE OF PROPRIETORSHP AAND IMPROVEMENT OF THE WORN. Bnifirm :eticratrita gi unif . TERMS-TWO- DOLLARS A YE'AR-POSTAGE FREE. This invaluable compendium, which was commenced in 1840, and has now reached its Twenty Fourth Number, with the unqualified approbation of the profession, and a very extensive patronage of non-medical readers, has recently passed into the hands of Messrs. STRINGER and TOWNSEND, its present Proprie- tors. It will hereafter be issued by them simultaneously with the London edition, by virtue of an arrangement entered into for the advance proof sheets, with the distinguished author, and will appear regularly on the first days of January and July respectively, in a greatly improved form as regards both paper and typographical execution; these, with the gradual enlargement of the work, and the obligation of the new postage-law, have made the trifling advance on the former price of subscription necessary. The work itself is so well known to the public in general that it -is almost needless to enter into any lengthened descrip-. tion of it. It constitutes a condensed register of medical facts and observations for the past year, and a complete retrospect of all that is valuable and worth pos-' sessing respecting the treatment of disease, gleaned from the British and foreign medical journals, and the transactions of the different societies and associations, and presented to the reader in as condensed a form as possible, and generally in the words of the respective authors. To medical men the great advantage offered by the RETROSPECT is its embody- ing, in a confined space, all the cream of all the medical periodicals, sparing them the labor of wading through many volumes filled with much trivial and unin- teresting matter, which must be perused in order to reach what is really valuable; and supplying them with a key, by aid of which they may find precisely what they require in any of the scattered publications of the day. To families and private individuals it is scarcely less valuable than to the professional reader-- since, although purely and in the highest degree scientific, its contents, are yet presented in a style so simple and unaffected that they are comprehensible to any ordinary intellect.  This admirable digest enjoys, throughout the world, a higher fame in its de- partment, and has a more extensive patronage, than was ever acquired by any other periodical publication. TERMS, invariably in advance, from PART XXXI 'or JTLYY , price $1; $2 per annum. The back numbers, or sets from the commencement, can be had at the following original prices, FREE OF POSTAGE: 24 Pauts, bound in 10 Volumes, Sheep Library Style, 4-2a Fobilme, $20- delivered free of charge. Parts 1 to 12,   .  .     .  50 en   each. s 13 to 22,        .  . 75 Cents each. I'  23, 24: .  .  .  .  .    each. The most liberal terms will be given to Booksellers and Travelling Agents. Wq. B.-Mail subscribers will particularly note that for $2 per annum, paid it qdvawe, the work will reach them POSTAGE FRE, in whatever part of the (Union.  STRINGER &amp; TOWNSEND, Proprietors and Publishers, Y'o. 222 Broadway,N2ew-Yorkh  &#xD;<pb n="132 (Advertisement) -133" xml:id="VAC7078-00000067"/> .^ , :: ^ 7 Stringer and Townsend's Recent Publications. Punch's Humorous Library. MRS. CIA -DLE'S CURTAIN LECTURES. By       Ptnch." With Engravings. New edition, from the revised London issue. 25 ets. PUNCE'S COMPLETE LETTER- WRITER. Do. do. 25 cents. PUTCHVI 'S COURTSHP. 10 Plates.    Do. do. Price 25 cents. PUNCHS HEATHEN MYTHOLOGY. Do. do. Price 25 cents. PUNCH'S LABORS OFHERCULES. Do. do. Price 25 cents. THE LONDONDO   MEDICAL STUDENT. *Do. do. 25 cents. THE LONDON MEDICAL STUDENT (Second Series.) 12 cts. Dickens's Last Great WorIk.  DAVID   COPPERFIEL)D, the Younger.     With Illustrions. Paper covers, price 50 cts.; cloth, 75 cts. STORIES-FROM HO USEHOLD WORDS, by Dickens. "Lizzy Leigh,'" the story of "A Coal Fire." "The Miner's Daughters," and "Loaded Dice  . 2 Nos., each 13 cents. George Sand4s  M 3aster-Pieces., CONSUELO. Four volumes complete in ONE. Price 50 cents. COUNTESS OFRUDOL4FSTADT: Sequel toConsuelo. 50 cents. Madame De Staels Greatest Work. CORINNE; or Italy. Price 50 cents. Douglas Jerroldis Select Works. ST. GrTRS AND ST . J4rMES.4    ted.  Price $8 cente. THE DREA4 AVfZR AR ND WORKER,    Price 25 cents. MARYM-ATURIN; a story of SociDstinctions sc    Price 25 cents. Levers Companion to  c "Charles O'Malley."5 YON CREGA Y, thdirish Gil Bias. By Lever. .Price 25 cents. Lamartine's Best Novel. GENEVIEVE; or, Peasant Love and Sorrow. Price 25 cents. Jenny Lind  i Songster" and i life." THE NIGHTINGtALE; or, Jenny Lid Songster. Price 50 cents. "FE O F JENNY LND. With Steel-Portrait. Price.2 cents. Thackereys Christmas Story. f 'TH. E ICILEBrUR    T    RrHNE With an Essay on the --e- Thunderer's Review (  imes). Price 13 cents.  1'* -; * '  .* *,            , -       &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
