<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7691">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ruth Churchill, or, The True Protestant </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7691</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2146</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ruth Churchill, or, The true Protestant</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>224 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>C. Shepard</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1851">1851</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-03-05">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Ruth Churchill, or, The true Protestant</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7691-00000001"/>RUTH CHURCHILL; OR, Xtmr ntste tant. A TALE FOR THE TIMES. "And the Lord said, Simon! Simon! Satan hath desired to have you, that he may sift you as wheat. But I have iprayed for thee, that thy faith fail not; and AFTER THOU tART CONVEVRTED, strengthen the brethren."-L-uke: Chap. xxii., Verses 31,32. BY A LADY OF VIRGINIA. NEW-YORK: c. SHEPARD &amp; CO., 152 FULTON-STREET.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7691-00000002"/> ENTERED according to Act of Congress, in the year 1851, by C. SHEPARD &amp; CO., in the Office of the Clerk of the United States District Court for the Southelmrn District of New-York. PUmDN Y &amp; R1VSSELL, PRINIETR8.   Note. THE author has no desire to exaggerate the doctrines of the Oxford Tractarians. She has always attributed to them   the belief, that "infants dying unbaptized, cannot be received into heaven." If this doctrine be not openly avoweda in their writ- ings, it is logically inferred from their views of the indisputable necessity, as well-as sovereign efficacy, of Baptism. Unless ori- ginal sin be washed away by the consecrated waters of bap- tism, they deem  it unscriptural to believe that the infant of a day old can be admitted into heaven. &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7691-00000003"/>  PREFACE. THE following simple narrative contains no ex- aggerations of the doctrines of the Oxford Trac- tarians. The author has heard- able and excel- lent men among them deny the necessity of a change of heart, as the preliminary of a Chris- tian profession;a ridicule the idea of conversion, and assert that only Episcopalians have a right to plead the covenant' promises of God. With a full conviction on her mind that these, are dangerous errors, and that their extension will greatly impede the usefulness of the Episcopal Church, she has endeavored  to array against them those powerful and sublime truths on which that Church is founded, as on the Rock of Ages.  &#xD;<pb n="" xml:id="VAC7691-00000004"/>  CHAPTER   I. RUTH CHURCHILL was an orphan, with- out near relatives, and with a very small income. She possessed some natural gifts, however, which were more valuable than mines of gold or silver, and were better friends to her than parents or kindred. A firm, well-ordered mind, a cheerful, ;equable temper, and to crown all, piety of no com- mon order, were her most valuable posses-. sions. Ruth lived till she was five-and-twenty with a maiden  aunt, who was a rigid  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7691-00000005"/> 8     RUTH CHURCHILL. Presbyterian, and enforced in her practice all the peculiarities of that' denomination. On the death of her aunt, she was left to the quiet enjoyment of the mode of faith in which she had been educated, and- to which she was ardently attached. Ruth's grandfather had been a clergyman ill the Episcopal Church, and the prayer-book, which had been his pulpit companion for thirty years, was her most valued posses- sion. Had it been possible to wear out a book by reading, this much-prized volume would possibly have gone to pieces; but it was so, carefully kept, and so tenderly handled, that it still remained in tolerable preservation. How it had been possible for Ruth to live peaceably with her aunt, was a problem never fufiy solved by the neighbors. Miss Patience Patieson was so tenacious of her t   .    RUTH CHURCHILL.      9 own orthodoxy, that she was never known to admit the orthodoxy of any one else. The prayer-book of her niece was a per- petual thorn in her flesh. No one could understand why the book had been suf- fered to occupy a station in full view of the venerable spinster; but there it' always stood, on a little stand in Ruth's own cor- ner, in company with an ancient Bible, and a few other valuable books of devotion. What was even more remarkable, was the fact, that no one ever heard the aunt and niece engaged in controversy, nor did the old lady ever abuse Episcopacy, till the 'door was fairly closed upon her niece. Then, indeed, her wan eyes twinkled, and her pale cheek flushed, as she shook her fist at the obnoxious prayer-book, and burst forth in- abuse of what she called treble- refined popery. But Ruth patiently endured 2   &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7691-00000006"/> : 10     RUTH CHURCHILL. all her trials-so patiently, indeed, that many persons thought she had no feeling, and others thought she was not aware that every body differed from her in opinion. True fortitude is often mistaken for in- sensibility. Ruth had never been the spoilt child of prosperity. Her mind had been strengthened by what the world called self- reliance, but which was in reality a firm trust in the only unchanging friend, the Sa- viour of sinners. The comfort derived from this source must be felt, to be understood. Ruth had tested it too long and too thor- oughly to doubt its    sufficiency for every human exigency; yet she would gladly have opened her heart to the' sym- pathy of her fellow beings. There are mo- ments when human weakness yearns for that interchange of feeling, which exercises the gentler sensibilities of our nature, and corn-   RUTH CHURCHILL.      " forts us with the assurance that we are un- derstood and appreciated by those around us. On the death of Miss Patieson, Ruth re- moved to a small cottage occupied by an old widow lady and her not very young daughter. Here she met with respect and kindness; but her associates were not very congenial to her tastes. The little pro- perty she possessed, yielded her a certain, though small income. In having this, she was better off than most of her compan- ions, who earned their daily bread by their daily labor. She paid a moderate sum for her board and lodging, and the neighbors looked up to her, because she  was not wholly dependent on others for a   main- tenance. Ruth Churchill could   remember when she sat under the ministry of the Episco- pal Church; but a   very long time had  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7691-00000007"/> 12     RUTH CHURCHILL. elapsed since the enjoyment of this privilege. Her lot had been cast among humble people, who did not aspire to what they called a genteel religion-in other words, a religion suited to educated and refined persons. V' We cannot aread well enough to be Epis- copalians," they would say. "People would laugh at us, if we tried to read in' public service. The Baptists' and Methodists: religion suit our homely ways the best." Ruth attended the places of public wor-- ship within her reach, and tried to feel her- self at home in every house of God; but herheart yearned, nevertheless, for the or- dinances of her own Church. Yet she did not repine at the privation so evidently imposed upon her by Providence. In short, her religion was deeply rooted in the heart, and no external circumstance could deprive her of its pleasures and its benefits. With   lRUTH CHURCHILL.     13 her Bible and Prayer-book she could make eheart glad, without any other accesso- ries to spiritual enjoyment. ' She loved to as- sociate with those who loved the Lord, what- ever might be their modes of worship. She sought the companionship of Christians of every denomination, anrid with these she di- lated on the wonders of redeeming love. Miss Patience had often said that the Liturgy was but an abridgment of the mass book; but one sleepless night she over- heard Ruth repeating the Litany in a low, earnest voice. From that hour she forbore all censure of the prayer-book to the day of- her death. Ruth had her own thoughts, when she one day found her aunt's thread paper between the leaves of -her prayer- book; but she said nothing, and no full discovery was ever made on the subject. Occasionally, when coarse, unlettered men  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7691-00000008"/> "'     RUTH CHURCHILL. led the worship in her church, Miss Pru- dence swas overheard  muttering, " that forms were better than such stuff;" and once she actually asked her niece to read the Psalms from the Psalter to her. 'I've heard people say they were nothing like the Psalms in the Bible," said she, "and I want to judge for myself." About five years after Miss Patieson's death, Ruth received a letter by mail, which seemed to promise a change in her mode of life. This epistle was from a distant relative, who had recently married an Episcopal clergyman, and .was actually coming to live in Ruth's immediate neigh- borhood. She had never known this cousin, in the third degree, and had little dreamed of ever becoming an inmate of her fami- ly. Yet the letter contalined a cordial in- vitation to Ruth, at which her heart bound-   RUTH CHURCHILL.      15 ed. The Rev. Mr. Hilton had just been ordained, and the Bishop of his diocese had appointed him a station in one of the waste places of Zion. Ruth certainly took little rest the night after she heard this stirring news. She rose at sunrise the next day, and went forth to meditate in the early morning. In spite of her efforts to curb the rest- less thoughts which beset her, she found herself borne .onward into the future by an irresistible impulse.  She pondered on the blessedness of associating with Epis- copalians; of hearing some other voice be- side her own read the sublime collects and prayers of her Church.  She thought of the privilege of Church-membership- of the happiness of enjoying at least a close sympathy of feeling and communion of thought with intelligent Christians. How t  i p   &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7691-00000009"/> 16 /    RUTH. CHURCHILL. delightful, thought she, " to enjoy perfect reciprocity of sentiment, and entire union of opinion--to think, feel, and act in unison with others for the first time in my life." Ruth dwelt, also, on the pleasures of refined intercourse, and felt herself approaching the consummation of every earthly  wish of her heart. Poor girl! she thought that the world abounded in Chrlistians far more advanced in holiness than herself, and she longed to profit by their example. It was her constant aim   to grow in grace and improve in holiness. In a short time after she freceived Mrs. Hilton's letter, Ruth heard that the new Rector had actually arrived. He soon paid her a visit, accompanied   by his wife, whose easy, unaffected manners gained the favor of all who saw her.  "You must come to us, dear cousin," said she, " as   RUTH CHURCHILL.      17 soon as we can get over the bustle and confusion of a new settlement." This frank and cordial invitation was warmly seconded by the Rector. "We shall soon have a little church established in this wilderness," said he; "five or six Episco- pal families will settle around us.. Money has already been subscribed to build a house of worship, and I shall commence holding the services in a large room in a warehouse immediately. They have given me quite a   decent house, with ground enough to plant trees and lay off a gar- den. The house has some   odd, quaint- looking  furniture in it ready for use, so that we  can go into it without delay." The Rector added some high compliments to Ruth, which jarred painfully on her feelings. She was afraid of commendation, and it made her uneasy to think that great 3  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7691-00000010"/> 18     RUTH CHURCHILL. things were expected of her. But those who never flatter themselves are rarely hurt by the praise of others. In fact, every thing was arranged in a short time, and Ruth was informed that her cousins wished her to join them with- out delay. Her quarter was nearly up with Mrs. Brown, and she gave notice to the good widow of her intended removal. But the very day before the one fixed: for her removal, the scarlet fever made its appearance in Mrs. Brown's family. This good lady had an interesting grand-daughter residing with her, to whom Ruth had be- come much attached. This child showed symptoms of illness, which alarmed her grandmother exceedingly. Ruth could not resist the joint entreaties of all her humble friends to postpone her removal. The case became speedily so critical that her ser-   RUTH CHURCHILL.      19 vices as a nurse were thought indispensa- ble. Ruth was untiring in cases where rest and comfort were to be sacrificed for the benefit of others. She never seemed to regard loss of sleep as an evil, and her sound health enabled her to sustain all sorts of bodily discomforts without injury. The child died on the ninth day, and Ruth bore all the additional burden of prepar- ing for the funeral, &amp;c. Then came the requisite period of quarantine, for it was thought dangerous to receive persons who had been exposed to infection for a con- siderable time after such exposure. Two whole months elapsed before Ruth found herself safely established as an inmate of the Rectory. Mrs. Hilton was charmed to have a companion.  She launched out in mingled complaints and self-gratulations as  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7691-00000011"/> 20     RUTH CHURCHILL. soon as she had installed her guest in a comfortable apartment under her roof: "Charles has longed for you," said she. "He needs help sadly, for even the Epis- copalians seem wofully ignorant of the doctrines and forms of their Church. You would have been amused in spite of your- self, had you been here the first Sunday he preached. Old Mr. IDay, it seems, had been churchwarden somewhere or other, before he came to this parish. Mr. Hil- ton asked him if the people understood the use of the prayer-book, and if there were decent singers to sustain their part in the service. He said, '0, yes; when the church is built, and an organ is procured. The neighborhood abounds in good singers; you will soon have a first rate choir, and Mrs. Dean will play the organ.  She is   RUTH CHURCHILL.      21 music teacher here, and a very good one. Don't fear for the musical department.' Well, when Sunday came, we went to church, and saw quite a number of peo- ple ranged in respectful attention round the long room. A sort of stage had been erected, instead of a pulpit. Charles took his place, and opened the worship. Mr. Day had to prompt people smartly, and he did it rather noisily and ostentatiously. But Charles got on pretty well, 'till he came  to  the ante-communion service. It seems that Mr. Day had not been used to hearing   this read, and  he was wofully put out by  it. When the Psalm had been sung, and the Rector turned to kneel down, Mr. Day   stood up with his mouth wide open. I heard him say ' Pillikens,' (a sort of by-word he uses.) Presently after, he began to tug at Charles' surplice, saying,  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7691-00000012"/> 22   ^  RUTH CH URCHLL in quite a loud whisper, 'Parson!* Par- son! where's all this? I can't find it in tile prayer-book.' Fharles very quietly showed him the place in his prayer-book, and hoped the difficulty was ended; but he was mistaken. Poor Mr. Day felt worse than ever; the loud whisper was renewed. 'Oh, the Communion! you ought to have told me. I hav'nt got the elements ready -you can't have it to-day.'  I felt so much for poor Charles, that my face was in -a glow, and I could not recover my- self entirely till the service was finished. But all these difficulties ended with that day, and Mr. Day has learned all what he calls the niceties of the service. Charles is indefatigable. He has gone, I verily be- lieve, to every house in the parish; and, would you think it, there are people who * Fact.   RUTH CHURCHILL.      23 call themselves Episcopalians, who have small reverence for some  of our ordi- nances? They actually dispute with Mr. Hilton when he tells them   that baptism Vwill wash away their sins. There is one old woman who is very stubborn in, error. Charles wants you to visit her.   She is sick, and probably near her end; but she will not be comforted or supported by the ordinances of the Church." Ruth Churchill was mortified and dis- tressed at this recital. Religion had al- ways appeared to her so solemn a thing, that she could not endure the slightest shade of irreverence or levity in those who spoke of it. She felt a little restless, to say no more, under the idea that all the world did not view the subject as she did. Charles, to do hin justice, was solemn and reverential enough; but there was some-   &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7691-00000013"/> 24      RUTH CHURCHILL, thing wanting, Ruth could not tell what, in his habitual modes of' speech. These feelings, however, were all lost in the important duty of preparation for the rite of Confirmation, which was to be ad- ministered by the Bishop of the Diocese on the following Sunday. Ruth had never been confirmed. She was anxious to com- ply with all the requirements of her Church, and felt great satisfaction in the anticipa- tion of that solemn rite, which was to bind her forever to the Church she most re- vered on earth. ,  .       CHAPTER II. THE following Sunday was a day of in- expressible comfort to Ruth  Churchill. She was confirmed, and for the first time in her life received the Communion accord- ing to the forms of the Episcopal Church. We have already stated that our heroine had attended   the  ordinances  of other churches, and  had been kindly received by people of all denominations. Her aunt had  often importuned her "to throw  off the shackles of prelacy, and stand forth a real Christian, free to pray in her own words, and worship in the simple manner of holy men of  old." But a glance  at her ever-present prayer-book had often been 4  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7691-00000014"/> 26     RUTH CHURCHILL. Ruth's sole reply to these entreaties. Miss Patience had refrained from unavailing re- monstrance, and she loved Ruth too well to have recourse to persecution. The visit of the Bishop had been brief. He had been so much engrossed by pa- rochial affairs, as to have little time for in- dividual attentions. He said a few strong words to Ruth at parting, which dwelt un- pleasantly on her memory after he was gone. He told her that her position was a most important one. "I shall rely on your exertions," said he, 'in aid of Mr. Hilton's efforts to establish and- maintain good Epis- copal order in this newly-planted church. When I return to consecrate the church, which will soon arise in this waste spot, I trust I shall find great changes wrought through your united efforts." Ruth was startled by this address. She   RUTH CHURCHILL.      27 had never, inll her deep humility of heart, believed herself capable of helping any one; on the contrary, she had an abiding sense of her own weakness, and a yearn- ing desire to  receive help from  others. Her clear strong sense of moral rectitude promised to secure her from the -adoption of dangerous errors. This-sense is usually strongest in people who have  never been flattered  into thinking themselves firm enough  to  stand  alone. She drew her spiritual strength from an unfailing source. She gathered her manna daily, and pre- pared herself anew for every exigency of life. Above all, she tried to keep world- ly motives from  mingling with her judg- rments of men and things. There was something irresistibly pleasing in Ruth's countenance and manners. She was not handsome, but  she had an eye  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7691-00000015"/> 28     RUTH CHURCHILL, that spoke of better things than beauty. Few could know her, without loving her. Her voice, too, had that soothing charm of musical intonation, which carries words straight to the heart. She soont became a general favorite in her new neighborhood, and Charles Hilton and his wife blessed the day when she became an inmate of their dwelling. Sophia Hilton was a well-meaning, warm-hearted woman. She had been educated at a fash- ionable boarding-school, where a foundation had been laid for almost every thing but religion. On her return home, she em- barked on a career of ease and self-in- dulgence. She had no parents, but a child- less aunt received her as a prize into her family, and determined to enhance her own consequence in society by bringing forth the attractions of her niece. .  '   ^   "  '  '.    RUTH CHURCHILL.     29 One day, this aunt was visited by a re- lation, who bore a high character in the world for piety and good sense. The next day Sophia was surprised to see her aunt enter her room, with a grave countenance, - holding a Bible in her hand; she seated herself' and looked earnestly at her niece. "Sophia, my child," said she, with a se- rious tone, " my kinsman lectured me last night till he made me shed tears. He told me, among other disagreeable things, that I had compromised your eternal safety, by letting you grow up without religion. Now, my dear child, I cannot give you what I have not got.  I could as soon give you a million of dollars, as I could give you Christianity. It is a boon which never was conferred on me.  No  one has a greater respect for religion than I have, but no one can be more entirely ignorant of its  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7691-00000016"/> '30     RUTH CHURCHILLO requirements; its doctrines, and I may say its influences, than myself. I have thought little about it; and, to speak the truth, have been unwilling to think about it. Be it my fault or my misfortune, I must plead guilty to great negligence on this subject. I have been afraid of reading the Bible, lest I should become an angry controver- sialist, like Mrs. , or a furious bigot, like Mrs.   -.  It has appeared  to me,  that people no  sooner become religious, than they get obstinate or illi- beral. But let this pass. I have brought you a Bible, and I request, nay, I com- mand you to read it.' What! aunt," exclaimed Sophia, "under the penalty of becoming obstinate or illiberal --of being a bigot or a controversialist?-- Methinks I had rather continue what I am-the pet and pupil of my dear, kind, , -.   RUTH CHURCHILL.      3  indulgent aunt." So saying, she threw her arms caressingly around the lady. But these blandishments were unavailing to turn aside the current of her aunt's reflections. ("Sophy, dear," returned she, "If you love me, you will do what I require. I only wish I could repeat all that 'I heard last night. My heart has been heavy ever since. My kinsman said some fearful things, Sophia.  I am resolved to read my Bible every day, from 'this time forward, and I earnestly entreat you to do the same."-. Sophia felt awed .in spite of her resolution to be light-hearted and  careless. "Well, aunt," said she, "give me  this important volume. I   promise you to read a little in it every day, perseveringly, till I get, as old Hugh says, from  Genesis to finis. Don't frown, dear aunt, I  will be serious," added she, seeing that mirth was o ut of place. ,.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7691-00000017"/> RUTH CHURCFHTILL. "I know that Christianity is a holy thing, and( hope I shall one day think more of it than- I do now, as a rule of action."  "Ah, Sophia!" sighed the aunt, "I shall join 'with all my heart in that 1hope. Per- haps better thoughts 1may come to us both. Last night I said, 'that I always had in- tended to become a Christian, when I had thrown off worldly influences.' I would you could have seen my kinsman.   He looked sternly at me, and said, 'How do you know that your tardy sacrifice will be accepted? Will God receive the world- tainted spirit, the sin-debased heart, with- out repentance? It is said in the Book of-Truth, that He denounces such, and bids them depart, as accursed! from his presence.' Oh, Sophy! I could not rest on my pillow with such thoughts in my mind. Indeed, I mean to begin this very   RUTH CHURCHTL.     33 day, and read the bible regularly." From this time, Sophy endeavored with sincerity to interest herself in the Bible. She gave up many of her worldly pleasures, and sought the companionship of serious people. "Things were in this state," said Sophia, when I became acquainted with NMr. iil- ton. After that, every thing became com- paratively easy to me. I read more, and listened to sermons with more interest. In due time I was baptized, confirmed, and received the Eucharist. I am very happy now, and no doubt it is Religion that makes me so." -Such was the companion and friend of Ruth Churchill. Our heroine was eminently endowed with the philosophy that makes the best of every thing: ay, and true Christian philosophy it is, for it is allied to that charity which 5  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7691-00000018"/> 34     RUTH CHURCHILL. "beareth all things--hopeth all things- and is not easily provoked." Ruth found quite as much delight as she expected in using her beloved prayer-book in the services of the Sanctuary.  She remembered how her aunt used to declare that she " should be worried to death by the incessant repetition of the same thing over and over again. 'Tis just like 'the house that Jack built,' Ruth. I wonder you can pretend to like it." , You forget, aunt," Ruth  would say calmly, "that the silly rhyme you mention, owes its influence over children solely to its constant recurrence. Now, the sublime litany, and the heart-stirring collects of our worship, make to themselves a high-way to the heart, by  the very repetition of -which you complain." "But, don't you get tired of it, child?" per- sisted Miss Patience. "I am sure I should."   RUTH CHURCHILL.      35 "No, dear aunt, I cannot tire of good things. We never become weary of sleep, do we?-On the contrary, nothing disturbs us more than the incidental interruption of our stated slumbers. We do not get tired of our regular meals, but find their stated recurrence essential to our comfort. We see our friends again and again, without wearying of their society. Nay, we love them the more the oftener we see them, if they are worthy of our love. The love of change is one of our natural infirmities; and those who encourage it never attain excellence in: anything.  Constancy is a virtue, and everything which encourages it is valuable to us. "Does the mother ever weary of the en- ' dearing prattle of her children? In short, are not all really good things made more precious to us, by the constant, unremitting enjoyment of them?  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7691-00000019"/> ' 36    RUTH CHURCHILL.  "I have listened often with comfort and  3 edification to extemporaneous prayer; but I must acknowledge that ignorant men often address their Maker in language very ill chosen and unsuitable. I always think,  that in the Bible, God addresses His people,  and in the, Prayer-book His people answer  ,Him. Holy men of old, caught the Spirit of the Bible, and transfused it into the forms contained in the prayer-book. It is there that we find the very words of in- spiration adapted to the wants of our souls. It -is a peculiar language, holy, and sublime, and eloquent. The oftener we re- peat it, the more we are struck withits fitness to our wants. We must feel it, while we read it, for its words are bor- rowed from heaven." "But, child," said the indefatigable Miss Patience, .the Episcopalians say nobody   RUTH CHURCHILL.     37 has a right to use his own words in prayer." "Oh, dear  aunt, I think  you are mistaken," said Ruth, earnestly. "I never heard Episcopalians make such an asser- tion. I know that my grandfather used his own words in prayer, for I have seen prayers composed by him, and written with his own .hand. They breathe the same spirit of piety which distinguishes all the compositions truly inspired by the Holy Spirit. Don't you remember, aunt, when once a young Presbyterian preached in your neighborhood--you owned that you thought his language inappropriate, and even offensive, and would not go to hear him again?" "Ay! child," said   Miss Patience, "I dare say such a thing may have occurred, but don't draw your conclusions too strongly from it. One swallow never yet made a summer."  The fact, however, could-not  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7691-00000020"/> 38     RUTH CHURCHILL. be denied. Miss Patience had lost herself, I j that is, her patience, on this occasion. The young man in question had called so   ; irreverently on the Supreme Being, that all persons of right notions had been    shocked. One old woman, after groaning   j in spirit for a few moments, actually called out, "Stop, lad! the Lord is neither thy kinsman nor thy servant, that thou should order him about in that fashion. Remem- ber the old saw: 'Too much familiarity breeds contempt."' Miss Patience always felt discomposed when this incident was mentioned. The most distant allusion to it would call up a blush upon her sallow  j cheek. Although Ruth derived much enjoyment from her' new privileges, there was an un- l defined feeling of disappointment pressing upon her heart. Episcopacy was not ex-   RUTH CHURCHILL,     39 actly what she had imagined. There was something inconclusive and unsatisfactory in her first impressions. Her cousins were estimable and kind-hearted. They treated her with distinction and confidence. Mr. Hilton relied upon her aid in draw- ing wanderers into his fold. "Talk with them, Ruth," he would say, , you have- an endearing manner that wins their con- fidence. From all that I have seen, the Episcopal Church is miserably underrated here. Even   its most stanch adherents do not understand it fully-do not ap- preciate it properly. Tell them it is the true road to heaven: the only 'Church in which salvation can be found. They don't think enough of the prayer-book. Teach them its inestimable value. Tell them it it the only guide to truth-the only true source of knowledge.' It is the voice of          ,         +  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7691-00000021"/> 40     RUTH CHURCHILL. the Church, and they seem  to regard it only as a record of its forms." Ruth listened. She could not assent to all that Mr. -Hilton advanced, and yet -she shrank from proclaiming her dissent to some of his opinions. The fact was, that her secluded -situation had kept her in ig- norance of much that had passed and was passing in the world. She discovered by slow degrees -that some portions of the Church to which she -was so much at- tached, had undergone changes, like all other earthly things. There is a restless desire for mutation prevalent among the sons of men.  Opinion has its tides like the ocean; these rise and fall, ebb and flow, in stated measure. Ever and anon the quiet watchers of the current of hu- man affairs discover some new impulse agitating the realm of thoughts, and pro-   RUTH CHURCHILL.    "41 ducing changes and  revolutions within. Laborious thinkers plunge into the vortex, and often lose themselves in hidden quick- sands. Most persons skim the surface, and finding here and there a strong rip- ple, they attribute it to some departure from the old channel of truth, upon which they break out into vehement lamenta- tions, and cry out, "The Church is in danger." We have strayed from the old ways of truth and holiness. Let us go back, and gather up the maxims we have lost. Let us revive old usages, and de- vote ourselves to the re-establishment of God's tabernacle among men.  But it is the spirit which has languished and needs revival. Forms enough  remain, to mark out the distinguishing characteristics of the Church. The fault is not in the outward fabric, but in the inward falling off from 6  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7691-00000022"/> 42     RUTH CHURCHILL. grace and holiness. Let Christians go to the fountain of life, and drink freely' of its waters. They will be renovated and strengthened. But they see not their own deficiency; they toil and toil for that which is not bread, while their souls be- come faint for want of pure nourishment. Remember the case of Hagar in the wilder- ness. She despaired of comfort; her faith was weak. She thought only of the things she had left behind, and deemed herself forsaken of God. She was not taken back to the dwellings of men, and supplied with comforts from their abundance;-No:    she was visited by a messenger from hea- ven, who showed her the fountain of liv- ing waters, opened for her use in the san- dy desert.  No doubt, in her hopeless misery, she thought that God abided in   I the home from which she had been ex- ,   RUTH CHURCHILL.      43 pelled, and 'could be found nowhere else. Thus it is with desponding  Christians: They grieve sincerely over the spiritual declension so obvious around them; but they mistake its causes, and increase the evil by using ineffectual remedies. God will send His Spirit to revive His Church, when Christians feel their real want of it, and ask it at His hands.  But as long as they multiply forms, and think to please God by so doing, they will make small progress towards holiness. Some people are so constituted as to find comfort in exaggerated rites- and multiplied ordinances. In the infinite variety of human charac- ters, there are many, no doubt, to whom the ministrations of the Spirit are as sealed lI mysteries. In the time of the Apostles even, there were men who "had not so much as heard of the Holy Ghost," while  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7691-00000023"/> "     RUTH CHURCHILL. others were rejoicing in its cleansing and sanctifying influences. Is it not so with us in these present days? Many stop short of a healing, saving, comforting faith, be- cause they seek it not according to God's appointed means.  They take counsel of the world, which always finds delight in forms, and deludes its votaries into the belief that a true Christian course is come patible with much  worldly  conformity. Those who rely on the inward ministra- tions of the Spirit, forsake the  world through choice. They need not its ex-     i citements. They ilove not its pursuits. Purer tastes predominate, for they are trans- I formed by the renewing of their :minds, until they have proved what is good and ac- ceptable in the will of God.  To people so transformed, mere worldly indulgences have no charm.  They obey the precept,   RUTH CHURCHILL.     4-5 "Be ye not conformed to the world," with- out difficulty, for they have no desire to partake the enjoyments of the worldly- minded,         .... . *  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7691-00000024"/> CHAPTER III. Mr. HLTON had been called in to give spiritual counsel to a dying woman, who had become a frequenter of the Episcopal Church under his ministry. The family to which she belonged were of the lower order of society, but highly respectable in character, and  independent in circum- stances. They had come into the Church for the first time when Mr. Hilton. be- came Rector .of the parish to which they belonged. Mr. and Mrs. Burns, the united head of this family, were people of sound judgment and consistent piety. They had frequented other churches before Mr. Hil-   RUTH CHURCHILL.     4" ton arrived, and had been sedulous culti- vators of a Christian spirit. Having al- ways had a yearning towards Episcopacy, they were rejoiced to see that form  of worship revived in their neighborhood. Their children had been carefully train- ed as candidates for eternity; and Chris- tian principles inculcated as the only pre- servatives of moral worth.  There was one hindrance to these good works, how- ever. Mrs. Blodget, the mother of Mrs. Burns, resided with her children, and threw many obstacles in the way of their Christian practice. It was this old woman who lay dangerously ill, and called vehe- mently for the consolations of religion. She had never cared for religion, according to her own account, until Mr. Hilton came into the neighborhood. During his first round of parochial visits, he had been  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7691-00000025"/> 48     RUTH CHURCHILL. much pleased with the state of things in Burns's family. His children were ready with their catechism, and the parents show- ed a satisfactory knowledge of the Bible, and reverence for the prayer-book. Fami- ly religion had evidently been cultivated; and the intelligent replies of Burns and   e his wife showed no ordinary acquaintance with the holy truths of the Bible.       Mr. Hilton was much gratified with what he deemed a prosperous commencement    A of his ministry. During his visit to this  X orthodox family, the Rector had noticed a   ] tall, spare figure, seated in the warmest , corner of the hearth, earnestly plying some  i household thrift. He thought her counte- nance harsh, and her manner discourteous; but she was old, and evidently infirm, and suffering. He spoke to her of joining his  Church, taking  it for granted  that the    RUTH CHURCHILL.     4 9 seriousness and piety of the family had emanated from her. She answered gruffly, that her daughter Kesia had dumb-founded her about religion. She did not deny that it was a mighty good thing; but her knees were not equal to all the kneeling, and rising, and standing stock still, that Episcopalians had to do. Besides, her eyes were dim, and she could not read in Church. She liked those Churches best, where the parson did all the read- ing himself. Mr. Hilton met all these objections as well as he could. He told her that infirm persons were not required to  kneel in Church--that she should be excused from reading the responses in consideration of her dim sight. "Your hearing seems to be good," added he, " and that is a great bles- ing, Your daughter can stand at your side, 7  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7691-00000026"/> 50     RUTH CHURCHILL. and read loud enough for you to hear. But there iso a grand-daughter, large enough and smart enough to do all your reading. Will you not take that duty upon your- self, Amy?" asked he, of a very intelli- gent girl of fourteen. Amy stammered, and looked confused. The fact was, that no- thing offended the old woman so much as to be put off, as she called it, upon her grand-children. She hated children, she said. Tile little ones lived in constant fear of the rod, which lay always beneath her chair. She never spoke a kind word to them. Her daughter never ventured, in the utmost extremity of her haste, to request her to take charge of an infant, even for a moment; on the contrary, Kesia's mater- nal duties had frequently to be set aside to gratify the exacting humor of a selfish mother. She complained incessantly that   RUTH CHURCHIL. 5L1 children never cared for their parents now-a-days-that all reverence for age had left the world. Many people more mod- erate and right judging than Mrs. Blodget, agree with her in the last opinion. Old people are of less value in society than they ought to be. One morning, Mrs. Hilton entered Ruth's room at an early hour. "Cousin Ruth," said she, "Charles has been summoned to two places at once, and he wishes you and myself to undertake one part of the duty for him. Old Mrs. Blodget is much worse, and she wants some one to read and pray by her bed-side."  Ruth was soon equipped for walking, and the two females went off together. The distance was long, and the -way rough. On their way, they  encountered the blacksmith's wife who had been sitting up with the sick woman.  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7691-00000027"/> 52     RUTH CHURCHILL. ' "Neighbor Blodget is powerful bad, la- dies," said she. , I thought she would have gone off in a passion last night. Dr. Bland tried to comfort her, but she as good as told him he knew nothing about religion."   "Stick to your drugs," says she; "they     j are of little account, to be sure, but you  ! know  something about them. It's your business to physic people. You are called in -to their bodies-so let their souls alone, if you please." Now, Doctor Bland, the Churchwarden, was a man of eminent piety-one who could explain the Gospel as, well as the Dispensary. Ruth knew him well, and valued him  highly. He was a Christian after her own heart. The two ladies found Mrs. Blodget in a most distressing condition. Before her case had become hopeless, her daughter and son-in-law had tried earnestly to ex- u. ....i   RUTH CHURCHILL.     53' plain the leading truths of the Gospel to 'her. But her mind seemed to resist con- viction obstinately and angrily. ,c You talk as if I was not a Christian," said she.  "Ain't I a member of the Church? I have been baptized-I have been confirmed--I have taken the com- munion. What more do you want? What did I join the Church for, but to get rid of all your strong talk about Christianity? I think religion ought to give me some com- fort now. Since I have put myself under the care of the Church, the Church ought to help me. But I have no comfort, and none of you can give me any. You havn't the right to help me. Let Mr. Hilton come. He can tell me that 1 am   safe. I won't listen to any of you. There was Kesia talking to me about my cruelty (as she called it) to my daughter Jessie; she wanted  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7691-00000028"/> 54:     RUTH CHURCH'ILL. me to send for her, and forgive her for mar- rying against my wishes. What nonsense! I cau't forgive her; she don't deserve to be forgiven. I am glad to hear that she is poor and miserable. She shall never see the color of my money. Ain't it my own?  Who has a right to it, I should like to know?" "Ah, mother," said Kesia, "you would feel better, if you could forgive poor Jessie ; and as for your money, mother, what comfort has it given you? You have kept it locked up for years, and never helped your children in their utmost need.  If you had used it for yourself, they would never have asked for it.  But there it lies-several hundred dollars." "How came you to know how much I have?" screamed out the dying woman ; "where, and when, did you see it? I wish to know."   RUTH CHURCHILL.     55 "Mother," said Kesia, "you talked about it when you. were light-headed. You told Mrs. Robbins last night, that you had exactly----- "Stop, stop! I command you," cried the mother, brandishing her arms. "Don't say another word. I never did tell about it. You have looked over my shoulders, when I was counting it, secretly." "Mother," exclaimed Kesia, "don't ac- cuse your own daughter of such meanness. I never saw your money. I don't know where you keep it." Ruth felt much scandalized at this scene. She waited for Sophia to speak, and find- ing that she looked perplexed and un- happy, she drew near the bed, and spoke with solemnity. "Mrs. Blodget," said she, "we   are all sinners-we all need a Sa- viour. You have neglected to find Him  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7691-00000029"/> 56     RUTH CHURCHILL, out, and seek His help, until your life is near its close. Let me entreat you, for your own sake, to call on the Redeemer of sinners, and lay your own load of sin ' at His feet, 'ere it be too late. God is merciful. Shut your eyes to all but your present troubles. Acknowledge yourself to be a sinner. Call on the Great Author of Salvation; say to Him, ' Save, Lord! or I perish.' You have but a brief spacte between you and the grave-the cold dark grave-where the worm will be your com- panion. Think of the terrors which await the impenitent. Think of the blessings of forgiveness. The time is short. Waste no more of its precious moments in idle mur- murs and angry complaints.   Make haste and forgive, if you would be forgiven. Re- member the conditions ;" and Ruth slowly and reverently repeated the Lord's prayer.   RUTH CHURCHILL.     57 She then opened the bible, and read the account of the thief on the cross. "Here you learn the fullness of heavenly mercy," said she, impressively. "Will you ask for- giveness? Will you throw off the deadly weight of  sin which crushes your soul at this moment? Mrs. Burns,", said' she, in a loud  whisper, "send   for Jessie. Let her be told that her mother is dying, and  she must be here to receive her forgiveness." "Not yet, not yet!" murmured the poor I   creature, writhing in agony. "Give me \i  time. "You cannot have time," said Ruth, em- phatically. "Your speech is failing. You may not be able to utter the words an -  hour hence. Death is hovering near your pillow." The dying woman turned her eyes, as i   pil i'-  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7691-00000030"/> '58    RUTH CHURCHILL. if expecting to behold the messenger of Heaven. She then made a feeble attempt to put her hand beneath her bolster. Ruth saw her purpose. She thrust her hand into the place on which the glazing eye still rested, and drew forth a pocket-book. The sick woman grasped it in her death- agony. "That," said Ruth, pointing to the book, "Iies between you and heaven. You can- not hope for pardon with a deadly weight like that upon your soul. Make one great effort--cast from you the mammon of unrighteousness. Send for your erring daughter; give her that money which has held your soul enthralled so long. What is it to you, at this moment? If you die without bestowing it upon the child whose need is greatest, the law will divide it in useless fractions among your family. If i   I         RUTH CHURCHILL.      69 you give it entire to poor Jessie, it may help her in her extreme exigency." Ruth spoke so calmly, her voice was so impres- sive, and her manner so persuasive, that the dying woman listened as if spell-bound. She breathed slowly and heavily; life was ebbing  away, but all pain  had  ceased. Ruth knelt, and, slowly repeated the pray- ers for the dying. A soft tap at the door was followed by   the entrance of Jessie, drowned in tears, and looking more like a spectre than a living creature. Mrs. Blod- get started, and  raised her eyes towards her  unfortunate  daughter. At first they were covered by   the death film, but for one  fleeting moment their vision cleared, and  she beheld the pale phantom beside her. "Mother," said Jessie, "I shall soon follow you.  I, too, am dying," and a hol- ow   cough  interrupted her speech. 'Let  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7691-00000031"/> 60     RUTH CHUZRCHLL. us part in peace. I have sinned and suf- fered, till my very feelings are dead with- in me."  The dying woman raised the hand which held her treasure. It trem- bled with an uncertain movement. Ruth guided it towards the weeping Jessie. "Take it," said a hollow voice, "and may God pardon me, as I have pardoned you. It was my idol. Oh, make it not yours!" She never spoke again, but lay com- paratively calm  and composed. In Less than an hour she drew her last breath. As Ruth and Sophia returned home after the death-scene just described, the latter sighed frequently, and appeared much op- pressed by melancholy feelings. Ruth, on the contrary, advanced with a firmer step than usual, and seemed rather excited than depressed. "I shall tell Charles how admirably you-   Il         :ERUTH CHURCHILL.     61 :j1t  have performed the task he appointed you," ,:H;gi said Sophia, smiling faintly. "I was really H    wonder-struck at your self-possessed man- ner, dear cousin. How  did you acquire    it. For my- part, I never can say a word on such occasions. I long to become use- ;:   ful to my husband, and I know   he ex-  pects it of me; but when the pinch comes, I am bereft of speech. I often con over very good things to myself. suitable for such occasions-, but when the time comes for    saying them, they are gone.   How  can you remember so much that is apposite and appropriate? You spoke as smoothly, and continuously, as if you had been a prac- tised orator. Have you any formula or manual to furnish you with words?" Ruth smiled, and answered, "Oh, yes, I follow  explicit directions, or I should never get along."   &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7691-00000032"/> 62     RUTH CHURCHILL. "Pray, Ruth, tell me where they are, that I may qualify myself for usefulness in times like the present," said Sophia, with simplicity.  "These are my rules," answered Ruth, in the same tone: ,Take no thought how, or what ye shall speak, for it shall be given you in that same hour what you are to speak. 'For it is not you that speak, but the Spirit of your Father which speaketh in you,' (10th chapter Matthew, 20th verse.)' "And you really  believe, Ruth, that God's Spirit puts words into your mouth? You, a simple unlearned girl," said Sophia, gravely. "Now, I should be afraid to en- tertain such thoughts. Do they not savor of presumption? Why, ministers them- selves, ordained and accredited as chosen- of God, are almost afraid to believe such things."   RUTH CHURCHILL.      63 "Why should they," said Ruth calmly, "or why should I hesitate to believe what has been said, 'And it shall come to pass, saith the Lord, that I will pour out my spirit upon all flesh, and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy,' (2 chap. Acts.) Besides, we are expressly told that these things shall be revealed unto babes;' also, 'that we must receive the kingdom  of' heaven as little children :'that is, with full confidence and childlike sim- plicity. Believe me, cousin, it is through believing too little, and not too much, that we fall into dangerous- errors. The mo- ment we begin to restrict ourselves in the degree of our faith,' we get into danger." Sophia sighed.  "You did not appear to believe that Mrs. Blodget was a  Christian at all," said she, "and yet my   husband said she  was one. He  told me  to re-  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7691-00000033"/> "     RUTH CHURCHILLo mind her of her baptismal obligations, and to warn her not to bring reproach upon the Church  which had  taken her into God's covenant, and given her a, right to all its benefits." "Did you think her a Christian?" asked Ruth. We are expressly told, 'by their fruits ye shall know them.' Think you she had borne any such fruits?" "( Alas! it is all a mystery to me. Some- times I think, cousin Ruth, though you are so good and lovable, that you are not a true Episcopalian. My husband does not admit one thing  on which you lay great stress. I mean what you call a change of heart, or conversion.' He thinks that baptism makes the 'Christian. Surely the prayer-book teaches that doctrine." "My dear cousin," answered Ruth, with deep seriousness, ( the prayer-book and   RUTH CHURCHILL.    / 65 the Bible teach the same things.   Our Saviour expressly says, in the third chap- ter of John, 'Except you be borln again, you cannot enter the kingdom of heaven.' Surely, our beloved and revered  Church wears this doctrine in her heart of hearts, for it is the very seal of her commission on earth. lWhen I say that Mrs. Blodget was no Christian, I mean that she had not beer  born again, according to the deep meaning of our Saviour's words. You re- member that the doctrine was strange to Nicodemus, who, being a ruler of the Jews, was no doubt -a man of knowledge and information. He expresses his surprise at such a declaration, and our Lord reiterates the assertion, supporting it with that beau- tiful and expressive comparison: ,the wind bloweth lwhere it listeth, and thou canst not tell whence it cometh, and whither it  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7691-00000034"/> "     RUTHi CHURCHILL. goeth: so ts everyI one that is born of the Spirit.' We hear almost every Sunday the words, (' hen the  wicked man: turneth away from' his iniquity, and doeth that which is lawful and right, he shall save his soul alive.' Now the Spirit of God alone can produce this reformation, and, Mrs. Blodget- had not departed from her wickedness. She had always been a self- ish, hard-hearted, avaricious woman, and she continued so to the hour- of her death.. Then, indeed, as you yourself witnessed, she relaxed in her love of money and her enmity towards, her daughter. The history of the penitent thief encourages us to hope that pardon may be obtained at the- latest hour. Our Saviour's words are positive and express: 'To-day shalt thou be with me in Paradise.' That was the reason why I chose that part of Scripture when I saw   RUTH CHURCHILL.     67, that she was dying, with the faint hope of touching her obdurate heart. "Yes," answered Sophia, "I am still full of astonishment at your success.' If 1 had spoken, I should not have taken that view of the subject. I should have soothed her, by assuring her that her sins would be forgiven, because she died in communion with the true Apostolic Church.  Don't think for a moment, however, dear Ruth, that I do not think your method the best. I am certain it is. Even while you are speaking, I remember texts corroborative of your belief--such as, 'John indeed bap- tized you with water, but I shall baptize you with the Holy Ghost, and with fire,' alluding no doubt to the' cloven tongues like as of fire,' which descended at Pen- tecost." "EEven so," said Ruth, "Mrs. Blodget  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7691-00000035"/> 68     RUTH CHURCHILL. had been baptized with water, but the bap- tism of fire, that is of the Spirit, she had not received, for those who receive this bap- tism  become ' new  creatures'-they are born again (of the Spirit) according to the words of our Saviour.  Young as I am, Sophia, I have seen instances of the con- version of very bad people. I have seen them turn from their wickedness and become new creatures. I have also seen people re- ceive baptism and confirmation and all the rites of the Church, and remain the same, worldly, or even wicked, people they were before. Surely Christianity must be in- tended to make mankind better. It follows clearly, I think, that nothing that does not make mankind better, can be true Chris- tianity."         - 1"Then you do not believe in baptismal regeneration, Ruth?" said- Sophia. "I have -   - I  ,     ,   RUTH CEURCHLL.     69 heard great discussions, and even conten- tions, on this subject. Surely, cousin Ruth, our baptismal service favors -this opinion." "Sophia," replied Ruth, with solemnity, "the Prayer-book is the work of man: the Bible alone is the word of God. Holy men of old who compiled the Prayer-book fol- lowed the Bible most closely.  If, how-" ever, there be any discrepancy between that book and the Bible, the Prayer-book must be wrong. There can be no appeal from the holy records, for they were given us especially to be our guide to heaven. God' is their author. He cannot err. Re- collect the awful- denunciation contained in the very last page of the Bible. ' If any man shall add to these things, or take away from the words of this -book, God shall take away his part from the book of life.' Therefore I repeat, that wherever  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7691-00000036"/> 70     RUTH CHURCHILL, the Prayer-book deviates from its most per- fect model, it must be wrong. The world has changed, of late; man no longer loves the beautiful simplicity which characterizes the Bible. Men's tastes are sophisticated. It has become customary to array the 'plain, intelligible truths of Scripture in such a drapery of opinion, that their outline is ren-  dered indistinct to human vision. The minds of men differ as much as their fea- tures: therefore we cannot wonder at, the endless variety of opinion prevalent in the world. Now, as the Gospel is intended for all men, it is rendered plain to every grade of intellect. Those abstruse doctrines which have been fabricated from simple truths, vary as' much from their original, as the carved and varnished furniture in our houses, varies from the trees of the forest, whence they have been hewn. This   RUT 'I'CHURCRILo;     71 is eminently the age of ornament and so- phistication, and, I fear we may addi of adulteration. Those sublime and beautiful truths which: shine out from the Bible as the sun shines from heaven, are overlooked and undervalued by a portion of mankind, Their perverted tastes crave , something mystical and   incomprehensible. Others, again, have a strong belief in the efficacy of Forms, and endeavor to bind ups the free Spirit of God in those forms, with the hope of rendering them efficient in them- selves. 'But this- can never -be:.- The form and the spirit will always be two as dis- tinct things -as the body and the-soul of man.  The form is the: visible part, and the spirit the invisible, part. In compas- sion to human weakness, forms have been permitted as signs, or- symbols of that which has no form---which cannot be em- -  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7691-00000037"/> 72     RUTH CHURCHILL. o bodied, because it is an ethereal essence. I must believe, because I have seen it, that the Holy Spirit may regenerate the heart of man without the instrumentalit'y of water. If not, whence was that cry, in the tenth chapter of Acts, Can any man forbid water, that these should be baptized which have received the Holy Ghost as well as we ' and whence was the promise of the Comforter, even the Holy Ghost, which the Saviour gave to his disciples? They had all been baptized, yet the Ho y Spirit had not descended upon them.  Our Sa- viour told them explicitly,' It is expedient that I go away, that the Comforter may come to you,' which comforter is assuredly the Holy Ghost: the Regenerator. I have always thought --that the full power of re- generating faith was purposely withheld from the apostles till after the Saviour had ac- \   I RUTH CHURCHILL.    73 complished his mission on earth. We see that although they witnessed his miracles, and Peter in particular boasted of his constancy, yet they all forsook Him when He was seized as a malefactor. Probably had they possessed the power of believing as they afterwards did; they would have resisted his seizure unto death. You know, when once they received the Holy Ghost, they never wavered in their faith. "Seeing all these things as I do," con- tinued Ruth, " you cannot wonder, dear cousin, that I think something more than: water necessary . to regeneration. I have known members of the so-called Baptist Church who continued to lead wicked lives after they  were immersed, though they boasted of having been made whole, every whit, by that rite, and claimed a right to salvation through baptism alone. A, ,   10  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7691-00000038"/> -74     RUTH CHURCHILL* "These mistaken doctrines make wild work in allny Church.  In some cases (as in that of Mrs. Blodget) they substitute presumption for faith. She was a proud, selfish, ignorant person. She wished to be saved in her sin's, whereas salvation is only promised to those who renounce sin, and ,he tried to convince herself that a mere OomFpliance with the forms of the Church would salve her.. In doing this, she was as,:mucdbhlaA idolater as those who worship- e&amp;d, "th e igrid enlalf before Mount Sinai. Ayi my-)dseax rBSophiaf while- we read' that Christians. nimust -^wTn k oat :their salvation witheai'ab ind-,trembilin'g we:'!ceannot think that i baptism ilofie canli;wa sh lawiay sin."  mid.-sph, -ia, eHed hwithii painful anriety;: t it these) ax uk, tU I M iIraihe. iiedi e dp e ^d aid : .;, at h i zihe3r iistt i xDarrive lhte i  truth !"  lt tn - qii i 't , i?.r'^ - ^   RUTH CHURCHILL.      75 "It is, indeed," answered Ruth, " if we trust to our own understandings to dis- cover it, or if we suffer any mere human reason to guide us in our search. I have always been struck ,with the suitableness of this prayer: Lord! I believe, help th'ou mine unbelief.' "When the glorious fact of man's re- demption is first impressed on the mind, every one experiences a sense of weakness, as if the truth were too great to be fully conceived.  Those who have never prayed before, are  irresistibly impelled to seek divine aid, to enable them to comprehend the wonders which break in -upon them. "I know not what I should have done without prayer, for I had no guide-no assistant in my  researches. It was then that I fully tested the Bible as a com- lmentary on its own revelations; and when  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7691-00000039"/> 76     RUTH CHURCHILL. I was awed by the flood of light that sometimes burst on me from that source, I would turn to my dear prayer-book, the only relic of my pious grand-father. There I would find the same truths, softened and mellowed, as it were, by passing through a less exalted medium. The Bible brought, me into immediate contact with holy things. I bowed myself, as in the presence of the Godhead himself, and trembled. But in the prayer-book, there were footmarks, so to speak, of the finite creature. I was less awed or frightened, it may be. In reading the, Bible, I felt somewhat as Moses must have done in presence of the burning -bushb; but in/ the prayer-book I found strength to comprehend this great wonder.  The prayers and collects gave me courage. I saw  that men had gone before me to these holy places, and had   p        KRUTH CHURCHILL.     " 1.                       f left way-marks to direct those who came after them. Thus I learned to love and revere the prayer-book, yet I cannot bear to hear it elevated above the Bible; neither can I endure to see the Church elevated above the Saviour-both of these seem to be done in our days." Sophia sighed again. She saw that Ruth rejected some of the doctrines taught by her husband. This made her uneasy. Dr. Bland, too, seemed to agree with Ruth in her perculiar views of scriptural truth. Both these Christians seemed to have the root of the matter in them. Their practice did honor to their profession. They were consistent Christians.  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7691-00000040"/> CHtAPTER IV. MANY persons began to detect discre- pancies of opinion between Ruth Churchill and her cousins. Mr. and Mrs. Burns could not help ac- knowledging that Miss Churchill had proved herself more efficient than the Rector, in the management of an obstinate sinner. Dr. Bland spoke of her in terms of' un- measured approval. One day Mr. Hilton alluded to the scene around Mrs. Blodget's death-bed, and said, half playfully, "Cousin Ruth, my wife tells  me you  are more than half  i recusant from our Episcopal doctrines. How  can that be? and you so stanch in resisting   RUTH CHURCHILL.      79 dissent for years, when you stood alone among Presbyterians and Methodists? Your grand-father, too, was a holy and devout supporter of our Church." "It is Episcopacy that has -changed, cousin Charles," said Ruth, playfully. "How  so?" replied the Rector, ready; primed for controversy. "I see great oc- casion for alarm  in these days. The Church is not revered in- all her ordinances as she should be.  Lightness, if not un- soundness, has come among us." "I think with Miss Churchill," said Dr. Bland, who was a frequent visiter, at the rectory, " that Episcopacy itself has under- gone a change." "I grant that," said Mr. Hilton, tri- umphantly.  "Our Church is coming out of the cloud raised by schismatics around her venerable institutions. It becomes her  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7691-00000041"/> 80     RUTH -CHURCHILL. servants to observe great strictness and caution in repairing her breaches, and cor- recting all her abuses. For instance, Dr. Bland," continued he, looking reprovingly at Ruth,. " there are Episcopalians in our day who impugn the validity of her or- dinances-who circumscribe their import, so as to deprive them virtually of all bene- fit. Miss Churchilll does not believe in baptismal regeneration." Ruth smiled gently. Dr. Bland antici- pated her explanation. "The 27th article of our Church,"' said he, " expressly states that baptism is a sign of regeneration, or the new; birth, so plainly required by the founder of' our faith. .Now, we have no right to confound the sign of any thing whatever with its reality-(the world is --only too acquiescent in these abuses, for they accord too well with its self-indtlgent   RUTH CHURCHILL.      81 customs.) The o'utward and visible sign, and the inward spiritual grace, are very different things. They that receive baptism rightly, are grafted into the Church--the promises of forgiveness of sin, and of our outward adoption as the sons of God, are visibly acknowledged by that sign. Now, I understand by receiving baptism rightly, ; that the baptized person shall in no way presume upon the outward ordinance as suf- ficient for salvation, but shall labor to ob- tain the inward  spiritual grace, by prayer and  self-denial. If the outward sign be all that is needful, why are sponsors ad- mnitted for the infant, and enjoined to cul- tivate the spirit of holiness in the young candidate for salvation? Those who be- lieve themselves regenerated by baptism, have not (in my   opinion) received the ordi- nance righqtly. It were presumption to sup-  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7691-00000042"/> 82     RUTH CHURCHILL. pose that God will save sinners so easily. They must work out their own salvation, by a righteous course of conduct--by hu- mility and self-denial." But have you no confidence in the sac- raments of your Church?" asked Mr. Hil- ton, in some alarm. The greatest," answered Dr. Bland; "when the recipient of them believes in their spiritual signification, and compre- hends them rightly-they are the signs that God will grant the aid of His Spirit to His people when they seek Him in His ordinances." "Something more is required by the Church," said Mr. Hilton, authoritatively. ,' She requires her members to believe that she has power to make her sacraments effectual."' "Not in mere external application, sure-   RUTH CHURCHILL.    . 83 ily," said Ruth. "I cannot believe that outward conformity is all that is necessary to salvation." "Leave these things to me, if you please, Miss Churchill," said the Rector. "Surely I I must know more of this matter than you. I am   an educated minister of the Gospel. It is my privilege to direct the judgments of others." I   Ruth looked up slily, and answered- "And   yet, cousin Charles, our Saviour says, 'I thank thee, Lord of heaven and earth, that thou hast concealed  these things from  the wise and prudent, and re- vealed them unto babes.' " Dr. Bland  was too  much amused not to smile, and the Rector was most op- portunely called away before he could re- ply to this home  thrust. Ruth never pursued  an advantage, or  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7691-00000043"/> 84    - RUTH CHURCHILL. triumphed in a victory. She could not bear to hurt anybody's feelings; yet she was as firm as a rock in sustaining her own principles. When they were attacked, she courageously defended them; but she never used ridicule or irony, or, indeed, any worldly weapons in her defence,. No one could get angry with her, for the benevo- lence of her nature- shone out through all her intercourse with mankind, and disarm- ed every evil passion which might be ar- rayed against her. Two years elapsed, and Ruth began to feel that her lot was indeed heaven-ap- pointed. She had fallen into the little niche designed for her in the social com- pact. Providence had meted out her des- tiny, and sweetened it with many mercies. - Her trials were just sufficient to make her remember that some of her best qualities   RUTH CHURCHILL.      85 had sprung up in adversity, and that every trial might be the  means  of further moral culture. Sophia had yielded insen- sibly to her influence. Although she still quoted Charles' doctrines as the wisest and best rules of action, she would not suffer any one to bring a railing accusation against Ruth's peculiar opinions. One day a clergyman who had settled in an adjacent parish, came to visit Mr. Hilton. After he had been kindly received, and hospitably invited to stay to dinner, he fell into easy discourse on the common topics of the day. Dr. Bland was one of the party. He always encouraged social, easy conversation, and the two ladies were never backward on such occasions. They sat in the little parlor, working diligently at the needle, and the visitor thought he had never joined a more agreeable family  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7691-00000044"/> 86     RUTH CHURCHILL, party. "How are you getting on?" said he at length, ",you say you have been here two years. What do they pay you, or, what is more important, do they pay you at all? I am told that not one country clergyman in fifty gets more than half of the miserable pittance which has been pro- mised to him. In six months that I have been at ---, they have not paid me enough to keep off starvation. My wife has two hundred dollars a year, and I have an aunt who sends another hundred every Christmas.' I work very hard, and live still more hardly. Luckily, living is cheap where we are, and my neighbors some-, times help me out with articles for the table. As for clothing, my wife is the most notable woman in the world, or I should be ashamed to go abroad.  Look at my best coat, ladies, and admire the ingenuity with which it is repaired.' !  .      -    I    RUTH CHURCHILL.  -   87 Both Ruth and Sophia examined a laby- rinth of darns, which reflected infinite credit upon the industry of the lady.  Their frank and liberal praise seemed to encour- age further disclosures. "I see you are making up flannel;" said he, " how nice and comfortable it looks! I don't think there is as much of that article in our house as would bandage a sore throat." Mr. Hilton told his guest the general circumstances of his situation. "I do not get a great deal," said he, " but my salary, such  as it is, is duly paid. I have no trouble in collecting. Dr. Bland there is my  churchwarden. He never loses a cent by negligence.' Ruth had great influence with the lower class, which she used greatly to the ad- vantage of all the neighborhood. She never  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7691-00000045"/> 88     -RUTH CHURCHILL. failed to impress upon the people the pro- priety of paying their Rector and their Schoolmaster punctually. She convinced them that common ,honesty required this at their hands, and made them feel the dis- grace of withholding just dues from those who depended on their punctuality for the comforts of life. All the tradesmen and petty farmers, &amp;c. &amp;c. in the parish, re- ceiveda hints from Ruth as she visited them in times of sickness or sorrow, to remem- ber "that the laborer was worthy of his hire."  One little incident may serve as a spe- cimen of her dexterity in this line of duty. The blacksmith's daughter had come home from school quite a pretty girl. An aunt had given her a year's better schooling than commonl, and Letty Andrews had become a rural belle. Pretty girls always   IUTH CHURCHILL.      89 want pretty clothes, and Letty  was urgent with her father for such indulgences. One evening Ruth called at the house, at Dr. Bland's request, to ascertain whether the baby  had taken the vaccine. While she was knowingly examining the infant's arm, she overheard Letty teasing her father to give her three dollars. i"What for!" ex- claimed Andrews, rather gruffly, " surely, you can't want another dress?" "Indeed I do, father," said Letty pertly. "I want a beautiful pink lawn that the peddler has over the way." "Well, Letty," replied the father, ( "I will tell yfou truly, if I give you that money, I must take it from what I have . saved to pay my pew rent." "Pew rent," repeated Letty, irreverently, "Oh, father, give me the money, and let 12  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7691-00000046"/> 90     RUTH CHURCHILL. the pew rent lay over. Any other time will do as well." Ruth now  came forward. "Mr. An- drews," said she, "I thought I'd just men- tion now, that Dr. Bland is collecting pew money. I hope none of our pew-holders will be unprovided. You know the Chris- tian rule,' do as you would be done by.' Is!t not a blessed thing to have such a constant reminder of our duty? I have often wondered, if the Sabbath had not been especially appointed, how many per- sons would have kept it. Suppose we had merely been told to keep one day in seven, without any particular day being specified, how many people do you think would, have hallowed any day'? But we have-been plainly directed, Mr. Andrews, in all our most important points of duty. The maxim   RUTH CHURCHILL.     91- 'do as you would be done by,' has helped many a, man to heaven, by keeping him steady to his Christian duties. When we know what our duty is exactly, we can soon bind our own hearts to perform it," "Good evening all of you." "Letty, I have a beautiful little prayer-book for you. I will give it you at the Sunday- school to-morrow. I was just telling your mother how much I approved your dress last Sunday. It was neat and becoming. I hope you will keep to the simple style, which suits both your person, and your father's fortunes." And Ruth went home, leaving behind her a good lesson, which was taken in good part. The very next work day, found Andrews at the churchwarden's door, with his pew rent all ready. Letty thought bet- ter of the pink lawn, and went without  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7691-00000047"/> 92     RUTH CHURCHILL. it cheerfully, for Ruth had a, way with her, when she descried the peccant princi- ple in the young hearts about her, to work at it gently and -prayerfully till the sore spot was healed. Truly may it be said, that influence is the talent imparted to woman -or the benefit of her fellow beings. Ruth worked so gently and tenderly at her task of moral amelioration, that her progress could only be discerned by the increase of virtue and piety around iher. Mothers looked to' her for correcting the faults of their children. Dr. Bland looked to her for help when any critical case occurred in his practice. Sophia became more and more convinced that her strength lay in Ruth's counsels and Ruth's influ- ence. While the Rector himself forgot to impugn her orthodoxy, wheni he saw her moving like a, spirit of light wherever his       RUTH CHURCHILL.      93 duties required her assistance. Indeed, she might have  been  seen  shedding  light wherever she found darkness. Sophia once said to her, s"Cousin Ruth, I feel inclined to keep the day on which you came among us as a saint's day." As for Mr. Boulder, the young clergy- man with the darned vestments, he took home many useful hints, and a large bun- dle of flannels and other comforts for his wife and child. He told his wife playfully that Mr. Hilton had two churchwardens, one male and the other female; that. they held up his hands when   he was weak, and poured comfort and   enjoyment into his bosom, as from a fountain, all the time. The best test of true religion is its power of subduing selfishness, the natural sin of hu- manity. Where we love  " our neighbors 3.  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7691-00000048"/> -94     RUTH CHURCHILL. as ourself," and serve him to our own hindrance, selfishness must be overcome. Ruth Churchill saw clearly in what con- sisted her advantages over others of weaker faith. She had never known prosperity. Her lot had been one of trial.  No one had ever tempted her to think of herself more highly than she ought to think, for she had been an orphan from her earliest recollection, and had never felt herself of importance to any one. "God has called me," she would say;, "to serve Him, and trust in Him, and love Him; for I have had none other to serve, trust or love." And Ruth felt the peculiar mercy of this dispensation, and was grateful for it. Many persons so situated would have bemoaned themselves as waifs and outcasts of society; but she truly felt how God can be the father of the orphan. Her reliance upon   RUTH CHURCHILL.      95 Him was more entire than it could have been where human ties hold their heart to earth, and exercise its affections there. s '   &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7691-00000049"/> CHAPTER, V. ONE day Charlels came into the room where Ruth was engaged in preparing the bread and wine to be used next day ill the communion.  "Cousin Charles," said she, "I never could understand how the doctrine of Transubstantiation came into the Church of Christ." (She did not tell hiln that it was a greater wonder to her how efforts could virtually be made to revive soI strange a doctrine.) "It was derived," said Charles, " from the Saviour's own words- at the last sup- per. ' Take, eat, this is' nmy body.' But they could not have considered that as literal, because he was not yet crucified.   RUTH CHURCHILL.     97 His bodily presence was with them. There are acknowledged mysteries in our faith, Ruth, and this is one of them." "The Incarnation is a -mystery, I grant, cousin Charles, and the coming of the Holy Ghost was a thrilling mystery.  I have often wondered how I should have felt on the day of Pentecost, when ' cloven tongues like as of fire sat upon the con- gregation.' But after the Christian faith was firmly established, there was no longer need for mysteries and miracles. I have always admired the institution of the Last Supper for. its beautiful simplicity. The Saviour had been a man among men---He was now to lay down his humanity; but he wished it to be remembered to the re- motest time; as He had wrought the won- derful work of salvation by' suffering in the human form, He wished to perpetuate the 13  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7691-00000050"/> '98     RUTH CHURCHILL. remembrance of that suffering. This He did in a simple and  beautiful manner. Partaking for the last time with his fol- lowers, the meal at which He had often presided, He enjoined them to retain the recollection of it through life. ' Do this in remembrance of, me.'  That is to say, 'Never forget that I was a man among you; that I laid down my life for you; that my mortal body was broken, and my mortal blood shed for your sakes.' "Henceforth He was to be a God, sitting at the right hand of the Father in heaven, where He would be accessible to his crea- tures by prayer. But Hee feared that the mortal might be forgotten in the immortal. As He had wrought out man's redemp- tion by condescending to take his form, He was desirous that this condescension should never be forgotten. He was about   RUTH CHURCHILL.     99 to consummate his glorious sacrifice. He was about to lay down His mortal life for his people; and they were enjoined to com- memorate this circumstance. What good did it do them, or does it do us, to be- lieve the wild fiction, that He intended to feed His followers upon His body and blood? It was quite enough that He suffered death for them, and that after death He would reign for ever in heaven. I never partake ' the communion that I do not recall, in the most lively manner, the memory of that scene. I see the Saviour, as a man, sitting among his disciples, the one whom he most loved leaning on his breast, and Judas, the traitor, dipping his hand in the dish. Ay!   in this commemorative ordi- nance I  am reminded of what it imports me much to remember, namely, that Christ, as a man, suffered and died for me. That  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7691-00000051"/> 100     RUTH CHURCHILL. He rose again in his glorified humanity, and ascended to heaven, still bearing the likeness of man as a vesture to his im- mortality, is a beautiful and impressive mystery. We are carried onward by these thoughts to the end of all things--the judg- ment-day and the general resurrection- when our own mortal bodies will be raised and reunited to our immortal spirits. Then indeed will old things have passed away, and all things be made new. Why should it be supposed that spiritual strength can be derived from feeding on the body and drinking the blood of the Redeemer in the ordinance of the Last Supper? There is something revolting in that mystery which I never can bear to think of-a perver- sion of the true text, and a misinterpre- tation of the true design of a most im- pressive institution. His mortal nature was   RUTH CHURCHTT T..    101 weak, how  could we get strength from  feeding on it?  That we may   derive strength from communing with His Spirit, is true indeed. By faith we meet Him in this ordinance. By faith we realize His sacrifice of Himself for the sins of man, for we think of the last scene of His life, when He eat and drank with His disci- ples, saying, (Do this in remembrance of me. " Ruth was really, so thoroughly under the influence of religion, that none could doubt the efficiency of her faith. Even when she differed most from her cousins, she gave such decisive evidence of being right in7 her practice, that her opponents were gen- egrally silenced. She seemed to revere her Church most truly, but she never claimed for it privileges which the Scripture (ac- cording to her interpretation) neverf meant   &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7691-00000052"/> 102     RUTH CHURCHILL, to grant. She once overheard two young clergymen speaking of the rights and privi- leges of the clergy. One was of opinion that all ordained persons had the right to absolve from sin, and the other "(thought it a pity that confession was not permitted in these days." Ruth could not help saying to herself- "Had these men been at Lystra, instead' of Paul and Barnabas, how quietly would they have submitted to be worshiped as gods. They would not have run about proclaiming-- Sirs, we are men of like passions with yourselves. Nothing, in fact, but strong worldly pride leads Christians to seek occasions for aggrandizement. They forget that humility and- poverty were the peculiar distinctions of holy men of old. The servants of- the Church look closely in these days to their own interests. Some   RUTH CHURCHILL.     103 of them, iudeed, imitate the sons -of Eli, by taking more than their lawful share of the things brought to the temple." But Ruth was grievously distressed by hearing clergymen of her Church declare that salvation was promised only to their body--that none who were not in the com- munion of the Episcopal Church had a right to plead the promises of God. "Is it not said to us, 'the gates of hell shall not prevail against you?' Are not we. the only true Apostolic Church, to whom alone the promises were made?" One young lady exclaimed---"Oh! I would not die in any other Church, for here alone can one be assured of salvation." One day she met a pretty little woman in deep mourning, weeping bitterly. She had just come out of the room in which the Rector received visiters, and seemed  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7691-00000053"/> 1.04    RUTH CHOXCHLL. overcome with grief. Ruth felt- so much for her, that she drew her into her room, and closed the door. She then recognized a new  comer to the neighborhood, who had appeared once or twice at church. "Mrs. Grey, I believe," said she, sooth- ingly; "pray take a seat near this win- dow ;" and she brought the mourner a glass of water. , "You are very good," said a sweet, low voice, broken by sobs. "I am   very wretched. It is only a week since I lost my  only child--a lovely babe of six months old." "Do not grieve so much for one who is assuredly an angel in heaven," said Ruth, stroking back the rich curls that    I hung in disheveled masses over a white brow. "Your babe is now happier than the imagination of man can conceive. It   RUTH CHURCHILL.     105 is among the chosen ones of the Savlour. Did he not say, 'Sufer little children to come unto Me, and forbid them  not, for of such is the kingdom of heaven?"' "Oh!" exclaimed the weeping mother, looking, up to heaven, (" could I indeed feel that assurance, I should weep no more. But my little one-oh! can I speak the word--my darling babe was unbaptized-- I thought so little of such things in my exceeding joy at having such a treasure! I was not religiously brought up. In short, to my great grief, my babe died without baptism." And another flood of tears in- terrupted her speech  Ruth took her hand, and said;, "I do believe, nevertheless, that your infant is in bliss. One so young-so free from actual sin-could never be excluded from  hea- ven." "  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7691-00000054"/> 106     RUTH CHURCHILL.  "Oh! bless you-bless you for those words," cried the poor sorrowing mother, throwing her- arms around Ruth's neck with passionate emotion. Mrs. Bond told me you  Episcopalians would not allow the possibility of such a thing. She said that unless my child had been baptized in your -Church, you did not believe it could possibly go to heaven. She said so last night, and I could not close my eyes af--- . terwards. This morning I came here to see the Rector.  Oh! he told me- his Church did assume it as a fact, that un- baptized children were shut out of heaven. He was sorry to say it, but he could not be false to his creed. Such was the be- lief of the Episcopal Church."' ( I cannot agree to it," said RUth, eager- ly. "' I know not where such an opinion is found, and if I did find it expressed   RUTH- CHURCHILL.     107 any where, save in the Bible, I should reject the doctrine. Comfort yourself. I hope you will save yourself all this misery another time, by bringing your children to the font betimes." "Oh! my dear Miss Churchill, how you comfort my poor heart!  As I have ac- knowledged to you, I know little about religion. I have always read a chapter in the Bible every day; but alas! it was a mere form, and; going to church was little more. I knew that there were pious peo- ple in the world, who understood the Bible, and   practised its precepts. I always hoped that religion would one day come home to my heart; but with shame I say it, I never could keep my thoughts from roving while I read and while I listened." "Many people are in your condition," said Ruth, "who are not ashamed of it. I  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7691-00000055"/> 108     RUTH CHUIRCHLL. hope the time will come when you will both read and listen with interest--when the Bible will become precious to you. It is the only safe guide of human conduct, and none can fulfil the duties of life worthily without its aid." "I know that I should think this, my dear Miss Churchill, but I have lived with people who talk so differently of this book --who say that it is so mysterious that none can understand it, and so, contradic- tory that none can fathom its meaning." "I pity you sincerely for having heard these things, my dear Mrs. Grey. I know how apt we are to adopt the opinions of those we love, without examining them. The Bible says of unbelievers, 'that they have ears, and hear not; eyes, and see not; ay! and  understandings, that understand not,' This plainly expresses their true   RUTH CHURCHILL.     109 state. They must hear preaching, and yet its sense never comes home to them; they must see that religion influences the ac- tions of men, and yet they will not bring their own actions under its guidance. As for the Bible contradicting itself, it is the only thing which harmonizes beautifully and fully with its own avowed motives and principles. You know we are all lia- ble to delusion and error, even in the commonest things. For instance, you can- not persuade an ignorant man that the sun stands still, while the earth moves round it, He will tell you that he knows the contrary, because he sees the sun move, while the earth stands still, for if it did move, he could certainly feel its motion. So it is with those who fancy the Bible contains contradictions. They will tell you that they see them plainly: and according  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7691-00000056"/> "O     RUTH CHURCHILL.,  to our old adage, seeing is believing. Thus will the ignorant man affirm that he sees the sun move, while it is most certain ihat it stands still. It is strange that people should profess to revere the Bible as the book of God, and yet suffer their imagina- tions to run riot in construing its mean- ing. The fact is, that many people read it with the design of fitting its doctrines to their own tastes- and opinions'; they have no intention of adopting its wisdom, and surrendering their folly. They want a little help in making up their rules of action, and they are -willing to borrow this little from the Bible. Natural pride and self-conceit close the mind to the convic- tions of wisdom.  You, cannot fill a full vessel. Room must first -be made in it before it can hold a new supply of any thing. Many people fancy contradictions in   RUTH CHURCHILL.     1Il the Bible; that is, they fancy it contradicts itself, when it only contradicts them. In the confusion of an ill-regulated mind, they take up God's holy book. They read here a little, and there a little. Some things pleases them, and they appropriate them to their own mental wants. Other things bear too hard upon their favorite dogmas, and are therefore condemned and rejected. But the sublime wisdom of that blessed volume is incomprehensible to pre-occupied minds. As I have already said, you can- not fill a full vessel. If men would come to the well-spring of life with a spiritual thirst, they would drink and be filled. But they first satiate a diseased thirst with the sickening draught prepared by the world. They turn away from the pure water of life because, they are full, and thirst not." Mrs. Grey listened eagerly to the words  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7691-00000057"/> ".2    RUTH CHURCHILL. of Ruth, and left her with a heart light- ened of its heaviest burden. In after days, when the spirit of '-truth had descended upon her mind--when she had learned to love and revere the Scrip- tures, she looked up to Ruth Churchill as the wise and good friend who had first directed her thoughts aright. Sophia loved and admired Ruth, but she sometimes had doubts of her orthodoxy. ("Dear Ruth," she once said, when she   I had listened to some of her explanations of Scripture, " do you not carry your views too far? do you not get beyond the bounds of the Church?" "I think not, Sophia. I truly hope not. I love my Church.  Ay! I love and re- vere her as the purest interpreter of the Scriptures; but I do not see many things which others see in her rules and ordi-   RUTH CHURCHILL,     113 nances. For instance, I cannot see in the baptismal rite, more than- a significant type or sign of regeneration-a very significant one, I grant, but still only a sign. "Baptism is a most expressive type of the outpouring of the Holy Spirit. Water, being the most powerful of all natural agents in cleansing the flesh, is a meet emblem of that great cleanser and puri- fier of the soul--the Holy Spirit of God. The Jews readily understood, this symbol, their ceremonial law imposing upon them the obligation of frequent purification, and their climate rendering great attention to neatness, requisite for their health and com- fort. "It is good for us to remember that the Jews were rebuked for insisting too much upon this outward cleansing. We cannot be too  careful to enforce the su- 15  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7691-00000058"/> "4     RUTH CHURCHILL. preme  necessity for inward purification. People who have been accustomed to the strict moral restraints of Christian society, are apt to forget the spiritual weakness of those less favored by education and position in life. They do not consider how easy it is for men, unused to these restraints, to fall into sin. Men of culti- vafed minds, too often read  the Gospel as they would read a treatise on, political economy, or a work on metaphysics. Their minds are strained and perplexed by divers views. The fact is, they! are not looking for truth. That is too tame a thing to satisfy them; they are looking for excite- ment, and they find it in conflicting doc- trines, and worry themselves in this most unprofitable labor. Meanwhile, those who look up to them, are mnisled by their er- rors. i *.s   RUTH CHURCHILL.    1.15 "Suppose the case of a city supplied by a perennial stream of the purest water. Suppose some of the citizens should pro- pose to dig around this stream, and ex- amine its sources, through fear that it was not, after all, so certain a supply as men believed. Those who had drank its waters thankfully for many years, and found them healthy and strengthening, would argue against the smallest change 1I1 its course, This opposition would only stimulate the advocates for change to yet further inno- vation. They would propose to open a new channel, and declare- their belief that such a measure would ensure the town a larger supply of even purer water. Nay, some would even affirm, that- turning the course of the  stream  would make its waters medicinal, as they would   pass through strata of medicated earth. Ra-  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7691-00000059"/> "6     RUTH CH URCHLL. tional people, who cared for none of these new things, would insist upon the purify- ing 'and cleansing properties of their stream in its original state; and thus controversy would arise, and discrepancy of opinion lead to a disunion among brethren of the same community. In this case, the learn- ed men would insist upon their superior capacity to decide all doubtful points. ' We have read much,' they would say. "We have access to sources of informa- tidn that you, know nothing of. Besides, we have heard it said that in former times, this stream had much stronger heal- ing properties. We only want to restore it to its pristine powers. It is for the benefit of all mankind that we would un- dertake this work; we are not selfish. *We would labor for the good of all.' Alas! the love of novelty is one of our   RUTH COSUtRCATILL    . 17 besetting sins, and the desire of being bet- ter than well, has led many to lose the reality, while seeking for the shadow. "Our doctrines do not need alteration. Our modes of applying them may be imr- proved. Let us retain our original supply of water, and drink from its fountain-head freely. All men can take of those waters, and we know that they have saved my- riads since the fountain was first opened in our barren wilderness." Sophia listened to her cousin with deep interest. Perhaps she wished in her secret heart that the Gospel had come to her in that beautiful simplicity which made its truths so attractive, as they flowed from the lips of Ruth. Her own views were in some lights rather indistinct than clear; but she believe'd that true faith con- sisted in receiving implicitly all that the  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7691-00000060"/> "8     RUTH CHURCHILL. Church regarded as essential to salva- tion. "But what would you have us do, cousin Ruth?" asked she, meekly. "If our lights are not sufficiently distinct to guide us, how are we to remedy the evil?" "By prayer," answered Ruth, emphati- cally. "Many Christians read too much, and pray too little. We are told to pray always, but not to read always. I believe it is impossible to comprehend the mys- teries of our faith, without divine aid. That aid can only be obtained by prayer. God is accessible to us only through that medium. The Spirit alone can explain the deep things of the Spirit. "Men talk of: not disseminating the sim- ple Bible, without note or comment. What are those notes and -comments, but the opinions of men of like passions with our-   RUTH CHURCHILL.     119 selves? Many of them are very ingenious and useful, but they are the work of hu- man reason. Vre want divine aid, and that, I say again, is only attainable by prayer. Show  me a' contented, active Christian, and let us ask him how he ob- tained his light and strength. Think you he will point out any of the voluminous commentaries on the Bible, and say there did I learn my faith? No: he will show you perhaps some little corner in a little closet where he reads his Bible, and say, there is' the spot where I asked for, and obtained the blessing of a saving, healing, sustaining faith. Ask Dr. Bland, when next you see him, if I am not right in this belief, I have never questioned him on the subject, but I feel perfectly certain that he is a praying Christian. There is  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7691-00000061"/> I20     RUTH CHURCHRIT L no mistaking the signs by which they are known." "But, cousin Ruth," said Sophia, a little disturbed, " you speak as if you thought we did not pray. Now I assure you, that nothing could induce me to omit my regu- lar devotions. I shut myself up, morning and evening, to pray. I repeat the prayers of the Church regularly, and, my husband says it is not altogether safe to use my own words in prayer." "My dear cousin," answered Ruth, put- ting her arms affectionately round her neck, "I feel certain that you pray sincerely, and that your prayers are heard--you are a dear, honest, kind-hearted girl, and I love you truly.  Your prayers are right, as far as they go; but there are times and seasons when more earnest supplication is x   RUTH CHBURCHT;TLT-.   121 necessary. You are a good wife, Sophia; you honor your husband, and no doubt take all his teachings without appeal to a higher power.  Now, I would have you ask the guidance , of One who cannot err in the completion of your Christian faith. I would have you ask earnestly, impor- tunately, perseveringly. Oh! how often do we feel the blessed influence of the Spirit come over our souls, when we have cried strongly in our hour of need! Never be discouraged, dear cousin. Recollect that you are asking for that which only God ,can give you.  Be assured you will ob- tain the blessing if you faint not. I firmly believe that the agency of Satan is shown in nothing more powerfully, more unre- mittingly, than in his efforts to keep Chris- tians from effectual prayer. How little 16  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7691-00000062"/> 122     RUTH -CHURCHILL. are we  aware of the real  cause of our disinclination to secret devotion! How little do we suspect that the evil spirit himself is throwing impediments in our way, when we are seeking a throne of grace! "I once knew  a simple old peasant woman, who complained that Satan hinder- ed her when she wished to pray, for a true faith. She told me seriously, that once when she had shut herself up for prayer, the evil spirit took the form' of a mouse, to distract her attention;, and that on another occasion, he came as a mosquito, and stung her so violently that she could not remain still for an instant. Those ideas are simple and rather ludicrous, but they came from a true and zealous member of our own communion."   RUTH CHURCHILL.      123 These things were strange to Soplia, for she rather believed that the idea of a change of heart was not a part of her hus- band's creed.  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7691-00000063"/> CHAPTER   VI. MR. HLTON   had a sister, who was married to an officer in the U. S. Navy. He had just been   ordered on a three years' cruise. The young wife was in despair at the prospect of this long sepa- ration. She had been cordially invited to' spend the period of his absence with her brother, and had accepted the invitation. Ruth and Sophia worked diligently at cer- tain preparations for this new and interest- ing guest. They got together every possi- ble comfort in the room assigned to Mrs. Devereux, (for that was her name,) not forgetting a cradle for the baby of three months' old.   RUTH CivURCHLL.     195 Late one evening the fair young crea- ture arrived, and was received with warm affection by her brother and his wife. 'Ruth thought she had never seen  any thing so lovely as the mother, not yet twenty years old, and the delicately fair fragile infant. Charles had no other near relative, and this sister was inexpressibly dear to him.   They had been left or- phans in tender childhood, -and had been adopted by an uncle, who  supplied the place of father to them both. Nothing could be more interesting than the appearance of Mrs. Devereux.  She was beautifully formed, with deep blue eyes, the lustre of which, however, was habitually quenched in tears. Her hus- band had been ordered to the coast of Africa, and his wife never mentioned this destination without a paroxysm of grief.  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7691-00000064"/> 126     RUTH CHURCHILL.. "Such a climate for my dear Alfred to encounter," she would say, "and he al- ways delicate!" - Then she would turn to her baby and fold it, to her bosom with a new burst of grief. The nurse of Mrs. Devereux's baby was an elderly woman of much experience in her profession. She had been chosen with reference to the utter ignorance and inexpe- rience. of the young mother, who reposed great confidence in her. Mrs. Alien (the nurse) seemed much distressed at the vio- lent grief of the mother. "',The babe," she said, " was very delicate, and the. constant excitement of the mother's spirits was very bad for the child,"  Sophia herself was aware of this. "Ger- trude, my dear sister," she would say, "try  and compose your spirits, for the sake of this lovely baby; while he de-   RUTH CHURCHILL.     127- pends on you for nourishment, you should endeavor to be calm. His health will suf- fer if you continue to give way to this violent agitation." "Alas!" replied the poor mother, "this is my first grief, and I know not how to restrain it." Ruth had been told that Gertrude Hilton, had been piously educated. The uncle who had adopted  both the orphans was an Episcopal clergyman of high moral char- acter. His wife had paid particular atten- tion to the beautiful little girl, who interest- ed every one in her favor. She had been brought up to believe in the infallibility ^ of the Church, and its direct descent from the Apostles. dharles had adopted the same views in the early part of his min- istry, but he had insensibly abandoned some peculiar points -of doctrine as utterly un-  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7691-00000065"/> 128     RUTH CHURCHTTFL. tenable in the neighborhood in which he was established. Dr. Bland and Ruth Churchill had ex- ercised considerable influence over him, in- somuch that he had well nigh renounced some of his doctrinal peculiarities; at least he had laid them aside, because, in truth, he got along (in common parlance) better without them than with them.  Charles Hilton began by being very tenacious of the dignity of his profession., He thought his- official station in the Church entitled him to high consideration. He sometimes found a stray hope floating about in his mind (scarcely discernible save at the high tide of his imagination) that he might one day be a bishop. He talked of the dignity of a priesthood derived in unbroken de- scent from the Apostles. Dr. Bland combated this idea.  He a ;   RUTH CHURCHILL.     129 thought it utterly impossible to trace this descent through sixteen or seventeen cen- turies of spiritual darkness and political confusion. "Remember," said he, " that the failure of a single link breaks your chain of evidence effectually. In legal transactions, the most entire continuity of evidence is absolutely essential to the es- tablishment of any claim.  Many  large estates have been lost for want of a slen- der thread of proof to connect a well established series of facts. Perfect unity is essential to truth. I have read much on this subject. I am anxious to surround our Church with the fullest possible proofs of her antiquity, her suitableness to the wants of man, and her 'excellence in all' important points. But if I cannot be a good Churchman without positively believ- ing in the unbroken descent of our minis- 17  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7691-00000066"/> 130     RUTH CHURCHILL. try from the Apostles, I fear I  never shall be accounted one; for I see no posi- tive proof to that effect. Nor can I dis- cern any great advantage to be derived from the establishment of that point. Some people say, ours is the true Church, because she derives, her descent from  the Apostles; others say, rshe claims descent from the Apos- tles, because she is the true Church. It ap- pears to me that her Christian spirit has been  deteriorated by her disputes on this subject. Some of the clergy    believe so imperatively  in .the  apostolic  succession,' that they  feel a sort of pride in. it, like family pride, as it is called. They  value themselves  on this far-fetched and dimly seen prerogative, and  engage in angry dis- putations on  the subject. Their attention is turned from  the  cultivation of brotherly love, meekness, humility, and  other Chris-   RUTH CH URCHLL.     131 tian graces, to the establishment of a claim that. the greater part of mankind deem utterly untenable. For my part, I would- rather see the Episcopal Church purified and spiritualized, than to see her surround- ed with a host of temporal dignities. It is enough for me that she was undehia- bly established by the Lord Jesus Christ -the great founder of all Christianity. Let her follow the 'maxims which  He taught while' on earth, and she will need no earth-bestowed honors to enhance her value. If the establishment of this point would have invested the Church with any additional strength or purity, her great founder would have confirmed it by spe- cial decree. That he has not done so, is (to me) a sufficient proof that He deemed it unimportant to her true interests. This eager desire to prove the unbroken apos-  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7691-00000067"/> 132     RUTH CHURCHILL. tolic descent of our priesthood, should bring to our minds the rebuke of our Sa- viour to His followers for desiring to be first. "It is plain that our Lord wished to see His Church 'humble,' 'lowly in spirit,' 'not puffed up.'  How can people read the history of His life without understand- ing the sort of distinction He desires for His Church?  Alas'! we are too weak a race to be entrusted with dignities, and the great Searcher of hearts knows it full' well. He has wisely appointed us to ren- der services that humble the heart, in- stead of filling it with pride.  It is only the heavenly Jerusalem, whose gates 'are of pearl, and her streets paved with gold.' It will only be when we are safe from carnal temptation, that- honors and dignities may be borne without danger." s . ,   RUTH CHURCHILL.      133 Mrs. Devereux  had just parted  from her husband when she came to her broth- er's house. All the family exerted them- selves to console and amuse her, but this proved a difficult undertaking. It was, as she said, her first sorrow, and she had never learned to bear 'up under disappoint- ment. She had lived for society, and had no resources within herself. Beautiful, gen- tle, and full of those lesser gifts which impart pleasure to those around, she had derived all her enjoyment from those sources. Passionately attached to her hus- band, the idea of- a separation for three years, bore her to the earth.  Her child seemed too nearly allied to his  absent father to give her comfort. She could not look at -the present idol without thinking of the absent one; for her affections were all idolatrous.  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7691-00000068"/> 134     RUTH CHURCHILL. Ruth thought of reminding her that "re- ligion was no weak source of consola- tion." "I love my Church," was her reply, "but at present my heart is too full of the absent one to think of aught else." She would sometimes sit in deep thought, and then exclaim with vehemence: "1 Three years! three long, lingering, grief-wearied years! What an eternity of suffering! Sure- ly death, present death, would be prefera- ble. My life-springs will be exhausted long-before that period can end. Each day seems an age.  How can I endure the long-protracted agony of three years- three times three hundred and sixty-five days! Old age will meet me half way of that term. Methinks time has already laid his bony hand upon me.  My limbs ache and shrink at the horrid :thought; ,   RUTH CHURCHILL.      135 and how will my beloved endure life with- out the very germ and marrow of his- existence-his Gertrude and her other self, his babe? Oh, life! life! thou art a dreary vacuum, in which my, vital powers will be annihilated, without the comfort of my bet- ter half of life, my husband." In this manner would the unfortunate young creature feed, as it were, upon the bitterness of her grief. Unluckily, Mr. Hilton was compelled to leave home for several days, immediately on her arrival.  He had already -expe- rienced, however, his own incapacity to administer consolation. The first night after her arrival, he passed many hours alone with her. He spoke of their early attach- ment, and hoped that she would be com- forted by his presence.  He opened his prayer-book, and tried to induce her to  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7691-00000069"/> 136     RUTH CHURCHILL. listen to the prayers she once thought so beautiful and comprehensive. But she lay almost insensible on every cessation of her I violent sorrow. "Ah, dear brother," she would say, 1" grief has exhausted my pow- ers. I have no capacity for receiving com- A fort. My  heart is brimful of its. own bitterness. There is no- room   for com-. fort."  In fact, there was no hope of ad- ministering consolation of any sort. Charles lamented his own helplessness, and left-his sister to the special charge of Ruth and Sophia. Meanwhile the fears of the nurse began to be verified. The infant, sickened. The nervous restlessness  of the  mother, 'to- gether with her frequent accesses of' hys- terical affection, made the food   she ad- ministered- to her child little better than poison. Mrs. Allen watched tenderly both /. ' . \   RUTH CHURCHILL.     137 mother and child.  About the middle of  the third night after their arrival at the parsonage, little Alfred became alarmingly ill. Ruth was up, and ready fobr efficient service in a, few moments. Sophia left her own baby, to aid in watching her sis- ter's child. Dr. Bland was summoned. He heard Mrs. Allen's account, and told Sophia that she must administer nourish- ment to the suffering babe. Its mother was in no fit state to act a mother's part by it.  Mrs. Devereux had been aware that her despairing grief would deprive her of the - power' she most loved to exercise. Having perfect confidence in Mrs. Allen, she said to her--" 3ty good Allen, I leave my dar- ling to your charge to-night.  Do not bring it to me, but let my dear sister give it the nourishment it may require." - 18  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7691-00000070"/> 138     RUTH CHURCHILL. In consequence of this commission, the nurse had removed the baby into Mrs. Hilton's nursery. The mother was there- fore ignorant of the illness of her child. Ruth and Sophia sat up with it, and Dr. Bland gave it some soothing medicine. Early in the morning, Sophia visited her sister, and found her so much indisposed, that she insisted on having medical advice for her. "We, have an admirable physi- cian in our immediate neighborhood," said she. "He is almost an inmate of our household. He is our churchwarden, and Charles thinks him one of the excellent of the earth." ' Mrs. Devereux was really laboring un- der great bodily discomfort. She was quite willing to see Dr. Bland, and he was soon introduced into her apartment. Dr. Bland had his sympathies strongly excited in be-   RUTH CHURCHILL.      139 half of this lovely mother and her frail offspring. After some little inquiry into the symptoms of his patient, he recommended quiet, and, if possible, sleep for her. "As for sleep," said she, tearfully, (';I court its aid in vain. My feelings are un- commonly violent, and my present circum- stances are sufficient to excite them to the- utmost." "You must make an effort to restrain them, my dear young friend," said the Doctor,  tenderly' and compassionately. "For the sake of your infant, strive to command your feelings. His health must necessarily be affected by your nervous dis- composure." "I am well aware of that, Doctor," answered the mother, weeping without re- straint. "I have resolved, for the present, to forego my greatest delight--my most  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7691-00000071"/> "O     RUTH CHURCHILL, precious privilege, and leave my babe to be nourished by his tender aunt." "You have done wisely," said the Doc- tor. "Indeed, my dear Mrs. Devereux, I have heard so much of your piety, that I expect great results from its influence over your mind at this trying period. Yqu have been educated in a pious famni- ly. You have been brought up, one may almost say, in the nursery of Episcopacy. Your uncle has spared no pains to instruct you in holy things. Now is the time to do credit to your instructor. Christianity is never so truly valuable as when it gives strength in our weakness, and comfort in' our affliction." Mrs. Devereux sighed deeply, and looked up imploringly. "Alas!' said she, "I know not how to apply to the Church in this my hour of need. I have reverenced   RUTH CHURCHILL.     141 her institutions; I have delighted in her ordinances; but my thoughts abide so te- naciously with my absent husband, that I cannot win them back, even to dwell upon that ritual, so beautiful and so impressive. I strive to repeat the prayers of my Church, but the words tremble on my tongue. My heart no longer delights in those holy. aspirations, once so attractive, so full of meaning. When our thoughts are free, Dr. Bland, how sweet it is to send them forth' in the appointed forms of our holy apos- tolic Church!--to reflect on the privileges we enjoy as members of that holy com- munion! To us alone the promises are given--with us alone was that covenant made, which gives us sweet assurance of heaven as our final home. But, oh!" added Gertrude, bursting into tears, "my Alfred is far away.  Without him, no: thoughts     ,  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7691-00000072"/> "2     RUTH CHURCHILL.  are sweet-no words have meaning.  My mind is a dreary blank-my heart is a wilderness of true and  bleeding affec- tion.", "Such love, my dear Mrs. Devereux, permit me to say, is mere idolatry,"' said. the Doctor, gently. "You can never hope for peace until you have subjugated these erratic feelings." - "Peace!" exclaimed Gertrude, wildly. "What, is peace, compared to the bliss of gratified affections? To live with my Alfred is joy-ecstasy-rapture! To live without him, is misery itself." The doctor administered a composing draught, and left his patient in a some- what more quiet state. "How sad it is," said he to Ruth, "to see a fair, gentle young creature so en- thralled by one absorbing passion. Her y   RUTH CHURCHILL,     143 mind will lose its equilibrium unless some counterpoise can be found to restore the mental balance. She has been brought up religiously, and yet has never learned the power of religion over the heart and mind. She has no idea that the grace of God can regulate the affections, as well as sub- due the passions. Her religion is a sacred mystery--set apart from common use, shut up from common observation. It is a grand and sublime thing to those whose thoughts are free to wonder and admire an abstract theory. To us, whose religion is the daily food of our mind, how   strange the idea of being deprived of its constant ministry! It is the atmosphere of our thoughts-they would wither and perish without it. What an awful state of misrule would come to pass here," added the Doctor, touching h'is forehead, ( were it not for the help which  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7691-00000073"/> "4     RUTH CHURCHILL. I derive from a strong and operative faith -a faith which evermore whispers within me, ' ask, and ye shall receive; seek' and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be open- ed unto you.'" "Ay!" said Ruth, "a faith which en- lightens the soul in its darkest hours, and prompts innocent thoughts and blameless actions throughout the daily routine of life. It is the constant influence of such faith which prevents the excess even of our best affections, and governs our most head- strong impulses. How often, during the passing hour, are we made to feel its power over our souls! Believing, as the Christian should do, not only all that God has promised, but all that He has perform- ed, we find a constant rule for our conduct in what we read and what we remem- ber. Our familiar thoughts and impulses   RUTH CHURCHILL. are thus biased almost imperceptibly by our faith. The ritual of our Church has so much of the beauty and holiness of the Bible throughout, that one would think its constant use would always produce a change of heart. Cornelius seems to have been converted by some such means. His prayers, and his alms were accepted, and ,he was supernaturally assisted in his ef- forts to become a Christian." "No doubt," said Dr. Bland, "he was an humble-minded man. 'Many persons in receiving the truths of Holy Writ, seem to follow  the guidance of human pride in their selection of its doctrines. They are struck with the mysteries and sublimities of the Holy Volume.  Their thoughts oc- cupy   themselves  exclusively with  that which elevates them. They overlook the injunctions to humility and lowliness of 1 19  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7691-00000074"/> "6    -RUTH CHURCHILL. mind.. Now, it is this very portion of the Bible which makes the practical Christian. He believes that God dwells with the lowly. He adores Him in the sublimity of His elevation; but he communes with Him in His humiliation. 'Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly of heart,' is a text that fills the Christian's heart with comfort." In the course of that day the .baby be- came seriously ill. Dr. Bland said to the poor desponding mother, "You must en- deavor to rally some mental strength,' my dear young lady.  Your life has hitherto been so prosperous, that you. have not learned to bear sorrow. JIn" gratitude to that Being who has ,bestowed on you so many blessings, you should rouse- yourself, and ask for strength to bear this' sudden reverse. Your child is not well. Your   l grief has affected its finely strung nerves."   RUTH CHURCHILL,     147 "IIy child! my darling child ill, and I not aware of it?.  Oh, Doctor, this is cruelty, and not kindness!" "You have been too ill youF,   dear sister," said Sophia, tenderly, 5bear any additional pain. Mrs. Allen and myself have done every thing which the Doctor directed, and cousin Ruth has kindly taken' charge of my baby." "Bring hither my suffering cherub," ex- claimed Gertrude, in an agony of alarm. "Oh, my Alfred, my   precious babe! I have neglected you! I have sent you from me!" "Remember, dear   sister," interrupted Sophia, ," that you consented to leave your babe to our care, for its own  sake. You were too ill to act a mother's part, and you consigned it to us."  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7691-00000075"/> "8     RUTH CHURCHILL. The child was brought in, and all hearts bled to see the effect of a few hour's sick- ness on its fragile form. Its little limbs hung listlessly; its lips were pale, and dark circles surrounded its half-closed eyes. Gertrude looked at it;with a ghastly ex- pression of terror. "My babe! my heart's treasure!" muttered she, "your father consigned you to -my charge, and I have neglected my trust. Wo! wo! to the neg- ligent mother." The child had been  threatened with spasms throughout the night. They now came on with violence. The poor mother swooned at the first perception of the truth. The scene was truly distressing. It soon became evident that the child could not survive. I It had always been delicate, and the nervous excitement of the mother '     ,    RUTH CHURCHILL.     149 had been productive of disastrous conse- quences to the infant., Mrs. Devereux recovered from her swoon, and rallied her failing strength to meet the exigencies of her condition. Pale and trembling, she strove to do every thing / directed by the physician. Dr, Bland en- couraged her to further efforts. "Remem- ber, my dear Mrs. Devereux," said he, "that the changes from joy to sorrow- from pain to ease, are common to all the world. Bear up under this trial, and you will gain strength by every exertion." Mrs. 'Allen showed great powers of use- fulness as a nurse.  The Doctor found her prompt and dexterous in following his directions. Suddenly she seemed struck with some thought. She stooped and whis- pered a few words in the ear of her mis- tress. The mother sprang up with a wild  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7691-00000076"/> 150     RUTH' CHURCHILL. gesture "My child! my child has never received the sacrament of baptism! If I lose him- now, I will lose him forever. He will be excluded from heaven, and ithrough my instrumentality. Oh, wretched being that I am! I delayed the baptism of my darling until my dear brother could per- form the rite. He left home immediately on my arrival here, and now I fear it is too late to-procure the services of a min- ister."  Ruth gently essayed words of comfort. "Your babe is too young to have com- mitted sin, my dear Mrs. Devereux," said she. "Surely the Saviour will receive such into His presence in heaven." "Oh! Miss Churchill," replied the af- flicted mother, "I dare not hope in- such a case.  Surely the Church will not; ad- mit. hope on such grounds.  My brother   RUTH CHURCHILL.      16i himself believes that unbaptized babes are not received into heaven. I have always believed what the Church teaches.  Pity me! oh, pity me, my friend, my misery is greater than I can bear!" To tranquillize, if possible, the mental ex- citement of her sister, Sophia sallied forth in search of anll old Episcopal clergyman, who often visited  a son residing in Mr. Hilton's parish. She had reason to believe that he was then at his son's house, and thither' Sophia hastened, with a heart over- flowing  with  sympathy.  Ruth remained with the suffering baby, lifting up her heart in prayer that it might be restored to health. Meanwhile Mrs. Allen drew Ger- trude into her chamber, and prevailed upon her to lie down. She held a long conver- sation with her in a low voice. Atter this, she repaired  to the nursery, where' Miss *&amp;  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7691-00000077"/> 152    RUTH CHURCHILL. Churchill sat with the sick infant in her arms. It lay in a stupor, and it was ob- vious to the experienced nurse that its little life was ebbing slowly, but surely, away. "Let me take it to its poor mother," asked she of Ruth, stooping to take up her nurseling. "She is more composed now, and I think she had better see it once more before it breathes its last." Ruth of course surrendered the babe to its own nurse, and was preparing to fbl-  low, when Mrs. Allen said, "had you not better look after Mrs. Hilton's baby?  She is away, and I think her nurse too young to be entirely trusted." Ruth was somewhat startled at this reminder, but she instantly acquiesced, and left the room without remark. She found her cousin's  infant in a profound slumber, and the young   RUTH CHURCHILL.     153 urse bending over its cradle with cease- ,ss watchfulness. "Don't be afraid of me, Miss Ruth," id, she, "I have almost felt to-night as  I never should sleep again, my feelings tve been so excited." Ruth observed that the night had be- me cooler, and she thought additional vering might be needed  for both the ildren. ",Go to the blanket-press, Su- n," said she, "and get me two cradle verlets. I will watch here till you re- n." Some delay was occasioned by the !culty of opening a bad lock. At length, wever,  the blankets were  obtained. th left one  with Susan  for her own :seling, and repaired noiselessly to the *sery with the other. The room  was 'ant. Ruth sat some time  in painful pense.   She then rose and went to the 20 ' a   &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7691-00000078"/> 154- RUTH CHURCHILL. door of Mrs. Devereux's apartment. - Gent- ly turning the lock, to her surprise she,. found the door fastened.  She stood /in silence pondering upon this incident, till her well-ordered mind came to -the con- clusion that the afflicted mother wished to have no spectators to her grief, and had suffered her confidential servant to exclude her at least. "I anm but a stran' ger," thought she, "though a deeply sym- pathizing one." Presently, the gentle voice of Sophilt was heard inquiring for the sick babe. She had failed in her errand,' The old- clergyman had left his son's house late the. preceding night. "Poor dear Gertrude," said she, compassionately, "how terrible to think of her agonies! Would she 'could believe as you do, dear cousin, that child-' ren can be saved without the rite of bap-   RUTH CHURCHILL.     155 tism. I think, in a like emergency, I should cling to any one who could offer me hope, however obscure and far-fetched." "I certainly do believe," said Ruth, "that infants of tender age, who cannot have committed actual sin, are saved with- out baptism.  The 27th article of our Church tells us, 'that the baptism of young children should be retained in the Church as most agreeable to the institution of Christ, and this after saying that they who receive baptism rightly, are grafted ilnto the Church by   that rite. Nothing here leads us to suppose that  infants are excluded  from heaven   by  the omission  of  the rite through  necessity. I cannot believe  many thing so inconsistent with . the mercy of Him who came to save sinners-- who suffered  and died' that they might be saved.  This case is very different from  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7691-00000079"/> 156.    RUTH CHURCHILL. the very common one of omitting the rite through  carelessness, or unbelief. Mrs. Devereux firmly believes in the- necessity of baptism. She has always intended that her child should be baptized, and only put it off through affection for her brother. No; I cannot believe that our blessed Sa- viour,] who said, c suffer little children to come unto me,' could refuse one such lit- tle one, for a punctilio like this. I rather think that those who hold so strict a be- lief, might be accused of preventing little ones froin coming to their Saviour.' "But, my dear Ruth," said Sophia, (" the question is not whether, the Saviour will permit them, but whether the Church be not armed with power to exclude all those who do not come   according to its ap- pointed rites. My husband insists greatly upon the prerogatives of the Church."   RUTH CHURCHILL.     157  "And, pray! who gavre the Church these powers, my dear cousin?" asked Ruth, earnestly. ( Did she not derive them from the Saviour Himself? If He said, 'suffer little children to come unto me, andforbid them not,' the Church has no right to forbid them. Such prohibition would be a clear case of usurpation." "You have not that reference for. the Church that I have been accustomed to see and feel all my life, dear Ruth," said Sophia. "I am  sometimes frightened by' your vehemence in upholding points at va- riance with my creed." "I think it a plain case, dear cousin," said Ruth: " if a  law-giver draw up a wise code of laws, and  leave them to be  observed by a nation, surely they ought to be  observed; nevertheless, if any of these laws be interpreted differently from  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7691-00000080"/> 158     RUTH CHURCHILL. the well-known meaning and intention of the law-giver, I, for one, would seek out the law-giver and learn of him the true interpretation of the code. I would not sub- mit to any construction of 'those laws at variance with .the spirit of their originator. The Church professes to have adopted the precise meaning of the Saviour in her sys- tem of rules and regulations. I believe she has; but if she depart from the spirit of Christ in her interpretation of His words, I think all true believers are justifiable in referring the case to the Judge' Himself, who is always accessible to His people, and has promised that He will in no wise cast out any who come to Him, believing in Him, and trusting in His promises. I am one, dear cousin, who so believe and so trust. I have too often gone to Him, and: received the help I needed and so-   lRUTH CHURCHILL.     159 licited, not to be firm and unshaken in my faith. Nothing but the actual expe- rience of God's  mercy, shown  to us according, to His own declaration, can strengthen us in believing. I fear the Church is- inclined to assume too wide a prerogative. After all, you know the or- gans of the Church are but men. who are liable to err in their estimate of the power entrusted to them.  We are Pro- testants;--let us not go too near the erring Roman Catholics in claiming power for our Church.  Only think of the absolute control exercised by the priesthood of that Church over its members. The poor and ignorant never' really approach the mercy- seat. The priest is virtually the object "of their worship. He interprets the de- crees of God to them, and   he forgives their sins. What will the priest think or  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7691-00000081"/> 160     RUTH CHURCHILL. say? is their cry, when they have sinned. I have seen a good deal of the evil aris- ing from. this system. -How strange it is, that men should advocate a religion which excludes every ray of light from the hu- man mind, and which has wrapped the world in spiritual darkness for centuries. As long as the Bible was withheld frommen, their ignorance was profound. Now that they have that inestimable blessing restored to them, let them enjoy it fully." "But, dear Ruth," said Sophia, " do not many people err from having too much liberty of' interpretation?" "It may be so," said Ruth; " but would you deprive mankind of fbod, because some are disposed to injure themselves by glut-, tony? Would you 'shut out the sun from your house, because some members of your family have weak eyes, and are apt to in-   RUTH CHURCHILL.     161 jure them by going too much in the full sunshine? People do say, my cousin, that some of our Episcopalians are going over to the Roman Catholic Church." "I know   they do, Ruth. Our good uncle has often told me that 'the love of many has waxed  cold towards our re- vered and beloved Church, and that the few who wish to revive her institutions fully among us, have been accused of lean- ing towards the Church of Rome.' He is one of the most devoted Christians I have . ever known, and a man of pure moral characterY withal. He is much hurt by the imputation of Romanism." "No, Sophy," said she, " it is from the doctrines of Geneva that we are in dan- ger. I shudder when I see the neglect of our ancient forms, ay! and doctrines, too, tolerated by modern divines." 21  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7691-00000082"/> 162    RUTH CHURCHILL. "Now, our uncle is so truly excellent, that I cannot think anyl thing he does can be wrong.  He is an honor to any Church." "But, Sophy dear," replied Ruth, "the best men may err in judgment. We may think their errors dangerous to the commu- nity, without impugning their moral worth as individuals." "These things are too deep for me, dear cousin," said Mrs. Hilton; "but I feel very uneasy about the baby.  Is it not strange that we are excluded from Ger- trude's room?" "I have been thinking,"' answered Ruth, "that your sister does not know us suffi- ciently yet to be at ease with us. Mrs. Alien seems a very nice person, sensible and sympathizing. No doubt Mrs. Deve-   RUTH CHURCHILL.     163' reux has been accustomed to rely on her as on a mother in times of trial." "She told me," said Sophia, " that her uncle had placed Mrs. Allen about her, and desired her to repose implicit confi- dence in her. Charles and Gertrude have been brought up by this uncle, you know. They regard him as a father; and since my marriage I have learhed to love him, and confide in him as they do. Indeed, he made me call him uncle before I was married to Charles, and I often forget that he is not really my blood relative." Ruth loved Sophia for her trustfulness. She had been told that the uncle, so much beloved in the family, was really an ex- cellent man, but not a sound theologian. He led a secluded life, and had been lat- terly too infirm in health to have a- regu- lar ministerial charge. He lived much  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7691-00000083"/> 164     RUTH CHURCHILL. alone, read a great deal, and had gradual- ly departed fromn the simplicity of pure Protestantism. He talked- and reflected much on the coldness of modern Episco- palians. His mind had imbibed the idea that this coldness had been occasioned by neglect of the forms and ordinances of the Church.  He believed that all would be rectified by a zealous enforcement of Church ordinances, which would induce a higher degree of respect for the Church and its peculiar doctrines. "I like not (he would say) this habit of generalizing Christianity. I call no people Christians but those who belong to the one, true, Apostolic Church, to whom the promise was made, 'that the gates of hell shall not prevail against her.' These are Christiians indeed; the others may think themselves safe, but they will have a ter-   RUTH -CujCHT T.-T-   165 rible awaking from this error, when they call, 'Lord! Lord!' and hear the sentence, 'depart from me, for I know you not.' Their case is clearly provided for in the Bible. I want all whom I love to be se- cure of salvation by -entering in at the straight gate, and following the narrow way which leadeth to heaven." This good old gentleman firmly believed that only Episcopalians walked in that narrow way, and entered that holy place."'  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7691-00000084"/> CHAPTIER VII. IT was near the meridian hour, when the door of Gertrude's chamber was open- ed, and Mrs. Allen appeared, moving soft- ly, and looking tearful and unhappy. "Ladies," said she, meekly, "my poor lady is more composed than I could have believed possible after what we have wit- nessed. At first her despair was terrible. She made me fasten the door, and I never could get an opportunity to open it; for several hours she held me close to her, and said she should die if I left her. The poor babe is gone to its rest. It looks like an angel, as it is--at this moment, I do not doubt, an angel in heaven."   RUTH CHURCHILL.     167 "I trust you have been able to convince the poor mother of that," said Ruth, shed- ding tears of true sympathy. "Ay! ladies, she does indeed feel as' sured of its happy doom.  She is calm now, and I think she had better be left alone for a brief space. Poor lamb, all her miseries have come on her at once. I be- -thought myself of telling her that her dear uncle was intimate with the Secretary of the Navy, and that he would try his best to get her husband recalled. In considera- tion of her great grief, I told her I was sure this could be done. Oh! it is the absence of the husband that goads her now. Strange to say, though she seemed wrapped up in the babe, she has borne its loss far better than I could have supposed possi- ble. You will see, ladies, I trust, I have done my duty faithfully. That good uncle  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7691-00000085"/> 168     RUTH CHURCHILL. --that true father-said to me, 'Allen, I trust my poor, tender, loving lambkin to you. She knows YoU, and confides in you. e When she goes among strangers, cling to her, and save her from suffering if you can.' " In fact, Gertrude seemed from that time to sink into a dull, quiescent state. She wept often, but not with violence. Her brother returned the day after the child's death. He was very much afflicted at her loss, and could not help reproaching lim- self for delaying the baptism of the infant. Charles had often avowed his belief in the absolute necessity of baptism to ensure salvation, even to children but newly born and without actual sin. Dr. Bland differed from him in his belief, and it was now some comfort to him to know that so good and wise a man held other opinions than his own on the subject.   RUTH 'CHURCHILL.     169 Gertrude received her brother with a burst of grief, but after this indulgence she became quiet and  sad as before.  Her heart seemed   closed against happiness. She took no interest in anything. Several letters from her husband reached her; he had not yet heard the news so calculated to afflict him, and she seemed to dread the reception of the first letter after that event. She seemed rather reserved towards both Ruth and Sophia. They thought this reserve proceeded from their differing from her in some points of doctrine. Yet she did not often speak of religion. After the funeral of her child, she remained some hours shut up with Mrs. Allen, in whose society indeed she appeared to take com- fort at all times. Dr. Bland questioned Ruth particularly concerning the state of mind of this in- 22  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7691-00000086"/> 170     RUTH- CHURCHILL. 7testilig young creature. She was in fact so lovely, so gentle, and so utterly ab- sorbed by one idolatrous attachfment, that all the Christian charity of her friends was awakened in her behalf. Ruth would have taken great delight in devoting her- self to Mrs. Devereux; but although the disconsolate wife always received her at- tentions gently and kindly, she avoided all subjects connected with religion. Ruth wished to draw- her forth and awaken a spiritual reliance on the Saviour in her sorrow-stricken heart. Ruth had lone rare- talent, which enabled her to render Ger- trude a touching proof of her interest in her present grief. She took likenesses in ,water colors with great taste and accuracy. With some trifling aid from .Sophia, she copied the cherub face of little Alfred so perfectly, as to astonish all beholders.   RUTH CHURCHILL      17 1 When the picture was' finished, Dr. Blan:t:?P took it to town and got it tastefully set as a bracelet. Gertrude received the gift with many tears, but much melancholy satisfaction. Ruth did not present it herself, but de- puted Sophia to make the offering. When the giver and receiver met the next day, Gertrude threw her arms tenderly around Ruth, and said, "I can only thank you for this kindness by loving you all my life." Yet even with this claim to intimacy, Ruth could -not excite the interest of Ger- trude in the direction she most desired. She longed to turn her thoughts to the spirituality of the Christian profession. "With such ardent feelings," thought Ruth, " with   such proneness to be ab- sorbed by one object, her heart needs all  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7691-00000087"/> 17     RUTH CHURCHILL. the aid that God's Spirit can bestow. Oh! that she would take  counsel from her own experience, and draw  near with a simple trust to the Saviour of all. Then she might taste the real blessings of a true faith. Then might she draw strength and comfort from an unfailing source. But, alas! her ed6cation seems to have closed up this avenue to the resources most prized and most resorted to in times of trouble. She knows- nothing  of them-to judge from appearances-she derives no -more strength and consolation from her Chris- tianity, than she does from her knowledge of music, or her love for embroidery. Each of these can fill up a vacant hour, and perhaps cause a temporary forgetful- ness of misery." When Ruth spoke of religion, Gertrude expressed her perfect acquiescence in all -   RUTH CHURCHILL.     173 the decrees and regulations of the Church. "What a comfort it is to us Episcopalians to have an infallible guide!" she would say--"to belong to a Church so wise and perfect. Oh! how I love my Church.  My dear uncle, what do I not owe him, for keeping me aloof from   all heresies, and training me to a jealous love of the rites and ordinances of the Episcopal Church? "Charles, my dear brother, I hope you, have no trouble in maintaining Episcopacy in its purity within your parish?" "Dear Gertrude," said her brother, "I trust I have some truly excellent persons in my congregation-some who walk by. faith, and not by sight. Some, whose daily practice is so fully in accordance with the Christian's -rules of life and conduct, that it were impossible to doubt their piety. I was young when I came here--young in  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7691-00000088"/> 174     RUTH CHURCHILL. my profession, and totally inexperienced. I began  by enforcing rigidly the pre- scribed forms of my Church, -oubting not their full efficiency to make good Chris- tians. But I found that many Christians of longer standing than myself-persons of sterling worth of character, and ardent piety, drew their inspiration from portions of the Bible of which I knew little. These acquiesced in all that I said, but they went far beyond me in estimating the re- quirements of Christianity. They loved and revered the prayer-book, but they drew upon the Bible more largely than I had-eemed necessary.   At first, I was much hurt, and even offended. I thought it presumptuous in them to pretend to in- terpret Scripture for themselves. I warned them, that the interpretation of/holy writ rested solely with'the Church, and that   RUTH CHURCHILL.     175 the laity were bound to receive her inter- pretations without appeal to-- any other source of information. They answered mildly, but firmly, that the Episcopal Church had - never claimed this right. That modern Episcopalians were innova- ting on long-established usages. In short, they boldly declared that' we were adopt- ing the dogmas of the Church of Rome, and taking her heresies into our own pure and orthodox communion. This declaration, supported by reference to the actual prac- tice of one branch of our Church, alarm- ed me into a more heedful examination of the Scriptures and the old customs of Epis- copacy. Dr. Bland pointed out to me the fact that Romanism was distilling sits errors slowly into the hitherto pure fountain of our faith. He observed, 'that notwith- standing the positive disclamation of some  &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7691-00000089"/> 176     RUTH CHURCHILL. of our modern Churchmen of any ten- dency to Romanism in their peculiar opin- ions, they had actually gone over by a pub- lic profession to the Church of Rome.' This could not be denied." Gertrude looked  disturbed, and said, , Well, brother, if, after all, that should be the true faith, can any one object to its adoption?  We are poor miserable crea- tures, too weak to bear sorrow. If the, Catholic faith contains elements of comf6rt, and sources of strength, not to be found in Episcopacy, who can blame those who adopt it? I have never been able to ,see what people call the great errors of that Church. There is surely great consolation in the privilege it gives of drawing help from many sources. The virgin mother of God, for instance,!-"To weak and friend- x   '   RUTH CHURCH ILL.    1" less females, what comfort there is in call.- ing on her, and receiving her assistance!" '"Oh!" my dear sister," exclaimed Charles, much disturbed,-"How  can you speak thus?' Where is there any warrant found in Scripture for investing her with sacred privileges? Are we not expressly told, 'that Jesus Christ is the only mediator between God and man?" "Oh, yes, brother," asked Gertrude, '"but may we not have intercessors? It is as an intercessor that the mother lof God is most valuable." "My beloved Gertrude," said Charles, taking her hand in his, with soothing ten- derness, 'rthink you that our Lord Himself swould not have revealed so important a point of faith explicitly, had He intended that His mother should be thus' exalted? On the contrary, does He not plainly an- 23  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7691-00000090"/> 178     RUTEH CHURCHILL. nounce that she is to be regarded as a mere woman, when He says to John, ' Behold thy mother ;' and to Mary, ' Woman! behold thy son ;'-and that disciple took her to his own home from that hour? 'What can be clearer, and more decisive of His meaning, than this declaration? Had He meant otherwise, -he would have announced to his disciples, in; that hour, that his mother was to be entitled the "Queen of Heaven," and to be invested with divine prerogatives. Episcopalians have never ad- mitted this obvious heresy for a moment  in their creed." "Ah! brother," sighed Gertrude, "we are told by all denominations of Chris- tians that religion is to strengthen us in weakness, and  comfort us in distress. Now, I have needed its comforts, sorely, my brother. I have striven to make them MY   RUTH CHURCHILL.     179 my own.  Alas! I saw  no help in the strict creed of our Church. What won- der, then, that in my despair I turned to sources of consolation not fully developed, it is true, in our own Church, but I should hope not adverse to its spirit? You were not here, dearest Charles. My heart was desolate. Oh, brother, I was left without help when my precious babe lay dying. Your wife was away. No one came near me but my good Allen; but for her, I should have lost my reason," and Gertrude clung to her brother and wept bitterly. "Poor Gertrude," said he, clasping her to his bosom, " you have suffered indeed. You know, my dearest sister, that duty called me from you. My wife, in her zeal to serve you, left her infant, and went away--you know, dearest, on what errand of love and pity.  On her return, Ruth  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7691-00000091"/> 180     RUTH CH-IUCHLL.  .  and herself found your door locked. They knocked, and no one answered.  Several hours passed before they were admitted to your presence. You remember these things, dearest?" ' I remember nothing distinctly," -said Gertrude, vaguely, "but my misery. Miss Churchill has entitled herself to my ever- lasting gratitude. Your 'wife has been a ministering angel to my necessities. Oh, brother, deem me not unloving- or un- grateful. Miss Churchill talked to me of religion. She spoke of a new birth unto righteousness. I had never heard of such a thing. My heart sunk within me. My uncle, you well know, made a jest of the idea of conversion. I learned my creed from him. I believed it to be pure, una- dulterated Episcopacy. He ewarned me that -heresies were creeping into our vene-   RUTH CA-IUICHLLo     181 rable, heaven-bestowed faith. I shuddered to find them under your roof. My good Allen was my  sole help in this day of darkness and of indecision. My uncle told me she was worthy of all trust.   If I have, done wrong, brother, I have been left to my own weakness. In the frenzy of my grief, I was incapable of reason- ing. All my love and reverence for my Church was of as little service to me in my hour of grief, as was the glorious sun- shine that made nature bright and beau- tiful around me." "Alas!" said  Charles,  , I have lately learned  that religion, to be truly useful to man, must be spiritually discerned. Truly is it said, 'God is a  Spirit, and they that worship Him   must worship Him in spirit and in truth.'" In that moment of real distress, Charles r  &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7691-00000092"/> 1 82    'RUTH CHURCHILL. Hilton experienced a faint breathing of the Spirit. He was strengthened thereby. Be- sides, a perception of something hitherto unexplained seemed to damown upon him. "Gertrude, dearest," said he, "is your nurse, Mrs. Alien, a pious woman?" "Oh, yes, brother," replied Gertrude, with a little hesitation, "She is the most pious- person I have ever known." , What Church does she belong to, my dear?" , She is a zealous Roman Catholic," answered Mrs. Devereux, without evasion. ' Our uncle knew what she was. He told me that I needed a strong-minded Christian to uphold me under my very trying circumstances. Mrs. Allen (so call- ed) is in reality a sister of charity. Our uncle says that these women are the only true copyists of the Saviour on earth. She   RUTH CHURCHILL.     183 made great sacrifices to come to me, and on account of the weak and sinful preju- dices entertained against her sect, she stipu- lated that she was to remain unknown while in your family. My uncle said that you were enlightened on such  subjects, and would not think the worse of her for her religion; but you went away so soon after my arrival, that I could not impart the secret to you as I wished. " "Oh, brother, you remember the conversa- tion we had together the evening before you left us. You told me then that you feared the Church did not admit the salvation-of unbaptized persons. Little did I think then that my cherub was so soon to be removed. When I found it dying--oh, brother! what should I have done had  not my good Allen been at hand?  She baptized my dying babe.   She rescued its immortal  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7691-00000093"/> 184     RUTH CHURCHILL. spirit from the awful doom denounced against the unbaptized. My Alfred is a glorified spirit. I do- not mourn as one without hope. My. babe is not lost, but gone before;" and she looked upward as if a burden had been removed from her heart. Charles Hilton sighed in the very depths of his spirit." Gertrude, my sister," said he, "you have been in such distress since my  return, that I have not told you something which I learned during my ab- sence. "Our uncle has quitted our communion, and openly gone over to the ROman Catho- lic Church. Had you seen the papers, you would have learned this some days ago. Perhaps you anticipated this deser- tion?" "No, indeed," exclaimed Gertrude, with   RUTH CHURCHILL.     185 some emotion. t"My uncle always denied that he held any affinity with the doc- trines of that Church, For a long time he spoke against the Romanists, as he always used to call -them, and was hurt if any one told him that he was verging towards their creed.  But before I left him, he had changed in that respect. He said they were, after all, the true Catholic Church, and rebuked   me for using the term  Ro- manist, in speaking of them.  He never gave me the smallest hint, however, of any intention of forsaking the Episcopal Church.- But Mrs. Allen has always ridiculed the idea of there being any difference between the Oxford  Tractarians and the Catholics. She says that the Oxford   divines have been gradually working their way back to Catholicism, and that all who follow them must perforce end in perfect unity with that 24   &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7691-00000094"/> 186    -RUTH CHURCHILL. Church. She says they don't exactly un- derstand their position at first, which makes them   disclaim affinity with the Church of Rome; but that gradually the light breaks in upon them, and they dis- cover that they have all along been jour- neying towards that land of promise, the genuine Catholic Church." Charles looked so unhappy that 5is sis- ter was distressed. "Dear brother," said she, ".you and  I have always thought alike. Mrs. Alien (sister Margaret I may call her in speaking to you) says that you and herself differ in no material point, and that every day brings you nearer together. Believe me, nothing but the exigency of my distress would have made me act so decisively without your counsel. I trust my dear, dear uncle will have us both in the same' communion with himself, for I ,.,   "   RUTH CHURCHILL.     187 cannot conceal from you, dear brother, that I am a Catholic at 'heart. All the comfort I have ever enjoyed in religion has been through the medium of their rites and ceremonies. I feel comforted to think that my dear uncle has cast his lot with those holy people of God." Charles Hilton- was unwilling to let his sister know how deeply her defection had wounded him.  He held a long confer- ence with his trusty friends, Sophia, Ruth, and Dr. Bland.  The two ladies were wholly taken by surprise by the unex- pected discovery of Mrs. Allen's real char- acter. Dr. Bland  counseled  moderate measures. The evil was done, and must be submitted to. Poor Gertrude was very young. Her mind might yet recover from the perversion it had' undergone. Mean- time her friends dealt very gently with  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7691-00000095"/> 188     RUTH CHURCHILL. her, and for the present tolerated her friend and guide, Mrs. Allen. Charles began to see- clearly the error into which he had fallen.  He read the Bible prayerfully, and the scales began to fall from his eyes. He saw that in magni- fying the prayer-book, he had forgotten that, excellent as it is, the Bible is its origin, and is therefore entitled to still more reverence and. respect. He perceived that, in his anxiety to become a good Churchman, heJ had almost lost sight of that law of love, without the fulfilling of which, no man can be a good Christian.  There can be no doubt- that much of the spirit of Christianity evaporates while men are disputing about its forms. The  prayer-book deserves our fullest reverence and' approbation, not because it is the organ of the only true Church, but   RUTH CHURCHILL.     189 because holy men of old compiled it faith- fully from the very cream and marrow of the Bible. , The words of inspiration are carefully collated, and used with so - little alteration of the text, that their true meaning may be-fully retained. The more we read the prayer-book, the more we wonder at the skill with which the Bible has been arranged into forms appropriate for worship, without checking or restrain- ing the spirit of the original. Such forms are invaluable aids to devotion; but let not our attachment to them lead to the great mistake, that nothing but these formb can be the vehicles of devotion. Those striv- ings of the Spirit which cannot be uttered, and those outpourings of the heart which overleap all verbal restraints, are understood and answered by a God of mercy.    The admirable manner in   which our Church   .     /        . I  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7691-00000096"/> 190     RUTH CHURCHILL. carries its members through the whole his- tory of the Bible every year, is one of our most important advantages. And the co-operation of the congregation with the, clergyman in parts of our beautiful ser- vice, secures the attention or all present. There can  be no absence/ Aof mind-no forgetfulness. All must unite in confession,-  in supplication, in praise and thanksgiving. How sublime and, comprehensive is such a worship! Yet it were fearful presump- tion to think that inone btit those who worship according to our beautiful forms are accepted by the Author of our salva- tion. Many a lowly heart throbs with fervent devotion, with no guide save the Bible. Many a ransomed spirit ascends to heaven, that has never loved and re- vered our prayer-book, because it knew it not as-a-Uanscript of the Bible--that Bible   RUTH CHURCHILL.     191 which had been its friend and counsellor through life. In many an humble retreat among the lowly in heart and in station, true religion may be found, shedding love and peace, and joy over the minds and hearts of men. It is there that its triumphs are most glorious, for it comes in a di- rect course from God to man; no inter- mediate agent interferes to impede or ad- vance the work. The Holy Spirit comes down from  heaven to fulfil His mission on earth. The Saviour sees of'the travail of his soul, and is satisfied. What has become of those men who worshiped God in Spirit and in truth before the Liturgy of the Episcopal Church was organized? Do we not hope to meet them    as deni- zens of heaven, if we are so happy as to attain that blessed home ourselves? In the 9th chapter of Luke we read that  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7691-00000097"/> 192     RUTH CHURCHILL. John said, 'Master, we saw  one casting out devils in Thy name, and we forbade him, because he followed not with us.' And Jesus said, 'forbid him not-he that is not against us, is for us.' When James and John said, 'Lord, wilt thou' that we com- mand fire to come down from   heaven, and, consume  them, as Elias did?'-he rebuked them, and said, ' Ye know not what spirit ye are of.' Alas! are there not many professors of Christianity who know - not what spirit they are' of 9-men of zeal and sincerity, but misled by that carnal mind which is -enmity against God, to de- part from the law of love and charity. It appears wonderful that a thorough ac- quaintance with the writings of St. Paul does not make men, liberal and charita- ble-does not, in short, imbue them with the spirit of the Gospel. Throughout the   RUTH CHURCHILL.     193 epistles of that true follower of Christ, we discern his Master's spirit borne in upon his mind, and .incorporated with his feel- ings. The leaven of a pure and strong faith has evidently leavened the whole lump. You cannot fail to see the Saviour Himself by the light that emanates from his faithful advocate, as he basks in the sun of his righteousness, In a short time after the death of Mrs. Devereux's infant, she received so press- ing an invitation from her uncle to reside with him during her husband's absence, that she felt bound by grateful affection to him  to accept it. She seemed most unwilling to give up the kind friends who had witnessed and participated in her sor- rows; but she -nevertheless yearned to go back td the guide and  director of her  early life. 25 5.7  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7691-00000098"/> 194     RUTH CHURCHILL. "I understand my  uncle,". said she. -," My faith has been formed by his pre- cepts, and I feel that his friendship and guidance will be valuable to one so weak as I am. But I'dearly love my brother; his wife and Miss Churchill have made to themselves a home in my heart. Though I have been so dull under their teachings, and have profited so little by their coun- sels, I can never cease to love the teach- ers and the counsellors." The fact was, that these zealous advo- cates of truth had labored unceasingly to scatter its seeds in the ifallow ground of a -mind that had met with little' right cul- ture. Although they were aware of the constant counteraction of Mrs. Allen's in- fluence, they persevered in letting in some little light through the medium of natural affection and kindly feeling.   RUTH CHURCHILL.     195 Gertrude besought Ruth at parting, to "tell her something that she could do to show her gratitude and love.  I shall never rest until I have proved my deep affection for you, my dearest Ruth," said she. "Think of something that I can do to gratify my own yearning love for you when we are separated." Ruth carefully prepared a manuscript volume, of small dimensions, to which she transferred many a strong passage from the Book of Life. Many a heart-searching truth-many a rich testimony of the Holy Spirit--such as she had found irresistible herself; to this she added Doddridge's Rise and Progress of Religion in the Soul, and Wilberforce's View of Christianity. She besought Gertrude to read some portion of these works every day-to think of what she read, and at the same time -to call to  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7691-00000099"/> 196     RUTH CHURCHILL. mind the time they had spent together, and the feelings excited in their hearts during their brief term of companionship. The promise was made with much sin- cerity and many tears. Mrs. Allen (the so-called) declared that she had never conceived it possible for Protestants to be so much like-Catholics-- so kind, and loving, and self-denying. Ruth had won her heart by nursing her during a rheumatic fever, and she prayed daily to the Virgin for her conversion to the true faith. Mrs. Devereux returned to her uncle, and " sister Margaret" went back to her own sisterhood. Two years passed away, and Mr. Hil- ton's church prospered. Imperceptibly al- most to himself his doctrines assumed a sound orthodox character, and he derived comfort-and strength from the change. He   RUTH :CHURCHILL.    197 acknowledged to Dr. Bland that he clearly saw the, erroneous nature of his first in- terpretations of Scripture. "It must be the object of religion to change man' thorough- ly," said he. , This change can only be wrought by the Spirit of God.   That potent agent works secretly, but effectually. No man who ihas once felt its power, can ever be mistaken in his subsequent views of religion. Until he has experienced its operations, he. may doubt its power, but never afterwards. No wonder that those should be always in error who begin by denying the necessity of divine aid in ac- quiring a true faith. It seems to me that this is the sin against the Holy Ghost so fearfully announced in Scripture as unpar- donable. "Suppose the case of a blind man 'sud- denly restored to sight, and beholding for  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7691-00000100"/> 3198    RUTH CHURCHILL. the first time the full-orbed moon in un- clouded glory. If he were told that this  was the sun, he might believe it; but when once he beheld the greater light in its full radiance, he could never again be deceived. So it is: with religion. There are many imposing imitations of the great light; but when once the Sun of Righteousness has risen Uponthe moral dariness of man, he can never believe in any other source of- illumination."  Charles Hilton had -no longer any room for the self-complacent feelings with which he once reflected on his own dignity and importance as a minister- of' the true Church. He now regarded himself as a servant of the Great Founder of Christianity, and sought from His Spirit alone the strength and meetness essential to the discharge of his duty. Dr. Bland marked the change   RUTH CHURCHILL,     199e in his young friend with true Christian feeling. He watched the growth of grace in his renewed heart, and rejoiced in its effect upon the outward man. There was no assumption of worldly importance, but a spiritual elevation of character, which gave moral dignity to the outward bearing of the Christian minister. Sophia, too, partook these changes, and could now say with truth, "that religion made 'her hap- py." With Ruth's assistance, Sophia strove to begin the education of her children, (she had now three,) by teaching them the great and important lesson of obedience. It has been quaintly said, that there are no child- ren in these days. The family circle con- sists of precocious men and women, who reason with their parents, and not unfre- quently convict them of error. This mis-  &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7691-00000101"/> 200     RUTH CHURCHILL. take in domestic discipline took its rise from the introduction of what was called rational education. Miss Edgeworth, a wise  and good woman, (and a beautiful writer,) was the founder of this system.=  It is rather astonishing- that the whole world should have been willing to let an old maiden lady lay down the law so positively on this point. People' seem to have lost sight of the prevailing belief. that mere theory can never be trusted in matters of importance. Miss Edgeworth's children, being all the offspring of her own imagi- nation, could be easily moulded into very wonderfm specimens of educational skill. It was her plan to allure children by scat- tering so many blossoms in the usual rug- ged pathway of learning, that they were not aware of any difficulty in attaining knowledge.  After all, we doubt whether   RUTH CHURCHILL.     201 the character be not more strengthened by habits of self-restraint and labor, than by the easy acquisition of tne elements    @ of knowledge.  At any rate, this way of A treading always on flowers, has superin- duced, as ,the " doctors" say, the habit of setting aside parental authority. Children who were not to be coerced in learning, shook off coercion in other things; and we sometimes  apprehend that parental au- thority has received a shock tnever to be recovered from, in the introduction of this  system. Ruth counseled her cousin to train her children to implicit obedience  from  their earliest years. It is true, that Ruth, like Miss Edgeworth, had   not maternal experi- ence to sustain, her theory; but unlike that lady, she had the experience of  Christian practice,  which goes to the root of all 26  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7691-00000102"/> 202     RUTH CHURCHILL. moral evil, and shows how it is to be cor- rected. Sophia was a tender mother, but Ruth assisted her in withstanding the al- lurements of early childhood, so as to maintain a steady check upon all wrong impulses. If mothers begin in time, their difficulties disappear as life advances. So- phia never suffered her children to demand of her a reason for her restrictions. They did not dare to venture on that little word why, so often the keystone of the arch of infant rebellion. Again, when Dr. Bland said medibine was to be taken, the little ones knew well that resistance was una- vailing. They soon found out that rebel- lion only magnified their own trials, for it brought upon them that which they could not bear-maternal displeasure. It is a common saying, that clergymen's children are always badly managed. This   RUTHi CHURCHILLo     203 may partly arise from  the fact, that the Rector or Pastor's children are the gene- ral pets of the congregation.   Children -cannot bear petting. They are human be- ings, and must be restrained; indIulgence only gives double strength to the natural principle of evil inherent in all mankind. Charles Hilton kept up a constant cor- respondence with his sister. He did not fail to explain fully to her the change he had   undergone since their early inter- course. Gertrude found her residence with her uncle a season of trial to her soul. He had been some years a widower, and having no children of his own, the task of ministering to his declining years devolved upon her.  The old gentleman    became helpless in body, and almost imbecile in mind. Some of his Protestant friends took advantage of this state of things to en-    .  .    &#xD;<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC7691-00000103"/> 204     RUTH CHURCHILL. deavor to undermine his new  doctrines. But a discovery of this attempt was met on the part of the Roman Catholic Church by a prompt remedy.  "Sister Margaret" was established in the house as nurse and spiritual superintendent. The old gentle- man died just before the return of Ger- trude's husband.  Mr. Devereux was a member of the Episcopal Church, and a strong-minded man. He removed his wife from all her former associates, and began what he deemed a reformation of the er- rors of her faith. He dealt tenderly with her in the course of his operations, and carefully avoided wounding her feelings. "I do not wonder, dearest," he would say, " that in your great grief you fell into error. You were too much occupied to remember that all secret, underhand workings are wrong.  Mrs. Allen dealt   RUTH CHURCHILL.     205. most unfairly in concealing her profession, and taking you from under the influence of your natural and true friends. You know now, my love, that the indulgence of any strong passion weakens the mind as much as the resistance of that passion would have strengthened it. I feel cer- tain that your having Mrs. Allen to en- courage you in the indulgence of your grief at our separation, prevented the ad- vice of your sensible friends from being regarded. I would not have you love even your husband too much, my own Gertrude. There is one to whom  your strongest love is due; for, are we not re- quired to love the Lord our God with all our mind, and with all our soul, and with all our strength? If we disobey this in- junction, we lose our title to that help which is , promised in every time of need.  &#xD;<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC7691-00000104"/> 206     RUTH CHURCHILL. You-would not have been left to the in- dulgence of such violent grief, had you  not. forgotten your obligation to love God supremely." Gertrude listened to her husband's words with deep reverence. "How could Mrs. Allen have made you give up your pure faith for her most so- ! phisticated and unnatural creed, my dear love? Even if we could believe (without warrant from the Bible) that the Virgin Mary is an intercessor at the throne of grace, what need have we of her inter-, cession? Think you that our blessed Sa- viour is not all-sufficient to help us- in time of need? Whatever is really proper for us, He will grant; and think you the Virgin or the Saints could procure for. us what is improper? How strange and ob- scure -is that notion of having so many, ,   f..    RUTH 'CHURCHILL.     207 hearers of prayer-so many different crea- tures to be propitiated. God is all pow- erful! Who else do we want? Our reli- ance in the supreme power must be weak- ened by this subdivision of-objects, if not of adoration, at least ofI solicitation." Gertrude was ashamed of her weakness. She found that she had been the dupe, or rather the instrument, of a jesuitical ruse. Her uncle had been long under the influence of the Romanists, and they had sent Mrs. Allen to secure the niece during her husband's absence. Gertrude -confessed to her husband that her mind had gradually 'been releasing it- self from the strange thraldom exercised by Mrs. Allen. "I read the books given to me by Ruth Churchill," said she, "and they contributed mainly to clear my mental vision.  The  &#xD;<pb n="208-209" xml:id="VAC7691-00000105"/> 208     RUTrtH CHURCHILL. peop le who visited my uncle, helped to disabuse me.  They talked before me in a manner3 that showed  me there was much planning and intriguing going on. There was always some ulterior end to be gained-some object of worldly interest to be accomplished. They regarded me as one of themselves; and took it for granted that my mind was thoroughly im- bued with their peculiar views. "Now, that was a mistake. When Mrs. Allen called upon the Virgill to comfort me, she did it so fervently, and told me so many instances of her interposition in the affairs of men, that my poor grief- shaken mind was overcome for a time. Besides, she removed from my mind the awful, heart-rending dread of my dear babe being shut out of heaven. I thought I owed her- an obligation that never could   RUTH CHURCHILL.     209 be cancelled. Now, indeed, I see things through a different medium.  I will not tell you the circumstances that weaned me from her influence; but they were such as changed my views, not only of her religion, but of her character. You cannot imagine how weary I became of her appeals to the Virgin. I soon learned to look upon her worship as wholly un- authorized by Scripture. You can scarcely imagine how little recognition there is of the Supreme Being in their worship. The ministry of man seems to be substituted for that of God. Yet the sisters of charity are regardless of their own  safety and comfort. They devote themselves to their vocation in a most praiseworthy manner. I always had   a profound  reverence for this class of religious professors; and it was hearing my uncle talk so much, of , .  .K   &#xD;<pb n="210-211" xml:id="VAC7691-00000106"/> 210     RUTH CHURCHLTT.  their holy walk and conversation, which made  me look  up to ( Sister Marga- ret.' Yet I found' her, when out of her vocation, as full of little worldly plans and manceuvres, as any devotee to the world." "Thus it must ever be," said Mr. Deve- reux, '" when the faith which actuates the mind is not of the right kind. A certain line of duty may be marked out, and fol- lowed with mechanical precision ;-great praise may be won by such a course, but there is no strong principle within, sup- plying the heart with pure motives, and giving a perpetual spring to the con- duct. "During my absence from home, dear Gertrude; I became intimate with a young clergyman, who was going on a foreign mission. We used frequently to walk to-   RUTH CHURCHILL.     2" gether for hours by moonlight ;- and dur- ing one of these walks he related the following incident in, hisf own life: "' I was educated for the ministry,' said he, 'more as a measure of expediency, than from choice.  My father was poor, but a rich uncle offered to give me a col- legiate education on' condition that I be- came a clergyman. My father was averse to my acceptance of this offer. He was not a pious man, but he had a horror for those men who brought up their sons to the ministry merely for gain. He used to say, ' that the Founder of our, faith cast the money-changers out of the temple, and these men were bringing them  in again.' But I had always been religiously inclined, my mother urged.   She said that from early childhood, I had been fond of going to church, and had expressed great regret  &#xD;<pb n="212-213" xml:id="VAC7691-00000107"/> 212     RUTH CHURCHILL. that we had not regular family worship. When questioned on the subject, I ac- knowledged -that I had a peculiar love for the ordinances of the Episcopal Church- that I wondered how  people could bring themselves' to worship in any other. In short, I gave such satisfactory evidences of having a call. to the ministry, that at fourteen years old I was presented to the Bishop as one who would soon become a hopeful candidate for holy orders. Self- flattery went a great way; but the flattery of my female friends convinced me that I was born" to be a shining light in the Church. "' Our old nurse showed, with great glee, a slip of paper, on which I had writ- ten-' the  Right Rev. Basil Thornton, Bishop of New-Jersey,' (that being my native state.) -My mind was certainly im-   RUTH CHURCHILL.      213 bued with no small share of.- clerical ambi-I tion at that time. My very dreams were tinctured with the same feeling. I imagined the triumphs of my pulpit oratory; and fancied myself the greatest Episcopal di-: vine of this or any age. I read the ser- vice of the Church aloud to the woods and waters, to perfect my enunciation, and strengthen my voice by constant prac- tice. As I grew up, I got the sobriquet of 'the parson,' and the boys at school used to shout amen, when   I finished speaking to any of them  on the play- ground. All this was of little moment. I kept myself from the sins of swearing and gaming, as utterly unclerical; but my heart was all this time as full of the world as it could well be of any thing. I was vain of my person--vain of my voice-of my  &#xD;<pb n="214-215" xml:id="VAC7691-00000108"/> 214     RUTH CHXURCHLL. talents; and doubly vain of my evident fitness for the sacred ministry. A"I grew up to man's estate without much change of character; but I learned to keep my vanity to  myself, because any display' of it subjected me to ridi- cule. "When I entered   the Seminary, I found there a distant relative of mine, who was also preparing for the Episco- pal ministry. We associated together; but our characters were wholly unlike. Allen Chepslow was the son of a Presbyterian divine. On my expressing surprise at his forsaking the Church in which he had been reared, he told me he had always pre- ferred the modes of worship in the Episco- pal Church. 'I had a pious aunt,' said he, 'who belonged to that Church. When   RUTH CHURCHILL.     215 I was fifteen years old, I fell into ill health from having the measles. My aunt invited me to spend the summer with her, and there I learned to love the prayer- book beyond anything except the Bible. My father is a very liberal man.  He was sorry when I told him that my choice was made, but he 'consented with- out hesitation or reproof. He conversed a great deal with me, and thought I was really fit for my   vocation. But, oh! Thornton,' said he, 'I have been very sensible of the onerous charge I am about to undertake. I have suffered many fears, lest, after all, my heart should be un- changed.' "'What do you mean?' said I. ' It ap- pears to me; that your case is very clear. Your preference for the prayer-book is a  &#xD;<pb n="216-217" xml:id="VAC7691-00000109"/> 216     RUTH CHURCHILLo decisive proof that you are called to the ministry of that Church.' "' Ay!' rejoined Allen, 'but I allude to that all-important point, the 'new birth.' I hope and trust that I am 'born again;' but it is- hard to decide upon this point. You know our Lord says, 'the kingdom of God cometh not with observation, for behold, the kingdom of God is" within you ;' and our Saviour, in his conversation with Nicodemus in the 3d chapter of John, says, 'the wind bloweth where it listeth, and thou canst not tell whence it cometh, or whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the Spirit.' This beautiful and ex- pressive passage is often in my thoughts. I pray most fervently for the (new birth of the Spirit,' and so, no doubt, do you.' "' Allen said this with so much solem-   RUTH CHURCHILL.     17 nity, that I felt momentary awe; but im- mediately after I smiled, and said flip- pantly, 'why, Allen, all these notions are misplaced in the Episcopal Church. This is genuine Methodism, I declare.' "' Allen- seemed somewhat shocked at my levity, but he answered in his usual tone, 'No, Thornton, it is Christianity, such as was taught by the Founder of our re- ligion HimnsefI--such as was taught by the Apostles after Him; and if it be not taught now, it is because men have de- parted from the true faith, and have be- come formalists,' "' I was a little startled. by such a new view of religion, (as-it was to me,) but I asked several of my fellow students what they thought of it, and. they laughed. "' The man is atn enthusiast,' said they. i"Surely it is enough to be baptized in 28  &#xD;<pb n="218-219" xml:id="VAC7691-00000110"/> 218     RUTH CHURCHILL. the Church, as ,we all are, to make us true Episcopalians.' "' Time wore on. I had frequent con- versations with Allen Chepslow on his pe- culiar views, and he labored earnestly to convince me that his was the true Chris- tianity. During our stay at the Seminary, Allen got seriously injured at a fire. His life was in danger, and he prepared him- self for the worst. I could not help being grateful to him for the interest he took in my conversion to the true faith, as he called it. One night the physician thought the crisis of his disease at hand. Allen was perfectly calm :i he spoke to me in glow- ing terms of the comfort he was then en- joying. "Thornton,' said he, 'if I can return from the world of spirits, I will see you again, Though, alas! the Scripture tells    RUTH CHURCHILL.     2219 us, that some will not believe, though one come from the dead to give them assu- rance of the truth.' "';He took a solemn and affecting leave of us all; and we all believed that his end was at hand. But a favorable change -came over him during the night, and the next day he was declared out of danger. "' Allen and myself were ordained to the ministry at the same time; but our lots were cast so far asunder, that we never came together- again. He went to the Far West, and fell a victim to the cholera. I learned from public report that his ministry was eminently blessed during the five brief years of his career. "'Meantime I remained among my old friends, and filled my station with credit and approbation. No one ever questioned my doctrines. I was said to be an elo-  &#xD;<pb n="220-221" xml:id="VAC7691-00000111"/> 220     RUTH CHURCHILL. quent expounder of the truth, and a zeal- ous advocate of Episcopacy. My course of life was smooth, and I enjoyed the consciousness of being in many respects 'better than other men.' I loved my Church, and believed myself one of the pillars of the sanctuary. "'And now, Devereux,' said my friend, drawing closer to me as we sat together, ' I have reached the most important part of my history. After five years of un- changed prosperity, I was awakened from my dream of security. "('One day (it was Sunday) I had preached to a full congregation. In the interval between the services, I sat in an arbor in my  garden, where I enjoyed pleasant breezes, and looked around on a beautiful prospect. I had fallen into gen- tle slumber, for the weather was warm, * ' AL ,*   RUTH CHURCHILL.    221 and, my thoughts were free. My afternoon sermon lay before me on a small table. I had been reading it over preparatory to its delivery. I must observe here, that I had been lately requested to give to the public my own views of the doctrines of Episcopacy. In the sermon before me I had enlarged on baptismal regeneration, and assured my congregation that it was found in the prayer-book--that bulwark of our faith-so precious to all true be- lievers. The manuscript lay open at that page. As I felt my senses gradually over- come with slumber, the words seemed to be repeated by some one near me. I started, and awoke thoroughly, for Allen Chepslow's countenance, radiant with light, was before me.  'Thornton!' said he, ' I have come to- warn you of your danger. All is fully revealed to me! I now declare to  &#xD;<pb n="222-223" xml:id="VAC7691-00000112"/> 22'2    RUTH CHURCHILL. you in the words of our Saviour, Except a man be born again, he cannot enter the kingdom of heaven.' "'I strained my eyes, but the vision had departed. The next mail brought the news of Allen's death.  He expired on the Sabbath day, so said the notice, 'full of hope of a glorious immortality.' There could now be no doubt, my-friend had returned from the world of spirits to con- vict me of error. "(From that memorable day, I assumed as a fact the words repeated to me by my friend. My convictions of error were poignant in-the extreme. I smote upon my breast, and cried, 'Lord, have- mercy upon me, a sinner!--Ay! a sinner indeed --one that had boldly withstood the word of God, and made the word of man my guide and counsellor.' *          - i   RUTH CHURCHILL.     223 "I  have told you this circumstance, my,dear wife," continued Devereux, 9"with the hope that you will feel it as I did. My friend Thornton is now a bright ex- ample of the power of grace to renew the heart." And Gertrude did feel it; with so many aids to conviction, she could not resist the truth "as it is in Jesus." Four years from the time of her first melancholy visit to her brother, she ar- rived at his house, accompanied by her husband, and bearing in her arms another little Alfred. She shed many tears as she embraced her dear friends, but they were tears of joy.  "Dear, dear Ruth," said she, "you never can know how much I love you, till you change- this world for another more worthy   of such  as you. There all things will be made clear. But  &#xD;<pb n="224-225" xml:id="VAC7691-00000113"/> 224     RUTH CHURCHILL even now, dear Ruth, I know one thing perfectly, it is this: 'Except ye be born again, you cannot enter the kingdom of  heaven.' "   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
