<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7606">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Wizard of the Wave </title>
            <author >Robinson, Fayette, (d. 1859)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7606</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The wizard of the wave</title>
                  <author >Robinson, Fayette, (d. 1859)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >107 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Stringer &amp; Townsend</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1853">[1853]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-02-15">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The wizard of the wave</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7606-00000001"/>THE  WIZARD OF THE WAVE. A ROMANCE. BY FAYETTE ROBINSON.  NEW YORK: STRINGER &amp; TOWNSEND 222 BROADWAY.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7606-00000002"/> Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year one thousand eight hundred and STRINGER &amp; TOWNSEND, in the Clerk's Office of the United States' Court for the Southern District of New York.   THE  WIZARD OF THE WAVE. CHAPTER   I. ST. JAGO. Do you know where St. Jago de Cuba is? It was once a great city on the eastern end of Cuba-one of those cities built by the early con-,  querors, and which even now preserve so much of the character of the old Moresque architecture, which has been perpetuated in all Spain and the colonies that emanated from it, since the days when the Arabs ruled the Iberian peninsular. The thick, massive walls of coral rock seem as if they were intended to resist an enemy, and the narrow- grated windows make every house seeim a castle. That, however, is not the reason of the great thickness of the walls, which were constructed for the purpose of shutting out the heat of a tropical climate. Sucli was the general appearance of the town ; and one of the most charac- teristic buildings was the Povada of the Serora Oapella, an old monos- tery which, by the gradual decay of old Spain and her colonies had subsided into a simple inn, frequented exclusively by the officers and crews of the national and foreign vessels which visited Santiago. The river was in the back-ground, and far away in the distance shone the glorious prospect of a southern sea. The sunset had all the gor- geous peculiarities of the southern ocean, the rose and orange hues ming- ling together and fusing themselves into tints which. Poussin might envy, and which Coreggio could not imitate. Far in the distance lay a dark, low, mysterious vessel, the black hull of which shone in the tropi,  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7606-00000003"/> 8        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. cal sea like a spot on the sun. This mysterious vessel had acquired a peculiar interest in the island, and was known to all as the "Wizard of the Wave." Far in the distance, half hidden by the long point which nearly shelters Santiago from the sea, lay the hull of another vessel, too far removed even to permit the tapering masts to be seen. The two vessels, in model, seemed fac similes, and there were some who thought that the one was but a shadow of the other. The Seniora Capella was keeper of the principal fonda of the city, whither came all the notabilities of the town and the officers of the ves- sels which from time to time visited the harbor; and on the night we speak of; early in the present century, it was crowded. Montaneros and Guajiros drank and smoked, chattered and sang; but amid all the crowd, one party became visible and distinct. Just in front of the window was a table, at which sat Hugh Hear- ton, master of H. B. M.'s Wizard of the Wave, Caleb Cuthody, surgeon  of the same, and Weevil, a mate of the Wizard. Not too far removed to be out of the reach of conversation. but too far to mingle in the society, sat Ralph Raddle, an able-bodied seaman. At another table was Faraguez, lieutenant of the governor of San- tiago-and an individual rejoicing in the name of Ralph Raddle, sat solitary and alone on a stool by himself. In the back part of the room were many sallors, and on the outside, peasants, men and women of the island, danced. At the time when our story opened, every voice seemed extended with mirth. Hearton, the master, in the uniform of his grade, a good, substantial, healthy-looking man, sat on the'right of the table-two of the other sides of which were occupied by Cuthody.(the doctor) and Weevil- and burst out in the following exclamation, the rationality of which none will dispute: ' "Curse on their noise! Doctor, can you not anatomise them?" The surgeon was busy with an olla, a Spanish dish, but one to which all sojourners in las antillas-have a natural proclivity; he waked up and began to speak. Before, however, we record the doctor's words, it may be as' well to describe his personalities. He had on a white monkey-jaclet, 'which betokened him to be a sailor; a white vest, of spotless neatness, which declared him a  gentleman; and the tight pants and gaiters, which all doctors, from Panglass to the present time, have worn. The doctor was fond of a joke, and said: i"Anatomise them! bless you, master! that would be easy enough, if I  had my instruments. Your argument, however, is rather too much even for a  doctor of medicine."   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE,           9 "Curse your landsman learning! Tell me, though, doctor, why in blazes does not the sun burn these devil's imps of natives as it burns us Why do they dance away as if, like Nova Scotians, they wanted to dance out the cold i"  But Mr. Weevil spoke. He was a little anatomy of a man, like a skin of parchment over one of the skeletons Cuthody used to study. His little round jacket, red waistcoat and big, sailor's trousers of fine duck, by the bye, told exactly what he was--a mate. "' Lord love' you, doctor!" said Weevil; " weather is nothing to them. They would dance in Davy Jones' locker, if the lid was shut down. Never mind, though, let us go back to first principles and the argument. Now, as I told you, listen to me: ("You are under a stake out on the foretop, 'all else close, a lee-shore a league on your larboard, and the eddy where' I told you. Now what would you do?" Hearton thought for a moment, and dipping his fingers in the glass, began to make all imaginable diagrams on the table. At last he said, "Listen to me, and I will show you." We will not repeat their scientific terms, though they shouted them loud enough to be heard at the other end of the city-; but at last Ralph Raddle, who had been a quiet looker-on, advanced, hitching up his trousers-which he wore in true seaman's fashion-as he did so. * "I daren't know as to that; but she be woundy quick to sail." "Caballeros," said Feraguez, advancing to the party; "they say that vessel is the ' Wizard of the Wave.'" "You are right, Mr., Spaniard," said Raddle. "Caramba, that is true; they tell me her captain is the devil." "D-n your eyes, Jack Spaniard! did you call my captain the devil? Call Charley Falkner the devil!" The surgeon, when he saw the sailor square off in regular Somerset- shire, crossed in front of them, and briefly uttered the word "Atten- tion!"Ralph at once dropped his arms, and stood erect, as if he had served  in the marines. The doctor uttered the other command, "Stand at ease!" "Doctor," said Ralph, "C I thought it were the lieutenant; but' it be only you.. Did you hear what that Spaniard said?" In the meantime Feraguez stood back in terror.     : The doctor said' slowly and carefully, "The gentleman told the truth. Captain Falkner :is-ahem!"   He then faced to the Spaniard, and said, " do you know, Sefior, he can call a wind when he pleases, and tell his ship to sail as fast as he wills."  .  x,  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7606-00000004"/> ].0       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. Feraguez looked amazed, and said, "( Why on earth dooes he come hither with his Wizard?" "Ah!" said the doctor, " that is exactly what you wish to know. Not even his crew do." ': None of them?" asked Feraguez. "No; not one." Feraguez, who be it understood spoke an English not exactly clas- sical, but very like that of a Gibraltar water-carrier, said, "The gov- ernor would give a hundred golden crowns to any one who could tell him about that ship. Perhaps you can." This was said with the peculiarly insinuating air Spaniards and the other southern races use, when. they wish to corrupt. The doctor, who was -a sturdy John Bull, fully impressed with the idea that any one who did not speak English must be a. Frenchman, seemed to hesitate, but at last dropped the words, as if involuntarily: ("A hundred crowns! I might get them." The Spaniard drank in every syllable. At last he said: "Goodl Sefior, you will tell me, and the hundred golden crowns shall be yours." With all the majesty of an Hidalgo, he wrapt his cloak around him and stalked away, leaving the two officers and Ralph Rad- die comparatively alone. When Feraguez was gone, there was a brief pause in the conversea tion, which was finally broken by R-alph, who again approached the table from which he had temporarily withdrawn, with- the habitual tug at his trowsers, everywhere recognized as the distinguishing char- acteristic of a sailor. He said: "Lord, Master Doctor, what on airth made you stuff up that Spaniard with stories so?" "Ralph," said the doctor, I did not tell him one. I said the cap- tain could order a wind when he pleased; so he can. I did not say, however, that the wind would come. I said he could order his ship to sail, as fast as he pleased. So he can; but, for all that, you know, as well as I and the cap'tain do, how many knots an hour the vessel can make.             ,         - -Weevil became enthusiastic, butt6ned up the breast of his jacket, and uttered the very nautical exclamation: "Give us your hand, old plank; for a betfter one never was built in a vessel;" and he took the captain's hand. "You have done what many admiralty-lifted lubbers never would have dared, even if they had eaten up their cocked hats and epaulets. You will, however, own that your vessel is in, devilish strange sound., ings."   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. ^ Hearton took his hand, and said, ' I can't say. Obey orders is the maxim, and the captain is as tight as a marine drum.  One more drink." ' Belay, belay!" said Weevil; "I have orders to execute, and the man we get them from gives orders. You are a good sailor, and the very sight of you brings up the very bilge-water of memory. Good-bye, good-bye! some day you will know more." The worthy mate looked intently into Hearton's face, as he spoke the last words, and hurried out, followed by all the sailors who had hitherto sat in the room, at a most respectful distance from their superiors, At the very door of the room he met a strange-looking customer, half sailor, hal-landsman, rejoicing in the euphonious name of Tim Treacle, purser's clerk of the "Wizard of the Wave;" and was saluted by the latter thus: "Stranger unknown, how are you?  Take a drop of nothing?  You belong to the schooner over the point, don't you?"  Weevil gathered up all his dignity, and said; 1"My master, I belong to the vessel over there, but how on earth do you know she is a schooner  Everybody knows you can tell the difference between a pig-tail and a dutch-cheese; but where, my little land-crab, did you find out what a schooner was?" - The crowd laughed, for a purser's clerk is the butt of every ship; and the more angry Tim Treacle Ibecame, the -louder was their iairth. Ralph Raddle, of all the crowd in the room, stood alone, and laughed louder and longer than ever, so much that he finally attracted the atten- tion of Treacle, who approached him in a threatening attitude. He said: "Stop your laughing; I won't stand it! Sure as'the rule of three is true, 'll fight. Call me a land-crab!"  Ralph laughed, and none can tell what the desperate clerk might have done, so warlike had he become, if Hearton had not stepped between them, and said: "-Come, lads, no quarrels, for we have far more important things to think of. . The natives here, T mean these Spaniards, think our craft the devil's own, and only a coop for a crew of fiends. They think we all come from the waters on the other side of Holmes' hole. Now this won't do; for as long as they think so, the devil a boat will come to us devils, with fresh Tommy, or anything else that is fresh."' "Ah!" said Tim, "I do suffer! I lived so luxuriously at home 1! Raddle looked at him, and said, drily, "Yes, your mother keeps a chandleris shop at Gosport"  "Well, Mrj Jolly--for let me tell you, Mr. Raddle, you be nothing but a marine--was not that a luxury? A1l I wanted, was in the shop.  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7606-00000005"/> 12        THE WIZARD QF THE WAVE. Didn't I get the nice corners of the loaves the baker left in the morn- ing? and didn't I dip them in the treacle? What have I got now? bad biscuits, bread and meat together, where bugs have been breeding for seven years, and meat that nothing but a boarding-axe can cut. I feel the difference, with tears in my eyes! I do-I do!" The purser's clerk walked to and fro in the most agitated manner,. and at last approached Doctor Cuthody, who said, "Tim, keep your tears to stirengthen your grog. These Jack Spaniards are all afraid of us, for I saved the life of one poor fellow by a cataplasm on his stomach, and the graceless hound said I put my hand on his stomach, and it burned him like a hot iron. By the soul of Qalen, I put a regular blister of Spanish flies on his bread-basket, and I took good care they should burn the graceless scoundrel!" "Ah!" said all and Treacle insinuated, "But, doctor, your remedies are twice as strong as those we serve." "Of course they are. We don't sell them." "'But, doctor," said Tim Treacle, " the worst of the matter is, they really avoid me." "They do, do they? That is very funny." Ha! ha! ha f" laughed all-and the conversation might have con- tinued much longer, but that a loud, cheery laugh was heard outside, speaking thus: "I Heave ho! my, hearties, what cheer? Donna Capella, ho I my she admiral Donna Capella "--and in rushed Tom Truck, coxswain of the Wizard-of the Wave, in the tight-hipped trousers and loose jacket of the sailors of the day. Tom sung the first stave of an old sea-song, "All among the Hottentots, capering ashore," etc. {' Yoho, my hearties! so you have all come to anchor in this roadstead? and it is the best in the island. But where is the old lady? Donna Capella,Donna Capella, ahoy 1" And Donna Capella entered. But who was she?  A nice, tight, snug-built .Spanish woman, of thirty-five or forty, very little the worse for wear, with a profusion of bracelets; jewelry and chains. She had just enough of the black blood in her Veins to give that wavy curve to her hair which is so great an attraction in the creole quadroons. Probably no race on earth dress so extravagantly as the natives of the West Indies, and- the white satin skirt, tight fitting-black velvet bodice, covered with silver lace, and the silk stocking and well-fitting shoe, disclose no small vestige of beauty. ' Aha, Selores Inglese! Setor Truck, I kiss your hands."   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           18  ClKiss my hands, Donna! not Tom Truck's sorry hands, but kiss. his lips, though they are stained with tobacco." As Truck spoke, he and all the company bowed with the most ludi- crous gravity. "Ah, Se/ior Truck, why do you make so much noise and bellow like a bull so much '?" TrAick said," Donna, the mosquitoes bother me so, I could not but yell. But, Donna, what can you -tell me about all the traps of the leftenant. Give me your advice now, my bumboat commodore." Donna Capella arose with an air of offended dignity, and said," I know nothing about bumboats or commodores; are you-sure your cap- tain cannot hear?" "To be sure." "Well, they say he is the devil," said Donna Capella. While you were all amid the storm of yesterday, -when the wind was highest and the water roughest, in came your captain, epaulets and all. He said, I Donna, the weather is bad. I waft some wine.' I went for it, and I saw, when I came back, your captai[ all dressed in black-black velvet. He said to me, ' Donna, some brandy!" "What! our captain?" "' Yes, your captain!" "Dressed ra black?" "Yes!" "Well?" "I was afraid, and ran back to where I left him; and there he stood, in full uniform, waiting for his wine. I tell you, your captain is the devil!"  The company present had heard this, but being all old sailors, they laughed at it, except Tim Treacle, who become completely overpowered, and fell at once into Heartoh's arms. As he did so he said: "Ah! ah! support me-I shall faint!" The crowd hurried around and fanned him, being more prodigal of attention than they would probably have been with many a better tnan. The doctor stepped up and said, "Wait a moment, until I breathe a vein ;" 'and he whipped out the case of instruments, which military and naval surgeons keep with them carefully as/other men. do their pocket- iooks. "Donna, did you see the captain's tail?" "See the captain's tail! no, I never look at captains' tails.1' "I am glad, for then I never would have recovered."  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7606-00000006"/> "       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. The master Hearton walked up and down the rood  silently, but evidently in deep thought; and shadows seemed to com and go'mys- teriously over his brow. .At last, Tom Truck said: "Stop your log, and just look at the master walking up and down there, like a ship in the trade-winds! Bless your soul! though in Donna Capella's house, his thoughts are in blue water. Ha! you do not think the skipper is the devil, do you? Ho! Mr. Hearton, what do you think?" Hearten said, moodily, "I cannot say, lad, for I am entirely out of my latitude, and I tell you what: last night I saw you put off with the captain in his gig, and had not gone ten steps towards Donna Capella's, when, bless your soul, I saw him plain as I see you!;' Tim Treacle had heard the conversation, and said, "Master, did you see the captain's tail?"' "See his tail! why?"          , "]Because, then it is certain that he is the devil.:" "Tim Treacle, do you think his majesty ever gave the devil com- mand of such a ship as that?" "Lord Bless you,sir, how should I know?" "The doctor seemed not a little amazed, and burst out with the exclamation, ': We must all be physicked. Bless my soul, here he comes!" The words were scarcely uttered, when the person of whom they spoke, Captain Falkner, master of the Wizard of the Wave, walked through the arched door-way and sat down. None had seen him enter, and they were not a little surprised when he said: "Donna Capella, when you have finished waiting on those gentlemen, perhaps you will attend to their captain." Up started the Donna, with a scream, and not a person was present 'who did not feel as ift something supernatural had taken place;.and they hurried to different parts of the room,.each expressing the deepest amazement and surprise. * Holy trinity!" said Donna. dapella.          . "Your honor here!" said truck. Bless my eyes!"  "Lord! I smell brimstone!" said Tim Treacle. Falkner appeared to hear none of these exclamations.. Perhaps he did not; but he walked across the room-all avoiding him, either from respect to discipline, or because they thought the devil was among them. When alone, he began to talk, as men will do, who have great objects to guard.'   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           15 (: Manly's story," said he, '" is true; for even those who have served with me for years, seenm affected by it. It is good, though, for it may- ay, it shall serve my purpose." He turned around to the hostess, and said'  "Come, my charming Donna, attend to the provisioning department, and serve out a stiff allowance to all my dainty Wizard's men, and give the captain, do you hear, a double allowance of cold water. A sailor's legs were not made for climbing over high hills, beautiful soever as the lime trees and orange blossoms may be." Donna Capella looked at him in amazement, and said, "In a moment, captain. Oh, that such a handsome man should be'captain of devils!" She left at once, to attend to his orders; and we may here say, that, though we have given what Donna Capella. said, in tolerably good English, she spoke the miserable lingua-franco dialect, which makes the patois of the American Mediterranean even worse than that of Etrope. Falkner turnted to his master and said, '"Hearton, let the eye of your experience see that the Wizard be taught and trim, alow and aloft, as a lady's boudoir. Truck, my man, do not be standing there, like a dol- phin at confession, but see the boat's crew rigged in their best. You, Treacle-  " "                   , "Your honor! your honor! Lord!" said he, aside, '-don't 'I smell brimstone?"                           . "Treacle, tell Se-geant Cartridge to have his men in parade order. I am going to give a ball on board." Ralph Hearton saluted, and said what a sailor says to every order: "Ay, ay, your honor." Tim was in amazement, and said: "A ball on board!"  "Yes, Paster Pursor's-clerk, I intend to give a ball on board, if you have no objection." "None in the least, your honor; but you will of course invite the ladies?" Falkner laughed, and said, "' Of course, I will; for what were a ball without their shining faces? We, poor sons of the sea, know too well what it is to be without the heaven of their society, to omit a single, . opportunity of enjoying it. The glories and wonders of old ocean, the sweet varieties of flower-covered lands, all pass as nothing to the lonely mariner; but were the partner of his fate, the girl he loves, companion of his perils, the boundles waste around him would be peopled with sweet hopes. The sun-burnt lands of all the world would be dear to him 'as his loved home, danger would be a dream, toil a  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7606-00000007"/> 16        THE WIZARD OF- THE WAVE. pleasure, and the hard-earned victory doubly proud and glorious; for her smile would thank him and her eye speak the share she bore in the bright fame he had achieved. Here, though, lads, is your grog. To women-ugly, old, young or beautiful-still they are the soothers of our cares. . Woman!" We need not say that the toast was drank enthusiastically.- The landlady's niece Dianez entered, and all looked at her except Tom Truck, who could have no idea that a woman was made for any- thing but a landlady. The brilliant black eye, the full rounded form, the pretty foot, and graceful figure of Dianez, were all displayed by her amber skirt and black velvet bodice, which is almost as universal in Cuba as thefaj, or sash in Andalusia of old Spain. The two coun- tries in fact are not unlike-men and women having the same impetu. osity of soul and thought, the same dark eyes, and the same fusion of languor and excitement, which makes them, either the most yielding or terrible in the world. "Your honor," said Truck. Hthat is, sir, it is miraculous, but 5Mr. Belford, the first lieutenant, your honor, knows-it is miraculous--last. night, when we were alongside, overhauled this idea of a ball. Says I, your honor, says I," That is the way to hook all the female fish of the island, old and young,; and, blast my eyes, if we don't show them that we men of the Wizard are not witches nor devils I Do you know, your honor, I have satisfied a good many of the female creters, that it was not the case with old Tom, at least sometime ago?"  "( No doubt of it, Truck; but just tell Mr. Belford, that I have taken the wind out of his' sails. Tell him, too, in his cruise up yonder, to keep a sharp look on the bearing of every height. He will know what I mean. Here, my lass, is payment; now give me the change." He took, fair Dianez around the waist, kissed her pouting lip, and went out, laughing merrily. Dianez had preceded him. The master sat silently for a moment, and then, with a thoughtful voice, said: ': He is a brave fellow. The king has no better officer." "You mtay say so, Master Hearton ; for a better sailor never trod a deck. As to his being old nick, why the'devil himself would not like to have him board his quarters."' a"I am not so sure," said Treacle, " that, there was not something infernai in his kissing DiaJnez. sIt really' made me jealous. I love that :  ' u.       ;,        .  . ,    i e,  ;: Truek looked'i at him with amazement: "Stop your gabble, young aiisblfledh^e;foei though fItotAf say much, I kindio',like- that young one,   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.  and I won't have your purser's mug between a sailor like myself and her. Ah! there is his honor, just getting into his boat., There she goes, behind the rocks.2    .  All took off their hats, paying from disciplinp, even at a; distance, all 'the respect due the roy i commission. They had scarcely done so, when a strapger entered the roQm an,d threw off his oroak He. wosre nth e :rss of th-e day in that countya  slouched hat with a.'plume, tight black pantaloons, a gray vest, a;di the. heavy Spanish boots, all wore in his land. The whole dresswas. trimamecd with gray, and, like his plume, was black as the raven's wing. All rpge at quce, perfectly paravlyzed: not at his entrane, but at thie striking likeness and alnmost identity of the strangerwjith the captain, the boat of'whom they had just before se en disappear. Dress alo ne made the difference, and but for it, none could have distinguished the stranger from' the captain.  ., '   W 'ay, Tim!". said Truck. "Tomn!" said Tim.         '             . Hearton caught te doctor's hanIad. $&amp;s e clec it. ; saOid :  ." Caeb CathodyP'     . , ,          ;  '[ Heartoan!" said the doctor.      ,     . All ooki ,with awnazement at ,the uiktpo0a, w ho -sat Sient:ay ieun, observing.  Truck first recovered himself, and ,ad  1  Z 1, I ;nev wsa, th skipper in black before.'" .     .            ... In .sad' tone, Heartona   I iE O 1 ,ta s p . hk er, skt ith* dv Dianezeated theom,      s "a ;  s  theestrah e qtarte ak and ewclaimedi in her on' tp ngue, Es el 4iabi p!" . : : . . The stranger wmi o pQ          t b.ub^    r, - Dianez, Baid z  4   BiDng .me some f yeor bet , tine a,; 1.n;a n 4 ter the ianezs was about to kleave, b.  - lie., ..   .... . . , cted, ter back, and said,. carel'ayi; .          ; :  -^^   S1 have, thrp ,a ,0 , , '"Mr. Weevil was here a moment since, si;."; ' Ah-!( ifhe be gone biung me teyipP ,i^ e",r te usknown, relapsed  4o, ;,il ancend iaft  , ,  etto, ,5p Truck recvered his pesenme,of,mina, i4 .   . i ".T at iB th: captain's voice, 1'll swear, and the Bla;ok :,'W'i i 1               t  O    -                ,              .  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7606-00000008"/> 18       THE WIZARD   PF THE WAVE. ".That is he, I swear," said Hearton; " see the gold chain he always: wears!" "I am not used to be fearsome,"' saidt Truck; but, by the powers, I am all in a cold sweat. I wish one of the lieutenants would come to overhaul that fellow's papers. Treacle was terrified to death, and could but exclaim, while each particular hair stood erect: "If 'I was only in Wapping, wouldn't I desert?!--and he began at once to move towards the door, when the doctor said, following him:         , "'ll Stop him."' "Avast, there, doctor 'we want you ; and he'caught the medico by the jacket. "Now,"1 said he, " that we are boarded by the ,devil; we cannot spare the doctor from the coclkpit.'" "Of course not, Truck," said the nmaster; " hold on to him. (He. arose and took the doctor's hand.) Hold on, old fellow. If the' devil is not very hungry, the purser's elerk will make a very decent lunch for him."  K Caleb Cuthody faced around, and, in the most professional manner conceivable, said, "Is prescribe an immediate change of air for all hands."    '   ' "'Well, well, it is, either the captain-or-or the devil," said'the group, each uttering in succession one of the members of this sentence! And they cautiously left the room. The stranger, who had caused all this comment, sat for some time quietly sipping his wine, and then arose and paced the room anxiously, and; muttered to himself: "Fool! fool! I bade him wait for me. No messenger either from the stupid governor! They leave me alone to play ou0t this desperate game, and I will not shrink from .it. This English captain, they say, is shrewd, sind commands as fine a bark as ever floated, yet I do not fear him' I, who have outwitted all men in all lands, do not fear this rude son of, ocean, clever and brave though he be. I have "a rich prize before me, unbounded wealth, peerless beauty, and, repose from a life of storm. There lies my craft, that naught that sails has ever beaten, and -- one more step in blood, and, then- a life of peace-- . I will not stop, and nothing shall make me doubt success." The dark man continued to walk to and fro in agitation, until another person entered. He turned 'abruptly to himi, and said: "Sluggard, you made your port: just in time to save your tide, but only in time...  Dianez in the interim  brought in more wine, which she placed   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           19 before them and then retired to the door, behind which, utseen by the two, she stood using the woman's privilege of listening. The new comer, in the, full, green uniform of a Spanish officer, and the name of whom was Feraguez, the lieutenant of the governor of Santiago, said, respectfully: "Sefor, I have been here more than an hour, but the crew of that English ship being present, I did not show myself." The stranger said,." True; the governor is in'vited to their ball. He must go, as all must who are to be companions of that journey we know of. Hear me! The' English are here either for good or bad, but be that as it may, the festivities of the evening will throw them off their guard. When the moon rises, after midnight, their vessel will not be able to pass the bar, and I will have thus seven hours the'start. My ship is all unmoored, and before they can well get to sea, will be beyond their reach." "And the treasure?" "Will be placed on board while the fools are dancing. Weevil will attend to that. Tell Don Jose he must join in their revels, and trust all to me; for though he see me not, I will be near. I too may dance, but it will be as the flame dances over the magazine, until some crevice is found, to enter and sweep all to ruin." "Iwill deliver your message. Adios, excetenza!" ' My G-d, I would as soon sail with- the devil as with him! I do not think he is a very good man." Poor Feraguez, though not far wrong, was not right; for the. person of whom he spoke, was 'one of those fearful men sent on earth seem- ingly as curses.  When he was gone, the stranger arose again, and pacing the room as he 'had previously done, resumed the tenor of his thoughts, which seemed to burst from his lips in words like tie fol- lowing-  "I Now for my mountain beauty! I will win the prize of her match- less loveliness, and she shall share' my trip, though all th'e British navy stood before me.' Ho, for the bower of beauty I The serpent's tonguo in Eden was not so sweet as 'miie shall be. She may haye friends who love her!  Pshaw, what. of that,!' I love her, and she shall' be mine, though I trample on'a thousand hearts to make my victory sure. ^ Now for the mountain and 'my irize "  The stranger put on his cloak and hat, and stalked rapidly from the room. Dianez entered when hee had left, and said, to herself, as she took- away the glasses:.       "    &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7606-00000009"/> 20        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. '"What can Me mean? no good, I'm sure. I'll think of it." And' she did think of it to some purpose, as will be seen; for women are great hands at unraveling mysteries.       i C H A?T E R  II. THE MEETING. THERE is no more beautiful country on earth than'Cuba. Its rich plantations, its glorious cafetals and sugar hciendas have often been described, and many a wild fancy has luxuriated in the scenes of deli- cious lapguor, with, which all is so redolent. The beautiful isles of the Egean, doubtless, have their beauty enhanced. by the fact that poets in all ages, from Homer to Byron, have sung them ; and for a similar reason, beautiful as they are, the great and. glorious Antilles are but half appreciated. They are not, however, without their romance, for there Columtus first comprehended the glory and greatness of his own acts; there De Soto, Ojeda and Ulloa rose to fame and distinction; and there lingers the lone vestige of European despotism in America Some day it must be the subject for the poet and novelist, though as yet, it has attracted no pen but .that of the American Irving, of whom may be said, as was of his great prototype :Goldsmith, "he touched nothingthat he did not adorn." .  One great feature of Culq. has, however, been rarely described-its mountaina. Likc those of Sicily, they rise high above the plains below, but unlike, ther ,haye many beautiful table-lands, which, since the colo- nization of .the .isand, afford a retreat for those of the population who, in the unhealthy season, were from their position unabale to. fly from the only curse of. the country- the vomito,of September. These moun- tains rie prsqim t.,! , ,thbe different character offoliage, and of growth beitoleknina 'dif:rent;cl'm'a'te and temperature. First in, the,plain are the guiava the palma-real,' with f the trunk like an Egyptian column, the. zpote, the limne, and the, ofrange.. Higher up, the .ipn-wood and the bastard mahogany, and on the brows the .pine and the Spanish olk-- 4all perpetually green. never changing, and almost realizing, those fanmous Armidanislands, w)ere ": sutmmer,reigned all-the year, and winter came not."   -  T s  y v erg toQ isavarious s th I trees: it ,reduces. On the lowlands are the coral rooks, the vast- concrete madrepore,; oa the,decli-   THE   WIZARD OP THE  WAVE.        21 vity cupriferous quartz, shale, etc.; and high up, towards heaven, great granite peaks, which prove the islands of the Mexican Glulf to be por- tions of the American continent, abraded perhaps when the gre'at lakes, whichi rolled where now the North American praries are, burst their barriers and swept down the Mississippi to the sea. In, one of the goriges of the mountains which rise westward of San- tiago, and from the highest point 6ofwhich might be seenthe town with the two vessels in view, (the one lay in the hairbor, while the other was anchored beyond the low point of land whch in fact constituted the harbor,) not long after the strange scene we have spoken of, stood four persons, three of whom were negroes, in the common cotton dress of of their class. The, fourth was Isabenda del Sandover, a Castilian lady, and daughter of the governor of Santiago.' : We are but poor hands at a description of female dress, and can say no more of the lady than that she wore the peculiarly rich dress of her country, and the veil which Spanish women ever substitute for'the hideous bonnet with which those of other lands for centuries have disfigured themselves. Her name was Isabenda, and she spoke thus to the eldest of the three negroes, the dress of whom showed that he was of: a superior gang, and a mem- ber of what is called, in that country, the gente 'de cask, and in portions of pour, own, rejoices. in -the less euphonious synonym of " house-gang." Her voice was clear and musical, and she said to the slave: "'Domingo! domingo! it cannot be that these English are as bad as you say they are. There lies their'vessel, like a stately bird; and those I saw before- my father sent me to this wilderness, were very good- looking, very handsore..                ' "Yes, donna. The devil in their country is very good-looking. He wears a wig to hide his horns, and covers up his tail with a long:skirt.'  "Bah! Domingo,"' said Isabenda, " that is all nonsense: 1" "It is true, donna, and he carries a green bag,'and theycall him lawyer!" "( That is foolish," rejoined the lady; " and I saw one far handsomer than our countrymen', who my father said wal an officer. He said, though, they were all atheists and very bloodthirsty. Heigho!'why did my father send me hither, where it is so lonely. He promised, too, that I should not be alone." "But, donhai you are not alone, for I am here." "But he said I should have a maid."' "Well, I am your maid, and a very good one too. Did I not nurse you' when you were little? why not nurse you now?" "Well, Domingo, it cannot be helped, and I must abide by my o e, helped', and, I must  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7606-00000010"/> 22       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. father's will. See, though, Dianez comes! He has faithfully kept his promise.".  Dianez came up to, the party at, that moment, and she was kindly receivedlby Isabenda, who bade her the warmest welcome. She ex- claimed:  "Now I shall enjoy the blooming flowers, and watch with joy the twinkling stars. I will be able to listen, too, to the murmur of the water-fall. How, though,is my, father? When will I see him?" -' He will come, to see you, secretly," said Dianez. He sent me up 'from my aunt's, and bade me say he would see you as soon ais possible after me."'  "Dear Dianez, what means. this mystery v  Were we not so happy until that English vessel came?,. Npow everybody seems afraid." I had an English sweetheart, "': said Dianes; and I am sure I thought him more of angel than a devil."         *  "Bah!" said old Domingo, " that is nonsense; three are no English angels. Angels nevyer speak English. All devils do though." a Domingo, what language do angels speak?" "Mandingo, to be sure, a pretty language is Mandingo ;" and the old man began a long, monotonous, negro chant, which might have lasted I g/ know not how long, had not the fair Castilian's father joined them. He was a tall, fine-looking Spaniard, preserving all the characteristics of his:race, but with a sad, melancholy brow, betokening deep and secret sorrow. He wore all the insignia of his rank, which well became him, and set off his person to the greatest advantage. He clasped his daugh- ter in his arms, kissed her, and half in ejaculation, half in conversation, said: "My child! my treasure I it were indeed a pity to blight the promises of thy lovely, youth. . Domingo, take -your companions with you. Do you hear?' Watch the point-the signal-point--you under- stand-so that my 'retreat may never be cut off. Be watchful!" "Yes, master," said Domingo; "I never sleep on my post, and will watch for the English devils;" and Domingo left with his sa10le com- panions., "' ianez," said the, governor, ' remain within, for I have something to say to you." Dianez left, and at once the governor turned to his daughter and said; "What ails you, my child? Why do you tremble so, and look so pale? are you, not with your father?"  '  Ah, yes!" said Isabenda, L" with a dear, dear father. You too, sir, are pale! What is the matter? . Tell, tell your child i Your hot hands,   THE WIZARD OF TH4E? WAVE.          23 your restless eye, the nervous motion of your lip, all conspire to make me fear for you. . Yet I know not what to fear." "Do not then," said Don Jose; " 'tisbest." .      - "Father," said Isabinda, "I fear. Tell me, father, the very worst. I will not tremble, then. What is the matter? Tell -me, tell me if you love me--if you love my mother. All makes me dread something, though I know not whlat, is fear?". "'Tis well, daughter, you do not." "Now," said Isabinda, " you make me tremble. Dear father, let me know the worst, and;. as. said) I will not tremble then--let me but share your fate,. whatever it be, Cast me not from you, if you love me. We were all happy before that fatal vessel came." "How know you that?" said the governor.. Who said I feared that vessel?, Who has dared-- -" The old governor paused, as:if to checkl thoughts that found too quick an utterance. ' Nay, I am wrong. Her anxiety alone makes her suspect; yet why deny? That vessel does annoy me.' "Why," said Isabinda, "should you, dear father, so dread and fear the English?"  ,Don Jose looked sadly at her, and said: "I have my reasons, girl; for their unusual presence may thwart the. labored purpose of my trouble life-may plunge me from a pinnacle of power :into the contempt of darkness and of poverty! I hate, I loathe their' sea-girt isle. AL wild memory of my youth pictures a ruined home--a blighted, name--heart- broken parents, and a fiend-like friend, false as the pit he sprangt from. Black were his deeds, black as the heart:within his breast, and tortur- ing as the eternal memory of his wrongs-and even now'drive on the refuge till no refuge can be found except in madness or the grave!  - "Father," said Isabinda, , this is awful." "True, girl, it is terrible ; but yet you Shall know all. ,The ,time is near, when I may be, perchance, stripped of power. You leave the island to-night."           , The, pale girl looked around with terror,. and throwing her arms about her father's neck, said: "Leave my lovely home--this' glorious isle-the spot where I have- trained my flowers, Where the feathered tenants of my orange-bowers come at my beck and call-leave- my home?"                  -  "Innocence and .youth, dear child, can makl a home wherever they will. Yon vessel is my fate  ..      , "Why so, dear father? They tell me its officers are frank and free."   &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7606-00000011"/> 24        TlHE; WIZARD OP THE"WtAVE,. "You will be aile to judge them: better;. for to-night we will attend the ball on board their ship."  - "Ah!". said Isabindai and!her young heart eat W'ith joy; " a ball : a ball I Af'd may I go:?-.a- ball:! a ball!"  ' Come, d ughiter, comel'" said the. old Spaniard. "'I will attend yoh.  'tGo'to the hermitage:'and prepare for the ball, which must, to a heart like yours, free from all guilt and shame, be joyous. Come, Dianez, and Domingo will- attend yoda."  And the: sad couple' left. Theonetwas weighed downf by memories of the past, and the 'other, despite herself, chuld n-ot but entertain anti- cipations of the future. 'Thus, is it ever; for in youth, as the great Jean Paul has said, ' we seb dinm shWadows :spread-before tis, anid in old age see nothing but{ darkness-behind us." Scarcely had they gone, when the clear,:lotd voice of Truik was heaid, shouting as if he rmannied the; anchor, "' Heave ho! master Tim Treacle, spread moie canvas! Come on! come on!"      . And around the declivity of a roek appeared Tim, pist1o in hand, with gTruck behind him, armed with a boat-hook.  Truck shouted again:  "Shake out a reef or two more, I tell you, or his honor will make a target of your stern-parts, Iby way of practice, Do you hear, you lubbber!"   "Any one," said the purser's lerk, "who bheard. you talk, would think I was a pointer-dog, iniste4ad of an :bfice*er  of his majesty's victual- ing department. - -Mr.:Belford is oo good a-sportsman ever to take me for a- partridge- or iguana. Do -you think he ftould ma;ke game- of me?" "Make game of you, Tim:! 'Lord, everybobdy does! But did not you join our convoy bedaue' you haid you' were good at beating up the game ," "But, Tom Truck, I have seen no game to beat. I have got a gun, you see,"-and Treacle shook his pistol ferociously-" while you have only a boat-hook., As, though you cannot shot shoot ihem with a boat- hookl,.I suppose you ha've your poclket fuill of fresh saIlt to sprinkle on their tails!" - It was rarely that Truck put on dignity; but now he looked grave as a'chgaplaini, or a midshipmania ebs1pecti-g pridifitiabn. He turned his quid twice or thrice in his mouth, and thefn boke :'ut sonmewhat in this fashion': u  I          ' ("You ugly, little, uncivilized powder-monkey!-do you dare to play   THE WIZARD OFP 'THE; WAVE.          25 tricks on me, Tom Truck, coxswain of'the captain of 'the Wizard of the Wave? you swab, you wretch, you salt junk of ingratlfude! Did not your mother rub out my chalk for tBbacco and smuggled gin, i-Iiwoubld just let you drown yourself in a :bucket iof, bilge-water , 'o6t- poke your speaking-trumpet at me, you wet nurse, you sucking cockney! Look here! now just start up a fox, a hare, or some other bird, or I will make all the blolly,-boys give you a h6ly: stoning, and grease you 'down with a salt eel afterwards. - Away with you, youd cribbing, allow- ance-stealing insect! or I will give you a box as big as 'a captain's, sea- chest."     ; Truck would probably have, put his threat into exeicution, had not a young man, in the handsome uniform of the royal :avy, entered. The new comer said: "Ava-st; there, Truck! What on earth has Little Slops been doing?" 'The new comer was Mr. Belford, of :'holm we have had oceason to speak more' than once. "'Done, your honor! done! He never did nythiiig. I brought him along because he bragged about his sportsmanship.. He teld me as'how he once went shooting in some' wild country they calls' Wardsworth, and was out with the king at Epping, or some where in foreign parts, where people hunts stags and sausages. Bless: your honoris eyes! I thought, before now; he whuld -ave started a whole convoy. Bah! he is hot worth a quii of tibaco! that has been ch:ewEd6for ever sotmany days." Belford laughed', and -said:; "'Well, Truck, there is nothing but an iguana to be started here."                4 "Mr. Belrford," said Treacle, ' you will eertainly remember, t hough this old sea-horse forgets it, that I acm neither a houndt nor a -ponter- dog. If, though, I can be of tuse to a brother sportsman, please com- mand me.  But this old sea-monster, to whom my mother, now an angel in heaven -- 'i Tom Truck looked amazed, and yelled, "My eyes! your mother an angel! I swear, lieutenant, she squinted.." "Never mind -that, Mr. :Belford. As :Sergeant Radd-le would say, it is eyes right now with her. She fed this old sealog with tobacco and good' Holland gin, and ;kept him cleani; and :in return, the old:vagabond i tempted me -to sea.' So the last of the house of ',Teacle .is now ir exile, wasting his sweetness on the desert air. Sir, sir, it is too panfhii;" and the purser's' lerk"began to weep- adly. "'Lord, Treaole, don't die!"said Tomn, or the devil -Will mix up the last of the Treacles with the last of his brimstone. You would be useful then, mylad, especially in the: GHasgow ships."'  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7606-00000012"/> -26 .      THE WIZARD- OF THE WAVE. This was too much for Treacle, the eyes of whom flashed as much as they could.'. He said: "I wish I dared to fight; but I cannoet."  "' Truck, I shall leave you and go ahead) Mr. Belford, if I see game, you may rely ,on me."  And Tim left in utter disgust. "Tom," said' Belford,'?"have you kept a good look-out ", :Yes, your honor, and not overhauled one petticoat. You must have made a mistake in your reckoning.", Just then- Tim was heard, crying out, "' Lord! O Lord! mercy!" and he rushed up to the two sailors, throwing himself on his knees, "A tiger! sir I sir! a wild cat! a lion! Ah, -such eyes!" -"Why the devil, if you be such a sportsman, did yoti not shoot?" *said Truck. . But the long, shrill scream of aiwoman was heard amid the foliage, and Belford at once recognized the Ivoice as Isabinda's; for it was-she he'had come to seek, and at once he rushed from the party. Truck would have followed him, but Treacle seized hold of him, and said:      * :"Would you violate your promises to my sainted mother?" "'Blast your sainted mother!" said Truck; '" let me go, for I want to see the game you are afraid to look at." And Tim. Treacle was left alone. "Ah, Lord! Lord!" said Treacle, "-I shall die i" and. he threw him- self on the ground at the report of a, shot in the brushwood, while Truck, rushing in with the old negro Domingo we have before spoken of, had nearly,stumbled over him. Truck gave the prostrate, purser's .clerk a hearty kick, and starting' him up, said:   . "You beggarly swab you, take care of this big. Ingee-rubber'bottle of the best Japan ;," and at. the same time -he threw the negro. on the ground.            . i,'   . i  Tim Treacle had been half the time in amazement, and finally awoke with- the, ,ory.:              ! "Dear; :\ dear! it is the devil!" ,- - "Yes,.Seior!" said Domingo, " the devil is always white. That is the devil!"         , v. Nothing more conclusively demonstrates the low condition of the :Guajirosqor peasants, and' the 'negroes of Cuba. at that day, than, the ,fact, t4ha all the, crowd started away in the most ludicrous terror, fully satisfied that, all Englishmen were devils. This wasan idea carefully   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           27 inculcated by the government, and a very sufficient reason why in Cuba the English have never"been able, to make any permanent encroach- ment. We stood amazed.; and after'a lapse of ti'me, Captain Falkner, whom we have seen before at' the Inn of Saint Jago, entered, bearing Isa- binda in his arms, followed by Belford and Truck, who dragged Do- mingo by the collar. -"Just in time, by Heaven!'" said Falkner. "Captain," said Belford, " had you not been just there, she must have died. Gad! how beautiful!" "Belford, take her yourself. If I look longer on her, I may become your rvaal" ' "Captain," said Belford, respectfully, " did duty .bring you to this mountain "               , "Bah! Belford, ask no questions. Look after the girl. There is about all this a secret of blood, which-- ask no questions. You will know more when the bowl is slung and the toast "Home " goes around the board. Till then, the Wizard of the Wave must use his power on land, and by incantations raise desolating storms and wonder-working transmutations. Belford! Belford! even now you seem to think me some Friar Tuck or Merlin, able by a magic word to change all the fate of creation." The Spanish lady appeared to recover her consciousness, and Falkner and Domingo, in obedience to one of those instincts unaccounted for, left Belford and herself alone. The young lieutenant, who possessed all the peculiarities of his 'native land, hung over the beautiful, dark-eyed Spanish maid; and while he nursed and attended her, uttered something not unlike this; "Strange are his words: ha! she revives. Gad! how beautiful she, is! Heavens! I saw her at the governor's!" The Spanish'girl reAived, and said: "The panther! where, where is it? Its eyes were'fixed on me! I had just left my father." "Who is your father?" Domingo stepped up, and said: "'Hler mother's husband!" Truck thought it the height of impudence for a black man to speak'; he had been on the Jamaica station; and said: "Father and mother! you know nothing of either, for you were made of charcoai and a grease-spot." "Lady, let me conduct you home.'" The lady bowed assent, and had already-half arisen, when old Domingo' started up, and said.  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7606-00000013"/> 28       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. - No, I will not! 'Let me take my mistress home; for my master would be offended if an Englishman spoke to her. "True! true!" said Isabinda; " yet he will not be angry if I thank you for having saved my life. Adios, sir, and believe no stories against your nation can ever preven't my gratefulness, to one to whom I owe so much."' She hurried away with old Domingo, and Tom Truck looked after her with amazement. 4' Phew!" said he, "is not that fine? a bumboat sailing consort with a spanking frigate! Bah! your honor, you had,grappled and hitched her, yet suffered her to sheer off. Lord! Lord I old Rodney did not do so." What Tom Tr-uck said was utterly unnoticed, for Belford continued to stand alone, and'moodily talked as if to himself. He said.: ' There never was, anything so beautiful. You fare right, Tom Truck; I was wrong to lose the cnase. Come on, and at least I will find her port."                       : "Ah!" said Truck, " that is the best thing that can be done now: but a stern chase is a long chase. May I go down in a waterlogged ship, if it be not a shame for a- sailor to .lose sight of such a pretty prize! I never do such things; for though they say I do not like women, I grapple everything that wears a petticoat-white, black, or brown!" The lieutenant had already gone, and the coxwain followed him. C H A P'T E R 'I I i. THE GROTTO. WE had lost sight of the purser's clerk just before the lieutenant met Isabinda, and meet him again, as old Truck would say, in strange lati- tudes. After be had been, so to say, driven away, he had rushed blindly into the undergrowth ; and after the lapse of a brief time, found himself at the entrance dof one of those caverns which are so common in all those countries, the formation of which is w hat geologists call secon- dary. When Treacle came to the entrance of the cave, with the peculiarity of all small minds, he could but exclaim :- ": hat an odd place, to be sure?-a kind of underground dining- room. Who would have fancied I could get into such a very agreeable   THE W-IZARD  OF THE WAVE.          29 place? It is quite a discovery, ]. declare. Lord! it is pleasant, for from the outside I can see the town. Somebody comes. Who can it be? May be the wild savage that lives here.   Here they come I Whither shall I go?" The sound of footsteps contihued to :increase, and Tim Treacle fell on his knees just in time to avoid being seen by the stronger, with black cloak and ,hat, we have already known at the inn of Donna Ca-. pella. The stranger passed hastily in, and said, as if he talked to, himself; "' Even now she is here on the hill, and in this cage I must hide her, which will enable me to carry her on board." He drew from a recess a small table and sat-down; continuing his meditations, and said: '; Little do the English think, from this high nook I have watched their every movement, since first they anchored on these shores." The stranger opened a chest, and, took from it a parchment, which he placed on the ground. "Aha!" said; he," naught like eating and drinking cures sorrow. All ready!  By this time, she must have crossed the bridge, and Domingo dare not resist. If he does, he dies. Now Donna Isabinda, the most faithful of your slaves:awaits you." The stranger left the cavern. Tim looked on, and though what his contrymen call timersome, he was no coward;, he said, as he arose: "Well, more wonders! I wonder'if it be bona-fide wine. I am so hungry-and so very dry"- -(between his, expressionof hunger and thirst, satisfying at least the last pf these two necessities of nature.) C"Hark," said he; "I hear footsteps I may be it was- ppison-no, it was not, no! no! it tastes too-good. , But may be no one knows what any- body meets in these strang 4ands. Lord! I am so thirsty! Lord! I am, off! I 1am off!" '  He rushed to;the door; but, at the. very outlet, pet. Truck, who ad- vanced, shouting, in his merry, cheerful, voice: Yo ho! your -honor! here is,-a port." " Oh, dear!" said Treacle, who did not recognize .the new comer; "here he is!" and the poor devil at once rushed into an excavation as he did so, muttering to himself: "Lord!, here is every-accommodation, evenigraves ready made." Scarcely had he uttered these words, when Belford, accompqnied .by, Truck, entered the cavern and looked around them. The scene ws -a strange one ;,for nop architect had morte delic4tely balanced a, .dome, than the great master-builder, -tur had .tis; icl. cate. .   &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7606-00000014"/> 30        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. "Lord bless-your honor! it's beautiful, and Nature has fixed up a supper fit for the Lord High-Admiral," said Truck, as, he pointed to the bottles which stood on the table. Tim Treacle showed his head, and in a fearful voice, said': l Master coxswain, are you sure it is wine?" Old Truck was a sailor who -had sailed around the world, and nothing on earth could amaze him; and the sound of Treacle's voice recalled too vivid recollections of the purser's store-room, ever to be forgotten. So he at once exclaimed : " Hallo, you mole! what is the next rarity? Come, Mr. mole, show your bearings."            .  "Oh, Mr. Truck, are you sure i't is wine? Lord r I thought it was poison." a    ' o  Truck, paid no attention to Treacle, but looked carefully around him.; at last he saw the roll which the unknown- stranger had opened, and taking it up, unfolded it. "What have we here?" said he. "Ah! he called it 'the code,' I think. But, Mr. Truck, do you think that is wine 2"                    . "' By the Lord! it is a code of signals, and the flags are not Brit- ish," said Belford, who had taken the roll from Truck. Treacle was in the greatest terror, but seeing how calm the lieu- tepant and coxswain were, sought to repress his terror, and said to Belford: "Please, your honor, are there no gold mines in these hills?" "Ah!" said Belford, yet lost in thought; "I the returns of the mines have recently been. much diminished. Robbery has been suspected, and Captain Falkner has doubtless been sent hither to detect it. By this chart, it will be easy to communicate with-the unknown schooner." "Ah!" said Tim; " the government will be liberal in rewarding the discovery of these proofs, and I will doubtless touch something very handsome." Truck seemed indignant at the idea of a purser's clerk claiming reward or prize-money, and shrieked out:  "You- impudent, young grampus -- He would have continued his harangue to an indefinite length, but that the shrill cry of a woman was heard, apparently immediately above them. 9"Come, Truck," said the lieutenant, " follow me." "'Aye, aye, your honor! Bless my eyes! warn't that a squall? Follow you, weazel, and be d--'- to you!"   THE WIZARP OF THE- WAVER           31 "Will I? I'll get under hatches till the squall is over, for the gov- ernment will never sufficiently reward the risk we run;" and. Treacle retired into the hole, whence he emerged when the sailors entered. Scarcely had he done'so, than the unknown -stranger entered the cave, wearing a black mask over his face, and bearing Isabinda in his arms. He placed her on a chair, and after a brief pause, for-Isabinda was no fragilely-formed being, said: "I heard men's voices on the other side of the rock: they however saw me not. She revives--oh! if her swoon would'last until the coast is clear. Hark! let me listen." 'j, lie stood in breathless attention, and after a moment, said: "Well; all is right."       Isabinda had revived, and looking around her, said wildly: "Where am I? What strange face is this? Do I dream? Whom do I see? Oh, you will not harm me? Let me leave this place!" The poor girl started to go; but the stranger interposed himself be.' tween her and'the outlet, and said: "You are right. I will not harm   you; but you must nbt as yet. leave this place." "' Heaven!" said the poor girl, " what'mean you?" "That henceforth and forever the'chain that unites us is indissoluble. The most tender love, riches and power shall be yours; but all friends are lost to you; for mine and only mine you must be from this hour." Isabinda uttered a cry of terror, and called wildly on her father and on Domingo, making the cavern ring again. ' "Be silent," said. the stranger, I if you would live;". and he advanced towards her.'          ' "Domingo! father! save me!" "Be silent, or you die." He seized,her by the arm, when the lieutenant and coxswain rushed  in; the latter with a single blow felling the stranger to the groundi while Belford took charge of Isabinda, and  Truck, in his peculiar style, said':  "Well, Rmyfine fellow, that is what I call a dead luff in the wind's eye. - Come, my  picaroon, off with'yohr velvet face!" The old coxswain pulled off the mask, and when he had done so- started back in surprise. "Whew! your honor," said he to the liieu- tenant, here is a sad affair, indeed I Why, it is Captain Palkner'!' "Captain Falkner!" safl pelford. "Just as sure as my name is Tom Truck. I saw him with this very dress on at Donna Capella's." ,  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7606-00000015"/> 32, ;      THE. WIZARD OF, THE WAVE. . Is he, dead?" said Isabindai ,  B0eford liooked aJ mzed, but slAouted , out ,to Trick,," Quick, bring water 1, Atry to revive him 1 Take this lady to some place of safety, and hurry back. Come, lady, fate has made me your champion, and -I will not fail you."    .    '  He took -the lady, wlq4. was almost overcome,r from the. cavern, and left Truck alone, as he thought.  The old sailqr soliloquized : "What on earth: can I do?  Wine will not put life into a dead, man. A precious stormy watch, I've got this spell!, The lieutenant will be tried and shot for mnurdering his captain,and Tom Tru'ck hupg as a necessary or accessory. Who the devil ever' thought the captain such a creature for the petticoats?  Truck made the, sage relmarkl however, that ,",sporrow is .dry," filled up a bumper" and swallowed it.. .He ewa V about to repeat the operation, ' when he was suddenly interrupted, Weevil, wQ;' it will be remem- bered, we have previously seen with the offiers of-tho "' Wizard of the Wave" at Donna Capella's,-rushed, in, followed by a portion of thecrew of the unknown schooner.                  . . ': Seize him!" said Weevil. ., Tr uck was no easy man t. be seized, even..by six antagonists; but, after a evere .contest, was overpawered. He bWgan , to rembnstrate, but, W  1evil uat once exclaimed: . "S top that,talkin g tackle "  The words were no sooner spoken, than a gag wa,ps:placed in the cox- swaips outh. '  ,    . t. "Come," said Weevil, " throw the murderer of our'captain over. the  cliff. Up with him; not a word. You;need not shake,yourhead, my fine fellow, for one or two minutes will settle all yqourtrox bles." Threeq of the pirqtes bore .rowk :aSa,.jand thres:t .:followed, with the. bodyof the mysteious8 'Sttajger. .  Truck continuedito .resis'-.ias wweAi ia he could, :and when- the:coastV was clear,- Tim Treacle peeped out.             ,'  I ut ne myqarters, sa d e, " r -I .:ihave to follow Truck over the cliff. I iah i waSsaboard. It is gtting dark. LordA! if they see me! Y very, lair of my .he ad. btandsqut likae acapstan-ar W!!,alls, sttil -Lowd,, Lod, f d! . . h'r  And Tim ,   psapp^red,.'m thq cavcri, which in ashorrtime :bad .. been enacted the material of at least.,thr4.m.}p dre ma. .    THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.            8 CHAPT E R     IV. A BALL, A. BsALL on ship-board! Few but those who :live in great sea-ports, 'frequently visited by national vessels, are aware what this means. If Lihey picture to themuselv'es a brilliant hall, hung with curtains, festooned vyi 1,h drapery, andfilled with perfume, they are mistaken. and will read %t description of a more picturesque and far different scene, The flush deck is cleared; all is removed except the battery, and  instead of golden torches, battle-lanterns,-the usual lustres of the deadly cockpict-are hung. Stars of cutlasses and bayonets reflect the. light: and every tag that floats on the sea, hangs in folds above. It iS n ot unlikely that a summer moon, surrounded by myriads of stars, lends its mellowing tints to the scene, and that perfumes of the flowers of some gentle land are wafted to the vesselzs side. Suchwas the scene or the desk of the Wizard of the Wave:,not long after the uiost perilous adventures we have described on the heights of Santiago. The deck was'filled with the dark-eyed dames of the island, nlingled with whom were Spanish' gentlemen, and here and there the. ,blue and gold of the British navy.' The band was on the quarter-deck, and the ship's crew, in white jackets and trousers, were. in view, The marines; in their scarlet jackets, were drawn up in, orders and the dance was:merrily proceeding. Gay couples twined; the luxurious waltz, and here and there, behind the cover of some sail, a couple might. be in- dulging in the luxury of a quiet flirtation, The dance at length cebased, and Falkner, with several of his officers, detached themiselves from the crowd; and though Manly the other lieutenant, and Hearton the master, werevisible, in their rick uniforms,   Belford was not seen.                     I  "Well, gentlemen," said the captain, c the ship. looks wh; and the fair ones of Santiago could not resist the. temptation of a ball. I hope, gentlemer, you will not permit any of them to doubt our mortality." The officers laughed, and were about :dispersing againj when Manly said: "The-governor has not yet- come." "No; tI wait; but to receive him,: and. then: I. must rgo ashore. Where, though, is Belford Who has see him.-? .'   . ;  , -  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7606-00000016"/> 34        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. "None have seen himi'," said Manly. "I trust nothing has befallen him." "Was rot my coxswain with him?" said the captain. ' Yes. sirl, and Tim. the purser'is clerk. They went on a murderous expedition ;1tahIiuit tihe birds. Tim .says he is a great sportsman. When I l tsh:.; i s etyes-- - "Clme. ' -,!tilclcull; to the ladies!-each to his part, away! It may be B,1lfortdl 'las ;l-e some discovery, and I nmust be on the watch, lest, ill thie trnl,luil of ttle nigit, they elude me. If the governor were on boardl, 1I culd eltdlic them." SClleely 1;1ld -lie luttered these words, than the voice of the watch W S'!,;rii tl I or'  i'l" out,:' l 3(Boat tdl I o si l!"I It iu;;l,.-l ald fronll it came Donna CapClla. and others, among wlomtu w;)s ; pr-o: io ;( most conspicuous dress. TIe new collers did liot, lows(.eve, :; ;ItU i'lltelrteree with the f'e3tivity, and a new da ce was at once Ioru!ll l. aoist all the officers. taking their places with the Spa:ish bel!s, .    ' Befor.. ltowkv(i., the music had beun, the watch again reported, 1"Bloat alloii'd!:o i ' Uid the reiply to the challenge was: ;' qEl gobelf,t' -,'"    * Scarcliy iltil t lic words been helrd. than the drums beat to quarters, the trlnumpets soun 'ded. and the deep- mouthed gnlns paid their hotmlage. The persoi nve . l;,veO already meiitioued as having come on board with Donna OLapellt..t atvancedt and hurried after Captain Falkner: as if to receive tite gove rlor.          !' Dion J,8-s de ate ioltoblI cam-; on board. with his, daughter and Dianez, and a(dvacliaed at. once, t o the captain, tthe hand of whom he shook. Falkner bowed liiidlly. and ilmuledia-tely afterwards the person in the gorgeous dress took the governor's arm, and with Isabilda was lost amrid the crowd.  Manly, -who was a bl(ff old lie,tenant. afraid of nothing, advanced to his captain nixd' said, ir)ly tl. t respectfully: Captain, .Who is tiaat. "getleman with the governor 2?" "We shall know when he takes off his m ask," was the reply, "Yes, sir; bult lhe has been Cxamining you most pointedly. ' Ah! Manly, he is welcolne. Sund Heartoln to me." At this lmome:t:)t Isabiludlt.. ,he o5rvenor, and the richly-dressed person we lhave sp)oken of, enteired the cabin. Falkner, without pausing, said: Ai Mr Manly, I am going ashore 'Not a word of my absence! When Belford eovmes, give hirx this..   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           35 And he placed a bundle of papers in the lieutenant's hand,  "Is, my gig ready?" Manly looked over the side, and seeing all prepared, said: ': All ready, sir." Falkner at once advanced towards the gangway ;- but before he had commenceed to ascend, Tim Treacle rushed on board{, and exclaimed, as he saw Falkner: "Alghost! a Fetch! the captain I the devil!" The poor lad, in his terror, rushed down the gangway.' This appari- tion, however, did not surprise Falkner, who quietly shook hands with Manly, and went over the gangway. Manly stood amazed, and said ": All this is'very strange. I do not understand; but on with the dance."    , The dance was resumed. and all went merry as a marriage bell, After a few noments, tihe governor and Isabindta, accompanied by the stranger, came up from' the cabin, the stangcer yet wearing his cloak over the lower part of his body, but uncovering his head and shoulder. 'A boat was heard alongside, and several officers advanced to the gang- way to welcome the new comer. Bclford sprang upon deck, and at onice received the papers wlhich the captain had left for hinm. He read them carefully: and approaclhed the governor, by the side of whom Isa- binda stood.' He too seemed to partake of the general surprise, and when he saw her, salid:         .  "Is it possible! the daughter of the governor!"Hie advanced, to- wards her, and was about to speak, when the Unknown advanced and removed his mask.       . When he saw his face, the young!lieutenant, though used to many a scene of dauger,-started back in terror, and exclaimed: ' Good- God! he alive I ' It is either an illusion, or he is the devil." The young nan seemed completel y overcomlle, and st-aggered-until almost fainting, into the mas'eels arms. He exclairled; "( It is, the captain, yet only a few momenuts ago I, saw hiln dead. I shall go mad 1;' The scene we have' described put an end to the dance. All rushed from the ship, and in a moment or two the ship:s crew alone remained. All this may have seemed most mysterious to the lookers on, but to us, who have followed fhe intricacies of the web of, the story, we liave 'been weaving, the matter will not seemt obscure,;, fr such' things lave more that one, happened since the d&amp;aysiof Perkia Warbeck-Nature  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7606-00000017"/> 86        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. sometimes loving to disport herself by strange similitudes, as she fre quently does by. contrasts. A deadly game was being played by the stranger, who, either by some deep-felt sympathy or antipathy, was arrayed with the captain of the Wizard of the Wave, Time will, however, eiplain all the mystery. Nothing will more truly describe the characters of Truck and Lieu- tenant Belford, who often will figure in this narrative, than the follow ing story, which had passed between the two during one of their long midnight watches. After a chat for some minutes- "I say, lieutenant," said Truck, "What on earth is the reason that women havew uch a passion for sailors? Bless your soul, sirOthe landsmen have no chance when the blue jackets are abOut!" ' "So it seems," said Belford, 'and sailors have strange fates with women. I could tell you a story to prove it.";, "Bide a bit, sir, till I strike the bell."- The old coxswain returned, and said: '"Heave ahead, lieutenant, and spin your yarn. I will listen as if the admiral had the trumpet. THE LIEUTENANT'S STORY. HENRY STYEkWELL was as brave a seaman as ever handled a marlin- spike, or mounted a maintopmast; ever kind and open-hearted, no man Was more respected throughout his .Majesty's fleet.  His messmates would have laid down their lives for him; his superior officers esteemed him as an equal, and the female sex, having once seen him, were ready to give their hearts into his custody. But, although Harry loved a petticoat as dearly as he did his ship, he had not yet seen a female with whom, he could fancy entering upon the sometimes rough voyage of matrimony. Harry Steerwell, at the time my story commences, was chief mate on board a vessel bound for the Baltic seas, and which, stopping at Carlscroom, he. became acquainted with an old blind man, of some property, and who had an only daughter, more lovely than imagination ean form an idea of. -Harry thought her one of the- trimmest-built craft he had ever clapped his two eyes upon, and, for the first time, he flt a sensation creeping around his heart that he could not but inter- pret into love. If Harry could judge by the smile that ever played around the- coral plis of Paulinia and the modest 'blushes which ever suffused her theeks'   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.            37 in- his presence, he might guess that she viewed him with anything but indifference; and, at last, emboldened by his hopes, and the friendship her father ever evinced towards him, he resolved at once to confess to her the real state of his mind, and to sue for a return of that passion he so sincerely entertained towards her. Harry was not long in putting 'this determination into effect-the maiden was delighted by hearing an acknowledgment of a riciprocal attachment-and the lovers had nothing left to do, but to throw themselves at the feet of Paulinia's father; and solicit his consent- to their nuptials, which they felt convinced he would not withhold from them. In this hope they were not disap- pointed ; the old man heard them with pleasure, and readily gave his sanction to their union. In the course of a few 'weeks after this, Harry became the husband of Paulinia, and their, bliss was unbounded. But soon the ardor of their joy was damped? when the time drew near for' the vessel to which our hero belonged to return to England. The bride of Harry was anxious to accompany him, for her mind could not endure, with any degree of patience, the thought of a separation from him whom her very soul adored; but, much as he adored his wife, he could not think of exposing her to the perils of the ocean, especially as she was now enciente; he therefore endeavored to calm her feelings, telling her he would return to England with the vessel, obtain his discharge, come back to her, and never be parted from her more. His persuasions and the counsel of her father, at length tranquillized her spirits, and she yielded her consent to the proposals of her husband. And now the day of separation arrived; it was one of the most affec- tionate that can be conceived. For a few minutes they hung around each other's neck, unable to utter a syllable, such was the violence of their grief; .but at last Paulinia, recovering herself, impressed a last fond ardent kiss upon the lips of Harry, and impressively addressing him, said: "My dear husband, you are going into foriegn climes, where tempt- ation may cross your path. I do not suspect your faith, Harry, but still it is a womanish weakness that I cannot entirely divest myself of. Swear then, dear Harry, and I will do the same, that in whatever coun- try you may be, or Whatever time or distance, you will never forget your poor Paulinia, but bring her back this parting kiss as pure as ,yo . now receive it. ' Impressed with the seriousness of her manner, Harry knelt, and rais- ing his hands and eyes towards Heaven, took the oath she required of . him.  Paulinia seemed satisfied; her countenance was once more 8  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7606-00000018"/> 88        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. enlightened by the. smile of composure, and, straining her husband for the last time passionately to her bosom, she uttered one more " fare- well," and rushed back to the home of her father, while Harry was soon afterwards sailing over the Baltic billows. In the course of a few months Paulinia brought into the world a 'beauteous boy, the very resemblance of his father, and, as she gazed upon the smiling innocent with fond transport, she pictured to herself the delight which her dear Harry would experience when he beheld the cherub countenance of his boy. 0Qh, how anxiously did she look forward to the time when she expected her husband to return! and even weeks before the time appointed. had expired, she rambled to the beach, and strained her lovely eyes by gazing upon the ocean, in the hopes of seeing the vessel in which she expected her husband to re- turn. But, alas! the time arrived; it passed; months followed, and still Harry returned not; what could be the reason? He was nof drowned?" Oh, no; she could not, dared not encourage such a dread- ful idea. "Ah, nol"? she would exclaim, in the words of the poet: "' I know there's a Providence sits up aloft, To keep watch for the life of poor Jack.' " But then, as she divested herself of these melancholy, ideas, others equally fearful beset her brain. Had Harry been false to her? Had he forgotten his vows, and plighted his vows to another? These ideas, however, she could not long entertain, and she reproached herself for thus suspecting the--fidelity of her beloved husband. But when years flew away, and she obtained no intelligence of him, then indeed did Paulinia begin to think that he had deserted her and her child. 'ive years were now elapsed since they had separated, and notwith- standing Pauliuia and her father had made every possible' inquiry, they were unable to obtain any tidings of Harry. Paulinuia, unable any longer-to endure this state of suspense and 'uncertainty, determined to depart to seek, by every means in her power, to ascertain the reason of Harry's prolonged absence. This resolution she put into execution as soon as a vessel bound for England stopped at Carlscroomn; and, after a pleasant voyage, the Bride of the Baltic and her little boy arrived safe at Queenborough In the meantime, t e sufferings of poor Harry had been of the most vexatious nature. When the vessel in which he had sailed had reached England, and he and the rest of the crew were about to go ashore, they were all pressed (it being in the time,of war), and our hero, with a few   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.            89 of his messmates, was sent on board the Insolent, one of the most noble vessels in his Majesty's n'avy. The reader may well conceive what his feelings were on this occa sion; a thousand titmes lie cursed his-faite, and then, wheli lie thought of his poor Paulinia, the misery she would endure- ;t his mysterious and unaccountable albsenco, aud the probability thleirc was tha t tlthey nmig}ht never meet again, his mind was distracted. Tile, however, somewhat appeased his grief, and the novelty of the sceines lie minigled in drew his attention partially from this affliction.  "In toil and battle five long years He did a seaman's duty," and was esteemed one of the bravest sailors in thie ship. At length the ship returned to Elgland, and what was our heroI delighlt to learn that, on her next voyage, she would drop the Baltic Ocean? He thercfore :resolved to purchase his discharge, and return to his dear Paulinia, never mnore to be separated from ler in this world. It was a merry night at the "Fire-ship," kept by old Ben Blaze, ,For merly a   man o'-war's-man, when the Insolent wals abofut to set sail froom Queenborough for the BaLltic billows; at least it was so for Harry Steerwell, for he anticipated the joy of his restora, tion to the arms of Paulinia--and he anticipated- the pleasure he should experience at beholding, perhaps, a son to do honor to his name and increase his hap- piness., i' Splice my maintop-sail,' he exclaimed, " if I wouldn't make the boy a rear-:ad;mliral!" ' After taking a parting glass of grog with -his old friendl, Ben Blaze, Itarry and his messnmates prepared to go on board, f)r already had the 1ignal-gun been fired for the;m to hasten to the vessel. The seamenii with leavy- hearts,,'kissed the tear-bedewed cheeks of their pretty sweetthearts. and vowed to cherish themi in their meinories with una- bated affection -during their perilous voyage, and all had departed on board save .arry, at the same time the Tally-Ho coach was about to start for London.     ,. At the motment EIarry was in the act of stepping into the boat to go to the vessel, his eyes rested on the neat little figure of a boy who was about to hasten to the coach. There was soinething in the face of this child, who seemed to be about four years of' age, that parlticulal-ly iute- rested Harry; the f6atures seemed flamiliar to him ; and as he gazed upon them, his heart swelled, and he could not help stopping and im-- printing a kiss upon his rosy cheeks. The boy appeared very well pleased with this attention, and' smiling archly, he said:  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7606-00000019"/> 40       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. ' Oh, how I do love a sailor."  "Do you, my little king.?" exclaimed the delighted Harry; l" bless his little heart!-now I shouldn't wonder but I may have a son aboutc his age at home. ' Lor! Lor'!' what a happy fellow I should be, to be sure, if that was the case! If I wouldn't make him an- admiral. shiver my timbers. So you love a sailor, do you, my little man'? And wwho told you to love him?" "Why," answered the child, " mamma always told me to love one as dearly as my life, for she said my father was a sailor, and you know' I must love my father." "What a sweet little prattler," said Harry; "oh, what a pleasure it must be to have such a child as this! Let me see if I haven't got a present for you, my little-man. Here, here is a silver whistle for you, and when you look upon it, do not forget the poor tar' who gave it you.  "Oh, no, that I won't," cried the boy, gazing with delight upon the gift. '"Bless you, bless you, my little man!' ejaculated Harry, onco more kissing the child, and not being able to stay any longer, he stepped into the boat that rowed to the vessel, while the child skipped lightly into the coach to his mother, which started almost immediately for London. What transport would have filled the bosom of polwr -Tarry, had hei known"that; this " sweet little prattler," as he termed jhim, was his own son. But such was nevertheless the case; and; 'in the very coach that started to London, at the moment the boat was rowed from shore, con- taining our hero wasiseated his beauteous wife, Paulinia; Alas I how would his mind have been disturbed, had he known the danger to which she was at that moment exposed! By a most 'remarkable circumstance, it so happened that, on ths very day on which the Insolent set sail' for the Baltic seas, Paulinia, with her child, had arrived at the Fire-ship 'in, to awaitt a coach to convey them td London. Thither had the distracted Paulinia deter- mined to go in search of that husband whom she now apprlellteved had deserted her,'and, as a last' resource, had resolved to apply to the Admiralty Office, to ascertain, if possible, whether iHarry was still in existence. It appeared that at the time Mrs. Steerwell arrived at the inn, an old gentleman, in a gray wig, with rather an unprepossessing counte- nance, and clad in a suit of rusty black, was standing in the yard, and saw her-enter. This individual was one Lawyer Twister, who being, as   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.          41 be deserved, unsucessful in his own profession (for he was an infamous old pettifogger), had become the villanodis tool of a certain Lord Rest-' less, a libertine and debauchee. This- guilty nobleman employed Twis- ter to entrap the unwary country maiden to satiate his sinful desires, and in fact he could not have selected a more able myrmidon. The moment Twister cast his eyes upon Paulinia, he was struck with her extraordinary beauty, and he beheld in her a woman that his lord- ship would be enraptured to get within his power. He resolved to gain possession of her, and with that design he insinuated himself into her company, and finding that she was a foreigner, he, by the most artful means, gathered from her an account of the errand she was going upon. This was a fortunate circumstance for the villain Twister, and he deter- mined to take advantage of it. He therefore informed her that he was  going to London, and, as it was extremey dangerous for a young female of her character to travel unprotected, if it was agreeable, he would ac- company her in the same coach. He also informed her that he had a friend in town, who was connected with the Admiralty Office, and who would be enabled to give her every information respecting the mysteri- ous absence of her husband. Paulinia, who had no suspicion of the real character of'Twister, and believing him to be a gentleman and a lnan of honor, thanked him politely for his offers, and with becoming modesty accepted them. By a strange fatality she stepped into the Tally Ho, to go to London, at the very moment the husband she was so anxious to see was rowed off to that vessel which was to bear him to the home she had left. It happened on board the same ship with Harry was one Lieutenant Oarr, whose tyrannical manners had rendered him hateful to' all the crew, and there was not a man among them but would willingly have consigned him to the sharks. Just after the vessel had quitted Queen- borough, Lieutenant Carr dropped a pocket-book upon deck, which con- tained documents to him of the greatest consequence. One of'the sailors who picked it up, knowing whose it was, was incited from mo- tives of revenge to destroy it., Harry, who was upon the deck at the time, xremonstrated strongly against this proceeding, but the fellow, deaf to his expostulations, threw the pocket-book overboard. Harry, with the most generous heroism, immediately plunged (ver the side of the vessel, and qaught it ere it sunk, and was hauled once more upon deck, just as the captain came up, and demanded the cause of the ioise.. Harry briefly informed him, 'and placed the' pocket-book in his hands. At that instant Lieutenant' Carr returned to the 'deck, in a state of distraction at his loss, which he asserted would ruin him. Observing.  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7606-00000020"/> 42        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. a smile upon Harry's countenance, le immediately conjectured that he was exulting in his misfortune, and in a lmoment accused hinm of having stolen it. The honest tar spurned the accusation with bec,minig o indig- nation, whichl so enraged the lieutenant, that he would lhave struck him ha'd not the captain interposed. "Hold, sir, I coimmand' you, on pain of' my displeasure," he said: "'would' you strike one of the best of fellows that ever trod a plank? You dropped your pocket-book upon deck."  ' "All!" eagerly ejaculated the lieutenant, " has it been found?" "One of the crew," continued the captain, " threw thet pocket-book overboard." ' Then I am ruined for ever," said the lieutenant, in despair. "Hear nme out, sir," resulmed the captain; : your po(ket-bok would have been lost had it not been for the heroic conduct of a llother of the crew, who, at the imminent hazard of Ilis own life, plunged in after it, and snatched it from the 'waves. It is here, sir'." "Heaven be praised," ejaculated the lieutenant, "I ami saved from worse than death. But oh, captain, tell. me to whoml I am indebted? Who is this generous .man?" "Behold, him before you," answered the captain, pointirng to Harry; :tlJe man whom you so hastily injured by doubting his honesty." Sliame filled the bosom of the lieutenant, and prevented hitn from speaking for a few minutes but gratitude at len)gthl found vent in the' following words to Harry: 'Generous, noble fellow; oh, tell me, 'how can I ever. repay you for the injury I have offered to you. Here are my hands lt , ne con, taitns a purse, the other the offer of my dearest fr'ieldship-talre them -they are both yours, and granlt me your pardonl for my irash asser- tions."  "Oh, your honor,'l said Harry, snatcling the emlpty iand of the officer, and gently spurning the e one hich contained the gold,;: this kindness more than repays me for the service I have been so fortunate as to render. Freely do I accept this, but offer me not the other, for I should feel myself to be unworthy the name of a British seaman if I accepted it." Harry fervently pressed the hand of the lieutenant to his heart. and every one on deck could not but express their unqualified hadmiration of the noble conduct he had evinced. From that day the lieutenant became an altered man; he had been taught a salutary lesson ; he profited by it,and soon became as much esteemed as he had-been before hated and despised.   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           43  Just after this occurrence, a letter was put into Harry's hand, which, on opening it, lie found to be from his old friend, Ben Blaze. Judge his feelings, on reading the contents, to learn that, his beloved Pauiinia had been at the iinn at the saime tinime that he wasand that she had, with her son, departed for London at the very time when he entered the boat to go to the vessel.. Harry was distracted at this letter: but the more so, when: he learned that she had been inveigled into the society of Lawyer Twister. Ben regretted that he had not discovered these facts until the coach had started, but he assured Harry that he would imltle- diately go to London, and on finding out his wife, inform her of every- thingl and frustrate the wicked designs of the lawyer. The anguish of Harry at the letter was unspeakable; but, after he had in some measure composed his feelings, lie uttered a prayer to Heaven for the safety of his wife and child, and was compelled'to en- deavor to co ntent himself by hoping for happier timnes ; and he was also not without a hope that Paulinia, having been informed by Ben of these facts, would lose no time in returning to Carlscroom, and might even arrive there almost as soon as himself. Nothing particular happened, the vessel soon stopped at Carlscroom, and with a light and anxious heart, Harry tripped on shore. He had  now brought his mind to calmn and hope; he could not but think he should find Paulina and his child here, and he formed thelmost deliaght- ful anticipations of the happiness that awaited him. Hie soon arrived at the cottage of his father-in-law; it was nearly six years since he had seen it, but it looked the same abode of peace as when h'e had left it. Harry s heart throbbed violently, and hope, fear, and anxiety pre- dominated by turns in his bosom. At length he determined to knock at the door; but, just as he was about to do so, he beheld two ruffianly- looking fellows, enveloped in cloaks and armed, approaching that way. From their manner, he suspected they were after no good, and, conceal- ing hilnself behind a tree that grew by the side of the cottage, he resolved to watch their actions. It was not long'ere he discovered from the conversation of the villains that they had formed a plan to rob the old man,/and he blessed that Providence which had guided his footsteps to the place at so critical a moment. The fellows having drawn their swords, burst into the cottage door, and entered, and Harry cautiously followed on his hands and. knees. On. entering the cottage, he beheld his father-in-law seated in his old arm-chair by the side of the table. He did not hear the villains ap- proach him, and Harry succeeded in gaining, the back of the chair behnd which he concealed himself.  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7606-00000021"/> "       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. The ruffians, with many oaths and threats, demanding the old man's money, rushed upon him with their weapons, which they were about to plunge into his body, when H:arry, to their fear and confusion, jumped up from behind the chair, with a pistol in each hand. Completely dismayed, they took to immediate flight, and our hero revealed himself to his father-in-law. - The old man was greatly aston- ished at the return of Harry, after so long an absence; but to his eager inquiries as to where his wife was, Walklman replied, in reproachful tones, that she had gone to England in search of that husband who had deserted her. ' Deserted her!" repeated Rcarry, most vehemently, and beating his brow; " oh how you wrong me I What! desert my pretty, my beloved bride; accursed be thq thought!" Hmarry then explained to the old man the cause of his mysterious absence--the intelligence he had received from Ben Blaze, and added, that having -purchased his discharge, he would return immediately to England in the first ship, and never rest until he had found out poor Pauiniia and his child, and restored them safe to Walkman, or perish iIn the attempt. Our hero was as good as his word, and in less than another week was on his voyage back to England., We must now return to Paulinia; whom we left Win the Tally Ho coach, going to London, in the company bf the villain Twister. Unsus- pecting as Paulinia was, the lawyer found it no difficult matter to effect the object he wished. By a specious tale he inveigled her to the house of Lord Restless, whom he made acquainted with every particular of her circumstances. - His lordship was delighted with the charms of Paulinia; and was determined that she should be his, at all hazards. What was'Paulinia's surprise and disgust, then, to find that she was made a prisoner in the mansion of that nobleman; and when her ears we're insulted by a declaration of his odious passion, she spurned him, as his baseness merited. But Lord Restless was not to be so easily abashed; and for months he kept her confined in his house, and daily insulted her by his base proposals and importunities. He endeavored to convince her that her husband was no more; offered to become a protector to her boy, and sought to prevail upon her, by a false mar- riage, to yield to his desires. Finding that the virtue of Paulinia was proof against alllhis arts, he became, impatient, and told her he would only allow her one day more to consider, and if she then remained obstinate, he would use force to make her comply. The anguish of Paulinia may be easily conceived; her only consolation   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           46 was in the society of a female domestic, one Sally Manders, who had formerly lived at the Fire-ship inn, and knew Harry well. She assured Paulinia of the existence of her husband, and informed her of every particular of his having gone to Calscroom in search of her, on the same day that she departed to London, and added, that she felt con- vinced Harry would lose :no time in returninog to England, in the hope of regaining her. At the same time, she said. she would -be most zeal- ous in watching vessels returning; and if she could meet with Harry, she. would invent some stratagem by which she might easily be released from the power of the hated Lord Restless, .and restored to her long- lost husband. This assurance somewhat consoled Paulinia; but, when the time drew on apace, and Sally could obtain no information of Harry, despair began to take entire possession of her mind. It so occurred, on the very day our hero returned to London, that Sally had been on her usual errand, when, on returning back over London bridge, she met the very object of her search. This'unexpected meeting was a source of great delight to both; but when Harry heard of the sufferings of his wife, and the danger she was at that time placed u* in, his bosom swelled with honest indignation, and he vowed that he would instantly repair to Lord Restless, pull his house about his ears, and hang him on the first lamp-post. Sally,-however, implored him to calm, his feelings, and patiently to act the part she had directed. She then informed him that she had formed a plot; to introduce him to the house as her cousin and the messmate of Harry Steerwell, whom he was to represent as dead; and having a, number of companions near the spot, while he was keeping his lordship engaged with this tale, she would admit them into the' house, when they might secure the villain, and liberate Paulinia and her child from his power. Harry highly approved of this plot, and he and the delighted Sally instantly departed to put it into execution. Harry was quickly ushered into the house, and, in the coarse of a short time, his boy was brought to him by Sally. With what rapture did the honest tar hug his' little son to his heart, and press upon his rosy cheeks the kisses of parental love. The little Henry recogpized him as the sailor who had formerly presented him with the silver whis. tle at Queenborough,: and showed his father how carefully he had pre- served it. Harry almost smothered him with kisses ; and, while he was thus engagedi Lord Restless entered the apartment.    ! As may well be imagined, he was greatly surprised at the appearance of a seaman in his houae, and the particular notice he was taking of the  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7606-00000022"/> "       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. child of Paulinia, and asked him who he was, and what purpose had brought him there. Harry could scarcely repress his passion, when he beheld before him the villain who hbad- so deeply injured him, and persecuted his lovely wife. His bosom swelled with indignation; a flush passed over his countenance as he bit his lips, but recollecting himself; he assumed a modest demleanour, and apologizing to his lordship, informed him that he was Sally's cousin, just returned from sea in the Insolent. "Ah!". exclaimed Lord Restless, " the Insolent-did you know there one Harry Steerwell?" "Know him, your honor," answered the hero, ' to be sure I did ; poor fellow! he:s gone aloft." "How! wl!at mean you?" hastily inquired the libertine. "Why, your honor, he's dead," replied Harry. "Dead!" repeated Lord Restless, catching eagerly at the welcome words ; "are you certain of that?" "Yes. your honor," returned Harry; it was my painful duty to see him, consigned to his last home." "Ah! by Heaven, that is a fortunate circumstance!" ejaculated Lord Restless, aside then turning to Harry, and addressing him, he added,. 4 4 Did you know the late Henry Steerwell's wife?" "Ay, to be sure I did, your honor," answered our hero, "and a pretty little craft she was-a finer never ploughed the ocean of life." "Circumltstances,' said, the libertine, "have placed her beneath my roof, and-but, no matter; all I wish you to do, is to see her, and make her acquainlted with her husband's death, as I wish to provide for her and her child and as a-rewardfor this service, take this purse." Harry took the purse with a very ill grace, but, to effect his purpose, it was necessary he should act up to the character he had assumed; Lord Restless shortly afterwards took his leave, and scarcely had he quitted the room, when a piercing shriek rent the air, and ihe bride of the Baltic was pressed to the bosom of her husband. We must draw a veil over this affectionate scene, for'we are certain 'that no eloquence could do justice to it; the little Henry alternately sharing the joyful caresses of his father-.with his mother. Their emotion  having somewhat subsided, a mutual explanation followed, and Paulinia eagerly inquired if he had brought back to her the , parting kiss as puSre as when she gave it?"  With a tender embrace Harry replied in the affirmative, and might have added, in the words of the --ballad;  r E *  { . ..   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.            47 "In toil .and battle five long years I did a seaman's duty; When pleasure called, I closed my ears And turned my eyes from bezuty. The wanton's tale of boasted bliss I heard,' but ne'er believed it; So back I've brought that Parting Kiss, As pure as I received it." Thus happily explained, they were continuing to converse of past joys, and for-mintg the most blissful anticipations of the. future when Lord Restless entered, and addressing. himself to Paulinia., pretended to endeavor to console Ler for the loss of her husband arid while lie was doing so, Sally took the opportumity of whispering in Harry's ear that his messlimates were then in the house, and oauly waited a signal frolm him to rusil in and seize his lordship. Harry winked at her significantly, and at that moment Lord Restless requested him to give anl account of the mannler in which Harry Steer- well had lmet his death. "Whlly, you see, yer honor," said' Harry, " my poor messmate' was a 'most venturesoime chap. So, one' day, lhe would go ashore-aiilong the savages.- Tie chief was a tall man, summaut like you, may be yer honeor and he was determined to take poor a;lrry's life; so lie raized his club, when at that Ilmomlent Harry perceived some of his imesnlates at hanld." All this time Harry was beckoning on his comipanions, who entered the room unperceived by Lord Restless, and stood behind, ready to pounce upon him, "Well,".continued Harry, "as I was saying, your honor Harry ad- vanced to the chief as I mlight do to you, and placing a pistol to his head, as I might do to you, he said: "' You, d---d scoundrel! ) Surprised at the emphasis with which Harry uttered these words, and his actually placing a pistol to his head, he was about to ask for an explanation, when he perceived himself surrounded by about twenty well armed sailors The whole was now explained, for Harry rushed to the arms of his wife. Sharme and confusion overwhelmed his lordship; he threw hiniself at the feet of Harry and his wife, imploring their forgiveness. Harry, with his usual generosity, acceded to his request; nor was Lord Rest- less worse titan his word; he gave them wealth; and never a happier couple returned to the home from which- they had been so cruelly torn, than did honest Harry S3teerwell and his beauteous Paulinia, the Bride of the Baltic. $  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7606-00000023"/> 48       TAHE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. "Well, Lieutenant," said Truck, "that aren't so bad; but blast my eyes, if I would have let that devil of a Lord Restless off so cheaply I He deserved to fall into the hands of a gang of cut-throats and robbers, and be compelled to live tin momentary expectation of death for a month or so-the libidinous old scoundrel!" How long Truck and the Lieutenant might have diverted themselves with narrations like the foregoing none can say, but the sailor's watch was over, and they returned to duty.   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           49 BOOK II. CHAP TER      I THE PIRATE SHP. THE scene changes, and the reader icy tranported to the deck of the unknown schooner, which lay beyond the long, low point of land forming the harbor of Santiago. The crew had not the ttim, regular air of dis- cipline which characterized that of the "Wizard of the Wave," but yet: had the air of strict obedience and of as much good order as could exist among any men who werenot restrained by the sanction of positive law. They were clean, neat, and- went through their duty with an alacrity which would have done credit to men in regular service. At the time our scene opens, they were busied, under Weevil's direction, in lowering into the hold a number of strongly-clasped boxes, appa- rently of great weight--while TomTruck, heavily ironed, sat looking on, with the philosophy which marks the old sailor in all conditions, when he sees himself powerless. Trucl'seemed as quiet and con- tented' as if he sat- on the deck of his own darling Wizard, instead of the Melchor, a piratical schooner; but one who could look into. his mind, would'see that was anything but the case; for though he said nothing, as he would probably have expressed it himself, he was doing an immensity of thinking. An old quadroon slave, the name of whom was Nanny, sat sewing on a low stool near the hatchway of the vessel, devoted evidently to her . work alone. The name of the vessel to which not only Tom Truck but our readers have been transported, was the Melchor, or the Evil One; and, unless old stories be all false, richly merited the appellation. The man-6f-war's' man wears no weapons about his person,. In regu-e lar vessels, pistols and cutlasses rest quietly in their racks, never to be taken down except to be used, and the dagger is a thing unknown. He who wore such a weapon would be esteemed a coward indeed; but such was :not he casee/with :the crew of the Melchor, each, of whiom ap-  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7606-00000024"/> 50        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. peared to look on his comrade as his bitterest foe. A pistol and dag- ger were in every belt, as if the enemy were momentarily expected. "Yo 1 heave! ho!" sang the sailors on the deck. "Yo! ho!" was echoed by those below, as box after box descended.  i "Clear away, ho!" said Weevil; :' be lively I I hate dead game, as the snake said to the buffalo, when he had made a carcase of him. Be e lively!" "Aye, aye!" replied a voice from below. Again and again the clues ran up and down; and box after box having descended, Truck took his pipe from his mouth, and said, after sanging a bar or two of a nautical refrain:  , You seem, lMaster Weevil, to have some heavy ballast there." "Ahal you have logged my name.!  Why, yes, Master Coxwain, you see we have to clap a ,pif, or two of ballast on light-heeled craft, just to steady them. You see, we had to do as much for you. They then mind their helm better." As the rascal spoke, he pointed significantly to Truck's irons. "Ah!" said Truck, " you are cute; and I take it your mother was a woman. I will, however, say this, that your vessel is a credit to her build, and her keepers are no fresh water-jacks, but regular salt dogs. Bless my eyes t she is clean as a woman at a fair." The old quadroon had been for some time watching the boxes descend, and finally spoke: "Weevil," said she, "tell me if more gold is coming on boaad?2" "Hush, I tell you "': said Weevil. . Nanny spoke in a half whisper, and said: "I will not I . Enough has come on board to buy a kingdom-and it is his-all his." "Hold your tongue, I tell you, for there will be enough for all." "I tell you, Weevil, it shall be his. only his. The oath binds me, but it shall be his, for he has been kind to old Nanny. We wauld give all, all to know; yet I dare not tell him." 4 -Ah!"' said Truck,!"Mr.: Belford was not far wrong, and they have been Sobbing the mines. Master Weevil, now be eivil, and .just cut a brother tar leose from these lashings, far they are not so comfortable as a silk stocking, for a gentleman at Bmy time of life. D---n it, man, I fever could bear the bitees, &amp; v ' ' Tibre she lay, all that dy, - In the Bay BIciscay-O.'" For a sailor will sing, even during an Amputation. : Skipiamte," :id We   . "dol yotrememibr swat was said tPyO "   THE WIZARD OF- THE WAVE.          51 a What!" said Truck, stopping his song. "Do I remember? How the devil am I to forget? No, I won't; I do not like the service." "When once you put foot on this deck, you must either join us or feed the fishes." "What?'" said Truck, ': do you think I am such a fool as to walk overboard? My eyes! I believe you are a set of d- d pirates I' The old quadroon, who had for sometime uttered not a word, screamed in agony, and like a Pythonel full of inspiration? exclaimed  "Pirates! whoever talked of the black flag  - I have seen him nail it to his. mast-head, and whoever. tore it- down?  Walk the plank! I lave seen it done by the timid and the brave oft and oft-by the blue- ,yed American-by the dark-haired Spaniard-by the Portuguese--he fho tried to burn his ship. Do you remember, Weevil, who fired that istol and shot him, as he knelt and prayed to Almighty God?" Weevil alternately flushed and became pale. He exclaimed, at last: "Stop that old devil mother's chronicle of blood I! I wonder she has lever been shipped'as an old croaker for the shark's maw below them;" "No, no, no!" said the old woman; " he hopes, before the old nurse ies, that she will break her oath, and tell him who he is---well, they aade me guilty--ha, hal the gold, the gold, all his/!"-and -the old roman continued to mutteron, moodily, to herself Weevil said to the watch, "Keep a, sharp look out,' lads, for I expect isitors aboard. Harkee, reship that fellow's ground tackle, for time 3 up, and I would not like the skipper to find him here." They released Truck, who continued to smoke calmly as usual, and id : -"What are you going to do with me, you    lssear-looking black. iards i" "A   very few minutes," said Weevil, -"wh decide that.' Will you )in us?               .  "What, fight with such a Peter-boat robbing crew I What, disgrace e  flag, under 'which I was born, and "under which I was edieated! urn mine-robber i -No, I'll be d---d if I' d o"  "  Mine-robber P' exclaimed Weevil, lashed into fury; " rig the plank- ere, for over he shall go; ballasted as he is.".  :He   was placed over the aide of the vessel, and Truck looked on, aoking as quietly as possible. Weevil said' to 1him, a Onee more I ask you if you will join me. I tuld not care any more-for drowning a  .at, of: land-lubbers, than I ud aparbcel of blind- kittenS. -Whent-ibogh) a manit:er!served his  ae at sea and learnelyato ;lotw-it8. igas,.itfis t&amp;ham/thatold::odeu./  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7606-00000025"/> 52       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. should be his executioner. It is disgracing the high road he lives by, and tacking a disgrace to the end of one's best friend. Truck said to him, in a somewhat milder tone: "You have but a queer-looking title-page in that black mug of yours, but there is some logic inside of you. Your speech shows extraordinary edication! I wish I had you bound for my private library!" "Will you join '? "Never!" said Truck, "but I will give you a bit of advice. Just practdie what you preach, and -take the drowning kittens for your test. Remember you have no right to clap the mop on the poor, struggling creatures; and when a gentleman like me comes on board your bloody craft, leave him a few moments to himself, to have a signal for his soul's salvation, and remember his poor old,mother -at home, without his being obliged to blubber like a baby before blackguards." - Weevil and the crew retired, and Truck leaned against. the mast, while the old quadroon, .ho had shifted her seat, was immediately be- hind him. His face he had leaned to the mast, as if to hide his feel- ings. "Do not turn," said the old woman; " do not notice me, but listen: appear to consent to join them." "If I do, I am d--d," said the bluff coxswain. "Fool.! you will then deserve death. There may be Beans-I may enable you to escape." ": You are a kind old mother, but---" "' Do not' call me mother.; -your speaking of your mother at home made me pity you. I saw one mother when her children were torn from her, and since then I have ever trembled at the word." Truck paused in thought, and said, inwardly: "Shall I do this. No, 'tis but a plunge, a few moments before my'time, in what I always thought would be my grave. Messmates, farewell!--I- mother-hang it, let me be a mat 1I Hark ye, you shark's fry, I'm ready for my moon- light walkl; but take my word for it, the ghost of Tom Truck will stick to this craft like a barnacle, till every lubber of her crew is hung dang- ling in the wind, like shirts on a washing day."  Weevil became angry, and shouted,'"Away to your fate!" The crew presented .their pistols; but Truck, nothing intimidated, folded his arms and confronted them. .  .    7    .  ' Fire awayi you aevil'sa imp8s!" said he ; b u but you dare, not--you would then have a few :honest men around; you, before you could cut the6 ble :of your -rascally kedge. Pirates.![ robbers! Old Nick will some day seize'you all, up to his red-hot gratings.  .-   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.          53 The pirates drew their knives and collected around him, while Truck mounted the board . Truck conitinued, "Could I just take you one by one----" He threw his pipe overboard, and said: '"There, I have taken my last whiff. I'm ready! Mother, I come! Farewell, blue sky, friends, and life 1",  He walked up the board, and when he had reached the gunwale, kicked the board from beneath him, exclaiming: "Take that, you lubbers, for I can die like a man 1" The stout old sailor sprang overboard;. and when heWhad done so, a cry arose from below, coming from many voices: "Yo ho, there, schooner!"' The watch answered, "Gig alongside ." " Gig ho!" said Weevil. "Is it the skipper?"  ": A voice was heard to cry, "A prisoner." '"-Weevil said, moodily, "' More prisoners Hthis is strange!"' The boat's crew, dressed neatly in white, ascended the companion- way, passing up before them our old friend Belford, with his arms pin- ioned and eyes blindfolded. He 'as under the especial charge of a ferocious-looking fellow, named Wilkins, who will turn out to be the quarter-master of the Melchor. Wilkins said to Weevil, "The captain gave this gentleman a free ,passage, and told me to tie and blindfold him. What the devil, though, were, you throwing overboard? You came near swamping us, and breaking Kit Cathead's neck; besides, you nearly knocked the fellow's life out of him. Hand up that lubber that fell overboard, some of you." The old coxswain was handed up, and Weevil looked at him and said, "So the poor devil is not to be drowned then?' "Why, for the matter of that," said the quarter-master, " two or three of us wish he were, for his irons played the devil with us. Look to your prisoner, for the captain -will soon be here, and with him such a beauty!--his prize. She is the governor's daughter-she is the cap- tain's prize." Belford, bursting with' rage, exclaimed, "Liar!" Wilkins said, coolly, "Talk on, sir, for it is all you will ever be able to do. Gid ho!" The captain's reply, "Ay, ay!" was heard. Wilkins said to some of the crew, as he hurried to the side, "-Look to the officer."  Weevil removed the bandage from Belford's eyes, who looked anx- iously around, and^ idc: 4           /  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7606-00000026"/> 54        THE WIZA-RD OF THE WAVE. "Where am I?-on board of the schooner?" "You are right." "Do you command her? Why did Capt. Falkner send me on board of her?"       -  L Captain Falkner .'" "Ay, Capt. Falkner! I thought him almost killed, and the: nest moment find him on board his own ship, dressed in the most fantastic manner. At a signal, he calls his gig to the ship's side, and sends me on service ashore. Before I have recovered from .my wonder, I find myself seized and blindfolded, andy to increase my surprise, am brought hither a prisoner. Weevil looked strangely at him, and said: You must be dreaming. *"Do you know the nature of the vessel you are on." "I can guess, from that poor fellow's state, that you are pirates." "We are," said Weevil-" throw, water on that poor devil; he is stunned." Belford hastened to Truck, and lifting him up, said: "Not dead- only stunned."          -  Truck recovered, and said : "My .head! my head! Well, drowning makes a fellow's head swim. Lord  Lord! yet here!-your honor, too I Have the blood-suckers got you?" Belford said, in a musing manner, "' There can be no mistake. I struck him, down, but I saw him on her deck-the same face, the same gold. chain. Alas, I am afraid the man I honored so is a villain!" Truck said: "A villain? Hfe is the devil! So he sent you on board this murder-tub?" Weevil bade him be silent--"Peace, fool!" "I will not; what do I care for you--a d--d salt-water burglar 1!: '! Schooner ahoy!" was heard from -below. "' Boat ho P" answered Weevil. , The captain!" was, the rejoinder. "The skipper!" said old Tom. 'Now I'll calk his sides and tar hls bottom for him, the changing dolphin.  He an ifficer of the navy!" / "Be silent, Tom," said Belford; " let us act like men, and not like women." i"Man the gangway!" said Weevil. "' ow. yu will see the com- mander of this vessel, gentlemen." Truck was removed some distance, but Belford stood watching all that passed, with the greatest eagerness.. Falkner's voice was heard, saying, "Keep the:gig alongside!"        , .                It)   THE WIZARD -OF THE WAVE;.          5 "e Ay, ay, your honor." ".By heavens!" said Belford, "'tis himself. Does he disgrace our uniform on a pirate's deck?" "So, Mr. Belford," said Falkner, ",you are welcome, to my. trim schooner. Weevil is all ready." "Yes, sir, 'all is ready; we wait but for your company." "Ah i" said Falkner, carelessly, " the governor?" "Ay, ay, sir-while the British are kicking up their heels in a dance." "We," said the, captain, "will ship our cable and stand out. Sir, you and that man will accompany me ashore." "Who? I?" said Truck; "I would as soon be blown from the mouth of a gun. 'Aren't you ashamed of yourself, Capt. Falkner? I speak with all respect, and be d--d to you!-but don't you blush as red as a soldier's coat, when you think what a d--d scoundrel your honor is 2  You gold-grubbing -pirate i My eyes! who would- have thought it"                 . "That rough sailor," said Belford, " tells you the'truth, Capt. Falk- ner, in his own rough way. From this moment I would, think myself justified in not obeying you. I will never disgrace the honor of my country's gag-and were we but on equal ground, the man that dis- graces its uniform, should not escape me." "That is right, your honor," said Truck; " let us get up a little hon- orable mutiny." Passively and ceoldly Falkner commanded silence, and said: "'I can command obedience, sir. Hand them    both into the boat. Harkee, Weevil, how many chests of gold are in the boat?" "Some fifty, sir." "Good! There are more to come. See that the state-room is ready. I will follow you, Mr. Belford." ': Resistance, sir, is useless, and I yield. to force." "Yield to what you please, sir, but be quick.1' Truck said, "My irons 4are---" ( Knock them off; we will take care of him. Weevil, be watchful;     , I must take advantage of their strange mistake." "Ay, ay, sir," replied the subordinate.: "Now, sir," said Tiuck, "I am to go over the side to -please a skip. per that disgraces his flag. :Well, I have been over for one rascal, and I see no reason why I should not for another. .But take this for a keep-sake, you lubberly atock-fsh!" The' old coxswain-dashed into the gang of pirates, and began to deal  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7606-00000027"/> 56        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. such hearty blows right and left, that moire'than one of the rascals measured their length on'the floor. He sprang over the side-and, as he did so, half a dozen pistols were leveled at him, so that his days would hve been ended, had not old Nanny interposed. The captain was now ready, and the boat was swiftly rowed ashore.". AP t  ' I C E A?      1 E 1R Irv THE PALACE. OUR scene now changes to the palace of the Governor of Santiago- to a magnificent sala; with pavement of tesselated marble, and .deep casements opening into a garden prodigally filled with- the glorious. vegetation of the tropics. Feraguez, the Spanish officer whom we have known before at the fonda or inn of Donna Capella, entered, and with him two slaves, bear- ing a couch, which they placed near the window and immediately'left. Feraguez looked for a moment around him, and seeming to scan the ornaments of the apartment, said "Carajo i it is a pity to leave so good a house! yet with the gold a far better one can be bought. 'Ha, excellenza! it is done--all done!"v "Is all on board safely?" "All the gold and papers. The jewels I have kept." "Are you sure they have no suspicion in the mines?" "None-none." "I have removed the troops. Bid my daughter hasten hither.' We have no time to lose." ("Not a moment.  Where shall I find her , Perhaps if I look through the rooms, I may find some stray article which has been for- gotten. Aha! that is not a bad idea for a teniente!"  Immediately after the departure of Feraguez, Isabinda and Dianez entered from the other side of the room. The fair Isabinda said: " How beautiful the ball was I Why did my father hurry, me so quickly away? I am sure, Dianez, the English seem, as poor old Do- mingo says, dear, delightful devils.' I wish my father had waited for the return of that handsome Belford, who has twice preserved my life." aH He doubtless, Senora, had his reasons. Do you forget, lady, that we leave the island to-night 1"   THE WIZARD 'OF THE WAVE.      '    67 : That cannot be; I will refuse to go until I'am able to thank my brave deliverer." "He doubtless, lady, had his reasons. Do not forget, Donna Isa- binda, that to-night we leave the island.". "That is impossible! He cannot mean to do so. Why should he? No, no, I will not! HEe cannot wish me to do so without one word of thanks to my brave deliverer. He cannot mean to tear me from my happy home, where I have passed my whole childhood so delightfully. I will mutiny." ' And will you," said Dianez, i mutiny on account of the house or of the defender? Forgive me, lady, if I think those devils of whom Domingo speaks, have cast some strangei spell upon'you-and if, instead of being the saviour, he- too may be the robber." 4"Robber, indeed!" said Isabinda; "I will quarrel with you, if you dare to say so; for his manly form, his expressive face, his frank demeanor, all declare him a man of honor. On my word, Dianez, I shall be tempted to turn champion for my champion, and call you out'   I wonder how I should behave in a duel!" "I am glad, donna," said Dianez, -" that you have such spirit; yet there may be time to save your father he seems to 'suffer in his mind. Know you who it was he introduced to you on'board the Wizard 6f the Wave?"  "; He told me, not long since, it was the commander of the schooner which lay beyond the point." '"Hear me Donna IsDabinda," said Dianez. "My aunt's house is on the road towards the mines. ' Once I had a lover, an Englishman, whom I shall never see again,; and I used to sit at the window and think of him? While there, I have seen Feraguez, your father's teniente, and a stranger dressed in black, bring boxes down from the mines. Once I saw your father with them, and-- " "Good heavens7!" said Isabinda--c in the night? If all had been right, would not, the governor's orders have made darkness unnecessary? Great God!" said the young girl, " what a terrible suspicion flashes across me!" '; Hither comes the governor," said Dianez;"I have told you this, because it was my duty to do so. I wtill lea ve you now, and hope your influence may save your father's name and hognor." 1t What shall I do?" said Isabinda. '"Don Jose entered the room just as Dianez left it, and said: "Are you ready, my child? for we must go at once."  "Whither, dear father?"  ,.                    -     .  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7606-00000028"/> ^-68      THE WIZARD OFTHE WA'VE. ",Hence,"' said the governor, "from this lazaretto of the mind. Whither we go, it matters not; but we seek America, where kings are powerless and titles worthless-to the United States." "You go, then, in the vessel which is in the bay?" "'Yes!" said the governor.       i ".Why go then by night? why leave in darkness and secresy? why does not that vessel communicate with the town?" "Ask me no questions." "Forgive me, dear father," said Isabinda; but I must. Iknow that I am young, yet feel enough that I can prize my parent's honor. Have you no public duties to discharge? What will the people of Santiago say, when they shall learn their governor has fled?" "What means this? Questioned by my child! Obey me, and be mute"P" "Father, I cannot! I would see you, surrounded by the officers of state, return your power to those from whom it came. You had do- minion over costly mines." "Mines!-of course I had," said the governor. Who dare asperse -my deeds?"                j "All will, when you have fled. Thy dare to t ell that gold has been brought at night from those same mines "  : "How so, girl?" "So it is. How else should I know?" said Isabinda. !-ave they?" said the governor. "Eternal fiends! Why am I thus pursued? Prom  earliest youth ruin and disappointment ever have dogged my steps. Thwarted in wealth, love, ambition, everything I When triumph seemed within my grasp, the brim has been torn away I Now, now too, my own child's hand- -" "Must I listen?" "Daughter, your pride of innocence would not permit you to think your -father guilty of a crime which would cause him to fly from his country?"2 "No, no, no lI ' said Isabinda."   , "I fled from England," said the governor, " though born upon the soil." Were I now to place my foot upon her shores, the scaffold and the executioner would do their duty on your outlawed -father." . "}How can that be? Father, oh father!" "Dear daughter, only ray of light to cheer my path, listen to me: I had a brother, brave and true.. All loved him. He had a nobi -name- the Earl of Monteville, He was older than I, receiving all ry father's yast estates, while I was penniless and poor. I. hated him. I loved   THE WIZARD OF THE, WAVE.          59 one beautiful as the morn, but she loved and married him. Ask me not why. I hated him." "Father, father!" said Isabinda. "Ay, he pitied,- as all did, the younger brother. He was promoted to a lofty place and went abroad. Three years rolled on, and they told he had two sons. They said the climate was unhealthy, and sent for me to hear his dying words. I came to Jamaica. With me was a hellish fiend, who called himself my friend." "-You found" your brother alive?" said Isabinda. "Yes, he laved. He scarce had time to bid me be a father to his sons and protector of his wife ere he died. Then did this devil friend begin his work. He whispered to me that those children stood alone between myself and one of England's proudest Earld'oms--  Wretch! Wretch!---   Guided by his advice, I sailed for England.  A pirate overtook our' unarmed ship. They said that it was strange we were not robbed; they did not do so, but took the twin boys from their fond mother's breast, and while she madly/raved, bore them away for ever!" "Ah!" said Isabinda, " this is fearful!" "She never saw them again, but died broken-hearted, and I became Earl of Monteville. On my rich estates, my friend, the pirate ;child- robber, soon joined me. He said the children were in safety, but never more could trouble me. I loved and married, and now offended Heaven -lets loose, in its justice, all its bolts upon me. You were born. At first I could not- love you, for my injured nephews ever stood before me. My friend seemed more a father to you than I can be. Even then the devil plotted your mother's ruin. Start not, Isabinda, for he triumphed and she fell before his arts. Look not as if you doubted, for she con- fessed it; and when I stabbed and trampled on the fiend, she clasped his body and cursed me." "Great God!" "All this is true: That hour is written on 'my heart and brain in fire. They tried me for his murder. Would you believe me, girl,; they tried and condemned me for killing the seducer of my wife? I fled the hated land.  The retribution of offended Heaven stripped me of all the wealth and honors I had gained by crime. They cast me forth a beg- gar. I could have borne all but the thought of her. I had deserved hate, but not from her. I had through him wronged- the orphans. But I loved her, the mother of -my child; yet on- her knees she cursed me as the murderer of her paramour. - Isabinda, even now, when thememory of those days come back, my brain -grows dizzy and my pulse grows quick. I feel-I know that I'am mad,"   &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7606-00000029"/> 60        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.         { The poor girl sank on her knees and wept. After a moment, she recovered her voice and said: "Yet, dear father, forgive me if I weep; for she was my mother."' "She is dead," said Don Jose. Bless thee, my child! My heart is now relieved. Prepare for night. Since that sad day I spoke of, I have served Spain faithfully; yet, though I shed my blood for it, ingratitude has been my reward.. I have planned a bold stroke to decide my fate. Just at the moment, that mysterious bark came like a wizard hither. That vessel is my fate. Now, when ingratitude has maddened me, and sweet revenge marked out a, golden path to satisfy the .wishes of my heart, black:,infamy would spoil me of my preyand thrust. me forth again a beggar." "Dear father," said Isabinda, " you must not go." "It is too late, my child," for no resource is left. No idle tears now, for in a few short hours we shall be beyond all danger. If I suc- ceed, princely will be my rank: I am a villain if I fail." "Give back the gold',' said Isabinda. "It is on board." "' Bring it back at once," said Isabiada. "He will not." "Then you are in his power?" .  , I am, alas 1" said the governor. c The guilty always are the slaves of those they trust. You will curse me when scorn points at you as the felons daughter. You who alone have loved this blighted and unhappy form, will curse me in your agony of shame." The governor seemed to suffer deeply, and buried his face in his hands ; but Isabinda knelt at his feet. "Give not way to sorrow,'. said she. c Think, father, think. Should you fly, eternal infamy sinks on you. It cannot be worse if you remain. May not the generous Englishman aid you to recover from the stranger the treasure you have committed, to his care? May not the stranger .deceive you in the end 2?" While this conversation was going on, the Unknown had entered un- -seen, and passionless as a statue, apparently listened to the conversation. His dark eye, his strongly-marked face, assumed a most sat'anic expres- sion. He said: "The end is come." Isabinda and her father started at the sound of his voice. The stranger continued.:   Let me not disturb you.. Another hour will leave the Wizard of the Wave within the bar. Sit- down, my lord, and let me meet. the   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           61 arguments of this most lovely pleader. Let me. tell her the English ship is here alone to seize her father. "Can it be so?" said Don Jose, while Isabinda stood in amazement. "Let me tell you this," said the stranger: c"The Spanish court have heard strange reports about the mines. Spain has no navy, but the closest alliance exists between her and England. This British ship waits but to make the proof more sure, and then your .father is a prisoner.. You know if he can find the proof----" "Then flight alone can save me," said the governor. "Who then, sir, are you?" said the young girl, " who urged him on to this dark step?" The stranger said, "Lady, I am his friend, and on me alone hence- forth you must depend for safety." ' My safety? what can effect that?" "The stain, lady," said the stranger, " on your father's name. Why, Don Jose de Sandobal, do you tremble now? Is not all right? Your daughter will accompany you, and--" At that moment Weevil came in; evidently in a great state of excite- ment. "How now?" said the stranger. "All is lost P! said Weevil; ';' the devil fights against us." "Fool P!' "He has been on board of our ship in your likeness. He has de- ceived us, and rescued two prisoners." "What! in my likeness!" -: He seemed yourself," said Weevil. He wore your face, and, by the Lord, your own gold chain!" ,    ' "Demons of Hell!" said the stranger. "It was ,3alkner, the English Captain."  "But the likeness?" said Weevil. "'Is wonderful and beyond my understanding. It has deceived his own officers. Under its protection, I have boarded his vessel, and now it seems he is aware of it, and has used it against me. Action alone can save all from ruin." "Troops are in the hall," said Weevil. "Troops!" said Don Jose. "Father," said Isabinaa, "you yet have power." "Mark me, Don Jose," said the Unknown, " disguise now is useless. Remain, if you please, but Isabinda shall be my companion." The stranger arose from his seat, and seizing Isabinda, handed her to Weevil.  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7606-00000030"/> 62        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. it Say, lady, one word, said the Unknown,-" and your father dies. I will not .be disappointed. Come, come, for every moment is of value." ".Dare you threaten me e" said Don Jose. d I dare anything! Hark! I hear footsteps! Listen to me, lady! you ,are at liberty, but stir not, speak not, or your father dies." The Unknown deliberately placed his pistol against Don Jose's breast, standing, however, s0 that none who entered could see it- although Isabinda saw it, Weevil at the same time exhibiting his weap- ons. The subordinate immediately afterwards posted himself on' the other 'side of Don Jose.  At that moment Feraguez made his appearance, and as the door opened, it became apparent that a party of soldiers stood in the passage- way with the officers, at the very door of the sala. When Feraguez saw the Unknown, he bowed, and said: "Welcome, Captain I Carrajo! Mr. Weevil, is all ready for the voyage? The soldiers, though, have come back. The officer says that all is well where they were sent. What shall we do with them?" Isabinda, in the interim, having remained in extreme terror, said: "Tell the soldiers." "The Unknown showed his pistol, and said: "Lady----" -  That single jesture was enough, and she sank on her knees, saying: is Good saints, assist us!"  "Had npt your excellency best order them to the mines?" said the Unknown. "It will not do, Seiior Feraguez, for them to cross our path. Eh?-you know  that troops are heeded there. Tell them to search carefully. You know they say the mines are robbed."  "' Ah, yes," said Don Jose; " to the mines!" and Feraguez went at once to give the order. The stranger withdrew his pistol, and the governor, half overpowered, exelailmed: "Forgive me, oh God! for I have acted thus only to save my daugh- ter's life." The troops left, and this terrible scene thus ended.   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           63 O CHA?T E R' III. DRUNKEN SAILORS. WE have been before at Donna Cappella's, and met there, among others, two worthies who will figure in this chapter. They need, there- fore, no introduction; for the persons we speak of, were Cuthody the doctor, and Tim Treacle the purser's clerk. Of course Donna Capella, in the same dress we have previously spoken of, was present. "Go back, gentlemen," said Donna Capella; "' you have had enough." Let us premise the doctor and the purser's clerk were both drunk, "I tell you," said the doctor, ' I have not had enough." c( No no," said the purser's clerk, i nothing like it." - Yes, Seflores, you have c om e with me like English devils-- gentlemen, I mean-you were very kind." "Yes, we were; doctor, my dear friend, one word with you," said Tim.  "After the unequivocal manner in which she said she loved me--"   (Tim was very drunk) ( True," said the doctor, "her disease was exhibited with such highly inflammatory symptoms, that i comes me, as a surgeon and a gentle man--" ( Yes, that is it," said Tim-" as a gentleman, l- " "You a gentleman!:' said the doctor. "It is I that am the gentle- man. You, you registrar of yellow dips, a gentleman I1" "I no gentleman!" said the purser. "' By the immortal honor of Plymouth! I a register of candles! What a re you  A blister on the service?-a bolus to the crew!-a poultice-prentice! You a gen- tleman! By the hereditary honors of my grandmother, who was lady's to an alderman, H-I ll- -- " "( Stop this noise," said Donna Vapella. a' This is always -the way With your countrymen, who drink together until they fightY .  "Donna Capella, beautiful as you are, do not be the least nervous. I will not annihilate the slop-seller. I will not pi out u'the purser's dip in your divine presence, but if he gets sick, I will give him such :adose of salts and senna as never was exhibited before. Your black eyes, I vow, are brighter than all the bottles in an apothecary's wiridow; your glance is more searching, than mercury} and your love, like ie oa'u- anha, goes up and down My visaera f -    &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7606-00000031"/> ",       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. "C Do you hear him, my lovely Spaniard?" said Tim. "In a week he would purge you to death. Try your own Treacle. ODid he not jump on your toes when he danced with youg? He must, however, answer to me for it." "No, Sefior, let him answer to me. Seflor Doctor, go on board, and to-morrow I will talk to you about physic." "Do you, then, reject me for that low, hustering animal-that sub- ject?" "Animal! subject I Pshaw I he has gone into the body-snatching line." "You shall meet me, though, with either pistols or lancets-swords, I mean"-said the doctor.  "Tim, I wish we had friends here to arrange our little blood-thirsty warfare." Just then the master came in, and said, "Ha, donna, safely stowed! I could not turn in until I knew that you were safe. WSell, when shall it be? I have spoken to the captain, and, if you like, he will marry us to-morrow. Shall he splice us before the week is out?" "Marry to-morrow!" said Tim. "Splice before the week is out!" said Cuthody. "Caleb," said Tim, "we are cheated." Tim walked ferociously up and down the room, and said, "I will be revenged-I will kill somebody." Caleb went up to Manly, and said: "Sir, H--" Tim echoed his words, and said: "Sir!" "Phew IP said the master, " what is in the wind?" "Tim," said the doctor, " you fight Manly, and I will call out Donna Capella."  "Aha!" said Manly, " if you want to fight, here are the documents. (He pulled out a pair of horse pistols.) I wave rank, and'-we can settle the matter at once. I wave rank." " It is not a good remedy for my complaint," said the doctor. "What say you, Tim?'" said Manly. "Dear Tim," said the doctor, "I will be your second." "No, I thank you, doctor."  , But, donna, have- you not a word to say to Tom Truckl, who has come ashore to lay up in ordinary and marry you?" 2" "'What, Truck!"Isaid Ilpnna Capella; " the Lord love his pig-tail!' Manly turned to the dotpor and clerk, and said: "All hands aboard! I fancy there is work ahead."   THE 'WIZARD OF THE WAVE.          65 Tim said, "Do you mean fighting? Doctor, I am very sick; donna, can you give me a bed?" Ah yes, donna, do so," said the doctor; "I will stay to attend to him." "Attend to him! Attend to the ship--I will see you aboard. Adieu, donna-one kiss. We have to board some planet-may be the moon! Lord! there is no knowing what we may be at, when the devil takes the lead!" Tim was, at once taken very sick. The doctor was assiduously attentive; but Manly hurried them both away, in spite of Tim's in-, creased illness and the doctor's immense assiduity. CaHAP TE R     IV. THE CRISIS.                 ] OURi scene now opens in a Posada or inn, which, however, is not lDonna Capella's.. It was a low, wooden ,house, with stables on one side and on' the other an open field. The lodging rooms were above, and were approached by a stairway from the room  to which we have introduced our reader.                      , Falkner, Belford, and ILalph Raddle, a mariner of the Wizard of the Wave, entered the room.  Since the boat left the side of the Mel- chor, rapid as had been its passage, much had taken place between the captain and his lieutenant. The latter had heard Capt. Fkllner's ex- planation; and though not satisfied, was at least able to hear it without excitement. It was not strange that the peculiar circumstances which took Belford on board the piratical vessel, should make a deep impres- sion on him, and that the apparent incongruity of the captain of a cruizer giving orders on the deck of a pirate-ship should seem almost inexplicable. Belford was not, however, aware of the dread mystery about to be unveiled to our readers, which made all this natural enough. :"Belford, my friend," said Capt. Fallkner,- "strive to throw off this apathy. I  have promised you an explanation which should, and I know will satisfy youi  Exert ycurself, then, for the honor. you think I dis- grace; for never were your own courage and fidelity morerequired." "Capt. Falkner, I have told you fairly why I, refuse to obey you. You yourself admit that my  reasons are faiirly grounded. Why this mystery? It must be useless, where the object is:i onoable."  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7606-00000032"/> "       THE WIZARD OF THE, WAVE. Falkner looked sadly at the young man, and said: "Belford, I trust you will learn to repent ever having suspected me of motives not dictated by stern honor and duty. The circumstances, however, are so utterly beyond even my own comprehension, that I feel compelled to use all forbearance for the doubts you-imply. Raddle!" "Your honor!". "Have you obeyed my orders to the letter?"  Every inch, your honor. I parted the men, and argued the mat- ter with Tom Truck, the coxswain of your honor, and he said: I Well, I will believe all is fafr, but blast my eyes if the captain is not the devil! I have,' said he, Cprivate reasons for thinking so.' He will be down at the signal for the boat's crew." "Raddle," said the captain, ,i you shall be promoted for this." "Your honor," said the marine-- " that I have seen you in two places at once, there is no denying; and everybody says you have rela- tions down below! But then I thought of the good I had seen you do, and said to myself: ' He who is kind to the poor, protects the weak, is merciful to his enemies, and. fights for his country, cannot be a bad man.' Damme, I would believe in the devil if he acted thus!" "Thank you, Raddle!" said the captain. "What think you now, Mr. Belford ." "Sir, I ask your pardon, and think as that poor marine does; yet, sir, I found you in such situations!" "You must have been puzzled--I admit it. The likeness between the pirate captain and myself is certainly strange and mysterious. He has, I am told, a chain like this on my neck.' Can it be that he too has a similar picture?" , The captain showed the lieutenant the portrait of a beautiful woman, and said: "It is my mother, whom I never knew.' Now, though, Belford, to work I Send my boat on board, and tell Hearton to -get the vessel over the bar, if there be water enough. I must watch my ehiefest prize. I need not tell you to do your duty to your country." "Nor need I, if your duty leads you to act against the governor, ask you to be merciful to him and gentle to his daughter. I obey you, sir; and if I have wronged you, ask your pardon." "Where' are the marines, Raddle?" said Ealkner, after Belford had left the room. "They are in the stables, sir. I smuggled them in, one by one." "' The rooms up stairs must overlook the sea, and I will use them. Perhaps, too, they command the road. Be watchful, Raddle."   THE WIZARD' OF THE WAVE. .          67 The captain ascended the stairway, leaving the marine alone. Raddle assumed an ultra-military air, threw out his chest, and said, ' Ahem, I command the land forces-! Blast my musket, bit I am promoted! Lord, if there was just a castle to storm, or a general to take prisoner, I would make my fortune. Hark! I hear the tramp of men , somebody comes this way." Falkner returned down the stairway he ascended. He wore a great boat-cloak, and said: "Raddle, I can get out of this window and bring up the crew to cut off retreat when they have fairly entered. Listen for my signal."  Falkner and Ralph left-the one going to the stable and the other in'the direction he had indicated. Scarcely had they left, when Feraguez entered the room, and was soon followed by the governor and sailors under charge of Weevil, bear- ing heavy boxes. Soon after, the stranger came in with a party, several of whom bore Isabinda in a litter. With her was the faithful Dianez. "Curse on them!" said the Unknown, " no signal appears to bring the boat. Fear not, though, sir; for we will wait till Weevil hastens across the neck of land and brings them round. This sudcen freak of Falkner's has ruined all my calculations." 'I must obey you," said the governor. "I beg you, though, take are of my child." "I will protect her with my life. A few pieces of gold bribed the keeper of this inn to have all quiet.. Poor fellow! he has few guests; and we will make free with one of his rooms for Isabinda till the boats oomne.  Quick, Weevil, hurry while I examine the rooms." Weevil said, "You had best keep close till I return." Weevil left. 'Aha!"- said Feraguez, " the coast is clear, and this English Jack '.'ar is done brown. Aha! now for the signal   - It must. be understood that Raddle, from the place where he stood, could see both the party in the room  and the captain; and when he v3awwhat was going on, muttered to himself: "Now is the captain's time,1" "Now," said Falkner, "is the time for my leap ;" and he sprang from the window almost at the very moment the Unknown entered the room.   The latter looked carefully around and descended, saying to the governor: "Do not bee uneasy, sir; there is a comfortable room above, where Dianez will attend her. Come, gentle lady, your father, your friends are here; you have no cause for fear, and in a short time will be in safety." X ' Father, father," sid the poor girl, "could I only think so 1"  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7606-00000033"/> 68        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. 6' All thought and hesitation, Isabinda, must be discarded now. If you would share your banished father's fortunes, flight is our only resource' "I will accompany you, father, for ever." "Go, daughter, to your room; Dianez will accompany you. Rest there, if you can, that you may have strength to endure whatever you may have to undergo." Isabinda, followed by Dianez, left the room. '"Now, lads," said the stranger, "L when Weevil comes, be brisk with the boxes, Twenty minutes more, and we are safe." "Are we not now?" said Don Jose. "Did you not say the Wizard could not cross the bar?" "She cannot, iftshe be yet at her moorings." "Whither do you propose to go?" a: What matters it to one who seeks to escape justice?" "What say you?" it Any port," said the Unknown, (c is welcome to him who leaves in- famy and the executioner behind him." ( Sir, you are insulting." a I speak," said. the' villain, ' only the language of the world." 6( Liar and scoundrel! your persuasion led me to this." "My persuasion would, if it couldj" said he, " have forced you to give me your daughter, without the danger of this expedition. If the noble governor of Santiago-if Don Jose de Sandobal--would thrust on me a'cargo of gold, one who from boyhood has roamed the seas, could not refuse so fair a chance.' An orphan without name, I have terrified the world, and needed only a partner of my fame. Your child shall be the rover's Queen, his deck shall be her throne, and the treasury of her'felon father her dower." "I may saye her,'" said the old man-" and I will, if I die." The governor unsheathed 'his sword and rushed on th'e pirate. The contest was, however, too unequal-for in a single instant he was dis- armed and stabbed. As he fell,- however, he seized him, and tore from his neck a chain and portrait which the villain wore. "Secure that door," said'the; pirate and one of his crew at once fastened it. Don Jose looked at the portrait, and exclaimed: "Merciful God! where got you this?" "Give it to me; it is my mother's picture." "Your mother! Great God, there is a retribution for our sins!" He sank exhausted, and at that moment a shrill whistle was heard,   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           69 ("Ha ha! that is the boat!" Weevil, followed by a party of sailors, rushed in, and said: "Quick, to the shore! The cruiser is all awake, and boats are pull- ing from her to land. Be quick, or all is lost!" Damnation'! hurry! hurry!" said the Unknown. A distant whistle at that moment was heard, and Raddle with his marines rushed in from the stables, firing on the party. - The shots were at once returned, and, in the contest, the straw of the stable which was next to the room became ignited. The blaze spread rapidly, and the- confusion became intense. It was not lessened when Truck rushed up the gateway at the head of a party of sailors, completely cutting off fall retreat. In the confusion, the old governor had seized the Unknown, whom he grasped convulsively. At that moment a cry was heard from above, which reached the old man's heart of hearts. "Ah," said he, " save my child! The fire spreads rapidly i save my child!"  At that moment Belford and Manly, accompanied by a large detach- :ment of soldiers, rushed into the room fully armed, and began a contest. They had, however, no trifling antagonist; for the Unknown threw him- self in advance, and exclaimed: '; Back! No power can wrest this treasure from me!" The governor place himself in the ranks of the cruiser, and with Bel- ford rushed on the Unknown, and sought to kill or'disarm him. Though two to one,they had found an equal; and Truck, perceiving it, sought to ascend the steps which led from a kind of gateway to the room. He was. however, met by Weevil-no trifling antagonist; and being at the' same time attacked by Wilkins, was hurled from the steps. The pirates had rallied, and the Wizard's crew were driven back; though Belford' and the governor forced the captain of the Melchor to retreat. -At last' Truck was forced to leave Manly alone apposed to Weevil; and when. the former sought to'ascend the stairway, a deadly contest ensued. In the meantime the noise on the outside became more intense, and Weevil was disarmed. Nothing but his adtivity prevented his being cut down; and in his retreat, he had nearly overturned Truck, who gradually was gaining on Wilkins. Manly followed him up, and Truck' advanced up the steps. A new phase of the contest, however, ensued; for the Un- knownj to whon the governor had been some time opposed, finally was cut down, and Truck met the antagonist he had long sought for. Cut- ting Weevil down, he met the Unknown, but had scarcely crossed swords, 'when Belford, though wounded, rushed upon' him. The contest con- tinued, the fire raged, arid thie Unknown 'overturning Truck, rushed up  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7606-00000034"/> 70        THE WIZARD' OF THE WAVE. the blazing stairway. Truck rapidly followed him, but the steps gave way, and while he was seeking to follow, the whole front of the house fell in. When the crash had subsided, anid the smoke cleared away, the Unknown was seen bearing Isabinda away, while Dianez clung madly to him. The old governor was apparently dying in Belford's arms. Anxious as he was to save the old man, he consigned her to others, and sought to regain the, pirate captain. It was, howeve'r, in vain; for, exhausted by his wound, he could not keep pace with him; and the ravisher, with the remnant of his crew, reached his boats. The yawls from the man-of-war had been left alone, and the pirates were able to escape, bearing with them the governor's unfortunate daughter. Manly and Belford could but rescue that portion of the gold which had been left by the pirates, from the ruins of the smoking posada, and returned to the vessel. The following story from Lieut. Belford, served in some degree to dispel from the minds ofehis companions the gloom occasioned by the sad events above recorded. THE .LIEUTENANT'S SECOND STORY. SOME' years ago, not far from Folkestone, in Kent, stood the neat little cottage of two virtuous and esteemed orphans, called Martin and Selina Roseberry. Martin was a noble-looking boy, with a heart pos- sessed of every good *feeling, and, although he was really young, when their parents died, his mind was so well matured by perseverance, that he possessed all the resolution of a man, and was, in fact, no bad pro- tector for Selina. The two children seemed indeed to live but in each other's happiness. Martin would run for miles to gather a nosegay for his little sister, or, bearing her in his arms, would ramble to the sea- 'beach to gather for her the prettiest shells. Martin was some years older than his sister, but young as the maiden was, she already evinced a heart and mind of the most prepossessing character, and charms which augured future excellence. Her figure was that of a perfect little fairy, and her countenance of the most fascinating description. She was doatingly fond of her brother, and was happy only when he was in her company. The orphans' had been left by their late mother to the care of their nurse, Goody Molloy; for Mrs. Roseberry had managed to accumulate a moderate sum of money by her own industry, which she left for the education and support of her children, until they should arrive at a   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           71 fitting age to provide for themselves, when the residue was to be given jto Goody Molloy, for her future support and comfort. And well did poor old Dame Molloy perform the sacred task en- trusted to her; for she loved the children the same as if they had been her own, and they returned her affection with equal warmth. Thus passed away, in uninterrupted happiness, several years, and Martin Roseberry was accounted one of the handsomest of boys in or near Folkestone, while Selina was accounted one of the prettiest of chil- dren the imagination could conceive. At this time, however, her happi- ness was somewhat marred by her brother taking a predilection for the sea;- and he would not rest, in spite of the affection he bore for Selina and the dame, till he became apprenticed to a collier. He performed several short voyages in this capacity, when the war breaking out, he was pressed; and years passed, and Selina heard nothing of him, neither did she know whether he was living or dead. Swiftly the time flew away, and Selina had become a fine-looking young woman, the admiration of the whole place, and the envy of all the men. However, there was only one on whom Selina'delighted to smile with any other feeling than respect, and that was a young fisher- -man of the name of James Heartwin. He was a fine, handsome young man; but having been left too early to his own will, he was enticed into the paths of folly and dissipation, and had so far ruined his for- tunes, that? unable to procure a. sufficiency by his own profession to gratify his improvidence, he was induced to become the friend and assistant to a gang of desperate smugglersi who had a qecret retreat in an old abbey on the sea-coast at Folkestone. James was not naturally depraved; his errors were not those of a naturally bad heart, but entirely owing to the giddiness, thoughtless- ness, and generosity of youth; and. frequently, in his serious moments, ,he was greatly troubled on account of his bad conduct, and made many vows to reform.             Z; Selina he loved with a passion the most pure and sincere, and when he found that her heart beat in' unison with his own, he reproached' himself severely for being so unworthy of her, and determined at last to abandon his companions, and, by his future behaviour, to make some reparation for his past conduct. The gentle Selina, too, as a sister, often advised him to repent of his errors, and yet she did so with such affair of ardent affection and impressive virtue, that he must have been a heartless villain, indeed, had he still persisted in his guilty career. There was one individual who beheld the passion James Heartwin !  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7606-00000035"/> 72        THE WIZARD OP THE WAVE. and Selina entertained for each other with feelings of the most bitter jealousyv. This was a'dissipated gentleman, who resided at Folkestone, called Sir William Pledger. - Blessed with every natural qualification, the baronet had succeeded but too well-, in his, nefarious designs. A more rQclkless, dissipated, or tyrannical villain, never existed. Numer- ous were the unfortunate victims of his treachery that lived to curse him, and now he marked the beauteous Selina for another. One un- happy being, whom he had met in France, and lured from her home, wandered about Folkestone, clad in the garb of a gipsy, a wretched maniac-lovely still, even in her desolation. Her name was Mabel. Sir William was perfectly aware, that while James Heartwin stood in the way, he had no chance of success with Selina, and he therefore formed a plan to remove him. He addressed a letter to the press- master, who was his particular friend, telling him that there was a cer- tain James Heartwin, a wild, worthless young man, whom it would be advisable to remove from the country, and if he wouldend a'number of men down to the Abbey ruins at night, he, would find him lurking about, and might easily force him on board the English man-of-war called the Britannia, then lying in the offing. This letter he induced one Bobby Crick, a busy, meddling fellow, a Jack-of-all-trades, in the vil- lage, by the promise of a handsome reward,.to convey to the press-master. But Bobby dropped the letter on the road, and, by a singular interven- tion -of Providence, Selina was passing at the time, who picked it up, and, perceiving that it was addressed to the press-master, and was not sealed, curiosity prompted her, to peruse the contents. How astonished was the damsel at the purport of the letter, and the treachery of Sir William Pledger.' In a moment an idea suggested itself to her mind by which she might save her lover, although it would be at the risk of great danger to herself. She -was resolved, .however, to run the chance. She determined, by some means, to procure a suit of James's apparel, and be at the place where the press-gang was to seize him, ill his stead.  She knew    that James was now absent from his hut, and therefore, dropping the letter on the same spot where she had found it, made the best of her way towards his residence. Bobby Crick, who discovered, to his no small vexation, that he had lost the important letter entrusted to him by Sir William Pledger, and dreading his anger, returned to the spot in a state of the greatest trepidation. To his infinite delight, he there beheld it on the ground, and, putting it into his pocket, he departed immediately to the press- maoter's. There was another being who had also watched the actions of Sir 8    THE W'IZARD OF THE W-AVE.          73 William narrowly; and, although her brain wandered eat times, yet she had still reason enough to, commiserate the misfortunes of her fellow- creatures, and to endeavor to frustrate the plans of a villain whom she had so much reason to abhor. She, therefore, employed a poor simple fellow named Jeremiah Supple, who dwelt in a miserable, leaky cottage on the coast, to go to James Heartwin, and warning him of his danger, advised him to be at his own hut at the hour the miscreants purposed seizing him. In the meantime, Selina had hastened to the hovel inhabited by James, who was absent, and gaining an easy entrance by the window, she quickly attired herself in one of her lover's suits, and bent her steps towards the. smuggler's retreat. As she left the hovel, James entered, and fancied he saw a form flit past him, but the night was so dark that he could not be positive; so he efitered his hut, where he busied himself for some time 'in ruminating upon the strange warning he had received from Mabel. The heroic Selina soon arrived at the dreary ruins which formed the smuggler's retreat. The hour quickly arrived, and, true to their agree-. ment, the press-gang entered the place cautiously; and seeing Selina in male attire, took her to be their victim, immediately seized her, and, in spite of her pretended resistance, forced her into the boat, and rowed her with all possible dispatch to the vessel. Sir William  Pledger had. been anxiously waiting the result of his nefarious stratagem; and when he beheld them, as he imagined, seize upon James, he started forth, and exulted over his success. While he was thus occupied, Mabel entered and confronted him.  Her eyes sparkled with reproaches as she pointed to the Britannia, lying in the offing, and which the pale mbon's rays just revealed to them. ", Sir William Pledger," she exclaimed " doubtless you imagine that your triumph is complete." 4c At any rate," said the baronet, with an'ironical smile, " my rival is secure James tHeartwin-- " t Is here!" cried Mabel, as she waved her hand; and, to the confusion' of the villain, the youth he imagined he had secured on board the vessel appeared before him. "-How is this?" ejaculated Sir William; "my rival here!  Who, thenp, was the individual seized by the press-gang?"  "' She thou wouldst have m'ade another victim to thy wicked passions, villain!" answered-Mabel; "Selina Roseberry."  :' Selina II' cried James "merciful powers! can. H hear aright? But on your head, traitor, depend upon it, I will have ample venge-  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7606-00000036"/> "74       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. ance for this outrage. Think not that your rank will protect you; for, though I am humble, yet is my arm strong enough to avenge treachery such as thine, and to stand up the champion of unprotected innocence." Sir William was thunderstruck, and could not reply; and while this altercation was proceeding, the Britannia set sail, and was soon out of sight.                          ' We must now quit the scene of the commencement of our narrative, and request the reader to accompany us to France, and to the interior of a French prison, when at that time a few of the: most gallant sons of Britannia were in the " bilboes."' Among these prisoners, who were all belonging to the Britannia, were Selina and her'own brother, Martin Roseberry, whom she had not seen for so many years, and who was also so much altered that it was im-' possible for any'one who -had known him formerly to recognize, in his strong, robust hardy tone of thirty, the simple, innocent boy of ten, playing on the sea-coast with his golden-haired sister, and gathering for her the prettiest shells to amuse her. Martin's name had never been heard by Selina on board the vessel, though she entertained a sincere friendship for him from the very moment when she first, beheld him; for his manners were so different to the rest of the crew. Martin had also felt the deepest interest in the sailor boy, as he called Selina, and often wondered what could ever have induced them to make a sailor of one so slight and delicate. Now they were prisoners together, Selina knew him as no other than Charles Jackson, though what were his real motives for assuming that name, we shall not attempt to surmise. Colonel de la Gariole, the governor of the prison in which they were confinedi was a gentleman who, in addition to many really good quali- ties, was, exceedingly vain and ambitious. The present-event was one he hailed with pleasure; the idea of his taking'-prisoners'so many of the brave English, he imagined would procure him no little honor, and he. therefore laid strict injunctions on his lieutenant, Clarispe, to look carefully after them, and on no account to suffer them to wander- beyond the limits of the prison-yard. The prison in whhich the sailors were incarcerated was adjoining (and only divided by a slight partition) one which was appropriated- to the confinement of French deserters, among whom were two notorious fellows named Lanfranc and L-amort; but more of them anon. 'On the morning after the capture of Martin and his messmates, the governor, who was anxious to see that they were all safe, summoned   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           75 them into his presence. Martin was the first that appeared -before him, and the honest tar hitched up his slacks, twisted his quid, and gazed upon the governor with the utmost indifference. The governor could not help admiring the noble-looking figure of the British seaman, and the honest frankness that shone in his countenance; and after contemra plating hitm for a few minutes, thus addressed him: Englishman, although we are enemies, I am anxious to show you how we treat those brave fellows whoin the chances of war have thrown into our power." "The chances of war," exclaimed Martin, with a smile; " avast there -belay! Your honor knows very well that it was an accident that threw us into your clutches. We were straying a little too far from our gallant vessel, the Britannia, when we were surprised by a lot of your maccaronis, and put into the bilboes; and yet you call this getting us by fair fighting. Shiver nfy topsails! had two or three of your largest vessels ventured to attack the Britannia, methinks we should have taught your honor a little more about the chances of war." , Englishman," retorted the governor, sternly, i' this insolent lan- , gnage will not be tolerated here, and cannot procure you any good." '; Insolent, do you call-it?" returned Martin; "why, you see we British tars are so accustomed to speak the'plain and honest truth to an ,enemy, that it comes as nat'ral to us as our mother tongue." ' Well, well I admire your candor, young man," said the governor; "and would wish to serve you. Besides, I do not hate your country; no, I have something there that binds me to it. I had a daughter there as beautiful as imagination can depicture; two years since she was seduced away from me by an English gentleman, and although I have made every inquiry after her, I have never been able to ascertain her fate. Oh, young man, can you feel for the sufferings of a parent thus cruelly deprived of the prop of his declining years? If you can, oh, say that ou will assist me in endeavoring to recover my child.- In a short time we expect that peace will be proclaimed between our two nations, and then your liberty will be granted you, and--" ;' Avast, avast!" your honor, interrupted Martin; " can you talk of my serving you when I am still your prisoner? N ow, if I were in your ionor's place, and I had taken a lot of brave fellows like myself and my messmates, merely by accident, I should say here is a ciown apiece for you, and you are free i do that, your honor, and then you will be acting like a man." 1"Well, well-," said the governor, impatiently, "I will consider more maturely of your- wishes. At' any rate, wait till to-morrow, and you  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7606-00000037"/> 76.       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. shallibe free; but, oh, promise to, assist me in endeavoring to discover my child."  J' I will not budge an inch from this spot," said Martin, resolutely, "unless at the same time you release at least one of my companions- a lad for whom I have'a particular regard, and whom i am certain would break his heart, if he were left unprotected by me.' The governor again hesitated, and at last assented, but persuaded Martin to delay his departure until the next day, as it would be neces- sary for him to mention his case to the higher authorities before. he could liberate him. 'With this request Martin very reluctantly com- plied-and the governor, giving instructions to his lieutenant to watch closely over the prisoners while they were allowed to walk in the yard, left him. Martin was now anxious to see his youthful messmate, to apprise him of his good fortune, and accordingly called him forward. Selina obeyed, and Martin greeted her with his usual kindness. , I have often wondered," he said, "how they came to make such a stripling as you a sailor. Why, your voice is as soft as a girl's; and your figure-aye, by my topsails, talling of that, my young spark, let me take a nearer view of your vessel." Selina blushed and trembled while Martin, with a significant leer, walked around her, and took a more minute survey of her person. ' Wheugh!" exclaimed Martin, twisting his quid, "I begin to sus- pect."  "Suspect what '" demanded the {(amsel, with much emotion. Martin whispered in her ear. Selina turned pale, but after a few minutes' hesitation, she said  '"Yes, indeed you are right--I am a woman; but now you have my secret, do not, oh do not betray me." "' No, my little beauty," said Martin, "C that I never will. Charles Jackson willretain your secret, and continue to respect-you. But whatever, my pre,ttylass, could induce you to turn sailor?" "It was to save one whoSm I sincerely ipved, from a plot laid by a villain against him," answered Selina; " but you shall know more anon; at present, be assured that I esteem you as a brother, for the kindness you have ever shown towards mne."  W "Well said, my young spark," remarked Martin; "' and when Charles Jackson shall cease to act like a Iman, especially towards a pretty woman, may he founder in the ocean of misfortune. But give us your fin, my  little beauty." , With that, Martin, in his honest, rough manner, grasped the delicate   THaI WIZARD OF THE WAYE.           " little hand of Selina with a firmness that brought the tears in her-eyes, and then, telling her of all that had taken place between him ad' the governor, desired her for the present to retire. Selina obeyed. Jeremy Supple, having by some means or other got on board the Britannia, and lurking about the French coast, was taken for a spy and brought in before the governor. He was now taken before Martin; who, recognizing him, somked him sarcastically on his niisfortune, and told him he was sure to be hanged. We need not attempt to describe the alarm of poor Jeremy; suffice it -to say, his terror was so excessive that it was not without the greatest difficulty he could support himself- while, at the same time, he ardently implored Martin to intercede for ,him with the governor.  In the course of conversation, Jeremy related all the particulars of his meeting with Mabel; the .plot that had been devised to impress James Heartwin; and the generous sacrifice Selina had made to save her lover; and the fact, also, of her being taken on board the Britannia instead of James. The name struck like an electric shock on the heart of Martin, and he looked at the simple Jeriemy with the utmost anxiety and impa- tience, as he demanded : * a Selina Roselerry, did you say? Tell me, was that the name of the pretty damsel whom you have described tot have acted in such a heroic manner? Speak quick, for my heart is aground until I' receive your answer." ' I tell you that was the name of the damsel,"' replied Jeremy; "and she was the prettiest maiden in all Yarmouth." "'; Shiver may topsails!--could it be?" cried the sailor, his heart beat- ing at double its usual pace; " say, should you know her if you were to see her?" "Should I know her?" repeatel Jereny, "I should think I would, too."  "Then we -will soon know all about this," exclaihned Martin. "Hil loa, there!" he bawled, at the yer;y top of his voice'; and Selina; at the well-known summons, rushed front the prison into the yard. In a mo- ment she recognized Jeremy, and uttered a cry of astonishment, whio at the same time said : "Ah, it is-it is Selina Roseberry."      - What language could do adequate justice to the feelings wtiich now took possession of the heart bf Martin, who strained his eyes in gazing with the most unbo'unaed deiliiht upon fedtures s, well reme'iibered-. features on which he-haid ever looked with transport,':but Which Se, had  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7606-00000038"/> 78        THE WIZARD OF THE We VE. almost feared he should never behold again. M3Iartin's career had been a hazardous one ; he had for years endured all the perils and dangers of the ocean, the battle, and the breeze; he had been several times wounded; and, at the very time he was expecting to be paid off, so that he might return to his native land and once more press his darling sis- ter to his heart, some accident had never failed to occur to prevent it, and to send him off to meet the dangers of the deep once more. "Selina Roseberry," at length he said, rushing to her with frantic delight and enfolding her in his arms, " my sister, my dear little sister!" Astonishment for a moment prevented the damsel from giving utter- ance to a syllable, but at, last she exclaimed: "What mean your words?   I can scarcely dare trust myself with such a blissful assurance,; and yet., now I gaze more steadfastly upon you, all the scenes of my childhood rush vividly to my memory." "Ah" exclaimed Martin, " it is not possible that you can ever forget them."                     - "Is it possible," demanded Selina, " that your iname, then, is not Charles Jackson?"   "; o, no," answered the tar, hastily, s" that was an assumed name; I am Martin Roseberry, your brother, who used to carry you, when a pretty little golden-haired child, to gather the shells on the sea-beach. My sister I my dear little Selina!" Fain would we describe the scene of mutual transport consequent upon the extraordinary and unexpected meeting of the brother and sister, but find it would take a far more eloquent pen than ours to do so properly. They wept tears of joy, and remained locked in each other's arms for several minutes. With what sentiments of admiration and transport did Martin dwell' upon every lineament of the lovely countenance of his sister, and recall' to his mind the peaceful joy of former days. His joy was now complete; and although his bosom swelled with feelings of honest indignation against Sir William Pledger, he could .not help blessing the accident that had brought about such remarkable events, and been the means of restoring him to the arms of a beloved sister, from whom he had been so long separated, and whom be had begun to fear Providence had ordained that he should never behold again. On the evening when these events ,took places the governor had ap- pointed to have a small festival in the prison-yard, and on that occasion all the prisohers- were to be allowed .to partake of the entertainments. Lamort:apd Lanfrane, the two deserters we have before spoken of, had foimed a villanous design to-put poison in the governor's wine, and (.   THE WIZARD OF THE    'WAVE.       79 thus to gratify a feeling of the most deadly revenge, Martin and his sister overheard their plot, ind, while they were filled with horror and disgust, they determined by some means to frustrate the diabolical plans of the miscreants  The evening passed away merrily, and little could any one have sus- pected the dark design at that very time lurking in the breasts of Lan- franc and his companion. The time approached, and the two wretches seized the opportunity of putting the poison into one of the wine-bottles, and were all the time narlowly watched by Martin and Selina,. The governor and his friends now approached, and prepared to set themselves at the table. In the meantime, Martin seized an opportu- nity to secure the bottle that contained the poisonous drug, and, after the governor and his friends had dranlS, he exclaimed to Lamort and his companion :            "k ' Come, comrades, let us all be sociable together! Drink! drink!" Lamort, never suspecting that anything was wrong, immedi:tely took the proffered glass, and, raising it to his lips, quaffed oil' the whole of, the contents. In a momen t his features assunmed a livid and ghastly appearance, his eyes rolled with frightful fury. and, with one horrible groan, he fell-dead upon the earth. "What is the meaning of this?" demanded the astonished governor. "Why, the meaning is, your honor," answered Miartin, " that these two fellows had formed a plot to murder you. I overheard them, and have thus been the fortunate means of saving you from a terrible death. Behold!" he continued, seizing Lanfiranc, and tearing the phial containing the poison from his bosom, or at least what remained of i t. N othing'could surpass the astonishment and horror of. the governor, excepting the feelings of unbounded gratitude he experienced towards IMartin Roseberry for the service he had rendered him. He, pressed his hand vehemently, and then vowed to be his firiend as long as he. lived. - .As to that, your honor," answered Martin, "I shall be most happy to be considered worthy of your good opinion, although I have. only done that which every min, and every true British seaman', would do-- namely, saved the life of an enemy, when attacked in a cowardly mainner."                  , ' ("You're a brave fellow, a .noble fellow," enthusiastically exclaimed the governor, still most cordially pressing his hand, He then ordered the. body of -Lamort to be taken away, aid Lanfrano to be immediately ,  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7606-00000039"/> 80        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. secured and placed in confinement. But ere they could do this, the ruffian. burst from the hands of the guard who had taken him into custody, and drawing a pistol fromn his bosom, presented it at Martin and fired. Most happily, however, for the brave seaman, it -missed its mark and the miscreant was dragged to a dungeon, amid the execra- tions of all present.  In the midst of the confusion which these events had excited, the governor's lieutenant made I his appearance in great haste, to inform him that the crew of the Britannia had made their way into the fortress, and were dealing destruction to all around them. Before the, governor had time to express his emnotion, loud reports of cannon reached his ears, and the next moment the walls of the fortress were blown down with a loud crash, and the brave-tars of the Britan- nia entered with loud shouts of triumph. Martin no sooner beheld his gallant messmates, than seizing a, cutlass from one of the enemy, he rushed -to join them in the affray.  The conflict was brief but desperate, while it lasted; the fortress was taken, and the governor and his men were placed in the power of their heroic enemies-thus showing the never-failing success attendant upon true valor and determination. Once more we must direct the reader's attention to Folkestone, and pass over an interval of several monthls, during which time peace had been proclaimed between France and Great Britain, and Martin and his pretty sister had returned to their native shore. It was a happy moment for them when the white cliffs of ,England met their gaze, and they were unbounded in their gratitude, to Heaven for'the protection it had afforded them through so many dangers and vicissitudes. To England,.alsoi, had hastened Colonel de la Garde, in search of his lost daughter, and much was the anxiety, the doubts, and fears-he alternately endured to know What had been her fate, or if he should ever- behold her again. He was accompanied by Jeremy   Supple, who had elicited from him that his daughter was no other than 'Mabel, and Sir William Pledger was the villain who had seduced her froni her home and the arms of her father.. This knowledge that worthy determined to turn to some -account. .  Sir William Pledger, who was soon made acquainted with the return of Selina, still longed .to possess 'her, During her absence his desires bad increased rather' than' abated" and henow w resolved 'to-let no oppbr- tunity'slip to get he' into his power,: The circumstance of her brother   THE WIZARD OF THE 'WAVE.          81 returning with her, presented an obstacle, but at length he invented a scheme to obtain the darling object of his wishes, that only the mind of a most heartless villain could concoct. In order to further these diabolical plans, he sought one Bobby Crick, as he was familiarly called, who had on former occasions rendered him- self a ready instrument of his vices, and by the offer of a large reward, tempted him to place a case of jewel's in Selina's box, so that he might accuse her of robbing him. This stratagem, he imagined, could not fail of success, as Selina had been in the habit of visiting a servant maid in his -house, and whom he having seduded, was ready, for money, to swear to anything her villa. nous master proposed to her.  Sir William, as may- be imagined, designed not to punish Selina; oh, no; that would have been to deprive him of all his hopes of triumphing over her innocence; he, however, thought that by holding out to her a promise not to prosecute, he might induce her to become his mistress, and thus all his long-formed wishes would be gratified. He thought that the dread of shame and punishment would prevail on her to accept any offers which might afford her a chance of escape, and, he therefore resolved to promise to pardon her, if she wouldyield to his infernal proposals. But little did the miscreant know of the real. and spotless character of that beauteous and virtuous girl, to entertain, for a moment such a base idea. Mr. Crick heard the propositions of Sir William with much attention, shook his head, and hesitated. Crafty and designing, he knew well. how to deal with the guilty baronet, and resolved to pay himself well- for the task he was wanted to perform. "Why do you pause?" demanded Sir William, with a look of im- patience; " do you fear to do that which I desire of you?" c' Why, why-you see, Sir William," Bobby faltered out; "I --' ,' Bah!" interrupted Sir William; " any one would imagine, to hear you, that you had never been guilty of anything wrong. This is not the first time you have been employed by me, and I consider that I have been the best friend you ever had." "Very true, sir," said the fellow; is but then you know that this is a very dangerous piece of business." "Dangerous!" repeated Sir William. "Why more dangerous than that you have before been concerned in? What suspicion can be attached to you?" "That may be all very true, Sir Williamu, returned Crick; "but tien   &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7606-00000040"/> 82        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. "I see the reason of your hesitation," said the baronet; " you havo not yet been made acquainted with the sum I am ready to give you for your trouble. Perhaps twenty guines may satisfy you?" Crick opened his ears eagerly, and his scruples, if he ever entertained any, were immediately done away with.  He quickly agreed and departed from the house. He had only just left the presence of Sir William, when the door was thrown open, and Mabel entering the .room, confronted- the baronet. Madness and sorrow had so altered her once blooming features,that it was almost impossible for any one who had known her in .her former days to recognize her now. Notwithstanding, Sir William could not help feeling the most violent emotion: at length having partly recov- ered himself, he demanded who' she was, and for what purpose she had thus boldly dared to obtrude' herself upon him, "You do not know me; Sir William Pledger," said lMabel, with a wild and melancholy laugh; " no wonder, no wonder-seeing how time has changed the features of one who once was fair, once was lovely and innocent. It is well for the guilty seducer, if his conscience can so sleep, that he remembers not his unfortunate victim--if he can forget the days when she was happy in her native home, and treasured in a fond father's bosom-that state of peace and serenity from which he enticed her, under the most specious promises, and by the most allur- ing vows. Would, oh, would that my memory was as weakl; oh, it is a good thing to forget "  " Woman," said Sir William, " what means this wild jargon? what would you have of me "  "Listen," answered Mabel, advancing nearer to him, and placing her hand on his arm, at the same time she fixed her eyes upon his counte- nance, with such an expression that made him shudder innately; " listen, Sir William Pledger, I have that for your ear which may serve perhaps to recall your wandering recollection." She then sang, in tones of melancholy plaintiveness, the following words: "Believe, though I may wander far, Far over land and wave, I swear by yonder twinkling star, None shall my heart enslave But her whose blushing cheeks I kiss With pearly moisture wet: By all my future hopes of bliss, I never will forget!"   THE ;WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           83 The mist was now banished from the eyes of the guilty Sir William; his heart palpitated violently; he knew her immediately; the tones of her voice struck upon his conscience, while the words of the song recalled to his memory a dark tale of the treachery and cruelty that smote him with remorse. It was the same song with which, in the days when she thought he loved her, he had so often sung to her. "Mabel! Mabel!" cried the conscience-stricken baronet, advancing towards her. "Nay, stand off! approach me not," said Mabel, advancing towards the door 'by which she had entered; " thy look is contamination  JSIabel has performed her errand; she has revealed herself to thee, and made thy dastard, guilty soul tremble; and now she leaves thee with -her bitterest curse." Thus saying, before the baronet could offer to move, she quitted the room, and left him to his own reflections. We need not: attempt to portray them.  For a few moments he could' not believe the evidence of his senses, and wondered how he could have seen Mabel so frequently before without being able to recognize her; but at length he threw himself into a chair, and, by reflection, endeavored to compose his feel- ings. Mabel, overcome by her frenzied emotions, and the exertion she had undergone in her brief interview with her cruel seducer, rushed wildly across the garden, and entered the fields beyond, where, unable to sup- port herself any longer, she sunk insensible on the earth. At this moment Providence directed the footsteps of General de la Garde and Jeremy Supple to the same spot.   Beholding a female on the earth, appearing dead or dying, Jeremy hastened to the neighboring village to fetch a doctor. The governor, whose syimpathy was greatly excited, now raised the poor girl in his arms, and she slowly recovered her senses, and opened her eyes.  "Where am I?" she said ;   " where is he, the villain, the monster, wewho ---    -       }-- "; Ah!" suddenly exclaimed the governor, in a state of great agita- tion; " that voice-those tones -are familiar to myears. Let me look at you more narrowly." lie parted the hair from-her forehead, and gazed lmore intensely into her countenance; Mabel looked up into his face'; they knew each other immediately, and with cries of transport, they fondly embraced. In the meantime, while these events were going on, all was happineU  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7606-00000041"/> 84       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.  atthe cottage of Goody Molloy. It may be necessary to give some brief, particulars of James Heartwin, who, after the disappearance of Selina, was truly wretched, and the more so as he was without the means of rescuing her; from his connection with the smugglers, he feared to make any complaint to the proper quarters, and although he vowed at some future period to be revenged on Sir Willaim Pledger, he knew his power too well for the present to make the slightest attempt of the kind. In this manner months passed away, but what language can suffiently de- picture the delight he experienced when Selina was restored to him, and he learned from her own lips that sle loved him, if possible, moro fondly than ever! Nothing could surpass the satisfaction Martin felt at the choice Selina hadmade. James had abandoned his former asso- ciates, and his father having lately died, had left him a farm and a little annuity. There was nothing then to prevent the union of the lovers, and la day had already been fixed, to which they all looked for- ward with the most anxious anticipations. On the evening when Mabel and her father had encountered each other, Martin, James, and Selina were all at the cottage of Goody Molloy, and were getting very merry together, when suddenly there was a loud knocking at the door, 'and Bobby Crick, at the head of a posse of men, entered. He quickly told his business, namely, that Sir William had been robbed of a case of jewels, and he suspected Selina of committing the theft, from her well known intimacy with Jane, his servant; and Bobby, therefore, being vested with ' a little brief au- thority,' had, as they might infer from the men he had. with him, come to search the cottage. It would be a useless task for us to attempt to describe the shame horror, and indignation of all present, at this most infamous and pre- posterous charge; and Martin and James, rising from their seats, would have immediately used forcible means to eject Bobby and his companions from the cottage, had it not been for the interposition of Selina. Con- scious innocence supported her throughout the whole of the trying scene, and giving the key of her box to Crick, she said: '"This charge, brutal as it is, is almost too absurd and contemptible for serious notice; it is well worthy of the man from whom it ema- nates:; however, restrain your indignation, my brother and James; this scheme .will but recoil upon the guilty, and [elina will be able to laugh to scorn the attempt made to injure her character." "',hiver my topsails!" cried Martin; " but I will teach the lubber, Sir William what-do-you-call-him, that however much he may think to o   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.          85. trample and crush us beneath his feet, his station shall not protect him from retribution. Justiceoshall be done, and this turn out to be one of the dearest tricks he has ever played. My sister Selina a thief! d---e I the word almost chokes me. H--" Selina again interrupted her enraged brother, and with the utmost indifference desired Bobby to proceed immediately with the search, and satisfy himself as to the truth of his allegations. Crick proceeded to unlock the box, and watching his opportunity, he slily placed the casket of jewels underneath some of the poor girl's wearing apparel. He now pretended to examine the contents of the box more narrowly, and at length coming to the jewels, he held them up before the gaze of all, and then said: "Miss Roseberry, you may protest your innocence, but pray, after tiiis discovery, how can you answer to the serious charge brought against you?" Selina gazed at the casket aghast, and for a few moments horror and stupefaction completely spell-bound every one present. "It is a monstrous stratagem, after all," at length exclaimed Martin; ': can any one believe so ridiculous an accusation?" "You may call it ridiculous, Mr., Roseberry," returned Crick; "but ]I am-afraid you will find it much more serious than you seem at pres- ent to think. It is my duty to take this unfortunate young woman into custody." "May I never go aloft," cried Martin, chenching his fist, and ad- vancing towards Crick, " if you attempt to lay a finger upon this poor, innocent girl, I will scuttle your figure-head, in the turning of a marlin- spike." Ruffian, begone!" exclaimed James Hfeartwin, his eyes flashing with indignation, " or ---               -  "Hold, both of you, I command you, as you value my love," firmly interrupted Selina;. "I fear not the malice of my enemies; conscious of my own innocence, I do not despair of being fully able to rebut this infamous charge, and obtaining -justice for the injury that is attempted to be done me." "The young woman must accompany me before a justice," remarked Crick; " and you know it is no use attempting to resist the law. I cannot help it. I am sorry for it; but the whole of it is, that duty is' duty, and I must perform it." Martin and James turned upon him a look of contempt, and then, in the most distracted manner, they proceeded to accompany the unfortu-  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7606-00000042"/> s8       STHE WIZARD OF .THE VJ'AVE. hate Selina to the house of a magistrate, the darnsel: on the way, contin- uing to support herself with the most astonishing fortitude under this despicable attempt to convict her of so great a crime.   . The examination having taken place, the magistrate remanded Selina till a future day, in consequence of the absence of Sir William Pledger, who had not yet sufficiently obtained firmness and effrontery to meet- the gaze of the innocent accused, The. parting that took place between Selina, her lover, and Martin, was of the most affecting character, and the two, latter returned home in great agony of mind ; in fact never before had they experienced such mental suffering.  a The villain, Sir William Pledger, was seated in his study the day after these events; when-he was interrupted in the midst of the medita- tions he was indulging in, by the appearance of a servant, who informed him that a man below demanded an interview with him. "Demand!" repeated the baronet, with a haughty frown; , this is rather bold, methinlks. Did he not mention his name?" "( He did, sir," answered the servant; " he called himself Martin Roseberry." "Ah!" exclaimed Sir William, somewhat alarmed, the brother of the girl suspected of--- Tell him I cannot see him." v The servant departed with that message, and the baronet waited with some anxiety to hear the result. He was not long kept in suspense. Presently he heard a loud noise below, and before he could recover himself, Martin stood before him.  We will pass over what took place at the meeting, with the exception of stating that it was one of the warmest description. Martin bitterly reproached Sir William with his villany and cruelty, and the baronet replied with equal acrimony, and at length summoned several of his ser- vants. After much difficulty Martin was ejected from the house, vow- ing vengeance against the-wrecth who was endeavoring to Dring shame, and sorrow upon his head, and all those who were connected with Selina. The day that had been set apart for the examination of Selina at length arrived, and Sir William, in order to further the nefarious pro- jects he hand in view, had sent to a magistrate residing in the district, who was a friend of his, requesting that he would conduct the proceed- ings. Mr. Rivington, however, was taken ill, and unable to attend; but he had sent another gentleman in his place, who wasx also, as he said, a brother magistrate. The individual was, a remarkably tall man,   THE  WIZARD OF THE WAVE.         87 enveloped in a long black mantle, that descended to his feet, and entirely concealed his form. His features were very handsome and there was, something in them that made Sir William tremble when he gazed upon them. The examination was proceeded with; every cir- cumstance was related with the most aggravating minuteness. When Bobby Crick was asked whether he saw the jewels in Selina's box, he laconically replied in the affirmative. I "And do you know who placed them there?" inquired the magis- trate. X I did," answered Bobby Sir William turned deadly pale, and was completely astounded at this unexpected answer. ': I did," repeated Bobby; "I have earned so-little by being guilty, ( that I'm going to try what; effect doing good will have on me. I put the jewels into Selina Roseberry's box, by order of Sir William, in order that he might get her accused of robbery." C 'Tis a base calumny v" exclaimed the baronet. "Liar i" cried'the supposed magistrate, rising with great dignity from his seat. "Friends, listen while I unmask this traitor to ye all. There were two brothers by the same father, who was wealthy and lord "of these estates. One was called Gerard Pledger, the other William. Gerard, the eldest, was good and amiable; William was base and envi- ous. They grew up. William coveted the wealth to which his brother was heir. He formed a cruel plot to destroy him ; he had him secretly seized, and conveyed on board a vessel bound for India, where he ordered him to be murdered; but he escaped, and he now returns to claim those rights of which this villain hath plundered him." "False-false as hell!" exclaimed Sir William. "s Tis true," returned the gentleman, : and your coward conscience acknowledges that it is so.. Behold, your brother Gerard stands before you! Begone, sir, from that roof you have long disgraced by your presence; resign that wealth you have unlawfully basked in, and thank my mercy that I do not punish your perfidy." Sir William, apparently abashed, rushed from the chamber, but had not been gone many minutes, when he returned with a number of smuggler, all well armed, who surrounded Gerard and the rest, and threatened destruction. ]n the meantime, however, Martin, who had watched the behaviour of Sir William, and suspected his intentions, had made his way to the ship, and brought a number of his messmates to the house. A smart contest now ensued, in which Sir William  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7606-00000043"/> 88        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. received a mortal wound, The sailors were soon triumphant, and such of the smugglers as survived took flight. Selina and her brother found an excellent friend in Gerard Pledger, and, on the day the former became the wife of James Heartwin, he gave her a sufficient marriage portion to render them independent for life. , .  Martin never married, but retiring from the sea, he resided with his sister and her husband, and was never so happy as 'when relating the numerous adventures he had met with during the' time he had min- gled in these exciting scenes upon the briny deep.   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           89 BOOK III. CHAPTER       I. THE MAIDEN'S DREAM THE pirates' boat swept rapidly, as the arms of twelve strong men could bear it, to the Melchor,-which lay just beyond the point of land we: have so often spoken of--and one after another the pirates regained their ship. Among the first to reach it was the Unknown, who bore Isabinda up the deck in his own arms, and hurried with her into the cabin. Above, all was noise and turmoil-for the sailors were putting in the heavy cable, the rattling of, the -links of which sounded like the jangle of devils' chains; and through the port-holes was seen the roll- ing of the waves. On the deck lay many treasure boxes, and the sailors were busy hoisting the guns from the hold to the open or flush deck. It will be remembered that the Melchor, except when at sea, was forced always to assume the appearance of a peaceable trader, and that every- thing like armament in port had to'be carefully concealed. When he had reached the cabin, Isabinda was nearly exhau-sted, and the Unknown pointed to one of the boxes which lay strewn around, and 3aid: "Cheer up! yours is a sad fate.; but fear not. It is best to die young and innocent, and not--  Bah I sit down and cease this trembling. HeMre you will be free from many, things that would offend you, young and delicate as you ,are-free from the oaths of the rude sons of the ocean, and the hopes which might spring up, futile as they are, from the vicinity of the English cruiser." 4' And is she, then, near us?" said Isabinda. ' They say she is the swift;est keel in their navy, and she well de-, serves her name. For seven years this vessel has never met her match;  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7606-00000044"/> 90       'THE WIZARD OF THEE WAVE, but now she has found a master. Curse bonthem, I thought they were in the bar I There is no hope, lady, however brightly your eyes may beam. 'Before I am taken, I will blow myself lup, and every person on board of her. "Great Heaven!" said the frantic girl. i "Roll on, ye waters, and speed my gallant bark! Cradled on the rolling seas, my life has passed upon your bosom. Boyhood, the spring. ing hopes of youth, scorn of fear, thoughts of glittering fortune-all have grown to power on your everlasting deeps. I I bear with me that which will realize my soul's most daring wishes:-wealth and beauty! Shall the hand of man ever wrest them from me . Never! by the dark, the unknown future-never! To you I give what through you I have gained." At that moment Weevil entered- the 'cabin, and the Unknown asked him: "o How goes the chase?" s"Still they near us. Half an hour since, we had them in the main- top, but now she is hull downi nearly." "Throw the other guns overboard, for we can fight them," said the Unknown. "Lighten her and spread every sail, for we must and will not be taken."         ,    ' "We must not, sir," said Weevil. "We will not. The cruiser has not yet begun to talk. Serve spirits to the men.  I will be on the deck when I have made my last prepa- rations.  You understand? 2" "Aye, aye; it is better to go to Davy Jones on ,the splitting timbers of our vessel, than dangle like scarecrows in an English port. I will go on deck." "You hear, lady, how things are?" said the piraete.  "Shall I see my father no more?" "Never, lady! but care not-if we escape, your life will pass with one who loves you better.  They say the proud, arch-fiend himself ad- mires virtue--and, guilty as I am, I love you with burning and undy- ing love.  You are mine, and Death alone shall part us." The noise on deck increased, and the pirate went to one of the ports. "Now, my fair ship, trust to your heels--for my last gun is gone." The sound of a distant gun was heard, and the pirate said, "She speaks. Weevil, show them the black flag. Now for my last duty!" The-pirate approached the magazine, and took from it a coil of fuse or slow match. 4 Father of all;' said Isabinda', " must I so young meet a dreadful   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           91 death? Must I so suddenly plunge from seeming happiness to that dark state we tremble so to contemplate? Spare me, sir, for my broken- hearted father's sake, if indeed he live. Save me, though, from per- ishing thus." The report of another gun was heard. The Unknown placed one end of the coil within the magazine, and said:   "The sound is no nearer; we may yet escape. Would that the darkness of the last night yet hung pall-like about us." Weevil came again into the cabin, and said, "Still, sir, she has the heels of us." " I will come on deck; you see I am calm. There is my line of life!"-and he pointed to the coil. "A terrible coil it has been, and ,always has borne within itself the seeds of its own destruction." "; We have many here on board sir," said Weevil, "who---" "I know-I know. I ask no man," said the pirate, " to share my fate." "That por ogirl, sir, and the sailor who is now a prisoner in the hold, they--" "They must share my doom, for none must live to tell my secrets. Weevil, when I give the signal to launch the boats, see all our people, in them. Bid them seek the nearest land, and, if they can, escape this English bull-dog at our heels."  The round of another gun was heard. "Look to her," continued the Unknown. "Spread every inch of canvass that will draw. Send me wine and a lamp. Wine! wine!" Weevil left to obey him, and the pirate turned to Isabinda and bade her sing to him:                    ,  "Let," said he, " the pirateds bird of the wild waters 1i4e like the swan. Sing, sing to me!" "His mind gives way. I cannot sing." "A sailor brought in wine and a lamp, and immediately after he had left, a rapid firing was heard, followed by cries and shouts. ' Every moment gained," said' Isabinda, "is precious. The cruiser may yet overtake us."             ! ," Sing!" said the pirate. "I would, but cannot. I tremble." "Tremble I I love, you as man never loved before. Had fate east my lot of life on the dull land, I would have been a tender guardian to you; as it is, I 'cannot suffer another to clasp your form. Even in  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7606-00000045"/> THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. death you are mine. Ha, ha! for many a day our bridal will be re- membered on this coast. The pirate and his virgin bride! Destruc- tion shall witness our contract, and seal it with desolation. Sing my death, betrothed and doomed love one. I await the warrant of annihi- lation in your sweet music. I beseech you sing!" The pirate threw himself on the floor and drank deeply, while his prisoner, taking a mandolin, touched its chords. 1 "I cannot sing. Spare me, and let me prepare for the fearful end approaching."   Another gun was heard, and the pirate laughed while Isabinda stood  aghast.   "Laugh not," said she, "for it is so- like my fearful dream." "Tell me your dream. I love such mysteriesJ My life has been one stormy, fearful, terrible dream. Tell me your dream, and let me hear at least the melody of your voice." "I dreamed that I slept at home," said Isabinda, " and that a ne- gro, who once had stabbed my father, seized me, He sat by me with a drawn knife." While she spoke, Tom  Truck descended froim above, and on his hands and knees crawled to Isabinda. He touched her, and the poor girl shrieked; but seeing who it was, contrived, to hide her emotion, and continued:   "He told me my life hung on his breath. I screamed then, for I saw a friend near me. I had a hope of escape, but saw that he was unarmed. I pointed out to him that my foe had at hand the means of destruction-that he had but to lift his voice, to call his brother ruf- fians. He said he would die for me, but I bade him be prudent, and pointed out where he could conceal himself." "Did he do so?" said the stranger. "He did at last. I threw myself thus on my knees, (and she knelt,) crying, ' Oh, Eternal Power, I implore thy aid--save! save me!" The agitation of Isabinda had increased, and Truck, understanding what she meant, hid himself.    The Unknown lifted her up, and said:   I "Why should you tremble at a dream?" As he spake, the sound of a gun was heard, followed by a crash that told that the shot had not been thrown away. "Hark!" said he, " they reach us now; but they cannot part us, You are and must be mine." "Mercy I mercy!"    THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           93 The stranger seized and clasped her in his arms. He said: "Shrink' not, for folded in my arms you will meet death. Stir not; no hope can aid you. Stir not, if you would escape what is worse than death. Yet do you shrink? I have not harmed you." Another gun was heard, and he continued, "Yes, by this kiss, you are mine!" Isabinda shrieked, and he continued: "Cease! Shrink not I This kiss!" "Help! help!" "Here is help, my 'lass," said Truck, starting up, "if I hang for it." He seized the Unknown and grappled. with him. "Put out the light, lady 1"  Truck was no trifling antagonist, and wresting a dagger from the pirate, stabbed him. While mad with pain, the'latter rushed towards the lamp, and bad nearly grasped* it ere Isabinda could comply with Truck's urgent request. The pirate shouted out, "Ho, there! deck! deck! traitors!"-and rushed again on Truli--who was, however, managing him very well-- when Weevill and others rushed in, striking the coxswain down. He would have been killed at once, when the pirate made them forbear, saying: "Hold; he shall die a fearful death before his comrade's have met their doom." This was the state of matters; and here we must leave the party,- premising that from time to time the guns of the Wizard were heard more and more frequently, and rapidly nearing the pirate. It was a painful and agonizing scene, condensing the misery of a century into less time than it has required for us to relate it. Let us now go to the Wizard of the Wave.  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7606-00000046"/> "       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. C H A?TER   II i THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.' THE whole, crew of the cruiser was on deck, anxiously watching the chase. Many motives actuated them. Falknerl sought to secure the performance of the duty on which he'had been sent. Belford was thinking of Isabinda, and many a seaman wondered what had become of their favorite Tom Truckl the captain's coxswain. Tim came on the orlop deck, and said:  i is They are fixing the tables in the cockpit, and I am to help the doc- tor in the operation."      .           ; A gun was heard, which startle&amp; Tim's nervels, and he exclaimed: "Mercy! two or three more such sounds will operate on me most un- pleasantly. I wish I could find a gun-proof box somewhere." '"' Another shot was fired, and the clerk continued: "Lord! if our guns affect me so, what will theirs do 2" Manly came on deck and placed his hand on his' shoulder, which had the effect of bringing Treacle on his knees, with an exclamation: "Lord I I thought it was a twenty-four pound shot. I have the ague. Do you hear my teeth chatter?"  "Get up, you fool. Here comes Belford, wntc has brought the lieu- tenant with a horrible wound on board." The doctor said, "Belford is wanted in the cabin; and look here, Mr. Purser's clerk, be careful to report below they state of the chase." Yes, your honor," said Tim. As he moved, another gun was heard, and he paused, saying, "Sir, must I go on deck?"      l ("Go, you devil," said Belford, " an4 be quick 1" a Dear! yes. I wish,"-said he, aside, "they may get me on deck P "Manly, the governor is badly wounded," said Belford. "Shall we take him to the cockpit? If the pirate fight, he will be better there.')  "Go to him at once; he were better there;" and, amid the firing, Manly left. Tim rushed in, and Belford asked: "i How is the chase?" "Pretty well, I thank you, sir. How are you?2" The poor lad had lost the little wit with which nature had endowed him.   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.           95 "This is no time forjesting." '"Ah, yes sir-a deal too fast." "What do you mean, sir?" "Oh, sir,' said Tim, "1I mean that her sky-scrapers cut the water with the velocity of her binnacle. Her helm is hard aport to starboard, and her bowsprit points over our tafferel. It is a certain road to victory. Hurrah! tHurrah!" ", Are you mad? Man, what does this mean? Raddle .report to me the state of things at the next gun." "Aye, aye, sir;" and the officer left. Tim said to Raddle: ,c Do you think they will fight?" "I hope so----" "Lord! I hope not. They'll make a general from you who saved a female from devouring flames. You rushed magnanimnously in and heroically out of them." "I did, with my own Dianez, whom I lost at Gibraltar." '  "I never heard of any such ship being lost." "Come," said Raddle,'"I must go on deck auld report the state of the chase." A gun was heard, and Tim said '"What is the use? the chase is reporting herself." "5 March, you slop-steali lg beggar, or I will stir you up with my bayonet."' v' Stab me in the back I Lord I Lord! the last of the Treacles will be lost.?' They left, and immediately after a sound like that of many steps was heard bn, deck, followed by shouts, and Falkner, Hearton and Manly came below. Falkner laughed merrily, and,said : ' Ha, ha I gentlemen, you see I knew the robber was about to tack, and a long reach now will shorten our distance from him."' "She is handled by a true seaman, sir, and obeys the helm like a court lady. -It is a comfort to a sailor to see such things at sea." "True, 5Manly," said Falkner.' "There is pleasure in a chase like this, when I feel like the poet's winged avenger. The viewless winds seem the coursers that fear me, and old Ocean's besom my battle-field. There is no joy like the wild enthusiasm of a master's conflict. I could sing like a gitl in a dance, or a sailor at a fair, or a negro at Punch and JAudy. My brave fellows, fortune is before you; a mine of wealth is in that vessel-enough to make a cook'a peer, if money could make a gentleman."  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7606-00000047"/> 96        THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. "Is the pirate, then, so rich?" said Manly. "He is rich as Crcesus. But go on deck, M1r. Manly, and plump a shot or two into the chase. Spoil her wings, Manly." "Depend on me, sir."           / "Hearton," said Falkner, ' I never seemed more gay, yet to you that have known me long, I will confess a secret presentiment of death or sorrow."  ". Death, sir!"              i "Answer not. I have no time for words. Take these keys'; if I fall, you will find directions about my property. For aught I know, I was born on the sea, and would wish to die upon its bosom." "Born at sea!" "An old seaman, who brought me up, found me at sea. I had this chain and locket around my neck. It is the portrait of I know not whom--perhaps my mother. I may never know."       A shot was heard, and the captain sang out: "Bravo, Manly! Did you reach her?" "Yes, sir; we saw the splinters fly." L Good! Try her again." Belford entered, and said, "The governor, sir, is dying; he raves for his daughter, and says she is on board the pirate ship." "Heaven forbid!" said Falkner. Hearton, go on deck and give them the benefit of your experience, while I visit this unhappy man." The master left, and Ralph Raddle joined the captain. " Our shot, sir, be playing the devil with the pirate, and Mr. 'Manly bid me tell you 'they are hoisting out their boats.' "They have, perhaps," said Belford, " scuttled 'he ship--  "And now, like rats, leave a sinking vessel. We must not lose the gold, nor you t he lady. Look to her father, Belford, while I do my best to lay the Wizard alongside the enemy. Cheer up man I all may yet be well." The captain left for the deck.   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.            9 C H AP T ER    III. THE ODEATHr-BED. DON JOSE lay on a'couch in the captain's cabin, evidently suffering deeply, while by his side was his Lieutenant Feraguez, who, to give even a bad man his due, had been assiduous in his attentions to his un- fortunate master :  ' Be silent, excellenza, they say the Wizard gains on, the pirate. You will see your daughter again." "Will they not see my guilt? I shall again see my child--yes, yqee  It may be tobJear her curse her felon father. The mocking world will point me out, andi, scorn's loud, voice will cry: "Behold the cheated robber!" Would I had died upon the shore il fire and agony, rather than meet the present hour." He sank back, overcome by the effort he had made. Belford came in, and said," Courage, sir! Thec pirates abandon. their vessel, and a Tfew short minutes will place us alongside Y A great commotion and shouting were heard  a odeck, and Belftart; said: ,( Hearton--Manly--what iewss?" Hearton replied: ",A boat from -the pirate ship comies towards usa and a female dress is floating in'the wind." t "Ha! my daughter! mny daughter!" said Dooi Jose; "I hail see heer again." "Save her, Maunly!, save her!"Said Belford. "Heaven grant it .may be so!' and he hurried from the cabin of the dying man.  'It is .plain they heve se uttled and deserted the ship. I:',wil! see, though." WNild with joy, Don Jose exclaimed : . Does she sink?. Ha!;' all evi- dence of my crime sinks with her ;" and he laughed hiaterioally, until he fainted in Feragueez's arms.-"            . Falkner and Belford entered the cabin, while the neise and shouting on deck continued.            .  It is a cruel disappointment, Belford. I thought, when I :aawa female in the boat, that the pirate relented and had returned ,yourlady. -Courage, though, man Hshe mnay not be on board. I have o'rdeed all in the boat to be brought below." "Steady!" ".Throw the rope 1" ' Heav,-ol" and similar nautical commands,wereheard on' deck; a:ndv iVdoii'/e e:xi .I.....  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7606-00000048"/> THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.   "He sent him," said the quadroon, "lto urge0you to come alongside, that he might fire the train and blow all to destruction." "Villain!-but he is taken," said Falkner. "Never!" said Weevil; " he threatened to destroy himself, the ship, the gold. and, the girl-and the rascal laughed triumphantly." ' Let him do it, but do not lift your hand," said Nanhy. "Speak plainly." Manly rushed in, and said, "There is a struggle on the pirate's deck. jTwo men contend and the woman shrieks." Belford and Manly rushed on deck, while Weevil muttered to him- self ': What can this mean?-Truck was secured below." I cut 'is lashings!" said the quadroon, exultingly. "Curse on 'you, hag!"-and seeking to rush on her, he fell, tearing the bandages from his wound. Let me die!-let me die!" "This is horrible!" said the captain. The old quadroon seized the captain's arm: "Pray," said she, "that he whom you pursue may die before you meet." She took the por- trait from the captain's breast, and said: "Listen! That was your mother, and the pirate is your brother. Your mother, Lady Monte- ville, was-" Don Jose had partially recovered, and rushed forward, saying: "Who mentioned Monteville? All are dead save--  Who, though, are you?" He spoke to the quadroon; and slowly recalling her features through the lapse of thirty years, exclaimed: Yes, 'tis Manguette, the nurse. Heaven has sent more witnesses." After gazing fiercely on him, she said: "Yes, Heaven does! . Murderer! fratricide! villain!-I know your' guilt." She sprang at the throat of the wounded man, and would have strun- gled him; but was finally, with great difficulty, torn away. Manly and several sailors entered the cabin, and Falkner placed his hand upon his heart and said, "He never more will see his child."  It is the judgment of God," said the old woman. The, dead bodies of Weevil and Don Jose were borne away, while Falkner went on deck to learn the condition of the chase, determined to inquire into all the particulars of the mysterious woman. When there, Manly approached him, and said: All is plain, for we can see that the lady is a prisoner on deck." Can he be my brother? Oh God, I shall go mad!"   &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7606-00000049"/> O ;Q0      THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. C H A PTER     IIV. THE FINALE. THE two vessels lay in the open sea, and far in the distance, so rapidly had they sailed, were seen the highlands of Cuba. Even at that distance, the perfume of the land breeze was perceptible--as great a rebuke to the terrible scene being enacted, as if the incense of the altar had been burned in the slaughter-house, The occupants of the decks of the two vessels were plainly visible to.;each other, and pre- sented most dissimilar features. That of the man-of-war was crowded with men, all watching the scene with the greatest anxiety, while at the wheel stood the Unknown, with none near him except poor [sabinda, who was bound with her hands to the binnacle. Through the bulwark, which the Wizard!s shot had crushed, lay an armory of pistols, and the pirate captain stood gazing at her with an eye full of gloating passion and deep revenge. Isabinda looked at the pistols. ;i,' iraggling to obtain one, -said : "Could I but .get one of those . ca lolns, I would at least have life and death in my own hands. Fathelr. father, sad was the day when you confided your own honor and your daughter to the care of an outlaw and a pirate. Merciful Providence, protect!-all hope is vain-that villain approaches me!" The pirate drew near. "The. helm," said he, " is lashed down; the running gear is made secure--ha,.ha! ,we hold our own, and the British will not easily regain the distance lot in heaving too for Weevil. Bride of the pirate, is it not joyous thus' to ride on the wings of destruction? Come, you xill love me for this bold manoeuvre." "You cannot escape.';         '  "I more-than hope it." He looked through his,glass at the deck of the Wizasrd, and, said:' "There is coimmotion there." As he spoke, the sails of the vessel were let fall. !He continued; "Can I believe my eyes?  They are tired of this obiase. Hooras! hoors! you coward dogs! What made you leave this noble boat, never before matched on all the broad seas? They selnd a boat. Think they I will heave to, to aid their trick I  Girl, you are now mine!" A  boat pulled from the vessel towards the pirate, and slowly but certainly grew more distinct.   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.          161 Isabinda had forgotten herself, and exclaimed, "Father, father, shall I see you no more?"- "You will not; you leave a felon father to become an outlaw's bride. Aye, a fitting match. It is well a fog is rising. The Wizard has lost his magic wand ; they make for the bay. By Heavens, I believe they, fear me!" And the Wizard did turn its bow towards the land, and in a. few. moments was completely hidden by the dense fog which nearly obscured the whole horizon. "All hope is lost. A reckless madness is now rushing on me. Though the waters swept over me, I would be glad to die." She strug- gled to free herself, but paused and said: "What would I do? Suicide! Peril my soul's salvation I Oh, save me! save me!" She knelt at the binnacle, and the pirate stood by, closely watching the closing mist. Isabinda was however startled, by hearing a piece of cord fall almost at her very feet. She started, looked aloft, and see- ing Truck, uttered a shriek which at once brought her captor, her. Truck, in the meantime, hid himself behind the immense sail.  "What means that shriek?" "My wrist is broken," said the poor girl, " and the cords crush inmy arm." The pirate unbound her. "Po6r girl," said he, " why should I play. the monster longer? We must not part. I will bear you to a land where pleasure waits your call, with wealth obedient at its beck. I will bow to you I love, as I have not done to the world I hate. What might I not have been, as yet unconquered in might of intellect by mortal man, bad the pure eye of this bright angel only smiled on me before crime had sullied my hand! We are alone on the waters. Youa are in my power, yet I harm you not. My foes are baffled, and I triumph. I am, -however, yet your slave. Yes, I repeat, despisingr human foes, hunted and branded, I bow to virtue and to you, a humble slave."      M The outlaw knelt, and Isabinda, in spite of her awful condition, could but pity him. During this conversation, Truck had descended the mast, and slowly advanced on-his hands and knees towards the binnacle. Never did a cat advance more stealthily on its prey-so that he seemed rather  moving shadow than a thing of life. He gradually passed around the mast, to the spot where the armory of pistols we have before spoken of were deposited. Selecting carefully the largest and apparently the  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7606-00000050"/> 102       THE'WIZARD OF THE WAVE. deadliest, he sprang on his -feet, and seizing the robber by the shoulder, said : "Now, Mr. Devil, or whatever you are, surrender: Aim I betrayed?"' said the Unknown; " and he, too rapidly to be prevented, discharged it at Truck. The old coxswain was not easily taken aback; but, placing his pistol at the pirate's throat, returned the compliment. All seemed terminated, for the pirate fell on deck, and Isabinda fainted in the arms of the rough soldier. A distant shout was heard, which recalled Truck's attention to what he had to do, and looking at his jacket, through which his antagonist's ball had made a hole, he said,: "My precious eyes! Master Tom, you had a nice escape there! Hark, Miss, Marm, my lady I that shouting 'we hear is from the boat that left the ship before this fog came on. Shall I hail them? for you be captain of this craft now." "Do not. Perhaps it may be some the crew who deserted the ship and are now on their return. See if he be dead."! ' No, Marm ; but my eyes! is it not like the captain-gold chain and all?" ' They come, do they not?" "Yes, they do."  He cast the wheel loose, and said, "t O, Lord, if you have only a catspaw for other people, give old Tom a capful." A hail was heard from the mist, and Isabinda recognized Belford's vorce. So, too, did Truck, who exclaimed: c, That is a trumpet I am used to. ' "Truce ahoy!" was the challenge. "Truce ahoy!" replied Truck. "Truce, ay? That is Mr. Belford's voice. I suckled him. Ho i ho! give way." During this conversation, the pirate captain had revived and turned to'a spot where. he saw a hatchet,; with this he advanced towards Truck, who was busy at the helm, and would doubtless have cut him down, had not the young girl called out and put him on his guard. The sailor, however, caught the weapon in his hand, and threw the villain on the deck, where he would have despatched him, had not Isabinda prevented him. c, Very well, Marm. I won't, but he is a precious chap! Curse me, if he knows when he is dead i  Give way, lads, with a-will," shouted he to the boat; c" and here goes for shortening the distance." He placed the spokes of the wheel in the young girl's hands, and cut   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.          103 away the halyards and clew-lines, and proceeded with the other ropes. Scarcely had he done so, when a boat appeared alongside, and Belford and the quadroon. appeared on the pirate's deck. t"It is he!" said Isabinda. We need not describe how the young girl rushed into his arms, and how fervently and passionately he kissed her. All the troubles they had undergone seemed atoned for, and the misery of the last twenty-four hours lost in oblivion. Truck pulled the old quadroon on board, and would have embraced her, but she repelled- him, and said: "- Back, fool! Is he alive?" Shle rushed to the pirate, and when she saw his condition, exclaimed: "Theodore! Theodore! Lost--for- ever lost " "Yes, nurse, you have Jived to see the. pirate founder. You must lighten my deaths darkest hours. Is this mother's picture . Was it placed on iny neck by her hand 2 Are, you dying, Theodore?" ;6 Yes, I die-quick, and tell me!" ' That is her picture. She placed it around your neck when the murderers tore you and your twin brother from her bosom and se!; you adrift on the wild, wild ocean, with your poor old nurse." "'What, nurse, was the name?" ' Your father was Earl of Monteville." The pirate sought to rise, and looked proudly around. "Then," said he," ][ was born of no common stock-a lordly descent. How know you this?"' L I know-I nursed you jfrom the hour of your birth. .But listen, Theodore: I come from your brother, the brave Falkner, with an offer of the means of escape. Your pursuer is your brother."  'Ha!" said he, " my brother! Then no other blood than my own could overcome 'me. Falkner my brother I Therefore were we so much alike. Brave brothers! Now I glory in you. Foundlings as we were on the ocean, side by side we might have- fought our way to fame. Let no one know his brother was a pirate. Mother, dear mother, plead for me l" The pirate kissed his mother's picture, and died: "The scene was one worthy of comment. There were two men even physically alike andsitmilar. The one, falling like seed on the ground into good hands, had Jbecome a credit to himself and his country, while the name of the other had become an opprobrium. Many'a mother ,                    .  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7606-00000051"/> THSE WIZARD OFP THE WAVE.   atrocities. When the Wizard reached the spot whret the vessel had been, not a vestige was- seen, and the vast treasures he had on board, among which was that stolen by the unfortunate Don Jose, had gone to the depth of the sea; Some day we may attempt to describe the search for it, and its retrieval. "-4. CONCLUt S I ON'. THE RETURN. WHEN the explosion took place, the boat in which Falkner and Isa- binda were, turned and was rowed rapidly to relieve Truck and the quadroon. It was time to attend to the injuries he had received, and the weight of the old woman sadly encunibered him. The whole party reached the vessel, where every care was given to Isabinda, and the vessel tacked and returned to Santiago de Cuba. The fact of the gov- ernor's defection was already known, and an officer had arrived from a neighboring port to replace him. To the new comer Feraguze endeav- ored, in spite of the wishes of Fainer not only to shield the unfortu- nate man, but to hide every trace which related to the career of his unfortunate brother. It was however impossible to do so, and th'e sharp exigencies of the Spanish law-the executioner and garrote-soon- brought him to the end of'his days. Donna Capella and her niece welcomed Isabinda with kindness and' boisideration; and as' she had now no protector, the scruples of her father's old chaplain and confessor, on the score of Belford's Protestant principles, were finally overcomne, and she was united to the accom- plished and fasciiating lieutenant. The felicity of these ardent lovers was now unbounded. The greatest' demonstrations of joy were exhibited' throughout sabind's large cir- cle of friends and acquaintance, and the( Ceremonials of the wdding day were enlivened not only with the wit of Tom Truck and the face- tious details of the' bridegroom, but: with the hilarity and boisterous merriment of some' of thebhoiceet spiris of the British navy--nd even the aforetime mysterious Falkner seemed- ow entirely divesteda of his infernal traits, and exceed'ed the others, if possible, in enhandcig tie already overiowflig cup' of joy. /  in a  few days the immense quantity of treasures left by the i     &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7606-00000052"/> 106.       THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE. the: lovely Posada on the sea-shre, was taken on board the Wizard as a-lawful prize; and the, dJisclosures, made by the pirate to Isabinda of otler hiddenrliches, together with the valuable jewels found upon the person of the governor at ,the time of his-death, conferred upon Bel- ford and his beloved bride a most ample fortune .  The Dianez whom it will be remenibered Radidle had spoken of to Treacle, was found to be the one he had lost in Malta; and at the same time that Belford and Isabinda were married, Dianez took the brave marine for better or worse. The Wizard, with her rich cargo, sailed for Jamaica, taking with her all who have figured in our, tangled web; and, after a few days, was despatched to England, where, Falkner, on producing the evidence of his splendid achievements, received the promotion he so richly deserved. Years rolled by, and the post-captain became an admiral, and the evi. dence which he had obtained from the old quadroon enabled him to recover the title of the Earl of-Monteville. Raddle and D ianez were dependents of his lordship, and lived happily and cheerfully at their sylvan :home, which was not far from the castle of the admiral, the Earl of Monteville. Let us pass many years. The earl bad married, and children grew up around him--the eldest of .whom, the Viscount Borden, saw and loved the dark-eyed daughter of Admiral Sir Eustace Belford, Our readers in him will recognize an old acquaintance, and the occasion of the marriage was celebrated in the richest manner. Oxen were roasted whole, peasants danced on the greern and fire-works were dis- charged. The dower of the bride consisted of the jewels which the unfortunate Don Jose had on his person when he died, and the settle- ment on the groom was formed in no small degree from the money which the pirate had purloined from the mines. All thoughts of unpleasantness, however, were removed, and the union of the two families was made complete., Let us leave them-here, with the single statement that Tom -Truck became the valet and confident of the earl, whom he used sometimes to berate atrociously, and of whom be used to, say," Blast my eyes -if I do not think his lordship, after all, is the devili!"  1  Tim Treacle kept an inn not far from the castle, and used to tell adamiring bumpkins of the famous fight he had with the pirate, in which ihe wonimmortal glory., Manly died a post-captain, and Hearton was laid up in -ordinary, as the Master'of Greenwich Hospital. An honor wasl in store for him.- Bluff Kitng William, the midshipman king, the only sailor except   THE WIZARD OF THE WAVE.          107 Canute who ever sat on the English throne, visited: his pensioners. Hearton was in uniform; and after a full examination of all the details, and calling around him those of the old veterans whom he remembered, he turned to the old master. He was old and gray, and reverently uncovered to the kirg, whom when a boy he had taught to splice the  ropes: "Give me your sword, Mr:; Heartoni." The master obeyed.            " ' "Kneel down!" He knelt. The king placed the accolade on his shoulder, and said "Arise, Sir Philip Hearton, a Knight of my Bath!" We have disposed of all of our characters, and here end for ever our story. THE Fti'   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>