<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd" xml:id="VAC7511">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Rambles in Chili and Life Among the Araucanian Indians in 1836 </title>
            <author >Will, the Rover (b. 1817)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7511</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Rambles in Chili and life among the Araucanian Indians in 1836</title>
                  <author >Will, the Rover (b. 1817)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >88 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >D.J. Starrett</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Thomaston [Me.] </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1851">1851</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-10-24">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5. Inserted OCR text. Linked image files</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Rambles in Chili and life among the Araucanian Indians in 1836</head> 
            <p>
               <pb  n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7511-00000001"/>AND LIFE AMONG THE&#xD;
'AIAUC ANIAI I DI lS&#xD;
IN 1836.&#xD;
PUBLISHERS NOTICE.&#xD;
p&#xD;
This book may be regarded as one of the varieties of the day. It is difficult to&#xD;
canceive, while perusing these Lamnbleswtere adventures so excititig and thrilling&#xD;
are so forcibly told, that it is a true and veritable narrative; but such,we assure the&#xD;
reader is the fact. The natural scenery in that sunny region is painted in the glow.&#xD;
ing tints of a faithfut picture. The character of that singular people, the Arauenni.&#xD;
ans; the lofty and magnanimous bearing of their warriors; the lovely. confiding,&#xD;
and affectionate dispositions of the rimaidenus, arc all beautifully delineated; and so&#xD;
vididly are the various scenes portrayed, that we s een to be transported to the field&#xD;
where they are etacte.l, and feel; the varied emotions of the actors. If some of&#xD;
these adventures and incidents, were related in a romance, the leader would prob.&#xD;
ably say they were exaggerated, so much mre strange is truth than fiction.&#xD;
THOMASTON&#xD;
D. 3. STARR ETT-PUBLISHER,&#xD;
1851.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="" xml:id="VAC7511-00000002"/>&#xD;
K~&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
ENTEaCD according to an act of Congress, i the year 1850,&#xD;
BY C'ORTHELL &amp;amp; KAMES,               ,&#xD;
Tn th   (CimvPs (OfFhe of the United States District Court of Maine&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
ADVERTISEMENT.&#xD;
The following Narrative was originally written without the least idea of publi-&#xD;
cation, for the Author's own amusement-a mere whim of the hour, "to perpetu-&#xD;
ate the remembrance of the thing," while it was fresh upon his mind; and ,to&#xD;
drive away ennui while a sailor on board the Chilian Brig of War "Achilles."&#xD;
At the solicitation of a few friends, it has recently been re-written in portions&#xD;
each week for the "Lincoln Miscellany." The task has been performed at such&#xD;
intervals as-the writer could spare fr'rm his daily labors, when his mind was har-&#xD;
assed with business matters :--le was, therefore, no less surprised than gratified,&#xD;
at the the indulgence and favor with which his hasty production was received&#xD;
during the course otf its pub ication in the "Miscellany." These pages have been&#xD;
printed in signatures weekly, just as they appeared in the paper, and if they are&#xD;
faulty. so be it.; the reader must supply the corrections, he being the only one who&#xD;
has had an opportunity to do so.&#xD;
These remarks are not presented to excuse errors, or avert criticism ; the writer&#xD;
is aware that he must bear the blame of the former, let him be guilty or not guil-&#xD;
ty; and he is quite willing to "bide the pelting storm" of the latter; his sole ob-&#xD;
ject having been-without any attempt at author-craft-to furnish those who re-&#xD;
quested, and others who may choose to read these "Rambles," a "plain, unvar-&#xD;
nished tale" of a sailor's adventures.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="" xml:id="VAC7511-00000003"/>&#xD;
OPINIONS OF THE PRESS.&#xD;
"7 The Lincoln (Thomaston, Me,) Miscellany is Publishing an original and&#xD;
highly interesting work entitled "Rambles in Chili,and hfe among the Araucanian&#xD;
Indians," by an annonyrnous author. * *  *  We can heartly pronounce it a&#xD;
work of rare merit. It combines richness of description, with thrilling incidents&#xD;
and marvellous adventures; and abounds in well painted delineations of manners&#xD;
and customs, useful observations of society, and accurate geographical history.&#xD;
The unobtrusive interblendingof a racy humor with the general flow of the narra-&#xD;
tive, will give it a popularity but little inferior to "Melville's Typee." The Aran.&#xD;
canians are an independent race of Indians, inhabiting the southern part of Chili,&#xD;
whom the Spaniards have never yet conquered ; and any account ot them cannot&#xD;
fail of being highly interesting. The work is likely to be widely read.&#xD;
[Norfolk County Journal&#xD;
It is put forward as an authentic narrative, and many of the scenes appear too&#xD;
natural and life like to be an invention of the author. The very minuteness and&#xD;
novelty of the details-preserve it from the charge of being an imaginary work.&#xD;
It is, however, a striking proof of the fact that truth is stranger than fiction, being&#xD;
full of stirring adventures, vivid scenes. and hair breadth escapes.&#xD;
The writer has given a very spirited deseiption' of the country through which&#xD;
he fravelled, and his pen has lent to some of the scenes and things portrayed an&#xD;
indescribable charm. He appears desirous to remain incognito, and uses a ficti-&#xD;
tious cognomen. Upon the whole it is a book well worth reading, which in this&#xD;
age of literary inundation, is saving uch in its favor.  [Weekly Mirror.&#xD;
It is a highly entertaining and instructive tale, giving a true and humorous de.&#xD;
lineation of the manners and custants of the Chilians ; a correct description of&#xD;
the scenery in and about the cities of Valparaiso and Talcahuano ; with a novel&#xD;
and interesting account of a three months sojourn 4rnong a nation of Idians, to.&#xD;
tally ignorant of any previous intercourse with white men.&#xD;
It opens with a sketch of sea life. The principal part of the work, however,&#xD;
is a true narrative of an actttl journey through the count'rv, by two fugitive sail-&#xD;
ors ; and the story of their adventures, reckless daring, and hair breadth escapes&#xD;
is another proof that "truth is stranger than fiction."  Although with little pre'&#xD;
tension to author-craft, the narrative is embellished with some of the most excit-&#xD;
ing and romantic scenes imaginable, and again with others the most comical. It&#xD;
is full of marvellous adventures, perilous journeyings, and glowing pictures of sce-&#xD;
nery and luxuriant nature.                               [Miscellany.&#xD;
We have heard many commendations of it, as abounding in variety of incidents,&#xD;
d natural and lively description.                [Lime Rock Gazette.&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
t '             C  f~f  r U"  r u 1  © f U U  t t te 1 ~  " ,&#xD;
&#xD;
'tA~~W..&#xD;
&#xD;
flTT A- nsm-t,-r .r&#xD;
&#xD;
u          ,         .&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAFTER&#xD;
9yw sfedsand neighbors, ar me tell  that her head and bows turned&#xD;
s'mp14 tale ; and mark me ell,  one direction and then another&#xD;
g m plain style may sound uncouth,&#xD;
It yields naught' else than bitter tuth.  having lost its power, was lashed&#xD;
Whit I have seen has been concealed  ships, and the helmsman sOO4&#xD;
Somewhat, till iow, from other ears;  Over the taf-rail,gazingdQWnon1th&#xD;
ray tonguehyevex iliresedled  sy surface of the clear blue wg&#xD;
,hT, scenes that marked my earlier years." him.&#xD;
On. a calm, pleasant evening in the  The courses hung in their brail&#xD;
month of March, 1836, might have been 'tiffuly festooned beneath the yar4&#xD;
seen off the coast of Chili, a solitary the top-sails as they flappedidly,&#xD;
bark tossing and worrying about on 4,the masts, kept tnie zithfthe  t&#xD;
long undulating swell that came rollingjand rolling of the ufl. Mihe tj-&#xD;
ib from the westward. Her hull and rigdails were dewed up and the yard&#xD;
ging betokened that .she was Americantield upon the cap; the watch&#xD;
and had any one been still in doubt of lows that they were-were nii&#xD;
her nationality, her sails would have sat- them, caulking, when they'shouf&#xD;
isfied thqn upon that point.  A still leen walking the deck, and awal&#xD;
nearer survey would have revealed to the their duty. But the sailors w*ho ire&#xD;
observer, three boats, suspended by tack- out responsibility, feel -that afde'&#xD;
les from her sides; she was in nautical they can get, during their watch&#xD;
parlance "a s uter," manning three is so much clear gain, eons Vqiit&#xD;
boats, with a crew of twenty-five men, will steal a nap when they can'6o o&#xD;
all told, and registering two hundred and impunity ; and, on a warm, still,&#xD;
fifty toes.                         night, it is diffctIlt foreev  he  Iie&#xD;
There she lay so completely becalmed keep awake.&#xD;
&#xD;
first ii&#xD;
-44&#xD;
&#xD;
s  - t  E:&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7511-00000004"/>&#xD;
10&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILL&#xD;
&#xD;
In this instance the officer is on the alert&#xD;
He has been promenading the starboard&#xD;
side of the quarter deck, looking first on&#xD;
one side, then on the other, or occasional-&#xD;
ly wetting his finger with his mouth, and&#xD;
holding it up to ascertain if any air is stir-&#xD;
ing, until he finally 'imagines a slight&#xD;
agitation of the atmospheric particles.&#xD;
Convincing himself of this fact, he gives&#xD;
the helmsman a poke which disturbs his,&#xD;
reverie, and callfhim back to his post, or&#xD;
rather to his tiller.&#xD;
"Haul in your starboard' braces!" he&#xD;
calls out to the men, who jump up al-&#xD;
most bewildered at first, but quickly re-&#xD;
covering themselves, the yards are braced&#xD;
up and the fore-tack boused well out to&#xD;
the eat-head.&#xD;
413Bend on to the main-tack and board&#xD;
him check'home, then lay aft to the&#xD;
"hi lower sails were speedly trimmed&#xD;
;',the order given to "sheet home top'&#xD;
g 1it-sails, and set them!"&#xD;
Whpn all was completed, the little puf&#xD;
had increase to a fine gentlebreeze, and&#xD;
th  ails began to swell out before the&#xD;
w iht of moving wind, spreading their&#xD;
e cave surface to the freshening breeze&#xD;
Son the water began to ripple in hec&#xD;
wake 4s she -dashed through the brine&#xD;
bdwing gracefully to the propelling pow&#xD;
e   wich was speeding her boldly for&#xD;
warct&#xD;
" Keep her a good rap full !" said the of&#xD;
.to1 the man at the helm, who, (bet&#xD;
p   on. reader, for not introducing mygeI&#xD;
bof ,);was'   hurmbl servant; the:&#xD;
agaiddressing me, he injured;&#xD;
"bodyou new strop that jewel'Woci&#xD;
o    tjio fore.topgallant yard to-day7&#xD;
T answered in thindafirmative,&#xD;
&#xD;
"How is the one on the top-sail yard ?"&#xD;
he again inquired.&#xD;
I informed him that I had put some&#xD;
new service on that also, and concluded&#xD;
that it would answer for some time yet.&#xD;
"Keep her off then, two points.&#xD;
Steady!" says he. "Let her go along&#xD;
north by west:! Rig out the top-mast-&#xD;
stun-sail boom, and reeve off the halyards!&#xD;
we will put the muslin on her,' said the&#xD;
officer joyfully, as he walked forward to&#xD;
see his orders executed.&#xD;
Two or three men instantly sprang&#xD;
aloft; the geer was rove and bent on,&#xD;
and the sail took its place on the weath-&#xD;
er leech of the fore-top-sail.&#xD;
Send . out that top-gallant-stun-sail,&#xD;
while you'r in the top I" shouted the ofi-&#xD;
cer of the deck, and in a jiffy thae'also&#xD;
went laughing aloft, to lend its feeble aid&#xD;
in tugging along the heavy hull.&#xD;
Away we now went, booming over' the&#xD;
- heaving bosom of the ocean, our canvas,&#xD;
decked bark rising and falling with the&#xD;
I gentle undulations, as ngracenilly athe&#xD;
I village belle, while recetVing her gaf'ad-&#xD;
mirers7 Thus we 'edntinued 'on through&#xD;
r the whole of the watch, the breeze stif-&#xD;
, aning as the night advanced; btt not a&#xD;
r cloud was to be seen, the stars were out&#xD;
, in all their beauty, striving to out-shine&#xD;
- each oter, while the moon ws appar-&#xD;
- ently doing her best to convince the&#xD;
world that she was as lhnportant a utnin'-&#xD;
f- ary as the sutn,&#xD;
g   We continued in this manner aboit&#xD;
f cour hours, when 'a sudden squal struck&#xD;
n its without any premonitory ymptons, or.&#xD;
warning whatever, It was "what sailors'&#xD;
k, call a "white squall,",&#xD;
snap went the top-mast.studdingself&#xD;
boom, 5cs by the yardI and aWR  lenV&#xD;
&#xD;
.&#xD;
'&#xD;
F&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBiifld IN OHILI.   .                     I&#xD;
the °sal flutteriing far to the leeward with  At this jucture, n   dingcf s  ret&#xD;
the smaller studding-shil afte it, in full upon us! Whit Watek Mas discby E&#xD;
chase. The bark ias suddenly thrown close upon our taioard bow M!ie&#xD;
u on  her  side,  the  timbers  and  spars  were  we  to  the  breakois that  weena arv&#xD;
creeking and snapping 'with the heavy hear thenm roar even abova e tr fat&#xD;
pressure, and the whole ship groaing as wind. The d anger nVe aidufst scaM&#xD;
if she knew her time had coipe.     as "Scylla," met us now a  Ch rbdi.'&#xD;
" Hard up your helm! Let go the hal-  " Ready a-bout !" roaiedlie&#xD;
yards! Haul up the mainsaill! clew but it was too late; just :as the' hafQ bek&#xD;
down the top-sails ! Brail up the span- gan to come into the wind,:and pitch in&#xD;
ker . were the orders given in rapid sue- the heavy swell, she rolld to windywrd,&#xD;
cession, and as rapidly executed by the with her taf-rail under, and as t. w4r&#xD;
vigilant crew, who had all come on deck came pouring in on deck,,she whired&#xD;
at the first alarm-though they had not with a. sea, and her ;bows rose  dfell&#xD;
blien called,--and were at work with right with a jar, that knocked us alkfrw ppj&#xD;
good'earnest.                       perpendiculars ! She was ,fasTP P  a&#xD;
T ogallant-sails were gone; liter. rock!                    t&#xD;
ally blown into atoms ! but the top-sails  I jumped on the heel of thphowspi&#xD;
still held, pressing the bark fearfully over and went ,ut as far as thr tight-h e4&#xD;
on her side, the water coming up nearly to examinlour situation. It '&#xD;
to the combings of the hatches,     momentary danger, the:rook w  fe #&#xD;
She remained on her beam-ends, ap; nately so deep in the water thet he&#xD;
parently some fifteen or twenty minutes sel's-fore-foot had settled ondits Isrnoth&#xD;
ere shoe righted, when .she- finally came round surface, where "it hunglong ego.&#xD;
ip slowly and grddualli to her bearings, for another sea to :lift her clear; he&#xD;
The Dicke ,had sprung into the weather he slid off, and away, she welit,, likle&#xD;
unyards with an axe, when the captain steed that has lost its rider." She we&#xD;
fortu lately' heckd himn firing,  soon brought again under aooamaad the&#xD;
Hold drn bit, my man, let's wait a pumps were sounded and thwel ms&#xD;
few itnieiits loner;'and those few rmo- ported empty; "to make ass rtierdqahlp&#xD;
Mionts deelded the case, in favor of the sure," they were sounded a . imb&amp;amp;en .t&#xD;
masts,' and they were providentially savedjtimes, and always with, theasme hap&#xD;
b Uhe squall was still severe, driving the result.&#xD;
bark mal y on. and throughh the sea,  We found that we had been aYri.ddb&#xD;
th her topeallyads on, thecap, and the the current and sea on to&#xD;
rTtl     han.4 oht. The winds howled Next morning we tempoa ri  pafr&#xD;
hearte orders of the captain, our damages;:and the captain eondluQd-&#xD;
Awld an, dismal chorus;  Away she to make for the port of Talethia  6&#xD;
kw hef  the waves which came   as' stock of fresh provisions hvi loeh&#xD;
Ug o  the odipled vessel, Whil th edy disappeared, and our watebttet&#xD;
h~ bamro5, cudling like a ruffle o'er low; we accordingly filed awy "&amp;amp;&#xD;
theia                              o fr  our*'s c   pory&#xD;
&#xD;
.&#xD;
&#xD;
1/ 1&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7511-00000005"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHIiU.&#xD;
&#xD;
e,    a genuine specimen of the&#xD;
en board. He went by&#xD;
me of sge Spunyarn, and "was a&#xD;
gf infinite jest."  His cockhey&#xD;
p       as amused me, and whenev-&#xD;
rppgrtuty offered, I would get&#xD;
d a~n some of his humorous&#xD;
y~~     wibiebhe had a bountiful stock at&#xD;
j  m pnd.&#xD;
THE COCKNEY'S YARN.&#xD;
3oe was sitting on the end of the wind-&#xD;
';   the eve after our late adventure,&#xD;
*ith a large quantity -of the Virginia&#xD;
*eedstuffedinto his cheek, singing" Hey&#xD;
Betty Mattin, tip toe tye," and looking&#xD;
bat dilihaily good natured, when I&#xD;
clapped him on the shoulder, saying,&#xD;
#tWf6'6JU  .' are bond into port, at&#xD;
it  f- jX1 fl56 k ed at nie a Moment, and&#xD;
hrWfrlied,"" why, this halftnothin to&#xD;
what we'stayed lout hin a- bloody hold&#xD;
brdvk  r 'hin won't, called the Testi-&#xD;
th  # j (Desdemona) hof New  York.&#xD;
Why, we was hout hover sixteen months,&#xD;
llviiig hon orse beeft! I'll till yer habout&#xD;
that 'fge, 'twas the last but one hafore&#xD;
rI:s'hipped hin the bloody hold tub at&#xD;
Ne* York. The cap'n was han hold&#xD;
-yThati'ailed from 'Nantucket; 'e was&#xD;
omfacetoffa rum customer too,hand when&#xD;
'  ,been feting the nip, egad ! warnt 'e&#xD;
a reg'lar tyrant? you'd better believe 'e&#xD;
w4 ; "is face was has black, has a tar&#xD;
lu ket1 hand the red lighinin come hout&#xD;
,-eyslike fire hout hof a pistol.&#xD;
'.r t mate, bast 'is eyes! was one&#xD;
h aean pgq, what'll pick coppers&#xD;
ha do is man's heyes; strike a man&#xD;
r 'e'pwn; har lick 'is mother just&#xD;
4h9n gby's gois to .hip for tother world.&#xD;
Is naie was Brock, but the sailors called&#xD;
&#xD;
'im Bruin, which they s id ment bear,&#xD;
hand a bloody cross hold  ear,'e was&#xD;
too.&#xD;
Well, these two hold '6ttentots, used&#xD;
to 'orse us habout, like as bif we was a&#xD;
parcel a dogs. This 'ard usage, together&#xD;
with bad wittles made hus hall as&#xD;
cross as hold nick itselff; .hand we&#xD;
hadn't gone into nary port, as I said ha.&#xD;
fore, for as good as sixteen months, hand&#xD;
we 'ad hall got habout 'alf rotted with&#xD;
the scurvy. Hour bread got a moving&#xD;
habout hof hits hown hacord,, hi4-tle&#xD;
bread locker,for hit was like the Piv-pintg,&#xD;
pretty thickly in'abited ; hand theater;&#xD;
-jumpin Jubiter! 'twas as thick has mo&#xD;
lasses, hand smelt as bif ball the rats hin&#xD;
the bloody hold dug-hout 'ad' died biia&#xD;
the water-butt.   .&#xD;
We 'ad a little chap aboard that 'ailed&#xD;
from Halbany; 'e was a real spooney of&#xD;
a fellow, hand hin a storm 'e always&#xD;
looked just like a sick monkey, 'anging&#xD;
hon a lee-back-stay. Hold Bruin,-blast&#xD;
'is keyes, knocked this- little chap hover&#xD;
one day, hand broke one o'. 'is legs ; at&#xD;
that the crew began to think times was a&#xD;
gitten too, bloody 'ard; hand they put me.&#xD;
hup to hact as a kind of a horatp, hand I&#xD;
formed 'em into a kind hof company,&#xD;
hand marched em aft hin a body,&#xD;
Says'I,. "cap'u, we is hall dissatisfied&#xD;
with hour craft, hour usage, hand hour&#xD;
grub; hand more ner that, blood 'as been.&#xD;
spilt, hand murder 'as been committed&#xD;
hon the 'ighseas, hand we shall beetnged&#xD;
as, pirates hif, we allow this kind hof&#xD;
bloody manslaughter hany longer; so&#xD;
we've come aft'like a man to tell you we&#xD;
decline going the v'y'ge anty murder."&#xD;
When the hold devil seed us coming,&#xD;
was'nt 'e mad ? 'e kept; hinteisptin me&#xD;
&#xD;
Jl #   time, sayi nobody hadn't beer&#xD;
killgdo, "'twgrnt no. piracy to Break&#xD;
znan's leg.&#xD;
He  ussed hands habused me worser&#xD;
nor hifX was a riggar;band :hordered us&#xD;
hoff-to "'duty, buit we didn't budge tack&#xD;
nor sheet, handpIbegan.t9 getmore cowr&#xD;
agous has I found I 'ad pluck to back&#xD;
me. Well,''e hand hol: Bruin, rushed&#xD;
into the cabin for their pistols. I knowd&#xD;
wlhat they was harter, so says I, ' boys&#xD;
can you stand fire ?' hand they hall han&#xD;
swered "yes," hand then says I, "just&#xD;
scatter about 'ere, hand they can't wing&#xD;
more nor two hof hus, hand them what's&#xD;
left harter the broad-side, must board hin&#xD;
the smoke, hand give 'em Jessee."&#xD;
Well hafore long the bloody hold scul-&#xD;
lions come hup, foaming hand raving like&#xD;
mad, hand looking as cross as an hold&#xD;
,maid, as has lost 'er last chance hof mar-&#xD;
riage, because 4f er false teeth dropid&#xD;
bout haccidently.&#xD;
." Go forward !" 'ollard the cap'n, as&#xD;
loud as a she lion, roaring at a 'ottentot's,&#xD;
'eels ; but we didn't budge.&#xD;
"Shoot the d--d raskills," says 'e&#xD;
hand they both let split at hus at wons't.&#xD;
I felt sumthin running into my side,&#xD;
just like a 'ot hi'on, boring through hand&#xD;
through me.  Thinks I, hits hall day&#xD;
'with me, but I'll die game hany 'ow, so I&#xD;
made a dive aft, hand grappled hold'&#xD;
Bruin somewhere by 'is top-'amper, hand&#xD;
hif I did n't pay 'im hoffhin 'is hown coin,&#xD;
then hits none hof me. Hafter I 'ad got&#xD;
through-with my customer, I tuck a sur-&#xD;
key hof the battle-field like hany wictori-&#xD;
ous General. I seed the cap'n was full&#xD;
has bad hoff as hold Bruin. Both on 'em&#xD;
'ad their figure 'eads gritty well knocked&#xD;
hi.-&#xD;
&#xD;
0&#xD;
&#xD;
n  , f(q~icpntgy rtp&amp;amp;t frc   M&#xD;
hfver,(r t 4@'gtRgg by      in&#xD;
fore) thatlwas 'ullp4 'te  a4&#xD;
,water, hgbout iilips,  tp~&#xD;
t4 part hows'eyer }t, a&#xD;
Iostcen boy,as fjqeacassegr&#xD;
a glass hof g rog,gy"s 'u lp1i&#xD;
ps 'art, ha1d, kicke4jg bget  Vho&#xD;
sayn a word to-nobody.&#xD;
We lashed hour prisoners 'together&#xD;
hand stowed 'em haway hin the 'ole,&#xD;
hand left 'em settin hon the cool boil&#xD;
casks, looking ezactley like  eifo&#xD;
hon a lee-cat-'ead, smilin at a wet&#xD;
Harter that we cracked hon the canva&#xD;
hand spread hall o' kites, from the ffe-&#xD;
rail to the sky-sail-poles, hand haway we&#xD;
stuck 'er for St. Catherin's, for a 'arbor.&#xD;
The Dickey worked 'er bin; 'e was a&#xD;
first rate chap; 'e took no part hin the&#xD;
bloody foul play hof'is superiors, hand.w&#xD;
made 'im cap'n&#xD;
Whendve got hinto St. Catherin's, e&#xD;
released the bloody hold Hrabs from b-&#xD;
low, hand they hagreed to 'ush the whole&#xD;
matter hup, hand say nothin about it pS&#xD;
we just walked ashore hand hagreed4to&#xD;
say nothin neither side. We was 4appg&#xD;
to get clear hof the bloody hold -o:in at&#xD;
hany rate, hand I rather guess the hid&#xD;
coveys 'ad got about enough o' i #&#xD;
BJow me! hif that wasn't a 'ard e ts&#xD;
take hit by hand large, hand I bles&amp;amp;'&#xD;
stars that I -d got hout hon hit wo:wU&#xD;
as I did, without loosing the auabat&#xD;
my mess."&#xD;
Joe finished his yarn just as  0It&#xD;
bells were struck, and we turned is1to&#xD;
dream of the green fields, ripe&#xD;
and pretty girls that awaited us on t&#xD;
luxuriant soil of Chili. The scurv&#xD;
made its appearance  two ortri&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7511-00000006"/>&#xD;
A       ;+r6Ol dis s brought on  ldpo western side of the harbor of Talcahua.&#xD;
#e"idifie Waifobhealthy provisions: na. The dolphin with his rainbow tints&#xD;
6*4e riadethe hlaiid of Si. Ma. was glancing in beauty through the blue&#xD;
t it i4a 4 of Bio-bio looming up watersthe porpoise gamboled wildly about&#xD;
"e and.   beautiful breeze waft. us making the feathery brine his play&#xD;
0o '     as tie 'little cove of St. ground, while the hated shark followed&#xD;
n t  along thl narrow bluff that close on our track like retribution.&#xD;
4 d itslf northward, forming the&#xD;
FRd  ta&#xD;
r4r*                           '&#xD;
n                              1&#xD;
o a&#xD;
l    ue  -&#xD;
ar fe ~&#xD;
pow ou 4&#xD;
&#xD;
or~ib '&#xD;
1 #r ri&#xD;
W*  r   a w&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER II'&#xD;
&#xD;
I shall never forget the sensations of in their own peculiar lingo,"I&#xD;
pleasure and, happiness I experienced, nmi-ti, nuee-nuee  cow-cow&#xD;
when after having been-, nearly elevenwyhee-nees, ahw! mi-t, iid, t&#xD;
months t sea, we made the harbor of Tal.-fli-ti, nuee-nuee' h -na-liht&#xD;
cahuana, the port to which we weretcow-cow, ah! pwrix er "14W&#xD;
bound, for the purpose of replenishingory rendered ito  h d&#xD;
stock of water and fresh provisions, and cahuanM, aine pl e, plenty&#xD;
preparing for another lengthened cirise, ty girls, l very go  Th&#xD;
Yes, for eleven long months, had thethe contrary no good, plent&#xD;
old bark been buffeting the briny ocean Tlittle x to eat, go way shi&#xD;
as her rusty appearance plainly indica.!thp9ughont the entire ,row, t&#xD;
ted, The long grass arnd baracles had germi feeling of happen&#xD;
gathered above the copper; the coal-tar pated 'ustication on soe.&#xD;
othe bends was worn entirely off, nud  With a gegtli breego&#xD;
thof ew spits of paint which remained harbor, slowlysweepig  as&#xD;
upon the, hull, wore 4ingy and blistered(QQereqnno, and bo  ing&#xD;
by the sorohing sun. -Upon the whol0the eastern 1hre, eo 1on Ws&#xD;
ih~ was epl~a~ e ~ -Ing or  a~i ~ ~ ~ l ~   h   V&#xD;
hey mixed, unuth looking crew, intes4of m st anid r    berlo&#xD;
regard to outward appearances were At opening    to intlcaf  en&#xD;
m fn1is4for the shlp,               hung like pider  wes W i&#xD;
S   handmanmfested unbo nded Joy,W        madthree or&#xD;
at thop  pet of goingyinto port; even the lststho4 n       a&#xD;
ofr Kaakassw      had three on eoard. o    fuine rw:. t ,. je"&#xD;
two fom the Sandwich Islands, and one kor, 4n4wheny       0t&#xD;
from the Seelety Islanoeknan to ahsnt Wahgy toyh ,&#xD;
&#xD;
tii&#xD;
1&#xD;
-list&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7511-00000007"/>&#xD;
R    13  $f   oxuuL.                             I&#xD;
&#xD;
- AMB LES IN CHILL&#xD;
&#xD;
16&#xD;
&#xD;
topse, hauled down the jib, and, round-&#xD;
iL to, under her spanker, anchored the&#xD;
oldbark in five fathoms of water.&#xD;
We were soon afterwards boarded by&#xD;
the official dignitaries, accompanied by&#xD;
Capt Paul Delano, an American, who had&#xD;
esd d here for a number of years, and&#xD;
become somewhat distinguished, having&#xD;
been appointed Capt. of the Port..&#xD;
other boats from ship and shore were&#xD;
soon along side of us.' Friendly were the&#xD;
greetings, and curious the questions from&#xD;
all parties; welcome were the tidings&#xD;
we received from   home; only a few,&#xD;
however, were fortunate enough, to-get&#xD;
letters, although each voyager's face was&#xD;
ith  p~iety as, .he ship bundles&#xD;
y et eaft entered ito-th9&#xD;
r    tunate, wh&#xD;
t,   mmure with&#xD;
4 a  .d I9 rs of one, soon&#xD;
f T1&#xD;
e  ar    o       uan   is onep&#xD;
no        en eAkeena.p-&#xD;
d, m/ju ce to  its  beauty.  .It&#xD;
an4boced, and perhaps some&#xD;
ies  onekst to West? and four&#xD;
norh to soth. On the western I&#xD;
re     ardthe'sea, an elevated str iof&#xD;
l    iky    'ord           rees - and&#xD;
ne t ss fron the month 6f' the&#xD;
'istn efIbpr or five miles, up I&#xD;
V4M e ond the to vn or Talcahuana,&#xD;
western sie of the valley, inf&#xD;
oaisloated. - "a   jahua f&#xD;
&#xD;
:rn&#xD;
&#xD;
To the eastward of the Head, and along&#xD;
the eastern shore of the bay, the land is&#xD;
loir, one or two small villages, and the ruia&#xD;
of -others, are seen, scattered along the&#xD;
shore.- The town contained at the time&#xD;
of which I write,tabout one hundred&#xD;
houses, a church, and'custom house, with&#xD;
groceries and pulperies,, in abundance,&#xD;
and the ruins of a number of buildings,&#xD;
thrown down in the severe earthquake&#xD;
which happened the year previous, in the&#xD;
month of February.&#xD;
"Among the ruins, were the crumbling&#xD;
walls of the once famous Fort of Talca-&#xD;
htiana, which in its palmiest days would&#xD;
compare with Gibraltar, in point of&#xD;
strength ; it was the last stronghold of&#xD;
the-royalist, and iany of the old guns&#xD;
lay. scattered-r about. :Fronmm this place.&#xD;
"Osdtio" led out his grand.army of 8000&#xD;
menu which 4vavimfinally defdated,,Apxil&#xD;
5 $16  on  the.- plans ?of Mypu&#xD;
thus -establishing the imdependane of&#xD;
both Chili and Perd.      #{K-&#xD;
SI.shall not attempt to give an account&#xD;
ofmy-ecruisings here although 'theybiight&#xD;
possibly entertain the reader, btconmd at,&#xD;
one to the incidents niore immediately&#xD;
connected .with my rambles.  -   ,-&#xD;
O n Stinday evening' the third of Afril.&#xD;
m18%;seltin company with two bAii  '&#xD;
of oui ew had just rern d ba d&#xD;
frbm a visit to the FrihCes, of New"-6d.&#xD;
ordh, anad Paoffia&amp;amp;,, kf Na ntd6et, botW ufbli&#xD;
ships; homeward boun'd.&#xD;
We found that the stirboardwat chad&#xD;
-eturned from their day' liberty on shore&#xD;
nd one of them, a istot, brawny Pbr t-&#xD;
nese called  rnm'o,,had come on board,&#xD;
ust nougK intoxigatedto -benoisa&#xD;
u       e     a        b n e    ai&#xD;
~uar eIsome.  t was sopiwlierebetween&#xD;
ee  . }. nj&amp;amp; . ei  i.?... rht 4.* 'ciock We  Wdr ll BL&#xD;
&#xD;
htiid7el68ini. the fordea t , wrd I was&#xD;
siting bn' iiy- chest, #hi h served the&#xD;
double purpose of chair and -suppei' ta-&#xD;
ble, with 'my tin-ot of tea by My side;&#xD;
when the drunke  Portguesecameup,,&#xD;
and very provokingly, kicked it over. 1&#xD;
caught.the cup in time to save about half&#xD;
its contents, which in retaliation,.I threw&#xD;
diremly into his face. Hastily brushing&#xD;
the wet tea leaves from his eyes] he rpaut-&#xD;
tered a desperate. oath, and grasping 1hs&#xD;
sa1eatlr knife, he rushed,. upon me with&#xD;
tie fury of a wounded tiger. .-It was but&#xD;
the thought and act qf the instant, on my&#xD;
part, to strike up eisknife with my left&#xD;
arm, draw my ownsj and plunge it an his&#xD;
breast.as he fell,upon me.&#xD;
I gas, borne , backwards against the&#xD;
bert}-bga ds by .the forge of the atac ,&#xD;
butjpstagtigepoyer g myself, thiew&#xD;
forward, and he fell bleeding anday&#xD;
uppg be deck. °&#xD;
Two ,or thee of the crew inst ntl&#xD;
sprang towards ne, ppoing that I h ad&#xD;
asQ een moritally wounded in the a ray.&#xD;
thy Wire ho   yev~rr soon conviined oa&#xD;
thegena trary. I hauonly -eeived a sliit&#xD;
enlupen n1y;arm. Tle whole affair was&#xD;
aste   ih -such' rap d y',th rt I could&#xD;
:eve fuly realize it&#xD;
was to b dpe now ?The cap-&#xD;
tai iwe onshpre, and I Was welt aw are,&#xD;
tht as aogn as he eaneoil beard, a1ndis&#xD;
cove 4 wh t had app~eed, JI should b.&#xD;
}plaoedin irons nd thrxWn itto  isog ,.&#xD;
1bere. .,Yrm-thOeoee hq p obasgigy as&#xD;
I sould bei tneferred to therdy&#xD;
W4+e   .,;r h 4tr e  Of rlop  f t  i r a s,&#xD;
f,^t: Nij* ,e ! ,hft a  , y t 'h satiusm,4 and&#xD;
htor course o pue. TI      ,!eMS&#xD;
enI  h   a e; it'w . s, or afinme&#xD;
&#xD;
frothing of'theiaffair Casyet,id I&#xD;
mined-ntmnediately ato leuve ttrg&#xD;
A young manonir h6a:d, brj  v0u' s&#xD;
" iARRY," who had been anxidusfrtsi&#xD;
time to get _lear:o '  h embjp+ dMCng&#xD;
my. thoughtsmimdi4i tely pppetQi  -&#xD;
companpme inmy fhliglt.     m de"&#xD;
. This propositio. I -eard withejyqt&#xD;
rnerely o. account oflhavinga&#xD;
ion, but he was ,a atote l&#xD;
feet in stature, and of i verprg   -&#xD;
sing appeargnee 1:wasal&#xD;
with the :Spanish aInguagedd 1&#xD;
-member of Watervillollegein4i p&#xD;
mate of one of my e&#xD;
i      only vtwv fr     ne n g&#xD;
we had been on the not    pa&#xD;
,4Iring the voyage. . JI&#xD;
a immetiately c p  enee'p&#xD;
onflor ongdeptat r     t~$&#xD;
dll biudle of neeeg ryg? tjJS&#xD;
. quantity  1foo ,,wpd s a1pJ&#xD;
ogAancw, we elpre 4i      rb&#xD;
gag way -oarda sipgjir go)&#xD;
g-otupnnedgarfy       pp4&#xD;
ai4 strikig puA bqjlfd4&#xD;
pesseN10q9 uwdgr th ggjIy4&#xD;
Wellsrpf 'wvA4lfgpeb&#xD;
i3 sfety, intig ueigbhr  '&#xD;
calledTP pe -Horn.'o do&#xD;
Having lantmed,  die&#xD;
to the hitusaeof -WO  Iy,   wn&#xD;
daong tjh galor 1      n    .&#xD;
of %?I11 $095    Afin&#xD;
~ersaIolve ago&#xD;
impression t4        , f  V&#xD;
bp gpgg g{+h~yr.T gggng$ e&#xD;
&#xD;
iT&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7511-00000008"/>&#xD;
U'&#xD;
&#xD;
RTEiS, IN C    .IL&#xD;
&#xD;
sidsg 6'it was our design t proceed&#xD;
Adaghdhe woods and by-roads,,to soie&#xD;
a ate¢he small towns oi the coast to&#xD;
sheleeward.              -.&#xD;
t oblock we bade a polite "adios"&#xD;
W    *hostess.  Yellowing the shore&#xD;
~long until we had passed the Custom&#xD;
i 4iggDand the ruins of the old fort all-&#xD;
d$1to;.we gained the road'leading to the&#xD;
th'y on eptfon, which was eight miles&#xD;
-dgtat, Passing over a slight hill, we&#xD;
depledhInto the level plain beyond,;&#xD;
,0Cil stretehed gut to the East some&#xD;
eor (Qpr miles, and to whe north as&#xD;
.ase otTd see.&#xD;
e road to Cdception crossed the&#xD;
p  a n easterly direction, which we&#xD;
1 U!we were about a mile from&#xD;
t aiahead, when   we struck&#xD;
*+narrow road leading to tli&#xD;
rred along as rapidly as}the&#xD;
4  i dld 'low  We neither saw&#xD;
I;tP Mny a hvin  thing during the&#xD;
ihe distant birk of the dogs,&#xD;
ee   keulowls, which sang t&#xD;
rd dismaltchorus and the moriig&#xD;
ftehrA    t 1  files on our way.&#xD;
4 o4   ntIVtho -sn was well&#xD;
s , pid    e from the high-way&#xD;
t u A  ew moments' rest; an  opened&#xD;
ry le&amp;amp; f bi " sid of a cool sprizn&#xD;
e spreading our table-upon&#xD;
epabtobk with a keen relish&#xD;
i&amp;amp;uit d pAfie had in store,&#xD;
i a tkrequent draughts of&#xD;
'  ~ fl  the spring&#xD;
(d ..r Eae beenfa&#xD;
at    tesene ofe       toodeSt&#xD;
{ xlhve the srpens from the&#xD;
.T ses'  rw esaw  themaround&#xD;
.  j     r ries, of  every  size&#xD;
&#xD;
tudes, one might suppose that Perseus&#xD;
had flown directly over this spot With&#xD;
Medusa's reeking head,&#xD;
"The gory drops distilled, as swift he flew,&#xD;
And from each drop envenoined serpents grew"&#xD;
Having carefully gathered up the frag-&#xD;
ments, we proceeded on our'route. We&#xD;
were now obliged to be constantlyupon&#xD;
the alert to escape observation, and&#xD;
whenever we heard the approach of&#xD;
horses along the road, we turned aside&#xD;
itgo the bushes while they passed. We&#xD;
were at last however suddenly surprised,&#xD;
and for a few moments believed ourselves,&#xD;
caught. About noon, uirhile walking-on'in&#xD;
earnest conversation, we saw three horse,&#xD;
mien descending a hill, about a quarter of&#xD;
a mile ahead, and in full view ; we saw&#xD;
at once that it would be our best course&#xD;
to keep boldly on, as our dodging now,&#xD;
would be -sure to draw their attehtion,&#xD;
and excite suspicion.&#xD;
Upon their near a pproach, we :discover.&#xD;
ed that there were two gentlemary and a&#xD;
lady in the company they drew up by&#xD;
our side and immediately began inquir-&#xD;
ing of us where we were frorrand&#xD;
where we were going ? Harry ,relied'&#xD;
"that we were sent out by the captain of&#xD;
our vessel to procure a bnllock'for beef"-&#xD;
but what' was our surprise to hear the la-&#xD;
dy cry out in broken English, "They are&#xD;
run-away sailors, I know-they' are.,' The&#xD;
men, however, appeared to be rather in-&#xD;
diffBrent as to who or what we were and&#xD;
soon they all rode on and 'left us with our&#xD;
hearts beating less violently. After this&#xD;
adventure, for fear of' its rgpetitiorn, we&#xD;
determined to-secrete ofselves for there-&#xD;
mainder of the day, and travel riisgthe.&#xD;
night. We accordingly ttrned°asidesand&#xD;
hid ourselvess in some low shrnbbeysthet&#xD;
bordered t1eway&#xD;
&#xD;
R&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
pwAl&#xD;
i '  fp S re&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER III.&#xD;
&#xD;
As soon as the shades of evening had villains, hiding secretly, on all&#xD;
gathered around us, We again started for- dogging our steps for the pu po&#xD;
ward.' 'r the first hour, the road was der and plunder. Our bundles&#xD;
tolerably good,' and we mrade rapid pro- and lightand We had theft&#xD;
gress, but presently we found ourselves out backsr by ur bets paedig''&#xD;
penetrating into a forest, bya path wlich breast and ov  the shoilder4y&#xD;
was so na r*w and  rass-grown that 'we the free use of oti a   s 4e&#xD;
cond   ith dificulty trace our way, and stout oakeen stick to asest&#xD;
what seemed to'add more to our embar- This We pursued our&#xD;
rss ht, i soon branched ofin opposite narrow  path in Isd I&#xD;
directions ''                       .  *'thcer, and&#xD;
"This.ust be the'one for iti'to'take,  s ead danced. '      4&#xD;
observed   y certpanion, "it seems to  "This i ?   dismaad 69&#xD;
lead farther into the country, aid isifry I  nefit is  s;mt .&#xD;
ani thing the plainest; whatsay you blindnmai-buf, to be&#xD;
comrade, shkll we risk' ?"  "Tou 'are here in the dark, and it *ou&#xD;
the ilot," Iepied, a'u T hase ful con- tlarly dIsagreeb  o   I&#xD;
fidence in your judgment,"           of somes v' e    t&#xD;
WYitlut sayingrnbre, Iarry dashed n, here y awa&#xD;
aid T 11vned itnrdiately i  ll; #tke.bI WAN , -    r i5chF "t aJm&#xD;
The forestepres ida  wifd1(d+f tMad agniptin's t  ghs   iixbh&#xD;
asdect, and I must 'confe ss; Igew some-s ie an w&#xD;
what nervous is We advanced.' f.frit   replid&#xD;
sted   tsi   "niy efs as a-kin ithe e  d         {vi . ig&#xD;
bblk'dest. ofGerrmanyt hronged  itiLo we ,as i&#xD;
&#xD;
.&#xD;
r&#xD;
i&#xD;
_, 5&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7511-00000009"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILL.&#xD;
&#xD;
t forest soon." Formore than an hour the same star, that good old Job gazed&#xD;
4ter his remark, we travelled on in si- upon and chronicled, more than 3,000,&#xD;
f -the darkness and gloom of the for- years ago ; having lost none of its loveli-&#xD;
est was so intense, that I made out to dis -utess since that far distant period. Nearer&#xD;
ce rn y companion's form, just distinctly to the zenith, in the "Virgin's Shock of&#xD;
enough to follow in his wake. About Corn," sparkled the itnar star "Spica,"in&#xD;
Gidightshe forst grew more open, and her solitary grandeur, and "golden ring.&#xD;
y we passed on we saw liglits gleaming ed Saturn," was seen ascending from&#xD;
faintly through the trees,' which apprised the eastern horizon, while wending her&#xD;
4i that we were approaching a village. slow way through the constellation of&#xD;
'Wi soon gained an apparently more open "Libra.", Close upon Saturn, came the&#xD;
country, but still took the precaution of gory "Antares,", another of those lunar&#xD;
passing the village by a circuitous route stars, whose positions have been deter-&#xD;
and emerged into an open road some dis- mined with such great exactness for the&#xD;
tanee beyond. We now, travelled brisk- benefit of navigators.&#xD;
Iy,'through a pleasant.open county, until  There is pleasure to be derived in gaz-&#xD;
thedawning of the day warned us, like ing up into that "world of worlds," and im-&#xD;
oltoagain seek a covert.,      aginipg their peopled with beings, sinless&#xD;
_   r{{ ed outI  a convenient spot, and happy, and brightas the own beams.&#xD;
4n e9irnr mthe ioadfixed up a It awakened pleasig associatios in my&#xD;
e   t  nong the, bushes, and con- rind, caniy ing ine back to the hours when&#xD;
reduring the.day.   1-in rayclildhood's home, 1 gaz eoitheir&#xD;
M  n~hVl bg   l     n  r  rian- a  A  r&#xD;
&#xD;
2*&#xD;
&#xD;
aJi by th: ancient astronome to::pre- ppurds popul tion ate grot p 4lt  fer&#xD;
sent the qconstellations, haveaut slightis t to  ;,_ aeing thek v fr n pr  W&#xD;
resmblance to the actual position; ofthe tW the eaxeof the Aola* 4n.i&#xD;
stxsthaj mark teheirutlines..'this how mid Saof Sp rsnd 1ig i5&#xD;
ey re  i eLerongU te ica ;:ai; s co i.nm psscssu.}",tanusa  ae wid&#xD;
pee        rg      stars W  e  eQf Gtefrst inarkable for , their quickneia l f te&#xD;
magnitud, tryo of ythe second;_and 4tl tioj, and pawgs of Wten ;&#xD;
abher of thO. third'The brightest star gen erally filled  h hi Nh .Qi&#xD;
"Aori "is in thmeouth and. represents and  are  cpnsidereds   . e  Uetetrseb&#xD;
thefoot;of theeross.        ^ ;',    diers                            "rx&#xD;
' ut to return iacl again. to our., own  Those who, remain in. tei ani&#xD;
planet. -We continued onthrough the vals, are ignoiant and uetifiou&#xD;
night, passing two or three Haciendas, or the laMt degree. TFha~t a  plati i&#xD;
Plantations, which here and there show ing 4lmost in +solitude, scattrefl&#xD;
themselves, like an "Oasis" in the desert, rugged country, without the mant ag&#xD;
and received with becoming courtesy the, ucation, and ;without=enjoy iag a  jd&#xD;
isual salutes from the watch dogs ,luring intercourse, houkjbe sunleo loawl&#xD;
the morning hours we approached the race, cannot be surprising.:&#xD;
neighborhood of a large plantation,:and  Here, almost; il  unlkogensd  pbli&#xD;
on corning up pith the farm house, dte- they spend, their dgsJn an4&#xD;
cid d,- - 9 were undoubtedly sj e w 4d, aBndthe' " eheerful ay a   ;J'&#xD;
ftprwiuysttoldly-appy for fotrd and seacelyiesschild of-t&#xD;
re 'We were Jdndlyswelcomed by t~ia Indian;angestogg qh&#xD;
inman t  t ; , Bugs   .graga, entref 4n general, consst of mud ,wall&#xD;
eg ,sgrere hospitablypatertineg thatched roof without furniture,  e&#xD;
4th qugpa extremely dgraked :c1as simple and rade     ithi Wato&#xD;
yet Ithene et they take a fncy, they are  Iri -horsemahshithey - ra" -&#xD;
lindlidgenerous to a faulted Wp in-equalled b  the  Mesk;, t&#xD;
formed them that we wer fror i Talka- brought Ldto it   O    i&#xD;
huaW boppd to. iMala. They provided, take to it a .ntul&#xD;
is with a.'reakfast of bred aped mi , does tothe wa e  ih, o14&#xD;
wlich p fer 'doing justice to, we rested conveyance whick has everW&#xD;
our  yes none .o twgjhous,,previous ed amottheatigd hils =,tr&#xD;
to. tJr/start., ,                  which the surface t ' IV Tr&#xD;
e p icipa  r rsz why neither   They.wear      i e&#xD;
S     t{ppp   or g  vghean as ,a ggcess-t which se esgy nl y1 4  4&#xD;
?A QO3rlog   ri the;  pj 9p   saddled enverigl os~&#xD;
re4 s tpe spostipp .  9   y    iggruo  day, and  b  t gt&#xD;
tn.teay4 f tprsejyqs ogve~  enitty   ifi         -      hriiluk&#xD;
itea  'm s    vas.opyg      gyptg   re for the head,&#xD;
l   the:pulajigj of tie U  4S Sto round th e gty,*d,&#xD;
In, $ggthg  ggdea, gnes jo ,wjhqle comfortable ga. s~                    c&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
K&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7511-00000010"/>&#xD;
m&#xD;
&#xD;
MIf1LS  OXL&#xD;
&#xD;
vT hgiavp'one viftue however, whiehi   Whohas, failed tonotice thylack ro fri&#xD;
{ jf     emulation by manyofaar dependence nng politicians ef)4he&#xD;
#       t ontrymen, viz: a spirit ot fint.present day !  ith what eoatte ptible&#xD;
agnlinidbyendenee. It is thatquali- humility do they bow and serapeto 3the&#xD;
"*i~  ranes the man and the want hirelings and He'ians of party inanaa&#xD;
X4# i  ;;ellow YI             gers ; those who are' alntot "alkystlie&#xD;
6 r ls anytngp ing  this world I ad- drones of society, yet have mtnaged to&#xD;
e it is= Wiridependent tan; a gain a strange influence in polities; who&#xD;
pii. .ecophat, a (favor-cnrrying look down with contempt upon the hon-&#xD;
Wrtch, I'detest as I do the hated breatlest workingman, whose toilis the nonr&#xD;
ny: Let man, as long as he bears ishmet that gives health and vigorous&#xD;
nh~~  of his rhaker, maintain those ifality to spiety. Nearly every 4andi&#xD;
iitioawhiob humanity should wear, in date for public favor bows reverentially&#xD;
o        V owerirg in a spirit of vasalage to this human scnm ; and it is by "this&#xD;
A folemai, or, puppyalike, fawn on base pandering of public men---th sup-l&#xD;
0s",  ultht deals= the blow. Let him port, encouragement, and patronageitra&#xD;
:  ,evtd maintain 'his rights, nor fail venly'extendedto them, by politicians of&#xD;
to expose thewrongs of society, but every party and clique, that such vile in&#xD;
s        arntionind wrong, wherev- fluence s affected.&#xD;
b3 found. Frown on the ty     Such has now become the state of ypt'&#xD;
dUma ifests a desire to overawe itics, that an independent na  ardot&#xD;
tat another and probe the possibly be elected to a public office th6y&#xD;
,,} i   r., : f corruption, with a feaar e in fact ostraciesd from tle public&#xD;
councils, like the wiseaind the Durefndii&#xD;
Cannot dress  ' Sparta of old. How often dz'w  see ithie&#xD;
M   . itn s asuwhere'my heart bids me frown. noble natnres,-who, seeking ne-itraih&#xD;
p espeethenmy heart says      er than, fame, would scorn to"'"A'tte&#xD;
*~jllin.' n myNeyttioathefor his trident, or Jove for hibi&#xD;
-yewolhhcir-like'ep   Nepttipe",&#xD;
n         .I m  s o Iafield b y  a  sto rm :  p o w e r  to  'th u n d e r," - le ft  fo rg o tte n  a n d&#xD;
4 !      valor, whocan she    "alone !  It cannot be - denied," though=&#xD;
bene th his tder,       with 'shame we confess it, that genius&#xD;
wiU to batter it'iand yet  virtue and id&#xD;
'and extnd thehandependence,willstrivefo&#xD;
popular favor, atperilousbodds against the&#xD;
the tynt, hate  supple knee, the flattering tongue  nd&#xD;
h ratd, nor my love,  cringing sou.    however, one,W&#xD;
i    fUili' Wealth aid rank  sonieishow ofthese noble virides, shoii&#xD;
ei{Nhoikas'irMtN I, shall have  perchance receie th niareP n iaj it&#xD;
grteitee ind, if eaisite   necessary to secure his election, his'8 in&#xD;
Ssece; bt they shal not pendance is very apt to take to itself'&#xD;
ey thoughts, ror sften down  wing  iy       y, d   ty trpo&#xD;
dda;,,f aord,     cormnenceihent of his duties; ;dnh&#xD;
ThM    dt a mieritless miAion:       is iiivarial'y the' case, If he is debir  of&#xD;
&#xD;
prerelecton, There isi o other way to&#xD;
cure ie evl than by refusing to elect&#xD;
th eppeond tirme, to the same office.&#xD;
Take our politicians and public men&#xD;
generally, and it Will be ,;fou-nd they are&#xD;
ilze:wost craven, dastardly wretches in ex-&#xD;
istence. Look for instance 4 the drivel-&#xD;
ling imbecile, who bore the title of Mayor&#xD;
of New York, and presided over the out..&#xD;
rageoum and co hardly massacre at the&#xD;
4stpy-place opera house, on the;night ,of&#xD;
the tenth of' May, 1849; merely to pam&#xD;
per the vanity and sooth the wounded&#xD;
pridetsa - score of -cowardlyaristocriati-&#xD;
cal nabobe; ordering the murderous fire&#xD;
instead of yielding to the wishes of a disc&#xD;
gus e4 ;and justly iidignant people, by&#xD;
closing thecontemptible show shop. What&#xD;
A lack of filmnss and independence was&#xD;
hg4iglayd, At the bid of a few bol-&#xD;
l9.  h.aated gristocrats, to order ade=&#xD;
-fencelessand iannoce nt multitude to he}&#xD;
slaughtered, in the vain hope that a want&#xD;
during mountebank vagabond would be&#xD;
permitted to make a harlequin of him-&#xD;
self, and abuse American citizens. What&#xD;
makes the butchery still more melancholy,&#xD;
is the fact, that the least worthy of the&#xD;
fifty murdered persons, was worth more&#xD;
to society, than a whole nationof such as&#xD;
encouraged and rejoiced in the massa-,&#xD;
cre.&#xD;
There are other public functionaries&#xD;
that have proved themselves as craven in&#xD;
their acts, as' has Mayor Woodhull; but&#xD;
few deeds however, have been followed&#xD;
by such dangerous results. A war of&#xD;
classes has been induced in that city,&#xD;
which, if not quieted, will one day result&#xD;
in utter ruin to the present lordly tyrants&#xD;
of Gotham.r&#xD;
' ut to continue my narrative. These&#xD;
&#xD;
I +t&#xD;
&#xD;
4Qko1o Span rdstathon   g ;,&#xD;
proud anddinepei 43n;, a&amp;amp;jp4&#xD;
may be go, for like Adamt fhy&#xD;
sw at,and gain their hniba arbepyb&#xD;
own brow '4oiaigpre. T hya&#xD;
generous  to  their  friendnsd cbt yl4t#her&#xD;
and cruel to their enae' ,4    4&#xD;
low on them tra*,a ilr  gn.gE ,&#xD;
pestilential city. ,&#xD;
After.leaving the Baien4dou&#xD;
soon carried 4s into the h arttf&#xD;
forest, the track gradually chang t ;&#xD;
a tolerable road to a narrow i&#xD;
which we traced with diffictiltiy.,{t=&#xD;
simply a.!circuitous passage b&#xD;
stumps of trees and around ditfiat&#xD;
logs and huge broken stones.&#xD;
the scene was,'unique: and ?r  Y .&#xD;
miense primeval treei=i edt&#xD;
beads towering'to thens     t,&#xD;
the live oak and hard pirie we&#xD;
irn abundane, fting g  t&#xD;
athwartithe' narrowedtsky'&#xD;
sun's rayswere ,struggling&#xD;
narrow opening, 'and castinga&#xD;
shade around, The wikit'Y&#xD;
shrubs,.and°gay, tresselledfvin&#xD;
ed the way, scatteringheirr&#xD;
on the morning air, and the&#xD;
sweet songsters, with plumag  t&#xD;
and soft as any from the frag nt  :r&#xD;
Isles,  sent  forth  their  m erry -aoiot l e a&#xD;
among the golden leaves of  ei^&#xD;
and flowery homes, as if they we  #&#xD;
turously praising the briht bh&#xD;
and the blushing flowers th&#xD;
in rich profusion through    tr-&#xD;
est. The singing ofte b&#xD;
skiped from branch to branch, te m4 u&#xD;
f the distant water-fall, tether&#xD;
the wild gamb91sof thie squtrrels,&#xD;
hasty retreat of the tiiid hM,     -&#xD;
&#xD;
MLEsrXegflJ,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7511-00000011"/>&#xD;
td  t I"  tie ; ' it o. tia ve long Woi s vMit, ere  r reargfi edr. j&#xD;
'i'   d i  r*-t'-lA         sld fehnilriend id&#xD;
ie at i9 s  m to epen within my-re dito bid mee stnt1i g1.&#xD;
0f1t     yinvite 91; vde eatioethentjuapin      ayan&amp;amp;dfrikkng its&#xD;
d*,5,,   h F4i4 tail about like little kittenadsn'turnig&#xD;
° Vth  ah ion if thought his .ighing eyes up -at jrein amiiiost&#xD;
ji 6|     4- io  , wre di1ifer ctida1ntrer, as  i  notiee wheet~r&#xD;
to                     Thesigs.  'hese J was please with his pistlayful .od&#xD;
rel darting acro eitirIk, e Here We have often sat duiwg many a&#xD;
of ia ir a ku+mmer -days:,m- happy hotir, regarding e .heh ther-aol d&#xD;
4heugteeh    dds; andthrough familiar friends. ,;'loved thie Iitt  crea,&#xD;
kneemt(dfwoods shatiskilrted the tare dearly,:and he in rtin semedto&#xD;
Nteemeta m        ' fthesid rel* Iee the utmost coifidrege V i' inei fret&#xD;
,  ~  ht  nd  joyo s  heart I quentlyan ag  over'k y  feet 1a; dleg&#xD;
' ie foatning mill;dam, and daring his gambols. Proud andhuypy&#xD;
slohe the Milt ;ponds - that. lay did I feel in the company of my singular&#xD;
amn~ gihem   t O pitt s and gay and amusing little pet. 'e disapjeted&#xD;
i me alidafthane. in time, and new"scenes hadAalio idtbr&#xD;
loigliairgrden banks, ted.his irnage, froi' my mind. Sa.it' is&#xD;
S   b   r94tei    no bolster with on dearest and imelyet     4   .&#xD;
iiear and, heated on they die and aresoon tfog tot. d IRet&#xD;
y4, beside:the "       iiranning a there upon which the moriWt&#xD;
S trin,otaul  ai e .ppdar- enlarge.      *               .*,A n&#xD;
leulifdstripedisquirel nor                               ;   .&#xD;
+ $ $ ¢¢ 7  i  AY r  ,. s  'e .  ,  .'  ' r ' r     a " }  b +&#xD;
&#xD;
A ri. K '  A'  . .A - ,.i  *f&#xD;
to% A~&#xD;
' t'AJ  4  At4A&#xD;
_  d, A 'l A  ~    ,  C UAAis A +i "  a  P'  ,  r&#xD;
t4   A&#xD;
&#xD;
A        , ,&#xD;
'A,&#xD;
A l      C           .&#xD;
&#xD;
'A     "A      ,    +           A      b *&#xD;
A  K    , r A, 6&#xD;
&#xD;
Our course led us on through the same&#xD;
interminable forest, where hoary old trees,&#xD;
the growth and decay of centuries, lay&#xD;
prostrated and scattered along the rough&#xD;
path, a track which seemed marked out&#xD;
by the wild animals that frequented&#xD;
these solitary wilds, rather than by the&#xD;
art of man. We passed on, mile after&#xD;
mile, up hill anddown valley,;and leaping&#xD;
the swift-running water course,noWclimb-&#xD;
ing over fallen trees, which lay at almost&#xD;
every angle, then hurrying down some&#xD;
.steep declivity, and emerging at the bot.&#xD;
tom of a deep ravine, or encountering a&#xD;
pool of 0gnant water. Then again af,&#xD;
ter a circuitous ramble we would strike.,&#xD;
and follow for miles the borders of some&#xD;
beautiful stream, aslimpid arthe air itself,&#xD;
among nooks and dales, whieh seemed&#xD;
fit habitations for Grecian nymphs and&#xD;
piping satyrs.&#xD;
I remember that we spread our dinner&#xD;
table one day upon the borders of a small&#xD;
Jake of crystal waters, surrounded with&#xD;
a profusion of wild flowers, and soft vav&#xD;
&#xD;
K ;e. }        roc       i&#xD;
.  :)  4;   Y&#xD;
3  t_&#xD;
&#xD;
ing willows, over-arehed by the  t&#xD;
cner'heaven's delicious blue,"   ry&#xD;
and sower of this lovely spot'       Y&#xD;
written over with the poetry yof&#xD;
place in fact,&#xD;
"So wondous.gand, the whot&#xD;
The scenery of.a ''ry  u&#xD;
We enjoyed a delightfuJ&#xD;
clear silvery waters, aid   i !&#xD;
hour or two near this fairy; b .eryy&#xD;
dedicated the place 1th4e&#xD;
few impromtu lines,bwhich rp4y&#xD;
the next pilgrim.: Indeed ,t   5~&#xD;
was evey day changingrs  p&#xD;
and dreary woods, to .the o e       y&#xD;
bower; from the small ltigt e&#xD;
ing to the rural village with1g&#xD;
and cottages of straw.&#xD;
, The roads in the imediat at&#xD;
hood of the vilages were( Ro&#xD;
ed, denoting theirmore        t&#xD;
Therannerin which we&#xD;
the inhabitants was, sei lah&#xD;
changing winds. At ytit&#xD;
the rudest threaten t tomu tth" s i* 4&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER IV.&#xD;
&#xD;
1 Atli&#xD;
NO'&#xD;
e  r  , ,' ~ -       1 "r  o:y  '  P .a "T  '&#xD;
ti  T  f  h~~tN  t  t  y  :¢' i  '.L rpT+"'  , sr&#xD;
",  .F    Z t t  Y ,  n~ t A ,"  r    "-L J&#xD;
f  -     r  r e  - "    a it c Yt  A  -&#xD;
.±  y     ,4     '"4A   4 A,  5 " , i F&#xD;
t ®    A.     y"&#xD;
Wry W&#xD;
&#xD;
f                       ,  .&#xD;
1&#xD;
"               ^                 }             "               {&#xD;
' 3                                            1&#xD;
t.. r                r f , y               1                       _&#xD;
&#xD;
k&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7511-00000012"/>&#xD;
IirXMBL ES ,  I cmu.&#xD;
&#xD;
en from 'their doors, with stones and&#xD;
ubs;" t other times, and places we&#xD;
f     be hospitbly and generously en-&#xD;
t.ed; At snehtines'we would exert&#xD;
^  q efres to the utmost to please those&#xD;
ere kind enough to afford us a&#xD;
;J  ta':}  s ylim.  -Harry would sing&#xD;
1; dI would dance, and we never fai1l&#xD;
other about us a large crowd whose&#xD;
.    end approbation  were expressed&#xD;
"y7 oisterous shouting, and swinging&#xD;
1 their hands.. Being modest men, we&#xD;
course received our blushing honors&#xD;
~ng9ky. .&#xD;
4; haverany a time smiled to, myself&#xD;
when thinking of our ludicrous pertorman-&#xD;
I -0 beforesthese kind butignorantSpan.&#xD;
ud~s.Wewere Actorst 'least ama-&#xD;
f, not  professional ones ; we&#xD;
red ourselves at the time to the&#xD;
mfing organ players, and our numerous&#xD;
were such as would adorn the&#xD;
Ssician's monkey. We had every&#xD;
tebiihly flattered with our re-'&#xD;
4 ondiethe audience we gathered&#xD;
V6tus  'Or'periormances were a least&#xD;
better  receive' than were those of&#xD;
*e(My at the fatal Astor-place Opera-&#xD;
t              f al th6 was driven  irn disgust from  the&#xD;
4t      the citizens of New York. There&#xD;
thisdiferehene however between u's&#xD;
1 s   pported and encouraged by the&#xD;
w od , backed by the military, we&#xD;
by the Demoordey, backed by the Ladies.&#xD;
4hose eoi g the Spanish race who&#xD;
ase~isposed to w'eceive a stranger at all,&#xD;
##hetbingupwith true Arabian hospitali-&#xD;
t4the4ieuce of it was, that the poor&#xD;
eis   orig whom we occasionally tar-&#xD;
*e    e saomely'ever in a condition to&#xD;
'r  'that 1wanianinfous virtue with&#xD;
ich41l4t- .&#xD;
&#xD;
It was, I think, the fourth day of our&#xD;
journey that we arrived at quite a flour.&#xD;
ishing little village-in fact it was more&#xD;
entitled to the name than any other on the&#xD;
route. We were accosted a short dis-&#xD;
tance out of the village by a man on&#xD;
horse-back. He appeared to be much&#xD;
pleased, saluting us with true Castilian&#xD;
politeness, and inviting us to pass the&#xD;
night with him at his house in the vil-&#xD;
lage. " Entres mi casa paisanos, tomar&#xD;
siesta, si todas a noches, muchos hay pon-&#xD;
chos," cried he with a bow. Si Signor&#xD;
con mucha gusta, mil gracias," replied&#xD;
Harry, as he gladly accepted the invita-&#xD;
tion.&#xD;
We were kindly welcomed by the farn-&#xD;
ily of the proprietor, and treated to some&#xD;
fine flavored native wine.  Nearly all&#xD;
the huts of the village were built of reeds&#xD;
plastered with mud, and thatched with&#xD;
straw. Few of them .contained more&#xD;
than one room, and those generallyrWith.&#xD;
out a floor. Here the inmates sit, sleep;&#xD;
and work in wig wamlife,- seldom look=&#xD;
ing beyond their pesent, wants. Their&#xD;
industry ebbs and flows, as plenty or po-&#xD;
erty prevail. We -were treated with&#xD;
great respect by the kind hearted villa-&#xD;
gers. We attended a dance Clled the&#xD;
&amp;amp;macusca, the Ibllowing eve g; and&#xD;
here we were tully initiated into the man-&#xD;
ners and customs of the place.&#xD;
The females in general, are robust and&#xD;
healthy; owing in a great nepasure to their&#xD;
diet of coarse bread and fruit. They 'are&#xD;
extremely fond of dancing, and- seer, to&#xD;
th*w all their energies into the business.&#xD;
The dance which they most prefer is this&#xD;
called the amacusca, somewhat rese n-&#xD;
ling the fandango; it waf perforied iian&#xD;
Amphitheatre, surrounded by apartments&#xD;
&#xD;
filledwithrefreshnients, &amp;amp;c., the stage'of attention fon the  Pos&#xD;
was under an open shed, around which will much sooner oe usf aiberty,{&#xD;
were grouped the old naidsand matrons they imagine is theresultof  d&#xD;
within the circle the young couple spring than a matter of indifference a'o&#xD;
to thermusic of the guitar, and violin. At' the age of about forteen,&#xD;
The couple begin dancing by facing each far advanced in love matter '&#xD;
other, flirting handkerchiefs about 'te monial anticipations, as one  r&#xD;
heads of their partners, approaching and  at eighteen. And she indigei i aUft;4&#xD;
retreating, then shooting off to one sidelsports arid blandishmentso f tilir&#xD;
and passing under arms. The short dress'dey of life, as sailors Woild s'y-" t&#xD;
of the females, and the prurient motions perfect looseness." And when she:rrties&#xD;
of both, are at war with all sentiments of I an constrained to say, that those b    s&#xD;
propriety; their movements are quite g'race- are carried into the domestic circle!#&#xD;
ful, those of the feet, pretty, but rather is very apt to permitthe intimacyleLd T&amp;amp;i&#xD;
amorous, the gestures may be.readily un- than her leige Lord. These&#xD;
derstood. Their heads are bare, profusely rarely if ever followed by any&#xD;
decorated with combs, and gay ribbons, on the part of the husband; they , $&#xD;
and for silk stockings they have a perfect took upon it as a matter of-&#xD;
an.         'tion to all partiesSaid" would&#xD;
t aped    strange to me, how the and resent as snicidial folly,$a&#xD;
others coild -itness, with pride and de= ticexplosion 'Lovdeintrgus&#xD;
light those exhibitions in their daughters; even to children, and are a  ev&#xD;
it'argued certain a false taste, andis'an source ot entertdnrixnet.'The _e  y&#xD;
evidence to what absurdities, custom and bf'their parent, are trietedit&#xD;
habit can familiarize the ind  They all levity as those of others H&#xD;
bNtray  heSpariish blood, it is seen in the r'mother counsel i'iadf vis t&#xD;
their nanners, their complexion and their terVis it stran ge slt th  hi  d&#xD;
stately forn; their large black ees are fdll look, rather at the exam plehah&#xD;
Sasan fire. They are extremely fond cep,"'&#xD;
'           I    r 1  , '    '  - x  i&#xD;
Y:  Ar              1, as                 /    ,'  'r   .&#xD;
_  o  s  }     ,  F  '  i  ,  ,  .    a  :r    .ir i -tlr'y~e1-" '  +rd    h} '4 ,,-"&#xD;
r     , t - ' "      i1 i ~~~it l   ' * a(, F 6r_&#xD;
&#xD;
*1&#xD;
&#xD;
~1J&#xD;
&#xD;
Stf  it   .  ''     {   1   - t,  , r _t  y  ,&#xD;
TLANT's VIA&#xD;
&#xD;
a&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7511-00000013"/>&#xD;
R~ABE N U&#xD;
&#xD;
%q~ u  b&#xD;
r "  r  7 ' r ,&#xD;
&#xD;
f '8  t j           CHAPTER       "V.&#xD;
u gay but dangerous vortex of the mother or aunt of my fair inamo&#xD;
0;1I   'and4, disipation, I found myself rata rushed on to the stage, grasped&#xD;
4    y the aid of Aladdin's magician, ga- me in her arms, as if I were a piccaniny,&#xD;
on ,.a the brunettes as they whirled and bore me off the stage, followed by&#xD;
the girl, whose shouts and thoseof the&#xD;
4     g gthe lwing hour with fying feet," company, somewhat raised sy temper.&#xD;
lng could .Iremain anidle spectator. But when I was finally' released and&#xD;
d myslf going through the panto- conveyed into one of the side apartments&#xD;
.ewith fever sh zeal, the perspiration accompanied by the .right jewel who&#xD;
r int largedrops opK my forehead had so fascinated me, causing through&#xD;
he viplence of the exercise. My her animal magnetism all 'py laughable&#xD;
rnewas one of those Castilian beauties mistakes, I felt a forgiving disposition&#xD;
whose combination of charms might stir come over me. Having seated myself&#xD;
he thisel of a Praxiteles. She was the beside her I endeavored to apologize for&#xD;
,;ishe0 health and animation, but I my inattention. I soon found she was&#xD;
ri not say more ; let the readers im- a wild thing, and fully armed with all&#xD;
imagination picture her as beautiful as it the brilliant weapons of beauty, wit,&#xD;
ny,. nd they will not come far in error.repartee, and a lively self-posession.&#xD;
?   so muehtaken up, with the person.  "Coma ci-a-mah esta in Americano ?"&#xD;
{ -ehs s of my. sloe-eyed partner, tEat enquired  she pointing  to my head.&#xD;
"M  as with difficulty I could keep time "Cranium" I answered .craniu  pelo&#xD;
;th music and go through the intri- punetero" said she, giving me a push&#xD;
e evolutions.                   which sent me back against the wall.&#xD;
ade several blunders much to the I gathered myself up with becoming&#xD;
am usement of the lookers on; at last dignity movingback to my little Amazon&#xD;
&#xD;
I had scarcely regainedciny seat howpv-&#xD;
er, when she renewed her interogatories&#xD;
with another question  which   fairly&#xD;
destroyed my gravity ofposition as well&#xD;
as spirit, and I rolled, on the floor corn-&#xD;
pltely convulsed with laughter; when Jt&#xD;
recovered, I made a hasty retreat into the&#xD;
crowd.&#xD;
Here I was soon caught up by&#xD;
a little creature scarce knee high, whoI&#xD;
insisted upon my taking a trip with herI&#xD;
on the boards. I plead my recent discom-&#xD;
fiture and fatigue, she would not listen&#xD;
to these excuses, and I finally proposed to&#xD;
take a stroll round the premises. She&#xD;
took my arm and beckoned her'sister to&#xD;
her side, and.havin each lighted a "pa.&#xD;
per cigarritto," they hurried mue off to,&#xD;
where a group of youngsters were liste-&#xD;
nig to an o14 woman. who was reading&#xD;
off the destinies of the curious enquirers&#xD;
from their open palms. They alttook&#xD;
their turns, and, the book of fate was&#xD;
laid; pen to them, and every word gree&#xD;
dily swallowed by the.crowd. What she&#xD;
,discovered in my palm,I shall not disclose,&#xD;
but I have full confidence in the- misi&#xD;
terionsdevelopement, for I could feei it&#xD;
"oing out of ry fingers' n " as&#xD;
plautely and palpably as Bo15'Acres could&#xD;
his courage, as described in one of Sher-&#xD;
idan's plays.&#xD;
These fortune tellers are quite numer.&#xD;
otis and are wll patronized;: they are a&#xD;
shrewd set and will tell a good story,&#xD;
for hailfa; real.&#xD;
,Our entertainment broke up about&#xD;
- twelve, and we all retired to our respect&#xD;
tive abodes. The gentlemen, I found&#xD;
at these entertainments, were much more&#xD;
sedate than the ladies, and su.h I le.&#xD;
lieis charaeteristijgof *Je Spanish&#xD;
&#xD;
character. The females, were drefl4&#xD;
in light airy material  hot&#xD;
low neck dresses With   athor fu n'&#xD;
probably that they may beless&#xD;
assed irt dancing, but perhaps&#xD;
turned ancle is an additionpamot&#xD;
We enjoyed ourselves minch&#xD;
rural village, and tarried herpthr&amp;amp;&#xD;
so loath were we to part fronM0p11r "&#xD;
made friends, and were estl #&#xD;
five or six miles on gir way&#xD;
younger part of the community.&#xD;
We traveled about twenty miles, '&#xD;
parting company. Having passed, during&#xD;
our walk, one of the isolated 'hacion&#xD;
we approached another quit #ir i&#xD;
and neat in its appearance,and   a&#xD;
application were cordially recei e  e&#xD;
proprietor took great pleasure in a&#xD;
ing as about the premises, and&#xD;
highly flattered with.our profuse  61&#xD;
pliments. Harry instructedlhrina&#xD;
method of fattening swinepogp9&#xD;
and corn, without drinkewhich the I&#xD;
was hardly inclnd to/ belie    ud&#xD;
succeed, but declared hisntien    of&#xD;
trying the experimentt.'&#xD;
At our next', stopphg plce  r   e&#xD;
night, the family consisted oa i&#xD;
wife and one daughter about  e4&#xD;
years of age. Harry    d glg dr&#xD;
family by his rapid executioas oa  -&#xD;
doodle and some other light.are 3pno&#xD;
the "banjo."  The young: dy -$a.&#xD;
vored us with some of her natie ve   s.&#xD;
I was under individual oblionsito&#xD;
her, for she furnished me&#xD;
linen- bandage for my'wo nd,&#xD;
begancto be so ew th&#xD;
having washed it gave iiie alsa&#xD;
which proved very:thealt   -t IIJ -&#xD;
&#xD;
.                                          i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7511-00000014"/>&#xD;
AMBES mN cStic.&#xD;
&#xD;
fLat8 ip.the afternoon of the tenth da'&#xD;
S g pilgrimage we found ourselve&#xD;
trMaibg along a path that appeared qpit&#xD;
i dlsic'bt and but little trod, and whit&#xD;
be'inngg to 'be apprehensive that w&#xD;
had strayed from the right path; we wer&#xD;
e'rtaken by tree Spaniards on foot&#xD;
T' y looked decidedly unprepossessin{&#xD;
in their appearance, and were contuinall'&#xD;
,   gour buntdles 'while whispering t&#xD;
eeh other, and at last made bold t&#xD;
.enquire its contents. Harry gave them&#xD;
td understand that it contained some root&#xD;
'and herbs which we had gathered by the&#xD;
yThis did not appear to satisfy, them&#xD;
1i dwyiile they were enquiring of Harry&#xD;
'het) er we were armed, (which I partly&#xD;
turderstood.) ' I slyly 'picked  up&#xD;
'droled 'stick; which had at the momen&#xD;
a tracted- my attention, being shaped&#xD;
inVh "like a pistol. This I thrust into&#xD;
bd6som leaving the part that resembled&#xD;
th handle protruding from my vest, and&#xD;
to Harry regheated him to reply&#xD;
o   ni in the affirmative, and direc&#xD;
' tWttentiou to me. 'Turning towards&#xD;
y perceived my sham weapon&#xD;
*high 'sufciently satisfied them upon&#xD;
t portant point; and they soon after.&#xD;
ids ttrnsd down a path' and "vamosed"&#xD;
d            o   a  tni s  atisfied"  that  this ' ruse  had&#xD;
a' d u a brush withthem eto say the&#xD;
'''heir manner was certainly very&#xD;
yilealariand as Harry remarked, they&#xD;
Woi&amp;amp;',aaviterin modo," if not "fortzter in&#xD;
.w0 :crved aside, into another path&#xD;
sqil ate:r this affair, and in two hours&#xD;
t $= e~q u e to a collection of six or seven&#xD;
'h!ltsesin m nairowM'opening ota the mar-&#xD;
gnoadeep and rapid stream. We ap-&#xD;
&#xD;
y plied to the first house for entertainment,&#xD;
s' but receiving the cold shoulderwe progee.&#xD;
e ded to another which we tried with no'et.&#xD;
e ter success. They refused all intercourse&#xD;
e with us, denying us even a cup of water.&#xD;
e We had passed nearly through' the&#xD;
t. groop, when observing a woman who&#xD;
g was standing in the door of her :hut&#xD;
y bestowing the maternal contributions&#xD;
o upon her infant "child, I accosted her&#xD;
o asking for water which she iminedi&#xD;
a ately brought. Harry, then enquired if&#xD;
s we could not stop at some of the houses&#xD;
in the - neighborhood during the night.&#xD;
. She shook her head and advised us to&#xD;
be gone ere trouble came upon us.&#xD;
We took the friendly hint and hurried&#xD;
a off; stopping half a mile further on,&#xD;
t we fixed ourselves a shelter for the night&#xD;
I and retiring early, took our supper. out&#xD;
in sleep for the want of'sometliing "more&#xD;
l substantial.&#xD;
l In the morning we made our breakfast&#xD;
upon a few wild berries and tenler buds,&#xD;
t and gaining the margin of the river we&#xD;
stood gazing upon the foaming waters&#xD;
as they rushed madly by,' wondering&#xD;
how we should be able to cross over.&#xD;
Our usual methods were impracticable&#xD;
here. It was to deep for us to ford, and&#xD;
quite too rapid and crooked for a slender&#xD;
raft, such as we had occasionally.been&#xD;
oblidged to tise. We walked dow, then&#xD;
up the stream f r rpany hours, and return-&#xD;
ing nearly to the village, we fell in with&#xD;
a man who upon our request, offered tor&#xD;
put us across for two rnals. (twenty 've&#xD;
cents.) We remarked to him that. we had&#xD;
no money, and after bantering with' hm&#xD;
sometime he finally agreed tor take: Is'&#xD;
over, f'or one of our sheath knives an d&#xD;
Belt. 'fe made thoice'of H arry's as he-&#xD;
&#xD;
4, {,&#xD;
&#xD;
'&#xD;
q&#xD;
,i :&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMLES IN CHL&#xD;
ing the newest and brightest, and produc. we discovered, much to our surprise&#xD;
mg hie boat, we seated oursves  the our bundles were safe ithe' bott&#xD;
bottom and commenced our diagonal tran- immediately suggested itself to; Dr wn4&#xD;
sit. We were swept 'down the stream that our late misfortune was purp s&#xD;
with fearful rapidity, but our ferryman contrived, the rogue being confided titht&#xD;
seemed tg be a complete master of his we should be swept among the r cka aert&#xD;
boat, and familiar with the navigation, drowned, and he wouldthus come int /&#xD;
judging from his sill in clearing the rocks possession of our bundle, which hi ti-&#xD;
and the eddies which danced wildly about cy might have led him to conjecture ea&#xD;
us. So  pid was the river that we were extremely valuable, but how l e oriiV-&#xD;
carried down the stream nearly half a mile ed to secure the prize so effectually flom&#xD;
in crossing a distance of scarce twenty being lost, I am still at a loss to e&#xD;
rods.                               plain.&#xD;
We :had nearly gained the place of This suspicion on my part probe b y&#xD;
landing on the oposite shore, ,,when our kept me afterwards more upon the alert.&#xD;
ferryman, while passing rapidly by a  We were obliged to light a fire for t'e&#xD;
point of land, caught his paddle somehow purpose of drying our clothesdu tdr&#xD;
under the boat, capsizing it 'in an-instant. Spaniard after rumaging in the top 'el'4s&#xD;
The moment we found we were going chapeau, soon drew forth his horn ofii&#xD;
over, both of us sprung, as if by instinct, works, which, together with a pipe&#xD;
towardsthe point of land we were just tobacco which every Spania&#xD;
sweeping past.                      with hijm as a part of his person lpara&#xD;
As Emerged from the water, I found phernalia, soon enabled us to light a re&#xD;
myself rapidly drifting past the boat, and on the shore.&#xD;
exerting myself to the utmost I finally  In the mean time I was engagedrn&#xD;
reached it. . Shaking the water trom my gathering a bundle of' sticks fotihe sittE&#xD;
eyes, Ifound'with satisfaction that both ply. Ven a short distance f&#xD;
of my companions were also sa  cling- fire chanced to turn myface i&#xD;
ing to the boat,, the Spaniard'.ting at section, and what was my sn'rila h"&#xD;
the stern, grasping a long bush which observe through a small openingof&#xD;
hung over the water, thus..keeping the bushes, the treacherous Spaniardn-fl.&#xD;
boat from  drifting dopw  stream. 'Just tiously creeping towards Harry =whom&#xD;
below us we;'observed with horror, that seated upon the ground, in the a&#xD;
the water rushed foaming among, sharp hauling off his boots&#xD;
sunkerrocs, where, had we been swept  My fears were intynediatelyred&#xD;
by the cur ent, we should have been im- suddenly and 'ste lthily reti  e, .&#xD;
mediatly drowned. "                 arrived near them just as lthe' vU&#xD;
We soon gained theshore, hauling our grasped his knife to plunge irdo tf&#xD;
craft along by 41he limbs that, fringed the pf my companionW '. gave a' shnt&#xD;
bnk    y suspicinthat foul play bad sprang forurd in: tirzis'tocatli  8&#xD;
been used, were somewhat excited, when, ing blade.  The' forces wit whk&#xD;
upon righting up the N0at on he shore, sprang upon him, bore the villaine e&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7511-00000015"/>&#xD;
1A 4LJJEIJALo.&#xD;
&#xD;
#hand wrenching the weapon from&#xD;
iS  I held it over him in the act of&#xD;
'thisfurious struggles, when Har-&#xD;
forward 'and grasped my arm,&#xD;
ryn, don't kill him--don't kill him!&#xD;
we hill have the whole neighborhood&#xD;
tIpon us if you do."&#xD;
After a few' moments deliberation we&#xD;
concluded, to put hirm into his boat and&#xD;
shove'her off into the stream, as being&#xD;
the lest way to get clear of him.&#xD;
Having dried our clothes, we gathered!&#xD;
up our bundles and pushed on from this&#xD;
dangerous neighborhood as fast as our&#xD;
legs would carry us. It appeared evi-&#xD;
dent that the Spaniard had calculated&#xD;
his chances, presuming that if he could&#xD;
suddenly kill Harry, who was a large&#xD;
aiad muscular man, he could with ease&#xD;
manage so light a person as I was; yet I&#xD;
felt t the time, when my nerves were&#xD;
stung by the excitement, that I could&#xD;
hive easily mastered two such as him;&#xD;
and I have no doubt I could, as my&#xD;
strength was always greater, and my&#xD;
muaseles quickly nerved up during the&#xD;
first moments of excitement, enablingme&#xD;
alwrysj n a rough and tumble scuffle on&#xD;
ai hps deck, to throw my antagonist at&#xD;
first, even if vastly my superior, in&#xD;
weight and size. In fact my greatest&#xD;
conceit at that time, ran in the direction&#xD;
&#xD;
along the rout. We passed several tar&#xD;
houses, wit out presuming to gain an in1&#xD;
troduction, until Towards evening when&#xD;
arriving near a small building around&#xD;
which we saw several children at play&#xD;
we ventured to try our success once&#xD;
more. We were however, uncerimoni"&#xD;
ously repulsed ; they turned loose upon&#xD;
us two large dogs, from which we were&#xD;
glad to make a hasty retreat, after having&#xD;
been handled by them in no ceremoni-&#xD;
cus manner.&#xD;
From all these symptoms we judged&#xD;
that our lot had been cast amongst a bar.&#xD;
barous people ; every traveller who had&#xD;
passed us of late. had whipped up his&#xD;
horse, refusing all communication with&#xD;
us. After halfan hour's further progress&#xD;
we found that we were nearing a village,&#xD;
and remembering the treatment we had&#xD;
already received front the neighboring&#xD;
villages and hamlets, we naturally hesi-&#xD;
tated to venture among the inhabitants of&#xD;
the village before us, fearing even worse&#xD;
results might occur, 'from such a proceed-&#xD;
ing; we therefore struck from the path&#xD;
concluding to pass. the village - by a cir-&#xD;
cuitous out, preferring to spend the&#xD;
night i ' e woods, rather than venture&#xD;
among the half barbarous Spaniards.&#xD;
After leaving the path we wandered&#xD;
on through swamps and low shrubs, over&#xD;
&#xD;
9±', my athletic properties, and physical thick hedges and wind falls, until it be.&#xD;
force, which was more than an average came so dark we could 'continue no fur.&#xD;
fo my age and, stature.            there; when having come upon a thick&#xD;
:tut course led us for many miles cluster of bushes, somewhat resembling&#xD;
through alovely country, abounding in our alder, we drept into the centre of the&#xD;
grapes, peaches, pears and apples thicket, and made our bed among the&#xD;
ih, a undance.  English walnits andjroots ,and dry sticks thatcovered the&#xD;
i l   trees were scattered in profusion ground.&#xD;
&#xD;
M.ABLE . fN CmJ&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER VI.&#xD;
It was a pleasant starlight evening end., In vain I gatheredethe folds,&#xD;
when we first sought our couch. but we saturated garments about me, endeaho ,&#xD;
had scarcely closed our ey s to sleep, ing to shut ouj the visions:that Wei&#xD;
ere we were aroused by the sound of growing too wild and oppressive  T&#xD;
distant thunder, and soon the fitful moan- furious wind :sounded drearilt u&#xD;
irgs of the wind told of a gathering the forest, like that inysterious  oanin.F&#xD;
storm y whichincreasing, at first accoi- of the ocean which with the cre orn&#xD;
panied by large drops of rain, soon burst mariner is the unwelcome hriager&#xD;
upon us in all its 'fury.  The dismal an approaching storm. At last the r '&#xD;
sound. of the pattering rain, the surges of blast came sweeping along withlg&#xD;
'the forest, and our own isolation and lit- less fury, .tearing oft the frail lisro~s &amp;amp;&#xD;
tleness, filledB mewith.a sense of the{the tortured pine, and scatteringthemo}&#xD;
most complete and helpless solitude.  every side, as it wended upon aitreia&#xD;
,Ahe rai nhaving penetrated our leafy of destruction and death.  eight&#xD;
roof, soon drove down in cutting blasts its horrors, hovered with vae g&#xD;
upon.ou' drenched and, shiverirng: forms. the cheerless and desolate forest,&#xD;
Oh never shall I forget that long and te- was gloom and blackness. I turned'&#xD;
dious night. In vaii I rolled from  sise aching head in 'vain  for shelter s,4ti&#xD;
to s id of myswimming couch, hoping drenchirg rain swept fiercely  th  .  tt&#xD;
to wory myselfinto, a slumber, but nottfrait retreat; and the glo  ofth&#xD;
moment of relic would, find, not a1 threw ts shadowy"dfantastic&#xD;
shadow of forgetfu  ss crossed my sleep-laround, while soundswild ;atd fea f&#xD;
less brain, but images wild and feartul were heard above the' storm. ,At&#xD;
would gather in the storm, causing my vale one ,might imagine he head&#xD;
wet and matted looks almost to stand on sharp bark of the wolf, or the distant&#xD;
&#xD;
01 Not:~&#xD;
&#xD;
.r'&#xD;
&#xD;
d&#xD;
n&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7511-00000016"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
g rwl of some other wild animal rise on&#xD;
the night blast, and then again all wasc&#xD;
still, save the distant sound of the patter-&#xD;
ing ainhieh came sinking to the heart.&#xD;
A   zgi Mthe distance would Gome their&#xD;
deeprumbling sound, as of some mighty&#xD;
tor arch of the wood torn from his bed&#xD;
by the sweeping night blast, and hurled&#xD;
thundering to the ground. And then tlje&#xD;
sounds died away among the trees;&#xD;
again the furious wind and rain alone&#xD;
swept by, the bitter blast howled on, and&#xD;
th. ominous wispering of spirits rose and&#xD;
fell.&#xD;
Willis has said that the sound of the&#xD;
dropping rain is musical and soothing to&#xD;
th,,ear.. It may have uttered melodious&#xD;
s nds to his poetic ear, while snugly&#xD;
sandwitched between two woolen sheets&#xD;
iii his garret bed; but had he made his&#xD;
solitary mid-night bed with us, in the&#xD;
miasmatic bogs of Chili, during that dis-&#xD;
vnal stormy night,: it would 'have struck&#xD;
1ess soothingly on his ear.&#xD;
At last we counted through the long&#xD;
l hours of that strange and sleepless&#xD;
fight, and the gray gloomy dawn came&#xD;
struggling through our leafy casement.&#xD;
At the first peep of day we arose from&#xD;
our disagreeable couch, completely satu-&#xD;
rated with the rain and stiffened with the&#xD;
cold, looking life a mere vapid dilution of&#xD;
our former selves. We rubbed ourbenumb-&#xD;
ed limbs, and performed numerous calis-&#xD;
thenic. exercises to restore the nearly&#xD;
suspended circulation. Our drenching&#xD;
hadsuperseded the necessity of the usual&#xD;
morning ablutions, and without any fur-&#xD;
ther cold water applications, we continued&#xD;
all' dripping; on our weary march, the&#xD;
storm having settled into a cold and driz-&#xD;
zly rain. Sadly and silently we picked&#xD;
&#xD;
our forlorn way onward, wading streams,&#xD;
climbing slippery precipices and stumi.&#xD;
ling over rocks arid underbrush.&#xD;
It cleared off about noon, and the smil.&#xD;
ing sun burst upon us, cheering our droop.&#xD;
ing spirits, and stirring the blood again,&#xD;
gladly through our veins, after it had&#xD;
been so long shrunk away from the sur-&#xD;
face, to escape the chilling touch of the&#xD;
night blast. We removed our wet&#xD;
clothes, and hung them to dry in the sun&#xD;
while we reposed under the shade of the&#xD;
wide speading trees.&#xD;
Our situation among a race of people&#xD;
as ignorant and wild almost as the un-&#xD;
tamed savage, was gloomy and unenvia-&#xD;
ble to the most romantic mind, and I&#xD;
mentally admitted  that "happy is he&#xD;
who neVer saw the smoke of a strangers&#xD;
fire."&#xD;
Having clothed ourselves and gather-&#xD;
ed a few berries and other fruit which&#xD;
we found in the vicinity, to eat on our&#xD;
way, we cut two stout walking sticks,&#xD;
and trudged on, hoping soon to again'&#xD;
discover the path from which, we had&#xD;
wandered the previous night. About' 5&#xD;
o'clock we found ourselves ascending a&#xD;
long sloping hill, its waving and undula-.&#xD;
ted surface abounding with thick clusters&#xD;
of a thorny minosa ; upon reaching the&#xD;
suinit the view that burst upon us was&#xD;
grand and beautiful. A world of, forest&#xD;
lay spread out before us, 'with many a&#xD;
beautiful lake glistening in its green fringe&#xD;
like a basin of silver; the long rapid&#xD;
streams that crossed and skirted' the&#xD;
green carpet, and scattered openings,&#xD;
were enchanting an beautiful' beyond&#xD;
description. On the opposite side of the&#xD;
valley, a long ridge of mountains reared&#xD;
their lofty summits in the distance, to dis-&#xD;
&#xD;
YI&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILL&#xD;
&#xD;
U&#xD;
&#xD;
l:"k VA'L-C.s&#xD;
&#xD;
pate our further progress. After a long to bring back my recollection to hoi&#xD;
time spent in gazing upon the lovely and them, and it would have 'beeA&#xD;
scene, and settling the geography, we pleasant cout Ihave had the faithto e&#xD;
decided that our course must be over thelicve it, but n.  fiucy was too weak,&#xD;
ridge, which rose on the opposite side.  sustain the speh  rticularly as the pee-&#xD;
We descended into the valley, and pie of my native v.lage are wholly unad.&#xD;
night coming on, we began in season to dieted to the 'practice of magical ats,&#xD;
prepare ourselves a nice warm shelter, for save now andathen a temporary sojourne.&#xD;
fear another storm might surprise us, as  We were up and stiring betimes,' eager&#xD;
it had the proceeding night ; a catastro- toresumeour journey, and followed alo'g&#xD;
phe, which we were in no humor to the margin of the stream near which(&#xD;
brave again. I killed a small bird with had pitched our tent. This ran murimte&#xD;
a stone, which I chopped up, mixing with ing along its pebbly bed, now sweeping&#xD;
green chesnut-meat and wild sorrel leaves, gently round some monster rock,\t'hl}W&#xD;
and eat with a relish which Iremember leaping down a broken bank, with wild&#xD;
to this day.,                       and boisterous mirth, as if in imitation 6f&#xD;
It was a singular coincidence, we each the far famed niagara, until a sharp&#xD;
of us this night dreamed of our distant gle in its bedpsent it coffin a different di&#xD;
homes in the pine tree State, and were reaction from our course.&#xD;
greeted i ourslumbers by fond parents, eh&#xD;
We journied on with! our packs u pon&#xD;
brothers, sisters. and friends, as though our shouldersliete n gx.'&#xD;
oursholdeslke the wandering eile of&#xD;
they had thought us long since dead. Erin seeking in our own beloved lnda&#xD;
Theserecollections of home, and distant e  aso           i   r&#xD;
. home and a rest from British arrogance,&#xD;
friends' softened  our hearts.  Every&#xD;
and cruelty. How we envied the plenty&#xD;
person who has known in the days of his and hospitality which he meets at every&#xD;
boyhood what it was to dwell in a happy&#xD;
step. 'Hard may be their lot compared&#xD;
home, to feel his little heart beat with&#xD;
with those who can "set under their own&#xD;
joy ,at the -similes, and caresses of fond,&#xD;
tevsmlesndho(arseesroffndlvines and fig trees;" but who ever heard&#xD;
parents; every one who has ever knelt of their being repeatedly&#xD;
.~~~                        ~~ othibenreeatedly driven from, the&#xD;
at his  mother's  feet,  and  earned  to  lisp d fr,&#xD;
Ins venng paye, ca sypathse  ithdoor, refused' a crumi of 'bread, 'or a etu.&#xD;
his evening prayer, can sy apathise with o  odwtr  n   bie    otk&#xD;
feelngsat hathou. Erlyassci-of cold water, and obliged 'to' take u&#xD;
our feelings at that hour. Early associ- hi bd ngtatrngho=hcf&#xD;
ourtheir abode night after night, on thleCold&#xD;
ations, and the happy, joyoun days of round; especially in a country bou&#xD;
childhood contrasted with our, present&#xD;
situation filled our minds with gloomily furnished by a kind Providence with&#xD;
.thoughts, and sorrowful forebodings.  the fruits of a luxurious clm&#xD;
To rally my gloomy thoughts, I boldly  Two hours travel brought us to the base&#xD;
asserted to Harry that those forms which of the mountainous ridge we had seen in&#xD;
I had seen, by some misterious enchant-' the distance looming up into the heavens&#xD;
nient, had asked and found this method with topping peals and ragged sides.&#xD;
&#xD;
;&#xD;
&#xD;
u&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7511-00000017"/>&#xD;
On nearing the mountains we found&#xD;
them to be a long continuous ridge, tow-&#xD;
ering far into the clouds, and crossing&#xD;
our course at right angles. They seemed&#xD;
indeed to form an impenetrable barrier&#xD;
to our farther progress, unless we could&#xD;
'discver some ravine or gap through&#xD;
which we might pass. Having travelled&#xD;
along the foot of the ridge, for two or&#xD;
bree' hours, without finding any pass&#xD;
through which we could reach the oppo-&#xD;
site side, we came to the conclusion to&#xD;
cl mberup the side of the mountain and&#xD;
sale its heights at the most favorable&#xD;
place which presented.&#xD;
We accordingly began our ascent at&#xD;
the lowest point, where the ridge appear-&#xD;
ed not more than seven or eight hundred&#xD;
feet in height; the sequel however,&#xD;
proved that it must have been mnch&#xD;
more.&#xD;
Near the base of the mountain the an-&#xD;
gle was not more than 25or 30 0, and the&#xD;
ground plentifully covered with low shrub-&#xD;
bery, our progress for the first hour was&#xD;
&#xD;
comparatively easy. From this time we&#xD;
found our way becoming more steep&#xD;
and ragged, the shrubbery began to disap.&#xD;
pear, the soil was loose and broken, and&#xD;
our footing was painfully insecure. - The&#xD;
earth and gravel crumbled away beneath&#xD;
us at almost every step, and the larger&#xD;
stones went leaping and plunging into&#xD;
the vale below, still with our eyes fixed to-&#xD;
wards the summit, we boldly pushed on,&#xD;
until obliged to rest from mere exhaustion&#xD;
and fatigue.&#xD;
On looking into the bosom of the val-&#xD;
ley below us, we were fully aware how&#xD;
steep and dangerous had been our course,&#xD;
and how much more formidable it ap-&#xD;
peared to us now, than while toiling up&#xD;
the ascent. But when we. turned and&#xD;
gazed at the prospect above us, we were&#xD;
almost discouraged, upon observing that&#xD;
scarcely one third of our task had been&#xD;
accomplished, and the remainder of the&#xD;
ascent appeared fearfully steep.-&#xD;
Shelving ledges, perpendicular cliffs,&#xD;
and overhanging crags, seemed to threat-&#xD;
&#xD;
1'S'V r ~ re&#xD;
31i&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER VII.&#xD;
&#xD;
en us with instant destruction, by falling point of another, similar to itself at a dise&#xD;
and sweeping us down this fearful de- tance of about three feet; when the il&#xD;
clivity.                           suddenly gave way in my grasp, and&#xD;
After a few moments rest, we again nearly lossing my balance, I for a rue-&#xD;
commenced scrambling upward assisting meant hung topling over the side. This&#xD;
each other as best we could over the most gave my nerves so severe a shock that it&#xD;
difficult and dangerous places. We soon was a long time ere I could stfieiertly&#xD;
found however, that we had passed the compose myself to make another effort&#xD;
Rubicon, that our only safety was to ad- in which I finally succeeded.&#xD;
vance forward. To retrace our steps was I now began to fully realize, that eve-&#xD;
utterly impossible, we had ascended too ry step might be my last, and with ,My&#xD;
far for that, even had we seriously cor- heart clear up in my neck, trembling in&#xD;
templated a retrograde movement. The every joint, like the wind shaken reed,&#xD;
only course left us was to push on and crawled on, clinging with a tenacious&#xD;
trust to fortune.                  grasp to the rocky wall. My eyes were&#xD;
I gradually edged away from Harry almost blinded by the perspiration, and&#xD;
who was a short distance in advance, to dust. The coarse sand had insinuated it-&#xD;
keep clear from the falling stones and self among my clothes, and so irritated&#xD;
dirt which come rattling down upon me. my skin that every movement was yat%&#xD;
Having now been full three hours on this ful in the extreme, and my raging: thirst&#xD;
perilous march, my thirst became so in- almost maddened me to desperation, still&#xD;
tense that I was glad to moisten my I kept moving mechanically forward with&#xD;
parched lips with the blood that trickled scarcely a hope of ever reaching the tap&#xD;
from my lacerated hands. With panting  I can even at this distant hour, vividly&#xD;
heart, and eyes dimmed with dust and recall every feeling and thought, of thi&#xD;
perspiration, I picked my way upward, awful period during which I was scaling&#xD;
now grasping a twig to assist me over a those dizzy crags, and hanging overtilse&#xD;
treacherous point, then gaining a narrow frightful depths,with the grimunwelce&#xD;
winding shelf, or wrinkle on the face of visitor staring me full in the face.&#xD;
the mountain, I would tremblingly creep With a panting heart I clambered on,&#xD;
along the crumbling precipice, by hug- along the very brink of the beetling cragi&#xD;
ging my, form as closely as possible to the which in some' places projected over the&#xD;
perpendicular wall above me, scarcely savage gulf; the wall so deep and per i&#xD;
daring to cast 'my eyes for a moment dicular that a plumb line might have Iieri'&#xD;
down the steep precipice by my side.  dropped a thousand feet below, almost&#xD;
On 'arriving at the abrupt termination without touching the wall. From thWf&#xD;
of one of those narrow and dizzy shelves, dizzy height I still ascended, mistrusting&#xD;
along which I had been groping "on all- every foot-hold, and cautiously ehaling&#xD;
fours," and crawling serpent like, I laid every root and twig, before traitix~46&#xD;
hold of a green bush that appeared firm- their support, and often would thy uar&#xD;
ly imbeded, in the rifted ledge, and en- in my hand showing the gossamer thread&#xD;
4eavored by ,its support to reach the as its were, by which my life was ass&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7511-00000018"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
"RAMBLES IN CHILI.                 3)&#xD;
&#xD;
peed, and the: necessity of unccasing'terly impossible, it having been with great&#xD;
o ltion inmy movements.           peril that Ihad gained the spot where I&#xD;
snai) swell or angle in the rocky wall then stood. Above me there was no chance-&#xD;
had:shut Harry from my view, but still I for escape, nothing was seen but the&#xD;
et ildoccjsionally hoar his cheering voice, smooth surface of the rock. Every bush&#xD;
or adeep rumbling sound would apprise and projecting crag that seemed to offer-&#xD;
m. that he had torn from its bed some aid had failed me; my brain grew giddy&#xD;
huge stoun, which startlingly awoke 'the when I gazed below. My left foot was.&#xD;
savage solitudes of these dreary wilds, in becoming weak, and my knees began to'&#xD;
its fearfully. impetuous course downward tremble violently. A short distance be'&#xD;
toth® plains.                       yond the reach of my right foot was a,&#xD;
At such moments of fearful anxiety I slight projecting corner of the ledge,&#xD;
would hold my breath in silence, expect- which I fancied I could reach, by letting'&#xD;
ing, also to hear the outcry of my corn- go my hold and jumping towards it, but&#xD;
panion,.as.he slid into the.depths below. for aught I knew, it was as frail as those'&#xD;
It was pot until I again heard his move- that had already crumbled beneath my&#xD;
ments, or his encouraging hail, -,that I feet; the chances were ten to one&#xD;
could breathe freely. While worming against me. If it gave way I should of&#xD;
pyself along the top of one of these nar course accompany it, in its fearful de.&#xD;
row scales of the mountain, my course scent; if perchance I failed to reach it,.&#xD;
ha led ne upward in a nearly perpen- death was. equally sure. I could not re-&#xD;
dicular~direction for some twenty feet, main where I then was but a few mo--&#xD;
with scarcely room to squeeze along. inents longer. Appalled and rendered&#xD;
At'  he top of the Jangle, I came to a desperate by the dreadful fate that threat-&#xD;
r"e evei)spot, but here the ndge along ened me, I made up my mind to try the&#xD;
which I had dragged myself suddenly fatal leap! I loosened my hold of the&#xD;
terminated in an abrupt angle of the wall. rock, at the same time forcing my head&#xD;
On arriving .at this stage of my zig-zag and shoulders slightly in advance of the&#xD;
journey, while striving to pass round the angle, and while my body was swaying&#xD;
angle, I found myself caught in a criti- fearfully to and fro on the baatling crag. I&#xD;
ca situation, the very recollection of made a desperate, spring across the fright-&#xD;
which makes me shudder. Every twig ful gulf. My foot caught upon the tiny.&#xD;
arid root which !eemed to offer the least point, where I hung for a moment in hor-&#xD;
sppportgave way one after another, snap- rible supense. -I had not given my body&#xD;
ping like pipe stems as I touched them, quite impetus enough, and I now felt that&#xD;
admy heart sunk dispondingly within I could not retain my balance; I was&#xD;
mea smy horrid situation became more falling backwards.! . To save myself I&#xD;
rnifest. I stood upon my left foot, part- pressed my -left foot with-violence against&#xD;
lyfaeigg the wall, at the extreme point the side'of the ledge, which held me- for-&#xD;
o the angle; my right foot seeking in a moment while I convulsively grasped'&#xD;
vain for A resting place. To turn round the rough wall with my right hand. To'&#xD;
mn rny narrow hinuts and retreat, was ut- my inexpressible joy, my fingers penetra-&#xD;
&#xD;
I1&#xD;
&#xD;
ted a slight crevice of therek, when I harry some eight or nine feet below sitt&#xD;
immediately recovered myself.  After ting across this broken trunk, "high&#xD;
regaining my upright position,in a few mo- anchored in the rifted rock," and with ap-&#xD;
ments morel had,. both feet again upon a parent indifferance, whistling someAfa-&#xD;
flat surface, and was in momentary safe- vorite air. " Halloo monkey !" cried 4&#xD;
,ty.                                'you are taking it fair and easy, dodging&#xD;
The tears of gratitude to heaven for my abou ton these pegs in the wall, for ex&#xD;
sunlobked for delivererance, gushed freely ereise ?  However I am glad to find yot&#xD;
fr-om my eyes. My frame seemed per- alive which I scarcely expected."&#xD;
fectly exhausted, and my brain was for a  "Well! heaven be praised" cried Har-&#xD;
moment completely bewildered with the ry turning his eyes up towards me, bearlid&#xD;
frightful risk I had just ran. After a few ing with joy and stisfaction. "I never&#xD;
moments I ventured to hail my compan- expected to see you again. I fell fron.&#xD;
ion, and hearing no reply, my heart mis- tlhat craggy jet, to the right, and just&#xD;
gave me. Still it may be, thought Ithat I above you, and landed in this tree just -a-&#xD;
am so exhausted and weak I did not at you see me, and here Ilhad made up my&#xD;
first mike myself heard, and I again mind, I should have to remain until thef&#xD;
raised my voice to'its utmost power, but birds carried me off by piece-meal."&#xD;
no answer came. I eagerly scrambled   "Did you hear me hail you a few me&#xD;
up, as just above me appeared to terrni- tnents since," I inquired,&#xD;
nate the swell that separated us. I -soon  "Yes, but I concluded you could not&#xD;
gained this point, and gazed down for poor get near me, and resolved to keep mnUnr&#xD;
Harry. After a few moments searching Ifyou take off your jacket and throw in&#xD;
gaze among the broken crags, and shelv- one of the sleeves I think I can haul ry-&#xD;
ing ledges, I discovered him about forty or self up."  I did as he desired, and pla&#xD;
fifty feet from me, setting across the bro- cin the other sleeve in a rent of the rock,&#xD;
ken trunk of a small tree, which had its and planting my knee upon it 'I held it&#xD;
roots deeply imbedded in a crevice of the firmly, while he drew himself up so as te&#xD;
wall, which was completely perpendicu- reach the edgesof the cliff with his hands&#xD;
lar above and around him, thus holding and with my assistance Was soon by&#xD;
him a secure prisoner.              my side.&#xD;
After looking about me for a few mo-  Here we shook the earth ftor p r&#xD;
ments, I noticed that a shelf of the ledge clothes, and sitting down, congratulate&amp;amp;&#xD;
ran nearly to a point just above him. ourselves upon- our success so far. .&#xD;
Along this passage I crept down towaqds was a giddy sight to look below, far doi&#xD;
him without having attracted his obser- into the distantavale from which we. ha4&#xD;
vation. At-the point where the shelf broke with so much toil and peril ascended 4to&#xD;
away,-was a sharp corner, around which this fearful height, where never. before.&#xD;
I easily swung myself, and slid down a had a "heavier foot than the wild heros&#xD;
steep inclined plain to a flat part of the trod." The sound of opr own voices rnig:&#xD;
ledge directly over his head.       strangely on our ears, 'as they echoed&#xD;
Having reached this point I discovered among these solitary wilds where never&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7511-00000019"/>&#xD;
40                       RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
before had human accents broken in gles, scratches and bruises, and many&#xD;
upon the mountain solituide hair-breadth escapes which it would be&#xD;
Having rested our elves we rose to unnecessary to narrate, we finally arrived&#xD;
continue our perpen icular journey. I in safety at the top of the mountain.&#xD;
turried to the place by which I had de. With bleeding limbs, but grateful hearts&#xD;
scended, but soon found that the ascent we immediately threw ourselves upon&#xD;
here,. was impossible;-it being nearly the ground completely exhausted with&#xD;
perpendicular, with nothing to serve as the fatigue of the day.&#xD;
foot holds. Above us was a smooth firm  Our raging thirst, however, would-not&#xD;
wall, without the least rent, crag, or bush allow us.longto rest, but soon drove us&#xD;
to assist us in the assent. To the right, the to seek for 'water. Casting eager glan-&#xD;
shelf on which we stood, terminated in a ces into every hollow and crevice, ,we&#xD;
dirdet perpendicular fall of unmeasurable soon discovered a, clear spring gushing&#xD;
depth. Harry suggested that I should out from beneath a shelving rock which&#xD;
clamber upon his shoulders and endeavor looked as inviting as a similar one did to&#xD;
tog each the edge of the shelf above us, Hagar in the wilderness. I kneeled upon&#xD;
which in fast was the only feasible the bank and the long draught which I&#xD;
scheme we could adopt. I accordingly then took was the most delicious one of&#xD;
mounted upon his shoulders, and after my life.&#xD;
stretching myself almost out of my The sun sank in beauty and grandeur&#xD;
,leeves, found that I could reach only o behind the western hills soon after our ar-&#xD;
within a few inches of the top. .I made rival at the summit. The beautiful golden&#xD;
one or two further attempts but could notints and sparkling rays reminded us that&#xD;
succeed, and was- obliged to dismount. she must be doubly beautiful and glori-&#xD;
&#xD;
Then we commenced "cudgeling" oni&#xD;
brains anew, to devise some means of&#xD;
overcoming these obstacles. My eye by&#xD;
chance fell upon a loose fragment of the&#xD;
ledge, which I placed under Harry's foot.&#xD;
and found it worked to a charm. I was&#xD;
raised, when standing again upon my&#xD;
companion's shoulders, sufficiently high&#xD;
t -reach the edge of the shelf, and was&#xD;
soon at the top. Having bent down a&#xD;
pliant branch which grew upon the edge&#xD;
of the cliff, Harry laid hold of the end,&#xD;
aid after testing its strength, soon stood by&#xD;
thy Wide.&#xD;
From this point, after numerous strug.]&#xD;
&#xD;
ous in her rising, and we determined to&#xD;
avail ourselves of this elevated position&#xD;
to view a scene so grand and sublime as&#xD;
a sunrise, amid the snow capped An-&#xD;
des.&#xD;
We selected a suitable place for shel-&#xD;
ter upon the margin of the, stream, by&#xD;
the side of a high rock, against which we&#xD;
placed long poles, and covered them&#xD;
over with brush; inside we placed the&#xD;
sofest bows we could gather.   Thus&#xD;
again, supperless, we sought our couch,&#xD;
on which we threw our weary limbs,,and&#xD;
I slept during the night.as sound as&#xD;
though rolled in the nicest rose blanket.&#xD;
&#xD;
'i&#xD;
&#xD;
U&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER VIII.&#xD;
Seamen in general are not a praying stealing on, and soon it began to re4e&#xD;
class ;. not so much so as they should be, the openings in the eastern mountaia&#xD;
considering their dangerous and eventful ridges, as if the narrow gorges were&#xD;
lives; yet I had not altogether forgotten lighting up with internal fires., The red&#xD;
the pious lessons I had often received glare still kept creeping on with deep&#xD;
from my now sainted parents, and I did ening tints, and gently gilding the fleecy&#xD;
sometimes follow their precepts acid ex- clouds that lay hovering above the moun-&#xD;
ample. That night, I am not ashamed tain tops.  The sublime scenery. w&#xD;
to say I offered up a feeble yet fervent opened in all its grandeur.' The clouds&#xD;
prayer to God, acknowledging his pro- were seen first fringed with crimson and&#xD;
tecting care and invoking his continued gold; thee, a beautiful pink, nestled in&#xD;
blessing.                          the folds, and lastly a delicate border oft&#xD;
Harry awoke me while the stars were clear silvery white, like the bright aurielt&#xD;
.yet bright ; a sweet gentle breeze was display of high northern latitudes, liand&#xD;
playing about the mountain tops, and we thie margin of these floating wreaths,&#xD;
were delighted to 'find it a clear, fresh, While the glorious sun came striggIg&#xD;
.and glorious morning. We gained the up behind the mountains, gaily mantling&#xD;
highest point in the vicinity, and calmly the eastern sky, with crimson, another,&#xD;
waited in anticipation of the glorious and still more gorgeous scene burst.upon&#xD;
spectacle. We were not long kept in our view in the opposite horizon; the scene&#xD;
waiting ere Aurora modestly began her had apparently changed suddenly from&#xD;
work by slightly 9aling the stars in the the east, and the brilliant view fleeted&#xD;
eastern horizon, and they soon went out across to the lofty range of snow capped&#xD;
one after another. As the last one faded mountains, rising with glittering white-&#xD;
Way, the faint light in the east came ness, peak after peak, in the south west&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7511-00000020"/>&#xD;
RAMBLE IN CIIILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
ern horizon, and standing out in bold re-&#xD;
lief against the clear sky. On these&#xD;
lwhite pyramidial peaks, the sun now&#xD;
strikes, lighting with its first rays, sum-&#xD;
mit after summit, and pyre after pyre,&#xD;
setting them all glistening with rosy1&#xD;
flames, like blazing cressets, kindled in&#xD;
the sky. Ten thousand hues resplend-&#xD;
ent with beauty were flickering and&#xD;
dancing among the craggy peaks, glow-&#xD;
ing with radient.splendor on our dazzled&#xD;
sight, and as the golden light descended&#xD;
the steep mountain sides, the whole range&#xD;
seemed dyed with glowing pink, and&#xD;
covered with sparklin g ge ms.&#xD;
What an intermingling of lovely hues&#xD;
and shades was here ! We stood silent&#xD;
and breathless, gazing upon the magni-&#xD;
ficent panorama, as though we feared the&#xD;
kast movement might dissolve the spell&#xD;
and break the enchantment; so supernat-&#xD;
ural and radiant was the vision, so sud-&#xD;
den and full of unimaginable beauty, so&#xD;
nvishingly delightful were the splendors&#xD;
which shot before us !&#xD;
"In breathless awe our eyes&#xD;
Coursed ip and down along the living light,&#xD;
Now low, and now aloft, and now around&#xD;
Visiting every step, each mount did seem&#xD;
Colossal ruby, whereon so inwrought&#xD;
Thesunbeam glowed, yet soft, it flamedintense&#xD;
Sextacy of glory."&#xD;
We watched the sun's rays as they&#xD;
s'.le farther down the mountains side,&#xD;
end saw the exquisite pink and rosy hues&#xD;
gradually lade away into the clear light&#xD;
of day, and then the lakes, forest, and&#xD;
vers in the valley below us, wveie light.&#xD;
d ip in turn, and became flooded with&#xD;
the golden sunshine of a glorious morn-&#xD;
The mountain sloped off on the west&#xD;
with i~ gradual desceit into the valley&#xD;
&#xD;
below; down this declivity we started on&#xD;
the run, and bounding forward with in-&#xD;
credible rapidity we soon reached the&#xD;
valley, which on all sides presented a&#xD;
fetile appearance, and our hunger now&#xD;
prompted us to seek the where-with-all to&#xD;
satisfy its cravings.&#xD;
We diligently searched about for those&#xD;
green berries which had heretofore( so&#xD;
much contributed to- our support. We&#xD;
discovered several different kinds but as&#xD;
we were totaly unacquainted with their&#xD;
properties we feared to eat them, and&#xD;
were forced to satisfy our present wants&#xD;
by chewing the bark of several trees&#xD;
which we knew from previous use were&#xD;
not poisonous.&#xD;
We wandered along without keeping&#xD;
any regular course until late in the&#xD;
afternoon when crossing one of theasmall&#xD;
streams that intersected the ground, we&#xD;
came suddenly upon what appeared to&#xD;
be a foot path indistinctly traced among&#xD;
the grass and roots, and leading up the&#xD;
stream a short distance, when it turned,&#xD;
diverging at right angles from the water.&#xD;
We immediately struck into this path,&#xD;
and rapidly hurried along, feeling confi-&#xD;
dent it woul conduct us to some human&#xD;
abode. Our first conjectures were soon'&#xD;
strengt en d. The track growing more&#xD;
and more c isti ct the farther we advanc-&#xD;
ed.&#xD;
Upon assing a tree which we had&#xD;
observed to bear a singular kind of fruit,&#xD;
I noticed that one of them had been&#xD;
lately plucked, the husks torn off and&#xD;
scattered upon the ground, and a little&#xD;
further on we discovered what appeared&#xD;
to be a piece of the fruit containing th'&#xD;
evident marks of human teeth, a convin-&#xD;
cing proof that it was eatable.. I point-&#xD;
&#xD;
42&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
43&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
ed this out to Harry, who immedi- ourselves approaching a hut by the way&#xD;
ately picked a few of the best lookinglside. Walking boldly up we knocked for&#xD;
ones, proceeded to test the quality, and admitance. No answer being given I&#xD;
we were overjoyed to find the fruit deli- lifted the latch and pushed open  the&#xD;
cious. It was a singular 'kind of fruit door. d We found the hut entirely deser-&#xD;
rather larger than our pippin, with a ted, and with no marks of its very recent&#xD;
rough exterior, but filled with a soft pulp occupation. Our conjectures were vari-&#xD;
resembling somewhat in taste our straw- ous and contradictory concerning the&#xD;
berries and cream; it melts as it were in habitation and its inmates. Aftei- a&#xD;
mouth, and finds its way over the palate fruitless search about the premises, we&#xD;
in a luscious tide.                made preperations for passing the night&#xD;
We also found numerous other trees here. Among the remnants of house.&#xD;
aid delicious fruit, which seemed scat- wifery left scattered about, we had found&#xD;
tered in rich profusion about us. What a'horn of tinder with the accompaning&#xD;
an abundance of wholesome danties, fire apparatus, and resolved to strike a&#xD;
thought I, and all growing here spontan- fire for the mere sociability of the thing.&#xD;
eously for the enjoyment of two wan- I gathered a bundle of dry sticks, and&#xD;
dering sailors, showing the kindness of soon had a bright fire burning among the&#xD;
our good parent in thus spreading a rocks in the center of the room, and the&#xD;
table so bountifully in the wilderness,  smoke went curling up through an apep&#xD;
We were afraid to eat as much as ture in the thatched roof.&#xD;
our appetites craved, having fasted so  We early retired to rest, after covering&#xD;
long, it might produce unpleasant results; a low shelf in one corner: that serve&#xD;
but   r supper of herbs gave us new for the bed, with a profusion of long&#xD;
courag  nd with lighter hearts we con- tender leaves which grew near at hand.&#xD;
tinue  on. Towards sunset we found&#xD;
&#xD;
+      t4 i Jz+',&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7511-00000021"/>&#xD;
It was near to or quite the 'witchingI&#xD;
hour of midnight; my companion was&#xD;
sleeping soundly by my side, and I had&#xD;
Just faflen into a slumber, when I was&#xD;
prtly awakened by feeling. some one&#xD;
take ite by the arm, speaking some low&#xD;
uhinteligable words. At first I turned&#xD;
restless away, but soon becoming more&#xD;
awake I could discern some person stoop-&#xD;
lng over me whose tears fell fast upon&#xD;
my face. I again turned towards the in-&#xD;
truder, and saw by the flickering light&#xD;
that it was a female form. As I turned&#xD;
she cried in an enquiring tone, 'dios de mi&#xD;
alma! tuno T'ilando? Finding myself in&#xD;
this singular manner accosted by a female,&#xD;
I resolved to see what would result from&#xD;
my assuming this new name thus mys-&#xD;
teriously suggested, therefore when she&#xD;
again anxiously repeated the question,&#xD;
I immediately replyed in a low tone 'Si&#xD;
Pi mi amor, yo say Vilando,' she sprang&#xD;
forward grasped me in her arms and&#xD;
devoured me with warm and ardent kiss-i&#xD;
&#xD;
es. These salutations were not in the&#xD;
least objectionable, or repugnant to my&#xD;
feelings, and of course I returned them&#xD;
with interest. She hurried me to the&#xD;
door of the hut where she stood gazing&#xD;
me full in the face, repeating several&#xD;
times 'Vilando! Vilando! usted Livinia' I&#xD;
caught up the name 'Livinia' and repeat&#xD;
ted it with accents of joy while she threw&#xD;
herself wildly in my arms smothering me&#xD;
with her affectionate  caresses. "Mi&#xD;
amor! mi vido!' cried she in her fullness&#xD;
of bliss. In the mean time all I could&#xD;
do was to repeat over what I had now&#xD;
ascertained to be her name and endeavor&#xD;
as far as in me lay, to return a portion of&#xD;
her loving caresses, not wishing to be out-&#xD;
done by a lady in such matters-&#xD;
Our noise soon awoke Harry, viho ex-&#xD;
claimed at the top of his voice, 'What's&#xD;
all this hubbub, what's going on here ?'&#xD;
My new found friend started in surprise&#xD;
on hearinganother voice. I soothed her,&#xD;
and calling to Harry, I hurridly explained&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES I&#xD;
&#xD;
what had passed, requesting him to settle"&#xD;
affairs some how between us, before the&#xD;
morning light should apprise herofthe mis-&#xD;
take. Harry came forward, and after a&#xD;
long conversation learnt that'Vilando' was&#xD;
her husband, who had gone out on a&#xD;
hunting excursion a number of days since&#xD;
and not returning, she had supposed him&#xD;
to be lost, and had therefore left her sol-&#xD;
itary house and returned to her parents,&#xD;
'who lived in the village close by ; that&#xD;
she had seen the smoke and light of our&#xD;
fire, and supposing that Vilando had re-&#xD;
turned she came immediately to meet&#xD;
him. Harry stated that the spirit of 'Vi-&#xD;
lando' her husband, had passed into my&#xD;
form, and in fact that I was "Vilando"&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER IX,&#xD;
&#xD;
N CHILI.                           45&#xD;
way into a village a short distance&#xD;
through the trees, containing some eighz&#xD;
ty or ninety houses, and half as many&#xD;
more in the outskirts.&#xD;
Every thing looked lovely around us&#xD;
as we entered this little villiage. The&#xD;
mornirg was now in its freshness,. the&#xD;
path was skirted by numerous flowers&#xD;
and shrubs of tender and graceful foliage;&#xD;
emerald winged parrots, skiped about&#xD;
among the trees, or whistled shrill and&#xD;
clear from the thatched roof. All along&#xD;
the banks of the river that swept silently&#xD;
through th'e village, were seen rich and&#xD;
luxuriant fruit trees, interlacing theik&#xD;
boughs ; some standing at the very edge&#xD;
of the bank, bending their gracefull bran-&#xD;
ches into the water.&#xD;
Their buildings were the usual frail&#xD;
reed structures, that one would hardly&#xD;
.suppose able to keep out the winter winds&#xD;
as mild and temperate as they are,&#xD;
Within they were if possible less cheer&#xD;
ful. Each house could boast of but'lon&#xD;
room only, which served in all the capac-&#xD;
ities of kitchen, parlor and bedrooni. IY&#xD;
each angle were placed the rustic ben-&#xD;
ches, for the couch, and occupied as a&#xD;
lounge by day, and a bed Jby night. The&#xD;
fire was built among a few loose stones'&#xD;
in the centre of the room, the smoke esca-&#xD;
ping, sometimes through an aperture pur.'&#xD;
posely left in the roof, and again as bed&#xD;
it could through the numerous acci4eilat&#xD;
rents and loop holes ; a few scattered&#xD;
blocks served for moveable seats, but,&#xD;
the ground itself was more frequently&#xD;
used.&#xD;
A flock of eager spectators followed s"&#xD;
along while Harry and our guide, ue4&#xD;
their tongues with the greatest dexterity;&#xD;
that could possibly be, concieved6 It&#xD;
&#xD;
although quite a different looking person&#xD;
than formerly, and could speak but very&#xD;
little spanish, all of which, he explained&#xD;
to her entire satisfaction. I endeavored&#xD;
to confirm the impression, by striving to&#xD;
be as affectionate as a fond and confiding&#xD;
husband should be.&#xD;
Harry and myself determined to adhere&#xD;
firmly to the story of the metempsychosis,&#xD;
well knowing that her good ,graces were&#xD;
desirable to secure our kind reception,&#xD;
and if perchance her husband should re-&#xD;
turn to get out of the scrape the best way&#xD;
, we could.&#xD;
We returned into the hut and having&#xD;
renewed our fire sat down and continued&#xD;
our conversation until morning- The col-&#xD;
loquial part of tjhe interview, I could not&#xD;
engage in, much to my credit, and conse-&#xD;
quently was obliged to go through my&#xD;
part of the play, in pantomime which I&#xD;
did with such gusto as to fairly astonish,&#xD;
Harry, with my repeated outbursts of af-&#xD;
tection, and unceasing admiration of my&#xD;
fair "inimorata." At day light she led the&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7511-00000022"/>&#xD;
48                      RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
.RAMI3LES IN CHILI.                 47&#xD;
&#xD;
appeared to me one complete Babel&#xD;
However, they explained the matter ac&#xD;
agreed upon, which I soon discovered, by&#xD;
the strange and curious glances that were&#xD;
directed towards ne, and the misteriou&#xD;
handling of my person by some of the&#xD;
bold ones among the crowd. The parent.&#xD;
of Livinia readily received me as themi&#xD;
son-in-law, and I was at once domiciliated&#xD;
as Lord of the castle inthe old hut where&#xD;
we had taken up our night's quarters.&#xD;
I cannot think that the whole commu&#xD;
nity actually believed in the story we&#xD;
'had fabricated, but not being able to&#xD;
contradict it or disprove the story, they&#xD;
let it pass, all for 'good gold.'  e en-&#xD;
deavored by every means in our power&#xD;
to gain the good will of the villagers,&#xD;
and were successful to an extraordinary&#xD;
degree. In a few days we were treated&#xD;
and feasted to our hearts content. "Livi-&#xD;
ia I found to be a lively companion, a&#xD;
little given to coqueting with the roystering&#xD;
blades of the village, but posessed of a&#xD;
kind and generous heart, and otherwise&#xD;
sufficiently domesticated. We often at-&#xD;
tended the lightly fandangoes, and Harry&#xD;
and myself frequently took occasion to&#xD;
make ourselves agreeable to the "senori-&#xD;
tas," and, although we were neither of&#xD;
us much destinguished for our galantry&#xD;
among the fair sex, we found our efforts&#xD;
in this line proved eminantly successful&#xD;
among these buinettes. Harry in partic-&#xD;
ular was changed to a regular Lothario&#xD;
and smashed up the young maidens hearts&#xD;
like pipe stems. As for me, such at-&#xD;
tempts were idle, for jealous eyes were&#xD;
ever on the watch.&#xD;
The men were an enervated puerile race&#xD;
spending tleir time chiefly in idling and&#xD;
loafing about, ,when not engaged in the&#xD;
sports ofhhe village.&#xD;
&#xD;
1I one day found a torn and soiled basis-&#xD;
s ness card which by dint of much spelling&#xD;
and supplying dificiencies, I finally made&#xD;
out to read as follows.&#xD;
HAZEN MITCHELL.&#xD;
Dealer in Lumber&#xD;
Bangor, Me.&#xD;
How this card wandered away into&#xD;
this out of the way place, others can&#xD;
conjecture as well as I can, but I care-&#xD;
fully preserved it, as containing the ouly&#xD;
scrap of the English language which I&#xD;
should probably see for some time.&#xD;
Soon after our arrival here, the whole&#xD;
village was thrown into intense excite.,&#xD;
ment, on learning the arrival of a small&#xD;
party of Araucanian Indians in their !vi-&#xD;
cinity. It was probably a small party&#xD;
lured hither by the chase, evidently&#xD;
unconsious of their close proximity to a&#xD;
Spanish town. These Indians ,are a&#xD;
brave and warlike beople, whom the&#xD;
Chilians have never been able to subdue,&#xD;
and they still hold undisputed sway, over&#xD;
a large extent of country. They are di.&#xD;
vided into numerous clans and hold&#xD;
the spanish race in the greatest abhor-&#xD;
ance, waging a war of extermination&#xD;
against the whole race, murdering the&#xD;
inhabitants of the frontier, and frequent-&#xD;
y making descents upon the villages&#xD;
and towns. It was considered by the&#xD;
Spaniards a praiseworthy act, and religious&#xD;
duty, to destroy these terrible enemies&#xD;
whenever chance threw them in their&#xD;
power. The present seemed a fitting&#xD;
opportunity, and the whole male popula"&#xD;
tion capable of bearing arms were soon.&#xD;
in their saddles. Harry and I,'of course&#xD;
could not remain behind, but fully armed&#xD;
and mounted, we joined theft ited&#xD;
&#xD;
J&#xD;
1&#xD;
i&#xD;
i&#xD;
i&#xD;
I&#xD;
j&#xD;
1&#xD;
i&#xD;
i&#xD;
,,&#xD;
;1&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
throng.  The most perfect discipline mined look, and charmed with the courage&#xD;
was preserved. Our commander was he displayed. We were however soon&#xD;
a veteran soldier, who'had fought in the seperated again by the reeling mass of&#xD;
'Liberating army,". under the redoubt- warriors, who were swayed about in the&#xD;
able "San Martin."  We took up our conflict, like the billows of the ocean. j&#xD;
line of march about noon, and in two fell to the",ground foundedd in my ari&#xD;
hours hard riding, our scouts reported us and side, just as the tide of strife and&#xD;
in the vicinity of the enemy. We soon blood receeded from me&#xD;
saw the smoke of their camp fires, curling As I lay upon my grassy bed watching&#xD;
up among the trees less than a mile the death dealing blows of the fierce&#xD;
from our present position.          combitants, I saw the brave youth with&#xD;
We diverged from a direct course, ta- whom I had crossed weapons in the&#xD;
king a circuitous path to the rear, hoping height of the battle, reeling and sinking&#xD;
thus to cut off their retreat and take them beneath the blows of a mass of his victo-&#xD;
by 'surprise. Having made our circuit, rious enemies, anid his tall form fell blee-&#xD;
we turned and stealthily advanced tow- ding by my side beneath the sabres&#xD;
ards their encampment, which they were crushing weight. The spaniardsrushing&#xD;
about breaking 'p preparatory to their with fury upon their prostrate enemy&#xD;
return homewards, They discovered our were about to dispatch him, when I in..&#xD;
approach in time to form themselves for terposed, and even at the risk of my own&#xD;
the attack resolving to sell their lives at life succeeded in staying their uplifted&#xD;
a bloody price. We vastly out-numbered blades.&#xD;
this little band of half naked savages, le alone of all that brave band of&#xD;
yet like heroes they fought and fell ;- at warriors survived the carnage, and furious&#xD;
the first onset, fierce and rapid were and loud were-their demands for the life&#xD;
their blows, as they charged upon our of my, protege; yet I finaly persuaded&#xD;
ranks, but death only was the rep ard of them to grant me this favor, as he was&#xD;
their devoted bravery, and as gras be- wounded and disabled. Harry also seo-&#xD;
neath the mowers scythe, they fell t ick onded me in my efforts in right good&#xD;
and fast upon the plains; still, as t ieir earnest.&#xD;
numbers melted away, they rallied  he  Our wounded, some si or eight in .&#xD;
closer, forming a chain of human  unks, number, were carried on ' ters to the&#xD;
whose bright steel flashed like lightning, village, I had my Indian friend conveyed&#xD;
in the sun. At last a furious charge from to my house, where we were laid side&#xD;
our more numerous troop, pierced their by side upon the same couch, his thank-&#xD;
centre, scattering and breaking  their full looks amply repaying me for inter-&#xD;
ranks, and we were thrown promiscuous- feeding in his behalf.&#xD;
ly together..                         Harry was more fortunate than I was,&#xD;
I found myself hand to hand with a having escaped with a slight discoloratiott&#xD;
noble looking Indian youth, who fought of one of his eyes. The bone of. my&#xD;
with the desperation of a tiger. ' I was right arm was shattered, whild the wound&#xD;
impressed with his resolute and deter- in my side, was but a flesh cut, and&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7511-00000023"/>&#xD;
proved to ho a matter of but little conse- the poor fellow. He caught my hand&#xD;
guence asides from the loss of blood,  and covered it -with kisses, and other.&#xD;
The 'dead bodies of our slaughtered wise manifested his joy. I impressed&#xD;
fows, were buried upon the battle field, the idea forcibly upon his mind, that ho&#xD;
and. the remains of our party were borne should be liberated as soon as he recov-&#xD;
i solemn triumph to the village church, ered,.but that extreme caution must be&#xD;
Where mass and prayers wyre offered for used. He seemed to recover more rap-&#xD;
their souls, and they were buried in all idly after this assurance of being again&#xD;
$Jid Kpomp and- pageantry of the church. restored to his hills and lakes, and of&#xD;
Many a lone virgin knelt down that night, again clasping the forms of loved ones to&#xD;
te pray as only loving woman can pray, his breast,&#xD;
tot~the soul of her departed lover; and   arranged our plans of escape in this&#xD;
ary;a fond bereaved mother, sighed wise. Guvedio was to appear still very&#xD;
over the form of her son, as he lay stretched sick and feeble, when any of the Span.&#xD;
out a mangled corpse upon the bier, but iards were present, but when we were&#xD;
with Spartan pride they bore the crushing alone, he was to exercise  himself as&#xD;
blow, while their religion comforted them much as possible. I had learned from&#xD;
withthe assurance, that this earthly part- him that he was the acknowledged sue&#xD;
jng is.not eternal.                 cessor of the present chief of his -tribe, a&#xD;
,. Between myself and the young Indian kind of'"governor elect." I furthermore&#xD;
captive, soon sprang up a sympathy and found that the chief was not his father,&#xD;
fellow feeling, which was not long in the successor being elected from among&#xD;
-ipening into a firm attachment and sin, the whole tribe, and probably taken on&#xD;
cere friendship. We were in a short account of his acknowledged superiority.&#xD;
time enabled to make ourselves under- I afterwards found that their native gov-&#xD;
stood by signs and looks, and by our dif- ernment was somewhat Pastoral, the&#xD;
6eult and   imperfect communications, chief being elected for life by the free&#xD;
whiled away the tedious hours of our re- suffrages of the whole community ; so&#xD;
povery. I was kindly treated by the that his office is more that of a father and&#xD;
whole neigh borhood, and I rapidly, im- counsellor, than that of a despotic ruler;&#xD;
proved under their kind and skillful treat- that they all looked up to him for advice,&#xD;
mhnt. My Indian friend, whom I shall and that the successor, although not ex-&#xD;
tall by his Indian name "Guvedio," I was actly ehosen, was by common consent,&#xD;
rejoiced , to find recovered as fast as'agreed upon before the decease of the&#xD;
-myself. I learnt from Harry, that it wasincumbent. Guvedio had been admitted&#xD;
the intention to send Guvedio to Morla and as the successor of the old chief, for&#xD;
gpnfine him in a dungeon, if he should three years. He described his country&#xD;
,recover. I imparted this unpleasant in- in such glowing terms that I fairly&#xD;
formation to him, while at the same time beca e enchanted with his description.&#xD;
I gave him to understand, that I should  After I had sufficiently recovered to&#xD;
)assist him to escape to his own country, walk about, Harry one day came to me,&#xD;
Whiich assurance completely enraptured saying that he was about to start in pur-&#xD;
&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
tRA1 i3IES IN c iiiA&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
40 ,&#xD;
&#xD;
48&#xD;
&#xD;
+&#xD;
&#xD;
Wit of a wite. I replied to hira that I&#xD;
thought there was but littl  need of&#xD;
that, but he seriously informed' me that&#xD;
he had heard of a rich old Englishman,'&#xD;
who had a large and valuable plantation,&#xD;
well stocked with cattle &amp;amp;c. He was al-'&#xD;
so the owner of a rich silver mine, a source'&#xD;
of unbounded wealth. This man was re-'&#xD;
ported to have but- one child, ai only&#xD;
daughter, whorl the father had frequent-&#xD;
been heard to say, he desired to marry to&#xD;
some countryman of his' own.&#xD;
The lady was described as, having a&#xD;
remakable strabismus of her eyes, and&#xD;
being somewhat deformed in her person,&#xD;
but Harry declared that the silver-mine&#xD;
would cover all these blemishes, and, he&#xD;
was determined to hunt her up. "But&#xD;
what is the distance to this 'El Dorado,"'&#xD;
I asked. "Some twenty or thirty miles&#xD;
only,-if I find it a pleasant place to live,&#xD;
I shall send for you, and perhaps by the'&#xD;
aid of the old man's silver mine, we shall&#xD;
be able to get back among civilized peo-&#xD;
ple once more."&#xD;
I could say but little for or against the&#xD;
project, and I found it useless to murmur.&#xD;
He parted from me full of visions of fu-&#xD;
ture happiness. I did not fully realize,&#xD;
until after his aepature, how much I was&#xD;
indebted to him for companioLship. . I&#xD;
grew lonesome and melancholy. Ibegan&#xD;
to imagine him in all kinds of danger&#xD;
my fancy pictured him dead or dying a&#xD;
thousand times, and I finally settled&#xD;
down in the firm conviction that I never&#xD;
should see him ag .&#xD;
One day after my Indian friend had&#xD;
fully recovered, and was descanting on1&#xD;
the happiness of his return among his&#xD;
people, I enquired whether they would&#xD;
receve me, if I should accompany him,&#xD;
&#xD;
Ion his retur . He appe as p     ::d&#xD;
|what to say in reply, but soon intgo&#xD;
by his signs that his pedjle were .i tel'&#xD;
opposed to the Sparliards; and wlef I ie&#xD;
formed hini that I was riot a&#xD;
although I could not make hiin u&#xD;
derstand the matter of nati6naliy, le;&#xD;
seemed pleased ; and wofId reped dver&#xD;
American with the most singular and v&#xD;
rious emphasis imaginable; aridl themern&#xD;
"no Spanio," the meaning of Whichlh&amp;amp;&#xD;
perfectly understood. I soon perceived&#xD;
that, as these Indians kniow nodii-sida&#xD;
of races other thannatives and S antardf&#xD;
it would be difficult to make them believe&#xD;
L was not a "Spanio." Still Guvedio, the&#xD;
more he considered the matter, the more&#xD;
anxious he betalne to introduce me to his&#xD;
people, and finally would not admit of a&#xD;
denial. I could but admire the delibera-&#xD;
tiveness with which he canvassed the&#xD;
question of taking me to his home,,and I&#xD;
felt perfectly satisfied after his first decis-&#xD;
ion, it would be safe for me to venture&#xD;
among them.&#xD;
Giving up all hopes that Harry would&#xD;
ever more be heard from, I decided&#xD;
to leave with my Indian friend ; the life&#xD;
that I led having become monotonous in&#xD;
the extreme. We made all our arrange-&#xD;
ments for the departure, and I had the&#xD;
young Indian (still apparently unable to&#xD;
stand 'alone,) conveyed to one of the&#xD;
houses in the village to be cared for,while&#xD;
my cabin was undergoing some repairs.&#xD;
I took this precaution to hide my conni-&#xD;
vance at his escape, not wishing to gain&#xD;
the ill will of those who had thus far be-&#xD;
friended me.&#xD;
The first night after his removal, the&#xD;
sick man disappeared. Their surprise&#xD;
can scarcely be imagined, on finding in&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7511-00000024"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILL&#xD;
the morning that the bird had flown. I lake, agreed upon between us as a place&#xD;
immediately proposed pursuit, but they all of rendesvoitz. There I found him with-&#xD;
acknowledged that it was useless, as he out much trouble, and mounting my&#xD;
had some six or eight hours start, little spare horse, he took the lead and away&#xD;
dreaming that all this time, he was some we scampered through the forest. In&#xD;
half a mile from the place, snugly hid in two days we were beyond the habita-&#xD;
a hole previously prepared. The next tions of the Spaniards, and the third day&#xD;
day I signified my intention of starting off we approached the borders of his own&#xD;
in pursuit of Harry, and providing myself country. We stopped. but twice during&#xD;
with two fleet horses, I started on my the first two days ride, nor more than&#xD;
cruise, leaving written directions for him three hours each pight, on the third how.&#xD;
should he return. Guvedio had preceded ever, we rested ourselves and our jaded&#xD;
me some two or three miles, and had horses during the night.&#xD;
stopped in the neighborhood of a small&#xD;
f-&#xD;
-4&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER X.&#xD;
I shall hurry over the particulars of Of this interesting nation but little, ac-&#xD;
this ride to scenes more interesting. - count has ever been given, and of the&#xD;
Reader, the region tro which we are interior tribes scarcely any thing is known&#xD;
now approaching, and the race I am John'M. Reynolds, Es'. made a short vis-&#xD;
about to describe, is far from being an it into the southern part of the country,&#xD;
imaginary picture. Itis well known to along the sea coast, about the year 1834,,&#xD;
the South American Traveller, that the and published a very interesting account&#xD;
Araucanian Indians still remain in the of the people. This is all we know of&#xD;
same wild and independant state that them, save a few general narratives;&#xD;
they did when Pizarro first landed on and from the deadly hostility existing be-&#xD;
the shores of the Pacific. They have tween the natives and the Spaniards, it&#xD;
sacked and burnt whple towns and villa- seems almost impossible that any of the&#xD;
ges, and laid waste a large extent of whites-unless by some such accidental&#xD;
country. They have also founded cities :hance as befell me-should ever ven-&#xD;
of their own which in turn have fallen ture among them. It is therefore a source&#xD;
into the hands 01 their enemies. The of gratification to reflect that these "Ram-&#xD;
city of Conception, now containing some bles" will .afford some interesting  in-&#xD;
20,000 inhabitants, was founded by the formation concerning a race so peculiar,.&#xD;
Araucanians ; and for many years they and a region so romantic, and delightful.&#xD;
held undisputed possession of a large sea- In the afternoon of the fourth day, while,&#xD;
port town south of Talcahuano called approaching the Indian village, the home&#xD;
"Aranco".                          of Guvedio, he was all alive with excite-&#xD;
It was here that the American ships ment.&#xD;
Hero, Herselin, and Ocean, together with - We had struck t  river upon the&#xD;
the English ship Perseverance, were tak- banks of which the'lage was sitt-&#xD;
en possession of by these natives, in the ated, and were wending our way along&#xD;
year 1820.                         its bank with our jaded beasts, when&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7511-00000025"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILL&#xD;
&#xD;
suddenly I observed lmy companion, leap&#xD;
from his horse crying, "Metina! Metina !" 1&#xD;
and at the same moment, I sawa young l&#xD;
Indian girl bound forward with a light&#xD;
airy spring to his side, apparently as ifi&#xD;
she had just droped from the clouds, and&#xD;
clasping her arms around him  without&#xD;
uttering a word, she stood surveying me&#xD;
with the most wild and enquiring look.&#xD;
I still kept at a respectful distance as I&#xD;
observed Guyedio explaining to her the&#xD;
relation in which I stood to him;'and his&#xD;
obligations to me.&#xD;
It was some time before he could make&#xD;
her understand that I was a friend. At&#xD;
last I deemed it a fitting opportunity for&#xD;
rue tooin te group, and dismounting, 1&#xD;
p uiked an oak-leaf, and approaching the.&#xD;
'timidcreature, I gently placed it in her&#xD;
liand. She receivd the sprig with so&#xD;
find and intelligent a look, as almost in-&#xD;
ced me to imagine she knew the son-&#xD;
tinnent'&#xD;
T will endeavor to describe the appear-&#xD;
-nce of this lovely forest maiden, as she&#xD;
afterwards occupied an important part in&#xD;
the drama of my sojourn among this sin-&#xD;
gular people.&#xD;
She stood about five feet eight inches&#xD;
hg height, straight as- an arrow; her fig-&#xD;
-re was plump rounded and natural,&#xD;
with a stately majestic carriage; her long&#xD;
black hair-as glossy as the ravens pluipage&#xD;
coated in waving tresses down her should&#xD;
deks, the jetty looks clustered in from her&#xD;
tooth brow, by a wreath of wild flow-&#xD;
ers and green leaves, which she wore&#xD;
around her head as gracefully as the&#xD;
"rown of the Brittish Queen.&#xD;
A plume of gaudy colored feathers&#xD;
intng gracefully drooping from her floral&#xD;
head dress, giving her quite a theatrical&#xD;
appearance. Her arge black eyes, were&#xD;
&#xD;
as bright and sparkling, as if a glittering&#xD;
tear was gathering in the rounded orb;&#xD;
her complexion was that of a dark bru.&#xD;
nette, and when the smiled, or was ani-&#xD;
mated in conversation, she . displayed&#xD;
a beautiful set of teeth, pearly white, be.&#xD;
tween a pair of tempting lips, that would&#xD;
almost make a lover forget his mistress.&#xD;
Her dress was of primeval simplicity.&#xD;
It consisted of a plain linen skirt,&#xD;
which was secured aro    her waist,&#xD;
reaching as far down towards her feet,&#xD;
as the skirts, of some of our beautiful dance.&#xD;
ing Nymphs, who have oft and many a&#xD;
time, entranced the patrons of the Bowe-&#xD;
ry.&#xD;
She wore neither shoes or stockings,&#xD;
yet there is not a belle in New England&#xD;
but would have envied, that small ele-&#xD;
gant foot, so narrow, so delicately form-&#xD;
ed, so beautifully turned at the ankle.&#xD;
In her ears she wore the brightest jew-&#xD;
els and fBowers, she could find. Her&#xD;
joyous laugh and gleeful shout, echoed&#xD;
melodiously among the hills. She was&#xD;
as wild and daring as the mountain goat,&#xD;
and almost as fleet and nimble in her&#xD;
antic sports. Such was "Metina" the&#xD;
sister of Guve dio, and upon further&#xD;
acquaintance I. discovered that her heart&#xD;
was all unscathed; the image of none of&#xD;
her brave wooers, had been stamped&#xD;
there. She was "in, maiden meditation-&#xD;
fancy free,"&#xD;
After a few moments conversation,&#xD;
Gutedio deemed it the safest plan to&#xD;
send her forward to announce our ap-&#xD;
proach, and impress the natives with&#xD;
frielship towards me, as the preserver&#xD;
of their young chief. She sprang nimbly&#xD;
upon pne of the horses, and was off in 0.&#xD;
mq~mppt,..&#xD;
&#xD;
52&#xD;
&#xD;
Never was a .scene more wildly pic growth of the forest, but beneath tle&#xD;
turesque, or more grand and beautiful, outspreading branches, was a carpet. of&#xD;
then this to which I shall no?' introduce rich green grass grown over profusely.&#xD;
the reader.                         with the richest flowers, save where the&#xD;
Near the head of a small lake some feet of the inhabitants had trodden it&#xD;
ten or twelve miles in diameter, and stud- down in the interlacing paths. Along&#xD;
ed with green Islets, was a large area of the shore of the 'lake, the cabins were&#xD;
nearly level ground scatteringly grown more thickly strown, but through the en-&#xD;
over with tall majesitic trees, while the tire clearing they were seen scattered&#xD;
green sward was thickly overspread, with about, each having a small garden plot&#xD;
soft grass and sweet flowers ; the whole neatly walled, and fenced round, filled&#xD;
strongly resembling the open pine forests with vegetables and the choicest flowers.&#xD;
of Florida, or the scattered oak openings  The whole place was alive. with mep&#xD;
on the shores of our western lakes. In- women, and children, who were wander-&#xD;
land, the lofty rugged Andes reared theiring about in pairs and groups, and htr-&#xD;
rough and impassable fronts to the vault ring to and fro. The children were racing&#xD;
of heaven.. Down   their steep sides, over the soft turf and wading along the&#xD;
the mountain torrents leaped in foaming margin of the lake, or sporting with the&#xD;
brightness, from cliff to cliff, and hurrying light canoes on its silvery surface. In the&#xD;
along in wild fury towards the lake more dense collection of cabins near&#xD;
plunged in one wild bound over the moun- where the waves of the lake ripplel&#xD;
tain cataract, into the quiet waters of against the strand, was more turmoil and&#xD;
the lake beneath. While other little rivu- confusion. Here the boats landed,..the&#xD;
lets and streams, that came bounding fishermen repaired their nets, the laun-&#xD;
from the same lofty iceborne fountain,when dress sung over her work, and other bums-&#xD;
they reach the level ground of the valley ness of importance was transacted, by&#xD;
would go meandering in silvery threads the staid matrons.&#xD;
among the grass and flowers sweeping The cattle, sheep and horses, were&#xD;
gracefully down to the sandy beach:  seen grazing among the rich grass. and&#xD;
The air was balmy and fragrant, and the gay birds tuned their sweet notes,&#xD;
masses of clouds were seen hovering as the sun shone upon the leaves, grass&#xD;
about the summits of the distant rnoun- and flowers. Such was the appearanee1&#xD;
tains. The tall trees not unlike the cocoa, of this lovely spot, when "Metloina,",the&#xD;
with their sweeping picturesque plume- flower of the village galloped into the&#xD;
like foliage were gracefully waving in quiet vale, and hurriedly annou,nced the&#xD;
the cooling breeze, and the birds were approach of her lost brother; with a stron-&#xD;
singing shrill and  clear among the ger friend, to whom he owed his life; and&#xD;
branches. The open grove alluded to, she added some compliments about the&#xD;
which night contain a hundred acres or stranger, which she probablythought 'the&#xD;
wore, was a perfect paradise. It was case and circumstances justified.&#xD;
almost overshadowed by tall majestic  We were sufficiently near to hear the&#xD;
.trees, without the rough unganl under- wild shout of joy, which went up from&#xD;
&#xD;
53&#xD;
&#xD;
0&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7511-00000026"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
the valley, echoing ameng the distant&#xD;
l ills, as the glorious news spread rapidl&#xD;
through the group. Soon we emerge&#xD;
into the clearing; my heart beat furiousl&#xD;
as I'beheld a mass of savages hurrying t4&#xD;
wards us. Metina was foremost in th&#xD;
group, still mounted. She galloped uj&#xD;
to our side, and soon we were in the cen&#xD;
ter of the dusky throng.&#xD;
They were all dressed nearly as airy a&#xD;
John Bull's protege, the celebrated "Mos&#xD;
quito, King," who, it .is affirmed by&#xD;
grave historians, holds his Royal Court&#xD;
in the back yard of the British Consul&#xD;
dressed in the airy costume of "a cocked&#xD;
hat, ied' sash and spurs," and seated&#xD;
astride of a Whiskey Barrel.&#xD;
My friend Guvedio was instantly dragged&#xD;
from the hose, and nearly devoured by&#xD;
the caresses of the glad natives. His sis-&#xD;
ter on some signal from him grasped the&#xD;
rains of my animal and hurried me out&#xD;
of the croud which was growing more&#xD;
and more dense, and rode forward to her&#xD;
own house. After a few hours I found,&#xD;
that Guvedio had settled all scruples in&#xD;
regard to myself. The natives would&#xD;
occasionaly wander towards the htit&#xD;
where I was seated with Metina and&#xD;
others, and offer to me their thanks for&#xD;
the kindness I had shown their friend;&#xD;
all of which save the kind and thankful&#xD;
looks' were at the time quite unintelligible&#xD;
to me..&#xD;
In an hour 1 was joined by Guvedio,&#xD;
who hastened at first to the domicile of&#xD;
the old Patriarch chief who enjoyed the&#xD;
discriminative appellation of Au-gus-ti-ne-&#xD;
vi. le received and returned the old&#xD;
man's fond embrace stating to him his&#xD;
situation towards me, the circumstances&#xD;
of ils escape &amp;amp;c, all of which was hear-&#xD;
tily approved by the chief and the whole&#xD;
&#xD;
L'1&#xD;
I lE&#xD;
x&#xD;
Y&#xD;
rr,&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
r'&#xD;
1&#xD;
&#xD;
F&#xD;
&#xD;
it tribe. The next day was selected to&#xD;
y present me'to the people.&#xD;
d   The lodges of the Indians were con.&#xD;
y structed in the most singular and prim.&#xD;
o itive manner. From each side of the&#xD;
e ridgepole, which was placed about eight&#xD;
p feet from the, ground, were stretched&#xD;
- dried bulls hides, extending on each side&#xD;
at an angle of about 45deg. to the ground,&#xD;
s where they were properly secured by&#xD;
- stakes &amp;amp;c. The back side, or rather&#xD;
pediment end, was closed up with the same&#xD;
material firmly secured with a sufficien-&#xD;
cy of stout thongs. About one third of&#xD;
l the front end was left open for the door-&#xD;
way, near which the fires were built in-&#xD;
stead of in the centre; the sleeping places&#xD;
Were arranged along the sides of the&#xD;
apartment upon the floor, they were com-&#xD;
posed of the softest palm tree bows&#xD;
placed with the stub end in the ground,&#xD;
and bent forward so as to lap one over&#xD;
the other, upon these were thrown a skin&#xD;
and a few light bed clothes of home man-&#xD;
ufacture. The bows were changed often&#xD;
and when fresh and new afforded a lux-&#xD;
urious couch. A large skin separated&#xD;
each bed from the main apartment and&#xD;
from each other. The cabins contained&#xD;
two, three, or four beds according to the&#xD;
wants of the family. On the front side&#xD;
of these snug bed chambers, was placed&#xD;
a large square log which' served for the&#xD;
seats. Their provisions, and stores were&#xD;
usually kept in a small out house attached&#xD;
to the main cabin, where were stored such&#xD;
articles as could be conveniently dispensed&#xD;
with from the house.&#xD;
The most scrupulous. neatness was&#xD;
observed in every department of the&#xD;
household, and the premises. Although&#xD;
the fire was built upon the grotind, the&#xD;
hearth was always kept clean and neat,&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLE&#xD;
no dirt of any kind was suffered to gather&#xD;
ar und the premises, and in fact the whole&#xD;
op ning was as clean and smooth as&#xD;
Bo ton common during the pleasant&#xD;
x nth of June-,&#xD;
No descripton of mine , can possibly&#xD;
give a correct picture of this delight-&#xD;
ful valley, nor can it be conceived by those&#xD;
of more civilized communities, who toil&#xD;
and drudge, on the cold and barren soil&#xD;
&#xD;
of Maine, "where thorns and  thistles,&#xD;
grow and flourish instead of wheat, and&#xD;
cockles, instead of barley ;" where a few&#xD;
feet of our rocky soil is often the bone of&#xD;
contention among neighbors, and the&#xD;
fruitful source of never ending quarrels;&#xD;
it cannot be conceived by such, how hap-&#xD;
py, contented and peaceful are the inhab-&#xD;
itants of this fairy region.&#xD;
&#xD;
S IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
55&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7511-00000027"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI                     57&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER XI.&#xD;
Our establishment was thronged dur- yet his tall stately form had but slightly&#xD;
&#xD;
ing the evening with numerous visitors,&#xD;
and I noticed with pleasure the univer-&#xD;
sal attachrd&amp;amp;ent with which Guvedio was&#xD;
regarded. He would turn to me often and&#xD;
endeavor to explain the substance of&#xD;
their remarks; some of the more fiery ones&#xD;
I noticed were anxious to sally out and&#xD;
visit the Spaniards with a sprinkling of&#xD;
war, and Guvedio appeared disposed to&#xD;
listen favorably to the scheme. His eyes&#xD;
would brighten up at the thought of&#xD;
victory and revenge. When we were&#xD;
alone I endeavored to dissuade Guvedio&#xD;
from the project of invading the Spanish&#xD;
settlements, telling him that in case his&#xD;
people succeeded in breaking up the&#xD;
village it would soon be again inhabited,&#xD;
as the Spaniards were as plenty as the&#xD;
leaves on the trees. I described to&#xD;
him the large cities of Conception, Santi-&#xD;
ago, and Valparaiso, and as I heard no&#xD;
more about it I suppose the project was&#xD;
abandoned or postponed.&#xD;
In the morning I was conducted to the&#xD;
chief, where I found assembled all the&#xD;
tribe, male and female. The old men&#xD;
and females were seated nearest to the&#xD;
chief, whose whitened locks betokened&#xD;
that the weight of years was upon him,&#xD;
&#xD;
yielded to the inroads of time. Guvedio&#xD;
sat at his feet, and myself, being the ob-&#xD;
ject of consideration, was seated close to&#xD;
my friend who acted as a sort of interpre-&#xD;
ter. In answer to the first question as to&#xD;
what nation I belonged, I gave then to&#xD;
understand that I came from the north, a&#xD;
great many miles, over a large lake a&#xD;
thousand times as large as theirs ; that I&#xD;
came in a large canoe that would hold an&#xD;
army of men. My description of the&#xD;
working of the vessel filled them with ex-&#xD;
treme wonder ; but old Augus-ti-ne-vi nod-&#xD;
ded his head in a knowing manner, and&#xD;
assured them that he had heard ot such&#xD;
a wonder before.&#xD;
I told them that the people ofmy coun-&#xD;
try were as numerous as the trees in the&#xD;
forest; that they traveled all over the&#xD;
world; that there was scarcely a spot up-&#xD;
on the whole globe which had not been&#xD;
visited by sone of them, and that I, par-&#xD;
taking of the- roaming character of my&#xD;
countrymen, had been led to visit them&#xD;
here. I furthermore informed them that&#xD;
some of my people could make machines&#xD;
to travel through the air like birds, and&#xD;
that some day they might be surprised to&#xD;
see some of them fly down from over the&#xD;
&#xD;
mountains and alight among them like a them to renewed attempts; and in a few&#xD;
large condor. In fact I left them impress- days they were as expert as the most&#xD;
ed with the most exalted opinion of both celebrated equestrian performer in Amer.&#xD;
myself and nation, while on my part, I ica&#xD;
had also imbibed,. in the mean time, the The females joined in the sport, and!&#xD;
highest opinion of their devoted attach- succeeded as well as the males. Metina&#xD;
ment to each other, and of the principles the belle of the village, was the most ex-&#xD;
that governed their social intercourse.  pert and sprightly lass among them all.&#xD;
The females were generaly handsome, The rapidity and skill with which she jer-&#xD;
modest and virtuous; their manners and formed these difficult feats were truly as-&#xD;
dress, it is true, were somewhat different tonishing. This daring and noble . girl&#xD;
from the belles of Broadway, but their was all life and animation, and from the&#xD;
general character for virtue and decorum, first moment of our meeting I was 'en*&#xD;
would pass a much closer scrutiny. Yet raptured with her superior loveliness, her&#xD;
the sexes mingled together continually in daring spirit, and with all, her deep devoid&#xD;
all, sports and pastimes, some of them tion and strong affections. She was often&#xD;
rather indelicate when squared by our the companion of my rambles and dx-&#xD;
own rules of propriety, as will be seen cursions, in which she showed her skill&#xD;
hereafter.                          in the use of the canoe, or guiding the&#xD;
Notwithstanding this, free and unres- mettlid steed; and when occasion called,&#xD;
trained manner, there had never been an she would glance her keen eye along the&#xD;
instance known of a family circle being polished surface of her rifle, and speed&#xD;
destroyed and their hearth made deso- the deadly missive with the unerring aim&#xD;
late, by the unfaithfulness of a wife, or of "Leather Stockings." At other times&#xD;
disgraced by the errors of a daughter. she would enliven the hour with her me-&#xD;
What a contrast to the Empire city, where lodious songs. While I gazed n this&#xD;
thousands of female souls are immolated beautiful creature, I must candidly admit&#xD;
on the hellish altar of 'the Brothel, that that, I oung as I was, the -arrows of love&#xD;
sink of semi-beastiality, the den of the "entered the breast of the wild dreaming&#xD;
unblushing harlot; and where, too, they boy."&#xD;
are protected by the depraved Judges as We were often followed in our tramps&#xD;
necessary evils,                    by whole troops of the bright-eyed village&#xD;
The males were a' stout robust class, in- maidens, who would caper about among&#xD;
ured by education and habit to a life of the trees and grass, each striving to out-&#xD;
exercise and activity, and extremely fond do the other, in their efforts to please, and&#xD;
of actirie sports.: On one occasion, I shooting from their eyes sparks as bright&#xD;
performed several somersets in imitation and gleaming as- those that Prometheus&#xD;
of circus performers, and walked ground stole frorp Heaven. They were all pas-&#xD;
among them upon my hands, a feat which sionately fond of flowers, forming them into&#xD;
highly delighted them, and in their ef- head wreaths, necklaces, &amp;amp;c., some almost&#xD;
forts to imitate me, they at first received covering themselves with garlands wreath.&#xD;
some severe falls, but this only spurre d ed from these bright jewels of the forest&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7511-00000028"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
The young people were in the habit and new, and was considered among the&#xD;
every few days of swarming into the ad, natives extremely healthy. A variety of&#xD;
jacent forest, in large parties, and gather-jdishes were served up while I was among&#xD;
ing a sort of sap that flows from a singu-:them entirely new to me; some of which&#xD;
iar kind of tree, resembling somewhat our I admired, and others which I could not&#xD;
small, white birch, but growing to the relish. Their salmon trout were nice, and&#xD;
height of forty or fifty feet; with a heart their method cf cooking them was a great&#xD;
or pulp like the elder runniog'through the improvement to ours.&#xD;
centre, the whole length of the tree, filling Both the lake and the hamlet on its&#xD;
a smooth round cavity as large as a man's banks bore the name of "Won-seta" deri-&#xD;
arm.                                ved from  two Indian words-"wone,"&#xD;
On puncturing the tree a fluid escaped, drink, and "seta," sweet;' consequently&#xD;
which was gathered into vessels by the meaning ", sweet drink," a name applying&#xD;
party, and carried to the villages, where with equal propriety to the limped waters&#xD;
after a peculiar process a most delightful of the lake, and the delicious beverage&#xD;
beverage was produced. This drink, made along its green and fertile bank,&#xD;
however, was only palatable when fresh&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER XII.&#xD;
One day I was conducted by Guvedio They pointed out to ie their parints'&#xD;
and Metina to their cemetery. It was tomb,&amp;amp;d I was strongly tempted to'reW&#xD;
a delightful spot, on one of the green quest 1iem to open one for my gratifica-&#xD;
islets of the lake, about an acre in extent. tion, but I restrained my Yankee curiosi-&#xD;
T   surface had been cleared of the trees ty, doubting the propriety of such a re-&#xD;
all excepting the margin of the island, quest. The sepulchres were so arranged&#xD;
which was skirted round with a thick bor- that the air had free circulation on all sides,&#xD;
der of low shrubbery. The open area and although the boxes appeared perfect.&#xD;
had been artificially planted with flowers ly tight, the air undoubtedly found en-,&#xD;
and beautiful shrubbery, whose perfumed trance within.&#xD;
breath went up in grateful incense, while  Their religious ideas were extremely&#xD;
the melodious songs of the birds were vague; from all I could gather, I was led&#xD;
heard as they sung their solemn requiem to believe they acknowledged the immor-&#xD;
among the old tombsq dedicating with tality of the soul-a spiritual existence&#xD;
holy sanctity this home of the dead.  hereafter, and also, that the spirits 9f,&#xD;
The bodies were placed upon stages the departed still hold communion with&#xD;
erected about eight or ten feet from the their surviving friends, and in fact gave&#xD;
ground, enclosed in strong wooden boxes. that as an inducement for good,,acts -at&#xD;
the air being so pure that no animal sub- all times,.as they were ever upder the.&#xD;
stance was in the least affected by expo eyes of those friends who were dead, yet&#xD;
sure to the atmosphere for ages. Icould ever present.&#xD;
ssearcely bring my mind to believe this at  Here thought I, in these aerial shrines&#xD;
first, but before I left I was entirely con- repose tha congregateddust of Won-seta's&#xD;
vinced of the fact by repeated observa- departed heroes; a race of Democratic&#xD;
tion,                               sovereigns with the sceptre departed&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7511-00000029"/>&#xD;
60                      RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
from them  and their crowns gone to which were scattered plentifully abon t,&#xD;
others. I traversed this grove of mortal. and provide also a necessary store for&#xD;
ity, this sad picture of that fate which is their few wants in case of accident.&#xD;
enshrouding all 'things earthly, with  By education and association they&#xD;
feelings of profound veneration, and were taught to respect the equal rights of&#xD;
an almost irresistible influence to do all, to aid one another in their wants, and&#xD;
homage to the bright and pure spirits, help each other in their misfortunes. Their&#xD;
which were gazing down     u pon me intercourse was all concord and unity ;&#xD;
from beyond the domain of death. Al- there seemed to be no cares, griefs, tron-&#xD;
though such a spot is calculated to im- iles or anxieties ; there were no heart-&#xD;
press upon the mind that great lesson of burnings or bickerings, murmurings, or&#xD;
man's mortal doom, and shadow forth the quarrels among them; all were equally&#xD;
image of the pale grim messenger and free, owing nothing to each other but&#xD;
his uncompromising warfare ; although love and kind feelings.&#xD;
the most tender and melancholy tssocia  That which I conceived promoted this&#xD;
tions are wont to crowd upon one,' while happiness, fidelity and simplicity of man.&#xD;
gazing upon the burial mounds of the red niers, was the total absence of those de-&#xD;
man, and listening to the soft waving of basing vices, cupidity and luxury, and&#xD;
the ygll9 Jeafed willows as they whisper their powerful agent money, the "root of&#xD;
their rnogrxful dirge over the gravesof allevil," leaiving them entirely free from&#xD;
the, Jndian warrior; yet here 1 dreamed a cloud ofcares, perplexities and the bit-&#xD;
of(.naught save the bright spirit shapes ter contests arising from the desire of gain.:&#xD;
ot death's unconquered victims,still hover With a country abounding in luxurious&#xD;
ing over this consecrated spot.     stores; each man is rich and content with&#xD;
eA few days sufficed to familiarize mae the certainty, that he caf, easily supply,&#xD;
with their habits and occupations, and ev- his own few wants without encroaching&#xD;
ery day seemed to interest re more and upon the rights of his neighbor.&#xD;
more in their characters. They formed  Their games were of the most exhilara-.&#xD;
es it were, one, family, bound together by ting character, and perpetual hilarity,&#xD;
the ties of' interest, education, , and the reigned throughout the whole community.&#xD;
ln established usages of their ancestors. Their time was consumed, sometimes by&#xD;
This little nation,;founded and nurtured domestic employment in their delightful&#xD;
upon these two essential principles, liber- village, and again in wild and extensive,&#xD;
ty and equality, lived in happiness and roamings far into the bosom of the mun.-&#xD;
cQntentment., Had fery ambition enter- taitn ridge, whither they pursued the wild&#xD;
ed into;their hearts, it would have found game even to the topmost peak, exposed&#xD;
no food !there. for its sustenance, and to hardships and, hunger, sometimes for&#xD;
would soon have withered away. Gen- days together. Their happiness is doub-&#xD;
eration after generation had been reared led, when after their return home from&#xD;
in habits of industry and the domestic these toilsome expeditions, ,they gather&#xD;
tues, enabling al taabundantly supply around their cottage doors,listenigggoand&#xD;
their families with the necessaries of lifejrepeating the stoi-ies of their hazardous ad.&#xD;
&#xD;
ventures. Then it is that the gayety&#xD;
and liveliness of their dispositions find&#xD;
free vent, and thejoyous song is borne up-&#xD;
on the bosom of the quiet lake.&#xD;
There seems to be something peculiar.&#xD;
ly favorable to the germ of patriotism and&#xD;
the developement'of noble spirits, among&#xD;
high and mountainous countries; some-&#xD;
thing that promotes the growth and ma-&#xD;
turity of free and noble sentiments. It&#xD;
was on mount Hope that the noble Philip&#xD;
made his last stand, and here it was that&#xD;
his young limbs were first trained to speed&#xD;
the hatchet and the arrow, and from the&#xD;
topmost peak of nature's temple he held&#xD;
communion with the great Spirit. It was&#xD;
the hills of Tyrol, the mountainous vil.&#xD;
lage of lurglen that ga. birth to Will.&#xD;
liam Tell, the deliverer of rocky Switzer-&#xD;
land ; many of the mountain sons of that,&#xD;
heroic region, have bravely fought for her&#xD;
independance, and those wild Alpine cliff&#xD;
long sheltered "Mezzini" and his com&#xD;
rades. The grassy slopes and deep blue&#xD;
gorges of the highlands of Scotland, have&#xD;
ever been the home of many a warlike&#xD;
clan. The Cpathian mountains have&#xD;
poured forth from her rugged sides clouds&#xD;
of warriors who echoed the noble Kossuth's&#xD;
rallying cry of liberty; and our own "Green&#xD;
mountain boys," during tlta, "times&#xD;
that tried men's souls," flocked to  e stan-&#xD;
&#xD;
leaves them free from disease and early&#xD;
decrepitude, and this healthful physical&#xD;
existence tends to increase still rmore',asp&#xD;
the germ is transmitted by family and&#xD;
blood through successive generations.-&#xD;
In this "oasis" of the wilderness, this&#xD;
secluded abode of happiness, I could.not'&#xD;
fail to contrast in my own mind the  einv&#xD;
ilized with the savage life, and Imust&#xD;
admit that the savage life as here repre-{&#xD;
rented produced the most favoxable, peO.&#xD;
ture of true happiness. I would rot;be&#xD;
understood as flatteringly and- poeficaly&#xD;
comparing with civilization, the squalid&#xD;
miseries, and the  mental darkness of&#xD;
savage life, as seen in the forests of Amer-&#xD;
ica, with their abject' poverty and drun-&#xD;
keness; or as seen in the wild bush of&#xD;
the south, sea Islands, whee,' notwith&#xD;
standinig the delightful descriptions, of&#xD;
poetic imagination, we find' the savage&#xD;
invariably miserable and a mere animal,&#xD;
eating dogs and raw fish, and sucking&#xD;
sour poi from their dirty fing rs; their&#xD;
bodies rank with the smell of cocoa-nut&#xD;
oil, and almost unanimously festering,&#xD;
under the diseases distributed among the&#xD;
south sea Islands by Capt. Cook.&#xD;
It is not such that I envy, but it is the&#xD;
character and habits of the Araucanian&#xD;
Indians, and of those only with whom&#xD;
I was associated, and by actual observa=&#xD;
&#xD;
dard of Jiberty; and heroically sustained tion noted their characterestic freedom&#xD;
it, "in the name of the great Jehovah and and unalloyed happiness, barbarous and&#xD;
the Continental Congress."         uneducated as they were.&#xD;
Such bold and daring spirit I found  No purse-proud hard-hearted aristoc-&#xD;
fully matured among the native warriors racy were to be found there, frowning and&#xD;
of this mountain tribe whose cradles were trampling upon worth and industry, while&#xD;
swung among the smooth glens and stu- toiling over the mid-night lamp, or expo-&#xD;
penduous steeps of the Andes, and their sing their life and health in ngenial labor,&#xD;
daring sports fostered and ripened the to enrich the cold and haughty tyrant.&#xD;
germ of brave hearts. Their mode of life;There were no venal Judges sitting&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7511-00000030"/>&#xD;
RAMILES IN CHILL&#xD;
with aomp and pride in the halls of jusje :perience the most opposition. they.&#xD;
tice, watching with cold indifferance the grumble at them if they  devote them-"&#xD;
laatseat wrung, from the hands-of honest selves exclusively to spiritual affairs?&#xD;
pove tgand boldly poeketedby the money complaining that the temporal interests&#xD;
gloated villain, or cunningly conniving at suffer; again if they attempt to encourage&#xD;
the dark crimes committed in high places. agriculure and industrial arts, a hue and&#xD;
Neither-do you there find innocent persons cry is raised that they are meddling in&#xD;
the victimsof afoul conspiracy and con- matters which do not belong to them, thus&#xD;
yicted y perjury on:the part of witnesses; placing those men and their prai worthy&#xD;
or gancor, venality, and hatred, on the efforts in a difficult position. It  eens to&#xD;
part of the*Judge,                  be more a spirit of jealousy at their- sur-&#xD;
Let no verdant, youth. or unsophistit prising sucesses than  any thing else.&#xD;
cated maiden believe that such wicked I was surprised to see that Lieut. Wise,&#xD;
acts;are not known in our free and en-,of the U. S. Navy, the author of "Los&#xD;
lightened land; that such passions do1Gringos," joins in this tirade. The for-&#xD;
noteatist, .in this, the most cnlightened eiguers, wh9 have settled on the Ilgnd,&#xD;
country :on 'the globe; for when they as y late visitor has remarked,  'are r the&#xD;
grow wiserthey will find that they were "Most subtile and dangerous enemies with&#xD;
greatly mistaken.                   which the king has to contend,-seeking&#xD;
t With their virttuaand fidelity I could to undermine the influence of his coup-&#xD;
not realize; that they were much in want selors, wihose intelligewee and experience&#xD;
afsa spiritual adviser, or needed! any in-- are bringing he Political condition of&#xD;
novationslupon their religrio's principles the kingdom fast to maturity. Their&#xD;
and; custons nor'did I feel it my duty selfish and misschievous dispositions are&#xD;
tointroduc to them any 6f the -nmer- masked under professions of friendship.&#xD;
ousisect riani doctrines that prevade civ- ThIey talk of changes for the better bhu&#xD;
olizeds communities. Yet I, am not one they aim at revolution. They .are wil-&#xD;
of those who delight to, ridicule arnd op. ig to run the hazard of a great plitical&#xD;
pose:the reformation which the missiona- etttihquake for.the chance of being hove&#xD;
re  are,:eigaged :in; no I honor the nis- into statioiqs of emolumetnt and power.&#xD;
ionary cause, and ever feel deeply mor- But if the present social fabric falls,.1Apy&#xD;
tified and chagrined at the. rengarks 'of will be buried in its ruins; and there they&#xD;
itheirp posers. Nor cool1 1: ever see uiay lie, sepulchurecd under the Jhorrors of&#xD;
how. honest .nen, when contenmplating a betrayed people, and the eNecrations&#xD;
the rapid improvement of the .Sandwich of the civilized workl.&#xD;
-Islands,.couldspeak lightly of those devo-  Now that I am speaking ;of the mis-&#xD;
'ted men,;who have brought about this sionarics, I will say a word of what they&#xD;
happy change. Yet it is a fact that the were doing fifteen years ago, they had&#xD;
-very men who, coming as. they do from schools scattered throughout nosttofthe Is-&#xD;
civilized and- Christian .lands, should. be lands of the Hlawaian gronp where the&#xD;
.the first toeustain this li' tie band of Christ natives learned to read and write the-&#xD;
tian teacher, are those from whom) they English language, and were taught all the&#xD;
&#xD;
1&#xD;
&#xD;
R ABLE ITV'OI tLT.&#xD;
&#xD;
r63&#xD;
&#xD;
branches which are acquired in our comgroves an d rich verdure  The bitnnna&#xD;
mon schools. At their schools the children aid oraine :trees reared their'- smiling&#xD;
ofihe chiefs were constant attendants. heads, and stretchedout tfeir bountkt s&#xD;
Thus early they imparted intelligence and arts laden with their precious and, life&#xD;
virtue to those who now influence; and giving treasures, and forests richwith trop-&#xD;
shape the destiny of these Islands, nor pical fruits, juicy and ltisciom0t Verevty&#xD;
are their works limited aline to this where spread around as if to tantilize the&#xD;
group. The following anecdote speaks suffering ci'ewv. These ehiaciatid nd&#xD;
volumes in praise of their efforts. dying men raised their heads, andga d&#xD;
Ira the year 1836 a vessel was cast with wistful eyes upon this tan iiizing&#xD;
away on oie of the Savage Islands  that scene as they were borne aldng by die&#xD;
dot the surface of the south sews. With'gentle breeze, snuffing tihe dbrs of tMe&#xD;
great effort:they allanded safe from the luxuriant'valleys and proves. 'A th y&#xD;
t'redk and built a hut upon the beach to swept ronnd a point'of land theydpetid&#xD;
-  f6tect them'froti.thescorching i'ayof the upon a qdiet ittlebay, with hi tets&#xD;
sun. Here:they were found by the natives hits scattered upon the sloping-des;&#xD;
captured, and conveyed to°the , village, in;the centre of the village, rose .a ltge&#xD;
a large fire was built and one after anotheristone church. "Oh here, are the mis-&#xD;
they were brought forward, roasted alive sionaries! we are safe" they exclaimed at&#xD;
and devoured by these benighted canni- once; and pulling close in to the shore,&#xD;
bals, one alone escaped to tell the tale.  they were met on the beach by the&#xD;
In later years another ship struck up-friendly natives, who held up the bible&#xD;
on the -coral reef and sunk, the crew and welcomed them to their hospitable&#xD;
barely escaping in the boats. After drift- shores.&#xD;
ing about three or four days, they saw What a change had taken place here&#xD;
the cannibal Island and pulled in to- in the course of a few years, and such&#xD;
wards the shore. When the morning sun changes are going on throughout most of&#xD;
dawned upon them it shed its golden the Islands of the Pacific, brought about&#xD;
light upon a delightful Island, with cocoa by the perserverance, zeal, and pious&#xD;
nut groves iising in all the beauty of tropi daring of the American  missionaries'&#xD;
calluxuriance, but they feared to land, and is it right, is it manly for intelo-&#xD;
They had heard the story of those who'pers to crowd in among them, and inter&#xD;
had preceeded them, and they very nat-'fere with their good works, endeavoring&#xD;
uraly dreaded the spear of the savage and to scatter discord and trouble among them!&#xD;
the demoniacal revels of the cannibals, At the Sandwich Islands, even the Gov-&#xD;
yelling around their roasting  victims. ernment of France has interfered, declar-&#xD;
They pulled slowly along the shore gaz- ing that their brandy shall be admitted,&#xD;
ing wistfully upon the clear streams of and the Roman Catholic religion intro-&#xD;
water issuing from the mountain sides, duced. And in fact they have attempt-&#xD;
leaping and sparkling in the sun's rays; ed the same game that they have played&#xD;
meadows faded away in the distance, so successfully with QueenPomair, and&#xD;
enchanting the eye with their shad y tthe Society Islands. The result of third&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7511-00000031"/>&#xD;
O4                          RAMBLES IN CHILL&#xD;
late attack is not yet known, I believeithese people among whom I had been&#xD;
our. government has done nothing, al- thrown as benighted heathens ; far from&#xD;
though the American mission aies were it. They were born among the moun-&#xD;
threatened with death, an 1r Consul stains and had a stern wild force it istrue,&#xD;
treated with indignity; but it takes a long which shed where their adles had been&#xD;
time for Uncle Sam to get his back up to rocked. They also looked  'th scorn on the&#xD;
n pitch of open resistance, although he has tricks of the toilet. The  did indeed&#xD;
often passed that point, beyond which for- wear plumes in their dark hair such as&#xD;
bearance ceases to be a virtue. It was were plucked from the pinions of some&#xD;
about ten years before he concluded daring bird that had battled, with the&#xD;
th give Mexico her deserts, and John mountai storm, and sipped tUle water&#xD;
Ball has beenbearding him in his den from the cataracts plunging verge; still&#xD;
fora long time. However, none can deny they are in a remarkable degree free from&#xD;
but the old fellow has good mettle in him fecity and disguised rvenge, as well as&#xD;
when he is once fairly aroused.        er traits of the savage, and are such a&#xD;
-'his digession arose from my excuse for people in fact as one might imagine&#xD;
lot turning missionary. I did not view dwelt near the confines of heaven.&#xD;
&#xD;
IU&#xD;
&#xD;
S.&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER. XIII.&#xD;
&#xD;
A singular costume is prevalent among ofour medical drugs,--as afo'reign neiiI&#xD;
this, and all the various tribes of Arauca- writer admits-is, to amuse and div t:t&#xD;
nians. It is recommended by tfie Disci- attention of the patient, while good dae&#xD;
ptes of Esculapius who flourish there, as nature performs hei work,:andcegt&#xD;
a remedy for certain diseases, and a grand disease, perhaps the practitionerofi4h .&#xD;
charm against most of the ills that flesh beap will not suffer by a comparison w&#xD;
is heir to. It is simply to wear a bean his more learned :brother of the pill.&#xD;
at the side of the head over the temple. a majority of cases it would be far:&#xD;
It probably operates very much as Chris- preferable to hang a bean to the~temnpe,&#xD;
ties Galvanic belts and rings do. These than to put ,a pill into the stomacbr an4&#xD;
simple doctors practice altogether upon of the. two, nature would, complain 0&#xD;
the botanic principle, and explore a wide of the bean, she might be sorely p,,&#xD;
extent of country, while gleaning their what to do with the pill,&#xD;
barks, roots, and balsams, from the wild  There is something singular heri&#xD;
glens of the Andes, and along the steep relation to sounds. The tremor of th a&#xD;
mountain  es, down to the plains and tiles of air acting upon each otlhqr, a.&#xD;
pampas below.                       preceptable at. a much greate ,,4is&#xD;
There is one thing they can boast of than I had ever before believdpqssUle,&#xD;
with pride and satisfaction ; their dimple I attributed this singular phenor a&#xD;
remedies never kill, even if they seldom the extreme clearness of the atrhosple¢&#xD;
cure. They rely much .upon the faith, and increased elasticity of the air,&#xD;
and conceit of the invalid. But it may think I am within bounds. when, I1,&#xD;
be strongly argued, in their behalf, that, that the common tones of a raaV&amp;amp; 4&#xD;
as the real design and legitimate province can be distinctly hear.aoI a lev&amp;amp;&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
_,&#xD;
§ff(, ,&#xD;
.&#xD;
-     s    s&#xD;
Y&#xD;
I&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7511-00000032"/>&#xD;
66                           RAMBLE&#xD;
at a, distance of three miles. Sounds&#xD;
aretore-distinctly heard across the water,&#xD;
which with respect to conducting sound&#xD;
is hdt14 greatest consequence. The&#xD;
soldier's watch-words, have been heard&#xD;
in this manner a distance of twelve miles&#xD;
in then ighborhood of Gibraltar, but. on&#xD;
the land it is far different. On the suT-&#xD;
f# of the lake from one side to' the&#xD;
® ex it appeared like talking in the&#xD;
sage room, and on a quiet eve a whisper&#xD;
pigy be heard from the opposite shores&#xD;
with ease.&#xD;
..he Irdians are, all excellent horse.&#xD;
a and they, manage the lasso with&#xD;
ai elkskill as their more enlightened&#xD;
geighboro; and there is no lack for horses,&#xD;
tley roam over the plains in countless&#xD;
vW-s9 but arie'seldom captured save as&#xD;
tdy ara reqttired for use,&#xD;
ey *Ul take one of these wild ani-&#xD;
x s and breakhimiri to the saddle,, in&#xD;
M :ye. In this sport the young ur-&#xD;
4tAre ever desirous to ehgage. It&#xD;
Wbulfften    1 fill me with wonder, and&#xD;
*.yp^s e to see the daring skill displayed&#xD;
while breaking in a wild horse, to the&#xD;
dle;and thei r eckless mirth at these&#xD;
feats of hormaiship. While con.-&#xD;
ng thd iuocence and happiness&#xD;
of these children of nature, and their fairy&#xD;
e I dold not-marvel that Guvedio&#xD;
d4  t flypo ied. to fly thither to his&#xD;
tntIikhhieatnoiige the. picturesque&#xD;
Y   of the Andes; toythe sequested hut&#xD;
tKe wild frui  and flowers that&#xD;
Mbo   W±ound it ; the 'chrystal streanais&#xD;
sh,;t li the green pastures ; the sweet&#xD;
like (that 'nipples on the smooth white&#xD;
dd;thevrdaintlawns and the anabrosial&#xD;
1VIfdsif thie-'earthly paradise. '&#xD;
'A fathons j~iitee and feast came ofi&#xD;
&#xD;
ES IN CHILI.&#xD;
upon the safe arrival of divedio, which&#xD;
I will not forget to describe. I think the.&#xD;
extensive preparations, were completed&#xD;
the third day after our arrival. A large&#xD;
bullock was to be roasted whole, as one&#xD;
of the dishes'to be served up upon this&#xD;
joyous occasion. In the morning early,&#xD;
my attention was called to the ceremony&#xD;
by noticing the village maidens prepar.&#xD;
ing a large plat of ground in the- centre,&#xD;
part of the comanon, by decorating th'e&#xD;
trees with garlands of flowers and swee-&#xD;
ping the green carpet clear of' all sticks&#xD;
leaves, &amp;amp;c., and spreading the calabashes&#xD;
upon the bright green sward. At a lit-&#xD;
tle distance the men were scooping out&#xD;
a hollow place in the ground, of sufficient-&#xD;
dimensions to contain the body of the&#xD;
animal which wasto form the principal&#xD;
attraction of the feast. 'After finishing&#xD;
the excavation-, a large fite of'dried wood'&#xD;
was built in the centre arid left to 'burn,'&#xD;
while some were preparing the uncon&#xD;
scions animal for the saerifice lHe was.&#xD;
killed, neatly dressed, and'brought to the&#xD;
primitive oven, inr which he vas pladea&#xD;
after raking open the glowing coals;i&#xD;
carcass was then filled with hot -tohet&#xD;
the remaining coals' 'were spread ndl&#xD;
glowing hot completely over:  the 'entire&#xD;
heap, and covered with ,d leaves, and,&#xD;
the 'whole complete  buried up with&#xD;
hot ashes and dirt.&#xD;
The females during this  nie, were&#xD;
not idle but busily engaged preparing&#xD;
the side dishes' and  accompaniiments&#xD;
within doors. '''&#xD;
After Completing all the'.'preliiinary&#xD;
arrangements, the 'hour of banquet 'r -&#xD;
rived. ' The horn'als sounded ajid the&#xD;
guests were soon sdated. The'stewalrds&#xD;
who had' voluAhteered for the o&amp;amp;esion&#xD;
&#xD;
I,&#xD;
&#xD;
UAMD3LES r1 VCRLL&#xD;
&#xD;
ThM'ro pelid the stfcking heap whi&#xD;
seit forth'td savory siel;"harpening t&#xD;
yapptits of th&amp;amp; eager throig.° Haulin&#xD;
forth the sizzli g mass they scraped o&#xD;
the few clingihg ermbers, and quiet'&#xD;
i    d1! b  di1Y            .  : Y.,&#xD;
Paced this delicate morsel of vineso&#xD;
upon a bed of clean, fresh leaves.&#xD;
Tow commenced the carving which&#xD;
was performed with astonishing dispatch&#xD;
the children were 'hurrying backward&#xD;
andfdrwards with the calabashes,suply&#xD;
ing the hungry party, and' in less tim&#xD;
than the Astor house waiters can serv&#xD;
thii rfst course of soup we, were all a&#xD;
work.4&#xD;
I had begged off from taking my se&#xD;
with Guvedio, and some of the olde&#xD;
men, and seated myself by the side o&#xD;
the lovely Metina nd a circle of othe&#xD;
fai Ny  hs' endeavoring to do the hon&#xD;
ors oftheable by passig round the extra&#xD;
and tcetras. I felt happy although&#xD;
cold scarcely understand a word of wha&#xD;
as said. They talked to me in their&#xD;
own lhio nd I replied to themin mmme&#xD;
yet stilliby looks and acts we occasion-&#xD;
al' ' understood a sentence, and this&#xD;
su ceded' in entertaining oeh other,&#xD;
Metina, in my estimation, was as love-&#xD;
l' "as 'te very scene before us, She was&#xD;
indeed in every action a genuine_ child&#xD;
df i ture. Her 'tallnagnificert forrn,&#xD;
hny cheekslowingwith liealtiand' her&#xD;
fal 5li  wduld haebrought; back the&#xD;
fires of youth tod'sie b6s'orn of a' lbany&#xD;
auchorite, and howr should I, with the&#xD;
blood of eighteen summers flowing like&#xD;
dancing wild fire through my veins-&#xD;
"Like Vesuvius' glowing tide,"&#xD;
ward off the    flame  of love and&#xD;
passion, which like lightning is bright&#xD;
and fleree                 isbih&#xD;
&#xD;
ch  "Who can view the iiend inose&#xD;
T o Wear it? Who cai ouriouslr, behoail-%&#xD;
T The smoothness and the sheen of beautieskegk&#xD;
Nor feel the heart can never all grow  ai&#xD;
I was greatfol-for her kind atteoao=&#xD;
I loved to hearheweet m usicas.,0t.&#xD;
I   ed to gaze on her lovely faoef&#xD;
peer into lthuse bright and sparkling  +s,&#xD;
ao pure and clear, that one .coulAp-&#xD;
h parently see through their innlost d g&#xD;
s inteoher very soul. I foundmthis'tigg&#xD;
gem ofthe forest gifted by natureBjth&#xD;
mind and intellect so natural andspiirg so&#xD;
e warm  hearted and affeotionatee th ,&#xD;
L that   'should have belied MnVv  ab&#xD;
had I not loved her'; and as I lay 'ith b&#xD;
upon the flower, strown ground byhe-&#xD;
r side, this tender passion made xd  p.,,.&#xD;
roads upon my heart&#xD;
. ToWards the close of theybaigq&#xD;
were cheered by joyous ani'iv't&#xD;
son their musical instruments .bas-a&#xD;
I particular strain/ a s-t tldof ione If&#xD;
t&#xD;
ant exploit, or' time hdored$dd,&#xD;
drew  forth frbnmthe whole ltt4'&#xD;
,wild burst ofapplause *hieh eehod&#xD;
and clear among the hills.s     :r&#xD;
The feast'lasted &amp;amp;ta t'tWti 4  $&#xD;
the ground  V'af left to"' the&#xD;
pOttion and we wete presetly&#xD;
'upon the lawn treading the&#xD;
Indiai daicer  Sea1     ibf&#xD;
vere formed; oe ron  theatti&#xD;
a little dietaic fasdrbl4 h&#xD;
tnass offro  iere y oth=a '     Af&#xD;
_r_ form for afgr nd  dr'l t+f&#xD;
music strue up; each leperate&#xD;
began to dance roani= n      .posit..&#xD;
tions, and the skill and zanoeii gt&#xD;
the figureseemed" aobe,  o't gt e&#xD;
timely chang&amp;amp;efrom one ring t h li  .Y&#xD;
er,ntil the euitsikr bad ai96b$&#xD;
&#xD;
d .   t                        s.,tl.;" ,,x.&#xD;
,  .&#xD;
'ti,&#xD;
&#xD;
_ a,   , -..             -.   ",,-., _  i '    r           i.                ; .  i n  rt;    " '  ,. +. "   :  .  }  . t y Y.Kn  ,r . st, x""&#xD;
s#   =. ,. 's:  ;-.b t  ,; ._     's" .;   ;.  "._..+. _, '  E."._  1.    , 'Srx ,     3.;_c" za"4e:t$  _;... n,,*irrA:;?aY.t '&#xD;
&#xD;
, k&#xD;
,.     .,,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7511-00000033"/>&#xD;
AM;1'SK      CHQILI,&#xD;
&#xD;
t   part in the inner circle. Frequent&#xD;
muista Ie occurred which seemed to afford&#xD;
ci ue1nent to the others.&#xD;
his' grand -entertainment- did not&#xD;
r ak tfpuntil nearly dark, when one by&#xD;
s'he company retired to their peace-&#xD;
-hey hav- a game called comicw,&#xD;
frdh resembling chess. This together&#xD;
tipyh another called quechu, a sort -of&#xD;
kgat rnnn, are their more quiet games,&#xD;
and'it) which they take great delight.&#xD;
said that polygamy prevails among&#xD;
h fiefs who.inhabit the coast, but in&#xD;
4hiirregiQn .I am confident nothing of&#xD;
ah;kind is practiced, and I amled to&#xD;
1elieve that it is only from the example&#xD;
ohlpir more enlightened neighbors that&#xD;
h ,ha-habit has been introduced'naong&#xD;
thiefsof the frontier tribes. There&#xD;
t   o-theitwomen are treated with less&#xD;
federationn than among the Won-setas.&#xD;
4   e title otithe-chief Augustenevi was&#xD;
dutimfUlnen, he being a subordinate to&#xD;
th   eeni, or head chief of altthe differ-&#xD;
epiraneanian tribes t aupolican, the con-:&#xD;
tjqeret of Gen. Valdivia at the-celebrated&#xD;
;tf l'e    apel -who like Hanibal WasI&#xD;
(#qient iione eye, and like him distin-&#xD;
}ishea forhis martial deeds,-was one&#xD;
s, enius of Ercilla the author of a&#xD;
S tg i.poe ti called, the "Araucania,''&#xD;
fer d imperishable renown on this&#xD;
kty4ian warrior by celebrating in&#xD;
'tie se his patriotism and military&#xD;
V"1&#xD;
&#xD;
exploits. His 'count of the amusing&#xD;
and- characteristic manner of Caupoli-&#xD;
can's election, sga proof of their ama ing&#xD;
strength and powers of endurance.&#xD;
It is described in the poem  that Ln&#xD;
coyan the former Togui had occasioned&#xD;
sonie dissatisfaction, and it was deter-&#xD;
mined to select another in his place, and&#xD;
the Ulmenes were accordingly assembled&#xD;
for the purpose of filling the vacancy; but&#xD;
were at a loss 'to select from among the&#xD;
aspirants, when Colocolo an old chief,&#xD;
proposed that the office should be given&#xD;
to the man who could prove himself the&#xD;
strongest of limb.&#xD;
"A leader bold this desperate state demands,&#xD;
To guide to vengeance our impatient bands.&#xD;
Fit for this hardy task that chief I deem&#xD;
Who longest may sustain a massive beam.&#xD;
Your rank is equal-let your force be 'tried,&#xD;
And for the strongest let his limbs decide."&#xD;
They acquiesed in the props 1, and a&#xD;
beam was produced of such an enormous&#xD;
size that the poet declares himself afraid&#xD;
to specify its weight. The first chief-,&#xD;
tains who engaged in the trial, supported&#xD;
it on their shoulders four and six hours&#xD;
each ; Tucapel fourteen, and Lincoyaa&#xD;
more than twice as long ; when. the as-&#xD;
sembly, considering -his strength the&#xD;
greatest were about to restore him to his,&#xD;
former dignity. - At this moment Caupoli-&#xD;
can the Ulmen of P lmayquen demands a&#xD;
trial- and surpasses Lineoyan; and he was&#xD;
accordingly: pronounced Toq ui or Gen-&#xD;
eral-in-chief by acclamiation.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
I4       . .&#xD;
&#xD;
N.&#xD;
&#xD;
'                 c&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER XI&#xD;
In the course. of my  conversations the practice&#xD;
pith Guvedie, I once described to -him informed-&#xD;
an arfiicial fountain. which struck  himwas in rapt&#xD;
with'thetrnost surprising wonder and astoan.. ordingly, w&#xD;
ishmeni so mch was he interested in the tion oftthe t&#xD;
description of his simple  contrivance having sel&#xD;
that iMemharked his speaking of it to a treo the gr&#xD;
number of the tribe, and as they alt ap number of h&#xD;
peered to be so curious about  it, the excavate a&#xD;
thought struck me that I could with their yards in diar&#xD;
aidconstruet one here, in the centre of a sufficient&#xD;
their delightful giope31 from the  hollow  ,The strea&#xD;
trees that produced the delightful be erage convey the l&#xD;
Ihave before alluded to.            "Wonseta"&#xD;
This part of;the story has .awakened the basin; a&#xD;
'some dubitation in the mindstof a few theystream .&#xD;
to whom I:have related itAnd it .neyto and ,a-treacl&#xD;
some of ry readers, appear rather fanci- points about&#xD;
tul, and c ll' forth the rebuke whieh receive the l&#xD;
the old' lady .administered to her# son were dexter&#xD;
wked he at empted, a she supposed; to teans to tak&#xD;
impose upon he credulity ,by the  story judged that&#xD;
f~ the fying fish.             'e     (teen feet&#xD;
-Iwas orvincedra my own ;raiad eA   Time few&#xD;
&#xD;
'A"i&#xD;
ability of thandetrtat d&#xD;
Guvedio of thy fptp9&#xD;
tures at the baredea' W&#xD;
1ith the approval anddod&#xD;
nbc       + omrn1 1ccd  ir,'&#xD;
tribe,  :naennneed  e   .s&#xD;
ected a spot nearly , in t&#xD;
ove for a basir 1 a esti&#xD;
ands turnedto in tcre&#xD;
.f artificial pofldeh butsp&#xD;
meter ndfour f     et&#xD;
outlet for the egrplus 4&#xD;
m from whiel ' 1&#xD;
bright sparklingwat   r&#xD;
was scheatyhalf&#xD;
rude dam.hwas rw&#xD;
to supply e sua     4,&#xD;
h du along   ' etve&#xD;
t two feetand al5#r}f&#xD;
hollqosJes,. hilaloe92&#xD;
on&amp;amp;aind providing. Idta4&#xD;
We the lgvelhof pa&#xD;
rmy founteittheaedw$4&#xD;
yapidlth swht&#xD;
my dspiihd,&#xD;
&#xD;
f; _     +"' 'ta .    ' Ste} "'-, . i'&#xD;
3                      2 t                iry&#xD;
f     'K ,  iA&#xD;
'                                _                  al&#xD;
y'&#xD;
J 4 .r=h. .d._ ..&#xD;
&#xD;
fi&#xD;
.t ,     q&#xD;
&#xD;
e        ' t&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7511-00000034"/>&#xD;
RAMBLElN CHILL1&#xD;
&#xD;
*itd this novel.scheme, and my heart gaining the highest, acessiblet points&#xD;
' l  ieme many times that all would be were seen following each other 'in rapid&#xD;
,Y fi  e1althoughiy reason taught me succession from every ,nook and rocky&#xD;
th$  o in pedirfleht'presented itself, but pedestal, revealing their pretty forms for&#xD;
td- eult'ttnatter-ofjoining the ends ofa moment ini the air before their fearfull&#xD;
teboden pipes securely. In this busi- plunge.&#xD;
p        Wonsetas were adepts, they    I have sat hours together watching&#xD;
dtured la gunr that worked  to a their glistening forms as they gambled&#xD;
j         mnd by'laying the logs firm  and among. the sparkling waters, and some.&#xD;
p-  i the ii carefuly,i I had strong hopes times forgetting the fairy land of imy pre.&#xD;
Sets. It will:be remembered that sent abode, I found myself looking nar-&#xD;
t4ikrogiwere forty or fifty feet long, with rowly torflns and-folks.&#xD;
; obitd hole ruling through the entire - At last our excavations were complet-&#xD;
rfth.   "ed, the pipes were all.laid and securely&#xD;
J   Te tiatives were very fond of bathing, connected together, one end elevated in&#xD;
~   xd:this work, in which nearly' all were the ,centre of the excavated pond abont'&#xD;
~gigeda being laborious hnd carina fr - five feet'from  the bottom  and covered&#xD;
j4 pratird, they were in the water three with a perforated cap like the pose to a&#xD;
'  f   ines  da ;both 'sexes minglid  arden water pot; allIthat:now remained&#xD;
6oiA     f~ together/their' black heads was to let the water on. doubt ifi any&#xD;
"iIi,-'_    M ingabt like the buoys contractor felt mdr aitiety orilhian:mind&#xD;
ig hetNIttw   sbietime beforo I 'at the sncce s of his most co'mpfloaitid&#xD;
fs I -   rdino y todesty sufileientlytask than f'did-{when about toIdtdhe' ai&#xD;
-fite ,t    c  ats as 'I had ter ,for the' first time into mr rustirf6;un&#xD;
,s,      floated in the surfson the'hain. When ail wasreadywith a trem;&#xD;
l        wport;itthee, other se.   blibg hand I removed the ping from the&#xD;
&amp;amp;   fe  y'fo and girls and even lit ,sbmerged end thus puttingg the whol c&#xD;
mzijceseacelygknee''high, were seen work to'an tarrediate test&#xD;
AEflig p the s'p sides of the   I stood foi  mometif almostibreathless,&#xD;
$$Id olie thatchade( part of the!aike;' waiting the result, 'the' nineity of'my&#xD;
Tds o t by the long roots and ind causing the.presitiration'tostand ii&#xD;
Niit V hen that hung dangling high large drops on my 'foehead  The na&#xD;
4 Naews~hesparing6 waters, 'then tives 'were standinye abatdinre looking&#xD;
igt     selves {head foremost f6oin with wOndet.at'my gitatedt afPeianb&#xD;
. o itst i  ing'-,rngs.  From  ah'aost I well knew  that -feiw, seenddd  would&#xD;
0",efpo sibs ii'they cime le aP njd'etermine the faithfuleds'f thel' ork/&#xD;
s4 from their:giddy heights,,a a1 aths I stoid in suspense, when shadenly&#xD;
,ti     +had penetrating deep into ,aloud and boisterous shot froni thie vi..&#xD;
th tyieding waes, with the clearness la'ge'bel w startled'tie+groe,  with'its&#xD;
etitfd   arrows 4  l      'deep~e~ebs;nd, way° theyt'scampered&#xD;
f       timtighteyed maids with like a flock of sheep to see th roauedof&#xD;
ghlanlifdii a   idowingtreaes...afterdthis boisiterona ent cry/whnr.eaWY fest&#xD;
&#xD;
or other conviviality was ip the course of lug the most antic and ludicrous capers&#xD;
celebration.                       can well be imagined. While I coty&#xD;
The first shout was enough for me. I among them it continued to be the&#xD;
knew the cause of this obstreperous vorite bathing place, and during th da'&#xD;
shouting, and almost overcome with joy was constantly occupied by more or les0&#xD;
&#xD;
I could with difficulty retain my feet.&#xD;
It was some moments ere I could suf-&#xD;
ficiently compose myself to follow  the&#xD;
crowd, as they hurried to the point, from&#xD;
which the shouting still continued with&#xD;
redobuled vigor, My pride was wonder-&#xD;
fully increased, when, emerging from the&#xD;
thicket, and entering the open grove, I&#xD;
saw the fountain 'throwing up its chrystal&#xD;
jets, which fell glittering in the sun's&#xD;
bright rays like. a shower or diamonds;,&#xD;
and reflecting a glorious -_ainbow  tat&#xD;
spread its gay arch over he surrounding&#xD;
throng. Them- glad: shots completely&#xD;
drypned the soaring of'the waters, and&#xD;
t'hr :dusky .forms contrasted strangely&#xD;
ith'the'fointain mist.&#xD;
-I hurried forward, threw ofd my gar-&#xD;
rit , adi phinhed,°into the centre otf&#xD;
thesparkling shower, where I was. in-&#xD;
styntly followed by scores of the'delight&#xD;
ederowd. This wassa axu y to themrbe.&#xD;
fore unknown,:and. their joy seemed to&#xD;
knowy no bou ds they spurted 'about a-&#xD;
mong the glittering drops and spray cut-&#xD;
g        ,.',        s r'c~&#xD;
66  '     n'&#xD;
&#xD;
sS              6&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
' t '1f6 FtiRe '  6  1&#xD;
R, 6' , ,::  . i ,  Lu: '  6&#xD;
'.46   4 ,+° 6p 6ye4,'     t  + t, 6 r 6  f 6  "6&#xD;
&#xD;
of the frolicking youth.&#xD;
It was a source of pride and satistQ&#xD;
tion, to sit at our"cabin door on - i"br&#xD;
moonlight evening, 'with Guvedio an4&#xD;
his lovely sister by my side, gazingtahd i&#xD;
the fountain as it threw up its brig1lt&#xD;
pure waters, sparkling in the gentle a&#xD;
very light, and listen to their words oft&#xD;
praise and commendation of my ingen&#xD;
ty and skill.- Whe4 rer Iwent, itffd&#xD;
I1 herd, myself extolled to the utm stW&#xD;
they ,much regretted that the fountain&#xD;
could not have beenbuilt previous to th*&#xD;
late visit of theNatenoe a ie&#xD;
nishied them with all theirni   i&#xD;
cle, and who were the&#xD;
litk between the  and the Teti&amp;amp;*n,&#xD;
ki d, like the Duichtraderst&#xD;
pire of Japan  Theyfttrnil sh the  it r w.&#xD;
change for theirrskinm-fu&amp;amp;e, W&#xD;
their importations, and thie mui i hi&#xD;
cotirse had been uninterr~tedt  y&#xD;
years One of 'the annunatrad&#xD;
panies had jast left th m  pry&#xD;
my appearance:                     ,&#xD;
&#xD;
I'&#xD;
6C,,,, '  6          .  64 '.  ''&#xD;
A          r.1 r'um6 1'" 6 1,4N&#xD;
a  6'  fi{' 7  ji 4 t r e  f4 f  '6a  H6&#xD;
1.    t_'   '4    '       ''  ' 1  t I  Gl  r fI   '   44 t~~t   Y44y(  1x&#xD;
6 66,6f 4~66 666~i~$  ~f,  'Y.4aj&#xD;
'A ~ ~ ~    ~    ~    ~   l '46 66  :l.A&#xD;
7 '6                    '6 I6 .  l  ''. .'  33 t ,  464&#xD;
&#xD;
I-&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES ' 1N , -CHILI&#xD;
&#xD;
5&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
ai&#xD;
'                    1&#xD;
1     ,&#xD;
4    'j  1  i&#xD;
T&#xD;
1,  t"    t           a   , F&#xD;
&#xD;
_*&#xD;
&#xD;
:   _ ,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7511-00000035"/>&#xD;
J heilake of Wonseta is one of the&#xD;
10% beautiful and romantic scenes in the&#xD;
wrldsurrounded as it is by beautiful&#xD;
mountain .landscapes 'of perpetual rich-&#xD;
nessmagnificence and beauty, the bold&#xD;
101310na ridges, and solitary cliffs among&#xD;
)iitghe little lake has nestled, gives it&#xD;
a tizOf sublimity and grandeur as im&#xD;
prep$ve, as its beauty is attractive. To&#xD;
egp oteits beauties and revel in its en-&#xD;
ehantingloveliness was my pastime; and&#xD;
indonapay with my lovely Indian maid.&#xD;
en     would paddle our canoe beneath&#xD;
son overhanging cliff which hung in1&#xD;
sota  grandeur above the still waters&#xD;
and 0"rough some shapeless breach, gaze&#xD;
o the high-born torrent, as he came&#xD;
1eins; from his-giddy shelf, twisting ands&#xD;
sio a in the aerial flight, till he dashes&#xD;
'idh deafening roar, on the whitened rocks&#xD;
below, then struggling in'his hasty retreat&#xD;
frt thebbiling chaldron,' rush,-with pan-&#xD;
bti reath,' to the calm embraces of the&#xD;
.placid lake. Again we would glide into&#xD;
&#xD;
the quiet nooks and dells, and land in-the&#xD;
deep recesses, where the light scarcely,&#xD;
entered,.and tread the deep mazes' of&#xD;
these caverns and grottoes of the cliffs;&#xD;
with slow ahd cautions steps,; then issu.&#xD;
ing forth again we would lay in our float-&#xD;
ing cradle on the still glassy surface of&#xD;
the lake, and gaze on the clouds, the&#xD;
rocks, and the deep rich foliage reflected&#xD;
on its bosom.&#xD;
While out on one of these excursions,&#xD;
enjoying the enchanting scenery of the&#xD;
lake and the landscape, I proposed that&#xD;
we should extend' our sail further and&#xD;
proceed down the river where I had not&#xD;
yet been. .Metina accordingly directed&#xD;
our head to the outlet of the pond, and&#xD;
sent the light fabric skimming over the&#xD;
glassy surface. On entering the river&#xD;
my eyes were enraptured with the love-&#xD;
ly images which were constantly pre.&#xD;
sentirg themselves, The scenery along&#xD;
the river was variable and, delightful, the&#xD;
,waters were, clear and transparent as&#xD;
&#xD;
a             G'' ,i     1 , ' ,    t&#xD;
&#xD;
glass. Along its banks the richest vege-&#xD;
tation flourished in abundance, and' here&#xD;
among fruits of gold, had been formed;ta&#xD;
delightful path, hugging the stream in all,&#xD;
its windings, gorgeously strown with ge-&#xD;
raniums, whispering thyrtles, and other&#xD;
flowering shrubs, along its winding ave-&#xD;
nues. At points along the. river,. gentle&#xD;
undulating declivities came sloping down&#xD;
to the waters edge from the far off' hills&#xD;
which lifted up their heads in the dis-&#xD;
tance, while the mystic and dark clouds&#xD;
hung like spirit shapes on their highand&#xD;
frosty cones.&#xD;
Sometimes a thicket of cane break,&#xD;
with tangled masses of wild shrubs and&#xD;
creeping plants decorated the bank, and&#xD;
were vocal with the songs of birds ; the&#xD;
streaming of the sunbeams on their gay&#xD;
plumage, the burnished river beneath us,&#xD;
and the dark belt of forest trees stands&#xD;
ing out in bold relief against the illumin.I&#xD;
ed sky, presented a gorgeous scenic&#xD;
view scarce equalled in the world. A-&#xD;
long the whole course of this delightful&#xD;
stream, its banks were margined with a]&#xD;
fringe of perpetual glossy verdure, and&#xD;
its bright pathway, winding in a thous-&#xD;
and graceful mazes, was charmed with&#xD;
the  musical notes of the featheredI&#xD;
songster and its own clear voice of gush-I&#xD;
ing melody,&#xD;
Along the sides of the gentle declivi-&#xD;
ties rising before us, were the fig trees&#xD;
and citrons, the luscious peach, and the&#xD;
high spreading palm, with the tresselledc&#xD;
vines in their richest foliage, decking the&#xD;
narrow areas, the whole together exhibit- l&#xD;
ingl one blended scene of rural loveliness,i&#xD;
For hours we skimmed' along in si-t&#xD;
lence, contemplating these solemn beau-&#xD;
ties ; the birds welcomed us with strains i&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER XV.&#xD;
&#xD;
of forest, mistrelsy, a,na the ht gso&#xD;
-dor whided in sweeping pirqles ak&#xD;
us. At spts along the lank  t}&#xD;
willow branches weespreeglly&#xD;
over the murmuring water,r$    gg&#xD;
arched vistas withthe foliage ;of tfhQ._g&#xD;
posite banks, andthe vcl ste ing gap&#xD;
'with asmultitude of gold and; iyg o j&#xD;
ers looked out from theiqrm,&#xD;
vines and smiled a welcome, as we float.&#xD;
ed slowly down their enchanting bower.&#xD;
We landed some three or four miles&#xD;
from the lake, at a small cabin on the&#xD;
bank, where we left our canoe, and mounts&#xD;
ing one horse we rode back and arrived&#xD;
at the lake in season to view a perform-&#xD;
ance in capturing the finny tribe, which&#xD;
would have put even Isaac Walton corn&#xD;
pletely in the shade. A long slim Indi-&#xD;
an in the primitive dress of our first pa=&#xD;
rents, was arranging his fishing inife&#xD;
ments upon the bank, among a crowd"o&#xD;
dusky forms; nis bait was simply a bright&#xD;
stone fastened to one end of string, the&#xD;
other end he held in his hand. Thua&#xD;
prepared he entered the lake a little Way.:&#xD;
and holding his glittering bait over thif&#xD;
water, and giving it a particular motion,&#xD;
with astonishing dexterity he would cater&#xD;
the fish with 'his disengaged hand,'a.&#xD;
they jumped towards the suspended bait.&#xD;
He thus caught and threw them as ft&#xD;
as he pleased, among the crowd gathif&#xD;
ed upon the bank, who scrambled  Nif&#xD;
up, thrusting the sharpened end ofea stl&#xD;
quite through them, ant arranged thein&#xD;
all round the fire which had been kin.&#xD;
ed on the shore, where they soon Were&#xD;
-oasted sufficiently for the table; thenll'&#xD;
he group gathered about and comzrioe.&#xD;
ed devouring them with the keenest i'el-&#xD;
sh. I observed that they were all' M'&#xD;
&#xD;
J      3         $         t&#xD;
A }            "     r&#xD;
' {.&#xD;
v&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7511-00000036"/>&#xD;
tremely fond of these little fish, I eat a&#xD;
fe t ile   re4palatable but I discovered&#xD;
ndflithti nartkable in them, save the&#xD;
m0fiwr'ia which they were captured,&#xD;
'ifilihtladd the primitive mode of&#xD;
co81Niffthem.&#xD;
-Ereds skill displayed, by an ig.&#xD;
noi'ttsonof thb forest, which any Cam-&#xD;
bd Idtiat might well be proud to&#xD;
inf tr1e Ii' such useful arts and sciences&#xD;
&#xD;
sin' ©   f4Y11TT TY&#xD;
&#xD;
consisted the young Wonseta's education&#xD;
all useful occupations were alike re-&#xD;
spectable. Like the present inhabitants of&#xD;
California, they admitted of no aristocracy&#xD;
of pursuits.; they did not conceive that the&#xD;
road to respectability must necessarily&#xD;
lead through the Pulpit, Hospital, or&#xD;
Court room, but all trades claimed, as of&#xD;
right they should, to stand on the same&#xD;
&#xD;
a      t           ,4~~&#xD;
M 444  4{1       "t&#xD;
1    3  t., 1J&#xD;
.444           -(&#xD;
y  (               a 1(&#xD;
i      :444   44&#xD;
0i la lJ ' of 44    4&#xD;
Q  b 41      444&#xD;
CC     6&#xD;
1  s  r   Sy&#xD;
&#xD;
'0.)&#xD;
&#xD;
41~&#xD;
j 'fi4 f  r4&#xD;
CHAPTER XVI&#xD;
A few days after my excursion down' The echoes of our horses Iidofs bb&#xD;
the river with the gentle nymph Jelina, the -solemn 'stillness of the " an ap&#xD;
a grand hunt was proposed by the young awoke the birds from their quiet  -&#xD;
bucks of the village and the-arrangements es as our little party galoped on ofdhxfrl&#xD;
made. for carrying it out in good style, together. We saw a few d  edie*es"&#xD;
The company consisted of some twenty other animals, but not a gtin Wefred&#xD;
or thirty, although it was often the case until late in the afternoon *dhei&amp;amp;Ie&#xD;
that they went in larger parties.  skilled a deer for supper, whihF  #hfe-&#xD;
The morning selected for our dearture pared about dusk. Having fini9ie'ddr&#xD;
was as beautiful and bright as any that meal we secured our aninfils;,itde&#xD;
ever dawned upon an eastern caravan, our tents and retired to rest for tli iiigit.&#xD;
while wending their way through the We were in our saddles early -thcfo1bof-&#xD;
wilds of Arabia, a cavalcade which my ing morning and after ridig faeW'h&#xD;
fancy led me to imagine we resembled we struck upon a swift a A Mi&#xD;
in miniature. Without any of the re- stream that came leaping down in '&#xD;
fined and too frequent accompaniments of mountains. Travelling up&#xD;
American pleasure parties of the present far into the Andes, we pitahed  .&#xD;
day, such as umbrellas, hat-boxes, cloaks upon its rocky banks, bel' rii fl6&#xD;
and rubbers,we mounted our noble steeds signs that we hadmade  bfu i-tte .&amp;amp; 8.&#xD;
and drew up before the door of one of tion and should find gameindb'-i a ,i  .&#xD;
the old Patriarchs, who came out and After properly securing bur%  dif"&#xD;
gave us his parting blessing, after which leaving a few of the cornpi~r %&#xD;
we galloped across the lawn and were keepers we started id purui'ti gf .&#xD;
soon buried in the forest.            The retilt oftli a'trnddi&amp;amp;%Hs&#xD;
&#xD;
4      4&#xD;
&#xD;
;&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7511-00000037"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES iN CHILL                  7&#xD;
&#xD;
five or six foxes, one vicuna, some half'&#xD;
dozen chinchilas, and a few of a species of&#xD;
rat whose skins are highly prized. The&#xD;
Guanaco,a species of goat considered very&#xD;
difficult to kill were seen in the neigh-&#xD;
borhood but none were taken. Their wool&#xD;
is fine and valuable, more so than any&#xD;
other animals which are sought after. I&#xD;
killed two of the chinchillas, which are&#xD;
little animals about the size of a cat-&#xD;
having fur not inferior to a martini. I&#xD;
also shot a large condor. This bird pos-&#xD;
sesses amazing, strength and will run or&#xD;
fly with incredible swiftness. They are&#xD;
three or four times larger than our eagle&#xD;
with wings at least fourteen feet from&#xD;
end to end. Its feathers are a dark brown&#xD;
with a white collar round its neck. After&#xD;
egpperi turned in, but slept badly owing&#xD;
1p, the excitement of the hunt, I was&#xD;
4apgeus to succeed as well as the'others,&#xD;
,.nd so far I had. All night ,I was busy&#xD;
lj pursuit of game full of eager anxiety.&#xD;
Wj  were off in the .morning scarcely&#xD;
waiting to swallow our breakfast. I had&#xD;
.shot nothing during the morning but one&#xD;
jQc although I had fired at and missed&#xD;
,two -others.  During  my peranbala-&#xD;
tions ihad gained a wild and romantic&#xD;
..ft.  among the mountains; on every&#xD;
ie ,ere numerous holes, caverns and&#xD;
pt eplifis, Ihad been led here in pursuit&#xD;
qfta olle looking Guanico which I was&#xD;
ipgly anxious to take. -While&#xD;
pgnt  creeping about among the rocks&#xD;
,igogsre d gbjecpf my pursuit justI&#xD;
be was aggig starting. for a run, his{&#xD;
vdwgol looking like a sun-wilted rose.&#xD;
1astily raised my gun and fired ; he'&#xD;
prOg forward severely wounded in some&#xD;
pastof   body. In his flight he darted&#xD;
~to on pf tihe cavernous holes, that pen&#xD;
&#xD;
etrated into the mountains; I hastily fol.&#xD;
lowed in his track but-soon. lost sight of&#xD;
him however in the darkness which per.&#xD;
vaded the subterranean vault,but hearing&#xD;
mysprize ashort distance in advance of me&#xD;
as he bounded among the broken stones,&#xD;
I pressed on, although with' extreme&#xD;
difficulty, my head often coming in con-&#xD;
tact with the low arches.&#xD;
The passage soon became exceedingly&#xD;
narrow and in some places so low that I&#xD;
was forced to creep forward upon my&#xD;
hands and knees. I crawled on in this&#xD;
manner some distance, hoping every,&#xD;
moment to lay my hand upon the&#xD;
animal which I was pursuing, when I&#xD;
heard a scraping noise and plunge not&#xD;
three feet a-head of me, and before I had&#xD;
time to think ot the cause, I found my-&#xD;
self tumbling down a deep clasm in the&#xD;
bottom of the cave, and alighted plump&#xD;
upon the body of the wounded Guanico!&#xD;
I dropped the gun during my descent&#xD;
but found it again without much difficulty.&#xD;
I was not seriously injured by the fall&#xD;
but what was my consternation to find&#xD;
that i was impossable to regain the top&#xD;
of the sedge from which I-had fallen. I&#xD;
tried in vain to clamber up the smooth&#xD;
steep sides, but on every side they were&#xD;
wet and slippery, and I only cut and&#xD;
bruised myself in my attempt, and I threw&#xD;
myself dcsponilingly on the ground ; must&#xD;
I remain a prisoner in this dark and dis-&#xD;
mal hole and like Othello's toad live upon&#xD;
the murky vapors of a dungeon? this&#xD;
question which I mentaly put to, myself&#xD;
again aroused me to exertion, I groped&#xD;
round in the dark and .dismal place for&#xD;
I knew not how long,. hoping to find&#xD;
some way of retreat, at last as the only&#xD;
alternative [resolved to follow the stream&#xD;
&#xD;
v&#xD;
76                     iA.MBL S IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
of water that run pouring along the bot-&#xD;
tom of the cave, trusting it might lead&#xD;
me towards daylight. With my gun in&#xD;
my land I groped my way along, crawl-&#xD;
ing on my hands and knees down the&#xD;
oozy sdes of steep waterfalls, or sliding&#xD;
over the slippery surface of the rocks&#xD;
through some low arch while stretched&#xD;
out at my full length, the merciless water&#xD;
washing my prostrate form; and again&#xD;
squeezing through numerous narrow pas-&#xD;
sages that seemed at first scarcely wide&#xD;
enough to admit a cat, or stumbling over&#xD;
broken fragments of rocks which covered&#xD;
the bed of the water course. I often felt&#xD;
that my race was nearly run, expecting&#xD;
momentarily to tumble over into some&#xD;
deep basin, dashing my brains out upon'&#xD;
the heaps of sharp stones at the bottom.&#xD;
What a horrid place was this to die in,&#xD;
with nought but the echoes of the rippling&#xD;
waters to knell my souls exit ! what a&#xD;
noisome mouldy shroud would cover my&#xD;
form in this damp and dismal cavern!&#xD;
I tried to whistle up my courage and&#xD;
drive away these horrid thoughts but&#xD;
every slip of my foot on the slimy ledge&#xD;
would kindle them anew. With these&#xD;
dismal thoughts I continued my sorrow-&#xD;
ful course through these winding subte-&#xD;
raneous corridors of the Andes.&#xD;
This it is true was the dark side of the.&#xD;
picture. Every situation in life it is said&#xD;
has its lights and shadows, and mine I&#xD;
found had its glittering points, and themes&#xD;
for variety ; for had the, hollow worldly&#xD;
honors of pomp and pageantry, the power&#xD;
to influence my pride, I might have been&#xD;
flattered with the idea that over my moul-&#xD;
dering remains would stand one of the&#xD;
proudest monuments in the world. That&#xD;
I should have above me the topling crags&#xD;
&#xD;
-of the lofty Qordilleras for Ty pedestal,&#xD;
and the earthquake's solemn monio&#xD;
chant forth my requium.&#xD;
After many. dreary hours of taure&#xD;
and suspense in worming myself ,hr ihih&#xD;
these  low  and   damp    arche;  I&#xD;
caught sight at last of a golden strea1pof&#xD;
day-light. I had emerged into   gr&#xD;
e opening where I could walk with eap ,&#xD;
and which appeared some ten or twe e&#xD;
feet in height; at the end, the lightust&#xD;
gleamed through a small and narrow Ceoy-&#xD;
ice. I hastened forward towards this gol-&#xD;
den gleam of light as fast as the darkness&#xD;
would permit, and discovered a narrow&#xD;
rent in the ledge not more than two or&#xD;
three inches wide. I was almost in des-&#xD;
pair at my disappointment,but knowingit&#xD;
was useless to despond, I began a search-&#xD;
ing examination on all-sides, and son&#xD;
found that near the floor the ledge was&#xD;
loose and shaky, so that with but very&#xD;
little trouble I enlarged the aperturesuf-&#xD;
ficiently to crawl out of my dreary prison&#xD;
house.  Aristomines, the hero of 'es-&#xD;
sina, could not have been more pleased&#xD;
at his escape from the subterraneous pas-&#xD;
sage of the horrids charnel cavern of Ce.&#xD;
ada, than I was at my final exit from the&#xD;
bowels of the Andes.&#xD;
It was quite dark when I emerged into&#xD;
the open air, and after two hours travel&#xD;
I saw with delight the fire of our srall&#xD;
encanipment, where stood my own ltte&#xD;
tent welcoming me with its 6pen portal.&#xD;
I arrived faint, hungry and weary, 'at ur&#xD;
welcome woodland bower. I found rny&#xD;
companions all in and anxiously waidig&#xD;
for me. They were much surprised0and&#xD;
amused at the rehearsal of my adventnr,&#xD;
and declared their determination to se~ure&#xD;
my Guanico on the morrow. I eat y&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7511-00000038"/>&#xD;
RAMBLE!&#xD;
stupper with as keen a relish as hunge&#xD;
ever gives, and slept through the nigh&#xD;
as sound and pleasant as a New Yorl&#xD;
miilionare on his soft velvet couch.,&#xD;
In the morning I found that my gut&#xD;
needed a great deal of fixing to get i&#xD;
in proper trim for duty ; it had received'&#xD;
somee pretty hard thumps and bruises dur&#xD;
ing its'transit 'through the earth. Witi1&#xD;
the assistance of one of my companions&#xD;
We managed to get it in tolerable good&#xD;
order, and after trying it two or three time&#xD;
at a mark, I was satisfied of its power of&#xD;
doing justice, when called upon to performs&#xD;
duty.              -    .&#xD;
We started for the depot of the under-&#xD;
ground rail-road which I had so thoroughly&#xD;
explored the dy previous, and after some&#xD;
ingenious contrivances succeeded in haul-&#xD;
ing out my prize ; this was the firstlour&#xD;
party had secured, and of course I was&#xD;
j ustly proud.&#xD;
During the remainder of this day we&#xD;
were all much more successful than we&#xD;
had before been ; we surprised a drove&#xD;
of vicunas, and succeeded in capturing&#xD;
several, we killed some twenty chinchil-&#xD;
las, ten or twelve foxes and rats, and- a&#xD;
few smaller animals whose names were&#xD;
unknown to me. I clambered during the&#xD;
day nearly to the summit of one of the&#xD;
lofty peaks, that raised its majestic head&#xD;
far into the regions of the clouds. As I&#xD;
toiled up the rugged steep, I thought of&#xD;
the gallant "San Martin," who led the&#xD;
liberating army across this formidable&#xD;
srrier-an achievement more daring and&#xD;
difficult than that of the renowned "Han-&#xD;
nibal" in crossing the Alps. BLdt no ob-&#xD;
'stacle could intimidate the stout and&#xD;
oble heart of San Martin ; he started&#xD;
'With is army from the western confines&#xD;
&#xD;
S IN CHILI&#xD;
&#xD;
r of the "United Provinces," and in their.&#xD;
t teen days he crossed the frozen'Andes, a&#xD;
distance of 300 miles, with baggage and&#xD;
artillery, over rugged and apparently in-&#xD;
n accessible summits, through narrow de.&#xD;
files where two could scarcely  w'alk&#xD;
1 abreast, and along the giddy verge of&#xD;
frightful precipices, icy with the eternal&#xD;
frosts which here hold their undisputed&#xD;
reign. Having conquered the Andes, he&#xD;
encountered the royalists at Chacabuco,&#xD;
and won a signal victory over the instru-&#xD;
ments of tyranny, he afterwards com-&#xD;
pletely overthrew and annihilated the&#xD;
Spanish army, and sealed the independ.&#xD;
ence of Chili on the plains of Maypu.&#xD;
I soon gained an altitude above the&#xD;
floating vapors of the earth. It was a&#xD;
grand and marvellous sight to witness the.&#xD;
clouds floating beneath me, and hiding'at&#xD;
ti mes all traces of the boundless forest&#xD;
and spreading out like the vast ocean as&#xD;
far as the eye could reach, with the moun-&#xD;
tain tops peering through the mist like&#xD;
islands resting on the bosom of the un-&#xD;
fathomable'deep. It required but a very&#xD;
slight degree of ideality to imagine the&#xD;
huge billows following each otherin rapid&#xD;
succession, and breaking against the&#xD;
mountain sides, sending their' whiteied&#xD;
foam curling up in endless shapeseven&#xD;
to their very summits, ad thence moving&#xD;
offin the distance like an ariii of Ossiarls&#xD;
&#xD;
shadowy ghosts.&#xD;
I was transported with the everchang-&#xD;
ing scene, and loitered away many hours,&#xD;
so loth was I to quit the enchanting spot&#xD;
but .the occasional report of my comrades'&#xD;
guns, reminded me that II was forming&#xD;
my character as a huntsman, and would&#xD;
be judged ly-ny success.&#xD;
Early one morning one of our party&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IM CHILI'&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
than if he had been a bale of cotton, He&#xD;
dashed again into the thick copse of will&#xD;
ows, where he was immediately followed&#xD;
by these brave and resolute fellows, de.&#xD;
termined to dispatch him there, or drive&#xD;
him forth again from his retreat; in the&#xD;
latter they succeeded, and I got one more&#xD;
good shot at his majesty as he appeared&#xD;
in the open ground, and wounded him in&#xD;
the leg, he still showed fight howevet&#xD;
and we gave him another volly, increase.&#xD;
ing the dose at intervals as opportunity&#xD;
offered, and by thus following our woun-&#xD;
ded adversary  up closely we finaly&#xD;
obliged hin to give in. He was a mon-&#xD;
ster, weighing I should judge from four&#xD;
to five hundred pounds. Our wounded&#xD;
comrade thought so little of his wound&#xD;
that we could scarcely persuade him to&#xD;
&#xD;
0&#xD;
&#xD;
came running in with the information that in the monsters shoulder. I immediate-&#xD;
alarge Jaguar, an animal but little inferior ly leveed my piece and'luckily shoi hira&#xD;
to the Tiger, had attacked him, and it was through the neck, when he directly' e-&#xD;
with great difficulty he had escaped the leased his hold, turned and trotted o"&#xD;
jaws of the ferocious beast. These ani- Is late victim with admirable 'nerve&#xD;
mals are sefdom seen so far south, con- sprang instantly to his feet, and 'gave&#xD;
sequently this news was enough to put him a full charge in the rear, which great.&#xD;
us all in motion, and we immediately ly accelerated his retreat. We prompt-&#xD;
started off in pursuit of the stranger. Af- ly followed his blood stained trail, and&#xD;
ter two hours travel we arrived in the were soon joined by our other comirads,&#xD;
vicinity of his late appearance, and beat in the chase.&#xD;
about among the tangled brush-wood, The sport now become truly exciting&#xD;
for a long time without making any dis- fully equal to the capture of a sperm&#xD;
coveries. TJpon consultaion we resolved whale. After tracking the monster for a&#xD;
to separate into smaller parties and scout, short time, he was discovered in a, thick&#xD;
the vicinity thoroughly. Three young growth of willows, foaming at the mouth,&#xD;
men and myself took a path whichas it and showing other sign; of rage and&#xD;
happenned, soon led us on the trail of the pain We made a calculation' as to his&#xD;
jaguar. We followed it up through a position and fired. Three balls only&#xD;
thick copse of brush-wood and tall grass, reached him and he again rushed out in&#xD;
keeping our guns ready for immediate the greatest fury, when another discharge&#xD;
use. The circumstances were so entire. was poured upon him, all of which ap.&#xD;
ly new to me that it nay well be sup- parently had no more effect upon him&#xD;
&#xD;
posed I held my piece with a very tena-&#xD;
cious grasp.&#xD;
Having observed symptoms that irdi-&#xD;
cated we were quite near to our adversa-&#xD;
ry's retreat, we threw ourselves into, In-&#xD;
dian file for our better protection, and the&#xD;
effective use of our arms, when just as&#xD;
our file-leader was preparing to descend&#xD;
a deep ravine, we heard a terriffic growl,&#xD;
and a crackling through' the under-brush,&#xD;
and before our advance-guard could re-&#xD;
cover himself, the fierce animal, with&#xD;
eyes that really seemed to flash fire, was&#xD;
upon him, and dashing his claws ihto&#xD;
the hunter's leg, threw him forcibly upon&#xD;
+he ground ; fortunately one of our com-&#xD;
panions nearest to them, observed the&#xD;
movement's; and almost as quick as&#xD;
tNought lodged the contents of his iifle&#xD;
&#xD;
79&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7511-00000039"/>&#xD;
s0&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI,&#xD;
&#xD;
hsve it bound up.&#xD;
It would not be at 'all interesting to&#xD;
give a detailed account of each day's&#xD;
proceedings, or the number of the ani-&#xD;
mals which were slain. Many of them&#xD;
were unknown to me and their different&#xD;
names I have long since forgotten. It&#xD;
will be'suflicient to say that after break-&#xD;
ing up our encampment, we mounted our&#xD;
horses with our booty and started for the&#xD;
shores of the Wonseta. There was a&#xD;
&#xD;
general rejoicing upon our return, and&#xD;
we were received with shouts and con-&#xD;
gratulations. Then folowed the presents&#xD;
from the hunters, of several little curios-&#xD;
ities gathered do sing their absence each&#xD;
his particuar favorite. It was many&#xD;
days    re the excitement of our- return&#xD;
su    d, during which time it was one&#xD;
continual holiday, in which the whole&#xD;
village united.&#xD;
&#xD;
6&#xD;
&#xD;
7&#xD;
&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
LI&#xD;
&#xD;
J&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER XVII.&#xD;
It was soon after our return that I wit- monies place each a hand on the head&#xD;
nessed for the first time the marriage of the candidates and repeat the.mariage&#xD;
ceremony, which I will attempt to des- ritual, which is responded to in certain&#xD;
cribe. The bride and bridegroom  are parts by all the associates in the lige,,&#xD;
each. decked out in their best "bib and The females then immediately grasp t1p&#xD;
tucker," and supported by an equal num- bride and hurry her off, while the poop&#xD;
ber of each sex, say ten or twelve cou. husband is expected .to secure her4 and&#xD;
pie who, forming two rings, join hands, bear her off; in spite of these mischievous&#xD;
and each party dance round their respec- Amazons, which is no easy ,matter, fes&#xD;
tive, candidates uttering a singular and pecially if the bride joins heartily. in the,&#xD;
peculiar kind of a chant, which is con- sport, and endeavors to hide fronghIer&#xD;
tinted some ten minutes, they then form liege lord, which is often the cas, with&#xD;
two parallel' lines, the males on one side the frolicsome faries. When the hg&#xD;
and the females on the other, with the band once has fairly got hold of his .et,&#xD;
Bride and groom at each extremity of ter half, the sport is ended and he bears&#xD;
the files. The prelimenary preparations her in triumph to his home.&#xD;
rare thus arranged by the assistants, when  I was much amused to see the ear-&#xD;
the officiating justices, (an aged male nestness displayed, and strategems resort-&#xD;
and female,), each approach the sep- ed to by the spectators, far- the purpose&#xD;
rate parties, and leads them through of throwing obstacles in the way of the&#xD;
the open file until they meet in the cen- pursuer while in chase of his frolicsome&#xD;
tre of the line  Here they are placed bride. They would often manage  to&#xD;
opposite each other, joining both hands exchange their dress in such a manner as&#xD;
while the master and mistress of cere- to deceive the bridegrdom. On one oc-&#xD;
&#xD;
. ,&#xD;
i                                    {&#xD;
i                             1&#xD;
_                    t       '&#xD;
~f 8&#xD;
t                    j&#xD;
,         r  {      jt           4&#xD;
A&#xD;
I&#xD;
S      ' ^V&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7511-00000040"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
casion I hinted to the man to select the swer, and, if in the affirmative, matters&#xD;
girl who most resembled his bride and were soon arranged and the nuptial knot&#xD;
pretend to carry her off as though un, speedily tied.&#xD;
conscious of his mistake.' This strategem,  The man, as a general thing, provided&#xD;
produced just the result that I anticipat- himself wth a house and the necessary&#xD;
ed, the bride seeing another about to furniture, previous to' his marriage, to&#xD;
supplant her place, entirely, broke from which he immediately conducted his bride&#xD;
her tormentors, and rushing forward at the close of the ceremonies ; except&#xD;
grasped the girl by the hand endeavoring when he h td a widowed mother, or a&#xD;
to release her from the arms of her hus- family of sisters, with no one but himself&#xD;
band, when he immediately dropped the to provide for them; in such cases he re.&#xD;
one the had at first secured, and grappled mained in the old domicil.&#xD;
with the other whom he now was willing&#xD;
to recognize as his newly made wife. in their construction, two or three men&#xD;
Each wedding was followed by sports  thei finishone, wi rall the out&#xD;
and games of various kinds, and was could easily finiture   llte  out&#xD;
considered one of the great occasions for ouse  d  The garde n yar&#xD;
feasting and hilarity. The marriage rites or five days.  The gves and yard&#xD;
were encouraged, by precept and exam- re and   by was a  les after  it-r&#xD;
pe and celibacy was unknown to them. ~ia e  a p     laig g  t th&#xD;
believed with Sternes, that "a good mess the happy coupe laying ou  te&#xD;
they       sed with   t     a g  . grounds, and staking out the enclosures&#xD;
hart bats some object to be kod a  with skill and neatness if not scientific&#xD;
the  purest' of our spirts suffer most precision; each performing their respec-&#xD;
under the destitution, notwithstanding the tive parts, and completing it according to&#xD;
torpid monk may seek heaven, comfort- teruidsklan        jdg   e. In&#xD;
les         e" Long courtships were this man ner, and in arranging their other&#xD;
alsosunpopur and    L fact were unnec- household affairs, was spent the honey&#xD;
ar nar, athey were all brought up to moon, and for aught I could see to the&#xD;
ether fros tnfhncy  and familiar with contrary the honey moon lasted through&#xD;
gehrfomifny,'n     fmha     ilife   'Their domestic affairs coukid not be&#xD;
every incident of each others lives. When life.&#xD;
the maidens improves upon in the least, by the most,&#xD;
th gestiori -wa popped, t' a     enlightened nations,.&#xD;
were generally ready to give a direct an- enlig&#xD;
v.,&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER XVIII.&#xD;
It was now the last of June. I had'my personal appearance was any waly&#xD;
been nearly two months among this pe- ;aptivating. We drank deep from Ou-&#xD;
culiar people, the weather'had become pid's fountain, and were as happy astw&#xD;
somewhat cold, the nights were frosty young lovers well could be. The ;ide&#xD;
and the tops of the distant mountains ture of "Claude Melnott's" honey moon&#xD;
were covered with a garment of snow in "the Lady of Lyons," is quite apropos&#xD;
which, by the way scarcely ever shroud- with a slight variation.&#xD;
ed the green valleys below.            "At noon we sat beneath the arching vasn&#xD;
All day Metina and myself had been  Wondering why earth could 'e unhappy&#xD;
rambling through the village, and among  Since heaven still left them youth and love,&#xD;
the tall forest trees, as we were wont to  And when night came beneath the breathles&#xD;
do, and when at last the clear beautiful  heavens,&#xD;
d                                     We'd guess what star would beour home&#xD;
day had faded into the . gentle tints of When life becomes immortal; while the 4.&#xD;
twilight, we bent our steps homeward,   very light&#xD;
and seated ourselves in front of the tent Stole through the midst of flowering trees,and&#xD;
door, Metina had thrown a loose cover-  every air&#xD;
ing over her shoulders and we began our Was heavy with the sighs of fragrant groves,&#xD;
g oAnd music from sweet birds, and the mur-&#xD;
evenings tete a tete. My private inter-  merings&#xD;
views with this lovely maiden, were, like  Of the low fountain that gushed forth&#xD;
most lover's, more interesting to ourselves In the midst of roses."&#xD;
than an account would be to others ; that There are often moments when my&#xD;
I charmed her ear with"Othello tales" of fancy carries me back to that bright spot&#xD;
my risks and adventures, I donbt not; of earth, although years have passed by&#xD;
for I was never coxcomb enough to think since I roamed through those fairy groves&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7511-00000041"/>&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
and glided in our light canoe over the 'far to the south rose on the clear night&#xD;
sparkling waters of the mountain lake, air, a wild prolonged shout, which came&#xD;
,vith one, around whose bright image my echoing up in long loud strains through&#xD;
memory still fondly clings with dear and the waving trees, and back again from&#xD;
tender recollections. Rapidly we dane- the neighboring hills. We were instant.&#xD;
ed over the tiny waves, or floated slowly ly upon our feet, and were, in a few&#xD;
by each cliff and cove aid headland, moments surrounded by some eight or&#xD;
watching the landscapes pictured in the ten who had been as suddenly aroused&#xD;
flood, and often at eve, when darkness by the wild shout.&#xD;
hung o'er lake and wood we were guid- The nature or this singular interruption,&#xD;
ed on our way by the lights from the I could not discover, and my excitement&#xD;
scattered cabins, which shone mysterious- was intense when I imagined I could see&#xD;
ly on the dark waters. The remem- deep concern and wonder depicted upon&#xD;
brance of those happy hours, are among the faces of the surrounding group, and&#xD;
the most beautiful visions of the past, the whole village tumultuously gathering&#xD;
and they rise at times in the magic cham- in the centre of the area, as was their&#xD;
bers of the memory, fresh and sweet as habit upon every important occasion. Of&#xD;
ever.                               course I followed the living tide, and soon&#xD;
I sometimes almost marvel how I could perceived that the cause of this uncom-&#xD;
ve been induced to leave so delighttul mon disturbance was still a mystery.&#xD;
ot, and perhaps I might not, but oth- The point from whence the sound issued&#xD;
e t4bigh faniiar faces would often gath -was immediately scoured in all directions.&#xD;
Sin my dreams of bome. Nature, here It may have been ten minutes or a quar-&#xD;
i istrue, inall its aspects heightens man's ter of an hour, when again was hdard the&#xD;
e3oments,the salubrious air, thede- same wild shout, but now much nearer,&#xD;
fi htful climate, render this spot a sec- clearer, and distinct than before, ara&#xD;
ondPaladise. VYet alas ! all these allure- immediately I observed Metina jump up&#xD;
agents could not cheat me out of the recol- and clap her-hands, making tov'ards,&#xD;
debtins; of my old new England home. shouting HTarry! Harry! (a name she&#xD;
"The parted bosom clings to wonted home  had ofter heard me speak.) It was a&#xD;
S  g4t that's kindred cheer the welcome&#xD;
MartE   -                        moment ere I could comprehend it All,&#xD;
Metinaand I were seated as I have but ,soon the joyful tidings burst. upon&#xD;
rderorbed, billing and cooing like two me. It was my friend Harry's approach&#xD;
young loving turtles, when all at once, that was thus mysteriously announced.&#xD;
t                                      _&#xD;
&#xD;
84&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER XIX,&#xD;
Knowing the directions I had left forabout us. When we were sufficiently&#xD;
Harry in'case of his return to the Span- recovered to look each other in the face.&#xD;
ish village, Guved iohad given directions to I was supprised to find my friend great-&#xD;
-his people that, in case he should, at any ly altered, his stoutjathletic form was worn&#xD;
time be discovered, they were to con- down and emaciated, his dress dishev-&#xD;
duct him safely to Wonsota, The run- yelled, and his appearance in every partio.&#xD;
ners' soon came in corroborating the in. ular indicated great physical suffering&#xD;
formation we had just received by tele- and hardship, which must have beenses&#xD;
praph, while Guvedio and others dashed vere indeed to have thus worn upon a&#xD;
on to meet the advancing party. For man capable of as great endurance as I&#xD;
'myself'I was almost overcome, with joy, well knew Harry posessed.&#xD;
I remained transfixed to the spot, nearly Without answering my numerous ques-&#xD;
in a state, of unconsciousness, and so tions, he directly commenced in a huyi-&#xD;
,continued until the approach of the par- ed manner, to inform me that a company&#xD;
ty recalled my wandering senses. I rush, of Chilian soldiers, dn their march to'&#xD;
ed forward into Harry's arms, and my ex- Valparaiso, were now passing not thirty&#xD;
cessive joy found vent in a flood of tears. miles to the westward of us, and anxious-&#xD;
The-stoic, with his. ossified heart, may ly urged me to start and meet them, a.&#xD;
say that we were femenine and chicken, matter which could be easily acomplished&#xD;
hearted, but I contend that it is not only by diverging to the northward and head-&#xD;
right, butrmanly, sometimes to weep, to ing them off. If this was to be done at&#xD;
give vent to the overflowing heart.  all we must start immediately. I saw&#xD;
We each wept long and loud,and but few that Harry was much, agitated, and I en-&#xD;
drieyes were seen in that savage group deavored.to persuade-him to take anight's&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7511-00000042"/>&#xD;
86                        RAMBLES&#xD;
rest and start in the morning, but the poor&#xD;
fellow had suffered so much, and deliver-&#xD;
ance now appearing almost within his&#xD;
reach, it was irrl)oSsible to induce him to a&#xD;
moment's delay;'and I must confess, as&#xD;
visions of home danced rapidly through&#xD;
my mind, I felt somewhat impatient. I&#xD;
accordingly turned to Guvedio and asked&#xD;
him for two horses and an escort to conduct&#xD;
us towards the Patriot army. The hors-&#xD;
es were immediately furnished, and&#xD;
Guvedio agreed to join the escort, not&#xD;
doubting, our intention to return again.&#xD;
In two hours from the time that Harry&#xD;
made his first appearance, five of us were&#xD;
dashing through the woods, under a full&#xD;
press of rein and spurs. We rode rapid-&#xD;
ly all night, and found during the next&#xD;
day we had struck the trail of the advance-&#xD;
ing column. I now explained to Guve-&#xD;
dio our intention, and the danger of his&#xD;
proceeding any further with us. The&#xD;
truth seemed to flash suddenly upon his&#xD;
mind. It was an event lie had not be-&#xD;
fore dreamed of, and consequently he was&#xD;
but little prepared  for the' seperation.&#xD;
He caught my hand ands with the most&#xD;
entreating looks and words urged me to&#xD;
return. 1 was greatdydistressed at the&#xD;
parting scene, and wi.h difficulty extrica-&#xD;
ted myself from his grasp promising to&#xD;
return again by and by if I lived.&#xD;
I removed my cravat. and placing it on&#xD;
his neck, directed him to give it to Me-&#xD;
tina. I then affectionately gave him a&#xD;
parting embrace, jumped on my horse,&#xD;
and dashed forward on the trail of the&#xD;
moving army. I turned my head once&#xD;
and saw my Indian friend, with lingering&#xD;
looki still gazing after me. I stood up in&#xD;
my stirrups,'lifted my hat, and swinging&#xD;
it round and round, gave him my final&#xD;
&#xD;
IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
adieu. We now put spurs to our horses,&#xD;
and drove on at a rapid rate, fully confi-&#xD;
dent we should come up with the encamp.&#xD;
meant before day break and so it turned&#xD;
out.&#xD;
We saw the camp-fires about midnight,.&#xD;
and rode boldly up to the entry. We&#xD;
were detained until the commander was&#xD;
informed of the circumstances of our ar-&#xD;
rival, when after a few words of explana-&#xD;
tion we were welcomed within the lines,&#xD;
and patrook of a soldier's fare.&#xD;
Our story excited much wonder, and we&#xD;
were looked upon with as much amaze-&#xD;
ment aswe had before excited among-&#xD;
less enlightened beings. During our&#xD;
march to Valparaiso, we were the lions.&#xD;
of the army, and our adventures, the&#xD;
theme of constant discussion.&#xD;
We arrived at Valparaiso, in a few&#xD;
days where we were strongly urged to&#xD;
join the army, on their expedition to Pe-&#xD;
ru. This arrangement we declined, but&#xD;
compromised the matter with them, how-&#xD;
ever, by entering the Patriot Naval ser-&#xD;
vice. The brig of war "Achilles," Com.&#xD;
Paul Delano, was laying in the harbor,&#xD;
ready for sea. We accordingly shipped&#xD;
in her, and immediately repaired on&#xD;
board.&#xD;
Valparaiso when viewd from the an-&#xD;
chorage, scarcely merits the name it&#xD;
bears, (the vale of Paradise.) At the&#xD;
first glance it appears dark, craggy and&#xD;
fearful; broken into suceessive hills, val-&#xD;
leys, and wild glens, with a small por-&#xD;
tion of sand beach, scarce wide enough&#xD;
for a mule path. In the back ground,&#xD;
hills iise upon hills overlooking, each&#xD;
other, and extending far in: the distance,&#xD;
where their summits are crownedby :the&#xD;
snow-capped Andes. Hero,'amnong these&#xD;
&#xD;
U&#xD;
&#xD;
RAMBLES IN CHILI.&#xD;
&#xD;
.m&#xD;
&#xD;
8/&#xD;
&#xD;
wild cliffs, steep promentoiies and bar.&#xD;
ren hills stands the city of Valparaiso, a&#xD;
place, which, when once seen, will nevi&#xD;
er be forgotten.  As the Rev. Waltei&#xD;
Colton says. "It will stand alone- in&#xD;
your after dreams, like Jacob's ladder.&#xD;
like the rounds of that airy vision, its buil -&#xD;
dings ascend roof over roof, till they seem&#xD;
to topple in the sky."  Vie wed from the&#xD;
sea its appearance is truly picturesque:&#xD;
the houses grouped thickly together, ap-&#xD;
parently without order on the three&#xD;
principal hills, with the valley's and&#xD;
spaces between, resemble several dis-&#xD;
tinct towns. A turmber of neat detach-&#xD;
ed houses are built on little levels arti-&#xD;
ficialy formed on the sides of the hiih&#xD;
fronting the harbor, while now and they&#xD;
a stray white house is to be seen on some&#xD;
lofty hill beyond.&#xD;
The harbor scarcely deserves the name.&#xD;
It is but little better than an open road-&#xD;
steac\, entirely exposed on the north and&#xD;
west, to the "Northers" which are often&#xD;
violent, and are an admonition to all ships&#xD;
to slip their cables. Many vessels have&#xD;
been driven a shore, on a rock, called&#xD;
"little Cape Horn."  On the south it isI&#xD;
protected by a little promontory, called&#xD;
'Puenta de Coro Milla,' where the shore&#xD;
is steep and rocky; from hence, the bay&#xD;
extends from E to W in the form of at&#xD;
gently curved crescent. Fort San Anton-&#xD;
ia is on the south inlet of the bay, andI&#xD;
"Castello del Resario," mounting six guns&#xD;
stands in the north part of the town.&#xD;
Immediately in front of the bay, and one&#xD;
fourth of a mile on the east and west, ist&#xD;
the principal commercial city of business&#xD;
and fashion. Back and westward of this&#xD;
are three large groups of houses scattered&#xD;
on the three hills, called by the sailors,&#xD;
&#xD;
0&#xD;
&#xD;
#   -&#xD;
&#xD;
the "Fore, Main and Mizen-tops:"' About&#xD;
half a mile eastward on the lowland, is1&#xD;
the 'A lmendra'-Almond grove=where&#xD;
the houses extend perhaps a mile or&#xD;
more; they are built like the others, prin_&#xD;
cipally of reeds, some are constructed of&#xD;
abedos. The Custom House - however is&#xD;
a beautiful and spacious building,, and&#xD;
from its situation on the mole where the,&#xD;
stranger first lands, is an object which&#xD;
attracts the attention of all who arrive&#xD;
at Valparaiso. Quite near the Custora&#xD;
House is another fine building called the&#xD;
Exchange.&#xD;
There is a peculiar inconsistency con&#xD;
nected with the interior of the dwellings&#xD;
which cannot fail to strike an American&#xD;
with sur rise. The plainest looking c t*&#xD;
tages which gleam from the topling cliffs;&#xD;
are provided with the most costly, and&#xD;
aristocratic furniture. The piano, the&#xD;
'harp and guitar are heard in almost every&#xD;
house.. They appear   singularly  out.&#xD;
of place in these savage abodes. The&#xD;
most elegant articles of ornament are al-&#xD;
so found in their fancy shops, and the&#xD;
ladies are decked out with large ribh tor-&#xD;
toise shells combs, wrought into various&#xD;
figures.,&#xD;
The Elective franchise in Chili is the&#xD;
same as in America. No property quali-&#xD;
fication is required, all go to the ballot&#xD;
box, yet a majority of them can scarcely&#xD;
be called independent voters, influenced&#xD;
and overawed as they are, by the priests&#xD;
and land-holders, by the priests at the&#xD;
confessional, and by the landlords with&#xD;
their (rentals,) for the innequality of the&#xD;
feudal system still survives as originated&#xD;
from Old Spain. The lands are owned&#xD;
by the privileged few, and their succession&#xD;
secured by theriight of entail.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="88" xml:id="VAC7511-00000043"/>&#xD;
1 AMBLIIS 1N CuILT.&#xD;
&#xD;
$olorig as this law of primogeniture ex- mony due to their rank. They visitg4&#xD;
its bChili will be far behind the age of every part of the vessel, and atddressc&#xD;
Republicahism: for freedom and equality the crew, three quarters of whom were&#xD;
are scions of the same stock, they flourish Americans and English in our own Jan.&#xD;
in the same soil, and yield their fruit in guage. About five, they took their leave&#xD;
the same season ; they are t win sisters and as they went over the side all haid&#xD;
and share the same destiny. On the were called to get underweigh, with light&#xD;
soil where equality cannot flourish, free- hearts we loosed our sails, weighed ,an&#xD;
don will soon wither and die.     chor and at six P.M. were standing out to&#xD;
The day of our departure we were sea for an offing, bound on a cruise to the&#xD;
visited by Gen. Prieto, the President ac- reward.&#xD;
tompanied by Don Diego Portales, his Thus dear reader,ends my ramblesin Chi&#xD;
minister of the interior, the same indi- ii, and if they have afforded you as much&#xD;
idvual who was traitorously assassinated entertainment, as they have others who&#xD;
by Florine and Col. Vidaurre, at the have occasionally listened to 'my yarns.&#xD;
commencement of the civil war, a few [ shall be satisfied; however much I iav&#xD;
months afternfards.  We manned the regret the faults that undoubtedly rfay&#xD;
yards and received them with the cere- be found in the hastily written narrative.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
 &#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD; &#xD;
            </p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>