<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7800">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>My Mother-in law </title>
            <author>Bricktop.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7800</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2248</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>My mother-in law</title>
                  <author>Bricktop.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>79 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>M.J. Ivers</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1886">[1886]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-04-06">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>My mother-in law</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (Cover) " xml:id="VAC7800-00000001"/>ILLUSTRATED BY HOPKINS.    &#xD;<pb n="0Advertisement (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7800-00000002"/> ATIONS BY BEST AUTHOIe.   Choice Collection of   COMPOSITIONS,   Carefully Compiled for School, Lyceum, Parlor, and other Entertainments, By FACSNOJS P. I SULLIVAN. CONTENTS OF No. 3.   PAGE. The Factory Girl's Last Day................ 3 The Bridge of Sighs. By Thomas Hood  4 The Sisters. By John G. Whittier ....... 5 Smiting the Rock ............................... 5 The Ruined Merchant. By Cora M. Eager 6 Knocked About. By Daniel Connolly... 6 The Burial of the Dane. By H. H. Brow- nell. .......................................... 8 Heroes of Greece. By Byron ............. 8 The Moneyless Man. By H. T. Stanton  9 The Drummer Boy ............................ 10 Catiline's Defiance. By George Croly... 10 Tho Picket Guard. By Mrs. Howland. " The Dying Street AraD. By Matthias Banrr 1 No Mortgage on the Farm. By John H . Yates .................................... 12 The Old Canoe. By Albert Pike ......... 13 Casablanca ...................................... 13 Next Door. Charles B. Howell ........... 14 Rienzi's Address. By M. R. Mitford.... 14 The Black Regiment. By GeorgeH Boker 15 Charles XII. By Johnson .................. 15 Cimmna's Love for Sinnatus. By Tennyson 16 Washington. By Biyant ................... 16 The Hand that Rocks the World. By Wm. Ross Wallace ...................... 16 Lenore. By Edgar A. Poe.................. 16 One Night with Gin ........................... 17 Life's Cotfilict. By W. Whitehead....... 18 Coeur de Lion at the Bier of his Father. By Felicia Hemans ...................... 18 Never Give up ..............................  19 The Unfinished Letter ........................ 20 The Miser's Will. By George BirdsPye. 20 The Lights of London. By George R S.ms 21 Sample Rooms .........  ...................  21 The Rose. By James R. Lowell.......... 21 Song of the Battle Flag ..................... 22 The Brave at Home. By T. Buchanan Read......................................... 23 Annabel Lee. By Edgar A. Poe.......... 23 The Cumberland. By H. W. Longfellow 23 He and She....................................... 24 Othello's Apology. By Shakspeare ...... 25   PAO*. The Blue and the Gray. By M. F. Finch 25 Bill and I. By G. H. Miles................ 26 Mill River Ride. By J. W. Donovan ... 26 In Memoriam. By Geo. D. Prentice.... 27 Horatius at the Bridge. IBy T B Mcaulay 28 There is N) Death. By Lord Lytton...... 29 The Eugineer's Story ....................... 30 Only Sixteen ..................... ............31 I'll Take What Father Takes. By W Hoyle 31 The Light House. By Thomas Moore... 32 Lochiel's Warning. By Thomas Campbell 32 My Friend's Sectet. By B. P. Shillber 34 The Maniac. By Matthew Gregory Lewis 34 Beruardo's Revetnge, Part III ............... 35 Bernardo and Alphonso, Part II. By John Gibson Lockhardt ....................... 36 The Kight" Toast ..3...................... . 6 The Child Violinist. By Austin Dobsol,. 37 Tom. By Conlstanco FenniinorH Wool on 37 Cleopatra Dying. By Thomas S. Collier. 38 Hotspur's Defence. By Shakspeare .... 39 General Joseph Reed; or, the Incorrupt- ible Patriot. By Edward (0. Jones. 39 Williamthe Conqueror. ByChas Mackay 40 Keeping his Word ........................... 40 Soliloquy of King Richard IlI. By Shak- speare ........................................ 41 The Little Grave ............................. 41 The Wounded Soldier ......................... 42 Clarence's Dream. By Shakspeare ......43 The Battle of the Baltic. By Thomas Campbell.  ................................. 44 The Bells of the Atlantic. By Mrs. Sigourney ........... ..................... 45 The Stormy Petrel. By Bryau W. Proctor (Barry CornwalD........... ....... 45 The Amen of the Rocks. By Gellert.... 46 Battle Flag at Shenandoah. By Joaquin / M iller............................. ........... 4 Black-eyed Susan. By Thomas Gay.... 47 Landing of the Pilgrim Fathers. By Mrs. Hemaus .............................. 47 The Three Fishers. Ily Chas. Kingsley 48 The Sands of Dee. By Chas. Kingsley. 48   Price 12 Ceins by Mail. 1 and 2 Cent Stamps taken. Address 1M1. J. IVERS &amp;    CO., 86 KVSS&amp;  U STREET, X N. .   ity.    MY MOTHER IN -LAW BY BRICKTOP.  ILLUSTRATED BY HOPKINS  .     M. J. IZERS &amp; CO., Publishers, .... 86 Nassau Street,  NEW YORK. ,;   &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7800-00000003"/> Entered according to act of Congress in the year 1886, by M. J. IVERS &amp; CO. a  A   In the Office of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington. ',    SOTH1LIN41AW. CHAPTER I. IT is the fate of some men to have mothers-in-law. Some ; -men don't appear to! be able to get along without them. Mar- riageable orphans are scarce. It has been sung (by an old bachelor, for money) that "a child in the house is a well spring of pleasure." It remains for me to sing about mothers-in-law as well- springs. My lyre is all right but my voice is none of the best. But there is no use of entering'into a tedious description of this "well-spring," for although they are alike as a general, bhing, no two men have the same experience.. I will simply give mine in a round, illustrated tale. Of course I was in love with Harriet Ann, or I. should nev- er have married her. So far was 1 gone on her that I never stopped to ask myself if she had a mother. But I distinctly remember that she hinted at being an orphan, probably by 'way of encouraging my interest. We were made one and struggled through the saccharine effulgence of our honeymoon,             . A month or so after that happy event was over with, my wife said to me one morning: "Brickey, my dear, I have just .  received a letter from my mother, and she says she is coming to pay us'a/good long visit. Ain't you delighted?"   &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7800-00000004"/> MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. NN "BRICKEY, MY DEAR, I HAVE JUST RECElVIB A LET'IT'K  FROM MfY MOTHER, AND SHE SAYS SHE IS COMNG TO PAY US A GOOD "ONG VISIT. AIN'T YOU DELIGHTED?"  She was holding the letter in her hand as she communicated  this pleasing bit of intelligence to me. I looked up from my paper. Wasn't I 'lad? Somehow or other I can't say that I was. But I was "fresh," and tried to make myself believe that my mother-in- law was only the ripened goodness of the beautiful bud I had snatched at the altar. I distinctly remember of looking in the glass a few moments after she made the announcement to me, and of not being able to recognize myself, my face had elongated to such an extent Seemed to anticipate something, as it were. I had never experienced a mother-in-law, but I somehow felt that I didn't hanker after one very much.   MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. During our honeymoon trip we had paid a, short visit to her mother, and although she was all smiles and good advice, I somehow thought that I would not care to have that two hundred pound mother-in-law for a boss. I dismissed the thought, however, for I was so happy that I could think of nothing but my own woutsy poutsy-ducky-dim- ity-of a wife. We left the old lady, who, by the way, was a widow, and continued our journeyings until the moon had waned and we became sensible enough to settle down to housekeeping.  OH YES WASN'T I GLADI  I K'iEW I SHOWED IT IN PM FAOcB FOR I 'ELT THE BLOOD TINGLING THE END OF MY NOSE.  &#xD;<pb n="6-7 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7800-00000005"/> 6         MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. A year had passed and we were getting along very nicely hen my wife made this startling announcement, that her mother was coming to live with us. "Pay us a good long visit," was the way she put it, but knew well enough, felt it in my bones somehow, that her good long visit meant a permanent residence. Oh, yes, wasn't I glad! I knew I showed it in my face, for I felt the blood tingling the end of my nose. "Ain't you glad, Brickey?" she asked again. Well, yes, of course anything that will make you happier Harriet Ann." "But you don't look very happy. Oh, she is such a splen did woman, my dear. So careful, such a good calculator. Not a bit like most mothers I assure you.'      I "I hope not; for if she is, Harriet Ann, she will rouse a sleeping lion. If she attempts to fill the bill of the average mother-in-law, I will teach her a lesson that she will not for get," I replied, almost fiercely. "Oh, oh! how can you talk so?" "Because I mean it, I will be the master of my own house and don't make any mistake." "Oh, arn't you awful, I never heard you go on so before But there is no occasion for it; my mother is a perfect angel of goodness and I know you will like her." "Well, I hope so, but if she is not-" here I banged my hand over my head and strode from the house, leaving my Harriet Ann in tears. But I meant business. How sorry I was that I had neg lected my physical training. My muscle was all down, and ' resolved to set about getting it up again without loss of time not knowing what might happen. After attending to business at the office I went directly to    &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7800-00000006"/> 8.         MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. a gymnasium and made arrangements with the proprietor to get my muscle up. There was yet two weeks in which to work before that two hundred pounds of " ripened goodness" arrived, and wonders might be done in that time. The professor under whose care I placed myself advised me to diet on oatmeal porridge and milk, as that was one of the best dishes in the world to feed and sustain the flAscle. Then he put me at the dumb bells. The next day he gave me Indian clubs to swing and the next I practiced on the flying trapeze. Even this was not deemed sufficient, and the next day he gave me a pair of boxing gloves and set me to knock- ing a suspended sand bag around. This was my delight, for I made myself believe that it was my mother-in-law, and ,the way I did "lam" it was a caution. But it must not be supposed that I got through 'with all this exercise without some mishaps. One day I would go home with a black eye, a bunged head, a crippled leg or bruised body. The artist 'has relieved me of a fuller ex- planation by picturing a few of my 'bouts in his own graphic way. All this, of course, did not escape the anxious eye of my wife, but I made various excuses for my mishaps and she never mis- trusted what I was up to. I can't swear that I made as much progress with my muscle as I ought, for the labor attending my violent exercise was al- most too much for me. In fact, at the end of two weeks I don't think I was so strong as I had been before. This might have discouraged another, but my heart was in it and the signet of conquest was stamped on my towering brow.   MY MOT"HR-IN-X&amp;W.       9 SEEING NO HOPE IN THS DIRECTION I SHOVED MY HANDS INTO , MY POCIETS AND BEGAN TO PACE UP AND DOWN TI F TRACPI. WASN'T I HAPPY? Well, at length the day of her arrival came, and I went to the depot to meet and welcome her. Wasn't I happy, though? We live just a little way out of the city and I haunted that depot an hour before it was time for the train to arrive. But the principal charm for me was the telegraph office, I listened to the clicking instrument and watched the expression of the operator's face.         .  You see, I didn't know but that train might run off the track or some other accident happen that would kill everybody on it. I venturec to ask the operator once if there was any newt regarding the next train, but he replied No, and said he guesse it was all right.   &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7800-00000007"/> How good that was of him! H-e probably thought I was anxious regarding the safety of some friend who was on board. Well, I was. Seeing no hope in this direction I shoved my hands into my poekets and began to pace up and down the track. Wasn't I happy! While thus employed I did not hear the approaching train and might have been run over had not the station agent yelled at me and asked if I was ambitious to give the coroner a job or trying to get the insurance on my life for the benefit of my wife. This brought me to my senses and I leaped upon the sta- tion platform just in time to save myself. The train came to a. standstill and out came the old lady, pulling and shoving half a dozen bundles and bandboxes after her. -I heard somebody who was looking out of the car window say, "Good riddance," and instantly concluded that the old lady had made herself felt among the passengers. She did not see me so quick as I did her, and after gazing up and down for a moment, she sat her luggage down upon the platform and began to hunt for me. She found tne very soon, and she made a break for me. I tried to avoid her but she covered too much ground and so scooped me in. "Lordy, massa, son-in-law, how de dew? I am so glad tew see you," she exclaimed, swinging her huge umbrella and div- ing for me. I extended my hand for a shake, but that did not satisfy her; did not give vent ti her great and overwhelming love. No, no. Throwing her asrms around my neck she proceeded to give me a hug that made every joint in me creak. Then she sought   mY MOTHER-IN-LAW.'.1*l THROWING HER ARMS AROUND MY NECK SHE PROCEEDED TO GIVE A HUG THAT MADE EVERY JOINT IN ME CREAK. my dewy lips, and in doing so nearly bit my nose off, and "gave me a kiss that woul have annihilated a large sunfish. , "My son, I am so glao to see you," she said between her hugs and smacks.                ' "Ye-yes-so be I," I gasped, a t the same time thinking what a poor show my muscle had with hers. "How is Harriet Ann? '       ' "Quite well." "Oh, my son, how glad I am to see you," she said again, and once more she made for me.                -  1 But I dodged and her huge arms came together with a sugm gestive thud. S.* a:  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7800-00000008"/> MY MOTaER-Im-LAW..  "You're not looking near so well as you was." "Oh, but I am feeling first-rate," I replied, bracing up with the intention of showing her that I was no kid. "Glad tew hear it, real glad. Come tew stay with you quite a while. Arn't you glad?" "Oh certainly." What a lie!  "Young people allers ought tew have an old hand around when they're first commencin'. But I'll set you agoing all right. Know all 'bout it." I groaned.  "But come, where's your kerrige?" she asked, looking around. SHE TURNED AWAY TO SEE THE STATION AGENT WHO WAS INSPECTING HER TRAPS, WHLE I WENT FOR A CHREW OF "MAYO FLOWER TO TAoE THE TASTE OF ER KIESX3  OUT OF MY TYOUTH.   "Haven't any. No carriages in town."           . "Wa], that's smart. What kind of a town is this, anyway?" " she asked, sharply.                   . "Oh pretty good I guess."   .. "Why don't you live in New York?" "Can't afford it." "Oh, pshaw! I've hearn you're rich." "Nothing of the kind I assure you." "Wal, I'm sorry. But how 'm I going tew get my things tew the house 8 Where d' you live?" "About a mile up this way," I replied. ' Goodness gracious!" "But I guess I can carry your things." She turned away to see the station agent who was inspect- ing her traps, while I went for a chew of "Mayflower " to tako the taste of her kisses out of my mouth. "rWal, come here," she called, turning to me. I walked leisurely to where she and her luggage stood. She gave me a sharp glance of iniuiry. Didn't appear to think I was very enthusiastic at her coming. "Now be careful," she said, pointing to a pile of her en. cased duddery. I stooped and begrn to load up. "Mighty queer that there arnt no kerriges in town," she muttered, as I was loading myself. "Are these all yours?"I asked. X "Why sartin. Don't call that much, I hope. Guess you don't know much 'bout traveling. Careful now!" "All right, ll do the beat I can." "I didn't exactly 'spect this. 'Taint exactly the way to re- ] ceive your mother-in-law, d' you know it 2"  1 made no reply and started towards home loaded down with bandboxes and bundles, while the old lady marehed          &#xD;<pb n="14 (Illustration) -15" xml:id="VAC7800-00000009"/> M! MOTHE&amp;IE:MAW. *   MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.        15-! along behind, armed with her huge blue cotton umbrella and a look which did not seem exactly angelic. She was evidently disappointed with me and the reception Tshe got, and the ground fairly shook as she put her big feet down upon the road. But wasn't I happy, though?  Not a word passed between us for some time. She was probably quite as busy with her thoughts as I was with mine. : How would it end? I gave it up.  While meditating over this conundrum a big dog that hap- pened to be passing along suddenly saw a smaller yellow one that he thought he could shake the stufing iout of, and evi- dently feeling that he wanted something of that kind, he set upon the poor cur and he ran between my legs as if seeking protection. Reader, did you ever get run into by a yellow dog Did you ever know a yellow dog that did not make trouble I had rather be run into by a locomotive. Then I know what is coming and what to expect. This yellow dog ran between my legs and tripped me up Yellow dogs always do that. I went to mother earth in a most demoralized style. Some of the bandboxes reached the ground first, and I was saved a broken head by striking it upon one of these bandboxes. But I went clear through it, I buried my mug in the mys- teries of that affair, completed the destruction of it while trying to extricate myself from its contents, while that yellow purp continued on and ran between my mother-in law's legs, and -over she went, wildly flourishing her umbrella and shouting. S' Scat!"Git out!" and making her teeth chatter as she came 4ownf.  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7800-00000010"/> MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. 1 WENT TO MOTHER EARTH IN A MOST DEMORATTZn STYE.. SOME OF THE BANDBOXES REACHED THE GROUND FIRST AND I WAS SAVED A BROKEN HEAD BY STRIKING UPON ONE QF THEM. Ithink a demoralized yellow dog would throw Homer Lane. Always get people down. My mother-in-law collected a crowd. Her voice would do. that anywhere. I extricated myself and attempted to assist her in rising. But she wouldn't have it. "Go 'way, you graceless scamp!" she cried, flourishing her umbrella over her head as she sat there on the ground. "Are you hurt?"I asked. "Hurt! you good-for-nothing scallawag you. See what, you have done to my best bandbox. "Itt. mv dear madam. T couldn't beln ;t. 1--"   MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.        1? 'Don't you dare tell me you couldn't help it. I see through you like a book. You are mad because I have come, and you, have smashed my things." "But the dog-" "Don't dog me!" she screamed, struggling to her feet. "Don't dare to dog me." a But I assure you-" "You do, eh?" she exclaimed, seizing me by the nose and' giving it a fearful twinge. Perhaps I can Phcenixize this by saying that I incautiously placed my proboscis too near her two digits which were at that moment contracting their grasp and that I held her there; with my nose until she cried enough.                     , t\      \ "YOU DON EH Ad SHE EXOCTATIVrnX, gSIltlNj B B Y THE NOSE AN GIVING IT A. FEAmIUL TWINGE.  &#xD;<pb n="18-19 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7800-00000011"/> 18         EMY MOTHER-IN-LAW. But I don't like to flower things. She had me by the nose. 'It was a moment of supreme anxiety. "How dare you treat me in this way?" she asked, trying- to twist the whole snoot off of me. "Madam, release your hold!"I cried. "I'll show you what is, what. I'll learn you to treat your mother-in-law in this way." At that moment some mischievous boys began to- have fun with the wrecked baggage. But she did not notice it, she had  her hands too full of the business before her. "Madam, I shall strike you if you do not release-my nose,". -said I. "You will, hey? I'd'like tew see you strike me, I would inn -deed," and she gave me a slap which nearly threw me to the ground. "Old woman, you are an old beast!" "And you, sir, a're a poltroon." "H-'7   - "Silence Pick up my things carefully and lead me to my- saceriflced daughter."  I felt just then as though I was the sacrificed individual, but I was not sure about anything. However, I gathered up her things and started on, resolved upon asserting- myself after. wards. Oh, wasn't I happy? But I resolved on a deep and swift revenge, I would teach -her to trifle with me thus. We finally arrived at my house, and mother and daughter flew to each other'sarms. I was willing, in fact, I wished they would get warm enough to melt together and be unable to get .apart. But, oh, wouldn't I assert myself? "My poor, dear child I " * c   &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7800-00000012"/> X20        -MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. "My dear, dear mother!" , hen they hugged and simpered and kissed. "Oh, my poor child, you have thrown yourself away I fear," said she; glancing at me. "Why so, mother " asked Harriet Ann. "Because your husband is a bad man." "And you are an old catamount, madam," I hissed. The old lady was holding my wife in her arms as she held her about weaning-time, and hugging her fondly. She started ,up as I spoke. "Do you hear that, Harriet Ann? Do you hear how your poor mother is being abused the first time she comes into the house?" "Oh, dear me, what is the matter " my wife asked, anx- iously. "Well, well, I guess he won't put on many more airs over me; I'll learn him his place," I overheard her say. "Madam! H" I approached her. "Shut up, sir." She approached me, but we didn't come to blows. "This is your angelic mother," I sneered, as I took my hat and started--towards the door. "But she will be wise if she neglects to rouse the lion in me." I glanced back as I was about to leave. The old lady had again returned to her daughter and once more taking her up on her enormous lap she was rocking p and fro, and both wer, indulging in " a real good cry." I drew my proud nose to one side in scorn and passed out of the house. The first battle had been fought and I was stir the boss of my own house. Things failed to work well th-atday. My bristles were up and I disdained chin" from anybody,   ANT MOTHER-IN-LAW.        21 I caught myself banging away at imaginary fat old women, ,veral times, and once while I was sending out my "awful right" for the purpose of giving that imaginary mother-in-law, one on her "bugle," my friend Carboy entered my sanctum unexpectedly and received it on his nose. He didn't like it a bit. "I'm sorry, old man, but the fact is, I was just showing myself how I shall 'paste' my mother-in-law if sle attempts to make any trouble in my house." "Well, I wish you would keep on showing yourself or showing her, and keep y,our fist off of my nose," said he, gath- ering up the gore in his pocket-handkerchief. / "Carboy, consider yourself an experimental sacrifice." He went away mad about something, How belligerent I was! I wrote blood-curdling editorials, 1 refused to take a drink when asked, and treated everybody uncivilly with whom I came in contact. The fact was, I had only begun to ponder seriously upon the indignity that had been offered me by my wife's mother, and the more I thought about it, the madder I became. Zounds! She had actually laid hands on my person! Had actually taken me by the nose because I tumbled over that dog and burst the crust of several of her bandboxes. Flesh and blood could not stand it; neither could gristle. And to think of it again, how did she dare to take my nose between her thumb and finger? I tried to think why I had not smitten her to the earth and then and there asserted myself! I finally concluded that her sex alone had saved her. But it would never save her again, that I felt sure of. My blood was up. She had roused the sleeping lion--let her take the consequences.  I grew hotter and hotter as I thought of it, and I longed for ^  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7800-00000013"/> 82 *  9    MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. the endof my day's work that I might-once more return to my' home and even more fully assert myself than I had done in the morning. When night came, I took a drink to steady my nerves. That is to say, I wasn't afraid of anything, but I don't believe ui going into battle with unsteady nerves. All great generals have contended against it. It did quiet me wonderfully, for by the time I got within a quartar of a mile of my house, I began to feel less inclined to figt. But not to be fooled with, oh no! "3 -'  C]DA. , YOU DON'T KNOW ME," I Y-FT T,n,'D THRUSTINI MY FP4C - CDSR INTO HER OWN, "YoU SPERAK oO IMPOSsrnr ITTES, MADMr    MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.        23 . If she behaved herself and did not molest me, I felt that I would exhibit enough of the Christian spirit to forgive her  for what she had done already. "But let her beware of the purring lion," I said as I opened the door and entered my Aomicil.  I summoned all my dignity and sternness as I entered the -sitting-room where I expected to find my enemy. But she was not there. My wife sat there alone. She did not look up as I entered, which was quite an uncommon thing. On the contrary, she always made it a  practice to encircle my willing neck with her fond, round arms, and ask me what I had brought her home that was nice. I at once suspected that her mother had been setting her  against me. "What is the matter?". I asked.   - She looked half-way at me with a half-way frown but  made no reply. Then my blood leaped again. "Madam, are you sick?"I again denanded, in a louder 'key. Well, perhaps not, although I might be happier than I am," she replied, with a little dash of bitterness.  "Yes, madam, and so might I be if the spirit of trouble had not entered my house."                  ' "I will not hear you abuse poor, dear mother in that  way, sir. She is a dear, good woman, and I wish you were as good." There it was! The cause flung right in my face. "Madam, you don't know the lion that is in me. Your mother must leave the house or I shall." \  She made no reply, as though she didn't care a fig wheth-  er I went or stayed. I felt myself grow a foot in my ain- dignation.   &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7800-00000014"/> -s-  ^      mzy D IOTHER-WN-LAW. o I SUCCEEDED IN KEEPING ON HER LAP AND HOLDING HER nTO * THE CHAIR, EVEN THOUGH SHE WAS RAINING BLOWS TPON TPE IXTREYMTY OF MY SPINE WITr[ HER SHOE. "Where is she?"I yelled. "In the kitchen." '  "Ah! I'll see whether I am to be traduced in my own house. I'll see who'll stay and who'll go," saying which I made a stride for the kitchen where in all likelihood the old' woman had already established herself as her headquarters, Mothers-in-law boss the kitchen. I  found her there as I expected, with her s eeves rolled up and putting things to rights. "Madam, either you or I must leave this house!" I hissed. She turned around and surveyed me from head to foot with. out making any reply. She was evidently afraid of me. "I  have always heard that a mother-in-law in a family is a source of trouble and blight, and I see thus early that you are , not an exception to the rule," I added.   MY MOTHElR-IN-LAW.        e-e "You behave yourself like a man andyou'll have no try -j le; but if you show me too often that my poor dear child threw herself awayi you may expect' to hear from me," said she, plao- ing her big arms alimbo and marching up in front of me. "Zounds, madam! This is my own house?" "Yes, mind your business and go in fand try to cheer up your poor neglected wife." "She needed no cheering until you eame." "What's that? Don't you give me any of your sass or I'll take you across my knee," she said, slapping her huge hands -together. "Madam, you don't know me," I yelled, thrusting my fice sclose into her own, "You speak of impossibilities, madam." "I do, hey? I'll show you." With this she attempted to seize me, but I warded off her hand and gave her a slap in the face. Then there was a strug- gle during which I succeeded in getting her into a chair and placing myself upon her lap, face downwards - and at right an- gles with her, and in that way holding her partially at bay. I don't pretend to say that I escaped unscathed. Science and right can not always succeed entirely against brute force. But I succeeded in keeping on her lap and holding her into the chair, even though she was raining blows upon the extremity of my spine with her shoe. She must have noticed how plucky I was in holding her in. to the chair and maintaining my place so earnestly. "There, have you got enough?" she asked, ceasing from her spanking for an instant. "Have you got enough, old woman? , If so, I'll allow you- to get up and go a-bout your business," said I. "Don't you sass me," she replied, again assaulting me. I soon saw that she a ore than a match for me in point  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7800-00000015"/> 92     6Y MOTHER-IN-LAW. "of brute force and felt that I could not conquer her save by the exercise of my superior strategy. Have you got enough?" she asked again. "I'm satisfied if you are"I replied, bound not to admit that I was not fighting.  "' And will you behave yourself?" "Release me, woman.!" "Will you promise not to sass me again?" "Yes. I'll promise not to take advantage of my victory." "Well, let's see if you will," she said, allowing me to regain my feet, while I did the same for' her. "But if I ever hear any more of your sass I'll spank you harder than I have this time."  "UltE, I HAVE MADE YOU UP A COUPLE OF NICE SANDWICHES, mOSE OF THEM OF HAM AND THE OTHER CORNED BEEF, AND IT'S ATLL WUr NEED. I'LL PLACE THEM RIGHT HERE IN YOUR COAT POCKET.2' SHE ADDED, DIVING INTO THE DEPTHS OF MY COAT TAIL.   *         r a* ,    MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.        27 "Madam, I refuse to hold any further conversation with you," said I, leaving the room.               as My mother-in-law was boss of the roost. Superior brute strength had done it and I was forced to hold my tongue when in the house.  But the mighty were not yet fallen. What I lacked in muscle I made up in brains and cunning, and while nursing  my wrath to keep it warm I concentrated my genius upon a  plan o operations against her.  For a week we never exchanged words. But the old wo-   .l man kept right along about her business, getting things to rights and revolutionizing the entire interior workings of our household. In the matter of economy she was heavy. She said we could reduce our family expenses one half, and she would show us how to do it.                 '  The old gal might be a sort of a hard-times angel, after all,  I thougt, but I felt sure that I should never learn to tolerate her, even if she taught us how to live for nothing. I was still determined to be rid of her.      , I-was putting on my hat and coat one morning for the spur. pose of going to town to business when she approached me with something done up in a napkin.  "You spend altogether too much money for your luncheons.  You have a good breakfast, and supper and not having any. thing to do, you don't need much of anything for your lunch." "Oh, ah, indeed. Who told you so?"I asked. "I know what you men are. You'll spend a'dollar or two, for a dinner and never think how quick that money you squan- i . der foolishy would buy your wife a new silk dress. Economy is wealth, and I want to see you get rich." "Doubtless."  a Here I have made you up a couple of nice sandwiches, one ,             &#xD;<pb n="28 (Illustration) -29" xml:id="VAC7800-00000016"/> M'Y 3O1THR-IN-LAW.-   MY MOTHER-IN-LAW         29 - of them of ham and the other corned beef, and it's all you needc I'll place them right here in your coat pocket," she added, div. ing into the depths of my coat tail. "But : don't love sandwiches." All right I'll risk you.' You won't starve so long as you have such a lunch as that in your pocket. If you loved your- wife or your mother-in-law you'd love cold lunches and save your money."- "Oh, I do love my mother-in-law intensely," I replied, bit- terly, while drawing on my glove. "I can't help whether you love me or not, but don't let me , hear yer giving me any of yer sass, or I'll-" -^  "Old woman, if you ever lay hands on me ain I'll shoot, you in cold blood," said I, savagely interrupti'gher. , "Stop yer talking back in that way or I'll take you over my knee again." I shot one of my terrible glances at her, but I had no time then. to enter into another wrangle-I should miss the train, so I1 strode majestically from her presence. 'here were deep and dark -plots working under my hat as I journeyed towards the scene of my daily toil. How grand nd complete should be my great revenge at last!  When a man is thinking of his mother-in-law, he is apt to, forget most anything else. It was so with me on this occa- s ion. So completely did she fill my thoughts that I forgot the lunch of sandwiches which she had placed in my coat-taill pocket, and might not have remembered it even when I got hungry, had I not been reminded of it by a pack of' half-starved dogs who were following closely behind me. At first I did not know what the curs saw in- me that-- attracted their attention. I never fancied dogs much anyhow, /  but this crowd evidently took uncommon interest in me.."  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7800-00000017"/> 30.        MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.          1 There were all kinds, degrees and bredds, but they all ap. peared to be nobody's dogs, and all very hungry. At length one more bold or more hungry than the rest, made a snap at my coat tail 'and I understood what the trouble was right away. I certainly might have passed for more of a philosopher if I had only thrown them the coveted lunch and thus got rid of both them and it, but I did nothing of the kind, I simply skipped, and the dogs simply ambled along after me at an easy gait, creating much excitement on the street as well as for me personally. "Hey, Bob," I heard on'e gamin shout, "Seethe cove as is a gadderin' up dogs for. a sassage mill. Hey!" "Twig his. nibs!" "Stop thief!" and various other complimentary remarks were passed upon me as I sped along. But I soon gained-the ferry and escaped from my pursuers, greatly to my delight you may well believe. Confound dogs, confound sandwiches; confound mothers-in-law. On board the fer-y boat I found myself in a crowd, and in trying to obtain standing room I forgot all about my trouble for the time being. I was crowded up in front of 'a very pretty girl, and you know how quickly one forgets home troubles under such circumstances. I suppose good looking young ladies travel on purpose to make poor afflicted men forget themselves. And they gener. ally succeed in making them do it. I feel certain that I should never have stood up under my afflictions had it not been for the pretty faces that smiled on me while going and returning to my abode. Well, I forgot all about 'my mother-in-law's lunch, and went to the restaurant as usual when I got hungry and was again made happy for less than a dollar. i           '    MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.         3X Man wants but little here below, But wants that little strong. As night approached I again wended my weary way homeward, or, rather, to the little kingdom where my mother-  in-law ruled. With my mind completely engrossed with the great ques- tions of the day, and watching which way a fascinating widow was going, I left the boat and started for the cars which were to take me within a few rods of my house. But those confounded dogs somehow got scent of me agai  and followed me to the cars. Of course I was safe then, al- 'N ADAM"SAM I, "THS IS ALL- YOUR WORK, YO-U PLACED TlA ONOND5ED LUNCH IN By COAT POCKET AND THESE DOGS HAVB BEEN FOLLOWXG      W     OD AN DAT, AD O ONTNT 00 T1  GETTING IT, T0    WIFM BY aOAT TABUSY T"Y HAVEN FO I LOWED MEH OME n zo-WAI't MYe flOAT TAiS Ti  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7800-00000018"/> 2 MY OTHER-IN-LAW. though I was not aware of it any more than I was aware of their hang-dog presence. They had evidently made up their minds to have that savory lunch, and so they followed that car until I got out. I had gone hardly a dozen rods before they made a bold and determined attack upon. me. "I fought them off on one side and they came on the other; but, to curtail my story, they succeeded in tearing the, skirts of my coat entirely off, and in getting away with that lunch. The curs curtailed me. But they succeeded in doing so, only because they could run faster than I could. Even the securing of the sandwiches failed to satisfy them and they kept up the chase, as if anxious to see if the sandwiches were a sample of myself. iatt         "        l M!  S A?P I G YS M A TL S iA TEMBDBP     ,A   EYALMD   OHR ' SICK r}l:!I YTnTTI) SLAPPING MY HANDS SMARTLY. ToI TD HE 'DSIRBID EBFPFECT, AND THEY ALL MADE FOR HER.   MY MOTHER-IN -LAW.        33 They followed me to my house, into my house, and into the presence of my queen of torments, my mother-in-law. But she wasn't frightened. She looked at me, at the pack of hungry dogs, and asked if I was going to take them to the pound to get the bounties. "Madam," said I, " this is all your work, you placed that confounded lunch in my coat pocket and these dogs have been oAllowing me around all day, and not content with getting it, together with my coat tails, they have followed me home." "Stuff and nonsense. It is only a weak invention of yours to dissuade me from my revolution in behalf of economy. But it will not succeed, sir," she said, stamping her big flat foot. "Harriet Ann shall have a new silk dress from what can be saved from your extravagant lunches. So, sir, drive off your miserable dogs, and remember who you are dealing with. "I can't drive them off," said I, shrugging my shoulders. ' I can, then. Git out!" and she made a dive for them. The dogs had evidently been waiting for some one to com. mence business, and when she attempted to kick one of them the cur grabbed her by the leg and began to pick the bone. She yelled and so did the dogs. I saw a chance for revenge and encouraged them on. "Sick em!"I yelled slapping my hands smartly. This had the desired effect and they all made -for her. -She fought for a moment and then turned and fled. Oh, it was such fun--for me and the dogs. I felt sure that they would kill her, and as my Wife was away on a visit, there was no witness at hand. I was about to be revenged! What a funeral I would give her. I laughed until I fell on the floor in a paroxysm of delight. I rolled in exuberant satisfaction. I tried to make an exclama. tion mark of myself by standing on my head, and for five rin-  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7800-00000019"/> YA MOTHER-/IN-LAW. BUT WHLE IN THE MDST OF IT, WHLE TOTTERING ON THE TO WAVE OF MY SUPPOSED FELICITY, I GLANCED UP AND BEHELD I MOTHER-IN-LAW LOOKING IN! UPON ME I! utes I gave myself up to the wildest demonstrations of entire satisfaction. But while in the midst of it, while actually tottering on the top wave of my supposed felicity, I glanced up and beheld my mother-in-law looking in upon me! Here was a dramatic situation. Not a word was spoken by either of us during the tableau.. I could feel the change in the expression which came over my face. I slowly gathered myself up and she slowly entered the room, all the while regarding me with much the same look that a cat wears when satisfied that her prey cannot escape. But I was not afraid. If worst came to worst; if she at. tempted to use personal violence towards me, I would again TE-N  LB  ORN  I!UO   Z   MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. .3 HEOWEVEI, I MET MHR GAZE WITH A LOOK OF CALM INQUIRY, AND WHEN SHE GOT TO WITHN ABOUT TWO FEET -O ME SHE SUDDENLY DREW HER FIST AWAY FROM MY NOSE, AND I SAT DOWN -ON THE FLOOR. throw her into a chair and place myself at right angles with her person and hold her down. She approached me, still without speaking a word. The lightning in her body was well pent up and sent out no warning thunder. But I judged from her looks that she was  mad about something. However, I met her gaze with a look of calm inquiry, and when she got to within about two feet of me she suddenly drew her fist away from nose, and I sat down on the floor. But I should not have sat upon the floor if that had not been the nearest thing at hand to sit on. Had there been no ob- struction I might have sat down a rod or two away. Of course I felt hurt at her conduct, but she didn't appear to care. She stood ove I me with her arms akirbo, still re. o cr W-  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7800-00000020"/> 36        MY MOTER-IN-LAW. garding me in silence. So of course I could say nothing, I wasn't going to open the battle by asking her what she meant by her conduct. But she soon found use for her tongue. "You are a nice man, arn't ychi? You sicked the dogs on me, didn't you?" Of course. What was the use of getting into an argument over a thing that was self evident? So I made no reply at alL If she had only mentioned some subject about which there was a question, then I might have joined her in the debate. But this is one of the mean ways about my mother-in-law. She always wants things her own way. "And- you were dancing, and laughing, and rolling your- self on the floor like a tickled hog, hoping I should be eaten up by your pack of hungry curs, wasn't you? But I wasn't, was I?" she said, again introducing a question which had only one side to it. "I am sorry they did not eat you up," I said. "You are, are you, you villain," she exclaimed, rushing upon me and raising her huge foot over my head as though about to crush me. I thought somebody had opened an old-fashioned umbrella over me, I got out from under it right away. It was quite evident that she didn't dare to step on me. She knew that that would be going a step too far, and that there was danger of rousing the lion within me. "You mean, despicable creature, you deserve more than the bloody nose I have given you." "Oh, that's all you can do; call names," I said, spitefully. "Oh, it is is it! Come with me," she exclaimed, seiz- ing me by the ear. She asked me to go along with her. and was strongly inclined to take my ear whether I went or not. So what 6   MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.        37 was I to do? But I wish it distinctly understood that I wouldn't have gone simply because she said so. I was too independent for that-I went to keep company with my ear, for fear it might be lonesome. "Come along, you  lily-livered apology, I'll-learn you what it is to set dogs on your wife's mother." "Be careful how you talk to me, madam, for it would not take much more to rouse the lion in me," said I, walking a trifle faster in order to keep up with and show that I was not afraid of her in the least. "Lion! Jackass more like," she sneered. "Ah, but even they have fangs behind. Be carefil, madam." "I'll be careful that you get what you deserve" she said, opening the door of the kitchen. X\                           I MY VIOLE E    THE PAST FW N   S    MY VIOLENT EXERCISE FOR THE PAST FEW M1NUTiIS HAD GIVEN ME A BAD HEADACHE, AND SHE EVIDENTLY KNEW IT AND WAS ONLY BENT ON CURING IT.  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7800-00000021"/> 38        MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. Of course I followed her in. I wanted to show her that I was not afraid of her, and that I could go just as fast as she did, even if she was leaning on my ear for support. In the center of the kitchen floor stood a tub half full of water. She walked towards it. The idea suddenly oc- curred to me to give the old she-devil a ducking in it. It would only be serving her right. She still retained her hold upon my ear, evidently being afraid to let go. The time for action had arrived. Sum- moning all my strength I seized her by the neck and we struggled over that tub. She appeared to be afraid of fall- ing or being thrown, so she seized me by the hair of my head.  But the struggle was of short duration. I suddenly re- membered that when I had complained of having a head. ache she always told me that holding it under water was a sure cure. My violent exercise for the past few minutes had given me a bad headache and she evidently knew it and was only bent on curing it. So I made no further re-. sistance and allowed her to have her own way. I told her afterwards that she had no occasion to be so rough; that if she had only said that she wished to ex- periment upon my headache, I would have allowed her to do so. But the way she went to work about it, made it seem as though she was forcing me to try her cure. And the words she used after holding my head under the. water until I was nearly drowned were very rough and un- called for. "There, you good-for-notaing gander; you sorrel-headed monkey, now see if you will ever set dogs on me again." The language was entirely uncalled for. She was connect- ing it with another affair altogether than my headache. But what can you expect from a mother-in-law, anyway! She ev.   I MY MOTil--LA           39 a m,' 1. 1 I VISITED THE CTHAIWnER OF THAT DEAR OLD LADY AND FOUND HER IN HER BED, GROANING WIT SOME KIND OF COLIC. idently wished to- convey the idea to me that she had forced my head into that tub of water. But I humored her for the sake of peace. There was a coldness between us for some days after that, in fact we did not speak at all. But one morning soon after- wards Harriet Ann informed me that her poor dear mother was sick, and unable to get up. I had not yet risen, but this an- aouncement nerved me. I visited: the chamber of that dear old lady and found her in bed, groaning with some kind of eolic. She seemed very low and wanted me to go right away to town for a doctor and I promised her I would. So after break- fast I set out, but I believe that this was the only time in my ife that I wished I lived ten miles from a doctor and was lama,  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7800-00000022"/> 40         MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. I BOUGHT A CIGAR TO ASSIST MY MEDITATIONS Perhaps the old angel was about to be removed from her hearth. stone! Perhaps I was on the point of losing my mother-in-law! Perhaps if I did not hurry I should be too late! I bought a cigar to assist my meditations. It was while meditating upon such a great mishap that I passed a newspaper office and beheld a startling bulletin giving forth facts something like these: "Horrible Triagedy!"A mat kille his mother-in-law!" The jury acquit him "!"All about it!" Here was news of a very interesting nature surely. There was something about it that fascinated, charmed me. A lad   MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.         41 C31j  i I7 "BI ! .I, Dri+e I 131 XT WAS WHLE MEDITATING UPON SUCH A MTSF[AP THAT I PASSED A NEWSPAPER OFFICE AND TREFfElD A STARTLING BULLETIN. thrust a paper under my nose and I bought it at once I re- solved to learn all about the affair without further loss of time.  So I went to a, saloon near by and ordered a drink. Tak- ing a seat at one of the tables I proceeded to 'brace up and read the account of that tragedy. But it wasn't so sensational after all. It was all about a man whose mother-in-law made his home so hot that he could not endure it, and he had set a trap or an infernal machine for her, in the shape of a bottle of !:4IP"    t   '" /f-%.  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7800-00000023"/> W0         JE M OTER.-IN-LAW. Oo I WENT TO A SALOON NEAR BY AM) ORDERED A DRNt ; TA3TWG A SEAT AT ONE OF THE TABLES, I PROCEEDED TO BRAOD UP AND READ THE ACCOUNT OF THAT TRAGEDY. gin, for which it appeared she had a weakness, and by some explosive mixture placed in it he had blown her to kingdom come. And he had been acquitted by a jury of married men. The thing pleased me and I ordered another drink. Thea I meditated. Should my mother-in-law survive this attack could I not make a two hundred and forty pound angel of her in the same way? I placed my feet upon the table and folding my arms I was soon lost in the realms of imagination. From there I was swept into the open arms of Morpheus, and I dreamed-dreamed all kinds of dreams about murder, hanging, explosive bottles, and I know not what all, when I was suddenly and rudely awakc .   MY MOTHER-IN-IAW.        4 7 /I / I PLACED MY FEET UPON THE TABLE, AND FOLDING Y ARMS I WAS SOON LOST IN THE REATLMS OF IMAGINATION. FROM TTFRliP, I WAS SWEPT INTO THE OPEN ARMS OF MORPH' US. ened by falling over backwards and giving myself a tremen- dous bang upon the floor. - Where was I  I couldn't seem to get my bearings at all. I sat there upon the floor and tried to collect my thoughts. What had happened and what time of day was it a -I glanced up at the clock and found it was nearly noon. What' had taken me to this place? Then I saw the paper and remem- bered having come into the saloon to read it. Then the fact of my having started off after a doctor for my dear, sick mother-in-law came to my mind. How could 1 have been so careless as to have forgotten that important matter? I would attend to it at once. So I paid for my re-                F  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7800-00000024"/> "        AL MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. I " I WAS SUDDENLY AND RUDELY AWAKENED BY FATITNG OVER BACKWARDS AND GIVING MYSELF A TREMENDOUS BANG UPON THE FLOOR. freshment, explained the Beecher-Tilton case fully to the bar- keeper, and then set out for the residence of the doctor. I chanced to find him in and in the course of half an hour we started on foot for my house. -I should not have accom. panied him back, but I thought perhaps I might have to at- tend to the arrangements for the funeral, and so I concluded to forego the pleasure of regular business that day and pay strict attention to home matters. I was always a domestic man. I pass rapidly over a space of time at this point, for the good and sufficient reason that I do not distinctly remember all that occurred during the next few days. I remember thaft   MY MOTRFt-IN-LAW.    ,         I X. g I /z/ I SAT -TlE RV UPON THE FLOOR AND TRIED TO COLLECT MY lTOUGHTS. WHAT HAD HAPPENED, AND WHAT TIME OF DAY WAS IT  my mother-in-law did not die. I remember that she must have recovered rapidly after I left her in the morning, and also that she met us while on our way to the house, and that she had some words with me, etc.  The probability is that there was a severe personal encoun- ter between us. At all events I came to my senses some time afterwards and found myself in bed with a sad and bandaged  eye, together with other black and blue spots on different parts of my person; which led me to believe that I had either been fooling with a mule or that my-mother-in-law and I had had another personal understanding. Perhaps I had killed her. Was I in prison No, I was in my own chamber and everything looked natural with the  exception of myself. Where was she, I asked myself. Harriet Ann came in soon after, with a dish of gruel in her hand and tears in her eyes and on the end of her nose. She smiled sadly when she saw me, and informed me that I had been unconscious for three days.  I asked her what had happened me, and with tears starting  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7800-00000025"/> -- "'^a T:^'^ we'Ima'^  I2 ^ ^  'i^ ?^  ..   Ii e She inro A.,L ']Ir!edMe'WRDS-VTuI  WA- Cause Ihad s  Paaeo   ITaC. Oler othe i- su/t )she had go t e for a &amp;oe0o aod  ted out aee 'me t gone up, dressed herself" 8ecarried a broo .    rs'sid It 'Was her aoreWepnoSureoeain. Bue w  ea Yere Imber that. Were sshe' I asked . Did Ior down stairs., Di urt her m uch,?,- have not her he eard her . Pmenti] ntn  bu ',V that Woman ,),etln aYhna howI could youI be so eunindt e akdm 4c2,s  ul  ]d  O-hr -iY   "What!  The old r hinoceros, I could kill her "Oh, oh!', was my wife's tearful her face in the bedclothing.   resPonse as ohe buried "Go down Stairs and tell her to leave my house I; I never wish to look up  o her face aga in di "Tell her tha lio you hink T besr for her to go before sh *oasersthe/ioni  me.  Tell her ha I iotsandanm  o   &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7800-00000026"/> 48        OMY MOTHER-IN-LAW. of her attempts at coercing me, and beg her for your sake to go. HarTiet Ann went sobbing from the room. I waited to hear the result. I did not hear what my wife said, but I heard the old woman's reply very distinctly. "You tell him," said she, "that if I hear any more nonsense out of his head, that I will give him more than he has bar- gained for." Just as though I was not then having more than I had bar- gained for! That settled it. That sealed her doom. She actually de- fied me, defied me in my own house. Then I began to ponder over the situation. It was evi- dent that she cared nothing at allfor the many bodily chastise- ments I had given her. She seemed to be able to endure any amount of physical pain, and the only way to effectually rid myself of her, was to make her a subject for the coroner at one fell swoop. But'how should I do it, how bring about a consummation so devoutly wished for? I pondered on the subject long and- earnestly, I could hear her sharp voice every now and then coming up from below stairs if I needed any prick to the sides. of my intent, and I resolved. I had lately discovered that the old lady was partial to a. drop of whiskey now and then, and I made up my mind to see the man who had exploded his mother-in-law by some- concoction, and learn from him the secret, after which I would. proceed to put it in practice. The next day I was able to be out and attend to business If- people asked what ailed my eye, I told them I raan against a door in the dark. But I was soon myself again and my mother-in-law seemed to fear the result of her wrong-doing and kept pretty well out-   MY xOTM-nEg-IN-LAW.  i A 1e WE SAT DOWN TOGETHER IN THE SITTIm  BOOM, HARNESSED:  OURSELVES TO OUR PIPES MND tE TOLD E FUNNY STORIES FOR. I HOUl'0on 0o, MUI ANG ME SO HAPPY THAT I FORGOT M MSERY,. of my sight. The cunning old wretch! She knew that it . would be unsafe for her to face me until my wrath had had time to cool. One day during my convalescence old Bob Jolly called. on me. Bob is one of the best in the world; loves his pipe and his punch; loves his bachelor freedom, and nothing doeshi old heart more good than to cheer a fellow mortal. We, sat down together in the sitting room, harnessed ourselves to our  pipes, and he told me funny stories for an hour or so, making me so happy that I forgot my misery. Then he told me about his club, the "Night-Key Club," and what jolly times they had'together; howtheyenjoyedfreedom and despised mothers-in-law. I was fascinated with it, and at and           . e p'  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7800-00000027"/> )   t   bY I6MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. =.J-:.                  I BUT THE ARCH ENEMY OF MY LIFE AND HAPPINESS HAD HER "U TO THE KEYHOLE AND OVERHEARD EVERYTHNG THAT HAD BEN SAID, ALTHOUGH I WAS AT THE TIME UNAWARE OF IT, OR I [OULD HAVE CHASTISED HER FOR SUCH IMPUDENCE. s solicitation, I promised to join it, to make a bold stride wards domestic liberty and nerve myself against that night. are of my existence, my wife's mother. There was to be a meeting that very night and I agreed to in him at a certain place and go with him to the club room. it the arch enemy of my life and happiness had her ear to e keyhole and overheard everything that had been said, though I was at the timn unaware of it, or I should have astised her for such impudence. r  L   Y MO i'RU -i-LW.         51.  II SHE OPENED THE DOOR AND DIRECTED ME W .iUWOE TO FIND TH . "EQUIRED PRESERVE CANS.                      Bob took his leave and I felt in a much better mood, at.1 Wo, apparently, did my mother-in-law. She spoke very kindly A so me several times and wore a smile which took me in very-  nuch, for I supposed she was anxious to make friends with  ne and bury the hatchet.     ,  Of course I know what is due from a man to a woman, and'  : ;herefore I assumed to reciprocate her good feelings and to . Side my hatred under the sickly mask of a smile. 'I worked a little in the garden and was trying to kill the , . time intervening before my appointed meeting for the club. While thus engaged, she called meand in a sweet voice asked f I would not go into the dark store-room for her and reach  lown a box of preserve cans which stood on the upper shelf: i: -uch, -or           X -,-,e hews xiui4  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7800-00000028"/> M2Y X OTHER-IN-LAW. I hesitated a moment, but finally went; I thought there was no use in kicking up another row with her, for since corporal  punishment failed to reform her, I concluded that the easiest way was the best for the present. She followed me up stairs. This store-room was a sort of safe deposit, a room with a strong, burglar proof lock on the door, wherein we could deposit valuables which were not used every day. She opened the door and directed. me where to find the re. quired preserve cans. "I'm going to put up some preserves," said she. But I made no particular reply. I wasn't going to sa r her that I felt entirely satisfied with her conduct. ,V!1l       1 /jlji   / i ( i -A. :'t WILL I? YOU WMLL JOIN THE NIGHET-KEY CLUBS WILL THrUS RUN OFF WIT1 A PARCEL OF MEN, WILL YOU? A") CAROUE WHLE YOUR POOR NE(fLECTED WIFE PIES AT HOEI WE'LL SEE ABOUT T1AT.-  89   XY IIOTHEB-IN-LAW.        63 . I pulled out a barrel, got on the top of it, in order that I might reach the shelf in question, when I suddenly found my-.  self in darkness and heard the strong lock click and the key ' removed. She had shut me in!                 I "Hullo!"I yelled, "what are you doing?"  Putting up preserves," I heard her say. "You old wretch, unlock that door."            X "Ha, ha! Will I  You will join the Night-Key Club,' - will you? Run off with a parcel of men, willyou? and carouse! while your poor neglected wife pines at home? We'll see about that."                          M Then I heard her heavy step retreating towards down     stairs and became fully convinced that I had been hopelessly i: trapped.              -  Was ever man so foully dealt with; was ever man so     i cursed by a mother-in-law?. I tried the door, but it was no use. It was too strong and I knew I was securely fastened in. Only think of it! -It was - nearly time for me to meet my friend Bob. What would he say? I know what I said; I cussed in square English. The old catamount had overheard our little arrangement and had taken this method to circumvent it! But wouldn't  i . I carve me out a terrible revenge? I called on several of the ! gods to witness that I would, Why had I neglected my dia-  bolical scheme to blow her into kingdom come? It served  'f me right. I should have been more watchful.         , I cussed and ruminated, ruminated and cussed for at least . ! half an hour, but it did no good. There I was in the dark, a prisoner. I found myself wondering whether a jury would hold me blameless if I should blow her head off with a double-l  barreled shot-gun.                      i I In moving around my hand came upon a bottle. I pulled  :  the cork and smelled of the contents. It w as w/it  . pa s w   " ;:  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7800-00000029"/> M- M MOTHEI:-IN-LAY' N MOVING AROUND MY IAND CA  UPON A BOTTLE. I PULLED THE OOE AND SMTTFT) OF THE CONTENTS. IT WA -9, VKX^Y. X BAMPLElD IT. Here wis a nepenthe. I remembered that I had placed it there a long time ago and had forgotten it. I sampled it. I shook the bottle and sampled it again. I found two other bottles and sampled them. I thought of that wondrous line, " Heaven tempers the wind to the shorn lamb." I was that shorn lamb if there ever could be one. I re. :solved to make amends for my shearing, Ind continued to sample from first one bottle and then another. I voted it a triumph over the situation. I soon regarded the "Night-Key Club," as only second fiddle to my elevation. Time flew and i cared not. V My revenge was is the future, my happiness A-nd the bright drea:rus which came over me as I sat there   ;"H f7S TAT, OL E fA X I ASKET, SHOVING TH EO O On  OF THE BOTTLES UDER HER NOSE.  upon the floor of that dark room! They were seraphic almost.  I forgot that I had a mother-in-law, forgot where I was. I took several drinks, but took no note of time. Mine w:as  strictly a cash business.                   I Presently I heard the key inserted in the lock. But I dn't  care. - I was in just the humor to triumph over her petty mas  lignity. I could even forgive her for the time being. She opened the door and looked in. If I had only thought  M of it sooner I would have made her believe that I was dead, L   fbeen suffocated in that close room.. But, I felt on too high a.. . ' e           '          .        : X  Are you there?" she asked  - YO, Ut  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7800-00000030"/> 5;6        MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. "Bet on it, ole gal, bet I'm here," I said, struggling to my feet and staggering out. "And what is the matter with you now?" I was armed with bottles. "How's yat, ole gal?"I asked, shoving the neck of one of the bottles under her nose. "You good-for-nothing wretch! If you haven't gone and get drunk. If I'd only a know'd that whiskey'd been there." "You'd drank it yourself, hey?-hic! Betyerwould." ;' How dare you, sir. I never touch such stuff." "Then your breath lies like a hauctioneer, that's all-hic! "Give me those bottles!" "Nomuch. Take a drink.' "Give me that bottle." "Nomuch. I'm boss here." "You are, hey? We'll see."  - So I SH:I'AI) HER AND BEGAN TO PUT HER THROUGH AND AROUTD.   MY MOTHER-IN-LAW.        67    I !-0 i, I "KE TILTON, I SIMPLY RECALL THE PICTUREE AND IT WAS AS IF I WAS THE UNDERMOST DOG IN THE FIGHT,. AND SHE WAS SEATED UPON MY PROSTRATE FORM, BANGING MY NOSE UPON THE FLOOR, AND AT INTERVALS FONDLINGr W'iT' MY SPARSE AUBURN LOCKS AS  THbUGH ANXIOUS TO GET ENOUGH OF THEM TO ]MAKE A RAG CAR-  -PET. But I never stopped to see. I wanted to whirl the old wo-  man in the mazy, to bounce her through the intricacies of a  polka or something of that sort. So I seized her and began  to put her through and around. She yelled like a stuck pig . for a minute, but I kept her moving. Oh it was such fun!  I That is to say, it was fun while it lasted. But somehow it didn't last long. She broke away and gave me a whack which sent me to grass. I recall the sensation at this late -day, and I remember that I wjs not sure whether a mule was  practicing upon me or whether. I was being put through a threshing machine,  -..      ;  at:. : '!, *                 "' :   &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7800-00000031"/> g8         pMY MOTHEBR-IN-LAW. Like Tilton, I simply recall the picture, and it was as if I was the undermost dog in the fight, and she was seated upon Iny prostrate form, banging my nose upon the floor and at inter- vals fondling with my sparse auburn locks as though anxious to get enough of them to make a rag carpet. Since then I have taken no stock in Dutch courage. Since then I have bought no more whiskey for emergencies. I came then to the conclusion that the brain must be fed in order to compete with muscle. She had the advantage of me in brute force; I must brace up on my brain power in order to hold her in check. From that moment I commenced to study stratagem. I tried to find the man who had blown his mother-in-law into a full blown angel, but failing in this I commenced to study up- on explosives myself. I -became convinced that she loved a drop of the ardent herself, and on that ground I worked. I visited the Astor Library, and every other library that would afford me any information on the subject. From that - moment I resolved to scatter her mortal remains to the four, winds of the earth. - At last she had succeeded in rousing the lion within me. Ha! ha! Book after book, tome after tome I waded through, with all the devotion of an alchemist in search of the transmuting secret. Finally I found it. Ha! ha! The subtle agent of my wrath was discovered! My mind was -now made up, and no compunctious visit- ings of nature should shake my fell purpose, or keep pace be- tween the effect and it I had already learned my mother-in-law's weakness for gin, and other nervines, but especially gin, and on that hint I resolved to work. For the next few days I was all smiles and   MY ]mOTHER-YDN-LA-.        i . -'UJING SEOCluET. ^ - in all wys omae her beievcee that I had not only surren- i But during all thistime the demon of diabolismwas at Work within me. I bough tw o botleo hgiahern thatnI o tended - to surpris e her witeh it as earnest of m y good isnentions, a r! I told her not to say a word to heora   ,aoe I knew if he promia me faithfully that she ld lea 0  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7800-00000032"/> 60          MOTHEU-IN-Lz W. 'Xi' IN THE MEANTIE I WAS MIrNG THE INGREDIENTS OF MY HePaf NAL MACUINE, WORKING WHEN XW  I COULD GET A CHANCE, AND WEEN THE BOTTLE WAS'PFULLY CHARGED I SEAT LD, IT 'UP JUST AS IT WAS BEFORE. not, that the old 'lady would hear of my intended kindness right away. In the meantime I,was mixing the ingredients of my infer- nal machine, working whenever I could get a- chance, and when the bottle was fully charged I sealed it up just as it was, before. The explosion was arranged to take place when the cork was pulled. I watched a favorable opportunity and secreted the bottle in her wash stand. The uncharged one I kept in my study to drink from whenever I felt the shadow of my perspective joy coming over me. Gin is a good thing to take before going to the undeitaker's, or when you feel that the c9,roner should be Ftmmoned.   mY MOTHER-IN-LALW.              .' My meth r-in-law, as I suspected, appeared to  o that  was bent on giving her some token of my esteem, and she to her room to see if the hen had laid. A length she went up after I ha&amp; secreted the bottle in her washstand. She visite the place ancdiscovered. d. Ilistened. Iheard hersay, a she held the bottleup," He is not a bad fellow, after all. How good and cielicate of-him to place this ' Old Tom,' where I could findit, Iwonae where I cn find a corkscrew                    \ . "                                .. w,&amp;Tow- IFAr. VOPAlYF OPP SaHm  I HErE ugWAz sTY. , /  ,                           ,  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7800-00000033"/> L JULV'X'LE  , r A HERD-    ,     n    m OF A , TTO &amp;4D I LLOW) AIIIxu ALL. ttOW aO0 kmLtE O. '   'Z M My hrt was fluttering li a galvano mete. Hear dhe go down btairs for a corkscrew, and knowin she would fi ne there, f took a private one from my p ckle and iser i into the cork of my own bottle. Whenheardthe e- )loslon I rolved to pull it out and drink t( the repose of her piritual pa s and the gathering tdgelher oi her corporal. I becams exceedingly nervous while waiting; I did not ear her return to her room, although I aferwards learned mt she dicl a, nc drank deeplyy to my health I have to deal ith more emotional events for a few moments. While waiing for her return, as I supposed, I felt the ed of a %fimulant. I proceeded to draw the cork f'om ,my, 1t0le for the purpo  of taking a dnk I remembr a "PPPOLofanfidrink. I remember a maneb   I '   MYOTHER-IN-LA.              -  I 'Was BLOWN UP AND SHE ENJOYED  M GIN IX At  I T. tion similar to the explosion of a steam boiler. The fortnight that followed is a blank. I am convinced that there is a "Providence that shapes on ir ends, rough hew them as we may," or something to this effect. It now appears that I made a mistake and gave her my bottle and reserved the charged one for myself. I was blown up and she enjoyed her gin in security. I remember, as I began to come to myself under the doe  tor's care, that I concluded heaven smiled on mothers-in-law, and that it was no use for me to work against them. There; was only one refuge left for me, -and that- was suicide. I could get rid of her by leaving the world, and that seemed to be my naly method of escape. I- I raaed om ihi for a long time, and when I was wen     i A * ': : t '  * -         . A, S X,! ^  &#xD;<pb n="64-65 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7800-00000034"/> -a.                  \ MXY XO":i-.N LAW [PpROCEEDED O DRAW TE COR  PROM   OTTL  OtT TH-0 COK JXlilyOTTL, FO!jTHTI VUrIOSE OF TAKING A DRINI. I REXIEXBEA R A SENSATION  Srl-r,AR TO THE EXPLOSION OF A- STOW  BOILER. THE FORTNIGET THAT FOLLOWE D IS A  BLANK.      ' enough to get out and to attend to business again. I was very sober and thoughtful Fate was against me and Hhad better submit. One day Deacon Coldslaw called on me. He was a-man I hated above all other men in the world. He was a hypocrite. If I  could consign both he and my notherinulaw to eternal torment I  would gladly have done it. The old wretch pretended that he wanted to inquire after MdtaM afterS ^yS^^^",^^^   MY MOTHER-IN-L3AWo        {i HE ARTIST TVA REPRODUCED  DEACON OLDSLAW tO A A fHOTOGBAPH, AND BEYOND SAYSI IT ITS AN EXOTATIRNTM l^f fi  42 OLD E BEENTlW LT  SEUFLUOUS TO D ADD A WORD.  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7800-00000035"/> C66   a    aX MOTHER-IN-.LAW. my spiritual and physical welfare, but I suspected he only wanted to see how we lived, and if there was a very good prospect of getting a new and improved steeple put on the church through my means and liberality. In fact, he had never been known to do anything without some selfish motive; and I was bound to suspect him. Deacon Coldslaw was a widower forithe third time. Three winwPs had developed into angels under his dispensation, and he was now looking around for somebody to fill the void in his bosom and house, especially the house.     , I didn't suspect at first that this was his object.. I thought he was trying to find where he could bag the most on account of that new church steeple that he was chairman on. I am bound to suspect a homely man, especially if he is a deacon. The artist has reproduced Deacon Coldslaw from a photo; graph, and beyond saying that it is ai excellent likeness, it would-be -entirely superfluous to add a word. It is a speak- ing likeness and speaks for itself. So there is no occasion fot speaking about it. The deacon was a truly good man. Second to Deacon Richard Smith of Cincinnati. He was an eminently pious man. He was remarkable for the length and loudness of his. prayers. As a wrestler with the throne of grace he had few equals, and he could wrestle with only one eye shut. With the other he watched the effect on the sisteren and saw what. the boys back by the stove were doing. He was a great favorite with the sisters, for he never failed to take each by the hand and ask tenderly about how they felt. So when the deacon became a widower again he was trebly an object of interest in the church. Husbands were not very plenty and he had served the unmarried feminine portion of the church very well during the past twenty years, having reo   II r   M 9rY MOTI113;--N-LAW.--67 HB BOWlED VERY LOW AND POLITELY TO 1HE1, AND SHE WAS EI- *EINTLY BOTH PLEASED AND FLATTERED. HE TOOK Il BY BND AMND HOPED SHE WAS WELL. lieved three al nost hopeless sisters of the dread they had of be ing old maids.               I hated him As I said before, I hated Deacon Coldslaw. I hated him almost as much as I did my mother-in'law' e came twice to the house, pretending that he felt anxious regarding my health, before I " dropped " to his little game, before I com- prehended the depth and breadth of his charity and good will. On the occasion of his second visit I introduced him to my angelic mother-in-law. Then I saw where hisinterestlay. He was trying to get acquainted with her. Suffering: Moses! how my heart leaped. !Did he wish to marry herq Did he have serious notiota .   of making Coldelaw of her t ! ).   &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7800-00000036"/> 68         MY MOTHEB-IN-LAW. He bowed very low and politely to her, and she was evi- dently both pleased and flattered. He took her by the hand and hoped she was well. He held her hand while he con- versed about the weather, the crops, and made a tender allu. aion to the late Mrs. Deacon Coldslaw. Was it possible that he was actually taken with her? Was there about to be an opening out of which I could go and leave all my sorrow behind? I could scarcely believe it. Good luck had never been a friend of mine and I was hardly prepared to believe that anything of this kind was in store for me. I watched her while he held her hand, and actually saw her blush and look at the old rooster with a coy, maidenly tremor in her eyes. The old hen-! But it pleased me and I resolved to leave no stone un. turned to forward the thing. If she was willing I was determin. ed that he should be, if I had to give her a dower to lighten the mntrimonial bed. Such an opportunity for doing good and paying off an old score at the same time could not be lost. I had asked myself a hundred times how I could get square with Deacon Coldslaw, and here seemed to be an opportu- nity. I waited only a day before I made some excuse to call on the deacon, at his place of business, and as adroitly as I could I brought my mother-in-law into the conversation. I found that he A mas interested right away. Then I seized him by the buttonhole and poured warm and eloquent praises in his ear regarding that angelic woman. "She is a jewel, my dear sir. Why, I never knew what it was to live and enjoy housekeeping until she came to live with us. She is the angel of my household, barring, of course, her lovely daughter. She is ripened goodness personified. ;   M MdOTSER-IN-LAW.        69 I POUND THAT HE WAS INTERESTED RIGHT AWAY. THEN 1 AdlSS M BY THE BUTTONHOLE AND POURED WARM AND ELOQUENT PRAISES IN HS EAR REGARDING THAT ANGELIC WOMAN. She is a great economizer and can reduce household expensee- one half, and at the same time set a better table and have things more comfortable than-ever before." "You don't tell me so!" said he. "I do, though. But why I should sound her praises to you, save in a general way, I don't know, except that you have seen her and canjudge for yourself," said I. "Oh certainly, I understand." Did he 2  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7800-00000037"/> @ - MY OTHER-IN-LA W. "Well- good day, Deacon. Come and see us often. My wife likes to have you call very much," said I, starting to go.' "Thank you, I shall do so." We parted. I seemed ten degrees nearer heaven. Be assured that I lost no time in interviewing mny dear mother-in-law. That very night I dawned upon her while she was sitting by the table. "I saw Deacon Coldslaw to-day," said I. *   "' Oh, did you?" she asked, looking up with some interest a Yes, and he sent his kindest regards to you." "Ah, did he " ^ Wished to be remembered kindly to you." i La!" said she, dropping her eyes in maidenly confusion. BE ASSURED THAT I LOST NO TIME IN iATEifiV1BWfKi1GG MY TRmAM ra-M-LA. THAT VERY NIGHT     , DAD O H   WHE "     SIING BY THE TAB /',        , WLP AS SXIMO 1TTIN BY TEli TAlF..I   IYD MOTHEm-IN-LAW.        1  Very fine man is Deacon Coldslaw." 'Yes, so he seems to be." "Quite wealthy." '"So I have hearn." i' Got a splendid home." "So Harriet Ann tells me." x     N Ha, ha! They had been talking about him, had they? ^    "And he has the reputation of being a very kind husband and a good provider." "I dare say." "And, by the way, you knew he was a widower?" "Yes, Harriet Ann told me so, and he said something about it I believe," said the coy creature, without looking up. "And he is looking for a wife I believe." "La me! ' You don't say so! How long has he been be weaved?" she asked, with a little sigh. "About a year I believe."    "i 'Poor man!" How tender and pathetic she Was getting! "I don't wish to say a word, but from the way he inquired after you I suspect that you have found favor in his eyes." "Oh, pshaw! How you do go on. You know he never thought about marrying me," said she, coquettishy. "I beg to differ, by believing that he saw your good qual. ities and took a fancy to them and you. Of course I spoke in the highest terms of you," said I, earnestly. "Did you? How kind. But you know I never had any idea of getting married at my time of life." Hadn't sle, though! ' At your time of life! Why you are a premium person- ification of ripened goodness. And you are not old. .Why, women nowadays are not fit to marry until they are forty."  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7800-00000038"/> MY MOTHER-IN-LAW. "Well, I sometimes think so myself. What does a green girl know of the responsibilities of a married life?" "To be sure. Do you know, I think no woman should get married until she is a widow?" "I perfectly agree with you," said she, without seeing the evident contradiction of my assertion. "So don't give yourself any uneasiness on that score. 'IThe deacon sees things in precisely the same light as I do." "Yes; but, la me! you are only joking. You are such a funny man!" "No, I was never so serious in my life.^ , - Well, marriage is a serious subject." "I agree with you." We parted that night with the most harmonious under. standing. She was evidently as much taken with the deawn as he was with her. If it could only be brought about; -if he would only mar ry her and take me off her hands-I would go on a three weeks' spree in commemoration of the event. The next day the deacon called before going to town to his business. He had a fine lot of turnip and lettuce plants; would I not like some of them? If I did, he would only be too happy to give me any number of them. I encouraged him. He shook hands cordially with the old woman, and talked for half an hour about the various kinds of turnip and lettuce. She seemed to know all about them. In fact, vegetation was her strongest hold. I left them alone, ate my breakfast, and at the end of an hour announced myself as ready to go to town. The deacon would accompany me. They parted slowly-the deacon and my mother-in-law. They somehow clung to each other's hands, and as they parted he was in a gay, almost ecstatic mood, and promised to come around early the next morning   ,  XY MOTHER-IN-LAW, . , .. THERE APPEARED TO BE AN UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN THEIr: THUS QUICK, AND WHEN SHE WENT TO THE FRONT GATE TO MEET HM-IT WAS JUST AT DUSK-TH:EY FLEW TO EACH OTHER'S ARMN: I2XKE -TWO YOUNG LOVERS. with his plants, and they would set them out together seeing- that they knew all about such things. Yes, he was there bright and early the next morning, but she was up and dressed, looking her loveliest, ready to meet- him. And they set out turnip and lettuce plants. They lingered in the garden until our late breakfast" was announced and then they partook of it as daintily as two doves. What a mockery to square appetites which they both had I: And they both spoke of the work they had done, and what. good appetites it had given them. We went to town again together and the deacon was pro; *   v   &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7800-00000039"/> 7rE4      - MHMY ]t[OTHEIR-IN-LAWo fuse in his praise of my mother-in-law; said he had not met such a woman in years. I encouraged his hallucination. That evening he called again. . There appeared to be an understanding between them thus quick, and when she went to the front gate to meet him--it was just at dusk-they flew to each other's arms like two young lovers. I kept out of sight; I took Harriet Ann out for a walk and kept away for two hours. I know what company is, and what constitutes a crowd. I didn't wish to crowd the old lady and the deacon the least bit in-the world. I spoke of the deacon to my wife as being the finest man I ever knew. She looked up in my face and asked-what had changed my mind so suddenly. I told her I was always down ,on a man until I found out all about him; and she never suspected me. "Do you really think he wishes to marry mother?" she asked. "It looks very much like it. -He certainly would not trifle with the old lady's feelings." "Old! She is not so very old." "No, she's' very young in some of her ways." "But if he should marry her, how lonesome it would be at home. Don't you think so 2 " "Oh, dreadful lonesome. Hardly to be endured. But we must not interfere with the ways of Providence, you know, my dear." She sighed a little. "Yes, it will be dreadful lonesome. I shall miss her so mnuch, I can hardly bear to think about it." We returned home and found them going through a reg. ular old-fashioned courtship in the parlor. But we did not   KY MOTHIEB-IN-LA. %       76 disturb them  We went to bed and left them still at it, and I haven't the slightest idea when they disbanded.- It was prob- ably late I am sure of it, for the old lady slept late the next morn-. ing, and I went away without seeing how she looked. This was a rarity for me. But things progressed and began to come together. Luck appeared to be preparing a broad grin in my behalf. Night after night for a month the deacon came and courted. the old angel. She appeared to like it, or at least she took to it as naturally as a duck takes to water. And what a change came over her! She was always dressed .in her neatest and wore pink bows. She appeared to grow younger every day, and the little coquettish and maidenly ways she had were surprising. To me they were laughable, but I hardly dared to breathe for fear something might happen to break it all: up. So I "I '   kept a stiff upper lip, smiled all by myself, and hoped for the best. At last she confided to us that she was engaged to be married to Deacon Coldslaw. f My heart danced like a jumping- jack. When in town I drank health and prosperity to the deacon, and the toast that she might succeed in all her undertakings. Still I hardly dared trust myself to such expressions as my joyousness suggested. I had never in my whole life been lucky enough in warranting the belief that this would-not all end in a bottle of pop with the cork out,. Well at length the marriage day, the happy day, was fixed, and I began to take hope. She bothered herself no more about our domestic affairs, but seemed to be busied in her mia&amp;'s eye with her own future ones.  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7800-00000040"/> 76        WY MO'lTlfiR-IN-LAW. I could come and go when I liked anid no questions were asked. Happiness already dawned upon me. I bought a wedding dress for the old girl and did, all in amy power to forward matters. I would have mortgaged my house and my future prospects- rather than had the thing go back on me at that point. But there appeared to be no danger of it. The deacon was all attention and anxiety, and she certainly met him half way and enjoyed it. Gossip was busy with their names and when it was given out that they were soon to be married, the old ducks of the chuich held an indignation meeting and protested against the deacon's going outside of the fold where he had browsed so long in order to relieve his lonely condition. Several of the sisters had spread themselves on purpose to catch the old man. They had even attended the funeral of his last wife and sympathized with him, and bade him take hope, and to see him ignore their painful condition and go to a widow for consolation, and one outside of the church, was too much for human flesh to bear. But he heeded them not, and to put a stop to their objec. fions regarding' her being an outsider, he prevailed upon her to join the church just before they were to be married, and thus won his way into everybody's esteem save those old dried herrings who linger around churches for the purpose of seeing some wife die in hopes of an opening for themselves. That great and glorious day at last arrived. Hope which had dwelt with me so long was about to end in fruition. Unless something larger and louder than a soda cracker ex- ploded, I was on the eve of emancipation. The wedding was a grand affair. It was held in the ehurch, and the church could not hold all who came to wit-   MY MOTHEl-IN-LAW.   THE WEDDING WAS A GRAND AFFAIR. IT WAS HELD IN THB H TURCH, AND THE CHURCH COULD NOT HOLD ALL WHO CAME TO WIT- NESS IT. ness it. Hundreds were there who had known the deacon as a married man. At least a half dozen were there who had fondly hoped to be made Coldslaw themselves. They were there to criticise. They were there with gall and bitterness on their tongues. And there were three burnt-out i others-in-law there. The mothers of the deacon's other wive- still lived, and they were there in all the glory of weeds and snuff. They had a common interest in seeing what sort of a creature Mrs. Coldslaw No. 4 was. It was only natural, you know. When the groom marched up the aisle with his bride, every tongue was hung in the middle. What a fright she was I How old she was! How much better he could have done! The half dozen anxious and disappointed ones were the ,loudest in the latter remark.   &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7800-00000041"/> , uv       yJr 1 -.I:1 jIIU jlYMO' -LERIN-LAW.. But the great majority commented after this fashion, "The deacon has sodded down three wives, but this one will have the pleasure of planting lettuce or something else on his grave." (  Well, it did look a trifle that way. But I was happy.: nevertheless. Harriet Ann and myself had seats of honor. In fact, I gave the bride away. I never gave anything away with so much pleasure in my life. I was reckless and was on the point of giving her away twice for fear she would not stay. The rector entered into the business with much heart. He had got somewhat used to marrying the deacon and it ap- peared to come easy to him. He had to take the book close tohis eyes, being -very near. sighted, but he did not fail in any particular. They were married! I certainly should have stood on my bald head had there been room for revolving. -I subscribed one hundred dollars on the spot towards putting a new steeple on the church. I felt like building a new church. After the ceremony was over the deacon's coach took them and ourselves to our house. I was anxious for them to go home. I wanted a 'fair chance to express myself. We indulged in a bottle of wine and said heaps of congrat- ulatory things, and finally they re-entered their coach and started homeward. Harriet Ann remained at the front gate watching them. She had thrown one of my old shoes after them and was watching them out of sight. But I was not. I retired to the house and began going through with all kinds of gymnastics and pantomime, indi cative of my delighted soul. I stood on my head. I yelled for joy. I skipped like a six-months-calf. I was never so' happy in all my life, and I actually hugged Harriet Ann and tried to stand her on her head in order to express my supreme delight. At last I was revenged on the deacon! At last I had got rid of my mother-in-law! Was ever man so blessed? Was ever man in such luck? The woman who had submitted to all my personal abuse, all my chastisements without flinching, the woman who esa caped explosion and all other death-traps, the woman who, '.                     . .     . *1     JUY MUTHA2R-i-NY-LAWo      aV ^bY alI,, ----. '----- ,  STOOD ON 'M TtRAD. I YET,T,D FOR JOY. I SKIPPED LIKE 4, SIX-MONTHS-CALF. I   WAS NEiVER SO HAPPY IN ALL MY LIFE, AND 1 ACTUALLY HUGGED HARRIET ANN AND TRIED TO STAND HER ON HEB 1TEAIA IN ORDER TO EXPRESS MY SUPREME DELIGHT - could not be got rid of in any other way was at last out of my house and mistress of my enemy. Success to her! Success to all who strive to free them- selves from mothers-in-law! Take warning by my experience. Don't try to hurry them to untimely graves, for you will be sure to get the worst of it, but rather find some one for whom you have a grudge and get her mairried. It is the only safe way Love is the safest Nemesis. THE END.  &#xD;<pb n="80 (Advertisement) -81 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7800-00000042"/> STANDARD RECITATIONS BY BEST AUTHORS. A Choice Collection of Beatifutl Compositions, CAREFPULLY COMPILED FOR SCHOOL, LYCEUM, PARLOR AND OTHER ENTERTAINMENTS, By PRANCES P. SULLIVAN. CONTENTS O;x     O No. 8.   PAGE A Psalm of Life. Longfellow................. 3 The Reaper and the Flowers. Longfellow... 4 Footsteps of Angels. Longfellow .  .......... 4 The Wreck of-the Hesperus. Longfellow.... 4 The Winning of Juliet. Shakespeare......... 5 Polonius'sAdvice to his Son. Shakespeare... 6 Home. 0. Goldsmith.....................   6 Thanatopsis.  Bryant.............................. 6 The Yankee Girl. Whittier...................... 7 'The Moral Warfare. Whittier................. 8 The Female Martyr. Whittier ..................  The Cities of the Plain. Whittier.............10 Answer to "Hate of the Bowl."  Anna F.... 10 Mercy. Shakespeare.............................. " Faithful. Rose Terry Cooke..................... Building and Being. Anon............ ...... I.. The Rag Picker. Thomas Dunn English.... 12 A Bit of Experience ............................... 14 'Who shall go first? ............................... 14 How we take it. Theo. D. C. Miller.......... 14 Shared. Lucy Larcom.......................... 15 Xing Coal.............................................15 The Annunciation. Adelaide Procter......... 16 The Sledge and the Pen. T. S. Cleary..... 16 The Warrior's Death ................................17 Louis Napoleon. Geo. B. Sims................. 18 Art thou living yet? James G. Clark......... 18 A Thought. Father Ryan................   18 The Fisherman. W. Goethe.................... 19 Reunion ..........................     20 Dreams. Dalnot.. ............................... 20 The Girl of Seville. Anon ..................... 20 Beth Gelert. W. L. Spencer.................... 21 'The Happy Man. James Thomson ........ 21 The Sculptor Boy. Bishop Doane............. 22  (*od's Time. Jean Ingelow..........  .  22   /i,     -    ' Pb PAGE Unfinished Still. Anon .........,........... . 22 The Daughter of Meath. Thos. H. Bayly... 23 The Golden Side. Anon........................... 24 The Death of Bawtie.............................. 24 O'Brazil-The Isle of the Blest. G. Griffin 25 The Bridal of Malahide. Gerald Griffin...... 26 The Miser's Fate. Osbone ......................27 Vailed. Anon......................... .......... 28 The Darling Wee Shoe. Dora Shaw ....... 29 The Closing Scene. T. Buchanan Read...... 30 The Old Man in the Stylish Church. John H. Yates ................................ 31 The Old Man in the Model Church. John - H. Yates ...................................... 32 Marston Moor. W. M. Praed ................. 33 The Dying Hebrew. Kimbie ..............3... 34 The Mariner's Wife. Wm. Julius Mickle.... 3 The Uplifting of the Banner. Baine.......... 35 The Pillar Towers of Ireland. D. F. McCarthy 36 Childhood and Manhood. Crabbe ............. 3 The Last Farewell................................  38 The Indian Chieftain.............................. 3 Questions. Henry J. Kent .................... 38 The Little Orator. Thaddeus Mason Harris 39 A  Stitch  in  Time.................................... 3 Mad Mag.  Leonard Wheeler .................. 39 The Palace o' the King. Wm. Mitchell...... 40 The Demon Ship. Lloyd MifiMin .   ........... 41 The  Robber...... ............. ............. ...... 4 Nothing to do................. ...... 43 Home. Anon.............................  43 Little Mary's Wish. Mrs. L. M. Blinn ....... 44 Smile whenever you can ......................... 45 The Mare, your Honor. R. Mountjoy Jephson 45 The Deadman's Journey ...................... 46 AnEpisodeinthe Life of an Actor. Roy Leslie 48   STANDARD RECITATIONS BY BEST AUTHORS. A Choice Collection of B EATUTIF:P    L T  C O I POSITI I pN-S, Carefully Compiled for School, Lyceum, Parlor, and other Entertainments, By FRANCES P. SULLIVAN. CONTENTS OF No. 4.   '.     PAGE. Resignation. By ,4W. Longfellow .... 3 At the Morgue. By Edmund C. Stedman  4 John Burns of Gettysburg. By Bret H arte ........................................ 4 The Pledge at Spunky Point. By John H ay ............. ............................ 5 The Ivy Green. By Charles Dickens ... 6 Conductor Bradley. By John G. Whittier 6 Ring Down The Drop-I Cannot Play. By J. W. Watson. ..........  ..... 7 The Battle-Song of Labor ................. 8 The Haunted Palace. By Edgar Allan Poe .......................... ............... 8 Mary, the Maid of the Inh.   Robert Southey...................  ............... 9 The Clown's Story. Vandyke Browne... " The Execution of Montrose. By W. E. Aytoun....................................... 12 The Old Forsaken School-House. By John H. Yates ...................... ...14 The Two Beggars ............................. 1 The Young Tramp. By Charles F. Adam 15 Song of the Mystic. Father Ryan....... 16 Truth-Freedom-Virtue.   An Addr ss to  a  Child .................................. 17 The little Cup-Bearer ......................... 17 Leaving the Homestead .................... 18 In the Floods. By Isabella Fyvie Mayo 18 Alabama. By Mrs. Hemans .............. 19 ' "If Things was only Sich." 'By B. P.  Shillaber ....................... .......... 20 The Mountains of Life. By J. G. Clark 20 Give me the Hand. By Goodman BarnAY  20  The King's Temple ........................v 21 The Portrait. By Owen Meredith ....... 22 r The Guard's Story ............................ 23  The Red Jacket. George M. Baker...... 23 Minot's Ledge. By Fitz-James O'Brien. 24 1 The Bondage of Drink ........................ 25 T The King's Picture. By Helen B. Bost- wick ........................................ 25 J Night. By James Montgomery............ 26 ' Custer's Last Charge. By Frederick Whit- taker ............ ......................... 26 M   3 Four Lives. By C  te. -f B. Freeman .. 28 Eternal Justice. By ,arles Mackay.... 9 The Fatal Glass. By Laura U. Case .... 30 Though Lost to Sight. to Memory Dear. By Ruthven Jenkyns ................... 30 i If.31 If .....  ............. .. ............ ...  31 Our Ships at Sea. By George W. Bungay 51 Scatter the Germs of the B jautiful 32 The Pride of Battery B. By E. H. Gassa. way ......................................... 32 I'm with You once again. By Gtorge P. M orris ....................................... Incident of the French Camp. By Robert Browning .............. ........... .. .. 33 Marion's Dinner. By Edward C. Jones. 34 Tale of a Temptation. By Alice Horton 34 The Sailor-Boy's Dream. By William Dimond .......................... 36 A Sailor's Story. By Mrs. C. H. N. Thomas ....... ......................... 37 Xerxes at the Hellespont. By R. C. Trench....................................... 38 The Flight of Xerxes. By Maria Jane Jewsbury .............................. 38 Hero and Leander. By Leigh Hunt ... 39 The  Avalanche................................. 40 The Surgeon's Tale. By Barry Cornwall 40 Clear the Way. By Charles Mackay .... 41 The Toast By Mary Kyle Dallas......... 41 Baby. By George Macdonald ............. 42 The Lips that Touch Liquor Must Never Touch Mine. By CGeorge W. Young. 42 The Ideal and the Real. By I. Edgar Jones .. .............     43 The Bricklayers. By G. H. Barnes..... 44 The Charge by the Ford. By Thomas Dunn  English............. ..........  45 Music in Camp. By John R. Thompson 45 Maturnus' Address to His Band. By Ed- ward Spencer .......... .................... Jo, the Tramp. By Edgar M. Chipimau 47 The Death of Hofer. By James C. Man- gau ...... ........... ..............  47 Memory. By James A. Garfield ..... 48 -1  -  - .  .4   Price 12 Cents by Mail. 1 and 2 Cent Stamps taken. Address M. J. IVERS &amp; CO., 86 KNASSS U STREET, .V. Y. City.  &#xD;<pb n="82 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7800-00000043"/> STANDARD RECITATIONS BY BEST AUTHORS. A Choice Collection of     * .  BE.: J -.TIF'T-L   C 00C1:POC   ITIONTSiS Carefully Compiled for  School, Lyceum, Parlor, and other Entertainments, By FRANCES P. SULLIVAN. CONTENTS OF No. 5.-    PAUE. Hate of the Bowl............................. Be Just, and Fear Not. Alford............ 4 The Laborer. W. D. Gallagher ........... 4 Masonic Emblems .............................. 4 Awake! Awake! (1861.) Elmer R. Coates 5 The American Flag. Joseph B. Drake. (  Wounded. William E. Miller............. 7 Cardinal Wolsey on Being Cast off by King Henry VIII. Shakspeare...... 8 Naming the Baby ............................. The Hornet's Nest........................ . 10 Let it Pass.............. .......................... 10 A Diunkard's Dream ....... .......10 Drifted out to Sea ......... ...... .. , " 1 he Field of Waterloo. Byron ........... 12 M izpah ................................. . 13 The Falls of the Sioux ........... ......... 13 In Fetters of Gold.............. ...... ...... 14 "Rock of Ages."...........*............  " The Sister of Charity. Gerald Griffin... 15 The Two Glasses...1................. .......... 16 True Heroism .............. .......... .... . 17 Some Mother's Child. Francis L. Keeler 17 Columbia. Thimothy Dwight ......... ... 18 Jenny Malone ..........................  1 Cripple Ben. George L. Catlin .......... 20 Earth'l Noblemen ..............  .. 20 The Triple Tie. Henry G. Perry......... 20 The tRosary of My Years. Father Ryan 21 The Hero of the Commune. Margaret J. Preston .................... . 22 Antonio Oriboni. Margaret J. Preston. 23 My Love. W. F. Fox ................  24 The Drummer's Bride ........................ 24 True Source of Contentment ............... 25 The Maiden's Prayer. N. P. Willis...... 26   PAiGE. A Boy. N. P. Willis .......................  26 True Faith. B. P. Shillaber .............. 27 Better Than Gold. Mrs. J. M1. Winton. 26' After the Battle .............................. 28 How a Man Should be Judged............. 29. The Last Redoubt. ,Alfred Austin.......30 My Wife and Child. Henry 1. Jackson 31 After the Ball. Nora Perry.................. 32;:  Come B;.ck. Thomas Dunn English ... 33; Death of Gaudentis. Harriet Annie ...... 34 Platonic. William B. Terrett .............. 3 The Silver Wedding. Mrs. C. M. Stowe 3  The Wants of Man.  J. Q. Adams ....... 8! The Diamond Wedding ...................... 37 [ Have Drank My Last Glass ............... 3 The Sailor'sFuneral. LydiaH. Sigourney 3f Two Loves and a Life. William Sawyer 4C Beginning Again .......................... 4( The W ine-Cup.................................. 4- Godiva. Alfred Tennyson .................. 4 The Regiment's Return. E. J. Cutler... 4  The Lover's Sacrifice ........................ 4 A Georgia Volunteer. Mary A. Townsend 4t By Different Paths .......................  4( The Prodigals.  Ernst M'Affey in the  ! "Current" ............................ 4( No Such Thing as Chance............... ... 4( The Bridge of Prayer ........................ 4( A Breath of Summer. William   Cullen Bryant ......    .......................  4 The Boys who Wore Blue are Turning Gray. U. A. Barrett ..................... 4' The Lost Child ........  ................ 4E Our Kind of a Man. James Whitcomb Riley ......................................  The Baby. J. W. Riley ..................... 4 *             i,   Price 12 Cents by Mail. 1 and 2 Cent Stamps taken. Address M. J. IVERS &amp;    CO., 86 NJASS U STREET, S. Y. Cit..   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
