<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7767">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Book for the Winter-evening Fireside </title>
            <author>Sikes, William Wirt, (1836-1883)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7767</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2218</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A book for the winter-evening fireside</title>
                  <author>Sikes, William Wirt, (1836-1883)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>96 p. plates </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Ingalls &amp; Haddock</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Watertown N.Y. </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1858">1858</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-03-28">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>A book for the winter-evening fireside</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7767-00000001"/>  The evening passed in the mirthful, happy style of all  such gatherings in country homes.   (P^ G 56.)  PAGE}P-   A BOOK FOR THE WINTER EVENING FIRESIDE. BY  WILLIAM     WIRT   SIKES. "When icicles hang by the wall, And DICK, the shepherd, blows his nail, And TOM bears logs into the hall, And milk comes frozen home in pail." SHAKSPEARE. OF  INGALLS &amp; HADDOCK:  OFFICE OF THE NEW-YORK REFORMER, WATERTOWN, N. Y. 1858.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7767-00000002"/> FROM INGALLS &amp; HADDOOCK  POWER PRESSERS. 8MART, BINDIER.   PREFACE. THE PUBL81HERS think that even so unassuming a book as mine, ought to flourish that unread feather of form- ality-A PREFACE. I suppose they are right. The writings which compose this work have nearly all of them been published before-in the columns of vari- ous newspapers and magazines-New York, Boston, Phil- adelphia, Utica, Watertown, etc.-and, for the greater part, were written when I had just commenced my pen- holding experience. Graver work has long superseded story-telling, in my case. In acting upon the advice of friends-to put together in this shape a few of the trifles I have penned, for the special delectation of WINTER EVENJNG FIREID---I have steadily aimed at furnishing VARIETY, " the spice of life." READER: if the little book fulfils its mission, (which is three-fold: 1st. To entertain-2d. To instruct-3d. To sell,) 1 shall be abundantly satisfied. Your obedient servant, THE AUTHOR. WATERTOWN, DEC. 10, 1859.  &#xD;<pb n="0 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7767-00000003"/>  CONTENTS. PAGE. BELLADONNA ---------------              9 BLESSINGTON'S CHOICE -----------         .--31 EXTRACTS FROM LEOTURES BY THE AUTHOR ------- -92 IST NOT HAPPY SCENE FOR YOU? -----      ------64 OLD LETTERS --------------------------------------28 SONG--THE ROSE MONTH --------     -------    68 SUMMER PICTURES,-----------   -----------------81' THE FORTUNE HUNTER ---------      -------   43 THE HYOCHONDRIAC-------------          - 20 THE LITTLE SINGER ..--------.-----   ----- -----65 THE STORY OF JEREMY LONG, OF POTTSBURGH---------82 THE STREET ------------------------------      18 THE THREE JEWELS .-------------------------- 70 WINTER PICTURES -..----- ,---- -------------- ---- 7 WHEN MY HAIR IS GROWING WHTE ----      ---  -41 ye MOURNFULLE TALE OF Ye COLLAR ---------------39  &#xD;<pb n="0Illustration" xml:id="VAC7767-00000004"/> The New-Year's caller, twelve o'clock at night, Feeling his fuddled way along the empty street. ' ( Page 7. )  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7767-00000005"/> WINTER PICTURES. 1. The bare trees, lifting up their naked hands; 2. The village, bound with ice and crowned with snow; 3. The ragged beggar, shivering as he stands; 4. The bull-dog, flying from his frosty foe; 5. The father, beating on through driving storms, Home, where the ruddy blaze his coming waits; 6. The dreary hovel, where no bright flame warms The wretches cowering over cheerless grates; 7. The children, romping in the pleasant rooms; 8. The school-boys, building snowy giant-men; 9. The merry parties, where the town-belle blooms; 10. The house-maid, cleaning turkey and fat hen; ". The gay balls, where the bright hours fly away To tune of pleasant viol and smooth horn; 12. The good boy, full of glee, on Christmas day; 13. The bad boy, empty stockinged, all forlorn; ". The New Year's caller, twelve o'clock at night, Feeling his fuddled way along the empty street; His hat a wreck, his tout ensemble " tight," Begging a street-lamp to "Come out and treat!" Poor, shock-haired wretch, with idiotic leer, And maudlin gesture, talking to the wind! Sad commentary on the young New Year!  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7767-00000006"/> 8'        WINTER PIOTuRES. Fit emblem of the old year-left behind! 15. The skaters, flying o'er'the frozen pond; 16. The stars that stud the cold blue vault of night; 17. The family circle, gathering around The WINTER EVENING FIBESIDE, warm and bright!   BELLADONNA. "WEtLI, cousin Tom, if you will solemnly promise not to print it, I will tell you all about it-.-what a little fool I made of myself, and all," "No, Allie, I will promise you nothing of the kind. It is the inalienable privilege of the profession to put its experiences in type, no matter, from what source they are derved; and while I am willing to promise that I will not tell to the world your name, I should prove false to the rights of Scribbledom if I should withhold any important information which it lay in my power to communicate. So, if you won't tell me on any terms save my unconditional silence, why I shall have to remain forever ignorant of your valuable experience; but I promise you, Miss, I will be even with you one of these days, for your lack of generosity. What if I should tell Charley French, for instance, of your flirtations with Arthur Canning, at uncle George's, the other evening? Would the. aake all square between us .? "Now, if you don't stop---" "Or, if that's not enough, perhaps it would make it right should I tell Fred Preston what has become of his breast-pin, that he is turning the world upside down in his search for- eh?" "H"--'       -  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7767-00000007"/> BELLADONNA. "Especially, should I set Charley on the scent! Wouldn't it be grateful to your feelings, coz?" "You may as well stop that, first as last, sir; for I declare you shall not hear a word of my story, if you undertake so to frighten it from me. Threatening, forsooth, to tell Charley of my flirtations with Mr. Canning! Why, what do you suppose I'd care, you sauce-box? I tell you what it is, you'd reach 'your point much sooner by ofering to take me on a sleigh-ride to-night, or by bringing me that copy of ' Aurora Leigh' you have been promising me these six weeks past." , Why! hav'n't I invited you-to take a sleigh-ride with me 'to-night, Allie? Really, I thought I'd spoken of it. That's just what I came down for-to ask you. You'll go, won't you, coz?--there's a good girl! As for 'Aurora Leigh,' why-allow me!"-and I drew from a cavernous receptacle in the tail of my coat, the coveted volume, and handed it to the lively young lady with whom I had been holding this conversation. Par parenthese, let me say-Cousin Alhe was a rosy-lipped, chestnut-haired lass, of some sixteen or eighteen summers, (I don't exactly recollect which, really-at any rate, I know that 'is about it,) who was blessed with a pair of the most enchant- ing blue eyes ever read of in tale of olden romance, or embalmed in undying verse. Not that those same incomparable eyes had never been made the theme of sonnet or song; I have painful recollections of certain youthful indiscretions of my own in that line, which live in musty scrap-books, and which, I pray Heaven, oblivion eternally may cover! But to resume the tete-a-tete between my blue-eyed cousin and myself.    BELLADONNA-.          11. "There! if that's not just like you, now," the young lady said, lifting a white hand and pointing at me a little arched finger, which, from very fatness and softness, would stay curled. And, .by the way, there was magic in that little finger---a part proper, however, of Allie's tout ensemble-awakening a desire in the beholder to take into his own broader palm, and endeavor to smooth straight the white piece of plumpness.- "You always surprise a body so," she continued, " when you do anything! I wonder if it would be possible for you to make a present, or extend an invitation, in the ordinary way." "Not if you were the 'party of the second part,' I am afraid! Those azure eyes of yours manufacture a goodly share of that eccentricity you continually charge upon me-did you know it? Pray, can you tell me how it happens that Mary never sees any of those outrageous peculiarities in me which are so prolific in your eye?" "Oh, you are forever preaching up Mary to me; as if a man's wife could see anything peculiar in her other half!- How ridiculous! I believe if you were to make a practice of wearing your shawl over your head, she would never notice its The idea, now, of there being nothing unusual or peculiar in that dreadful habit you have of trotting the baby to sleep to the tune of 'A frog he would a wooing go!' Awful!" "Well, there, Allie, let's quit this! Give me your story all about the Belladonna, quick," and I looked at my watch very anxiously. "Come-4I am all ears." "I beg leave to opine, most wise cousin, that you are partly tongue, or you would not'have kept yourself waiting here this length of time, to hear yourself talk."   &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7767-00000008"/> 12     BELLADONNA. ( Hear my-self talk! . Ha, ha!-pretty good! H-but come, let's have your experience, without more words." " Well, to make a long story short---" "' There, none of that!t Not a bit! I want no dodging sentences round corners; please give us a sober, honest story- nothing extenuating, nor setting down aught in phonography." Then cousin Allie told her story. I withdraw Tom from the remainder of my sketch, and will let Allie ramble on in her own way, -isuring the reader that there is pith in her narrative -when it is found.  ALLIE RAMBLES ON IN HER OWN AWAY. I saw, the other day, in your paper, an account of the practice of certain European belles, of rendering their eyes brilliant by anointing them with extrait de belladonna. Now, I have a species of intense contempt for my tame blue eyes-I don't think they are lively enough to suit my character. They will "languish," in every possible place,-on every possible occasion, when, truth knows, my heart has no such intention. So I was determined to try this delightful " eye-opener." (I got that word from a young gentleman of my acquaintance-I suppose it means one of those dreadful mixtures they sell at hotel-bars, don't it?) But you may well believe I was not quite so wild as to try the thing without understanding it at all -for, in fact, I was a little afraid of it-it seemed so very unnatural. So I asked uncle William, (who I supposed would of course know all about it, being a physician,) and he said if I wanted to try it, he would make an- application for me, assuring me that it would not make a "blind man " of me, at   ]RELT ADON-TA.        1 the worst. I sat down in a big chair, and the office-boy stood behind me to hold my head. It made me feel queerish, I tell you--it was so like getting one's tooth pulled, to sit in a big chair with a man behind one's back, holding one's head. But I sat as still as a kitten, and watched uncle's movements. - Reaching up to a shelf, he took down a little white porcelain jar labeled "BELLADONNA." From this he took a dirty black phial, with a short stick thrust in at the mouth, imbedded in a mess of stuff which I verily believe was the blackest substance I ever beheld. A Timbuctoo negro might have made a. black mark on his face with it.. I thought I detected a sober twinkle in uncle's little gray eyes, as he held the stick under my nostrils. Faugh! how it smelt! "Beautiful-ain't it?" said uncle with the utmost gravity. "Equal to Dutch cheese!" said I, in reply. "See here!" said he, holding the bottle toward me and pointing to the label. I looked; I read; I was frightened; the label said, "DEADLY NIGHTSHADE." "Why, uncle," said I, "how could you deceive me so?" "Deceive you, child," said he, "I have not deceived you." "Why, I thought you were showing me belladonna, all the while," said I. "It is belladonna--it and the deadly nightshade are identical."  I was astonished at this, to be sure; but I was not going to back out, by any means, after I was all ready for the operation. So uncle took another phial, containing, as he explained to me, a dilution of the same drug, and I bent my head for him to approach my eyes.- With a small, soft brush, he anointed the  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7767-00000009"/> "; 'BELLADONNA. ball of each eye. It was a little painful, but Peter held my head tight, and I was too proud to scream. It wass done.: I ran to the mirror to note the effect. There was no change. I turned an inquiring glance upon uncle, and he answered it with: You will not observe any change immediately. In a half orthree quarters of an hour you will. Your eyes will sparkle like diamonds at the party to-night. Ida Hunter, with her piercing black orbs, will find in you a rival, or I am no pr6phet.' I left- the office and hurried home. After laying off my things':and adjusting my dress, I again approached a mirror.- I was frightened! My eyes shone like a panther's! The blue field was nearly covered with a large and still dilating pupil. But my fright was brief, and gave way to delight at the effect the new toilet accompaniment had produced. I reveled in anticipation of the entrancing brilliancy which would beam from my eyes, at the party in the evening at Mrs. Dudley's. But long hours intervened between the present and the contemplated soiree. How should I pass the weary time? It seemed- as if I could not brook the ordinary recreations and occupations of home that afternoon,-I hadn't been so impatient before in, OO! I don't know how long. What should I do to kill time, and (if I must confess it,) show my bright eyes  At length I resolved' to go shopping. To have a handsome' dry-goods, clerk gaze into their raven depths was at least better than nothing. -As opened the door leading to the street, after making my   Brr tAMPONS.          ' 15 excuses to mamma, it seemed as if I had thrown wide: the gates of celestial glory; not that I saw golden 'foors,or diamond thrones, or snowy-robed angels; but: thb light, the light!-it was excruciatingly dazzling. I closed the :dor after me and stepped into the street, my eyes aching the whie like red-hot balls in their sockets. The sun was pouring down its rays upon the white snow in a flood of unheard-of brilliancy. My eyes closed  themselves to the -remotest degree ftht they were capable, without shutting outright. I would luvae given my best robe for a parasol or a veil, as I walked on. The light grew more and more insupportable; (my little wisp of a bonnet afforded, of course, no protection whatever to my eyes;) it grew still more intense; I clasped a hand upon my brow; I muttered a prayer for relief; and finally, unable to proceed further, I closed my eyes and stopped short in the street. Oh, what sweet, delicious relief I felt, as the soft lids enveloped the burning balls! It was like thrusting a, burnt finger into cooling water--only more so; it was the sweetest rest I ever enjoyed. As best I could, I retraced my steps homeward; I entered, rushed to my room, threw myself into a rocking chair, and opened my throbbing eyes once more to their proper width.- The light in the room was mellow; I felt no pain now. Yet I carefully avoided the windows. I hav'n't patience now to recount to you my reflectionsl You may imagine them. But you will not need to be told that I was content to await the fall of night before venturing out again. At length,-the hour came. I was deposited at the:door of  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7767-00000010"/> 16          Btr,rTAPONXNA. the Dudley mansion. I entered, and flew to the ladies' toilet room. A glance in the glass told me my eyes were in fine array. The blue iris was now almost completely obscured by a pupil of sparkling black, only a faint line of the old azure bordering it. I was delighted, and in excellent spirits. In company with another I descended, and was ushered into the brilliant drawing room. Mercy! I almost screamed, as the brilliant glare of the gas-lighted parlors flashed upon my shrinking eyes! It was too much; I could not endure the pain.\ I beat a hasty and inglorious retreat, returned to the toilet room, donned my things, and was carried home in Frank Hunter's sleigh. Ida Hunter was left to reign undisputed queen, with the natural bright black eyes Heaven gave her. I retired to rest with a powerful headache, and actually wept myself asleep, lamenting my own folly and its distressing end. The next day my eyes were still too sensitive to permit me to leave the house; and it was not until the next that I called at uncle William's office. He laughed like an old ogre as I related my sad fortunes; and apologetically said he was not aware my eyes were quite so weak! Well, I had nothing left for it but to forgive him, to lay to heart the lesson I had learned, and to ask him something more of the nature of the poison he had administered me. "We use it," said he, "for the purpose of applying to the ball of a patient's eye, in order to expand the pupil, and thus enable us to perceive the condition of the organ to better advantage. It is very powerful in its effects. A little of it rubbed upon your forehead, your chin-your shoulder, even- will dilate the pupil, and give you, besides, a stunning   BWr r.AnONNA.          17 headache. Let belladonna alone, Allie," he concluded, "for, my word for it, those foolish ladies who use it are running a terrible risk of inducing amaurosis, a disease of the eye nearly certain to result in incurable blindness." "What time shall I expect you to call for me with your sleigh, cousin Tom?" 3  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7767-00000011"/> THE STREET. SITS the poet in his garret, and o'erlooks the busy street, Listening to the drowsy patter of the million's bustling feet, Coming faintly, borne up to him mingled with the clouds of dust; With the creaking of the axles groaning with their load of rust; With the shouting of the draymen urging on their sweating nags; With the whistling of the picker as he slowly gathers rags; With the yawning of the loafer lolling on an empty box; With the banker's pattering footfall as he walking dreams of stocks;  With the urchin's merry chuckle as of conquest he doth boast, And the clattering of his marbles as they rattle 'gainst the post; With the shouting of the newsboy as the Herald he doth cry; With the rumbling of the carriage wheels that bear the proud fair by; With the barking of two big dogs fighting i; the swaying crowd That cheers on the snapping wretches with its curses deep and loud;   THE STREET.          19 With the grinding of an organ, by the bustle haply drowned, The Italian's hand denoting it, slow wagging round and round; With the banging of the hardware rolling from the iron stores; With the pleading of the beggar, as he shows his stinking sores; With the yelling of the frantic youth who peddles pop-corn balls; With the rapping of the town-belles, making fashionable calls; With the whining of the small girl who molasses candy sells; With the gossiping of school-girls, and the ballad-singer's yells; Mingling with ten thousand noises, borne up skyward on their way ;- Sits the poet, listening, musing, on a dusty summer day. And he says, The world is selfish; to himself each man is wed; And be sighing turns within and slowly breaks his crust of bread. They are selfish,--says the poet,-crushing Love beneath their feet; GOD forbid I should be like them!-like the plodders in the street  w  ei  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7767-00000012"/> THE HYOCHONDRIAC. "O-H-H---D-e-a-r!" The walls of the dismal old room would, under common circumstances, have echoed the drowsy exclamation of the miserable, peevish, self-tormented hypochondriac, as he sat propped up in his soft easy-chair; but even the antiquated plastering had become so imbued with the laziness of the tenant, and the exclamation had acquired such a repugnant tone from age and reiteration, that the room was silent. The walls of the chamber were papered strangely in accordance with the character of him who groaned without cause therein, being one broad and dull expanse of drear and melancholy blue-a dull, dark, sombre blue. In one corner stood a sideboard, with a complete assortment of bottles upon it-from the big quart bottle down to the two-inch phial. On a table by the window, covered with a greasy black cloth, was a copy of Scott's Bible, with dust on it so thick that one might with his finger write his name on the cover; and around it were standing more bottles. On the mantel a porcelain mandarin solemnly nodded his head amid a gloomy array of- bottles. A light-stand stood near the invalid's chair, bearing a work on geology, a wine-glass, a tea-cup of mixture, and a couple of-bottles. And there sat the grunting old cancer on the face of society, with his bloated cheek resting on one   THE HYOOHONDRIAO         21 shoulder-his fat hands folded on his big paunch-his feet in warm bandages, and supported, by a prop-his eyes rolling from one side of the room to the other very imploringly-traveling industriously back and forth between the portrait of his aunt at his left and the closet door opposite. "O-h-h-h-d-e-a-r!" He meant it to be very plaintive and gentle, that would-be wail, but one could almost hear it across the street. Reaching out his hand for his cordial, prepared by a dandy quack, who wore a glossy short-cloak, a shining hat, a white neck-tie and a wealth of beard and moustache, Oliver suddenly coughed.- You think it no matter if he did cough. Oliver would disagree with you; he feared to cough--worse than he ever feared a tailor's bill in his young days-for he could not cough without violently shaking himself; and knowing this, you will readily surmise that he shook himself now. He did. And the consequence was, he upset the light-stand,-bottles and all,-with a crash. "Washington! Washington!" he bellowed, with all his stress of voice. Straightway the door was thrown open, and a well-dressed, neat-looking negro showed his polished countenance. "What want, mas'r?" "Washington," wheezed out old Ferment, reproachfully, "why-don't-you-come-more-gently-when-I--call " "B'g p'd'n, mas'r," said Washington, penitently, making a low bow. "Big pudding, sir!" exclaimed Oliver, starting up, and regarding his attendant with a stare of astonishment-" what  &#xD;<pb n="22" xml:id="VAC7767-00000013"/> 22    '    THE HYOCHONDRIAC. put it into your black head that I wanted a pudding, sir? Say-who gave you authority to-ah-presume, eh?" Washington returned the stare, with compound interest. "Why don't you answer me?" "A-a-a, I'n't say n'fn 'bout a pudd'n, sar! H---" "You didn't, eh? Ah, you sooty villain, it's lucky for you that your poor master's unwell, or your impudence might cost you a good thrashing. But what are you standing there for? Pick up this stand here, and then go for the doctor." With a groan, Oliver sank back on his cushions to muse on his servant's expression, and to endeavor to comprehend what induced him to say " big pudding." He thought it strange, very! He was sure he didn't want anypudding at all,-nor any veal, either, for that matter-for such a desire would be preposterous for one in his situation-a man whose feet had become encrusted with stone, and yet which were as tender as -chickens! What put that into his head? He was certain he couldn't tell! Chickens were tender; so was veal; but he didn't want any-not he! A man in his condition-an invalid, want chi---poh! he scouted the idea. Washington departed on his errand, and ere long ushered Dr. Foolemall into the apartment. "Aw! my dear Ferment, and how are you to-day, poor fellow," said the quack, grasping Oliver's big fist in both his own delicate hands. "Oh, doctor, doctor!" groaned Oliver, "'I feel terribly to-day, terribly. I am afraid my legs are becoming encrusted as well as my feet. -Oh! how horrid it is!" "Poor man! poor man!" said Fooleman, sympathetically:  &#xD;<pb n=" (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7767-00000014"/>   57"l--,I    -1I  &#xD;<pb n="-23" xml:id="VAC7767-00000015"/>   THE HYOCHONDRIAC.         28 "what will become of you? Let me see!" and stooping over, he felt of the extremities mentioned; "worse and worse, I find! The petrifaction is gradually encroaching upon the corporeal pomposities, and I fear that ere long the bivalvicus auricularius will become completely coagulated. The hyphen ugen is as tergious as a calcareous animalcule." "What's that?" gasped Oliver. "Oh! excuse me, sir,-will speak more plainly,-we professional men become so-habituated-you understand me! I meant to say," he continued, tapping the leg with his finger, "simply, hard as bricks!-or more properly adamant, sir.- Resemble one faction of the Democratic party strongly-haw! haw! haw!" - attempting to be witty; adding imi   an under-tone, as he laid aside his hat and cloak: "and his head resembles the other faction, I apprehend!" "Doctor," said Oliver, "don't you think I had better discharge my present servant? He is getting so very impudent that I shall be tuined by him yet." "Discharge him? By all means," said Foolemall; pursuing in a confidential tone, "fact is, my dear Ferment, I have long secretly wished that yp t wculd discharge him, fearing as I do that his stupid bluntness will be the means of producing an ilf effect on your disorder. But I had not mentioned it, lest it might wound your feelings-not knowing what relations there might be existing between you." " Re-la-tions!" "Aw, don't mistake me, sir. Social relations, I alluded to; merely social relations." There was a pause, during which Foolemall took a phial  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7767-00000016"/> 24        THE HYOCHONDRIAC. from his case, and mixed a draught. This operation complete, the professor of physic arose and repeated: "Yes, sir, discharge him, sir; by all means discharge him!" and then, after giving a few directions, he left, telling our hero to be careful and not let his legs get jarred. Washington was discharged. He shed a few "' unavailing tears," and then bade the hypochondriac a reluctant farewell. Washington's successor made his appearance in the shape of a genuine Yankee embodiment of wit and shrewdness, crowned with a free-and-easy white hat, and armed with an umbrella of orthodox hue. After having been in his new position about a. week, disgust overcame policy, and Zedekiah resolved to either cure his master's foibles, or incur a discharge from his service. One morning as Zedekiah entered the room to brush it up and arrange the bottles, on approaching the invalid's chair he was as usual warned by that gentleman to beware lest he should hurt his legs. "Wal, now," said Zedekiah, coolly, " to come smack to the point, wha1t in Jerusalem's the matter with yer old legs, anyway?" "Matter!" exclaimed Oliver, "what do you mean to insinuate, sir?" "Oh,! nothing-nothing at all, sca'cely. I never inquired what was the matter, y' know'! Thort I would, that's all." "Oh! yes," said Oliver, much relieved; and then stooping over, he proceeded to elucidate to Zedekiah that his pedal extremities were "encrusted with stone." "The dickens they be!" said Zed, indignantly; "what! them legs? So's yer old granny' mustard and stone!' Them   THE fHYOCHONDRIAC.         25, legs is as perfect as mine, sir! Can't suck me! Hold on harf a minute; le's see how a knife'll fit on 'em! Dare say it'll turn the edge, quicker'n greased lightnin'-I'll try." And so saying Zedekiah produced a big jack-knife, sharpened to cut a hair. But Oliver stayed him in dismay. "T-t-take care! Please understand that Dr. Foolemall says they must not be. bruised or injured in any manner, lest the immediate petrifaction of the entire body ensue." "Oh, he says it'll en-sue, does he? Wal, I'll resk it--I reckon en-sue don't mean happen-ef it-does, I'll pay damages!" and with this he seized the astonished Ferment by his heels and dragged him out of his chair. Then grasping him by the neck he set him on his feet, and exclaimed- "Wal! Don't en-sue, does it?" "Miraculous preservation!" gasped Oliver. "Miraculous granny!" said Zedekiah, as he retreated from the room, well satisfied with his management. Zedekiah and Oliver had a private little conference next morning, which resulted in the following scene:- About ten o'clock Foolemall visited his patient, and found him standing in the door. "Aw! well-really! I am astonished! I am delighted to see you out this morning. Had not anticipated so pleasant a result for my prescriptions," said Foolemall, with a dolorous ex- pression of would-be congratulation on his face. "Zedekiah," said Oliver, sternly, looking calmly over the head of the quack at the Yankee, as he stood complacently smoothing his hair at the head of the stairway-" show this gentleman into the streets!" 5  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7767-00000017"/> 26        THE H  OOCIOrtAO. The AEsculapian -stammered out a few words of astonishment, but followed the Yankee to the door, and quickly descended the stately steps, assisted in the process by the broad toe of Zedekiah's boot. Time flew. Zedekiah remained with Ferment many months, but one day he told the old bachelor that he must leave him, and return to Vermont without delay. The intelligence was received with deep regret by' Oliver, who tried his best to induce Zedekiah to remain. Finding all' efforts in vain, he turned his attention to devising some means as a substitute for the faithful Yankee ; and he and Zed laid, their wits together, when the following conversation ensued:- "Wal, Mr. Ferment," said Zed, "if I ain't mistook, you know very well what is the cause of all your trouble?" "Yes," responded Oliver, "I suppose I do. It's all imagin- ary, I have. not a doubt, but it's none the worse for that and the hang of it is, I can't help it, unless I have somebody near me-some one in whom I possess confidence-to keep me con- tinually warned. Do you see?" "I du," said Zed, looking intently at the floor, and sliding his pen-knife back and forth in his fingers; "yes, I du see the fact, but no way to get round it; iUnless-unless you can get a good servant." "Exactly! But I etant dobit. They'neimere torments, as a class, and as such I alwaysf'regard them Consequently, I should soon find myself swearing at 'em, if they ventured to remind me of my weakness-and so, you see, I'd slide back." "I see," answered Zed, as he put his thumb aside his nose, apparently engaged in deep thought. "By turnip-tops!" he   THE HYOCHONDRIAC.          27 suddenly exclaimed, springing from his chair, "I've got it!" "You have? Good! What is it?" "It's all in three words, Mr. Ferment, three blessed words- get a wije!" "Ho! ho! ho!" roared Oliver. "Ha! h! ha!" echoed Zed, slapping him familiarly on the back. The advice was followed, dear reader, and-it answered. Oliver Ferment declares that he is now the happiest man that walks the planet called earth.  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7767-00000018"/> OLD LETTERS. I'VE been reading those old letters, Those old letters in the chest, Where I laid them many days agone; And they have filled my breast With many longings, sad and sweet, Which ne'er may be allayed, For the idol of their wishes was Long'since in silence laid In the dark, and lone, and gloomy grave-yard old, 'Mid rank, wild weeds, and grave-stones grim, And earth-clods, clammy cold!       J O, for the scenes those pages bring, To the memory of my soul, When a guileless child, 'mid wildwood's shade, And free from all control, With her I loved as children love I rambled, from the hour When gorgeous Sol the hill-tops crowned Till Luna's silver shower Softly fell o'er earth: and then, with weary feet, We lent our steps their homeward course, In dreams again to meet.   OLD LETTERS.           29 And I have letters here that she Wrote when maturer years Had placed a thrilling in her smile, A melting in her tears; When many virtues sweetly shone Upon her cheerful face, And blushing Venus gave to her Each .winsome, girlish grace That had won the hearts of other lads than I, And waked in other breasts than mine, The lover's deep-drawn sigh. O, light-touched pages, can ye not Bring ter to me once more,   , To gaze on me with those fond eyes, As oft she gazed of yore? To tell me, as her guileless lips Have often frankly told, The deep, warm love that burned for me In the chambers of her soul? No, no-I rave-she sleeps in Death's cold arms, And mould'ring into ghastly dust Are all her girlish charms! I would not weep; but Memory Has shown to me the Past, And opened gates that lead to roads Where I -have trod my last;  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7767-00000019"/> OLD LETTERS. To flowery roads where youthful loves Like wildwood blossoms bloom- But, ah! for me their loveliness Is darkened by a tomb 1 A tomb-a grave-where sleeps my heart's first love, Whose soul has bid adieu to earth, And lives in realms above! -.   BLESSINGTON'S CHOICE. "Be kind to thy mother; for lol on her brow,. May traces of sorrow be seen."-Favorite Melody. "WELL, Blessington, so you've come back to locate with us, have you? Got enough of traveling and all its vexations, I presume?" 4Enough? As you please about that, George-but I find no vexations so weighty as to overcome the pleasures to be en- joyed in travel, by any manner of means. However, I have returned to settle down in my own native land, and my good genius seems to have thrown Tyrol in my way; so here I remain, and have commenced practice as you see-or rather intend to commence, when any business may present itself." "Excuse impertinence, Harry," said the first speaker, with a roguish look, "but-you'll get a wife, I suppose? You know that's an absolute necessity in these days; to say nothing of performing an act of kindness to the scores who are waiting but to be asked." "Well, I am not so certain as to the truth of the last remark; nevertheless, I have some intentions of that nature. By the way, George, can't you introduce me to some of the Tyrol ladies, that I may find a maiden to my liking? You know that I'm a perfect stranger in these parts."  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7767-00000020"/> 32        BTr..STNTGTON 'S CHOICE. "Good!" said George, springing from his chair, and thrusting his thumbs into the arm-holes of his waistcoat. "'Pon honor, I should be delighted to introduce you to some of my lady ac- quaintances. Ahem-! 'Miss Jones, my friend, Mr. Blessington, of-of---'--where' shall it be, Harry? Paris, or London, or New-York, or where? By my troth, Harry, you're the only mortal that I'd give a fig to exchange situations with; but you, with your fortune, your figure, your---" "There! there! George. I declare, I was in hopes you had discarded those old ways of yours. It's exceedingly disagree- able, if you knew it, to be descanted upon in this manner, to one's face. But come, when for those introductions?" "This very night, Harry, If you please. I'll go -with you and call on some of my host of familiar acquaintances. By the way, there's one young lady, Miss Somers, a cousin of mine, who saw you at church last Sabbath, and who wishes to make your acquaintance. And--would you believe it?-she even told me so slyly. Yet there's no great wonder; for a man of your magnificent build-- " But Blessington closed Hart's lips by placing his finger upon them, and together they left the office and disappeared up the street. These two young men were old schoolmates, and were quite familiar in their manner with each other. Blessington had been' traveling in different lands for a couple of years previous, and on his return to the United States had fallen in with his friend, George Hart, some years his junior, and withal a pretty wild, though whole-hearted fellow. Both were quite wealthy, and both of very prepossessing appearance and manners-but Blessington, if either, the more so.   BLESSINGTON'S CHOICE.        33 On the evening of the same day in which we introduce them to you, kind reader, they sallied out as they had agreed. We cannot detail their pleasant evening's ramble; sufice it to say that Blessington was convinced that Tyrol was possessed of as charming ladies, and as kind and hospitable souls, as many other places of greater note. The Miss Somers of whom Hart had spoken, Blessington found to be a lady possessed of com- manding beauty, and a power of conversation he had seldom seen excelled. Accomplished, elegant, and lovely, it may to you appear strange, reader, when we tell you that our hero was not at all prepossessed by her appearance. He saw, or thought he saw, a species of unwomanly pride, a sort of glory- ing in her own attractions, and a scorning of all "lesser lights," that, to a man of his disposition, was anything but pleasing. At another place, however, he saw a lady, who was introduced to him as Miss Ella Cole, who appeared possessed of all those qualities of the heart for which he sought. And, indeed, what beauty there was in her expressive features owed its existence to the genuine artlessness, affection and sincerity shadowed forth in each particular lineament. Young Hart was not slow to observe that Blessington appeared inclined more strongly to "tarry yet a little" at this place than at any other during the entire evening. That night Blessington had a dream, in which certain mild, loving blue eyes, light, sunny ringlets, and a petite figure bore no insignificant part. There was another, too, whose ruby lips seemed to curl contemptuously towards the meek one, and whose piercing black eyes seemed to flash down upon her the fires of hatred. 5  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7767-00000021"/> 34        BLESSINGTON' CHOICE. Some days after, Blessington met Miss Somers at a soiree at the mansion of Colonel Aubert, and she appeared delighted to see him. Blessington, in the nobility and generosity of his heart, was equally pleased at meeting her, and early solicited the honor of her hand for the quadrille. A thrill of pleasurable emotion ran through the proud beauty's breast as Blessington took her hand in his to lead her upon the floor, and thus the finishing stroke was put to the work that rent from Flora Somers her proud heart, and placed it in Blessington's posses- sion-he all unconscious of the precious treasure he had obtained, and with his own safe in the place that God ordained for it. O, ye that speak of the folly of prating of woman's wiles, know ye that when she determines, with her whole soul, to win a heart, it is twenty to one that, in spite of all human obstacles, she will accomplish her purpose. This was the spirit now roused in Miss Somers' proud bosom. She saw, with her apt intelli- gence, the state of Blessington's feelings with regard to her, and she resolved that, come what would, she would obtain from him that which alone could content her ambitious soul-his unbounded affections. Did she succeed? You shall see. From that hour forth a change was noticed in the entire de- portment of Flora Somers, and many were the conjectures as to what might be the cause thereof; but all were equally distant from the truth. Her haughty bearing in society had yielded to one of apparent humility, kindness, and a -desire 'to gratify those around her. Blessington noticed it, and, far from sup- posing the real truth, he concluded that such was her natural disposition, and that his first impressions were the result of   BLESSINGTON'S CHOICE.        35 some unaccountable state of his mind at the time of his introduction to her. However this might be, it was observed that his visits at Dr. Somers' were of frequent occurrence, and soon every gossip of Tyrol had another match in her eye. Few doubted that Flora Somers would eventually be Mrs. Blessington. And if our hero had been interrogated upon the subject, his replies-if he gave any-would not have been greatly at variance with this belief. Might a peep have been taken behind the parlor curtains of Dr. Somers's mansion, on the occasion of some of these calls, one might have seen how "Soft eyes looked love to eyes that spake again." Thus matters stood. You who have passed the ordeal of love, and are now roam- ing in the fair fields of Hymen, can imagine what were Harry Blessington's intentions and Flora Somers' expectations,- while you who have only read of such things, must content yourself with the testimony of the initiated. Thus matters stood. One evening Blessington had sallied out for recreation rather earlier than was his wont, and was on his way to Dr. Somers', intending at once to make known his intentions to the " most adorable of her sex," and be consigned to " everlasting misery" or the supremacy of bliss," as she should decide. He reached the door, and had laid his hand on the bell knob, when he heard a voice sharply enunciating words that struck a chill to his heart's cord, but whose pronouncer's voice sounded terribly like that of Miss Somers. He paused and listened.  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7767-00000022"/> 36        BLESSINGTONS qHOICE. "Well, mind your own business!" was the exclamation that greeted his ear from within, and in a voice which there was no mistaking. "Flora!" reproachfully murmured the gentle voice of Mrs. Somers. And then followed the doctor with- "My daughter, are you never to desist from your unfeeling disregard of a mother's love? Are you never to repay, even by respect and kindness, the anxiety and devotion with Which she watched over your earlier years? It wounds me deeply that a daughter of mine should persist in thus treating one who loves her as no other being on earth ever can. Qo to your room, Flora, and remain until you will ask your mother's for- giveness." The hall door was then closed with a bang, and Blessington heard the foot of- his heart's beloved ascending the stairway. He tarried no longer, but turned away, and hastily retraced his steps to his office. Locking the door behind him, he threw himself into a chair, and from the bitter emotions of his soul, exclaimed- "My God, what have I heard! Can it be that my own dear Flora is possessed of a heart like this? Though I tear the cords of my soul in shreds, I never will take to my bosom one who can thus treat her mother. Spirit of my sainted mother- idol of all my earthly dreams-never will I forsake the vow I plighted over your corpse!" Bowing his head sadly upon his hands, Harry Blessington be- came lost in the memories of the past. Hallowed associations arose to his view, and passed in solemn retrospect before his i mind. He thought of his boyhood's days-of the old stone   BLESSINGTON'S CHOICE.        37 mansion that stood in the leafy grove-of the happy hours he had spent in those ancient halls; and he murmured a grateful prayer to Heaven, thanking his Maker for thus revealing to him the yawning abyss into which he had been about to plunge. After this came a calmness and capacity for deliberation, that ere long recalled to his mind recollections of Ella Cole - she who, months ago, had appeared so attractive to him. As it was yet early, he sallied out, and a few minutes' walk found him at the door of the humble brick dwelling at the foot of the main street in the village, where Mr. Cole had long lived and  pursued his honest calling. As he was about to ring, his hand was again arrested by the sound of a female voice-not in a . loud tone, but softly, lowly, like the murmuring of distant mu- sic. It was Ella Cole, reading a tale to her mother, who was listening with earnest attention. "Ella, my dear girl," called a manly voice from an adjoining room, " will you please bring me the last number of the&amp; 'Liv- ing Age?' It is on the parlor table." "Yes, father," said Ella, springing up. "Excuse me a mo- ment, mother." "Be quick, dear," was the mother's reply. Light footsteps were heard tripping over the floor, and soon was heard again the voice of the sweet girl reading to her mother.  Blessington could not resist comparing this scene with that of the hour previous. Being reluctant to intrude on the happy circle, he again retired and sought his office, but with far different feelings from those which had but just before dwelt in his breast*  &#xD;<pb n="38" xml:id="VAC7767-00000023"/> 38        BLESSIGTOWNIS CItOICE. He called the next evening, and was more than ever convinced of the good qualities of Ella Cole's heart. She remained Ella Cole not long thereafter, but now rejoices in the name of Blessington, and proves a source of unceasing happiness to her worthy husband. Many wondered at this marriage, and none more so than the two ladies most intimately concerned. Harry Blessington is not the only one in the human family who regards a mother in the light nearer approaching an angel than any other mortal: nor the only one who knows that in the degree which a girl is a good daughter, in the same degree will she be a good wife.    &#xD;<pb n=" (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7767-00000024"/> It was Sunndaye-he wendydd his waye to ye churche. ( Page 38.      &#xD;<pb n="-39" xml:id="VAC7767-00000025"/> Ye  Mournfulie Tayle of ye   Collar. I. Now. all ye younge menne, pray attende to my tayle, For feare to drawe tears from yr eyes it sd faile, And e'en now let mee warne you -olde, younge, large and smalle, O! bewayre, leste yr collar is too stiffe or too talle! II. There was once a younge manne who hys name I'lle notte stayte, Who mette, by his collar, a horribell fayte! It was Sundayye: he wenndyd his waye to ye churche, And hymsellfe on a seat in playne view he did perche. "I. Nowe atte ye same churche this younge manne dyd attende, ye good pastor's sermonnes you wd thynke hadde no ende, For sowe he ranne onne wythe hys tedious droane, Verye few keppt awayke untille yt hee was donne. IV. This younge manne, who hys collar was starchyde sowe stifflye Preserved bys uprightenesse till ye olde manne reached "5the;" "1    &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7767-00000026"/> 40          THE COLLAR. Atte "6the" his hedde, now awearye, dydde shayke; At "7thiie" with greate efforte he stylle keppt awayke. V. At " the " he commencyd to nodde, it appeares, And hys collar-oh, horrore!-atte eache nodde, cutte hys eares! Hee, unknowinge, stylle noddyd, thof ye duce was to paye, And hys collar, unyieldinge, it still dugge awaye! VI. Lo! atte " 6the , ye collar shot through lyke a rockette, And hys eares, severed cleanlie, droppit in eache coate pockette! And nowe tayke advyse, iffe you wille notte bee cured: Iffe you weare standynge collars, gette yr eares sayfe ensured!   WHEN MY 1AIR ISm GROWING WHTE. FRIENDS about iy pathway cluster, And their pledges oft renew, Yet I sometimes, musing, wonder, If they always will be true,- : If-when I am growing older, When youthiadeAth from' my ight- They will dall epart- j,  rfi the -, When my hir is growing w   e?  Love now sits upon my threshold, Guarding every nook with care, Lest some messenger of evil Come to sting the treasures there. O, as age descends upon me, And I feel the coming night, Will Love still watch o'er my threshold, When my hair is growing white? Now my home contains three treasures, e Daughter, son, and gentle wife, And they are to me so precious! Making light the load of Life. 6  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7767-00000027"/> 42     WHEN MY HAIR IS GROWING WHiTE. Years are rolling into chaos, Soon will dim the vision bright, Shall I still possess my treasures, When my hair is growing white? Blessed- hope! each day -'tis brighter, As I mark the gliding year,. And my heart grows light and lighter, As the Future draweth near! GOD, Who watcheth kindly o'er us,. If 'ti -blessed 'm Thy sight, Save and guard my household treasures, Till my hair is growing white!   T'HE FORTUNE HUNTER. SHADRALCH SitL wILESS was one of those deluded individuals who are always on the look-out for a legacy from some un- known and un-heard-of rich relation, an accidental -" freak of fortune," or some wonderful discovery of hidden ingots of gold, pots of piratical plunder or miserly hoarding-the which should result in coffers-overflowing with wealth, without subjecting its owner to toil in its accumulation. He had apprenticed himself successively to a baker, a tinner, a shoemaker, a clothes-cleaner and a saddler; had undertaken the study of medicine with Dr.. Cathartic; -had entered the office of lawyer Pinchgrip, and been discharged for refusing to clean the spittoon and sweep out o' mornings; had measured tape a short time behind the dry-goods merehant's counter; had peddled books out of a tin box; . had studied daguerreotyping; had taken -seven different excursions to places pointed 'out to him by mysterious dreams, on bootless errands after buried money-chests; and'was now, at the time this narrative opens, porter and mau-of-all-work for the villageltavern at Shawhurgh. In his earlier years, as, vera- cious Shawhurgher's relate, Shadrach, while a, bnker'8 boy, had" fequently manifested 'a tact for painting; but, having been sent with ia couple of' loaves to a purchaser, one day, he paused on his errand to execute a figure of- a peculiar nature on a stone walU, this he did so much to his own intense de-  &#xD;<pb n="44" xml:id="VAC7767-00000028"/> THE FORTUNE HUNTER.   light, that in his glee at contemplating it, he pitched the loaves, one after the other, over the wall, then chucked his hat after the loaves, and began to - execute . Virginia bre4kdown on the sidewalk. This little eccentricity cost the juvenile Shadrach such a drubbing, that it drubbed all his taste for art entirely out of him, and he never lifted pencil, brush nor chalk since. SWrgti N   been S daP-s " tative p ple,"f a 4 on, for twr!ty ye!rs,!Ugh being the length Qf hi' Sojeurp on e art] at k time oQ which I write 0., Op nning,i, N vemb, a r,4 etd te h . arr ro ,. where Shadch ws ^lumbe rin$g ' ,r: a, b g.n .te ing to: the wal ilaaarig bill, Mano-. -i, g     ,"4z E iti  - "Cotwnl'ation of ta4lfntt '"?eti s. wlvig tiews," ind lWtr ordinary. and L4a  r !.b^q it of Ventrilotuss i"T' i tapping of the tckia- Cgkp ,r snoing; hero, whQlazily turnae his eyes on thi *wi4 and after a satisfactory -urvey opf that persqoa ge ^,s a^d sau ttred up toq thee scene of action with hia bwd 't 'is: b^,.che$s, pketq. H e then fell to, reading the sme, fr t irh he lat4 I that the sttp. ndous eastalish mtent would. w   t .i tt!e qaoua dining-hall of the, Shawhugh hotel,Q o ti eve pil of the cponing Thanksgiving-day. Shadrach ws iJ ,sscel t the anticipated glory he should. enjoy as4 dpoop t1Q.^nr ln c$ nittep. of arranggeents, by virtue of his posit'i. as, ,9tr, *ap W ie.!y concluded. tp prolong. his stay athe tept^ er u,^t 3e nmexorble event, transpired., sh-,vin     n   , sodi4 the eibo; t exhiJ iWd, .athl lStw urghisflockd- tot bebold; it, departed* an4 -         .sa,; hi},esse it i e had received the iaget "O&amp; tow,9 do1l1, a week, en   his travelitgqp ,p,    "  &#xD;<pb n=" (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7767-00000029"/> In his glee at contemplating it, he pitched the loaves, one after the other, over the wall, then chucked his hat after the loaves, and began to execute a Virginia break-down on the sidewalk.                (Page 44.)   I  &#xD;<pb n="-45" xml:id="VAC7767-00000030"/> TIME ORruxid aufw  .        4g If he would accept the position of organ-grinder to the 'exhibi- tion; and he accepted. Shadrach now saw his way clearly-quite sou In his peram- bulations about the country, he should hit upon his long looked- for discovery, by which his pockets should be filled, and his hands freed from irksome labor all the rest of his days. He was confident that the road to wealth was now open before him, and . "Hope told a flattering tale" of pots of money in underground caverns, to which the wizard wand of some good genius should guide him. Shadrach found his new occupation dull work. His vanity was not long gratified by the curious stares of the urchins on the. front seats, as he entered the hall, hat in hand, on tip toe, and disappeared behind the mysterious green curtain; it soon became an old story. And when there, he had to lean against the wall and grind out melodious sounds for two hours on a stretch, to keep the sleepy audience awake during the. drowsy transpositions of the magical paintings. It was dulI, and he begaza to think of changing his occupation., But no! for onee he was settled. His "  one idea" had completely gained ascen- dency over the promptings of his laziness, and he could not tear. himself away from his organ with its two. dollars and trav- eling expenses. The expectation of. "his luck," as he called it,. had settled down into a firm conviction that e ery mile he traveled, brought him nearer to the realization of his dreams. He grew- morose and crabbed,- brooding over his continued dis- appointments; his cadaverous countenance lengthened daily,; aadahisieyes glared axiously on every one he saw, as though  &#xD;<pb n="46" xml:id="VAC7767-00000031"/> TR  I FORETU=E UUJTiF   he expected to be saluted and directed where lay his " luck."' But in vain; he found it not. At the taverns where he stopped during the perambulations of the exhibition, he had been in the habit of dropping to sleep in the bar-room during the dill day-times; -or when the humor seized him, sauntering lazily about the streets in search of his ': luck." But he soon fell into theohabit, instead there- of, of perusing the newspapers on the bar-room table, and his eyes glistened eagerly whenever he lit on one of those marvel-" ous items called "Freaks of Fortune," relating how some poor devil suddenly became rich. However, his own name never appeared. One afternoon, he had pitched his tent in a small town on the line of one of our great railroads, which railroad came to a termination inNew-York city. Looking over the advertise- ments of 'the great dailies, he found one reading thus: FORTUNE TFTNG. - Madame OSOMYDDTH, the celebrated -Jewlsh. Fortune-tellei, is holding her soirees at No. -- Broad- way, where she will be happy to meet any who may favor her with a call, and will reveal to them how they may form agreeable matrimo"- nial alliances; where favored individuals may find fortunes, their future destiny, &amp;c. Terms, five dollars. "That's -it!" exclaimed Shadrach, as a broad grin of intens-. est delight spread over his countenance, changing his usually solemn phiz 'into one of such magical brightness that those who. saw him thought he had gone crazy-especially when he seized a slumbering gentleman's spectacles from his nose, and with the paper in his other hand, commenced madly to execute his youthful favorite, the. Virginia breakdown. "Found at last! Mine, mine, mine! I'm in I  Ha!. ha!" and crushing the  &#xD;<pb n=" (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7767-00000032"/> "('That's it " exclaimed Shadrach, as a broad grin of - "That's it!" exolaimed Shadrach, as a broad grin of inten- sest delight spread over his countenance, changing his usually solemn phiz into one of such magical brightness that those who saw him thought he had gone crazy--especially when he seized a slumbering gentleman's spectacles from his nose, and, with the paper in the other hand, began executing his youthful favorite, the Virginia breakdown.      (Page 46.)    &#xD;<pb n="Illustration" xml:id="VAC7767-00000033"/> "MON DIB I Vat for you ill, go avay, Mr. Sheefless?- Aye I not pay your salary regular?"    ( Page 47.)    &#xD;<pb n="-47" xml:id="VAC7767-00000034"/>  THE FORTUME HUNTER.   newspaper into his old and napless hat, he rushed into the street with a burst of hysterical cachinnation, and sought his employer, the proprietor of the exhibition. Come to say good-bye to you, Mr. Trompeur; would thank you for the two dollars due; a sudden call to New-York city; will grind my farewell strain this night." Monsieur Trompeur was thunderstruck. "Mon Dieu! Vat for you will go avay, Mr. Sheefless? 'Ave I not pay your salary regulair? Vas de--" "'S no matter, Trompeur," said Shadrach, with increasing pomposity, " my reasons is good ones; and when you sees the announcement of my adventures in the papersthen you won't wonder no more. Pay me what y' owe me, and I'll grind to-. night. Otherwise--"  "Eh bien! ze pay is ra-ady, sans doute-oui, certainement; here is ze two dollare; let me express ze little hope, Monsieur Sheefless, that you will not go avay; vous avez ze good situa- tion, ze salarie munificente,- ze kind employaire, and oh! c'est charmante! ze travailing expense paid in ze bargaine! Vous vill not leave me-vous voulez avec me restir-mon cher Shadrach; ze- language is not so full of ze mots grand pour expresser ze attachment, ze affectione, l'amour excessivement, that I 'ave become involve in vid you, so long et so faithful mon valet de compagnon. It grieve me much to part vid you; mais vous voulez act your own plaisir." "Yes, sir," said Shadrach, obediently, as he received his two dollars. That night the tedium of grinding was relieved by the thoughts of freedom to-morrow, and wealth in the distance; and when the morning dawned, Shadrach was on hand for the   t; 47.  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7767-00000035"/> 48        THl FORTUNE trNTER. train; bright and early, And never bore locomotive suth a "countenance of destiny," as did that identical "morning run " in the eyes of our, hero, as it came snorting and shrieking through the tunnel opposite where Shadrach waited. He took. his seat ina car with a ticket for New-York. He had fifty doli lars in his pocket, the savings of a year's grinding, and he felt independent, though he looked like the ghost of an old-clothes man, with his sunken cheeks, blear eyes, and outre garments- the donations of landlords, bar-tenders and hostlers. The train reached its destination, and Shadrach found him- self amid the bustle and- tumult of the great metropolis. It was yet early in the day, andaShadrach determined to find the fortune-teller at once; but the next thing -was to put' the determination into execution-not so easily accomplished, however. He knew- not what portion of the city he was now in; but he(felt confident that he should-know Broadway, wh6ei he saw it, from its width; anld he was sure he should hit upm it some time in the day, if he kept walking about. He knw6 altogether -too much to ask his way of anybody-for he haA heard of New-York before, and had his " eyes well skinned for sharpers." With all the buoyancy he was capable of, he began his tramp; but the descending shades of night fbund him still tramping, and Broadway's wide domain still to be discovered. Hunger pressed,- and he entered a hotel and called for Supper. Here we leave him to pursue his. blundering, way unmolested, and'-beg leave to transport the reader to the reading-room of the ." St. Nieholas" and introduce' hhim to two elderly ge6itle- men, who are engaged in a tete-a-tete by themselves. - Do you live in Shawhurgh yet, Mr. Bradley," said one of   THE FORTUNE HUNTER.         49 the gentlemen, who wore a pair-of gold-rimmed- spectacles. "Yes," said Mr. Bradley, "I still live there; but I have removed from the residence I occupied. when you were my neighbor" "Indeed!" "Yes, I have purchased the estate of Colonel Guiteau, and live upon it now." "What! that old castle! Why, there was such an odium attaching to it I should think that you would dislike to go there." "Yes," said Mr. Bradley, "I know there had been some foolish superstitions clinging to it; but common sense has nothing to do with ghost stories, and I cared not a whit whether it was considered haunted or not, so long as there was a chance for speculation. I got it for a small sum, compared with itg real worth, and can sell it for quadruple what it cost me, including all subsequent expense."  "But it was a mere rookery-the house; and the grounds were over-run with tangled weeds, brush-heaps and dead trees." "-The house was much better than was commonly supposed, Mr. Bower; and a slight application of the magic wand -of a carpenter and joiner on its haunted beams, added to a moder- ate exercise of the stone-mason's subtle arts, has rendered it a beautiful aud - substantial mansion, bearing a wonderfully modern look, when you remember its antecedents. Then the grounds readily yielded under the labors of myself and men, and I: have laid them out with spacious paths and avenues, with large and. beautiful plats between, bountifully covered -with flowers, which my wife and daughters delight in tending."  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7767-00000036"/> St)50      THE FORTUNE HUNTER.. "But that mysterious old well, Mr. Bradley, that was said to have been the scene of young Madeline's death. I should think that it would cause a sort of gloom to rest upon your place." "But you forget, Mr. Bower, that that too is susceptible to change." "Why, yes, to be sure! What have you done with it?" "Do you remember that large, flat stone that barred the en- trance-gate to the grounds?" "I do." "Well, sir, that stone covers the well; and above it is erected as beautiful a Summer-house as you would wish to see." "Well, ha-! ha! that was fine, indeed!' But you had some distance to carry the stone, did you not?" "Oh, no, not any serious distance. It is but fifteen or twenty yards from the gate to the well, and a pair of stout horses dragged it that distance easily." "'Well, truly," said Mr. Bower, smilingly, "it must be you have -apleasant place there.; I declare, I must visit you some time this Winter." (So do,; we will be delighted to see you. We have a fine prospect from the windows of the east tower, looking out upon the river at the east, and down upon the village at 'the west- for the mansion stands upon a hill, you remember?" "Yes, I remember it perfectly," said the other. The conversation now turned upon the price of lands in the region of Shawhurgh, and we, caring nothing about that, will take our leave, and return to our friend Shadrach, who, is now   THE FORTUNE HUNTER.         51 in the arms of sleep, snoring away the anxieties and fatigues of the day. In the morning he inquired at the office as to where Broad- way might be located, and was told that the street was but a few steps from him. "Just get into that 'bus that is passing, and they'll set you down where you wish, sir." Shadrach was not exactly satisfied, but suffered himself to be seduced into the omnibus, where he sat in silence and deep meditation until at last he reached No.--, the residence of Madame Schmyddthe. The heart of Shadrach Shiftless now began to thump in his waistcoat in a manner that was rather alarming. The " crisis" had come, and his strength almost failed as he thought of what was before him; but summoning all his courage, he pulled the bell and was admitted. A servant demanded the five dollars fee, which Shadrach paid without a question, when he was in- stantly admitted into the reception room of the Jewess. The sun's rays were completely excluded, and the pitchy darkness was rendered still more profound by one dim lamp that flicker- ed in gloomy silence alone on a table at the remote end of the room. Shadrach fell on his knees in awe as he felt himself alone amid the ghostly silence of -that mysterious place, and he inwardly cursed his rashness in having ventured to enter; he reflected that at a stroke from some unseen wizard hand his head might be severed from his body, and the world would never miss him, nor his whereabouts ever be inquired of. Sud- denly a bell was heard booming in the distance in a hollow, muffled tone, and sounding like a knell of death; it slowly and gradually increased -in loudness, growingsmore and more  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7767-00000037"/> 12- :      THE FORTUNE HUNTER. audible, until its boom! boom,! boom! rang like ten thousand judgment trumps on the shrinking ear of the poor fortune- hunter, and swelled, and throbbed, and reverberated in stunning cadence from wall to wall, as the affrighted man fell prostrate on his face; now the clanging clamor grew milder-the loud- ness gradually decreased in power-the tone died mournfully away-until at last the boom! boom! boom! became inaudible. A voice rang through the room like a bugle-blast, exclaiming- "Who comes to inquire 'of the dim, mysterious future, and test the skill of the Jewess from the Holy Land?" Shadrach started to his feet, and gazed in terror and with quaking limbs, into the thick gloom around him, but answered not. "Thy name, mortal!" demanded the voice again. Shadrach felt that he must reply, and with cold, clammy sweat in beads on his forehead, stammered- - "Sha-Shadrach Sh-Shiftless." "Whence comest thou? and where wert thou born?" "Come from all over the country. Born in Shawhurgh!" replied Shadrach. "Thy age?" "Goin' on twenty-nine," sung out Shadrach. "What seekest thou?" "A pot o' money, or su'thin' of that nater!" "Enough!" again rang out the bugle voice; and the single light was extinguished. Horror now seized on our hero; he felt a qualm creeping over him like a living thing; he shuddered in terror, and would have ran, but his limbs were powerless as in a dream;   THE FORTUNE HUNTEE  .       53 he began to mutter an old prayer his mother had taught him, "Now I lay me"-when suddenly he was startled by a loud, and stunning, hissing noise, resembling the escaping of steam. Then the gas-lamps burst forth with a brilliant glare, and, as soon as Shadrach could rub the mist from his eyes, he beheld, standing on a pedestal at the far end of the room, a figure clothed in glittering garments, and with her right hand extending a golden wand. Her hair lay wildly about her bare shoulders, and she beckoned the stranger to advance and kneel before her. lie obeyed, and with renewed awe witnessed the beautiful being pour incense from a phial upon a fire which burned before her in a silver censer, muttering inaudibly as she did so. At length she began her revelations. "Mortal," said she, in a silvery voice, "tthy name is Shadrach-.thou wert born in Shawhnrgh-past a score of years ago--and thou seekest a fortune." "Wal, I swum," whispered the astonished Shadrach, ,u she's right there, anyhow!" "The stars are propitious to-night," said the Jewess; "thy desire shall be thine, and wealth shall gleam "before thy glad- dened eyes. Know, then, that in thy native place there stands a ruined castle, where years agone lived a noble colonel, called by men,' Guiteau,' and that, in the desolate garden surrounding this mansion, there is hidden, 'neath a massive stone, a chest with many dollars in gold and silver, placed there by one who lew sweet Madeline, a maiden fair and lovely, and beautiful to 'ehold. Go, then, mortal, and follow my directions that thou   i layest gain for thyself this gold. But first, O privileged item f frail humanity, to propriate the genii, thou must place upon his pedestal ten golden dollars."  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7767-00000038"/> THE FORTUNE HUNTE.  'Whew!" was Shadrach's involuntary ejaculation; but as the vision of the buried money-chest danced enchantingly before his eyes, his hand sought his purse, and the gold eagle came forth. , Shadrach," then resumed the woman," take up thy t and proceed to the place of thy birth; travel only by night, and shield thyseand nd sleep by day, for if the sun's rays fall upon thee in thy journey, then is the power I now give thee of no avail; enter thy native village and advance up the hill whereon stands the castle of Col. Guiteau, and, leaping the gate that guards the entrance to the grounds, proceed in thy path for twenty yards until thou shalt reach a light an4 fragile house, o'erwreathed with leafless vines; though now the path is obstructed by the tangled weeds of long neglect, fear not, O Shadrach blest, for by my magic power the path for thee is free! Within this light and fragile house, kneel humbly, and with thy spade remove the earth away. Not long wilt thou labor ere thou shalt reach the level stone 'neath which the treasure lies; then labor on, remove the stone, and seize thy precious prize! I have done! Farewell!" Darkness returned; a hand seized that of the awe-struck man, and he suffered himself to be led to the door like a child and ushered into the street. Shadrach took long strides for the railroad depot, and left in the first train in the direction of Shawhurgh. As he rattled on he had leisure to think over what had passed, and O how he hugged himself for joy, and gleefully contemplated the delicious vision of wealth before him The words of the Jewess were received as gospel, -and not a shadow of doubt lingered in his         .           .  .  .   THtE FORTUNE HUNTER.        5 mind in relation to his good fortune; he cogitated on the'very minute nature of her instructions to him; and resolved to follow them out to the letter. "I swum!" he suddenly exclaimed, "I've broke one of 'em a'ready." '"Have you?" said a passenger, whom the exclamation had startled from a doze; (" did it hurt you much?" "Eh?" dreamily answered Shadrach. "Oh!" and the man dropped off to sleep. Leaving our hero to make amends for his first transgression as best he can, and to pursue his nightly journey alone, let us make an explanation touching the prophetic knowledge of the veracious Madame Schmyddthe. You will remember, reader, the conversation in the reading room of the St. Nicholas. If we had observed closely, we might have seen, sitting near the conversers, a business-like appearing man, who with -a pencil seemed to be cyphering out some perplexing question in a memorandum book. Looking over his shoulder, we read as follows: "Shawhurgh-Col. Guiteau-large castle-house on a hill-well, covered with a flat stone-twenty yards from gate- summer-house over spot," &amp;c., &amp;c. Reader, this man was not a newspaper reporter; he was the fortune-teller's pimp. The lights blazed merrily in the mansion of the respected Mr. Bradley, and the guests gathered in the great old parlors, both the rosy faces of youthful mirth and the more placid dames -of demurer years, bent on having a rousing, romping, real old- fashioned Christmas party. Among the guests we perceive the  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7767-00000039"/> 6        TTHE FORTUNE HUNTER good-humored phiz of our old friend of the St. Nicholas, Mr. Bower, who, the reader will recollect, had promised to visit the Bradleys. ,It was cold and stormy without. The wind whistled around the old walls, and rattled madly at the mullioned windows; while a blinding snow-storm rendered it impossible for one out- side to perceive through its dense mass even the lights that gleamed through the diamond-shaped panes. The evening passed in the mirthful, happy style of all such gatherings in country homes; with games of divers names, which owed their chief interest to the number of kisses with which they were in- terlarded; and friend Bower more than once found himself at the point of being smothered by a bevy of laughing girls, by whom he was "judged" to be attacked en masse. "Oh! Mr. Bower!" "Ha! ha! ha!"  "How you blush, Mr. Bower!" (as though his red, face could be made to blush a deeper red!) "t How timid you are, Mr. Bower!" (as though a man could be aught save timid, under such an 9onslaught!).  The reader may never have beeni a guest at a Christnas party in:a country town ; if so, it will be difficult to conceive of the genial joy exhibited on such occasions. Old mnn and matrons seize this annual festal day to doff the gravity of years, and mingle in the games with a gusto which the remembrance of by-gone days and youthful mirth excite with vivid powers. Mrs. Bradley (fat old soul!)toddled around after friend Bower in "Wink 'em slily," with her glowing cheeks suffused with tears of laughter; while Bower, wig all askew, pulled the circle hither and thither in his frantic efforts to elude the dame, con- gtatulating himself on the youthful sprightliness he displayed, and thinking he never was so simple before.   THE FORTUNE HUNTER.        57 Be Wr w 1, oh. ye denizens of cities! for the honest joys Hait a  Yppy rralUity knows can never be yours. The costly 4rappings and gilded gewgaws that deck your polished drswing ToOoms; the slksand sntins that rustle through the .mazes of tthdance; the diamonds and paste, the gold and glitter that gleam on the studied costumes of your rouged belles; all are Unsaemly attendants on the honest mirthfulness that lights the rural hearthstone, and brightens the rural hall. But go, if you will, among the people that the country village knows, and it will need no long sojourn to introduce you to the hearts and hospitalities of the lads and lasses that laugh the time away in Christmasparties like the one we chronicle. 'wames of divers names, and pastimes of every sort, though of but one character, lent the hours wings with which their flight into the past was rapid and unnoted. There was the in- dispensable mock-marriage, too, in which Mr. Bower was the groom, and little Carrie Bradley the bride; and the .tiny ".twelv-year o-d" and the burly bachelor were joined in holy w edlopk-J oe Loomis acting the priest, and winding up the solemn ceremony with an emphatic "over the left!" Howev- e,. the bride was kissed, and kindly congratulations exchanged on all hands. Tine passed. The old clock in the corner pealed eleven. The guests were -gathered .about the great old fire-place, where tke huge 10ogs of wood hissed and crackled before them, and the flames -went merrily roaring up the chimney. The nut- hhs And apple-paings-relics of the late onslaught--had all heen arried aw-ay. .Jokes were gradually getting less lively, anl dpowwjaess began to creep over the weary eye-lids of the 8  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7767-00000040"/> 5,8;       THE FORTUNE HUNTER. guests;, but they fell to talking by couples as they sat-and ere long each was busily immersed in a conversation with. his neighbor. Joe Loomis was conversing about the mock-mar- riage, with Ida Brown-thought real marriages were much more reasonable. So did she. - Jeannette Rose and Frank Temple- ton were turning over the leaves of a book of engravings, and passing comments upon them.  Frank liked the picture of "the girls" best, while Jeannette modestly preferred "scenery and such." Alice Willis and Edward Engham were earnestly discussing the question whether Mr. Bower's snuff-colored coat, or Charley's blue, with its brass buttons, was prettiest. While Mr. Bower himself was conversing with Mr. Bradley in regard to the old superstition that clung round the house. From this the conversation turned upon ghosts, ghouls, goblins, and spir- its in general. The dispute became very animated, and with increasing fervor came increasing loudness of tone, untill soon all the guests had ceased talking, and were eagerly listening to the disputants. As the discussion grew less earnest and final- ly ceased altogether, nothing would do but some hobgoblin tale. "A ghost story!" said Jeannette. "Yes, a ghost story! a ghost story!" was caught and reit- erated by all. And ghost storiest were told. With that monotonous, sol- emn drone, that the most interesting retailers of the horrible delight in, the dreary tales were spinned out, until the listen- ers began to start at the tapping of the wind on the pane; un- til the lasses shrunk closer to the lads, as if expecting protection from them; until the. stroke of the clock-hammer that told the mystic hour of midnight, sent a thrill through the frames of the timid.   THE FORTtsi? HUfEll.        59 "Tell us the story of Madeline, Mr. Bradley," requested some one. Oh, I would rather some one else would do it for me. Re- ally, I cannot do the narrative any degree of justice, for the romance of it has been wholly driven out. of my head by the familiarity of its scenes with the music of the saw and the jackplane, which I have introduced here. Still, if you insist upon its H" "Yes, yes, you must tell it. No one else knows it so well," said Mr. Bower. "Well, as the story runs, there formerly lived on these grounds, in this mansion, a Col. Guiteau, who then owned all the lands hereabouts, on which Shawhurgh has grown into ex- istence. It seems this Col. Guiteau had professedly lived here many years; but with his domain under the superintendence of an agent, had really spent a great part of his time traveling in Europe-returning occasionally. One Summer he brought with him a maiden said to have been surpassingly lovely. She seemed to be very melancholy and sad-always strolling much alone through the great groves about, and often bursting into sudden and violent weeping. It was supposed that some deep - sorrow-blighted love or remorse-was preying at her heart- many accrediting it to her alliance with the old colonel; but she could never be led into conversation. If she was address- ed in a kind and sympathetic tone she would murmur some Italian sentence, burst into tears, and move hastily away.-- During the day she did little else than sigh and weep, but it was noticed that when the colonel returned at night she met him with calmness, and sometimes even with a cheerful smile.  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7767-00000041"/> 60'       THE FORTUNE HUNTEI. Her favorite retreat was at the brink of the old well that lay in the garden just below the aviary, where, kneeling on the turf, she would. gaze into its depths for hours. At length, one night, she was gone. The colonel caused the woods and sur. rounding country to be scoured, in vain; until at length attention was turned to the old well, and in it was foundi he beautiful maid wrapt in the sleep of death., Many yea. passe ed; the colonel followed his young bride to the laud beyend the skies; the mansion was fast decaying.; and foolish storis were abroad that the place was haunted-that through- thete rooms where we now sit the ghost of the beautiful Madeline wandered wildly up and down, or hovered over the brink of the old well, singing mournful songs above her watery grave." It was not long after this that one intimated the lateness of the hour and the propriety of departure Then they bundled into their mammoth sleigh at the door, and soon were moving down the avenue leading to the roadside gate. They were not so lively as is commonly the case with sleigh-loads of young people, and the dreary tales they had been harking to had east a feeling of gloominess over them that would not yield to mer- riment. One of the bravest made a faint attempt at a whistle, but gave it up as a vain thing. Suddenly the sleigh stopped. Joe Loomis stuck his head out and inquired what had broke? "Broke!" said the negro driver, ;' by gorry! I dunno whalt broke; but demo ar bosses has got frit about suthen. Hark! Dar! Hr dat ar! By gorry! wonder what dem be!" Joe sprang out, followed by the rest of the boys, and ran   THEE FOawUN. lTUI'1j'j'.      6i fOward'; whena they distiactly hear&amp;a groanafronmthe Summero houfe, beneath whick Jwe knew wa&amp; the old well; They paused. The sound was repeated, louder--,soloud at the girI. heard it and asked what it meant; and when Joe replied, all tremulous with agitation, "Hope I may be hung if it don't come from that old well," one of them fainted, and all were very much alarmed. They returned to the house, and soon succeeded in mustering a party, who sallied forth to the well, properly armed. When they stood in the Summer-house, and heard the shouting that arose from beneath their feet, some were for running back, but were persuaded to remain and unravel the mystery. As the stone was rolled away, and an agonizing groan rose full and audible upon their ears, human nerves could bear no more; light heels took light heads swiftly away, and terror sent the principal portion of the congregated valor scampering furiously up to the house. Mr. Bradley, Mr. Bower, and a domestic, however, were more philosophical, and though they were excessively mys- tified, finally succeeded in hauling forth the woe-begone, despairing phiz of Shadrach Shiftless, and shortly after a pair of heels, surmounted by legs whose owner was either, so nearly frightened to death, or frozen to death, that he trem- bled like an aspen-which said heels no sooner felt terra firma than they assumed their powers of locomotion, and rattled off down the road that led to the village, with a speed that was astonishing to contemplate. Shadrach Shiftless wipes off horses' legs and cleans stables at a hotel in the village of Blandby, at the date of the first publication of this history. He still looks for his "luck" D  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7767-00000042"/> 68 'F     . THP: TOIBTlNNC HUNTER. 62        THE FORT     . with unwavering confidence;; avowing that the only thing which prevented his securing the pot of gold, was his first transgression, in traveling by daylight.   IS'T NOT HAPPY SCENE FOR YOU? WaHEW the moon shines full and round; When the air is cold and clear; When the snow is on the ground, And the ring of bells we hear; When the prancing horses glide O'er the smooth and glittering way; When the cozy fur robes hide Only TWO within the sleigh; Gliding on beneath the stars,  As they wink upon you two, Say, O! loving lad and lass, Is't not happy scene for you? When the brilliant[ hall is gay With the light of chandeliers, Glittering on a bright array Of Columbia's cavaliers; And when beauty gives the scene Glowing cheek and beaming eye,- Music sounding lively strain,- With this scene how few can vie? When 4 fair women and brave men" Thus the yearly fetes renew,  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7767-00000043"/> "    ISIT NOT HAPPY SCENE FOR YOU t Say, ye Terpsichoreans, then Is't not happy scene for you? When the evening shadows fall, And the lamps are lit at home, Glistening on the parlor wall, :Cheerfdilglows the little room)! Welcome then the group of love Gatheing round the -social fire!- Emblem of that Home above, To which the heart's best iopes apire! Beauteous scene of wedded life"! Memory's canvass throbs anew! Smiling children, gentle wife, Is't not happy scene for you?   THE LITTLE SINGER. *. * * ONE Sunday evening, Fitz Morner happened to drop in at one of the churches at an early hour. He was not over steady in his attendance at any particular church, for he' thought he might profit as greatly by the enjoyment of variety in this as in other matters-and, therefore, was unaware of the exact character of the meeting. He soon learned. There were but few present, and, according to custom, he appropriated to. himself the inmost corner of one of the pews near the desk. Whether he was sleepy, or "musy," or careless, orwhat, it matters not; but true it is that in the twinkling of a grimal- kin's caudal appendage, he found himself in the midst of a bevy of little girls, who crowded into the seats on all sides with their happy, rosy faces, with their little hymn-books in their hands, and their little eyes sparkling with vivacity.. It was done so quickly, that there was no help for it but to sit' still-if there had been means of escape, he would have seen bliss in ignorance, in the premises, and kept his seat accord- ingly. In a few minutes, the children began singing: "Sweetly sing sweetly sing! Praises to our Heavenly King!" Little girl in striped blue dress and bright eyes, after a slight -display of timidity, extended a tiny book, hesitatingly, as much as to say- "Perhaps you would like to look over, sir r" 9  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7767-00000044"/> "        THE LITTLE SINGER. He took the corner of the little book, while a pleasant glow ran over his countenance, as much as to say-   . ; "Bless your little heart!"-  He attempted to sing. Whether the little girl was unaccus- tomed to hearing the song sung so bass-ly, or whether she thought her companion didn't exactly know the tune, is 'not' recorded ; but certain it is, she paused in her singing to snile, to look curiously up in his face, and then at the little girl next her so queerly!  He sang'no more! The little singer resiumed her praises, and the writer fell into a "brown study," as they say. But it was not exactly brown; that is too sombre.-. Memory went back to the old 8abbath School in the little wooden " session house,"-far away. Fitz Morner was- again a be-collared and be-jacketed ' Sabba' School scholly;" again he sat with his mates on the uneasy wooden bench, with feet dangling in hopeless estrangement from the floor, reciting his seven verses to the sunny-faced teacher ith the light, curly hair; again he was the successful competitor for the prize of good scholarship, and took the wondrous paste-board copy of the ten commandments with a heart full of delight; again he joined in the children's song that rolled heavenward from a hundred little throats; and now-there-in the great church in the great city, he forgot his age, his condition and his whiskers, and became again a scholar. When the Superin- tendent asked the children to rise and sing, and the little girl with the blue dress and bright eyes again offered the book, he arose with the rest and joined in the song. "I'm a pilgrim, and I'm a stranger!" !   THE LITTLE SINGER.        67 sung the children; and he was with them. Whose fault was it that he didn't hear what "the man " said to the scholars?- that is no more than he did years ago, Whose fault was it that he could not see the high pulpit, and the stained windows, and the fretted ceiling-nothing, save that little blue-painted room, far away, with its plain desk, its oaken shutters and white sashes, its dark, square "air-hole" in the ceiling--fraught with storied visions of black cats and "spooks "-and its little, brown table with the green-lined contribution boxes? He was  there; he was listening to the drowsy exposition of the Bible. according to Barnes' Notes; he yawned as of yore, and was about to tell John to nudge Lewis and wake him up,-whea- the congregation arose and dispersed. The fresh air restored his senses, and he wended his way home to dream confusedly of well-thumbed Testaments, marbled-paper library bo'ks, and little singer girls in blue dresses and bright eyes.  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7767-00000045"/> SONG "THE ROSE MONTH." [From ABIADNE, OR THE HSTORY OF A LIFB, an Unpublished Poem.] JUNE, June, the rose-month! Love ye it, my lassie? Laughingly the waves leap on, By their borders grassy! Gentler is their rippling song, Singing through the vales along, Heigho! on they go! Dancing through the rose-month! June, June, the rose-month! Saw ye, love, its coming? Dancing on the scented wind, By bright gardens humming!       L See the zephyrs playing now With the tresses on thy brow! Heigho! on they go! Toying through -the rose-month! June, June, the rose-month 1 Yield to its caresses;   SONG.           69 'Tis the hand of Nature, love, -Toying with thy tresses. Kiss my darling, zephyrs kind; Fan her forehead, loving wind; Heigho! shall I grow Jealous of the rose month? June, June, the rose-month! King of breeze and flower! Wedded to thy rosy queen, Welcome to our bower! Singing through the vales along, Ever&amp; may our loyal song Louder grow, love, "Heigho! The rose-month! the rose-month!"  I  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7767-00000046"/> THE THREE JEWELS: The Secret of Wealth, Wisdom and Power. IT was midnight. I had just returned from where a great assemblage had been spread before me, as I sat in a secluded nook in the organ loft in Calvary Church, unheeded and un seen. The grand old organ had been pealing its thunders of harmony through the arches of the magnificent sanctuary, and the glorious peans had rolled around amid its carved corridors and polished columns in strains of heavenly cadence, and bursts of overwhelming power. The velvet-lined pews were crowded with items of mortality, bedecked and bedizened with all the tawdry appliances of modern fashion; beautiful faces were upturned before me, all unconscious of my ruminating eye; and fair dames and lordly cavaliers read the solemn serv- ice of the church, and worshiped the Most High from golden- clasped prayer books, kneeling upon richly cut velvet to be- stow outward homage upon Him who rode into Jerusalem upon an ass, and went about the world clothed in raiment which not one of these but would have repulsed with disgust and aver- sion. Chests and coffers of coin had been expended in thousands upon the exquisite workmanship of the edifice; and more   THE THREE JEWELS.         71 mines of wealth were glittering in golden crosses, studded with precious stones, rings and armlets innumerable, and jewels without mention; and glistening in the rich and variegated hues of silks, satins and fine fabrics that clothed the immense concourse thus spread below me. My eyes had grown weary with the brilliant sight; and now, as I sat alone in my cham- ber, musing on the vagaries of fortune, they drooped heavily with weariness. "What," thought I, "were the means by which this mass of wealth was accumulated? Where am I to look for the secret that shall yield me coffers overflowing with treasure?" And as I mused a voice came gently, softly breathing in on the midnight air, through the open window, and it whispered, ' Seek and thou shalt find!" I bowed, in token of acquiescence in the valne of the advice, and to mani- fest my gratitude therefor; but I was not satisfied. - Many had been the words of wisdom I had heard that night from the man of God. Gray-headed and old, he stood clad in his ministerial robes at the sacred desk, and proclaimed the truths which he had gleaned from the dross of the world, and gathered into the store-house of his mind, during his long journey over the fields of life, where, being gathered, they were called Experience; and I longed for the wisdom which the old man knew, and sighed as I remembered that to win it I must devote the happy hours of my life's morning to the dreary walls of a student's domicile. Again, I was not satis- fied. As I had descended the upright stairway that led from the organ-loft, and passed into the wide vestibule to the sanctuary of God, I had met the stern gaze of one of creation's lords, as  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7767-00000047"/> 72        THE THRni. JiWELS. he strode pompously forth from beneath the fretted doorway; and I had seen the crowd draw deferentially back before him as he walked, leaving the space clear that he passed on to where stood his carriage, with its four richly caparisoned steeds. As the footman followed the dignitary's person, and, bowing low with -uncovered head, closed the coach-door after him, and as the coachman sprang to his seat and reined the fiery coursers aside, which whirled up the street with their precious load, I had heard one say, "That is General - , the most powerful man in this country." Then thought I, "Where shall I find power, also?" And now I sat musing on them. Wealth, Wisdom and Power-the three great desiderata of life-how could I make them mine? The lamp on the mantel burned dimly before my weary eyes, and soon it was quite unseen. Fatigue had con- quered me; my head had fallen upon the table near me, and I was in dream-land with my queries. Morning came, but peace of mind came not with it. The sun came streaming in at the tall window, and across my pil- low, recalling the mysterious command I had reeeived on the previous night-"Seek, and thou shalt find!"But I knew not where to seek, nor how. The world was spread out before me, but what direction was I to take? As I cogitated the perplexing point, I sauntered into the street, and wandered on in a dreamy half-consciousness. The question became more and more unanswerable as I mused on it more; and ere I broke from the trance into which its contem- plation had led me, I was far out in the rural regions, and the city's smokes curled upward to heaven in the dim distance. I   TIE TBREE JEWELS.         73 had nfver been into the country in this dlrection before; and wag totally ignorant of its nature until then. However, it struck me as being strangely gloomy and forbidding in its guise. There was not a house in sight-not a sign of civilized life; nothing to disturb the oppressive stillness, save the cawing of an occasional crow, or the rustling rush of some squirrel which my footsteps had startled from its covert, and sent flying away through the dry leaves into the dense forest at the roadside. On the opposite side of the highway from the wood loomed a huge barricade of rocks, dark and rugged, which seemingly glared down with a grim aspect upon me as I stepped slowly on. I knew not whither I was bent; but I felt no inclination to pause, and so, submitting myself to the dictates of fancy, I strayed aimlessly along. As I advanced, the road grew more and more gloomy. The great pine trees shot perpendicularly heavenward at the right, while the huge granite cliffs broke the view to the left, and seemed to stand in defying mien to the storms of centuries, frowning with gloomy grandeur on the less majestic forest near. A feeling of loneliness crept over - me like a pall, and oppressed me very disagreeably, so that, in order to dispel it, I suddenly began singing in a loud tone; lbut the echios reverberated along the rocky palisade in such a Babel of multitude that my stunned ear shrank before them, and I ceased as suddenly as' 1 began. As the last echo died away, methought I saw, fa on in the distance, a human being. A more strained and earnest vision revealed that I was right. There stood a mah, high up on a jitting crag of the rock, with his hand raised to his forehead, shading his eyes, gazing toward me, He renained thus until 10  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7767-00000048"/> 74        THE THREE JEWELS. I had reached a point nearly opposite him, :t which I paused. "How art thou, friend?" was his salutation, in a loud voice. "I am well, father," I replied; "good morning to you." "Thank thee, lad-thank thee! Thy words are music to my lonely ears, and the sight of thy sunny face doeth my old ieart good. By my troth, I must see thee more! Come up, lad, come up-I would talk with thee." "Aye, and so I will," I returned, "if you will tell me two things: first, in what mode I am to climb to you up the side of this barren rock; and next, whether the crag on which you stand is large enough for two?" "Thou art a keen lad," said the old man, smiling; "but to thy first inquiry I will reply, Climb thou yonder tree, and thou wilt see from thence a path that will lead thee safely here; and to thy other-No, there is not room for two, but verily I will make room, by taking myself into my palace. Come up thou!" And the old man disappeared into a cave in the side of the rock, which I had not observed, being so directly beneath it. Hesitating but a moment, I sprang into the tree, and thence continuing in the way which I then observed plainly, I was soon at the entrance of the cave. "So, so, lad," said the old man, as a benevolent smile beamed on his pleasant features, " thou art here, indeed; and though I am right glad to see thee, yet I marvel much how thou didst find the way hither. What sent thee, lad?" ' You will have to ask Providence that, father; my own will was wholly an idler in the matter. The rising sun found me   THE THREE JEWELS.        . ; near, and my bed but just forsalen. My steps were guided by some unseen power, methinks; at any rate, I amn here, with a light heart, and a prodigious appetite." "Hst not breakfasted yet? Indeed, then I shall be de- lighted to welcome thee to my repast-; and if thou likest good venison, thou shalt breakfast Well."  With this my host busied himself in his preparations for the meal, leaving meample opportunity to view his person, which an aperture overhead in the rock, admitting the light of heaven, enabled me to do easily. He was, apparently, a very old man  his beard was white and flowing, and fell luxuriantly upon his breast. i His long, white hair was parted in the middle, after the manner of the Nazarites. His person was of the average height, but straight and erect as a cedar; and he was clothed in a clean, though coarse, plain robe, girded at the wast with- a rope. His eyes were grey, deep and brilliant,--flashing out from beneath a towering forehead, whereon was scarce a wrinkle. The venison was excellent, and the meal quickly despatched. Then seating ourselves on a rock at the entrance of the cave, looking toward the woods, we prepared for converse. "Well, my brave lad," said the old man, "it is long since I have seen'a face as sunny as thine, for it is long since I have seen that of ny human being, save the reflection of my own in the waters of the pure spring in the forest opposite. But who art thou? I would know thy history." "It would be of no interest to you, father, for it is unevent- ful; but methinks there is a sage experience limned in your  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7767-00000049"/> ts9    TIO W THREE JifWtI venerable countenance that might be valuble to me. I wa born in a little village many milqs awyy,and I eow pusue my humble calling in yonder city, wjhere the nmokes rise up,-aim- less, knowing not the proper sphere of my ambition. ,uRt the graeat ed4 I intend to seek is, the acquirement of. Wealth, Wis dom and Power; and your wsords may prove of upe Mt ne, father, if you will but act as my adviser. Can you not?'" "   I can? mny l1d I can. From the experience of my life- have le4sps. treasured, which now I will tell to theet. it  well I 4ib that thou hast been directed to my hunble cave; but therein I see the hand of a ruling Providence, who has thy destiny in his grasp. It is well; for ten to one but anothlr would have told thee his experience had found these 'things useless; and .this would not haye satisfied thy young spirit.  sh11 npt tell thee this. No; for thou art right in thy belief that the poessisqn of Wisdom, Wealth and Power can confer l^appiRe s; thoq art right. I will tell thee a few short chapter from the experience of my life. "At thy age the same queries beset me as have troubled thee; and I, being possessed of a spirit of .much activity, set about their attainment. I took as a rule of life this-First seek Wisdom, from which cometh Power, with which Wealth is acquired. "I bent my steps towards the halls where education is pop- ularly supposed to be found; and, seeking the company of the wisest of the teachers, and the most learned of the students, I anticipated that, eventually, I should become imbued with their wisdom. But the longer I remained with them, the more thoroughly I became convinced that long indeed must be my   THE THREE JEWELS.        7 stay ere I found my object there. Immersed in text books, apd plunged into rules and problems, from morning till midnight, they pored away the hours; and diease took many away, ,But such as were Spared, instead of being filled with wisdom, only became puffed up with conceit and bigotry. Were a question mooted, they quoted standard authors in proof of the correct- ness of the position they might assume, and scoffed at the Unclassical vulgarism of practical demonstration. Were it un, dertaken to prove to one of these that a deer is cloven footed, he would summon text books to his aid-and should it there chance to be laid down that such was not the fact, he would cleave to his standard authority, and rolling his eyes obstinately heavenward, would quote the mistaken passage, though the cloven hoof were presented and shaken under his determined nose. "Again, were some idiot to assert that robins had horns, the book-worms would fly to their closets, and pore over innumer- able volumes to solve the problem, which a neighboring sports- man might have demonstrated with his gun to their complete satisfaction. Perhaps not the same, my son, but just as foolish, were their ways, and my soul became disgusted with such means of obtaining wisdom. "Then I sought many of the reputed savans of the land, but none so wise but that they were on some point bigoted, and thereby turned all their wisdom into questionable wares. At last I sought the learned Rudolpho, in the city of V , who had the name of being almost a prophet. Inquiring at his residence,.I was told that he had gone to have his shoes repair- ed; and towards the neighboring cobbler's stall I wended my  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7767-00000050"/> 7$8     TTHE THREE JEWELS* Way., Rudolpho sat upon a bench near the lowly cobbler, con-: versing with him as he plied his awl and waxed end.  L"I And so, Crispin,' said he, ' thou hast learned all this wls- dom while poring over thy lapstone in this unobtrusive cot?' "'Aye, all this, good sir, and much more that I could tell' thee, had I the mind to call it to my tongue's end promptly.' "Well, my friend, I thank thee for thy words,' said Ru- dolpho, as he buckled on the renovated shoe; 'health be with thee, honest cobbler; and mayest thou grow in knowledge- many years to come!' " So saying, the savan bestowed a coin upon the laborer and departed. Following him, I accosted him with- "' Most honorable sir, I beg thy pardon for my boldness; but art thou not the wise Rudolpho?' "' I am Rudolpho,' was the meek reply. 'And who art thou'  "' A worthless adventurer, good sir, who seeketh wisdom, and craveth a few words from thy prophetic lips; and if thou wilt heed my wish, the blessings of a poor but ardent soul be thine!' "'Go,' said the wise man, kindly; 'thou art young. Why come to me for wisdom? I am not wise; I do but learn. Until thou art convinced that there is no wisdom save that of learning continually, thou wilt remain unwise. Ponder my words, and go thy way!' "Bowing, I passed on; and passing, pondered; until my reflections yielded me the truth, which I worded thus---' He is wise who learns fom every one.' It was done. The first jewel   THE THE!E JEWELS.         79 was fixed in my crescent, and it shone out with a clear light upon my pathway, as I set forth in search of its companions . Being already wise enough to profit by experience, -I turned my steps now to the courts of the most powerful of known men-the ruler of my country-to learn the secret of Power. Entering his service in a menial capacity, I was rapidly ad- vanced from one post to another, in reward for my faithfulness and tact. My reputation for keenness and penetration of judg. ment grew daily; and ere a twelvemonth had elapsed I filled the post of confidential valet (half companion, half secretary) to him whose service I had entered as a porter. Now was I in immediate association with one who wielded power as a play- thing in his grasp; one whose word was law; at whose sum- mons armed men mustered themselves in thousands to do' his bidding; at the wave of whose hand slaughter and butchery ran wild through kingdoms; whom to displease was either death, or punishment and endless disgrace. "'This,* said I, as I sat one night awaiting my master's re. turn from a banquet, this is what I have been seeking; here is power almost unbounded-and what can there be greater?' "I was answered by the entrance of the mighty one, himself under the subjection of a mightier, who wielded him stagger- ing hither and thither in puerile impotence, and finally sent him reeling headlong upon the chamber floor. That mightier was the demon of the wine-cup; and as I looked on the prostrate ruler, I said-- "'My master is a slave. He is ruled by his passions. How much mightier, then, is he who reduces his passions to subject tion r'  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7767-00000051"/> s$80    THE TtREE JEWELS. I walked forth into the wotld with the second jewel ii my crescent- "Wealth! What need had I now of it? My passions being now. kept under complete subjection, money, with which to gratify them, was unnecessary. But there remained a jewel yet unfound, and until I had obtained it, my labor was not donei And seeking I found that jewel also; wealth became mine. Not the wealth of lucre, but the wealth of a contented mind, which possesseth a value that mountains of coin could  never buy. "Retiring from the haunts of men - sought repose in this humble cavern, which has become to me a palace. Each famil- iar object is to me as valuable as though carved-in- glittering gold; and here, passing the time away innocently and happily, the THREE JEWELS are fixed in my crescent, where their beauty shall light my path in glory to the grave, guiding me safely through the valley of the shadow of death; and through the mercies of Him who is All-Wise, All-Powerful, and Rich in untold abundance, I trust to find a home beyond the azure depths of yon heavc:s blue. purity. Go, my son, and take with thee the wisdom of these words: "He is Wise, who learns from every one. "He is Powerful, who governs his passions. "He is Wealthy, who is contented." As the last tone of the musical voice ceased, I raised niy head from where it had fallen, andsthanked the Vision that had taught me that which otherwise might have consumed long years of bitter experience. The secret was' mine. It is the lodestar of my life.'   SUMMER PICTURES, 1. The moon, that shimmers through the silent leaves. Where hearts that love sit softly holding hands: 2. The swallows building 'neath moss-covered. eave'; 3. The bare-feet, printing in the soaking sands; 4. The green trees, rustling in the cooling breeze; 5. The lark up-winging to the morning sk y; 6. The huntsman, sitting at his royal ease, While evening shadows, lengthening, pass him by; 7. The house-dog, basking in the setting sun; 8. The urchin, lolling on the soft, green grass; 9. The school-boy, sighing that his task be done, And taking dunce-rank in the spelling-class; 10. The town-belle, flitting in and out of shops; ". The salesman, redolent with winning smiles; 12. The doctor, making long and lounging stops; 13. The lawyer, poring, case-less, o'er his dusty files; ". The pen-drudge, sallying forth with line and hook, And gun and bag, to court the varied game; 15. The pebbles, glist'ning in the lucid brook; 16. The clouds, in Sol's declining glory tipp'd with flame. "  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7767-00000052"/> JHE STORY OF JEREMY LONG, OF POTTBRGUGH. . Traveling by railroad is apt to ,be dull business; but now and then the peregrinator picks up an acquaintance in the cars, who proves an exhaustless reservoir of amusement. It was my good fortune once to fall in with one of this class, while on a trip to Gotham. As I stood leaning against the f' cabin" of the ferry-boat which plies between the railroads at Albany, my attention was attracted by a somewhat lean and lengthy specimen of human- ity, who stood clinging to a rusty looking valise, and gazing through a quizzing glass at the objects on the opposite shore. He was immediately entered on my lists: An Oddity. I had just become interested in examining him, when the ferry-boat touched at the landing, and amid the general rush he was soon lost to my sight. But as I was about to step upon the platform of a. car, I was accosted by a heavy voice behind me with- "Spring up, sonny!" I obeyed, and turned to see who had thus addressed me, when- "Oh! beg pardon, sir! I didn't see your whiskers! But you're such a small person-such a very small person, that, really-but never mind that!"   THE STORY OF JEREMY LONG.       83 While speaking, We hid entered the r, and I found myself seated at the side of the lengthy individual, congratulating myself on the prospect of an interesting ride. He introduced himself as Mr. Long-Jeremy Long, late of Pottsburgh; and in return inquired my own name, which I mentioned. Wed covtfesed on ti6 tariot Is tope of interest-the weathei, the scenery on the road, the erdps, the eleCtioi;, &amp;c., &amp;c.,--on all of which 1 found my companion well informed. Atf the Poughkeepsie station Mr. Long retired to "iefrtesh his corpo- real syiteii" he said; " not having grfthbed' since the previous day." He returned, to0plaeetly wiping th6 6rtmbs from his lips with a red silk handkerchief, and reniarked, as Be resumed hailsi6t- A' They hate hig' bivaivesg in hils section of the couftry, sir. They are firtState- -ee fiist-rate. 1 am toMi the quality of the fruit increases in a direct ratio;, ir, i6'm the tir'e a person iSe- e oittthurgih tntil he atritves in New York-is it i?" i I am not aware, sir," said I, "never having extended my travels as far as Pottsville.' "Pottsburgh, I'm much obliged to you-Pottsburgh! Then, probably, you did not know Appleton Potts, sir?" "Well, no, sir-I believe not!" "Dry up, half a secind, if you please," said her, "I, -.--" and taking a key froti. his pocket, he arose, adjusted hisr glass, and began fumbling in hit valise. He soon produced there' from a packet of papers tied with a brown itrittg, whence he drew forth a* wellthatri ed manusetipt. This he handed to me. I opened it. A Sketch in pencil adorned the hed 'of the  &#xD;<pb n="84" xml:id="VAC7767-00000053"/> THE STORY OF JEREMY LONG.   page, and underneath was inscribed: "This is an accurate picture of Appleton Potts." Below, I read:  TO AN ASPIRING MAID "Upbraid me not; I never swore--" but further perusal was checked by the stranger, who exclaimed: "Well. do not read it now, I beg, Mr. Swipes. Who do you suppose writ that?" I could not tell. "Well, no-naturally not," said he. "Perhaps you had, not inferred, during our conversation, that I was a-an-a- ahem!-a poick, a bard?" "No, sir," said I; "candidly, it had not occurred to me; but since you have directed my attention to the fact, it appears :reasonable for me to anticipate that such is the case." "Right, sir-correct-very!" A pause ensued. I now determined to hold my peace, and allow the strange man to unburden himself of the tale which I felt sure he was aching to tell. At length- "Oh.! these women-women!" said Mr. Long, with a deep- drawn sigh. "Would you believe, Mr. Snipe, that an indi- vidual of my appearance would fall in- love-in love with a woman?" "It is a very common disease with the sex, I believe," said I, deferentially, beginning to wonder if this austere personage was going to make me-his junior by a dozen years or more- the confidant of his love affairs?  "True," replied he; " and that article of poickry which now so calmly reposes in your palm, was a direct result of a trans-   ,$84  &#xD;<pb n=" (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7767-00000054"/> I' i "This is an accurate picture of APPLETON POTTS." (Page:84.)  &#xD;<pb n="-85" xml:id="VAC7767-00000055"/>   tOME STORY O3 JEREMY LOiG.       85 action of that nature. You see-but thereby hangs a tale!" and Jeremy Long, late of Pottsburgh, arose, divested himself of his hat and white kerchief, glanced at his watch, seated him self, cleared his throat, and began- "You see, Pottsburgh is one of those bewitchful, retired little hamlets where civilization is not more than skin-deep; where maidens dally and lovers sigh, unmolested by the rude arm of the police officer; where Augustus J. Potts keeps a dry- goods store; where the late firm of Long &amp; Carver formerly run a saw-mill on the banks of a lovely stream that rolls through the green. forest, and glides, in swan-like majesty, over the dam; where-but I am straying from my subject. Excuse me, Mr. Tripe, and I will endeavor to confine myself to simple facts. "In Pottsburgh I lived, and pursued my humble callin'; was very generally a popular fellow, (speaking as though it was somebody else I am talking about;) took the lead in all the frolics, apple-parin's, dances, pic-nics, and etcetera and etcetera, which came off in the village. It was not known that I was a poick, and consequently I was treated with all the freedom and familiarity extended to other men. There were those, indeed, of the girls, who would sometimes poke fun at me, after the manner of those parts; all which I took good-naturedly, being willing to look down on the little creatures a-enjoying their- selves-even at my expense. "It was at an apple-pairin' at Squire Cheerly's that I made the acquaintance of Kitty Fencer. She was a lovely creature, with soft, dewy, red lips, light, curling hair, downy cheeks, and such eyes! From the moment that I first beheld her, I  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7767-00000056"/> 86      T  sa 1TB OK =r9S9Y LOQ . *i0ved t at innarryh I I *ounfd. If waas -elly resoltio, Mt. Whie, whith I thauk-heavein nd Appleton Pottis for pievet Higifne to keep! Te trathof thia *lftl apa ta pyofri I tell you that she was the merest ilrte of f wo in, thee ,t high or tteteaboutsiand I amy as you see mne-ong. Sa!' ha! .-eXuse the exuberance of my wit Mr rSliter: natlr' you ktow,-hea m!    ;  i I went hiomi with her from t4at patti', wtieh -*a 'abont foutmiles from where she lived. Her foikst ao afrtelr e af bor t Ot ten ot  ' losk; but: I prvsitied-on 'em to let her stafY ad I woiuld iee her saf. hwome. I wasglad I had mniet het there, fot I s - s comneious ho* ridictloeas I showld have ppieared *ilki*g at iter id&amp;-4  flirt itmpressios. being niodt lasting. I t&amp;iughtit real lucky that I had met her where I could carryher hoer  in' fij tstter. "Oh! :si, I cae never forget that night, s; e th pale- rboon &amp;oiie d6intf n ti t*vo-iae and her-tu cked #e cdilft irer tiatt taber ;: eshesugged up edloe to me, latfghing aid )k*g t, tety ill 1the way adc&amp;I drivifg them two blfow hoaeW e 'tea'-ed HltWing over tLe smootth siowi with My heart dIoenk- ift against i&amp;y ribs hard enough for her to beartif she tried "t'had hot. been acquaitted wi ith Kity' very ong befo the village g6osips: bafgai to talk abm6 t iit, amd it' sn6 iS to fie tioer *Wa such fun made of a: courtesip bfore in Pottsbirgh; Well, there was a large fund for it, I'll all6W. It Iooktf omnite- to mei tnow to think of my courting Fuch -a little thing-but I was In love; nm when a msn's in -lov hi rieanon isitekeea away in sOme old cupboad, you know, there to remain until the knht's tied*    THZ &amp;TOMY OF JrE  S V IXMY .   '  8(. - f Wf el, I'm glad ome one else took compassion on my four Sad atrove to rsi .eme ; but oh! how I could have Euraed that rTan. at ttie. I could .kiss him now, D o't lag0h, Mr. Wiper, I clca .kis aaad this kissing popens'ty of Mnne wu aa  active worker in my redemption. t Kitty Fencer had not long been a resident of Pottsburgh; if she bad 'a been,-she would never have imbibed that prejudice' ofthers-.for such a kissing set as- there is in Pottsburgh you nevr se!  "'It, as^ 4t lhad fer me 'Q jee Lt 4pp*Pon pRots ws trp in to yring i $to .Miss itty's favor ; but ha4d Twy I n4 i., and Kitty had kind 'o tQo. ikipg : ne. To be sIrf Popte t was a better looking nma than I, and Kitty had told me p, bs t I never imagined that anything had ever passed betweeek'.m, And I knew, that, spite of his good looks, Potts was not near as clever a fellow as I; besides that, I am a man of property, sir, and :was considered worth more than any other man int the neighborhood of Pottsburgh, which- fact had a most wonderful effect in softening the angularities of :my person with the feminines.  "One evening I went to see Kitty, and was met by her with a face covered with smiles, as .she took my hat and hastily led me to a chair . :She then began^ fumbling in that mysterious pocket of hers, and finally fished up a letter, which she handed me to read; while she took a seat by my side? 'to help me laugh over it,' as she said. "A glance at the thing showed me .that it was pickry. -I hastily looked at the bottom of it, and there was the name--' 'Applaton Potts.' I read it, and at everyline I waxed madder  &#xD;<pb n="88" xml:id="VAC7767-00000057"/> 88      THE STORY 06 jINk  LONG. T. and madder.. It was an avowal. of love, sir-an avowal of love--to xrintended! This alone was. sufficient to fire up the indignation of a man with a jot of spirit in his breast; but, sir, judge of my rage, when I read also the lines : Jeremy. Long is a butcler's son; A butcher's son is he; The son of a butcher, he was, is now, And evermore shall be." Sir, I was. dumb with passion ; my face glowed like a fiery furnace. I seized my hat, vowing that i would flog the blak- hearted wretch within an inch of his life. But Kitty clung so imploringly to my coat-tail, and screamed- "' Oh! don't"go now, Jerry-wait till to-morrow-dout go and leave me, there's a good fellow--I was going to have such a good time with you this evening  "I yielded, sir, partly because a mai ought always to yield to the voice of entreaty, when he's in a rage; partly because I was afraid my coat would be torn, (my very best, sir!); and partly because I had no objection to enjoying 'such a good time' myself. So I smothered my rage, and seated myself by Kitty's side. Somehow, my arm found its way over the back of her chair, and then wel talked love, you know-love. We had just about got it settled where we would live, and etcetera, when I felt so precious neat; that I turned and snatched, what I thought all right enough-a kiss I "Alas, sir, I hit her prejudice I Did you ever see a woman in a perfect fury? I have. J-o-h-n Roass! what a recollec- tion Whew! how the things flew round in that room for the                      . *           ' ' ^   &#xD;<pb n="Illustration" xml:id="VAC7767-00000058"/>
               <pb n="-89" xml:id="VAC7767-00000059"/> 'rTH  SuTOEY OF JERTCMY LOtN'     89m" spae ':of about: fiftynine; econds,! I didn't knqwt for sure which end-imy head was on; nor what I was- doipg, nor wh.1t  sboul&amp; probabl^ cdnlud, to, do! But; I knoQw a, coupl of- chiirro sattered around4 rather wild-; that oneola, tin paiw went rattling and clattring off under the-thle as-thoughtugged byA. a le'on .ofi impsa;: and that theeat-.the .unfortun^te ca t! which- certainly was not at all to blame--.was frightened clean, put of her 4itsiadawent: spamperirng:e  arou tromnr , over the tables' under the;rs^r, and finally bang throuigh a window panie, withl her tail standing erect as a cedar of Lebanon, if not quite as- ,!arge. /Velq, sir, that little gal put m out of the house! :   I. iaprang into the road, hat in hand and heart in mouth,- who should I tneet but Potts-that stupid Potts!o The mooiQ shon fair and teq; Kitty stood on the steps and saw. the reiecgntre,: .Sh nade, but one bound intothe road, and ti-?the. twinkling of a saw-log, Appleto', Potts, son, of tugustu:s,. Potts, was in that house, the door was bolted, and I was roll. ing my eyes at the moort /  "What thougts crowded my brain, as I. stood' there, statue- like, in my sadness! Was this a preconcerted- scheme? Was I a dupe? Was Potts successful? Well, sir, I finally placed my hat on my head, and spread myself across the snow-crusted fields, home. "The die was cast. Appleton. Potts was in, and I was out. It didn't take long for all: Pottsburgh'to know the tale; genius is proverbially sensitive, Mr. Van Swiper, and I:couldn't stand it; so I kind o' concluded&amp;'it'would be as- well- for me to sell out and travel-for my health. 1.2- -    -4t        ':,                                                                ,                    .     -      -, , Me, -x,  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7767-00000060"/> 9,r-,     T   r STORY 0f JBEXT. LONG. "But, sir, I am'comforted bythei ifeetiona that the Potts burghers. have discovered, ere -this, the genius they have sent from their midst, I left seveal poems to old acquaintances in Pottsburgh, atd one. to Kitty Fencer--that one, sir, which is * now in your gentlfmanly grasp, sir and which I have now the honor of 'requestlng you to accept, as a slight token of my sin- cere regard-for you."'  "Read it not, Mr. McPiper, until a week shall have elapsed, when I shall be far away on the billowy ocean, bound for disA taut lands."    '  I was profuse in my expressions of gratification at Mr. Long's tale, and assured him that it should be laid before a sympa- thizing public. The poem proved to be as follows. With its originality I have nothing to do. Mr. Long may have been its author; but I think I have seen it before, somewhere:- 'TO A' AsPIRING XMAWD.  "Upbraid me not; I never swore Eternal loveto thee;:  For thou art only three feet high, And I am six- feet three.  "I wonder, dear, how you suppose That I conld stoop so low; 'Tis only few oan tie. a knot;,  Though all may fik s a beau .  -  "Besides, you must coifess, my love, The bargain's scarcely fair, For never-could' we make a 'mac , Although we made a pair.    THE STORY OF JEREMY LOG.         9 .. -  "Marriage, I know, makes one of two, S: i.,'   .- .But eheres the horrid borne;.  The priest declares, if you are one, That I, at least, am four. ' ('Tis true that moralists have said That love hs got no eyes; But why should all my sgglls be heaved' For one who has no size   .  . "' Tis. usual for a wife to take H ,er husband by tthe arm;  ' Blt pray excuse me should I hint A sort of fond alarm-  ; .      ' "That when my arm I offered you, That happiness to beg, Your highest effort, dear, would be  To take me by the leg. "I do admit I wear a glass- Because my -sght's not good,  But were I always quizzing yot, It might be counted rude. "And though I use a convex leh^ - By all the gods I hope My wife will never look at me Through Herschel's telescope I 'Then fare thee-well, my gentle one, I ask no. parting kiss; I must not n br ak my back to gain So exquisite a bliss. ' But if you eyes love again, Love on a smaller plan; For why extend to six feet-three  A life that's .but aspan'- .  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7767-00000061"/> EXTRACTS FROM LECTURES  'BY TIE ATUtOttOR, [IT having been suggested that- few brief extracts from my Lectures would add still further to that VARIETy which is the leading aim of this little work, I have hastily selected the fol- lowing, as scraps most easily detached from the connected line of argument in each case,-though possessing no especial in- trinsic merit.--W. W, S.] [Frolm "THE TtHREE MYSTERIES: LOVE, MATRIMONY; DEATH."] WHEN I am asked, At what age should a man or woman marry? I am disposed to rebuke rather than answer so foolish a question-a question so manifestly- the ffspring of a mind having no proper conception of the grave subject before us. The ages at which marriage is fit and proper, vary with the in: dividuals in each individual case. I ah iho .advocate of early marriages-no advocate o$le marriages ; but, if a young ma:n makes up his mind, honestly and with good sense to aid him, that- it is right, and best,;-that he should marry when he is eighteen years bld, my blessing be on his, betrothal! And equally so, if a man concludes he had better wait till he is five. and-forty. If any man.-youig or old--wants precedent in forming an early or late matrimonial alliace, there is precedent for him. Mahomet was married: at twenty-five; his wife was   OE              '93 iir.   pcri9i ben; h          'iit3s "fed y. , ^M^  iiB^rea    t^itee  h^is4M  as etae ne"u s dbl4i eolbWrd, the'rat -ahnd jutly hon*ed iphi. kan th  t, tarrimud vt tity v; iis wife varts 1it-tft o. 8"SbeJiz   thewifeaiea, alxd },iwiien about fity 'yeas of :a^f,inaied'a. gi if sii[teon. tir. Parr, celebrated 'to veiry 'ieadaeOhistory'io less tor is exeleencies than fr his ecen- 't^cditic s bna il ^jo ih iwidbw when he was 1-20 yeats old!' v is- toy fnreists pedeitsin the lives of great and good*eht axd omeAn, eWer  e,fr atteora judentthe   iostigular. 8'of  s we i   ;anf y nriowledge, Adam and Evewere naiiaied iore heTy rtere a year old! But :that nin *who is nbt tmstiieietfly certain he -oughteto "itnr, 6th do to ithobnt a -precedejnt, had ,betterf wait U little 'lone'r. Ifci'tt -ld enough'" yet! iron $XTM TIb2 -iYAND Soor AMOR ."ol ALXt 1borihouTd be '"labor of love ;" else It can hot lay 'lelima-to nobility.- Nether ian it attain to the highest excel- tene.-ele.' Whether labortig "'ith ththe pen, he pencil, the ieltge-lhamner, the graiver, the plough, the lancet or whatever etse,ithere-is no nobilitiy attehing 'tolabor unless it be perform- b'i:for love of itself and its results upon health and happiness, titer than for love of the money or goods it will bring to he tiores ofhim who Wtrks. These may ensue, as the natural ani jihstresult dfomat's abot; but 'they should hot be held up con- "niialy 'before his byes, for the -effect of that is to lead 'hin tfo Viw h'is fibor 'therely as a tool wherewith he "may acquire wealth; and thus hnbilit'becomies a 'myth intothas cohae;cfd /;  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7767-00000062"/> "          EXTRAOTs. 9           . XlsJcrs.       ' with labor . For what, thei, islabor, buta highway over which a man treads toward some more desirable goal? Liabor must be loved for itself; and then it will become truly ifole, and be so recognized everywhere: and by all. The maschist ,who feels himself a machinist for life,- the writer whi feels himself a writer for life,-the sculptor who feels himself a sclptor for life,-and that the grand goal of that life, is to make his ma- chinery, his writings, his sculpture, the grandest of their. kihd, that man, will look upon -his employment as the send of his earthly aim; (for in this lecture I am not speaking of things spiritual; but only things temporal;) and viewing it in that light, his pride will be to glorify his work, and thus to manifest the highest nobility of, labor. But it isnot so now--except partially. ,Now, men look on, beyond their. present employ- ment, and, at the end of a long avenue of years, in the path of which lie piled pieces of work side by side with moiey-pots, they behold a pleasant mansion, where, to use a common term, theymay" "etire from business." Retire from business? For what? That they may walk lazily about the streets, of, their native place, grasping a gold-headed cane, talking slow politics, and laying up for themselves the blessings of gout, dyspepsia, rheumatism and other ills resulting from inactivity. Whaat an ambition for a live American citizen, to draw out the tedious time sucking sleepy spittle from the carved knob of a walking stick, and "living on the interest of his money." Live! He does hot live-more than a bloated, fungus lives - He has no life,--no energy,-no expression of soul,-he is a libel , American Independence! He [does not live; he merely pro- longs an existence-just as an oyster does!.     .   E TIBCITB.        i .fjL EXTTAOT6.           96 - . e li"ive in deeds, not years; in thoughts, not breaths;  ., ,;in feelings, not in figures on a dial; . We should count time by heart-thrrbs: He most lives ,. Who thinks most,--,feqls the noblest,-acts the best. ',  And he whose heart beats quickest,.lives the longest: Lives in one hour more than years do some, Whose fat blood sleeps as it slips along their veins.!" X,;  ho ( itCo d sleeps ' -    e,  D" What glory for a man who has been all his life a worker-a benefit to the world--to resolve himself into a vivified manikin, inwhich the. digestive organs try to do their work, and the haadasperform "mere motions," which owe nothing to brains  There is no more degrading sight to an eye that appreciates labor's nobility, than to behold two hands, which have been strong and muscular for years with active labor, suddenly be- coming soft, and fat, and flabby, like a lady-dowager's hand, and losing their muscle in inert waste! '  Do not understand-me to advance the idea that there is no nobility attaching to thatlabor which has for its aim the sus- tenance of a family, and the promotion of health in the laborer. This is the exception to our rule. There is not a little of gen- tite: nobility-in the courage and fortitude with which a poor hodticarrier supports his family by shedding perspiratioh at the rate ddf ten ceilts an hour, month after month. He is worthyof our admiration, who thus toils on, for a pittince, that he may s'pport in comfort his wife and six children. It is when he foygets himself, and his duty, and those at home who have deainis on him, and becomes a miserable sucker at the mouth of a black bottle with a devil in it, that the hod-carrier loses his claim on our respect.   &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7767-00000063"/> 4-    \     E^TO PTS [Fromt. ; WILLIA WIBRT." OOR subject afforded an example of progress worthy of-emur lation, in the eafly age at which he entered upon the' practice of a profession universally admitted to be one of the most ar- duous on the lists. No false'idea of his own youth and inex- perience led Wiliiam Wirt to delay entering upon:;.a caeer-of  useful activity as soon as he was ready for it; and through his  life the ris exhibited the same disregard 'of tht slow-coach wisdom which would prate of "years " to young-men with souls ,  on fire. with the gloribus1 emulation of attaining; to a plae4. in:  w'the ratlns of: humanity's worers and- society's aidsto ad ane- ..- ment. Sleepy, leather-pates! who wer t ill their-fortieth year. in learning the A B C's of human nature, and wh,- not-haing  yet advanced farther, look with affected contempt on- those quicker minds that, grasp the grand lessons oflife ina- day, and:  are compelled to behold these other plodders along in' the ele- mntatyg hblrqohes statxding aloof from: themand- .pating of:the- hot-headed: y'ouths who-forget their. sphere and travel .toa: fiat. Too fast!--therte is no such thing as'traveling; toofast, if yo.'r, traveling right. It is those who tread:- in dariness, who:-need. to travel slow-; the engine-brain that carries a lampiniits for head to illumine its way, may rush on t, night wth nearythe same security as by day. So long as; the path is clear' andithe. mindsound; the greater the speed attainable the better.; &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
