<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7289">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>K. N. Pepper, and Other Condiments Put Up For General Use </title>
            <author>Maurice, Jacques.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7289</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1750</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>K. N. Pepper, and other condiments put up for general use</title>
                  <author>Maurice, Jacques.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>258 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Rudd &amp; Carleton</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1858">1858</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-11-29">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>K. N. Pepper, and other condiments put up for general use</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (Cover) " xml:id="VAC7289-00000001"/>K. N. PEPPER, And other Condiments. i     &#xD;<pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7289-00000002"/> I   "Vive la Bagatelle!" K. N. PEPPER, And other Condiments; PUT    UP   FOR -GENERAL      USE BY  JACQUES MAURICE. "Forgive my general and exceptless rashness, Perpetual-sober Gods!" Thmon of At/ens. "Mr. Pepper's voice is as sweet as a bagpipe." MACOGAWLEB, in Pa/ Cfford. NEW YORK: RUDD &amp; CARLETON, 310 BROADWAY, M DCCC LIX.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7289-00000003"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 188, by JAB. W. MORRIS, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York. L CRAIGHEAD, Printer, Stereotyper, and Electrotyps, Caxton I3uilbing, 81, 8s, and 85 Cueb Street.   TO Louis GAYORD CLARK, Es2. DEAR CLARK, I remember a winter evening when we sat chatting together in your san&amp;um, sipping a mild and wholesome beverage (tea, was it not?), or answering some exaggerated shriek of the passing wind with the mild satire of a peaceful pipe. Little Elliott had climbed the paternal knee, and mis- chievous Jose hovered near, in no wise "afraid of her father." The bright coal fire sent a cheerful gleam through the room- O cosy snuggery!-and made the delicate wreath of smoke that had settled about your head appear like an indifferent halo. It was the place for that delicate coronation. The lapidary-work of this literary Mosaic was hardly yet begun; but it happened that, by a nervous anticipation, I fell a musing, in one of the natural pauses of our chat, on a certain  &#xD;<pb n="vi-vii" xml:id="VAC7289-00000004"/> Dedicatory Letter. after-question which had needlessly perplexed me. At length, putting myself in communication with my heart, I heard that organ say, distinfly, "Jacques, if thou canst not find here the man to whom thou shouldst dedicate thy work, thou mayest go farther and fare worse." I have presumptuously taken my own advice. Considering our friendship, your kindness to Mr. Pepper, and the liberal use I have made of your name in these pages, perhaps it is a wonder I should ever have debated the point at all. W!,en you have inspe&amp;ed the volume, you will have found it "full of I's within," like the Four Beasts of the Revelation; and it must be confessed, that in neither interior can we see much need of them. But it is my wish and timid anticipation one day to possess a greater fund of modesty-or the counter- feit of it-my youth and ripening worldly knowledge lending some encouragement to the desire. Take kindly, my dear Clark, these firstlings of a "vagrom" genius; and share with me the fervent hope that it may some- time "bourgeon and blossom" toward a better fruit. Your attached friend, JACQUES MAURICE.   NEW YORK, Sept. 1, 188.   PREFACE. (WRITTEN BY P. PEPPER PODD, ESQ.) --------0 .. My young friend, the Editer and part Auther of this hook, Informs me that, having wrote a great many prefaces for it-.some Hundred, 1 Understood him to say-and finding the last one somewhat poorer than the first, which he declares was not fit to be perused before a Dog or other animal, he willDepend on me to Do it for him. I gladly undertake almost Any thing for a friend like what he is: but I Confess my pulse runs up to 80 when I Surrender myself to the Task. Preface is hard to write, for the Generality of Mankind. Mankind are not use to it. When they go to write on it, they can Not think of any thing to say. It is Compleatly so now. Mr. M   said' ( remember his words): Now, no Fooling, Mr. Podd. None of your nonsense. Be plain, brief, and to the point. To Say this, is uncom- monly easy; to DQ it, is particularly Difficult. In my Opinion, a Work of Literatoor ought to be its own Excuse or else it should be Consigned to the fire, or perhaps Mutilated by   &#xD;<pb n="viii-ix (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC7289-00000005"/> Preface.                  : Tairing. As long as the Wonderful genus of PEPPER consents tc illuminate a Book, that Book, in my opinion, can not Need a Excuse. I may be Mistaken, but that is my Opinion. But to think Different, is the Lot of Mankind. Mankind scarcely ever agrees. Mr. M   thinks perhaps he himself has not Done as well as he might, and says he is Afraid he will be Overshadowed by Mr. PEPPER'S genus, and thrown into a unpleasant Shade by that Individual That Effect will of course be Produced. Hexpect to share that Gloom with him. But we should be Proud to Prostrate ourselves at the Foot of GENUS, regardless of its size; and let our Gaze wander tp his lims and body, until it rests with Satisfaction on his glorious Feachers. Mr. M    has (1) Talents and (2) Education, but no (3) Genus; Mr. PEPPER has (3) Genus and (1) Talents, but no (2) Educa- tion; (1) and (3) hiding (2) pretty Much. From this Statement- made not without Study-it is so vividly Apparent as to be quite Plane, that PEPPER is (to Employ the Languige of Racers and inferier men), A-head. Upon my showing the Foregoing to Mr. M    ,he Remarked that I had Done it. That is what I intended. I Meant to Do it. I am glad he is Satisfied. He says he will not Detain me any Longer now, and will continue the subject of himself himself, in another Department. My Readers must not be offended if I take my Leaf before an Intro- duction. I act for Another; and when he demands, in a Imperative voice, "Go," I must of course Stop. P. 1. P.   CONTENTS. -0--- "Are you looking for any one in particular? as the mite said to the microscope."-Punch - -0----   To the Reader,   *   *    *   Page 13   Biographical, .   .   .   .   .  Genus: a Sketch. By Mr. Podd. Juvenile Poem by Mr. Pepper. Alegaiter &amp; Wotter Snaik. Astronomy,   .   .   .  .   .27 In a familiar (but not impertinent) Lecture. Mr. Pepper's Second Feat,    .   .   . Soliliqy: Adrest to a Berd onto the fens. The Anguished Bride,    .   .   .58 A Tale. By Willie Wilton Willoughby.   &#xD;<pb n="x (Table of Contents) -xi (Table of Contents) "
                   xml:id="VAC7289-00000006"/> x          Contents. Page Mr. Pepper's Third,   .   .  .     73 The Suferings ov a Man. The Erie Canal,  .   .  .   .     76 A Mild Rhapsody. Mr. Pepper's Fourth Achievement,.       85 A noad to the Comeck. A Tedious Story, .    .   .  .     go To Angelina,.    .  .  .   .    105 Mr. Pepper's Fifth Labor,   .    .   108 Letter and Poem : To mi littel hous. A Lytell Geste of Lewys Clarke,   .    115 Mr. Pepper's Mournful Sixth,.    .  .  120 Letter and Poem: To the aingel as is gone. On Noses,   .    .  .   .     125 Mr. Pepper's Great Ode,    .  .    132 To the Greek Slaiv. Phrenology of the Heavens, .    .    137 Copy of a Painting by Mr. Pepper. The Little Frenchman, .    .   .    141 A Poem (and Poet) Cut Short,    .  .  15 A Pause,   .   .    . .  .    152   Contents.         xi Mr. Pepper in the Vale of Shadows,     .  1 Letters from Podd and Pepper. Lager Bier Lyric,  .   .   .  .     6 Taken from the lips of an imported Cockney. On the Clam,     .  .   .   .    64 Mr. Pepper's Eighth Upheaving,    .    171 Weelbarer. Into 2 parts. An Adventure in the Dark,    .   .  , 180 (Calculated for the meridian of several small places.) Mr. Pepper's Astonishing Ninth,   .   .  189 Eklips. Pharaoh,    . A  Tale of Bricks. December in the Country,        .  .200 Mr. Pepper's Thrilling Letter,    .   . 202 To   Venus,  ..              209 Answers to Correspondents,    .  .   .212 By a quondam Editor. Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh,    .   .219 Tirkel: a  Pome.             21 Mr. Podd's Essay,      2. 21 To the World.    3  &#xD;<pb n="xii (Table of Contents) -13" xml:id="VAC7289-00000007"/> ii    Contents. Page   - 'epper Redivivus, .  .         236 2 Sonnet to Pete.          - Warning,    .  .  .  .    239  Effects of the Abolition of Capital Pun-ishment. Ir. Pepper re-Pete's himself, . .   243  Pete: an averij pome (for length.) L Delibation on Style, .       . 250  "Envoi. . . 25' Envoi.     .  .  2.55  255  "   TO THE READER. --0----- FRIENDLY READER: In this page-the Vesti- bule, as it were, at a small Museum of Fancies- I welcome you to the show, and wish very heartily you had brought your friends. You entered my "grounds" at a Gate constructed by that finished archi- tect, Mr. Podd; and had I not chosen to set it near my house, you might have been obliged (or get in, quite unhandsomely, the back way) to tire yourself in an Avenue dark and dreary, rough, and horribly winding: the clumsy work of the proprietor himself. That modest gentleman (who has stepped from the first person and gone aside to view himself), with a winning smile and bow of ineffable courtesy now opens the "inner door;" and having whispered an assurance that he will be ever at your elbow-explain-  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7289-00000008"/> BIOGRAPHCAL. ----- T is all well enough to talk of the ease with which biographies of common men-generals, statesmen, and the like, are written; it is quite another thing when the subject happens to be a genius, like Mr. Pepper. I made that discovery before I had thought of my work five minutes. Had not my good angel served me (proof of his existence was getting neces- sary) I really think I should have given up the task- appalled by my reverential notion of the poet, and a sad lack of material. Indeed, I had at last reached that pitiable state-oppressed by the necessity of say- ing something under this head, and the fear of not being able to say it-I fell to asking of the circum- ambient air, in a feeble whimper, Why was I born? in the received style of heroes (and girls) in a bad way.      A    &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7289-00000009"/> Biographical.      17 for which he will please accept, here, the thanks of one who ranks him second only to the great Pote himself: GENUS: A SKETCH. "A CREEK. A House, a lowly Tenement, on that creek. A BoY, a Small boy, in that creek, Paddling. Geese in the Distance. That Creek, every Drop of which is sacred, is Squab Creek. That Tenement is the Residence of the elder Mr. PEPPER. Those Geese are his. But who is the Child with the Golden Locks? That is the future Individual, Mr. K. N. PEPPER, Esq. He Paddles as only a Poet can Paddle: and grows up as only a Poet can grow up. "Genus tells him he must not mind his Father: and he does not mind that Father. He has been destined to Dig. Genus Dig? Genus can not Dig: genus does not Dig! He Soars, living on Apples. But that great and mighty Spirit could not express itself in a manner to do justice to hardly Any thing. It often felt Ashamed of itself. Only once (in its twelf year) did it do much. But what more do we want? What will we have? "Here it is, with the stile preserved. It has been    &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7289-00000010"/> 1 8         Biographical. in my Possession upward of ten year; and I know it Genuine. Notice how Brief it is: A-FISHN. "WEN I go a-fishin I kepe a-wishin With al mi mite fur fish to Bite Wen i ketch small i fele no fun Wen i ketch biger i say thats the figer ef you wos moar fish ide hev my wish after al ive tryde i ant Satisfyde fishin is smal onles you git god Hol demosthens 4 corns 5 guy. ' "How Wonderful and Good that is I Genus was then but twelve! "As Mr. PEPPER may Prefer to write an Auto Biro- graplhy of himself himsel, I cannot be asked to Do it without Pain. The World would rather I would not. The World will wait with Pleasure for Mr. PEPPER. It will be enough if I say that after his   Biographical.       19 Flash of Genus at twelve, I watched over! the tender Twig of Mr. PEPPER'S Brain until it grew into the Hardened Wood you now see it. "He often had pains in his Bowels. Severe as they was, he bore them. It does me good to write: He Bore Them. His Genus told him not to take Cam- pher. He did not take Campher. No true Poet will repine at the Severity of internal Pains. They School him: they make him Great. "I watched over all of Mr. PEPPEB'S Poems. I rejoiced when his first Master Piece was wrote. I also rejoiced when the second one came into existence. I have been in a continual state of rejoicing ever since. "If he had not gone into the Country, to be alone, and commune with the Voice of NATURE, he would not have wrote to me. Then my name would never appeared to a Note in the KNTICKERBOCKER. But when that letter came, I knew it belonged to the World. And in giving it to the Owner, I found my Humble Name throwed in. "Such as it is, and being, as I am, the Bosom Friend of Genus, I hope the World is not Averse to "Its Humble Friend, "MR. PEPPER PODD."  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7289-00000011"/> 20        Biographical. Thanks, dear PODD I "The World" owes you much, for this; and how fervently it is to be hoped you may get your due I I do not well know what can be added to the com- prehensive sketch of Mr. PODD's. The subject of this memoir had few adventures, during the eight years in which his genius was a-blossoming. Like that of a kindred spirit (Shakspeare,) his seems to have been rather a tame youth; affording no salient points to any but the most elaborate biographer. He did not even steal a deer, or small dog. The tranquillity of his life, during this period, was ruffled by nothing more tempestuous than an occasional thrashing at the  :! hands of his father; who seems, rather unreasonably, to have insisted on having his son do violence to his instincts by occasional vulgar work. But we may forgive the elder PEPPER these rude inflictions: he thought he was right, undoubtedly. And he was un- consciously perfecting his son's genius; for the "Divine Flatness"* is conditioned on a certain amount of suf- fering. Little did the harsh father think that while he "tanned the hide" of his son, he dusted both his jacket and mind! * Mrs. Partington. 1.;   Biographical.        21 Passing over, then, the petty incidents of those eight years: gladly leaving them to some future and more drivelling biographer, we find him  at twenty obeying the now well-defined instincts of his higher nature, and taking a stand on the ramparts of poetry, as one of the sentinels of that perfecter taste which the rude world is ever assailing. How naturally do we advert to his First Great Poem, which burst on the world more than four years ago, and dazzles it a little even now! There is some mystery connected with this poem, that does not attach to the later; ones. It was first sent to one C. Conklin Neppins, editor of a Magazine called the Quog Ladies' Litery Gem; but as he was himself a poet, of small capacity but ridiculous pretensions, he saw how imminent was the cutting of his literary throat with the razor of a greater genius, and was silent. When Mr Pepper had grown tired, waiting for NEPPINS' recognition, he sent a copy of the poem, which he had fortunately preserved, to a man above these petty jealousies, Mr. Clark, of the Knicker. bocker; and with it the following note: &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7289-00000012"/> "demosthenes, 4 corners, "febuerry the 5, 188. "Mr. C. "in mi distres &amp; travil i am 4st to apeal to you to redres mi greaviances, which hes ben al but toar nakid by the roothis edditer ov the quog ladys litery Gem. i cent the en- cloaged specimin ov blanc vers to him, &amp; he oanly remarc with a noath it wos too blanc fur his collums. ef you shood onforti- netly thine diferen you will ov coars faver your reders bi a printin ov it, to sho that Genus aint confined concloosively to the larg Potes, "sir yours with Respec, "K. N. PEPPER'" What a firm and undying consciousness of Genius does that note present! See how    nobly the editor there addressed came to the rescue:- - "It must have been sheer envy, on the part of Mr. C. CONKLIN NEPPINS, that excluded the following stirring 'pome' from the columns of ' The Quog Litery Gem.' We take an early occasion to do justice to the talents of the author, K. N. PEPPER, Esq., who has ' chose' the hydraulic measure, because, next to hydra- meters, he seems to consider it the most 'effectooal':"  -% , z  "A 'fMA   ?,r    - L'..." '.L    23 BJECK: A COLUSION BE"WEEN A ALEGAITER IND A WOTTER-SNAIK: TRIUMTH OV THE VOTTER-SNAIK: DETH OV THE ALEGAITER: ONCLOOSION. Their is a niland onto a river lyin, Wich runs into Gautimaly, a worm Kedentry lyin near the Troppicks, cuverd with sand: Here &amp; their a symtum ov a Wilow, Hangin ov its umberajus lims &amp; branches over the clere streme a-meanderin fur below. This wos the Hoam ov the now silent Alegaiter, Wen not into his uther Elemen confind: Here he wood set onto his egs a slepe, With 1 i observant ov flis and uther pasin objecks. a wile it kep a-goin on so: Fereles ov dainger wos the hapy Alegaiter l But alas !  in a  nevil Our he wos 4st to Waikl that dreme ov Blis wos too swete fur him. I    mornin the son aroas with unusooal splender: Wich also did our Alegaiter, a-comin from the wotter, His scails a-fiingin ov the rais ov the son bacc to the fountin-hed wich thay ariginly cum frum. -:  But hevin hed nothin fur to ete fur sum time, he Wos slepy, &amp; gapt, in a  short time, widely,&#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7289-00000013"/> 24          Biographical. Unfoaldin sune a welth ov perl-wite teth. the rais ov the son sune shet his sinister i, Becos ov thayr mutooal splender &amp; wormth. the Evil Our (wich i sed) wos now cum: Evidently a good chans fur a wotter-snaik ov the large Speshy-wich sune apeard into the horrison, nere the bang ware repoasd Camly in slepe the Alegaiter be4 spoken ov. about 60 foot wos his Length, (not the 'gaiter,) &amp; he wos aperiently a wel propoarshund snaik. Wen he wos al ashoar, he glared onto the iland with approval-but wos sune "Astonished with the vew &amp; lost to wonder," (frum WOTS.) (fur gest then he begund fur to se the Alegaiter.) Bein a nateral Ennemy ov hisn, he werct hisself into a fury, also a ni posishun. Be4 the Alegaiter wel cood ope His i, (in uther werds, perceve his dainger,) the Snaik hed envellupd his body gest 19 times with "foalds voloominous &amp; vast," (frum MLTON,) &amp; hed toar of severil Scails into the confusion, Besides a-squesin him awfuly onto his stomick. gest then, bi a fortinat turn into his affairs, He ceased into his mouth the cairless tale ov the unreflectin wotter-Snaik!--groan desperat, He, findin that his Tale wos fast, squesed terrible, wile thay roald al over the iland.   Biographical.           25 it wos a wel-conducktid Afair: no nbis Disturbd the Harmony ov the seen--exsep 1's, wen a Wilow wos snaped into bi the roalin. each ov the combatens hedent a minit fur holerin. So the Conflic wos naterally tremenjusl But sune bi grate 4s the tale wos bit compleat- ly of: but the eggzershun wos too much Fur his dellicat Constitooshun. he felt a compreshun onto his chest, &amp; generaly over his boddy: Wen he egsprest his brethin it wos with grait Dificulty that he felt inspird agin i's moar. ov coars this Stait must sufer a Revolooshun. So the Alegaiter giv but 1 yel, &amp; egspird. the wotter-Snaik realed hisself of, &amp; sirvayd, Fur say 10 minits,; the condishun ov His Fo: then, a-wunderin wot maid his tale hirt, He sloly went-of for to cool. Poor hapiles Alegaiter I tis sad to thine Like the Lemons you onfortinatly went in. But rest onto the Sand, ef you hevent roald into the wotter: &amp; rest into the Wotter, ef so be youv roald in. How menny air ap to thine not, wen in dainger But fall into slepe cairles  I sech air woak Frekently wen al cuite too lait, &amp; thay sadly fele the Embrais of the Enemy: growin weker &amp;   weker, 2  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7289-00000014"/> 26        Biographical. Be4 thay no it thay cant fech thayr breth- &amp; the consekens is, thay sune di. From the time of the appearance of this poem, the "movements" of the distinguished Pote are sufficiently well known, through his own writings, and those of his excellent relative, Mr. PODD. Hence the author of this brief biography has little more to do. That little he has preferred to divide into lesser bits, which the reader will find prefixed to the several effusions of the bard, as they appear in this volume. Had not Mr. PODD already furnished an eloquent analysis of Mr. PEPPER'S character (contained in his note intro- ducing one of the poems), it would be proper for me to fulfil the whole duty of man as a Biographer, and attempt that difficult task. But, thankful that my labors have been thus essentially lightened, and con- gratulating both my readers and myself that I have now so nearly finished, I close this sadly inadequate sketch, with the expression of my deliberate convic- tion, that Fame--"if she understand herself: and she think she do "-will " never desert" her favorite PEPPER.   ASTRONOMY: IN A PAMLIAR (BUT NOT IMPERTINENT) LECTURE. --.m--.---0-  Let us reason together.--HOLLOWAY. I hope here be truths.-MEASURE FOR MEASURE. INTRODUCTORY. SELECT a clear night. Now take a plummet, and if you hold the string between your thumb and finger, so that the ball is free to move, it will not move, but point directly toward the centre of the earth. To be frank, this has nothing whatever to do with our subject. I may remark, however, that if it pointed directly up, instead of, down, it would call your attention to a number of glistening little spots on the firmament, and perhaps one large one, all of which you have probably noticed before. It you have not, you will be obliged to me for turning your attention that way: and I must say, parenthetically, I think this the dullest audience I ever lectured before.  You will please not applaud. It is of these celestial luminaries I intend now to speak.  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7289-00000015"/> 28        Astronomy. HSTORICAL. ASTRONOMY is that science which treats of the opinions of people in regard to the heavenly bodies. In the light of this definition, perhaps it would not be proper to call it one of the " exact sciences;" but fortunately for the objects of this lec- ture it will not be necessary to class it at all. The science was invented by an Italian, whose name was Tronomi. As Christian names were unknown in the remote age in which he flourished, he was distinguished from his elder and less renowned brother in the man- ner peculiar to the period, and which still obtains among primitive nations-as for instance the aborigi- nes of America. Like many other scientific men, even of our own day, in ordinary affairs he was very much of a donkey, and of course was better known to the populace by his mistakes than his discoveries. Indeed, with the usual justice of popular decisions, he came to be called "Ass Tronomi;" and, while the name obtained, it was in time transferred from the savan to the science of which he was the founder. He was the friend of Paul, afterwards the Apostle, and died about the year twelve.   Astronomy.          29 GENERAL VIEW. The heavenly bodies have no resemblance whatever to human bodies, or the bodies of the lower animals, and are not necessarily in heaven; but the word Heaven, in an astronomical sense, is supposed to mean simply Space, and therefore may include places which cannot be found in the biblical heaven. These heavenly bodies consist of fixed stars, planets, and comets; of which, those first named are by far the most numerous; indeed, it is supposed that were the stars no larger than hazelnuts it would take an able- bodied man, forty-five years of age, twenty years to measure them- in a half-bushel measure, or rather longer by the peck. It is however believed that, upon an average, their size is somewhat greater than that of the Nut with which they have been compared. At their present immense distance from us, they are not as great objects of interest as they would be if nearer. It is thought by some philosophers that, were they as convenient to the hand as railroad stocks or government securities, this interest would reach as high as twenty-five per cent. It will readily be seen that their distance from us must be enormous, when  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7289-00000016"/> 30        Astronomy. we reflect that none compute it to be less than two sabbath-days' journey, while some have placed it at upwards of five thousand miles. It is believed by many that, notwithstanding the anxiety sometimes evinced by poets and others to convert favorite stars into permanent residences, they would prove but indifferent lodging-places, except perhaps in the sum- mer months. In the familiar expression "My stars!" one is supposed to refer to stellar property of the above-mentioned description to which his title has been proved, and which has been duly surveyed and staked out. Upon paper, stars are usually represented as having five points; theatrical stars generally have more. These points, in the first instance, are the rays; but it has sometimes been found that the innumerable points of an actress do not make the expected raise. FIXED STARS. The fixed stars-so named by some Yankee, to signify that they have been properly repaired-are now pretty generally believed to be suns. It is a significant fact, however, that many of them have f male names. From their singular habit of twink-   Astronomy.        31 ling on all occasions, they look like so many strug- gling beetles which have been fixed to the wall with a pin. Many suppose them to have been named from this circumstance, rather than from the one first named; but I think that no one can weigh the claims of the two hypotheses calmly and dispassionately and fail to decide in favor of the Repairing Theory-as it has been beautifully named by a distinguished mo- dern astronomer, whose name I am forbid mentioning by an innate sense of propriety. No one should think meanly of the stars for mak- ing their greatest displays on the clearest nights: man, himself so arrogant, ought never to censure the pride of a little star! THE PLANETS. All the heavenly bodies of any consequence, with the two exceptions of the fixed stars and the comets, are Planets. They are between thirty and fifty in number, if we include the asteroids--and perhaps it is but kind to do so, since it is only of late these have had the justice done them to be recognised at all. The planets do not consider it a mark of disrespect in anyone to call them by their given names; though  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7289-00000017"/> 32        Astronomy. they do not "come" when thus called, sooner than the President of the United States, or a very bad dog. They revolve about a certain fixed star which their own inhabitants have named the Sun; his real name, however, is Daniel Phoebus. This Sun gives away annually immense quantities of light and heat; which is very good of him, considering the pitch at which the times have arrived. In truth, he is sot kind and generous and unsuspecting, that many of his pretended friends are enabled to work him vast injury. The planets are remarkable for their finan- cial ability in effecting loans of the before-mentioned necessaries from him, and coming around him regu- larly year after year. Instead of returning the Sun's light when they have done with it, they distribute it broadcast among their friends and dependants-which perhaps is more creditable than keeping it to them- selves, as they do the heat; and this circumstance would afford us encouragement to hope for their ulti- mate reclamation were it not that they have continued in their present circle of dissipation beyond the me- mory of the oldest inhabitant. These impositions are likely to continue so long as their warm-hearted sub- ject has light to lend, or is represented in the pictures   Astronomy.         33 with a face of such rotundity and preternatural good- nature as must continually encourage them. VENUS, being the only female among the planets, and a very handsome one besides, should have the place of honor, and is therefore mentioned first on the list. It will excite the sympathies of the tender- hearted to learn that Venus has all her life been per- secuted-in point of fact, overwhelmed, with the impertinent attentions of the other planets. It is believed she was formerly partial to one MARS, a warlike neighbor of hers, with a remarka- bly red face; but their many quarrels and fallings-out came to disturb the harmony of the spheres to such a degree, that it was found necessary to separate them. EARTH otherefore stepped between; but while the peace has been effectually preserved, I regret to state that he has been made the subject of much unjust obloquy and reproach. It is thought, however, that Earth will keep moving on-performing his accus- tomed revolutions as per programme till further notice. JUPITER is a very good-sized planet-indeed, quite large for his age-and is expected soon to be old snough to set up for himself. He has suffered ex. 2*  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7289-00000018"/> Astronomy.        35 think himself handsome. He is quite vain of a num- ber of rings-only two, I think, after all-which have been presented him by some infatuated foreign planet of the other sex. He is in no way remarkable, and we pass to URANUS, or You-rein-us-who named himself out of compliment to the Sun, at a time when he supposed himself the farthest from the sway of that luminary, and that the title might serve the latter as a perpetual reminder of the allegiance of all his subjects. He is sometimes called Herschel-from the two words her and shell; but the difficulty of determining with any satisfaction what female is thus mysteriously placed in the possessive case has latterly thrown the name into disfavor. Uranus is a good planet. Little MERCURY is page and errand-boy to the Sun, who keeps the sprightly planet about his person, and may be said almost to carry him in his pocket. Being so near the fountain of heat, Mercury never freezes, and thinks nothing of going up to five hundred in the shade. A crop of little planets-at present called Asteroids- are springing up around Mars and Venus, and four    &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7289-00000019"/> 36         Astronomy. of them  have gone in society for a considerable time.* They seem  disposed to band together and move in a circle by themselves. It will not be neces- sary (or indeed easy) to repeat their names. Hanging on the confines of the Sun's estates, and apparently looking for a weak place in the fence, a planet called LEVERRIERt has been observed and * Should any question the soundness of the theory wrapped up in this sentence, they will find it strongly supported in "HORN'S Examiner into ihe Laws of Nature," in which may be found the following eloquent passage: "The planets Jupiter, Saturn, Herschel, and so on, bring forth their seeds in like manner. What a lot of young planets they have revolving about them 1" Professor Horn, the learned author of the above-mentioned work, is a deep thinker and profound philosopher. In the tame book may be found this remarkable axiom: "A man or woman possessing a contracted skull, prevents expansion of'mind in man." Farther extracts from my learned friend will be given in the course of the lecture. His is no common mind; remote ages will do me honor for having been the first to say it. t This planet was discovered by a Frenchman; and as a proud and perpetual assertion that Uranus, discovered by an English rival, was not the very last and farthest of the planets, he called   Astronomy.          37 warned off the premises. He has the appearance and actions of a vagabond, and it. is hoped he will sheet off in time to save himself trouble. This I fear quite exhausts our list of planets for the season. I may say, however, we are in constant communication with discoverers (and manufacturers) and hope to be, able soon to swell the number very considerably. MOONSHNE: AN ANECDOTE. One day, in turning over the playthings which had amused his youth, old father Sun discovered a num- ber of ten-pin balls, parts of various sets. It occurred to him that here was an acceptable present for his little planets. So, calling out-"Look sharp, my lads!" he threw them all out from an upper window, in one handful. A glorious scramble ensued. Jupiter, being very much of a gentleman, would take but four, though entitled, from his age and respectability, to at least half of them. Earth, having been unaccount- it the very-er-or, in French, Le Verrier. Some have proposed naming it Neptune or Nap-tune, as its " part," in the perpetual concerted celestial music, must, from its mortal slowness, have a tolerably soporific effect.  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7289-00000020"/> 38        Astronomy. ably timid on that occasion, secured but one. But the forward and greedy Saturn was known to have seven after the division, if division it may be called, and is supposed to have secreted several more.  What became of the others, is not certainly known. Uranus, it seems, got several-six, it is said ; and some declare they have seen one in possession of Mars. Nobody was gallant enough to bring one to Venus, so she remained without. But the pith of the story remains to be told. He discovered that they who had been fortunate enough to secure any of the balls, had conceived the idea of having solar systems of their own; and having set their globular gifts flying around their heads, in imi- tation of their great patron, were nearly bursting in the effort to afford them the necessary light. This sight so tickled the ribs of old Phoebus, that a fit of inextinguishable laughter seized him,-so to this day it is animating his visage. In the excess of his sly humor, he allowed himself to shine on the little moons-well knowing the planets would be deceived into the belief that they were doing it themselves. It is even said that the infant planets which have sprung up between Mars and Venus are only fragments of a   Astronomy.         39 larger planet which had burst itself in the ridiculous endeavor to illuminate its moon. This, however, is not probable. The lava from eruptions, so frequent on the earth, is also thought to be no more than the per- spiration consequent on similar and super-terrestrial exertions. MORAL EPISODE. The animalcula which infest Earth--called human beings-annoy him very much by persistent attempts to excoriate him, and penetrate to his vital parts. It makes him angry also to be called "Mother Earth." In one way and another, they had at one time goaded him to that pitch: of madness that he nearly extermi- nated them by drowning. He has since been sorry he did not do the work more thoroughly. THe has however contrived another method of effecting his purpose, tiat bids fair to accomplish his end with very little trouble to himself. By the raising of little wrinkles and ridges on his skin in various places, he has divided them off into separate bodies or nations; who imagine that naturally they are each other's ene- mies, and have been long engaged trying to extermi- nate one another. At the latest dates*- there is every * Written in 1855.  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7289-00000021"/> 4        Astronomy. prospect of a success equal to that which attended the exertions of the Kilkenny cats. They are intolerably conceited, withal; and every nation is inclined to think every other barbarous, cruel, and rapacious. There is, however, but very lit- tle difference in this respect-the human nature per- vading them all. Yet one of these is far too modest to praise itself; it is called the Yankee Nation. George Washington-an individual who flourished a sword in the eighteenth century, and left his mark- belonged to this nation; and so do a great many at the present day. We belong to it. There are over twenty-five millions of people now living in this country: and the most of these are slaves-some to others, and the remainder to themselves. [Who can think of his country without emotion I My enthu- siasm should now be pardoned; for, having carried me away, it has at length in the kindest manner restored me to society, friends, and my subject.] THE MOON, AND TELESCOPES. All nations have united in praising the Moon for Ir modesty and good sense-in both which relations she is quite above reproach, and stands unimpeached. -.us   Astronomy.         41 An "exiled Italian" once remarked, that the moon was more useful to us than the sun; because the for- mer shone in the night, when there was the greater need of light. The observation illustrates anew the extraordinary acuteness and sense for which his peo- ple have been praised so long. We, therefore, take the warmest possible interest in that luminary, and even call her the Moon, as a token of distinction and pledge of encouragement. From the intense desire of astronomers to bring the moon into something like a friendly vicinity, they have been led to the invention of instruments, whose action is calculated to entice her. The Tele- scope-a round instrument, long in use-is in great repute fori this purpose; and one species, called from its habit of mind the reflecting telescope, is said to possess a sort of fascination for her. This fact illus- trates in a remarkable manner the good sense which has been already mentioned as one of her attributes. Many claim, however, that she will come farther for a good refracting telescope than for the other kind; and a somewhat peculiar experience inclines me to this view of the case myself. r  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7289-00000022"/> Astronomy.  SOMEWHAT PECULIAR EXPERIENCE. A few years since I sat about improving, and, if possible, perfecting the refracting telescope. It is well known (to at least fifty men of science) that the great desideratum in this instrument is a material which shall unite in itself quite a number of nearly opposite qualities; such as, for a single instance, high "refractive" with a low "dispersive" power- there being a limit to the size of glass lenses, and consequently to the number of rays of light admit- ted from the object, on account of the rapidity with which this fatal propensity to " disperse" strengthens when we increase their size and refractive power.* * ' Achromatic telescopes"-characterized at first as a "lame invention"-are said to get over this difficulty quite hand- somely, notwithstanding their rheumatism. At the time of which I write, I had not seen them. Mr. RICHARD (vulgarly called DICK), in his Sidereal ieavens, speaks of Aerial Tele- scopes: but I have no time for such light matters. He pro- nounces the Dorpatrick (sometimes abbreviated to Dorpat) Telescope in Russia, a very capital instrument. He thinks it is capable of "multiplying" almost as fast as the Babbage Calcu- lating Machine; and that it can " bring up" anything except a family of children: domestic pursuits being somewhat out of its   Astronomy.                  43 Having observed the extraordinary amount of light which recently has been received through the Spirit- ual mediums, I conceived the idea of doing away entirely with the secondary lenses, and of filling the instrument with fourth-proof whiskey. I am re- joiced to announce that the experiment was success- ful, though unfortunate. REMARKABLE LUNAR PHENOMENA. Having at length made everything ready, and pre- pared myself by silent meditation,-not forgetting to establish a communication with the medium by means of a stop-cock in the side of the instrument,-I covered the moon with my telescope, and took a view. For a space, all was darkness. At length a voice of more than mortal sweetness exclaimed, in thrilling, technical accents,-" Uncover your object-glass !' The darkness was accounted for. In my haste and agitation I had endeavored to look through a plate of brass, of considerable thickness. I did as I was directed; and as I looked again I was not disap- 'scope. Mr. Dick is not addicted to extravagance in his state- ments. Of his predictions it is said that, mirabile dictu I they all "come true," as the darkey said of the auger.   &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7289-00000023"/> "        Astronomy. pointed to find the moon within eight rods of me. I at ouce observed that the " man in the moon " was nothing more than a huge, fantastical erection,-in truth, a house;-whose two upper windows, being illuminated, were plainly the eyes. In one of these windows, the sash being up, a man in his shirt-sleeves was leaning carelessly, and smoking a short black pipe. As soon as he perceived me, he shaded his eyes with his hand for a moment, and then, as if assured, started up eagerly and shouted at the top of his voice,-"Maurice I my old boy,-how are you?" I replied, through my tears,-"Very well, thank you, old fellow,--how are you?" "O, so-so,-so-so," said he, as he wiped his mouth with the back of his hand; "the old 'ooman's be'n complaining, lately, and I'm a little anxious on her account, but I'm very well myself." His classic language and elegant tastes at once showed me he was a gentleman of education and refinement. In the course of an animated con- versation with him, I gleaned facts which, while they are unsurpassed in interest, are of the utmost im- portance to the scientific world.   Astronomy         45 AEROLITES. The mystery which has hitherto enveloped these singular and dangerous visitants he at once and for ever dispelled by this episodical remark: "Them 'hot shot' I throw down once't in a w'ile,-how often I've thought of the fun they must make! To see a chap run to pick 'em up,- and how quick he concludes to drop 'em Hand to hear him wonder where the d-1 they. come from, too!-0-! ho! ho! hoe! 0-0-O! ho! ho! ho!"-and the excessive laughter made him turn black in the face. ECLIPSES. The marked frequency of eclipses, of late, has come to be an immense annoyance to him. Many a valuable day has been lost to him; and many a time and oft has he missed his way, being overtaken by the sudden darkness when far from home. He says we on the earth have no idea of the terrible nature of a solar eclipse at the moon. And indeed it must be terrible, in its suddenness, from the absence of that twilight shading which the presence of an atmosphere would induce.  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7289-00000024"/> "         Astronomy. ATMOSPHERE. A BREEZE. I inquired what possible use one's lungs could be to him where there was no air?* "( A very proper question," said he, gravely; "it?s a bore to be with- out it: but my wife is musical; and twenty times a day she gives me an ' Air, with variations,' by some windy composer,-and by the time I've heard two or three I don't want anything." On the uttering of this piece of sarcasm, a portentous face appeared over his shoulder.  "It's awful dull, up  here," said he, after a pause: "I wish, a thousand times a day, I was back to your planet." "What!"I exclaimed, in wonder,-" were you    ever one of us?" "Why, bless you. yes!" he replied; "I come here to fill the place of t'other man."  "Yes! yes!" shrieked    his *In reference to this interesting subject Professor Horn remarks as follows:--"It is no wonder that the scientific astronomer can see no atmosphere round the moon that carries vapors of water; the moon is too young yet; the moon has not 5 et matured. The moon cannot produce vegetation as yet and consequently don't require atmosphere to carry off vapor of water, until the moon arrives to her degree of perfection to- bring forth vegetation."   Astronomy.         47 wife, tauntingly,-no longer able to contain herself,- "he had to come, Maurice,-he had to come!" "Hold your tongue, will ye " said the Benedick, sternly,-" what do you know about war?" "War!" she thundered,-"-it wasn't war!-it was that foolig piece o' poetry you wrote!" "W'at piece, hussy!- w'at piece?-tell 'im 'f y' kin!--tell 'im 'f y' kin 1" said the husband, curtly and doggedly, with his hands in his pockets; upon which he ejected slowly a slender stream of tobacco-juice from between two front teeth. "What, you wretch!--do you dare to say you didn't write ' Hi diddle diddle!' and git sent here for speakin' so disrespectful of the moon!" "Wrote 't y'self, wife,-know y' did!" said the man, nervously, and looking uneasily at her from the corners of his eyes. "O-O-Oh! you villain!" she shrieked, with energy; and, with that, ran back,-her "noble form " being lost in the " dim profound " of the room. There was no time lost, however; for I had not yet begun to wonder " what next?" when- "Take that!" issued from the distance-also one of my friend's "hot shot,"--which, to his great joy, missed him and passed out at the window. The next moment an accident occurred. The " falling body"  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7289-00000025"/> 48        Astronomy. struck the object-glass of my instrument exactly in the centre, and penetrated even unto its heart and veins-performing the office of a purge. My eyes were injured somewhat by the explosion, and became greatly inflamed. When I had returned to my friends, they took the liberty to disbelieve my account of the accident; and invented a theory which, singularly enough, when taken with the wther, precludes the idea of an experti- 7zenlam crucis,--the lunar phenomena, the damage to the instrument, and the redness of my eyes, being explained on either hypothesis. COMETS. These heavenly bodies resemble snakes in being all head and tail. They are unlike snakes in having a very fiery appearance: red snakes, much to the regret of naturalists, being astonishingly rare. Comets lead a very irregular life, and are a scandal and disgrace to all their connexions. We have seen the eagle descend from a great height and take the newly- acquired means of subsistence from the industrious hawk,-flying away from  the astonished bird as quickly as he came. Before the hawk recovers the   Astronomy.          49 ordinary use of his senses, the eagle is lost to sight, and not particularly dear to memory. The efforts of the comet are attended with the same disgraceful success. Watching his opportunity, he rushes down when the sun is so distracted by his many cares as to see nothing apart from them; and taking from that unsuspecting luminary as much fire-wood as would last him, if frugally used, twice the length of his natural life, flies away to his own country,-- wasting incredible quantities of light and heat, as he goes, in vulgar and ridiculous display. He has the unblushing audacity to come back again, after a few years, sometimes very much shorn of his splendor, and presenting a very ordinary appearance indeed. When sufficiently near, he repeats his disgrace, and provides himself with a new tail. Comets frequently rise to that pitch of -variety and extravagance that they will unfeelingly sport two, three, and even six tails, at one and the same time,-flaunting them in the very face and eyes of the injured sun.   But Justice at last overtakes the offender: six-tailed comets are never seen but once. At a time when people did not know everything- which we may suppose to have been before the 3  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7289-00000026"/> 50          Astronomy. advent of the present generation-comets were looked on with a jealous eye.*   No sooner was the cry,- "The Comet!" raised, than one-half thought there would be war directly, and the remainder that he designed staying his stomach with two or three of the planets. While these induced a tremendous and infernal clamor by means of shoutings, tin-pans,and calabashes, the former ordered an infinite number of MJisereres to be sung, and made appropriations for ammunition and the public defences. When we con- * Much of the honor of having removed such of these vulgar prejudices as passed to this generation may be claimed by Pro- fessor Horn: "Comets should not be looked at with alarm and terror where they appear in the countries of our solar system. They can only be organized bodies, for the purpose of moving out of the great city or great empire of solar. systems into infinite space, there to collect matter, and return into the city, distributing their matter through the solar systems to nourish and compose the young planets. The long tails which they drag after them, can be nothing more than matter they leave behind them; the sun shining on it gives it the color of the rainbow." How plausible the premises, how ingenious the argument, how convincing the conclusion I Mark the play of fancy at the close. Verily, this "Horn" shall be exalted!   Astronomy.         51 sider that while on the one hand the earth remains a tempting but untasted morsel, on the other wars innu- merable have taken place, and that these theories were equally plausible,-we cannot avoid the conclu- sion that, when war or other calamities threaten. a na- tion, it is better to bluster and make a great noise than to waste money in appropriations or piety in prayers. CONCLUSION. It is manifestly impracticable to embrace, within the limits of a single lecture, more than a tithe of the details of that science to which it may be devoted. Many astronomers, in similar cases, have tried to get in two-tenths, and have ignominiously failed. I might perhaps have touched off the "Nebular Theory" of Newton, were it not already exploded; or expanded on the "Contraction of the Earth;" or stopped to in- quire if the "Motion of .the Sun in Space" was seconded,-I might have driven the car of Speculation along the Via Lactea, only that my way was clear: but, nilly willy,* I have now reached the end. I think I hear some one ask, Who held the stakes when Con- stellation trotted against Galaxy? I reply,-O'Rian; * Latin.  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7289-00000027"/> 52        Astronomy. the studs were groomed by Boots and the Little Bare, and ridden by those stars in the sporting firmament, L. D. Baran and Ark Toorus. Again I am ques- tioned: one of my hearers inquires if I am a lineal de- scendant of the great "Ass Tronomi "? I hanswer,- 'Ardly. His mine the Hitalian haccent? ADVICE TO ASTRONOMERS. From the heedlessness consequent on professional enthusiasm, astronomers are liable to affections of the lungs and throat. When you have had tightness at the chest for a week, accompanied by difficulty of breathing,-lungs inflamed,-expectoration difficult, --much fever,-flesh disappearing;-then know you have a cold: I may say-a SEVERE cold. Don't neglect it. I repeat, with affectionate earnestness, don't ne- glect it. Consumption, that hollow-eyed monster with such an extraordinary appetite, begins to lick his gory chaps when he hears an astronomer say "As- trodoby " for Astronomy. My SIDEREAL PILLS are now afforded at one dollar a box. aS TAKE THEM c     They are not for a day, but for all time. They absolutely pounce with delight on Dis. ease, and tear him with hideous yells from the   Astronomy.        53 body. Their cry [is,--' Buy us, and we'll do you good." Astronomers!--AVOID THE NIGHT AIR ; and when you feel particularly well, and know you ought to feel ill, do not lull yourselves into fatal security; but commence at once taking these pills (one at a dose), morning, noon, and night. Cultivate both your equanimity of mind and your taste, by the daily perusal of my Circular. BPERSEVERE,? and you will be happy.  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7289-00000028"/> MR. PEPPER'S SECOND FEAT. -------- HAVING learned, soon after the appearance of his first poem, that many papers had copied the effusion, with laudatory comments, the excitable poet could contain himself no longer; yielding to the im- pulses of his higher nature, he immediately conceived and gave birth to a sentimental "Solileqy," which, with daring license, he addressed to a "Berd on the fens." Fearing the consequence of his indulging much in hasty composition (so ruinous to young authors), I affected to disparage his first poem, declar- ing he was fortunate in getting it published at all, shorn as it was of its moral, and that nothing but care and faithfulness could keep him in the place he occu pied. His reply satisfied me that I had been officious, and did not well understand him. There is a fine   Mr. Pepper's Second Poem.        55 contrast between the fire and energy of the "Colu- sion," and the tender melancholy and melting pathos in which the "Solileqy " abounds. SOTLRQ QY, ADREST TO A BERD ONTO THE FENS. COMPOASED BY MR. K. N. PEPPER, ESQ., WHLST RECLININ ONTO A SHED CLOAST BI. Mi pirty litle Animel, a-settin onto the pickits 1- How fur hev you floo to-day-say, pirty Berd? (doant ster-i aint lookin; so be not in hury.) How ide like fur to set thayr, onto the next pickit, ef it woodent hirt, &amp; mi heft woodent braik down the fens, &amp; you wood stay &amp; let me smooth of the fethers. (its moast butiful Ploomig, i swow!-but to resoom:) How i long fur your wings, pirty Bird, so i cood fli of. ide leve this werld, i wood, &amp; go sumers els. Your vois is so swete, too,-i wunder if thay put shuger in Wen it wos maid I How i wood like to be a- singin al day, &amp; at nite go to roost onto a lim, Cairles!-in slepe ide dreme ov mi mait, &amp; say: Hope your a-dremin ov me likewais, mi mait." Ken you fli to the clowds &amp; bac in a minit? So cood i, mi pirty, ef i oanly hed your wings. But you woodent kech me a-comin back tho, after ide got sech a start: o no, pirty Animel! ;de fly to the Hevins. &amp; git prict onto the pints ov the stars-  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7289-00000029"/> VIr. Pepper's Second Poem. ide pie at the man in the Moon, &amp; maik him wine his left i- ide-wots the use a-tockin, wen you doant no nothin? You aint me. Your oanly a swete pirty Berd, always a chirupin, &amp; you aint Mellencollic &amp; sad. But i am: ime full ov potry &amp; felin, &amp; author ov varis pomes: but o ide say go to al, ef i cood oanly fli with wings. How ide looc doun &amp; se rivers a-runnin, with men onto the bangs a-kechin ov fish, &amp; Bufalows a-roamin the prayris, with hair al stremin, &amp; injans a shootin at ramden with bos &amp; ars. ide fli to south ameriky &amp; se the Snaiks in the gingles a-crawlin &amp; a-swallerin ov little Bois. &amp; then ide fly to afriky &amp; se the Elefans, 1 a-fitin with the Rinoserus, &amp; a-givin ov him fits with his trunc, wile he wos a-gittin ov his bowls chaingd bi the ivery Tusc ov his Ennemy. afoar ide got much tand bi the rather worm Son belongin to afriky, ide fli to aishy, inhailin the C air on mi way-to the Kedentry, &amp; a-tryin to Banish the smel ov the afriken nativs. in gloris aishy ide se menny a Tiger a-chaisin the chines &amp; a-bitin a pese frum the leg, Wich wood maik me so sad ide pressently cum over to rooshy a-wunderin wot maiks Mr. CEZAR so prowd ov his Cussax-- 1st taikin a lingerin looc at the tal fouls in chiny. aext from rooshy ide cum into tirky, bein so ni,-   Mr. Pepper's Second Poem.   not expectin fur to se much on acount ov the smoak, But not riskin a sques onto the nec with a bo-string Bi a-refusin to talk a litle Sublim Poart with the suitin. But, dere litle Berdy, aint you tired a-folowin mi fortins, &amp; not hevin no help from your wings? onhapy Animel I how sory i am ime so crule  Ef i hedent a-sudenly thougt ov your felins i mite hev onfortinetly carrid you all over urup. But cumin hoam ore the oshun wil sune restoar helth. now youre hoam --want that did quic, pirty Berdy ? But the cus hes floo &amp; desertid the pickit, &amp; nothin is left but i &amp; the shed &amp; the fens-- nun ov wich cant fli. ongraitful litle rip: after al my delliket atenshuns, hese throo bac Sech welth ov afeckshun into mi pend up boosum! So it alers hes been. o i shel di i thine, Bi sooiside, after ive roat 2 or 3 moar pomes. in 1 i shel bid fairwel to a Werld onfelin, &amp; maik it so harrowin &amp; afecktin that every boddy cant hep sheddin torrens ov teres, &amp; bein blindid-like, fur severil days, bi Wo. &amp; al the laydis wil were " K. N. Pepper, Esq.," onto pincushins, &amp; wish he hedent cum to *sch a woilent End: He so young and hansum too.-but i cant go on. i fele bad: ile desend frum mi eminens &amp; talk suthin worm. Fairwel wicked Werld; &amp; you, onfelin Berd, adoo  3*   &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7289-00000030"/> THE ANGUISHED BRIDE; OR, THE ECHOING PISTOL. A TALE. BY WILLIE WILTON WILLOUGHRBT "Such is life." CHAPTER    I. EDOUARD. A spirit yet unquelled and high, That claims and seeks ascendency.-BYRON. His was the gifted eye, which grace still touched As if with second nature; and his dreams, His childish dreams, were lit by hues of heaven- Those which make Genius.-L. E. L   . HANM.-He was a man, take him for all in all, I shall not look upon his like again.-DAVID COPPERFIELD. EDOUAD BLANCHFORD, in Body and Fortune --in everything but Mind-had been Frowned on by a cruel Fate! He was born of poor but honest   The Anguished Bride.      59 parents, and marked slightly by the small-pox. In spite of these great Obstacles to Success-to which may be added an unfortunate reddish tinge to his hair-he had a noble Mind; indeed, he was possessed of, and as usual made miserable by, the most exalted Genius I At the early age of ten, he had constructed, entirely alone, a perfect Wheelbarrow, with side-boards and all! It is related, that immediately on completing this miracle of Mechanical Genius, and without wait- ing for the plaudits of the World, he put on the side- boards, and filling it with the largest stones he could find, magnanimously wheeled it off a Precipice-in his enthusiasm very nearly going with it. There was true Greatness of Mind! He had already risen above the Smiles and Nods of a Hollow World, and was calmly happy in the contemplation of his Genius, and in planning similar great and noble Deeds for the Future! "What if I am poor, and slightly marked with the small-pox!" he would ejaculate, in a burst of proud, disdainful Rapture,-" what if my hair is a little reddish -or entirely brick, for that matter;-my Genius, I am happy to say, is not marked by that fell disease,-it has never had a complaint of any kind. I know I'm  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7289-00000031"/> VV    ,  oxne Anguished Bride. smart I Something whispers it in the sweet balmy gales of Heaven, and thunders it quite distinetly in the Cataract! I am determined to impress the con-  X viction on the World. Oh! I am as certain, as I am  I of the unfortunate color of my hair, that I shall Do Something in Time! and mayhap (for who knows what Heaven has in store for him?) the Whole World may yet be at my feet I " Edouard did not always talk in this way. No; far from it At times he was frigid with sad Melan. choly! In fact, this was his unfortunate condition most of the time. His worldly-minded parent would Dften address him, at these moments, in the most un. feeling manner. Thus, on one occasion, observing "s unhappy son plunged in deeper melancholy, by alf, than he had ever seen him in before, he insulted tim by this remark:                  - "Cheer up, Ned! [by such short diminutives would e presume to approach his talented son!] cheer up, Vy boy, and take a little so'thin'."  The reader will at once infer, from this remark,  that the elder Mr. Blanchford was not a stranger to  the Fatal Bowl. Did his noble-minded son accept    B   I'he Anguished Bride.      to the parental advice? Quite the contrary. Hereplied as follows: Sire! tempt me not You can't comprehend my nature. *  *  * Oh! Father"  *  What he would have said, is lost to his besotted Parent and the World, and can only be conjectured; some Noble Sentiment would undoubtedly have escaped his lips. As it was, overcome by his wounded Feelings, and a certain shock his spirit always received at the very thought of the Intoxi- eating Draught-intensified by the fumes of his Parent's breath-he fainted in that Parent's arms. CHAPTER    II. HORTENSIA. A thing of beauty is a joy for ever.-KEATS. Of such is the kingdom of heaven.-WALTER SCOTT. HORTENSIA AMELIA PLANTAGENET    lived on an eminence in the outskirts of the village, in an elegant and expensive mansion of White Marble. Her father was worth Millions of Sordid Dollars, and of course he was a proud, cold, unfeeling Wretch.  There was  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7289-00000032"/> 62     The Anguished Bride. a hard look about his eyes, and he seemed to be always thinking of some new scheme to increase his wealth, or oppress his Poor but Honest neighbors. Hortensia Amelia-although no reader would perhaps expect it-was a Noble Girl, and despised all the lovers her sordid father and proud mother had provided for her. These lovers were all members of the Wealthy Classes, and were very ignorant and conceited. Cain Sharkey, one of them-being possessed of nearly five hundred thousand dollars, and belonging to a high Family-was looked on with great favor by both of Hortensia Amelia's Parents. She, on the contrary, in her artless way, would frequently remark that she "couldn't bear him!" ...... When her Parents began one day to remonstrate with her on this apparently reasonless prejudice, she burst into a passionate flood of silent tears, and then, for the space of half an hour, gave herself up to un- conscious musing. When she had recovered from her emotion-which her Parents had observed with astonishment-she frankly confided to them her views of Destiny, the World, Happiness, the Unattainable, and Communion of Mind.   The Anguished Bride.      63 "Parents!-progenitors!" she at length concluded, "urge me not! I can never be Cain Sharkey's wife! I loathe him!-I detest him 1" Whom did she love? Alas Hpoor Stricken Deer -as yet, no one possessed the priceless treasure of that Noble Heart I  .......... One night-a terrible night-I may say, a Tempes- tuous night Ha solitary rush-light gleamed from that proud Mansion, quite late in the evening. Let us not be mistaken. We will now state distinctly that it was past one o'clock. The Parents were talking in Low Tones, cruelly deciding the fate of their daughter, without making her a party to the scheme. Soon finishing their consultation, and shaking hand sover the agreement to this Deed of Injustice-perhaps Blood!-the Father went to, the door and called sternly to Hortensia Amelia. She was not awakel   *  *  *  *  * She had gone to bed at nine o'clock, and had consequently been four hours reveling in the sweet dreams of Unconscious, Unsuspecting Innocence. She was a sound sleeper-innocence is ever sound asleep  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7289-00000033"/> The Anguished Bride.  by one o'clock-and she was not easily roused. Alas i better that she had never been awakened !-in which case she would have awoke of herself, in a Better Place. She came to the head of the flight of magni- ficent marble steps that led to her bedroom-saw her father's stern face glowering on her from the foot- and, comprehending at once the extent of her Misery, gave an unearthly shriek, and sank upon the floor!   CHAPTER III, THE RESCUE. Alas, sir ! are you here ? things that love night, Love not such nights as these.--KING LEAR. The night was dark and fearful, The blast went wailing by.-MILTON. EDOUARD was abroad that night. Yes I his fever- ed brain was on the rack I His thoughts were too mighty for rest!  Ie went out to hold communion with the elements. They soothed his soul, even while wetting him to the skin. The hoarse voice of the astounding blast shouted "Return !"--the deafen.   The Anguished Bride.   ing thunder made the same appeal! Their entreaties were in vain! He kept on. Why did he direct his steps toward the dwelling of Hortensia Amelia? Because his thoughts were there! He had long dreamed in silence of that Angelic Face, and often, of a dark night, had he paced before her window, braving the generally savage watch-dog, and hoping for a gleam of her lamp to cheer him. All that pre- vented his being frequently cheered in that way, was the fact of her always retiring so early.  *   * *  a   e *  a   ,  *   e *   *  0  0  *  e      *   4 What means that solitary rush-light-that angry call-that fearful shriek ? Instinct told him immedi- ately that the Being he had so long in secret wor- shipped-devotedly but despairingly-was in dan- ger! Further directions, from Instinct or any other person, were superfluous. Knowing, through some superhuman Agency, that the window just over him, in the second story, was the one he must enter, if any-and having a secret conviction that the door was both double-bolted and strongly barred-he stepped back a few paces, and for part of an instant communed with himself.   &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7289-00000034"/> "     The Anguished Bride. What did he do next? Any common man--con- sidering that the window was upward of twenty feet from the ground-would have done nothing. Edou- ard Blanchford was not a common man. His ac- tions, his habits-the very fact of his being in such a place at such a time, prove that he was no common man. His very next Action--so Brave and Diffi- cult-has a tendency to make the fact still more apparent. Collecting all his energies (of which he possessed many), and receiving just then some Super- natural Aid, he ran with the velocity of lightning, and sprang through the window-dasshing the sash to atoms I and lacerating his hand to such a frightful degree that several drops of blood seemed on the point of bursting from the wound I HORTENSIA AM LTTA had had a Presentiment that Deliverance was to come through the third window from the right, looking south (the very window!) and for several minutes had been watching it with anxiety. When she saw that Noble Form burst through it, and with the acquired momentum run   The Anguished Bride.      67 forward several steps to save himself from falling-- she uttered a Shriek of Pleasure, and with the most touching tenderness of tone inquired anxiously if he were hurt* "Are you?" he asked, with frantic eagerness. "I am very well, now /" she replied, casting down her eyes; and then, in some confusion, was about to say nothing, when, catching a sudden glimpse of the Bloody Hand of Edouard, she shrieked once more, and immediately tore a strip of linen from one of her under-garments to bind up the wound. Touched and melted by this evidence of affection, and partly overcome by the Superhuman Effort he had made, as well as the loss of blood, Edouard asked Hortensia for a glass of water. Casting upon him a look of mingled mild reproach and Unfathom- able Love, she said: "How can you think of water, love, at such a moment?" "Then fly, love-fly with me-at once-at once /" he cried, seizing her unresisting form, and leaping madly from the window I '      *3      * c* ** eeee*  e  e   $  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7289-00000035"/> 68      The Anguished Bride. CHAPTER    IV. THE FATAL FIREARM. Last scene of all, That ends this strange, eventful history.-As You LIKE IT. To be. or not to be; that is the question.-ANON. O death! where is thy sting?--IRVING. This is the last of earth.--DR. JOHNSON. How Edouard found himself at the door of a cler- gyman two miles distant, with the insensible form of Hortensia in his arms-is every whit as miraculous as his wonderful leap. Oh! ye Worldly ones of this Earth! learn, in this humble Tale, that the only Ma- gician, the only real Wonder-Worker, is LOVE I A slight application of hartshorn to the nose of Hortensia Amelia having  "brought her to," they were quickly made one; and Hortensia having feed the clergyman, as Edouard had forgotten his purse, they at once repaired to the Beautiful Valley which he had selected as their future residence. Precisely a minute after their departure from the clergyman's house, Mr. Plantagenet and Cain Shar- key arrived-their six horses, as well as themselves, all breathless and foaming.   The- Anguished Bride.      69 "Here's a go!" cried Cain Sharkey, in the elegant phraseology for which he was distinguished. "Plan- tagenet! my intended Father-in-law!" he proceeded, "mark me! I must have vengeance I damn me!" 1"Certainly," replied the obsequious, fawning Plan- tagenet,-" of course." With that they leaped furi- ously into their carriage, and drove impetuously away. It was eve; or, rather, it had been eve, and was now night. Edouard and Hortensia had passed the evening in a state of bliss unspeakable-holding each other by the hand, and gazing fondly into each other's eyes. "My lovel" at length said the blushing bride, "my eyes grow heavy, and I am weary; I think I will retire." Upon which, kissing Edouard affec- tionately, she glided from his presence like a thing of grace. Edouard then rose; and, after yawning wearily, and rubbing his heavy eyes, began to pace the room furiously, and weep- briny tears, at the same time tearing his already thin hair, and rending  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7289-00000036"/> 70     The Anguished Bride. his apparel. At last his surcharged heart found re- lief in words: "Alas! what have I done? Wretch that I am I Villain I Monster! Cold-hearted Abortion! I have doomed Hortensia, the tenderly-reared, to a life of Misery and Want! I am poor, and the World has not yet done me justice. How can I repair the Mis- chief I have done? Alas! there is but one way! Come, sweet Friend," he continued, drawing a richly- mounted Pistol from his bosom, and kissing it- "comel relieve me! Oh! relieve me-I pray, re- lieve me from this Load which seems large enough for six! Hortensia Amelia, my fond Bride--a last adieu!" A report rang through the little cot, and reverbe- rated for Miles along the valley. A Shriek soon fol- lowed, ten times as loud and Appalling. Cain Sharkey and Mr. Plantagenet heard both I "I know Hortensia's voice!" said the elder of the two Travellers, in a confident tone--leaping from the carriage and clearing the fence at a single bound. He saw an object clothed in white, standing at the corner of the house, with a handkerchief at her face. Reader, that Object-that Weeping Object-clothed in white-standil g at the corner of the house-in   The Anguished Bride.       71 Agony--was-HORTENSIA   AMELIA BLANCHFORDI Bride and Widow in one, or rather five, short hours I t "Father!" she shrieked, without removing the handkerchief from her face-" go in! and behold Your Work! Your Son-in-law, Sir, is dead!"It is, Sir, a Sad Fact;! * X  Reader! she lives--but she has never married. A constant melancholy shades her fine features and im- pairs her appetite. When -Edouard Blanchford is mentioned in her presence (which has never but once happened, as her friends avoid the painful topic), she weeps. I saw her turning the crank at the well in her father's yard. I mentioned Edouard Blanchford. She wept and turned away. Her only comfort is in Labor. Consequently she weeds the garden, in her Widow's weeds, and affects the passer-by to tears by such a touching sight. Cain Sharkey, after a life of dissipation, fell a vic- tim to his passions, and died very Unhappy. Hortensia Amelia's father has Changed! He is  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7289-00000037"/> 72     The Anguished Bride. now a good man. His wife is now a good woman- old, but happy, and devoted to her daughter. Edouard's father now sleeps by the side of his Noble Son. Reader, farewell and, in your intercourse with your brothers and sisters of the great Human Family, ever "Speak gently to the erring." -------eri n g .':: :-   MR. PEPPER'S THRD EFFORT. ----o--- THE forebodings of Genius are of the nature of prophecies in embryo; but when they happen to fail of their realization, as did the forebodings of Pep- per, alluded to in the following paragraph, which the Knickerbocker prefixed to the poem-the world re- joices, and looks out as usual for new poems: "Again are we favored with a spirited ' Pome' by Mr. K. N. Pepper, who touches nothing that he doesn't ornament. In a private note to the Editor, he intimates that his poetical power may be failing him. Not so: there are parts of ' The Suferings ov a Man' which are fully equal to portions of the' Lines to a Berd onto the Fens.' Oh, no; Mr. Pepper must not lose confidence in himself. He has only just com- menced his career; he has been writing, as it were, 4  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7289-00000038"/> 74     Mr. Pepper's Third Effort. 'with one arm tied behind him.' Macte virtute, Mr. Pepper :" THE SUFERINGS OV A MAN. COMPOASD INTO RIME BI MR. K. N. PEPPER, ESQ-. As he traveld bi the way, this Man wos herd fur to say (al aloan he wos, you se,) i wish i hed sum 1 fur cunpany. But thair he wos, al aloan, &amp; that is Suferink, we oan. But as he wos a-goin frum hoam, gitin kind ov loan-sum, He side severil times cuite hard, mournfuly a-stroaking ov his baird, until his Suferings wos so intens He bload his noas bi the fens, Becos ov his absens ov mind- He not bein eny ways so inclind: Sech Wo 1-but cumpany wos ni to him moast sertinly: He heerd a yel, sum distens of, &amp;, as he afterwerds sed, it wos a Dog, &amp; that Dog wos hisn- the saim as he hed left a prisen-   Mr. Pepper's Third Effort.        75 er to hoam at 11 in the 4 noon. this maid him kind ov mad soon; &amp; as the Animel cumd lickin around He swoar Venjens onto him imejitly. o sed he, as he stompt onto the ground, ime mad enuf, i am, to fli: So it bein a litle cus ov a Dog, He jest tooc him by the nap ov the nee &amp; felt amungst his tog- ery; tooc out a fresh cud into his chec (ov tobacker) &amp; scuirted the guse into his fais &amp; i's moast perfuse, &amp; maid him yel sum, i shood thine: Pereodikelly a-wantin ov drino fur to whet up his parchment tung. &amp; now mi song is moast sung: the Dog becaim (spekin perlite) much regused; in fact, he dide:- &amp; so did the Man, sum time after, ov the scarlit Feiver  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7289-00000039"/> THE ERIE CANAL: A MLD RHAPSODY. T QUESTION if there is a single "packet" now 1 "rnning" on this canal. Ten years ago, there were fleets of them. Alas, that Time should work so grievous changes I Unblest as I am by reminiscences of experience in the elegant recreation of guiding a " leader,"--or the more absorbing and scientific pastime of "steering;" accomplished in naught that pertains to the respon- sible post of "bowsman;" and never-to forget an occasional timid Jew, in Chatham   street-having been hailed as "Captain," afloat or ashore: still, gentle reader, I know the Erie Canal, well. I know, too, that the not-infrequent and familiar tales of   The Erie Canal.        " "tempestuous passages" through endless surges, the  "mountain-waves," tie trepidations of the "cook," and the imperatively-necessary "reefs in the stove- pipe," are baseless and shameless inventions of the projectors of " rail,- and other roads,"-or the slander- ous attacks of would-be "dead-heads," who were obliged to pay for dinners the same as when on land. For, look you; it never in such-wise befell the writer hereof; who, favored by gentle gales, clear skies, and glassy waves, had ever reached the "haven where he would be," unvexed by the strife of ele- ments, or lashings of rebellious surges. O that those halcyon days would come, once more!  Holland be ever blessed in thine honest fondness for slow motion!' America let rail-roads curse thee -kill thy children-warn thee of that fell destroyer - Haste I What whilome traveller on this canal can be pre- sumed to have forgotten the soothing strains that were wont to steal from the horn of the steersman, as with his; brown right hand he placed it against the side of his mouth and breathed his soul through a very small aperture? the left meanwhile guiding the swan-like motions of the boat! And the noble craft,  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7289-00000040"/> 78       The Erie Canal. "thing of life" as it was, how the gates of the lock would joyfully open to receive it: like the arms of a paternal one, who was about to fold in his embrace the prodigal, at last returned, from husks, to veal and his father! Ah! then we could feel that Music is a spirit, not partial in respect of tenements, but, with a sweet forgetfulness of self, tobacco, and horns, (whether of tin, or fluid mixtures,) ready to further the ends of her benevolent mission by dwelling in the humble breast of a steerer of boats. For a time we forgot the idle distinction of " passengers" and "crew," and united in heart-felt eulogiums on the wonderous skill of the enchanter. The Erie Canal is no imaginary affair-a kind of myth, that men talk about, but never see: it does not float on the sea of idea. Oh! no; it is confined by an immense number of locks; and statistical writers, in their honest moods, call it, in language singularly appropriate, a " fixed fact." In contemplating this wonderful (I tad nearly said preposterous) Ditch, the mind is missed from its accustomed place: it is, in short, lost. A feeling of awe comes over us; and, in the eloquent language of the ancient matron who feasted her eyes and   The Erie Canal.         79 curiosity on the novel sight of an elephant, we are led to wonder if this be The Canal " all the way along." It is like " linked sweetness" in the length of its drawing-out. What is it but a silver String to the great Violin, the Empire State?  How it trem- bles, between its " bridges," when crossed by the rays of a summer sun! The music is translated into audi- ble sounds by ten hundred steersmen- Who play to the rocks, As they come near the locks, The music of heavenly spheres: How the echoes awaken When the tin horn is taken By the " stern" man who blows it, and steers l-- which little burst of poetic enthusiasm may serve to assure many who long suspected that the Divine Afflatus may be evolved by the contemplation of canals., To illustrate the possibilities of the imagination, let let us conceive the Erie Canal to be eliminated: wiped out with an adequate sponge, or ejected from its place ' )y one of the " roads" afore-mentioned. Better still,  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7289-00000041"/> 80       The Erie Canal. believe it never to have been: a faith which will resemble, in magic power, that of those who count Shakspere to have been a myth. To have a favor of such magnitude granted so readily, at the risk of ema- ciating the conscience through starvation, exposure, and neglect, emboldens me to follow this career of infamy awhile longer. We will now suppose the New York Historical Society to have discovered, near Buffalo, an Obelisk-an undoubted Pompey's Pillar, which never supported anything and has long ceased to support itself; or a Cleopatra's Needle, with no " eye" to be " drilled, counter-sunk, and warranted not to cut," but beyond a peradventure a genuine article, if we may judge from the few feet of it still left above ground. Inspired by a sort of traditionary instinct, the Society above named determines to trans- port the Obelisk to their own city, for erection in the Park. It comes within the limits of our " supposi- tion" to have them consult with engineers, and finally, with any but humorous intentions, quote the language of Confucius and confess it to be "no go." Disdain- ing the aid of the hackneyed yoke of oxen which "drew the inference," cuffing the ears of the wag who suggests a " poor-man's plaster," and hopeless of the   The Erie Canal.        81 efficacy of "moral suasion," even when couched in the most "moving accents," they yield themselves to as deep despair as philosophers can feel, and never cease to regret that Obelisks, like facts, are such I     "stubborn things." But aid is vouchsafed. Omnipotent Fancy will I   have a "streak of lightning," the plough of Time, or five thousand Irishmen, excavate a Furrow through the centre of the State; she fills it with water, on whose bosom she launches " scows," ornamented with captains, bowsmen, and  steersmen; she kindly whispers a preliminary warning,--and then, in a com- manding, rough, military voice, shouts to the column, "Advance!"  Every hieroglyphic on its time-worn surface squirms with reluctance, and all its figures "grin horribly a ghastly smile;" yet the Anglo- Saxon energy of the gallant boatmen makes light of the pillar, and it becomes a Pillar of Light: illumi- nating its own darkness by the diabolical glare of interior, stony curses. To the music of -horns and , saving of glazed hats, this venerable Relic of a former age bids farewell to the hole whence it was exhumed, and is soon lowered into, and. resting in, its "Iong home," the scow. In an insignificantly brief 4*  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7289-00000042"/> 82       The Erie Canal. space of time, if we compare it with eternity or a year of the new planet, the Needle reaches New York, and threads the streets, at the head of a pro- cession,-inspecting everything with its eye, as it goes along, and discovering a good many fine points; but, not yet recovered from its astonishment at the changes that have been going on since its day, making but few remarks. The Park at last receives it, standing; the Fountain has a holiday, and is allowed to play; and on the current "list of new arrivals " one may read: "O. B. LISK, from Buffalo;" In these latter days of economy and moral restraint, they who " go down to the deep " of locks, and are vexed with the toils of inland navigation, do not indulge, to the same extent as formerly, in the luxury of the Sulphureous Oath. Truly, the "canaler" of early times may be said to have been "clothed with curses as with a garment." But the world, including the world of fresh-water " salts," is growing better: on the canal may now be found many "moral" men-yea, many "praying" men. Yet is the canql not a fine-spun paradise; the towns through which'it threads its shining course have not   The Erie Canal.        83 come as yet to cry to the distant hamlets and villages, "We are holier than ye." "Drivers " may still be heard communicating unpleasant sentiments to stupid "Ieaders," and invoking celestial aid to the consign- ing the lights, hides, souls, and other component parts of those offending beasts, to regions infernal, or spirits diabolical. But the mfillennium is coming. Already a goodly number of the " vips " can read, and many consent to peruse the tracts and, volumes left with them by the plain, simple-hearted, but earnest men who have taken our inland waters as the "field "of their labors. Verily, a great and happy change shall have taken place, when the captain, though it be only of a scow or log-raft, shall be a gentleman; when every bows- man and   steersman shall take "Watts's" to his bosom, shouting spiritual songs; when the cook shall season his dishes with a prayer; when each driver shall eschew profanity and tobacco, and  take the hand of every other driver, calling him " brother;" when the lock 'tender shall joyfully hasten to "hurra the lock!" summoned thereto by a warning strain from the Old Hundredth Psalm--the delight of the steersman; when the collector shall lay down  his  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7289-00000043"/> 84        The Erie Canal. Bible with a placid smile, that he may make out a "clearance:" when, in short, the Millennium   does come. [If steam is really to come into general use on the Canal, where, I would ask, are we to go who are in love with the romance of inland navigation? Away with this base, utilitarian project I Who wants to be blown up on a Canal? There would be no attractive notoriety in it-no chance for damages against the Company. Keep off this steam, or I pack up for Holland.]   MR. PEPPER'S FOURTH ACHEVE- MENT. '           .   -  ---o--- THE Great Comet of 1853 was not without its "mission"-which evidently was to inspire our poet, and thus proclaim the majesty of intellect. His ode is in blank-verse-" a deviation," said a critic, "from the shackles of poetical rule, which marks the man of ' genus.' But the thought, the thought is the thing. Observe the variety and ' reach' of the poet's fancy :" A NOAD TO THE COMECK. ROTE INTO THE SUMMER, BY MR. K. N. PEPPER, ESQ. All hail, grait Loominarry-twicet al hale I Grand fizzikel Visiter, youm welcum I in regions ov Spais, wair al is silens,  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7289-00000044"/> -    - ---.- .. ,&amp; A-,ll; vcviIenL. &amp; there4 no nois is herd, its dificult to traivel &amp; not waik up sumthin: But you hev dun it so fur moar than 50 yeres, to the satisfacshun ov al present. With untirin perseverens se him sail onto a rowt as no 1 ever thougt ov goin. Wen hese frose the bar al of ov his hed, &amp; lost so meny milds ov tail that he cant tel wether hese a-goin forids or bacards,--- then he shutes down to the Son fur to worm up, &amp; put on a litle bam of Columby or warpean. Sech hard were it is fur him to stop, that hese lost the nac throo wont ov practis. o Comeck!-a-goin round &amp;  round the son,- Wi not sum time or uther wind him up, &amp;, a-taikin the rains ov Guverment into your teth, up &amp; giv the soaler Cistim a nairin? Cum,--blo your wissel; the plannits is on a train: Emigrans into the frunt; ov colusion no dainger: Gupitter 'll doo fur a balens-wele- Satern 'll ring wen thays sumthin ahed- Mars fite al irishmen as wont pay the fair- &amp;   venous so swete ile ride with her miself. (wot a nidee, now, fur a singul man!) Wele notifi the smal stars onto the rowt to looc out for the Comeck wen the bel rings I   lvir. rcppcru r ourmiL  A^cimcvemenn .   07 Wele saw up the milky Way fur fire-wood, &amp; yous the orory Boryals fur a signel-lite: Wich wood caws a stonishment to spring frum the i. But act your-Plesure--we doant wonto dicktait-- oanly we shood be hapy to cum the perpoasd arraingmeant, Miss Terious Comeck --wens doo you shoot? Ware wos you wen you 1st thougt ov flyin? Wot put it into your hed to cum this way, a-surprisin ov the natyvs?-is the stait ov your financys sech you cant supoart moar tale? o Comeck!-peraps its loansum, traivelin so- But you doant no the mizzery ov a felin hart: Youm al hed &amp; tail; so ov coars cant fele. i sumtimes wish i hedent no boddy, too,o-- fur then i mite be hapy.-plese ex-kews mi present emoshun-i cant always Banish the thougt ov Wo. o mity Loominarry 1 immens Miss Terry H-say now, wos it troo You hed sum thougts ov a-soin up the Erth? You aint noomeris for that persedin  o no, Mr. Comeck,-youm too smal. You mite hac of a mountin or 2, praps, Bi a snubbin ov your tale onto a pyrrymid; But the bMorril part ov Comunity, Woodent se no libbertys tooc with the muther Erth--  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7289-00000045"/> O5 O Mr. Pepper's Fourth Achievement. o no, Mr. Comeck, as wos sed be4. 1st egsersise, &amp; git sum mete onto your ribs, &amp; like samson let your bar gro long.- we no your tallent into the sailin line- we acnollig youm sum onto fire-wercs: But doant be foolish becos you no how. You cant sercumnavoygrait Erth like you doo the son, Without a-gittin ov your bed noct of. the son is indulgent, &amp; not a tal snapish; &amp; hes so much biznes, atendin to al the plannits, that a-givin ov fits to Comecks is soopirfloous. But its a litle diferent here. so bewair, &amp; taik the folowin advise frum a fren: We shel alwais be very glad to se you, Wen actin ov your part into the grait Sercus, &amp; not gittin out ov the ring &amp; a-throwin dert. But the idee ov fitin onto sech a scail, We cawl prepostrious into the egstreme. After al, i doant thinc your intenshuns wos cereusa: the grait Comeck is too magnannymus to liev sech a nidee. i hoap your felins Hessent bein hirt; if so, plese taik notis Your admirer is rash almoast to canker, &amp; lashed hisself cuickly into angry waivs wen he wos be4 cuite cam &amp; slepy-like; &amp; al fur nothin, as we air hapy to se. So doant be rash yourself, Miss Terious Comeck,   Mr. Pepper's Fourth Achievement. 89 But folow into the trac ov your ilustris predysessers. Your frens into this seckshun air noomeris, &amp; thay expeck the illustris Comeck to doo his dooty- Wich is, to sail around &amp; say nothin to noboddy: Not hittin the plannits, &amp; a-steerin clere ov the stars. (n. b.) plese tri &amp; let out a litle moar tail.  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7289-00000046"/> A TEDIOUS STORY. HOR. O day and night, but this is wondrous strange! HAM. And therefore as a stranger give it welcome. There are more things in heaven and earth, Horatio, Than are dreamt of in your philosophy.-HAMLET. HE  other evening I sat at my table, writing. A little chilly rain was falling, and the wail of the September wind, in the trees, sounded strangely like the hum of a vast mosquito. "Thank Heaven!"I murmured, with much emotion, " the rascally pests will trouble us no more this season!"This appeared so just a reflection, I laid down my pen, and leaned back in my chair, supporting my head in my hands, spreading my well-turned legs with some compla- "ncy, and idly musing on a young female friend   A Tedious Story.       91 who (by reason, doubtless, of the rich, youthfully. pure nectar in her veins), is every season two-thirds devoured by the egregious vampires. At length, rousing from this somnolent reverie, and bending toward my task, I was surprised, and I own a little startled, at seeing an immense, venerable-looking mosquito, resting on the margin at the head of my sheet. I knew   the case demanded promptness. "Thus falls the Last of the Mohicans!"I cried, with less wit than exultation, aiming a stroke with my ruler, "That might determine, and not need repeat." On the instant, the threatened insignificant raised one of its fore-limbs with a deprecatory gesture, and, in the tiniest voice imaginable, cried, "Hold!" "Humbug l" interposes the reader: "Away with this Munchausen-this Gulliver!-Remember we are not marinesl Try again I Get a Peace I How know you it was not a miracle, like that which astonished Balaam, a few thousand years ago? To tell the truth, reader-to confide to you a favor- ite but oddish fancy of mine-I have long believed  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7289-00000047"/> 92       A  Tedious Story. there are times when it is permitted us, if we then desire it, to have communion with the usually mute orders of inferior creation. That such intercourse has been rare, in these latter years, is no proof it is not possible; and I am sure, if a stupid animal has ever "conversed like a native," a sprightly, intelli- gent, ingenious, cunning insect might be thought to have that power.  I confess I have upon occasion addressed cows or other animals, half hoping, half believing, they would not only understand, but speak. I do not doubt I was always apprehended, and feel a little disappointment at having but just been favored in the way I have desired, and not, after all, by an animal (which was my dearest wish), but by an inlsig- nificant insect, for whose race I have all along enter- tained not only disrespect but hate. You shall presently see, my reader, there mustshave been a purpose in the sudden gift of speech to the insect, having reference to the very feelings I have mentioned. I can very readily imagine your further murmurings of incredulity, and querulous general, disapproval.  "The mosquito had no organs of speech," you are on the point of remarking.  Had the venerable donkey of Scripture? How know you   A Tedious Story.        93 this, about the organs? "But his voice would be inaudible," you protest. I think I have observed it was very faint; and one may readily believe my hearing (which is generally excellent), was on that occasion helped by some peculiar state of the air, or of my system. But I do not think it dignified to have engaged in this effort to make my relation appear plausible; per- haps I should have made no digression at all, and have depended for defense on a note at the end. I am in hopes the story will be found to speak for itself, as did the mosquito. Now I am naturally a weak and tender-hearted man; I do never needlessly afflict or maim a living thing, or indeed much mar inanimate ones. I am even particular to have my newspapers preserved, in neat files; and when one is torn, there is a certain feeling in my breast, growing out of a sense of fitness, just as carelessly torn and lacerated. But a sort of instinct has always prompted me to kill mosquitoes. I have even been led, through a prejudiced estimate, to ask, What were they made for? I own I was a little surprised with the conduct of the venerable insect; but I have since been exercised  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7289-00000048"/> "      A Tedious Story. with wondering I was not more astonished. Struck at once with a sense of the enormity of the act I con- templated, I dropped my weapon, and said, "I beg your pardon-I really had no malice. It was but the mere following a habit." "I have no hard feelings, sir," replied the mosquito. "I almost beg your pardon for stopping you, for I could easily have avoided the blow, and left you to your reflections; but I have looked forward to this moment for many a day. Instinct advises me the time has at length arrived when I may safely and profitably communicate with one of your race. You perceive, sir, my size is somewhat unusual; and when I assure you my age and experience are equally uncommon, you will, I hope, be ready to treat me with more consideration than you have lavished on an innumerable martyred throng of my fellows." A sigh, of considerable profundity for such a little body to heave, escaped the loquacious insect, which now paused an instant and panted vigorously for breath,---its former stock of which, considering its volume of voice, I had begun to wonder was not spent before. At length it thus resumed: "I do not imagine that anything I could say would   A Tedious Story.       95 have the effect to change the opinion your race has of mine. Indeed, my hopes did not look that way. You regard us-reasonably enough, I admit-as bloodthirsty and inhuman creatures. You jest des- perately about our 'warlike trump,' and illustrate your hate, in the absence of physical proof, by the uncomplimentary titles you heap on us, and the gene- ral tone of the language you employ against us. Thus, you would not credit the assertion that the droning sound you dread and stigmatize is a sigh of - regret at being obliged to pursue our horrid trade, in obedience to the cursed instincts of our race. We are not fond of blood, but absolutely know of nothing else that will sustain our existence. We must live,   you know."    I was about to quote here the well-known reply of Dr. Johnson to a similar remark. Smiling with melancholy gaiety, and waving a dextral limb as though asking a favor, he immediately continued as follows: "I think I anticipate what you would say; at least, I am sure there was some sarcasm in it. But, could you realize it, we are not without our import- ance in the scale of creation, and subserve a purpose  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7289-00000049"/> 96       A Tedious Story. by much more useful than any your philosophers have grudgingly assigned to us.  This, however, though not altogether foreign to my design, is not the subject in my mind and heart at present." The mosquito here smiled grimly, and said, "It must doubtless amuse you to hear me speak of these possessions, which you have all along believed were peculiar to the genus homo; but how could I address you, without a mind; and how exhibit feeling, without a heart? and, I assure you, my kinsmen are not themselves disqualified to boast in that regard. "I will proceed to say, my object-which, I con- fess, is a little selfish--has reference more to myself than to my race in general. From my youth, sir- I see you smile again; but a lifetime is a lifetime, whether it be a man's or a mosquito's--from my youth I have been painfully conscious I am not like other mosquitoes. My life has been spent in lonely thought and distracting speculation. The bitter, jealous, utterly uncharitable tongues of detrac- tion and defamation have been busy against me almost from the hour of my birth. The wittier and more malicious of my race have cracked an infinity of jokes at my expense, while the graver and more   i          A Tedious Story.       97 respectable have consistently frowned on all the plans and new ideas I have spread before them. I have aspired, sir, to the character of reformer and philan- S .  thropist. But, alas my heart has ever stood in the way of my success. Had I been worldly-minded and sordid, my talents would speedily have asserted their claims, and secured me, in their exercise, both honor and wealth. I see you smile again; you are ready to ask in what consists the 'wealth' of the mosquito?  What! do you fancy we are for ever on the wing, and have I no home to call our own?'--as one of your great poets, Mr. Bunn, so beautifully and touchingly says? Try and think better of us. A mosquito with an ordinary sucker can draw, it is calculated, in one flight (which may consume an hour of time as you reckon it), enough sustenence from the veins of your fellow-creatures to answer his needs for a whole day. Of course, then, with the day's work so readily accom- plished, he may dispose of his time pretty much as he pleases; and were you curious enough, you might chance to find him decorating his abode, or sitting at the feet of some philosopher of our race, learning wisdom, and, I am free to admit, cunning. But I digress: I have intimated to you that I am unfor- B'          5  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7289-00000050"/> 98       A Tedious Story. tunate as regards the relations in which I stand witch my fellows. It has all along been my fate to be mis- understood, and (of course) unappreciated. My pre- tensions to the character of philosopher have been scouted, and my general claims to excellence unmer- cifully derided. It is hard, sir," said the insect, with much emotion, and betraying once more some symp- toms of fatigue, "it is hard, when one has devoted his life to his race, to be misunderstood and suspected by the very ingrates over whom his spirit has been poured!" Here he wrung his lancet in agony, and a micro- scopic tear trembled on his eyelid. I essayed to cheer him; but, with the mournful flourish of a disengaged fore-limb, he politely waved me back to silence Having once more recovered his breath and spirits, he steadied himself on several legs hitherto unem- ployed, and proceeded, as follows: "I have no desire to bore you, either with my tongue or my ' javelin,' as we facetiously call it,-and will not, therefore, rehearse the innumerable disap- pointments and mortifying repulses that have been visited on me. I may, perhaps, be pardoned, how- ever, if I mention two of them, as they by much    A Tedious Story.       99 transcend the others, and stand, like mountains, on what I may, in this connexion, call the general plain of my life. Above a month ago, I broached a long- considered scheme for the public good, which I was confident would be received with approbation and gratitude. Expressed at length, my plan was an 'University for the training and perfecting of our youth in the art of pursuing a maintenance with safety and success.' I need not say what were my feelings on achieving but ridicule and abuse, in lieu of that long-courted fame I knew I deserved. 'Ex- perience is the only teacher,' they cried. 'But of what consequence is experience to one who has been crushed in gaining it?' I would respond. 'By my system, few or no valuable lives will be sacrificed; and thus, a reigning fear being quite dethroned, the general happiness must be infinitely promoted.' With equally cogent arguments did I sustain the other fea- tures of my plan, and combat the several objections that were urged against them. But I was a stranger, and totally unused to the employment of winning friends. I failed; was called a visionary; and was absolutely driven back to my haunts by the jeers and even execrations of the people. Nevertheless, I did  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7289-00000051"/> i o100     A Tedious Story. not relax my efforts to serve my kind, and in due time was ready with another plan, this time founded on a principle of benevolence still more abstract, but exacting so little of any one, and working such an immensity of good, on the whole, that I fondly hoped none would seriously object to it, while the many would at once reverse their former hard decision, and welcome joyfully my scheme and me. I will briefly explain: I discovered, quite by accident, while sup- ping on the superabundant blood of an alderman, that by a simultaneous mental and physical effort, the mat- ter usually deposited in the puncture, and operating as a local poison, might be retained; and thus the pains I had often witnessed with tears-obliged to inflict the wound, yet powerless to avert the pain- might be for ever prevented. With a heart bound- ing with joy, I made haste to proclaim my disco- very,-seeing in it a new and quite practical means of not only sparing the human race much pain, but, as a natural consequence, very much lessening the anxiety of that race to compass the extermination of ours.' l Noble insect!"I could not here avoid exclaiming. "You will presently see how highly I must needs   A Tedious Story.       101 appreciate your generous expressions," returned the mosquito, apparently much affected. "You will, I hope, believe me, sir, when I assure you that, instead of being hailed as a philanthropist, I was universally derided as a preposterous, milk-hearted ninny, and advised to by all means put in practice my darling theory without delay. There was even some talk of having me privately strangled, as a no longer tolerable nuisance. It almost broke my heart, sir," said the much-moved insect, struggling with its passion, and soon so far giving way to that tender flood as to cease entirely and vent a diminutive sob. My efforts to comfort and re-assure it were long unsuccessful, but finally were so fortunate as to inspire it with an appear- ance of cheerfulness. "I have done," it said, with a sigh. "' The gift and privilege of your human speech are at length afforded me; and I see I have not been mistaken in the one I have selected to hear me rehearse my woes, and hand my name and history down to an admiring pos- terity." "I will gladly do as you desire," I hastened to say; "and it shall not be my fault if you are ever for- gotten."  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7289-00000052"/> 102      A Tedious Story. - The mosquito, much moved, bowed its acknowledge. ments, and seemed at a loss for expressions sufficiently warm to convey its feelings of gratitude and attach- ment. After this was gone through I remarked,!"Though I have not a superabundant stock of blood in my veins, I would be pleased to have you illustrate your discovery by a painless operation on any part of my body you may select: for, as you justly remark, it is the pain that vexes us, and not the loss of blood." ' Nothing would give me greater pleasure," said the mosquito, with an alacrity that a little surprised me, considering its hitherto air of languor. "Many of our race," it said, with sprightliness, "prefer to attack the feet or neck of a subject, as being usually less exposed to the elements, and therefore tenderer, than the hands and face; but an experienced mosquito is not so particular, and could even get a tolerable living from so unpromising a tract as a thumb-nail." With that, the loquacious insect took the air, and was at the point of alighting on my hand, when drawing back timidly, it said, "I feel it is weak to doubt you, yet I own I am seized with misgivings lest your old prejudices sur-   A Tedious Story.       103 prise your newer judgment, and I should be crushed in the general result." This notion appeared so quaintly whimsical I could not forbear laughing, as I re-assured my tiny friend, declaring that, whatever happened, its person should be held absolutely sacred. At length, appearing to have quite overcome its timidity, it alighted on that soft part of my hand between the base of the thumb and the knuckle-joint of the fore finger, and at once inserted its amiable tube. I could not help observing that now it looked uncommonly like a very common mosquito. In my speculations as to the cause of this apparent change, and general admiration of the talented pest, I now think I must have spent a good half- minute; but then I was surprised to find he had so soon finished his meal. Fancying, all at once, I felt much of the usual pain (and certainly a most pre- posterous swelling at once testified he had not wasted his time), I was about to murmur a little, when he cut me short by this most expressive gesture: Standing on the summit of the living mound his treachery had raised-which, swelling and rising every moment, seemed destined shortly to place him in apogee-he coiled one of his fore-limbs around his ensanguined  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7289-00000053"/> 104      A Tedious Story. tube and flourished the doubled end of another before it as though turning an imaginary crank fixed in the end. He heightened the effect of this expressive pantomime by pronouncing, in a cheerful, even tri- umphant tone, the sententious apothegm, "Sold!" Upon which, staying barely to wink his sinister eye in an aggravating but wonderfully knowing manner, he took his flight. Somewhat bewildered, I rubbed my eyes a little, although I was never half so wide awake, and groaned in much bitterness of spirit, eyeing meanwhile the huge, inflamed, aching mound of poisoned flesh on my hand. "Sold! and by such a contemptible little 'cus?"I murmured spitefully, as I went in search of some hartshorn.   13 O From the fatigue of " heavy reading" nothing relieves one so effectually as a quiet and tender strain of genuine poetry-such, perhaps, as the fol- lowing :- TO  ANGELINA. THE.-This passion, and the death of a near friend, would go near to make a man look sad.-MDSUMMER NIGHT'S DREAM. HOW   oft to thee, sweet one-eyed friend, Must I confess my errors  Here at thy feet again I bend, In your prim, tidy little room; And own I envy one, for whom Strabismus has no terrors. From hobbies, and that sort of thing, No man could well be freer; I sing of twenty when I sing- I talk of hundreds when I talk; But when I tread my lonely walk You are my one-eyed dear. 5*  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7289-00000054"/> 106        To Angelina. Ohl who can scent that breath, so rich, Or note those blooming freckles, Or spy that jaunty wig, (you witch 1) Without admiring you a " heap," And rating you " uncommon" cheap At twenty thousand sheckels I Talk not of gold-for you will bring A. fortune in your "grinders; " Those bilious ramblers, staggering, With "ample room and verge " for most To play at " hide (for some are lost) And seek "-with Dental finders I The line of beauty in your nose Beats Hogarth's grandest notion; For his, I think, had but two bows, But yours has half-a-dozen crooks To heighten your angelic looks, And seal my rapt devotion I And need I praise thy skinny lips, Thou well-preserved old angel I Thou seest my muse but lightly skips Those wrinkles-which, I doubt me not, Are " lines of beauty " too, and ought Not to be deemed a strange ill   To Angelina.          107 That sword-like chin I often dream Is very near another Owned by myself; and then I seem To smack by instinct-while the paint Which I rub off seems like a faint Impression of-"MY MOTHER I  Graceful machine Hcontrived (Gods Hhow?) In some past generation: What is a limp, when such as thou Are lame?-When we o'er earth have sWept, Where shall we find your match-except In your imagination I      . Then take, thou free-gift of the skies-- With bulbous feet so tiny, Oh I take, before thy lover dies, His wretched heart, and make it beat Like your prepost'rous Dutch repeat-- Er, dearest ANGELINA 1  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7289-00000055"/> MR. PEPPER'S FIFTH LABOR. --------- THE   poet had long been silent. The editor of the T Knickerbocker had received from  some misguided imitator, who thought to step into the shoes of his exemplar, a poem entitled, "Stanzays Adresed to mi Suetart," and which he had declared inadmissable: exclaiming with fervor: "' Is the sword unswayed? Is the  chair empty?' Mr. PEPPER  is 'himself alone I'"  At this stage, the following letters arrived, and cleared up the mystery. "We    thought it very strange," said the editor, "that a poet like himself, whose reputation has become so thoroughly esta- blished, should be content to repose upon his laurels :" "DEMOSTIENES FOUR-CORNERS, June 20, 1854. "MR. CLARK, EDITOR: "SIR: Since your fruitless investigations saying that you hoped the sword was not sheathed, or asking if the sword was   Mr. Pepper's Fifth Labor.        lo9 sheathed--meaning my friend Mr. PEPPER'S pen, I conclude-I have now made up my mind to inform you definitely relative to that Great man. "( First I may say that I adore Mr. PEPPER'S genius, although different. I am, as you may say, one of his Antipodes. I am his friend. I and Mr. PEPPER have sprung up into manhood's ripening Sheaf side by side, and called ourselves Friends from earliest infancy. Sir: He has been a blessing to me: I'm proud to have been the first that see into him, and I discovered much. He has got a mind. He is playfulbut gloomy: Humor- ous but solemn: Simple but intricate: Pathetic but ridiculous. Sir: I hand you a letter from Mr. PEPPER. It reveals much that perhaps ought to be sacred. It was wrote to me, and the Autograph is genuine. I would not lose that letter for five dollars. "I send it because it contains one of those Gems that have so delighted, astonished, and entranced the civilized world. -It is peculiarly PEPPERIAN. "I send the whole letter because a Gem always looks better in a setting. His setting is wonderful. "The private life of great men is a topic at once interesting and good. Good, because it invites people to leave busy cares and live as they live. It is no damage to Mr. PEPPER, because he will be deprived of the Magazine this summer in consequence of not being within fifty miles of a post-office. He will not therefore see it. But pardon me: I keep you from the rich repast in store for your mind. "With consideration. Sir: Yours. P. PEPPER PODD.  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC7289-00000056"/> -.. jrr^- o J stulI LdDor. "P S. You will notice how Mr. PEPPER'S poetic mind trans- fers bodies of water, when I inform you that the one which he has called PEPPE'S Lake* is but six rods in width and two feet eight inches in depth. Its former name was Mudsucker Pond.'  Oh I the powers of that individual's Genius!I am proud that any part of my name resembles his, and I give it prominence in honor of him.              P. P. " PEPPER'S LAIK, Gfune 15th. DERE FELLER: Wot wood you thincs ef you shood see me now I! EIere i am, a rusty katin, fur away frum everthing, bi ;he side ov a lovly egspans ov wotter-wich, as i hev Lst discuverd its Beutys, &amp; doant no no other naim, aph mi oan cignacher to it. Hevin retired frum  the werld fur a sesun, to com- ne with Nacher, &amp;  giv mi genus a restin spel, i liv ke a   nankerite, al aloan bi miself-a-fishin &amp; a- comin &amp;   a-seein ov the things gro. i doant wair nothin but a  shirt &amp; pant, as here the cloathin is soo- irftoous; mi baird hesent ben teched fur suthin over a eke, &amp;  i looc savig, i ken tel you!-but o how Tran- * "TaT somethi might serve to perpetuate Greatness and the Tristing-place for Genus." *              'I   ivir. recppers ru run tauor.    111  kil i am!- i breth now, &amp; slepe cuiet. ime a-gainin al  the wile; &amp; ef I doant stop soon i must bi a noo        I soot. i am a-compoasin a Grait Pome, mi boy, bi spels, &amp;      i V1s in a wile i thro of a litle feller, bi way ov varity.   ! mi genus is ever a-sterrin, &amp; kepes me oncumfertabel      (* moast ov the time, bi resun ov the presher. wot it wood doo ef it hed a chans, i donno. but the conse- kenses wood be dredful to mi helth. You no we         i;: Littery men air trubbeld a good dele with pane in the     I bowls, &amp;c4th. o how i delite to rise with the Son, wen the doo is onto the gras, &amp; wock into the woods wair its dri!--i hear the Berds a-cherrupin so hapy it     ,. maiks me fele bad; &amp; i ask Wi it is ime so mellan-        colly &amp; sad?--wi Wo kepes a-hangin aroun &amp; maiks       i me carry his cloak?   No boddy spekes, so i anser:      i Genus. thairs the cecrit. o wot a cus wen youve got too much!--ef i hed a litle moar, ide spine away,       ; &amp; finelly di. as it is, ime verry febel; so i fish, &amp;     i dyit strong, &amp; roam into the darknis ov the Ainshen      j Forrist. You smil, and thine ov Musketer. but youm  rong. musketer is a blessing, ef propperly too.  doant the scrachin maik you onhapy, &amp; aint onhapines the food ov genus? wi, ime so onmindful i let him       tf  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7289-00000057"/> "2    Mr. Pepper's Fifth Labor. bite, &amp; scaisly doo nothin,-oanly i hev swoar to thine sech a appetite is denid to hewman Beings. musketer must liv. he is the part ov profidens as bites, &amp; nothin wotever ken chaing him but a-bringin ov him up bi hand. egskews the goak. i inkerd a naxident wilst a-salin onto the laik the uther day. i wos a-lyin onto mi ores in the senter ov the laik, a-dremin ov Faim &amp;c4th, &amp; wile so doin i fel into a depe studdy-also shallo wotter, wich was mity fortinet, wosent it? i waidid out sloly, a-thinkin wot a nar escaip it wos; &amp; thougt ef it wos deper eny wers nerer the shoar ide bi a life-preserver. Wilst a-reclinin onto the bang, a-dryin on miself bi the Son, the mews caim   suddently, &amp; i compoased the folowin lines: TO MY LITLE HOUS: A-FRUNTIN ONTO THE LAIK. o Hous Haltho you speke not, i speke, &amp; say you shant be forgot: Altho youm nothin but boards, &amp;  ov Goald hevent no hoards- likewais no Windos, egsept 1 lite in the bac, to let in the Son, (bein wair i slepe and stay wen it rains).   Mr. Fepper's F'itth Labor.       113 i must say ive tooc no pains to consele my afeckshun fur your presinks. o no!--altho youm a Hut, your fren thincs a Pallis wood be inconveanyent: Becos no i likes to be sent Wen hese tierd, up 3 or 4 pair stairs to bed. hese got uther Afairs          i to fateag him onto the 1st floor. o no, dere Hous HAmbishun is ore; &amp; i liv in you contentid as the Cezar duz into his largist glas Pallis, wich cost 2000 dollers. So it is allus. Nachers scollers lerns how to be hapy evry wair: Wen trubbel cums, they doant cair, But fle away to the Woods &amp; git setteld. Hoo wonts goods, or munny, wen he may git chetid, &amp; hev al ov his hapines defetid Bi a-puttin ov his trust into Prinsis. &amp; uther Tirans as doant settel thayr biznis? no, dere Hous!-giv me Nacher &amp; you, &amp; ile travvil this Werld throo, a-fishin, &amp; a-roamin, &amp; a-compogin potry: &amp; may i be AT HOAM wen i di. Wot doo you thine ov that last line: aint it Huj? -thats ariginel, mi Boy. Genus dwels into that line.  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7289-00000058"/> "4    Mr. Pepper's Fifth Labor. But i must stop a-ritin. rite to me al about Nzck- erbocker, &amp;c4th. it doant cum here. i wonder ef its stopt a-publishin. i hevent roat fur it now far a good wile. Now mi Boy, be cairful ov your helth, &amp; anser this imejitly. frum your fren K. N. PEPPER.   A LYTELL GESTE OF LEWYS CLARKE. "Lead forth, O clarke, the chaunting quire." D-LENORA. [The origin of this fine old ballad, is enveloped in considerable mystery. It may possibly have been contemporaneous with "Clym of the Clough," or even "The Nut-Browne Mayde;" but a more plausible supposition is, that it was written about the time of (Mr. Pithaddle thinks a little before) the well-known "Robyn Hode." It is certainly a very old and very singular production; and it is amazing that neither Percy's "Reliques," Ritson's two collections, Evan's "Old Ballads," "The Crown Garland of Golden Roses," nor indeed any important work, should contain it. It seems to have existed in Folio MS. for many years, and, so far as the editor can learn, has never even sparkled from a broadside, or the pages of a black-letter tract. From some data in the possession of the editor, and furnished by the very old but still intelligent person who sang it to him, it is rendered tolerably certain that the hero, "Lewys Clarke," was the editor of a (for those days) very good magazine, called the Nyker Bogger-whatever that may have meant-and at the time the poem was written had begun to cultivate the full  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7289-00000059"/> "u   A  LEytell ueste of Lewys Clarke. beard-being jealous of his friend "Chlarlys Elyott," a painter, of great celebrity, because Charlys had an uncommonly fine one, of that pattern, and was much admired by the ladies. The appearance of Lewys, at that time-his beard being about a quarter of an inch in length-is said to have been formidable in the extreme. A little boy, aged four years-the son of religious parents--is reported to have been so crazed at the sudden sight of him, as to fall a swearing with great vehemence; which habit it never afterward left off, much to the grief of those excellent people. It died, of a compound curse, after lingering fourteen years in extreme profanity.] ie  first Bftte. x t ITHE (i) and lyften, gentylmen,' And well my ftorye marke; "I ihall you tell of a good yeman," Hys name was LEWYS CLARKE. He was a man that myrthes cowde, (2) "Whiles he walked on grounde; So courteyfe a yeman as he was one, Was never none yfounde." Ynne (3) mani bokes had he delyght, Yet was he fcaunt of baird: For fhauvynge was he bende betymes Ynne mornyng: fo he cared. Lewys toke hym a gode wyfe, Shope (4) to hys harts defyres, Full mony yere he dwalt with hyr, Ynne hows of hys own hyre.   A   Lytell Geste of Lewys Clarke.    117 On (5) tyde (6) he frode ynne hys gardaun "And lened hym to a tre ;" And by hym fitode hys cumly feir, (7) And wurds thys Much spake she: "Lewys, to thys my rede (8) geffe (9) ere: Ynne pyte let thi here, ( o) Lyke eremite or goodlye clerk, d D Comen (12) upon thy lere. (I 3) Elf muft I wepe my eyen owt:" Hyr (14) teres begond comyn ; (15) Then befpake hymn Lewys Clarke All unto hyr wyth wynne: (16) "Gramercy, (I7) luve," fayd Lewys, And kyft hyr lytell hond; "For newe ( 8) heft thou fyxit my mynde : (19) Thilk (20) teres I pray commond." ilje 3eon e  .tte. i4, YTH (21) and lyften, gentylmen, o' All that now be here," To Lewys what fhold nowe befall, Ynne (22) londe where that he were. Now is (23) Lewys went to the toun, Hys baird he ftrokyt wel; And preftlye (z4) chaunted of a fonge: "' Al rowynde my hatte," (25) yt felle.  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7289-00000060"/> "8    A  Lytell Geste of Lewys Clarke. Then fpake that gentyll yeman: The teres fland ynne hys eyen-- "GODAMARCEY! (26) longe (27) yehone (28) Thilk manli heres of myne! "Thys ylke (29) day CHARLYS ELYOTT (3a) Sail (31) paynt wone blythe of blee: (32) And eke (33) we (34) envye dy nerly, That nere nike (35) baird hath hee." Thos pleaufantly hee recht Charlys, Woo (36) toke hym for fum noder: (37) "' Ynne confeyuence, (38) neybor, wold you goo?(39) I lyk not of your odour." Sone as Elyott kent (40) Lewys, Hym feyd: "Now, Lewys, doe Ynne pyte choppe (41) for hewman feem, Or call me frend ne mo." (42) "Alas!" then fayd good Lewys, "Alas, what have I do! (43) What ys to me a flowynge baird, Yf Charlys ys my foo?" (44) Now have Lewys ifwore hys othe, For home hee begond to serch: He was as will of rede, (45) ynne trouthe, As ever was hare ynne Merch. EXPLYCIT (40) LEWYS CLARKE AND   CHARLY8 ELYOTT- -QUOTH JACQUE8 MAURICE.   A   Lytell Geste of Lewys Clarke.      119 1Lossar. 1. Crowd up. 2. Could raise a laugh at his own expense. 3. In: not hotel.   4. Constructed. 5. One: half of two.. 6. Morning before breakfast. 7. Own heart's queen. 8. Advice: gratis. 9. Give, or lend, according to disposition. 10. In facf, neither here nor there. The word is significant of bristles. 11. Savan. 12. The same without the n. 13. Cheek: in which Lewys was not lacking. 14. Lewys's wife's. 15. "1 Coming, Sir." 16. Joy: not wine. 17. Much obliged to you: no alusion to Park of that name. 18. Now, if ever. 19. Mind: no great matter. 20. These: not silk. 21. Another way of spelling it.  22. The same house. 23. As.: you're one if you don't remember it. .24. Wretchedly, in this case. 25. The title of an ancient hymn. 26. God be thanked.   27. Along of.  28. Each one: not Ochl Hone!   29. Very: very likely.  30. Pinxit.  31. Shall  not Sarah.  32. Of majestic countenance.  33. Also: sometimes Ezekiel. 34. With: as, will you drink we me?  35. Such-like. 36. Who: thus, woo be you?    37. Other: not sonnambulist. 38. Conscience: a myth': a good joke, to talk of Lewysis con- science.  39. Go: (0/)  40. Kenned: in justice, caned. 41. Change: no small change here. 42. No more: being as near as our ancestors thought it prudent to come. 43. Done : as, do brown: meaning, done to that tint. 44. Foe: notfoo-foo. 45. Disturbed in mind-;: displeased: angry: mad. 46. "That's all, abut" &amp;e. 3g sr^  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7289-00000061"/> MR. PEPPER'S MOURNFUL SIXTH. --0-- OW   for it.  Brace yourself with a little cordial, and then take my hand.     Feel. along carefully, and-there; stand still a moment. Mr. PODD is speaking: "Demosthenes Four-Corners, July 20, 16k4 "MR. CLARK. EDITOR. SIR: Since I favored you with my last, great changes have obscured the face of the sun of Liberty and Happines, which have been in the Habit of shining in favored spots regular. Despots continue to sway the aspect of things. But their reign is short, Sir. I repeat it: Short. Changes must come. As a significant fact, Mr. PEPPER has changed. He is no longer playful. He is gloomy-gloomy. I am afraid his genus is about to sink in a blaze of glory and go out. Yes Sir: I be- gin to be alarmed for his Existence. His heart is too suscepti- ble: Altogether. It has been touched, Sir: Rudely touched. Many of the strings have I fear been snapped. But let the elo- quent and feeling letter he wrote upon the subject tell the tale.   Mr. Pepper's Mournful Sixth.       121 It will be seen that he is the combined victim of Affection and a Tyrant. But my hand is influenced by the emotions of my heart. It trembles. ,Adieu.     "P. PEPPER PODD." "Pepper's laik, guly 12. "' DERE FELLER: Hevin I's moar a opertoonity ov cendin you a few lins, i avail miself ov it to l'st, moar pertickeler as i hev much to inform you wich i cant berry into mi oan boosum. "' O PODD, PODD, wot hapines-wot misery--wot rapcher and goy-wot mizzery &amp; Wo ive sufferd sens i rote be4. - it semes moar like a dreme-oanly i no it aint, &amp; a dreme woodent maik me loos so much in boddy. ime thin as a waifer, dere boy-&amp; a good dele witer onto the serfis. mi apetite (wich you no wos alus precaris) hes now dwindeld into nothin, &amp; i doant beleve ive ete a hanful in 4 days. i kepe insid the house &amp; lay onto mi fais, a-groanin dredful, &amp; a-syin al the time i doant groan. but i no it must be a speshy ov ageny to hev to wait long fur a explanashun ov this miss tery. ile releve you in but few werds. it wos the 21th ov gune. erly in the mornin. i----o my felins is sech i doant no as i ken revele. wi did i comens the haroin tale? but ile subdoo mi emoshuns &amp; pereede with camnes. rite pen 1--kepe a-ritin. paws not. "' i hed jest got threw a-washing out side the doar, &amp; wos a-wiping miself onto the toul, wen i herd a shrik giv by a butiful yung lady in ageny. i looct around iu frensy, &amp; saw nothin. in a instant a 1 hors wagon floo around the corner, drawed by a frantic animel. in that wagon wos a man a-hoaldin ov the lins &amp; a yung Lady. mi resolooshun Nvos tooc. i put a stun into 6  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7289-00000062"/> 122    Mr. Pepper's Mournful Sixth. the toul, &amp; wen the hors caim up i spotted him. he dropt so cuick the man &amp; yung lady boath picht forids, &amp; wos a-pickin thayrselves up wen i turnd around. wot a Vizzion she wosl tlhroo al the dert i cood se Butyl ' Mi preserver ' sed she, in a angilic vois, a-settin ov herselft onto a stun. i floo to her, &amp; maid a faint ov follin onto 1 ne. 'doant,' said she, 'youl derty your pans:' wich wos troo, besids bein considerit. so i dident, but i tooc her hand &amp; sed she wos welcum to mi servis, wich wos no trubel, &amp; ide be hapy to spot a hors fur her evry day. she smild hevinly, &amp; sed i wos A-JACK' (a cmart ainshen.) i cald her HELIN, wich she sed wos a mistaik, as her naim wos HANAH GANE WALTERS. i then sed she hed also mistooc my cignacher, wich wos Mr. K. N. PEPPER Esq. Youd orter seen the looc ov surpris &amp; plesyour as her fechers wos spred with wen i opend onto her with thnat anounsment I she tooc notis ov me for a ninstant kind ov wild, then sudently giv way to her emoshuns &amp; wept. in a short time the toul sacherated with her teres, &amp; i wos a-thinkin ov gittin a dry 1, wen she dride up the fount, &amp; she &amp; the man wich she cald pa, as wos hirt onto his hed, staid with me severil days. i red al mi pomes to her, &amp; we got pirty thic. al to 1's the Faither rekiverd &amp; anounst that thay must go hoam. ' Ken you leve?' sed i, in broken ax cents &amp; a thic vois. hers wos thic wen she sed she coodent no way. we then hugd. wot bliss! but the crule Faither put in his ore, &amp; AL wos ore. he hed to choak her of. as he wos a-levin he remarct that he wos werth $900 dolars, &amp; he thougt it wos redic- kalus, raither. but ef it wos spoart to him, it wos deth to me &amp;   Mr. Pepper's Mournful Sixth.       123 her. She sed 2 or 3 times she shoodent ete eny thing; &amp; the onfelin Rech at last spoak &amp; sed it wood saiv vittels. Wen thay disapeard roun the corner-she a-waivin her hankerchif, i a- hoaldin up mi hans in mewt dispair,-i sunc onto the floar, &amp; in my ageny toar of al mi vest buttons in 1 gerk, &amp; struc sumthin hard onto the floar. it wos 1 ov mi aingels puf-coams, as fel in the hart rending struggel. i dident mind the ile, but kist it al the rest ov the day. its be4 me now. its al as kepes me aliv. heres wot i rote wen i becum cam enuf to hoald a pen: "'TO    THE  AINGEL  AS IS GON. "CO HANAH, HANAH, HANAH dere: I   C GANE WALTERS I wers the vizzhun now? Dispers fur ever moar i fere (bi) Your Faither with the angry Brow. Is o HANNI! ken i say youm gon? To a onkind Fait must PEPPER bow? A. then wele pile our cursis on- (to) Your Faither with the angry Brow. "LO wot a load to carry round I To fre hisself he donno how: A onhapy man now wock the ground- (its) Your Faither with the angry Brow. "'but, lovly HANAH, doant dispair, doant taik on bad, doant rais no row; 1 man 'l feel remors &amp; cair- (its) Your Faither with the angry Brow.  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7289-00000063"/> 124   Mr. Pepper's Mournful Sixth. "'wot chaing hes cum it oar our dremes I Wot Hap'nis l's, wot miz'ry now! But Gustis lay the blaim, it semes, (onto) Your Faither with the angry Brow. "in Graiv we mete, ef no waris els, Mi HANAH dere, i make a vow- Or sooner ef Deth the spirrit cuels (ov) Your Faither with the angry Brow. "'o PODD, PODD-i wos afraid i shood di be4 i got that dun. but its dun now, &amp; i doant no wether to send it to her or let it be found amungst mi efex. ef i doant hury it wil be the last. Dere PODD, good bi--peraps fur ever. PODD good bi, good bi. 1's moar good bi, from your old fren K. N. PEPPER. "n. b. encloased is a loc ov mi hair. ef i di, let my funerl be privit. let HANAH GANES puf-coam be berrid with me. tel her i wos troo, &amp; dide fur her. "'Fair weL                 K. N. P." F   ON NOSES. Said Aaron to Moses, "et's cut off our noses. Siad Moses to Aaron, 'st' the fashion to wear 'em.'  HOW the above amusing and authentic anecdote has been preserved to us, would be an interest- ing question for the antiquary. Considering the lapse of time since the date of that remarkable conversation, it ought not to surprise us that so little of the lighter chit-chat of these humorous High Priests should now remain, but rather that any scrap could have clung to the memory of man for so long a period. Where Aaron acquired a notion so absurd, cannot now be learned. It would appear that the influence of the  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7289-00000064"/> 126        On Noses. more sensible Moses was sufficient to prevent the precipitate Aaron from ridding himself of a feature which, however unornamental, was certainly useful, if not indispensable. After reading a statement so dis- paraging, one cannot help losing somewhat of that respect for Aaron which, in a general way, attaches to the cloth. No matter if his nasal protuberance was as homely as that of the little boy who complained to his mother that his nose ' grew pugger and pugger every day;" he could on no principle be excused for sever- ing it from the face for which it was made. And if the act proposed would have been one of pure wan- tonness-which we suspect was the case--we cannot find words sufficiently energetic for the adequate ex- pression of our shocked-nay, horrified feelings. On the other hand, we honor Moses with peculiar homage for his manly and dignified stand upon the nose of his friend. Note his gentlemanly deference to the opi- 2 nions and usages of the community. In his laconic but comprehensive reply he says only, "It's the fashion to wear 'em." It is proper to infer that this reply had the happiest effect upon Aaron. It presented to him the inconvenience of being without a nose, in connec- tion with the idea of singularity-of being " out of ^0   On Noses.         127 fashion;" which, in those-days-when a man at two or three hundred was still thought young-must have been the most terrible one that Moses could have sug- gested. We may also believe that Moses had a rever- ence for the nasal feature, as a feature; and that it pained his sense of fitness and proportion to imagine the human countenance as divested of it. It is this feeling with which we sympathize most deeply in the present article; for the question of fashion has come to affect the shape, rather than the existence, of the nose. It may sound oddly to some to speak of the nose in this technical way; but let them ask almost any mother to describe how, by innumerable pinches, she fashioned the noses of her offspring--redeemed them from "pug"-ness, or checked their banian-like tendency to turn toward the root-and they may be- gin to realize that the idea is not absurd. Beside the notion of mere servile imitation, in these artist-minded mammas-shaping a nose after the rich Mr. A's, or the fashionable Miss B's-two ideas may be mentioned, as having a particularly controlling effect. First, and most widely prevalent, is that of beauty. Few are insensible to the beauty or effect of a well-turned nose. After the eyes and mouth, per-  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7289-00000065"/> 128        On Noses. haps the nose takes the first place in a description of features. "She's very pretty-that is, would be, were it not for that horrid nose!" or, " what a fine nose Mr. C. has " are expressions familiar to every one. The other idea is that of character. There is a great deal of character in a nose. That is, the nose is often made quite an index of character; not always, or per- haps often, willingly-but insensibly, and not the less surely. Both these ideas will be further illustrated in the following analysis. The Grecian nose is usually considered the finest and most noble of all the varieties. It is distinguished by its being " well planted" between the brows, and straight upon the ridge, and by its firm, well-turned nostrils. It lends dignity and grace to the counte- nance, and is significant of truth, honor, purity, and delicacy of mind. Nobleness, openness, and liberality of mind and heart are suggested by it. It may be mentioned here, however, that these signs are by no means infallible, and the same may be said in relation to those which follow. (My pocket was once picked by a Grecian-nosed thief.) The Roman nose is also much admired, as being indicative of manliness and vigor of mind, and lofti.   On Noses.         129 ness of purpose. The ridge, instead of being straight, is raised in the middle, generally so as to form an ob- tuse angle, though sometimes it has a continuous curve. This variety of nose is suggestive of strength rather than delicacy of mind, and of prudence than generosity. Both the varieties which have been men- tioned depend much for their favorable significance upon the purity of their "lines," and degree of per fection of " chisseling." The Aquiline nose is curved and hooked, like the bill of the eagle. It is usually accompanied by sharp- ness and activity of mind, but is indicative rather of acuteness than solidity. It is also an accompaniment of cunning, selfishness, and rapacity. (If the reader, or his wife, has such a nose, he will of course know the case is an "exception.") The Retrousse nose is vulgarly called the " turn-up." It is rarely accompanied by nobleness or greatness of mind, but rather signifies one absorbed by self. The possessor of such a nose may be witty, sensitive, and "thin-skinned," but rarely generous, manly, or high- souled. On this kind of nose " hats " have been sus- pended. The "Pug"-nose-the poor little pug-nose; what  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7289-00000066"/> 130        On Noses. need be said of the pug-nose? Everybody knows the pug-nose. Not " big enough to pull," or small enough to be called a wart, it can neither be blown nor worn with satisfaction, and is only possessed by men as little in proportion as the excrescence itself. Napo- leon gave small-nosed men a particularly wide berth- and there was reason. There are modifications of all these varieties; and, indeed, a great portion of all the noses may be termed modifications. Then we have the " bottle-nose," the i( carbuncle nose," the "rum-blossom nose," the 4 squab-nose," the "flat nose," and the nose with the knob at the end. The next to the last named-variety embraces the African nose. A wide nostril denotes a deep, full chest. A very red and highly-inflamed nose is significant of " apple-jack," which is a " weak- ness." Washington had a very fine, wide-ridged Grecian nose. The Greeks are generally supposed to have Grecian noses. Wellington had a remarkable Roman nose, and most Romans have them likewise. John Randolph and Tristram Burgess had aquiline noses. "TUrn-up," and " pug" noses are not commonly sported by great men.   On Noses.         131 A race of people-thank Heaven becoming extinct -called Yankees, have succeeded in converting the nose into a musical instrument,--of wondrous power, but somewhat deficient in sweetness. It is not com- monly considered so good as the natural organ, and, it is to be fervently hoped, will in time be disused. We have only' to fancy the human countenance divested of the nose, to agree with Moses that the nasal appendage is " very good in its place." The ad- vocates of Aaron's theory are becoming rare. [4 Q                             ,  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7289-00000067"/> MR. PEPPER'S GREAT ODE. --o-- EADER, I have not the heart to add to the elo- quent words which follow, introducing to the world what seemed Mr. PEPPER'S last letter and poem :- "The ' Great Pore' has emerged from the desolateness of his transient rusticity into the light of society and 'frens.' But alas I PEPPER is a wreck I Let his note 'revele.' Its sombre shadows disclose a ponderous 'wo' which his sensitive delicacy alone warns him to withhold, in all its magnitude and tragic horror, from a too-easily-affected community. PHcEBUSI how much ' genus' can suffer, and not ' cave l' But the reader must not be kept longer in suspense " "1 Demosthenes proper, "Oetobir lth, '54. ' MR. IL. GALERD CLARK, ESQ.: "MR. EDITER--after a long silens ov uperds ov 8 munths (in consekens ov bein fir remoov rum feverything bi a   Mr. Pepper's Great Ode.        133 laik, a fishin fur mi helth) i hev now returnd hoam to Di. theres no resun wi i shoodent, as i hevent got nothin fur to liv fur, now. mi tale shel never be toald to no boddy-much les to hir. i hev only comunicatid the cecrit to 1 fren. no boddy els coodenthi it fur munny. but i mene to kepe a-ritin potry al the wile, til i cant hoald a pen. then ses i, Goast, go up ile welcum deth cuickly, onles a sertin oald tiren soon egspires, wich aint prob- ble, as meen men never di. But the Werld shel thinc ime gay --mi pomes shel be rote so cairles. encloased is a noad to the grek Slaiv, wich plese cend to the comitty,* ef not too lait, as i feer. ef so, plees keep the saim, as a me Mento ov the moril Kerig ov   Yours fur a few days oanly, K. N. PEPPER. !"p. s. i doant cair about the $100 dollers. giv the munny to sum yung man as is gest marid to the objeck ov his chois &amp; startin into biznes. wot doo i wont ov munny? ide lik it per- aps ef that oald tiren----but i say no moar, egskews my emo- shuns. thaym overpowrin &amp; daingerus.      K. N. P. "A NOAD TO THE GREK SLAIV. '" l's moar, mi Pen, asoom 1's moar the trasis ov blanc Vers: 1's moar spring litely into em. doant gerk. go cam &amp; cuiet; but git on fire gradily, mi pen, &amp; giv the subjeck Convulshuns I * The "Cosmopolitan Art Association " offered a prize for the best Ode to the Greek Slave. Mr. PEPPER had a mind to con- tend for it.   &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7289-00000068"/> 134     Mr. Pepper's Great Ode. "STATOO I (good hevins! wers mi i's?-ime blind I) STUN PICTER I hail Hin consekens ov your glory i shel be compeld to hev a operashun performd fur' Cat a rack, immejitly. i thougt i cood go this slo; But i se it cant be dun: youm al powrful: your influens is sech, ime al ov a trembel, &amp; fele a sort ov sicnes a-cre-pin into mi stomic slo but shoor-like a gimblit into a board. wos you al sculp frum 1 pese? say, Perfeckshun 1- hevent you got no goints maid ov putty, nor nothin? But no; i feel youm perfeck: i thinc, at leest, that POWERS'S story otto be giv ear to- wich ses youm al hac out ov a marble stun. (imortel POWRS I wot a genus fur sculp 1) distingguisht Femail I a-standin thayr onto 1 leg-- in silens admired bi hundreds, i supoas- you ken apreshait the felings ov her as went in swimmin, &amp; soon aperin l's moar, discuverd nothin into the plais ov a good soot ov Cloas: as wos a-lyin thayr But 1 short minit previs-supoasd to be hern. (pardon me, grek, for the alooshun.) But wot need hes Buty, fur menny artikels ov aparril? how menny ladys you se wich sertinly thinc EVE'S fashion wos the handyest, but thay parshelly giv in to custum, out ov the nateral kindnis ov thayr harts 1   Mr. Pepper's Great Ode.        135 wos that the stile wen you wos animaitid? then wot did you cawl makin ov a toy lit? frum your compleckshun i shood thine peraps you dined prinsiply onto your natyv Air. it must hev ben ov a solider maik than nited Staitsen air, wich is mity thin dyit wen used egscloosiv, as i otto no. o Slaiv--but i leve you to ges wots hapend: oanly remarkin that 3 wekes ive livd onto it; But at last poor Nacher hes cum round to vittels "wot butiful hans-so delekit &amp; wite l thats moastly dun bi activly a-doin nothin. i no a yung lady as hes got sech hans- oanly not cuite so very wite &amp; teanty, oin to a crule Faither as maiks her were. her naim is HANAH G. W. her feet air larger, But woodent be efher shoos &amp; stockins wos of. her arm, ef anything, is bigern yourn; &amp; shes raither better lookin into the faiso firther comparrisuns wood be but ges were, owin to the present inconvenyent fashins; But no dout thay wood be faverbel to HANAH. i no her figers shorter, likewais her noas; But in them fechers statoos must be pardond, fur sculpers hev inoomeribel rinkels. POWRS thincs Buty lays in hite &amp; length- But 1 looc at HANAH wood chaing his hul idee.  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7289-00000069"/> 136     Mr. Pepper's Great Ode. yet hoo wood hev al Buty ov a peese? STATOO I fur your stile youm perfeck I your looc ov cam disgust is probbly rite, altho sum harts wood gladly se thee smiL your air is forin, sos your nashun too; you air the verry Picter ov a grek in chains, &amp; no dout a 1st chop sampel. it doant tan you much to traivil, i se: youm probbly well cloathed, exsep wen shoad; then your dres is egstreemly lo in the nec: Bein a vizzionery Bloomer, without enny pans-- or a full dress, posessiv cais under stood. "i must now bid you a abrupt adoo, fair STATOO I felin al the distressin simtums ov a pereodikel atact ov pain into the bowls. MABBLE STUN ENTERPRIS HFAIR THEE WEL '  I-   PHRENOLOGY OF THE HEAVENS. A PAINTING. BY MB. tErtPER. ON   the next page but two, will be found an engrav- o  ing from a "Shove Dover," by Mr. Pepper-who, like T. Buchanan Read, is an artist-poet. The follow- ing  extract from  the remarks of J-  M   ,the eminent critic, it will be perceived, even from the engraving, are profound and lucid, as well as just: "This remarkable work is the first of its kind. We are at a loss where to place it. We cannot, perhaps, put it before the greatest of the ' Chef d'oeuvre Productions' of Landis, the cele- brated apostle of 'High old Art and Literature,'--he of 'the  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7289-00000070"/> 138    Phrenology   of the Heavens. Capitol of this Commonwealth, contiguous to which, he 'is a native;' nor can it be placed behind that painting; for then it could not be seen at all. It must take its own place." "The chiaro-'scuro effects, in this painting, are very fine: so fine that most unassisted eyes will not be able to perceive them. Mr. Pepper's handling is quite-nay, excessively, free; and he works up his, inspirations with-in short, his brush. His color- ing cannot be excelled, for intensity of blue; while the general tone, considering the subject, is uncommonly moral. Were we hypercritical, it might be obvious to remark, that the best paint- ers of celestial scenery represent stars with five points instead of six; but of course it does not become a liberal critic to notice such a trifling blemish: the artist may have seen stars with six points. "It is interesting to note those little inaccuracies which evince the carelessness of true genius. Thus, the left fore-leg of the bear is fore-shortened too much by about the thirty-second of an inch. But how amply is this oversight atoned for in the extra- ordinary amount of intelligence thrown into the face of the bear I The tip of this celestial animals nose is full of meaning. And the grace and repose of his figure-particularly the tail-chal- lenge the encomium of every lover of extremely High Art. "The accessories are well managed; the artist has them under complete control. Indeed, they have never been managed in quite the same way before. On a careful inspection of certain marks, we cannot resist the impression that the picture was at   Phrenology of the Heavens.        139 first intended as a mere skiagram; but that the suggestiveness of the subject induced the artist to fill it up, with all that elabo- rateness of finish now observable in it. How exquisitely faith- ful are the claws of the bearl How delicately pencilled are his ears 1" "We understand that an engraving of this admirable painting is being prepared, and impressions will be ready for subscribers by about the middle of September. Artists' proofs-with a gift- book-one dollar. Without the gift-book, four cents. The exquisite jokes, in parentheses, were invented by Mr. Podd-whose spirits went so high, on the final completion of the painting, that for the space of half an hour his gravity entirely forsook him."  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7289-00000071"/> FRE NOLLIG OV THE HEVINS. F]BOM THa ORIGIAL PIOTURVBZ, Is THB P0sBeBION or P. PEPPER PODD, ESQ. [REMARC.] Heer we hev a picter ov the Hevins, as thay apeerd be4 the stars wos fixt acordin to Act ov congriss: fur wich we cant be too graitful. Venous-al bloody-is seen onto the rite, gest a-settin-peraps fur to hach (wich goak is pirfeckly arigenaD: Grait Bair, rampan, with his tail a-flyin, is the prinsi- pal objeck into the frunt-sed bi Connysoors to hev a pecoolyerly sagashus looc out ov his left i: Moon, over the left-wich is a bad sine; shood chaing with Venous. (End ov the Remarc.) (Desined &amp; painted, &amp; the Remarc compoased, with grail expens-espeshelly the arigenal Goak-fur to be shoad bi Mr. Winter: wich the pris he coodent pay:-remarkin that chee, Genus wos al he cood afoard to encurrig. n b. no Solt musl be put onto the Bairs tail.) *('   THE LITTLE FRENCHMAN. OWING to the continued operation of those natural laws which govern the motions of the earth, and the impossibility of the sun's rays penetrating the bodies of the planets, it was night in Bugtown. I will conceal nothing: the hour was eleven, and it was dark for -as yet there was no gas in Bugtown, and the moon was away that night, attending to a little business-in fact, pursuing her reflections in the groves of Persia, where she has been, from the eari liest ages, afflicted with a passion for wandering. I am not prepared, of myself, to assert that it was very dark; but I firmly believe it was, because Rose Water, who had been standing for ten minutes on the steps of her father's house, trying to see her own hand, which she held before ner face for that purpose,  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7289-00000072"/> "2    The Little Frenchman. said it was; and I have no intention of disputing a lady. An insect-which, in flying about with unusual ardor, had covered itself with perspiration- happening to touch the hand of the lady, just as she had delivered the opinion ascribed to her, and light- ened herself of a ponderous sigh, she added, in a tone of considerable vexation, "And, I declare, it's rain- ing. How provoking r' A sigh followed, compared with which, the other was as nothing, in point of weight and general dimensions-the latter being decidedly longer, while at least as broad and thick as its predecessor. She then went in. [It is probable that a portion of my readers are surprised that I do not lengthen the preceding sen- tence by the addition of the word "lemons;" sup- posing, of course, that our heroine immediately engaged in some unique employment, with consi- derable energy--all of which may be expressed in that brief and elegant phrase. No; she went in, as I said-feeling sour enough, I dare say, but nothing near as acid as the fruit mentioned. Another intelli- gent and acute portion of my friends are, doubtless, ready to suggest the substitution, for "went in," of the phrase "turned in," as more comprehensive, and   one Little Frenchman.      143 savoring of probability, at that hour of the night. I confess I am not smitten with a mania for economy in words. In due time I should, perhaps, have- alluded to Rose's going to bed; though I doubt if I would have been quite so minute, in the description of that process, as Mr. Keats, in his "Eve of St. Agnes." Let all readers leave the narration of the story to me, and read on with child-like confidence in the excellence of its management.] Why had Rose Water for so long a time exposed herself to the night air of Bugtown--knowing full well, as she did, that fever-and-ague was prevalent in that section? It is quite probable that Rose had her own reasons for it. It is no affair of ours. It may not be thought particularly impertinent, however, for me to mention that she was friendly to one Count La Vendre-or "Lavender, the little Frenchman," as he was good-humoredly termed by the boys of the village-who was spending the summer in the country, his home being, since his exile, in New York city. Every one except Rose seemed to think the count of no great account, and found it difficult to account for her preference. [I fancy a sneer of ineffable scorn to be wreathing  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7289-00000073"/> "4    The Little Frenchman. the lips of some critical readers. Not for the titled foreigner do they feel that contempt. Oh no they already love the little Frenchman. That scorn is for me, the author. "A man who will pun," they say, in tones of cutting severity, " or attempt the ringing of changes on words, merits the contempt of the general reading public, and the reprehension of his friends"All the same to him, if he don't get it. Losing sight of even the truth, in my devotion-to a whim, I shall go on to say that-] The little Frenchman could count on one good friend, at least, in Bugtown: one whose slightest taste never ran counter to his own; one who delighted to hear him recount his Othello-nian adventures-the account of which would often make her heart beat faster than she could count; one who, to all appear- ance, received the veracious narrative without any hesitation or mental discount: counting the count as honest as any he in the county, or, indeed, the coun- try-not mentioning the continent, as unwilling to countenance that wholesale manner of statement. There I Rose went in. [Which makes the third time I have alluded to that sensible action, and lays me   The Little Frenchman.      145 open to censure on the score of redundancy in lan- guage. No one but a fool would again repeat the assertion.] Leaving her to grope her way up to her room-muttering, as she went, that the various "stories" were I' not so interesting as some she had gone through," I return to the count-whom, by the way, I do not remember to have left. The count was standing-no, I can't lie: sitting-at his window in the village hotel, at the same hour (the reader will remember-eleven-how significant ) and also chiding, but in bad English, the unpropitious elements. To add to the horrors of his condition, the wretched little Frenchman was drunk. Like any other conquered son of Gaul, he did not seem to be aware of his situation, but conversed with the in- habitants of Pandemonium, and other low society, in a strain of energetic, but tipsy volubility, that must have disgusted even the lowest of that class, and estranged for ever the friendship of the more intelli- gent devils. "By gar zis is too bad!" he at length remarked-- cooling a little in both language and feeling. "Rose Vattare I she vill say I am ze dem foo-oo-ool! I vill go, if it shall r-r-rain peech-fork "  So spake brave 7  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7289-00000074"/> "6     The Little Frenchman. Lat Vendre, the little Frenchman--adding the single expletive, "Sacre!" [The sagacious reader has, doubtless, already guessed--much to my surprise, and entirely contrary to my intention-that our Gallic friend, the vivacious La Vendre, and Rose Water had made some arrange- ment, probably clandestine, to be consummated that night: say running away, getting married, and coming back, repentant and forgiven, after many years, with a coach-and-six, six children and half-a- dozen servants. "It would be so nice!" murmurs some pretty blue-eyed creature in curls and 'teens. "Just the plot for a short novel," pronounces her literary and elderly sister. Ge-nrls, it shall be as you say. That 2was the plan. I swear to you, that was the plan. Let us watch its fortunes.] Tile solemn tones of the village clock tinkled musi- cally and sadly as they tolled: no-struck: no- marked with feeling emphasis the hour of eleven. The hour-hand gravely pointed to the Roman charac- ters XI., on the dial-face, and, in conjunction with the more mercurial minute-hand, embraced affectionately the hour included between them. Soon the minute- r ,.lil1, with ill-tilned levity, offered to bet his brother   The Little Frenchman.      147 that he would give him eleven-twelfths of the whole course the start, and overtake him in less than an hour and a half. "Done!" said the selcf-onceited senior, forgetting his dignity in the excitement of the moment, and at once engaging in the race. Racing was no new thing to them; in fact, they were old hands at it. While this undignified farce was acting in the steeple, the little Frenchman, all unconscious of that, and nearly everything else, pursued below his eccen- tric course towards the dwelling of his charmer. When he had arrived within a block or two of the house, continuing his recitations by the way, the shocked and distressed elements could no longer restrain their grief, and wept profusely. Notwith- standing this evidence of atmospheric agony the pro- fane Gaul continued to rail, until he stood beneath the window of Rose Water. It would seem that he felt a little disappointed at the general aspect of things on his arrival. Though straining his eyes to a dangerous degree of tension, he had not been able to discern the rope-ladder hanging from the window of his Dulcinea; and it would have been a very singular discovery if he had, considering that there was none there. There was no sign of Rose; no indication of a desire on her i    "'  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7289-00000075"/> "8     The Little Frenchman. part to change her quarters, even though she should thus secure the " eligible, well-watered and every way desirable piece of property, soon to be sold." The count had thought he had known what sadness was, in days gone by. Indeed, he had often feelingly observed the same to Rose; but now he was certain he knew. While his feelings were getting ready to cul- minate in some affecting speech, the window above him slowly raised, and two young ladies peered cauti- ously into the darkness. "There he is!-he has come, after all," whispered Rose to her companion, as a flash of lightning for a moment revealed the dripping and melancholy figure of the little Frenchman, now rush- ing to and fro in a state of dismal distress and un- healthy  excitement. Was the elopement, then, to take place, and make a happy man of the count, not- withstanding the unpromising aspect of affairs? We shall see. At length, as the accumulative, blighting unhappi- ness of his state, without and within, came upon him with resistless force, he clasped his hands, and gave vent to his injured feelings. "By   gar! zis is tr-r riste diffecultee! I shall be mad I   ROSE VATTARE!  Vous make dem foo-ooool   The Little Frenchman.      149 of me! It is not kind! I shall str-r-rike mon head on ze wall! I vill now r-r-run!"-which intention was hardly called for, as he had been running all the while. ' Nevertheless, it served to quicken the speed of the unhappy Frenchman, who now made directly for the wall as though he were charging a battery; Suddenly he stopped and clapped both his hands to his stomach, losing at once both his color and anima- tion. The bad liquor, the excitement, the rain, and the melancholy had done their office. "H am ZEE-EE- EEK!" whimpered the miserable little Frenchman. "I will go back to ze hotel!" He was too thorough- ly plunged in distress to be aware of the smothered laugh which stole down from Rose's window, and fol- lowed him merrily a good distance. Mightily glad to reach his destination was the Count La Vendre. Shutting his door on the world with its cares and troubles, including a portion of his share in both, the still unhappy Gaul stood for a moment con- templating himself in the glass. Then, with a mut- tered "Sacre!" the little Frenchman, now thoroughly disgusted, rushed to the bed, threw himself on it, and groaned himself to sleep.  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7289-00000076"/> t A POEM (AND POET) CUT SHORT. "One dem'd grind."-MANTAL1NI. STROPHE. r SHADE of Mother Googe: that long since fled (No one knows when, exactly,) to the sky: Bend, pr'ythee, bend thy venerable head- Look down, good Ghost, if with but half-an-eye, And see a struggling poet rhyming here. Oh I for a moment lay your knitting by For work more fitting: write, make blunders, cry- Drop but a line, a stitch-a pitying tear; Do anything, to prove you sympathize In his distress; so will you hush his sights Warm his cold heart, inspire his lazy pen- And make him yours devotedly. Amen. ANTISTROPHE. METmHNKS a voice, all thin and quavery, cracked, Steals down in whispers: "I am Mother Goose.   A   Poem  (and Poet) cut short.    151 Take my advice: Unless by Want attacked, Never again thy Pegasus unloose: For I should now be living on the earth, If Fate had with my genius made a truce, Consigned my well-known Melodies to the deuce. And spared those labouring pains which marked their birth:" And here, a sob assaults my tender ear, So natural and " old," I think it queer Those vocal sounds should have the least existence, Just travelled, quavering, such an awful distance.  EPODE. GOOD heavens --can it be so--is i' Mother" right? Is "Goose" au fait in matters of this kind?- O Matron, Sage-ess, Wisdom's Shade!--this night I bend an old twig to your turn of mind. The world should know, that a tremendous poet Majestically leaves himself behind-- timself thus martyrs, whistles down the wind. 'Tis sad to have much genius (and to know it)- Compelled to choke it down, or lose a life; But she was all unequal to the strife,- And Hmy poems, or my breath resigning, Make now my choice-and straightway stop my whining. ,  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7289-00000077"/> A PAUSE. PERHAPS it is just as well, my tender-hearted reader, to postpone the   shock of Mr. PEPPER'S harrowing next. Suffer yourself to be detained a little while by a few trifles. Try a crumb   from the Orient:- FABLE FROM THE ARABIC. One morning the Sun said to himself: "This is the day I have fixed on for the annihilation of Raschid al Ferez, the bareheaded despiser of my power. The wretch must die I I have said it." He then began to travel over the sandy plain, which soon was ready to fuse with the extraordinary heat. But what astound- ing sight has filled the sun with wonder, and checked his blazing progress across the heavens? Raschid al Ferez is no longer bareheaded I "Alas I " said the over-heated luminary, in a ter- rible perspiration, " why am I always a day too late? A friend   A   Pause.         153 to my intended victim has robbed me of my prey by sending him, from New York, one of' Whang's Gossamer Hats.' I know them! They are proof against anything I can do in Arabia. When I get directly over the comer of Broadway and T'other Street, I will endeavor to burn up their establishment."* Or a sententious and oracular home-made tit-bit:- A HAPPY  EXPEDIENT. One day, when Time was young, the Graces, clustering round him, desired to know how long he was to exist. Conscious of his ignorance, but, because his locks were already grey, wish- ing to be thought wise, he thus replied: "For Man was I created. He dies: to him I exist no longer." (This is very funny.) Or a sentimental taste:- UNREST. Alas I what strangers we are to sweet content 1 What trifles move us!  Geometricians tell us points have "neither length, breadth, nor thickness, but position only." Our school-days being over, how many of us-dwelling in blest obscurity, but lacking neither in length, breadth, nor thickness--are ever vainly sighing to be points I * Picked up in the street: supposed to be intended as an advertisement.               7^  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7289-00000078"/> 154          A   Pause. Or a narrative and anecdotical morsel:- AUTHENTIC INCIDENT IN WASHNGTON'S "FE. Washington was one day walking in his front yard, when who should come in, unperceived, but La Fayette. Bursting with the humor of his idea, the Marquis stole up to the General and slapping him on the back, roared out: "Wash I my old boy -how are you?" "Tol'ble, Mac," said Washington, with that perfect self-possession which he always exhibited,--"I feel-but stop: I smell dinner I Wait here a few minutes, and I'll fetch you out a bite." Or a biographical slice:- TORRICE rT. This was the Italian gentleman who discovered the vacuum. While engaged in a bustling search for it, he originated a style of answer to impertinent inquiries, that has since become common. His inquisitive uncle observed the flurry he was in, and cried: "' What are you looking for, Torry?" "Oh, nothing," was the reply,-which both incensed and silenced the old man. Torri- celli, being a man of genius, was modest, and did not make much of his discovery; but modern scientific men affect to see a good deal in it. Nature is said to abhor a vacuum: but it is thought slie resembles many other solid old women, who are remarkable for making a prodigious fuss about nothing at alL Or a jocose sip or two:-   A  Pause.          155 A HEAVY JOKE. (EXPECTED TO GO THE ROUNDS.) The most amusing geological curiosity is a "Grin' stone!" ANOTHER. The most emblematical one (significant of a stupid cow-fight) is the greenish mineral "Hornblende." CONUNDRUM. Why is this book like the Russians at Sebastopol? Because it is pretty well Pepper-ed. Or an epigrammatic final puff:- JENNY LIND'S LAST NOTE. A-sighing in her garden, one damp morning, She looked where Goldy in the; window sat- Who, dozing there, that moment dropped his hat. She picked it up, the act with song adorning, But stopped, in both,--that instant having warning Her sighs would hardly let her reach A flat. "But, soft: behold!"  A Tribute to Genus. Thus Clark, with energy: "MR. U. C. SKIPPERS sends us 'A Dress to K. N. Pepper,' from which we segregate the following. But, Mr. SKIPPERS, PEPPER can't be imitated-he can only be approached at a very great distance:"  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7289-00000079"/> 156          A  Pause. "GREAT PEPPERI thou star ov 1st magnitude In the litterrary cistem, receve mi offerinks In yur own stile ov blanc vers witch dont Yu nevr fursak. Youm eeny about the fust Poik livin witch kums up 2 mi idees. Wat a free an unparalel han yu strik the Kords with, dont yu? Youm grat youm punkins  Yu ken sale on, grat barb, like the elektrik sparc Witch darts the hevinks thru an rips the klowds Considrable, an sumtimes strikes barns; Jes so youl rip the klowds of ignerens &amp; erer. Yu ken beet eny livin poek &amp; not B tri He bet, with yur rite han tide behin ye." 481^aJ^^^ iSI fS i ^a 3rs 0^   MR. PEPPER WALKS IN THE "VAL- "EY OF SHADOWS."9 HERE is much, in Civil War, to justify our fears when threatened with it: much, very much, in Toothache. But when a man, and that man a poet: a man of imagination, feeling, sympathy, affection: has reasoned with himself, and come to the conclusion that Suicide is the only thing that can make existence supportable, we infer at once, that man has suffered, and very likely been unable to sleep much for several nights. We know it I Reader! fancy yourself possessed of the organiza- tion of a PEPPER. It is hard to do it, but-fancy it. Then, in imagination, overwhelm your gentle spirit with misfortune, neglect, enmity, disappointment, and the hereditary misery of Genius: go on,-goad-  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7289-00000080"/> 158 Walks in the Valley of Shadows. ing yourself to that pitch of madness that life becomes "a burthen and a curse:" keep up this unpleasant "posture of affairs" a few days or weeks:--then cal- culate yourself up, and see what you come to. You will think (and SKIPPERS will agree) that it is "not exactly the cheese" to be in, a great while. You may have desperate thoughts of-but no; even then, com- pared with PEPPER, you would be happy. For he must leave the angelic HANNAH JANE.   The "rub" was to rub himself out of her society; and not to yield up beefsteak and the light of day. That part cannot be imagined. The annexed correspondence, when it appeared in the Knickerbocker Magazine, spread (very evenly) a gloom over the continent of North America, from the Isthmus of Darien to 82 50'; which is giving Melancholy the largest latitude that can be afforded in the present state of our geographical knowledge: "Demosthenes Four-Corners, Jan. 10, 186. MR. CLARK': EDITOR: "SIR: After reading the inclosed letter which I have just had the melancholy Pleasure of receiving from our mutual friend Mr. K. N. PEPPER, Esq., you will of course lay aside all other Con- siderations and weep with me. Sir: Tears are good. He was   Walks in the Valley     of Shadows.     159 worth rivers of them, or, if I am extravagant, creeks. I say wasp for I consider him a Relict. He was, but is not. He is dead to the world, although he may feel alive. He is a singular instance of the experimentum Crucis. It is not too much to say that I regret his absence. He has left a void' which I fear Aches. My children were wont to greet him playfully, and received Brazilian nuts at intervals. The three-cornered productions of South America may be supplied, but where is the Benefactor? Perhaps you do not wonder that I am weeping; perhaps you do not wonder that four children and an angelic Woman have streaks of dirt on their cheeks. You can feel for them. You have been in the same painful situation. "But a flood of emotion appears to be rising. I must close before I am carried away. "With consideration: Sir: Yours, '"P. PEPPER PODD. "P. S. As the Transaction will be unknown to Mr. PEPPER, I will send you Part First of the Great Pome as soon as I receive it from him.                   P. P. P." ! IDEER FELLER: ': ive fled. fal to were a-makin up your mind as soon as you reed this, &amp; resine yourself to the idee. i no it will hert your felings, but it wil soon be over. PEPPER is a-goin to kil hisself. His fren PODD wont never, never be a witnes ov his ageny, &amp; ketch his last breth. tHis axcents must be waisted  onto the desert air, &amp; his i's wil never be cuverd with smal coins. o the hapines ov a-sayin Fairwel to Wo, &amp; a-lookin for'ids to  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7289-00000081"/> 160   XWalks in the Valley    of Shadows. "' A good time a-comin, Boys, onto the uther side ov Gordon I' But ive got a grait Were to finish-wich wont be under severil weeks (the saim as i aloodid to last summer wen i felt so gay &amp; hapy). i am a-goin to dedecait it to you into 2 parts. the 1st i wil send soon. you air to kepe it al til you no i have deseized miself: after wich event you may egsersize your plesyour. amungst mi efex is severil smal pomes as i throo off bi od spels. if you ever colect mi wercs, they air to go in. Thers no use a- tryin to find me. ime invizzibel to the hewman Speshy; ime effectooally conseled by nothin. "' ef i doant git time to rite to you 1's moar be4 i shovil up this mortel coal (frum SHAMK.) taik this fur the last. PODD, i fele distres. i cant rite. Fairwel. "'frum your suferin but soon releved fren. "  K. ?. Pr'". ' t   "AGER BIER LYRIC. TAKEN FROM THE LIPS OF AN IMPORTED COCKNEY. ---- Sense and reason show the door, Call for my BIER, and point me to the dust. NIGHT THOUGHTS. LoVEL. How much, Sir, may a man with safety drink; JOHN. Sir, three half pints a day is reasonable; I care not if you never exceed that quantity., "AMB'S JOHN WOODVIL. --.--0--.. YEN- -Iingland vos my dwelling-place, an' "boots's" vos my station, I thought our hale an' porter vos complete in hopperation; And not a Scotchman come to us but vos ableeged to hown, That vos the jolliest juice o' malt vich 'e 'ad hever known- The jolliest hever known.  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7289-00000082"/> 162       Lager Bier Lyric. I couldn't think o' Italbion without a tear o' pride; An' ven the day vos finished, with my pewter by my side, In 'appiness I'd smoke my pipe, a stoppink for to quaff My liquor, vether it vos porter, hale, or 'alf-an'-'alf- Or jolly 'alf-an'-'alf. And ven I vos aboard the ship, a-goink for to leave My native land so fur avay, I 'isted of my sleeve, An' finding of it vet with tears, I vent atween the decks, A-feelin' wery mis'able without my Double X- My jolly Double X. But ven I'd j'ined the stars and stripes, and dropped my hac- cent too, I found a German custom 'ere, as vos a little new; So now I takes my Lager Bier vith all the other fellers, And finds it hev'ry block or two in all the hoyster cellars- The jolly hoyster dellars. They keeps this precious "Lager;' in the jolliest little kegs I And all the more you drinks of it the more you keeps your pegs; Vun man 'ad drunk five gallons, and vos takin' of another, Ven, feelin' werry generous, he give it to his brother- His dry and jolly brother. The Germans thinks the vorld of it, and vell the fellers may, For it is meat an' drink to 'em, and bed and clothes, they say   Lager Bier Lyric.         163 And every child has Lager, too, it's fed to ev'ry babby- For givin' of 'em milk would be to treat 'era rayther shabby-- Too jolly mean and shabby. The papers they'm hall full of it, heach jolly writer too; And many says hif you should give the inwentor vot's his due, You'd go and make a saint of him-a sort of Dutch re-Peter, To tell vot time our hale give in to somethink rayther better- The Lager, vich is better. So, 'eWe's my jolly Germans, vith their jolly yellow 'air; My spry and vitty Germans, hall so 'appy and so fair; And 'ere's the 'uman Blessing as ve prinsiply 'old dear: The jolly, jolly German, as inwented Lager Bier- The jolly Lager Bier. T^fYZ^^P "/V3 Hf E'^  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7289-00000083"/> ON THE CLAM. nO  THOU queer creature-thou mixture of meat 9 and drink, and miracle of oddity; thou that art neither " animal, vegetable, nor mineral :" in a word, BIVALVE!--look up, and behold thy champion! It was well thus to commence with an apostrophe to the genus. Let me now address myself to the species. Ineffable Clam!-But hold! what noise was that? Why this fearful tension? Startled Clam, allay your fears; for here no sacrificial knife is thirsting for your vitals. The mouth may "water," the inner man may " yearn "-but shall they be satisfied? The fatal steel is far, indeed, from these bloodless haunts; so are the "pepper and vinegar." In the   On the Clam.        165 light of these encouraging facts, dear Clam, dismiss your agitation; silence your "1," and be cad)m. What! harm thee, dear Clam, after this brief and interesting acquaintance? Rather than see thee in- jured, I would see dozens, yea, bushels of oysters swallowed, and feel no pity. Let us be friends, then; we are friends. There I I knew you would be open and frank with me. Now please be quiet till H Shut again   "Still suspicious." Too-sensitive Clam. But am I doing justice, either to the character of the Clam or of my own sentiments, by this untimely levity? Far from it; all Clam-dom shall bear me witness. It is impossible to contemplate these interesting objects without emotion-a watering of the eyes, and mouth. The genus Bivalve has many varieties, but in none other of these can we feel a tithe of the melancholy  interest that attaches to  the Clam. Spurned by his aristocratic relative, the oyster, and treated by humans with comparative indifference when both are subjects of contemplation, the Clam, by nature sensitive, feels his degradation deeply; and, although conscious of his many and decided  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7289-00000084"/> 166       On the Clam. merits, submits meekly to be misunderstood and undervalued, and even to have his modesty mistaken for an ignorant and stupid acquiescence. Injured bivalve! Thy delicate organization must needs suffer many rude shocks during thy brief but troubled existence. While thy mental sufferings are of a character and intensity known only to Clams, thy body, after enduring the buffetings of many a rude wave, and the jealous attacks of the injurious oyster, is almost certain to undergo violent torture and a cruel death at the hands of the genus "homo." Inoffensive and long-suffering creaturel Is he responsible for the flavor of his flesh? we indignantly ask; must his amiable disposition change? Must he become proud and haughty like his cousin, the oyster? Must he sink his native dignity of charac- ter, and herd with his fellows, in schools, from a cowardly idea of safety? Must he leave his modesty and the mud together? The meanest and most pusillanimous Clam in existence would spurn the idea with an indignation approaching to anger, if Clams are capable of so gross a feeling. No; thanks to the native independence of his race, each Clam is   On the Clam.         167 to himself a king, and to his foes an armed republic! To an equal he never yields; to a proven superior he submits with a graceful dignity. In times of peace the Clam is a philosopher; and, as far as possible, passes his even, quiet, and peaceful life in lofty meditation and the cultivation of the graces. How rational, how pleasing a life is this! Alas! that it should be perpetually disturbed by traditions of a ruthless foe in the upper world I Ah I could these prove but airy visions whose fabric were baseless! Alas! that dread experience proves them but too true!-A dire calamity cuts short the medita- tions of genius. Into those classic haunts the rake descends; and the peaceful philosopher, feeling that resistance were worse than   useless, drops a silent tear-which, were he an    oyster, would turn to a pearl-and   sighing a tender farewell to his native mud, with Stoical firmness rises to untried scenes in another element.  These "Countried scenes" are gene- rally of a very harrowing description, and need not be enlarged upon-the single word knife suggesting as much horror as a kind-hearted person would care to have expressed in words. Even when he escapes  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7289-00000085"/> 168       On the Clam. this almost inevitable fate, it is only to die a more lingering and cruel death from exposure and neglect; in fact, he pines away. How melancholy, then, is the compliment to human nature when we say, "As happy as a Clam!" Happy  He is never happy, even at "high-tide." Even upon his calmest reveries will intrude the painful thought, the fatal certainty, of final separation from all he holds most dear. Haplpy! When a man is happy he mingles with his fellow men. But when he is wretched, does he not brood in silence over his woes, and cultivate retirement as his only solace? Tis thus, ah yes-thus with the unhappy Clam I "Wrapped in the solitude of his own origi- nality," and giving his genius play, he may for awhile forget his woes; so do disconsolate mortals. But happy! Name it not, even in a jest. Let us not wantonly trifle with feelings doubtless more keen and sensitive than our own. There is hope that for the Clam a brighter day is dawning. Already a sense of justice inclines the lover of bivalves to victimize the callous oyster rather than his tender cousin. The oyster is gay   On the Clam.        169 because he has no fine feelings. He looks down upon the modest Clam, who does not care to enter his circle, and while rightly judging his thoughtful connexion unfitted for hollow amusement, he affects to despise while he really envies him. The oyster is light and trifling; the Clam, solid and practical. The latter may improve with time; the former must retro- grade. If we must choose, then, let our cry be, "Death to the oyster!" The question has been asked: "Do oysters ever fall in love?"I must answer, rarely, if ever; Clams, always. The ordinary oyster is incapable of the sentiment. There can be no more melancholy subject for contemplation than that of a Clam that is the victim of hopeless love.  What could sooner check the violence of mirth, and jsubdue us to a state of trembling commiseration, than the thought of a Clam in tears? But there, I touch a too tender chord. In the ardor of defence I have gone too far. If, in the absence of oysters, we are ever reduced to the melancholy necessity of dining off Clams, let us treat them gently: disengaging them quickly from the shell, and, without mangling, effecting an instant 8  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7289-00000086"/> 170       On the Clam. deglutition. Then let us invoke the Discontented Shade, and humbly ask forgiveness: pleading a dire necessity, and engaging to so'regulate our taste for bivalves, and confirm our discrimination of the species, that we may come to look upon the CLAM as sacred.   MR. PEPPER'S EIGHTH UPHEAVING. )EADER, how gladly would I spare thee every tear thou must shed over the woes of PEPPER I But the stern duty of the faithful chronicler must be done.  Read MR. PODD's affecting note: Demosthenes Fox Corners, March 12, 1855. "MR. CLARK : EDITOR: "Sir: The Repository of the most wonderful Poem of modern times has the pleasure of transmitting it to you. It came last night, enveloped in Mystery. If that is too poetical an expres- sion, allow me to substitute Brown Paper--which appeared to have been taken from a package of candles. "This will justify the expression. It is significant. No note or direction-explanation. Again significant. His name signed in his own Blood, which Skepticism would call red ink. Alas I significantl A faint but perceptive odor of Lanterns. Signifi- cant I  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7289-00000087"/> 172   Mr. Pepper's Eighth    Upheaving. "Is it not wonderful? Was he ever equalled in Pathos by even Ancient Authors--as, for instance, GULLIVER? (And be- tween ourselves, Sir, were the Poems of SocRATEs so remarkable as to forbid the rising Impulse to honor the Descriptive powers of PEPPER?)   Sir, in Sickness he is Great. All of his Poems show it. He never alludes to sickness without affecting me to tears: in fact, I often feel sick myself. You will not fail to notice his great improvement in Penmanship. I think he has Prac- tised. I know he has. If he did not spurn such things he would always spell as well as he writes, But what part of Genius is orthography? "If he has gone-oh if he has /-and the thought is Mad- ness-or at least unpleasant-let us be thankful that his Great Work is finished. It Lives I And Posterity will not (I am con- fident) willingly allow it to Decease 1 "From a surcharged heart. "Yours,   P. PEPPER   PODD." WEELBARER. INTO 2 PARTS: PART THE ITH. DEDEOAcT TO P. PEPPER PODD BI THE AUTEBR MR. . N. N. P"vPN. aq. NOT that ime in eny thing ov a hurry, o muse, (its cumfertin to no youv got a muse,) Wood i adress Thee on the subjeck ov A large Pome. For varis is the oportoonitys ive giv Thee to wock up to the Captins ofis &amp; their to settel or maik your frend a nofer;   Mr. Pepper's Eighth Upheaving.        173 But you hev slited al mi Overtoors. o is my preshus muse a-goin to leev &amp; finelly be no moar herd ov enywers? Ken nothin worm her (at present) coald shoalder? Return &amp; smile on PEPPER, o his muse l Remember hees desolved al pardnership With evry thing, &amp; is a onhapy Berd as thincs ov flyin oanly a few days longer. cum &amp; help smooth his delekit wite ploomig, '&amp; teech his poor vois oanly 1 moar song: So then he'll go in pese, &amp; you may find consoalshun in funerls &amp; sech. (Now hevin be praisd-mi muse she is a-comin.) Go 4th &amp; se the Yelow Berd so hapy I G(o witnes Blu-G(ay, a-spoartin in the son I A. se the Ant a-pilin up -the dert sereen &amp; smilin, likewais industris. Behoald the Elefant, a-floppin ov his eers, Mindles ov Driver wot pecs onto his hed. Sech wos ABNER. WOS he -moar? he wos. His Faither followd chopin, &amp; his Grand Muther wos religis. His oan muther onfortinetly dide from the effecks ov Sassig. as she wos pius "wen she thus did di, she tooc her oanly son &amp; frely sed:  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7289-00000088"/> 174 Mr. Pepper's Eighth Upheaving. ABNER, your muther is egspected up, &amp; reely cant stay &amp; talk of her things. ABNER, mi preshus-youm a oanly son, &amp; ov coars your bruthers aint noomeris. Wot i say you ken at last depend on. mi prinsipel last werds is, Never Cu.  Your Faither, ABNER, never did but I's, &amp; he wos sic fur uperds ov 2 wekes." so ABNER cuicly swoar he woodent cus, &amp; then she looct at him &amp; the oald man: a-regrettin as the Sassig wos so harty: &amp; a-sayin Good Bi, in a febel vois, Wos a-travelin Hoamerds in about 1 minnit. "ABNER, shes gon " the oald man then remarct= Bi way ov comfortin his wepin son: "so she is, Faither," the yung man replied; "she wos, a good un, ABNER," then he sed; "so she wos, Faither," the son sed agin: &amp; then the oald man fel l's moar to chopin. ABER gest then hed tooc a gob ov weelin Dert frum a seller as a man wos digin. Being wel paid, &amp; very stout hisself, He dident loos no time in bein onhappy. He felt gest like sum hefty Berd a-flyin, or wel-grode Ant a-bizzyin ov itself; Hede sing &amp; wissel al the liv long day,   Mr. Pepper's Eighth Upheaving.        175 &amp; oanly stop fur vittels &amp; terbacker, or at a Pig to gerc a stun so playful o Hapines I wot maid Thee up &amp; leve? o Fait I wy wos you so fixt that you coodent Help a 1's deservin yung man cald ABNER? Alas I sech is Hewman Nater, i feer. Wen maid to go rite, wi shood it be pervers? As wi shood ABNER hev spile-t the pirrymid ov Blis bi a-settin ov it onto the cmal end? But so he did, in an onfortinet moment,- As in the next Part we shel presently'sho. PART THE 2TiH o MUSE, pervide a hankercher &amp; weep I also, peraps it wil be rite to refews vittels &amp; drinc as long as you ken stan it. Weer a-comin to the darc side ov the picter, Wair WO is roat in blac al round the fraim. Be cairful, muse, in a-roalin up the kertin, as it is maid ov Craip, &amp; is cuite esy toar. o hev you seen the fond maternel Hen, With al ov her egs cmashed bi a roothles Fo? Hev you discuverd Egel, a-cumin down on wings ov Nite, becos hers wos shot of bi a shot-gun? &amp;* ie astonished Dog Looc round with indignamhun at his tale  &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7289-00000089"/> 176 Mr. Pepper's Eighth Upheaving. severd bi crule Boy be4 his i's? Wot Disapointment fur the helples Dog  Wot straing Dissatisfacshun fur the Egell Wot Wunder fur the long secloodid Hen I Al these hev felt the inflooens ov a chaing. (e-speshelly the onfortinet ca9 Dog.) Hen wos I's hapy-Egel wos-Dog wos Wair air thay now? at present Chaingd &amp; gon I ABNER WOS a-weelin. as a Berd wos ABNER; (Feelin, not weelin-as a Berd doant weel;) oft a-playin ov his oald gaim with the Pigs, &amp; a-wisselin cairles, wen he dident sing, or a-thinkin ov Buty as wos fur away. But al to 1's the hefty 'barer dropt, fur ABNER felt a tiresum fit cum on. Wos ABNER huffy?  ime afeerd he wos, Becos the fit wos sudent, onbenoanst-like. He set doun onto the 'barer with a gerk, &amp; in a ninstan keclled onto a nail &amp;   toar his pans a gash wich say 3 inches. Wos thay a  Nevil Spirit a-hangin round About that time, with nothin fur to do? Wos this the Evil Our?  Wos Perteckshun Gon frum mortels fur about I minit? no matter, now, wot wos gon : ABNER CUSSED I   Mr. Pepper's Eighth    Upheaving.    1" there wos comoshun amungst things direcly: the Hevins shoad simtoms ov a-turnin blac: the winds wos evidently a-prepairing fur to houl: erth giv a oder like rotten pertaters; &amp; wot wos wunderful-WEELBARER GROAND I Evry thing seemd to be a-waitin fur sumthing. About that time, it seems, sumthing cum: WEELBARER SPOAK I (Bi the way, ABNER Wos a-felin dredful, as you mite supoas, &amp; altho he wonted to git up, he coodent.) "ABNER 1" sed the stern Weelbarer, "ABNER I Youm aweer as youv ben a-Cussin, ABNER: You swoar to your oald mother how you woodent, &amp; now you'll see L, ABNER, perty cuic." so then it riz &amp; pitched him of ov the trac: &amp; the Hevins, as hed ben kindly a-waitin, Dide blac imejitly, &amp; the winds roard cuite savig fur sech short notis. Raither displeesd With the aspec things wos a-wairin jes then, He keched his breth, &amp; put fur sumers els. But Egsersize ov runnin spiles the cistim, onles you feel like a-goin. So, as these onpleasant sercumstansis follered ABNER, He dident engoy the goak. He felt insultid; His felings hed ben teched with a rood hand: Besides, it hert wair he struc frum the 'barer, 8*  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7289-00000090"/> 178   Mr. Pepper's Eighth Upheaving. &amp; he wosent wel hisself. He hed setteld into a nesy trot fur severil mild, a-beginnin fur to hoap fur plesenter wether; Wen SCUEKE I SCUEKE I SCUEKE! he hears a sound behind Like a immens WEELBxRER a-comin awful I o ARBER, fli I &amp; to your speed ad v ings I (frum MLTON.) No need to tel him, fur the cus did fli. He caim soon to a River, (bangs wos hi,) &amp; a-thinkin it mite be Gordon, wos afeerd. a littel sercumstans confermed his suspishins. He heerd the SCUEKE, &amp; a awful rumblin sound, &amp; afoar bein cuite prepaired, wos buct in. this wos a noo cos for Dissatisfacshun; So he swum acres the rifs cuite angry-like, But got out so refresht that he maid 2:40 With a ese unparaleld, considerin the straingness ov the kedentry. (al this wile the furis wind kep up 1 awful shrik, a-displayin abillity ov no common order; Darcnes wos a-perspirin ov blac inc; &amp; the elemens generally wos onfrenly.) Soon anuther unplesent thing cum up. ABNER SMELT FIRE I &amp; a-lookin al around Saw into the frunt (gest rescuin ov hisself,) a HOAL! it smoakd sum, &amp; hed a fire down in  He smelt Brimstun 1's in a vile! He heerd   Mr. Pepper's Eighth Upheaving,        179 Groaninl Tie heerd Cussinl Ite heerd Fites Il He wos a-thinin ov a-goin awa  y kind ov cairles, Wen a awful deep vois sed-Pica IN, ABNE   RI H  Ee heerd a rumblinl WEELBARR cairn up &amp; goind into the entretyl G o x , ABSER, It sed, astonisht at his hangin of: &amp; then, cuite axidentel, run agin him. He saw the mistaik w 08 a-goin to proov faitel, So he braist hisself, &amp; giv a shrik as left the furis Wind seclooded into Ekos; &amp; a-felin sertin as a nuther oath Woodent be ap fur to increas the expens, Be indulged hisself as he wos a-goin doum n b. let us hoap the last Cus wosent notist in the confuzion. MORL IS OBVIS. .....................................I  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7289-00000091"/> AN ADVENTURE IN THE DARK. (CALCULATED FOR THE MERIDIAN OF SEVERAL SMALL PLACES.) TUESDAY, August 18. IR. EDITOR:--There is not a quieter person in the village than I am: I rarely have an adven- ture, and do not often have the good fortune to be astonished into a new sensation. When I am thus favored,--when I really do have an adventure,--why, all my friends are pretty sure to hear of it, sooner or later. Last night- It is really a wonder I have so commanded myselfl Perhaps you'll not believe me, but actually I have not told a single person (nor any married ones); hav- ing determined to be strictly impartial, and tell every body at once.   An Adventure in the Dark.      181 Last night- I am afraid people will not credit so strange a re- cital: it is rare, nowadays, to find any one who has seen the   but stop! let me not anticipate. Last night- I am half a mind, now, to keep it to myself. Yes -no, people will call it an idle tale: yes, I will tell it. It may do some good; at any rate it will be a relief to me. -Last night I had occasion to visit the upper part of the town, and was going up the side-walk, in the direc- tion of a certain liberty-pole. It was quite dark, and the hour was late; so I was obliged to proceed with some caution. Notwithstanding every care, I ran against a post in front of the Doctor's office, and received such a shock as I don't care to experience again very soon. A little farther on, I damaged my- self by a full length contact with the fence, in my anxiety to avoid posts, and then concluded to avail myself of the guidance it afforded. At the corner by the pole, I had taken my bearings, and was about to strike out for the fence on the next corner, when' a shrill, though faint feminine voice called out, as though from a distance:  &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7289-00000092"/> 182   An Adventure in the Dark. "Hallo-o-o-o!" I judged, from the tone, that the possessor of the voice was not so much in immediate danger, as in some sort of predicament, in the extrication from which she required aid; but I had not the slightest idea what direction I should take. "Hallo 1"I shouted, in return. "Hallo-o-o-o 1" again came from the distance. ' All right, it's up the street," I muttered, starting on. I soon discovered I was mistaken. "Don't go-I am up he-e-e-re!" As true as I am writing here, Mr. Editor, it came from the top of the liberty-pole! "What the d-- 1 are you abo-o-o-ut?"I sang out, at the top of my lungs. (I am always a little profane when excited.) "Come up and I'll te-e-e-ell you t" replied the odd- ly-situated female. Rather provoked that she had not sense enough to come down, instead of inviting me up to break down with her--yet determined not to yell again, for obvi ous reasons-I commenced the ascent. I reached the " cross-trees " with some difficulty, but to my surprise found no one there.   An Adventure in the Dark.    183 "Hallo!"I barked, a little angrily "Oh! how you frightened me!" said the female- apparently about twenty feet higher up. "Don't say another word," she went on, "and you shall soon know why I am here." "How do you stick there?"I asked. "Oh I I can't tell," she said, " it astonishes me, too. But I must hurry and tell you why I came here. I've been here at least two hours. I was going by that empty house on the corner, when I thought I saw a light shining under the door. 'Something going on here,' I said to myself; 'this must be looked into.' So I mounted the steps, and had just got my eye well to the key-hole, when the door flew open, and two horrible-looking objects, in black, seized me and ran through to the cellar door. A sort of bluish flame was coming up the stairs, and with it a smell of sul- phur that almost choked me. Notwithstanding my shrieks and struggles, they hurried me down, and left me, half dead, on the ground or pavement of the cel- lar. When I had a little come to myself, I saw that the sulphurous flame came from a large, circular open- ing in the ground, by the side of which sat a being who I at once knew must be the d--1! O! I can't  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7289-00000093"/> 184   An Adventure in the Dark. describe him To use a common phrase--' he must be seen to be appreciated.' Black, diabolical, terrible, -he seemed to chain me where I stood, by the very magic of his awful eye! -' Ha! ha! old woman!' said he, 'have I caught you at last?-I don't know what to do with you, now I've got you. You'll set all my dominions by the ears, if I take you with me. Al- though you've done me an immense amount of good in this village, I can't make up my mind to think of you as you deserve. I positively can't keep from de- spising you.'" "Rather complimentary,  from  him/"  I re- marked. "Awful,---aifu 1!" she replied;-" but don't inter- rupt me.  'Old woman!' said he, 'you can't see me, by day-light; but many a Sunday morning have I sat on the steps of those temples, in which I am so abused, in order to observe the people as they come in. You should see me skip nimbly aside, at times, to avoid being trampled on; you should see me follow in some old fool who is soon to become my prev.- some sanctimonious hypocrite, grown grey in his whining habits of mock piety,--who has almost in- eluded himself in the list of converts to the belief in   An Adventure in the Dark.       185 his holiness.  At the church up there on the hill, I have been better pleased at one thing, than I have been in all my travels-pretty extensive, too, they have been. Not even in the larger cities, like New York, is spiritual snobbishness carried farther. They come in so late, sometimes, I can't contain myself, but skip about those ample steps for joy; I climb the lightning-rod, and tap softly on the bell, in mock- ery of their tardiness.--That's reverence, is it?- that's Christian regard for propriety, and the feel- ings of your fellow Christians?  Aha  were it not for Fashion, and especially for the respect which those pay her who can't even claim acquaintance with her, I think I should despair of quite a large portion of your fellow creatures. (For the real truth is-it is not the fashion, except in some out-of-the- way place like this, to be late at church.)-But- 1 forget myself. I shall try and like you, old wo- man. It does me good to think of all you're doing for me here.  The bickerings, jealousies, and general ill-feelings you create, incite, or circulate,-the mighty mountains you continually make of mole-hills--that kind of service saves me a world of trouble. There I  &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7289-00000094"/> 186   An Adventure in the Dark. I have bored you long enough. You will stand by me, won't you?"-What could I do but promise him? I would have done any thing to get away from that horrid place. He let me go. Before I reached the top of the stairs I looked behind, such was my curio- sity, and he had vanished; the ground was closed up, and all was smooth as before. Yet such was my fright and agitation, I rushed out, and, for safety, scarcely knowing what I did, climbed this pole, on which I have hung ever since." "Got through, have you?" said I. "Yes," she replied, '" and I'd thank you, now, to take me from this horrid pole." "Who are you?"I asked. "I would prefer not to tell you, till you have helped me down; for I'm afraid my name will prejudice you against me. I may say that I have long resided here-as I find many congenial spirits, and am heartily welcomed to half the homes in town." "I ought to know you," I remarked, "for your voice is familiar enough; but I really don't recog. nise you, and I am resolved not to assist you till   An Adventure in the Dark.     187 you make yourself known." I was thus severe, because, from all she had said, I was a little sus- picious of her. "Ohl well," she said, with forced resignation, '"if you oblige me, of course I must tell; for if you leave me here, I shall die--and I have many friends in this village who will weep for me. I belong, sir, to a nu- merous family, mostly daughters. My family name (it is one of great antiquity) is Gossip. I am some- times called Innuendo (a pretty name, I think), and sometimes, Sneer; but my proper title is Scandal. I-" Al You needn't go any further," said I; "and you won't, if I can help it. Good night, Miss, and plea- sant dreams." With that, I descended, unheeding the dismal howling of the hag (or the assurance that she had something interesting to communicate), and stum- bled along home-having run into five trees,two posts, and an old cow, besides filling my hands with slivers\ from the fence. Whether the "old woman" finally got down of herself, or was blown away in the night, I know not. She wasn't there this morning, and I discovered no  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7289-00000095"/> l88   An Adventure in the Dark. "mangled remains" at the foot of the pole. I'll bet you a year's subscription she is alive and well, and has made twenty calls since daylight. Your fatigued friend. BORED-TO-DEATH, Chief of the Own-no-doggies. SS Irsa   MR. PEPPER'S ASTONISHNG NINTH, "Our noble Prince is found! Let the woods with joy resound."--CINDERELLA. ROOM there for Mr. PODD 1 DEMOSTHENES FOUR CORNERS, May 16. g UR. CLARK, EDITOR.-SIR: Although the emotion of joy is yet agitating this mortal Frame, I can at least compose myself sufficiently to inform you that the immor- tal Poet still lives My despairing search after the Body was changed into a joyful discovery of the Soul, still in connexion with that body. Just as I was giving up the search in despair, I found him reclining upon the summit of a Shed, in the attitude in which he composed that most affecting of Poems, the ' Address to a Bird on the Fence.' His eyes were closed: Genus was sleeping. Having with some difficulty attained the elevation alluded to, I Joggled him. Over the next ten minutes, with your permission, I will drop a veil. * * *  *  *  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7289-00000096"/> 9go    Mr. Pepper's Astonishing Ninth. "Sir: He has suffered. He is now at my home, slowly re- covering from the exhaustion and Misery, which he assures me always follow a Great Effort. , He has even ventured upon another Poem, in which we discover strong traces of his master Hand. I am confident no other Poet-certainly no mere Philosopher-could so clearly explain his subject, and at the same time bathe it so effectually in the Eternal Waters of Genus. The Arcana of Nature are mere trifles to an Intellect like his. "I never shall forget the answer he once gave to the Proposi- tion of a shallow wise Acre. It was so philosophic and so Just. The intelligent Acre said he had no doubt that in digging to- wards the centre of the Earth, we get warmer as we go down. To which Genus (with a face like STEPHENSES) answered, like an Oracle: ' What makes water the coldest in deep wells? ' "But my feelings have carried me too far. I could write on this Theme (I think) a week-having, at stated times, a Meal and a few hours' sleep. "I send the Poem alluded to, warm from PEPPER'S Brain. "With consideration, Sir, Yours, "P. PEPPER PODD." Mr. CLARK received that Poem.      What did he say-what could he have said of it but this:- "We thought so! When we saw the moon in eclipse pale her ineffectual light in the still mirror of the Tappaan-Zee, we   Mr. Pepper's Astonishing Ninth.       19l said, 'in'erdly,' ISurely, surely PEPPER is looking at that pheno- mena ' We were right; for here is the proof of it. And what a perfect thing it is, in its wayl--what a Torso of a glorious statue of Genusl "- EKLIPS. "BEHOALD the moon, diminisht into nothin I At 1's hese chect, his brite career cut of. 1's he wos rejoicin that he wos abel i to afoard sech a good artikel ov lite, He bein smal &amp; not yet got his groath. But the praises as wos lavisht onto him Hed the efect fur to onsettel his mind. He thougt ov his rivels as wos gellus, &amp; wos afraid hede git hert; or wots wers to a sensitiv loominery-squencht. "His wers feers, alas I air sadly realizd. Altho he wood shine, yet we se he cant: in consekens ov a peculer arraingment A1 ov his eforts doant doo no good. Wi did Erth Step in so furis, &amp; elbo of ov the trac The sweet moon as hed delited thousans? Wi? did i say wi? i sed wi. Evidently becos he wos a-burnin too much ile. He wos a-exertin ov hisself in a onnateral maner. Cood he expec to shine so alas? Dident Erth no it? Dus Erth no eny thing?  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7289-00000097"/> 192   Mr. Pepper's Astonishing Ninth. Hes he administerd a chec onto the occaishun? Wi did the clowds cum up &amp; compleet the seen? Wi? Becos al nacher simpathizes. They regelates each uther. Wen 1 goas it too fast fur his helth, thay al resun with him,- 1st mild; &amp; ef that doant doo no good, then raither stronger, as we se. its supoasd that 2 or 3 sech corecshuns in a year is al as keeps him frum a-maikin a fool ov hisself. "But mi muse she is a-levin. Shese afeerd to trust her PEPPER sens the Grait Pome. i expec it wos raither hard on her, Gugin frum mi oan melancolly sitooashun, Wich is Bad. alas! like unfortoonat Moon, the Pote wos too cairles in the yuse ov his ile. His firewercs wos fine, but too egspensiv: So Nacher steps in, nocs Genus concaiv, &amp; he is presently a agerwaited Hewman Eklips cv the wers kind. sech is the misfortoons ov Genus." iL Qsa t,5y [.?* w  ^   PHARAOH: A TALE OF BRICKS. THERE unhappily exists a, widely-extended preju- dice against Pharaoh. He is charged with hav- ing hindered the children of Israel from leaving their I lodgings in Egypt on the first of May, thus forcing them, by construction, to stay another year. But how he can have incurred this charge, I cannot conceive, when it is well known that this good king would not lay a straw in their way. True, we are told, and believe, that he refused to let them go: but all hard feelings must melt away when it is known that he was here playing the part of the philanthropist, if the date of the transaction would hardly let him play the Christian. 9  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7289-00000098"/> 194         Pharaoh. There is a game with cards called Poker, easily to be learned, but wonderfully fascinating to those who engage in the practice of it. This enticing game was indulged in to a frightful excess by the younger and even the older Israelites of that day. It is well known that amongst the phraseology peculiar to that game, is found the word ' Go,' which, perverted from its integrity, means to stay, and stake more money. Now these youthful but sadly profligate Hebrews did nothing, in their leisure hours, but play at poker; and the suburbs of the city, in which they principally re- sided, would at those times ring with the technical chanting : "' I'll GO you three pieces better 1" "I'll Go you six pieces better 1" etc., etc., the sound of which discordant tumult would often reach the ears of the king in his royal palace. Filled with solicitude for the welfare of his beloved people, the good and gene- rous PHARAOH questioned with his prime minister in regard to the best means of suppressing the game, and preventing the ruin of his subjects, speaking as fol- lows:-"I don't want to say, Children of ISRAEL, d-n you, you must stop playing Poker! for that would perhaps hurt their feelings, and indeed might end in hurting mire, which you are well aware are   Pharaoh.        195 very tender. What are you forward enough to ad- vise?"Upon which the prime minister bowed three times to the ground, each time casting a little dirt on his head (which, having watched his opportunity, he took occasion to wipe carefully off on the skirt of the king's robe), and went on in, the following tiresome manner: "Your Royal Highness is aware that your Royal'Highness could put an end to those pernicious practices among a portion of your Royal Highness's subjects " "Stop there!" cried the king, with some irritation; "don't 'Royal Highness' me so much: it's annoy- ing!" "Very well, your Royal " "D-n you 1" shouted the now enraged king, 6 I'll have you drowned in my fish-pond if you say that word again 1" "As- your Majesty pleases," said the compliant minister  "As I was going on to say, when your Majesty cursed me---- "Nor 'Majesty' either," interrupted Pharaoh, get- ting a little unreasonable, which is so very odd in a king. "Well, Sir--you old fool "  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7289-00000099"/> 196        Pharaoh. "There, now-go on," said the pacified Monarch "I think," pursued the minister, "I think " "First I've heard of it," said Pharaoh. "It's so!" said the minister, being the first record ed use of that now common expression, of which he was undoubtedly the originator. "Or at least I was thinking," pursued the conscien- tious minister. "Oh!" was the laconic interjection of the king. "I was thinking you might give out that there was one word in the Egyptian language, to hear which always afflicts you with a species of moral insanity, and " "What the d-- 1 is that?" cried the profane but otherwise exemplary king. "Oh! it's something you'll hear enough of, if you live long enough!" which was literally true. "Well, go on," said the impatient potentate. "You therefore decree that the obnoxious word shall be no longer used-that word being 'GO.' Now, if you rob a game  " "Ketch me!" chuckled Pharaoh, using a popular phrase of the day. "I ain't like the common run of kings: I don't rob. I 'take' though." Ix   Pharaoh.         197 "So do I," added the minister. "I was going to say if you take from a game its technical phrases, you destroy it. Think of it, old boy I the abolition of one little word, of two letters, will save the twelve a tribes of ISRAEL from damnation!" "Eloquent, saucy, and correct," said the king. So the edict was issued: and unjust history records, without comment, that PHARAOH would not let the children of ISRAEL GO I True, those unfortunate children "didn't like it much," as some of them remarked at the time; it was not in human nature for them to like it. But, at the same moment, they could not justly attach much blame to PHARAOH. Their feelings are perhaps sig- nificantly expressed in' the following couplet, which, at jovial meetings of the grand-children of ISRAEL, was wont to be given as a toast, and drunk with groans, and other more antique demonstrations of disapproval: "LET the toast ne'er vary, O, 'Insanity' to PHARAOH!" in which amusing lines many affirm to discover only a playful allusion to the innocent ruse of the king.  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7289-00000100"/> 198'        Pharaoh. Many other things might be mentioned of our hero; as, for instance, his having given its name to the neighboring sea, from a bright expression of his little son, then just three years, ten months, and nine days old; who, being taken for the first time near the water, thought he detected a vermilionish shade in it, and in his laconic way cried out: "Red I See!" But PHARAOH was not one to be talked about like any common man. We are apt to insult the shades of great men by "letting on" all we know about them. This is wrong. One other little incident may be mentioned, which, as it wound up PHARAOH, may serve to wind up this sketch of him. PHARAOH, it is well known, was drowned one fine winter, while skating on the Red Sea. He was follow- ing MosES, who had " dared" him; but being a much "heftier man than what MOSES was," unfortunately "went under" at a thin place, at the same going over Jordan; which (what with his skates, etc.) we may imagine to have been rather " a hard road to travel" than otherwise, particularly as that river was not yet frozen over. It is related that MOSES went on, un- consciously, for a dozen miles or more, and then,   Pharaoh.        199 thinking it was " mighty still behind," turns around, and finding a reason for it, says: "Where's PHA- RAOH?"We may fancy the inimitable sly humor which MOSES threw into this remark, as he undoubt- edly fancied he had " distanced him," and knew well enough where he was. He had " rather left him." PHARAOH was a good man. Let him requiescat if he wants to, selecting for the locality, C, or any other convenient Red letter of the alphabet.  &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7289-00000101"/> DECEMBER IN THE COUNTRY. r           -------- THESE falling flakes, which fill the street- With mud, Cover your cow, which slowly chews Its cud, With such a coat!-so white, and neat l-- In spite of this defence against the dews She must feel cold. She's old: You see it in the horn. That monstrous pig- So big And dirty it can well adorn "No place like home "- Trots forward in its known, invisible trail,. (How that deep grunt its fat sides shook I) And sways its tail In agony.   December in the Country.        201 You see How shivering bipeds look, And walk, And talk: And how they swear I Good gracious I Bob-see there I Mud two feet deep I What's in it? Let's take a peep: I've seen it I What news? Two overshoes I I9  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7289-00000102"/> MR. PEPPER'S THRILLING LETTER FROM NEW YORK. THE thinness of the poet having become excessive, and, to the affectionate PODD, alarming, that gentleman  reasoned with himself, and finally and munificently concluded to send him  to New  York, for a change of air; hoping that he would return with health, both of body and mind. Soon after his arrival, he wrote to his benefactor the following letter, giving an account of his varied adventures: "ST. NICKOLAS HOUs, New York, Oct., 1855. "FREN PODD: "DEER FELLER: Hevin got setteld into mi new corters, i imejitly remember mi oald reverens &amp; Aw fur your karicter, wich is simular to WASHNGTONS oanly you haint bed no chans to fite &amp; develup your talens. Youm a partickelerly mute   Mr. Pepper's Thrilling    Letter.    203 HAM DONE &amp; a raither ingloris MLTON (wich tribyout. plees acsept in remembrens ov me.) "altho we New Yorkers doant thine nothin ov it, praps a breef discripshun ov this sity wood be interestin &amp; instrucktiv 2 a kedentry feller like you. New York is comprised onto a iland wich is sevral mild long &amp; raither less brod. the prinsipel road is Brodway, besides wich their is as much as 19 or 20 uthers, be the saim moar or less. in varis plaisis is a liburty Poal, oald with aig. this is al i ken thine ov now. so ile giv you discripshun ov mi adventers sens i left your hospital Manshun. "It wos al rite onto the boat. dident you notis how the Captins i's sparkeld wen you introdoost me? So thay did al the way down. he wos a-complainin ov soar i's wen we got heer. he giv me the 1st chop ov everything, &amp; i dident hev to pay a red sent. I heerd a lady wisper 'hoos that distingish furrin lookin individooal, a lenin so graisfully onto his elbo?' wen she found out, she coodent help fallin into luv imejitly. but as i discuverd her faither wos oanly a aldurman, i very properly looct coald onto her. (besides, how cood i furgit HANAE GANE ) wen i wos a-comin of ov the boat, the yung lady stood thayr with her frens, &amp; sed, 'heer cums the red- haird foo-foo aginl' wich wos verry kind ov her, as ime alus angshus to be noan. frum the ' red hair,' &amp; not noin wot 'foo- foo ' ment, I thougt at 1st she wos mad a littel; but a yung man wich i saw afterwerds sed ' foo-foo' ment german Barren,' &amp; that the germans (espeshelly the Barrens) wairs red hair out ov  &#xD;<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC7289-00000103"/> 204    Mr. Pepper's Thrilling Letter. cliois. how strong is womans afeckshun! she doant chaing fut nothin. "How they pull a feller onto the docks wen i got of, sum littel Bois cumnd a-runnin up, &amp; sed al to l's-'cary your carpit-bag, mister 1'--techt bi sech kindnes, i wos a-givin ov it to 1 ov em wen a nuther 1 sed-' ile cary it fur 5 sents;' 1 moar yeld, with tears into his i's, ' 4 sents,' &amp; so thay kep a-goin down, a-hunchin ov ech uther, til 1 sed, 'ile cary it fur nothin,' &amp; as i coodent wait fur em to git to payin me fur the chans, i let the last boy hev it, fur wich privelig he seemd moar thankful than i wos to git it dun so cheep. as i wos a-goin to Nickerbocker Offis 1st, i askt a man with a wip wair Brodway wos, &amp; he sed '4 mild further on,' &amp; askt me ef ' ide hev a carrig-oanly a doler.' noin i coodent afoard it, i toald him i wos fond ov wockin, wich he sed it wos cuite lucky i wos. after goin 3 or 4 blocs i cumd to a nice wide road &amp; a L ov a nois. i askt a man wot it wos cald, wich looct at me a spel as ef struc with Astonishmeant, &amp; sed--' wair did you cum frum, greny? that's Brodway '-&amp; then i noo the man with the wip hed ben a-lyin. i wos a-goin bac to lie him, but thougt i woodent. "wen ide got up a littel ways i met a wel drest yung man wich looct egzackly as i looc into a glass: it wos gest as ef a man wocks out &amp; sees hisself a-comin along. i cood se Genus into his i. he notist i wos a-lookin at him, so he cumd up &amp; sed he thougt he noo me. wen i toald him hoo i wos he went into rapchers, &amp; sed he admird me so mu hll he didnt no as hede be abel to expres hisself. he oferd to show me sum sites,   Mr. Pepper's Thrilling Letter.       205 so we went along together. we soon cum to a plais dug out in the side wock wair thay wos a-buildin a cuppel ov uvens-llke. lie sed wede hev wor soon, &amp; them wos to put Bums in, to blo up the British &amp; French. he sed evry hous bed 1 or 2, reddy to tech of. wot a awful plais fur a horstil Army I i thine i heer somethin go of now-&amp; se about 1000 evacuatin ov the sity. i thine i se a hul Army fall bac i thine i heer em cus &amp; then i thine i doant. "Perty soon we cum to a corner, wen mi fren remarct that a man wonted to se him, a few doars down this street, &amp; toald me to wait fur him. i ges likely he found his fren, fur i waitid so long that foalks toald me to moov on, or els git mi feet out ov the way; boath ov wich i finelly did. wen i got to 348 i found i hed to cros the road, &amp; bi giminyl how the drivers swoar at me! - i cum purty neer gittin run over, too, also ov a- fallin down &amp; a-gittin mi pans derty. wen the Boy giv me mi carpit-bag, wot wos mi serpris to hev him put out his hand &amp; say --cum, mister, hand over that shad-scail! 'Sech iyln P' i wos so astonisht i stood putrifide to the spot. i raisd mi bag to strike at him, wen he run of, observin--lperaps i dident se no boddy a- handlin ov your oald silver watch nor nothin /'-wich alasl PODD, wosent no goak. it wos gone I i went up stairs with a hevy 'Hart, &amp; a teer into mi i. "wen MR. HEWSTON discuverd hoo wos his visiter, he manifest deep emoshun; &amp; a-smoothin ov his gray &amp; wite Baird, sed- 'this is the prowdest moment ov mi life!' wich i thougt cuite likly. a yung man cald SLY fel onto his nee, &amp; gaisd at me with  &#xD;<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC7289-00000104"/> 206    Mr. Pepper's Thrilling Letter. speechles addorashun. 'SLY,' sed MR. HEWSTON, 'We woant were no moar to-day. MR. PEPPER, air you fond ov Appel?' wen i replide i wos, he toald MR. SLY to gO out &amp; git me 1: wich roas &amp; went. i found how rite wos his naim, wen he caim bac. the Appel hed a peese bit out. wen i remarct onto the goodnes ov proffidens in a-maikin ov the Appel, he sed Appel wos good. then he sed the Publishers Assosiashun, hevin herd i wos a-comin, wantid me to oner the cristel Palis with mi presens at a Feast ov Authers, amungst wich i stood so elevatid. ' thayr,' sed he, 'you'll git lots ov the produckshuns ov the Orcherd, ef you doant git nothin els ;' wich las part he spoak into a melon- colly toan, as i afterwerds discuverd he hed resun for. he now giv me a wite card, about 2 foot wide, with ' G. P. P.' roat onto it in ritin, wich evidenly ment-Giv Pepper Plais. eny ways i no it hed that effect. ' wile i wos a-settin thayr, hoo shood cum in but MR. CLARK. he noo me bi instinc, imejitly, &amp; in a Profetic vois sed-- i noo as how Graitnes wos heer I &amp; now how doo you find yourself, o yooth?'-to wich i replide into mi usooal graisful stile; after wich we went down &amp; hed Clamb onto the I shel. He sed i must go hoam with him, up the river, &amp; inhail the patriotic air OV WASHNGTONS Hed is, &amp; JOHN ANDERSON'S gallus. no sooner sed than dun. at 3 p. m., wich wos a few ours after, we startid; &amp; into a incredibel short spais ov time we glided oar the lower part ov the Hudson, &amp; found ourselves ^ way up a hill in Pier- mont, a-standin be4 a Butiful cottig, &amp; a-engoyin a splendid vew ov the river, conseeld bi foz. i aint got time, &amp; it woodent be   Mr. Pepper's Thrilling Letter.      207 fair te tell al about wot i saw, &amp; did, &amp; herd, &amp; thougt, &amp;c., but ile oanly remarc, that thay wos so kind it seemd as ef i wos bac to mi deer fren PODD'S agin 1 thing as hapend next day efec- tid me to teers. wile we wos to dinner, in cum MB. N-- (wich is a fine man) with 3 red peppers, maid into a bokay, wich he sed his wife sent fur a triboot to Genus. M R. CLARK got up &amp; maid a Butiful speech, a-presentin ov em to me, &amp; sot down l's moar to his Lam. i tooc the triboot with emoshun, &amp; wen i roas to respon, ii teers run so) i coodent. i never wos so afectid into, mi: life--&amp; i hoap i never shel be agin, at leest not into the saim way. mi apetite was compleetly spile't.  i thine i must rite about seein the Relicts ov the Revoloo- shun sum futer time: but i cant help spekin ov MR. FOLGER, the gentelmanly oaner &amp; proprieter ov the '76th Hous.' ef his i shood pirseeve this, may it lite onto it with plesoor &amp; a smil: his wifes i also. "Ii am a-stoppin now at St. NICKOLAS obpS, becos it sounds so much like NICKERBOCKER. How different frum mi littel Hous a- fruntin onto the LaikI' altho i git the werth ov mi munny, i shant hev no munny to git the werth ov, ef i stay bheer much longer: i shel hev to looc fur a hoam kep bi sum Benevolen femail, wot gives-you cheep vittels. "i went up to cristle Pcals amungst the uther authers, &amp; hed a golly time. severil ov em sed how thay coodent thinc ov ritin eny moar boocs, now ,'.e commenst. MB. BRIANT (a pote) with a wite Baird, sed mi stile wos a long shot ahed ov hissen. he confest mi ' Crek Slaiv' cuite noct the spots of ov his Tanny-  &#xD;<pb n="208-209" xml:id="VAC7289-00000105"/> 2o0    Mr. Pepper's Thrilling Letter. topsy.' he sed, oald as he wos he ment to beet me yet: but he ca-a-a-nt, you se; no youst a-tryin, no dout he'll conclood to stic to his Poast, like a sensibel man, &amp; not tri to fli like Egul. "WASINGTO. IRVING shed teers wen he se me. he sed 1 re- minded nim ov somnolent Jo, in Picwuwic. (wots that, i wunder?) not to sho mi ignorens, i sed-'so a grait menny hev toald me;' wich seemd to pleese him. he sed he wisht he cood go out &amp; drinc with me, but he supoasd hede hev to stay thayr, &amp; droun risself in the Aquis Elemen. i foun Appel thei.. Appel wos good. 1 long-windid feller, after hevin a pair ov tin Lungs maid (as i am creditably informd)--but i must stop. ile tel you moar ill mi next. "Yours wile the Vitel Spare continoos to shine, "it N. PPER. "To P. PEPPER PODD, ESQ., "Demosthenes: 4. C." ^^!1^   TO VENUS. TT having been remarked, in the presence of Miss , that "WEAN-US" was probably the evil star of infants, the justly indignant lady felt it incum- bent on her to issue a Vermillion Edict, commanding from the perpetrator of the unfeeling "joke," a Poem and retraction, on pain of perpetual banishment from her presence.  Hastily seizing a pencil, the unfortu- nate youth commenced the following lines, just as the clock was striking seven:- MOST lady-like and admirable VENUS I I call upon those worthy "'coves" of old-- That fifer, Pan, and his rare chum, Silen is, To aid me in a liquid measure, bold; And I'm resolved the Afflatus sha'n't get cold Till we have hatched a poem up, between us. And let " some angel guide my pencil;" (stamped-  &#xD;<pb n="210-211" xml:id="VAC7289-00000106"/> 210         To Venus. "BROOoKMAN and LANGvDON: No. 2 :") I'm cramped, But not for thoughts--only for skill to word 'em, They're all mixed up: his Majesty has stirred 'em. These lines I pen for you; and if I've blurred 'em. Please to remark: a reductio ad absurdum." I know it seems invidious to select, To other stars-who can "shine," for they prove it; But they forget, Ma'am, the profound respect I feel for you, and what there is to move it. For though you " cast reflections," as they say, And borrow splendor from old Father Sun, I'm sure the old man gladly lends a ray Or two, to such as you;-and, now I'm on The subject, I may say, in all affection, That you, without this much abused "reflection," Would not be noticed; even your connexion With some "First Families" were no protection. We're pleased with all your habits, Madame Venus, And only laugh at this vague Stellar charge. We " view" you, oft;-perhaps you may have seen us, With " naked eye" or telescope so large (How small we must look through the other end 1) Admiring your proportions by the hour. We think a deal of you, celestial friend, And learn to like your odd displays of power. ,$   To Venus.          2" When you "get up," you are our "Morning Star"' And when you don't, our "Evening Star" you are. But, pardon me: I'm too familiar quite; Allow me one verse more-and then, good night. Pale Goddess H-Empress of the starry host I Thy gaze serene, it hath a wondrous power: I dream at times thou hast a soul, almost, Thy beam doth so ensanctify the hour. And now, thou star, I could a paean raise, In measure grand, triumphant in its praise I Sweet monitor: so, when I'm lost in sleep, Thy cold, pure beams upon my senses creep: I deem them rays, tinctured with love and truth, Strayed from the altar of immortal youth; They flood my soul with rapturous dreams of bliss, And seal each vision with a shadowy kiss. I,-'.Q  &#xD;<pb n="212-213" xml:id="VAC7289-00000107"/> ANSWERS TO CORRESPONDENTS. BY A QUONDAM EDITOR. ---0--- THE   LONG  AND  SHORT  OF IT. /ILHELMNA     ERNESTINA.--Will the Editor of the Prime Mover tell me what is to be done with a silly fel- low, who lives opposite us, and does nothing, all day, but sit in his window and stare at me and my sisters? Is there no way of stopping his impertinence? A   way-and an effectual one--occurs to us at once. Let the sisters persuade their father to remove to some other quarter of the city, without letting the young man know  the new locality. It must be a   serious annoyance to our fair (she must be fair) correspondent, and her (perhaps) equally fair sisters, to be bored throughout the whole of every day, in the manner   Answers to Correspondents.    213 described. We presume the young man is the son of wealthy parents; that he has discovered the secret of living without food or exercise, and that news and knowledge come to him by intuition. We judge this from the described inveteracy of the youth's habits. We have not the right to suggest that Wilhelmina Ernestina and her sisters may look through some others of the (no doubt) numerous windows in their house, or else for a few days absent themselves from their accustomed -and (it seems) habitual seats-that the enamored youth may either die of grief, or get the impression that they have gone to the country, and so go to the country too. We say we have not the right to make the above suggestions, because we fancy it would be impertinent. The sisters have doubtless long ago discovered and rejected all our plans in turn, except, we think, the first-of which we take new oc- casion to remind them. Were we of a violent temper, "sudden and quick in quarrel," and much more to the same effect, we should perhaps have advised our correspondent to procure the assassination of the offender, or resort to some dreadful display of ven- geance more condign and signal. Doubtless the pull- ing-out of his nails with red hot pincers, would very  &#xD;<pb n="214-215" xml:id="VAC7289-00000108"/> 214    Answers to Correspondents. soon have occurred to us as extremely suitable-but perhaps not, on the whole, so significant as searing his eyeballs with a fiery instrument prepared for that purpose. But we are naturally phlegmatic, and are now very cool; consequently we do not think a re- sort to these extreme measures quite the thing, how- ever just or beautiful in idea. We cling to our first suggestion; with a last reference to which, we take our leave of the ladies-not forgetting our best bow and simper. FITZ JAMES FITZ JAMES.-I am an idler, for it is my disposi- tion-my nature, to be lazy. My excuse is, I can afford to be the drone I have described; and, furthermore, I have an " aim in life," notwithstanding. I am an observer of men (and women) and manners. I am a philosopher; I intend to be a novelist. I have been engaged making a study of three frights, who live op- posite, and have ogled me, by the half day, for many weeks. They appear to be eaten up with pride and vanity, and are so idle and worthless, not to say unornamental, they must certainly be a burthen, as they are a disgrace, to their parents. It has been their habit, till recently, to divide their attention between me and the passers-by in the street. Every young man, of more than passable appearance-especially if his apparent condition betokens wealth, is subjected to the battery of their glances, and sought to be enticed by their immodest charms. The young (?)   Answers to Correspondents.       215 ladies seem at last to despair of any important impression on me, and have come to affect a prudish indignation whenever they catch my admiring gaze. As my studies in that quarter are now complete, I turn them over to you, Mr. Editor, and antici- pate at your hands such a management of their case as shall happily result (to all appearance) in a salutary reform. If Fitz James's description of the three (idle) graces be correct, we do not accept his offer to " turn them over" to us. We should be in a sad case to know what to do with such   unproductive property. Our plan is this:-Of course everybody, including every idle young lady, reads the Prime Mover. Let the three graces see Fitz James's letter. It will make them very indignant-perhaps, for a while, furious; but it will do them good. They will then see themselves as others see them: a most desirable realization. But if F. J. F. J. has exaggerated his picture in any par- ticular, we warn him of perilous consequences. We will not interpose to save him-he must miserably perish. SORROWS OF AN ORGAN-GRINDER. DEAR MR. PRIME MOVER:-I am a poor Italian. The Italians, you are aware, are born in Italyr:--0 Italy-my country l- shall I never, &amp;c.  &#xD;<pb n="216-217" xml:id="VAC7289-00000109"/> 216    Answers to Correspondents. Forgive my emotion: I was once, sir, a Duke. I owned an island near Corsica, and was a man of considerable conse- quence. One day my island-with castle, horses, cattle, domes- tics, fowls, wife, park, children, summer-house, servants-in fine, everything I had in the world, sunk in the sea, [which is very- deep there;] and when I came back at night in my boat, [I had been gone since breakfast,] I missed my possessions very much. I had a horse that I perfectly idolized. I became exceedingly mad. "I will have some of them," I shouted, very loud; and letting down a rope with a hook at the end, I drew up, at the third haul, the very organ which I now turn for you and my other friends. "It has been my plaything in happier days; now it shall be my support and solace," I again spoke, [very loud,] to the surrounding sea. I rowed to the main-land quite cheerfully, and commenced my travels. I need not tell you I at last arrived at the Land of the Free, &amp;c., for happily my presence confirms my story, and makes all further proof superfluous. I find, much to my sorrow and grief, [also astonishment,] that the organ is not reverenced in this land as it is in Italy. Oh, Italy! when shall I see thee? &amp;c. I find, here, that to guide the delicate ventages of the Organ's sweet-toned stops, is not a dignified and respectable employment. Alas I where is the taste of America? in which land I am hailed with indecent familiarity by even policemen- whose savage tones, as they hoarsely shout " move on I " indicate contempt, and awaken the Italian blood in my Ducal veins. Are   Answers to Correspondents.       217 they respectful enough to a Duke, even granting that Duke is in exile, and has lost his possessions?- My talented countrymen Bellini, Rossini, Verdi and Doni- zetti, [most melodious of them all; you ought to hear me play his Finale to Lucia ] are not understood in thii country by the mass of the people. When I interpret their divine melodies, even my sweetest cadences, my most graceful turns, are all unheeded, unappreciated. A vulgar copper or two is all I get for Rossinil a curse may follow Bellini I a contemptuous "get out " is almost certain to insult the name of Donizetti. Why is this? ANGELO PAESIELLO GORGONI. Sure enough--why is it? GORGONI has ground out a pitiable case. We are afraid the mischief lies deep (probably in the pedal-base) among the organic elements of society. Mankind have many wretched quips and cranks to answer for, and among them are prominent those which are turned at the expense of the organ-grinder. Some organs, we confess it, are intolerable; they are out of tune, and out of place, always. Their tone is squeaky, and their average harmony very inharmo- nious. But (how providential!) there are degrees in organic excellence, or perhaps we should say demerit; and there are -some we tolerate-nay, admire. To 10  &#xD;<pb n="218-219" xml:id="VAC7289-00000110"/> 218    Answers to Correspondents. this latter class we gladly believe Gorgoni's organ belongs. We think no one can reasonably include, in one sweeping denunciation, the whole class of these instruments, since Thalberg has seen fit to play on a French musical contrivance that cannot compare, in tone, with some street organs we have heard, and thus dignified an occupation which before, as Angelo Paesiello intimates, has not been in much repute among us. There may be a " brighter day dawning " for our Ducal correspondent and his fellows-for the common run of whom we sincerely wish better organs, more willing and liberal listeners, and the completest ex- emption from the sneers, taunts, kicks and general injurious and prejudicial treatment of the world. Selah. A&amp;.. \^   Mr. PEPPER'S AMAZING ELEVENTH. o---- PERHAPS it may be doubted by some over-saga- cious critics, whether Mr. Pepper--K. N. Pep- per, Esq.-is really the author of the subjoined great work.  I see no other way but to let these people go on doubting. If the internal evidence of its authenti- city is not strong enough  to satisfy them, I firmly believe that even a sight of the poet himself-swear- ing by a large-sized terrapin-would fail to convince them. Perhaps, infact, there is no real foundation for this fancy. I sincerely hope it is but a fancy. TIRKEL:   A POME. DEDEOAIT TO MR. HBULTON INTO 3 PARTS. PART THE 1TH. DISTINGUISHT MUSE I your humbel fren stil livsI Throo 1 yeres streem he hes sadly Navvigaited  &#xD;<pb n="220-221" xml:id="VAC7289-00000111"/> 220 Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh. &amp; not ben swalerd by the bilos. Muse! He hes ben coald-his clothe ben also wet, His helth verry poor. He hes hed inflooenzy &amp; Alas! soar throat. Biles hes contin- ued fur to maik pereodikel aperens, &amp; his hart hes ben wel ni broak compleetly. Muse! your humbel fren wil not complain: The glory ov his acheevments pays him wel Fur evrything inflicted onto him. The imortel pome wich gest 1 yeer ago You helpt him fur to rite, wil ever liv, &amp; magnify his naim like telescoaps Wich maiks a grait Werld ov a litle star. o Muse I no fire, no wotter, pain in bowls, or even Hanah's Faither cant him stop; Fur Potry is the spirrits as preserves His Soal frum a-spilin: taik Potry away, &amp; onfortinet PEPPER must dri up &amp; Vannish. Ken you, o Muse, then hev the cruelty to hang of like you did be4, &amp; peraps Not cum at al? likely you may thine, Becos i dident di wen i sed i wood, ime never a-goin to-wich is a mistaik. i feel this time, o Muse, as ef i coodent Deseev you ef i tride. besids, the goak (Ef youm onfelin enuf to cal it sech) is raither stail; &amp; wel you no i doant   Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh.        221 Doo nothin twicet alike: beleve me, Muse, this time i di without reserv-to l's. i hev prepaired a loc to send to HANAH, tooc frum the moast conspicyous ov my hair- Shoin how i doant cair now fur loocs, &amp; never did much-but now no moar--alas I o Muse-as wos so offish about the Weelbarer- Good Muse-without wich evry poete hes got A bad coald &amp; cant sing: i taik my oath ile never cum to you fur help agin. Wot doo you doo fur egsersize wen you Aint a-puttin up ov potes fur to rite? it seems you otto be thankful fur a opper- toonity fur to maik a yung man faimus. Now cum &amp; help me, Muse, doant be a afeerd- PEPPER must rite the pome-he feels his *Our Hes cum, &amp; wood be glad ov your assistens: o thinc a minit ov the onborn Milions Mi gentle Muse, as 'll be ableeged to you I At last youv roas abuv your preguludis- i feel your fire a wormin up mi blud- i kech your breth so sweet &amp; bamy too: Mi preshus Muse 1 beleev me yourn til deth I "Ambishun I powerful soars ov Goody Nil l' So sung the- Copper pote with silver toung- (onhappy she, with sech a misabel faither 1)  &#xD;<pb n="222-223" xml:id="VAC7289-00000112"/> 222 Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh. How ken you be a-settin pepel up to dooin things wich soon thay find thay cant I its perfeckly yousles to deni the charg- &amp; ime hapy to se you aint a-goin to. Fur shaim I you otto be in beter biznes. You rooind NAPOLIN-a cmart man, Also CESER, ELICEK SANDERS, Mr. CRUMMEL, &amp; 100 uthers into the saim serkel- A1 likly men til you saild in &amp; spilet em. it wo, a onwarrantabel Libberty, &amp; cus you fur it &amp; wen you leev the Hewman Speshy a minit, its oanly fur to insite a Resareckshun into the peesful brest ov sum onfortinet Animel. i now alood to TIRKEL: ded &amp; gon- Wich his story i shel now perseed fur to sing. FUR away, bi shoars ov the wild Oshun, Sitooaited about 20 rods frum the wotter, Lay a peesful pond-not larg, not deep, But a fair sise fur a moderat Tirkel. On it wos varis logs, good for to set on Wen the sun shines, &amp; dive of wen Man Cums with stun or dubbel-barild shot gun. Nise tender frogs wos plenty &amp; not shi: Evrything wos faverbel: &amp; heer livd Hapy &amp; contentid fur meny yeers--a TIRKEL. He wos the kind cald MUD, becos he never   Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh.       223 Mindid the dirt, but tooc to it wen persood. in cam Contentment he wood set fur days onto a log, a-dreemin in the Son. Ketch him a worryin I wot shood he wory for? He hed al he cood ete &amp; drinc &amp; wair- (Wich last sounds good, but doant signifi much; Like haf the comon potry--but to perseed:) He wos satisfide he coodent doo no beter. the sentiment ov Wor he never felt, Consekently wos mild &amp; Lam-like: Paraps his oanly folt al that time wos His not hevin Energy enuf naterally, &amp; afterwerds his not noin wen he wos wel of. the Berds, a-flyin over, wood say to thayrselves: "Hapy, hapy Tirkel  Thayr he sets, esy, With no cair onto his mind, no trubbel Fur to liv; wilst we, poor fethered Songsters, Must fli &amp; look sharp wether we wonto or not." His mind rund moastly onto a femail Tirkel Wich livd into a nuther pond like hisn &amp; hedent no cruel faither fur to order her: Consekently thay wos together moast ov the time. o, hapy wos these 2 inosent Animels! Like Bobby-lines as wissel al the day- Sweet Tirkel-Flowers, a-bloin side by side I        I     .o  &#xD;<pb n="224-225" xml:id="VAC7289-00000113"/> 224, Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh. PART THE 2TH. (HARK I doo i heer a roar?-i heer a roar.) Go stand onto the shoar &amp; vew grait Oshun I Se the ships, skooners, &amp; morfodite Brigs Wich carry such imens cuantitys ov every thing in varis direckshuns oar his boosum I Se em leev the inteligent Shears ov germeny Also ov ireland, Liverpool, Frans, afriky, A-caryin ov pepel, iern, wimmen, Umbrels, &amp; salers, with uther things too tegus Fur to menshun: se clowds ov nite obscure sweet Moon, (Wich i 1's adrest a pome to-&amp; sed everything:) Behoald Darcnes kech evry 1 bi sirpris, &amp; Ship pichin verry much: waivs roalin bad: in plais wair its 60 or 80 feet deep: Alas I sum a-cryin: captin raither afeerd: Waivs (as i sed be4) a-roalin awful I IF*SE-TIRKEL is cam. " he wocks the botom Like a thing ov life." (frum BYRON.) wot cairs this awful Savig ov the briny Sees Fur eny sech smal maters? cuite nothin I Alus cam, he sleeps--dreems-etes minnys- Roams in feroshus mewsings throo the wotters. Wen he gits disgustid with 1 kind ov food, (Wich Se-Tirkels air raither apt fur to doo,) He goas &amp; dyits onto sumthin els   Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh.        225 Cuickly-becos Helth speeks &amp; ses: "' TIRKEL! Taik mi advis-be cairful, or youm gonI " Wich consekently results into Eels &amp; sech. Wen his feerful i gits set onto a Clamb, His inerds is Regoised with it to l's; Oister likewais. nothin escaips his vizzhun: Wich pirsipitaits the berth ov the yung Wail, the muther bein so confuged bi its glans- &amp; maiks the faither trembil &amp; bring tribyout ov ile. Wots mity Swoard-fish into his hans-wots Se-snaik, Conkerer ov Alegaiter? Wacks I Wot ef this mity objeck ses: " ile go ashoar I " He dus so direckly, a-dispisin ov paspoarts. Wen he apeers abuv the Aquis Elemen, Wot dus he say? Thees werds with Dignity: "Fairwel, oshun! fur a few minits, Adoo! ef i choos fur to taik fresh air, Hoos biznes is it? Let eny ov these cussid land Animels Sho thayr fais: How i pitty em ef thay doo l ile sho em how the magisty ov Se-Tirkels Hes got to be observed onto al ocazisns t i woodent yous no pirsonel egzershuns: o no I ide depend onto mi i entirely;-ide Wither em I --- i wish fur to hev these Egs preservd  thay shel be I &amp; be the Mejum fur fewter Tirkels!" So sayin (&amp; wot cood he ad to sech remarcs?) He graisfly retirs like the meek-ide fon (frum MOOR), 10*  &#xD;<pb n="226-227" xml:id="VAC7289-00000114"/> 226 Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh. &amp; leevs 2 or 3 mild ov the onhapy shoar A-moarnin fur his los. His Magestic tail Waivs a Eligant fairwel to everything, &amp; he is seen a-goin doun like the settin Son, With splender &amp; enthugyastic Aplos. PART THE 3. AMBISHUN I remembring wot i sed to you into the 1st part, it wont be nessary to Ashoor you ov mi contemp; but peraps Youm 2 bizzy a-rooinin ov pepel to go bac- in wich cais cus you, with immens disrespec. Cum forids &amp; looc at sum ov your were I Stand &amp; observ that silen pond thair- Dride up with Sorow almoast into nothin 1 Sise cum up frekently frum the cuiet mud: A vois moarns &amp; ses, "Alas I poor Tirkell taik fur away his meloncoly shel- Gether up the trankil inosent clos- &amp; berry em in silens, cuietly. o, he wos al mi fansy panitid him: (frum MOOR) &amp; he is gon-sweet, luvly Tirkel I " ----that vois hes stopt-hes dride up like the pond- or wot is left ov boath is verry smal sise. the wind wos a-blowin worm frum the South-est, (it wos the time ov the Yelow feiver),   Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh.        227 &amp; brot the smel ov orangis &amp; afrikens Frum the troppicks cuite fresh &amp; saloobris. the pond ov the Mud-Tirkel wos cam--also His mind, maid trankil bi a good nites rest. Hevin servayd his fechers into the wotter, He adrest ov hisself into these few werds: "TIRKEL I wil you taik a wock this fine mornin?" To wich he replide with plesyour: "Sertinly, &amp; much ableeged to you: " wich setteld ov the pint. o, se that graisful Animel a-wockin I Wot dus he dreem ov? HAPINES, ov coars: A-winkin to the tre-toads as he goas- Wich resolvs fur to serenaid him bi nite, Pirformans to comens a 8 o'clock persisely. Alas l--but Muse keep cuiet fur a few minits. Fait toald him fur to taik the bangs ov Oshun, (Wich he hed beefi thair, so thougt nothin straing- Bein a admirer ov grait boddys ov wotter:) So he went, wel pleesd with hisself &amp; everything, A-hummin, also a-tryin fur to wissel. then he wocked fur a wile, a-lookin down, Wile WO set a-straddel ov his shel, A-lookin verry Meloncoly, &amp; a-sheddin ov teers. o, ef sum 1 cood hev turnd him around , imejitly, wot diferens it wood hev maid I But noboddy dident-hens the Catastrofy. Sudently Mud-Tirkel cum fur to looc up:  &#xD;<pb n="228-229" xml:id="VAC7289-00000115"/> 228   Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh. Wot wos a-hed? zothin ony a SE-TIRKEL: As ef that wosent enuf--wich i raither thine it wos. he stood with Magisty-a-wunderin Wot that littel cus wos thair, a-cumin. His douts wos soon dispeld bi actool facs. "ten wos you born?" sed he, wen "Mud " cum up; "A-4 you wos I " sed Mud-Tirkel, with Dignity- Not imejitly pirsevin ov his sise; "Say that agin / " sed he. Mud-Tirkel sed it: &amp; then thay roas &amp; stood onto thayr hind legs. "Arize! my son--strech evry nerv " (frum WOTS) then sed Se-Tirkel, a-lookin doun &amp; a-holerin so the uther 1 cood heer; "o, i ken heer you, verry plain!" sed Mud: &amp; imejitly discuverd he wos smal. With al his egzershuns, wich wos verry grait, He felt he wos a inferor kind ov Tirkel; so, a-lettin ov hisself doun as esy as he cood, He cast his long &amp; lingerin tail behind (frum GRAY,) &amp; a-syin deeply, startid fur the pond. in goin bac he stopt fur 1 moar efert, Bein afeerd he hedent dun his best : He sweld so hard his shel begund fur to crac-- &amp; yet remaind a verry smal Tirkel. How hard it is fur to swel much wen youv got A shel!" he sed, in Considerbel ageny, A-givin away to the preshoor ov his felings.   Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh. 229 He felt bad. he wos sory he tooc the wock: "Cus him," sed he, "fur a imens Humbug!" (Aloodin to the uther TirkeD. after wich His spirrits forsooc him, &amp; he wos tooc sic. His femail fren did evrything she cood: "Cheer up!" sed she, 1000 times per day: But no youst-he dident taik no interest. she begund fur to git scairt--&amp; wel she mite- to se him a-sinkin in spirrits &amp; in mind. At last he refewsd fur to hoald no moar Conversashun, &amp; orderd -her of ov the premisis. Wich persedings tooc her with serpris: "Mi sweet Tirk-y is a-gittin huffy, aint he?" sed she, in a afectin vois, cuite sorowful- Wich maid worm wotter ov his isy hart, &amp; cuverd ov his shel with perspirashunl: "' Furgiv me, luv, &amp; stay-ile go misef l" sed he: &amp; then onfortinetly went. the settin sun went doun as he went up. He hed prepaird a few remarcs fur hir, Aloodin in onplesant terms to Ambishun- Wich Deth cut short in a onfelin maner. the tre-toads sung-but cuite a diferent song: (it wos a Disapointment to em al, Fur thay wosent verry fond ov miner mewsic:) it broak the femail Tirkel's hart to heer it: Her Spirrit now hangs round the silen pond  &#xD;<pb n="230-231" xml:id="VAC7289-00000116"/> 230 Mr. Pepper's Amazing Eleventh. &amp; speeks the werds aloodid to abuv. se Tirkel's egs wos al wosht away in a awful storm as hapend that saim nite; &amp; he wos finisht bewtfuly hisself, Bi a larg &amp; splendid stroak ov litenin Wich overtooc him wilst a-huntin fur em. Mi preshus Muse I your PEPPER taiks his leef. He wont hev no moar ocaishun fur your servis. His WERC is finisht-also his poor Life, Neerly. he thanes you verry much fur al Your kindnes, wich hes bein the maikin ov him. He hoaps the Warnin wich we se abuv Wont be cuite lost onto the Hewman Speshy- To wich, also to you &amp; mi deer HANAH, i leev mi faim, &amp; say at last: FAIBRWEL I   TO THE WORLD. AN ESSAY.* FOUNDED ON SENSE AND DR. CYRUS THOMSON. BY P. PEPPER PODD. rHE World is sometimes called the Earth. Sorne- - times we . ead of the Corners of the Earth: the earth being round has no Corners.    The earth is * As it would be a pity should any part of this valuable paper fail of its due effect, I will do what I can to elucidate it by annexing such portions of the note by which it was origi- nally introduced to the public, as have a particular bearing on -t    the subject. Mr. Podd "was recently much struck with a brief literary work entitled 'A  hort Treatise on the County of C nondaga, and written exclusively by Dr. Thomson, of that county, botanic physician, probably with his left hand tied behind. Mr.  &#xD;<pb n="232-233" xml:id="VAC7289-00000117"/> 232        To the World. round, as we see: eclipses showing it, through smoked glass, at the proper seasons.   The seasons are four, viz.: Spring, Summer, Autumn, Winter,- the last being the coldest. People have been frozen to death in this season. Seasoning is used in Victuals. Victuals cannot be eat on a full Stomach. [What say the Geologists: Red Sandstone is the oldest Rock in P. reveres the world's Benefactor and Friend, now that he has perused the pamphlet I have mentioned, and in the effusion I annex has, in his humble way (as he modestly says), emulated the classic model afforded in the Doctor's style. Mr. Podd desires me, however, to disclaim for him any hopes of having attained to real excellence, in this composition; and to say that all he really expects is some slight credit for having called the attention of men to one greater than he, and whom, he thinks, the world should not willingly let die-if herbs and praise can save him. "The Doctor's powerful essay is addressed to a reasonably large and somewhat comprehensive circle of acquaintance; thus:- "1st, To the Ladies. "2d, Mechanics, Farmers, Lakes, Rivers, Mills, Soil, Roots EHerbs, Crops, Rocks, Gravel, Land, Clay, Brick [being a thoroughly-baked one himself], Lime, Plaster, and Salt.' "Mr. Podd's is addressed simply ' To the World. "   To the World.        233 the world. It is called Red Sandstone because it is Red and Sandy. Here we see its advantage over Hair. Hair never being Red and Sandy at the s me time.] To return to the Stomach': This we could not do if the Stomach was full. FIRST FOR THE STOMACHS. Suppose a Man: Tliis we have a Right to do. Agree that he has a Stomach: Man being a Digestive Animfl. Reflect that this Stomach may be abused: Not by low Language, but by high Diet. Poor Stummy [which playful Term means Stomach], he gits Sick. Is not here a call for the healer? No more (at present) for the Stomachs. AGAIN FOR HERBS. The World has places where vegetable Substances grows: These are Plants.   Plants: Herbs. The transition is effected in a Minute, because there is no transition to make. Now, suppose an Herb. Agree that it has got into it a Juice i Which stands to Rea- son. Allow a Medicine in the Juice that hits Sto- machs. Grant there is one [or more] Physician with a name that he conceals: This Doctor not only being  &#xD;<pb n="234-235" xml:id="VAC7289-00000118"/> 234        To the World. ( Death on Fits,"-to use a playful expression-but Attentive to Stomachs.-Mark the effect!  He sees the Relation [a Blood Relation]. He takes and gits the Medicine out of the Juice. In a commanding method, he says to the Stomach: Gil Well!   The tone of his Voice gives tone to the Stomach, and he proposes to Heal all Diseases, at a very low Charge : Considering first the number of Stomachs.     Next the World growing such immense quantities of Herbs: Which are for the Healing of the Nations. No more for the Herbs and Stomachs. ODE TO DISEASE. It is important that you should be cured. First, because you can't be endured. Again, people have been known to die: Therefore fly! fly I fly I fly I fly! flyl Disease leave 1 No more deceive I Disease I ring your Nell I Sick people git well I git well I Git well I git well I git well I No more for Disease.   To the World.        235 A TOAST TO THE LADIES. You are the Motherwort, Man Root, Ladies' Slip- per, Angelica, Archangel, Fern, Queen of the Mea- dow, Ladies' Sorrel, Nanny Bush, Rose Willow, Squaw Weed, Lovage, and Sweet Flag of the World. No more for the Ladies. No more for the World. FINIS. .ca  &#xD;<pb n="236-237" xml:id="VAC7289-00000119"/> PEPPER REDIVIVUS. HAVE been told that, soon after the completic of the "Tirkel," a very happy accident prevents the sudden extinction of the fire in Mr. Peppe breast, and consequent vainless sighing of the wol for a few more poems " of the same sort." Havi actually resolved on self-destruction, as intimated his last work, he stood, tall in his desperation a stockings, on the brink of a fearful precipice-a te: ble illustration of the lengths to which poor hun nature may be driven. Swinging his arms w mournful energy, he began, with awful meaning, well-known couplet:- "One, to begin; two, to show; Three, to make ready; and"---   , -  Pepper Redivivus.        237 "Four, not to go!" shouted Mr. Podd, who that in. stant arrived, in time to complete the thrilling extract and perform (himself being the only instrument) a thrilling extraction: viz., his friend from the jaws of Death! (The best professional dentist in the world would have called for his forceps.) Seizing the des- perate Pepper, he made the glad announcement that old Walters was dead,  and Hannah Jane free! That the terrible revulsion of feeling produced in the poet's breast by this overwhelming news, should have caused him to swoon with joy-who can wonder? He did swoon. About the next thing he did, when he had revived, I should judge to have been some, thing that made the following note and poem possible, even in the natural cause of events:-* North-Demosthenes, Sept. 15,1857. "Mr. CLARK: i supoas you doant need to be informd that 'i stil liv,' &amp; am part ov the firm ov PEPPER &amp; WALTERS, delers in Domestic Hapines, &amp; sech: efyou doo, heerbi taik notis to that efec: ime a ni naber ov fren PODDS, wich livs at the 4 corners. "i raither giv out, in my last pome, that mi Muse bed ben set * Clark says, PEPPER's long silence wos a consequence of his "disgust at the temerity of his puny tribe of imitators." I think it belonged to love and happiness.  &#xD;<pb n="238-239" xml:id="VAC7289-00000120"/> 238       Pepper Redivivus. fre, &amp; coodent be cald on at site fur no moar inspirashun: wot may astonish you, i hev roat a littel pome without consultion ov her; bein a adres to my infant Son, now severil munths &amp; a number ov days oald, &amp; constantly gitin oalder. ef you thine it wil doo to print fur mi frens, &amp; isent entirely behind mi oald stile, plees      insert &amp; ablige yours, K. N. PEPPER. N. B.: i coodent git it al into 14 lines (wich maiks a sunnit), so ive roat the rest into proas. SUNNIT TO M LITTEL SON PETER. ' WELCUM, sweet cus, to your faither's family-serkel I sech littel Red republikens as you Wercs revolooshuns every wers, 't is troo. taik your oan faither, now, wich rote the "Tirkel," "Weelbarer," &amp; a few moar sech pomes: youv maid him hapy; but youv sp'ilt his genus. No moar imortel Wercs 1 but PETE, between us, i shel git up a practikel were, on Hoams, With cullerd cuts (youm 1) on evry sheet, ile cal it PBPPER'S last &amp; graitest Aim, (1 wich i raither thine is hard to beet.) DomestigHapiines shel be the naim: inspird bi HANAH GANE, your nateral muther, &amp; roat bi your faither, onles youv got sum uther parrent, wich aint likely. PETER I gro up &amp; maik a distinguisht man-is the prair ov your luving faither,     K. N. PEPPER.   A WARNING: OR THBE EFFEOT OF THE ABOLITION OF OAPITAL PUN-TSHmMNT. "Here are a few of the unpleasant'st words That ever blotted paper."-MERCHANT OF VENICE. "Punster: A quibbler, a low wit."--WALKER. I AM   melancholy when I think how  often time and ingenuity are wasted, in efforts to distort words from  their legitimate meanings and achieve a question- able popularity by the paltry trick of childish plays upon   words. All such wretched  stuff is foreign to the  dignity of established writers.  Entertaining these views, how was I pained and grieved, the other day, to receive  a note which convinced me there ex- ists a person who finds his happiness in the very pur- suit my   taste has condemned,! How   I  pity that  &#xD;<pb n="240-241" xml:id="VAC7289-00000121"/> 240       A Warning. young man!  How glad I am to know (as I have lately learned) the vice is not so rooted in his nature, by the practice of a long life, that it may not in time be extirpated! In that benevolent hope, I indulge the youth (for he is no more), and consent to the in- evitable disfigurement of this volume, both to please him, and afford the world the startling evidence of his present dreadful condition. It will be seen, that he rarely or never arrives at a good pun (if such an adjective may be coupled with so very common a noun), nor indeed does he seem to aim that way; but contents himself with wretchedly lack-lustre quibbles and forced conjunctions of similar sounds. Below is his wretched effusion; but I am not in haste to reach it.-I think he should never die: at least his shade (when he does) should "keep shady" when Dr. Johnson's approaches. (How true it is, that "evil ' communications' corrupt good manners"--and habits! I have caught myself at last indulging in the pitiful luxury of a pun! I am consoled by the reflection that it is a very good one, when compared with his, and by the resolution I herewith firmly make, never to attempt another). Indeed, from a horrible discovery I have this day made, I think he   A  Warning.         241 will never die. He called upon me, and in the course of our brief conversation confessed he was once guilty of an act still more criminal than the composing that piece.   Then I said, commiserating the poor wretch, "Sir, if you are the Wandering Jew, heaven help you." His brief and melancholy reply was: "* I am!" --and sighing deeply, he vanished with a sad grace. "TO TWO TOADS. "PBO-LOO. "O Great, full, grateful sound: a nightly payment-though there is no pay meant-by my little customers, those cuss'd hum- mers of the pond. I owe them, now; and soon my Muse shall '0' them. No strange topic to pick up, while those pond,erous tones, seemingly by tons, come forth, and forthwith shake all the air with their 'air'-which has no I variation, nor ' shadow of 'turn'-ing,' nor shakes,' nor t(h)rill'ing harmony. Come here, and hear  That awful strain is an awful strain on my tympa- num.  I should be pleased at the prospect of being eased: seized, by death: deceased-without being diseased. Open, O pen! in puny pun-y style, a stylish poem that I owe 'em; which, in its witchery of numbers, may make numbers- of others, m-others, br-others, and all t'others) cut short, by a short cut, these 'winding bouts' in which they are winding about; and as these two 'cometo,' let others come too, and "  &#xD;<pb n="242-243" xml:id="VAC7289-00000122"/> 242        A   Warning. all come to a stand--taking a standee, where they can 'stand easy' (say form into position), safe from interposition. "THE VIR* SAYS: "Songsters I your song stirs my bosom. (Such a stir has your singing effected 1) I'm affected-I soon shall ' boo-hoo' some, Not checked by your singing ' affected.' Your ' key' you keep pitched, when you pitch on it; The reason was ever a mystery: To hold it so, do you keep pitch on it?- A key were never amiss, tarry. "But, Toads!-to des-cribe this scribe's raptures, Must take (you must ' take l') two long chapters. Some salve?-(Oh, that salvo D-I've wrapped yours About a girl's hand (too long chapped, hers); With the small box I plastered-then pitied her, As the small-pox soon mastered, then pitted her: Thus kin being wholly unfitting her- The skin being hole-y, and fitting her.' "Sweetness could no further go," the author adds, in a quotation. There is no need of it. L"Sweetness" has gone quite far enough. Poor JEW I * The Hebrew knows Latin.   Mr. PEPPER RE-"PETE"S HMSELF. NTO one can reasonably expect a happy man to be very sentimental.  The poet is happy: hence the subjoined great Poem   is cheerful in its general tone, and dike the denouement of a noveD very ap- propriately .terminates the list of his remarkable achievements. Whether he will ever again court his Muse, is a question which time alone can determine :- PETE: AN AVERIG POME (FUR LENGTH:) DEDECAIT TO L. GALERD CLARK. BY MR. K. N. PEPPER, ESQ, SING PETE, o Muse!-he bein mi littel Boy- AMi oanly son-with short &amp; strait wite hair, &amp; (at present) the Mezels. wot he wil go into next, peraps you no, but i doant. His culler isent good, &amp; the saim remarc  &#xD;<pb n="244-245" xml:id="VAC7289-00000123"/> 244    Mr. Pepper Re-"Pete"s Himself. WNil apli to his apetite. The Doctor ses PETE hes got the moast MEezels he ever see onto a boy. he likewais ses, gudgin bi the stoc, He'll wip em, &amp; giv em haf to start with. (Wairin i agre with doc, &amp; go him sum better.) Now go it Muse-give us a good 1 on PETE. PAWS, strainger, &amp; talk a looc at a Cradel about 1 yeer ago. wot doo you se into it? (as the man sed wen he saw the feller a-lookin into Futoo- rity.) 1st observ that luvly Form, a-rockin ov it. thats HANAH GANE, a mild wooman, week as a fool, &amp; thinkin ov Baby, ile bet 50 sents. thairs a wooman, now, a man ken be proud ov. But taik a nuther looc into the littel Cradel! se suthin Red? thats the present PETE- say 1 day oald! hees a-yellin. taint much Fur a yel, but as good as moast yung yels. a-smilin kind ov plesent, HANAH settels him, &amp; presently gits him so he doant even grunt. Wot a uncomon luvly thing is a yoothful infant! Droolin doant spile it, for its pa &amp; ma I its a kind ov Bud-a ignorant Bud- a no-nothin Flour, wich aint u- Flour- a inosent Aingel, a-chaingin into a Man &amp; a-gittin cuite smal wilst a-goin throo I   Mr. Pepper Re-"Pete"s      Himself.   245 its littel hed is al smooth; it haint no teth; its fechers aint worth menshunin, thaym so teanty. different frum dog, it ken se to l's. (Cat doant se wel, long at 1st.) Wot is rich, youm releevd, the very 1st thing, about thayr bein born Dum, &amp;c4th. How the littel cusses wil yel, sumtimes I PETES a good exampel ov the yellin kind. But thats pain in Bowls--Genuses complaint: i hed it, this mornin, so i thougt ide dL thats wi ime a-ritin this minit. But to return, as the Comeck sed. TMAK a nuther vew.  dozen at saim pris (as the man sed wen he giv his boy a lickin.) Wot do you cal that, a-wigglin onto the floar? thairs the Potry ov Moshun, dun up smal. thats PETE, at 6 munths. How he creeps, tho I Few Babys are cmart at 6 munths. its nothin but yel, yel, yel, with moast on em. How different PETE I PETE incuires. PETE lerns. Wots he a-lookin at now? a hoal into the carpit He noas it otto be fixt. He almoast ses so. fix it PETE, wile your hand is in. (He Dus it throo HANAH; heer she cums, with a nedeL) industry &amp; Pete!-wot a site for a faither! the contemplaishun ov Babys at 6 munths is fine.  &#xD;<pb n="246-247" xml:id="VAC7289-00000124"/> 246   Mr. Pepper Re-"Pete" s Himself. How interestin, to se a littel rip gro 1 How Astonishin that Milk is al he wonts I Wots ham &amp; egs, or sider, or a pipe, to him? * He thincs ov nothin but a-groin. wot a pity Hees got to go throo so much, incloodin Sicnes I so much a-goin throo him at the saim time. HANAH GANE stics to it PETE sed pa as plain as eny body, at 6 munths. His i's wos a kind ov blooish wite at that perid. not a hair onto his bed eny wers. HANAH sed his noas wos exacly like mine. or wil be wen he gits a noas, i replide- At wich HANAH laft moast mewsikel. But to cum agin, as the Collery sed. LooC 1's moar, pervidin time aint presin. Wot doo you se now? as the mise sed to the OwL in a corner ov the Gardin (the north corner) a angelic Form, under a plum tre, a-hoaldin a Baby. (PETE at 12 munths.) looc twist; 2nd time a good wile, with both i's. aint the Bud a cumin on Grand? HANAH too is uncommon wel, you se. everything is a-smilin, incloodin the cmal dog. Sorry to trubbel you, but looc gest over-bed. Without a-strainin ov your i's much, youl probbly se   Mr. Pepper Re-"Pete"s Himself.        247 A clowd blacker than wot scairt ABNER, wen he cut. thats cuttin teth &amp; canker Rash, boath raither haisty. the clowd cums down: you se nothin: but Mity I how you ken heer, thoe  A rip with good lungs stans a good chans. PETES chans is uncomon good. 1st clas. Babys at 12 munths air plesent fur to looc at. thair is sumthin fine in a yeer oald Boy. Hair cums on good; likewais teth &amp; noas. thay begin for to swel sumtims wock I thay say ma &amp; pa cuite distinct I thay Doant drool much; thay ete masht tater: &amp; engoy life pooty cumferbel, considerin. Wot a gurl dus at 1 yeer i doant reely no. ef PETE, now, wos a gurl, i supoas i shood. i doant taik no interist into gurls. But to leev that pint, as the man sed to the Bagnit. TAIK 1 moar looc, as the drowin man sed Wen he cum up fur the 3rd time. thairs a Vew I (PETE at 18 munths.) Air you struc much? as the litenin sed to the man. Wot a cus, at a yeer &amp; i, aint he? oanly' 18 munths I wot a chaing, in 6 1 taik away the Mezels, &amp; wair is his ekal 1 How the Mezels spots a boy tho I How HANH laft, wen i askt ef GODFRYS Corjal wos good  &#xD;<pb n="248-249" xml:id="VAC7289-00000125"/> 248 Mr. Pepper Re-"Pete" s Himself. fur the Mezels I opodildoc maid her agin. i thine i tooc sulfer &amp; molasis, but aint shoor. PETE is pashenitly fond ov Caster ile I Becos i supoas it is sech an egspensive drinc. He raither prefers coald Prest ile. (Worm, with milk: i taik it coald without.) At 18 munths) Baby's air a rich site. With sum atenshun to noas, &amp;c4th, (not moarn a minit in a day, at that,) You ken maik em shine I thayr conversashun isent wot you may- cal instructiv ; but it kind ov melts into a parrens felings, &amp; pleses al but uther parrens, with yung 1's-- Wich thincs thay aint no grait shaiks after al, Compaird with sum thayv seen. (HANAH herd Missis JEFERS say them verry werds to her husban) wen thayd ben a collin hear, Be4 thayd fairly got to the gait; thay Hevin 2 or 3 squockers ov thayr oan) i beleev. Youd thine twos I dozen, bi the nois.) Wen thay git a littel oalder thayr kind: ov handy about a Hous; fedin pigs &amp;c4th, fechin wotter, Splittin kindlin wood, &amp; a duzen uther choars. i shel feel bad the 1st time i wail PETE. i reely doant no as i ever ken, hese so pooty. i ges ile let H-ANAH doo it wen nessary, &amp; tri &amp; keep onto the rite side. But   Mr. Pepper Re-"Pete" s Himself.     249 enuf onto that hed, as the man sed wen hede kild his wife. Muse much ableeged. Fairwel. WOT doo you thine ov PETE? I now dismiss the gifted PEPPER: muttering, with an air of mingled confidence and timidity, this vener- able and deprecatory apothegm:- V MATLA GRAMMATICA NON VITIAT CHARTAM." 1.1' ^-,W!  ^3 v. --   i  &#xD;<pb n="250-251" xml:id="VAC7289-00000126"/> A DELIBATION ON STYE. --o-- E M A N  A T I N G  F R O M  M Y  A N T R E. AS I grow older-I am so old, now, I am almost a fool,-my taste for really fine writing grows stronger and stronger. An elegant piece of composi- tion affects me much as a fine painting does. I pre- sume, reader, you are impatient to know my ideal of fine writing. I am not only impatient but anxious to lay that ideal before you. If you have thought but little on this subject, you will be amazed at the simplicity of my method of arriving at excellence, and charmed with the ease of attaining to heights quite inaccessible before. To show the wonderful grasp of my own unaided mindI I will now condense, into one sentence, everything in my system that is at all essential. The prime and   A Delibation on Style.     251 ultimate desideratum of him who aims at nothing below the mountain-peaks of excellence in style should be the shunning all common features. Thus, he should employ only unhacknied terms; avoid all idioms; and preserve, under every phase of subject- matter, a certain dignity, a quiet loftiness of tone, beyond the reach, or indeed comprehension, of medi- ocrity. Let the composition in hand be high-sound- - ing in terms, and majestic in its, general flow,--and whether you are likely to be understood or not, you may safely count on the admiration and respect of all your readers. Let me elucidate my system. I will suppose the case of an audience assembled to witness some per- formance at the Academy of Music-a delay-and an unexpected speech by a stranger. At the risk of offending you by associating, with excellence, a very uncomplimentary shadow, I will indulge myself in two reports of the affair; the first, a humble approach to the style I worship, and the other, a re-cast of the subject, in a commoner mould. Among other and more important advantages of my system, you will perceive that, by it, length may be secured-which writers will allow is no slight advantage.  &#xD;<pb n="252-253" xml:id="VAC7289-00000127"/> FIRST REPORT. a AN immense, luctating throng was collocated.  All ages and conditions were there commingled; senile sires, and grandames long in drear senes- cence, alternated with unablac- tated infants and the interve- nient growths of humanity. For a period there was some- thing quite lethargic in the quiet; but ere long the deferring began tg commove the people, and ominated a general con- citation-the prognostic and final diagnostic of which was the now friequent allision of hands, opertaneous curses, and streporous, vague shouts with no apparent purpose.  The catacoustic results of this re- sounding prolusion were as- tounding; the reboation by the walls commingling and unsig- nificising the sounds, and dis- tracting as well as deafening the unfortunate being necessi- tated to be a listener. But at last the effect of this popular commotion was manifest. An orgillous, ponderous, englutted, oleaginous, atrabilarous indivi- dual with a cane, took his ope- rose way to the centre of the space before the curtain; upon which, a seeming prolocutor among the people ejaculated ' Order!' and caused the tumult to subside. The obese stranger possessed rather a plebeian than aristocratic look; and his ver-   SECOND REPORT. "A regular crowd was jam- med into the Academy. Old foozles, of both sexes, were there-so were squalling brats: In ten minutes from the time the affair was advertised to come off, 'the jolliest row could be confidently looked for. Yells, hoots, claps, stamps, and groans shook the walls, and stunned everybody. Just in time to save a regular cav- ing-in of the building, a fat, pompous-looking old chap, with a solemn air, a cane, and a dull red face, appeared before the curtain, and waddled to the centre of the stage,-where he stood awhile, puffing and sweating: dike a bud) not yet ready to 'blow.' For a mo- ment ns chances of being heard seemed rather slim; but all doubts were soon removed by   meil countenance was bathed in that aqueous effusion which usually results from heat and excitement. He at once began indesinently to pour out a cataclysm of incoherent elo- quence, abounding in exple- tives and periphrasis, and ex- hibiting, throughout, a perplex- ing semidiaphaneity of mean- ing. His utterance soon be- came inspissate; and his wan- derings, in body and mind, be- trayed his familiarity with loxodromics.  He seemed en- gagcd in a luctation with his emotions. Repeated indiscreet humectations of his whistle ] had   evidently  overpowered him. He had begun to hesitate I for words, an ill-directed pty- alism was suffusing his hirsute appendage, and he was aiding his meaning with frequent grimaces and  ceiliads (being E threatened with complete ob- mutescence)-when his per- formances became unbearable to the people, who now indulg- ed in the frequent ejaculation, E -'Exsiccate!-Exsiccate!' Hiss- es aided the dehortation. -A  humorous person in the throng denominated him   ' that rare 8 plant, the Anemone,' other- c wise, the Windflower. They threatened, if he remained, to f effect his forcible metathesis, and subject his fleece to inus- tion. One well-versed in phy- t siognomy would have discover- ed in his countenance at this sl   the mighty yell of ' Orderl from a pair of brazen lungs, which cry majestically shut down the noisy crowd at once. The fat Unknown commenced his remarks; but it soon be- came fully evident that he was drunk. Nobody could make head or tail of his speech, or give the remotest guess at what he was driving at. His voice grew thicker and thicker; he stumbled awfully, and gave other evidences of being well swizzled-such as making faces, and winking significantly, to aid his meaning. The crowd were soon disgusted. Cries of 'Dry up!-dry up I' became frequent, and hisses,- hoots, shrill noises of various kinds, effectually flabbergasted him. This effect was partly brought about by the apples, oranges, &amp;c., that showered around him-one hit-  &#xD;<pb n="254-255" xml:id="VAC7289-00000128"/> moment strong indications of intimidation and alarm; for the expressions of displeasure were now ecumenical. The defoe- dated atmosphere was resonant with the tumult. Projectiles were traversing the whole inte- rior-impinging freely against his person. He now digni- fiedly placed his zoophoric cane under his arm, salaamed with grace, and passed majestically from the field of vision. His stately avolation, conjoined with the simultaneous sibila- tion, afforded a diverting in- stance of the overwhelming power of the popular will. The ponderous quondam declaimer, being stricken in the sinister optic by a flying missile, pro- bably proceeded to negociate for a xerocollyrium." Is comment necessary?   ting him in the left peeper. So, concluding to tortle, he drew himself up, proud but disgust- ed, bowed sarcastically, and dignifiedly cut his lucky. No use trying to stem a crowd. The first thing the greasy vic- tim probably did, after leaving, was to buy a plaster for his bunged eye."  &#xD;<pb n="256-257" xml:id="VAC7289-00000129"/> 256        L'Envoi. full, your part in that friendly chat which I should take the care to set going. I am ready, now, to lay aside, as a thing to be disused, this comic mask, with its exaggerated grin, from behind which I have some- times peeped for a moment, to set you thinking by the apparition of a sober countenance. I would love to listen, with a pleased and serious attention, to all you would kindly say: for the voice of a friend is a pleasant music to me, and is never wearisome. But this may not be. Much against my will, I must alone sustain the burden of this last commu- nion, if there be one;-on me devolves the duty of reviewing our brief acquaintance, of expressing good wishes for the future, and bidding the final adieux. As we observe, in actual life, that they who are most affected by the nearness of a separation, are the least heartened to make a flourish with their protestations; so it will become mne to cultivate a brevity, in this place, and a manner chastened by subdued emotion,- and not to weary you with prolonged and insincere assurances, or shock- your nicer feelings by the display of an unnatural gaiety. "It is certain that good Humour do wonderfully heighten Beauty," is a cheerful sentiment found in   "Envoi.       . 257 Mr. PIPS his Diary. Beauty not less of mind, fair reader,- than person. How may we promote this "good Humour," so justly valued by Mr. PIPs? Why, in no better way than by the reading of cheer- ful books. If Mr. PEPPER and I have made a book of this kind,-if it should happen to have brightened some dull faces, or lightened for the moment a few heavy hearts--why, I cannot say I am sorry we allowed ourselves to write it. I might almost address: my associate in the language of the warm-hearted Mrs. GAMP, who, at the termination of some alter- nated funereal labor, exclaims to Mrs. HARRIS with cordiality: "I hope it won't be long afore we works together, off and on, again." On second thought, it would not be possible to make that classic language apply; since Mr. PEPPER will' hardly lend himself again to the schemes of a literary speculator. But there is nothing to prevent me from again skimming the cream off a most prodigious quantity of the "milk of human kindness," and blessing the world with the oleaginous result. Stupid me! where is my pet figure of the "Museum of Fancies?"You will remember I made a great flourish with it when I bowed you in. But every  &#xD;<pb n="258-259 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7289-00000130"/> 258        L'Envoi. one, now and then, "misses his figure." So you have "seen everything," have you? And now, I suppose, you want your money back. "Don't you wish you may get it!"I see I wrong you: you were but regretting the smallness of the collection. I could easily have made it larger; but I thought it wise to err on the safer side. Perhaps, so far from being displeased, you have at times half allowed yourself to think it would be a fine recreation to "make such things" yourself.  Strangle those fancies, my friend, as fast as they are born. Even the frailest, of the fabrics you admire, were not made without labor: and the artiste had not always a grin on his face. Be thankful you have the heart to laugh at conceits which to him have long outlived their point, if they ever seemed to have one. You "must be going?"  Well, good-bye:-did I hurt you? Ah! it has been remarked my grasp is hearty. I see one may be too cordial. Let me wave my hand, and say: FAREWELL. THE EXHBITION IS CLOSED: AND THE SMLING PROPRIETOR (A GREAT HUMBUG) GONE WITH THE MONEY.   NEW BOOKS And New Editions Just Published by RUDD &amp; CARLETON, 310 BROADWAY, NEW YORK. I# 4 N B.-RUDD AND CARLETON, UPON RECEIPT OF THE PRICE, WILL SEND ANY OF THE FOLLOWING WORKS BY MAIL, postage prepaid, TO ANY PART OF THE UNITED STATES.   THS MODE MAY BE - ADOPTED WHEN THE NEIGHBORING BOOKSELLERS ARE NOT SUP- PLIED WITH THE DESIRED WORK. DOCTOR ANTONIO. A Love Tale of Italy.  By G. RUFFINI, author of "Lo- renzo Benoni," "Dear Experience," &amp;c.  Elegantly bound in Muslin, Illustrated, I zmo., price $I oo. BEATRICE CENCI. A Historical Novel. By F. D. GUERRAZZI. Translated from the original Italian by LuIGI MONTI. Muslin, two volumes in one, with Steel Portrait, price $I 25. A WOMAN'S THOUGHTS ABOUT WOMEN. The latest and best work by the author of "John Halifax, Gentleman," "Agatha's Husband," "The Ogilvies," "Olive," &amp;c.   Bound in muslin, price $I oo. ROUMANIA. Comprising Adventures of Travel in Eastern Europe and Western Asia. By JAMES O. NOYES, M D. Profusely illustrated. Large i zmo. Muslin, price $1 50.  &#xD;<pb n="260 (Advertisement) -261 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7289-00000131"/> 2       LIST OF BOOKRS PUBLISH ED TRUE LOVE NEVER DID RUN SMOOTH. An Eastern Tale, in Verse. By THOMAS BAILEY ALD- RICH, author of "Babie Bell, and other Poems." Ele- gantly printed, and bound in muslin, price 50 cents. DEAR EXPERIENCE. A Tale. By G. RUFFINI, author of "Doctor Antonio," "Lorenzo Benoni," &amp;c. With illustrations by Leech, of the London Putnch. Muslin, price $1 oo. FOLLOWING THE DRUM; Or, Glimpses of Frontier Life. Being brilliant Sketches of Recruiting Incidents on the Rio Grande, &amp;c. By Mrs. EGBERT L. VIELE. Muslin, price $1 oo. COSMOGONY; Or, the Mysteries of Creation. A remarkable book, being an Analysis of the First Chapter of Genesis. By THOMAS A. DAVIES. Octavo, muslin, price $2 oo. NOTHNG TO WEAR. A Satirical Poem. By WILLIAM ALLEN BUTLER. Pro- fusely and elegantly embellished with fine Illustrations by Augustus Hoppin. Muslin, price 50o cents. THE SPUYTENDEVIL CHRONICLE. A brilliant Novel of Fashionable Life in New York. A Saratoga Season Flirtations, &amp;c. A companion to the "Potiphar Papers." Muslin, price 75 cents. BROWN'S CARPENTER'S ASSISTANT. The best practical work on Architecture, with Plans for every description of Building. Illustrated with over 200 Plates. Strongly bound in leather, price $5 oo.   BY RUDD AND CARLETON.       3 THE ATLANTIC TELEGRAPH. An Authentic History of that great work; with Biogra- phies, Maps, steel and wood engravings, Portraits, &amp;c. Dedicated to CYRUS W. FIELD. Muslin, price $I oo. ISABELLA. ORSINI. A new and brilliant novel. By F. D. GUERRAZZI, author of "Beatrice Cenci;" translated by MONTI, of Har- vard College. With steel portrait. Muslin, price $I 25. K. N. PEPPER PAPERS. Containing Verses an 1 Miscellaneous Writings of one of the first humorous contributors to ",Knickerbocker Magazine." With Illustrations. Muslin, price I$ oo. THE AMERICAN CHESS BOOK. Prepared by PAUL MORPHY, LouIs PAULSEN, and the chief Members of the late New York Chess Congress for 1857. Muslin, 12mo. Fully illustrated. (In press). THE CAPTIVE NIGHTINGALE, And other Tales. Translated from the German of KRU MACHER. A charming book for the Young. Fully illustrated. Muslin, gilt back, &amp;c.,. price 50o cents. STORIES FOR CHLDHOOD. By AUNT HATTY (Mrs.: Coleman). Beautifully bound in cloth gilt, and profusely illustrated. Put up in boxes containing 12 ass )rted volumes. Price per box, $4 oo. GOOD CHLDREN'S LIBRARY. By UNCLE THOMAS. A dozen charming stories, beautifully illustrated; bound in cloth, gilt backs. Put up in boxes containing 12 assorted volumes. Price per box, $4 oo.  &#xD;<pb n="262 (Advertisement) -263 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC7289-00000132"/> TTLIST OF BOOKS PUBIbHED HUSBAND vs. WIFE. A Domestic Satirical Novel. By HENRY CLAPP, JR. Illustrated by A. Hoppin, in colors, on cream paper, ir Illuminated Missal style. Muslin, price 60 cents. ASPENWOLD. An Original Novel, of interest and merit. By an Ame- rican writer. Illustrated with original designs on wood by Howard. Muslin, price $I 25. "ECTURES OF LOLA MONTEZ, Including her "Autobiography," "Wits and Women of Paris," "Comic Aspect of Love," "Beautiful Women," "Gallantry," &amp;c. Muslin, steel portrait, price $1 oo. "FE OF HUGH MT,ER, Author of "Schools and Schoolmasters," "Old Red Sandstone," &amp;c. From the Glasgow edition. Pre pared by THOMAs N. BROWN. Muslin, price $I oo. KNAVES AND FOOLS; Or, Friends of Bohemia. A Satirical Novel of Literary and Artistic Lite in London. By E. M. WHTTY, of the London Times. Illustrated. Muslin, price $1 25. THE COTTAGE COOK BOOK; Or, Housekeeping made Easy and Economical in all itt Departments. A most practical and useful work. Bi EMLY THORN\WELL. Muslin, price 75 cents. THE CHRISTMAS TREE. A valuable Book of Amusement and Instruction for tht Young, containing Stories upon every subject. Illus tratcd by KE:NN,'Y M EADOWS. Muslin, price 75 cents.,   BY RVTDD AND CARLETON.     5 EROS AND ANTEROS; Or, the Bachelor's Ward. One of the very best of Mo- dern Novels. A story of strong interest, and written with true poetic feeling. Muslin, price $x oo. DOESTICKS' LETTERS. Being a compilation of the Original Letters of Q. K. P. DOESTICKS, P. B. With many comic tinted illustra- tions, by John McLenan. Muslin, price $i oo. PLU-RI-BUS-TAH. A song that's by-no-author. Not a parody on "Hia- watha." By DOESTICKS. With I15o humorous illus- trations by McLenan. Muslin, price $I oo. THE ELEPHANT CLUB. An irresistibly droll volume. By DOESTICKS, assisted by KNIGHT Russ OCKSIDE, M D. One of his best works. Profusely illustrated by McLenan. Muslin, price $I oo. NOTHNG TO SAY. A Satire in Verse, which has "Nothing to Do" with "Nothing to Wear."  By DOESTICKS, P. B. With Illustrations by McLenan. Muslin, price 50 cents. THE OLD LOVE AND THE NEW. A very charming Novel, containing the very elements ot success. Written by Mrs. JULIET H. L. CAMPBELL. Handsomely bound in muslin, 12mo., price $1 oo. "FE OF SPENCER H. CONE. Being Memoirs of the late Pastor of the First Baptist Church in the city of New York. Prepared by his Sons. Steel Portrait. Muslin, price $1 2S.   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
