<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7696">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>St. George de Lisle, or, The Serpent's Sting </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7696</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2151</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>St. George de Lisle, or, The serpent's sting</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 p. l. 9-34 p. 1 l. plates </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Barclay</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1858">[1858]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-03-07">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>St. George de Lisle, or, The serpent's sting</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="" xml:id="VAC7696-00000001"/>
               <pb n="0Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7696-00000002"/>ST1. SAGE!  9E  [TSYTE: OR, THE SERPENT'S STING: A TALE OF WOMAN'S DEVOTION &amp; SELF-SACRIFICE. "HOW' E THE :MoHTY FAUS.", 'A TRUE AND THRILTffNG NARRATIVE OF CRIME IN HGH LIFE, IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK.  PHLADELPHA:- PUBLI'SHED-BY BARCLAY 00G 734 MARCTRT STREET.  &#xD;<pb n="0-9" xml:id="VAC7696-00000003"/> Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1858, by BARCLAY &amp; CO., In the Clerk's Office of the Eastern District of Pennsylvania.    ST. GEORGE DE LISLE:  OR, THE SERPENT'S STING. CHAPTER I. IT was a winter night, in the year eighteen hundred and fifty-six, cold, clear, and invigorating. A thousand jets of gas-flame shine effulgent over one of the most brilliant audiences evet assembled within the walls of the Academy of Music, in our great Metropolitan and Empire City. FParquette, boxes, balcony and :ampitheatre are filled. A sea of human forms -sweeping in graceful curve, tier above -tier, from floor to ceiling- sit expectant of pleasure; all, for the time being, willing to banish care, and paint smiles upon their faces. Diamonds glitter, and the pale sheen of pearls gleams, amid the flash of bright and soft eyes; plames wave, and flowers emit fragrance that makes one involun- tarily think of our. lost home-Paradise I And now, from'the orchestra, swells out music, such as makes the heart thrill. It is the prelude to one of Rossinifs operas-and to night is to be the first .appearance, before an American audience, of one of Europe's greatest musical celebrities - The overture is almost through--a few last melting symphonies are stealing over the senses, when, a laced curtain fronting a proscenium-boxi is withdrawn, as a lady of marvellous beauty and queenly presence, magnificently attired, enters it, and seats herself in one of its costly chairs, She is accompanied by her husband and a beautiful little girl of ten years of age.  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7696-00000004"/> 10        ST. GEORGE DE LISLE; OR, Numerous are the glasses raised from all directions to inspect the party; and many the greetings exchanged, with occupiers of the more aristocratic portion of the house, by the new comers. They are Mr. and Mrs. St. George De Lisle, and their daughter. There is an air of quiet repose, unmixed with hauteur, which so-certainly indi- cates high breeding, evident in all the lady's maniner. She seems created for a nobler end than to be'a mere leader of ton; Her husl band is a tall, slender, gentlemanly-looking man-his face expressive of great intellectuality, but upon his brow-sits a cloud of care--- which, even the gay scene cannot dispel,--and there is a furtive expression in his blue eyes, which will not "look you full in the face," -that indicates an unquiet and restless mind. But why wonder that: Mr. St. George De Lisle,--the extensive Wall St., operator,-should have an anxious look? His daily ventures involve thousands I and, although it is said, wealth pours in 'upon him in a golden flood, still larger and larger are the sums risked in his operations; for their success-with numberless exaggerations-is the theme of every tongue.  But the stage curtain is rising H-and the fasinating pageant is passing  before the enraptured gazers. Music, gorgeous scenery, artistic grouping, dressing, such as habitudes- of courts alone can see, all contribute to the charming spectacle. Kind   reader, such is an Opera; and while the hour is thus engaged by these five thousand people, permit me to introduce to you Mr. and Mrs. St. George De   Lisle. They are none in that crowd of fashion and beauty but would feel honored to make their acquaintance. Mr. St. George De Lisle is the youngest son of a wealthy gente. man,.still living at a very advanced age, in an inland town in the same State, and about a hundred miles from the city of New 'York. When a boy of fourteen he had been sent from home to push his own fortunes in the great city. Alone, and almost without help, he had struggled up to his, present position. The old gentleman seems proud of the success of his son, but never to any extent assisted him. His name and family associations gave the boy, even when, engaged in humble services, in enviable social position. Houses of high fashion and wealth were opened to him. The boy resolutely turned stone after stone out of his pathway; -and, when twenty-two years of age, presented a  noble specimen of a young man of high. moral   THE CURSE OF Ta FORGER.         ," bearing, of kind heart, and of intellectual cultivation seldom excelled. He was greeted on all sides by smiling faces and invited every where. Commissions of profit were constantly proffered' him in his business; and St. George De Lisle was esteemed rich, initel- lectual, high-born, and well-bred.' He was surrounded by hosts of friends, and flatterers; was feasted, slandered, borrowed from and cheated; 'Happy St. George De Li$le I When about twenty-three years of age, De Lisle was induced, to further a business operation, to visit England. Letters of introduc- tion were given him tofamilies of title and--distinction, as well as to those of high political position. His business affair prospered beyond  his highest expectations; and, after its accomplishment, he resolved to spend a few weeks before his .return home, in making the " run of the Continent;"-that is, to visit Paris, some few of the German cities; sail along the Rhine; climb some of the mountains of Swit-  zerland; gaze on Florence, Naples, and Rome; and come back to America, more bewildered than-instructed, by what had been seen. While in England, most of his time not devoted to business, was -spent in visiting places of interest or amusement in and about Lon- den; or, in partaking of the hospitalities which were lavished upon him--as they mostly are upon every well-bred American-for each one of- us, inn a Briton's eye, seems as "a chattered King."  His brain as well as heart were all untouched; and the sun of prosperity, shone brightly upon him. Happy St. George De Lisle I One evening towards the close of his -intended sojourn in London, he sauntered into the world famed show-rooms of Madame Tussand. "These are a succession of apartments filled with exquisite wax statues, in addition to relics of History, including many articles- that belonged to Napoleon Buonaparte. The exhibition originated it Paris and many of its most striking peculiarities are connected with scenes that occurred during the time of the French Revolution." , Passing through rooms of state, where may be seen Kings and Emperors-the very coronation robes worn by Napoleon anda Joe- phine,-you come to a cool, damp room called the Chamber of bor- rors.- It is dimly lighted, and here is the very knife that dedapi. tated the heads of Marie Antoinette, Louis XVI., and many others, good and bad--and here stands a model of the Guillotine-the same size-in every respect complete-and in working orderl" Reader, do you exactly understand, ]ow this horrible machine was 4d       o  &#xD;<pb n="12-13 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7696-00000005"/> 10     +^ 3  S GEQA E JDE LISLE;, OR, CpOstrucd,:-a ndhe' nay in, w htch: it Aoperated? Although I cannot show j, theoon0 in Madam Tussand's exhibition room, I can describe  xtito you, and if:u w il giv me, your, attention,at, least .one item, of ;inforimatio9onwgprth kowingi will be lodged, in your. mind in conse- quences of, :perusil my little nrrative.. . i - The 'G9  tijM i osistoQf a heavy plank abonut seven feet long and of sufficient width to allow a; man -toalie;down upqn it., It is rtsed;.some two!nd a hbalf feet from .the. ground. .There are attach- ed: to the p lanka number of strAps byi whiPh the victim was bound to, it i At ,the:had extremity of the plak. ar e Pwo prightst fifteen fe t high, leaving betw een the two a, sp ce of one foott Each. upright, ho a smoogth, wetadi groove .fgcing the other, ,Up, and do:n these ' grovesthe knif! lides., Almost under the, knife:.are two boards hayVing a sem irclp in each--the under one is stationery, the upper ' onp is movesq.-band these two boards fit aronnd the neck of the poor / wretch, whose head is; to ble cut off. To make..the, descent of the: knife more rapid and forcible, it ia .heavily backed with iron. The knife falls from the extreme top :of the uprights-sliding down the groQQv..witth the, rapidity of lightning -.and in a moment, its fatal Vork- i donel :",         . , ItJw as with a cold hill of- terror that St. George. De Lisle sur- veyed the :furnituroof,this, dismal room, '." Human .skulls, original infernal machines, and hmurderous weapons of all kinds, were scattered around, and here 4.nd there, stood or crouched: the figures, in wag, so true ,o. nature. that, they. :almost :seemed .to, breathe, of noted 'con- apihri tors, highwaymen, .brigands and murderers."- -.-BisfeelingofTelief Was great on agai a entering the other apart- meotanclnd.:ssing, through ".' The Hall of-Kings " linqd with fifty-five pfirtraits ilrsge ga s,!f. EuropeanI sovereigns, :be came: back to the principal Hall.   -         -        .  Madam Tussand. was a: g'regt republican and evinced much interest in;American: history., Thhere was in this-apartment a fine painting, represnting. thescenein iE:rnt,of, the, State .House in Philadelphia, immqdititely. ffter ..tie:e signing of the pDeclartiaiQn of Independence. Thegrpuping.,was admirable-and, he:could nothutwondpr that in Europo 4.here should exist so much higher an estimate of the capacity' of theingidents of Americann History to all, into-requisition illustra. tions of high art-rwhile: at home in this. particular there, is so great neglect, nay, analmost: entirodverlooking. He turned from his ex- ,A.-   : leche liie Scene in fron  the State House in Philadelphia in 1776 immediately  after the Declara . tion of Indepen ce- being a section of the fine painting in Madame Tussand's exhibi-. tion atld which io  closely, connecd with the fate of the characters in thib narrative.  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7696-00000006"/>   THE CURSE OF THE FORGOER.        15 amination of this picture, :and observed right in front of an inimita- ble statue of the immortal George Washington and contemplating it, an old gentleman with gray hair and a proud aristocratic bearing, attended by a young and exceedingly beautiful girl of eighteen suih- mers. Their conversation although carried on in a low tone was so distinct in its enunciation that, without designing to listen, he could not help hearing what was said. And as the lovely girl expressed her heartfelt admiration for "America's proud hero"-,his blood thrilled, and he felt as he had never felt before. They passed on, and it seemed to him as though the plumage of some bright Tropicalbird had, for a moment, flitted in beauty before him, and then faded away into obscurity, forever. Ho was at length aroused from his long reverie by a cry of dis- tress, and a running to and fro of many persons. Something terri- ble certainly had happened,-what could it be? ,The gentleman and his daughter had proceeded-on, through the rooms, and the young lady not wishing to stay a moment, after a hasty glance had revealed to r the character of ' The Clhamber of Horrors,' had returned to The Golden Chamber or Shrine of Napo- leon,'--a room filled with Napoleonic curiosities, obtained thlrough the agency of goverment and well worthy of attention-while her fatlher, with a strange fscination, lingered behind, and examianed with an intense interest, its various horrid furniture. At length the old gentleman, who had been in Paris during some of the fearful atrocities of the French Revolution, thought he would try to realize the exact feelings of the victim who is to be guillotined. Hie was alone. So lie approached the fearful instrument-laid down upon the fatal plank-adjusted himself properly-his head through the nock- board, and, while looking up towards the knife, he suddenly dis- covered it slowly sliding down. He attemplited to grasp the rope, by which the knife was drawn up to the top, and which in his ignorance he had managed to displace; but it was beyond his reach--nearer and nearer the knife slid towards him, articulation failed-lihe could utter no sound-destruction was inevitable; and chill damps of perspiraw tion oozed from every pore. Just then, one of the attendants entered the room, and with inimitable presence of mind. rescued him-but now insensible-from his perilous position. He was not an inch clear of the neck-board when the weight of the knife, after salpping through the entangled cord, came down with a harmless crash."  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7696-00000007"/> 16       , ST. GEORGE DE LISLE; OR, The first news that reached the young girl was, that the old man was killed; and it was her shriek of agony that aroused St. George. He hurried towards the spot; and ascertaining that life was not ex- tinct, rendered efficient aid to both. Restoratives were applied, and unwilling that they should be left alone, he offered his services which were adccepted, and accompanied them home in their carriage, which was in attendance at the door; a plain vehicle, with- only a coach- man. They drove towards one- of the most fashionable quarters of the metropolis and stopped in front of an, elegant mansion. A number of servants were in immediate assiduous attendance, and, finding that he would be no further needed, he was about retiring, when the, young lady said, with a tearful face, "You will, I hope, kind sir, call again and see how my dear father is. We shall ever remember your services with gratitude." At the same time she handed him two cards. He bowed his thanks for the invitation; and saw the old man assisted by his servants go up the marble steps, and through the massive door of the stately house-his daughter seemed scarcely to touch the ground as her figure flitted- gracefully alongside. He- turned away when the door was shut, and then at the next street gas-light looked at the cards. Upon one- was engraved- "William Henry, Earl of Grassmere ;" upon the other "L Lady Adelaide Harriet Mowhray." There was no sleep for St. George that night. And for many days and nights he thought of little else than the-"Lady Adelaide" and her father. The continental trip- was forgotten. The poorold man never recovered from his fiight-a slow nervous fever set in, which, in a few weeks, terminated his life. 'His daugh.. ter was his only surviving child, and the title with his estates, pass- ed to a distant branch of the family with whom he had not been on, friendly terms. He had had- one son who died suddenly about- three years before--and now the Lady Adelaide was almost alone, with what appeared, to one accustomed to splendour and her style of living, but a small fortune of fifteen thousand pounds sterling, or about seventy-five thousand dollars.- St. George De Lisle seemed her nearest friend. She consulted him about all her plans and if the thought of vhatt-she should do when he was gone, crossed her mind, she banisheodjit, without answering the question. But the -tithe came, when return he must- and, reader, perhaps you will not be so surprised as he was, when I   THE C  sB OP T B FwBOEB.        17 tell you she consented to come with him, not as the "Lady Adelaide Harriet Mowhray,"' but as Mrs. St. George De Lisle. There was quite a furor of excitement among the upper circles of New York about the- titled bride of young De Lisle; and although no large parties could be attended by the bridal pair---on :account of the recent death of her father-the select re-unions which they graced with their presence though small as regarded numbers, were exclusive in the extremesnd recherche in the highest degree. Still all things seemed to say, happy St. George De Lisle I But the Opera is over. The people are going home. Carriages are rolling over the paved streets, waking up or disturbing those who go to bed at proper hours, and reader, I will now close my first Chapter, and go to bed, too. a(HAPTER II. IT was late the morning- after the Opera, when Mr. St. George De Lisle arrived at his counting room down town. The day was one of harrassing perplexity and he shut himself up several times, at inter- vals, of "half an hour at a time," as was his habit when business demanded unusual attention; with instructions, that were perempt. ory. "on no account to be interrupted." At length, the day's work was over;-and his carriage- Lad come to take him home. He had an old and care-worn look and ascended, almost feebly for so young a man, the carriage steps;-but there passed over his face an expres- sion of relief as the vehicle rolled, further away, up town. His home was a beautiful one; and though the house  Depot large, its appointments were complete in all their detail%,-and an impress of elegance pervaded the whole establishment. The family numbered in all six children. The oldest boy was away at, school, and the next was the girl, who had been with them the preceding night;--the others, of both sexes, ranged, down to a two-years-old boy baby. A lovelier family never blessed a man's hearth side. They were to, dine at home that day, with a few invited friends; and, after dressing for dinner, but a faew minutes elapsed when the guests began to arrive. The dinner wa s:elegant, well served and '.  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7696-00000008"/> 18        ST. GEORGE DE LISLE; OR, passed off without accident. The hour for retiring from the table, that is, eight o'clock P. M. was near, and as all the guests were en- gaged elsewhere for the evening, Mr. and Mrs. St. George De Lile expected to spend this Saturday night alone. The company rose from the table, and after a few brief adieus, departed. Mrs. De Lisle had wanted for months one quiet evening at home with her husband. She saw, with a woman's instinctive perception, that there was some concealed source of anxiety upon his mind, and she was determined, if possible, to know what it was, and share it with him. She was a true woman, and a true wife. She had laid awake at nights oftentimes, wondering what it could be, that was wearing upon him. It was not that he was peevish or unkind, but he was abstracted, gloomy and melancholy-even when he smiled his face looked sader afterwards, and those fitful lightings up to her imagining were like the gleamings of an unearthly light upon a whitened tomb. Now was her hour for knowing all, and she was determined to do so. She had with thig intent, returned to the drawing room, where Mr. De Lisle was sitting alone, with his eyes shut, in a velvet chair; -and the care-worn look was written so deep upon his face, that she paused for a moment to disturb him. Her heart ached for her hus- band; but oh I why would he not tell her all his sorrow? A loud ring at the door bell startled her, she knew not why;-. and he, with an alarmed expression which was quickly chased away, said, "I wonder who that can be!" and again closing his eyes sat silent, until a footman entered with a note upon a silver waiter, which he handed to his master, Mr. De Lisle opened and read it to the end. His face turned white as marble, and his lips trembled; still he retained a com- posure that was almost terrible; and said to the attendant: it Tell the bearer, there is no immediate answer." The man bowed and retired. De Lisle, clutching the paper in his hand-his lips parting and teeth set firmly together-then sank back inhis seat, the picture of anguish, and despair. His wife sprang to his side, and, fondly caressing him, said: "St. George, by all that is sacred, tell me what this means. Any thing is better than suspense. Tell me in mercy, and at once!" "I cannot, oh, I cannot!" replied the wretched man.   1 i I I , I i a I  &#xD;<pb n="20 (Illustration) -21" xml:id="VAC7696-00000009"/>  THE CURSE OF THE FORGER.         21 -"But you must, my dear I Do not fear for me. I can endure. I am your wife. If it is poverty you dread-that does not appall me. Only tell me what it is." It is worse than poverty. It. is disgrace!" and he covered his face- with both his hands. ' The proud woman shuddered; but one look towards the bowed down man before her, enabled her to. regain some portion of her self- possession, and she replied: , Even that, St. George, I can share with you, and be of some com- fort. But our children, -oh our children, cannot they, be saved? Tell me: oh -tell me, what is it?"-and she threw herself on her knees at his feet. g"In pity tell me." "There it is-that will tell you all-and oh, it is enough to sadden your heart forever. Wretch that I am I Would that I never had been born!" She took the paper and read it through.. Its contents, alas I told her all., It was a letter from one of the oldest -and most respected of. New York's wealthy men, and the president of a leading Bank, one with whose family they were upon terms of social intimacy, and who had been oftentimes a friend to St. George in his early strug"ts. It stated that a note wlioh professed to have the .signature of a wealthy firm drawn to'his order, and, which had been negotiated by himself, was known to'bea forgery. .,A bank notice had been served by a mistake of one of the bank .clerks, upon the firm, a whole month too early. It had been disclaimed .by them, and with a desire to save him, if possible, from exposure- he had now :thus written to him. How still that room was! The ticking of the magnificent time. piece on the mantle fell painfully loud upon the ear... 'At last, in a hloarse whisper, she said: "And is this one note all?" "No!" was the reply in a whispered tone, so low, that, but for the excited nervous tension of the moment, it cOuld/,not have been heard. This was, thuns far, the most crushing blow, and the woman's heart nearly sank beneath it-but again;she asked: : "' In all to what' amount1?"There was a 'pause :--oh, how long, and fearful it seemed I btiil,'nb answer. - Again the question came, but now tin a determined, slow, and with that peculiarly clear enunciation for which she ais:so. remarkable ,-.her fate: must' be known. i, In all, I think, about thirty thousand dollars:" was the answer.,  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7696-00000010"/> 22        ST. GEORGE DE LISLE; OR, "St. George, if that be all, surely exposure may be saved Hof the sin it is not a wife's province to speak-all I have, may cheerfully go to wipe the debt out." , "Alas, my wife, that is all gone already. There is not a dollar of your fortune left. It is all, all gone I " "Surely this house and furniture are worth something. I sup- posed they were mine:" was the calm reply-no shade of anger, but sorrow such as an angel might evince for the erring, was expressed in her face. "Adelaide I "-and the words came out, one by one, with intervals between, of different lengths,--" reproach me if you will-I am, I, feel, more wicked than you can think me--but, I tried to keep up as long as I could.--I could not bear that you should have to change your style of living-losses came, after losses.--I tried to make them up, and only made others.-The deed of the house was in my name alone, :and I mortgaged the property to its full value; of the furniture I also gave a bill of sale. And when all this money was gone, I: "--the  man could not utter the word that, to his own wife, confessed him a S Tte was not a sign of irritation or impatience manifested as he proceeded, and when he stopped she rose, bent down her head, kissed'his pale brow, and said, 6"My poor, poor husband, how littledid you know me. ' Oh I what could have been mere poverty compared to0this? But now there is one thing must be done. Our children l They must be saved this disgrace. Oh, our-children I?I am thankful my dear parents are both dead." And she left the room. He heard her going up the nursery stairs, and falling on his knees he prayed in agony to the Almighty whose laws, as well as those of man, he had broken. It is ever thus in the hour of wildest trouble-- even the criminal when headed in on all sides, turns to his Maker for succour. Mrs. De. Lisle gazed in quiet grief upon the younger four of her little flock, all sound asleep-and scalding tears fell upon them. Her oldest little girl was on her knees at her evening prayers, and a few, words of murmured supplication for blessings on those she loved fell like balm upon her heart. She lowered the already dim light so that the child might not, when she arose, perceive her face, and then, after kissing her good night, she entered her dressing room.   THs CURSE 'OF THE FORGE.         23 Rapidly changing her splendid dinner costume for a dress of plain material, with bonnet on, and shawl in hand, she returned to the drawing room, where, still crouched in utter abjectness, her misera- ble husband. ,' De Lisle, you must arouse yourself-every moment is precious- ' if you have-a spark of love for your children, for me, you must act 1i like a man. This dreadful thing must be kept a secret-I am going  to see Mr. Duval-he was once our friend and surely kindness caused him to write you that note. He has experience, and to take counsel with him now, seems to me, the wisest thing I can do. And while I am gone write out a full* description of all those notes and where they may be found-do not fail me in this.," She placed writing implements on the table beside him, and left the house. An half hour had scarcely passed when she returned. There was still upon her face the same expression of calim determination and resolve. 'She asked for the paper upon which he had been writing, and upon being assured that it contained the whole account said: I shall start to night for Hudson. You must watch tenderly over all our little ones while I am gone. See that Willie does not miss me. I shall try and be back on Monday morning. Mr. Duval thinks, with me, that I had, best go and see your- father and Nbrothers. It seems to me the only hope The last train leaves at ten o'clock, but as it is a way train, I can reach it at its last stopping place in the city, which is quite near this, a quarter of an hour later. I hane a cab now at the door, and am all ready to start."  She took his trembling hands within her-own--pressed them ten- derly, and said:-," There is one thing more I ask-pray,--oh pray, -pray for help from on high," The wheels of a carriage driving rapidly, and growing fainter in the distance, gave assurance that Mrs. St. George De Lisle had com- menced her midnight journey, towards the home of her father-in- law. A.   &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7696-00000011"/> 24         ST. GEORGE DE LISLE; OR, CHAPTER    III. WHAT a fearful night ride was that --alone, and haunted with'such sad forebodings. The huge locomotive shrieked and moaned; now vomiting forth sparks, and then yelling like some reljoicing fiend drawing on to destruction its freight of h uman prey, as it rushed on- ward with the speed of the wind. Had an eternal nlight settled dowln upon the world? She-longed 'to reach the end of her journey, yet, trembled with fear at the thought of the momentous results whichI hung upon the communications she had to make. At lengthl the dawn broke--fdr morning will succeed night, no matter how wretched we may be. It was still early when she reached the hotel at- Hudson, and securing! a private room, she despatched a note, asking an immediate interview, to the younger of Mr.. De. Lisle's two brothers living in the city,'but who htid, because of marked success in life, obtained an almost para-! mount influence over his father. An age seemed to elapse before the return of her messenger, but! at length he arrived, and with him Mr. Charles De Lisle. He was a man of about fifty years of age; one who ]lad grown rich and hard-hearted&amp;. Money had been his idol; and a system of econorm- ical saying--except where'his own individual comfort was concerned-- several successful operations in real estate, and a continuous prac- tice of note shaving-the security being ample and the rates enor-. mous --had resulted in developing a character disposed to selfishness into one, in which the predominating ideas of self and gold had swal-  lowed up every other consideration. He was gentlemanly in exterior, and with a bland smile, "Wished to know what could have induced! his fair lady sister to come alone to Hudson, at such a time-l And why she had not, at once, driven to his house, instead of remaining at the hotel?" "Charles, we are in trouble; dreadful trouble!' and disgrace, fear- ful to think of, is on my track!" The bland smite vanished-and the hard expression, which always I foreboded evil to his solicitor, stamped itself unmistakeably upon his i   THE CURSE OP TEE FORGER.         25 face. This had the effect of recalling her faculties, and she proceeded, in as few words as possible, to tell him all the circumstances of the case. His face grew angry, and flushed purple with excitement-and when she had finished, he hissed an imprecation through his teeth, and it The extravagant scoundrel I! he had better run for. it." re But remember his. childrenw yourself, and your, children I We. will all suffer immeasurably if the thing is not hushed up,. ,True:"-he said. "Blast the villainl My own boys are of the same name, and are now in New York just started in business. It is, dreadfully unfortunate I I will consult with Edward: "-and leaving the room he was seen quickly walking down the street, towards the house of the oldest brother. Mrs. De Lisle took courage. She knew Edward'S was a kind heart.. Hoe felt for all in distress, and surely for his brother-whom as the !njamin of the flock, the little onel and whom their dying mother had charged him to, be kind to, and watch over--he would couns el tenderly. She kneeled down and thanked God for the one ray of hope that was darting across the troubled waters of her soul. Edward had not half the influence with the father thiat Charles possessed-for he himself had been one of the unfortunate-s in life, that is, had always been in straitened circumstances--but through Charles, their father could be influenced to any things The two brothers soon returned, The face of the eldest was full of sorrow-and, his head sunk down heavily upon his chest. He 'walked with his hands folded up under his arms; and approaching Mm. De Lisle, he said, in a kind, mournful voice: "Sister Adelaide, from my soul I pity youl" then, after a short- silence, he resumed--"St. George do this oh can It be? I would as soon have thought the angel. Gabriel would have comlnitted a henious crime!" and turning to Charles, he. said: , Brother, we must save him! St. George has had but little from our father, and although this sum will swallow up far anore than any single portion he could give to a child?--yet we must each be willing to lose a part to save him from disgrace. "But,"--and the angry cloud again- spread over the brother's face- "it is not fair, or just, that we should,have to suff r for his exyava. gance and rascality.-It is too bad--itis: shameful   &#xD;<pb n="26-27 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC7696-00000012"/> 26        Sr. GEORGE DE LISLE; OR, ' True, brother;-but exposure would hurt Us all more than the de- " crease of each share our father would leave us. Your boys, for in. stance, would suffer disadvantage in their business were it known that the family blood was tainted with this crime, far more in worth than the few thousands you would thus lose!"  Edward saw he had touched the right cord to influence Charles, and, after some further conversation, it Was at length resolved that they two should break the subject to their father, and induce him, if they could, to advance the necessary money to -redeem the whole of the forged paper--and that, if they were successful in thus influencing him, Charles Do Lisle should return with his sister-in-law to New Yorlk, to attend to this business. They then left her, and' wended their way sorrowfully to the pater. nal mansion. She prayved and hoped-then feared and prayed again. How wearily, oh how wearily, did the time drag along. The brothers broke the matter as well as they knew how to their  aged father. It seemed at first to completely stun him. His son a forgerl  His son, the bright boy of whose success he had been so proud?   "No; they surely had had  a night-mare dream, and were dreaming still: or, maybe, he himself had the night-mare 1--Oh would they not awake him?"-and   the plaintive voice of the old man begged ha two -sons, for God's sake, oto awake him from his horrible ,-g dream.  It was a piteous sight. Tears streamed down his withered cheeks, and he trembled all over like an aspen leaf. Tihe three men wept togetler. At length, after they had in some degree pacified him, they told him of their plan for saving St. George, and the credit of the family, by recovering all the forged notes, and their joint wil. lingness to sacrifice a portion of their inheritance to effect the object. His other children-for the family was large-were scattered over different parts of the Union, and time would not permit of their be- ing consulted. The exigency was imperative, and what is done at all, must be done at once. He gave a stolid assent to all they said-- only asking now and then. "Is it not a dreadful dream ;-oh my, sons cannot you awake me?  It is killing me,-oh it is killing me!" He was passive in their hands as a little child- signing with trem- bling hands, one after another, papers giving the power of attorney to his son Charles to sell various stocks that he owned. The amount swept away nearly the whole of the personal estate of the old go*      &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7696-00000013"/>  THE:. CURE OF .Tn FORGEB.        29 tleman-leaving however his real estate intact,- which was large and very valuable. While thus engaged, Edward hastened to the hotel to relieve the anxiety of Mrs. De Lisle.* She then, for the. first time since her arrival, shed tears. They flowed copiously; and the kind brother administered all the consolation he could devise--but, ah, how little was that,-the frightful future loomed up, dark and terrible. They spent the day together. It being Sunday there would be no return train until after twelve o'clock P. M., when the Albany train would stop: on its way down to New York. A message was received from Charles stating that he would be ready at that time to accom- pany his sister home, and desiring her to be ready. It was thought best for her not to seek an interview, at present, with her father-in- law. He was too much afflicted tole War it. As twilight darkened. around, Edward prevailed upon Mrs, De Lisle to take a soothing opiate and to endeavor to obtain. some; rest. As he left the room she clasped within both her hands. his own, and poured forth her gratitude to him in such a strain of touching; pathos that he was deeply moved-and he could only reply by a murmured prayer that their great All-father, would guide and help them. The miserable woman threw herself upon a sofa, and, worn out as she was, sleep came to her relief. For several hours she slum- bered soundly as is oftentimes. permitted to the extremely wretched; -the convict, the night before his execution, with the shadow of the gallows falling on him, sometimes thus sleeps-then, more un. easily she breathedi dreams began to disturb her repose-?at first, indistinct-and disconnected, yet all distressing. Pale phantoms passl ed her, and pointed menacingly onward--jeering demons laughed malignantly in her face--serpents glided along the path and, hissing out their forked tongues, lifted their snaky eyes and watched her as she moved along. At last she seemed to have entered a dense forest. The rocks and sharp- Stones over which she had walked had torn: her shoes into shreds, and, with, bleeding feet-she endeavored to make her way through thorns and. briars, urged on by an irresistible impulse. Weary and painful was the journey. There was- no light, save that of the lightning as it fitfully gleamed,-displaying horror- upon hor. ror. It seemed hours that she thus wandered;- until, at last there was revealed to her, peacefully. sleeping upon thei brink of a dread- ful precipice, her children. They were all there, and locked in each others' arms. Another fitful flash l--and, in, a bush behind them,  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7696-00000014"/> s0        -ST. GEOBGEE LISLE; OR, crouched an enormous tiger; his eyes glaring fiercely, and in the very act of springing upon them. Her heart ceased to beat--yet, in a wild agony, she rushed forward- and catching the fearful glance with her human eyes gazed steadily into those of the brute, until, cowed down, hais huge form gradually relaxed, and he slunk away into the darkness. Peal after, peal of thunder now shook- the earth--and'.the clouds suddenly rolling away, there appeared, winging his flight to. wards her, an angel form, and with a smiling face he whispered as he passed, "Mother! thus hast thou saved thy children from the FOR- GER'S CURSE 1"She fixed -her gaze upon his upward flight, until his  brightness seemed a brilliant point in the sky, and, when she awoke, the evening star was shining full in her face! Their journey back to New York'as performed in almost total silence. Mr. Charles De-Lislelat immersed in thought by his sister's side-and she, with her lefden weight of grief, thought of, her child- ren and her husband. When they reached the depot he declined accompanying her home, but told her to say to St. George he would see him at his counting room, at twelve o'clock noon, of that day. He then bade her a cold adieu, and was lost amid the crowd. The grey light of morning was stealing over the city as she entered the chamber where her husband was lying, but .bot asleep; and, on throwing herself down- by the bed-side, she exclaimed: "Thank God, St. George. We are saved;-we are savedi"' The feelings of the poor wretch can be more easily imagined than described, as she recited how she had succeeded. In a faint, but gentle voice, he thanked her, saying, she "' was the one that had saved him, and it would ever be remembered." Then, cowering down, as if afraid of the approaching day-light, he wrapped the bed clothes around and over hinm, and groaned in utter and complete' prostration. A few minutes afterwards the mother was in the nursery with her children, fondly caressing them. The little things-their loving eyes full of wonder at their mother's absence, and now this early visit- never before seemed so dear to her. In turns they threw their arms around her, and covered her with kisses. At last, little Willie, eager to make some out-of-the-way demonstration of affection, after dipping, his tiny hands into a basin of water laid them upon her forehead, saying, '; Mamma dot a headache?--me tool her head!" and, as she gazed into his sweet face, it seemed as though -the lineaments of the angel in her dream, were again before her. i   TE    CURSE ^F  O "  F3 CHAEPT   ER I:T I A  r twelve o'clo ck, punctua tohis appointment, M r. 'ha rles D e Lisle entered the counting room of hisbrother . The wo men looked into eac  h others' face for a moment, without speaking,-at length Charles broke ou1t: lSo St Geore! you have succeeded in dissipating the money of the family and stabbing into its reputation, too. Ithink thedevil must have gotten possession of you!" "I fear he has, Charles ; " was the reply, in a mournful voice. "One question now, St. George I Docs that paper contain a list of all those accursed notes?" It does " was the answer in c a tone that to gainsay its truth was impossible. :We must then get to work at once;" was the rejoinder. down and write to each of the holders of those notes that, having come unxpectedly into apossssion of funds, you will esli the obliga- tions if presented immediately. There is a pressure in the money market, as I know to my sorrow, for I had to sariace terribly, some of father's stock-and the greedy fellows will be glad enough to have Letter after lette r was dispatched; and note after note presented, nd the sums paid. Mr. Duval himself brought the note upon which andthe discvery had been made, and kindly advised with the hrothels. He told them A* but few knew of it-and that they, though shocked and grieved, felt kindly towards St. George and pitied him." Before the clock struck three, the pile was complete, lying on the desk before them. Charles stretched out his hand, and taking the notes placed them in his pocket-book, saying": I must hand these over to father:" then buttoning up his coat, he prepared to leave. "St George, you had better give up your present business. Indeed it seemz9to me you must. Father told me to say that, under no circumstance will he ever assist you againe Good bye :" and the man,of few words, and hard heart,' walked steadily out intothhe street, passing without notice the mystified  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7696-00000015"/> a32   .ST. GiOBG. DE L1SE; on, clerks in the outer room, who wondered in low tones to each other-  What the deuce was up our governor seems mighty fush to day.', That night Mr. and Mrs. DeLis were again alone. Several of the children remained in the drawing room after tea, and their playthings lay scattered about the flo. Both re silent neither wishing communicate the sad tho ghts that re uppermost in their mainds Raising her eyes they fell Ppo. an old picture which was one that had been over a contury in her father's family, and which represented afl incident in its history. It represented an interruption of a bridal ceremony' The fair girl in bridal robes there-pictured was hergreat-grandmother, and the cos. tume of the whole group was quaint and old-fashioned. The lady  had been betrothed to -her great-grand father, who at that time was an younger son, -with little in, prospect, a soldier, and belonging to a regiment stationed in India., A wealthy-and titled suitor presented and she was led to the hymeneal altar compliantto her father's wises'. A  bishop in full canonicals, had proceeded some distance in the cere. mony and had just repeated "If any man can show just cause, why they may not lawfully be joined together, let him now speak,"-when  from the hall a manly voice shouted, it I can and will,even at the p'int of my good sdArd!" and in rushed the soldierlover; and the bride,  throwing herself into his arms, was borne triumphantly' away. The thoughts of her own bridal-and now she was far away from her father larnd.-:arose to her memory. Her luasband's. famil 'all  estranged, and he a  guilty, disgraced man,-and she turned in the direction where he sat, looking so forlorn and hearthroken, that her eyes wateredr with tears Just then the door- of the room opened, and old Mr. De Lisle came tottering inf e isi trembling limbs could scarcely sustain him His thite hair fell over his shoulders, and in q uivelring accents, he asked: "Where is St. George,? where is my n?', St. George could not- answer, and he looked towards where he satS. St.  eorge O and a flush of anger rose -in his; face "is this all, true? Miserable boy  how could you. thus act? You have,.killed your old father; but from 'this moment I  consider you. no longer my son'! and -turning round he slowly left theroom,and hoduse, r     THE CURSK OF THE FORGER.         3 as a train arrived, suddenly resolved to go himself to New York. Immediately after his arlival he drove to St, George's house; anda,  ill an hour's time, was now again on his way back to Hudson.  The next day he took'to his bed, and in a few wee'ks more 'he losed his eyes in death. Before h died, he, miade a n' W111i, in which his expressed intentions towards St. George er6ea ea'ed out. The blackness of darkness seemed ithoettle around the 'fate df St. George De Lisle. A few months of lWgglirg, such as the drown- ing man makes who cannot swim--and the five days' wonder of New York was, that "the rich De Lisle had failed l' Former friends shrugged their shoulders and said "No wonder; they lived too high ." and when the list of invitations for their next party ids made! out, the De Lisles were forgotten to be included. It does not take the fashionable world long to- forget a family whose steps are treading down into the Valley of Humility--and if they quietly let them pats without assisting their descent by abuse, it is rather the exception than the rule. The mortgage on the house was foreclosed; the bill of sale of the furniture entered up-; and, almost penniless; with an aching heart, IDe Lisle sought refuge with his family on the second floor of a small'house in an: obscure street, lying in a part of the city -of which'the family had scarcely known the existence. Thus they lived -Mr. De Lisle seeking employment, day after day, without finding any I Hope grew faint within him. He now feared every one knew his fatal secire't-- and as day, closedin after day, and he could get nothing to do-his brow" lowered and face paled with suffering and anguish. He would mutter words to himself, as he walked through the stieets asking for any kind of work-the wreck of the once envied St. George De Lisle. The "Curse of the Forger" was on hiin.  His wife did all she could-she worked hard and saved all she knew how to do. But the little they had grew daily less; article after article, of dress and furniture, was sold, and now the Demoni'hunger began to stare them in the face. Matters were at this dismal pass when, one night just as it was grow- ing dark, their little girl came'in, saying her father had given her at the door, four dollars to hand- to mamma and to say, '"That he would not  be home that night, as he was going to Hudson to see Uncle Edward." De Lisle had met an old clerk of his whom he had 'prevailed upon to lend him five dollars; four of which 6'e ttus appropriated;, aiKd ^   &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7696-00000016"/> 34        .ST,. GEGRGE De LISLE. with part of the fifth, he bought a second-class-ticket to Hudson. The day had been hot and sultry, but rain was falling when he arrived, and, as it was so unseasonable an hour he hesitated, now that he was a poor man; to wake up his brother's family. He walked for along time about the streets-those streets where he had played wie an 'ocent boy. Oh, little did he then dream that he should e'er b  what he now- was--a man branded, like Cain with a sense of in/k His whole life passed in review efore him;-and he wandered on and on, until he found himself far on the road to the grave yard where his dear mother lay buried, and by her side that father whose last look upon him had been so stern and unfor- giving. He climbed the enclosure and approached where they lay in an elevated portion of the ground. He then crawled, all dripping and wet, close to the side where his mother lay, and rested himself upon the mound. Oh, how he longed, as he used when la boy, to lay his tired, aching head upon her bosom, and be soothed by her gentle hand. But the storm, which he had scarcely noticed gathering thicker and blacker, now broke in surly vengeance overhead. The heavens are all a-flamne, and peal after peal of thunder shakes the earth. Oh, what a blinding flash is that Hdown comes a thunderbolt-whizzing as it falls, and, in a twinkling of time, it is all over. De Lisle, is dead!- struck by'lightning alongside his mother's grave, About a week afterwards a letter from her busband's relatives, sealed with black, containing a hundred dollar note and. the sad infor- mation of his death and burial in the family lot,. at Hudson, reached' Mrs. De Lisle. She was now alone, with her children. The cold heartless wol l1 was before her; and she revolved many plans in her mind, as to what she could do to keep them, and herself,' from- starving. In a more comfortable house than that in which we left them, but far away up town beyond the fashionable precincts,-at work, day and night, over a sewing machine, may be observed'sitting at a window, a tall and stately but sorrowful looking woman. Notwithstanding" her employment there is a regal air about her which cannot fail to inspire respect. Reader, that was once, the "Lady Adelaide Harriet Mowhriay "-- and she whom the fashionable New York world knew as the elegant Mrs. St. George De. Lisle I    &#xD;<pb n="36 (Illustration) -37" xml:id="VAC7696-00000017"/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
