<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7482">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lost Will </title>
            <author>Porter, A. E. (1816-1898)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC7482</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1935</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lost will</title>
                  <author>Porter, A. E. (1816-1898)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>294 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>H. Hoyt</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1860">[1860]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-01-16">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The lost will</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7482-00000001"/>   THE LOST WILL.  BY ANN E. PORTER. "By grace are ye saved, through faith, and that not of your- selves, it is the gift of God."--PAUL. BOSTON: HENRY HOYT. No. 9 Cornhill.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7482-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1860, by   Printed by Entered , n     t y , y   ilTHE LOST WILL.  INTRODUCTORY CfTA      E. 'NOT many years ago there was a curious old escretoire sold at Wne of the furnit r e auction shops in Boston.   It was during the antiquarian feer, when everybody was seeking for relies of olden time, that this piece of :furniture attracted the atten- tion of an old gentleman whose tastes led him in that direction. He gave orders to have it repaired and cleaned, and was present when the workman, on taking out the drawers, discovered a secret compartment which contained some time-worn, yellow papers. The workman threw them down, as of no  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7482-00000003"/> fc     'I'k"THE LOST WILL.  Value, but the old gentleman picked them up nd carried them home. One leisure day he sat down to e;amine them, and was gratified at seeing the familiar lame of a gentleman whom he had known many years before as a member of the legal profession, and highly esteemed by a large cir- ele of friends. Farther investigation proved that these pa- pers were valuable, and that great inquiry had  been made for them after the death of the owner. The discovery of them led me to make a journey to one of the hill-towns of Vermont, to take the deposition of an aged woman, who was ! said to have some lknowlef-ge of these papers, and of the family history of the owner. It was late one Saturday evening when I got out of the cars at a small station about one milefrom-the village. I was doubtful where to direct my steps, as'the keeper of the station informed me there was no inn or any public house of entertainment. Seeing my hesitation,   THE LOST WILL.       5 and that I was a stranger, he added, "Maybe they'll take you in at the ' Old Fox Tavern;' 'tain'tno tavern now, though, but Mrs. Seth Fox, she that was Martha Slade, lives there, and in the summer time she takes boarders from Boston. You can try there, and I'll send my boy to show you the road and carry your valise." It was a fine Autumn evening, and the scenery wonderfully beautiful and attractive; the corn was just ready for the sickle, the orchards were loaded with fruit, the hills green to their sum- mits and-dotted with sheep. The walk of a mile seemed very short with such beauty on every hand. The house, which appeared to have been an inn of some importance in its day, (if one might judge by the barns and stables,) looked very tidy and inviting to a weary stranger. The boy- led the way into a large square room which must have been formerly used as a bar-room, for the bar itself remained, and the pipes and faucet through which formerly the  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7482-00000004"/> 6      THE LOST WILL. strong beer ascended from the ample hogshead in- the cellar beneath. But now books and papers occupied the shelves, and nothing to drink was to be seen, save some water in a large stone pitcher, which was flanked by two beer glasses.- The floor was white and sanded, and a fire was burning on the ample hearth. Mrs. Fox met us here, a comely matron of middle age, who willingly admitted us is a guest, when she learned that we wished to re- main over Sunday, that we might attend to our business on the first day of the week. I re- marked that the house and especially the room, reminded me of the good old days of slow trav- elling and country taverns. "Yes," said she;, we have kept the house pretty much as it was formerly. My husband has, a great fancy for this room, and allows no alterationfrom what it used to be in his uncle's time; and almost every evening through the year, he has a little fire made on the hearth, and Smokes his pipe and reads the newspaper.   I         'THE LOST WILL.      7 But perhaps you would prefer the parlor, sir ;" and she opened the door into a handsomely fur- nished, modern looking room. I thanked her, but preferred to remain where I was, which I did, until called to supper into a large, old fashioned dining-room, where I found a most tempting repast- chickens, light biscuit, berries, &amp;c., &amp;c. I sat on at my window that evening, look- ing up at a noble mountain which reared its head high up towards heaven, and from that to the brook' which flowed at its feet, sparkling in the moonlight, as it run on through a fine rich meadow. How quietly I slept that night, and what a change from the noisy, dusty city, which I had left that morning! I was somewhat disappointed in the morning to learn that there would be no preaching that day on account of the absence of their minister, for I had seen the meeting-house on the hill, and had fancied that I should hear one of the good, old-fashioned sermons, from one who was aatue a  artor to this flock on the hills. iI -\   ,  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7482-00000005"/> 1'T it LOST WILL. We shall have a deacon's meeting," said Mrs. Fox, and I think perhaps you may enjoy it, for our deacon is one of the best men in this world, and I never hear him pray but I think of the passage- "It is good to be here"' - Notfithstanding whit Mrs. Fox said, I was hal tempted t remain at home, and read by my open window, or go up the mountain with my Bible, and-read there the Psalms of David. ( But I am t church goe both from habit and principle, so that when the' bell- sent its sweet summons over the hills, I went up with the fam- ily to the house of God. The deacon was a fine portly man of sixty- five or nGore, with a large head and features rather coarsely cut by nature, but full of intel- ligence and goodness. The expression of his face won my interest ati once, and when he prayed I also said in my teart- Iris good to be here." He wasp evidently an educated man, fr his language was choice and his ac- cent good. In the afternoon they held the Sunday   THE LOST WILL.       9 school, and here the deacon was superintend- ent. In this capacity also he seemed like one who had heard his Master say, "Feed my lambs," and the lambs themselves seemed de- lighted to follow his voice.  in the evening, as in almost all country vil- lages, there was a conference meeting, the sub- ject being given out by the pastor the Sunday previous. This evening it was the "'New Birth." I shall never forget the deacon's re- marks on that subject. He spoke as one who had felt the burden of sin himself, and who, like Pilgrim, had quaked beneath Mount Sinai, and exclaimed, "Woe is me; for I am un- done ;" who had struggled to justify himself by the works, of the law, but had learned at last what Jesus meant when he said, "I am the way, the truth and the life." There was the sweetness of humility and the dignity of the Christian combined, and howev- er talented the minister might be, I for one was satisfied that he was absent. That very evening I learned that the deacon X +, . , - ,   &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7482-00000006"/> 10      THEir  LOST WILL. was the lawyer to whom I was directed for as- sistance in my investigations, and that the old lady that I came to visit, was in the very house where I was staying. She was unable to leave her room from age and infirmity, but her mind was-tIar, and her memory good. I rmained in Westhrook a week, and gradually, by conversing only a little while at a time with her, I gleaned the following incidents which I have thrown together in the form of a narra- tive.   CHAPTER I. THERE is no prettier village in New Eng- land than Westhrook, a quiet little place at the foot of Eagle Mountain. This mountain is the highest peak of a- short range connected with the Green Mountains. This range is a spur of those higher hills which give Vermont its name, and which are so justly celebrated for. their greenness and beauty. Westhrook was so called from a fine little trout stream, which, flowing from an ever-iv- ing spring, hidden like a great diamond in the mountains, comes dancing and laughing ,over the pebbles, and through the maple woods, but more quietly across the big meadow, till grownt quite sedate, like a young bride at the altar, it loses its virgin name in the broad Connecticut. Westhrook is a farming village, and, at the  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7482-00000007"/> 12     THE LOST WILL. time my story commences, the principal build- ings, aside from, the little one-story farm- houses, were the large meeting-house on Strawherry Hill, the little red school-house in Green Lane, the tavern, a two-story building, painted white, with a large sign, bearing on one side a picture of Washington, and on the other the representation of a fox. The latter was quite a tolerable painting, considering it was executed by a young Westhrook genius, who had never been out of his own State, or received any instruction in the art. But he -had hunted foxes often, and as he drew and :i ^5iinted from a specimen which he had himself taken in a trap, and was aided by a natural taste, with a large share of imitatiq  the spec- tator was almost led to believe, as he looked at the sign, that the cunning animal had proposed to sit for his own portrait. It was the gray fox, called by naturalists (Canis cinereo) - the gray coat and bushy tail were well represented, but that it was no fancy sketch, an acquaintance wyould know, for  -Is *-w - . ' -,* V 5 --     TH)U LOST WILL.        (-  i3 the fur was shaded gradually darker, till upon the hip-and shoulders it became a very deep gray ; then the sharp head and the little black- ish gray triangle upon it, which gives such a droll expression to the face, were not forgotten. On the whole, this sign was the pride of the owner, and the admiration of all the boys in the village. But a stranger, on riding through the place, and seeing the grave visage of our re- vered Washington on one side of the sign and sly Reynard on the other, was led to wonder what was indicated thereby. Now a-days, when travellers purses are so cunningly emp- tied at our fashionable hotels, the emblem would only be considered a candid confession, but in those anti-railroad times, our country taens s were in reality places of entertainment and rest, and Westhrook tavern was one of the most orderly and well-kept houses on the stage. road from Windsor to Boston. No sooner did a gentleman draw rein at the door, than the landlord himself hastened to wait upon his guest, but if a lady was of -the party, he irUae &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7482-00000008"/> "     THE LOST WILL. diately ushered her with his best bow into the parlor, and then opening another -door would say, "M/rs. Fox," when a comely matron made her appearance, and at once, by her kind, gen- tle manner, made the stranger feel as if the inn were a home. Mrs. Fox! aye! that was the secret of the sign; Fox's tavern was known throughout the region. For fifty years it had retained the name, the son succeeding to the father and keeping up the reputation of the house. It is known no more now, for the railroad runs one mile to the east of Westhrook, and there is now no- inn in the village, but I am told the sign is still in ex- istence in the garret of the old tavern. The Post Office was in a small building ad- joining Fox's, and this completes' the list of public buildings in the village. The most im- posing house was 'Squire Dennie's -it was a large white building, two stories high, with dormer windows, and stood on a slight eleva- tion, with a very deep yard in front. There were some fine large elms in the yard, and a ;!:1   I        THE LOST WILL.       15 row of sagar maples, beside cinnamon roses, li- I  Dlacs, snow balls and syringas. Squire Dennie was reputed rich. He owned a meadow farm, and a great deal of pasture land on the hills;  then he was considered the best lawyer in the county, and had more business than he could well find time for. Then he was not a hard man as country lawyers are apt to be; but easy, good-natured, sociable with all his neigh- bors, and trusted by them, so that he oftenpre- vented a law-suit, when'his purse might have gained by the opposite course. Still his wealth increased, and he was called by all his friends a lucky man. As he grew older he became quite corpulent, owing perhaps to his spending most of his time either in his office, or riding in his chaise; but his health was good, and no family made a finer appearance on Sunday, in the old-fashioned square pew, than 'Squire Dennie with his wife and four children. X He had business in the adjoining towns which often called him away from home; but though these absences were frequent he nevi:X 4   &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7482-00000009"/> 16      THE LOST WILL. returned without meeting his group of little ones at the gate, all- eager to greet him, and the little girls to secure a seat beside him, and ride. up the drive-way. The least deimonstrative among the children was his oldest boy, George Dennie. George was a quiet, handsome lad, with a fair complexion, brown hair and blue eyes, He was his father's favorite, and it was' a common remark of the neighbors --"If that boy was like most children he would be ruined, for he is always allowel his own way."  His way was never thwarted by his parents, and the children seeing this indulgence in their parents, naturally followe heir example. George was a sedate boy for his years, having little interest in the common sporty of boys; he seldom play- ed ball, or " wolf," or hoop, or any of the ac- tive amusements in which children so much de- light. But he never refused a game of mar- bles, and would sometimes spend hours in this way, while chequers backgammon, and all quiet games of chance or- skill had always a charm for him.               -   ?  THE LOST WILL.       IT A :::fg; As he never failed to beat, his sister Mitry, the only one of the children old enough to play with him, would sometimes say- "Please, George, don't ask me; ,you know you'll beat, and I don't like always to come off conquered." "You'll only learn to be the better player," he would reply; "come, father is going to play a game with me this evening, and I want to practise so as to beat him -I did once last week." Now   Mary understood chequers, and was quite skilful at the game, but somehow, she said, George always beat; if she looked off the board a minute, or if mother called her away an instant, George was sure to get into her king row; she didn't know how it was, fI but there whs no fun in playing with one that always beat." 'Squire Dennie had great hope that George would study law, and take his place and busi- ness when old age should overtake him. He had already made some progress in his studies, and was called the most graceful speaker in the     .P  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7482-00000010"/> 18     T'I&amp;H LOST WILL. public school. He also understood farming very wel, and was able to assist his father in the management of the land. When he was fourteen years old he was fitted for college, but his father preferred to keep him with him-. an- other year. "Then my boy for college, and I shall expect great things from you," "I will be at the head of my class, or I'll not graduate at all," said George. "Tut, tut," said his father; " don't be so ambitious as that, or you may ruin yourself; no, no; do the best you can and be satisfied. There, run over and ask Fox to lend me five hundred dollars; it's strange that with all my business, I'm always out of money. I have thousands and thousands owing me, and no se- curity. I am determined to go to work imme- diately, and set my, affairs in order." Ge0ge runs over to the tavern, and in a moment, the landlord, smiling and happy as ever, is indhe office. "Willing to lend you the money, 'Squire; happen to have it on hand -but, you'll excuse ,    i   .  ."  THE LOST WILL.      19 me if I want security. Not but what I'd trust you as soon as any man, and sooner too, but it's always best to be on the safe side." "All right, friend," said the 'Squire ; "what security will you require?" "Suppose you give me a mortgage on that pasture joining my wood lot?" , "Very well," said the complaisant 'Squire; and the mortgage was duly drawn and signed. The 'Squire was altogether too easy about his own affairs; he knew that his business was extensive, and that there must be a large sur- plus every year, after his family expenses were defrayed, but he often repeated the remark to George - "We must look into things, and straighten affairs; if I should die it would be a difficult matter for any one to do this." As he said this, he thought of his own vig- orous health- "Only I have too much body, George--I do not like to carry so much weight- I must exercise more." The next morning after making this remark he set off on his semi-annual visit to the county&#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7482-00000011"/> 20      THE LOST WILL,   K  town, where he had a large number:of cases in court. The court was in session some weeks; the lawyers boarded at -ne hotel, where the landlord prided himself on his fine- djmners. The temperance cause had made little progress then, and wine was always an accompaniment to the table. Moreover a social glass was taken at other times. 'Squire&amp;Dennie had just been made Juctge, and he had to drink congratulations with all his friends at court. He was social and hospitable himself, and forgot that there was too much fuel already in his system; that high-seasoned food, and spir- ituous liquors were only the match to combus- tible materM. But he was in fine spirits, eve- rything seemed to prosper with him, and when he turned his horse's head homewards, and rode slowly and comfortably in his easy chaise, he said to himself-- I'm a lucky fellow-got the best business of the county, and am Judge at forty. Who knows but I may run for Con- gress next year?"   :1   i,:;  1'l THE LOST WILL.    21 It was a delightful road, and the season one of the pleasantest of the year. October frosts and suns had changed the green of the trees to scarlet and gold, and painted the apples, and ripened the products of field and orchard. 'Squire Dennie thought of his own farm and meadow lands, and, satisfied with his home, stopped his horse a moment, as he came to the summit of the hill, (for roads in those days never went round or avoided the hills) from whence he had a view of Westhrook, nestled at the foot of Eagle Mountain which protected it I as a loving mother her children.  "Home i again!" he said to himself; " hope Bessie and the children are well. Get up Billie ;" and he applied the whip gently to his favorite. His return from court was always quite an event in the family, not only because his ab- sence was always regretted, but because he never failed to bring them all some substantial token of his remembrance. This evening they waited somewhat impa- tiently; they had expected him by four o'clock,  A  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7482-00000012"/> 22      THE LOST WILL.  but another hour passed and-he did Inot come. The supper was prepared butz remailed untast- ed. The sun went down behind the mountain, and yet they waited in vain for the familiar sound of Billie's quickened trot, as he neared his own stable.      6 Mrs. Dennie was a calm, quiet woman, not easily alarmed; but she bade George run over and see if Mr. Fox had heard anything from the court.  es; Mr. Fox himself had come from there that day. The 'Squire's horse was harnessed, and was standing at the door, while the 'Squire himself was stopping to take a part- ing glass with a friend. ' I shall be at home by four o'clock,' he said, as I le ft." Mr. Fox had been busy with his guests, and supposed that the 'Squire was already with his family' Now, indeed, there was some little anxiety, but, supposinig4at he had been detained by these :f:iends longer than he intended, Mrs. Deniie gave the children their supper, and, putting the blaby to bed, sat down with her   -i .T/'G'iE LOST WILL      ' 23 three children to await the coming of her hus- band. But as the darkness increased, her anx- iety became greater, and her kind neighbor, Mr. Fox, began to wonder at the 'Squire's delay. His wife, who hal one of those large, good hearts, big enough to feel sympathy for all in trouble, came into the bar-room about nine o'clock, and said to her husband, "Joe, I am worried about the 'Squire; I shan't sleep to-pight if he don't come. Suppose you harness old Gray, and ride a piece up the hill-road." Mr. Fox laughed.  "Why, wife, do you think the 'Squire has been waylaid and rob- bed?"  "No,'no," she replied; ' but I feel just as if you'd better go; and John, you go with your father." "To protect me from the robbers?" said her husband. Mrs. Fox did not smile, but answered grave- ly, "I cannot tell why I wish you to go, Mr. Fox; they are all anxious over at the house, but George. He tells his mother there's no!  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7482-00000013"/> 24"     THE -LOST -WILL.  , need of worrying; his fither i: i  when he gets ready ; but I know-the p'o"fomian is getting dreadfully nervous. You will go, won't you, Joe? ' "Yes, yes wife; in five minutes. John, bring the wagon round, and we'll ride up )he road a piece." Two hours after this the kind-hearted Mrs. Fox had a sad duty to perform. Her husband had not started a moment too early; the 'Squire had fallen from his carriage in an apoplectic fit i The patient horse stood by the side of the road, waiting in vain for his master to as- :Aside the reins. There were some signs of life in the fallen man, but he was not able to speak, and appeared insensible to what was going on around him. 'They bore him slowly home, while Mrs. Fox tried to prepare his family for the sad event. The village doctor shook his head gravely, as he examined his patient there was no hope, for the eyes were insensible to t, speech was gone, and the only life perceptible was in the hard, irregular breathing.   THE LOST WILL.      . 25 He: :remodl some hours in this state, when unexpectley to every one, he seemed to rally a little, and appeared to recognize George, who was standing near him at the moment. There was a murmuring sound as if le made an effort to speak, and the doctor, whose ear was close to the patient, recognized the words-"4My son-- care-- mother children." It was a charge to George, and was all he could do to show his confidence in him. The doctorsupposed that this rallying gave hope of life, but it was only the flickering of the dying candle. Before sunrise the husband and father was robed for the grave, and lay in the large, cold parlor, silent and unconscious of the deep grief which had fallen thus suddenly on his household.     .    ' &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7482-00000014"/> CHAPTER II. GEORGE DENNIE sat alone in his father's of- fice, the third day after the funeral. His mother had not yet recovered from the first stupor of grief-- from that 'crushing sense of desolation, which follows a great sorrow. The community sympathized deeply in this afflic- tion, and friends from far and near came with kind words of consolation,  Among others, Gov. Berry, a nhe-hearted man, who filled most worthily his high station, and who had been a warm friend of 'Squire Dennie, did not forget the family in their be- reavement. He lived in the town of B--, not many from- 'Westhrook. He was a man of ath,:;nd--shis fine mansion, and well cultivat- ed grounds were the admiration of all who saw   1 '. THE LOST' WILL.      27 He came into the office, and finding George X i, alone, patted him  gently on the shoulder- "Well, my boy, we must bear with resigna- tion the trouble which God sends. It is hard to lose a father; quite as hard, perhaps, for a father to part from beloved children. I have lost two as noble boys as a father could desire to possess and now in my old age, I have but one wee lamb left-my little Nellie--God bless her! And she is so frail and delic:  that I tremble lest, some rough wind bear herx away from me. I am come now to persuade your mother to let me take you; not to glve you away, that would be too great a gift. But I will supply your father's place; will superin- tend your studies till you are through college, and have completed your law e6 in my of- flee. What say you to this plan?' The boy's eyes brightened, his ambition could desire no more, and he readily-acquiesed in the plan if his mother's' consent could be gained. "Perhaps," said the good man, it will be=-  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7482-00000015"/> 28      THE LOST WILL., i  best to propose no changes t-her ju t yet, but now that I have gained your consent, I will call again in two weeks." Thus the matter stood. George, meanwhile, pleased with his future, and resolved that no obstacle should prevent his acceptance of the Governor's offer. Again he was alone in the office, but this time agitated with contending feelings. On m^ ^^tiinm ation of his father's affairs, it was found ?ail hHere would be but little remaining after -:-Oe payment of the debts. As is too often the ease, the family must suffer because the father had neglected his own, affairs ini his attention to the business of others. The kind-hearted and shrewd Mr. Fox explained to George how matters stood, and had given him the following advice: "Now, ny boy, is a chance to exert yourself, and show your mother that the son -can in. a measure, supply the father's place. If you can only manage to pay off some of these mortgages, you can save a fine farm for your family. I have looked into matters close- - .'                 ,     '- THE LOST WILL.     29 ly; :one thousand paid down in the course of three years, will do all that is required. I will wait longer for my own pay.' "But how am I toet that thousand," said George. "Aye, aye, my boy; an old fox like myself is too shrewd not to find a way, if you will find a will. My boy Sam you know has been in the shoe business in Boston. He has received five hundred dollars per year and board; he is . now promoted and has one thousand. I can " secure you his place, and I calculate that by the third year, you too can have a thousand-- you are smarter naturally than my boy, though God be thanked, he is a better son than I deserve. Now what do you say? The place    : is) kept vacant for you till next week. You : see,as I reckon, you can manage to clear the thousand in three years easily, and then your mother can feel that herself and Uttle ones are provided for. I would do better for you if I could, ut I do little more myself than make both -ends meet." &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7482-00000016"/> 30      THE LOST WILL. George thanked Mr. Fox, for-his offered kindness, and said he would think about it. "Well Joe, what did George say?" was Mrs. Fox's first question on the return of her husband. "He didn't say whether he would or wouldn't," said her husband, "I gave him till next week to think of it. I suppose the poor fellow feels his father's death so deeply that he is hardly himself." "Well, I don't know about that," said his wife. "I should think he'd jump at the chance to help llis mother in that way. Sam says there are fifty boys now that are ,ready and would be thankful to take his place. George Dennie is not so great a favorite with me as he is with most folks. He's handsome, that's cer- tain; and his pretty face and soft voice takes wonderfully with some, but to my mind hand- some is that handsome does; and if George Dennie don't take up with this chance, I shall rub him out of my books. "Don't be hard on the boy; wait and see."     i!::i:     THE LOST WILL.       3 Meanwhile George sat in the office, leaning his head on his hand in deep thought -an ex- pression of contempt curled his pretty lips. "Shoe business! so, so, I'm to go into the shoe business, and be second best to Sam Fox, a clumsy, homely fellow, that never went be- yond the rule of three in arithmetic, and is too mean, or pious, or whatever he calls it, to drink a glass of wine or smoke a cigar! Shan't It have a nice time of it with him? And then all my earnings save my board and clothes, must go to clear ofF these hateful mortgages. . hat benefit will all this be to me?-it will take every cent to support my mother and .the chil- dren. Quite a contrast to the life I shall have at the Governor's," and the vision of the Gov- ernor's house and gardens rose up before'him. There was a gardener to keep the grouXffiaif . order, and a man of all work in the hoisee, professional cook, (and George was fond of the: table, perhaps from the too great indulgence of his mother,) and there were two or three fine horses in the stable.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7482-00000017"/> 32     THE LOST WILL, "I shall not even have to brush my own boots," he said to himself. ' "I mean to go to Yale or Cambridge -for I don't suppose the Governor will care if it does cost more; they say he's as rich as Croesus. He said he'd take me through college, and then let me study faw in his office - and perhaps, who knows, he may do more for me still; he's only that one sickly child, always on the couch,when I have seen her. Yes; I'll go to the Governor's. It's too good a chance to throw away."'  Then the vision of his weeping mother rose up before him. With-what agony had she wruag her hands that morning and exclaimed "What shall we "to?  Oh, George; if we could only pay all the debts! There must not one debt remain  to sully your father's memory." Then, too, came the dying words of his fath- er: 4 My son, take care -of your mother and the children." He seemed to hear that voice again from the grave; even then he almost 'fancied his father sat in the large, leather-covy /        ;iJ       ' THE LOST WILL.       33 ered chair, at the table, and as he looked gravely and kindly upon him, repeat those words. George was not then hopelessly selfish j -the partiality of his parents, and the indul- gence of the whole family had tended to foster that feeling; but now if he would but'listen to the still, small voice, that whispered to him- "Honor thy father and thy mother." "Seek not your own, but the interests of your family," he might conquer this fault, and become a wor- thy son, and a true man. Now was the time to seek wisdom from above, but George forgot to do that--he was ' doubt and perplexity. It was hard to yield afuture that promised so bright, for years of toil that would bring little benefit to him save the consciousness of having done a noble deed, and -saved his mother from - anxiety, perhaps want. -Would that he might pray now -  this Is the first important step of his life-it may decide his destiny forever. It seemed almost as if an angel were there, whispering to him; for there came for a  moment, a  picture before his eyes,  q                 &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7482-00000018"/> 34      THE LOST WILL. *         ; of their pleasant home staved, of a grateful j mother and happy  children. And "Our    i George has done it," from a mother's 1,s.   : Yes; I will live for them. I an strong and  healthy. I will take my father's place, and my mother shall never know want or toil." This response was trembling on his lips, when Jeff. Devoll entered the office, and seated him- self in the vacant arm-chair by the table -the very one in which George had almost fancied he had seen his father a momient before. A cold chill ran through his frame for an instant, as he glanced at Devoll, but it passed away the moment the latter spoke. Devoll was a young lawyer who had studied for a while in "Squire Dennie's office, and as Mr. Fox said, ' Was  just cut out for a lawyer, for he knows no -con- science only his client's interest, and measures right and wrong only by the amount of his fee." He was tall and heavy, but loosely built, with a large head, which looked unnaturally so, from the great mass of black, coarse hair   THE LOST WILL.      35 that surmounted it. He had a fierce black eye, thick lips and high cheek bones. 'Squire Den- nie never liked him, but he was once, heard to say that the man carried his credentials in his face, and if any trusted Devoll it was because they were too stupid to read Nature's hand- writing. But Devon was getting business and had gained some causes which increased his reputation for shrewdness and talent. He was even known while pleading the cause of some orphan children to be so overcome with emo- tion as to be unable to proceed. To be sure it was not known till years afterwards that the large amount which he thus secured for them was wholly in his own bands, and while he made twenty per cent. upon it, he gave them only five. , "Come, cheer up, George," he said, pleas- antly; " don't kill yourself, moping for what can't be helped--haI what's this! an unfin- "ished game?" he said, as he cast his eyes upon a chess-board which lay upon the table. "Yes; Governor Berry proposed a game it *     '   &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7482-00000019"/> 36      sTHEL LOST WILL-. the other day, and we had played an hour when he was called away." "Ah, indeed; I wonder if I may venture to take His Honor's place --he's generally on the winning side." "He said when he left, that I would surely beat him, and laughed as he added, I'll re- treat with honor now.' " "Ah, indeedI then I shall have a poor chance; but, what do you say to finishing the game? I'll do my best." A strange thought flashed into George's mind; suppose I decide this matter by chess? Devoll shall be governor, and if he wins I am for college and the life of a gentleman; if I win I'll be John Fox's clerk." Now George well knew when he said this to himself, that Devoll was always considered a poor player, and that in their games seldom came out victor - never, when George, put forth all his skill; therefore he thought he was very magnanimous, and was listening to the voice of conscience.   TIlHE LOST WILL.     387 They commenced playing, and had been busily engaged for some time, when Lucy F-ox entered. She was a beautiful child of ten, a genuine little fairy, always overflowing with fun and good nature, and withal so gentle and loving, ready to weep at suffering, and so  B quick to laugh in joy, that without being at all - conscious of it herself, she was a general favor- ite in the Neighborhood. "Mother sent me over here, Mr. Devoll, to tell you that old Mr. Shipman, of Grafton, is waiting to see you." "A man of dollars, and therefore must not be kept waiting; excuse me a moment, George, I'll not be gone long," and he depart- ed hastily, while Lucy lingered at George's side. "Don't you want to learn to play, Lucy?" said George. "No, Georgie; mother says that she hopes none of her children will like games. I don't know about this game, with such queer look- ing red and white images, but chequers and  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7482-00000020"/> 88      THE LOS4WILL,. backgammon and  cards she dislikes very much. You know some men waste a great deal of time in the bar-room, and sometimes they play for money, and sometimes for spirit; and they often get very noisy and troublesome. Mother was so afraid that Sam would like to tplay cards, that she make him promise he would never touch one, and he says now he is so glad, for he has seen hundreds ruined by ito. "You talk very wise, Lulu, for a little girl." "Do I, Georgie?  Well, now, I want to whisper something in your ear," 4 "I should like to have you, Lulu." "Here the'n," and she drew near and put- ting her little chubby arms round his neck, whispered - "Don't play with Jeff. Devoll.' "Why not, Lulu?" "Hush! don't speak loud; he'll hear us."  Oh, no he won't; see, he is talking with Mr. Shipman, in the tavern porch." "But he' does hear everything anybody says; when mother says anything about Jeff,  she talks in a whisper."  so; . , s   THE LOST WILL.      39 "But, why mustn't I play with him, Lulu?" "Because he'll beat you, George; and you know you do not like that." ";'What makes you think he'll beat me, Lulu?" "Because he plays this game so much." "What, chess?" / "Is this chess?" "Yes." "Well, it's the same as this; he plays ever so much with old 'Squire Powers." "And can he beat the 'Squire?" "Yes; becamse 'Squire Powers bought a bottle of wine to pay, he said, and he. told father that he believed the devil helped Jeff.; wasn't that wicked?" George turned pale a little; had not Jeff. always told him that he was not learned in the game, and had he not almost always come off second best?" For a moment he resolved not to play the game out-he could now excuse himself. He was still more inclined so to do, when Lucy  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7482-00000021"/> lUt     THE LOST WILL. putting her little hand on his shoulder, said ooaixgly-"Now, Georgie, please not play with Jeff.; stop now, and come with me to the orchard, and get some red-cheeked apples. I can't reach them, but you can, Georgie." George cast a glance at tli board; as the piecee stood, he was sure of beating. "Better stay," he said to himself; "if she only knew, she would wish me so to do." "See here, Lucy," and he went on explain- ing the pieces and their position; "now, you see, Lulu, I shall be victor."  But the child shook hr curly head. "No, no, Georgie; you will not,? am sure you will not; as mother says, sometimes, I feel it all through me that you will not." The instinct of the child was stronger than II any argument, and perhaps her very certainty  appealed to George's selfishness, and in the bottom of his heart he thought, "Well, if Jeff. beats, I shall consider that I'm -bound to the Governor," Just so strange and contrary is the human heart sometimes.   : -   THE LOST WILL.      41 Lucy divined that her words were not hav- ing theLdesired effect, and she took another tack. "Georgie, I should be almost as sorry to have you beat Jeff., as to have him beat you." George opened his eyes in astonishment "What now, Lulu?" ' Why, you see, Georgie, Jeff. likes to beat as well as you do; and he doesn't like to have: anybody excel him; he will not love you as well after it." "Poh! poh, Lucy; do you think I care. whether Jeff. Devoll likes me or not?" At this moment Devoll entered the office and took his seat; "Now  for it, George; I wouldn't have missed this game for a cool hun- dred." Little Lucy stood with her hands clasped before her, looking very earnestly at the play. ers   .  "Come, sit on my knee," said Devoll. "No; I rather not," said Lucy, edging her- self towards George.  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7482-00000022"/> 42   ,  THE LOST WILL.  The latter rose and drew a high-desk chair : towards the stable, and lifted Lucy into it. ] This raised her considerably above the players, and there she sat for two hours looking grave- ly and anxiously down, watching the progress of the game. Had the German painter who designed the celebrated picture, the "Game of Life" been present, he would have pronounced it an admirable tableaux of his design. Jeff. with his fierce looks and disordered hair, and - big, bony hands, might well represent the evil one; and George, ' with his delicate, boyish face and fair hair, the youth who had staked his soul; while the beautiful, earnest face of little Lulu, seemed-like that of the guardian an- gel who would fain draw the youth away.,' Aye! there are angels in our daily paths, t but we know them not. It was two hours or more, as I have said, before the game was finished, and during that time not a word was spoken, save as it related to some move. The players became so absorb- * !   THE LOST 'WILL.      43 ed that they forgot even the presence of Lucy, and as they drew near the conclusion of the game, when, even to her unpractised eye, the game seemed tU be going against George, she sat perfectly still--not a word escaped her, but her hands were clasped more tightly, and had the players have looked at her they would have seen by the fluttering of her dress, that her little heart beat very hard. There were but four pieces on the board-- one move more and the game was decided. i Jeff. made that move, and raised his eyes with a look of triumph. George pushed the board aside and turned to Lulu-two tears were slowly coursing down her cheeks. "Come; Lulu," said he cheerfully; "we'll go now for the apples." She did not answer, but turned to the door, and before he could stop her, she had run, with the speed of a fawn, across the street to her own home. "Devoll, can I see you a minute," said  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7482-00000023"/> "     THE LtST WILL. Chubbs, the sheriff, as he put his head in at the open door. Jeff. left, closing the door behind him. Geore was left alone once more. He walked across the room, saying to himself-"Well, 'my destiny is decided; I'm sure I tried hard enough to turn it." That strange human heart once more. l   CHAPTER m. "YES, my son," said the fond ther, for- getting herself in the happiness other child; "yes, you must go to the Governor's. He is very kind and we must not refuse such an offer. We shall get along some way;" and she comforted herself with bright visions of what her boy would become, surrounded by the advantages of his future home. George did not tell his mother of Mr. Fox's plann- "Surely," he said to himself, "it isn't necessary ; she would never like to see me en- gaged in the shoe business; she has too much pride in me for that." The day of his departure came; it was a sad day for his mother, for her heart yearned over her boy, and the sight of his handsome face was pleasant to her from day to day, more  45 Il  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7482-00000024"/> so now than ever. He had his father's fore- head and eyes, and she trusted that he would in a measure supply his place. Now, she was in reality giving him away, for when he re- turned to her, it would be as a man, and no  more her boy Georgie. The thought of his departure was so painful to her that she tried to forget her loss in his happiness. Like many other mothers, she was willing to sacrifice her- - self for her child. The other children did not - express so, much regret; they loved George,  but he had been rather exacting and selfish,  and as he seemed so delighted with the idea of ii going, they seemed to think they too must sympathize in his pleasure.  The most sincere regret at his departure was  felt by little Lucy Fox. "Oh, Georgie!how  can you go and leave your mother and the baby? I wouldn't go away from my mother and father for all the Governors in the world." : "Why, Lulu, wouldn't you come and live with me if I were Govrnor?. " "Yes, Georgie; if you were Governor, and   'tU LST'- 'WILL.     47 lived in your pretty house, right here, and I could run over home every day." "Well, Lulu; I mean some time to be a governor or great man, and then I want you to be my Lulu all the time. Will you promise it?"                1 "Yes, I will Georgie, if you will never play any games with Jeff." "I never will, Lulu; but what will you give me to bind your promise? something for me to keep and look at." "Let me see," said Lulu, as she pursed up her little mouth and stood very gravely think- ing. "I'll give you my Boston doll I the nice one that father bought last New Year's." Georgie smiled; the little girl had offered what to her was most valuable. "No, Lulu; one of these curls will do," and he took one of the inglets in his hand. "Oh, you may have it and welcome," and she clipped one quickly and handed it to him. "And this is for you," he replied, handing her a little gold locket, containing some of his  own hair. ,%  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7482-00000025"/> Now all this was nothing more to Lucy than childish friendship. She had been a playmate of George from infancy, and he had great in- fluence over her yielding, loving temperament. On George's side, there was more of sinceri- ty and earnestness; he loved, as far as his selfish disposition would admit, more than any- thing else in Westhrook, this pretty child, and in his vision of the future her image was al- ways mingled. It was a bright, cold day, when George en- tered the Governor's house as his future home. The large sitting-room looked very inviting, with its rich Brussels carpet, the ample fire-  place with its marble hearth, and its polished fire-set, bright with hard labor, and the reflec-  tion of a large wood-fire.  There was a bay window were rare flowers  were in bloom; two or three choice pictures : adorned the walls, and books and papers lay  scattered about in a kind of agreeable disorder, which made one feel at home at once. Now, George's home, though considered quite an es-  A,           AtI   THE LOST WILL.       49 tablishment for Westhrook, was, after all, only a large farm-house of the better sort, and the ,refinement and quiet elegance of his new abode, pleased his fastidious taste, for George had, naturally, a taste for beauty. "Now, my boy," said the"Governor, -" you must make yourself at home at once; there will be only two weeks before your college term commences, and we will take this time to get acquainted. Nellie has been an invalid for some days, but to-morrow she will be able to come down; meanwhile you and I must amuse ourselves as well as we can," and the good man looked at the boy, well pleased to see that his fine face and figure was an additional ornament to his pleasant room. George had amusement enough for a few days, in looking about the town, which was much larger than Westhrook, and boasted two hotels, two printing offices, from which issued weekly, two respectable newspapers, each, of course, asserting that their political views were those of the immortal Washington, and that         . '..  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7482-00000026"/> 50  .   THE LOST WILL.          X their neighbors across the way were leading - the nation to destruction.. A political fever  was at its height at this time, and Governor Berry was delighted to find that George enter- ed with interest into the contest.  There was no great enthusiasm in his nature,  but he read and understood the position of par- g ties, and speculated with all the coolness of an old politician upon the results of the coming -I election and the position of parties.  "Just the boy for me," the Governor said; "why, he understands every movement as if it ,i were a game of chequers, and he watching the  result."      v .            . -i On the third day after his co g to B-, as he entered the sitting-room after dinner, he found Nellie lying on a couch, which was    i drawn up near the fire. 'She was very fair and delicate, and looked like some beautiful : piece of statuary, as she reclined there in a - pink mering loose dress, with her dark hair patted plainly on her forehead. Her face was  regularly beautiful, though quite pale from re-, : ffi , I s . . ^i   THE LOST WILL.      51 cent illness, and a sweet smile played round her mouth as her father seated himself beside her. "Now I feel at home again," he said,; but George will read the paper for us, until you are strong and well as usual." "I'm glad, (oeorgie, you have come to live with us," she said, "and I am so glad, too, that your name is George; that is the name of my brother in heaven; his hair was just the color of yours, and curled too as your's does. I was afraid your sisters would not let you come away, and I told papa that I wouldn't believe you were coming, till I saw you seated in this very room. Don't you like B--- al- ready?" "Yes; very much indeed," said George. "I like it better than Wresthrook." Nellie seemed a little surprised at this, and opened her eyes wide, but she made no reply, and afterl a moment she said "- Papa had promised that I shall ride to Westhrook, and bring your sisters here to make us a visit, on  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7482-00000027"/> 62     THE LOST WILL. the first mild, sunny day, so if you feel home- sick you must be thinking how soon you will  see them."  "I do not think I shall be homesick, Nel- lie." "Perhaps not, while papa is at home, but when he is away, and that often happens, yo cannot imagine how lonesome it is here." "You forget, Nellie," said her father, "that George goes to college in two weeks."  ' Indeed, papa I I did not understand this. I am sorry you are going so soon, George. I  thought you were too young." "I was prepared last year," said George, A looking the least bit in the world vain of his acquirements. "And you are only fourteen years old, Georgie, and yet know so much Latin and Creek! Why, I havn't gone through my Latin grammar yet," "And never will, I hope," said her father. 'Come, George, read us the remainder of John Q. Adams' speech. He is an old college i.   TITE LOST WILL.      53 friend of mine, with a mighty strong will that will drive him through the world in a straight line, I fancy." George read well for a boy, and both the Governor and Nellie enjoyed it. At the close f the reading came the old Vermont evening eat- nuts and apples; and then just after the clock struck nine, the Governor handed Nellie a little Bible, and she read a Psalm, and then father and daughter (for George was not a singer) sung together that sweet hymn com- mencing- "When all thy mercies, O my God." When that was closed, one of the domestics remained to assist Nellie to her room. "Let me carry you, my child," said the Governor.  f "Oh, no ppapa see how strong I am!" and she rose from the couch, and raising her face to kiss him, stood a moment with his arms round her, and then turning to George, said: Good-night, Georgie; to-morrow I hope you will read a little Latin to me." Then for i'  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7482-00000028"/> 54      THE LOST WILL.  the first time, as she walked to the door, George perceived that little Nellie was deform- i ed; that her back was bent, and that the pro-  tuberance thus formed made her look like a little dwarf.  George had called at the Governor's house A two or three times with his father, but Nellie was always at such times on her little couch, for she had been an invalid from infancy. For a moment George felt a repulsion towards the child; anything that lacked symmetry and beauty was peculiarly unpleasant to him. This is not wrong in itself, but in warm-heart- j ed, generous natures, this feeling is followed by an emotion of pity, and if the unfortunate one is worthy, this pity ripens into affection, and the very deformity binds the union more strongly. But George whose better nature had not been developed, or rather I should say, that  the selfishness of his heart had never been sub-  dued by any effort on his part, or by the pow-  er of God's grace,--therefore as he lay down i"   THE LOST WILL.       55 upon his pillow at night he reasoned thus:- / "I never shall like Nellie; I always did hate to see a hump-back, and the very sight of her will make my stay here unpleasant, for I must walk and ride with her, and treat her as if she were my sister. But then there's the Gover-  nor to suit, and it is all up with me if I dis- please Nellie; any one can see at a glance that he'd rather lose his election next year, than ave any one treat Nellie badly. I won- der how he can love her so;" and George for- got the sweet, calm face, in thinking of the de- formed back. The next day was one of those mild, sunny days that sometimes come to us in November, and seem as if departed autumn had turned   X backward and we saw her bright face agaid.  Nellie felt quite strong and bright, and her father proposed that George should drive her out a short distance. "Don't go far to-day," he said; "be care- ful, Nellie." f                   s S, ,        A,      V  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7482-00000029"/> * 56     THE LOST WILL.        l "May I go as far as Brown's Mills?" said  Nellie. "Yes, if you wish; it is a warm, sheltered  road, but don't stop long in the house, if you call to see the little Slades." "No, papa; but I must go in 3ust a mo- - me l%."  "Of course it would be too hard for you to X pass by such a dirty, ragged set as they are." "Oh, papa! they are not dirty and ragged now; don't you know how nice they look in Sunday school?"             X "Yes, to be sure; thanks to you for that. But it will not last long, I fancy."   d "Perhaps not; but poor Mrs. Slade is to be pitied. She is sick most all the time, and has four little children crying round her." "They always laugh when you come, don't they, Nellie?"               "Then I must go often, papa." At morning devotion Nellie played on the piano with so much simplicity, and sung so sweetly the following hymn: , ' -                  f         THE LOST WILL.         57 Our Father in heaven We hallow thy name; May thy kingdom holy On earth be the same! Oh, give to us daily Our portion of bread; It is from thy bounty We all must be fed. Forgive our transgressions,  And teach us to know  That humble compassion Which pardons each foe; Keep us from temptation, From weakness and sin, And thine be the glory, Forever, Amen." George did not anticipate much pleasure in his ride, from the little -description which the Governor had given of Brown's-Mills.    The road, however, was pleasant, for it followed the windings of a little brook, and for some distance neat little houses were scattered here and there, with orchards and gardens attached, looking as if the inhabitants were thriving and industrious  After travelling two miles they ?       '        i  i  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7482-00000030"/> THE LOST WILL.  came to a little settlement of some eight or ten  small houses, and a grist and saw mill. The  mill itself looked old, and was surrounded by ! logs, old wagons, and rubbish of all kinds, while : the dwelling-house, near by, which was larger  than the other tenements, and boasted a coat of white-wash, had, like the mill, a tumble-down  look, with its broken fences, and cracked win- dows and dirty barn-yard. In front of the I house were two pigs that had escaped from  the pen, and twice as many children, and if a  close comparison had been instituted, the latter would have been found most deficient in clean- liness. The other houses were but imitations of the  larger; old hats and coats were stuck into the  broken windows, gates hung by one hinge, and the tottering wood-sheds were supported by  old boards. The bare-headed children looked a blue and cold, as they 'stood in the door-way gaping at the carriage, or run round shoeless, in the dirty street. George looked on for a while without say- *           h i  --.'           d   TI'lE LOST WILL.     59 ing a word, while his lip curled, and his nose turned up a little, but then it only inhaled more strongly the flavor of something which seemed very much like cabbage boiling. "I guess they raise cabbages here," he said. Nellie laughed merrily. "You are not quite pleased with this part of our town," she said. "Pa' once re- marked that the hardest part of his Sunday duties here, was to endure with patience, the 'compound of villanous smells,' as he express- es it." "What can your father have to do here, on Sunday?" asked George, in some surprise. "Why, you know these children must go to Sunday school, and they do not like to come to the school in Mr. Walker's church, because their clothes are: not good enough; and I think  our congregation, which is rather a fashionable one, equally dislike to see them there; even Mrs. Moore, who is a member of the church, said she did not think it was right to have the little, dirty, profane crew, as she called them, mingle with respectable Sunday schoolchil-  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC7482-00000031"/> 60      THE LOST WILL. dren. I suppose she expressed the opinion of many others. Mr. Walker and papa thought differently, and wished that the people here would come to church and bring their children  with them. Papa gave up two pews for their I2 usebut one of these joined that of Mr. Mills, the wealthy grocer, and he said he wouldn't  pay another dollar for the support of the minis- try, if the Brown set were allowed to remain there. I don't know how the matter would  have ended, had not Mr. Walker preachedjust about that time, a very strong temperance ser- mon, which displeased both Mr. Moore and the  Browns. Mr. Moore sold the rum, and the  :; Browns drank it, and they were both equally displeased. The church lost Mr. Moore's sub- scription of forty dollars to the minister's sala- i ry, and the Sunday school lost all the Mill  'Hollow children. I proposed to Ellen Wright, one of my friends, that we should have a Sun- day school here, in the school-house, and I  persuaded father to turn superintendent,"' "That's odd business for a Governor,'7 said  Georgce.   THE LOST WILL.       61 "Oh!, but you wouldn't think so if you will come and see him. He never looks so hand- some to me as when he prays with these! little, white-headed children around him. He prays as if he were one of them and knew all their  little wants and sorrows. I thought he was the handsomest man in the State on review day, when the military companies all came out, and father reviewed them. He rode on horse- back; you know what a noble, high-spirited horse Jennie Morgan is, and my father sits as erect and easy, and guides her by a word, while nobody else can mount her at all. Then his aids, Mr. Kellogg and Mr. Burr, rode by his side, proud, I thought, of father's appear- ance. "Oh! I enjoyed it, Georgie; for I love bright and beautiful things. The showy unm- form glittering so in the sunlight, the music  that made my heart bound, and my father, so tall and stately, receiving so much respect and honor! It was a proud day for me, Georgie, and made me very happy. But not as happy as I was when father consented to come into *  .  \    A,  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC7482-00000032"/> 62      THE LOST WILL. ' that little old school-house and teach -these children. I was so happy, Gcorgie, that I  wept. Did you think anybody could be so  happy as that, Georgie?" "I never was," said George. "Here is the house," said Nellie; "we'll stop here." It was the last one in the settle- ; ment, a very small brown house, with an un-  mistakable air of poverty all round.    i The four little Slades were playing with a  yellow dog in the street, but as soon as they  saw Nellie, they ran into the house exclaiming,  "Miss Nellie has come! marmmie, Miss Nellie  has come!"                 i "Now, George, if you will please to carry  this basket into the house, you need not stay  any longer unless you prefer; but you may ride to Mr. White's, as my father requested,  and get his watch, which is there to be mend-  ed, and then return .for me; I will be ready. Mr. White lives only half a mile from here, on BLtook Lane." George lifted the basket and entered thel house like on% performing an unpleasant task g       '   THE LOST WILL.      63 and then waiting upon Nellie to the door, glad to be relieved himself from remaining any longer. Had he done so, however, he would have been astonished to have seen how suddenly those noisy children hushed their play and gathered round Nellie, with almost as much reverence as if they believed her descended from another world. Even the rough, cross- looking dog crouched down on the floor, and was quiet as the children. A sick woman lay upon the bed; she was very thin and pale, save a little flush on each cheek. She extend- ed her hanto Nellie but cculd not speak for a moment, o  cccount of a violent attack of coughing. When that ceased, she said in a feeble voice, though her eyes were bright with pleasure, "Oh! Miss Nellie, how glad I am to t  see you! I believed you would come to-day, for I prayed so earnestly for you last night - you know you told me that God would hear me when I prayed." "Yes," said Nellie; "and I have been  ,.  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC7482-00000033"/> praying for you, that he would forgive your ? sins and give you the hope of the Christian be-  fore you die."              ? "And that is what I want to tell you;  when I saw you last, I felt that I was a great : sinner, and I wanted to make myself better, i I tried and tried but it didn't do any good. At last I thought of what you said, that our weakness was made strength in Christ. In  : Christ, I kept repeating, and then I took the  Bible you gave me and read the passages which you marked -' Come unto me, all ye  I that are weary and heavy laden' - He that  confesseth and forsaketh his sins shall find . mercy.' And, Miss Nellie, I have got a new view of Jesus Christ. It seems now as if he came to save just such sinners as live down here in Mill Hollow, and if he were upon  earth he wouldn't scorn us. Don't you think sBO?"  "He scorned no one when he lived on earth," said Nellie; "and he says expressly that he came to save sinners."   lxj&amp;a LOST WILL.     65 "Yes ; I know it and feel it," said the sick woman. "I can trust him now! I can trust him now! and I can trust my children with him. Oh! Miss Nellie, I am going to die and leave them, but Jesus will take care of them. I have given them to him. But my poor hus- band! Oh! Miss Nellie,- now that I am sick, he drinks more than ever; but when he is sober, he is a kind, good husband. I have been thinking, Miss  Nellie, if you would ask Mr. Brown not to sell any rum to my John, perhaps he would listen to you, as most everybody does." "And now, Miss Nellie, pray for me, one of the prayers where you tell the Saviour just what is in my poor wicked heart, and ask him for what I need, and thank him too. Thankl  him for what he has done for me. Last night I heard him say, 'Daughter, be of good cheer, thy sins are forgiven thee.'" Nellie did kneel and pray by the bedside of the sick woman, and while she was praying George came, and as he stood a moment at the di  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC7482-00000034"/> VU     'lti LV 1' W boL Lij door, which could not be tightly shut, he heard  that low sweet voice pleading with God to bless this family, and ease the suffering of the dying. He had a glimpse of the group of chil- dren, standing in quiet wonder, the silent dog,  the pale sufferer, with eyes closed and hands  clasped. -  From all this George turned away, half in  wonder, half in contempt. "And this is the  Governor's daughter," he said' to himself, "and in that old school-house, the Governor teaches a Sunday school!"  "Here I am, Georgie," said a clear, pleas- ant voice a moment after. "Oh, how bright  i and pleasant it isl " she said as she stepped out into the sunshine and looked up to the  clear, blue sky. But not half as bright was the day without, as the moral sunshine she had left within.  4, '      / 1'8   CITAPTER IV. A FEW days after the call to Mill Hollow, there was 'a cold storm and a heavy wind; such weather as is common in Vermont, and comes like the hoarse blast of a trumpet, ush- ering in the artillery of winter. It is a warn- ing, heeded alike by all classes, who set to work diligently to fortify themselves against the enemy. The last potatoes are dug and housed, cellars that are not better guarded are banked with straw or tan, doors are listed, double windows put on, water pipes protected, barns made tight, sheep driven to their pens, while indoors the thrifty housewife is busy  making woollen garments that her household fear not the snow.  The Governor was one of those good house- holders who superintend all ,these matters per- sonally, and hardly a vine in his garden, or a 67  t   &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC7482-00000035"/> THE LOST WILL.  -% : house-plant of Nellie's, but received a little of his care. One morning at breakfast, after he had risen early, and had given some directions about re- pairing a stable for his favorite horse, he said to George : - "I have been thinking, George, that you might like to go home for a day or two, and see if your mother needs a little of your help before winter sets in.. My man, John, is going to Westhrook to look after some sheep which I have there, and you can go with him if you would like." "Thank you, sir," said George, "I would like to do so." "And if there should come another such a pleasant day as that of last Thursday," said Nellie, "may I ride over and bring George back with his sisters?" "Yes, my daughter; it is a good idea." "Then, George, you may look for 'me the fiist sunshiny day." But it so happened that on the first pleasant day a message came that Mrs. Slade wished to   THE LOST WILL.   69   see Nellie. She was very ill, and it was thought would not survive the day. "I can hardly advise your going there," said her father; ' you are not strong enough to go through such a scene. Let Mrs. Mills, the housekeeper, go in your place."  "Oh, no! no, papa! it would be too cruel o deny a dying woman so simple a request; my first duty is to her, and she is so happy, so ready to die, that I think there will be nothing painful in the interview." "At least, let Mrs. Mills go with you." There was no objection to this, and the two hastened on their mission. Mrs. Slade was still living, but very near death. Her eyes brightened as Nellie drew near, and she tried to raise her hand to wel- come her. Her husband was by her side kind and attentive, though overwhelmed with grief at the thought of her death. Nellie had per- suaded her father to see the miller, Mr. Brown, and beg of him to keep liquor away from Slade, at least the little while his wife had to  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC7482-00000036"/> 70      THE LOST WILL. , live. The promise was given, and an interest  excited among the neighbors to help him keep i it. "I'll not drink a drop," said af kind-heart-  ed fellow, "for two weeks, Slade, if you will  join me." Now this man had not been without his dai-  ly dram for many years, but there is often among such people genuine sympathy in the hour of sorrow. The neighbors were kindly officious at this time, but they all drew back respectfully as Nellie came to the bed-side, and asked Mrs. Slade, as she pressed her hand, if she felt will- ing to depart. -  "Yes, yes; Jesus is precious. I can trust him - he has forgiven my sins for his sake,  I am accepted; but, Miss Nellie, will you : promise to take an interest in my children? talk to them sometimes of their mother, and tejl them that the precious Saviour will,:be their friend, too, if they will come to him ' ) Nellie assured her they should not be forgot-  ten, that she would try and lead them to Jesus. i1   THE LOST WILL.      71 "Now pray with. me, once more," was the request, in a feeble voice. Nellie forgot everything, even the presence of the neighbors and the husband, and poured out her soul in prayer, and while she prayed, a change passed over the face of the dying. Her eyes closed, and the watchers thought she had fallen asleep, for there was no struggle, no groan, but her countenance was peaceful as a sleeping babe. The spirit had been borne on the wings of prayer to heaven. "Oh, Mrs. Mills, I am so glad we came," said Nellie, when they were seated in the car- riage; "I never saw any one die before, but now there seems nothing terrible about it.  'Falling asleep in Jesus,' that was Mrs. Slade's death."  Nellie was now but twelve years old, but she had led this poor woman to the Saviour, and though the child did not think of herself or her own efforts, there was great peace and quiet in her soul that day. The next morning she rode to Westhrook. 1i ,'* e  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC7482-00000037"/> The blue sky above, the clear, bracing air, the distant woods, still draped in their many color- ed robes, though every breath of wind sent the leaves in little showers to the ground; the woodpecker's note, the venturesome squirrel,  that, perched on the old rail-fences, would  turn its bright eyes to the passer-by, a mo- ment, and then run on with a nut in its mouth, all were sources of great amusement and pleas-  ure. "But somehow," she said to herself, as  she rode alone in the carriage, "I never felt quite so happy before - I love this world, so  full of beauty, and it never seemed brighter than now; but heaven is nearer, just a step -  not such a dark and gloomy valley between as X I had pictured. Then the calm, peaceful face i of Mrs. Slade seemed before her, and she re-  peated the words-  "Oh, Death, where is thy sting?  Oh,wrave, where is thy victory?"  Nellie had never been to Westhrook, and the view of the village from the mountain road, pleased her very much.              THE LOST WILL.       73 "Oh, John, stop awhile," she said, as they came to a turn in the road, from which they could see the village spread out before them. "How pretty the houses look, clustered to- gether in the valley, and see the church on the hill, and the little school-house, and, like a bright silver thread, the brook runs along; yonder it makes a bend, and see what a broad, beautiful meadow, like a bow; the water em- braces it as if it were a child it would gather in its arms." "Yes, ma'am; that is called 'Indian mead- ow' from an old Indian who owned it for some years after settlements were made here." "And what is that long, white house, with a high sign-post before it?" "That is Fox's tavern where we are to stop, Miss Nellie." And the house opposite is George's home; I know it from his description. It is a beauti- ful spot; I almost wonder George is willing to leave it; our town is larger, but this seems to me such a quiet, lovely spot."  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC7482-00000038"/> lrt      ':-.nLdX J Y[lB  VVY LJ.  The sign of the Fox amused Nellie much; she was quite fond of sketching herself, and had a native taste and genius for it. "But I! don't like to see General Washington with a  a fox on his back," said she. They had no sooner stopped at the door of the tavern, than George, who had recognized  a the carriage, came to welcome Nellie, and ask John to drive round to his mother's. But   : John who had received directions to place the horses in Mr. Fox's care, was already assisting  Nellie to alight, and thus she had an opportu- nity of being ushered into Mrs. Fox's parlor, and receiving the civilities of the good dame. Little Lucy Fox was sitting in a low chair, intent upon marking a sampler - a species of work very much in vogue at that .time. Her colored silks were spread out before her, and she was studying the mystery of a strawherry border. The entrance of a stranger interrupt- ed her, and she raised her head, flinUing back  her curls as she did so, with one hand, while  with the other, she held her canvass and nee- * '!2   T1HiEt LOST' WILL   .   75 die. Nellie's sweet face attracted her at once, and she involuntarily threw her work down and hastened to place a seat for her by the open fire. As she did so she observed Nellie's deformity, and at once her whole heart became interested in the stranger. On the other hand, the exceeding beauty of Lucy drew Nellie's at- tention, and she found it as difficult to turn away her eyes, as she would from! a rare and newly discovered flower, or a charming pic- ture. The beauty of the two children was quite dissimilar. Nellie's face was fair, rega, lar and pale as chiselled marble--there was much expression in it, as if a pure soul looked out of those eyes, and the longer one studied the face, the more there was found to admire. But there was, what we do not like to see in a child, as if the spirit were purified by suffering - -grown wise before the age of wisdom. Lu- cy, on the other hand, was a little, plump, kit- ten of a child, with eyes brim  full of fan, and the prettiest little mouth  in the world, that loved to open itself and chatter as the  birds , , &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC7482-00000039"/> * U     TLAt L(OS'L' WILL.  love to sing, and when she did laugh, which was often enough, on each plump, rosy cheek, there were deep dimples, so that eyes, cheeks 8 and mouth laughed in concert. But now she ; looked quite demure, and seated herself with ; her work in her hand, but with her eyes wan- : dering in great curiosity, her mother mean-  while, bustling about, throwing fresh wood on 3: the fire, and sweeping the already clean hearth. In a moment George appeared, and  then Lucy divined at once, that the stranger I s Nellie Berry, she knew before the intro-  uction which immediately followed.  There was a mutual attraction between the  two, and Nellie was much pleased when  George said, "Come, Lucy, bring your sam-. pler, and take tea with my sisters, and help us  to introduce Nellieto Westhrook. I am afraidi' she will find quite a contrast to her own home. 5 "Indeed, George, I like it very much, and I  think I should like to stay here, especially in  summer..  "I am  glad you like Westhrook,' said  (**'il   THE LOST WILL.       " Lucy, "for I think it is jgst the prettiest place in this world. I like it better than Windsor, or Springfield, or Boston, and I have been to all these places in my life. If you will only go to the Indian meadow, in strawherry time, andl up Eagle mountain at sunset, and trout fishing in the brook, when the fish are plenty, you would say it was pleasant living here." "And I will do all this, next summer, Lucy, if you will go with me." "Yes, indeed; and I can take you to the woods, too. I know where the first violets grow, and where there is plenty of trailing ar- butus. Do you know that pretty flower, Miss Berry?"                      , "Don't call me Miss Berry; call me Nellie,"  said her companion. "Yes; I know the arbu-  tus, and I love it dearly." They were now at Mrs. Dennie's. There was a look of pleasure on the widow's face, whenever George came in sight, for she was very proud of her boy, but she looked sad and care-worn-her trouble pressed heavily upon     I t          ,      t a  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC7482-00000040"/> ---    J H.HLLE JLUO'JL' VJLJLiL. her. Her two daughters, Mary and Ruth,  were quiet, pretty girls, the elder, a home-lov- ing, neat house-keeper and a great comfort to : her mother. Ruth, had been a sort of pet of her father, because of her attachment to books, and now, nothing pleased her more, than to hide away in the garret, and read all by her-  self, hour after hour. Charlie was but a baby yet, just learning to run alone. Mrs. Dennie and her daughters had striven in every way to make George's visit pleasant, but he had already learned to think BI - far preferable to Westhrook, and  /was constantly telling of it, and often saying,  "There's nothing here in Westhrook--oh,  mother, if you could only live in B -!" No one disputed him but Lucy, and she  would laugh and say, "Now Georgie, you only  make believe so; you know you haven't Eagle mountain close there, nor our pretty brook, nor the baby, (dear little Charlie,) nor Mary and Ruth and me.  Oh, Georgie; you do love : Wsrook best, I know you do. But then," - -,    tI nl JU'T W ILL.  'I she added in a whisper to Georgie, "you have Nellie; isn't she beautiful?" George smiled rather doubtfully. "Do you think so, Lucy? look again." "Oh! I know what you mean, Georgie; but when I look at her face, and hear her voice, I think she is the sweetest girl I ever saw; and as for her back, I think I see only angel's wings folded there." "You are quite fanciful, Lulu." "Why, no Georgie; only you know in our  old Bible there's pictures of angels, and there's one with his wings folded, and his face is beau-  tiful, so that when I first saw Nellie, I just thought of the angel."  "I am going to Yale next week," said .. George. "Aren't you glad?" said Lucy; "you have wished so much to go." "Yes; but I shall not see Westhrook again  for a year " "Oh, Georgie " and the plump face was made as long as possible, and the bright eyes grew suddenly dim. , *             *.: ' -  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC7482-00000041"/> 80     THE LOST WILL. "Can't you write letters, Lulu?" "Yes, indeed; I write a long letter to Sam,  every week: when I began I always got fath- er to write on the outside, but now I can write straight and plain-' Mr. Samuel Fox, 29 1-2  Hanover street.' Sam says he'd rather lose ten dollars than one of my letters."   ) "Then you must take turns with my sisters in writing to me."            X "Yes, indeed; and I'll write you all about  the school, and the farm, and my heifer, and the lamb you gave me. OhI I can always find enough to put in my letters."  The children enjoyed themselves much; I Nellie was able to take a walk with Lucy, and then they all rode to the Big meadow, and to a curious cave in the mountain. To Lucy's! great delight she received an invitation to ride to B--  with George apd his sisters, the next day.  The presence of the group afforded the Gov- ernor more delight than the children them- selves. He gave up the day to their amuse- . .;            . .;   THE LOST WILL.       81 ment, and when they returned he loaded thea carriage with flowers and fruit. "Why, mother," said Lucy, on her return? "he wasn't like a Governor at all; only just the happiest, kindest, merriest boy I ever saw." fi /      j  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC7482-00000042"/> CHAPTER- V.  THE Governor had so much confidence in   : George that when he left him in college, he  gave no parting advice as to his conduct and habits. Perhaps the good man forgot the dan- gers of college life, or having gone through himself with so much honor and credit, he  trusted George would do the same.       : The boy was so ambitious to be at the head of his class, that there was little danger of his being an indolent scholar, but that same ambi-  tion led him to wish to dress as well, to play -I as good a game, and to drink as many glasses  of wine as any student. He was naturally  cautious, and therefore did not venture at first  so far as others, so that at the first year of his college life, he stood well in his classesd atRd  t was considered one of the most promising stu- : dents.  82   THE LOST WILL.      83 He had kept up a correspondence with his sisters and Lucy, and received occasional let- ters from Nellie. The latter was pursuing her studies under private teachers at home, her health not permitting her to attend school. George's long vacation was anticipated by his family at Westhrook, as well at his friends at B  , with great pleasure. But that one year had wrought some chang- es in his former home. His mother haAd found, after the settlement of her husband's estate, i " that she had but a small income left, and had  given up her large house and moved into a small one story tenement, formerly occupied by the farmer who had been employed by her  husband. Mr. Fox, who had been a shrewd, kind friend, was dead--ded suddenly of fever  -and poor Mrs. Dennie's affairs were, by  some unfortunate mistake, in the management of Jeff. Devoll. The latter had taken her hus- i band   ffice, and his name. had supplanted that of the 'Squire, on the door.  The old sign still hung by the tavern door, o'r.  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC7482-00000043"/> 4  -    JTHE LOST WILL. for John Fox had taken his father's place, and  assisted by his mother, the house sustained its  former reputation. But "Sam," whose suc- cess in the shoe business had already promot-  ed him to a partnership, had formed some  plans for Lucy, to which she and her mother -P gave a reluctant consent.  Sam had married a worthy girl of West- brook, and Lucy must go to Boston and attend i3 school there. Her brother was only too hap- py to give her the best teachers, especially in  music,'for which the child seemed to have as  great a taste as the birds. All this made   George's visit at home a sad one. Jeff. in the-,  office annoyed him exceedingly; his mother's  straightened circumstances, pricked his cd-  science somewhat, and when he heard Ruth  wishing that she could goto school and fit  herself for a teacher, as Lucy was doing, the  remark did not soothe his trouble. The meagre fare, the plain clothes, the nar-  row house annoyed him, and he could not look  at his mother's sad and worn face, without re-   ' ' 'i   TH'iE LOST WILL.   -  membering what Mr. Fox had said   "Fol- low my plan and your mother will 'be made happy." He tried to forget these things in trouting, i and riding, but they would force themselves  upon him at times.  "Oh, George," said his mother, one dy,  "did you know that' Jeff.' had got the mead-  Ai ow, and the pasture, and our house, "too? I can't understand it, for law is all Greek to me; but Mr. Fox said, just before he died, that 'Jeff.'s ' claim was exorbitant and illegal, and that he would see that I was not defrauded by him. But it was too late; the good man was never able to do anything for himself after  ::, that, and Jeff. has it all his own way." "He's a rascal," said George, "and I'm half a mind to fight him." His poor mother looked up in astonishm "My boy! never talk so. Wermust bearS  patiently, I suppose; but if I live till you havei learned your profession, I shall feel as if I hadt? a strong arm to lean upon at least, my old, dren will be nrat. ?           , , ' S       '               W P  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC7482-00000044"/> Well she might think so, as she saw her tall, manly boy, walking the street. Nature had been bountiful of her gifts to him, and of him to whom so much was given, much might well  be required.  Fight Jeff.!" To have seen the two to- gether, ode would tremble for the fate of the fair-haired, slender boy that should venture to ! fight with the g rat, bony, hard-fisted fellow,  that stood six feet two in his boots, and looked X strong enough to crush George with his foot.  But, in truth, George's desire to fight vanish-  ed the moment he had turned away from his  mother. It was only when with his mother  and sisters that he felt troubled about them-  the sight of unhappiness, or want, or pain was  annoying to him, and he would like never to  see it; but once out of sight it was out of  mdind; he did not like the exertion of trying to -  edy it. Nellie, on the contrary, was al- ways seeking out somebody that needed help,  and she never rested till she had relieved the trouble that she found. -  .      '3-8,.      .:   T'lHl LUST WILL.     87 The little Slades were not forgotten, and were comforted a little in their loss, by new frocks and bonnets, and the privilege of a good school; and all the dwellers in Mill Hollow / "' were gradually becoming better and happier, under the quiet influence of this child. Her deformity seemed only to increase her power  to do good, for all felt that one who could be so cheerful and patient, and wear so sweet a smile under so great a misfortune, must be loved also of God. But few knew how this child of twelve had struggled and conquered. ; When she was but seven or eight years of age, her mother noticed that she seemed weaker than other girls of her age, and could not run and play as they did. * Soon one shoulder projected more than the other, and the spine was more curved than it should be; the anxious mother, who was so frail herself that life seemed to hang upon a thread, was keenly sensitive to this misfortune. The best medical aid was procured, and the child was taken to Boston, where she submit-  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC7482-00000045"/> 88      THE LOST WILL.  ted very patiently to what was to her suscepti- ble frame a species of systematic torture. She would lie for hours stretched upon a board; she carried weights, and practised gymnastic I: exercises; she was patient under all the  stretching, the compression, the climbing, the  }rubbing, the carrying of sand bags, &amp;c., &amp;c., insisted upon by those who sincerely desired - to restore symmetry to the little body that H! bore so sweet a face. Nellie herself was so anxious to be well and i strong, that she omitted none of the discip- :-i line required. She shrank from the idea of  deformity with all the strength of a nature that  was so fond of beauty.            :! But she grew worse rather than better, and at last, the physician, an honest, true-hearted  man, told her mother that it was of no use, her back could not be straightened. Anid all that he recommended was careful attention to her general health.  When Nellie learned this from her mother's  lips, she was very unhappy and even rebellious, and her spirit was sadly disturbed  '  Iiiii   THE LOST WILL.       89 "Then I don't want to live, mamma; I'd rather die. I h9pe I shall take some terrible disease and die quick." Ah my child! my child!" said her mother, remember who has ordered this affliction for you. "But God might make me straight as well as others," said she. "I can't love God any more, no mother, I can't," and she burst into a passionate flood of tears. / The mother said nothing for a few moments, till the storm had somewhat abated, and then she"bade Nellie recount the blessings which God has scattered in her path -then she told her of heathen children, of the drunkard's fam-  ily, of the thousand homes of wretchedness in our own land, of children deformed and maim- ed by the brutality of their own parents, and of others brought to an early death by starva- tion and want. To all this Nellie listened re- spectfully and 'with apparent calmness, but down deep in her little heart the bitter waters were surging and foaming in rebellion to her fate.   &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC7482-00000046"/> That night her pillow was wet with tears,  and when morning came she still asked God  that she might die. Nellie was naturally a  proud child, and being the only survivor of four children, the rest having died in infancy, e would have been petted and spoiled by indul-  gence, but her judicious mother saw the .danger and avoided it, governing with a firm, even , hand, the child she loved too well to spoil. Some days after the conversation referred to :-: above, a blind preacher called at the house, and X on being invited by Mr. Berrie, remained some  days. He had learned submission in his great i affliction, and as he expressed it, found light in  darkness. 'He loved the society of children  and Nellie's voice attracted him. Blind people  find that the loss of one sense is sometimes in a  measure compensated by the increased keen- ness of the others. Now he listened very at- tentively every time the little girl spoke, and  then he sat and mused upon it. There was something in the tone of the voice unlike that of most little girls of her age, a minor key that   THE LOST WILL.       91 seemed to set the good man thinking. After awhile he called her to him, laid his hand upon her head, put his arm around her and drew her towards him, while Mrs. Berry, who lay upon a lounge looking at them, saw an expression of pain and sympathy in his countenance at once. Yes, the blind man now knew almost as well as if he had had eyes, that little Nellie was afflicted too, and he understood noW why her voice had that plaintive tone. He said nothing however upon that subject, but talked with her about her dolls and her kittens, and asked her to read some stories to him, and they two became so interested that they passed almost the whole day together. When night came, he said to her, "Nellie you have made a poor, blind man happy to-day. Ihave seen with your eyes, you have led me at about the house and garden, and read to me  why really I haven't been so fully reconciled to the loss of sight for a long time; in one respect you are like the Lord Jesus, you have been 'eyes to the blind.'" : .  .           k  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC7482-00000047"/> i -"-    Xlri L'J .HNLL..    , ILiL It would have done the blind man good,  could he have seen the s ile that lighted Nellie's face, but he guessed how bright the face was, from the voice that answered him in a sweet, lively tone. "Why Mr. Beck, I have enjoyed the day  very much myself; I like to read to you, and i if you please, to-morrow morning we will walk in the orchard, where the pears and apples are  ripening."  "I should enjoy that very much," said he "for I like apples and pears now as, well as when I was a boy."  Nellie went to sleep that night happier than ! she had been for many days, and she sprung  out of bed as soon as she awoke in the morn- ing and drew aside the curtain to see if it were a pleasant day. The sky was clear, but Nellie after taking a glance all around the horizon, ran across the entry to her mother's room that faces the West, and looked out of the window up to Eagle mountain. , "What now?" said her father, who heard the patter of the little bare feet *. ' .Ij   THE LOST WILL.      93 "Oh, I only want to see if the sun shines on Eagle mountain," said Nellie. "You know, father, that before it rises in the East, it shines on the mountain top. I don't exactly under- stand why, but sometimes the smnmimwill be as bright as gold, sometimes of a eautiful crimson, and at others a rich, deep purple; it is golden this morning, and the windows in the little house on thp top shine as if each one was a great topaz, like the jewel in mamma's ring. Now I know it will be pleasant, and I can walk in the orchard with Mr. Beck." "Now for one morning kiss," said her fath- er; and as the child greeted her parents, a sense of their love settled upon her heart, and  she felt happy; but when she returned to her room and Betsey came in to help her dress, and put on her braces and her padding upon the shoulder, and bade her hold her head up, and walk straight, the old bitter feeling came over her, and Nellie thought for a moment, that she wouldn't pray that morning. Hadn't she prayed ever so many times that God would t.    ' ',   &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC7482-00000048"/> ".THE LOST WILL. make her straight and well, but her prayers were not answerd. The habit, however, was  too strong, and she read her chapter, and prayed for a blessing on the day.  The blind man and the little girl waited only  for the sun to dry up the dew on the grass,  and then Nellie, with her hand in his, went  through the garden path and over the stile to the orchard, which was on ground sloping to  the south. The grass was thick, and of a rich green; the trees were loaded with fruit, : though only the early kinds were now ripe. The "Summer Hovey " were almost gone, and  there were only a few "Sops of Wine," but the "Porters," and the "Moodys," and the  "Red Cheeks" were in their prime, and some of the pears were delicious. The good, old fashioned St. Michael, the Governor's favorite, were plenty, and Mr. Beck, who remembered : the fruit in his childhood, enjoyed them very much.  They sat down on the grass in the shade of  an old apple tree, the patriarch of the orchard, i * His   THE LOST WILL.       95 and Nellie brought a specimen of each kind for Mr. Beck to examine, and she was aston- ished and delighted at his accuracy in guess- ing. "This is a pearmain russet,' and this is a 'Roxbury russet,' and this is i ' Baldwin,' and this is a 'greening,' he would say. "How do you know? how can you tell.?" Nellie would exclaim; "if I were blind they would all seem alike, only some I should know   : were large and some small."  "Oh, no, my child; you would soon learn a thousand little differences which you had not observed when you had your sight.  Now, here is a summer pearmain; this apple is al-  ways oblong in shape, a d is deeply indented . ! at both ends--how -ifferent this from the Maiden's Blush, wlich is always flat, with a very smooth skin. There is an apple, now, that is green all over, and here is one that is - red."                 - ,. -  The blind man had been handlig these ap- ples very carefully, before speaking. This , .i.?\:  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC7482-00000049"/> qr, ddr qvlr .dr,., ..L.;L u  JL o..t. -&amp;. VT -L.. JL, \ delicacy of touch and nicety of perception, seemed marvellous to Nellie, but not nore so than the cheerfulness of her companion, whose misfortune seemed not to have soured his tem- per, or to have seriously interfered with his enjoyment. She brought him flowers, and he amused her by his minute descriptions. Your wonder will be lessened," he said, 4 when I tell you that I am aided by memo- ry. I was not blind until my tenth year, when a stone, carelessly thrown by a school-mate, deprived me of the use of one eye, and through -:inskiful treatment of this, the other became afiected, and finally resulted in the total loss of sight. It was a hard struggle before I be- came-reconciled, and I never conquered till I learned through God's grace, to say, 'Thy will be done."' "Nellie, did you ever think how patiently Jesus Christ suffered when on earth?" ("Yes, sir," said Nellie; "I know how pa- tient he was in his trial and crucifixion." "Yes, Nellie; but I was not thinking just **.   THE LOST WILL.       97 then of his death, but of his life. For thirty years he was despised and rejected of men, a man of sorrows and acquainted with grief; but he cheerfully, lovingly bore it all, because of his great love to man; and sometimes I re- joice almost that this heavy cross, (for, Nellie, it is hard to be shut out from thee light of heav- en, and the dearer light of loving faces) is laid upon me. By bearing it with cheerfulness, yes, and even rejoicing in it, we are more like him."  Nellie's eyes were turned earnestly to the speaker, but his words sank into her heart.  From that time she began to study the life of / the Saviour, and was never afterwards heard to murmur, but every year found her more meek, loving and gentle.  When her mother died, poor Nellie's heart was almost broken, and once more the old longing came over her to die, and find rest with her best friend. Her father found her  kneeling by her mother's corpse, praying that prayer.  I          , ' ' i "  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC7482-00000050"/> 98$     "/THE LOST WILL. "Nellie, my child, would you leave me?" There was a tender reproach in the words that led Nellie to see her own selfishness, and from that timne she resolved, like the blirid. preacher, to live for others. Thus the misfortune of the child proved her greatest blessing, for in living for others, she surrounded herself with grateful, loving hearts, and no young girl in B--    had so many fkiends, or was so warmly loved as Nellie Ber- ry. Her health was so frail that few-supposed shbe would live beyond her childhood; but she gradually gained in strength, and the third year of George's college life, found her more igorous; than   - ever before. The winter ofrthat year she passed in Cuba, at the suggestion of her physician, her father who could not long be separated from her, accompanying her. Is '    CHAPTER VI. IT was George's junior year 'm college; as a scholar he stood well, and had never received an open reprimand from his teachers. Some of the students who had not :een as fortunate, said that it wasn't because Dennie was any less deserving of reproof than themselves, but he had a faculty of never getting  caught in a scrape. Perhaps one reason of this was, that he never had any intimate friends. He room- ed alone, and, unlike most college student4 had no wish for a  confidant. He had neither warm friends nor enemies, owing, it may be, to his natural secretiveness and cautiousness. ' When his patron went to Cuba, he deposit- ed a  sum of money in the Bank, more than sufficient to cover all George's bills, and told the cashier that it was subject to Qeorge's or- d  .  -,            *   &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC7482-00000051"/> u     J L "..l-l .m..mv"- - - A-. We mentioned in the first chapter, George's ndness for games of chance ; he had acquir- L this taste in a measure, from his father, Ad, becoming very skilful in them, was proud his proficiency. He had often played chess  i Id drafts with his college mates, but as yet ad seldom e'n ed in' a game of cards. rambling was tciobidden by the college ales, and the Prelent had often pointed out D the young men, itsdangers. Unfortunately  )r George, he had found in his present- class,  O few students who, regardless of all laws, had act privately, and indulged in the forbidden Iport.  The temptation was strong to join them, andi Le was once called mean and niggardly that he did not do so. This taunt, however, did not move him. He was not an impulsive, fiery temperament, to resent at once a provocation. He took such things coolly, and a spectator might fancy ,that he overlooked it. But it was not so.    never forgave an insult; he only pol :it for the time, but he' did not      , ,., 9   THE LOST WILL.      101 forget it. He carried in his heart a concealed weapon, to wound when he was sure the giver would feel it most keenly. This cool, calculating temperament has more power to resist "temptation, and is therefore more guilty when it yields. George inwardly determined that the young man who flung the taunt shtuld suffer for it. He was a high spirited fellow, who would be exceedingly mortified by disgrace; frank, open, impulsive, full of animal spirits, he had frequently been guilty of mischievous acts, and had received a private reprimand from his teachers, on various occasions, but they loved him  too well to resort to extreme measures, unless compelled by some direct violation of' law. His name was Harper, and he was a Vir- ginian.  He had indulged his love of card playing till it became a passion with him, and he was often obliged to pawn his watch and  1 his diamond pin to raise money   pay his "debts of honor,'" as he called them-* l,  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC7482-00000052"/> 102     TiHE LOST WILL. His chum, Watkins, was in George's room, one day, when Harper rushed in quite furious- ly; "Holloa! Watkins; I'm  hard up. Do help he if you can. Fifty dollars to pay, and I'm two hundred ahead of my allowance now; here's a letter from ' the governor,' who posi- tively refuses another dollar till the term bills come in. What's to be done? I'm not allow- ed to play another game till this debt is paid." "The best thing you can do is not to pay it," said his friend  "Oh, Solon, Socrates, Solomon! with the wisdom of all three, what a judge you will make! Now I've taken your advice, down with the cash. Never give a bitter pill with- out a sweetmeat after it." "Seriously, Harper, I can't do it; I'm poor, you know, and must quit college six months and teach school, to earn money to pay my bills." "Jerum-! stop; I promised my mother I wouldn'swear, and I won't, but I feel des- perately -e it." ^ ,    '      ^:   T'HE LOST WILL.     103 "Pity you didn't promise her you wouldn't gamble." "Goodness! gracious do you think the good woman ever dreamed I'd do suci  a thing? Lands' end! These mothers don't know what their precious sons are sometimes guilty of in college life. Therel've a mind never to touch a card again; for wouldn't it vex her righteous soul to know what trouble I'minnow? I've half a mind to confess the whole to her, premising that she shan't tell the 'governor;' he'd come down on me like a Ni- agara, but she would shed a few tears, then send me the money, and ask me to promise never to touch a card again; and I should do it, because, you know, a fellow with a fraction of a heart couldn't deny a mother' .   '. "You're on the right track now," said Wat- kins; "go ahead." "But shan't I feel mean, though? Then I I can't bear she should know I ever touched cards; no, no; the thing won't answer at all. I shall be like a school-boy, begging off from t  X ,  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC7482-00000053"/> whipping. I believe I'd rather go to the 'gov- ernor' himself, and take the torrent's roar." "I can lend you the money," said Dennie, quietly. "You lend me the money? Did I hear aright?? " said Harper. "Yes; I said I could lend you fifty dollars till close of term." "Oh, Pythias ! thou hast saved thy friend I Romans, countrymen, rejoice with me  I am saved!" and Harper "cut a pigeon wing," and danced round the room with delight, while Dennie counted out the money, and wrote a note -for Harper to sign. George was very correct in his knowledge of business. Watkins looked disappointed. He loved Harper as a brother, and he had hopes that this perplexity might lead Harper to quit card playing. As George had foreseen, this was not the first time that he was called upon to lend Har- per, till finally he had to confess to the cash- ier, from whom he drew his own funds, that he   THE LOST WILL. im   105   had imprudently lent money to Harper, and must wait some time for repayment. Now he knew very well that this cashier was a particular friend of the college president, and that in some way Harper's affairs would be made known to the latter. Thus a train was laid till finally Harper was discovered-his playing became known, and his debts, which amounted to some hundreds, discovered by the faculty. He was of course suspended, to the great grief of his mother, and the indignation of his proud father. George had his revenge. But he was at last caught himself in the meshes of these young gamblers.     Having played a few times, just to show his skill, he was persuaded to play-the stake being an oyster supper. Once in the current it is diffi- cult to turn and row against the tide. Little by little he was led on till he craved the excite- ment of play; for, as is often the case, a cool, quiet temperament like George, becomes more interested in such sport, than in more noisy games of college life. '  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC7482-00000054"/> THES LOST WILL.* At first George was successful and won often, but at last the scales turned, and he was astonished and alarmed when he found that he owed a hundred dollars more than he was com- missioned to draw. Oh! how he regretted that he did not listen to the still, small voice that whispered to him, "Beware," the first time he played for money. It was a quiet summer evening; he was sit- ting by the open window of his room with a book in his hand, when a student came, and puting his head in in at the door, said, "Ten o'clock, No. 6. ' Mum's' the word." George knew what that meant. An hour af- terwards he went out, and on his way to the place, called at the Post Office, and finding a letter in Lucy's well-known hand, returned to his room to read it. It was as follows: WESTBROOK, June 8, 18- DIAF,  GEORGE: Mary says it is my turn to wrt;e, and I am glad it comes while I am at home, in dear old Westbrook.   TRii LOST WILL.          107 I wish you were here, for it certainly never looked so pretty before- perhaps I think so, because I have been in the city so long, sur- rounded by red brick houses and paved streets -but the grass is greener and dandelions brighter and thicker than usual. The apple trees are in blossom, and, oh Georgie I is there any thing more beautiful than an orchard at such a time ? I cannot sew at all, though I meant to hem- stich ever so many shirt ruffles for Sam, and I can't read either.  John laughs and says, 'Lulu, give it all up, don't try to sit still, at all, run out doors and dance and sing as much as you please.' And so I run, and when the robins sing, I sit under the tree or climb up into the branches and sing too; and, will you believe it, some of the birds answer me?    So soon as I stop, they begin, and yesterday a mocking bird, who has a nest in the syringa bush, sang the same tune that I had sung. He did, Georgie, for cer- tain. John's wife takes nice care of my gar- &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC7482-00000055"/> JLO      li L I DU/f JL!IV lj J  den, though I help her a little every morning; the tulips you gave me have increased, and they look richer and more finely dressed than the beautiful ladies on Washington street, and the hyacinths are so fragrant that I wish I could put one in your button hole. The lilacs are in fill bloom, and the violets down in the woods havn't gone yet; I was so afraid that they would be, that I ran down the very first even- ing I returned, but the season is later than usual this year, and there they were, very dear, precious old friends, with a smile and a wel- come for me. i I had a curious notion that they were glad to see me, and (don't you laugh Geor- gie,) I couldn't pluck one of them, but I sat down and talked to them and sung to them, and I go every day to see them -you remember what a pretty place Sit is in a hollow in the woods, an4 how fresh and mossy around. I have been up to the mountain, clear to the tip-top. I wanted to see all Westhrook at once. I love it as much as John's wife doe her baby, and that's not a little, and I love every house   T'i LOST WILL.     109 and every old man, woman and child in it; no, not exactly either--I don't love Jeff, because you don't like him, and because I don't think he's good. He's doing a great business, and Uncle Solomon says he's 'mazin smart,' but I don't love him at all. This morning he said, ' Come Lulu, I am going to take a long ride over to Indian  meadow, and round by the Brook road; get your bonnet and ride with me.' But I dropped him a courtesy and said, 'No, I thank you, Mr. Jeff'-why Georgie, I don't like his great dark face, and when I look- ed at his mouth I felt just like little Red Riding Hood when the wolf said-'Now  I am going to eat you all up,' so instead of riding with Jeff, Ruth and I went over to see old Mrs. Ames, who is' bed-ridden with the rheumatism, and carried her some!cream and cake and cheese. I have never liked Jeff since  he beat you at chess, and that reminds me that Mary told me yesterday all about poor Harper, that was sent away from college. I'm so glad it wasn't you. I believe you don't play cards,  &#xD;<pb n="110" xml:id="VAC7482-00000056"/> LoU     ,T'JE LOST WILL. and I'm so glad; Sam says it is th ruin of hundreds. Don't ever, ever play cards, Georgie. Your mother says, 'George is so fond of games, I have been very much afraid he would be tempted.' But I tell her 'you are strong, and can say no.' I heard yesterday that Nellie Berrie rettirn- ed a few days since. I hope she will come to Westhrook while I am here. Georgie, I want to be good like here I try to obey my mother, and be kind to everybody, but there's some- thing in her heart that there isn't in mine; I wish I knew what it was mother says she is a Christian - well then I want to be one, and I wish to see Nellie to ask her how I can be- come like her. I have got most to the end of my sheet, and hav'nt writtean-4ilf I ntended, but perhaps as much as  Will wish to read. I shall stay here till t rst of September. and we hope you will come home before that time. Your mother and sisters send love, Your affectionate friend, LUCY.'   &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-111" xml:id="VAC7482-00000057"/>   THE LOST tILL.      1" George read the letter the second time care- fully and slowly, and while he was, doing so the clock in his room struck nine. Therq was still an hour before he was to meet his compan- ions. "I have half a mind not to go at all," he said to himself and his mother's sad face was before him. Then Lucy stood by his side; it seemed for a moment as if her little plump hand was again on his shoulder, as in Ad the old time, in his father's office, 'when he was  playing chess with Jeff. "Now, donut,s eorge --please pdon't!" And then he remembered how sad that little face looked when he played,  and how the tears ran when she fled from the office. "No, I will not go," he again repeated, "I'll make some excuse,-- land he settled himself,  to his books, after -placiig Lucy's letter care- fully in his pocket-book.  He had not been studying long' when a stu- , dent entered.  "Ready, Dennie?  See here^.: he said, as from under a clo i he produced i bottle of wine, and a can of oysters.  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC7482-00000058"/> 1iz     'TliJ LSC)j'T WILL. "I think I'll not go to-night," said George, faintly. "Then I shall be disgraced; for the fellows said you wouldn't come,-that you just joined us to find out what was going on, and perhaps turn informer,-that you never wouldlay down one dollar there. I declared, on my honor, that you were too much of a gentleman for that, and if you were not there to-night, I'd pay the whole cost of the supper." i George made no reply, but rose and took his hat. There was a feeling in his heart which he would fain keep there-that even mother, and sistEp and Lucy, wouldn't like to have him called men. When he arrived at the place, he found the windows darkened so that not a ray of light could be seen from the street, ald they had to traverse one or two long, narrow passages before coming to the room, and then gained admittance only by a certain pass-word. All this indicated wrong-doing, and George knew it, and for a moment he thought of home and friends; but it was only a moment, the   THE LOST WILL.      113 transient feeling was exchanged for the thought, "all college boys have- their scrapes; I'm not as bad as most of them, and I know just how far to go. I can stop when I please, which is not the case with all." They were a merry set, full of jokes, and only deterred from making a loud noise, by fear of discovery. The playing commenced, and George took out his pocket book for some money. As he did so, Lucy's letter fell out, and when he stooped to pick it up, he thought of the words within,--" you are strong and you can say no;" and once more he felt the little hand upon his shoulder-"Don't, George- please don't!" So strong was the impression that he rose up, and was going out, determined not to remain; But a sense of the mortification he must endure deterred himp, and he sat down, saying to himself-"I'll not come again." From that moment, he forgot every thing else in the excitement of play; he was not aware himself of his strong passion for such  amusement. He was fortunate and won; this  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC7482-00000059"/> "4     THE LOST WILL. was not strange, for he was wary, cool and deliberate. It was considered to be mean, in the club, to refuse to play after being so succesgful, that George thought it was no more tha:n honorable to go again. And by that time, the still small voice, became fainter and faint- er, till as i have said, George went on, and was a hundred dollars in 4debt over his allow- ance. Vacation came, and found him in this condition. "What was to be ene?" He was sure that his best friend, the Gover- nor? would be seriously displeased. George was xear-sighted and shrewd enough to know that a man of his noble, generous nature, so ready to forgive little faults, would be slow to overlook such grievous misconduct as gambling, night after night, in direct disobedience to col-, lege authority, and to the wishes of all His friends. A good man justly offended can only be appeased by repentance and reformation in the offender. George was hardly ready to promise this, for he was resolved to win the next time, and, if possible, make his loss igood. n - '"       , .  .  .  .   THE LOST -WtL.     115 But he had taken the money sent to him for his term bills to pay his " debts of honor." On his return to B., he was most warmly greeted by Nellie and her father. They were both proud of George ; helhad grown tall, and was now a handsome young man. Nellie's eyes rested on his white forehead and brawn curling hair with all a sisters feeling; it brought back from the dim past a vision of her infancy; a-fair, boyish face, with just such sunny curls. George, on his ;side, was more brotherly and kind in his attention to Nellie, than he had ever been before, and drove her out often, and ask- ed about her Sunday school, and her per pro-  teges. He read to her, and helped her in her lessons, and he begged her to go wih him to Westhrook. This last was very pleasing to, Nellie, and she never seemed happier then when walking or riding with Lucy and George's sisters. There was a very warm friendship sprung up between Lucy and Nellie. cSellie can you come and sit with me in ' *;'                .    ,  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC7482-00000060"/> "6     TuHES LOST WILL. the old summer house, in the garden, a little while?" "Yes, indeed," said the latter; "but I am not strong to-day, Lulu. I cannot run like you. Can you walk slow?" "You'll see if I can't, Nellie. I know I'm always running and dancing, but you lean on me, and I'll go just-as slow as a snail. There, lean harder, I'm very strong. Why Nellie, I was never tired in my life, and never sick; so don't be afraid of hurting me." As they were crossing the street from Mrs. -Dennie's tot the Fox tavern opposite, they met Jeff Devon, who observing Nellie, stopped and was about to offer his services to aid her up the steps of the tavern porch-or piazza. Lucy discerned his intentions, and quick as a- flash, stepped forward to prevent him. "This way, Nellie; here by the side door, it is easier here." Jeff understood her movement, and turned away, but not until he had had a view of Nel- lie's face. It was a face, as we have said be- fore, full of expression,-of suffering patintly   THE LOST WILL.      117 borne, of passion subdued. Even Jeff was a little moved by it, and the face lingered in his memory as one muses 'upon some riddle that they cannot solve. It was not common to see such a face on so young a girl. ' Who was that?" said Nellie. "Oh, that was Jeff-Jeff Devon,-the law- yer here ; don't you see his sign on the office door, opposite to us. Jefferson Devon, Attor- ney and Counsellor at Law--I don't like him; I perfectly hate him; he is a bad man, and I was determined he shouldn't touch you, Nellie. I can't bear to have him touch me; but I'd rather that than put his great big hands on you." "How do you know he is so bad Lucy?" -Why, George says he has cheated his moth- er out of her property ; and-and I don't know; he's always scheming some wickedness, I fancy." They were now at the summer house, and Lucy, Who had brought cushions, arranged a seat for her friend. ( Now, Nellie," said Lucy, "I want you to tell me how to be good, like you; not just  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC7482-00000061"/> 1A -    THE LOST WILL. what. they mean by a good girl, but-but what mother says you are--a Christian." Nellie looked at the face turned so earnestly towards her with an expression of love and ad- miration, which did not imply that she thought there was anything very bad in Lucy. "You, mean, Lucy, not good like me, but like Jesus Christ. I see that you feel that we need something beside a naturally amiable dis- position, and what is called native goodness." "Yes, indeed, Nellie. I have been thinking a great deal about it, lately; and I know, if others don't, that I am a selfish, proud little body, and don't love my enemies, and am often angry and wicked." "I-saw that you did not love your enemies from your treatment to 'Jeff,' as you called hi, just now." Lucy blushed crimson. "Why, Nellie, we can't love bad folks." "Jesus Christ loved them so well, that he died for them." Lucy mused a moment. "Well, Nellie, I    TH"E LOST WILL.    119 couldn't, and there it is. When folks are bad I want to punish them in some way. Now I should be glad if Jeff should lose allhis money." "Wouldn't you rather that Jeff should be- come a good man?" "But he don't want to be good, I guess." "Ay! there is the trouble,-perhaps he does not see that he is bad." "Why, no indeed; I suppose not." "Many did not who heard our Saviour, but he was not angry at that, he only said-' Fath- er forgive them, for they know not what they do.' " Then Nellie went on to explain in her simple, quiet way, that Jesus Christ came into the world to save sinners, and through him a sinful world is redeemed. Her little friend listened meekly and loving- ly, and sheknew now the " way of the cross;" and it seemed at first a hard way. But she never afterwards lost sight of it, and all through her life, she looked back to this interview in the summer-house, as a beginning of a new life I , s  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC7482-00000062"/> 120     'THii  LOST WILL. her, or, as she expressed it, when a woman, I then saw the wicket gate and the path up the hill of Difficulty. It was amusing afterwards to see how she tried to speak kindly to Jeff, and she often prayed that he might be come a good man. Nellie could not help seeing that Mrs. Dennie was perplexed with her straitened circumstan- ces, and with a thoughtfulness beyond her years, proposed to her father that Ruth should come and study with her for a year or two-it would be pleasant' to have a companion( It was Ruth's wish to become a teacher, and Nellie was hoping in this way to enable her to do it. ' "I'm a lucky fellow," said George to him- self, as he took the stage on his return to col- lege at close of vacation. "Not a word about those bills--time enough, now. I'll win back my money, and then adieu to cards f Your boy is a fine looking fellow," said a by-stander to the Governor, as they stood on   121 -THES LOST WILL. S the tavern porch when the stage rolled away from the hotel, " and stands high in his class, I hear." "Yes, said -the governor, with a feeling of pleasurable pride, "I expect much from him." One only trembled for George. Nellie, with her clear, single eye, saw thatheneath George's fair exterior there was no knowledge of what St. Paul meant, when he said, "By faith are ye saved; through faith, and that not of your selves, it is the gift of God." Her warmloving heart was full of prayer for her adopted broth- L C,      .     &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC7482-00000063"/> CHAPTER   VII. IT is near Commencement at Yale. There had been a great deal of speculation as to whether Dennie or Watkins should receive the Valedictory.  The latter was poor; he had struggled manfully to keep his place, but it had been hard. He had taught school win- ters, had sawed wood for the wealthier stu- dents, had worked at manual labor for almost any one that would pay him well, and, to make up for time thus lost by day, had studied deep into the night. But with all these obstacles he had managed to stand decidedly first in his class, and not a student doubted his right to the Valedictory. George  came next, and might have been first had he not lost so much time in his favorite amusement. The contest between these two, had been principally in their Greek studies.  Dennie was originally 122    '   XTHU JUOIL Allh WJLLO ahead here, having entered college with more knowledge of Greek than most Freshmen pos- sess. But the last year found him somewhat ^ behind WVatkins. The latter finding the ex- penses of the Senior year greater than he ex- pected, had found it necessary to take more hours from study than he had previously done, and to atone for it, had risen before light and studied an hour or two each morning. This is a dangerous habit for any, one, and especially bad for students in Greek, the study of that language requiring such fixed attention. Poor Watkins soon found this out to his great sorrow, for three months before the close of the term his eyes failed him, and, with a feel- ing which those only can understand, who have suffered a like trial, he had to relinquish staddy save' for an hour or two by day-light. Then George who had relaxed somewhat when he found that he must stand second, devoted himselfunweariedlyto study. He forgot for the time, that he was now again in debt, or, if he thought of it at all, believed that his suc- J  "^ ^ ^      .      "  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC7482-00000064"/> 124    , THE' LOST WILL. cess would atone for all such errors. But, students, who are eagle-eyed at such times, soon saw through George's object, and were not pleased. Even the officers themselves felt great regret -at Watkins' misfortune, but at the examination stern justice required that the Valedictory should be given to George. His pleasure, however, was somewhat marred' on receiving it, to overhear some students say, "Mean, wasn't it? . if he had been generous, he would have renounced his claim at once; Watkins would have done so in his place." One word from some of the students to the Faculty, would have not only deprived Den- nie of his appointment, but have sent him home in disgrace. He owed already a larger sum than he could command, and Watkins knew it, and how deeply he had indulged in the forbidden amusement; but, like all the rest, he was silent as the Sphinx. Of course the Governor and Nellie were present at the Commencement exercises; Ruth - and Lucy having a special invitation, had come   Il E LOST WIL.     125 down escorted by "brother Sam," who, hav- ing prospered amazingly in the shoe business, had now a little leisure for intellectual im- provement, and was rather pleased than other- wise, to see old 'Squire Dennie's son acquit himself so honorably. As for Lucy, she hid herself in a corner of one of the old fashioned pews and kept her veil over her face, for strange to say, when everybody else was smil- ing, the odd child that loved fun and frolic so well, was actually shedding tears. Nellie was quietly happy, proud of George, and delighted in her father's pleasure. The bustle and ceremony of Commencement were all new to the girls, and was equal to a fairy tale; but the good old Governor had sat upon the stage with other dignitaries, many times before, but never since his own gradua- tion, did he feel so much interest as now, for there was no one that acquitted himself more creditably than George. After the morninmg exercises the Governor and his paty were all invited to a great--d-  &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC7482-00000065"/> wkv     THE LOST WILL. ner, where Ruth and George were particularly noticed; but Lucy had declined the invitation, shrinking from quite so much notice, and pre- ferring a quiet dinner with "Sam," where she could think it all over alone-how nobly George bore himself, how handsome he look- ed, and how much everybody admired him. Lucy did not understand about the pale stu- dent in green glasses, who sat in a distant cor- ner, sad but not envious; disappointed but submissive. She, did not know anything about it then, and it was well she did not, for with her warm, impulsive heart, the pleasure of the day would have been spoiled. She heard of him years afterward, and her heart ached then for his disappointment. Mrs. Dennie sat at home and read Ruth's glowing account of the Commencement with a heart full of love and gratitude. Few persons had known her struggles for the last ew years; she had purposely kept her poverty from George, always telling him that they should a along very well; they would manage in   THE LOST WILL.      127 some way till he was through his profession, and then she must lean upon him for support. Charlie, the baby, (that was) was now a rug- ged little boy, and the fond mother often look- ed forwar to the time when his elder brother /would take the place of father to the little one. Mary was a faithful daughter and took iupon herself the cares of the house, making butter and cheese, and working hard to relieve her mother, whose health was delicate. But with all their toil, they found it difficult to keep even with the world, and Mrs. Dennie had long felt that her path was hard. Lucy's visits to Westhrook were like rays of sunshine to Mrs. Dennie, and we might add to the whole neighborhood.  She cameevery summer to pass a few weeks, and each year she grew more loving and lovely. She was now a tall, graceful girl of fourteen, full of health antvivacity, 'and not at all likely to be spoiled by city life. "If Sam" has a great house with fine carpets and mirrors, and jr- vants, it isn't half as pleasant " shi iid, 'as  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC7482-00000066"/> 1[28     THE LOST WILL. the woods and- flowers and birds of her old home." One summer day, a year after her interview with Nellie in the summer house, she went out on a bright, sunny morning to gather straw- berries on Eagle mountain. There was one spot on the side of the mountain which sloped southward, where the earliest berries were al- ways to be found. 'Lucy resolved to surprise John's wife with a basket-full for tea. Her path led through a meadow at the foot of the mountain; this was the meadow that had once belonged to 'Squire Dennie, and which many believed "Jeff" had acquired by some techni- cality in law, which gave him a legal, but not a moral right to its possession. When Lucy came to the path, she saw Jeff. there superin- tending some laborers who were building a fence. Lucy, we know, was quick and impul- sive, and very indignant at all wrong. Only the day before she had learned from Mary that they were now under the necessity of hiring their cows pastured, so much had their land   THE LOST WILL.     129 been reduced in the settlement of the- estate. As she said, "she couldn't bear the sight of Jeff.," and was turning away to find another path to the mountain. But Jeff. was too quick for her. He let down the bars, and bid- ding her "Good morning," said, "-My buggy is here, Lucy; let me drive you to the foot of the mountain." "No, I thank you, Mr. Devoll;" said Lucy, with a little toss of the head which meant more plainly than words could have expressed it, "I don't like you at all, and wish to have nothing to do with you." Jeff. was shrewd enough to see it and un- derstand it, too, but he merely bowecd and stood a moment looking after her as she trip- ped with a light step across the, meadow, Lucy didn't turn back, she was only too glad ' to get away from him, but she couldn't quite put him out of her mind. '"There," she said to herself, " it is too bad; the very sight of him makes me out of humor for the day ;" and her face flushed, and her  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC7482-00000067"/> 130      THE LOST WILL. step quickened as her indignation rose. She found the berries, riper and thicker than she expected, and was surprised to find when she had filled her basket, that the sun was so high in the heavens. She sat down under a tree, and was allow- ing her busy fancy to picture George's future. It was a very bright little day-dream, and bright for herself, too, for was her own future not mingled with his? It had been for many years; and the little locket that he had given, her when he first went away from home, still hung around her neck, its resting-place ever since the parting in the old office. She had had many presents from George, more costly ones, but none so precious to her as this. She was older now and understood things better, and George himself had said to her, at Commengement, "Lucy, it is for your sake I value these honors." Lucy supposed herself far out of sight and hearing, and as she picked over her strawher- ,*        v    THE LOST WILL.        131 she began singing one of the songs of her childhood: "When o'er earth is breakinT Rosy light and fair; Morn afar proclaimeth Sweetly God is there; Sweetly God is there." As she repeated the chorus, she was startled and vexed to hear a man's voice take: lp; tie song. At first she thought it was Jeff.'s, and she rose up indignantly, with flushed face and headerect.  But as the singer went on-   :: "Let us learn these lessons Taught us everywhere; And if sin assail us, Think that God is there;'  Then at last with angels, Ever bright and fair, Singing glorious anthems, We'll see' God is there,'" Lucy recognized the voices of the mAnister of Westhrook, a faithful, hum le, devout 'man, for whom she entertained great respect and reve r  e  -. He was o  "who: Ioved his!:for -jA u  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC7482-00000068"/> 182     THUE LOST WILL. and felt the responsibility of laboring for the salvation of souls. He knew Lucy's voice, and thus answered her. He was on his way to visit a poor family who lived in a little house near the mountain, and by taking this path he could enjoy the scenery and the walk. He sat down a few moments and entered /into converation, and Lucy was only too glad to hear him. He was one to whom she could talk freely, and there was almost always some perplexity in her pind, some doubt about a doctrine or Bible truth, and Mr. Herbert made it so plain to her that she liked to go to him. Lucy had already a trembling hope that she was a child of God, but it was singular that one of her bright, impulsive, hopeful tempera- ment, should not have stronger evidence and firmer faith. Mr. Herbert was one of those ministers whose hearts are so full of God's love, and so "apt to teach," that religious topics never seemed forced upon others; his whole conver- sation was godly, and it is not strange now, v , i '. : * I ; - ' . .    THE LOST WILL.      133 that his remarks upon the beauty of the day glided into that deeper, spiritual discourse, which showed he lived that higher Christian life which Moses called "Nalking with God." "I don't know," said Lucy; "I am much troubled about this 'giving up all for Christ.' I dare not, Mr. Herbert, come forward and profess myself a Christian, till I can say with St. Paul, 'I count all things else but loss save the knowledge of Christ Jesus.'"  "Perhaps, Lucy," said the minister, " you are troubling yourself with unnecessary per. plexities, wondering whether you could be a martyr if called to the stake, or, if you could leave all and go to a foreign land; or, if bou give up lands and houses and friends, as the early Christians did, for Christ's sake and the gospel's," "That's just it, Mr.. Herbert; I have no confidence in myself that I could do these things, and I know if I cannot I am not a child of God." "Suppose, Lucy," said Mr Herbert, "that  .pe Luc    sad31.  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC7482-00000069"/> 134 5trHOi LOST WILL. you first ask yourself, 'Am I doing the duties that lie nearest to me?' If we can perform these, we may hope that God will give us strength for greater, when we are called to them. If you are not required to be a mission- ary in a foreign land, are you doing all you can for Christ here at home? Is yoaur example such, that others around you may- know that you walk with God, and be led to follow you. "If you can practice the self-denial that is Sequired daily of those who would live for oth- ers, love their enemies, and do good to the un- thankful and evil, as Christ did, then you may be sure you could follow the Saviour as the holy women of old did, even up Mount Cal- vary." Lucy was silent and thoughtful for a  few minutes. This was ^ new test to her, and she was inwardly trying herself by it. Mr. Herbert sat looking round on the beau tiful scene spread out before him. He loved the works of nature as almost every true Chris- tian does, but this good pastor never .limbed - f ::,  *   *    'T'HE LOST WILL.     135 the mountain, but he turned at last from sky and clouds, woods, fields and river, to the little houses scattered here and there in the vallies and on the hills, and to the dwellers therein, and prayed like a good shepherd that he was - "Father, let not one of these be lost; re- member them all when thou comest into thy kingdom." The meadow at the foot looked green and fresh; the men could be seen at work on the fence, and Devoll's horse and buggy still stood under the shade of a wide-spreading elm, while the lawyer himself was in busy consultation with some client, who, not finding him in his office, had sought him here. "I wish that man was a Christian," smid the minister. "Who do you mean?" asked Lucy. ', Devoll, the young lawyer." "He is far enough from it now," said Lucy, :j! with a degree of asperity in her voice, which : caused Mr. Herbert to turn and look inquir- =mgly at her.      '  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC7482-00000070"/> --     4 X- A a s4 yVe0l y 1.J U J Lucy, who had no secretiveness in her char- acter, added, as if in reply to his questioning look, "I despise that man, and I don't know as I have faith to believe that he can be convert- ed." "Lucy!" said the mirnister, in a tone of mingled reproof and surprise, " would you lim- it God's power? But I think you must have allowed your prejudices to lead you astray. There are strong points in Devoll's character; his intellect is above the average of country lawyers; he has a clear head, is able in de- bate, and enters with his whole soul into any business he undertakes. Like St. Paul, if he became a Christian, he would work for God, as he now works for worldly riches and honor." "He works well for himself, I acknowl- edge," said Lucy; "but he has little regard to the rights of others." Mr. Herbert understood Lucy now, but, as he had his own opinion about Mrs. Dennie's  affairs, and as that opinion warihardly more   -Tisl LOST WILL.     137 favorable to George than to Devoll, he was si- lent. The minister had studied George's char- acter more closely than, any of his friends, and, in his own mind, felt that the selfishness of the student was as displeasing to God, as the shrewd worldliness of the lawyer. , It is not good for our peace of mind, Lucy, to indulge such feelings towards any person, and especially towards a neighbor that we meet daily. May it not be Christian duty to overcome it? Help me, if you can, to show him the beauty of a Christian life." "Oh, dear!" thought Lucy, "'if it is a Christian duty to be kind and sociable to Jeff., then I have a cross to bear." Such were her thoughts as, near midday, she came down the hill. The day was warm,  her walk had been long, and she was a little weary. It did not occur to her mind that she might have an opportunity to test' her willing- ness to follow Mr. Herbert's -advice so soon. But as she came to the meadow, there stood Jeff's horse and buggy, and he was just about  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC7482-00000071"/> 138    - THE LOST WILL. getting in to ride to the village, as she came to the bars. She would gladly have retreated, - but that did. not seem possible, and, as she went forward, her face involuntarily assumed the same haughty, scornful look which she al- ways tried to put on when she met Jeff. The minister's words occurred to her - "Help me, if you can, to show him the beauty of a Chris- tian life." "Lucy," said Jeff.," I know you are tired, and if you will not, ride with me home, you are welcome to the horse and buggy; Jennie is spirited and will not bear the whip, but I be- lieve you understand  horsemanship so well that you need have no fear." Lucy choked down a very uncomfortable sensation, for even a compliment from "Jeff.," was more unwelcome to her than a harsh word. "Thank you, Jeff.; I will hardly venture to drive Jennie ; you had better keep the reins, but I will accept your offer of a ride, and she sprang quickly into the buggy, without ait- ing for him to aid her.   ITHE LOST WILL.       139 Devoll looked   surprised and gratified. They had two miles to ride, and for the sake of conversation, Lucy remarked that she had met Mr. Herbert on the mountain, and remain- ed longer than she intended, adding- "I al- ways like to talk with him." "If there is anything in religion, I think that man is a Christian," said Jeff. "If!" did you say? asked Lucy. "Yes, I said if, for did I believe as Mr. Herbert does, I should live like him."' Lucy remembered what the minister had said, that if Jeff. was only a Christian, he would work for God as he now worked, for himself. She did not feel inclined to enter into any argument, but she simply remarked, "Mr. Devoll, I think no one can study the life and character of Jesus Christ without being convinced of the truth of Christianity." "Perhaps not; I suppose I have judged it too much by its professed followers. I have some- times thought I would sit down seriously and examine the Bible for myself- read it as I do  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC7482-00000072"/> "O     T HE LOST WILL. Blackstone, with a desire to understand the truths it teaches; but my business occupies my time, and, like most other men, I put off such things till that convenient time, which I believe never comes." "Mr. Devoll," said Lucy, (whRtPa struggle there was in Lucy's heart just then.) "I have a Bible which Nellie Berry gave me, with ,passages and references marked by her own hand. It was the means of great good to me, and I wish you would take it and read it, turn- ing to her references as you read." "Be sure I will," said Jeff. "I'll begin this very day, Lucy." "Wait a minute, then," said Lucy, whose impulsive disposition always led her to act im- mediately. "I'll run and get it now." She went to her room to procure the book, while Jeff. stood at the steps waiting. In her haste she forgot to remove some little notes of her own which she had made as she read. Jeff. thanked her and drove away, wondering ot a lttle within himself, at such kind treat- ment from the hitherto scornful little lady.   THE LOST WILL.      141 It was true that Jeff. had been sadly ne- glected in his childhood; his father was intem- perate; there was a large family to provide for, and the discouraged wife and mother had gone to an early grave, leaving her children to fight the battle of life with many odds against them. Jeff. had great ambition, a strong will, and much physical endurance ; step by step he had fought his way along, but all the time a feeling as if the world had wronged him, and he would settle the bill as best he could, had taken pos- session of him, and he had too often been actu- ated by it. When Lucy saw Jeff.'s great handgrasp the precious, gold-claspedTfible, her heart misgave her, and she felt as if it was almost polluted by the touch. Then Mr. Herbert's words again occurred to her-"Help me to show him the beauty of a Christian life," and she bade JeffE "Good evening," with a smile, and then ran up to her own room and had a hearty cry. "Oh, dear! it is so6 hard to be good! i  &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC7482-00000073"/> CHAPTER 5V111. GEORGE DENNIE was a student of law in his patron's office, but unfortunately the Gov- ernor was away a great deal, and George- was left much in the society of a junior partner, who, though a fine scholar and eloquent advo- cate, was a man of loose morality, and of great, recklessness in money matters. He was past forty but unmarried; and having thus no home or domestic ties, often invited George to pass his evenings with him at his hotel. The at- traction here was often greater than the quiet parlor where Nellie and Ruth were reading, sewing, or practicing. The girls tried to make that home pleasant to the brother. Nellie's eyes always grew brighter and her cheeks had more color when "brother George " was with them. He, had learned soon after he came into the family, that the way to the father's heart- "2   THE LOST. WILL.      143 and purse was through the daughter, and he had acquired the habit of polite and respectful attention to Nellie. Besides this, George was naturally quiet and gentlemanly in his man- ners, and had a pride in being so; as a lawyer, he bade fair to win a judge and carry a jury by blandness of manner and persuasiveness of rhetoric, rather than by the sledge hammer mode of argument, which was Jeff.'s forte. George's manners were particularly pleasing to the gentle Nellie, and having so few on earth that she could claim the right to love and live for, she centered a world of affection and interest on her adopted brother, as she called him. Her father never spoke of him in this way; he had been careful not to encourage this idea in George. It had been his intention only to educ tehim, to fit him for life, and when he had thus armed him for the battle,- let him go out and gain strength in the contest by his own efforts.. The young man himself unr- derstood this, so that no false hopes were raised to end in disappointment.  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC7482-00000074"/> "4     THEB LOST WILL. But Nellie would have made any sacrifice for George. She had looked forward with much pleasure to his return from college, be- cause he would be at home while he was study- ing his profession. "Don't, George," she would say,  eave much to do with Mr. Tracer; he is a scholar and a good lawyer, but I fear he hal-k ttle moral principle." "Never, fear, Nellie; with your father's ex- ample on one side, and you for a monitress on the other, I cannot go far astray." "Oh, Georgie, that will never do. You must have strength within yourself to resist temptation - strength from God." "Well, Nellie, then you must pray for me; I set very little value on my own prayers." "I do pray for you, Georgie, every day, and sometimes every hour of the day;" and Nel- lie's eyes filld with tears, as she looked earn- estly at George, who thought only as he saw the flushed cheeks and moist eyes, " how pret- ty Nellie would be, if-- " and then he turn-   'THU LOST WILL.     145 ed away; "poor thing, it is well she has mon- ey and position;" then came a vision of Lucy, so healthy and bright, so buoyant and beauti- ful, and as he walked down the avenue, he hummed the song- "A jewel that a king might wear." George never wavered in his interest in Lu- cy he was proud of her beauty and acquire- ments, and his was not a fickle temperament ; whether his love would have enred if misfor- tune or loss of personal charm had come to Lucy, we know not. Mr. Herbert, if asked the question, would have gravely shaken his head, and said, "I should have my fears." It was Nellie's birth-day, and the close of Ruth's course of study. A school had been obtained for her, and the next morning she was to leave to try her fortune as a teacher. She was in fine spirits herself, because she was sure now, that she could aid her mother. It was a winter's dayi clear and cold; but the sunshone  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC7482-00000075"/> ightly on the hills white with snow; and on e old pine woods, where the deep green foli- re was brightened by the white fringe that 'ooped from every bough. The governor was in Washington, but he eve orders that Nelly must have a birth-day trty. Mrs. Mills, the house-keeper, was a otherly, good woman, who had been so long the family, and was so highly esteemed, that ke was not only house-keeper, but Nellie's iend -and counsellor. Then Mr. Berry wrote tat George was now old enough to do the mors of the house in his absence, and he )ped the party would go off pleasantly, even he should be absent. The young folks were pleased, and Nellie, ho naturally shrunk from such amusements, itered with her whole heart in the matter, hen she found that George and Ruth were de- ghted with the plan. For a week, she puz- ed over the receipt book, and was half of the me in a brown study over cakes and custards, rhips, jellies, &amp;c., &amp;c. Whatever she did,   must be well done; and Mrs. Mills, who felt that the responsibility and the honor belonged, in a great measure, to her, entered into the mat- ter with great zeal and good will. George, too, was called in as counsellor, and the four had various long consultations upon  ornamental cookery, and in the selection of guests. For a day or two, George was as active as Mrs. Mills herself, but as the time drew near, he was more reserved, and seemed silent and almost moody. Ruth rallied him a little upon his indifference, and he replied, almost testily, "I'm too busy for such matters." "Never mind," said Nellie, "don't trouble him Ruth, we girls forget that George has grave studies to occupy him now; only, Geor- gie, you must promise to give us the afternoon of Thursday, for-we need your taste in arrang- ing  some matters. Mary was invited from Westhrook, and Lucy from/Boston. The latter wrote that she should certainly be there to see -Ruth once more, unless there should come a snow-storm that six horses could i,  &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC7482-00000076"/> "8      T6HB LOST WILL. not breast. The day dawned bright and fair, and gave prospect of pleasant weather to come. Matters had gone well in the -kitchen,--the oysters and confectionary had arrived from the city, much to the quiet of Mrs. Mills' nerves, -the turkeys were roasted to a turn, and set away to cool, and the pantries and cellar were stored with cold ham and tongue, and all sorts of delicate cookery, which would have puzzled many heads to name, but Mrs. Mills could give receipts for all with mathematical accuracy. The girls had retired to their rooms after an early dinner, to rest awhile. George, too, was alone in his room, for he had promised to re- main inthe house. But he was thinking little of the party just then. He sat at a table with' writing materials before him, and was very earnestly writing, again and again, "N. W. Berry." His head was bent down, and every turn of the letters, every heavy stroke, or hair mark, was studied, then would he throw the scrap of paper aside, as if dissatisfied, and rise and walk the -room, muttering to himself, "It v   THE LOST WILL.     -  49 must be done, what's the use of deferring it? If these debts are discovered I am ruined for life. If I can pay 'em in this way, and replace the money before he returns from Washington, I am safe enough. Perhaps he never will dis- cover it, he is so easy about money matters, but Tracer will expose me if I don't pay, and then, ard then, and then I " Then George would sit down again and write, but his hand trembled, or the pen was bad, and lie could not satisfy himself. Thus he spent an hour, alternately walking and writing. At last, as he was walking back and forth, an idea occurred to him, -he had the signature, and placing a note over it, was about to trace with his pen, when a carriage stopped at the door, and Lucy's bright, radiant face was upturned to George I He dropped pen and paper to the floor, and his own face was crimson to the roots of his hair. Again, as twice before in his life-time, she had come between him and temptation, or rather, for there was nothing out of the common course  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC7482-00000077"/> "UV     -'   LOSTr WILL,. in the matter, he had been for the moment with- held from crime by her presence or her mem- ory. "Saved!" a voice seemed to whisper, and George went out of his room, locked the door, and came down to meet Lucy. The three girls stood together, but the most beautiful was Lucy. She had retained the beauty of her childhood, but beyond this, there was now an expression in her face that gave grace and dignity to her whole manner, as of one at peace with God, at peacse with her own soul. The first greeting over, the girls retired with Lucy to her room to remove her travelling dress, and George was left alone in the room. He stood leaning upon the mantle for a mo- ment, then turned hastily away and went up to his chamber. "If I don't do this I am surely discovered, and then she is lost to me, -my only safety is here."?  But it he took the papers from the floor, he   MTHE LOST WILL.     151 *started, dropped them again, and turned to the door. He fancied Lucy was there, and he heard her voice, "Please don't, Georgie," but it was very low; he listened a moment, -it was only the echo of her clear, merry laugh in the adjoining room. He hesitated a moment, and then deliberately, calmly, arranged his pa- pers, and traced with a firm hand the signature. "There, that is perfect; Brown's eagle eye can't detect that, if he has been cashier these ten years." I Thenr George folded it, threw on his cloak and hat, and walked down street as quietly, and spoke as blandly to every one he met, as if he were only out for the purpose of meeting friends. He went into the bank, presented the check, recounted the money after Brown, bade him good morning with a smile, and walked away. One hour from that time he was at home, as- sisting the girls in some ornamental arrange- ment of the rooms, laughing and talking merri ly. I said laughing; George did but little ot  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC7482-00000078"/> 152     THE LOST WILL. that, for 'he never, from childhood, laughed heartily. It was not his habit, but Lucy made up for his deficiency,-from childhood, she was a merry laugher, eyes, mouth, and indeed her whole body laughed, when in one of her merry moods. It is a fact, though I cannot explain the phi- losophy of it, that many persons after com-mit- ting a crime, are more calm and self possessed than they were for days before the deed was done, and while they are yet innocent, save in thought. George became more sociable as eve- ning approached, and when the guests arrived, Nellie was proud of his manly, affable bearing, and the quiet, gentlemanly way with which he greeted all the guests, not excepting the very homely Misses P., in green d'laines, which made them look so pale and ghastly; nor even the old maid, Miss Nolles, who was arrayed in a white crape, made very low in the neck, which, as her neck was exceedingly long and bony, rather served to expose her want of beauty than to display her charms. But George   , THUE LOST WILL.     153 waited upon her to the supper table, and listen- ed very complacently to her bravado mode of singing, and turned the leaves for her. Just as supper was announced, and George was leading Miss Nolles from the drawing- room, there was a sound of voices in the hall, and Judge Hall was heard saying, "Good evening, governor, good evening I This is a pleasant surprise, surely, - we are all here to greet you, just in time, too, for I hear '1 Dy the summons to supper." i I    "Why, father I this is pleasant,-how did you come at this hour?" "I should have been here two hours ago, but for an accident to the coach; but I am glad to be so near the right time. Ah! my rose-bud, is that you?" as Lucy stepped forward to greet him, after Nellie and Ruth had welcomed his return. "A sight,of your merry face pays me for my long dull ride, -where is George?" "Oh, doing his duty, sir," said Lucy, "he was leading Miss Nolles out to supper, a mb- ment sirce."  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC7482-00000079"/> 154     THE LOST WILL. "Right, right, he is a good boy,- let me supply his place as well as I can, though a gray -head will hardly match those dark curls as well as George's brown locks," and the gallant old man gave his arm to Lucy, and they moved to- wards the table, followed by the t rty, who felt that the evening was brighter or his pre- sence. All save one. When that voice fell on George's ear, he turned pale as the crape of Miss Nolles' robe, and a sickness came over him, so that he felt faint as a feeble woman. He rallied in an instant, however, and said to his companion, "There is a pleasant place by the bay-window,--let me lead you there." "'Oh, how beautiful the tables look, Mr. Dennie." "What shall I help you to, Miss Nolles?" "Where all is so tempting, I know not what to choose," was her reply, t" select yourself." What George did select he cared not to have told, but the lady was somewhat amused todfind cold turkey, ice cream and Charlotte Russe, on the same plate.   THE LOST WILL.      155 "Dishes are scarce," she whispered to a Idy who stood near. "Or the gentleman absent minded," was the reply. "Excuse me a moment, Miss Nolles, I see some ladies who have niot come out to supper." The lady bowed her long neck with as much grace as she was mistress of, and George open- ed one side of the glass door to make his way back to the drawing-room, without encounter- ing the crowd that were pressing forward. The cold air was welcome to him. He stopped a moment, pushed his hair back from his fore- head, and let the fresh breeze blow upon him. "What shall I do if discovered now," was his first query, and his blood seemed to curdle: in his veins at the thought. "Confess your fault," whispered conscience. "Better now than later. A kind Providence has sent your friend here just at this time. Go to him before you sleep, lay your whole heart and life open before him; receive submissively what punishment he may inflict, and henceforth, be true to him and yourself."  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC7482-00000080"/> 156     THE LOST WILL. Such was the first suggestion of George's conscience, as he afterwards acknowledged, but pride forbade, and the tempter said, 4Secrete your sin, carry a bold face, you may win the game yet." George listened, and -conscience was silenced. He passed on, and entered the drawing-room just as the governor, who had led Lucy into the dining-room, turned back to offer his arm to the Misses P. Thus they met, face to face; the old gentleman cordial, hearty as ever, and George with his usual smile and respectful ad- dress. "So it seems you and I were on the same errand; well, well, we old gentlemen must sub- mit to be eclipsed by the younger ones, but I'll not yield all to him. Miss Jane, the pleasure of your company," offering his arm to the elder of the two sisters, while George followed with Miss Susan. For the rest of the evening, not a guest there would have dreamed from the calm, handsome face of George, as he moved freely around the   THlE LOST WILL,      157 rooms, that there was within his soul a tempest of fear and guilt. It was hard work for him to smile and repeat the thousand little nothings which form the staple of party talk, and yet he dreaded the breaking up of the party. -What might not the morrow have in store for him? But the good people of B. were not accus- tomed to late hours, and at the now unfashion- able hour of eleven, the last carriage had rolled away, and the family stood in the deserted ban- quet room. Mrs. Mills was receiving the compliments of the governor for her fine table, while the girls dike most others of their sex and age,) were trying some of the dishes of which they had not partaken during the evening. "Oh, George, do have some of this jelly cake," said Nellie, "I did not see you eat a mouthful while the guests were here." "Nor I," said Ruth, "but I did see -him pile. Miss Nolles' plate as if he supposed she came here in a famished state,-turkey add ice  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC7482-00000081"/> 158     THl LOST WILL. cream together, -extremes met. I ventured, George, to provide her with a saucer and spoon to cover your deficiency." "-Thank you, sister; but I intended to be very civil to Miss Nolles." "Yes, I'll defend you on that point," said the governor, " you behaved as every true gen- tleman should. I was pleased to see you leav- ing the young beauties of the party, and be- stowing your attentions where they were the most needed and. most prized." Nellie smiled (nd looked grateful. "My daughter," said her father, l"et me wait upon you up stairs to your room. I am afraid the excitement and fatigue of the party will be too much for you; I was anxious to reach home on this account." "Oh, father, I am not at all tired,--I think the party has done me good; everything has passed off so pleasantly. It has been delight- ful. Don't you think so, Lucy?" Lucy, who looked as fresh yet as a rose bud in the morning, replied, %j   THE LOST WILL.      159 "Yes, indeed I and I should like to begin it all over again now." "Oh, youth!" exclaimed the governor, "Iife's brightest season I What would I give for one more draught? To be honest, children, I think my easy-chair and slippers by the fire- side, will be more agreeable than all the -nice dishes, fine music, and pretty speeches of the evening." "You shall have your wish, sir," said Lucy, "please let me escort you to your elysium, yon- der is the-chair," "and here are the slippers," chimed in Ruth, " and here the dressing gown," added Lucy. "Ha I ha!" said the old gentleman, "I am really in fairy land; you see young gentleman, that we older ones are not wholly pushed aside yet; all three bestowing their favors upon me,- a, while you are left to take care of yourself." "Take a seat upon the lounge, 6erge," said Nellie, "I know you mudt: be tired, for you have worked hard to-day."' The curtains were drawn, the door closed,  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC7482-00000082"/> and the little circle gathered round the bright fire for a few minutes. ' Now, children," said the old gentleman, 'I have come home only for three days to rest, and I hope to be allowed to sit in this easy chair, surrounded by my fairies. George, I shall de- pend upon you to attend to business matters for me; and Ruth, we will keep you here a little longer, that I may have your company on my return. I did not like the idea of your leaving home alone, and Nellie and Lucy must make music for us. You see I am planning for my own happiness." "None the less for ours," said Nellie, who looked brighter and happier than usual. "Now, Lucy, a good-night song, and then commending ourselves to the protection of Heaven, we will retire to rest." 4f   CHAPTER IX. "Will the governor be down to the Bank, to-day," said Brown, the Cashier, to George, as he came in on some errand from Mr Berry, on the morning after the party. The question was carelessly asked as Brown was folding a letter. George turned pale, and for an instant he thought his guilt discovered. He did not reply at once and the Cashier turn- ed towards him- "Why, Dennie, how pale you look! Rather the worse for the party, I suppose. For my: part I should like such an one every week, What was I saying? Oh-I asked, I believe if the governor would be down to-day?" "I think tiot, he is very tired." "To-morrow is the meeting of the bank di- rectors," said/rown. "Just mention it to him, if you please." 161  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC7482-00000083"/> THE LOST w l..u. George got away from the bank as soon as possible, but he thought to himself, "I shall not charge my memory with that commission. At one momenthe thought he would leave town, and if discovery came, he could remain away. But then what a dark future before him! He took along walk thinking the matter over. Perhaps all will be well yet. His hopes, whispered, Brown did'nt seem suspicious and with this thought George returned home, where a  happy group awaited him. Lucy was not there, for John had come over from Westrook for her, but the Governor and Nellie and Ruth were busy with some new books, which he had bought, and Mrs. Mills was just bringing on lunch. " Oh, George I" exclaimed Nellie with unus- animation, "come and look at our New Year's Presents--a set of law books for you, the British poets for me, and this silk dress for George turned to the large table and there   THE LOST WILL. .63 saw an expensive and choice set of such works as he was needing. For a moment he was humbled, and conscience stricken. How was he treating the friend, who was so constantly mindful of his wants? He stammered out some thanks, while his friends attributed his hesitation to his modesty and gratitude. - He took some suitable notice of the other presents, holding the silk to the light and ad- miring its lustre and thickness. George passed the afternoon writing for Mr. Berry, and the evening, in making some fare- well calls, with Ruth. These,at his own re- quest, were short, for his timid conscience did : not permit him to remain long out of sight of his patron; he had a fancy that he could in some way avert discovery while they were to- gether. The next morning, when George drew aside  the curtains of his window, he fouid a cold, driving rain storm without. "Good luck!" he  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC7482-00000084"/> exclaimed, "the Governor will not go out  t day, fortunate for me at least, that he has a bad cold." " George," said the old gentleman after break- fast, as he sat looking at his memorandum book, " will you do some errands for me in he village? I suppose a rain storm will not keep you in the house." " Not at all,. Sir. I shall be happy to do any thing in my power for you." "Let me see-you must settle Bates' bill, be sure and take a receipt, call round and see Mr. Walker, and hand him this little package; its my, New Year's present   he   iter forget to go to the bank and ask if there important business before the Directors '"^ Brown asked if you were coming, yester- day, and I told him you were not verywell, and he said there was nothing of importance requiring your presence."   [Ah, George, George! one sin is the parent of many others.]    "Glad of that, glad of that," said .the old gentleman, "I was afraid that they were having some little trouble about their charter, and if so it must be settled at once, and I should be an important witness. But I'm glad enough to stay quietly at home. Its pleasant in our old age to have young limbs and young hearts to do for us. Had'nt you better take the horse and sleigh?" "I prefer walking, Sir!" "That's right--the oak grows strong by breasting the storm, now off with you,- but be sure and be at home to dinner. I want to have you with me as much as possible while I am at home." The three:days' allotted by Mr. Berry for his visit at home passed quickly away. On the 'fourth morning the stage came punctually at the appointed hour, and found the old gentle- -man and Ruth warmly wrapped in cloakslaind 'furs ready for their cold ride. Mrs. Mills and Ruth, and George were all  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC7482-00000085"/> 100     THE LOST WTILL. desirous to do something more for the comfort of the travellers. Nellie had a couple of free- stones heated and wrapped in paper, for their feet. George had persuaded the driver to put in extra buffaloes, and Mrs. Mills was tying a piece of kid over the cork of a bottle of cough drops, which she was telling the Governor he must reme mer and take " a tea-spoonful every morning, Sir. George had seen the trunks securely strap- ped on and now came in-"Me 'ready, Sir," the last words were said, the last kiss given, and to the sound of merry bells the large, com- fortable, country sleigh, drawn by four noble horses, glided swiftly away. George stood on the porch looking after it, till it had turned the corner and ascended the mountain road leading westward--then he could hardly refrain from a shout, so great was his relief. "I'm a lucky one," he said, " time and chance are my friends." -' .-   THE LOST WILL.      167 "George, don't stand out there in the cold," said Nellie, pleasantly; "' come in and sit by the fire awhile." "We shall be lonely, George', I am afraid. Ruth's absence will make a great void in the house."  Poor Nellie sobbed as she spoke: her warm, loving heart clung so closely to her friends, that partings were harder for her than for many others. "' We'll try not to be, Nellie ; I must stay a home more. Look for me, this evening, to read some of these new books, with you." Nellie's eyes brightened.  "Let us read Cowper, together, George; his poetry seem best read by the fire-side. I fancy that he loved quiet, domestic life very much, and yet he was never married." "I believe some, of the best poetry on mal ried life and domestic bliss, were written b men who were never married, or who lived un- happily with their wives," said George. "No, no, George; I think you are mis- taken."  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC7482-00000086"/> 168     T'ii LOST WILL. "Why, Nellie, read Milton; doesn't he say of marriage ' The only bliss that has surviv- ed the fall,;' and no writer has so beautifully delineated such bliss, as that life of Adam and Eve which he pictures in Paradise." "But remember, George, that Milton had daughters who made life very pleasant to him." "True, Nellie; and I sometimes wonder that our poets do not oftener describe that beautiful affection which exists between father and daughter; it's a very pure and satisfying love, if I may be allowed to judge by what I see. "Oh George, you are right; there is no earthly happiness to me like the society of my father, and I make it my daily prayer that I may not let my love turn to idolatry." "There are not many such fathers, Nellie." "True, true, George; you and I are favor- ed. Do you know, George, I think that fath- er loves you as well as if you were his own child?"   T'HiE LOST WILL.     169 "He loves me better than I deserve," was the reply; and for the moment George feJt all that he said. As he walked down street to his office he heartily regretted the past. "Now if I can only manage to pay that note before he sees it I'll keep clear of such things hereafter. But if I am discovered he may not be hard with me. It's nothing more nor less, I sup- pose, than forgery." As the word passed through his mind he shuddered. "A forger!" he mentally repeated. "Pshaw! nonsense I I didn't mean anything wrong --and I'll set it all right yet;" and George walked on, and many that saw the tall, handsome young man walking along Main street that day, envied him; such a favorite with the Governor, and, with such fine talents--lucky fellow  But let us turn bac to Westhrook. Though it is winter, and the snow many feet deep, and though the winds blow cold from the hill tops, and sweep in long dreary blasts through the  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC7482-00000087"/> 170      rfiE LOST WILL. vallies, yet there is life and enjoyment there. ]Wright warm fires are always found in Fox's tavern, and there are meetings and singing schools in the village, and merry sleigh-rides, where healthy, happy young hearts beat to music and laughter. There is a light also, late at night, almost always in Jeff. Devoll's office. He studies late and rises early; it used to be said that he was finding out all the crooks and turns of the law, by which, when he chose, he could make the worse appear the better side. We will turn back a little in this history. When Jeff. re- ceived the little Bible so daintily bound in Turkey morocco and gilt, Lucy need not have feared that he would use it roughly, because he was large and rough himself. At any rate her fears would have vanished at once could she have seen with what care it was covered, and what a nice little box was provided to keep it in. When night came and the whole village was wrapped in sleep, save himself,   THE LOST WILL.      171 JefF. closed his office blinds, fastened his doors, and sat down with that Bible in his hand. At home in his childhood, he had heard his father scoff at the book, and as he grew older he had imbibed the idea that it was suited to the weak minds of women and children -'that strong men needed no such teaching. But 'in his law practice he found that the most learned advocates in their county courts, was well versed in the literature of the Bible, quoted it often, and always with respect. This led him to say that he would at least become better acquainted with it, but, with the excep- tion of going to hear Mr. Herbert preach more- frequently, he had not made much progress in Bible knowledge. Now he resolved to read Lucy's Bible through, to read it as he would ,' Chitty on Pleading," thoroughly, critically, and without any prejudice, if possible. Jeff. had quite a good opinion ofthuman reason, and of his own in particular, and he was sure if there was a flaw in the argument he could de- tect it.  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC7482-00000088"/> 172     THE LOST WILL, He was about to begin at Genesis, for the idea of reading it through in his leisure hours, in the course of a week, did not look at all dif- ficult. Jeff. was used to hard work. He had worked hard ever since he was old enough to saw a stick of wood. He had earned his own board and clothes when he was but ten years old; (to be sure the fare was hard, and the clothes nothing to boast of,) but it took many hours of labor to pay for them. He had work- ed harder still to fit himself to study law, and thanks to an iron body, and an iron will, he was thus prepared to dig in the hard soil of le- gal studies. Jeff. had little fancy, and his mental powers seemed to partake of the tough- ness of his physical fibre, so that when he studied law, he went to work as if he were subsoiling a hard -New England farm. He, couldn't drive a 2:40 in a- gig, over a race course, but he could manage a heavy plough and four oxen, and turniup the ground into long, deep, straight furrows. As I said, he was opening the Bible at Gen-   'THE LOST WILL.      173 esis, intending to go straight through without any omission, when some small papers, closely written over, dropped out upon the floor.. He picked them up; on one was written- "Read first, dear Lucy, the Ten Commandments, and then examine your life and heart by that test; see what the apostle James says in James ii. 10. Jeff. therefore turned to the twentieth chap- ter of Exodus. Now, as a lawyer, he should at least have been able to repeat this compen- dium of God's will, but I am sorry to say thatt, Jeff. could not have recited the Ten Command- ments as correctly as the youngest scholar in Mr. Herbert's Sunday school. He read slow- ly -"Thou shalt have no other God's before me."  The lawyer understood full well that to keep a law perfectly, we must keep it in the spirit as well as in the letter. Here then he was stopped at once.  Unlike the heathen, he had no God.  He had never worshipped at all, never- prayed to the Christian's God, or even had a form of worship. II       *   &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC7482-00000089"/> 174     THE LOST WILL. "Guilty- on that count," he said to himself; he read on, and hesitating on the second, con- cluded to write himself innocent here, when the thought occurred - "If I havn't actually made a graven image, have I not had an idol? have I not worshipped something beside my Creator?" Again he plead guilty, and went on: "Thou shalt not take his name in vain," &amp;c. Alas! for Jeff. The bold swearing of his boyhood came up before him, and the more restrained but not less offensive profanity of his more ma- ture years. Guilty again, and his heart own- ed it. The fourth he read slowly and with much thought. In some law case in which he hjad been engaged not long before, Sabbath break- ing had come up before the Court, and the learned advocate to whom we have once before referred, made a beautiful and able plea in de- fence of the Sabbath. He showed its wise de- sign, and its benefit to the race, in a temporal, as well as a moral view. Jeff. was struck with \   THE LOST WILL.     175 the argument, and had often thought of it; now it came with great freshness to him, and with it his own labors on that day.  How many law books he had read, how many cases prepared, how many rides had he taken to see his clients, and how  seldom  he had even thought of its sanctity. "Guilty Guilty/" again said the man, who, for once, meant to be honest with himself. Jeff. paused a moment on the fifth. Poor fel- low! he could look back on his childhood, only as one looks on a dark and gloomy pic- ture, fall of pain ; he could just remember his worn, suffering mother whom he would gladly have aided if he could, and a  brutal father, turned at times to a demon, by the influence of rum. There was no'loving care on one side, j nor respect and  honor from the children. "What might I  not have been?" asked Jeff in some bitterness of spirit, ' if 'Squire Dennie h ad been my father, and I  surrounded with such influences and friends as George Dennie has -had!"   &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC7482-00000090"/> 176     THE LOST WILL, Jeff. had always felt crushed and mortified at his origin and poverty, and he was aware, too, that in his person and manners, he was very deficient. He was, perhaps, too sensitive on this subject. "I would that I could have honored my father," he said, as some of the angry words and cruel blows which that father had given him, came up before him. He left a blank here and passed on; "Sure- ly not guilty of the sixth," he said; but here was a reference. "He that hateth his brother is a murderer." "Ah! what am I, then?" he asked himself, as all the bitterness of pqrty strife, and all the revengeful words and feelings of which he had been guilty were recalled. He had heard of 'Squire Dennie's remark, that ,G The devil was written in Devoll's face,' and he had not forgotten it; slowly, but surely was he seeking his revenge. Here then, he stood a condemned criminal, for- the purpose was still in his heart, and to give it up would be like plucking out an eye. He paused long   THE LOST WILL.      1 here and thought; butto one conclusion only could he come-- If this was the law of God, then he was a sinner." The seventh he would pass over lightly Jeff. was what the world calls a moral man, but alas! Nellie's references only proved that all impiety of thought, was a violation of this com- mand. On the eighth, Jeff. dwelt a moment. Here his naturally clear head and sound reason was a little at fault. Like too lany of his pro- fession, he was confused, thinkg that a le- gal right barred all discussion; but here, too, Nellie's references were full, and he soon learn- ed that a legal right might sometimes be ac- quired in property, or rather that the imperfec- tions of man's law, might lead him to possess that to which the more perfect law ofGod might give him no laim  He thought of Mr. Dennie's meadow, which he obtained for half its vailUe, by some legal process, (so termed,) at I eastr This perfect justice between m  an an d nan,  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC7482-00000091"/> 178     -THE LOST WILL. which God's law required, was hard doctrine for a young lawyer, whose pride had been to work for his client, and shut his eyes to the right or wrong of the claims.. The ninth and tenth were s: closely connect- ed with the eighth in such matter as were now in Jeff's thoughts, that a violation of one in- volved that of the others. "Guilty, I believe, on every count," he said, as he closed the book, and began walking back and forth in his office. "Yes, guilty, and re- commended to mercy only on one -- " It was midnight, but the lawyer had no de- sire to sleep. Back and forth he walked, try- ing to persuade himself that the Bible was not an inspired book, - that it was simply the work of man. But no, that cannot be I This very code of laws is proof enough of its divine origin. No mortal man could improve it, --it lies at the foundation of all laws. Blackstone, h;mself, could never have written his great work, if these had not existed before   THE LOST WILL.      179 him. They are the source of all our common law, and the strong and deep foundation on which men have reared their superstructures. They lie deep down in the moral nature of man,-and He 'vho made these laws, made them for man whom -Ie created. "He that offended in one point, is guilty of all." Ah! Jeff. Devoll, if that is true, then you are, a sinner." "But, can I keep these laws?" he asked himself. "I'll try," and with this resolu- tion, he resolved to leave the matter that night. It was a restless night, however, and when he rose the next morning, he turned to the little Bible again-and following the notes; he opened to Matt. xxii. 37. The lawyer came to Christ," and asked him which was the great commandment of the law, and thus Jesus an- swered: "Thou shalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy hear-and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind ;-a hd the second is like unto it, "Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. On ,  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC7482-00000092"/> 180     THE LOST WILL. these two commandments, hang all the law and prophets." Then to Romans, vii. 12. "The law is holy, and the commandment holy, just, and good;" -and again, Rom. iii. 23. "For all have sinl ned, and come short of the glory of God." "I know I have for one," said Jeff., as he mused, Bible in hand. Rom. iii. 20. ," Therefore, by the deeds of the law, shall no flesh be justified in his sight; ;   for by the law is the knowledge of sin." r By the law is the knowledge of sin," re- peated Jeff. '"Yes, I know that full well. I feel as if my heart was like a- room, full of all sorts of reptiles, and unclean things; but the room has been shut up dark and close, and all these evil things hidden, even from myself now it is as if some one had brought a strong light into that room, a light that pierced'ever: corner, and left not one hiding-place for th loathsome reptile, or venomous snake. Ther they were in all their deformity; and-the poo man felt like David, when he exclaimed: *^   THE LOST WILL.   1   E " O Lord    thou hast searched me, and known me; -- thou hast beset me behind and before, and laid thine hand upon me." Jeff. went out to his business ; he thought to shake off these thoughts that oppressed him, but they came to him at every interval ;--they intruded themselves in the street, and in the house, in the office and the store, till, like St. Paul, he felt that when the commandment came, sin revived, and he died, but without the law, he was alive. Day after day, he carried about the burden of a broken law, shown to him by the light of an awakened conscience. He did not make much progress in reading the Bible in' course, for he invariably turned to the commandments, and the references con- nected with them, and read them again and again, till they seemed burned! into his brain; and while the strong-minded, clear-headed law- yer, the iron man,. who could bear so much toil and physical suffering, without a murmur, bowed his head and wept like a child, asking   &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC7482-00000093"/> "vm .   .4a da Ja..a . oa!V.-LU Tt J--VL Je from the depths of his heart, as did Paul, whe the Lord met him on his way to Damascus "Lord what wilt thou have me to do." J(   CHAPTER X, t  O   ONE morning Deacon Lyman, a vener As iold man, whom every one esteemed, but was humble and lowly in his own opir i!1 ^came into Devoll's office with a paper in hand. His manner was rather hesitating ', :! i timid, as if he doubted whether his enr would be an agreeable one to the lawyer. A! :called in this morning, 'Squire, to see if and he turned the paper over a little nerv ,Ii i  ly, in his hand. "I thought perhaps, mo you'd like to sign a little towards Mr. ] bert's salary; you've never been called on fore, and we want to raise all we can. 'Sq !Dennie's gone, you see, and Mr. Fox, too, that makes quite a difference. We don't v to lose Mr. Herbert he's a faithful sera in the Lord's vineyard."   &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC7482-00000094"/> 184     THE LOST WILL, "Mr. Herbert is a fine man and a good citi- zen," said Devoll; "let me see your paper." The deacon's mild blue eyes brightened, and he sat a little more firmly in his chair. Devoll glanced over the paper, and then took a- pen and wrote a moment. When the deacon re- ceived it back,- he looked at the name, and see- ing the figure " 2," thanked God, that Devoll, whom he looked upon as an infidel, would give even that small sum. He thanked him and rose to go. He was very deliberate in his manner. Devoll thought he wished for the money at -once. He took out his pocket book. "Perhaps you would like it now," he said; "just as convenient;" and counting out twen- ty dollars, handed them to the deacon. The : er looked surprised, opened his paper again, and examined it. "Ah! ah! twenty, was it? Much obliged, 'Squire; it will be quite a help to us;" and the good-man walked home with quite a lively step. "Betsey," said he to his good wife, ' look   THE LOST WILL.      185 here!" and he showed her the paper. "There, I went into Devoll's oMce, hoping I should get five dollars from him for the support of the gos- pel, though I hadn't much faith that I should, for I supposed he didn't believe in the Bible at all, and he's pretty close-fisted, besides; but don't you think he put down twenty dollars without a moment's hesitation! I couldn't be- lieve my own eyes at first, and called it two dol- lars; but he paid the "money down, and there it is; good sound currency--two ten dollar bills on B---  Bank, N. Berry, President, Silas Brown, Cashier." "Praise the Lord " said the deacon's wife, as she stood looking at the paper in the dea- con's hand, her own on his shoulder, while the frill of her white cap just trembled a little as she spoke. ; Who knows," added the deacon, " but he 'may be brought into the kingdom yet? I feel my heart much drawn out in prayer for hm." As he- spoke the door opened and Mr. Her- bert entered; nothing strange, however, for hec 71'      '   &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC7482-00000095"/> lived next door, and was in almost daily. The deacon showed the paper to the minister, who read it with a smile, and then said quietly -- "I am not surprised." "Well, it is 'mazin' strange to me," said the deacons " because I hain't no faith, ye see, for Devoll; I knew his father and grandfather be- fore him; a desperate hard set,- desperate hard;" and the deacon wiped his spectacles and put them in their case. "Have you seen anything, Mr. Herbert, that led you to think the 'Squire's heart was softened towards the word?" "No, nothing  at all," said the minister; "only I have been led to pray much for him. It has seemed to me that he was a man power- ful for good or for evil; just such a soul as Satan desires to have, and  I have wrestled much in prayer for him." "I was just telling Betsey," the deacon re-. plied, " that I feel my own heart drawn out to pray for the young man." "'Well, suppose we  have a prayer meeting )n the spot?" said Mr. Herbert. AL   JlJCsL 1- JU V10 VT 1L U-. JL * "With all my heart," was the reply, and the three knelt and prayed for the lawyer-never were more fervent or heartfelt petitions sent up-, ward to the Mercy Seat. How little they then dreamed that poor Jeff. was struggling under a sense of sin and ex- claiming, as did St. Paul, 4' Oh wretched man that I am! 'who shall deliver me." Some days after the deacon's visit, Mr. Her- bert made an errand in Devoll's office. It was aftereight o'clock ona cold November evening. Jeff.'s office was very warm and pleasant; he was apparently busy with some papers, and Mr. Herbert took up a newspaper and read awhile. Before long, however, Devoll's papers were: all arranged and carefully laid away, and pro- ducing a dish of apples the two entered into conversation, and accidentally fell into a little argument upon their respective professions, which led Mr. Herbert to remark that some knowledge of law was very: E eful to a clergy- man, and added that Saint Pdul was perhaps more successful as a preacher, from having been brought up at the feet of Gamaliel.  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC7482-00000096"/> 188     THE LOST WILL. "Paul was evidently a man of culture, and able to reason well," said Devoll, "and I think he must have had a large share of moral cour- age. If I recollect history right, he was among the sufferers under Nero, and narrowly escaped death, on one of his visits to Rome. Does he not speak somewhere of being delivered from the power of that lion." "Yes, in his second epistle to Timothy. It is astonishing when one sits down to reflect up- on the character and life of Paul, how much he was permitted to do and- to suffer. He was perhaps naturally impulsive and energetic, en- tering with his whole soul into whatever he undertook-and before his conversion found aA much pleasure in persecuting Christians as he did afterwards in trying to convert the Gentiles. History tells us that he- was a small man, only five feet nine inches in height, bald headed, with a gray beard, but he had great power over those with whom he was brought in con- tact. But just think what he suffered? -( "Five I    t   '1THE LOST WILL.     189 times received I forty stripes, save one, three times was I beaten with rods, twice did I suf- fer shipwreck, a night and a day was I in the deep, besides his nakedness and hunger, his perils by land and by sea, and worse than all-- his perils by false brethren. Why, Mr. Devoll' I do not wonder people were convinced of the truth of Christianity by such a man." "They must certainly have been convinced of his sincerity--did'nt he fight with wild beasts at Ephesus also," and Devoll rose and took a Bible, not the little Bible,. that was too precious a treasure to be freely handled, but a common edition, which looked, by the way, as if it had been much handled, though not an old book. The leaves were turned down in various places, notes and pencil marks here and there. These things did not escape the notice of the clergyman, and though he did not manifest it by word or look, he was much surprised at the knowledge of Scripture which Devon manifest- ed. He wud t have been more so, had he known  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC7482-00000097"/> 190      T-11th LOST WILL. that all this knowledge was gained in a few short months, and amid the pressure of import- ant business. It was impossible for the con- versation to proceed long, without a disclosure of Devoll's feelings. His heart was too full, his conscience too thoroughly roused, and Mr Herbert too pene- trating for much concealment. But the minis- ter was cautious, and had great sympathy and kindness of feeling;he knew by experience all the struggles of a conscience striving to be at peace with itself by the works of the law, and the utter helplessness of a proud will unwilling to yield to the simple terms of the Gospel. The evening passed away, but the gentlemen remained. Devoll was walking back and forth in his office, the muscles of his face working violently, arid his whole appearance that of a strong will wrestling in some stern conflict. The minister had turned from the epistles to Christ's interview with Nicodemus --then to those words of our Saviour--"I am  the way, the truth and the life-He that cometh unto me, I   THE LOST WILL.      191 I will in no wise cast out-He that believeth on me shall never die. By grace are ye saved, through faith, and that not of yourselves, it is the gift of God." "Ah! that is it," said the lawyer, "you can- not think how much that passage has troubled me-now if I could do any thing of myself, I would do it, I am strong, I couVl suffer any penance, perform any labor to get rid of this burdening sense of sin." "Work out your own salvation with fear and trembling, knowing that it is God that worketh in you, both to will and to do." But my friend, let us pray, let us carry your case at once to the Saviour, and ask with St. Paul, Lord what will thou have me to do?" i "With all my heart," said Devoll, and they knelt, while the minister, calmly and quietly, but with deep reverence, bore the heart of the struggling man on the strong wings of his faith up to Calvary,.  Devoll's head was bowed, and he saw, as he never saw before, a dying Saviour suffering for  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC7482-00000098"/> 192      THE LOST WILL. man. The prayer was long, but neither heeded the lapse of time. When they rose, Devoll did not seat himself, but continued to walk the room. The tempest was hushed a moment, but the lull was short. After a silence of some minutes he spoke, ' I'll tell you what it is, if I yield to these impressions, I have some crosses to bear. Do you know Mr. Herbert, that I have been hard, taking advantage of technicali- ties, and asserting my rights to the utmost ex- tent of the law. My pride recoils from retrac- tion, I believe I'd rather take the Jewish thirty- nine stripes. Mr. Herbert turned to Christ's interview with Zaccheus-" if I have taken anything from any man by false accusation, I restore him foretold. And Jesus said-This day is salvation come to thy house." The hour of midnight was past, and the minister must leave, but as he said "Good night," Devoll wrung his hand.  "( God helping me, Mr. Herbert, I will come out on the Lord's side. I see clearly now, that   THE LOST WILL.     193 only at the cross of Christ can I lay down this burden of sin," Poor Mrs. Herbert had been anxiously wait- ing the return of her husband, and imagining that all sorts of evil things had happened to him: for he was in the habit of taking long, lonely walks in his parochial visits. How was she surprised and delighted when -he told her where he had been and how he had been em- ployed. "Is Saul also among the prophets?" she asked. "Not so, wife. Saul's conversion did not prove sincere. Let us say as did our Saviour, of Saul of Tarsus, ' Behold he prayeth!" Not many days afterwards Devoll called on Mrs. Dennie, and they had a long conversation which ended in her receiving a title with mort- L gage deed on certain land which she supposed had passed away from her; and indeed she could never have obtained it by any legal pro- cess. But Jeff.'s eyes were opened now, to moral as well as legal rights. From that time  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC7482-00000099"/> hu-    AJHc L j Xb WILL i Jeff. Devoll was that rare character so difficult to find, but so noble when found an honest lawyer. It required moral courage and self- denial, and Jeff. understood well what was meant by the expression --"Like plucking out an eye, or cutting off an hand."   I CHAPTER   XI. "SPRING-CLEANING!"Every housekeeper understands the meaning of that compound word, and though many men give it a different signification from their wives, they are not at a loss to understand its application. It is generally considered a period of woman's entire control within doors. Many women seem to enjoy the confusion and bustle incident to the occasion; and of this class, was Mrs. Mills, the house-keeper at Maplewood, Gover- nor Berry's residence. She was one of-those thorough, energetic women, who do not allow a cobweb or a corner to escape their penetrating eyes. Martha Slade was now under her tui- tion, and the little girl followed her about in a sort of puzzled wonder at the various manoeu- vers, of taking up and beating carpets, washing windows, turning boxes, and bags and draw- 196  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC7482-00000100"/> iNj     THE LOST WILL. :rs inside out, making, in fact, great confusion, ;hat the future quiet may be more highly prized, According to Mrs. Mills' rules, which by the way, were as stern as the Medes and Persians, the cellar and garret, and all cupboards, had been thoroughly cleaned, and the chambers were next to undergo this process. The Gov- ernor had allowed Nellie a liberal, but with his usual exactness, a definite sum, to be expended on any repairs which she might think necessary. Mrs. Mills, with her innate love of manage- ment, had already, in her fancy, appropriated it. First, to a new set of curtains, and a new- fashioned easy chair for Nellie's room, and to various kitchen utensils, which she thought would be useful in labor-saving. Then we" must manage "to get a new carpet for the parlor, and take the parlor carpet for the sitting-room, she said to herself. She had even laid awake nights arranging these mat- ters to her own satisfaction, never once dream- ing of any opposition from the gentle mistress   TItE LOST WILL.     197 of the establishment. But what was her as- tonishment, on the very day she had made up her mind to lay her programme before Nellie to hear Martha, who had gone to the door in answer to the bell, say, "Mrs. Mills, there is a man at the door who has a roll of' carpeting and some furniture, where shall I tell him to put them?" Mrs. Mills had her hands in dough, but she took them hastily from the pan, and holding them up carefully, to avoid coming in contact with anything, ran into the hall. At the same moment, Nellie opened the sit- ting-room door. "Good morning, Mr. Smith; bring them right in here, if you please." He obeyed her and drove away; Mrs. Mills looking on in silent wonder. "Oh, Mrs. Mills I come and look at my pur- chase. I hope you will be pleased with it." "In one moment," said the housekeeper, "I will put my bread in the pan, and be there di- rectly." In the meantime, Nellie and Martha had un-  &#xD;<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC7482-00000101"/> ]198     THE LOST WILL. rolled the carpet, and had taken the covers from a beautiful little writing table, and four chairs to match. "Its beautiful, I think, Miss Nellie," said Martha. It was green and gold, the figure was small ---a grape leafwith grapes and tendrils.- Mrs. Mills had put on her spectacles, and now came in with a yery critical look. "It is all fitted and made, Mrs. Mills," said Nelie; "I thought it would save you some trouble." "But, my dear," said Mrs. Mills,'with a puzzled look, " havn't you made a mistake; it is not near large enough." "Oh, yes I it must be, for father measured it himself, for me; you see, we wanted to keep it al secret."  "It cannot be for the parlor, then." "Oh, no! indeed,"  and - Nellie smiled; "there, I -forgot you were not in the secret; it is for George's room; and see this desk, and -the chairs, are they not pretty?"   t   THE LOST WILL.      199 "Yes, very pretty, indeed; but I thought- I had my mind made up - that you would get a new parlor carpet this spring." "No, I think we will make that answer another year. I had set my heart on buying these things for George's room;,- it has taken a good deal of my money; but never mind, Mrs. Mills, you shall have those tin pans, and the new coffee pot, and the egg-boiler; and I have engaged a painter, for the pantry and kitchen, and father ordered a new stove." ' "And what, pray, will become of your room? where is the new paper-hanging, and window curtains, and that easy chair I spoke of." "Never mind those, Mrs. tMills, I care very little about them; but, do you suppose that you can clean George's room, and nail this carpet down today. I want to enjoy his sur- prise this evening." "Yes, that's no great job, with Martha to help; but I ain't at all particular about the new stove in the ,kitchen; I just happened to take a fancy to it - like as not, I shan't like it !f *   &#xD;<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC7482-00000102"/> 200     THE LOST WILL. as well as the old one, fater all," and she hurried away into the kitchen, where John, the coach- man, was taking a lunch. There she ventured to give vent to her feelings. "I declare, I'm vexed and disappointed. I believe the girl would be a martyr, and die like old John Rogers did, if she thought it would make others happier. Gone and bought that nice carpet and furniture for him, when I'd set my heart on fixing up her own room! Tain't a bit of matter- about these young fellers, any way; the more you pet 'em, the worse they are. And, to my thinking, there's as good, and as handsome young men in the country, as George Dennie." "You speak my mind exactly," said John, "but Miss Nellie seems to think there ain't his equal any where. But, may-be, she don't know everything ;-its my opinion, that George Dennie isn't - isn't - well, any better than he ought to be." "Well, there's one thing I haint liked at all m   THE LOST WILL.      201 and that is his staying out so late at night. He says, that he has a great deal of writing to do at the office ;-well, may-be he has -and may-be he has not." John looked knowing as he repeated: "And may-be he has not." "Well, it is certain, Nellie thinks that George is the pink of perfection; and, for her sake, I'll make the best of him ;--so, I suppose, there's nothing else to be done, but to clean his room and put the new furniture in it," and Mrs. Mills went up stairs, with an air that said, "Its more for her, than for you, Master George." But, when Mrs. Mills was fairly at her work, she never asked herself for whom she, was worling ; but how it was done, and she bustled away with all due energy; requesting Nellie, not to make her appearance, till she came for her. To Nellie's surprise, the whole work was done, before four in the afternoon; and Nellie, and Mrs. Mills, and Martha, were delighted with the appearance of the room. The carpet harmonized with the paper, and contrasted  &#xD;<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC7482-00000103"/> 202     THE LOST WILL. prettily with the fresh white curtains, and Mar- sailles quilt. Nellie sat down by the little writing desk, and thought it was too high for her; she was sure it would be just right for George. She had selected some flowers, and placed them in a little vase on the table; and arranged a few other matters, according to her fancy. ' Now, Mrs. Mills, I'll give you a surprise! While you have been busy here, I have tried my skill in the dining room ; so that supper is all ready for father, when he comes home. He had some business at the bank, which will de- tain him until five; and, as he was not here to dinner, I thought I would have an early sup- per." "Now, I am sorry," said the kind-hearted Mrs. Mills, " for you will be so tired, that you will not enjoy the evening." "It rests me," said Nellie, " to see this room; I like the carpet much, and every thing is so pure and fresh, and spring-like here, that George will be very happy, I've no doubt. I must   THE LOST WILL.      203 just take one look more," she said, " and then I'll go and rest, till father comes." She went down to her sitting room, and laid down upon a little lounge, near the window; where, she was sure, she should hear her fath- er's footsteps as soon as he entered the ave- nue. It was one of those beautiful spring days, when all nature seemed waking up to praised and love. Nellie sat looking out upon the lawn; there was a bed- of crocuses in bloom; and the sweet breath of the hyacinths, came in at the open window, mingling their perfume with the English violets ;-the buds were swell- ing on the shrubbery and trees, and -- " birds and streams Mingled their voices, and the glad earth seemed A second Paradise." Nellie was very happy; in her own heart was that quiet peace, which those only know, who have learned to say with St. Paul, "Whether living or dying, I am the Lord's; and to rejoice with joy unspeakable, in the blessed hope of 9in forgiven."  &#xD;<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC7482-00000104"/> 204     THE LOST WILL. She looked on the beautiful scene before her; and her refined taste, and artistic eye, appre- ciated all its beauties; from the deep blue of the sky, the violet tints of the distant mountain tops; and the sheen of the river that wound its way through the town, stopping in the mea- dow to mask a graceful curve, lingering as if to enjoy the rich verdure which it imparted. "How blessed I am  " said Nellie. "How can I be- thankful enough for my blessings! The lines have fallen to be in pleasant places; and I have a goodly heritage." The clock struck five, and she turned her eyes to the road, to catch the first view of him. "George will come with him," she said to herself; for as her father was in the carriage, he would naturally take him in at the office, - the law office was close to the bank. But a quarter of an hour passed, and she saw nothing of them; it was singular, because her father was always punctual. She went out and walked down the avenue, to the gate, where she could   THE LOST WILL.      205 have a view of the road, for a -long distance. Nothing was to be seen of the carriage. "Perhaps they have important business at the bank," she said to herself. "Ah! I recol- lect now; he did say something, about some difficulty which they have in getting a renewal of their charter," and she was sure, he had re- gretted that he had not attended to it long be- fore. So quieting herself, she returned to her lounge, and took her sewing for a few minutes. Gradually, however, the daylight grew fainter, and she went out again to see the sun go down behind Eagle Mountain. This mountain, was nearer Westhrook, than B---; but there was a fine view of it, from Maplewood; and from early childhood, it had been one of Nellie's amusements, to watch the various changes, which sunlight and shadow made upon its top. There was scarcely two hours of the day, that it looked the same,-" ever changing, ever beautiful," Nellie used to say. Sometimes in the morning when the sun was rising, it would fling its rays athwart the sky,  &#xD;<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC7482-00000105"/> 206     THE LOST WILL. and kindle on the mountain top a flame that glowed like a beacon fire; sometimes it would fling such brilliant tints upon the fleecy clouds and mists that had wrapped the mountain in gloom before, that suddenly it seemed like a king coming forth -in royal apparel-then again so soft and delicate was the drapery, such a min- gling of violet and rose color and purple, that one felt soothed and tranquilized, and as Nellie says, would sit and gaze upon it, till I felt as if my spirit was borne upward on spirit wings to heaven. Now as Nellie looked she saw only a large, dark, heavy cloud resting on the moun- tain, not a ray of sunlight gilding even its out- er edge; and though it was not sundown, the sun itself was obscured by clouds, and a cold, chilly wind had risen. Nellie felt that sudden - depression which people so sensitive to chang- es in nature are apt to feel, and after running hastily once more down the avenue, to look out upon the road, she returned to the house dis- appointed and perplexed. She closed the- win- dow and sat down, looking out with an anxious   THsE LOST WILL,     207 face. Rousing herself in a few minutes, she went out to seek Mrs. Mills. She found her up stairs, sleeves rolled up, with a handker- chief tied over her head, and duster in hand, just finishing, she said, "her day's work." "Well, there now! most seven o'clock, did you say?" "I never know how time passes, when I'm house-cleaning; but I'm most through-shall finish to-morrow, and then I do hope I shall have a little rest. 'Tis 'ma,7in' strange how much dirt collects in a house in one year. Not come yet, did you say? Why, what in the world can have detained them?   I told Martha to go down and make the tea. when you :rung, and I suppose the child wouldn't go before if she starved. She's a queer thing- you told her she must mind me, and I don't know but she'd jump into the well if I said "You ain't worried, are you? you look sort of pale; some business keeps him. Lawful sake, Nellie; men tell sometimes about .their me .e, som  &#xD;<pb n="208-209" xml:id="VAC7482-00000106"/> A   d---S08  THE LOST WILL. capacity o business, and laugh at us women for being sh long doing anything.' My gra- cious! they inderstand the knack of putting off and talking forever about nothing as well as we women. fols. But you must have some supper.- I'll just slip on a clean dress aid smooth my hair alnd get you some." "No, no, Mrs. Mills; I'm not hungry at all. I'll wait till they come. I suppose I am a lit- tle more impatient than usual, because I was hoping George would be here to see his room before dark." "There, now!" said Mrs Mills, "I'm sure I hear the carriage." "Yes; there it is," said Martha, who had been watching at a window. The door of George's room stood open and Nellie stopped to give one glance. How pleas- ant it looked! God bless him I she prayed within her heart, and fit him for a brighter mansion above ; and there came a sigh as she thought that George had no hope that his heart had been renewed and purified by Di- vine grace.   THE LOST WILL.       209 She went down stairs and out of the hall door to meet her father. He was just getting out of the carriage at a side gate which opened on a little alley not far from the door. Nellie went forward a few steps, and stopped short in alarm. Her father looked very pale, and his step tottered. "John, I must trouble you to help me into the house," he said; "I am not well." The kind-hearted coachman looked concern- ed. "Lean on me, sir; lean your whole weight," he said; "I am strong." "Father," said Nellie, "let me help you, too. Are you faint, father?" A groan escaped the old gentleman, and for a second was his only answer; but seeing the pale face and frightened look of his daughter, he said quickly - "Don't be alarmed, Nellie; I shall get over it soon. Go with me, John, to my room." John did so, and then stood for farther or- ders, after seeing the old gentleman seated in a large easy-chair. "Nothing more, 'John--  &#xD;<pb n="210-211" xml:id="VAC7482-00000107"/> r1CU    THE LOST WILL. nothing more; no, thank you, Mrs. Mills -not the camphor. Send me in a cup of strong tea, and one for Nellie, too; I shall need no one but her." "Close the door, Nellie," he said, as Mrs. Mills left hastily for the tea; " now come, and let me lean my head upon you for one mo- ment." Nellie stood near, and threw her arms round him, and the head with its crown of sil- ver lay for a moment near her heart. "God bless you, my child; you are my greatest comfort in this world. Don't be alarmed; this is heart-sickness, Nellie - not death. No, no; but I believe I would have chosen death. I loved him- I trusted him- I thought to lean upon him in my own old age." "George! George! father, has anything happened to George?" asked Nellie, with a quivering lip and a blanched cheek. At this moment Mrs. Mills appeared with the tea. "Bring some supper for Nellie," said the Governor; " and, Martha, draw the little table near my chair."   THE LOST WILL.      2" "I shall be better soon, I hope; thank you, Mrs. Mills. My hand trembles yet, I see-; but rest and quiet will restore me." Father and daughter were again left to themselves. "There, now, Nellie, we'll drink our tea, and then I will tell you all; it is best you should hear it from me." Nellie obeyed her father, but never was tea so unwelcome, before. The old gentleman leaned back in his chair, and clasped his hands together a moment. "It seems a dream, a horrible dream -it can't be true; and yet Brown is so sure, and the proof is so strong!" "Father, tell me all," said Nellie, pleading- ly; "where is George?" At this moment, while they spoke, they heard George's step in the dining-room, and Mrs. Mills say- "You're a lucky fisherman, George; that is a nice string of trout, for breakfast. But, did you know how ill the Governor is?" "Ill! did you say? No ; where is he?"  &#xD;<pb n="212-213" xml:id="VAC7482-00000108"/> 212     THE LOST WILL. The answer was given in a low voice and was not heard by Mr. Berry and his daughter, Mr. Berry rang the bell for Martha, and sent word to George, that he would like to have him remain at home during the evening. "Nellie, George has been very dear to us; I cannot say that I have thought him warm- hearted or very affectionate in his disposition; but on that very account I supposed him less liable to temptation. I thought so cool a head was united to principle. But, Nellie, George has been guilty of forgery! Not once, merely; but in the Bank, to-day, I found two notes to which he has forged my name, and on which he has drawn the money! But that is not all. These debts are gambling debts! Oh, Nellie; we have been cherishing a villain in our home. This, is the young man that I thought would be a brother to you, a son in my old age! It has come upon me like a terrible blow. I did not know it until after Bank hours, and it has seemed to me, since then, that I have grown ten years older. I thought I had, more cour-   THE LOST WILL.      213 age and strength, but when I was coming home, and reflected how much pain and sorrow he had brought upon us, I was entirely over- come. But we must meet it, Nellie. I am stronger, now, and I feel that for some wise reason, you and I are to suffer this discipline." While he was speaking, Nellie sat with her hands clasped tightly in her lap, and her eyes fixed upon her father. She seemed struck dumb with astonishment, and even when he closed, she did not speak. Her strange, rigid look, alarmed her father. "Nellie, my child, speak to me; we both suffer." Slowly and with a stran manner, as/e moves in a dream, Nellie r se and went to her father; she laid her hand on his shoulder, and said--"Father, they have spoken falsely of George; it cannot be; no, no, George would never do so; he knows you never denied him money." "Yes, he knows that; but ah, Nellie, it was to, conceal the guilt of gambling that he did  &#xD;<pb n="214-215" xml:id="VAC7482-00000109"/> 214     THE LOST WILL. not come to me.  I have seen Tracer; he knows it all, at least George's habits, and he has had his suspicions about the money. SHe knows nothing of the forgery." "Tracer is a very bad man, father; perhaps he wishes to injure George." "No, I think not; it is for his interest to uphold George, and he was very reluctant to acknowledge anything." George was heard to go up stairs to his room. The. sound, while it sent a pang through Nellie's heart, aroused her a little from this stupor. "Father," she said, with al- most her usual animation, "I will- go to him- he will tell me all," and she started to leave the room. "No, Nellie, no; alas I it is too true, and I must think awhile what is my duty. He has made himself amenable to the laws of the country, A   forger and a gambler! Oh, George! George! that you should come to this!" Nellie sat down, the very picture of helpless- ness and despair. Her father rose and tried to   THE LOST WILL,.      215 walk across the room, but he seemed very fee- (Alas!" thought Nellie; " this sudden trou- ble has made my father old ;" and the sight of his faltering step and bowed head made her weep. It was well, for tears were a relief, and she felt afterwards calmer, more resolute, more decided what to do. They sat together, father and daughter, for some time; little was said, but when the time of evening prayer came, the family were gath- ered as usual, and Nellie, read and her father prayed. To his daughter, that prayer seemed like the petition of a little child, earnestly ask- ing to be guided by a loving father. George was present, and inquired in a respectful man- ner after the health of the Governor. "I would like to see you in my room," said the latter. Up to that moment George had not suspect- ed anything; but there was something in the manner of asking, and much, too, in the suspi- cion excited by a guilty conscience, that made him tremble as he entered the room where his friend and father awaited him.  &#xD;<pb n="216-217" xml:id="VAC7482-00000110"/> CHAPTER XII. IT was nearly midnight when George went up to his room. Nellie had not retired; she was in her chamber, and had wept and prayed all these long hours. The storm, which the dark clouds at sunset had foretold, was now raging  without; the rain poured, the wind blew, and the night was very dark. Nellie had often turned to the window, hoping to see one star, but it only seemed darker every time she looked, and within her soul, too, all was gloom. Her faith was sorely tried, for it is hard to find that those we love have proved themselves unworthy; we turn from the evi- dence of guilt at first, and when it forces itself upon us, as it did in this case, upon Nellie, how the brain reels and the heart sickens I But one thought was uppermost now in Nel- 216   'TiJE LOST WILL.     217 lie's mind--' Must George suffer the legal pen- alty of his crime?" She had learned from  her father that it was imprisonment in the State Prison, for not less than ten years. She would willingly have taken the punishment upon herself---"I could bear it," she said; "I am only an unfor- tunate, deformed girl, and shrink from contact with the world; innocent I could bear captivi- ty and be happy; but George, poor George I so handsome, so accomplished, so fond of socie- ty. He must be saved in some way; perhaps he will never do wrong again.  I know hie will not, when he learns how much sorrow he has' caused us. If I only knew now that he was sorry." She stepped out into the entry. George" was just going into his room and she followed him. He set down his lamp, and throwing himself into a chair, leaned his arms upon the table and laid his heal down.  His attitude was one of utter hopelessness. And well it might be, for Governor Berry, had thought- it  &#xD;<pb n="218" xml:id="VAC7482-00000111"/> 218      THE LOST WILL. necessary to lay aside all tenderness, and re- press the sympathy and kindness which he felt, for he was not a stern, hard man, but he felt that the case required that he should han- dle it like a skilful physician, dealing with a desperate disease. Under the threat of executing the law to its extent, he had drawn from George a full con- fession of his guilt. This confession -was not given frankly and nobly, nor with any appear- ance of great sorrow ; but it came reluctantly, slowly, and with many excuses for himself and much blame to others. There was not one sin- gle remark that im"plied regret for causing so much pain to his friends, and when Mr. Berry referred to his mother, George did not seem much moved, but when he spoke of the public disgrace and exposure, and to the punishment which would consign the forger to a felon's cell, George turned pale and trembled so that- he could scarcely keep his seat. It lasted but a moment, however, and then the lips were firmly set, and there was a look of determnria- tion which puzzled his aged friend very much.   &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-219" xml:id="VAC7482-00000112"/>   THE LOST WILL.      219 "Now George," said he, "I have but one thing more to say; my disappointment in you is great -how great you can never know. I have been proud of you, proud of your talents, proud of your personal appearance. I had hoped to lean upon you in my old age, and re- new my youth in your aspirations. This is all over now, and I can trust no more. I give you this alternative-for I cannot yet bring my mind to doom you to imprisonment. I will pay these notes, and as no one but Brown knows of them, I will use my influence to in- duce him never to mention it; then I will give: you five hundred dollars to finish another years' study. This I will do, provided you will sign a pledge, never to handle a card again, and will leave B--, never to return." George was silent a moment; he seemed to be revolving the proposition in his mind. "Otherwise," added the Governor, seeing his hesitation, "you are my prisoner, and the : evidence of your guilt ihe taing out the ::: notes.  &#xD;<pb n="220-221" xml:id="VAC7482-00000113"/> zzV     TFHE LOST WILL. 'I accede to them," said George, rising to leave the room. "Meet me here, then, to-morrow morning at eight o'clock, and I will have the money and papers ready." George left the room bidding the Governor "good night," with as much ease and suavity of manner as ever. For the first time, this self-possession and ease of manner annoyed the old gentleman. Now it appeared to him only the outward polish, concealing a wicked heart, the mere gloss of sin. "How could I have been so deceived in that boy?" he asked him- self; and for years, too " "George, George," said the gentle voice of Nellie, "look up; it's me-it's your sister Nellie; will you speak to her?" He did look up, and there was shame and angerin his face. "I wish I was dead, Nel- lie; I am going to kill myself." "Oh, George, George! don't say so; you are sorry, are you not? You will repent, God will forgive you, and we shall all be happy   THE LOST WILL.     221 again. I've been praying for you, George, and now, you will pray for yourself, will you not?" "I don't care what becomes of me, Nellie. Your father says I must go away from here, and never come back again. You needn't care anything about me, for I shall never see you again."    , "Going away, never to come back! Father say that? Did he say it, certainly?" "Yes, or I go to prison." "Then all our plans for the future have van- ished. And you were going to Cambridge one year, and then have a law office in B---; and Georgie, do you know I thought you would bring your mother here, and make her so hap- py in her old age." This hadn't entered into George's plans, but he did not deny it. "It's all over now, Nellie;" and George laid his head down, sullen and desperate. Nellie stood by, looking hopeless and sad. For a moment nothing was said, but all at one  &#xD;<pb n="222-223" xml:id="VAC7482-00000114"/> 2252   l!Hk LOST WILL. the young girl's fae lighted up. "George, will you promise me\never to gamble any more; more than that, never to play cards?" "What's the use, Neie?  You'll never know what becomes of me. I've got to prom- ise it though, I suppose, an( may as well say yes. "Does any one know of this trouble but father and Brown?" "No; unless Tracer suspects." "Well, now George, do you believe you would ever do such a thing again, if you should live a thousand years?" "No, Nellie; I only wished to pay these notes before your father discovered them, and then I was going to stop." "Oh, George, what a mistake you made! Didn't you know that father would have paid a thousand dollars any time, rather than have you do so?" "I didn't know, Nellie; I wasn't certain jabsout that, or I would have told him long ago."   THE LOST WILL.      223 "Oh, George!"Now if Nellie's heart had not been so pure, and she conscious of that de- formity of person which would ever debar her from thinking of marriage, she would not have finished the sentence as she did; but her inno- cent, loving heart, only spoke in its frankness. "Oh, George, you don't know how much we loved you, how dear you are to us, or you would have trusted us more. We love you too well not to forgive, and if you would love us as much in return, we would shelter you from all harm if possible. George, I wish I could suffer for you." The young man looked up at Nelly in a sort of wonder. Her eyes were bright, and he thought he saw that she was planning some- thing more agreeable for him than the alterna- tiot which her father had given him. "Good night, George," she said, " now don't forget that you've committed this sin against God, and must ask forgiveness of him." He rose, and opened the door for her, and stood in the hall with the lamp, until she wAs  &#xD;<pb n="224-225" xml:id="VAC7482-00000115"/> -3224   -  'THX  LOXS WILL. at her own door. f Good night," she said again very pleasantly, and he returned the salutation. She osed her door, but his hand- some face and fe figure seemed still before her, with his look of utter hopelessness when she went to him. It was nearly morning. Nellie was not at. all sleepy, and she sat down for a moment at the window, when suddenly between the rifted clouds a star peeped out, and Nellie smiled, for it seemed to her a harbinger of good. She threw herself upon the bed and slept awhile, but awoke with the first dawn of day. She had intended to do so; for she resolved to have an interview with her father before George should come down. She supposed the latter would not sleep, and might rise before her. Alas! she was mis- taken. She had not-read George as correctly as her father had done. George had slept well, and was still sleeping 'when Nellie, with a noiseless step, passed his -door and descended to her father's room.   THE LOST WILL.      225 She knocked lightly- her father opened to her. He was up and writing. "Why Nellie, you should be asleep!" "I could'nt sleep much, father, for thinking of George." "Well, Nellie, we must give George up. I am the more reconciled to it, for I now see him in his true character. We have been deceived in him, we have loved, not him, but an im- aginary George, which his form, we thought, represented. It is strange that we should be so blinded; but he certainly had the appear- ance of a young man of principle and good habits." "-Perhaps he has been led, away, father, by evil influences--you have not much con- fidence in Tracer's principles." "No; but I warned George there, and I am sure, with his cool temperament, he is not so likqly to be led astray as more impulsive boys. But I am sorry I left him so much with Tracer --it was wrong." "Are you going to send George awlf father?"  &#xD;<pb n="226-227" xml:id="VAC7482-00000116"/> 226     THE LOST WILL. "Yes, at once, and a night's reflection only makes me more determined in doing so. I will do right by him, Nellie." "Have you thought of his mother, father?" "I do not think his affection very strong for her, Nellie; and if he should continue in his evil ways, he would be a, greater trial to her. I am hoping, that once away, he will see his errors and begin life anew." "George is very sorry father; I think he will never be guilty of the like again." "Has he told you so, Nellie?" "Yes, or the same thing, and he has pro- xmised to do better. Father, you know we all -need forgiveness." The old gentleman sat and thought a mo- ment. "Nellie, I can forgive George; from my heart I can forgive him, if he is sorry for what he has done and truly repents; but I cannot think it best for him to remain here- it will be better to throw him on his own re- sources at once."   THE LOST WILL.      227 Nellie looked sad, for she was disappointed, and her father who knew every change of that fair face, understood it. A pang shot through his heart as he looked at' her, and in one instant, like a flash, the thought passed through his mind.  George never will, for he is not capable of returning such love - better let him go now, it will save both of us from future sorrow. There are moments when we have been thinking deeply upon any subject that its future bearings seem revealed to us, and our duty is so plain, that we are sure we are right. It was so then with the clear-headed, wise old man. But Nellie was thinking only of George's suffering, and how she could advance his happiness. "Father, I wish it were possible for you to give George one more trial." '" 'What is that, Nellie?" "Why let him go to Cambridge as he wishes for one year. Let it be a year of trial, and then if he fails, do by him as you are now in- tending."   &#xD;<pb n="228-229" xml:id="VAC7482-00000117"/> :228    ATri LOST WILL. Her father shook his head. She clasped her arms round his neck.  Be merciful as your Father in Heaven is merciful." He clasped her to his heart. "My daughter, I feel that I am weak in yielding; something tells me that my firmness is better for the young man than your compassion; but we'll see, we'll see. George comes to me at eight o'clock. "And if, father, he should be penitent, you will forget and forgive, and George will be ours once more, better perhaps than before." "You forget, Nellie, that his crime is against the State. It is not a mere personal injury to me - he is liable at any moment to a prosecu- tion.' ' Oh, but father, if he does well, we will protect him; at least we will beg mercy for him. You are not a magistrate, now, Father-- they only call you Governor from courtesy, so you will not suffer officially." "You are a nice little casuist my child ; there, you may run away now, for George will be here soon, and I must have some strong pro- mises from him."   THE LOST WILL.      229 They met again at the breakfast table. George was there too, and there was little per- ceptible difference in his manner, save that he said but few words, and retired to his room as soon as he rose from table. But Nellie was very happy, for she had suc- ceeded. George was to go to Cambridge in a few days, not to be banished from them. Maohy times during the day her father heard her voice in song, and then it would suddenly break off. She was sad, but happy nevertheless, and Hope whispered a brighter future.  &#xD;<pb n="230-231" xml:id="VAC7482-00000118"/> CHAPTER X Il. In those days the mail fron Boston came but twice a week to B , and " mail days " were anticipated with a great deal of interest. Nellie had not many correspondents, but these few were highly prized. The day after the incidents related in our last chapter, she received three letters, one from her Uncle Berry, her father's only brother, a bachelor in Boston, nearly her father's age, one from Ruth, who had found a pleasant home and a profitable school in the West, and the third from her friend Lucy Fox. As they have a bearing on the future of some of the charac- ters in our narrative, we will give extracts from them, commencing with "Uncle Frederick's." MY DEAAR NIECE: I had hoped to have been with you this week, but am prevented by illness, and there- ^    *    230 ,*   THE LOST WILL.      231 fore will use my pen instead of the tongue. As spring opens I long to be in the country, and the desire has been very strong to visit once more the old homestead in Vernon with your father. In my dreams I visit the little red house, play by the side off the brook with Nathan, drink from the old oaken bucket in the well, and go to the little school house on the hill, dinner-pail in hand. I had my trunk packed for a run up to your house, when this old trouble in my leg came on, and shut me up within four brick walls; where I hear the rat- ling of wheels over the pavements instead of birds singing, and the showy dresses of fashion- able ladies instead of flowers, green grass, bushes and trees. All this wearies me, and I am the more disappointed, because, that on the first of June I am to sail for Europe, where I shall probably be obliged to spend the summer, hunting up some old family documents for the Chase family, who are supposed to have fallen heirs to a large estate left by a deceased re- lative in the old country. We lawyers have  &#xD;<pb n="232-233" xml:id="VAC7482-00000119"/> 232     TIIE LOST WILL. some strange adventures now and then, and I am anticipating a little amusement ateast in the work, as it will lead me to soine of the old mansions in the north of England, where I shall find life different from that of this country. I feel, however, a strange reluctance some days to the task, and had I not promised to go, I think even now, I would change my plans, and spend the -summer with you. I wish I could see your father before I leave, but I know it is a tedious journey for him to come; as we grow older we cling to home more closely, and dis- like more and more the bustle of city life. iLTife s uncertain; and at farthest, he and I have but few more years to live, and I wish we might spend them together. When I return from this trip, I intend to fulfill my long formed intention to close my business here and spend the rest of my days with you. If your father is at home, please hand him the enclosed note. It contains some little items of business which I wish he would attend to for me; if not at home, please hand as soon as he returns.   THE LOST WILL.      233 Now, Nellie, I wish you would write to me one of your good long letters, and tell me all the little items of your daily life, and what wild flowers are in bloom. I wish I had a dandelion have now in my sick-room; the very sight of it would make me feel young again. I like dandelions and wild violets and johnnie jump-ups, and trailing arbutus, and checker- berry vines, a vast deal better than all the fashionable flowers with long names and great prices that they have for sale at the florists. And that reminds me of the flowers and berries on Eagle Mountain. I suppose they grow there now as when I was a boy, and other boys climb for them, and little girls come troop- ing down with their bonnets trimmed with, them, looking prettier far than all the jewelledC'4:v ladies of a court. But ah me I that twinge in my hip reminds me that I shall never climb that mountain again, never look from its top on the smiling villages, and the beautiful river at its feet. Never mind, I see before me a broader river, and :beyond "sweet fields all dressed in  &#xD;<pb n="234-235" xml:id="VAC7482-00000120"/> living green," and mountains of delight on which, in the true second childhood, I shall leap as a hart, and run and not be weary, walk and not faint. Oh, this blessed hope of immortality! What would old age be here without it? Bless God, Nellie, for it, too, in youth. Good by, my child. My blessing be upon you. Yours, truly, FREDERIC BERRY. When Nellie had finished reading this letter to her father, he said, "To-morrow, Nellie, I will go to -Boston; tell Mrs. Mills to have every thing in readiness for me. I must see Frederic at once. Poor fellow! He's got a genuine fit of home-sickness." "He shall have a basket of wild flowers, father, too, if you will earry them." "Yes, indeed; put in some wet moss, and John shall ride over toVernon and get some trailillg arbutus from the old woods at home,-he can go this afternoon, -and some dandelions, too, i    THE LOST WILL.      235 from the meadow, and some violets from under mother's bed-room window. We put the roots there when we were boys. Those were pleasant days. Fred and I were happy youngsters then, and the old gentleman heaved a sigh. Hear what Ruth says, father: 'I am very happy in my school, and what is better still, am making money. I have just sent mother twenty-five dollars, not a great sum to be sure, but it will be some help to her, and I hope to do still better. 'Mother writes to me that Jeff. Devoll has secured the meadow to her, and is very kind in doing her business well. He hopes he has become a Christian. I wish it might be so. The Westhrook folks fancy that all his kind- ness is interested, and that he wants our Mary for a wife. I hope not; for unless he is a dif- erent man from what he was formerly, I do not want him for a brother. Perhaps it is only gossip. 'I shall not go home for two or three years, and by that time, George will be in business,  &#xD;<pb n="236-237" xml:id="VAC7482-00000121"/> "ou    'THE LOST WILL. and then mother will be relieved from so much anxiety and care. With how much pleasure we look forward to that time!' Lucy's letter was long, closely written, and full of such little items of her every-day life as she knew Nellie would like to hear. She was an admirable letter writer, because she wrote just as she talked, with no long, fine spun sentences, or tedious apologies. We give that part of her letter relating to West- brook: "You will be surprised to learn that I have been to Westhrook, and that without visiting you. I did not intend to go so early in spring, but Sam has " set up a carriage" you must know--quite an event, of course, and he was resolved to have a certain span of horses which my father raised. Perhaps you may have heard me speak of them, they are so much alike, and so handsome. We call them the 'Twins." John agreed to change with Sam, and as the business must be done immediately, and Sam could not leave, Sarah and myself ^ji'^  . "o   THE LOST WILL.      237 went up for the ride. We could not stop long however, but I would have one visit to Eagle Mountain, and a run in the woods, where I found plenty of wild flowers, with which I loaded the carriage, and they are now in vases all over the house, whispering to me all day long, pleasant stories-of home and old times. "Have you heard about Jeff. Devoll? Oh, Nellie, I bless God that you ever gave me that precious little Bible. I never told you what I did with it, but one day when I was feeling particularly annoyed with Jeff., and in one of those moods when the very sight of him in Westhrook was like a nettle in a flower-bed, I suddenly recollected what you said, that I  must try and overcome such feelings, and so I made a strong effort, and much against my will, accepted, an invitation to ride home with him from Indian meadow. I do not recollect how it came about, but during that ride he said that he had never read the: Bible, and promisedo. do so thoroughly. I thought to myself, how much good he might denj ve M.  &#xD;<pb n="238-239" xml:id="VAC7482-00000122"/> 238      THE LOST, WILL. reading yours, with the references and pencil notes, and on the impulse of the moment I lent it to him. I was sorry the next instant, for it seemed almost a sacrilege to let such an infidel, or pagan rather, have the precious volume. He kept it so long, too, that I was afraid I would never see it again ; but, can you believe it, Nellie, that took, under God, was the means of his conversion. Mr. Herbert told me all about it on the first evening of my visit, but I could hardly believe it; and John's wife, who is not a Christian, though she is all but one, did not seem to have much confidence in Jeff. To be sure, she said, he was very much altered, every one could see that; but men could assume a character when they were seek- ing a wife, and she thought that Mary Dennie was the object of his efforts. This made me doubt some, because my faith for Jeff. was al- ways so weak. But the next day as I was in the garden, working over m1y hyacinths and who should come along but Jeff. with a in his hand. I had gone into the IX . . .   THE LOST WILL.      239 summer-house, and was separating some gladi- olus bulbs, when he came in, and, strange to say, I did not feel that dislike to him that I have always felt before. One glance at his countenance sufficed to show me that he was an altered man. Don't you know, Nellie, that the love of Christ in the heart, leaves its im- press on the face? "And don't you think that religion has a re- fining, softening influence on one?  True hu- mility is gentleness, and gentleness is one sign of a gentleman, is it not? Be that as it may, Jeff. apologized for keeping the Bible so long, and, though he said but little, I could see it had been a spring of living water to his soul. I suppose I was a little stiff and reserved, the least bit haughty, as has always been my cus- tom with him, but I did not remain so long, for as I took the little Bible, which he had brought in a box, and saw how fresh and clean it still looked, but as I held it in my had, i it seemed to open almost of its own accord, ^e: book of John. (You know how full t .  i  &#xD;<pb n="240-241" xml:id="VAC7482-00000123"/> SV     THEi LOST WILL. erences are there,) and my eyes fell upon the * passage -' For God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son, to be a propi- tiation for our sins,' &amp;c. "That has been a very precious book, Miss Lucy," said he; and thus commenced a con- versation which lasted an hour, and I only wish you could have been there. Why, his heart is full of love to God, and, like St. Paul, he is working as earnestly for Christ, as he formerly did against him.     "Our good minister, Mr. Herbert, tells me that he seems especially raised up to keep alive and quicken the church 'here, which had become like that of Laodicea, neither cold nor hot. As for his selfishness in the matter, Mary tells me that he has never even so much as called there of an evening, and has been kind to Mrs. Dennie from a sense of justice. "In conversation with Mr. UHerbert, I said, 'It astonishes me, for I did not expect it. I thought George would be a Christian before this, ad, lnder Nellie's influence, perhaps a   THE LOST WILL.      241 minister, but as for Jeff. he was such a rough, unhewn, misshapen stone, that I thought he. could never be fitted for God's temple.' Mr. Herbert smiled and said, 'For ye are sated by grace, through faith, and that not of your- selves, it is the gift of God.' Mr. Devoll will yet be a polished stone fit for the Great Build- er's hands." "I forgot to say that I could hardly find heart to take the Bible away from Jeff., he seemed to prize it so much, but it happened so that when I was in a book-store in Boston one day, I saw one almost exactly like it, and fear- ing that I should never see yours Again,  I bought it, and as I remembered a great deal you had written in yours, I wrote the same as nearly as I could remember. I had used it daily since, and I told Jeff. that I was too self- ish to let him retain your gift, but I would ex- change with him. He seemed perfectly satis- fied, and putting mine in his little box, he, bade me 'good morning,' and as he walked away, I said to myself, 'well there, Lucy' Fox, who &#xD;<pb n="242-243" xml:id="VAC7482-00000124"/> 242     TIlE LOST WILL. would have thought that you could have talked an hour with Jeff. Devoll, and taken pleasure, too, in it?'" Like almost all girls, Lucy always had a postcript to her letters, and, like them, too, put the most important part of her letter in the postcript, or what in her inmost heart was the most important. P. S. "I have not heard from George for a month. Perhaps my last letter did not reach him. Where is he now?  Lucy did not add that she had avoided go- ing to Wsthrook for that very reason. She was now a young lady, and the girlish frank- ness was exchanged for maidenly reserve; but the little worn locket still lay near her heart, and deep within that heart, was enshrined the old love, warm and fresh as ever, living like the violets, deep hidden beneath the snow. r Before Nellie had time to answer this let- ter, George was on his way to Cambridge. "Lucky again!" he said to himself, as he r'   THE LOST WILL.      243 mounted the coach. "I did not think two days ago that I should ever see the law school of Cambridge." "Lucky!"  [Ah, young man, why did it not occur to you that a kind Providence was, by his goodness, trying to win thee to repent- ance?] Two old men sat together in a large cham- ber at one of the hotels in Boston, both of them silver-haired and venerable in their ap- pearance. They resembled each other, but one was of a larger build and more portly frame, more ruddy and fuller-chesteds as if he had always breathed mountain air, and lived where sunlight was free; the other slender in form, with features rather more delicately chis-  elled, and that pallid look which a sedentary life in the city gives. His dress too, was of a more modern cit, and worn with a little more deference to fashion. The Governor had, or at least his brother fancied so, a stronger resemblance to their  &#xD;<pb n="244-245" xml:id="VAC7482-00000125"/>  mother than himself, and partly for this reason, and also because he was the elder, he had felt a peculiar tenderness and affection towards him. Frederic returned this feeling with in- terest, and the two brothers were perfectly conversant with each other's affairs, and shar- ed their joys and sorrows. "I am sorry," said Frederic, as he sat in his easy-chair, with a vase of Nellie's wild flowers on a table near him, "I am sorry that I must leave    home  this spring.  I have a strange shrinking from the voyage, and am half a mind now to give it up. I have settled all my worldly affairs as I should do, did I know I was to die; and here in this box, are valuable papers which I hope you will take charge of for me, and settle my business if we never meet again." "Poh, poh, brother, your sickness makes you low-spirited; cheer up. It is I   that will die first, and I    came down  now  partly on similar business. If I     should die while you are gone, you will, on your return, take charge of my af-  THlE LOST WILL.      245 fairs, and be a father to Nellie. It will make death easier to know that she has such a friend and father as yourself. I have made my will, one copy of which I leave with you, and have arranged all my business in such a way that there will be little to do. Only for Nellie's sake, should I mourn to leave this world." "And should you die, which God forbid, for many years eo come, if my own life is spar- ed, Nellie will be a precious charge. She has been to us both a household angel, teaching us how to live nearer heaven." The brothers passed gradually from this sad  subject, to their childhood, living over again those pleasant days, and forming plans to spend a part of- the next year's summer at their old home.  The Governor staid some days with his brother, assisted him in making his arrangements to leave the country, and they thanked God at parting, that they could hope to meet in heaven, if not again on earth.  &#xD;<pb n="246-247" xml:id="VAC7482-00000126"/> CHAPTER XV. How often are the best laid plans of men defeated! The utmost vigilance is not suffi- cient; the strongest props prove weak, the firmest friends sometimes fail. How few wills are ever executed to the let- ter; how many testators would start with as- tonishment and terror, could they return to earth and see how futile were all their cau- tious schemes. How   often the widow and .fatherless find their portion lessened by the greed of the very men whom the husband and father had trusted so confidently in life. It is a sad lesson, often given, but too sel- dom heeded, that human nature is very weak and very erring.     So  had  Governor Berry moralized, and    therefore he  determined  for once that all his worldly affairs should be so  arranged, that when the summons came to die. he would find himself prepared, and -could say, ' I am ready to depart." He had a large property, and Nellie was- his only heir. Her health was so delicate, and that of her mother's family, the members of which had all died young, that he could not anticipate long life for her, and to marriage he did not give one thought. Nellie's delicate health and her misfortune forbade that.- He therefore secured an ample fortune to Nellie, to control as she chose, and the remainder of his property, save some legacies, he gave to cer- tain benevolent objects that were very dear to him. He was a lawyer himself, and every- thing was drawn with the utmost exactness and care. To George he left only a thousand dollars, for the old gentleman had become so well convinced of the young man's want of principle, and the temptation which money would be to him, that he could not conscien- tiously do any better by him. One copy of his will, as we have seen, was  &#xD;<pb n="248-249" xml:id="VAC7482-00000127"/> 248     THE LOST WILL. left with his brother, and another deposited among his own papers in his sleeping-room. This work done, he felt that one part of his preparation for his great change was complet- ed, and as he was now past seventy, he said that he felt each year only an unexpected ad- dition to his lease of time. He gave up much of his public business, was more at home, while between his daughter and himself, the ties of affection were more closely drawn. George spent his vacations at Maplewood, but there was now a reserve between the old gentleman and himself, which seemed impos- sible to overcome. He was always kindly treated, and an interest manifested in his stud- ies ; but the old familiar address, the joke, the warm confidence, the fatherly greeting, were wanting. Nellie was pained by this, and strove to rake some amends by a thousand little sis- Ai rl attentions, which George appeared to appreciate more than formerly. The correspondence   between Lucy -and Nellie continued, and a warm, sisterly feel-   249 T  1HE LOST WILL. ing sprung up between them, so that their hearts were open to each other, all but on one George had found it very pleasant to visit his old playmate, Sam Fox. To one wholiked luxury as George did, and esteemed all the little elegances of city life --the house, and its Sam, whose honesty and capability they had thoroughly tested; and while Sam used the wealth they had obtained for the gratificatio of his family, he still had an eye to economy, and inherited a large share of his fathers shrewdness and foresight. He had never fanied George much sinet he refused to labor for his mother, and chose a life of greater ease at the Governor's for Sam, who had begun at the lowest round of the lad- der,had a great respect for steady, honest labor; for that independence which wauld a -9,-ag I ,O  &#xD;<pb n="250-251" xml:id="VAC7482-00000128"/> 250      THlE LOST WILL. eat no bread but that won by self-toil. He used to tell how his tired, blistered feet would ache when he carried parcels home, from travel- ling long dusty hot streets till he was faint and sick, and how hard he worked to save the first hundred dollars, which proved a good invest- ment; for when the firm found out his economy and self-denial, they promoted him at once.* Notwithstanding, George was very elegant in his manners, and considered rather a brilliant scholar--not remarkable for his application; but he had a fine voice, was a fluent, ready speaker, and apt debater; but Sam would often say, "Lulu, beware, it is not all gold that glitterss; a fellow that will not make sacrifices for a mother, may not make a very faithful hus- band." "Oh, but George will do much for his mother ,. whenqhe gets his profession. She is looking ? forward with great interest to that time." "We'll see," said Sam, " meanwhile Lulu, remember that Mason is a true friend, sand has -a warm honest heart. I have known and tried   251 THE LOST WILL.       25 him from childhood. Then there is King, the young minister, who would sacrifice every- thing but principle for you, and Hunt, who has supported an invalid mother ever since he was twelve years old. I never saw a more devoted son. Take a brother's advice, and ddn't fling pearls away for a counterfeit diamond." , Poor Lucy would try to laugh when Sam talked so; but in spite ofherself, her lip would quiver, and the tears start There was ome- ting about George which troubled her very much. With her quick instinct, and keen penetration, she feared that he was not so con- scientious, not so God-fearing as she would like. He was fond of gay society, and though he had often assured her that she was dear to him as his own sisters, and whenever he refer- red to his future plans, mingled her wit yet he had never asked any promise from her, nor had there even been any pledge between them, save the little childish exchange of gifts, years before in the old office. And yetGeorge knew-ithat Lucy regarded him in a differena :  &#xD;<pb n="252-253" xml:id="VAC7482-00000129"/> 252     THE LOST WILL.   , light from the other gentlemen who visited at her brother's, and he would have resented it, had she shown special friendship for any one else. Lucy retained her childish beauty and sim- plicity of manners. Her fair, fresh face, and graceful form, her sincere, but unostentatious piety, and her impulsive affectionate heart, made many friends. But her old attachment for home and the friends of her childhood were very strong, and George was associated with what was most dear to her-; their friendship had strengthened with their growth, and it was true that no one else was so dear to George as Lucy. But his cautious, selfish temperament, would never bind himself. ' No," he would say to himself, "I will wait; who knows the future? ' Alas! he would sacrifice even Lucy for his ambition.. She, in the mean time, hoped, wept, and prayed. ' Why cannot he become a Chris- tian? and when she would hear from West- bro  of Jeff's zeal for the Lord, she would k!, ' Why was he chosen, and George left?    l, til LOST WILL.     253 And then Mr. Herbert's answer would come, '. For ye are saved through grace by faith, and that not of yourself, it is the gift of God." And then she would pray that God's spirit would work in him, and lead him to the cross of- Christ. Sometimes he would go with her and listen to the most direct, heart-searching representa- tions of the truth, and Lucy would think, "Oh, George, must, he will feel this;" but when they returned, he would sit and calmly dissect the sermon, as a botanist would analyze the flower. It would seem as if he heard only with his calm, cold intellect. Alas! dear Lucy, he had resisted that goodness which leadeth to repentance i he had so often stifled the voice of conscience and yielded to tempta- tion, that the still small voice ws now rarely heard. But pray on, such prayer has a reflex influence on the Christian's heart. Pray on, did I say?  Alas I alas! woe be unto him who has trampled such prayers beneath his feet, who treads the path of sin, shutting his ears to the gentle voice that wins him back.  &#xD;<pb n="254-255" xml:id="VAC7482-00000130"/> 254     THE LOST WILL. Poor Jeff., with his hopeless mother, his drunken father, his godless home, his almost pagan ignorance, would have found more mercy than thyself, when the Lord should come to reckon with his servants. George's year at Cambridge was out. He was now admitted to the Bar, and the world was all before hifn. Tracer was dead; the Governor and Brown were the only men who knew his secret, and George felt that he was safe. Sin was hateful to him, only as it brought worldly disgrace. Maplewood seemed more like home than any other place, and though he went to Westhrook and remained a few days, at his mother's earnest request; he returned there, and once more found himself in his own chamber, which was always kept in readiness for him, by Nel- lie's thoughtfulness. He was undecided where to commence busi- ness, and had written some letters "West, to which he was now waiting a reply.   T"E LOST WILL.      255 Another spring opened, and Nellie was wait- ing with great interest, the return of Uncle Frederic, to spend the summer with them. The old house at Vernon had been repaired, and the farmer who lived there, had given up his two best rooms, that the two brothers and Nellie might remain as long as they wished. But letters came, that Uncle Frederic was still detained; he had other business committed to him, and, moreover, he must wait till some law decision was made, and every body knows the proverbial slowness of law affairs. "' This is a grievous ,disappointment," said the old gentleman to Nellie. "I believe I am in my second childhood, for I feel this as)I used to the trials of my boyhood. Moreover, it takes me to the city again, a journey for. which I feel no inclination." "Why, father, cannot George do it for you?" "No, my child, it is on business for Frederic, and I would trust it to no other hands." "You are not well,- father; couldn't you defer it a few days?" [.  ...,  &#xD;<pb n="256-257" xml:id="VAC7482-00000131"/> ZOO     TH'iIEiS LOJbi1 WILL. I may be worse, was his reply, and as it is important to be done, I will do it at once. 'What thy hand findeth to do,' you know, Nellie." "Yes; perhaps you are right, but I shall be very anxious for you." "No, no, not so. When I return, we will ride over to Westhrook, and bring Lucy home to stay awhile. She is there now. Her bonny face, and cheery music, will do us good." Two days passed away. It took a day and a half in those old times to go from B--  to Boston, though it was only a hundred miles distant. The time passed wearily to Nellie, as George had gone to attend a county court. He re- turned home on the third day, and they rode out together, the day following, to Mill Hol- low. It was pleasant to see the change which had been wrought there. The mill-wheel still turned merrily, and when there was water there was always grists to grind, and the miller in his powdered hat and dusty coat, had the   THE LOST WILL.     257 rare reputation of never taking more than due toll. The old houses with their broken window, and ragged fences were gone, and in their places small neat houses with white palings and trim little gardens. Hyacinths and tulips, and many choice gar- den flowers abounded, that had come from Maplewood. The street was lined on each side with young shade trees, and "Mill Hollow" was now a pleasant place to ride through. Even George found nothing to criticise, for, instead of the vile smell of boiled cabbage, the fragrance of the hyacinths saluted him. Temperance and SundaySchools had brought these blessings with them. Martha Slade's father had reformed and married again, a nice, amiable woman, who took good care of the children. But they always came once a week to Maplewood and took tea with Martha. Nellie learned from one of her Sunday School  &#xD;<pb n="258-259" xml:id="VAC7482-00000132"/> i258     THE LOST WILL. scholars, that one of the families that used to live in Mill Hollow were sick, and in great poverty. They lived two miles distant, but she resolved to visit them the next day. She did so; her carriage loaded with comforts, and carried great consolation with her. She was stepping out of the carriage just at dusk, when Mr. Walker, the clergyman, met her, and giving her his arm, waited upon her to a seat. There was something in his countenance and manner that startled her. How quick we read sad tidings in the faces of our friends I She looked up at him; her heart trembling, and lips essaying to speak, but no sound r escaped them. "Nellie," said the minister, "your father 'has been very sick."  "How do you know? Where is he? Take  me to'him," she exclaimed quickly, as she rose from her seat. "Yes, my dear girl, you will go to him, but he cannot come to you'"  6           9F   THE LOST WILL.      259 She clasped her handsa deadly paleness overspread her face, and her mute agony, as she ' turned to the speaker, as if still doubting, but fearful that she had understood him only too well, was sad to look upon. She would have fallen, but her kind friend laid her on the couch, and said, "Nellie, he is in heaven, do not wish him  back."' She pressed her hands to her forehead; there was a strange dreamy look about her eyes. Poor child! The shock was too great, and niin  to her, for a few minutes she became insensible. Mrs. Mills came, and bathed her head and hands, then darkened' the room, and sat down by the poor stricken one.         - When she awoke to consciousness, her first  thought was, "Oh, that I had died too!" and such a sense of loneliness oppressed her, tat- she felt life insupportable. They brought the good old man to'his oWn home. The large house was crowded with friends and neighbors, who mourned for him with true sorrow. 4t   :rb  &#xD;<pb n="260-261" xml:id="VAC7482-00000133"/> 260     THE LOST WILL. George and Nellie rode as chief mourners. The brother, who would have gladly supported Nellie in this sad hour, was far away. The largest procession that had ever been known in B., wound its slow way along the valley and up the hill-side, to the home of tile dead; and as they laid the good man in hIls last resting place amid many tears, Mr. Walk- er, from the heart, exclaimed, as they laid- the earth upon the coffin, "1 Blessed are the dead that die in the Lord." It was a sad household at Maplewood, for every one felt that they had lost a father. Luby came to her friend, and her cheerful, hopeful temper, and her sweet words of conso- lation, were like balm to the stricken heart of Nellie. When the latter recovered from the first shock of her grief her religion showed itself in a sweet resignation that was most beautiful to behold. It is a very common question, and though it 'often seems very heartless, it nevertheless,'bA the way of the world as soon as a man dies ,   T THE LOST WILL.     261 to hear "how much was he worth, and how did he dispose of his property I " ! I the case of Governor Berry, this was aske, with sonme interest, by many who knew his benevolence, and the extent of his property. No one, however, seemed to know much about it, excepting that Mr. Walker said that there was a will, unless the old gentleman de- royed it within a short time, for he lhad signed as a witness.* George, of course, heard many of these re- marks, and no one, perhaps , had more curiosity upon this matter than himself. One day Nellie handed hima key and her father's watch, and asked him to lay the latter in her father's desk; "For," said she, "I clan not go there yet." George did as tshe requested; and on open- ing a little drawer on the inside, in which he thought t p to lace the watch, he observed a folded paper, 'on which was written, "Last will and Testament, &amp;e." N" o1w, thought he, my curiosity can be gratified  but, at the  &#xD;<pb n="262-263" xml:id="VAC7482-00000134"/> 262S.    TH1B LOST WILL. same moment, Mrs. Mills, who had observed the door of the room open, came in. "Ah," said she, "is it you? I did not know that any one was here ;" and then, with that shrewd, quick wit peculiar to women of her class, she passed swiftly by where George stood, and she, too, saw, "Last will and Testament." George closed the desk, unconscious that she, too, had a glance thereon, and went back to the sitting-room where Nellie and Lucy were sitting. He handed the keys to Lucy, but he observed that she placed them in a little box in her work-basket. All that day George seemed in a sort of muse or brown study, as we sometimes term it, and the day following, he was very absent- minded. Lucy attributed it to regret and sor- row for the loss of his friend and father, and strove to interest him in a book which she was reading. On Sunday, Nellie was too ill to attend church, but she would not allow Lucy to re-   THE 1 LOST W ILLd.   zu main at home on her account. The whole family were in the habit of attending Sunday School, excepting Mrs. Mills and George. When the latter returned from the morning service, the house seemed deserted, it was so silent. Nellie was in her chamber, and Mrs. Mills came down very silently, and remarking that Nellie was asleep, brought some luncheon in for George, and retired to her room. As George sat there, his eye fell on the work- basket, and the little box-one moment he hesitated, and then walked across the room, and possessed himself of the key. Awhile he sat there with it in his hand, and reflected. Then listening, and hearing no step, he went into the room which had been sacredly closed ever since the day of the funeral. He turned the key and opened the little drawer. At that moment, Lucy's step was heard in the hall; she had been anxious for Nellie, and returned home. George hesitated, stopped, and dropped the paper back into the drawer. He heard Lucy open -the sitting-room door, and then, as  &#xD;<pb n="264-265" xml:id="VAC7482-00000135"/> 264     THE LOST WILL. if not finding what she sought, turn, and go lightly up stairs. Again, George took up the paper, and this time he did not hesitate, but put it in his pocket, closed, and locked the desk, and walked away. "No harm done, by merely satisfying my curiosity," he said, and he went to his own room. After locking his door he broke the seal so carefully that he thought it could be re-fasten- ed without detection, and read. The docu- ment was long, each specification very minute, and it was some time before George came to his own name. "One thousand dollars!" he said; "a paltry sum, surely, compared to his whole estate. One hundred thousand, and fif- ty thousand of that flung away to benevolent societies I "He threw the document down, and walked his room  in disappointment and anger. Two hours passed and the paper still lay upon the floor, while he stood at the win- dow in- deep thought. The supper bell rung-he stooped down, took the will, locked it in his own desk, and   THE LOST WILL.      265 went down to tea, in appearance placid,' self- possessed and bland as usual. It was a pleas- ant evening, flowers were in bloom in the gar- den, and the lawn looked cool and fresh. Af- ter tea he and Lucy strolled out there, while Nellie, who had come down from her room, sat at the window. Scattered clouds moved lazily along; there was little air stirring, and a soft, dreamy haze hung like a light veil over the distant hills. George and Lucy walked onward uncon- sciously till they came to the grapery, where they seated themselves, and some slight word, like one musical, note waking a pleasant song in memory, recalled their :childhood, and one after another pleasant reminiscence came up till time flew rapidly away, and the setting sufi reminded them that they had already stayed too long away from Nellie. "7Vhat happy days those were," said Lucy. ' I am inclined to think with the poet, that we are never so happy in after life as in child- hood." s   &#xD;<pb n="266-267" xml:id="VAC7482-00000136"/> i2;iO    THE LOST WILL. "But it should not be so; I suppose," said Nellie, who overheard the remark, "life should be a continual progress in good, and of course in happiness." "Oh, dear," said Lucy, "but it is fight, fight all the time against selfishness and sin; we can never rest." "Nor should we wish to, Lucy; but only think of the happiness which conquest over evil brings! One temptation resisted is worth more than a year of childhood." "I think you and Lucy can know little about such happiness, then," said George;" for how little have you to resist!" "Why, George," said Lucy, "we have a world of foes to fight; the heart is full of evil, you know -but, as Lucy says, one conquest even, is worth a great deal - one temptation resisted, makes us strong to resist another, 'But he that weakly yields to sin, Will almost always yield again.' " George knew that by experience, but he never spoke of himself on such matters. In a l   THE LOST WILL.      267 few moments he left the house and took a long walk. H-e thought at one moment he would resist the temptation which haunted him as if an evil spirit dogged his footsteps.  But George had listened to such suggestions too often to have them withdrawn by any slight rejection. "When sin hath held its empire long, 'Tis hard to break its stern control; Nought but a power divinely strong Can turn the current of the soul.  It was dark when he returned home. The young ladies were in their room. George re- tired to his own. He lighted his candle, and read over the will --then rose and walked the room. Suddenly, as with a desperate resolu- tion, he seized the paper, and put one coraer of it to the lamp. It caught fire instantly, and he carried lamp and paper and held them over the stove, till the latter was one little black heap, which a breath might blow away. For a moment George was frightened at his deed, then muttered to himself, ' Now, Lucy,  &#xD;<pb n="268-269" xml:id="VAC7482-00000137"/> ^OO     THE LOST WILL. you are lost to me forever; this is punishment enough, surely." He brushed the heap of ashes into the stove, retired to his bed and slept. Some weeks passed  the estate of Gover- nor Berry was to be settled, and inquiries were made for his will, but search was fruitless. Nellie suggested that her Uncle Frederic would know all her father's wishes, and the settlement of the estate was deferred till his re- turn. But Uncle Frederic never came; the vessel in which he embarked from England was lost at sea, and the two brothers met in heaven. One warm day, Mrs. Mills, in her avocation as house-keeper, removed the little stove in George's room, and like a tidy woman as she was, thought to remove the ashes. In doing so her keen black eyes, aided by spectacles, which she wore on all occasions, discovered two scraps of paper, one containing "N. B. Berry, B--, Jan. 6, 1806."  And another,   J LJLA.  JUV I JL Y .r UJLJ* .aw U the words, "I give and bequeathe."   She probed the ashes carefully with her hands, but nothing more was found. She shook her head, and there were strange suspicions in her mind, thoughts which she dare not clothe in words. "But I'll tell the facts, I will," she said; "and 'll show these to Nellie, I will." But for wise reasons, she never did show them to Nel- lie, though they were carefully preserved in a little worsted housewife, amid a few ancient relic s reeled  &#xD;<pb n="270-271" xml:id="VAC7482-00000138"/> CHAPTER XV. IT needed but one act more, one crowning act of deception- for George to complete his plans-an act so heartless, so cruel, that I blush to record it; and were I writing fiction, I should be strongly tempted to disguise or palliate the facts. But when a man has yielded again and again to temptation, it is like a railroad car going down an inclined plane, every foot of progress only accelerates the speed. Then the way of sin is so alluring, so deceptive- "She hath a thousand treacherous arts To practice on the mind." The Bible hath said, "the love of money is the root of all evil," and I know of no instance where this passion is more odious than when a bad man, for his own selfish purposes, practices   THL LOST WILL.     X'( 1 on the affection of a warm-hearted, innocent woman. We have seen how Nellie, in her loneliness and sorrow, clung to the few friends which were spared to her. No wonder, then, that when Lucy leftMaplewood, and George re- mained, that she should cling to him with all the affection of a sister. She had always sup- posed, had hoped, indeed, that George would marry Lucy, and that they would reside in B. In the fullness of her own generous heart, she had resolved to share her property with George, and had formed many little plans for their hap- piness. She was surprised when she made some playful, girlish allusion to the subject to hear Lucy say, "But, Nellie, there is no engage- ment between us." "Oh, but there will be," said Nellie, her eyes brightening, for she thought George'was. only waiting to make a home for his bride. But George confirmed what Lucy had said, some weeks after her departure, and added som   we             de  &#xD;<pb n="272-273" xml:id="VAC7482-00000139"/> 272     TEIl LOST WILL. that Lucy would probably be happier with some one else. The true woman instinct of Nellie, led her to think differently, but she said nothing'. A year afterward, all the good folks of B. as well as those of Westhrook, had plenty of food for gossip in the reported marriage of George and Nellie. Many doubted, some shook their heads and looked wondrous wise, but said nothing; a few added, " no wonder, who could live with Nellie and not love her in spite of her misfortune? The young man is acting nobly." There were two persons, one in Westhrook, good Mr. Herbert, and Mrs. Mills, the house- keeper, at Maplewood, that had their doubts and fears, and would gladly have prevented the marriage. But our precious Nellie was to be perfected through suffering. In the purity of her own heart, she loved George, and like many, per- haps, most such single-minded persons, she suspected no evil. She could hardly believe   !\       THE LOST  WILL.      273 at first the story of his affection ; but George understood all those little arts, with which a man with graceful person, polished manners, and a bad heart, can practice on a woman's faith. It never once entered Nellie's heart, that he had another prize to gain by ruining her. "Of course," she thought, "he will share half any way; he cannot think I would do otherwise ;" but selfish people do- not ever sus- pect others of generous motives. Brown, the cashier, was a prudent worldly man, and kept his own counsel. The wealth with- which George would be endowed by his marriage, would confer power --it was not safe to offend him. One patient sufferer alone, bear her own sor- row in silence. Lucy struggled with all the earnestness of a humble Christian to bear this great disappointment of her life. Her eyes lost their brightness, lher cheeks, their rich bloom, and when she smiled, it was sadder than a sigh to see, for it passed so  &#xD;<pb n="274-275" xml:id="VAC7482-00000140"/> : 'i     THE LOST WILL. quickly away, and was succeeded by a look so full of pain. She never spoke of the mar- riage, even to her mother, save once, when Nellie's letter came, begging her to come and act as bridesmaid. "Mother," said she, "will you write to Nellie for me, and tell her that I am not quite well, and must be excused." "Yes," child, said her mother, who was a plain, common sense motherly woman, without a large share of sensitiveness, or the least romance in her character. "ButI hope you don't feel disappointed about George." Some- how or other he never was a favorite of mine when a boy; I never did fancy these hand- some, lady-looking men. Perhaps, because your father was a rough, sturdy, hard-working man, and such a good husband, too, that I think well of those men who are more like him, than those smooth, polished gentlemen, like George. "But I'm glad he has money for his mother's sake." "For his mother's sake." Alas! Alas I During the few years that Nellie lived, that   TIE LOST WILL.      275 mother was watched and tended with a daugh- ter's care. But that time was short; for it was impos- sible, for even Nellie, so slow to suspect evil, not to learn at last in the intimacy of married life, that George had deceived her; that he had married her for the wealth she had brought hims, This revelation was the cold hand of death laid on her heart. Her health failed gradually, and for awhile, her pale face, sweet in its ex- pression, still, but so sad, seemed to her friends to have " passing away" written upon it. It was then that Lucy, forgetting everything but the comfort of her friend, came and minis- tered unto her. The two friends were together constantly, and Lucy promised Nellie that she would never leave her till death, and that her last sigh should be breathed in her arms. She kept her promise - and as Mrs. Mills expressed it, "It seemed like Hopeful and Christian, only they couldn't both go over the river together, and that made Lucy sad; for,  &#xD;<pb n="276-277" xml:id="VAC7482-00000141"/> '276     THE LOST WILL. said she,  m"I must ,stand on the bank of the river, while the slining ones on the other side, are waiting to bear you to the celestial city."- "Yes; I see them, said Nellie," and I feel that I am going to join "the innumerable company of angels, and the spirits of just men made perfect." My mother, my father, dear little Eddie, and Mr. Beck, who, though blind, led me to the cross of Christ. I can almost see them now, and hear the song, "Blessing, and honor, and glory, and power, be unto him who sitteth upon the throne, and to the Lamb, for ever and ever." "Sing, Lucy, sing something about the Saviour," and she begun in a falter- ing voice, herself, "A guilty, weak" - But Lucy took up the words:- - "A guilty, weak, and helpless worm, On thy kind arms I fall; Be thou my strength and righteousness, My Jesus and my all." Nellie never spoke after that. Oh! sir, I 'cannot tell you how lonely the house was after Lucy went away. She went the very day   THEl LOST WILL.     2" after the funeral, and she never entered the house afterwards. I used to wish she would look in once awhile just to give me a bit of comfort; but ye see, sir, in less than a year after that, the 'Squire, that's what they called George, after he mar- ried Nellie--well, what should he do, but ask Lucy to come and be mistress at Maple- wood!" "And what did Lucy say to that?"I asked. "Why, sir," she tossed her head a little, and the old color came back to her face, and she gave him just such a look as she used to give Jeff. inthe old times, only ten times more stern, and said, "Not for the wealth of the world, would I be your wife, George Dennie." Ye see, sir, I heard it all, for I happened to 'be down here, visiting her mother, at the tavern, -when the 'Squire made his call, and we heard' the conversation; for Lucy didn't even take the pains to shut the door, when he called; the door between the parlor and the dining-room ' ' . -- ., L "t-..... ml r,  &#xD;<pb n="278-279" xml:id="VAC7482-00000142"/> 278  T- Hr    LOST WILL. and he was so engaged, he didn't see that it was open. It did me good, sir, it did." "And where is Lucy, now?"I asked. ' Why, don't you know that, sir; I thought you knew that before I begun my story " I assured her that I did not. "Well, then, you know that the 'Squire Dennie married again, a cold, proud, woman, and he had children; but there's not one that's a bit of comfort to him; his daughter married against his Will; his favorite son died; his other is a spend-thrift; but, sir, you wouldn't know he had ever had trouble, for he is just as bland and polite as ever. You've seen him, sir; don't you think him a handsome old man?  I could not deny the regularity of his fea- tures, and the almost feninine delicacy of his complexion. "You wouldn't think, o look at him," con- tinued the old lady, " that his- mother was sick and bed-ridden, for a -whole year, before she A d3 andc that the 'Squire didn't come near her   ,T'H1 LOST WILL.     279 during all that time. No, I'm mistaken, he did come just two days before she died, and then he came again in great style to the funeral, and afterwards he built that great marble pillar in the grave-yard to her memory. 'But Deacon Jeff. was a great comfort to her. She didn't lack for any thing, if he knew she wanted it. Ye see, Ruth was married, and settled West, and Charlie was working his way along to be a doctor, (his brother didn't help him any), and poor Mary, who. had worked hard all her days, was most worn out with care and hard work. But Mary is well cared for now. Deacon Jeff. and his wife call her sister, and they've taken her home to the old house where she was: born-only 'it don't look much as it did in /  those days. You can see it across the road, isn't it a pretty place, with its peayzas and bay windows, and its lawn and shrubbery? I call it the "palace beautiful;" you remember in the Pilgrim's Progress, there was such a place built for the relief and security,of :pil- w , . .P-'  &#xD;<pb n="280-281" xml:id="VAC7482-00000143"/> -ims on  he way to Mount Zion. Now, every ie that is on the way to Mount Zion, all pil- ims in trouble, and poor, and aged saints  ways find rest and refreshment at Deacon "' But, what about Lucy, my good woman, want to hear more about her?" "Why, hain't I told you, about her?" she ked with a little querelousness in her voice, thought I was talking about her all the [ assured her that she had not mentioned her nae for ten minutes.    ' ' Oh, well then, I'I begin and go all back bin.  You must know that Lucy didn't like ive at Boston any more, it was too gay for at Sam's, but she came home, and lived h JQon's wife, here- in the tavern. They I got a new road to Boston by that time, so t  there wasn't ne'er as much custom as nerly, and the Boston folks were talking It a  railroad. John said, that when that built, he'd have to take down the sign, shut up tavern.           -    '   "Lucy didn't go about singing as formerly, but she went about doing good. Wherever there was sickness, and poverty, and suffering, there you'd find Lucy Fox.  She had a great many offers of marriage, for she was hand- some as a picture, but she wouldn't listen to one of e'm. Mr. Herbert? the minister, used to say, that she was his right-hand helper, and so modest, and humble, too, that' every body loved her. "She got to be almost an old maid, and people thought, may be she'd go out as a missionary. I've a notion that she thought of it herself. But one day Deacon Jeff. was taken sick. He boarded  at Mrs.  Denie's --they  said he boarded there purpose to help 'em, paying a," high price for his board, and taking care of things for the widow. I don't know how that was, but he didn't board at the tavern anfLy   i: more after Lucy came to John's to live.' Jeff. didn't appear much as he used to; he'd got wonderfully polished up, he had travelled all over the States, and spent a year in Philadel. , c  .9              ^  &#xD;<pb n="282-283" xml:id="VAC7482-00000144"/> 282 -282     '1THE LOST WILL. phia, and one in Europe. Then, he was ap pointed Judge, and that's his title, now, I sup- pose, but they'd got into the habit of calling him 'Deacon,' and he says that's the most honorable title, so they say, 'Deacon Jeff.;' its the most natural you know. Well, where was I? "Deacon Jeff. was sick,' I suggested a little implatiently. "Yes, yes; he was down with the 'typhus,' it raged dreadfully in these hill towns that year, and e'en a'most all the neighbors was sick. - There were twenty deaths in this little place. Almost everybody had a touch of it, but Lucy, and folks thought it was miraculous how she escaped, for she was just as: strong, and fresh, and healthy, as ever. She said it was only because she bathed, and exercised, and was very careful of her diet, and kept her mind quiet. I think myself 'twas because she was so good, that God fulfilled his promise, There shall be no evil befall thee, neither shall any plague come nigh thy dwelling; because thou   THE LOST WILL.     283 hast made the Lord thy refuge, the most High, thy habitation.' "At any rate, she was round day and night, wherever she was needed. "One day Charlie Dennie came over in great trouble. Deacon Jeff. was very sick, and the doctor thought he must die-it was just at the time of the fever, but they could get nobody to watch. Mary was so tired, that the doctor had given her medicine, and sent her to bed, and Mrs. Dennie was very feeble, so that there was no one but Charlie to do a chore. They were all ailing, too, here. John was just getting up from the fever, and his wife had a young child.  "While Charlie was telling his trouble, Lucy turned pale, and then red, and seemed thinking what to do. At last, she spoke .up quite pleasantly to Charlie, who looked sad enough, 'I'll come. over, Charlie, and help you, to- night.'  "Charlie was very much pleased. 'Then, perhaps, he'll get well, Lucy.'  &#xD;<pb n="284-285" xml:id="VAC7482-00000145"/> 84  -    TIE LOST WILL. "Lucy put on her loose wrapper, tucked her curls behind her ears, and taking a little basket, with some of her own remedies in it, went over to Mrs. Dennie's. "Jeff. wasn't in his right mind all the time the fever run so high. The room was very close and warm, and the sick man thought he was, burning up. She let in fresh air, bathed his head and feet in tepid water, gave him some cooling drink, and arranged his bed and pillows more comfortably. In moving the last, -she found under one, the little gold clasped Bible which she had given him so many years before. "He put his hands up, and missed it. ' Where is it.?' he asked, almost fiercely. 'Where have you put it?' '-Oh, Mary, you'll not take that away, will you? It has her name in it, it is my greatest treasure; and when I die, Mary, remember, I want that buried in my coffin with me. You'll not f6rget, will you, Mary? Speak, Mary; promise me that, and I shall die easier.'              I '   285 rITE  H LOST WILL . Poor L ucy stepped a little m oreto the hed of the bed, and answered in a low voice- Yes yes , here it is;' and she laid the Bi- Yes, yes, herertis"          ^ t ble where his hand could touch it. ,' Hee soon fell asleep aind contr ary to the doC- tor's advice, she let him sleep; but she sat by ;his side au the time, gently rubbing him, and watching lestthe sleep should be too deep and thus weaken him e for ,During that sleep there seemed a change for the better; the pulse more natural, the skin the   changeyexs more moist and lasoft. hen he seemed to be waking, IUc slipped out of the room and call- ed Charlie. in the mornilg the changeWa so favorable that the doctor came over and asked Lucy to continue her nursing for the , Deacon Jeff. seemed surprised and gratied, but he was too weak to talk. He watched her every moment that he was awake, and when inher duty as nurse, she moved lightly about the room, his eyes rested upon her with such interest and pleasre, that the very sight of It            '  &#xD;<pb n="286-287" xml:id="VAC7482-00000146"/> 286     THE LOST WILL. her aided his recovery more than all the doc- tor's stuff he took. 3 "i I don't know how it happened, for Lucy  never told it all, but she nursed him till he was out of danger, and she found out in that sick chamber that Jeff. had loved her ever since she was a little girl, but he never dared to tell her so- and when Lucy learned that he thought she was too good and lovely for him, and that in his deep humility, he felt unworthy to touch the hem of her garment, then she felt humbled, too, that he who had struggled so hard to conquer, and had become so good and noble, with-so much to contend against, should think so much more highly of her than she de- served. "I can't tell, sir, how it happened, but, as the Bible says, 'it came to pass,' that in process of time Jeff. and Lucy were married. The wedding took place here, and it was the- last great party before the old sign was taken down, and what was singular, too, it was the last couple Mr. Herbert ever married.   THE LOST WILL.      287S t "His words were prophetic, for when he fin- ished the ceremony, and pronounced them man and wife, he said, ' Lord, now lettest thou thy servant depart in peace.' He died soon after. "But, sir, it would have done your heart good to see Lucy after her marriage. She grew young and handsome; she was good and hum- ble as ever, but she climbed the hills an sang the old songs and made us all merry. As for Jeff., as John Fox expressed it, he thought, the very ground that Lucy trod upon was blessed by her presence,-and he looked all the time as if he wanted to say, Bless the Lord, oh my soul, for his great goodness unto me.' There never was a happier couple than Deacon Jeff. and Lucy. They're old folks, now, but they are just as happy as at first, and their children are blessings to their parents and the world." The old lady had talked so long that I de- , ferred any further conversation till the next day. i She was over ninety years of age, but her memory of past events was wonderful.  &#xD;<pb n="288-289" xml:id="VAC7482-00000147"/> 288     THE LOST WILL. She told me in my first interview with her, how she came to be at the old Fox Tavern. "After Nellie died," said she, "Maplewood never seemed pleasant to me. The sunlight was gone, and I felt all the time as if I were in a tomb; Martha staid, for she was left in my care, and I had quite a notion of buying a lit- tle house and making a home for ourselves. But Providence opened the way for us, just as the 'Squire was about to bring his new wife home. Johin Fox had moved to Boston and taken one of them big taverns to carry on, and let this place to his cousin Seth. Now Seth had business at Maplewood, about some hous- es, and he took a fancy to Martha, and I gave my consent at once, for the Fox's are a likely set, and Martha would hear to nothing else but I must come to live with her; and here I am, a poor, helpless, old woman, but you'd think I was a queen, the way Deacon Jeff.'s wife and Martha treat me. t( But then, sir, I'm telling you a deal about our folks, and maybe it don't interest you at all, but old folks like to talk of the past."   THE LOST WILL*      289 The papers which were found in the old es- critoire contained among other documents, Governor Berry's will, and a correspondence between the brothers Nathan and Frederic, upon the disposal of their property. I had some curiosity to know what the old lady would say when I should produce them, and I purposely deferred this interview until I had ' learned the facts which she had already given me It was a pleasant morning, when I entered her chamber, and found her propped up in ant old-fashioned, high-back easy-hair, busy with her knitting. She greeted me very cordially, and seemed all ready for a talk; nothing pleased her more than to find a listener who would sit patiently while she talked about old times at Maplewood. Her mind was very clear this morning, and- I introduced the subject by asking her about Frederic Berry. It was pleasat to hea her tell of the affection of the brothers, andshe sh came garrulous upon it.' I asked her if she, [       ' I!  &#xD;<pb n="290-291" xml:id="VAC7482-00000148"/> vZv     ';.tLOST WILL. i ould know their hand-writing. She laughed "- I guess I ought, for Nellie almost always showed me the letters, and I have some writ- me by themselves, when I kept house at son, and had the care of things at the old homestead." - A11 showed- her the papers, and looked 4idmdu for her spectacles. "Never mind the spectacles, sir; I haven't worn them these ten years; I can see to retd fine print as well as Martha. Ah! that's it; that is his old familiar writing; you see that odd quirl to his r's. lie didn't write quite so fine and handsome as Frederic, but the sight  of it does me good in my old age. There I he says-' I hope you will not disapprove of my bequests to the Bible and Missionary Societies. Nellie will have property enough beside. I * only regret that' I have not given more in past years, but my will makes some amends.' Why, sir, he was always giving and giv- ing His will Then he did make a will-I always knew he did, sir. I felt it in every  t  ,   ,  -   , ' j    THE LOST WILL.      291 bone; but I don't know-I don't know, sir; it's strange that it never came to light;" and the old woman fell into a fit of musing, from which I did not rouse her for some minutes. I was looking over the papers. "Here, Mrs. Mills," said I, after a while, "is something which reads very much like a will, and seems duly attested. A little paper was attached to it which contained these words -* ' An exact copy of this will is in my desk, deft hand drawer) in the east room at'B-.'" The excitement of the old woman was -o great that I was afraid of the conseqiuences. She pounded on the floor with her cane, "Martha I Martha Slade, come quick." Mrs . Fox came in somewhat alarmed, for Mrs.: MiW' voice was strong and loud, unlike * the feeble voice of age. "There, Martha, now I know why I have lived to be over ninety years old. ihave been tempted to doubt God's justice, but I want to tell you now, never to doubt it, if you should live to the age of Methusaleh." 2   .   ,           .  &#xD;<pb n="292-293" xml:id="VAC7482-00000149"/> 292     THE LosT WILL. When she read the will, her shrewdness led her to see at once through George's conduct; everything was made clear to her. 4"Now, Martha, bring my little housewife, the red and green ; it's in the top draw of my :nreau. I haven't seen it for twenty years, -biut I guess you'll find it there." It was produced, and the papers which she drew from the ashes were safe, and the writing legible. Moreover, a word or two which Hhe had failed to discover on the scorched and blackened part, was deciphered by the more practiced eye of a lawyer. She related the circumstance of having seen the will in the 'drawer, George's hesitation and guilty look, the finding the papers in the ashes, allwith the untmost minuteness, and she did not Wary even under the most thorough cross-examination.  Then she recalled the sudden illness of Gov- ernor Berry, on his return from the Bank, and her awn suspicions of George at that time. SDe referred us to Brown, who was still living in B  .--, Here we met with more caution i-       ."   Tng'-l LOQ T WILL.    2%3 and worldly prudence, but the evidence of the forgery was at last produced, clear and irrefra- gible. We would fain leave this last page a blank, for it is sad to see an old man, who has appa rently held a high position in the community', who has had offices of trust committed to him, suddenly fall into ignominy and contempt. We have many such instances, and the world wonders that men with sp much to lose, shold so suddenly yield to temptation. But the truth is, that the man was corrupt all the time, for we never become so utterly wicked at once. There has been the slow, gradual indulgece mn sin, but it has been conT cealed by at outward show of goodness, Whi, * like the whited sepulchre, is fair only without. George Dennie found now that " the way of the transgressor is hard," for though the strict penalty of the law was not visited upon h;r, yet for ten years (for he lived a little . byon his three-score and ten,) he was a wreflt lonely, unloved man..   &#xD;<pb n="294-295" xml:id="VAC7482-00000150"/> f2E4     rlST3i LOST WILL. The heirs at law were at first inexorable, and would have taken everything from him; but as he had kept the principal good, and in his selfishness, hoarded his ill-gotten means, they left him enough to keep him from want. But he left Maplewood a disappointed, broken- hearted man, for his idols were shattered. He had cared for nothing but a reputati on among men, and the means to gratify his selfishness. These gone, and George Dennie was bankrupt for earth and heaven. The once fair, talented boy, of whom his friends expected so much, and who won the first honors of his class at college who was guilty of none of the grosser vices of society, and who was fitted by nature and education for a bigh position, sunk so low in the estimation of his fellow-men, that none were so humble as - to do him honor. He had trusted in himself, and his own deceitful heart had led him astray. Verily did the apostle say--"By grace are ye saved, through faith, and that not of your- selves, it is the gift of God."   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
