<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC7995">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Minister of E.; or, Evils in the Church </title>
            <author >Tellall, Temperance.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC7995</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The minister of E.; or, Evils in the church</title>
                  <author >Tellall, Temperance.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >59 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >The author</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Skowhegan [Me.] </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1862">1862</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-06-02">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The minister of E.; or, Evils in the church</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC7995-00000001"/>THE BY TEMPERANCE TELLALL  PEIISED FOR T HE HAUTTHOB fi  BY*TE M?E RA GE TE L LALL- P;FBIJllD FOR THE AUTHOR. }    &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC7995-00000002"/>   THE  MINISTER OF 'E., "How is your spiritual prosperity, and what is the prosperity of the church whereyouhavebeen stopping," said Aunt Grace to me, after the usual salutatioas, on my return asfter a long absence from mynative vil- lage. The question was so sudden and unexpected and I was so illy prepared, to give such an answer, as I knew would please my good Aunt, that instead of replying to her question, I felt a deep shade come over me, and unconsciously heaved a sigh. My Aunt not only posses - sed the kindest of feelings, but was a woman of keen penetrations; a nd as she fixed her dark hazel eye up n me, it seemed that I should wit h- er beneath her gaze, that she could read the inmost recesses of my heart, and knew all those conflicting powers of darkness ihat were at work there, not only to destroy my peace of mind, but to weaken my faith in religion.  "You know," I said recovering, "all is not right," that some thing bears heavily on my mind; and if you will goqwith me, in imagination, to the pleasant country village of E., and enter a neat little cottage, shaded by tree;, on the banks of a small yet beautiful river, that winds romanticly by it; I will impress as forcibly as I can, on your mind, the cause of the deep sorrow, that has taken possession ofmy heart. We will walk into the parlor, where a cheap woolen carpet covered the floor, some half dozen cane bottomed chairs face *each other by the windows, a short distance from the middle of the room, is an easy rooking chair, well cushioned, and having a neat look- ing tidy suspended across its back. At one end of'the room, stands a birch bureau, containing muslins, linens and a variety of articles for sunday wear; opposite from that, and on the front side of the room,. between the two front windows, is a centre table covered with books; over which hangs suspended a'mirror that reflects at- a single glance, every piece of furniture I have described to you. By these windows we will seat ourselves, because it is in full,view of those objects, most pleasing to the eye, and the best calculated-to call forth those greatful emotions of mind, which so often lie dormant and hid. We will raise, that window a little, that is partly shaded by trees, near the door at the entrance of the room and throw back the blinds that we may better en- joy the singring of birds on the broad spreading branches of those trees, and be refreshed by the gentle breeze, that comes laden with the most  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC7995-00000003"/> 4 delicious odors, being sented not only by the roses near the windows; but by the wild flowers of' a neighboring: woodi This is a retired part, of the village, and we hear but little beside the singing of birds, except' the clatter of carriages over the bridge, too and from the mills on the opposite bank of the river, and'the constant rushing of water, as it falls perpandicularly over the Ajam; at the foot of a gently rising hill and emptys itself into its bed of waters below. There it forms a foamy substance, winds; round a steep bank, and glides swiftly away. I have watched the bright and lucid appearance of that beautiful water fall, all glittering in the; rays of the sun, until I have become so enraptured with the scene, that I have forgotten for the time being, that sin and sorrow are our constant attendants, here, that foul deception often lurks behind the fairest enterior, and have %made myself believe that love flows as freely from the heart as ftom the lips. But these visions only come to go again and leave my mind in a mare desponding state than ever, when the sad reality would force itself upon my- mind, all are not good wlio seem to be, it is not all gold that shines. -But to return to my stoQry. Tis cottage where I have taken you, is, occupied by- the Fairdea lerse Some sixteen years ago; Mr. Fairdealer was united' im marriage to, cousinr Frank, (an old schoolmate of 'mine,) and" since that time, I havebeen; a frequent visitor in the fanrily.. At the age of four- teen,. Mrs. F irddealer gave good' evidence of having passed from nature1 to grace. She then united with the Congregational Church in her awn' native town, and being artless and confiding, she regarded her minister with something nearly allied to a Godlike reverence, and loved the members of he church, with an affection that was unbounded, and by the impulse of strong religious feeling manifested much zeal in the cause in which she was engaged. But a long succession of trials in the church&amp;hve not only weakened her faith in Christians, but paralized her efforts for, usefulness, and destroyed much of the vitality of her re- ligion. This may be seen in the expression of deep anxiety that rests Qu her countenance, and in those traces of sorrow, that are marked in her features. She is now in the kitchen attending to her domestic af-, faiira, for she has no servants, and is obliged to do her work alone, withll the exception of what is done by Rose, (her oldest daughter, a girl' of ' some ffteen summers} and that is but little, since she continually finds something to do for-herself. Yet she may now be seen in the sitting- room putting away playthings, that two roguish little children have strewn about the room. One whose name is Willie, is a black-eyed little boy of'seven; the, other whose name is Ida, is a curley headed little girl offive. While Rose imagines she has a very hard time, and thinks if' her little sister who was three years younger than herself had lived, she wotld not have had such work to do, she threatens to box the childrens ears, if they turn things upside again, then bommences to wash their faces. She will put a clean tire on to Willie, and dress Ida in her new calico frock; then after changing her own dress, she will make her appearance, accompanied by those children. Mrs. Fairdealer will also come into the room when every thing else of importance is attend- ed to, dressed in neat lawn;: with a plain collar on her neck, pinned Fith a smll Una benmig breastpn, containing a lock of hair once   worn by a sister of hers who has long since slept in her grave. We will ask Rose and her little brother and sister to sing, for it will not only entertain us but encourage them, and please their mother, I know of no better way to lessen my own sorrow, than to seek to, lessen that ofthose around me; it has been said that the happiness we impart to others will flow back to ourselves in a tenfold. proportion. Mrs. 1F. and also her husband are generous and social in their manners; if we stop to tea, the table will be loaded with a variety of food, that will not fail to please the most observing eye, and gratify the taste -of the most delicate appetite. Those mills you see on the opposite bank of the river, just this side the one with the sign, of manufacturing, carding,. anl cloth dressing ; are a grist and saw mill, and, are owned: by Mr. Fairdealer. If you look a few moments, you will see him come out from the door of his mill,. and take a heavy grist from, that carriage standing there, and walk back with as much ease as though its weight was nothiing. You will not think strange of this, when I tell you that he is some six feet high, and has a muscular frame. He has well pro- portioned features his complexion is sandy, and the air of independence which he ever carries with him, gives him. quite a commanding appear- ance. . Mr. Fairdealer is not a professing Christian, nor is he a believer in revealed religion; yet he is honest and; upright in his dealings, and has the reputation both. far and near, of being the honest miller. He is cool and calculating in his temperament, thinks twice before he speaks, and seldom says that for which he afterwards has cause to re- pent. He has no sympathy with the wonderful, or marvelous, and re- ceives nothing for truth, that is out of the common course of reasons unless he knows from his own observation that it is such. A little more than a year ago, when I came to reside for a short time in this fmily, there was trouble in the Orthodox Church; Deacon Treatcher- ous by his repeated acts of dishonesty, had so injured Mr. . Fairdealer,  that his wife who was member of the same church, for that reason stay- ed away from the communion. I had been in the house but a short time, before I preceived that something either real or imaginary, was troubling her. She knew from the enquiring look I gave, her, that I was desirous of knowing what was then revolving in her mimd; and without hesitation, said in a sad and suppressed tone of voi e, I was just now thinking what my feelings were at our last communion; then poured into my ears, the story of her trials, to whicht I listened in mute astonishment. "But you have not told me," I said, "what your feelings were at your last communion. ' "We were seated, she said," with that degree of solemnity in her tone and manner, that-made mee feel that. I' realy was in the presence of a higher power, "to pArtake of -those emblems prepared for us in the remembrance of Christ, when I accidentally caught the eye of this deacon, whose character Ii have described to you, not knowing before that he was there. Afi he rolled his -fierce -blackl eyes, out from benea-th long bushy eye brows, I could think of nothing - but Judus; the blood ran cold throughmy veins, and notharbly knowing what I was about, I left the house.: On reaching home, my husband onet me- at the door and pereeivitg my gittion, enquired ,what it W  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC7995-00000004"/> 6 that troubled me. But when I :had explained it all to him, he only' laughed at me, for having any thing at all to do with the church, tried, to persuade me to believe that there was no reality in religion, that it was an outside show, practised by the artful and designing, to deceive'- good and honest people. He verily believed what he said, for by a; very mysterious providence, he had been constantly annoyed by hypo- critical professors: It has so seldom been his lot to- deal with a genu,- ine Christian, that when ever he comes across such an ones he lays it all to their natural disposition, and says they were born so. But it -will take more than he can say," she continued, "or any thing  I have' ssen yet, to induce, me to balieve that there is no such thing as a chang0 of heart; yet I must say with sorrow too that I have lost much faith- in professing christians, and I am scared when I think how little confi.- dence I have in others, until by their repeated acts of patient self de.. nial and disinterested benevolence, they prove themselves to be indeed and in truth 'the followers of Christ. Ever since I left the4 comrn murion so abruptly, I have made it a subject of prayer to know if I was in the way of my duty, and notwithstanding I find much in my heart that is wrong, that God requires much at my hands he does not  receive, I amn firm in the conviction that he does not require that of o me. .True, Christ communed with Judas, bu-t it was before and not af- ter he betrayed him, and it is nowhere recorded in the New Testament that Christ ever communed- with a person, whlo had proved to the world' that they were vile." When she had spoken thus eloquently in defence of herself, she ceas. ed speaking and for a few moments remained silent. During this time I made up my mind that whatever a person under an enlightened conscience believes to be right, having asked direction of God, for them, it is right, however wrong it may be for those who think otherwise.-' While Mrs. Fairdealer was relating these trials to me, Rose, who was, sitting in the farther corner of the room, drew her chair nearer to us,. and remained in profound silence. Willie and Ida, who were playing hide and seek, stopped all and stood before us as eager to hear, as though a fairy story was being told them. And yet it had been re-- peated in their hearing, a dozen times before. (I am afraid," I said to Frank, taking her into another room, "that you do your children great injury, talking these things before them; they will soon enough learn to distrust others,- they will soon enough learn the frailty of' human-nature without hearing it from a mother's lips.. Let them be artless and confiding while they can. Too much knowledge of human nature before the judgment is matured, is apt to have a bad effect on, the mind, and learn one to think lightly of religion." Before Mrs.. Pairdealer had time to remind me, that I was a little faulty in that re-. speot, as well as herself as it was in their presence I desired the revela. tionof her trials: Rose entered the room all animated with the idea of.' leaving the Congregationalist meeting, and going with me to the Metho- diits "H wanted to go last year," she said, 'but mother would not let me because I should have to go alone, but now you have come I shall have some one to go with, and shall I not go ;" she said turning around' and addressing hermotiler who affected. a little surprise,.that she should   7 think of such a thing as leaving her Sabbath school class, and going. a mile to meeting, when it was but a few steps she had always been.-- But rose was importunate in her intresties, and it was evident after all that Mrs Fairdealer cared but little, whether Rose went to her own meeting, or left and went with' me to the Methodist; though she gave, no decided answer. "I hope next Sabbath won't be be a rainy day," said Rose to me, just as her mother left the room to prepare tea for the family. "But- there is one thing sure, if the weather will not permit me to go there to meeting, I shall remain at home." I replied to her that I hoped it would, be pleasant, for it had been some months since I had had the privilagoc of attending a meeting of my own persuasion, and it would be a luxury. for me, to be once more within: the walls of a AMethodist Church; not that I considered the Methodist any better christians than other del- nominations, but the manner in which they conducted their meetings was more congenial with my taste, and the doctrines they inculcated accord- ing to my idea were more in accordance with the teadhings of'the 'word, of God. At length the week passed away and the next Sabbath's sun, shone gloriously upon us. It then was in the early month of May, the. trees were putting forth their leaves, and the grass was beginning to look green. i We had had a cold and dreary winter, for months the snow had- lain in heaps about our dwellings; the fro3t had often covered our crystal panes, and shielded the sun from our view. Under such circum- stances as these the signs of returning life and beauty to the vegetable world not only gladdened my eyes, but inspired me with new desires, that this heart of mine so cold and destitute by nature; of all that is truely beautiful, might through the warming influences of the rays of' the sun of rightousness; be prepared to produce in rich abundance, the fruits of true religion which not only gives beauty to the soul, but peace and tranquility to the mind. I will ask God, I thought to myself, to, enable me to lay aside all worldly care and anxiety; and spend this day in a manner that shall be pleasing in his, sight. Trusting in Jesus who is able to save to the utmost all who come unto him. Just as these de- sires had formed themselves into a resolution, the clock told- the hour of ten. R-ose had been standing some ten or fifteen minutes before a largo mirror putting on her bonnet and shawl and puffing her rich auburn hair first this way and then that, in order to see which way would look the most becoming. All this time I had been standing with parasol in one hand, and holding the latch of the door with the other, expecting: every moment Rose would- be ready to start. "We shall be late to meeting," I said just as the last. hour was sound' ing in my ear. "I can't help it," said Rose, earnestly, 4"I must be fixed to suit me if we are." "I will start ahead then," I said;, and closed-the dbor behind me. Saying 'at the same time, I shall walk slowly and 7ou can over- take'me. As I opened the gate and passed'into the street, the birds sang most sweetly, the air breathed her richest, perfume, and the whole: canopy over my head, was exceedingly beautiful. I stood for a few moments, not knowing which most to admire, the golden rays of tha aun, the silvery fleeces that were suspended in the heavens, or the clear  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC7995-00000005"/> xzure of the sky. These things produced emotions so' pleasing in' myk mind, that I tried to imagine how beautiful heaven must be, and so lost. myself in thought, that I knew nothing of what was passing around me,. until I was ascending the declivity of a hill, a short distance from where I was going to church. Then the loud pealing tones of the deep sound- ing bell, in the steeple of the Congregationalist Church brought me to my senses. On looking behind me, the village through which I had passed seemed nestling in a beautiful valley among the hills. And peo-. ple from all directions were flocking to the house of God. My com- panion Was a short distance from me, evidently hurrying to overtake me and, wandering why I was walking so fast. I did not tell her, that be- ing inspired with the hope of reaching so beautiful a place as heaven,. had accelerated my walk, and I had forgotten her, but-that to go late to meeting would not only attract attention, but setting a bad example. Soon we reached a low wood house, painted white, and having neither belfry nor steeple; yet by the horses and carriages that were hitched on the opposite side of the road, and people gathered about the door, we know it to be the Methodist meeting house, since no other denomina- tion held a meeting in that part of the town. We entered with due reverence, and seated ourselves in a pew in the body of the house.- Soon those that were about the door and others with them came in and seated themselves in their accustomed places. Yet the congregation was small and scattering; scarce a familiar face met my eye. Still I felt that I was in my Father's family, and believed God to be. present with uq., Just then another stranger entered walked slowly up the aisle, and seated himself in the pulpit. His dark glossy hair hung in waves about his high and intelleetual forehead, and curled over at the ends. His dress was the latest fashion, and finest materials. His linen bosom which was white as snoW, had evidently felt the weight of the polishing iron. A white linen handkerchief embroidered at the corners, was tied in a square knot about his neck, exposing the,- embroidery to view.' His manners were graceful and pleasing, there was something: noble in his bearing, and his countinence was clothed in smiles. Yet there was a hidden meaning in the expression, of his dark hazle eye, which I had not the ability to unravel. I have no recollections where he took his text, for my mind was so. fully occupied with the man, that I forgot to notice when he gave it out. But his ideas and manners of delivering them, were both deep and original, and his -voiee swelled witlh, rich melody. All listened in the profoundest silence, and felt that their intellects if not their hearts were feasted. At noon the brethren collect. ed in groups about the doors, the, sisters around the corners of pews, by the windows, and in the entry, all talking of one and the same thing; the wonderful -talents of their minister. Members of other churches,. and those who made no pretentious -to religion, were equally loud in their praises. "Can you tell me the name of the minister who preached to us to day," I said to a good sister, who pereetving that I was a new commer, made, it in her ray to speak to me, and .make my acquaintance. "His: nameis Fops-worth," she said, he is an English gentleman who, ^aoe from Roaglan4 a few years ago, and preached. awhile in Canada,   but has recently come to the States to go through a course of studies ir C. Then he is a student I said. Yes we are not able to support a conference minister, and are obliged to put up with one who has little experience, and'little or no time to study his sermons, or visit the peo- ple. But we are wonderfully favored in the one we have this year, for his wonderful talents far exceeds our most sanguine expectations. Justas she was repeating the last sentence Br lF6psworth who had been shak- ing hands with all he could find, from the grey headed old man down. to the merest child, stood by her side, unexpected by her, and heard what she 'aid. His eyes danced with delight, and his countenance wore a blander smile than before, and he gave us each a hearty shake of the hand, saying at the same time. I intend to form a bible class next Sabbath and hope to see you and all the rest of thesg ladies in it." By the happy glances that were ex- changed from ooae-o the other as he made this remark, Br. Fopstorth felt confident -in the expectation that his class would be a flourishing one, and that he should not fail to interest them. When we returned from meeting in the afternoon, Rose without stopping to lay off her bonnet and shawl, or even to take breath, rushed into the' sitting-room, where her father sat reading the latest news, while her mother wtas amusing the children with the pictures, in the Sabbath school booaby they had that day received from the hand of their teacher, and related all H- have said to you about Br. Fopsworth, adding that she herself was per- fectly delighted with him. 4"Is he so wonderful a man?" said Mrs. Fairdealer, addressing me, and thinking Rose from the impulse of a strong imagination, had ex- agerated somewhat in speaking of him. I spoke in the highest terms of him, and said I was very much surprised to hear so smart a sermQn it! 4 place where the salary was so small. Mr. Fairdealer had been hoern, ing all that was said, and laughed 'ot of both corners of his mouth agd smiled a credulous smile. I caught the expression of Mrs. Fairdealer's[ countenance, and read there that she had some lurking fears within, that, he might not prove so wonderful in the end, But Willie and Ida, were, all on tip. toe, tQ go and hear him preach, 'and world not be pacified un-. til their mother had promised them that they should go. with us on the 'following Sabbath, if it should prove a pleasant day. At length after some consideration, Ars. Fairdpale, said anxiously, 'I wish I was able to walk that distance, I would go. occasionally to that meeting, rather than to go to my own, where. there is such a lack of disipline in the ehurch. 'Although I am wiiling they should drop my- name, if they chose to do so, I shall never leave my own society to join that of another, for Congregationalismr was installed into my wind when I was a child, and has grown with my growth and strengthened with my strength. It is only the unhappy circumstances in which I am pleaed, that gives me those desires to attend the Methodist meeting, al'ough I consider that they can be equally as good Christians in one. church as the other." Some months after this, during a, time of additional grievances in the. Orthodox society, Mrs. Pairdealer said to me, :.'it is pleasant this morn% ug, and 1 think I wil go to your meeting. I ahoqld like to hear that  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC7995-00000006"/> man for myself, I have heard so much about him. Rose can take the children," she said, "and go to this meeting, I expect there will be a time about it, but I cannot have them leave their Sabbath school any more. I am sorry they have taken it into their heads to go to the Methodist; I do not see the meaning of it." I replied that "Br. Pops-. worth took a great deal of notice of children, and they thought a greatr deal of shaking hands with him." But with less trouble than we had, anticipated, the children did as we wished them to do, and .irs. Pair-. dealer had the satisfaction of hearing Br. PiJopsworth preach, and also of attending his i"Bible class," which was that day uncommonly interest-. ing, as also was his sermon. Bat for' the sake of argument on one question I did not agree with Br. Fopsworth. I told him I could not see why it was not tar more easy-for Christ to suffer, who I believed knew all things, and was equal with the Father, than for a poor short sighted human being, who seldom if ever knows why God afflicts him. To know why we suffer and to see the good that is to result from one's sufferings, it seems to me would be to turn our misery into joy. In. asmuch he said as Christ was capable of enjoying infinitely more than man, he was also capable of infinitely more suffering, and when the sins of a whole world were crowded upon him, our sufferings were but as a. drop in the bucket compared with his. At the close of the Sabbath school, he came along to the pew where I was sitting, shook hands with. me. and also with Mrs. Fairdealer, saying that he would like to stop. the followingt Saturday night at her house. Mrs. Fairdealer who had previously invited him to come any time when he could make it con- plaioeqt on the occasion of his making a pastoral call at her house, was delighted with the idea, and expressed the great satisfaction it would; give her, to receive a visit from him. Then turning to me he said. '-We shall have the opportunity of discussing that difficult question more fully, and that is the reason I select the following Saturday night, to stop at the house of your cousin." That,day after-the services of the Sabbath school at noon, it was whispered around in the Congregationalist meeting: house that Mrs. Fairdealer had gore to h ear Mr. Fopsworth ; and some fears were enter-% tained, that she might leave her own meeting entirely, and find a homeo withl the Methodist. "'How do you know that she has gone there?" said one. "She is not in the habit of going away from  her own meetig;, not evenl for a Sabbath." 1 She was sen  going in that direction with that cousin of hers,. wii) is stopping with her."  "Well" said the other, "things are in a. bad state in our society; we do. not prosper; we have no conversions, and their is but little love. manifested for each other am on the, mem- bers of the church,." aThere is a,n enemy in the camp." said one who had been listening to thRe conversation, "and who .onders we don't prosper." During this time the greatest attention was paid to Vgrs.. Fitrirdealer, byt he Methodist, for it was, known by all who knew her, that she was disaffected with one of the Deacons in her own society, and a secret hope was indilged by all interesteA in that church, that aie would- continue   to grace that meeting with her presence, and also contribute something towards the support of their minister. Not only was-that society weak and a little help duly appreciated, but a secret jealousy had crept into fhe societies that each thought themselves superior to the other. The Congregationalist believed the Methodist to be spiritually proud, while the Methodist believed the Congregationalist to be temporally so- Members had gone from one society to the other, and it was believed by each that those who had left their society, had been influenced by mem- bers of the other. Thus they lost much of their interest for each other's prosperity, and sought more exclusively theni own. That night at the supper table, Mrs. Fairdealer made known to her husband Mr. Fopsworth's intended visit, and said she hoped he would avoid appearing reserved or distant towards him, and by being social, would make him- feel himself at home. 'If he comes into my house and behaves himself, I shall treat him well," said Mr. Fairdealer coldly, "and give him a few dollars." At the same time helping himself to a large slice of beef steak, that had been nicely served and placed in an earthen platter near the centre of the table, then spoke after the following ironical manner. "I shall prosper you say if I give to the ministers, and you know how .well I have prospered giving to your Congregationalist ministers. You know how well I have been treated by the beautiful members, they have in their church,. and I am going to give to the Methodist ministers now, I do so love to prosper." In years past Mr. Fairdealer had given to the Congregationalist society, for no other reason than to gratify his wife. He did not give a. great deal, for he was owing for his mills, and wished to pay the in- terest, and a certain amount of the principal, every year, that the debt need not accumulate upon his hands, but gradually wear away, and in order to do this, it was necessary to practice econemy in spending his money. His wife had not unfrequently told him, if' he gave. to the minister, he would be none the poorer for it, but would prosper all the better. Thus when he met with losses and all through the instrumen- tality of members in the church, he took great sasisfaction in remind- ing her of it, whenever a favorable opportunity presented itself, in order to prove to her the fallacy of her doctrine, till at last she had no longer any confidence -to ask him to give to her minister. About this time the Methodist society were struggling hard for an existence, and Mr. Fairdealer knowing the secret jealousy that was ex- isting between them and the Congregationalist, contributed his mite for the Methodist. Mrs. Fairdealer felt so keenly the irony of her hus- band's remarks, that she said nothing, but finished her supper in silence. But being persuaded in my own mind, that no one who bore the name of Methodist, would treat him any other way than well, I could not endure the thought that he should think, thus meanly of them, and was not slow to say. "I guess you will lose nothing for what you do -for, the Methodist, for they will receive it gratefully, and respect you for your generosity." Mr. Fairdealer stopped eating, looked into my face and smiled so contemptuously, that to suppress, the indignation that was riing in. my breast, I bit my lips, and said not an other word. But.  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC7995-00000007"/> Bose, before she had finished eating her pie, said sorrowfully. "Thanks. giving day comes this week and I wish Br. Fopsworth was going to be here then for we shall have every thing that is good to 'eat." Her mother was then placing the fragments in a manner that would make them look as invitingly as possible and take up the least room in the pantry, but stopped all, as these words dropped from the lips of her daughter, o contrive what she should get to gratify his taste. "The English live differently from what we do," she said thoughtfully "and I: do not know- what he will like, but I must save my largest stuffed turkey, and plum pudding." Here she stopped short, but would have gone on naming a variety of good things, that would have made one's mouth water, had she not just then recollected, that it was Sunday, and such thoughts as these should be banished from her mind. Then lifting a silent prayer to heaven for grace to spend the Sabbath as she ought, she again resumed her labor of clearing the table, and putting the dishes into the sink, for Rose to wash, preparatory to reading a very interest- ing book- she had taken from the library. Mr. Fairdealer had been listeniang to hear what Rose and her mother had to say, and knowing full well that it would be a source of unending mortification to his wife if she failed in the least degree of having things to her mind, and also being aware that little else would be thought of, or cared for, during the week, except to have every thing in order, when' he should come, declared he would not mind having ministers come to his house, if there was any such thing as getting or doing any thing nice enough for them; but so 'much word attention must be paid to ministers, than any other class of people, however worthy they might be, he dreaded to have one in his presence.. It is pretended by their followers, he continued that they are such holy men, that the things of this world are under their feet, that their minds are not on earthly but on heavenly things. But woDe would think it was the reverse of all this, by the care and anxiety that is:manifested, to more than gratify all their temporal desires. Mrs. Pairdealer feeling that 3he was half in the wrong,.maaifested no disposition to defend herself. But being convinced that she was more in the right,than her husband imagined, I could not refrain from saying that ministers were public property, ;that they were interested not only i- the spiritual b6t temporal welfare of all, and it was the duty of all, to seek every opportunity to make them happy. That too much care add anxiety vas manifested about such things by many, I did not pre- tend to:deny, for baving done to the extent of our ability to gratify a person, we should be satisfied, feeling that is all that is required of us, nd 'give :ourselves no trouble, because providentially things are not to our mind. We should believe that a true servant of God, will hold all temporal things as secondary blessings having their minds fixed on that which is of infinitely more importance. A preparation of heart to cn- joy the thappy state of the, blest in heavens, with a disposition to induce others to ,seek, that happy state faor themselves. If we believe others to Vb itterested in our welfare it' is not so necessary that they. should be a-minister it:order thaj we may love them, .and seekl to do them good} unless we ae have sunk fir f bow ourselves, and degraded our human nature. But we know by sad ,expiente, that the world taken as a whole   is selfish, while we believe better things of ministers, who sacrifice Mnuch earthly good, to preach Christ and him crucified to a sinful world for much less compensation, than is afforded persons of their abilities in other occupations of life. ,I1 wish I could convince you," said Mr. Fairdealer candidly, "that ministers are not only the most selfish but the most proud and self-con- ceited people in the world, and in my opinion the Br. Fopsworth you think so highly of has-committed some crime in his own country, which Ivas induced him to flee to this, not only to avoid suffering the penalties of the law, but the shame and disgrace that would be'heaped upon him there. And here he calls himself a minister, to gain the confidence and respect of the people." ",Quite likely he fetched a letter of recommendation with him," I said confidently. "What if he did," said Mr. Fairdealer abruptly, -4that could easily have been forged by him or some accomplice in crime." I knew Mr. Fail dealer to be a man of good judgment, still I did not consider it valid, when exercised upon ministers, for I knew that be hated them, not because he considered them to be good, for if he had he would have respected them, but because he believed the love which they professed for God and man, was exercised only for self. Being aw;are that I was multiplying words for nothing, I said no more and nothing more was Raid by any one, excepiing what was said by Willie and Ida, who kept a continual chattering between'themselves, imragining the time would seem very long before Br. Fopsworth should come, and dividing it off into periods, in order that it might appear as short as possible. The next Fridaynight after much care and toil, preparing not only for thanksgiving but for the minister, Mrs. I Fairdealer said to Bose. We must rise earlier to-morrow morning than usual, for may be Mr. Fopsworth will come in the afternoon; and if he does. I should like to have the work out of the way in order that we may the better entertain him." Then addressing me she said, '(your work is not so driving but that you can entertain him, if we are too busy, is it 2"    vt  I readily assured her that it was not, and that I would also be in ! readiness to assist in any domestic affairs should my services be neeIded. Accordingly early in the afternoon of the next day, I dressed mnyself in prim, and seated me in the easy rocking chair in the parlor, with no other occupation than my book, waiting the arrival of Br. Fopsworth.- I had rendered such assistance to Rose and her mother as was needed and they were -nearly in readiness to receive him themselves. That af- ternoon wore away and Br. Fopsworth did not come. The sum sank behind-the western hills and the hours of grey twilight stole- gradually upon us. That hour so favorable for "calm and holy mussings, when those who are weary from ihe labor- and care of the day, can call' in their wanderingthoughts and enjoy the tranquility of the hour. Br. Fopsworth will be here soon I then thought, and explain more fully the suffernog of christ, as he promised me he would, in the Bible cltrss. I must bring all those arguments against it of which I can imagine a skeptic to think, while he shall readily' confute them all, 'and- make it, appear all plain to my mind, how deep was 'the agny which Christ 2 -    e  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC7995-00000008"/> " endured for sinners. Just as my mind was wrought up to the highest pitch of imagination, a loud rap was heard at the door, I rose and hastily opened it, Br, Fopsworth stood before me. In consequence of walking fAst, in order to reach here before the shades of evening shoutld overtake him, a sligh't flush tinged his cheeks, and his complection seem. ed unusually fair. You are good as you are beautiful I thought as he took off his hat and bowed gracefully in my presence. He walked in threw off his overcoat and appeared to be very much at home. "This is a superior article," I said, as I rubbed one corner of the coat he had taken off between by thumb and finger, to ascertain the fineness of the quality ; then folded it nicely and laid it on the bureau. "It is is indeed a superior article," he said, "and was presented to me by the ladies of my society, and I believe that you and your cousin are among the members who presented it to me." I told him "I believed we threw in our mite, for we both esteemed it a privilege to give to the minister who preaches for us." "Then will you be so kind as to give me some blacking: to black my boots," he said, dooking mischievously at me, then down at his feet.)- "They were-not blacked the Saturday before," he said viewing them 'more critical'y, and they troubled me exceedingly in meeting. "It is a pity"I said joking, "that the Sabbath should be passed unpleasantly, just for the want of a little blackiing." - Thcugh his boots would have looked very respectable fobr the generality of people, they were not altogether beconming for one so genteelly dressed as Br. Fop- worth, and a little polish would evidently add to their beauty. Just' as I was going for the blacking Mrs. Fairdealer came in, and inquired if he had been to tea. On being told that he had, she immediately lighted the kerosene lamp and placed it on the centre of the table taking care that the bible should be disencumbered from the rest of the books. and placed where he could readily lay his hands upon it. I had hard- ly prepared the blacking before Br Fopsworth commenceed singing with -so deep and melodious a voice, "That better land," that. one would al- most imagine the never fading glories of that heavenly world were about to unfold to our view, and its rich strains of music were 'being wafted through the air to fall enchantingly on the ear. I hastened with all possible speed, to the place from whence the music proceeded, and Br. Fopsworth was holding Willie on one knee, and Ida on the other, wl o were evidently in an extacy of delight. Rose sat by the window all enraptured, and Mrs. Fairdealer herself thinking the music was heaven- ly, rose and opened the door that it might be heard the more readily by her husband, who had seated himself in a farther room, in order to be as far from the minister as possible. And notwithstanding he prided himself so much on being cool and calculating, he so far forgot himself ,'as to lay aside some very interesting political news and listen with evi- dent satisfaction until the piece was finished. While Br. Fopsworth was in the kitchen blacking his boots Mrs. Fairdealer said to me. 4"How sorry I am that his health does not permit him to hold prayer meetings, Mr. Freeman would willingly let him have his hall, and what a goodly number would be attracted there to hear him sing." I told her that I missed the class-meetings more than any thing else,   15 and I wa; very srry tihe members were so scatter!ng that we -couid not meet once a week, and have Br. Fopsworth for our leader, for I think he would be present to class I said if his health is poor. "They (an have their class meetings here," said Mrs. Fairdealer quickly, rather in hords thfey would. "They can have them in the sit- ting room Mr. Fairdealer won't care if they come in at, this door and don't disturb him, in the other part of the house." ,*Was you. talking about class-meetings?" said Br. Fopsworth as he entered with his shining boots, and seated himself in the rocking chair. When Mrso Fairdealer said they can have their class meetings here, she was so much in earnest as to elevate her voice so,high as to be heard by Br. Fopsworth in the kitchen, one door being left part way open, and an other unlatched, and he hastened to tell her that he was intending to- have class-meetings Sabbath noons in place of the bible class, when the traveling should become so bad that children could not get out to Sab-' bath school. I was not a little delighted to hear that we were going to have class-m'eetings, yet I was sorry that they were not-to be on week day evenings, for I had so long been accustomed to attending evening class-meetings that the change would seem unpleasant. As conversation seemed to wane, Br. Fopsworth related some of the most wonderful events of his life., the singular manner in which he had !become acquainted with intelligent women. Some the mrost interesting part of his courtship, and told how delighted he should be to see his wife and infant boy, that were then in Canada. Are you not goin, to fetch them on here," I said, "that we may have the privilege of seeing them." He replied ,"that they were coming soon to visit among the people and he should be happy to introduce her to me." Just then we were admonished by the clock that it was getting late, much later than we were aware, and after having our evening devotions, Mrs. Fairdealer conducted Br. Fopsworth to his room. It was a large square chamber well ventilated, having four large glass windows, they had heavy blinds and -were well curtained, with fine bleached curtains, that reached from the top to the bottom of the windows. A toilet containing brushes, combs, &amp;c., stood beneath a mirror that was situated   between the two windows faceing the road, that ran along by theriver. A wash stand was in Ote room with wash bowl, and pitcher filled all most to overflowing with pure cold water. A fine linen towel was laid across the stand, anwl another beside it, of coarser material. One solitary chai- stood by a bed of live geese feathers so neatly dressed that one could! not detect a wrinkle on the fine linen sheets with broad hems, and pil, low cases hanging nearly to the floor. The covering was free frorn spots, and white as show. "I hope you will rest well to night," said Mrs. Fairdealer, placing the light on the stand, then turning to leave the room. "If you wihb for m re air you can raise some of these windows or open the door." He, thanked her, appeared delighted and expressed a wish that his dear wife could he there to share the benefits of her kindness, and en- joy with him that comfortable lodging. "I am sorry we have no hair oil for Br. Fopsworth," I said somewhat troubled, to Mrs. Fairdealer, meeting her in the: sitting-rooni and know-  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC7995-00000009"/> 16 ing she heard him enquire for some just after prayers. "'An  I recole lect too," I said, "that the tea-bell is among the nlissing, and I don't know Ltow we shall get him up in the mo-ning. tie wishes to be called a half hour before breakfast and I don't think it will appear well to rap oni his door."  Willie can go and call him." she said, then looking surprisedl at me said, "I thoulght you did not believe in troubling aboutC things over which you have no control." . While Mrs. Fairdealer was thus reproa ching me, I heard Mr. Fair- dealer laughing in ,the opposite room, and as a guilty c nscience n: edls no. accuser-, I believed him to be laughing at me, and on goinog into his presence was convinced that it was so, for he still laughed and mocking- ly said to me "how shall we get him up in the morning." Rose seeing the fun goinzron and wishing to join in the spert said, she know he wanted the hair oil very much, for he asked fobr it before he rose from his knees. He had arisen I sa;d, though he might not, have sat down in his chair, wishing to have it told correctly, and feeling sorry that I was the cause or this foolish jesting, and 'also that I had given myself so much unnecessary trouble. The next morningo after Slaving swept, dusted and bur breakfast well under way, Mrs. Fairdealer said enquiringly, "you and Br. Fopsworth did not discuss that subject last evening that you was speaking about."  "No," I said, "he must have forgotten it, he has s) much in his brain that he can't think of it all at once " "Whly  did not you introduce the subject yourself," she said, thinking she would have been interested in he i-ng him explain upon it. I repliel that I did not feel at liberty to do so. Besides I was veryr highly gratified in listening to the stories he told about himself.  ,I think he must have been a forward youth to preach when he was but eleven,years old," I said. ;"He certainly must have had a natural talent for preaching,"  Irs. Fairdealer made no reply, for just then the water boiled over in the tea- kettle. and it was necessary that she should hurry to take it from  the fire, but I knew from the expression of her countenance that she thought she would like to have seen the congregation that sat under his preach- ing. The water having boiled it was necessary th it the coffee should be put steeping and a variety of other things were thought of that needed attention, so we called Rose who had been long enouugh primping at the glass, to help us.                r "You must wash these children," said Mrs. Fairdealer to her, and I went to work setting the table. After spreading a white cloth over it, I fetched the best dihes out of the cupboard and put them on, while Mrs. Fairdealer basted the turkey that was warming in the oven, and talcing care that the large mealy potatoes that we, e baking there, need not be scorched.. When breakfast was nearly ready, I asked Mrs. Fairdealerf if she had not better dispense with one kind of pie, either custard or mince, for the table was so crowded with food that I could not make it look to suit me, and reminded her that fashionable people did not think of such a thing as having pie in- the mornin - She replied that she oared nothing about the fashion, her only desire.   f7 was to have something that Br. Fopsworth could relish. But you may Bakee. off the paddi  if you have a mind to do so; perhaps he may re- turn to-night, and if he does, I shall need it more then, then I do now, I suppose he will not thirk of corning here to-dinner, it is se far. No, I told her he has a regal r dining p-la e near the meeting house, and it would be of no use to ask him. Tihatt mornin Mr. iFairdealer made his apipearance at the breakfast table, but it was not until the blessing had been askedl and we were half done eating. He did not have to be, in- trolduced to 13r. Fop)sworth, for he had mnet him accidentally the night- bethre when lhis wife was conducting'him to his room, and received an, introdluction to him ;' so all he had to do, wits, to say good morning to Br, Fopswolrth, who looking roguiishy into his face, said now you in- tijilFe I to stay awLay V i, I w h1ad finished our breakfast to avoid seeing nme, bat yeo1 rmi.;s:.t of it. ' Tlerr w-as s i) lmch truth in these remarks that iMr.. PFirdealer coul(di not refrain from laughing,- and was so social, }all the time we were eatin, that I flattered myselfTie took quite a like- ill to the minister ,Justr bzfore we startel for meeting, I wentto Mr. Fairdealer and as;kqd bhiut if I h a:l aiy mnoney -for BrT. Fo'psworth, he siid no, not a cant, I as'Ced hiln the r -soa, h said he had been sauced by him at the bretkfalst t;lble, and hle did not feel it his duty to give h m any.  Lkfrirtr(ds learnreAthXt 213 handed some to the collect)rP and told himn to) give it to Be. Fopsworth. That m)rning' Trs. Fair- dealer woul i have gone to the 31ctholist instead of Rose. It was a fine mJrning, the air w s col! and invigorating, and she would havb enjoyed th3 walk, but her en rgies were esxiaust;d and she wa. obligel to lay dowl as soon a3 we haL le't the hoase.. When we had gone a short dis- tan e, tose cjmm 3aced wmziki g more sl )wly and beckoned' to me to do taie sam , then whispered s so sftly to me th t Br. Fopsworthl could not shear, and said she thought he was queer for a minister. I asked her reason for thinking so, she said that when she was passing through the fro,.t entry, the door that led into the parlor was standing open, and she heard him sing,  I wish I was married and. nothing to rue.  Withi p eilty of money and nothing to do. I ,told her I supposeI he was absent minded, you know how often I say no when I mean yes, aad yes when I mean no, and how   often I am caught singing, one thing, when I am. thinking of another. Besides we were conv rsing last evening about Maria Mionk and Jane Ray, and - thit is a ditty Jane used to sing in the convent. Rose then threw the mantl. of charity over his apparent in3onsistances, and believed while he was singing those empty lines, deepel and more holy thoughts were the companions of his mind. l By this time Ba-. Fopsworth was cuite a distance ahead of us, and loomd around to see what we were ubout that woe did not keep up with  him, and waited until we reached the spot where he was standing "If you do not walk faster," hs said as we drew near to him, .'( shall have to offer you my arm." I rod him I guessed we should keep up  with him  now, and Rose laughed at the idea of being sleeved to meeting by a minister. dome weeks after these iucidents oc3urrzl news came that Bl. Fops.   &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC7995-00000010"/> worth's wife and child had arrived. "Don't tell Rose,"' sa:d Mrs. Fair  dealer to me, as I communicated thisintelligence to her, "for I -am in- tending to hear him preach to day, but if Rose hears that Mrs. Fops. worth has come she will tease to go herself " When we had started for meeting I told Mrs. Fairdealer that I really believed she,had turned Methodist.         - "No, I have not turned .Methodist," she said firmly, "nor do I con. sider Br. Fopsworth as spiritual as ar. Piety was, the minister who. preached when first I indulged a hope th t my sins were forgiven. Yet I am very much-interested in his sermons and gain new ideas when ever I hear him preach." -We were rather late to meeting that morning, yet I took the liberty to glance across the meeting house anil give one side way glance behind, me, in hope of seeing sister Fopsworth, and my eye rested on a fashiona- bly dressed lady sitting s linme three or four pews back of me holding in her arms an infant, sowme five or six months old. By this time' the chorister had pitchod the tune for singing The congregation rose and turned round to face the singe s, but instead of that t-cy looked froml all directions to the baby, some tu:ned side ways in their pews, while others peaked over their shoulders, and little children were sFen to turn. square round, for not only was it a curiosity to see a baby at fmeeting; but the baby belonged to their minister. At noonall had to have aa introduction to the mother and child, before they would consent %o leave- the house.  Those who remained, gathered round them, group after group, called the child the Prince of' Wales, and other titles of' equal honor. As I stood looking earnestly into its face to sae if I could de. teet any look of its father, Mrs Failrdealer, to direct my .attention to her, hit me with her parasol, then asked me to hand her the child. I took it from the arms of its mother and gave it to her across the pew. The child was very prettily dressed in red spotted delaine, and emhroidl ered flannels. Sister Fopsworth did not look remarkably intellectual,. nor had she any features of remarkable beauty, yet she was rather good ,looking. S he had a pleasant blue eye and wore a smiling countenuance, with an expression of self complacancy, which unite 1 to a self'onfildent air, told plainly that she was perfectly satisfied w th herself and all that belonged tO her. When Mrs. Fairdealer handed the child to iO mother- she invited her very cordially, to come and make her a long visit, and. sister Fopsworth replied very pleasantly that she should be happy to do  so. The next day the news was circulated among the Congregationalist people, that MaIrs. Fairdealer was becoming very fr endly to the AIetho- d&amp;st, for not only had the Methodist minister stopped all night at her house, but she was seen up to his meeting, holding his baby, and she had also given his wife an invitation to visit her. ' About this time I thought of teaelxing a school and not understanding some principles of Algebra,. sufficiently well to teach. it, I took my book and slate under my arm, stepped. into a sleigh and rode down to Br. .Shifting's to board, a few weeks; and be assisted by him in my Algebra, for he was an old school teacher and could teach me in that science, all that it was necessary foxr no to know. Br. Shiftings was a full blooded Methodist, and loved Methodism as he loved, his very existence. Although he was what   might be termed snug, and would be sure to look out for the half cent in,) trade, and see that not a particle of any thing was lost, he was willing to make almost any sacrifice, and pay the highest. tax of any one in or- der to sustain Methodist preaching in the place.. His wife., though a pale sickly looking woman, with frail constitution ani delicate health,. left no stone unturned' and lost no opportunity to guard well the interests of the 'church, and by manifesting'too nmuch care and anxiety was apt to hinder more than to forward the progress of Methodism. They lived. on a farm, some two miles out of the village, and hbad but few neighbors the most of whom lived at a distance. Although it was a beautiful place in summer, and an abundance of flowers and subbery grew in the front yard, it was dreary and dessolate in winter, when wind and snow sported together, and howled piteously around the old farm house.- This farm house had weathered the beating of many a winter's storm, but by being repaired and painted presented quite a new appearance, and was also proof against all the conflicting elements without. Br. Shifring, was usually absent through the day, feliing trees in his wood- lot, or hauling wood some six or eight miles to market, where he could reoeive ready compensation for .it all, and spend- his evenings at home. Daring Br. Shifting's absence, his wife was-left with the company of no one except an only child some three years old, and was therefore happy to receive me as an inmate into their family, "How glad I shall be of your company," she said when I told her of my wish, "for you have no idea how lonely I am here. My husband will also be happy to assist you in Algebra, for mathamatics- is his favorite study, but my health being poor I shall desire you to assist me about my domestic affairs enough ito ballance the work you will make. This was just what I desired, for it would not only be a phisical but mental benefit to me, and I should also have less to. pay for my board. I had been there but a few days, when sister Shifting's entered the sitting room one afternoon where I was seated on a lounge solving a problem in algebra, and enquired if I would be willing to assist her more than usual .the following week, because sister Fopsworthl and child were, expected there to make a visit. I told her I would willingly ac- commodate her, and perhaps it would be best for me not to try to study much that week, for doubtless sister Fopsworth would wish me to, take some care of :her child,. besides I should not appear very social with a book in my hand every moment I had to spare. The next Monday Br. Shifting's made u fire in the parlor instead of making it in the sitting room, for it was more comfortable there, and would warmi tLe room adjoining it where sister Fopsworth and child were going to sleep. The room- was well warmed, and we had justheeni talking about their coming, when we heard the ringing of bells at the door. "4The Fopsworth's have come," I said, and we all rushed to the door to meet them, They drove up to the house, and a fellow student of Br. Fops-- worth's whom they called Br. Shieldings was holding the horse for him - to help his wife and child out of the sleigh. I am glad to see you, we all exclaimed in one voice, and immediately they rushed into the entry I then took the babe for sister Fopsworth, while, she and the rest of the &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC7995-00000011"/> AW company was waited into the parlor by sister Shifting's. Br. 'Fops- worth seemed very much hurried, that morning, for in company with, this fellow student of his, he was going to Some favorite place, to spend the day. So when sister Fopsworth had taken off her bonnet, cloak and victorinu, and I had relieved tWi child of the shawls and blankets that were wraped about it, to keep it warm,  he gave me a faithful charge to take good elre of the baby, then kissing them very affection- ately promised to be back that evening to spend the night, and accom panied by Br. Shielding: left the house, stepped into the sleigh and ware soon out of' sight. In a few momelits the child was asleep in mny arms, sister Shiftinos warmed some pillows, and laid them in te- cradle, there I laid the sleeping infant that looked soilike the pieture of innocence. hilile sister Shiftings was in the kitchen preparing dinner, to Smake conversation with sister Fmpsworth, I enquired of her if she were never homesick here among strangers. "How- can I be homesick where my husband is," she said, in a tone of voice that implied an impossibility and- with an expression of counte- nance that told how nmuch she adored him. "How glad I am," I replied. having grett confidence in his superior- ity "that you are united to one -who is so kind and affectionate and who so possesses-such-brilliant talents.." "I am indeed fortunate," she said seeming to fee; that God had be-- stowed a more liberal share of earth's blessingson her, than le had onl others. Then with a great deal of sympathy .in her tone and, manner, she, said, "you were never married I believe?" ' I told her that I never was, but was contented with my lot, and had no reflections to cast upon lmyself, for I had never received an offer from. gentleman with whom I thought I could live happily, and had no reflections to cast upon providence, for God knew what was best for me. She then gave me such a sublime look as I shall never forget, believing I was not only a-perfect mode of christian resignation, but that all the christian graces were fully developed in ny character-. Thinking by this time that sister Shiftinogs needed my assistance in the kitchen I asked to be excused, and left the room. The afternoon came and passed very pleasantly, the baby was good, anAd sister Fops- worth seemed very happy, congratulating herself that she was so soon to see her husband, but when nine o'clock came; and he made not lJas appearance, her countenance was the picture of anty, and she said in a distressed tone of voiee,ifhe does not come soon, I shall thiik something has befallen him. The minute hand passed round to half- past nine, and she walked the floor in agony, saying what should I do if my husband should die, and leave me in the States, with no friend or relation but my child, thenft threw herselfupon a sofa, (which ' was a part of the furniture of the room, and burst into a flood of tears.. "Don't trouble yourself so much about him," I said, believing. the man was alive and 'elI,' and would return the next morning if not that night to greet her with his presence. 'I shan't sleep a-wink to night,' she said, 'ifhe don't come, for I shall know that he is either sick or dead." "If he is, it will be known, and we shal be isormed of it before   morrning. It does not look reasonable to suppose that he has fifllen- dead corling here, yet it would not be an impossibility"I - said, feelit gi but little sympathy for her. For having never had' any such trouble myself, I was not prepared to see why she should not trust providence for all that is to come, believing that God has a watchful care over us.., and will not leave or forsake us in the hour of trouble, and that was. not all, I was just unfeeling'enough to throw out a, few hints, a little easily, that my happiness taking the time together, Iwas equally as, great as hers, though she was united to the man who was all the world to her, and whom she loved with -untiring devotion. And more yet,. while sister Shiftings was sympathising most deeply with her, telling how' she had often experienced the same anxiety herself, when her husband had been absent through the day, and not returned until an unusually late hour at night. I so far forgot all rules of politeness, as to take my Algebra that was lying on a stand beside a lamp that was burning- brightly there, and lose myself to all the sorrow that was sinLing s8O deeply in her heart. "I have gone to my window," sister Shifting said, "and looked out 'when it was so dark and stormy that Icould scarcely seemy hand bYo. fore me, when all without seemed an impenetrable gloom, until my eyes have grown weary by looking, and my heart has become faint within me, because I could see no signs of my husband's return. " Br. Shiftings was setting by. the stand opposite to me, he lhad been. posting accounts but as sister Fopsworth became'more and more alarm- ed about her husband, he stopped making his pen go so fast, and put in a word or two, now and then he grined at what his wife said, andi looked as though he felt foolish, then closed his book, and went out to the road and looked with all his eyesight to see if he could detect any signs of a human being, but nothing that moved or had the appearance of life met his vision, so he came into the house) saying if he knew, where to find Br. Fopsworth, he would harness the horse aind go for:- him, but by the time he would beo likely to reach the village, people. would have retired, and there would be no place where he could en- quire for him. "I hate to have you go," said sister Fbpsworth,. which was only a polite way of asking him if he. would. 4'Ifphe is not here by ten, o'clock, I will see what I can. do about- finding him, said X! Shiftings, and his whole appearance indicated that he thought it would be like hunting for a needle,in the hay mow.--- Thinking perhaps it was rather unbecoming in me. to appear so indif-. ferent, I thought I would act the part of a hypocrite and appear to. have sympathy for her, thoughk I had none, thinking she would lose all, confidence in my goodness and there is no hFm in being a little der. ceitful I thought when it was only to make others happy,; or whetn politeness demands it. BuhI did not have to act-the part of a hypo-s crite, when I looked into her face and saw how disfigured was her countenance, and how swollen were her eyes from weeping, and when H told her that I pittied her; it was only the real feeling of my heart.-'. A few moments past ten when BD. Shiftings was making preparations. to go for, the horse, thee: door opened and Br. Fopsworth stood,. before,   &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC7995-00000012"/> 9- Q; us. The happy change which his coming produccld in the appearance. of sister Fopsworth you call imagine, while I halve not the ability to. discribe it to you, but it is sufficient to say that hbr sudden transition from grief to joy was instantaneous. , "I knew you well enough," she said smiling very affectionatcly, "to know that you would colme to-night, if you were alive and well, and because you did not come as soon as you said you would, I had the inost fearful forolodingss that something had befallen you." "My deal wife,".he said, pressing her delicate fingers in his hand, and kissing the fair-lips that addressed himl, "I thought you would. not be'troubled about me if I did not come as soonzas I had anticipated, because it is such a bright moonlight night, and the stars shine with such unrivaled briliancy. If it had been dark or I had seen any ap- pearance of a storm, I should have returned much earlier, though the people where'we were stopping, were turgent in their entreaties that we should tarry all night, but I told them my wife would be expecting me Uand have walked as fast as possible in order- to reach here before you would have retired." After being an eye;witness, to so much of earth-, ly bliss, I retired to my room, better satisfied, with my condition in" life than ever before. Ido not know as. I wasfpharisaical, at least I did not mean to be, but I thanked the Lord that my happiness,was not thtus dependent upon oircumstarces,. and believed: that nothing. earthly a-d power to distroy the peace and tranquility- of 'my mind, but there were secret windings in the depths of my heart I had not fathomed, and, I knew not what I could bear. The next -morning when Br. Fops. worth had left Br. Shiftings in order to pursue his studdies at E, it appeared evident to me that I had either fallen somewhat in his wife's estimation,' or that there was little or no congeniality of feeling, be. tween us, for although she appeared friendly to me, her whole conver- sation, which was about her husband and child, was directed to sister Shiftings and not to me. She -said to her one day not knowing I was in hearing that she felt embarrassed whenever she talked of her husband before me, for I believe she said, that she is not interested in the con- versation. She is very much interested in your husband, sister Shift- ings replied, but she never was married and thinks it savors of weak- ness to have our husbands uppermost in our minds. I had noticed that she not unfrequently left mny society to seek that of sister Shift- ings at times when I would be seated, by her side, with her infant' in my arms,- though sister Shiftings were ever so busily engaged in her domestic affairs in the ]kitchen, but did not know the reason only as I guessed it. This to be sure was of no consequence, still I wished to make myself a grecable to her, because she was the wife of our minister and also member of our cHurch. So every moment sister Shiftings re- / quired not my services, I devoted either to her, or her child, and spar- e I no pains to, inake them happly. Thus at- the close- of the week had so far fallen into her good graces, that she complimented me to sister Shiftings, saying I had some most excellent qualities.. The next day was Saturday- and Br. Fbpsworth came to stop over the Sabbath. This afforded me t, great deal of pleasure, for. I always enjoyed his society. ,tdo believe," said' sister Shiftings on Sablbathl mbrning, while we uK   223 ' were preparing breakfast, "that there is a similarity of feeling between you and him, for you seem to understand each other perfectly, and one would think that you'were old and intimate friends, and yet you have not knomwn each other one short year." "I told her I loved to converse with him because he was so deep and original, while he seemed fond of asking file questions, because I was so free to give my opinion, however absurd my idea's might seem to others. Furthermore that I had a particular regard for all minis- ters not only because they were the servants of the nost high, but be- cause 1 believed them to possess, i refinement of taste and feeling,which is uncommon to those whose minds -are continually occupied with the things of the world. The next week while Br. Fopswqrth's family were visiting at one of the neighbors, to make up lost time, I attended with renewed diligence to my Algebra, and read some every day in French, and should have thoagaht of but little beside, had not sister Shiftings appeared unusually sad. As she walked the house, heaving every now and then,- a deep- drawn sigh, I must keep it a secret, she said on my enquiring what it: was that troubled her, then turning deadly pale left the rfm. I will not say my curiosity was not a little excited, and I began to think within myself what means I could devise to ascertain what it could be that was so grievous to her, and also seemed enveloped in so much mystery. She seemed happy all day Sunday I thought, and in the evening rode some two miles to a prayer meeting, which was held in the back part ofrthe town, accompanied by Br. Fopsworth, and since then I have zscarcely seen her smile. This road led through a long piece of wood and for the distance of more than a mile not a human residence met the teye. Who knows but in the midst of that solitary wood remote froma human observation and where none could listen to hear he has taken -occasion to reveal something to her which is the cause of all this un- happiness. They seemed happy when they went away, and a pleasant smile rested on each countenance, as he drew the buffalo more closely around her, then snaped the whip and started off at full speed: It was a lovely evening, the pale moon lent her silvery, rays to escort them thither, the snow cripsed beneath the horses feet the sleigh bells rang merrily in the evening air, and they were soon 1l to view amid the trees of the forest. When they returned I enquired of Br. FopsWorth how he liked the prayer meeting. He replied that they needed in- struction how to pray for they had no systemlin their prayers. I look- ed at sister Shiftilgs and there was a mysterous expression resting on her countenance which I could not devise, but which sent a thrill of sadness to my heart. Just then Br. Topsworth stepped into another room, and I enquired of sister Shiftings if he was as interesting in pray- er meeting, as he was in his sermons? She replied that- he was not: and it seemed ,to pain :him if a speech was not eloquent, and a: prayer-was not scientifically made, all were embarrassed in his pres-s enge and we have not had so -poor a meeting at all she said and ap- peared decidely -out of tune. I therefore came to the c  0nclusiont that she thought he lacked spirituality, and for {hat reason and for that alone she was dissatisfied; with him,. but when she :left  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC7995-00000013"/> *24 *the room .in the manner that she did, I was convinced that some. thing deeper than all, that, was the occasion of her sorrow. The next time I saw her. I enquired of her how she came by the secret, if Br. Fupsworth had told it to her. She. did not seem disposed to answer my question, but the tell-tale blushes on her cheeks told more plainly than words, that if he was not the author of the secret, she had learned it from him. Being aware from my appearance what my opin- ion was she enjoined on me the strictest secrecy, than frankly and with. out hesitation confessed to me, that the secret laid between her and Br. Fopsworth, she had told it to her husband, but no one else knew it, but her God, and not for the world would she tell what it was, for accident- ly I might speak of it, or by some means or other it might leak out, find should it be known he could not step another step in the ministry. I never should, have told you that there was such a thing as a secret, -she said, had I not felt that I was compelled to do so. Br. Fopsworth rs very much respected now, and not for anything would I have them dlose confidence in him, for our members are few and it might be the tmeans of entirely -breaking up the meeting. Knowing full well sister Shiftings dreaded nothing so much as anything like disgrace in the church, I made no farther enquires, but to ascertain what feelings sister Shiftings indulged for him herself, I enquired if she expected to attend his meeting the following Sabbath. I have a great straggle in my mind about it. she said, and if I should consult my own feelings,;should never go to hear him again; but if I do so it will be noticed by the congrega. tion, and many will be enquiring my reason for not attending meeting. I had never since the night Br. Fopsworth stopped to Mr.' Fairdealer's considered  him deeply pious, but I had believed him high minded and possessing all the characteristics of a true gentleman. But these things had an influence on my mind, he fell in my estimation and the fall  -:brought to my heart keen sensations of sorrow. The next Sabbath when I saw him to meeting, the first thing I thought about was the secret, and though he preached a most eloquent sermon, it did not reach my heart, I was not a little surprised to see Rose there for it was bitter cold, and asked her at noon how she gained courage to face the wind and walk-through the snow on so bleak a day. I have something to tell you she said, with agreat deal of animation, -and asked me if I ,. remembered the Levee the Methodist had a few weeks ago, to raise money to pay the minister. I replied that I remembered it well, being one of the number present. Well Br. Fopsworth came the night be- fore, in co0mpany with Br. Shieldings, and the story is current through' the village that past nine o'clock that night they went to an oyster saloon, purchased oysters, and carried them to Mrs. Talkative's to be cooked, and before they got through with their byster supper it was past twelve o'clock. She sent by them to get her aper that was there or at the next door and rather than enquire for it, they purchased another of the kind and carried that to her instead of carrying her own, less people should know where they were going with the oysters.- I do not know as there was any harm in that; I said, or as it is any body's business.} If it is not every body makes it their business, because he knew the house to have a  bad name, he-had been told by the leading members of   25 the church that Mrs. Talkative was in the habit of receiving gentlemen callers and to be prudent about going there, he also knew that her hus- band was not at home because they called in the afternoon and received permission to go there with the oysters and were told by her that her husband was .away. How does any one know- that, I said, thinking probably it was a flying story among those who liked to have something to laugh about, and nothing more. You know she said, Mrs. Talkative can keep nothing to herself, though it be against her, she had to tell of it to Mrs. Newsly the woman who does her washing. Mrs. Newsly going from place to place washing, does her part towards circulating it, whiltethe people laugh and say, if he had not known what kind of a hous it was, aand that her husband was not at home, he. would have stayed away. It is likely the man thought no harm in going there, biut why did you not tell me of it before, I said, feeling sad that he, should thus be laughed about and made the sport of the unthinking  multitude. Rose made reply that it was but recently that she had heard of t' her- self, and had had no opportunity of revealing it to me until, the present. Notwithstanding my sympathies were in favor' of Br. Fopsworth, my- better judgment told me that if nothing more, he had acted imprudent- ly, yet I said to Rose that they would getmen to say nothing against' Br. Fopsworth, until I had seen something in him myself to convince me that he was wrong. In returning from mleeting that afternoon, we passed Mr. Fairdealer's and notwithstanding the weather was so severe, we were obliged to wrap ourselves in buffalos to keep from freezing, I begged leave of Br., -Shift-- ings and wife, to stop just long enough for me to run in and see cousin Frank a moment. i"Be spry as you can," they said, 4"for the horse is unwilling to stand in the cold."  I did not stop to walk but ran - and, opened the front door, and passed into the sitting room. The first one" I saw was Frank, and enquired of her very abruptly if Br. Fopsworth' carried oysters to Mrs. Talkative's the night before the levee. She re-' plied that he did, "and asked me why I did not come in and sit down." I told her they were waiting for me out to the road and I could not, stop but a moment.     . "I was up that night," she said, c"at a much later hour than usual," for Wilhe had taken a severe cold and was threatened with a, fever.-' Mr. Seers the gentleman who boards with me, had come in la'te that.. night, and seeing some one in their back yard, asked me if I knew who it was. I told him I did not recognize him, then looking' at the clock saw That it was just half past eleven. Having so much anxiety ab6ut my child, 1 thought no more about it that night, and the next; morning I was so busy cooking fir the levee, that I had no time to ihink of it, and probably should not have-thought of it had I not all these things to have occupied'my mind. But somefortnight afterwards I heard people laugh and tell this story about Br. FopsWorth a nd lMr; Shieldings, and not believing they were the ones who- wre there at the time, I made enquiries of MrS. Newsly, wh6 report said was knowing to the fact, and was informed by her'that the story was;true, andlearz- ed more fully into its :particulars. IA felt not a&amp;little-sorry, that he s'hould: be 'spokeni- thus 'l1ightly of , Q               *  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC7995-00000014"/> realizing that it would bring a wound upon the cause of religion, and by attending his meeting a number of times, I lhad learned to love and re- spect him as a minister, and often spoke highly of him, to the mem. bers of our society. Notwithstanding it bore so heavily on my mind I unburdened my feelings to no one, except my intimate friend Mrs, Sympathy. I knew that while she would symnpathise most deeply with me, she would keep it a secret within her own breast. I then gave Rose a strict charge to say nothing about it to any one, however. much it might be talked of by others, but I suppose she thought 1 should speak of it to you when I should see you, and took the liberty to do so her- self. "I don't think he meant any thing criminal in going there, I said though he may have acted imprudently." "It is not for me to say that he did," said Mrs. Fairdealer firmly, but he bhad no business there, it was not setting a good example. Slr. Piety would not have gone there, no not for the world. Well do I re- member how careful he was to avoid even the appearance cf evil. No one could truthfully say a harmful word of him, and when he was persecuted, it was for rightouness sake." "Don't be so eloquent," I said, "Ibecause there was no real harm in his carrying a few oysters to Mrs. Talkative's." "If the cause of God had lain as near his heart as it should, he would -not have done anything that if known could injure the feelings of the church over which he was placed, and who were looking up to him  as their example, and with the mind I now have I shall go no more to -bear him preach."         . I stopped no longer to reply to what was said, for to -my sorrow I recollected that my company were waiting for me in the cold. In order to apologize for having stopped 0o long, it Seemed necessary to mention that I had been listening-to something exceedingly painful. This of course excited their quriosity so much, that they were unwilling to wait tntil we should reach home, to learn what it could be. I could not make up my mind to say anything to Br. Shiftings about it, but told it as softly as I could to his wife.' "What does Mrs. Fairdealer think about it," she said, appearing to feel very much troubled "she believes his piety is not--so deep as it should be," I replied,L ,and thinks she shall go no more to hear him preach." "You tell Mrs. Fairdealer she is not liberal enough," sister Shiftings said, With no small degree of inpatience. and in so loud a tone of voice, that Br. Shiftings with no little astonishment, enquired what she could mean, and it was but natural that she should tell these things to her husband as soon as possible. I took some pains to lean forward that I might have a better apportunity of looking into his face, and witnessing the changes in his countenance, as with a heart beating with sorrow ahe poured them into his ears.               - He appeared equally as dissatisfied as his wife, that people should surmise evil of their minister, and was equally as free to. throw blame on Mrs. Fairdealer for saying she thought she should go no more to 'hear him preach. I could but recollect that that was the first Sabbath since sister Shiftings bad had ouch struggles in her own mind about hearing   him prealh, an 1 ka3a fall wall it was only the ardent desire she had that their s )eiety miht prosper, that itduced her to do so. I recollected too ho w mnuch more earnestly Be. Shiftings had prayed in- his family devotions the post wee', that their minister might not be left to bring a reproach up)n the causa of religion, and how much more lightly he had spoken of him in conversation thxan he had been wont to do. Ab),nt this timie t!lroe had been a disaffection among she singers at the C(on nre tationalist s. A number of theam had been to the Methodist that day to meeting, and aided in the singing. They had given out word that they should sing no more for the Congregationalist society, and for that reasoa they were almost sure of their continued services at the Methodist's Thereforc watren it was known by Br. Shiftings and wife, that suspic- ions were resting on the character of their minister, they felt as though they could not nor would not have it so. Our meeting is beginning to prosper finely, and we have labored hard to get it where it is; Br. Shift- iang sail, looking sad and appearing to feel not a little disheartened.- But if these evil s rmnisings are iV circulation about Br. Fopsworth, I fear it will not only do us great injury, but be the means of entirely breaking up the society. Sister Shiftings symlnpthies were all with her husband, her fears and anxieties w31re the slmni, ani they dwelt long and sorrowfully upon their trials. Finally sister Shif;tings consulted with her husband to know if it wa^s nat bit for him to g) that very night ; 1 have been informed to- (day she said, that ke intends to carry his wife to Mrs. Talkative's to pend a week with her, notwithstanding there are many of our society, who are waitcing anddesiring to receive a visit from her, and are not a little sarprised that Br. Fopsworth should think of such a thing as car- ryitny her there. If you see him she said, and tell him the gossip of the neici/borhood, and invite him to bring his wife to spend another week wit i us, I think he will not carry her to Mrs. Talkative's, I should rather have her here a maioh longer timna altioao'i my health is so poor I s'lould be unable to wait upon her alone, thAn to have her spend one day with her. &amp;-I shall not consent to say anything to him about it," said Br. Shift- ings decidelly, for it will do no good. He knows full well that any of us would rather sutfer almost any inconvenieace, to'entertain them our- selved, than to have him go himself or carry his wife to Mrs. Talka- tive's. , le was told the first of his coming here, by me and several others, what kind of a house she kept, and also of .the danger there would be of his suffering in his reputation, if he went there to stop long. or at unseasonable hours. Br. Fopsworth is one who will not be dictated by a man, yet he may be influenced by a wedman. I h:.d been waiting all the while Br. Shiftings was talking for an op- portunity to say that Mrs. Fairdailer would be very happy to receive a visit from sister Fopsworth, k'for she thinks from what she has seen of her"- I said, ",that she is a very agreeable woman.'" Just than, sister Shiftings recollecting that I was inten'ding to 'go to the village, tho nex t day- to see that all things were in - readiness for the school I was intending to teach, asked me if I would be kind   &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC7995-00000015"/> -enough to step into Mrs. Talkative's, and tell: Br. Fbpsworthl about; these things. He will probably be there with his wifeb before you. are, and though she will not belikely to go away- ultil she makes her visit, if Br. Fqpsworth knows what is going on about him,- he will not be likely to spend the following Saturday and Sunday there. H hesitated and considered whether it was best for nme to do so or not,. while sister Shiftings became more urgent in her entreaties that I should, and the next morning when I was ready to start for the village this was the, last request she made of mre, and said if'she knew I should not comply with her wishes,. she would go herself on purpose to make ' it all known to him. "I shall go to the village to night," she said, "with the horse and  sleight, I have some shopping to do there, soa ifyo are ready you can come back with me." S"Then I shall have a ridk both ways," I said to Br. Shiftings, as he was pla'cingta grist of wheat into the back part of the sleigh, in order to make a step answer for a step, or as the old saying is kill two birds with one stone.       When I started for the village, I was at a stand to know whether it was Inmy duty to comply writ sister Shiftings request or not. Yet I was aware that she exspected it. of me, and that , great would be her, disappointment if I failed to do so, for that would be the last oppor- tunity any of us would have of seeing him before the last of the week,. since the afternoon train of cars was to carry him to C. But thinking 'it over and over in my mind I came to the conclusion, that to be wise, I should keep silent. That it would be decidedly unbecoming in me :to speak to him on the subject, when it belonged to the leading mem- b ers of the society to keep their minister posted in all those thin% it would: be fpr his interest to; k mq,;;. Notwithstanding Br. Shiftings made some enquiries about myselioot, how many scholars I expected to have, and expressed his opinion, as. to what was the best mode of governing a school, not a word was said by either of us on this subject, which seemed of so mackh importance, ane, which was uppermost in our mnids. When we reached Mr. Fairdealer's, he stopped just long enough at the door, for me to step out of the sleigh, and then brossed the bridge and 'drove up to Mr. Fairdealer's mill. ' This mill was just opposite, and in full view of Mrs. Talkative's residence, and while the grist was being ground, there was plenty of time for him to have seen Br. 2 Fopsworth, , had he, the faintest hope that he could have influenced his mind. This a of course, confirmed me still more in my resolves to keep silent. When I entered the house, Mrs. Fairdealer Was all through washing, and her clothes was hung out on a line between the house and barn.- "'tou. seem to be smart," I said, "to have your washing done at so early an hour;" looking at the clock and seeing it lacked fi fteen minutes of ten. She was just ringing out her mop to wipe the last board on her kitchen floor." Her cheeks were flushed from labor,and thtere was an excited expression on her countenance as she said, 1"I am some expect- i g Mrs. Fopsworthk here this week, and I wish to be in rd&amp;i 8,aess. for   her, thinking if I have to spend too muah time about the house while she is here, she will be homesick, and not enjoy her visit." "She will not be here this week," I said, *for she is going to spend it at Mrs Talkative's." "To Mrs. Talkative's," Mrs. Fairdealer replied with a great deal of surprise, as though she thought somehow or other, 1 must be mistakened in the place. "&amp;Yes to Mrs. Talka tive's"I said, with considerable emphasis, implying that there was no mistake at all about it. '.If she is a pious, devoted woman, as a, minister's wife aught to be, she 'won't enjoy Mrs. Talkative's society a week." Oo1, this remi ids me of the request sister Shiftings made of me, I said, and that was, th:tt I should tell you that yVou was not liberal enough, because you said you s oald yo no thore to hear Br. Fopsworth preach. ," Then you told her wh tt I said, but did you tell her why I was not more liberal," said Mrs. Fairdealer, Earnestly, raising her eyelids and placing on me the whole bigness of her full black eye so expressive oF conscious innocence. "*I do no; know as I did in particular," I said, 'but you can have the privilege of that yourself to nirght, for she is coming to the village, and will stop here to see if I am ready to return with her." Towards -the hour of sunset, Br. Shiftings' hose was seen coming down the hill, sister Shiftirgs was in the sleigh behind him, but did not s;op until she had been to the store and done her shopping. Daring this time Mrs. Fairdealer improved every moment, preparing supper, and doing her chores for the night, in order to have the better opportun- ity of freeing her mind to sister Shiftings, and giving her reasons for not being more liberal to Br. ropsworth. When sister Shiftings came to the door, I ran to meet her and invited her in, te'ling her Mrs. Fairdeal- er wished t3 see her a few moments. While-I was handing'her a chair by the stove, she inquir ed if I was ready to return with her and also if I had seen Br:. Fopsworth. I'told her I could not arrange my business so as to go until the morrow; and then if it was pleasant, I could walk down, if not, I could wait until another day. When I had answered the first question, I did noi attempt to answer the next, until she had asked it the second time. I then replied to her that I met him' on the street, but could not make up my mind to say anything to him on the subjeot referred to. Her countenance fell in a mnoment, and she said if I had told her plainly that I would not do the errand, she would have come and done it her- self. Just then Mrs. Fairdealer entered the room, and relieved me somewhat from the embarrassment in which I found myself, by mention- ing inadvertantly, that Mrs. Fopsworth was visiting at Mrs. Talkative's that week. Sister Shiftings colored, and hardly knew what to, say or how to turn it off. Knowing how to sympathize with her, as I had just been feeling uncomfortable myself, I replied that sister Fopsworth was a good little woman. This put the words into Mrs., Fairdealer's mouth and she repeated what she had before said to me, that if she was a pi- ous devoted woman, as a minister's wife aught to be;, he would not en- joy Mrs. Talkative's society a week. Then took occasion to give her rea. sons for not being more liberal towards Br. Fopsworth, and said that he want there with his eyes wide open, and knew where he was going.  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC7995-00000016"/> "Probably he thought her husband was at home," said sister Shift.. ilg, wishing to mxke things appear as favorable as possible on the side- of Br. Fopsworth. ",No," said Mrs. Fairdealer confidently, "for he called in the afternoon-and received permission to carry his oysters there at that unreasonable hour' and was also told by her that they. would have to take care of their own horse, since there was not a man about the premises. He took Br. Shieldings with himn," said Sister Shiftings evi- dently miking her last resorts, to excuse Br. Fopsworth. This excuse seamed so insignificent to Mrs. Fairdealer that she said nothing but look. eli her impatience.. and sister Shiftings feeling repulsed. said it was get ting late and she must hurry home, then bidding us good night left the house. The next day proved, too rainy, and for that reason I did not go down to Br. Shiftings until the day following, I found both him and his wife appearing much more reconciled to the state of affairs than I had antic- ipated; blut made no inquiries about it at first, thinking they would refer to. it themselves. But as they did not seem disposed to do so, I asked sister Shiftings how. she felt now, about- Br. Fopsworth's going to Mrs, Talkative's and carrying his wife there} she seemed, disposed te say as little about it as possible; and gave a knowing look. to her husband, who, had just come into the house, and was pulling off his mittens to warm his fingers by the stove, and- notwithstanding his face was all shriveled by the. cold, it assumed an animated expression as. though -a bright ray of hope was causing the blood to flow warm, through his veins.- sister Shiftings catching my dye, and perceiving that I was endeavoring to read their thoughts, looked steadily on some sewing she held in her lap, and swiftly plied her needle. In a few moments when Br. Shiftings had gone out to his work, I asked her if she did not suppose that Br. Fopsworth had heard by some means or other that he was laughed about. She hesitated to speak, and appeared ill at eas, but being awarelthat I was satisfied of some. fthing going on, Idid not fully understand, she said in a whispered tone of voice, (as though she expected some evil spirit near to catdh, what she had to say, and waft it on the wings of the wind,) if I would: keep it all to myself she would tell me what she had done. "I came  from efro  Mr. Fairdealer's the other night," she said, "Gia such a fever of excitement, that I stopped for nothing, but sat down and wrote Br. Fopsworth an anonymous letter, I addressed him  as be- loved pastor, and told him-as kindly as I knew how all that I had heard said about him, and word for word what Mrs. Fairdealer had said, but did not call her name. I only said she was not a member of our society, and-closed by telling him he could, abide by his own judgment as to, whether it was best to spend the following Saturday and Sunday there, and go from there to the-pulpit or-not, and figured at the bottom of the letter, from. a church member'" ," Did Br. Shiftings think it advisable for you to write in such a way," I  said, thinking it would have been better, if she had had the boldness. -to have signed her name. ("My  husband gave his consent," she said, and thinks I have not act- ei imprudently: "stil , entertain sore-Pears that Br. Fopsworth imay  .   mistrust meto be the author of the letter, and r am, half inclined at, times to be sorry that I wrote it, though I wrote it for his-good. The day before Br. Fopsworth usually came to town the traveling was- exceedingly bad, for an abundance of snow had fallen, and being driven by the wind, laid in heaps inm the road, and it was with difficulty that the 'traveler could plough his way from one- place to another, and for that reason had made up my mind that we should have no company that day, when I saw the shadow of some, one passing by the. window where I was seated. Being thus taken by surprise, I jumped up and hastily opened the door before he,had time to rap for admittance. and to my \ great astonishment, found myself in the presence of' Br. Fbpsworth.- But instead of meeting me with all that warmth and cordiality of man-- ner by which he had ever been charaoterised, he appeared cold and dis. tant. Before attemptin6g to come into the house,--he looked so steadily and inquiringly at me, that I instinctively dropped my eyes to the floor;. and could think of nothing only that he wished to know if I had lost confiience in hisintegrity. It was, with the most painful sensations that I waited upon him into the home, and gave him a chair by a warm. fire that was burning brightly on the hearth;-- Without stopping to sit down myself, I stepped into the kitchen, where sister Shiftings was preparing an early supper ; thinking her hus- band who had been absent since early in the morning, would not only come home cold, but faint and hungry. As I entered she naturally turned her eyes upon me, and perceiving my countenance was unusually sad, inquired very feelingly what it was that troubled me. "Br. Fops. worth is in, the sitting room," I said, "and he appears so unnatural, I cannot help feeling that he is ia trouble, and have for him the deepest sympathy."                          - ,tHe has received that letter,'" she said, not a little confused, ,and by some-means or other he-knows it was from me. Will you, be kind enough to be sitting the table while I go and talfk with him about it."-- And without stopping for anything else, she left the kitchen: and'seated herself with Br. Fopsworth in the sitting room., O e half hour had passed away; supper had been ready some time- but no one was ready to eat it. Br. Shiftings had not returned, nor- had his wife finished her interview with, the minister. Being aware that she had nothing very private to communicate to, him, only that she would feel less embarrassment to say what she had,' to say, with no one present but him, I cautiously opened the door, and" asked them if they had not better come out and take tea, since Bt, Fopsworth must feel the need of Something warm, to drink, after having- walked so far through the snow, and Br., Shiftings would not find fault  if he had to eat alone. Br. Popsworth shook his head and saicdhe had promised to take tea, at Mrs. Talkative's, and he should not fail in, his promises, besides he would not be deprived of -the luxury of taking tea with his wife, -who was there and expecting him.  Sister Shiftings urged him, but to no, purpose, he was still inflexible.  She then'stepped into the kitchen. to -e in what way the supper could-:best be kept warm untilher husband :s.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC7995-00000017"/> return; anI to the question asked how Br. Fopsworth felt about the letter she replied that he had not received it. "What sent him here to-day then, I said, and why does he appear a) strangely?" Some one at the village has told him that my husband ha's got something against him,and he has come to see what it is." 4'pid he give his reason for coming from C-- a day sooner than usual, I said, and without receiving any definite answer, to see how he stood affected, I immediately sought his presence. Sister Shiftings having told him what she had written, he seemed very desirous to know who the lady was that was going r) more to hear him preach, and declared if he could find her out, he should call her' to account, and make her give her reasons for saying: so. Then looking earnestly at me he said, "I think it was a friend of yours " I felt: my face redden to my ears, but endeavoring to appear calm, I replied that I had a great many friends, and she who sAi I it might also be my friend. I was well satisfied that by my frieni he meant Mrs. Fairdealer, it was but natural that he should mistrust her, for she lived next door neigh,- bor to Mrs. Talkative and he had been toldoby sister Shiftingi in a'n l swer to his artful inquiries, that the person who said these things, saw a light there unusually late on that eventful night when the oysters were cooked, and also that she was a memberof the Congregationalist Church. No other person who was a member of that church lived in the. right di. recti mn to distinguish whose dwelling might have been illuminated, 'still Br. Fopsworth was conscious of needing more substantial evilence, and this evidence he was endeavoring to draw from me, but sister Shiftings referring to the subject, accidentally called Mrs. Fairdealer's name. "That's enough, said Br. Fopsworth, and took his hat and started for the village. With the greatest anxiety, sister Shiftinrs followed him to the door, and used her utmost endeavors to persuade him to desist from his imprudent undertaking. "It's no use for you to say anything to me about it," he said, and with the greatest indignation, rushed from her presence. Notwithstanding all this, I could not make myself believe that he would so far forget all the kindness that had been shown him - by Mrs. Fairdealer as to treat her- ill; and when sister Shiftings appeared troubled about it, I endeavored to persuade liher to believe that it would amount to nothing, still I was uneasy about it, it was constantly in my mind, and I sought the first opportunity that presented itself to see Mrs. Fairdealer. This being the next Sabbath when I was- on my way to meeting, in company with Br. Shiftings; it become necessary for him to call with me. We had hardly seated ourselves in the house, when in the spirit. and tone of 6ne:who feels that they have booeen crowded, she commenced relating the manner in which Br. Fopsworth called there, the night he left Br. Shiftings in such a rage. "Hearing the door-bell ring unusually leud, she said, I thought that some one must be in great haste, to see Mr.. Fairdealer about having some grinding done, and immediately ran to, open the door, without stop,- ping to throw off an old apron I had pinned about me to keep the dirt from my dress; while about my work. But finding myself so unexpected-   ly in the presence of hir. Fopsworth, I was 'embarrnssed, and for a few moments could not collect my thoughts to invite him in. But imagine my surprise, when he accused me of' reporting stories about him. I could not think what he could meany and losing all respect or care for him, I thought no more about my old aprono. But giving him a chair in the parlor, I inquired in astoiAshment what he could mean, and told him plainly and frankly I had reported no stories about him. He then gave a full account of what he had learned from sister Shiftings. I then confessed to him what I had said, and how I came to say it, andi ; told him that I had not the remotest wish to injure him, but all in vain, he left the house saying he must leave E., with a good character, and deep seated malice was written on every ligament of his features. Br. Siiftings being present and hearing these events related by Mrs. Pairdealer; groaned a little and hammed more, but on the whole seemed to think that Br. Fopsworth meant well but had yielded to temptation, and needed our prayers. Rose went to the Methodist's that day, -but it was for the sake of a ride. Her mother tried to persuade her togo to the other meetinfg, and, probably she would have gone there had we not toldlher that we could take another along withb ums as well as not; and that we should be hap- py of her company,. Mhrs. Fairdealor became still more decided in her opinion, thama before, that Br. Fopsworth was unfit for a minister; for if he could =a lead himself, she thought he certainly could not others, and for that rea- son she was unwilling that Rose should sit under his preaching. She believed that precept without example, so far from leading a soul to the Saviour, would be the means of weaning them from al! that was truly good. I did not return with Br. Shiftings that night, but stopped at Mr. Fairdealer's in order to be in readiness to commence my school in the. morning, Mrs. Fairdealer had been to, Leotirng tkat dat to thp. Con. gregationalist's and on her way home obtained the following .news.- That Br. Fopsworth the past week, while at C., received an anonymous letter, mailed at E., informing him of the stories that were in circula- tion about him, and the effect it produced on the mind of one individ- ual, who for that reason was going no more to hear him preach.- On making enquires at'the post office, he was informed that 3Br. Shift- ings was seen to drop a letter into the box, directed to him. Without stopping to make further enquires, about it, he went directly to Mrs. Talkative's informed her about the letter, told her he was on the track of the one who wrote it, and it would be a saucy job for them. Just then his wife who was in an adjoining room, hearing the voice. of her husband, took her child from its crib, and hurried into his pres- ence. He, stopped to greet them very affectionately, then gave Mrs. Talkative a knowing look and told her he was going down to Br. Shift, ings "tand if you will inform me about what time you -will have your tea, I will not fail to be in season to take it with you." lMrs. Talkal- tive then informed him of the precise ltwie her tea would -be ready, while his wife regretted very much that he should go. 1'I have irn- pprtant business that must be attended to," he said, and bottoning his  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC7995-00000018"/> s               ' coat more closely about him, commenced Ilis long asn tiresome wal "Thoose who are knowing to the facts continued M rs. Fairdealer, feel confident that it Was either ir.. Shiftings or his wife, who wrote the letter." "Do you know whichl one it was," she'said, 'looking steadily at me, as if determined to assertain whatever knowledrge I might have about the affair, whether I was, willing to reveal it or not. ' I felt my nerves tremble from the crown of-my head, to the soleof my foot, for fear I should betray by some mleans or other her by look or motion, thiat I knew who wrote the letter, and was, puzzled for a mo-. ment to kno w what answer to make. Then told her as frankly as I knew how, 'that I was confider t I'  letter had been written while I was there, and if written at all, had been written during my absence. iMrs. Fairdealer thinking from this that I was as ignorant about it, as she was herself, made no farther enquiries, but manifested not a little dissatisfaction that what she had said to me and in her own house, shiold be the cause of all that disturbance. , Bfing conscious that I had done no intentional wron, and bein, aware also that it was far from the design of sister Shiftings to bring out the name of Mrs. Fairdealer as she did, I was not long in convinc. ing her' of the same, and restoring her to those kindly feelings she had ever entertained for her.                 m A few days of quiet passed by, and I began to believe that our trouble would be hushed, that Br. Fopsworth would never mention it agasi, when one of my scholars an interesting little girl of saeen twelve or thirteen summers, fetched me a letter. mailed at 0. I took- i and, hastily unlosing the seal, found it to be from Br. Fopsworth, ald en. closing another letter, directed to Mrs. Fairdealer. The letter written to me, read as follows. '"Dear Sister, please hand the following note to Mrs. Fairdealer, I hope you will say as little as you can about this troublesome affair.- I hope and may say believe that no blame will ,be attached to'- you, this hope I indulge for all my members; however- whether or no the ,person in fact will have to suffer. I don't know but I shall put the. thing to law yet, I should like to know what Mrs. Fairdealer could think when she reported'abroad about my asking a little hair oil of you the night I stopped there just after prayers. I think she must have missed heir way.'"Tours with respect, SOLOMON FOPSWORat. At the bottom was a postscript, I wish you much success in your school. When I  had finished reading my letter, it was time to commence my school in the afternoon, I need not tell you that I ocanmenoed it with a  heavy heart, and that my curiosity; was alsa great, to see th-, inside of the letter that was written to Mrs.. Fairdealer, for your judgment and reason ,will teach you all that. The afternoon seemed unusually long, aRd when my school was closed at night, I waited for nothing but hurried home, and landed Sirs. Pairdealler her letter, telling her it was from, B:r. Fopsworth. ,She looked wildly at me, and then at the, letter, as, if apprehensive some dirb calamity was about to overtake her, and taking it from, my hand, commenced reading its pages. Before ?Ie had read, one. lie, the. color left ler cheeks, and she. looked the   picture ,of death, thenc sinking down into a chair by my side evidently overcome with grief, she handed the letter back to me beckoning to me to read it. With a heart moved to sympathy I took the letter and read as follows: "Madam I am sorry to be compelled to give you the following notice but I am aware that s6rrow and suffering should not deter us from our du ty to God and each other. In my judgmeht you are, guilty of re- porting slander on my character, and also on that of my dear wife, and unless you see me between this and the third of Alarch, and account for such conduct in a satisfactory manner, I will on and after that time take such measures as to justify my character, and punish the offender, as ,.hall suit mle best. You will see me at A. K. Peaceable's, Saturday, Sunday and Monday next."         SOLOMON FOPSWORTH. "If' I had had no trouble in my own society," she said, when I had finished reading the letter, I could bear it better, but every body will believe on the account of that, and because he is a minister, that I havre injured him. 1'Although his being a minister might prejudice the minds -of some in his favor," I said, "people have eye sight, and will be led to see sooner or later, wherein he has acted injudiciously. All things come out right, if not in this life, in that which is to comie." Before giving Mrs. Fairdealer time to reply to whatI had said, I handed her the letter Br. Fopsworth had written me. When she read where he had an'idea of going to law. Though her fears were much excited, ahe said I shallenever confess to him, no never, for I have nothing to confess, and her voice and manner were indictative of the decisions of her character. "I never said anything about his asking for hair oil," she said in surprise, as she read the next line, then it oc- cured to her mind that Mrs. Talkative-came into her house Saturday afternoon of the past week, the day following Br. Fopsworth's return from C., and her tongue was continually running about Br. Fopsworth and family, saying much that was not in their favor. "Something," said Mrs. Fairdealer, "seemed to tell me that she only wished me to say something that she could carry back to them, to make trouble, and was careful to say nothing, but Rose for the sake of talk mentioned that circumstance about the hair oil, and that circum- stance had not been mentioned before, since the night of his staying here. 'I was tried- wih her for doing so, and told her never again to reply to anything that might be said, by s  artful a person as Mrs. Talkative." ,Without doubt"I said, ,Br, Fopsworth has told her what you said about his wife, that if she was a pious'devoted woman as a minister's wife ought to be, she would not- enjoy her society a week, and just out of revenge, she would make you say something that you would be sorry for having said," This seemed so probable to the mind of Mrs. Fairdealer, that she persuaded me to go with her that night to Mr. Peaceable's. "Mrs. lopsworth is stopping there this week, she said, and I will tell her a few of the things that Mrs. Talkative has said about them, just enough to give her a little insight into her character, that they may not be so ready to notice what she may have said about me."  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC7995-00000019"/> It was a bitter cold night, and we should necessarily have to face the wind, the distance of a anile, but being told by Rose that sister Fopsworth had- been to lrs. Newsey's that afternoon, and was proba- bly there then, we started with more courage, hoping that would be as far as it would be necessary for us to go. It was but a short dis- tance to Mrs. Newsey's, .and we were soon at her door. As we knock- ed for admittance, the figure of some one passed by a window through which a light was brightly shining and came to let, us in. It proved to be Mrs. Newsey, and we enquired of her if sister Fopsworth was within. -.She is," Mrs. Newsey replied, "but is making preparations to return to Mr. Peaceable's." "Then we won't go in," said Mrs. Fairdealer, "but walk directly down there, that we may be in readiness to see her when she comes." "You had better walk in" said Mrs. Newsey, but Mrs. Fairdealer thinking it might be more agreeable to sister Fopsworth to see her at Mr. Peaceables as she might not wish to be delayed, declined the invi- ' tation. When Mrs. Newsey had passed into the house. we stopped a -few moments longer at the door. My cloak had becolme unpinned, and while I was borrowing a pin of Mrs. Fairdealer to replace the one -I had lost, sister Fopsworth said, she knew we were intending to speak to her about the fuss, and she wished to have nothing to say about it. This detered us not, and we walked as fast as our feet would carry us, until we reAched the residence of Mr. Peacealle's. Sister Peaceable met us at the door in her quiet easy manners, and invited us into the sitting room. Here everything wore an air of neatness and comfort, and had I not glanced at the unhappy countenance of Mrs. Fairdealer, all, but the good and beautiful, would have been banished from  my mind.  In a few moments sister Fopsworth came smiling so pleasantly, and meeting us so cordially I could hardly realize that it was with sorrow- ful feelings she had anticipated our designs in going there. Mrs. Fairdealer then whispered something in the ear of Irs. Peacea- , ble, who after asking to be excused, went with her into a private room. In a few moments sister Peaceable opened the door into the room where we were seated just far enough to look in and-beckon to sister Fops- worth to join them. A dark shade crossed her brow, as she handed me her child, and followed sister Peaceable into the room where Mrs. Fairdealer was waiting fobr them. In their absence, I was amusing myself with the child sister Fops- worth had thrown:into my arms, when all of a sudden I heard an un- earthly groan. - It grew louder and still louder, until alarmed, I ran to the place from whence the noise proceeded, and found sister Fops- worth helpless in the arms of Mr. Peaceable, who was conveying her to thti nearest bed, which was in a snug cozy room  adjoining the sitting room. Sister Fopsworth was. troubled with the heart complaint, and when- ever any unpleasantnews come suddenly to her ear, it was almost sure to overcome her.  Thus when:Mrs. Fairdealer poured into her ears, some of the things Msr. Talkative had said about her and her husband /   the blood stopped circulating about her heart, and she fell senseless to the floor. Both Mrs. Peaceable, and Mrs. Fairdealer were nearly wild with fright, but they soon regained their presence of mind, and Mr. Peaces-l  ble was called to their assistance. When Mrs. Peaceable had placed an extra pillow under her head. ,that it might be a little more raised, and her husband had lain her comfortable in bed, Mrs. Fairdealer used such means and applied sucl restoratives as soon produced a free circulation of blood. When sister Fopsworth had ffully recovered, she took the hand of Mrs. Fairdealer telling her she could come and confess to her husband just as he had said. Mrs. Fairdealer's mind was too fully occupied with her grief to reply, Mrs. Peaceable said nothing, but wore a sor- rowful expression on her countenance. She felt keenly the trouble that was brewing, but wished to live in peace with all. Being weary of the scene, I begged of Mrs. Fairdealer to hurry home, telling her it was getting late: It was sometime before I succeeded int getting her started, and sad were the reflections she cast upon herself: for being so unwise as to say what she did to sister Fopsworth. "If I had only waited and asked my husband's advice," she said, "he would have told me better." "You did what you thought was for the best," I said, "then why do you reflect, but still she was dissatisfied. But may be when we reatw.! home, her husband will laugh her into reconcilation, I thought to my- self, as we drew near the house, and saw him entering at the front door, having just returned from the mill. As we passed into the room where lhe had s6ated himself, he could not help noticing that we were in trott- ble, for neither of us smiled or attempted to speak. And w}iile the silence was painful, it seemed equally so, to break that silence, by rc- vealing the cause of our sorrow. At length Mr. Fairdealer- enquired of his wife in his usual fit,},2' way, what she was giving that Orthodox look for, if she had been to mieeting. The way was then opened and we gave him the letters tc, read, and made him acquainted with the events of the evening. I need not tell you the effect this produced on the mind of Mr. Fairdealer, for yon already know enough of him, to know that he would bear but littie from any one, who might be called a minister. But I think if 3Xr. Fopsworth had happened in at that time, he would have ordered '!:itn out of the house. With a voice elevated by anger, he requested tlte letters should be kept. iLet him put the thing to law," he said, "and I will stand him a law suit, until I spend every cent I have. I hope Frank, he continued, that after this, you will adhear to what I tell yom and let the minister's alone. I should think you had seen enough by this time, to convince you that what I say about nminister's is true.- I should rather have given five dollars than to have had you gone- to Mr. Peaceable's on so cold and windy art evening as this, and on ,so foolish an errand. I hope now you will let the subject drop, neither trouble yourself, nor think of it any more, and I will fight all your bat- tles for you. It is just what will suit me best."  Neither Mrs. Fair- dealer nor I felt that we had anything to say, and therefore kept silent.   &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC7995-00000020"/> :rEven Rose was much shagrined, and instead of speaking as pertly in his favor as usual, hung her head, and said nothing. Willie and Ida owere. sleeping sweetly and soundly in bed. How I wished I could be free from care and anxiety like them. And had it not have been for the thought of living my days over how gladly would I have been: a child. How I wished I had never known Br. Fopsworth. If I had stayed away from his meetings, Rose would not have gone alone, and if Mrs. Fairdealer had not heard so much in his favor she would not have been attracted there herself, and all this trouble might have been avoid- ed. With these thoughts agitating my mind, I retired to my room, but could not sleep, and all before me looked an impenetrable gloom. Early the next morning I sought the room of Frank, she complained of a head-ache that was severe, said she had passed a sleepless night, and requested me to close the blinds that she might get a little sleep. As I turned to leave the room she said, if when your school is done at night you will calf up and see how Mrs. Fopsworth is, you will do me a great favor, and commenced weeping. That day I thought much and tried to consider what course it was best to take to put a stop to Br. Fopsworth's designs. Mrs. Fairdealer will never confess I thought no never. To-morrow he conies in the cars, I shall have no school and can meet him at Mr. Pcacetable's as soon as he arrives and try if possible to remove all prejudice from his- mind. When I returned that night I founrd Sirs. Fairdealer more comforta- ble than when I left her in the morning. Her first inquiry on my en- tering the room'was to know how Mrs. Fopsworth was. I replied that she was well as usual and arose that morning at her usual hour. ;The next morning soon after Br. Fopsworth's arrival, I entered the room where he was seated with, his wife, from a word I caught that fell from her lips, I thought she was telling him something' about our calling there, as we did, and was convinced that it was so, when a moment afterwards she left the room, and he enquired if I had received the let- ter he wrote me, I wrote one to Mrs. Fairdealer he said, and supposed she would keep it to herself, but instead of that she had to run to my wife with it and make her sick, I did not intend she should know any- thing about this trouble. I recollected what we heard her say the night we called at the door of Mrs. Newsey's, I recollected too of having heard Mrs. Fairdealer say that she was free to speak of 'what her husband had told her about the trouble, and that it was things Mrs. Talkative had said, that over- came her, yet I did not tell him so, but told him Mrs. Fairdealer was very sorry for having mentioned what she did to his wife, and would not have done it for the world had she known what the consequence would have been. 'These things are killing her," he said, "appearing to feel indignant at Mrs. Fairdealer, and to have great sympathy for his wife. "She is herself the greater sufferer," I replied, "for she has not yet recovered from the effects of the letter you wrote her, and the events which followed, but has been ill ever since." I then reminded him how kindly he had been treated by Mrs. Fairdealer, and that even then she would not harm a hair of his head. ,Why can't she hear me   preach," he said, indignantly, "and his lips curled with scorn."  It is evident she considers me guilty of immorality, and she will have to. confess. "If she thinks so she keeps it to herself," I replied, "'for she has never said it, she thinks that in going there, you was not setting a good example, and that it was no place for you, and if you had felt the weight of your calling as a minister should, you would not have gone there at that unseasonable hour. Perhaps she is not so charitable as she should be," I said, "but you must recollect that she has frequent- ly been deceived by those whom she has supposed to be good.-- Her husband has no faith in Christianity, and though she is -herself a firm believer in religion, these things may have some influence on her mind." "Well she Fill have to confess," he said decidedly, "nor is she the only one who will have to do so," but sister Shiftings must confess for writing the letter." i"Sister Shiftings is a friend to you," I replied, "and though she might have been injudicious in writing that letter, she wrote it for your good and the good of the church over which you are placed." Atmy request he took the letter from his pocket, and read it aloud.- None but the best wishes and kindest of feelings were expressed in the letter, and it seemed to be written in confidence, and with a heart over- flowing with sympathy, yet after reading to its close, where she wrote you can now abide by your own judgment, as to whether it is best to spend the following Saturday and Sunday there, and go from there to the pulpit or not. He said, ;"does she think I am so low that I can't go fromn there to the pulpit," and he said it in a tone of voice that told how keen was his indignation. "It is not intimated in the letter that yaou were low," I said, appearing much surprised that he should think of such a thing, or suffer the idea for a moment to find place in his mind. "I will let her know,"' he continued, "that I and my wife can go to any place however low, and come out as pure as we went in." "Sister Shiftings, is aware," I replied, "ithat in this place, many are watching with jealous eyes, the conduct of professing christians espec- ially ministers, and that to be useful, it is sometimes necessary that we should avoid doing some things which in themselves may be innocent, but would injure our reputation and destroy our influence for useful- ness. This knowledge that your reputation was endangered, and fear- ing the evil that would result from it, was what-induced sister Shiftings to write you that letter, and my opinion is the less -you say about it now, the better it will be, for you and the cause of religion in which you are. engaged." "You reason well," he said, 'but do not think as I do, and unless they acknowledge, I shall call a public meeting of the whole town, I shall then read the anonymous letter, and expose both her and Mrs. Fairdealer to the whole assembly." ,What do you expect to make of it," I said, "-you don't pretend to deny but that you went there, and carried your oysters, at an unseason- able hour." "I wish to expose them far the harm they try to make of it," he said, 4,and I shall do it. Because I happened to be in the badk yard at a later hour than Mrs. Fairdealer thought proper, she directed Mr. Sears attention to the window as though it was something criminal, and  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC7995-00000021"/> Ithe next day went about town reporting it with artful insinuations that. i was guilty of crime." , I then told him the truth about it, just as Mrs. -Fairdealer had told it to me, word for word, but he would not believe it to be true, and said Mrs. Talkative had told him all about it. Mrs. Talkative has told you too, that Mrs. Fairdealer reported abroad that you asked a little hair oil of me, but it is a mistake, it was Rose who thoughtlessly men;- tioned it, after having listened to some of the idle stories Mrs. Talkative had been telling about you and your wife. Br. Fopsworth made no enquiries as to what those stories were, but pretended to believe that Mrs. Talkative had told the truth about the hair oil, and that Mrs. Fairdealer had said many things about him that I knew nothing about.,           .   . Feeling very much dissatisfied with his appearance I arose to leave the house. When I had bid him good morning, and, was closing the door, he enquired very pleasantly, if he should have the privilage of seeing me on the following Sabbath to meeting. I replied, that duty would call me another way. "Mrs. Fairdealer is in trouble now," I said, "andI shall leave her only when it is decidedly necessary." Having reached home and informed Mrs. Fairdealer of my ill suc- cess, and what his mode of punishment would be, unless she should acknowledge to him,. I told her that he seemed equally offended with sister Shiftings for writing the letter.        ' "Then Mrs. Shiftinfgs wrote the letter, and you was knowing to it," said Mrs. Fairdealer inquisitively. I had spoken before I thought, but turned it off by saying that Br. Fopsworth read, it to m(ei and said it was writaen by her. 6"I reallyt believe he thinks she has no confidence in him," I said "although she hlas given him no intimation of the same. I guess he remembers the ,secret." "Secret what secret?" ejaculated Mrs. Fairdealer in surprise. 'Iere I had forgotten again, and mentioned the secret which I had promised faithfully I would keep'to myself, and could find no means of turning it off, as I did my other mistake, and therefore told as little about it as possible, and received the promise from  Mrs. Fairdealer, that she would tell it to no one, but, keep it Within her own breast, 1 pondered these things which Br. Fopsworth had said to me, over and over in my mind, and the more I thought of themn the more they magnified before me, until they gained that degree of importance which caused' me to resolve that however pressing our domestic cares, the fol- lowing Monday night, I must go down to. Br. Shiftings and inform them of the feelings that- were existing in the heart of Br. Fopsworth. "I would go to-day," I said, "to Mrs, Fairdealer but there is so much to be done it is impossible for me toget away." Mrs. Fairdealer seem ed equally as desirous of seeing them as I was myself, and expressed a wish that when I  did go, I should invite them to come home with me, "Y '?You need not go on foot said a gentleman who had called up to the -door, for I am going that,direction, and can take you into *my sleigh. 'fI don't know but I am inquisitive, he said, as I seated. myself by his ide, abut something seems to be troubling you,. Being aware he had heard much of the gossip about the Methodist minister, I merely allud- UI   d to it toit, 1,a] told him such thing were an injury to the cause of reli'- gion. "EHf is doubtless a bald an," said the gEntloman thoughtfully, ,"lid is conlsiderel so by the public. H-l llight its well stop preaching first as laS;t," he coantiLnLd ",for he will never be the imeais of saving one soul, or lltingr the-ch'urch one jot more spiritual.". Hviln ra::lheld ly journey's end, .I thanae J the gentleman for my ridle, alnd w\valked directly into the house. Br. Shiftings ald wife seem- edl, vry chr'3firFl and halppy, they 1had hbeard nothing about the trouble sinle taeo mr1n-3ing B:3. Shit'ing:, ctthted with 1me to Mr, Fairdealer's and were dispo sdl to believe it wtts dying -away. At length sister Shiftintgs said ewitiringly, you did not get out to lmeeting yesterdtay?!"o I replied it did not seem convenliert, nor did I care about going." They anxiously wivshel-to know thet re'son since ]I hadcl been a constant at- tenllant on public worship, :anl had halrdly failed of filling my place' in church sinc  a I hlrT tommncollll  going to that meeting. I paused for. a lliollent thenl tol tol thn I did not thilk favorably of the umilister.. "Br. Fopsworth has received is, rc xomlnulmndatioln to-day," they said, "and when conference sets he is to be ordailled. I lhope you will not be offended with him becausa M)I1s, Failrdealer is,' they said, -Lbut the next Sabbath we shall see you there.' "Ift'seens to me he was in a hurry about securing his recommenda- tion," I sfaid, "I suppose he wished to make sure of it before he kicks up the fass he has in contemplation, thinking that afterwards he would be unable to obttin one."  They seemed to foel a little troubled,. anid anxiously enquired what I could mean, I then invited them to go home with me, telling them that Mrs. Fiairdealcr would inform them all about it. ,It does not seem possible to suppose that he has any evil designs," they said, 4"for he dined here to-day and he never appeared more pleas- a1ntl and a(grieeable than -he did' then." "Hc was albout securing his recolmnmendation," I stid, "he is long headed about some things, though he may be foolish about others."- Sister Shiftings then told her husband he had better get the horse and harness him, for if they were goincg itwas time they were started. It wasa but the work of a few moments, and we were soon on our way at ftill speed. We had gone but a short distance however when Br. Shiftings commenced driving more slowly, and enquiredl if I clid not think I was rather unchlaritable towards Br. Popworth, and his wife said she hoped I should have wisdom enough not to deide aainst him, in tfie presence of Afir.'Pairdealer. ("Unless I am bleside myself they won't get me to say: anlythinlrg against him," she said and she said it with so much decis- sion I could not, refi-ai'n *from asking her, "if she supposed the world had no just idea what should be the conduct of professingO christians."- When a member is persecuted for rightousness sake, when some little defect in their character is magnified to a large one, or when unhappily they may hlave stepped aside from the; path that leads to holiness and heaven, but are desirous of retracingh their steps, then and only then is it our duty to stand by and encourage themr;  "We should ihot judge,"  said sister Shiftings, "No, I replied but by their fruits ye shall know them, and when you can prove to me that malice and revenge are the. - \  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC7995-00000022"/> fiulits of the spirit, then aridC only then will I believe that Br. Fobps- worth is a true Christialn." Ry this time we had reached the residence of 3I r. Fairdealer's. We entered and found r'ts. Flairdealer sittin in an easy chair, holding ill ],er hands these letters froio Br. Fopsworth.. Sister Shiftings seated Jilrself by her side and enquired very feelinl,g for her health, "I have not been imyself," she replied, "since I received that letter, handing the s. ame to Br. Siliftings to read, and felar I lever shall be Lgain, for it is cnltinually inl miy mind, land I learn also thalit Br. Fopsworth is offend- cd with you."   "Offendedl with mle," ejacutlated sister Shiftings with C;riphasis. "-Yes for writing the letter ," said Mrs. Fairdealer calhly.. "Who knows that I wro-to a letter," said sister Sliiftings in astonish- lli-nt?"4He read it to Tenmperance and said it was written by you, and all who knowanlythinug about it feel confident it was written either by ' you or your husband." Being aware she mistrusted that they had come by their information through mly instrumenta lity it seemed lceess'lry that she should receive Ia explanation of the whole affair. Althou(gh the change in her coun- tenance was visible, she would not admlit anly change in her milnd, and seemed to think that IBr. Fopsworth had not deceived her about receiv-- ing the letter, and that none could know with any degree of certainty, froml whence it originated antd seemed to think it was all surmised. When Br. Shiftings had read Mrs. Fairdealer's letter he said noth- ing but looked sorrowfully'and handed it to his wife, -who after reading it herself, looked earnetstly into the face of ..Mrs. Fairdealer, and said, 'you are going to -acknowledge are yot not?v, No,. Never," said Mrs. Fairdealer,. "while I have my senses or can distimnguish between right aInd wrong." "I think I would acknowledge, or do. anything, before I would have a fuss," said sister Shiftings, ,if I were not to blame." "He told Temperance, that you too would have to make an acknowl- edgement," said Mrs. Fairdealer promptly. d Sister Shiftings had not realized until that very moment, the injustice of eaknowledging that we have done wrong, when we are conscious of having done right, and with no little embarrasment changed her opin-. iou. Br. Shiftings said he must go the  next morning and see Br. Fopsworth, since he had not yet left town, and learn what he could mean.   Both he and his wife were indignant towards him and left Mr. Fairdealer's with feelings. somewhat changed from what they were when they went in there.  The next night when Mtr. Fairdealer came to his supper, he, seemed unusually pleased about something, and my curiosity being excited I enquired&amp; if he: had been, hearing -good news. Mr. Shiftings is down on. Mr. Fopsworthl he replied," "it has fallen. into his own dish, and now he begins. to see things in their true light. He has been to see Mr. Fbpswortk and I ratherrguess he did: not appear altogether so agreeable as he did before he received his recommendation. 6"How do you know," I said, feeling desirous of learning, how he came by- his information. "4He was in my mill a little while ago, and said he knew  a secret about him, that if knowa, would. put him down from. preaching, and if'   he calls out any body's name in public that secret he says shall be re-. vealed. He spoke with so much determination, and appeared so de- termined in his manner, that I rather guess he will make a go of it.- Now you can see for yourselves," he continued, "how people cover up in ministers what a man of the world would be banished for, until the: day of his death. Just look at it he said, this secret was known whent his recommendationa was given him, to show how Godlike he lived and how well he filled his station as a minister. An-i had not M'It. Shift-. ings wife been called to make her confession, he would still be-regarded a saint." Mrs. Fairdealer having, caught a lisp of the secret before, had sucht an increiasinr desire to know what it could be, that she sent Rose down to Br. Shiftings with a special invitation for him arid his..wife to come that week at the earliest opportunity, and spend the day with her.- KRse found sister Shiftings quite unwell, her feelings were so wrought upon that nighlt she called with her husband to Mr. Fairdealer's, that she had been obliged nearly all the time since to keep her bed. S"I ,m better to-day," she said to Rose, "when she had received her invitation, and if my health improves as much to-morrow as it has to- day, I and my husband will call and see your mother." The next morning Mrs. Fairdealer seemed unusually smart, and there were strong indications that she would yet rise above her trouble.- ",How relieving it is," she said, "as she was assisting about some light work, to feel that we have some one to help us bear our burdens, I never could have borne this severe trial alone." "You thought hard of her for bringing out your name as: she did," I said, ,but now she is in trouble like yourself, you seem united to her in / the strongest bonds of friendship." Just then the door opened and sister Shiftings entered leading her little girl. Her husband havingf business in the village did not come in -with them, this gave us a- better opportunity to find out the secret. Sister Shiftings looked pale and careworn and sank down into a chair that was handed to her, nearly exhausted. I hastened to help them off with their things, and while Rose was carrying them away, Mrs. Fair- dealer embraced the opportunity to ask her what the secret was that Mr. Shiftings knew about Br. 'opsworth, that if known would put him: down from, preaching. "Did my huaband speak of a secret concerning Br. Fopsworth," she said, in surprise!"If he did he ought not to have done so, probably he- felt indignant at his wrongs." "Yet I cannot reveal it, she said, unless ho brings out our names, but so sure as he does, that secret shall be revealed. "I do not believe he- will ha've courage to do it, I said, if he hears of that." - "I have not the least idea that he will, sister Shiftings replied, for if he knows any. thing at all, he will know -better than-to doso."- "But what can the secret be," Mrs. Fairdealer again inquired, 4"did he kiss you, and would that put him down from preaching." Sister Shiftings replied; and to relieve herself from embarrassment, she followed me into another room. It is no use for you to say to; the contrary, I know from your appearance, that he kissed you; I said:  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC7995-00000023"/> " to her, when we were alone. She made signs th me that he really did, but that was not the secret, and shook her head to give me to under- stand that it would be of no use to make any farther inquiries. Sister Shiftings, as well'as Mrs. Fairdealer, had lost all confi-dence in Br. Fopsworth; we-all expressed ourselves freely amLona  o'urselves, and the time passed so rapidly that we thought nothing about dimnner,. until it was so late we were obliged to get that whieh was the most handy. Br. Shifting s business kept him away until nearly nlight, bat when he came he dropped many unkind remarks that Br. Fopsworth had made about Mrs, Fairdealer. "He says your wife has longl been known as a busy body, and troublesome woman, and he is sorry that my wife and others have become complicated with her," Br. Shifting said, addressing Mr. Fairdealer. "Others, must mean me," I said, feeling morepl eased than provoked, for. I knew that no. good minded person would comle forward and say that Mrs. Fairdealer had ever- injured them or meddle'd with their basi- ness; and if he receivedhis information from any oie,. it must have been either fromn N Mrs., Newsey or Mrs. Talkative, and probably from both. Mrs.. Fairdealer had lived in that place ever since her marriage to Mr. Fairdealer, and had always been known as a strong lover of jus- tice, which uni-ted to a quick perception of right and wrong, -might to a person of more lenient' disposition, gave her the appeatrance of being too exacting, ,but those who carefully read their bibles, and wished to. square their lives by the same, would see nothing umreasonable in the path she marked out for herself and others to tread. Ir.. Fairdealer smniled at what Br. Shiftings said, with evident satisfaction, for he. could see at a glance that these things would never injure his wife, but go to prove that the wrong might be found -concealed in ,Br. Fops- worth's own breast; and thus his sentiments would be gaining ground, and converts added to, his belief. That night sister Shiftings and lirs. Fairdealer parted as one friend parts with another, each prom- ised to stand. by the other, in the hour of adversity, being apprehensive that trials which were the most severe, were about to overtake thiem.. The next night Rosewent into several of the neighbors, and learned that all sorts of stories were in circulation about this affair, for Mrs. Talkative and Mrs. Newsey were warm friends of Bro. Fopsworth; and ever since they heard of his receiving his anonymous letter, had,. been busy reporting that which was untrue, and exciting the sympa- thies of the unprincipled in favor of Br. Fopsworth. It hnd also beent circulated about town, that Mrs. Fairdealer had talked so unfeelingly to his wife about the fuss, that it had come very near ending her daysl and many in her own society mlanifested little. sympathy for her, think- ing she might have kept awayfrom the methodist's, and attended her own meeting. I called myself, into Mrs. Talkative's that night of an errand; her little girl attended my school, and wished at recess time, to be dis- missed. Thinking it might not be the wish of her mother, that she should be dismissed thus-early, I called to, see about it, and beoie I had time to do my errand, she inquired very. impertinently how Mrs. Fairdealer felt now,v knowing as she did, that Br. Fopsworth was going ,2.i        o   45 - icave her in the shape of nothing. I guess before she gets through with it she will wish she had minded her own, business, she said before i had time to reply to the inquiry she made, and then went on to say that Br. Fopsworth knew how saucy she had been to her own minister, and also the fuss she had made about Deacoa Treacherous, and was de- termined to make her smart for what she had 'said about him; '"and when he needs the letter no more that Mrs. Shiftings wrote him, he is going to give it-to me. and 1 shall have her taken up for saying I am a woman of bad reputation, and she will have to prove it." I knew that could easily be done, but only said it was nothing to me,. apd after having done my errand, went home and found Rose telling her mother about these stories that Mrs. Talkative and Mrs. .Newsey had put in circulation. Mrs. Fairdealer saw me when I went into Mrs. Talkative's and was so well acquainted with her disposition that. she felt confident she had lost no time in talking about her, and was very inquisitive to know what she said. . I looked into the face. of Mrs. Fairdealer; and seeing there thlle'ois of deep seated melancholy, and believing that she looked upon things much worse than they really were, I avoided telling her, though, niot to her satisfaction, for Mrs. Fairdealer had her friends, and they too were of the better sort. The next morning Mrs. Fairdealer was decidedly worse, both in body and mind, and when I asked her what I could do to make her more comfortable, she requested me to get Wil- ley to go up to aunt Charity's, and ask her to come down and stop with her, that day. Aunt Charity was a Christian in every sense of the word. She was a member of the same church, as Mfrs. Fairdealed: and they had long been intimate friends. Being in possession of' s heart overflowing with sympathy, she abounded in good works, and many is the time that she has been as' an angel of mercy to Mrs. Fair- dealer; waiting upon her in sickness, or speaking words of encourage-. ment to her in the hour of trouble; reminding her that these light af. - flictions which are but for a moment, sliall work out for us, a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory. "We are short sighted human beings, she would say, and cannot se6 why it is that we are called upon to pass through these trying scenes, but at those times we should be submissive in the hands of God, believing he doth all things well, and will ever rule all for our good. " That morning when I went, to my school, I met aunt C('rity on her, way to Mrs. Fairdealer's. "How did you. leave, Frank," she aid, as I drew near her, and inquired for her health," "'oorly,^I said,.and her mind is in so dejected a state, upnless she has some one; to sympathise with, and encourage her, I have my fears that she will go into a de-. cline. She thought if she could enjoy your society, and have you to, make her bed and fix her- something that she could relish to eat,. shec, would feel better." "I will do all I can to, make her- comfortable and happy," she said, glad of the opportunity ofadmPinistering to thee wants of a human be- ing, and especially one whio belonged, to. the household of faith. Each day as it passed away, fo q! Mrs. FiA!ealer no better, but. gradually worse, notwithtaanding;iut: 0iCharity- came daily, to admin[-.  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC7995-00000024"/> " 'ister to her temporal wants, and daily spoke words of encouragement 'i her car. My sympathies being enlisted in behalf of Mrs. Fairdteal- er, tand feeling it my indispensible duty to do all in my power to relieve her from the sad and desponding state in which shes had fillen, when the next Saturday night came round, I again called on Br. Fopsworth, thinking if he knew the state of Mrs. Fairdealer's mind, and also her declining health, if there was one chord of tender feeling in his heart, I could somehow or other persuade him to desist from his unjust de- signs. An expression of sadness rested on the countenance oft, sister Peaceable as she waited upon me into the parlor here a kIerosene lamp burning brightly on a centre table, contrasted beautifully with- the dtarkness without "I can't endure the thought, she said that, this trouble should be mentioned in public, and I hope you may be able to influence 'hihm to say nothing about it. I will go and speak to him, she said, and tell him that his presence is desired in the parlor." The few moments I spent alone, I was thinking how I should intro- duce the subject to Br. Fopsworth. My heart came into my mouth ; I trembled at the sound of his footfall, and it was with no smlall degree of embarassment, that I said good evening to himi as he opened the door and came into my presence. He tried to smile, but in vain, it was. only a forced contraction of muscles, and his countenance expressed hate and revenge. After a moment's pause, I said, with my voice trembling with emotion, and looking imploringly upon hili,- -[ ha re conle again to see if in view of Mrs, Fdirdealer's declining health, and the desponding state of her mind, you will not pardon her for saying she will go no more to hear you preach. "She cannot come and ac- knowledge to yon I said; for. she is not able to leave her room," "They are stubborn, he said, and determined not to come and con. fess to me, but I grow firmer and Oragil, in my determination to ex- pose them in public." Finding that by all I could say, I could not awaken his sympathies, I appealed to his judgment and reason.: Do you not think it would be. five times as colvincing to a majority of thinking people that there was guilt attached to your going there, by the course you have taken, than it would have been, had you passed by whatever'might have been said 'about it, and acted as though you were innocent. There is such a thing as living down slander; a lie it is said,'if let alone, will run it- selfto death, but no lie has been told about you; you went to Mrs. Talkative's at a late hour and carried oysters there for he-r to cook and that you do not pretend to deny, but what your conduct was while you was there, is known to no one but yourselves and your God, and how you are going to prove yourself innocent, by bringing it before the pub- lic is to me a mystery. "I took Br. Shieldings with me, he said, in a confident tone of voice as though that of itself was a sufficient pr6of of liis innocence." "'What if you did, I replied, he might have been guilty as well as yourself, and all the way I can see for you to prove yourself innocent, is to live innocent now. You are aware that from the very nature of the case, suspicions will esat upon your character; for what has, -s   47 been, may be again, and ministers that have appeared far more devoted than you, have been found guilty of crime, and your knowledge of hu- man nature should have taught you before you went there that it would occasion talk." Br. Fopsworth looked troubled, and ill at ease. Yet he said firmly to-morrow I shall give notice what my intentions are, and next week I shall send my wife to Canada, for these things are killing her, and the following Sunday I shal read the anonymous letter and call out sister Shiftings and Mrs. Fairdealer's name, and then if they do not acknowledge I shall have to go to-law. I then appealed to his belief in an overruling providence. Do you think I said, 6"if you are innocent that God will suffer this to harm you, or that he will leave the disgrace of it, to follow you to your grave, and if he Should, do you not believe your crown of glory will be enough brighter in another world, to pay you for all you suffer here." ,You make a good mediator." he said, ,'but you have no influence on my mind," and he compressed his lips and his countenance was inflexa- ble. I could see therefore that by all I had said I had affected nothing, and feeling that I had done my whole duty, and there was nothing more that I could say, I bade him good night and left him to his own reflections, resolving that if be told anything in public about Mrs. Fair- dealer that was untrue, that however crowded the congregation I should arise and contradict it. I knew full well if he told anything to her in- jury, he must tell that which was false. I had been informed that he had the written testimoney of both Mrs. Newsey and Mrs. Talkative, of things that Mrs. Fairdealer had said, when I knew she had never said them. It is my duty to tell the truth I thought, and truth will bear its weight. With these thoughts floating in my brain I felt my spirits somewhat revive, a ray of hope crossed my mind that God would never suffer him to prove the innocent guilty, however firm he might- be in his determination to do so, but that it would fall back upon himself where it belonged. When I told my intentions to Mrs. Fairdealer,- a smile of gladness lighted up her countenance, and she looked happier than she had for a long time before. "I am willing the whole world should know, what, and all I have said, but to have Mr. Fopsworth in the presence of a crowded congre- gation give the impression that I have been reporting stories about him and tell that which is false, seems to be more than I am able to bear, and if you will contradict the wrong statements he, may make about me you shall lose nothing for your pains." The false stories that were in circulation about Mrs. Fairdealer, and continually reaching her ear, caused her to be more and more earnest that I should do as I said I would contradict them if Br. Fopsworth should report them in public. The day that Br. Fopsworth chose for this, proved to be the last Sabbath that three or four of the most substantial and sound minded brethren were to spend in the place' as the next morning they were to start for the far West. They could not endure-the thought that the. lst. qohWnth thay should spend on their own native soil, shoald thus be  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC7995-00000025"/> profaned, they wished for a more holy remembrance of the day. On 8aturday therefore 'they met at the Depot at the hour Br. Fopsworth usually arrived, to persuade him if possible to let the subject drop, but, he was not in the cars, and they had not the privilege of seeing him.- Rumor said however, that he had stopped at a depot in another part of the town. Therefore the Next Sabbath morning, the Methodist meet- ing house was crowded with people that seldom if ever attended public worship and were only there out of curiosity to hear what Br. Fopsworth might have to pay, bipt to their great disappointment he did not come, and they went- home feeling much chagrined at their ill success. Vari- ous were the conjeetures that were made as to what was the cause of his absence. Some; thought we should never see him any more, others thought we -should. Nearly every day that week, I told Mrs. Fair- dealer, I did not believe he would come back again. "I wish I could think so, she would say, but I do not believe we shall get rid of him so easily, for a man so stubborn as he is, will never yield to trifles."'      - Saturday came and I felt so sure that we should never see Br. Fops. worth again, th'at I did not think of him for the morning, but about the usual time of his coming, I chanced to be gazing out of the window, that looked over to Mrs. Talkative's. The snow flakes- were- falling thick and fast, and were driven by a furious wind; but amidst it all I saw a gentleman coming down the street, that I took to be Br. Fops- worth. His rich locks intermingled with those flakes of snow were sporting in the breeze,^as he drew  nearer and still nearer, until he reached the residence of Mrs. Talkative's, then turning to the right he opened the gate and walked deliberately up the steps that led into the house. "That is certainly Br. Fopsworth," said Rose, who had been watch.. ing him ever since he came in sight, and until he had closed the door and was safely housed from the beating storm. He must be on some important business, 1 said to Mrs. Fairdealer, as she drew near the window, to catch if possible the last glimpse of- him before he should be hid from our view. "Probably he wished to find out what is going on, by Mrs. Talka- tive," she said, and sank back into her chair. That afternoon itiwas rum6red about town, that Br. Fopsworth was well posted ini what was to be done, and was prepared for it. **So am I,"' I would say to all who chanced to say anything to me about it, and nerved:myself up to the work. The Sabbath proved mild and agreeable and mustering all the courage I could command, I started off to meeting. Br. Fopsworth was in the pulpit' when I reached the place, antd seated myself in the very pew where I sat the first time I heard him preach, but how changed did he seem to me, and how changed was the expression of his countenance. I could hardly realize that it was the same Br. Fopsworth that less thlan a year ago I had so nmuch admired. Nohappys mile:lighted up his features, but as I looked at him, I met a cold and haughty frown, and a look of bold defiance, I felt then that I'was nerved and fortified for anything I might have to encounter, and addressing a friend who was sitting by /         '  r                  my side, I said in a 'decided toie of voice, and loud enough to be heard by Br. Fopsworth., if he makes any wrong statements to-day about Mrs. Fairdealer, I shall certainly contradict then, then turned my eyes towards him to see what effect it 'might have on his mind, and pale with anger an unholy indignation flshed from his eyes. Instead of feeling to quail beneath his presence a double lortioh of strengthand Fortitude came to my aid, and raising my voice, one pitch higher than -before, I said, "he'll find he's not the low Irish and English to deal with, but Yankees."  I could not tell where he took his text that forenoonw nor one word of the sermon, but it was not because I was interested in the man as in the first instance, but the reverse of it. That noon Br. Fopsworth as usual walked up and d)own the aisle) shaking hands with those who tarried behind, and as usual tried to .appear happy, but all in vain, no happy expression lit up his counteiaunce, for an expression of painful ahxiety had taken its place. After passing round ini fionit of the altar he requested the members of the church, both imale and female, to pre- sent themselves in the wing'pews, on the right side of the house as we walk up the aisle. One sister steanding by my side reminded me that t should present myself with them) I hesitated not seeing any 9ther female present herself, I then persuaded this sister to go with me, and we seated ourselves together in a pew behind the brethren. It was with- painful anxiety that I waited the result of our meetings until after a' little embalrlsment, Br. Fopsworth commenced somewhat after the fol1 lowing manner,  I now throw myself into your hands and it is for you to say whether I shall defend mny character this afternoon or not." Br. Shiftings sat in the further corner of a pew front of me, and turned neither to the right nor the left, but kept a continual looking dowln to the floor. "Those who think I had better not bring the subject before the public this afternoon may manifest it by raising their hand," said Br.- Fops' Worth, after watching with intense interest the countenances of those who were before him, Br. Shiftings knade no mnotion but continuedt to look down to the floor, while one or two raised their hands. "Those who think I had better bring the subject before the public this afternoon may manifest it in the same way." No one had any motion but Br. Inquisitive, who lived some some miles out of the village and had not received suitable information- as to' what those stories woev that weae afloat about Br. Fopsworth, and wish%-: ed tobe told then aind thie that he might the bette jtrdgd Whether he' should' speak in defente of hilmself ol not. Br Floswrth thelh comrn mnenced and told -the whole-story about his going to Mrtr Talkative' with tde oysters) about, hi;s tking Br. SliieldiiWigs thityh h how he was' watched by Some evil '-ihidd people, and all abdit it : and" witho'itf readinig the ano-iyous letter, which was the fouidatitii of ail the trotibles, re ented -Mf&amp; Fairdealer as the :rst' one wh6' sa6 i ht8ii in,: the back yidl, arid directed :tr. S ei;rs ateai:ti;to th WtIiObWiatiatl. first one who went taboiut ttot bfffn Vhta ptirirf' i ti1h arftil inmsnutatioia that he'taS'gitlty'of'iiia tilitv; -  ,Prmitme to rifl  ou i s-d whet - .         ' ,  , 5                         r   &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC7995-00000026"/> 50 that Mrs. Fairdealer directed Mr. Sears attention to the window, "you have been wrongly informed, it was Mr. Sears that directed Mrs. Fairs dealer's attention to the window." "I think not," Br. Fopsworth re- plied, "Mrs. Talkative informs meto the contrary." E"I have always known lIrs. Fairdealer," I said, "to be a woman of strict veracity in all my acquailtance with her, I never knew her to wave the truth and what she says, I would believe as quickly as though I -had said it myself, and that is the story she tells, Mrs. Talkative oi the other hand, is a woman who cares but little-what she ,ays, if she can only find some one to listen to her, and no one who knows her, unless they are disposed to make trouble, would notice what she said enoughl to tell it after her." Br. Fopsworth's eyes flashed fire, and he was be- gining' to bear down upon me and make it appear that he was in the right, until fortunately I saw Mr.'Sears wats present in the house and was ready to call him to witness to what I had raid- Furthelmmore I told him that Mrs. F'airdealer instead of going about town the next day in the manner he had been informed, was at work heart and hand pre- paring something for the levee, which was solely for his benefit. Br, Fopsworth colored to the back of his ears; some of the brethren looked ground upon me as though I had no right to, say anything while one brother left his seat, the sister by my side became uneasy and followed him, saying she had courage to stay no longer. .Again Br. Fopsworth commenced and made another statement that Mrs, Fairdealer reported abroad how late, Mrs. Talkative sat up to cook the oysters for him.-- "You mistake," I said, f"it was Mrs. Talkative herself that reported that story." This aroused his indignation to the highest pitch, and looking upon me with the greatest contempt imaginable, he ordered ine to leave the pew. I neither replied to him, nor left my seat, but it ,seemed to me that I should sink beneath it, and fall to the floor. "I bid you again to leave your seat" he said in a louder and firmer tone of voice, and looking upon me still with scorn; yet 1 remained motion- less, and seemed as immovable, as though I had grown to my seat.- He tehenrappealed to my honor, my religion, and my ladyship to leave the pew, still looking upon me as though I were but a worm that trawl- ed beneath his feet, but I leftit not until I had corrected all the false statements that Br. Fopsworth had to make about Mrs. Fairdealer, taking care each time, to tell him very respectfully, that he had been wrongly informed. It may seem strange, how I gained courage to still persist in contradicting the minister, but if I had not told sister Shiftings what Mrs. Fairdealer had said, she would not have written it to Br. Fopsworth, and all this trouble would have been avoided. Al- though I did not consider myself in the least to blame, in this respect, I believed it my-indispensable duty, to see that nothing be added to the truth. It was finally decided by the brethren that these otorier were circulated-by those outside of either church, to destroy both, and it would not be advisable to bring it up in the afternoon, besides Mr. Fairdealer was a map that would show proper resentment, and if there was any chance to go to law, would be likely to do so. Br. Fops- worth feeling much ehagrined that he had made out nothing, withl dissatisfied expression resting on his countenance, put on his . overcoat and started for his dinner. Br. Shiftings 'took a piece oof white paper   51 and lead pencil from his pocket, and passed around among those who were standin; in groups, telling how Br. Fopsworth had been abused, and how they wished he would make them smart for it, and asked each and all of them, how much they were willing to subscribe for a minis- ter the coming year, and by each and all he met with a cold repulse . Some said it was no use to hire a minister, for a fiuss would be picked -up with him if they did:. Others said if they would hire Br. Fops- worth they would willingly give .omething. All felt indignant at Br. Shifting S, beettiso it was well understood who wrote the anonymous letter, although they kept a continual questioning amongr themselves' who in the world, they thought could have the imprudence to write a letter, without signing their nllame to it. "Who do you think it could be," said one to me, as I passed down the aisle where they were busily talking. "It is none of my businesi who wrote the letter," I replied, "but doubtless it was written for his goosd, tlnd if he had taken it so, it would have been all well enough." "I don't know as there was anything crriminal inhis carrying oysters to Mrs. Talkative's," ,aid another. "Neither do I care anything about that," I said, "he mightshave gone there, and been innocent as ,nn angel, as fir as immnbrality is concerned, but the course he hastaken with Mrs. Fairdealer I consider decidedly unchristian; nor was there a particle of christianity in thift letter he wrote her."  "4I saw a copy of the letter staid another," very pertly, 4"and thought it was a beautiftl one. "Mrs. Fairdealer las been kind and hospitable to Br. Fops. worth," I said, "talthough she was nof a member of his society, and he had no right to look for any marked attention from her, yet he lhas re. ceived it, aWnd because she does not think 8o much of hin as formaly, Irld has said a few things he does not like, in her own house and where she erpected it would go no further, he is making all this trouble:" - None   seemned to appreciate: what I said, and it did not take me long to lcarn th;at all the sylnpathy in that house, was in favor of Br. Fops- worth. While the greatest indignation was manifested for the one Who wrote the letter; much blame was attached to Mrs. Fairdealer, and I was considered as partially insane for speaking in her defence. In consideration of how I had been treated by 'r. Fopsworth, and how I as regarded by -the church and congregation, I could not have made up my mind to have stopped to the afternoon service, had it not been for the thought that there was a possibility afterall that he might brilg this subject before the public, to please a multitude of curious listeners. I remembered how firm he appeared to be, each time I had spoken to him about it, and that he had said nothing would prevent him from do- ing as he had unllertaken. You may well imagine, I did not consider it a1 luxury to be within the walls of a  lMethodist house but an irksome task. You too imay imagine that I  felt somewhat relieved When with no little embarrasment,lie notfied tlke convregatio n that the church Was not Willing that he ,saould mnake public those names, who had talk- ed about him unnecessarily, There was a  disappointed look on  many-- a   countenance, and many alppeared dissatisfied not know ing wLat it- could mead. Twice they had   aome to have their curioslty satisfied and twi  e they had been defeated, They did not think Br. Fopsworth was      ^^  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC7995-00000027"/> tlhe man, to back ouit of anythntg like that, and how- mysterica it seem- ed. Whet the benediction-w as pronatoneell and the congregation had become a little dispersed, )1 waflked up, to the altar and in as mild a tone of voice as I could oommnand, told Br. ]opsworth I should go there no more to hear himn preach, liat beeecaue he had been to Mrs. Talka- tive's to stay all night, nor orlybecause he had wrongfully trented Mrs. Fairdealer,. btet because he had ordered me out of the pew, I felt that my presence was aot desired there. He then gave me such a look ,as I never sa^w expressed ia the countem nllce of' a humtan being before, and hope. I sxay nlever see it again, I believe he would like to' have trampled nme under his feet, and gnashed upon me with his teeth, for foaming with rage, he saidl, 4get out of my sig't, I never wish to set eyes on you again., you, have been trouble enoIugh to lme to-day, and you have xo honor. no religion and no ladly about you." "Is it right," I said candidly, 'kto. bring tihese things fiorward on the Sabbath, and give the accused no, chance to defend' themselves or be defended." He only repeated what he had said before and looked if possible still more revengoful., Just thein Mrs. Talkative came along to the altar, stepped up by my- side loolked up, to. me as innocently as onre whlo had never done,wrong, and asked me in the same milnocent tone of voice, if I hllought she had sined. I replied that it wa s nothini,) that concerned me, neither did I trouble myself-ibout it, but ollly 'wished to inflorn Br. Fopsworth of my mtain reason for going no mnore to hear him prealch.. She theni turned to Br. Fbpsworth iand asked him very kindly, if he would, go home with her to tea. He&amp; replied that it would not be con- yenient for him. to go that night, all d proliseod to call .the next day.-- Just then I happened to think we were mn,il;g quite a conspicious ap- pearance, and sruddeuly looked about mle, to see if [ could detect the eye of'anylonel resting pon us, and llwherever I looked in whatover- direction, a pair-of evil eyes were fi;xed ats contemptuously on me as, though I had- been guilty of crime. "What does she want to stir that utp again for'?" said one. "I should be ashamed of it." said another. Pleeling my spirits sink within mler I passed into the entry, I hardly knew how. Horses and carriages were standing about the door, and whileI was waiting for them to be out of the way, Br. Fopsworth came, atong, as he past by mie I took the liberty to tell, hiln that in his more, Calm and thoughtful moments, I hoped he would call to his, remem-. brance the last words he had ever said to me,. thinking it7 possible that some time or other he might be sorry for it. I wish you never to speak to me again," he said, and hurried out of nly way. It was with quick and hasty steps that I hurried home to Mr. Fairdealer's. The supper was waiting for melon the trable and at any other time would have tempted my appetite, but I could not eati and it remained untasted before me. The Fairdealer's both old and young were all eager to hpar-the result of the meeting, and before I had time to collect my thoughts to tell them, they had made enquiries all about it. In at. tempting to answer their duestions I barst into a flood of tears. Mr. Fairdealer only laughed at my weakness, but his wife with painful ,anxiet, piquirejt-what in, the world had happened to me, Rose showed,   some marks of sympathy, but declared it would take more than one minister to nm:ke her cry, she knew. Willie and tda who had kept by my side ever since I came into the house, looked pitifully upon me, and with all that tender compassion which is characteristic of childhood told me not to cry for that ugly miniister. Feeling that these was sympathy for' me though it was but from a child, a tender chord in my ,nature was touched, and my tears the more freely flowed. Findingdiit impossible to suppress my feeling, I sought a place where to weep.-- "O my God,' I said, "why are all these trials heaped upon me, is it -that I have sinned or is it the trial of my faith," and I asked for strength and fortitude to bear them. - When I had sufficiently recover. ed; command of myself, I passed into the sitting room where the fiamily were waiting anxious to hear what I was tabout to say. All the while I was relating these things there was an expression of triumph in the countenance of Mr. Fairdealer, 6"O you will yet have your eyes opened," he said, "fyou will yet learn that ministers can do almost anything." He also manifested consid- erable surprise, that when he commenced relating his grievances, he did not begin at the foundation and read the anonymous letter as he should. "I believe I can rest no longer," I said after duly considering these things, "until I go down to Br. Shiftings and learn that secret.. They have promised if any body's name rwas calleLout, that secret should be revealed. I accordingly went and found sister Shiftings allt 1dy to; start for a prayer meeting to be held in the back part of' the town.- Without cermony I seated myself by her side and told her I had come to learn the secret. "[I have no time to tell it to you now," she said, *'but step into the sleigih and ride ta meeting with us, and there will be more time to attend to that when we get home." 4"How could I set in my seatt," I said to Br. :and sister Shiftings, while we were on our way to meeting, and hear that which is false said about one who has always proved to be my friend, ,and not contradict it, had I done so. my conscience would have condemned me". Botlt Br. and sister Shiftings spake approvingly of what I had done, and said if Br. Fopsworth was a Christian he would certainly have to ac- knowledge to me. The meeting let out early, and in good seasbn I found myself once more by a warm fire-side at Br. Shiftings, and while. he was taking care of hs horse I tried to prevail on his wife: to reveal the secret be- fore he should come in, since in his presence, I sthoild not dare to listen to it. "I did not tell you that I would reveal it," she said, "nor can I ,do so.' "You gave me to understand that you would," I replied. "'Br. Fopsworth wrote to me last week," she said, "informing me that he should read the anonymous letter I wrote him, in public and tell its author, unless I should acknowledge to him. I immediately sat ddwn and wrote an answer back, telling him he was at liberty to do so. And since there had been so much said about it, I hoped he" would, but sa sare as he did, I told him what the consequence would be, and that  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC7995-00000028"/> * 54 ) the secret between' him and me should be revealed, but otherwise, I should say nothing about it.- He has neither read my letter, nor called out my name, and I must therefore keep my promise." "You said if any of our names were called out, that secret should be revealed." "Mrs. Fairdealer's name was not called in public," she said, "it was only before the few." Mrs. Fairdealer feeling somewhat disappointed, that I had not found out the secret, and also that I appeared less dissatisfied about it, then sle could imagine, expressed her determination to find it outherself. *"Don't be so troubled about it," I said, "I don't know as I have any desire to know more than' I do now, for we have already learned enough to convince a thinking person that the secret must be anything but good, for were it not so, Br. Fopsworth would not have called the members of the church together at noon, but in the afternoon would have read the anonymous letter, and exposed your names to the public. Therefore for fear of having the secret exposed, he could think of no better way to crawl out of what he hadd undertaken, than to call those members together in the lanner he did, knowing full well they would never give their consent to have it brought before the public." Mrs. Fairclealer then declared she woutd tell every one she could that there was a secret, and from that time forward both she and Rose as 'well as Mr. Fairdealer lost no time in circulating it abroad, until it ;became the regular buy word of the day. This so increased the hatred and envy of Br. Fopsworth's friends, that they met together and agreed to make an album quilt for his wife, that he might know there. were 'hearts in that place, that were not only ready to stand by and defend&amp; him, but hearts that sympathised most deeply in his wrongs, and) would ever remember. him as their kind and affectionate pastor. The ground of the quilt was to be of the finest white iirien, ornamented with the -nicest crinison silk, cut in the fornm of a tulip. This quilt was to be quilted in a room over the depot, where every one could have an op- portunity to witness the taste that had been displayed by the ladies of E, and admire the beauty of the quilt, In order to. secure as many squares as possible, they took their scissors and patterns to meeting with them, and spent their intermissions in cutting them, for 'those who had none.. Mrs. Talkative would have given a square, but Br Fops- worth- had not called. om t those names as she expected, nor would he consent to give her the, letter that sister Shiftings had written'hiim, and -she declared she would lave nothing to do with it, But Mrs. Newsey gave a square; and believe me sister Shiftings gave, a square.. But it was given to iregaii the favor of the people, yet the act was not ap' preciated; for so. strong Cwere their prejudices against her, they could see no beauty in her square.. ' Br. Shiftings had been seekinge subscribers for another minister, and - been: refued, unltil he had not only given it into the: hands of Bxr. Judgwell to see about hiring one, but was convinced that something lust be- done to secure the favor they had lost, or the coming year,. 'they could have no Methodist preaching in the place. Therefore out, ef poiey hee aiM his wife turned in. favor with Br, Eopsworth, andt one: )   afternoon sister Shiftings was seen riding with the minister ever to thei' depot to see the quilt. About this time Br. Shiftings happened in to Mr. Fairdealer's, and by the way of conversationa enquired of Mrs. Fairdealer if sh'hadfseen, Br. Fopsworth lately.       t The last time I saw him she said sarcastically, he was riding out with your wife, 'I rather thought he wanted to get another secret. Br. Shiftings: was just then helping himself with keen- appetite to- a warm dinner but when he received this answer from Mrs. Fairdealer, he seemed to lose his keen relish for the fbod, and the knife went heav- ily to his mouth. After stammering a long time however he said, Br. Fopsworth thought exceedingly hard of him for reporting what,. he did about the secret, until he learned that it was the injudicious course he had taken in this affair, and nothing more, for if he -Ihd persisted in what he had undertaken, it would not have been going according i to the rules of discipline, and that of itself, would have been sufficient to put him down from preaching. "You told my husband," said Mrs. Fairdealer firmly, and looking him full in the face, "that there" was a secret which no one knew but you and your wife. Nor is my husband the only one you have told of it, I can produce other men, and menof responsibility will come bfo- ward and say you have told the same to them.". It then occured to his mind that he really had spoken of it to; others. O how glad would he have been just then if he had never said anything about that secret, but the words had gone forth and he could not recall them. 'If hehad kept silent about that, his wife might have- been pardoned- for writing the letter, for it was the secret that then seemed the greatest barrier to their favor in the church, and instead of revealing, it, as they should, it seemed to be their great study to work oaut of it, and they fancied by so doing they should be more successful in forwarding the progress of" Methodism. "You promised," said Mrs. Fairdealer, "that if any of' our names were called out, that secret; should be revealed; but instead of that,. you sat in your seat, and listened to the abuse Mr. Fopsworth gave. Temperance, without saying a single word." Br. Shiftings after hamming a long time said, "Temperance didiOntgo( according to the rules of parliament, Br.. FOpsworth he said had always been used to debating, and saying what he had to say without being interrupted, that when he received those freqient interruptions from her  it embarrassed him so he 6ould make out no. story at all, and at last he lost his patience." Here I could keep silent no longer, and told Mrs. Fairdealer to say nothing more, since there was no satisfactionr in multiplying words with a person who had one mind to-day and another to-morrow. "I dont know what there is about me," he. said, "that I can't make any body like me. Irve tried to take neutral ground, and have offend.- e d the whole."  Then Rose notwithstanding it was very unbecoming in a young girl like her,. undertook to tell him what were, her idteas. of neutral ground.. It is not to be on one side, she said aad finding the. popular favo  ^  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC7995-00000029"/> 56 the other, pass over onto that, but to say nothing - on either side.'" Receiving this so unexpectedly from her, perplexed and agravated him still the more, and he said "Temiperance was very miuchl excited, so much so, that Br. Inquisitive thought she showed guilt, and that was the opinion of two or three others, who left their seats on accou nt of it." Soon after Br, Shftings left the house. AMeanwhile the quilt that was being quilted over the depot, came on bravely, as;,vany of the sister as could easily set round it, had quilted egch day until-it had been rolled up so many times it would have to be rolled up no more, and but one afternoon's work would complete the job, "I must see that quilt," said Rose when I had told her of this, 4'before it comes out of the frame," and off she started. The last stitches were being taken in it as she entered the room where they w were all congratulating themselves, that they had been thus successful in their undertaking. They- cast an evil eye at Rose, than glanced at the quilt, as much as to say see what we have done, and no thanks to you, not all the evil surmisings that can be heaped upon 3Br. Fops- worth shall induce us to lose our attachment for him. They did not asay that in so many words, but every appearance indicated it, whena with a proud air they went to work taking the quilt out of the frame. Just then Br. Fopsworth made his appearance, his eyes Were all sparkling with delight. All were captivated by his smniles, as he ad- dre;ssed them in the following eloquent strain. umWhen it is asked ine how I was regarded in E., I shall take them  to hiy residence, and show them this quilt, I shall read those names that are indelibly writ. ten there, and ask them what better recommendation a man needs to - show that he wds loved and respected in a place than that." All manifested, much regret that he was so soon to leave theim. "'How I wish we could have you preach to us another year," said one sister who had quilted on it every day since. it had been put into the frame and would gladly have gone to the extent of her ability to- wards his support another year. Just then Br.. Judgewell happened ins Rose saw: those sisters talki}gr with him., and saw Br. Ffopsworth tke him aside and talk with him iu an undertone. She never heard a woid1that had been said by any 'of them, yet her fears were greatly excited, that in some way or other, Br. Judgewell would be influenced to hire Br. Fopsworth another year, anid she watched the countenances of each until her vivid imagination told her that her fears would all be realized, and she came home all in o. perspira tiox saying ".I da believe that Br. Fopsiorth will cone back another year, I cannot tell you how much interest there was mani- fested: for hUim in that little room over the depot." The idea of Br. Fopsworth coming back another year was indeed Oppalmig to Mrs., Fairdealer.  It is altogether probable if he does," he said, "that he will continually be. seeking revenge, and probably go 4to, 1v,. and I. cannot endure the. disgrace: of it..' "You need not fear that I said, for Br.. Judgewell is a far seeing nman, and can, see at once,. what the result would be,- and though they nway be ever so, earnest in their solicitations he has. too, much judgment. X,  ield to, them w"     ,    57' Dayfs passed and Br, Fopsworth had left town, hiS friends. had gone with him to the depot, and taken the lastlingering look of him when Br, Shiftings came into Mr. Fairdealer's apparently iin great haste he was going to conference, Br. Fopsworth was to' be ordained and he wished to be in season to witness the solemnity of the scene. O my God I said mentally am I surrounded by intelligent thinking being5s, or is it all a dream, have the church thus far degenlerated, or was there never purity in her? Will she receive those in her embrace who are guilty of misdemeanors of which many who make no preteln- tionls to religion would shudder to, think. A chillness came over me,  placed my hand on my forehead, and found myself to be in a cold perspiration. So painfll were my sensations at that time, that I made up my mind to have nothing more to do with the church believing that by so doing I could live a life more exceptable'to God, and consequent- ly be, more successful in gaining heaven. -When Br. Shiftings reahed conference, to. his surprise Br. Fops- worth was not there. It was ascertained that having a sum of money enttrusted to his care to be devoted to one of our benevolent institutiolns and a large quantity of his grandfather's sermons from which he had preached ever since he had been in E., he had fled to Canadta, there to meet his loving wife. who had unbounded confidence in his -integrity, and having his recommendation to present, he could there be ordained  and by the aid of his grandfathler's sermons, could easily astonish the people with his eloquence, ,and with the magnificent quilt to show he couldt not fail of impressing the minds of the people with the idea that by all he wa;s loved and respected. This combined with the artfulness of his disposition, and easy graceful manner, wotfld secure for him a passport into any society. Titus elevated above the common rianks, manylll  a sincere follower of Christ would be led to reverence him as their superior, while they would pass by or look with indifference uporn a plain honest christian, whose life might be a life of unobserved use-' fulness, and who, walked hunbly with his. God. Notwitisftanding Br. Shiftings and his wife were willing to sacrifice ahnlmost aything, even principle itself, to secure Methodist preaching, their efforts were unsuccessful, and with a heavy heart he bolted I the door of the meeting house, and since then no sound, of prayer or praise hals been heard within its walls, nor is there to be, until they reveal that secret. These things were daily in my mind, and there seemned suoh an indiscribable wrong about them that daily they wore upon my constitution. A thick mit seemed to veil my mental vision, I could not look beyond the cloud and see' why God permitted them. Nor could I endure seeing Mrs. Fairdeal er look so pale and care/vorn, for since I had fallen into the same state of mind myself, I was but a poor colfobrter, and I resolved to leave the place, and seek once more my native home, where by mingling with those I had loved in other years, early associations might crowd upon my recollections, and thus in. a. measure chase from my remembrance the bitterness of my sorrow. "I cannot have you leave us," said Mrs. Fairdealer :when I had told her my intentions, and I need not tell you that I experienced equal pain, in being separated from the family, for if ever youe have suffered with   &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC7995-00000030"/> i f ,58  a friend, if ever their sorrows have become yours, you know how it unites our hearts together as the heart of one. Yet 1I packed mly clothes in my trunk, gave a boy a piece of silver to wheel it to the depot and after taking an affectionate leave of Mr. Faifrdealer and hi s wife, started, ccompanied by Rose, Wille and Ida, to take the cars. In passing by the house where aunt Charity lived, she ran out to tile road to nleet me, and droppedsuch words of kindness in my ear as were like balm to my wounded spirit. I wished fronm my heart I was as good as she, that I could be happy under any condition like her, and remembered the time when I thanked the Lord that my happiness was not dependent upon circumstances. yet my mind had become so affected by those evils by which I had been surrounded that I was strongly illn dlined to attribute Aunt Charity's goodness to her natural disposition and believe with Mr. Fairdealer, that she was born so. All admit there is a vast difference in the/natural disposition of people, and it is admitted by all, that many outwardly livebetter lives without it t an others do with it. True some have changed their course of life ,d become better citizens, but they may have learned that the course which they have been pursuing is productive ofmisery, while a caante of haic course would be productive of happiness, and who knows btt after all thatis allthereistoreligion. ThusI reasoned until L shuddered at MY Own thoughts and had reached the depot and heard the whistling. of the cars. Soon they stopped in front of the depot, and while the bag. gage was being'thrown on board I kissed Willie and Ida, gave one part- ig word to Rose and stepped aboard myself. Just as t'iey were starlt ing, I glanced from the window by which I was seated, to take the laust lingering look of those I was leaving behind. A  tear was tricklii r down the cheek of Rose, Willie and Ida looked sad and'seelnedl unwil- ling to leave the spot at their sister's request. As I gazed my eyed sight became dim by tears, and burying my face in my pocket hand kerchief I wept like a child, while with unceasing, velocity the cars were carrying me further and still further from those I loved with almost a sisterly affection, and from the place where I had experienced those deep and heart felt sorrows. Having related the story of my trials, i looked earnestly into tle face of nmy good Aunt, to learn if possible what place it had found in her heart. Tears had moistened those dark penetrating eyes of hers and giving me a look of mingled love and pity, she said, I weep truly on account of those evils, yet far more on account of your inability to bear them. To think that after having enjoyed the comfbrts of religion for a score of years, you should thus easily be turned aside. For a score of years you have listened to the instructions of self-denying ministers whose lives have been lives of usefulness and whose object has been only to do good in the church you have found your warmest friends, those who have rejoiced with you in prosperity, and in adversity have never forsaken you, but I,;Pe sustained you by their sympathies and their prayers.  Mr. 'airdealer klnows nothing from  experience of tile effiets of religion upon the leart, he has kept himself aloo frolm all religious influences and is a stranger to that deep fountain of love, that prings up from the depJhs of the soul purifying the affections and cans. *iyn th afetosadXus   Y . nng the heart to go out in love to all, even to those who are our bitterest enemies and has no means of judging except by the effect it produces on others, thus when he is annoyed by hypocritical professors, it'is hot so much to be wondered at, that he shouldf say there is no purity in the,  church, and no, divine reality in religion.' We are erring mortals at best, and nIany who would do good, find evil to be present with them. ,Look back upon your life and see if there have not been some incon- sistances in your conduct. Look at your own heart and see if the rise. ings of self have not sometimes-mared the beauty of your religion.- Because the church is not what it should be so far from being a reason why we should leave it, is a reason why we should remain in it to seek as much as in us lies to raise it to that high standard of moral purity which God requires, realizing we are not our own but have beenbought with a price, Could you behold the glory that awaits the believer be- yond the grave, you would account these light afflictions which are but for a moment as nothing ; or could you see the good that is to result from the patient endurance of trial, you would not be turned aside by the petty annoyances of to-day." "Remember" she said, looking earn- estly yet compassionately upon me, "we should not seek so much to be happy as to be good, and if this had been your greatest care, and your faith in God had been as strong as it should have been, none of these things would have moved you." There was something in the mild tones and gentle persuasive manners of my good Aunt, as she said these things that affected my heart, and I resolved by the help of God, I would rise above those trials which be. fore I had believed insurmountable, and a sence of God's unending love, such as for months I had not experienced took possession of my heart, and free firom sorrow as though nothing had ever troubled me, I trod once more upon my native soil, gazed upon its scenery which to me was the most beautiful I had ever seen, and visited the friends of my child- hood. THE MND. i    &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>