<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8018">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Travels of the De le Telle Family </title>
            <author>Thankfulla.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC8018</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2456</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Travels of the De le Telle family</title>
                  <author>Thankfulla.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Courier Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Buffalo </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1869">1869</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-06-08">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Travels of the De le Telle family</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8018-00000001"/>TRAVELS OF THE DU LE TELLE FAMLY LETTERS FROM EUROPE. BY THANKFULLA. BUFFALO BUFFALO: THB COURIER COMPANY, PRINTERS. 1869.    &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC8018-00000002"/>  PREFA C E. MY FRIENDS: After the urgent importunities of the Press and the repeated solicitations of Book Publishers, for a volume of the Travels of. our celebrated Family, my scruples have been vanquished by the indefatigable Bonner, who knows so well how to overcome obstacles. My repeated refusals to bring these letters before the common mind of a promiscuous people, arose from the knowledge that the untraveled public'cannot appreciate with the discernment of con- nosieurs, the refinement of nations and the specimens of art, which we have had the privilege of enjoying to an unusual degree. Mr. Bonner having finally appealed to my benevolence,-offered to give the profits ofthis work to some charitable object,-thus putting refusal beyond my power. I shall clothe this book in the simplest language, hoping that my own countrymen and women will be instructed as well as amused. The history of our famous Family is so familiar to the public,  that it requires but a passing notice. There are few who do not know how the sale of our sheep farm of forty acres placed us in afflue'nce, and made us the welcome guests of crooned heads and the nobility of foreign countries. The family in ancient times bore the cognoment of Dolittle, but upon our first visit to France,  &#xD;<pb n="4" xml:id="VAC8018-00000003"/> 4            PREFACE. we were- able to prove our French extraction, and found that the classic name of Du Le Telle, had been corrupted by the vulgar- isms of Americans into Dolittle. During our first trip of six weeks we visited all the countries in the known world, and with a tractability never equalled, some of the members of the Family became masters of all the lan- guages, both dead and living, thus enabling us to pass from one country to another, receiving the most -brilliant ovations and familiar greetings. Truly our fame had proceeded us. After our return to our own country time hung heavy on our hands, the climate did not agree with us, and we'missed the soci- ety and refinement which had been ours while abroad, and deter- mined to make a second voyage. The family consisting of our mother, the widow Du Le Telle, her two daughters-Remarkabella and Thankfulla, Aunt Stebbins, and Caleb, Jr., sailed on the twentieth of October, and after a pleasant trip of ten days, arrived in London, from which place my first letter is dated.  &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-5" xml:id="VAC8018-00000004"/> - L'ETTER PFRST-L;ondon.-"Our Mutual Friend CharIes.'-Page 5.   5' LETTERP FROM THE DU        E   'ELLES LETTER   FIRST. LONDON, Vobv. 2, 1868. DEAR FRIENDS: The next morning after our arrival in this place we received, at an early hour, "Our Mutual Friend," Mr. Charles Dickens, an acquaintance of our former visit; he having been informed of our arrival hastened to call upon us and escort us to some places of interest. He is a very simple, pleasant friend, and he has a great love of America and the Americans; but of course, he is vastly more grand in England, where everything is so much more mag- nificent. He insists on our calling him Charles, because he dotes on familiarity. The' first thing that attracted my notice, as we started on our walk, was the transparency of the atmosphere, enabling persons to see at great distance, and giving a person the idea of perpet- ual sunshine. London is quite a place; it has a great many chim- neys, and a great many brick; also some few streets, but mostly alleys. Regent street looks rather nice, and the Strand and Oxford are sometimes lively, but the people think and talk the most of the River "Tems," although, I think it looks larger to them at 'ome than it does to us, although small sized boats can navigate it. The "Terns " is the great glory of Charles. Here, he says, is one of the crowning glories of the world. "What are other streams to thee Limpid Lovely, L Tems!' Glittering on thy bosom Flash the watery gems,  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC8018-00000005"/> D6    LETTERS FROM EUROPE. Only with the ripples, Gaily, Flash along, Some poor lifeless feline Murdered for its song; Or some defunct canine, Proud of the tide he stems-- Swollen with the Glory Of dying in the Tems.' Pure and Lovely River, Let me quench my thirst From Thy scented bosom, 'Till I'm fit to burst.'" Here was a pause. Charles having given vent to his over- burdened national affection, was rather inclined to subside into himself. But while he was subsiding, we got a chance to take a view of the city from this point. Here everything bore evidenee of the characteristic fastness of the English. "We next visited Hyde Park--it is built mostly of grass and trees. The land is, I believe, owned by Mr. Hyde, but if was found to be unsaleable, aind so he lets the people ride and walk there. At the entrance there is quite a good sized statute that used to be owned by Mr. Wellington, and there was another big figure there that they told us was A. Killer. It was erected by the ladies out of guns and shooting irons. The English women are a great deal smarter than our countlywomen--to do such heavy work.   I think that Mr. Hyde must like farming pretty well, for I see he still keeps his sheep and cows pastured here. Well, I would advise him to hold onto it; he may be able to real- ize as much from his sheep farm as we did from ours. But on we go, hurrying on to the Tower of London. This was the work of William Conkrer; and his son, William R. Conkrer, has put a great many improvements onto it-and after a time they hired two splendid workmen, Thomas Becket, and Bishop Ely Longchamps, to finish it. Now it has the appearance of having been built a long time. A great many criminals have been con fined here, and they sometimes felt pretty bad too, for the jailer told us that they had many times washed the floors with their tears. But the place where William Wallace was shut up, I was   THE DU LE TELLE FAMI Y.  most interested in. He wrote a great deal of fine piano music during his incarceration, one of these being "Le Rave." No wonder the poor man was raving, shut up there. I suppose he must have stolen something. The building and its horrible sadness so affected us, that Charles insisted on our going directly to Windsor Castle, as it was near dinner hour, and Victoria would expect us to dine with her. After a charming ride we entered the garden of the Castle, and found the Prince of Wales waiting on the stoop. He escorted us to his mother, and after an affectionate greeting Victoria thanked us for the compliment which we had made her in coming to see her, and was delighted at the prospect of the information which she could obtain, in regard to America, from our own lips. She asked what we thought of Bunker Hill Monument, and we told her that we had always been told that the cemetery where it is was very pretty, but as we had never been in Florida, we must give her the impressions of others, instead of our own. She asked Remarkabella to tell her about Niagara Falls. She told her that it was quite a watering place; they had a good tavern, a big bridge, and a large paper mill, and she never heard of the water being dry. Again, she asked if we had ever heard the big organ of Boston play. Miama told her that she never allowed us to look out of the windows'when they went by-for organ grind- ing was considered a very low calling with us. Victoria expressed herself really charmed with our intelligence, and said that it was unusual for Americans to be so familiar with their own country, and after doing ample justice to the roast beef, plum pudding and brown stout, we spent some time in the royal apartments, exam- ining the gobbling tapestry, which seemed very much like paint- ings. Victoria. then insisted on it that we should all visit her in her summer residence, Buckskin Palace, and she wanted mamato sleep with her some night, as they were both widows and such good friends. The Prince seconded the invitation to us, and took us into the kitchen to see the preserves that his wife had been making up. He is quite proud of his little wife. Soon after this, we took our leave, "Our Mutual Friend," Charles, wishing to  &#xD;<pb n="8" xml:id="VAC8018-00000006"/> 8         LETTERS FROM EUROPE. visit -the Bank of England during banking hours. He deposits there. The Bank of England is a rather pretty building, and most of the English put their money there for safe keeping. It is very safe there, and very little of it ever finds its way out. As the met were not in a mood for talking, we went opposite, to see the Exchange, and although this is a great visiting place, we found ourselves the observed of all observers, and the extreme humility of all classes towards us, evincing the unbounded admiration of the people for us, affected our modesty so much, that we felt that we could stay no longer. . So, on we went to Westminister Abbey. This is the English burying ground, but I think it is not select enough. There is no distinction between poor and rich, high and low; poets, kings, soldiers, and all grades are mixed together. But there was some wonderful pieces of statuary on the tomb- stones, although I saw no pictures here by great artists. I thought the two always went together. Over in the poets' corner, we missed the name of Mr. Lord Byron.  We always liked his "Child Harry " so much. Shakspeare also lies here. He was -a first-class player, and some old-fashioned people read his plays now days. We noticed a great many other great folks' names, but did not see anything of Mr. Waverly's name, who wrote so many pretty novels; but among the Henrys, Richards, Charleses, ones, twos and threes, we found something for a little calculation. While we stood there trying to enlighten ourselves, a hired girl from Winsor Castle made her appearance, with a message from Victoria, offering us the coronation clair that stood in the Abbey, but, after examining it, we concluded that it was so old, that it would not pay for bringing home and repairing, when we declined taking it. She gave us our choice of the jewels deposited in the Tower. Remembering that we had an engagement to take tea with the Countess of Birmingham, who used to teach school in our district at home, we hastened back to the tavern, knowing that on the morrow we should be whirling away to the land of the Scots.   &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-9" xml:id="VAC8018-00000007"/>   THE DULBTELLE FAMLY.         9 LETTER SECOND. EDINBURGH, VOv. 7, 1868. DEAR FRIENDS: On our entrance into Edinburgh, we were saluted by the calls of the buss-man, "D'ye gang to the Red Lion '"Supposing this to be some sort of a show, Caleb, Jr., thought we had better go and see it. A red lion was certainly a new sight, and Aunt Steb- bins, who had not accompanied us on our first voyage, declared that seeing the animals in a country was better than any other part of the show; she had always heard tell that folks that went to Europe, always went to see the elephant. (By the way, we are getting tired of having Aunt Stebbins in our party, for she is so thoroughly American, that we are shocked by her vulgarity. She would insist that everything she saw arf eat in London was so "pesky poor, that she wondered Englishme could eat so much of it.") But to return to my story. The b-man drew up in front of a small house, with a painted , on the sign, when Aunt Stebbins exclaimed, "'You don't say you keep your lion in the house?"The man seeing her confusion said, "' Ye dinna ken by the sign at the dure, that it be the public house for mon and beast." "My dinner can by the side of the door! La sus! What do you mean? You must be dreadful observin', when you seen all my luggage was a bandbox and a portmanteau."  "Gang and tell your mither, my mon, that here's friends that wad tak a het supper," and, jumping up, he flourished his whip, and we entered the-best tavern in Edinburgh, We soon had a supper of oatmeal porritch and bannocks, and it being night, we thought we would not go out until morning. After sleeping very well, (for,- as Aunt Stebbins said, we were "clean beat out,") we enjoyed a breakfast of oatmeal porritch and bannocks, and started for Edinburgh Castle. This used to be the old homestead, and it is still standing on the land belonging to the Scotts. There was a pretty large family of them, and the boys were always quarreling, until the old man  &#xD;<pb n="10" xml:id="VAC8018-00000008"/> 10        LET"ERS FROM EUROPE. Scott settled it by taking all his jewelry and putting it in an old chest, and locking it up. The old man died soon after, and his folks forgot about the chest, until finally some of the English, who had got possession of the old house by means of a mortgage, opened the chest and found all the old man's jewelry. Since then, everybody that goes to see the Scotts, takes a good look at the jewelry; but I wonder that they don't have the stones re-set, for these settings are dreadful old-fashioned. As this was all we wanted to see here, and there was. none of the Scott family living there now, we thought best to keep on to the Palace of Holy Root. It is said that this Mr. Root was a very excellent man, and he had a daughter Mary, who married a Mr. Darnley, who was a jealous sort of a customer, and he killed a hired man of his, who was an Italian, because he thought that Mary liked him pretty well, and she taught him evenings to read and write and spell. Mr. Darnley was pretty mad about this, and so he came in one evening and tackled him, and pushed him into her aunty's room and finished him. They have saved some of the blood-spots and keep them for a show. Remarkabella says she thinks it is most too bad that all these great deeds should 'have happened in the old countries, because now our American pictorials can't have any "blood-and-murder" stories to illustrate. I think myself it wouldimprove their style somewhat to put something interesting in them. Mrs. Darnley had a great many convenient things in her bed- room, but I don't imagine she was a very good housekeeper, for everything looks as if it had never been cared for; but she did some very nice worsted work, and Remarkabelia is going down there some rainy day td take off the patterns. She can use Mrs. Darnley's work-basket instead of her own, it will be so convenient standing right there. Here there was a strange party of men entered, and we concluded to go down to see where Bob Burns was buried. He was a son of Bill Burns, and was a great flirt, and he wrote love verses to a great many girls at the same time; but he has got a very pretty tombstone over him, and the girl that he finally married had a good picture of him, which they put   I Q  &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-11" xml:id="VAC8018-00000009"/> LETTER SECOND--Edinbarg.-The meeting of the Clans.-Page I .   THE DU LE TELLE FAMLY.        " on the stone. Here are some lines of his, which have never been published out of regard for his wife's feelings. They were written to a girl in America after his marriage: Oh, 'Rusha I wad ye ken my love, Sae mickle and sae true, Ye wad gie ivry ither mon a fecht, 'Till Bobby could see you. In leaving this place we were filled with grandeur and inspira- tion at -the exquisite appearance of the Highlands. The farms here are the most productive in the world, the dwell- ings are beyond description, and the manners and customs of the people are elegant. Their dress is a little odd, the men folks wear frocks and long stockings, and all their clothes are checkered. They wear their hair in ringlets, the prevailing profession of the country being hair-dressing. There is no country equal to them in this respect. Every Scotchman understands curling. Their style of dressing the hair, explains the reason why the men wear bonnets; but with all their womanish arrangements, they are a ferocious set, glory- ing in the " kilt." Our landlady knowing the next morning would be our last in Edinburgh, invited the Bart family to breakfast with us. Air. Mac Donald Bart., " "t Pherson Bart., i" "1 Dugald Bart., " " Gregor Bart., accepted the invitation; the rest of the family being out of town. Our meal was a sumptuous one-a barn dare chucky, oat lmeal porritch, and bannocks. The company could not understand our haste to leave Edinburgh, but we explained to them that Caleb, Jr., had received a telegraph from Egypt, urging him to go there: right away, because Mr. Powers, the man we hire to sculp for us, has found in the catacomb, where he has been digging lately, a run-a-way Circassian slave, and he wanted Caleb, Jr., to come right on and tell him what to do with her; he could not work very well with that woman -there, and as we were paying him fifty 2  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8018-00000010"/> 12        LETTERS FROM EUROPE. cents a day and his board, we did not want him to lie idle long. Caleb, Jr., will probably be gone some three or four days, and we intend, in the meantime, to go to Dublin, and-from there te Paris, being in time to meet him there. Napoleon is all the time hurrying us up; he has written six letters to Ma in two days, urging us to be in time for the great ball at the Two Lerries. LETTER THIRD. DUBLIN, Nov. 9, 1868. DEAR FRIENDS: The first person we saw on our arrival was 'George Francis Train. he had just come out of jail. We knew him well in our own country. He used to tend sheep and do the milking for grandfather. He worked for his board until he got into, a love scrape, and the girl he wanted sacked him. This made him crazy, and he has never recovered from it. The people of Ireland feel great pity for him, and they let him stay wherever night overtakes him. When we met him, he was hurrying on to get to Phoenix Park. He was going to lie on one of the benches that night. We asked him to assist us in finding Mr. O'Donohue, and this he was pleased to do. So on we went up Sackvill street until we came to an alley, and there, standing on the head of a barrel, with his shellalah flourishing, was The O'Donollue. "Indade, and is that you, Miss Dolittle? The top of the morning to yese. I was givin' an, illigant address to the spalpeens-bad luck to 'em. But its glad I am to see ye, bedad. Its meself that knows ye for a good woman, and many's the time ye tould me, when I was down hearted, ' Cheer up, cheer up, Donny, and meybe ye'll be in the parlemint yet. Its many a   THE DU LE T VFJLTE J FAMLY.       13 poor lad like ye has come til Americky to git idicated, and when he wint back to Ould Ireland, he was hired imagetly by the par- lemint men.' And its meself will take ye to Dublin Castle, and its the Lord Leftenant will welcome ye, and to-morrow I show ye the pride of Ould Ireland." 'The morning came, and with it a long letter from Caleb, Jr., setting us into a fever of excitement. On reaching Egypt, he found a beautiful woman awaiting him, and then she told him that she was the daughter of the King of Circassia, but, being white, her father wanted to sell her to a Turkey man, and, she objecting, ran away and hid in the cata- combs, where Powers found her. Caleb, Jr., "loved her for the tale she told," and he determined to bring her to us, and if possible make her his wife. He wished us to hasten our visit in Dublin, but to be sure and see Dublin Tricks before leaving, and tell him that he was anxious to measure arms with him., We therefore decided to see all we could that day, and leave for Paris on the morrow. We visited Trinity School House and the Irish Bank. This is well patronized by everybody, for there is scarcely an Irishman but what owns his mansion. It is a very flourishing country, and the people love those in authority over them with devotion. Their rulers are very just and kind people. "Where is the blarney stone?"I asked of O'Donohue. "Sure, and its yoursilf shall kiss it, Thankfulla, my darlint, or I'll put myself in the place of it, if yese willin'. Ye shah niver take your pretty face out of Ould Ireland, widout it goes wid ye. Its meself will give it til ye. It has bin wid the O'Donohues for many a long' year, but I'll send it til Americky. It will be of more use there than it is in Ould Ireland just now, for it is losin' its virtue wid the Government men." I was sorry to say good bye to The O'Donohue; he is such ai agreeable man. But, true to his promise, he left in my safe pos- session, as a souvenir of Ireland, the blarney stone.  &#xD;<pb n="14 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8018-00000011"/> "        LE"ERS FROM EUROPE. / LETTER FOURTH. PARIS, NOOV. 12, 1868. DEAR FRIENDS: When we entered the depot, we were met by Napoleon and all his court. The city was alive with excitement; the bells were ringing, the cannons firing, and confusion was general. We intended going to the Grand Hotel, but Napoleon insisted that we should put up with him. He said Eugenie was expecting us, and she had put the spare room all in order.. The house was pretty well occupied just now with some of their cousins, that had come in from the country to go to the ball,. but he should give us the best places in the house, if he and Eugenie had to sleep up stairs. When we arrived at the palace, Eugenie stood at the hall door, waiting, with open arms. IShe looked very pretty and clean. She had on a white lace dress, with spangles on it, and white satin slippers. She kissed Ma rapturously, and was then introduced by Ma to her distinguished sister, Madame De Stebbins. We were ushered into the best parlor, and, after taking off our things, Eugenie took us into the 'dining room, and told us that if we wanted to wash up a little before dinner, we would find soap, water and towels in the other corner of the- room. We were glad of the chance,' and I washed my hands vigorously, not only because they were dirty, but because I had on a ring with seven big diamonds in it, that I bought of a pedlar for five dollars." I wanted this to shine pretty well, because I thought it was larger, than Genio's.  Pretty soon Napoleon came in, and we all sit down to dinner. We enjoyed our meal immensely, our, host being very agreeable. He objected to our calling him Napoleon; it was so formal. He would esteem it a great favor if we would say Nap; it was more friendly. After dinner, we strolled through' the apartments, noticing the new improvements. The whole house had been fieshy painted and whitewashed the day before our visit. We   &#xD;<pb n="-15" xml:id="VAC8018-00000012"/>    THE DU LE TELLE FAMLY.        15 spent the rest of the day alone, the remainder of the company being by themselves. When evening came, Nap wished us to sing for him. He said that the French were not a musical people, and he had not heard any fine music since we were there before. Would we please favor him with that national air, Polly Hopkins? At ten o'clock, we concluded to retire, and we were "shown to our rooms. Ma and Aunt Stebbins slept in the spare room, and Remarkabella and I occupied a cot bed in the Throne Hall. The room was -fixed up very pretty; a very nice lamp was hung in the middle of the room, ,and gobbling tapestry around it. We slept very well indeed, considering the strange place and the noise of the rats. We arose at six, and, after dressing, we met the family in the Hall of the Council. This room is good size; is hung in gobbling, and has some good crockery vases in it. The chimney piece was carved by Johny.- After exchanging the daily courtesies, we all went into the kitchen to wash. (This is the style with all the first families in Europe, and especially amongst the royalty.) While in the kitchen, Aunt Stebbins made a discovery. She saw one of the girls skinning some kind of animals, and she asked what they were. They told her squirrels, for soup, but she said they were the funniest looking squirrels that she ever saw. Their tails were long, and just like a file. She did not believe them creturs ever climbed a tree. During breakfast, the conversation turned upon America. Nap thought it the only perfect government in the world. He said it was his experience that hired help would always do better for you, if you let them do as they liked. He never believed in bossing much. Give them full license, and masters and servants were a great deal happier. He said he had heard that Andy had a good deal of trouble with his hired men, but he thought if he would give them a little more freedom, and let them express their minds just as they wanted to, that they would know their places and keep them better.  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8018-00000013"/> LETTERS FROM EUROPE. tie asked us if Victoria gave us anything when we were in England. We told him that she gave us our choice of the crown jewels of Scotland, and offered us the coronation chair. He said, " that was just like her, so parsimonious; he guessed she had a sort of a mean feeling towards us on Andy's account, but he should not wonder if that canal boat Alabama business stuck in her crop, and if it was him he would not pay her another cent on that. But he would not have anything to say about it; it was none of his business; and he despised meddling so much, that for that reason he declined having anything to say about the Mexican affairs.  He was afraid that Andy might feel a little putchy towards him, because he would not speak a good word about that Mexican Farm; but he thought that it might look a little like his wanting it himself, and he had already more farm than he could well cultivate." He asked us next, to tell him how our countrymen enjoyed themselves and spent their time. Remarkabella told him that our friends at home were rather * verdant and unsophisticated in such matters. That balls, operas, and concerts, and theatres, were things that the Americans knew i nothing about. . They had paring bees, husking bees, house warm- ings and general trainings; and in Chicago and New York, they sometimes have cock fights. Americans are a very rough people, and their style of enjoyment is equal to their appreciation. "Ah! indeed!" said Nap, "one would suppose them to be the most finished people in the world, judging from your illustrious family." "We   have become accomplished by means of our travels, and associations with the learned and royal of the old countries," -said my sister. (It was most fortunate for us that Aunt Stebbins did not under- stand French, for she has a bad habit of interrupting conversation when it concerns her own country people; whom she thinks, are the most remarkable people in the world.) Breakfast being ended, we separated to prepare for the great ball of the evening. Throughout the day, the brooms and dust- ers were flying; and before night, the house was in perfect order.   THE DU LE TELLE FAMLY.        17 Eugenie asked Ma's advice about serving the tea-table. She finally concluded to pass the tea around; and our dresses for the evening became the subject of attention for the rest of the day. The ball opened at six o'clock, by Nap leading in Madame Du Le Telle, followed by Eugenie and Aunt Stebbins, and Remark- abella and myself. Mamma in seal-skin dress, with embroidered flounce; Eugenie in white bobinet lace robes, with muskrat panier; Aunt Stebbins in tarletan-red, white and blue-(always retaining her national colors, and selecting cotton goods that will be sure to wash;) Remarkabella-the belle of the evening-in mauve chintz, and blue and gold swansdown ; and my humble self in "Gro de rNap," in honor of our host., Quantities of admirers, thronged about us, eager for the oppor- tunity of dancing with such celebrities. Lord S. remained near my sister the whole evening urging his suit upon her, in the most importunate manner. It is' true that lie is a married man already, but that does not signify in France, divorces are very easily obtained. Whether she reciprocated or not, remains to be seen in the future. The gay ball closed at eleven o'clock, and we dreamed until the morning of Counts, and Kings, and Crowns. But with the morning came the information that Caleb, Jr., and his fiance, would arrive the next day. Fiancy! what a pretty name, and how did Nap know what her name was. We were of course crazy to see this wonderful prin- cess. The next question was, how to receive her? At last we decided that dear Nappy should go to the cars, and we should all assemble in the Senate Hall in full dress, and be seated in order, so that on her arrival she might not be chilled by our formality. That subject being disposed of, we concluded to take a stroll through the garden, and see something of the surrounding houses. As we were leaving the house by way of the pavillion of Flore, we observed some large crockery vases; and speaking of their being rather pretty, Nap said: "You must not return to your own country, without visiting some of the potteries of Europe." 3  &#xD;<pb n="18" xml:id="VAC8018-00000014"/> IS      .  LE'RIERtS FROM EUROPE. Aunt Stebbins, understanding this in part, said: "Oh yes, the will just suit me; we've lived on soup so long, that I am starvir for a good mess of pot victuals. I was wondering the other daj if there wan't nobody in the country who could get up a biled dir ner. I don't care a fig for French cookin', and I shall be gla when we git there." Nap laughed delightfully, and talked of Aunt being interestin and eccentric; but I think, if shet belonged to any other familI than the Du Le Telles, her eccentricity would be called ignorance Nap has a very pretty flower garden, and their house is in a vert good neighborhood; and I think they must be quite sociable, tfo they have built on purpose a Place of Carousal, and a Place c Concord. Very near is the house of the Louvre's. They have very good museum in it, and possibly Barnum might buy it vert low, to add to his collection. A little beyond this is the hous that Louis Phillips used to live in. For some reason the neigh bors did not get along very well with him, and so they wen there one day and mobbed and destroyed the house. In the garden I saw a statue of Ulysses, but I do not think i, looks much like him. I guess the person that scalped it, neve: had seen him. I might detail very minutely the trees and grass, but it is mJ purpose to speak only of things which it has not been the privi- lege of other tourists to view. There is little to interest, in fact in the city of Paris. The population is so small that it will nol warrant any great outlay of expense, and yet the place is really more thriving than any other European city. France is doing a large business in importing, and their exports are principally French cooks; this will, in time, enrich them beyond estimate. The people of Paris have considerable manners, but no taste. It is a great pity that Eugenie should be so untasty, for the folks pattern after her quite a good deal. Our family has been of great benefit to her in selecting becoming habits, and in fact almost all the articles of her present wardrobe were dictated by some member of our family. Her chignon was a present from the   \ 1   *  &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-19" xml:id="VAC8018-00000015"/> LETTER FOURTH-Par*.-Caleb, Jr., and Guide, on their way to raden.-Page xg.   TIIE DU LE TELLE FAMLY.        19 King of Ethiopia by our solicitation. But why am I writing of fashions and follies; they are masculine and unwomanly, and we have at present enough on our minds to contemplate in the meet- ing with Fiancy, she who is to be so intimately associated with us in our future. Morning.-The hour has passed, and the greeting is over. We have found Fiancy quite interesting. Nap is really infatuated. I think Eugenie feels his neglect, but she says but little of course. Dear Nappy insists that we must have the wedding in Rome, and that the Pope must marry them. He is willing to accompany us there and give the bride away, if Caleb, Jr., will pay his expenses, Of course this will be the most distinga, and by a little financier- ing we can accomplish its Ma advises Caleb, Jr., to go to Baden-Baden-in advance of us-and replenish his purse, and then to meet us at Rome on the eighteenth. We will wear the same dresses which we wore at the grand ball. They are not known in Rome, and their elegance will make them attractive; it will be more economical too, which is quite an object. The bride must be dressed elaborately, of course, and we will borrow Eugenie's chignon for her. Caleb, Jr., must wear his elegant blue coat, and we will rub up the but- tons a little. It seems Nappie is somewhat of a hurry to get to -Rome.  He has business of importance with the Pope. (He is in no hurry to get rid of us, of course) and thinks it would be rAore agreeable for us all to go together. I think we shall start tomor- row. I shall not write again until we reach Rome. P. S.--This letter being from France, I wish you to remember that all of our conversation, while there, was in French; and I should have written in that tongue, if I had not always been opposed to the mixing of languages in books. I have ventured  it in English, thinking that it may possibly be understood; but, if it is not, I shall write-henceforth in French-entirely.  &#xD;<pb n="20 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8018-00000016"/> 20        LW'ItAS FROM EUROPE. LETTER FIFTH. ROME, -2ov. 17, 1868. DEAR FRIENDS: When we got to the Vatican, we found that the Pope had gon, out to make some calls. We therefore had some chance to loot about us. The house is built with wings to it, and, the Pope sleeps in the right wing. Here we found a great many interesting pictires A man who was waiting on us told us that he was glad that we came that day, for the Pope was feeling pretty well, and some times his health did not permit of his seeing visitors. We spen an hour very pleasantly before the Pope's arrival, and were sur- prised when a very pleasant face looked in upon us, and a pleasant voice said, "Thank you, ladies, for this unexpected but agreeable meeting. You do me honor, Napoleon, in bringing me the society of ladies. You are thrice welcome to the house of Pio Neno."' ; Nap then explained that the party had come all the way from Paris for the purpose of having the wedding ceremony performed by him. "And who is the bride to be?" he asked. "The fair Fiancy, the crown princess of the King of Circassia," Mama answered. "Only too happy," said Pio. "Remain with me until to-mor- row, and I will perform the service at St. Peter's." At eight o'clock the following morning, a wagon drawn by two Roman oxen made its appearance at the door, to convey the bridal party to St. Peter's church. When it became known that the Pope would perform a wedding service at the church, all Rome turned 'outto witness it. It was a gay scene, and one never to be forgotten in the annals of Roman history. Artists were there by scores, to paint us, and, for weeks after, paintings and prints were sold about the streets, illustrating the famous wedding.      d   "MTKll FIFTH-Romleo -Str Peter's Church--where the sledding Eeremony was per 'formed,--Page 20,  &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-21" xml:id="VAC8018-00000017"/> LETTER    FIFTH-Rome.-The bride at her toilet.-Page 21. /   'THE DU LE TELLE FAMLY.        21 When the services were concliuded, and we were about to leave this most beautiful church, Caleb, Jr., took out his wallet, to pay the Pope. He had intended to give him fifty cents, but Mama whispered that he had better make it a dollar, for he had done it up quite nice. We were glad to have Caleb, Jr., do the liberal thing, although at home you can get married by a justice of the peace for twenty- five cents; but I liked that service better, because you get more for your money, and it is more popular in foreign countries. We purchased of a celebrated painter here a picture of the wedding, which we shall carry with us when we return to America. The picture is in such demand here, that we paid for it the fabu- lous sum of one scudo. To-morrow we bid good bye to Nap, who returns with dear Eugenie to Paris, and we shall remain here for a day or so, to make collections from the works of art, and to improve our style of music somewhat. Fiancy is wonderfully gifted in voice. Verdi considers her superior to any singer in Rome. He thinks that she can perfect herself in the Italian language in a couple of days, and will be fitted for any stage. Last evening, we heard the most finished of Verdi's scholars perform; she had been singing for some time before I noticed her, and finally, hearing what I supposed was a scream, and hastening to the window, I saw Madame Torleni accompanying a hand organ. Verdi is justly proud of her. I asked him once why he did not send her to America; her fortune would be made at once if she were there. 1 I know that," he replied, "and I have six others to go with her. I am at present confining my attention to training and exporting organ girls; they most all of them secure a fine posi- tion, as soon as they reach America." But I must tell you right here of a note which arrived to-day from Leopold, insisting on our spending some time with him. We shall be obliged to decline this invitation, as I feel that I cannot deny myself the pleasure of climbing the Alps, and we cannot accomplish both.  &#xD;<pb n="22 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8018-00000018"/> 22         LETTERS FROM EUROPE, Oh Italia: land of the sunny skies, Chuck full of classic lore; Rich: for thy gems and arts Would fill a great big store. Could we forever rest, On thy pure snowy breast; Rain, hail, nor thunder pest, Could drive us from the nest. There is something about this country that is very inspiring; it is here that the Muse delights to make it her home; every new object of interest fills me with grandeur. But these rapsodies unfit me for the sober realities of life, and I must chop right off and proceed to business. We shall start for the Alps in the morning, stopping at Genoa to get some velvet. I will give an account of our ascent of the mountain in my next. LETTER    SIXTH. BERLIN, Vfov. 20, 1868. DEAR FRIENDS: We started at sunrise to make the ascent of the Alps, and when it was suggested that we should ride, Remarkabella and I objected, so the rest of the party concluded to ride, and we to walk. I'd rather walk ten thousand times, Than ride upon a donkey- And maybe if I'm cast away, I'll meet with some poor monk-ey. Remarkabella was sure that they had monks there, because they always had them on very high mountains. After a perilous ascent, and many hair-breadth escapes, we reached the summit of Mont Blanc. Here, under the influence of the wildest emotion, I wr6te these lines which I send to you, because they are considered superior to Colebridge's:   E - "  , LETTER SIXTH-Berlin.-Preparing to climb the Alps.-Page 22. k  &#xD;<pb n="-23" xml:id="VAC8018-00000019"/> G          i   THE DU LE TELLE   FAMLY.        23 High upon the tops I'm standing, Oh thou mighty, lofty Alp I With the wind and snows around thee, One might almost freeze their scalp. I have climbed thy lofty summit, Up thy sides I've found my way- But thy head is cold and stormy, I don't think I'd care to stay. I've no doubt the lightening flashes Wiggle round thy hoary head, And I'd rather you'd excuse me- 'Cause I have no feather bed. And perhaps the white capped cloudlets Have their fits of kissing you, But I've no umbrella with me And maybe I Id get wet through. So I'll leave thee, mighty mountain, Leave thee in thy glorious pride; And maybe when next I view thee I will think it best to ride. After we descended the mountain, we stopped at a Swiss house long enough to inquire for the Veil of Chamouni, and to take a look at the Shammy. The woman of the hut was gone out, and so we could not get a look at the Veil. Entering our velocipede, we started for Berlin, which we reached after a two hours' ride. I will state here that we have adopted this mode of conveyance, because we find it takes us over the ground with more speed, and indeed, you will see by the dates that our journey could not have been accomplished in the same time, in any other way. Here we are in beautiful Berlin. I am' sorry that America has never offered any inducements to the German people to emigrate to our country. They are such a fun-loving people that they would teach us how to enjoy ourselves.  &#xD;<pb n="24 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8018-00000020"/> 24        LE'lTERS FROM EUROPE. Of course, never having seen any Germans, you cannot appre- ciate what I say of them, but tley are very intelligent, and boast of their literature. We are staying at present with Mr. Bismarck, and I saw in his library this morning two valuable works, by their great authors, Goethe and Schiller; The Fair Sausage Vender of Saragossa, and The Red Robber of the Rhine Mountains. They are very readable, and a great acquisition to any library. The language of the people is very smooth and flowing, and easily learned. At the first outset, you encounter what are termed jaw-break ers; and after you are well through with the operation, there will be no further trouble. Having had our jaws broken, on our first visit to this country, we were of course under no inconvenience at all. The next morning after our arrival, Mr. Bismarck was cutting up some meat, and of course called it by its German name, "fleisch." Asking Aunt Stebbins if she would have some, she looked up with holy horror. "Be these the folks that the missionaries tell about, that eat each other up? Be these people cannibals? Dear me, I thought it was bad enough to eat frogs, and all sorts of things as the French folks do, but it is a dreadful sight worse to eat human beings." An explanation soon satisfied her that her life was not in dan- ger, and that she could eat without affecting her conscience any. Mr. Bismarck is worthy of his fame. We were very hospitably received and entertained. We had the great German delicacy, sour-krout, as often as we could wish it; and the softest of feather beds under us, and feather bags over us. I think this must be very comfortable in warm weather; how our own beds sink into insignificance beside these of the Germans. When visiting the Thier-garten, we pass through the Brandy- burg gate. On the top of this gate is a brown cart drawn by brown horses. I believe they run away once, and followed Napoleon to Paris; but they got them back, and they have not stirred since.   kM i: l LETTER SEVENITH--Venice.-The Czar taking leave of his wife to take Ma out on his hand-sled.-Page 26.  &#xD;<pb n="-25" xml:id="VAC8018-00000021"/> if--  i   THE DU LE TELLE FAMLY.        25 The Thier-garten is a great place for visiting. I was surprised to see so many beer rooms near it, as that is a beverage that is little known in Germany, and the people are not fond of it. I saw in this place a new kind of geese which are all feathers, and can be picked six times a year. I suppose that raising geese forms quite a prominent part of woman's work there, for I know that the women are delicate and not- used to hard labor. But I must hurry on to my description of Pottsdam; Mr. Bis- marck desiring that we should visit the house of the Great Fred- erick. Fred was considerable of a chap, or he made the folks think that he was. He was a pretty good house builder, and made quite a business of training dogs; he used to fiddle some- times, besides. Although he was a jack-at-all-trades, he must have died pretty poor, for his body was lying in a plain lead cof- fin, and never has been buried. His remains are in one of the Pottsdam churches, although the house where he lived was at San Souci. Fred was very fond of adventures, and he had a great reputa- tion as a fighter; and for seven years, he followed that profession almost entirely. There was a large barn back of the house, and we gave it a glance as we left. We spent last evening at a literary gathering, and refreshed ourselves with lager and bretzels; and when we crawled into our feathered nest, we felt sure that Mrs. Bismarck was in the goose business pretty extensively.  &#xD;<pb n="26 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8018-00000022"/> 26        LBrTEES FROM EUROPE, LETTER SEVENTH. VENICE, JbVv. 30, 1868. DEAR FRIENDS: Since writing my letter from Germany, we have visited,-by urgent invitation of the Czar,--St. Petersburg, and on our return to Italy, we took Greece in our way. I shall give you a short account of what we saw in these places, before closing my last letter from Europe. St. Petersburg is quite a growing village; they have a very large meeting house, and several other big buildings. The pOpu- lation are very united, and there is no distinction or cast amongst them-one man is just as good as another. We went in one day to see the Czar and his Court in session, and found that their manner of holding court was different from any other nation. They were living persons lying in state. It is generally very good sleighing there, and the Czar drew Mama around to see the statute of Peter the Great, on his hand- sled; the rest of us walking behind. As near as I can describe this statute of Pete, it is a very big man, on a very big horse, on a very big stone, and a snake under the horse's feet. It is all brown, and I suppose it is the efect of the weather. They have but very few shows there; and indeed I have not seen a circus since we left America. They have not any very good looking jewelry there, and the Czar picked out the best diamond, which he owned, and it was presented in Court to Mama; the Czar making the speech, and Ma responding; Mama sitting, and the Czar kneeling. It was a beautiful tableau. Greece.-We are more familiar with this spot than with almost any other. The people of Greece are very honorable and will rank among the greatest trades-people in the world. They deal principally in hogs, hair oil, butter, salves, candles, perfumery, Grecian bends, and statutes. I believe two men named Solon and Lycurgus made most of the statutes; we made a very fine collection from among them.   :4 - LETTER SEVENTH-Vcnice.-Diamond presented by the Czar of all, the Russias to Mama.-Page 26.  &#xD;<pb n="Illustration-27" xml:id="VAC8018-00000023"/> LETTER   SEVENTH--Ve#/ce.--The Dodge andRemarkabella yachting.--Page 27. '   THE DU LE TELLE FAMLY.        27 Grease has become almost a household word with our country- men, so familiar have we become with it; but I am sorry to see that this knowledge of Grease should have improved us so little. There are very few Spartan mothers amongst us. Venice.-Here we are visiting the Dodges, and enjoying our- selves immensely. They are very princely in their way of living, and of course we feel perfectly at home. Mr. Dodge has been building some very nice yachts, and he takes us out sailing very often; particularly Eemarkabella. :He seems very much smitten with her charms; as, indeed, who is not? I have often been asked if she did not take daily baths in the fountain of Perpetual Youth. I cannot answer certainly in regard to this, but if she does, it is on the sly. I shall not attempt a description of Venice until I have con- cluded my visit, and then I can write more interestingly. When you hear from us again, we shall probably be in Asia. Whether on Afric's sunny soil, Or Syria's tented plain, Or whether we list to the Moslem call, You shall hear from us again. 4   &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
