<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8373">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Edward Wilton, or, Early Days of Michigan </title>
            <author >Woodville, Fanny.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC8373</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Edward Wilton, or, Early days of Michigan</title>
                  <author >Woodville, Fanny.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >124 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >s.n.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1851">1851?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-10-05">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Edward Wilton, or, Early days of Michigan</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="" xml:id="VAC8373-00000001"/>Oose ' w  o     ,  .     t t  ,   -.'    .  *^ ' ,'            ' ,-  F'ur mlwyself, I ne+-er read a lplefae, excepit tiioe to Scott's -tove1s; ; "ut as tit-te, differ iln tlin?, as in all othler latters, I rrill ventutre a few , Z lines in .- xplnatioll of this little tale, Bfr the eulightment of those whto ch]oose ,^o lnow soainething of w-lhat is offlred to them in the follolrin ,)a'gt's, 't, etndl..I those pages are so fortunate as to fiind any readers.,  I', i's I I.;iloned inLanman't,1 s "History of Michigani" that ayoung, man, -who, :;tld ,I,: I n stolen by the savages in early childhood, and lbrought lp as th- son of a powefil chef, without the least ]knowledge of. his real ,11 hom :.nl i indled, becamle, when he had reached ann age to think -  for Jiiiii-t, (I-^,iions of leaitinvl the .Indinis i, and rejoiing his own-  pe(')ioe. ' lid -so, withl the reluctant consent of liJs red father, and  joiinll' :tr 'my, speedill distinguished himself by his italentsi and n  b)braver'y, \.:i-}l- hLe ]11mad. hi]isi(elf exceeedingly usIi(efulI by lis intimate nowle dgo , .idi:an chllaracter and halbits, as the wn - of S18i was, . 1-! tlen apploaching, and the savages along o-(or wes;tern frontier grew ' ' ldailymore troublesome Rand .iholent.      '  .- . -[e was, sme t with a small detachment to. secure the safet reteat: of a. prll of ttroop, ( and1 some families, ifom whe ort hp Where. Chi, c^ now stan its; and Mr. LAmarnllny - rxaC ta.1 t, ...r;1 -- .::t  and enutriati:s been regalrded by' the comlmllnding officer the lanea- '  ble massacre, which followed the e'taetatid lv -,tl .  W: t,::WtCld lhavie ' been avoidel. In despair at the h]orrors which he found himseilf un.-i:; ' 1le to avert, he thlew himself into the thickest of the fiAght, andm ;..  his death at the hands of his early companions.      -/ t I have ventured in the conclusion to deviate somewhat from the!e lrti -  of history, and throughout the work, to alter times aid Plal I  will only. add that I am indebted to Mr. Lanman's veryiiesti ng.  "History of Michigan" for the historical part of my tale, and request. ; the ind ence of the public for all faults and defciencies.* - - * a l?O ii,&amp; 18-i,   FANNYE  WO-ODVI    :. -   f KALAf U .zOO May, 1851. * F-AN',                       ' ", ..   . V' "  ?....    &#xD;<pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8373-00000002"/>   EDWARD WILTON, OR, EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN. CHAPTEA I. Fon many years after the English had relinquished the .possession of the military posts of Michigan, which were then almost the only part inhabited, except by Indians, little or nothing was known of the iuterior of the Peninsula. The dead level of the swamp, extending as far bare as the eye could reach from the top of the Fort at Detroit; thheoldd rocky Island of Mackinaw, gave no promise of the loveliness:w, ch] awaited those, whose courage and perseverance led them to penetrat the forbidden wastes, upon the Lake shore, and aloIg thk Detroit andt St. Clair rivers. The Indians, feeling that the ignoranot of -the;-XW man was all that preserved to them their beautiful prie,etheir- clw' streams, and their park-like woods, were careful to keep bhim sth'...l ror; and the few hunters who gained wealthfrom the ValUablef0irs:whi .h they collected in this region, represented it -as evyen nmoe Wild'and des0o late than the frontier, that no others might be induced to: seek the k mode of enriching themselves. The generation of warriors who had fought by the side of Pontir: had nearly passed away, but there still remained some aged meti,i w . had first trodden the war path and lifted the tomahawk under th'eguid.  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC8373-00000003"/> 6   -         EDWARD WILTON, OR ance of that redoubtable chief, and his deeds, were still the falvorite theme of tale and song at their feasts. The hatred w'hich the Ottawa chieftain had borne towards the Eng- lish had been transferred by his descendants to the Americans, when the stars and stripes of our nation took the place of St. George's IRed Cross on our western frontier forts. The secret emissaries of the Enlglish na- i tion, spared neither pains or presents to foment this feeling of dislike, and in consequence, our military stations resembled isolated fortresses in a hostile country, rather than forts for the protection of our own territory. 'This mutual distrust between the Indians of the Peninsula, and the Americans, prevented the early settlement of one of the most beautiful portions of our Union. Only a part of what now forms the State of Michigan had been ceded by the Indians, and the forest %warriors were not neighbors so desirable as to tempt even our enterprising pioneers to fix their residence very near them. Our Indian affairs were in this unsettled state, when rumors of an ap- proaching war between England and America, caused a strong sensation through the country generally, but far deeper and more fearful among the' inhabitants scattered along the fioonlltier. The Indians, by the daily increasihg insolence of their manners, and occasional allusions to the time when the hated American shouldbe driven again to the se* shore, showed that, they were prepared to take part in the conflict, and the hor- iors: of Indian warfare were yet fresh in tie memory of all. Among those whose hearts sunk at the prospect before than, none felt greater agitation and distress than the family of Mr. Wilton. For Miany years they had resided on the banks of the River Raisin, or Rosine, asith is called in some of the early French treaties, in a small settlement of French fur traders. Their original reasons for preferring this remote and dangerous place of abode, to the more secure neighborhood of the Fort at Detroit, they had never given; and they remained there,in spite of the increasing danger, though they had already suffered deeply rfom the aggressions' of the savages, who, fourteen years before, in one of their visits to the settlement, had, as was supposed, carried away withe them little Edward, abeautiful boy of six years old. Some fancied insult- from Mr. Wilton had provoked this revenge, the deepest and most bitter that could be devised, and from the day of his disappearance, his wretch- ed parents had been unable to fain any tidings of him. No one had   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.           il seen the Ilndians take the child, and some thought that the little' fellow had wandered into the woods by himself, or had fallen into the river. For days the kind hearted Frenchmen at the settlement assisted the father in his search in the woods, or endeavored to find the lifeless body in the river, but all in vain. No trace could be found of the beautiful and affectionate boy, whose winning ways and fearless spirit had made him a general favorite, and it was with heavy hearts that they at last gave up the search as fruitless, and returned to their homes. The Indi- ans had committed no other aggression during their visit, and at first few thought of charging this upon them, but andId Frenchman who had stood by Mr. Wilton when lie thoughtlessly questioned the veracity of the chief of the party, had noticed the fiery flash of Sagito's eye, and seeing that he was silent and moody duriig the remainder of their stay at the settlement, at once dgclared his Wlief that Edward was-still alive, though in the hands of one of the most -wailike of the forest chiefs. sYou maye your fair boy yet, my friend," said the old man, "'Sa- gito is not often cruel to children, though a great brave in-his nation, and hirevenge towards you will be as completely satisfied by carrying away your little Edward as by killing himn-if you can only keep Madam Wil- ton from  dying of grief;, as she seems likely to do, you may bothllb so happy as to see youl' son again."   -        .  Monsieur ])uval was right.  Edward was indeed a prisoner to the savages, and proceeding with them  by rapid marches towa-the inte- rior of the State, where we will follow him in another chapter.;' *   -. , -' i;   &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC8373-00000004"/> 8           EDWARD WILTON, OR CHAPTER II. j/ Mr. Wilton's was the last house which the savages ware obliged to pass in leaving the village, and as it stood much nearerl/he forest than any, other, there was less difficulty in the capture of the child than might have been supposed. Sagito led his warriors from the settlement with a slower step:than usual, and as they approached the house of Mr. Wilton, he said to the Indian who was nearest him, "The pale face told Sagito that he lied; shall Sagito carry the scalps- of his squaw and children into the forest F" The warrior only replied with a grim smile, and altering the positionl of his tomahawk a little, turned from the trail they were following to- wards the cottage, but before he had taken more than two steps, Sagito laid one hand on his arm, and pointed with the other to a large tree near them, under which, lay Edward Wilton in a deep slumber. Sagito had frequently seen him in his visits to the village, and at once recognized the child, who had pleased him by his fearlessness, when the other chil- dren of, his age wept and trembled at the presence of the red man. It was in June, and the little fellow, wearied and heated by play, had thrown himself down in the shade and dropped asleep. \ His bright brown hair, curling all the more richly for the warmth of the weather, was pushed back from a forehead of exceeding whiteness and beauty, and his long black eyelashes rested on a cheek of the richest bloom.- One little hand pillowed his head, and the other grasped -a cluster of wild roses which he had gathered from a bush that twined around the tree, and which in its luxuriane of bloom and beauty, seemed to shed a rosy glow over the sleeping child. While the savages gazed, some pleasant dream seemed to pass through his mind, and the smile, that stole over his small rosy mouth, deepened the dimple in his cheek. He was a study for a painter, that fair boy, as he slept all unconscious of the dark looks bent on him, and though the party paused but for a moment, iomething softened, or, at least, altered Sagito's plan of vengeance.   EAXLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          9 "We will leave the scalps," said he, " but the white man shall look in vain for his child when he comes home," and as he spoke, he lifted the sleepingr boy carefully in his arms, and satisfying himself by a glance that he was not wakened, went on with a quicker step, and followed by his party they soon disappeared in the woods. They had proceeded silently and rapidly on their way for more than an hour, and were already several miles from the village when Edward awoke. As he roused from his sleep, and met the gaze of the Iindian Chief resting steadfastly upon him, he passed his hands across his dark bright eyes, as if to dispel some troublesome dream, but when he remov- ed them, and still saw a face so different from the one wlich had always till now met his waking, the look became wilder, and as he endeavored to spring from Sagito's arms, he exclaimed: "Where is mamma, I want mamma. Sagifo, is it you?" l{e continue-  ed as he wakenied more completely, " oh take me home!" The warrior retained him in his grasp with but a slight exertion, and replied with a more gentle tone than he generally used, "The homes of the pale faces are far behind us; Sagitoe will'take the boy to his lodge tand he shall be a great brave."'      - "I do not want to be a brave, and Imust say my prayers to marmea, and sleep in my own little bed; no, I cannot go with yoi," said ,the child, but his voice trembled, and his lip quivered as he spoke, and when he heard the calm, stern reply, "The boy will go," he burst into bittier tears, and his fibs were so violent that more than one tomahawk was lifted, as if death were the easiest mode of stifling the grief of the little sufferer; but his captor had other views with regard to him. "The child shall not die," said he to those who had made the-move- ment; " there is a vacant place in Sagito's lodge, and the lip of the child- less mother shall smile again when he gives her the young eagled-eyed boy." A single word of assent was the reply from the Indians, and the-C hief continued in English as he placed Edward on the ground and took hold of his hand, "' Will the little one show that he is worthy to be the son of a great Chief? let him dry his tears, and walk with my young -men, and not whine like a sick girl."  The sorrow of the poor child, so rudely torn fron all that he knew or loved, was not, however, easily control0led;- e               , * I " '  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8373-00000005"/> 10           EDWARD WILTON, OR and he still wept bitterly as Sagito led him along in silence, but with an effort to accommodate his pace in some degree, to the strength of his young companion. They soon reachlled the bank of a small, but clear and beautiful streail, tvhere they evidently intended to encamp for the night. The suni had not yet set, but it had sunk so low that it was invisible to the wanderers, though a few level rays pierced the forest. coloring the still stream like molten fire, glittering the tomahawks of the savages, and giving a golden lustre, like a glory to the brown curls of the little captive. "See," said one of the warriors, " the Great Spirit smiles upon the young child." The Chief turned and touched the boy's shoulder.- The Great Spirit will hear his son speak in the woods as well as in the house of the ile face." r,  Edward gazed"t him for a moment before he comprehended his mean- ing, but Sagito spoke English readily, and when he repeated his words, the little fellow knelt at the foot of the tree where'he had thrown hiim- self, and recited the simple and beautiful prayer which is taught to child- hood wherever prayer is heard, and which he was never more to utter, as had been his wont, at his mother's knee. His voice was broken by sobs, but the Indians listened silently and with reverence to what they knew was an address to the Father of all, although to most of them it was an unknown tongue.' A fire was now lighted to dispel the insects; their simple meal, of which Sagito in vain offered Edward a portion, was neateri, and preparations made for slumber. Sagito had fastened one end of a deer-skin throng around his captive's waist, and held the other in his own hand, to prevent the possibility of an escape; but it was un- cessary, for the child, awed by the darkness of the forest, the melancholy note of the owls, calling to each other throughlthe gloom, and the feel- ing of, novelty in every thing, nestled close to the warrior for protection, and ere long, with the blessed privilege of childhood, forgot his sorrows - in a sleep as calm ashough he still rested under his mother's eye.   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          1 CHAPTER       III. The early morning found the party of warriors with their little com- panion, still bending their course towards the northwest; sometimes keeping along the bank of the river, but with that love of directness which is almost always found to characterize an Indian path, occasionally taking a more direct course through the forest. Edward still mourned. for his parents, and at times entreated to be taken home, but the Indians, who already regarded him   as the son of their Chief, treated- him with kindness. Naturally gentle-to the children of their own race, and none of them, with the exception of Sagito, having had their evil passions brought into play, they endured the little fellow's bursts of grief with more patience than a party of whites might have shown under the same circumstances. One or the other would carry him    when he became weary of the continued march, andwhen rested and refreshed, he was again on foot at the side of Sagito. So much that was new and beauti. ful met the eye of the young traveller, that for awhile his grief was half forgotten.  it is difficult for those who have never seen the Michigan woods in the  leafy month of June, to imagine their beauty. Every sense is ap- pealed to and gratified at once. The large trees, placed at such distances from each other that every graceful bough is fully revealed to view, cast their waving shadow upon the turf beneath, which, free firom the tangled underbrush so common in eastern forests, presents a surface of the richest reen, enamelled with flowers of every shape and hue. Some of these ise almost to the size of shrubs, while others are scarcely taller than t'he soft grass among, which they bloom. The delicious strawherries, glow- ing as if a shower of rubies had fallen among the blossoms afford both perfume and refreshment, and the trees are filled with iusic from their feathered inhabitants. Can we wonder that the Indian, depending so much upon external impressions as we know that he does, should have felt this to be almost a paradise, and have resisted to the last the fate  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8373-00000006"/> 12  '         EDWARD WILTON, OR which is gradually taking from his grasp all this loveliness, converting it into unshaded fields, and deforming it with the ungraceful, houses and barns of the white settlers? An older prisoner than our little hero might have found some conso- lation in the beauty that met his eye as they traveled day after day in this picturesque wilderness; now following the course of some clear bright stream, now skirting around the shore of some crystal lake, with miniature bays and promonotories,- where the forest grew down even to the water's edge, as if it loved to see itself reflected in so fair a mirror, and anon crossing one of those beautiful little prairies which abound in this region. Edward would gather the flowers which bloomed in myr- iads along his path, and carry them till his eye was caught by some of a different beauty; he saw the doe, with her young fawn by her side, startled by the\ sight of human beings, bounding deeper into the forest, or a brood of young patridges would fly up from before his feet. All appealed to the happy and volatile nature of childhood, and drew his thoughts from his own sorrows. When they halted at mid-day or eve- ning, he made baskets of the enormous grape leaves which drooped from the trees around them, and filled them with the crimson berries that grew in sucl4 wild luxuriapce amonig the grass; and when one day, they came suddenly on a lovely little lake, with a brood of young wild ducks floating on its glassy surface, he uttered an exclamation of delight, as gay as had ever burst from his lips. Occasionally, the party would pa, the night in some friendly Indian village, instead of encamping in i*e open air, when Edward-was consigned to the care of the women, while the warriors smoked together in the lodge of the chief.- He was an object of no small curiosity to both women and children, many of whom had never seen a white person, and hearing of them as a rapacious, and cruel race, whose only object was to drive the Indian from his home and the graves of his fathers, that they might take possession of the beauti- ful country he inhabited, they naturally associated them in their own minds with all that was terrible and repulsive. But the extreme beauty of this child of the pale face, delighted no less than it surprised them; and when they saw him kneel at night and reverently repeat his little prayer, awe was added to their admiration, and they regarded him almost as a being from some higher sphere.            .,  o    EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         13 The fifth day of their journey had nearly closed. Early in the day they had reached and crossed a river, clearer and more beautiful than that on whose banks Edward had been accustomed to play, and running 'toward the west; but before the sun had quite sun'k, they came to an abrupt bend in the stream, which here took a northerly direction. On the opposite bank of the river, scattered along a level plain and over a beau- tiful bluff, which rose not quite a quarter of a mile from the water, were clusters of Indian huts. The women were many of them attending to their rude gardens, and the children were engaged in various ways around them,] but when they saw the forms of Sagito and his warriors advancing from the forest, a shrill shout of welcome and delight was sent up. This was new to Edward, for in the villages they had passed the visitors were received in respectful silence by both women, and children, and as he turned his dark eyes inquiringly to the face of Sagito, the chief said to him: "It is the home of Sagito, and the young Eagle Eye shall learn to paddle his canoe in the waters of the Kalamazoo, and hunt along its banks, till he is old enough to go on the war parties of men."  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8373-00000007"/> "          EDWArD WILTON, J)R  i.      . , 'CHEAPTER     IV. Edward Wilton was. soon formally adopted as the son of Sagito, and taught to consider himself as belonging to the tribe. Too young by many years to commence his education as a warrior', lhe was left entirely to the care of Nadesha, the young and lovely wife of the chief. Her only child, who would have been of Edward's ag)e lhad he lived, they had lost nearly a year efore; and from the time of his death, Nadesha had seemed to grow more and nmo're jistless alld depressed. SShe still pursued ]her daily duties, from whichl no circumstances excuse an Indian womanl, but the low song which flowed uncoinsciously from htr lips, .as she wrought her husband's moccasins, o .weeded the corn which was to foirm their winter store,'was heald noha onger, and the laugh. ali osft at musical as the song, seemed hushed for ever. "The soul of Naadesha has followed her; bov to the sweet southl-west," said one of,the old Indian women: "Nadesha herself with soon follow."           ' B,ut after her warrior husband had led the little captive into their lodge, and said: "Let the heart of Nadesha be comforted; the young Eagle Eye shall be to her like the son whom the-Great Spirit loved too well," she roused in some measure from her apathy, and though she could speak no En- glish, and her adopted son could not yet make himself understood in her langruage, they continued to holkcsome communication. Nadesha spread the soft skins fir his bed, she placed before him the most tempting fruits, the most gayly wroulght mocochs of maple sugar, and 'the sweetest of the corn cakes, and she covered the moccasins which she made for him with the richest and most fanciful embroidery. As the summer wore away, the wife of Sagito regained much of her forimer cheerfulness.' Her voice was again heard with some of its old gaity, and at times her soft darkieyes flashed with mirth, but the cloud which had darkened her soul never entirely passed away, A pensiveness, like the haze of the t    EAPRLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         15 Indian suinnler, which softens rather thln o'bscures the sun, remained to mnark the change in her whLo had been the gayest of the forest maidens. But thfl little Edwarld, or Eagle Eye as he had been named on his adop- ,tioll, could always bringl the light to her eye and the smile to her lip. The child lhad not yet ntirely forgotten hs own early home, but day after day his impressions became more and more indistinct, until the memory of lhis own fair mother, and indulgent father, his brother and his lovely sister, was like the. recollections of another state of existence. He was never called by the name which he had heard from their lips,. and as lhe improved in his knowledge of the Indian tongue, Sagito grad- !lally ceased ;pi)eaking to himl in English, a language which the red man will never use if he, can avoil it. Separatedt from eve-ry thing which, could keep) alive in his memory the banks of the Ia;iisin, and the faces, which halld ance siled on him there' and. treated withl unv-arying kind- n11s in lis new home, it is not to be wondered at that the' childogradually. assimilalcted lhinself to the llabits and mn-ners of those among whom his lot was c:tst, and tooSk his share in the amlusements of the Indian lboys of his age, or assisted his new mother in her lihter duties, with as Dgayl a heart as ever beat in the bosom of childhood. Toogether would he and Nadesha skiIn over the clear waters of the Kalamazoo in their frail but graceful birchen boat--nor was it long ere he' learned to guide the slioght canoe as dexterously as his companion. Together in the summer - they roamed through the woods in search of berries, or the materials for dyingr the gay hues hch the Indian loves, or in the autumn soug ht the marshes for their winter store of cranber- Mies, or gathered up the nuts which the frost had loosened from their husks. As he grew older, no arrow was more certain than his to bring down the bird or squirrtel at which he aimed, and none of his companions so successful as he in catching the fish which are so plentiful in the Kala- mazoo and the Lakes in its vicinity. That part of the tribe of Indians to which he belonged; still resided chiefly on the banks of that fair river where, at that early period the foot of no white man had ever intruded and for some years from the day when he last kissed his mother, and -bounded  ' gh the open door of their cottage, Edward Wilton had never seen a white face, except as his own was mirrored in the tranquil C river or some glassy lake.  He knew he belonged to the' race, which all '  I ' -'! '  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8373-00000008"/> 16          EDWARD WILTONX OR around him seemed to hate, and some glimmering recollections of another state of life would at times pass through his mind. In his early child- hood, every question 'which he asked concerning his home, had been unanswered or studiously evaded, and he had gradually ceased to inquire -or wonder why he was the only pale face among all he knew, or why he was loved or cared for, when he heard the fiercest invectives poured forth against his nation. It was enough for him that-he was the adopted son of the bravest chiefs of the Pottowatomies, that he was occasionally allowed to accom- pany the younger warriors in their hunting parties, or listen with them to the tales of the older ones around their Iwinter fires; and when Sagito, on his return from one of his long absences, gave him a superb rifle, and with it permission to hunt when he pleased, adding a hint that ere long he should aim it at nobler game than the deer or the wild iat, the happi- ness of the young Eagle Eye was for the time complete.  O                               .   EARLY DAYS IN MOTHAN.        i C HA PT ER V. For some time after the disappearance of our young hero from his home, the grief and anxiety of Mrs. Wilton were almost ovarwwhel h -n Her fevered imagination represented her son 'in every possible Hateof suffering, and at times her husband teared for her reason, no .lessS 4 for her life, and he wished to remove her from the place whiaoh ad ee the scene of so much misery, but she clung with a sort oardOSsplring. fondness to the home where she' hadfltseen h/beautiful yv :ven the door through which he had passed when le ieft tihe huse forAbe last time wms hallowed in her eyes, and when Mr-Wilton proposed t returned to their eastern home and. friends, she would reply, *"No, Arthur, if we leave here, we leave the last hope of hearing what has been the fate of our child. Now, we at least have the wretched comfort of questioning the fur hunters who come from the interior. ; We can ask them if they have seen the bones of a young child bleaching in the forest, or if it be possible that he is still alive, and among the fearful savages, may not some of them have seen him?"        ; Her husband at last acceded to her entreaties, and determined to remain where they were, for he too, felt thatithey weore more likely to gain tid- 'ings of Edward there than any where beside, and the kind' rophecy'of old ifonsieur Duval had more weight With lim thanhe diared acknowl- ede to himself    ' .  "             '  ' Months and years rolled away, and brought no solace to the bereaved lparents.' Every trapper who came-in was eargerly questioned but one had seen the -issing one, With the iapse of time Ars. Wiiton became mote calm,and devoted herself to her two remaini n children with ai . intensity of affection and anxiety, hicih is perliaps knovn only to those'  who  have had a part of thei tieasues. taken' frotm'th m"': S he could scarcely endure to have 'them away from heri own eye, and enl Pli who was a year or two older than the lost Edward, began to join' in 'hl  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8373-00000009"/> '1 8         EDWARD WILTON, OR boyish pleasures of his companions, the struggle in her mind was terri- ble. She would not debar him from the sports natural and proper to his agre, and yet she never saw him leave the house with his fishing rod or rifle in his hand, that she did not count the hours and minutes -till his rnturn, and teel almost surprised when he would bound into the house, loaded with the trophies of his successful sport. Philip Wilton remembered his brother well. He remembered that thley had been playing together on the very day, and it seemed the very hour, of his disappearance, at s cme distlruce ficm tleir father's house and that Edward had proposed they should go in and rest, but he had refused, preferring to continue his employment. "Well," said the youngrer one, "1 will go in and ask mamma -to tell me a story, and gather some roses at the great oak tree as I go, and when it is cooier, I will come and play with you again." ' He turned to go toward the house, and Philip continued his occupa- tion for a while, then wearied of the lonely sport, went to the house to find his brother; and this had been the last that had been seen of the little one. Bitterly and often had Philip reproached himself for refusing his last request, for he thought, and he knew his mother felt, that Ed- ward's fate, whatever it was, might possibly have been averted, had he, the older and stronger of the two, been with him. But this feeling was never mentioned in their many conversations on the subject. "Only wait in hope, dearest mother," Philip would say, "till I am a man, and I will not leave an Indian wigwam on the Peninsula unsearch- ed. I feel certain in imy own mind that those dark savages carrieA off our dear little Edward. If they had killed him, they would have left his lifeless body, and if he had wandered away by himself, he could not have gone so tar but that my father, with so many kind friends, would have discovered himn." "to not talk to me of hope, Philip, where your brother is concern- ed,' saiLd iis. Wilton, "sand above all do not talk to me of going into yond vr dlreary %ilderness in search of him. Is it not enough that fte of the blithi boys whLm I so loved to sing to sleep in their infancy sl culd be takln trcm me, but that the other should rush upon destruc- tik,. 1 o I :t think of leaving your father and me for a search so utter- lyN hopeless."   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.       .    19 But though Mrs. Wilton called the search a hopeless one in speaking to her remaining son, there was still in her heuart a latent hope that some tiding of her lost darling mig'ht reach her ears. She watched with a nervous anxiety every party of Indians that entered the village, if among the elder ones she might recognise Sa'rito, or if with the youngrer mem- bers of the party there should be one whose form and features showed a different descent from his companions. But she watched in vain. Sagito never returned to the settlenment on the IRaisin from the day, when Mr. Wilton so fatally offended him, and after Eilward Wilton reached the Kalamazoo, he had never been fifty miles away. from his western home. "Well, mother," said Philip one day in return to her entreaties that he would give us his scheme, " you know I cannot go yet, and perhals before I am old enough, we shall regain our lost treasure in some other way." "I may at least hope to meet my child in another world," said Mrs. Wilton sadly, as she left the room, to regain in secret, prayer the calm- ness which always deserted her when she spoke of Edward. She now never mentioned his name to indifferent persons, but to her husband anti children she talked of him frequetitly, though she never did so without losing ti:e self-control which it had cost her so nany mental struggle to obtain.                 ' a           .  '1  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8373-00000010"/> 20            3DWARD WILTON, OR CHAPTER VI. nime was fast removing what had been the principal obstacle in the way of Philip -Wilton's search for his long lost brother, but the fears of his mother to whom he was devotedly attached and the anxieties of his father, prevented his putting a project so long talked of into execution. He "had now reached the age of twenty-two or three, a noble specimen of youthful manhood. By no means regularly handsome, there was a spirit and intellect in his dark eyes, and a grace in all the movements of his fine athletic form, whichi rendered him more interesting than many whose features were more perfect. : He was the boldest hunter, the most fearless rider, the gayest dancer in the settlement, but so frank, so kind in his disposition, that his superiority, though universally acknowledged, provoked no envy, and Philip was a general fayorite with old and young. His parents seemed to lavish on him a double portion of affection, and his fair young sister loved and looked up to him with that holy, unself- ish devotion which is so beautiful in the fraternal relation. Mr. Wilton, broken down in a great measure by cares and sorrows, and beginning to feel that the hope, which had sustained him for so many years must at last be given up, grew d3ily more dependcnt on his remaining son; and then his mother, Philip could not withllstand the mute supplication of her eyes, when any aIllusion was mllade to his leaving home, so that though he now felt himself of an age to cncouniter the dangers of the forest, there seemed daily less likelihoodl ofi' thl search being commenced. There were other reasons too, to dstain him. It was well known in all the western frontier .settlemcnts thlat their siavage  neighbors were constantly growing more unruly and dangerous. The French hunters who came in with their furs represented the whole inte- rior in a state of commotion. Councils were held in the different villa- ges, the war dance gone through, and the war whoop raised. Belts and messages were transmitted from one tribe to another, and the Indian /   EARLY DAYS IN M'ICHANm.        f'l deputies from the north part of the Peninstla iwere accompanied by Eng- lishmen, who inflamed to a still higher pitch the already violint passions of the red man, and promised them the assistance of their White Father who dwelt beyond the great water, to drive the Americans bak'to0t*rds x the rising ft, and -finally innihilate them entirely. Tiis was notinsm for one of the hatred race to venture among them, and Philip relictantly gave up, for the present, the dream of his boyhood and youth; the hope of returning to his mother's embrace his younger brother. "I wish you could remember Edward, Mary," said he one day to his sister, "you can scarcely imagine how beautiful he was. Young as we both were, I used to listen to the praises lavished on his beauty, and wish that I too was fair. I do not wonder that our poor mother still pines so deeply for him."  "She would have done the same for you, Philip," returned his sister "I cannot imlgine that a "miother's heart can be influenced by beauty- and I think few would feel that you needed to envy any one's good looks but I have always supposed that you and Edward looked alike." "We both had dark eyes," said Philip "and I fancy this was the only point of resemblance, and Edward's eyes were more like yours than mine, except that his were always ready to flash with mirth, and looked as though a tear had never dimmed them, and our mother's sorrows have stolen into your heart, and given too sad a brightness to your eyes. My poor mother! what will become of her if war should really -be declared, and I fear t will be before long. Wereit not for you and my mother, I should look forward to it with a very different feeling, but what you will do when I am away, I cannot tell." "You, Philip! surely you will not leave us-you will not join the army; that indeed would kill my mother. Let others go, who can be spared, but do not let. our parents hear you speak of this scheme." '; My father knows of it already, and has given his consent; he feels as I do that every arm will be needed that can strike a blow for our coun- try, and would you have me a laggard in the cause, Mary? I have the promise of a commission as soon as war is declared, and then Henry Gffingham must comfort you and my mother too, if he can; he is a cler- gyman and it is not his province to fight." * ; : '          'S t}  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8373-00000011"/> 22          EDWARD WILTON, OR "None can comfort us for your absence, Philip," replied Mary, with a crimson blush, and Mr. Enffingham, I am sure "t Here comes Mr. Effingham to answer for himself, so I shall leave you and Mary, an I go to talk this over with -ny mother," and Philip .Wilton vaulted over the garden fence as his sister's lover walked quietly through the gate, ,   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         23 - CHAPTER VII. L At fifteen, Edward Wilton found himself happy in his forest home, and among the swarthy faces which he had known from childhood. To Sagito and his adopted mother he was bound by strong ties of affe tion, Until he was of an age to leave the care of Nadesha, he haad been her constant companion. The gentle and sorrow-subdued spirit of the Indi- an woman clung with the deepest love to the beautiful child whom she believed that the Great Spirit had sent to replace her own son, and few mothers could have been more devoted to the children whom they had loved from their earliest infancy, than was this daughter of the forest to this scion of a foreign race, who was so suddenly thrown upon her kind- ness. And the young Eagle Eye regarded his adopted mother with far more affection, than the Indian youth of his own age are accustomed to show the females of their tribe. Gifted by nature with an affectionate: heart and an eager, enthusiastic disposition, his Indian education had been in- sufficient to destroy these instincts, or render him quite, "A stoic of the Woods." He had learned to endure pain without a rbrmur, for this was easy to his high and manly spirit, but he had never bin able to smother every demonstration of natural feeling, or concealed Hthought and pulrpose of his mind with that deep cunning which seeminnate in the heart of an Indian.  There was too, an instinctive chivalry in the heart of the white boy, and he would often assist his gentle mother in her more severe labors, at an age when one of the dark skinned youths iarround him would have shown his manhood by adding to, rather than releasing her cares, so that the tie between the two was in some respects more like that between a white mother and her son, than the relation as it usually exists in an Indian lodge. Sagito, the adopted father and the t,*)r Of our hero, in all warlike accomplishments, was on many accounts a very favorable specimen of the Indian race. Brave, even to rashness, he was  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8373-00000012"/> 24           EDWARD WILTON, OR less sanguinary than most of his brother warriors, and it was to this re- deeming trait in his character that Mr. Wilton owed his exmption from even a more fearful punishment, than that which followed his thought- less speech to the chief. Many another of the forest braves would have ,left the charred timbers of his dwelling, and the lifeness bodies of his wife and children, to remind the unhappy man that an Indian warrior never forgets or forgives an insult. Less blood-thirsty than many of his nation/, he was also more just in his dealings with those with whom he came i'conitact, nd had, ;by management and cuniiing, or his influence O6,r his'chmpanidons, savred th life of more than one white man, wiio udildt otiierwigi have fallen a victim to the fury of those around him. Buti there wa'i one point on *hich he was inflexible. No white trader Ii^as alowetd Xt bring to Saito's village the poison fire water which hias e;v4 been' the Indian's worst enemy. He would neither touch it him.- self or allow those under his control to do so. - , Let not mybrothers take the bad medicine of the pale face," said he, "it'is but given to destroy their senses, that the trader may obtain twen- ty beaver skins for the value of one. The clear water of the springs Will qiiueich our thirst, and corn and vension satisfy our hunger, but the fire water wil do neither. It is theevil manito of the white man, let us r;ive itfrom our villages." Owing to these masterly traits in the character of an Indian chief, Edward had known less of the dark side of the red man's life, than might naturally have been expected. He had always- seen and was now al- lowed to join in the war dance, and the exciting songs which accompany it, 'utibee freom the influence of ardent spirits, much of its usual horror was abent. It was not until, at the age of eighteen, Sagito took him with a chosen band of his young warriors, to a village some two or three day's distance from his own, to meet deputations from the other tribes, and hear the Italk!' of an English agent, who was endeavoring to excite the warriors gainst their American neighbors; that the young Eagle Eye beheld the demoniacsorgies which invariably follow the introduction of ardent spits into an Indian camp. He bad frequently heard of the strange ef- fects produced by the firery drink presented by the white man to his In- dian allies, and he no longer wondered that his adopted father had so   * k EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         25 rigorously prohibited it to his young men, nor at the stern sadness with which the chief looked on at the cup which was rapidly circulating from hand to hand under the direction -of the English officer, who in vain desired Sagito to partake of it, assuring him through his interpreter, that "it would make him very strong, very brave to fight against the Yankees who were seeking to despoil the red warriors of their rights, and drive them from their land." "Do my English brothers take medicine to make them strong and brave when they wish to fight " asked Sagito with a Scornfu smiite "'The red man is strong enough withouet-he needs no medicine; an let my white brother beware how he offers the fire water to my young men. They are unused to it,.and might forget wlien they had dian it, and take him for one of the Yankees. Let 'my brothers b careful n' The stern tone of the chief, and his significant iook conveyed a' warning to the Englishman, even before his words were translated by tie interpreter, and he lost no time in removing from thte v 'icmit of one whom he saw he could neither hlatter or delude.    / e  01 o' * t ; . S  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8373-00000013"/> 26          EDWARD WILTON, OR CHAPT'ER    VIII. While the officer was conversing with Sagito, that wily chief had, with the usual reluctance of an Indian to speak English, and the diplo- matic cunning of a forest Statesman, allowed the interpreter to translate for him, althou gh he understood every word uttered by the white man. During this time, E lward and the other warriors were seated at no great distance from Sk iito, though of course not in the circle of chiefs, and the sentences which were spoken in English produced a strange confusion and excitement in the mind of the young man, who now for the first time in so many years haard the sound of his native tongue. The fea- tures and dress of the white man, who had not deemed it prudent to display the British uniform, deepened the impression, and recalled the scenes of his earlier childhood, as a single word or look will sometimes brig. some long forgotten dream indistinctly to the memory, and as we so often do in regard to a dream, he strove, but in vain,to define more clearly to his mind the half-formed thoughts and images so suddenly presented before it. He was surprised to find that not only the sound but the meaning of many English words, was familiar to him, and his first impulse was to attempt to join in the conversation, but that would have been contrary to all rules of Indian etiquette, and he kept hs station quietly, though his flashing eye and changing color showed his agitation. The riot and confnsion in the camp of, the Chippewas became more general, as the spirits which had been distributed by the Englishman roused into fiercer action the savage nature of the Indians. All cere- mony was now at an end, and the sedate dignity of the dark warriors was exchanged for a wild fury of speech and action, which caused the emissary of the British Government to wish most heartily that he had been ordered on some less perilous, or more honorable duty, than that of stimulating a band of yelling fiends like these to attack and murder those, of his own color and race. While these uncomfortable reflections were passing through Capt.   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         2 7 Mordaunt's mind, his eye was arrested for the first time by the figure of Edward Wilton, as he leant against a tree at some little distance from the rest. The lurid light of the Council fire shone upon his form and face, and gave his waving brown curls, which had not yet been shorn according to the customs of the savages, his large clear eyes, and regular features, so clearly to view, that, although he wore the Indian dress, and his blanket was wrapped closely around his person, the stranger at once perceived that he was not the only pale face in the. company. He turn- ed to his -interpreter, one of those coure'urs du bois whose habits and employments render them perfectly familiar with the red man,- and said in a low tone:  ' Look at yonder fellow, leaning against that tall pine. He is no more an Indian than I am, Can he be an American in disguise, watching our proceedings? It would be well to be certain on that point, for I have no instruction to proclaim my errand to the Yankees."  J   d"Parblue, Captain!" returned his companion, "he would be a' bold Yankee who would venture into the heart of a Chippewa camp i'r these days, and in a disguise that even your English eyes can see through. He is a white man, or rather boy, that, is clear, but he belongs in- some way among these red gentry. Stolen when he was a child, I fancy, and brought up by some of them."                ^ He is a noble looking fellow, whoever he is," said Captain Mokdaunt, but I would rather see him in a British uniform than wrapped in that blanket, or half naked like those furies who have thrown theirs aside to dance and yell around the fire. Six feet high and an- eye like a hawk's I he would make a splendid soldier! Jacques, you must find out who'he is, and we will try to take him back with us and teach him the white fashion of fighting." "Its not an easy thing, Captain, to find out an Indian's secrets,andthey never like to say much to strangers about their captives, I will talk to the lad himself, however, and see what metal he is -made of ;" and Jac- ques left his employer, taking care, however, not to approach the. object of their curiosity immediately, lest the quick suspicions of the Indians might be awakened; bult after some careless conversation with other members of the camp, he reached the side of the Eagle Eye, and said, as he threw himself down at the foot of the tree where the other wa standing: or   &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8373-00000014"/> 28          EDWARD WILTON, OR My young brother, wears the blanket and the moccasin, but he has not the dark skin or the smooth hair of the red man. Has he dwelt so long in the wigwam, that his white brothers are forgotten ", "The memory of the whites had long faded from the mind of the young Eagle Eye," returned the young man, " but now that-he has seen a pale face again, his home comes back to him, but dimly, as he has seen the trees along the Kalamazoo when the fog begins to break on a sum- mer's morning." 4"The Eagle Eye does not then dwell in the lodges of the Chippewas," said the Frenchman, who knew the residence and dialect of every tribe on the Peninsula, and inferred Edward's home from his allusion to the river.  "! am the son of Sagito, the chief of the Pottawattomies,' replied the youth, drawing himself up with a degree of pride in his connexion with so noted a brave. "'Ah, Sagito. I have often seen him, and I remember it was he that refused: the cup of liquor to-night. He is a great warrior, though over serupulous on some points. But will not the white son of the chief put on the coat and cap of his English brothers, and stand by their side when they go to fight against the Yankees I' -  Edward's eye flashed. "When the Eagle. Eye is wearied of his In- dian home, he will speak to his father, and the chief will point out the way to the villages of his own people. The home of his white father is not among the English." Thus much had Edward learned concerning his early home, from one ' of the older chiefs, and as he watched the fierce festivities of the eve- ning, and heard the insidious speeches of the Englishman, his mind had recoiled with instinctive horror from joining in an attack upon his own people and perhaps upon his own kindred. There was a determination in his tone, and a firmness in his manner, as he replied to the proposition of the- Frenchman, which convinced the latter that any attempt at per- suasion would be useless, and though they conversed for some\ minutes longer on indifferent topics, he did not renew the subject which had so nevidently offended his young companion.     EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          29 CHAPTER IX. Edward saw no more of the English captain or his French acquaint- ance, for having that night received the pledges of the chiefs that they would keep their tomahawks in readiness to lift against the Americans. Captain Mordaunt passed on, to form the same unholy league with other tribes; a league, which the annals of our country show, was but too faithfully kept. The chiefs who had come from distant villages, to listen to the eloquence of the Englishman, departed from the Chippewa anip, well supplied with the gifts which an, Indian so dearly loves. But though the Eagle Eye saw no more of the white strange, the impression which he made was deepened rather than effaced by absence, and he felt' an almost uncontrollable desire to hear his own language spoken again, and to know more of his own early history than he had ever been able to learn. It was towards the close of a lovely summer's day that Sagito with his party encamped on the eastern shore of one of those beautiful lakes which are so frequently found in Michigan. Edward had thrown himself at the foot of a tree, from whose branches an immense grape vine drooped in' rich festoons of verdure. Before himn lay the lake, like a silver mirror, set in a frame of .emeraldfoliage, and the richest flowers enamelled the grass on which .he rested. :The sun wa past setting and d sent his last rays from among the gorgeous crimson and gold and purple clouds which floated around in the Sky, in a br ldge of living fire, spanning the like fi'om s}h ore to shore, like that narrow fiery. pathhwy over whichb the M0os!ems believo they slall pasl , .to Paradise. SaBgito st:ood near,s leaning on his rifle. Years had not bent his tall fornm , or altered, the stern .thouhtfulness of his countenance., The other Indians of.-the party were occupied in different. ways, preparatory to the nig;t s repose, and even as Edward looked, a similar scene, rose suddenly before his, fe. vered and excited memory. Just such a glorious summer sun set on the bankls of as fair a lake, though not the same; the trqes bending there, as now, under their weights of foliage, the dark forms busied around  " ::  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8373-00000015"/> 30          EDWARD WILTON, OR and that proud chief resting on his long rifle. But had he been the sama himsielf! No: he could almost see, so vivid wag the picture in his mind the young child who sat by himself gazing with fear and wonder on a scene so lnew to him; 'and for .the first time in many years, Edward . Wilton knew that he remembered one of the incidents attending his capture 9 the Indians. It was one, however, which threw no farther light upon his bewildered mind, and, but for the previous stirring of memo  at the sound of his own language, might never have recurred to himyet slight as it was, it had engrossed him so completely that his adopted father had spoken to him twice without reply, and he almost started as Slagito touched his shoulders. "Does my son sleep! his eyes are open, but he hears not. A warrior should keep his ears awake, though his eyes are closed in slumber." The familiar voice and implied rebuke, recalled the young man to himself. "Let my father speak once more, and his son will hear," said he, rising to his feet with that respect for superior years, which is one of the Indian virtues. "Were the words of the Frenchman pleasant in the ears of the Eagle - Eye when he talked with him by the tall pine in the camp of ;the Ojib- was?" asked Sagito; " the pale face has ever two tongues, one for the red man and one for those of his own color; with which did he speak to my son!" ' Npt with that which he used to Sagito," answered the young man, "for he would have his son leave him to wear the coat of an English soldier, and fight against his own people with the pale faces that come over the great waters." "Would my son go?" asked the chief, in the same calm tone with which he had commenced the conversation. "He told the white man," returned Edward, " that when his Indian home was no longer pleasant in his eyes, Sagito would tell him the way to his own people, and that he would never fight against those to whose Tace he belonged: did he speak well?" "My son is yet very young," said Sagito, after a silence of a minute or two, " he has ever been free as the wild deer of the woods; if he leaves thie lodge of Sagtito for the village of the white man, he will be like the ox wlich they use to help tear up the green earth. Wift he not go on Ithe war-path with his red brothers, when they dig up the hatchet again?" I' Would my father have me lift the tomahawk against those of my   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         31 own race? When the Er gishmat calls on the chiefs to make rea;ly for the war-path, the adopted son of Sagito will look for his white father, and stand by the side -of his white brothers in battle." "The snows will have fallen and disappeared more than once before then," said Sagito, " my son can think long of the words he has spoken' now. Let them lie still in his mind till the leaves of another summer, are coming upon the trees; then his father will talk with him again." , The chief turned away as he spoke, and left the young man to his own reflections, which were in truth of a most mixed and painfill nature. ie endeavored again, and still in vain, to recall something of his early home and friends, and run over in his mind, as if they were some mystic talis- man, the few words of English which he had so lately heard. lHe remembered, that some three or four springs past, when the waters of the Kalamazoo were at their highest, a little Indian boy belonging to their village had strayed away, and after being sought for two or tlret days, was found entangled in the roots of an old tree which had fll!en into the water. The trembling anxiety of the child's mother, and her wild despairing griefs when- he was found, came freshy to his memory, and he wondered if he too had been mourned for by his white mother; if she had so grieved over the child she was never to see again. Then there arose before him the-gentle form of Madesha, and the soft dark eyes which for so many years had looked with such tenderness uplon himin, and he felt that the heart of the Indian wonman would almnost break in a separation from him who had for so long a time filled the place of her own son in her bosom. While these thoughts were passing throughl liiS mind, the twilight had faded away, and one by one the starls l;td comet to see themselves reflected in the clear lake below. Tile other mnmbers of the party had sunk to; sleep, around the fire, but thoughl Edward qlay down in his place, it was not long before he forgot in slumber the thhougts which had haunted him incessantly since he saw the Englislmlna. \ .  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8373-00000016"/> 32          BDWARD WILTON, OR CHAPTER X. The summer passed heavily for Edward Wilton. He had lost forever that happy thoughtlessness which had always till now been his compan- ion, and'which required nothing more than the consciousness of having brought down a greater number of deer than any of his young com- panions with the English gun which had been the gift of Sagito; or some similar triumph, to bring the gay light to his eye, and the smile to his proudly curved lip. Occasionally through his life the thought had arisen that he was one by himself, an alien from his rightful home; but he was so tenderly cared for by Madesha, so well beloved by the brave chief whom he called father, and so great a favorite among the youth of .his own age, that the feeling was dismissed almost as soon as it entered his bosom, and until he had seen the two white men in the Chippewa encampment, few of the Indian youths who hunted and fished along the banks of the Kala- mazoo, or darted over its waters in their birchen canoes, bore a lighter hey t than the white boy who had been so strangely cast among them. But from that night a change had come over his spirit. He. was. no longer satisfied With the simple, occupations of his past life, and he felt. a strange yearning to be among his own people, and to hear his own lan- guage. He spent hours aind lays, which his companlions hloght were employed in hunting, in wanderinog idly among the beautiful hills which rise so gracefully a mile or two from the river, or .ying at the foot of a tree, striving to recall something of his home, and repeatinrg eveery,Eii;  glish word which his memory could furnish. At times he felt half inclined to leave his Indian home at once, and seek some white settle- ment. He knew that some daiys journey to the east, were several villages ; he had a faint idea that from some one of these he had been taken, and he had early learned to find his way through the woods with the uner- ring accuracy of an Indian hunter. But his resolution wavered when   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         33 he thought of his gentle Indian mother, the noble Sagito, and the young warriors with whom he had grown up, and who were dear to him as brothers. The laugh and the song of the forest maidens, more- over, was pleasant in the ears of the young man, and though he had no particular object of affection among them, there were many with whom he had played in childhood, for whose necklaces he had gathered the scarlet berries of the wild rose, or poured into their small hands the earliest strawherries, and showed them whereo find the richest banks of moss and the gayest flowers. He felt thatne pair of dark eyes which now gleamed softly bright to welcome hiy return from the hunt, or the distant excursion, would be dimmed; one }weet laugh hushed, and that the Springing Fawn of the Kalamazoo Wuld mourn for his absence as a sister for a beloved brother. Another and a better reflection would sometimes enter his mind. He had always heard from Sagito and the other warriors that the whites looked down upon and despised the Indian, even while they flattered and cajoled him to mould; him to their will, and he asked himself if the same contempt would not be shown to one who had been brought among them, and who knew no customs but theirs. As months passed on, and these with similar thoughts filled the mind of the Eagle Eye, his brow grew graver, his step more slow, and the sedate thoughtfulness of manhood seemed all too soon taking the: place of the gay buoyancy of spirit which distinguished him among all the young men of the tribes. The watchful eye and loving heart of Madesha had marked the change in his manner from the day of his return from the Chippewa encampment, but she was unable to conjecture the cause. "Did my son leave his -soul bshinl him when he camo from rthe camp of the OjibwasF" said she to him one day, as fhe threw hfiself listlessly down upon a pile of skins in the lodge. "Did hesee-theri ; maiden with softer eyes or a lighter step than he can find oh the bailks of the Kalamazoo, or has some evil medicine been given to him, that he no longer cares for the sports of his brotherl"  "Neither, my mother," replied the yoi, " but he heard a voice which spoke the worda lie knew in his biflllSJol, and they were pleasant in his ear as the first call of the spring birds to our maidens. The voice 3  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8373-00000017"/> 3 4          BDWAIRD WILTON, OR- still speaks to him, and whispers that he should seek the place where he first heard them, and in listeningo to the whisper, your son has for- gotten His mirth."  This reply carried a pang to the heart of Madesha. She had sup- posed for many years that her white son had entirely forgotten his early home, and the language of the pale faces, and she fancied that his life  would be spent continually among her own people. In searching for the cause of Edward's thoughtfulness, she had never for a moment imagined that he could meditate leaving those with whom he had spent so many years in apparent forgetfulness of every other tie. "It is a bad voice," exclaimed she, " let not my son listen to it. JThe  Eagle Eye is the son of a great warrior and chief: let him hear the words which Sagito will speak, and he will drive away the strange voice from his ear and from his heart. He will go on the war-path with-is father, and when he returns, he will be a great bravie, and our maidens shall strive'with each other to win a smile from the lips of the Eagle Eye, or a gift from his hand. Will my son hear the counsel of his father ' "When the leaves of another spring are on the trees, Sagito has : promised to talk with his son," replied Edward, "till then, the chief has bidden him keep the words in his own heart. If it be a bad voice it will go away, but it tells him now that he must not go on the war-path- against his own people." The Indianwoman sighed deeply and turned away. With the! natural feeling of an affectionate wife and a dutiful subject, she had thought that no resolve could withstand the eloquence of her husband and her chief, but when she found that the subject had been mentioned by the Eagle Eye to his adopted father, and that Sagito had not either forbidden him to leave them, or changed his purpose by persuasion, she felt there was little probability of his remaining. It was some consolation to know, however, that the autumn and winter would pass before the young man would seek another home, and Madesha clung, with the strong pertinacity of hope in the human heart, to the idea that something might yet induce him to dwell still on the banks of the clear river where was now his home.   EARLY DAYS IN M0HGAN.         35 ^^a e    HAPTER    X[. Among the young warriors of the Pottawatamie village, there was one to whom Edwalrd Wilton had always shown the earliest attachment. Otaginqi was the older of the two- by a few years, and had acted as a sort of guardian to the young pale face when he first come among the dark skinned children of the forest. It was Otagimi who had first taught him to bend the bow, or climb the trees in search of bird's nests, and had defended him from the laughter and jeers of the young savages of his own age, when they found the new comer ignorant of accom- plishments in which they were already proficient. The quick intelligence and active spirit of Edward, aided by the instructions of his friend, soon placed him at least on a level with the young scoffers, and many of themn ,were forced to acknowledge his superiority in the very acts of which his ignorance had moved their mirth. Years rolled over the heads of the two youths, but brought no diminution of their friendship. Together they -had hunted the deer and the wolf through the beautiful forests around them, orspeared the bass and the pickerel, in the crystal waters of the lakes. Even when Otagimi attained to the dignity of manhood, the intimacy and affection continued, though they could no longer be so Mcoii i . together as of old. The young Indian- was the son of a chief Fiio did h been killed some years before in an affray between the Pottawatahie and one of the tribes beyond the lakes. There had been a deadly fieid between the two tribes from that day, and while yet very young, Otagimi accompanied a band of the elder warriors on an excursion against their hostile neighbors, to revenge the death of his father. The Eagle Eye was still too young tobetrusted onthe war-path, but his joy was s groat when his friend returned, laden -with the trophies of his triumph, and pronounced a  great brave by the older warriors, as if himself had been the hero.               , At the time of the visit to the Chippewa encampment, Otagimi had  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8373-00000018"/> 86           ZDWAUD WILTON, OR been absent on a visit of Indian diplomacy to some tribe far south of the Peninsula, nor did he return till the tulip-dyed leaves of the forest proclaimed the approach of the season which the hunter loves. He- quickly perceived the change in his friend whose gay spirits seemed quite to have deserted him, and whose pleasure at their meeting, though it brought a transient gleam of light to his eye, soon gave place to a thoughtfulness that was almost gloom. It was one of the most beautiful days in October, when the two young men left the village for a hunt. They had, by tacit consent, turned their steps to the south, and had proceeded but a short distance when they roused a large deer. He led them a long chase, nor did they gain a fair shot at the noble animal, till he reached a lake some miles from the villages, at whose shore he paused to drink, fancying that he had at last outstripped his pursuers. But the security of the poor crea- ture was of short duration. Edward's quick eye caught a glimpse of his prey through the trees, and as the still woods rang with the report of his rifle, the deer fell forward, partly in /the water, and partly on the smooth shining sand of the lake beach. The hunters sprang forward,. but life had departed ere they reached the form so lately full of grace, and they soon disposed of the spoil. The skin was taken off and the finest parts of the venison secured for transportation to the village, to- gether with the antlers, which were of uncommon Size, a fire was kindled, and while a portion of the deer was cooking, they threw themselves down to wait for their simple meal. It, was a scene of no common beauty on which they gazed. The lake which was several miles in circumlference, was almost encircled by low rounded hills, forming miniature bays and promontories, and covered with rees, which, in their'autumn beauty, exhibited the richest vareities Oof coloring. Not a leaf seemed to have left its place; the foliage was thick and luxuriant as in June, but no bed of tulips or dalies could :display more gorgeous hues.. The sky was of that clear, glittering blue so seldom seen except in our autumn months, and the few white clouds wlhich flecked- it surface, only served to deepen the azure amid whichh they floated.  The young chief and his white brother were not insensible to thle loveliness around them, though neither spoke of, it, nor indeed was the   EARLY DAYS IXN MCHGAN.        3' silence broken at all for some time. The Eagle Eye had ever been the first to commence the conversation, anffhe sat now looking over the rippling waters of the lake, as though his life depended on his counting every tiny wave which broke at his feet, while his companion occasionally buried himself with the fire, or made some new -arrangement of the spoil they were to bear home. Otagimi seemed at-last to weary of the stillness, and turning to the other, he exclaimed: "Has the Springing Fawn frowned upon my brother, or refused his gifts, that he is as grave as a medicine man , Sagito can no longer Ay of his son that he is toogay and light-hearted for a warrior. What. has darkened. the light in my brother's eye i"         ] ' "Has Sagito talked with Otagimi since he came from the southern lodges," returnedEdward, " has he told him that his people are to sharpeu their tomahawks, and make re'ady'their scalping knives so that. w!henahe- Englishman sends a belti they shall go on the war-path against the whites who dwell on the border of the eastern lake " ' The young chief looked with some surprise at his friend, -My brother surely does not fear to head the war-path, or:to hear the; guns of the pale faces! Should not the news of the war-belt bringyjo:y to the soul of a young warrior 8 Is it for this that mv brother's vol is  darkened "  There was a sound of wonder and reproach in the voice of the Indian, that roused the sleeping pride of his companion,- and the dark; eyed of Edward Wilton had never flashed mnore, like those of the bird for whom; he was named, than wlien he answered:  "Does my br)ther think I am a woman, that he asks meX if IfItB-A Lift the tomahawk against the tribes who dwells towards thsettiing$un^ and the young chief shall find if the Eagle Eye is afraid Olik! rlfim thunder storm; but he will not go to fight against h'mown, :popie,':o the call of the English soldier."            ; 5  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8373-00000019"/> 8         DOWARD WILTON, OR CHAPTER XII. "Does the Eagle Eye count himself one of the pale faces, when the- bravest chief of the Pottawatamies has called him his son? Are not  5 his people those with whom he dwells, the people of Sagito," said Ota- ! gimi, " and will he refuse to follow his father on the war path "  The warm heart and ardent feelings of the young white man felt  the full bitterness of the implied rebuke, tnd it required all the power  of his Tndian education to conceal the emotion he felt, as he replied to his companion.                             i "Would Otagimi go with the warriors from the northwest to set ire to the lodges of his father and brothers; would he throw the tomnahwik at the heads of the women and children of his own tribe, ' though he had been among the strangers so long that the memory of his home was faint and uncertain in his soul as the glancing of the fire. ty on a summer's night? The heart of the Eagle Eye will always be warm for his Indian father and brothersbut when they march against his own people, he must leave them, and stand beside the white soldiers to drife them away from the villages." The Indians are strong believers in the ties of blood, and ever re- gard with distrust and dislike the renegade whites, who occasionally, from some pique at those of their own color, join the savages in their ferce onslaughts on the white settlements, so that the young chief c6uld not oppose the determination of his friend. "-The words of my brother are very good," said he, after a silence of some duration. But the hatchet is not yet dug up. Let the Eagle Eye dwell i the village by the Kalamazoo, and hunt with- his broth- ers till the war belt comes from the English pale faces." a I will stay by the clear river," replied the other, " and Otagimi will hide the words I have spoken, in his heart, as the snow will hide the green earth in a few moons, and when the snows melt away, and the st^- ms are free again, the chief and his brother will talk again the white villages and the pale faces."   RBARLY DAYS ItN SMCHOAN. g. The heart of the Eagle Eye seemed lightened of a part of its gloom by the knowledge, that one at least, among his red friends would not disapprove of his course in leaving them. During the few minutes that Sagito had spoken to him on the subject, the countenance of the warrior had shown no emotion, and his words had been as carefully guarded as his face, so that his son had been unable to conjecture what effect his avowal had produced on one whom he regarded with both love and reverence. Nadesha, he knew, would oppose his departure, as far as lay in her power. It was something on which her mind co6ild' admit of no reasoning; she could only feel that the beautiful ltand Af- fectionate child who had been her solace when her heart was almost broken at the loss of her own little one; the -brave and noble youth who had shown for her a tenderness and respect unusual among her own people, was going to desert her for strangers, and the thought was insupportable. All this Edward knew from the few conversations he had had with her on the subject; he attempted at first to reconcile her to the idea of losing him, but he found it useless, and at last ceased to speak of it- To no one else had he mentioned his intentions, till the return of his most intimate friend allowed him to open his heart. Nothing more was said by either, of the plans of the younger warrior, while they re- mained by the lake shore. In silence or indifferent conversation they proceeded with their meal, and prepared for their return to the village with their spoils, and during their walk homewards they found suffi- eient occupation in the destruction of the lesser game with which the woods through which they passed abounded. At one time a flock of wild turkeys tempted a shot, then a convey of partridges started up with their loud whirl from before their feet, or a fleet of wild ducks on some one of the small ponds which they passed, called forth the sharp report of their rifles. The excitement of a successful day's hunting,; the exhilerating influence of the pure bracing air, added to the happi- ness of having found sympathy and approbation in the heart of his friend, restored something of his old gravity to the countenance of Ed- ward Wilton, and Nadesha remarked with mingled surprise and pleas- ure the smile on his lip as he threw down his game at the entrance of the lodge. I  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8373-00000020"/> 40         . BDWARD WILTON, OR "I have brought my mother a fine skin to make into moccains/, said he, " and vension to dry for the winter, and here are birds for her ' and for my father." "My son and his gifts are very welcome; his gun has done well to- day; will he not rest by the fire until his mother makes ready the food he has brought?" said the Indian woman, as she rose to take charge of this addition to her labor. Edward laid aside his gun, and threw him- I self daon op some skins by the fire, which the keen air of an October twilihtgh ade grateful even to a hunter; and as he did so, he perceiy- ed for the first time since e entered the lodge, the slight and gracefid figure f an Indian girl who had been seated near Nadesha. '             . ' f   .   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGANF,        41 C/IAPTER    XIII. The fire light which revealed the form of the young maiden, oould scarcely have displayed a more exquisite picture of Indian loveliness  The glossy dark hair was confined in one heavy braid, which was wound wound her head passing just above the forehead, and fastened  M a knot behind. Her complexion dark though it were, was so clear and soft, that the fitful light showed distinctly the changing color of her cheek, and rich deep red of her lips, and the dark eye which was fixed on the fire, was more softly brilliant in its rays than the eyes of many a dawing-room beauty in " the light of a chandelier."' Her dress was a sort of gown of gay colored calico, fastened in front by several brooches, but over it she wore a garment resembling somewhat the Polkas and Jenny Linds of the present day, and quite as graceful in its shape, though of very different materials, for it was made of the softest *deer skin, dressed until it was nearly white, and richly ornamented with the colored quills of the porcupine. This was thrown a-little back from the neck, perhaps from the heat of the fire, or possibly' be- cause the brooches showed to somewhat better advantage, and arouvid the slender throat was fastened with a golden clasp, a coral necklace of some value. The unusual ornament 'for an Indian lodge had been the gift of a white trader to her father many years before in return for some service rendered him by the warrior, and its possession made the springing Fawn the admiration and envy of halfjihe girls of her; tribe l Biaelets of the same material as the necklace, and belongingg to it, were fastened on her wrists; her small and beautifuly formedi haiindi wero, earele3sly locked together in her lap, and as she h]alf sat, ial-f r &amp;dFed'on a rude couch near the fire, one little foot in its richly wroug&amp;iht mbeAii, showed below the broadcloath leggins, worked with sare'- an'd -htite beads. The Indian maiden was good and single heasited  hnwais beautiful; but she was human and a woman, and whehi'ii terbiniad to take her roll of :birch bark and quill, and wiok :iri   &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8373-00000021"/> 42           EDWARD WILTON, OR portion of the day by the side of Nadesha, there was a secret, almost unacknowledged thought that the Eagle Eye, whom she knew had gone out with his gun in the morning, might return to the lodge of his father before she had fully mastered the intricacies of the embroidery pattern she hadf proposed learning from her friend; and it might have been this consciousness which had caused her to smooth her hair even more carefully than was her wont,. and add to her attire the corals which  so well became her dark skin.                    2 Edward did not speak immediately when he saw the fair visitor, and  she remained apparently uncolbious of his presence, though her ear had been even quicker than Nadesha's to detect the familiar footfall at the entrance of the lodge. But as the silence seemed to be growipg embarrassing to both parties, the girl arose, and murmuring something of assisting Nadesha in her labors, was proceeding to join the elder wo- man, who was already busied in preparing some of the birds for the supper of the young hunter. "Has the Springing Fawn been the whole day beneath the roof of the lodge," asked the young man as she rose from her seat, 'the craa- ,berries are ripening fast in the marshes, and I looked for her canoe among themn for it was wont to be soonest filled with the scarlet fruit." "There is the little summer yet to come," replied the maiden," when the wind from the southwest blows softer and warmer than it does to- day, and the'sun does not glisten so brightly on, the water. I love better the soft breath of the summer when it sighs through the woods after 'its dead flowers, than the keen air that brings the leaves from their boughs."                  \ - Does not the'Springing Fawn love the later summer all the more," said Nadesha as the'maiden joined her, " because she was drawn from the rushing waters'of the river, when the southwest wind blew over the land, and her eyes opened again to life under its soft skies!" Nadesha was right in her conjecture, though her companions replied not to ,the question, but proceeded busily with the labors which the older of the two had commenced. Some two or three years before, when Edward Wilton and the Indian maiden were just springing from hildhood into youth, the young pale face had saved the life of the beautiful girl who now  stood near him, with some peril to his own;   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAI .         43 and the event had made so deep an impression on the heart of her who, was rescued, that even the season of the year when it took place, seemed dearer -and sweeter to her, she hardly knew why, than the bursting loveliness of the Spring, or the glowing beauty of the sum- mer. At the time alluded to by Nadesha, the Fall rains had boeen unusu- ally heavy, and the Kalamazoo, with its pretty little tributary, the Por- tage, had risen so far above their usual level, that the Bfats on either side of the two rivers were completelysubmerged, and presented rather the appearance of a broad lake, than two distinct rivers. The freshet was subsiding during the Indian summer, though the rivers were still much above their ordinary level, when the Springing Fawn, with the thoughfulness of her age, chose to launch her canoe into the troubled waters, with the intention of crossing the smaller o f the two streams, not very far above their junction. The force of the current, however was too much for her slight strength, and though more skiul in the use of the paddle than many of twice her years, her frail boat soon became unmanageable, and drifting down into the larger riv- er, struck against a thee which lay buried in the water, and overset. The girl clung to the branches as the canoe floated rapidly away, but she could not support herself above "the water, and must inevitably have perished, but that the young Eagle Eye, who had seen the boat with its light burden, as it whirled down the stream, ran with the speed of a deer to the bank, and dashing into the deep and dark waters, caught: the insensible form of the young girl, and with some difficulty reached the shore again. He laid hiss charge on the bank, and the soft balmy wind soon restored her to herself. The boy thought but lightly of the enterprise as far as he only was concerned, but the grateful and suoep- tible heart of the Springing Fawn, cherished them emory of the scene and all connected with it. Therm was not a more dangerous spot for miles in the Kalamazoo than that where she was rescupd. Even when the water was at its usual level, there was a deep and dangerous looking eddy there, the bank was abrupt, and rose a few feet higher there than elsewhere in the vicin- ity, and when swollen with the autumnal rains, as the river then was, the water dashed with the giddy swiftness of a whirlpool, and, but that Edward was strong beyond his years, and perfectly fearless, the loss of ?  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8373-00000022"/> "          EDWARD WILTON, OR two young lives might have paid dearly for the temerity of the maiden  A huge oak tree grew just upon the bank at this spot, and it was under its almost leafless branches, that the Sp riiiIDg?ta found herself ly- ing with her dripping garments, and wet, t Igfghair, when -she again awoke to consciousness, and from that toied the roots of the old oak was her favorite seat. There she would steal away from her young companions, to braid her baskets, or work the mocock or the moccasin, whileshe lived over and over again with the tenacions memory of af- fection, every incident of her peril and escape. The young Eagle Eye became enshrined as a sort of hero in her mind; she had known him from the time of his first appearance in the village, and they had often shared each others childish sports, but now the young pale face seemed something far superior to: his dark companions in her eyes. Edward, on his part, felt-a new and lively interest in the gentle girl whom he had saved from  an untimely death, and a sort of friendship grew up be- tween them, which both felt to be pleasant for the time, and one of them at least asked nothing more. It whs to her that the Eagle Eye presented the gay feathers of the birds he shot in his boyish hunting excursions, or the early fruits he found in the woods. Once he was fortunate enough to bring down a noble.,eagle as it soared high in the blue sky above him, and while he was complimented by the elder warriors in the laconic style of the In- dian, on the keeness of sight and quickness of aim which had proved fatal to the kingly bird, and envied by the younger ones for the posses sion of the splendid gun which had contributed to his sucoas, the Springing Fawn wreathed its dark plumage in her hair with the proud  yet tender and unselfish triumph of a loving heart in the praise of; the' beloved. 4          sARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         45 CHAPTER XIV. Until the period when Edward began seriously to contemplate leav- ing his forest home, he had been almost unaware of the strength of his affection for the gentle Indian girl, whom he had rescued from the rushing river. He knew indeed that her voice and laugh sounded more sweetly musical to his ear than those of the other maidens of the village, that her step seemed lighter and more graceful, and the beam of her dark eye clearer and softer, but he was not alone in his admira- tion, for the Springing Fawn Was decidedly the beauty and belle of the tribe as she grow up to womanhood. Unused to look into the dim and uncertain future, and in his boyish thoughtlessness satisfied with the present, for his gun rarely failed in its aim, and the Fawn always received his gifts with smile., why should he disturb the placid currant of his life with care for the tim' to conm3? ' But when hi3 Viwit to the Chippewa- camp had roused deeper anl more serious thoughts in the breast of the younj man, and he bsean to form plans for rejoining his own people, one of the ms3t bitter cJx3iderations that present d itself before him, was the necessity of a soepration from the g ntla mi'd.3n whom,'till now, he had fancied he ragwrdd only as a sister. lie knew that n) other cull be to him lik3 th3 g-nlat pl tymtoe of his childhaod, the admiration of his mare mialy yaars, and at times he was alm)dt tOmted to renounc3 evary dream of anothar m)de of life, and settle himielfcns3tantly in the h thltiof an Indi- n, for hi felt certain that the fathsr of the Sprinjing Fawn, would never refuse her hand to the adalted sun of Sprit), and his heart whispered that the miid-n looked with cold333s and indifference ,n all the yung man of the vii- laje saw himslf. Thoue were but flet'in- th- u this h)w3Ver, for ttie sightof th-i whith mtn, and the s:auai of his own dimly remembered language, hadb awakened thoughts and desires which might never rest again till he stood with the peo;,le am ,nt who!n ha was brn, anlld'to whom he of right bslonjecd. Ha so etime3 imagined that - he miglit V r  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8373-00000023"/> "         nEDWARD WILTON, Olt return to his Indian home, and take froim thence tihe forest flower to, bloom among the paler beauties of his white kindred, but he was too ignorant of the habits and feelings of his own race, to guess what might be the reception of the Indian girl, and while he dreaded that they might look with contempt on him who had been so long the associate and pupil of the red man, he could not endure the idea that they would despise still more her whom he should bring among them.   I Then conflicting feelings gave a variableness to his manner, which the subject of them was not slow in perceiving, for there never yet was a woman, be her color what it might, whose heart was not quick to feel the slightest change or coldness in the look or tone of him she loved, as the clear lake to show the shadow of the passing cloud. To the Sprinoing Fawn, Edward had never mentio fed the circumstances which had changed him so rapidly from the fappy boy to the grave and thoughtful man; and from a feeling that her husband might not wish the wishes and intentions of their son to be known,Nadesha had been equally silent, though she: would gladly have unbosomed her sorrow to one who was her chief favorite among the young maidens of the tribe, and who in return regarded the wife of Sagito with affec- tion only second to that she bore her own mother. Many a time when the two were seated together, had the lips of the young girl quivered, and her heart beat quick, with the anxiety to enquire if her elder com- panion knew ought of the shadow which had dimmed the smile of the Eagle Eye, and as often had she remained silent, or spoken of some indifferent matter, from the fear that Nadesha might think her curiosi- ty unmaidenly, or that the answer to her question might give her even more pain than her present suspense. This day she had deter- mined to make one more effort to discover the cause of the change in him, who had, till that fatal absence, been ever the same to her, and when she saw the two young men leave the lodge, gun in hand, she soon made her arrangements to pass the day with Nadesha. But hour after hour had glided by, and still the words were arrested on her lip, till she could assume the careless tone which she meant should conceal her emotion.          j At last came twilight; the work of the tw females was thrown by, and while the younger congratulated herself that her friend could not   EA RLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         4 now watch the changes of her counttenance, she altered for the hun- dredth time, the form of her intended query in her own mind; then as she fancied that nIothlng should prevent her speaking at that mo- ment, came the familiar footsteps of him whose image filled her heart, and the inquiry must be postponed until another day. She felt a bit- ter pang as the young man seated himself without noticing her, for- getting that her own seat partly hid her from his view, and that the change from the clear twilight without, to the fitful blaze of the fire within the lodge, had for a moment dimmed his vision. When at last he spoke, though his tone was more like himself than any her ear had caught for many a day, she thought it cold and indifferent, and in the attempt to reply as coldly, her voice had a strange sadness, all un. like the merry sweetness of former days. The sound thrilled to the heart of the young Eagle Eye, and for the first time he wonderedif the maiden had noticed the gloom which his adopted mother and his bosom friend had both remarked on his countenance. He knew not, how often absorbed by his own sad thoughts, even in the presence of her he loved, he had passed unnoticed the lively sally or gay repartee from her lip, but the unusually plaintive sound of her voice, aroused him to a new train of thought. ,/  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8373-00000024"/> 48          EDWARD WIILTON, OR CHAPTER    XV. For some time after Nadesha had alltded to the reason of her young friend's partiality for the lovely, but melancholy season of the Indian summer, there was silence in the lodge, one of those oppressive, un-  comfortable periods of stillness which few have been so fortunate as not to have experienced at some time in their lives. A silence, not from vacuity of thought, but from the pressure of thoughts that none dare trust in words. -Edward had not heard his mother's remark, which indeed was not intended for his ear, but the few words uttered by the Springing Fawn, had carried his mind back, for a moment, to the day when she lay lifeless on the river's bank, and from that mo- ment until now, he had never seen a shade of coldness in the maiden's manner; but to-night he fancied there was displeasure as well aa sor- row in the sound of her voice; he longed to hear it again, but hecould not speak to her of what lay nearest his heart, and on what indifferent or trifling matter could he dwell? Nadesha was silent, for a host of melancholy thoughts had taken possession of her heart. She knew, perhaps better than any other person, how completely the happiness of the young girl was bound up in her affection for the Eagle Eye, for a woman is apt to be a quick and acute observer of the affections of others, and in this cave, the interest of a mother and a friend was ad- ded to the usual feminine sagacity, and she felt too severely how com- plete a wreck that happiness must be, if the young man carried his present plans into execution. At first she had hoped that his dreams of rejoining his own nation would fade, when he contemplated the ne-- cessary separation from the Springing Fawn, but that hope was reluct- antly dismissed, for she saw that his determination was firmly made, and that he would adhere to it, whatever sorrow might bring; and her own grief seemed on the misery in store for her young-companion. Her hands were mechanically busied with her labor, but her thoughts were too sad for utterance, while her young assistant appeared equally   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.       4  49 engrossed with her own reflections. It seemed to each of the silent party that one of the others must speak, but none seemed equal to the task of breaking a stillness which every moment became more formid- able. Not thus had the minutes been wont to pass, when in former days Edward had found the Fawn in the lodge of Nadesha. The In- dian women are naturally merry and talkative among themselves, and Edward had never until lately, acquired the calm, grave demeanor of ' the Indian warrior, so that the gay jest, or lively repartee of the young people, and Nadesha's approving, laugh, had often rung through the now quiet lodge. \ It was a relief to all when Sagito entered, and seating himself near his son, enquired as to the success of the day's hunting. They were all accustomed to be more silent and reserved in the presence of the X Chief, and his entrance seemed to restore the dwelling to something more like its usual state. The two women still pursued their occupa- tion in silence, but in their happiest days they would have done the same, when the old warrior was seated by the fire; while the Eagle Eye, in replying to his father, seemed to regain something of the ani- mation he had brought from the woods. "My father will have no lack of venison or bear's meat in his vil- lage in the winter," said he, " the nuts are thick on the trees; his young men will find plenty to do with their guns, and our women need not b  idle for want of skins to dress, or meat to dry." The Great Spirit is good"' said Sagito, " he will send his red chii- dren all they need, and when they have driven away the pale faces% the Buffalo will roam over our prairies again, and drink of our clear waters, as lie did in thee days of our fathers." "And does my father think," asked the young man, "that his peo- ple can drive the white man back to the sea . I heard him say once9 that from  the day they landed on the shore of the great waters; and turned their faces toward the setting sun, their course had been as sure, though .more slow than the fire which spread over the woods and prai- ries. Will it be more easy to turn back the pale face, than to make the fire retrace its path over the scorched grounds?" "My son is young," ieplied the chief, 4 he did not hear the words which Otagimi brought from Tecumseh, and his brother, the medi-  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC8373-00000025"/> 60O           DWARD WILTON, OR eine man who talks with the Great Spirit. He tells the red men to join together in the war path, and never let their feet turn back to the villages where their wives and children dwell, until they have driven the pale faces into the salt and bitter water whence they came. The Prophet says that the Great Spirit made this land for the Indian, and put the bad water between it and the country of the pale faces, that they might not meet and quarrel, but when the red men quarrelled among themselves, a little bird flew over, and sung to the white man,. and told him his red brother's land was the best. Then they left their own for this, but the Great Spirit says that if his Indian children will i *9 live at peace with each other, and be again like brothers, he will give i them the power to drive the pale faces away, and they shall again pos- i sess the land that belongs to them, and where the bones of their fath- rs rest" \i 4  U      EARLY DAYS IN MCHTAN,.         S3 CHAPTER XVI. ' And when is my father going to lead his young men on, the war' path," asked Edward with some anxiety, "are the different tribes now: ready to lift the tomahawk together?" "'Not yet, my, son," replied Szgito, "for there are many tribes to, whom belts and messages have'been sent, and whose words have not yet. come back to the ear of Tecumseh.   Some dwell far to',the Sout, where the waters never freeze, and the leaves drop from the trees without. being changed by the keen air which we feel here. They will have &amp;l11en, perhaps, more than once before all is ready. There is much to be dones, but when the red men are once more united as brothers, and go upoi the war-path to drive away the pale faces, they will never rest until they can again roam ,free over every foot of the land which the white man now calls his own." Edward Wilton was hardly prepared to hear of so extensive a cnsI- racy against his white kindred. He knew that the Peninsula tnries wrew, almost unanimously pledged to stand by the British in a contest widi was considered inevitable, though perhaps distant; but he was entirely unaware, until now, that the Indians through the country were banding together, with the intention, as it seemed, of annihilating the white men on the Western Continent. Nothing had been said by Sagito of their' English allies, but to Edward's quick intelligence it appeared evident that Tecumseh, and his still more powerful brother, must contemplate using them as tools, first availing themselves of their assistance inA - stroying the Americans, and then uniting the whole Indian force to dver them in their turn from a country which all alike coveted. He had hear&amp; accounts from some of the older warriors of the great and terrible gous. of the pale faces, and the strong buildings which they had erected, in s a many places, to shelter themselves while ther fired on the compara-iw defeaceless Indians; he knew, as he had said to Sagito that their com \  *  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC8373-00000026"/> X,'3         :EDWARD WILTON, OR I ' I 'ow far had been ever onward, in spite of the resistance which the forest arriors had offered, and it seemed to him impossible that a union could Ebe formed powerful enough to destroy this mighty race.       I In speaking to the young man Sagito had for the moment forgotten  hat he was himself by birth one of the hated intruders on the soil of the red man, and that even now he was meditating his departure from i tose with whom he had been apparently identified for so many years. , Yhe mind of the chief had been so completely absorbed by his patri- eo6c and triumphant visions that all other considerations had sunk into iWvinon. He already looked forward to the time when the broad lakes, MSe mighty rivers, and the beautiful forest of his glorious country should t:fTree from the detested presence of the white man, and, for this too vmas part of the scheme of the leading chiefs, the Indian should have thrown aside every token of his intercourse- with them, and have return- a to the simple weapons, and still simple dress, which satisfied his fathers. gith head and heart full of these thoughts, and forgetful, as we have said, to whom he was unburdening them, even the schooled and statue like countenance of Sagito showed some surprise, when his auditor asked: ' And does my red father think that one who was born among the pale a ees, whose kindred are those marked out for destruction by the red mau, should go with him, and perhaps kill his brother by the side of his itaher's grave, because Sagito brought him from them to his village so Song ago that the memory of his first home is lost " -My son has lived all his life like a warrior, and not like the pale &amp;ces who shut themselves up in their trading houses, till they fear the ar of a summer night, and cannot find their way for a day's journey  trough the forests. The Eagle Eye would pine among them for the   ; Seedom of a hunter's life, as the wild deer which has been caught, pines y XUe bound again into the green woods."               : "The words of the chief was rather an evasion of the question than an  ainswer to it, and so the young man felt it, but when he. repeated the ,pery in a somewhat different form, Sagito only said: 'My son had better think of his words till the green' leavesecome Bagn; perhaps before that time some bird will sing so sweetly in his iar that he will again forget the foolish tongue of the pale facesi and be 'Biing to stay with his red brethren."   ARLY DAYS N   MNICHGAN. .r I He rose as he spoke, as if desirous of ending the conversation he hat so unthinkingly commenced, and left the lodge. Edward paused ftor . moment, thai1 he might not seem to intrude upon his adopted father and then without speaking again to the females in the lodge, he too p . aside the curtain and went forth, to calm his troubled thoughts in thXe clear stillness of the night. The dwelling of Sagito stood on the rising ground, at some little dis- tance from the river, and sufficiently elevated to allow the eye to trace itm graceful winding. Oak trees were scattered about the hill and over the plain at its foot, yet not so thickly as to hide the water, gleamineg through their boughs like burnished steel beneath the unclouded light of a fuiO moon. All was still, save the monotonous sound of the rushing watem, which came softly sweet upon the ear at that distance. The songs and-  gambols of the Indian children were ended for the day, and a perfeet quiet reigned over the groups of low huts, so distinctly visible in th? clear frosty light. As Edward Wilton gazed around, he could identif many a spot endeared to him by some childish frolic, or boyish triuiphi. Even the tree under whose boughs he had laid the senseless form of the. Springing Fawn, was] perfectly distinct, and  as his eye rested on ite branches, they seemed to him to stand outeven more conspicuously thal the rest, as if to remind him of those early happy days. o,                 .                  - ,     , .   I        t  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC8373-00000027"/> ;44          BIDWARD WILTON, OR CHAPTER XVII.  Not a single word of the conversation between Sagito and his son I as lost on the attentive ears of the two women who were still silently y reparing the game which Edward had brought home. To Nadesha Sthere was little in it that was new, but it deepened her sorrowful con- w Ancfion that the parting she so dreaded, for other hearts a w!as her own, was inevitable. -But the few words which had fallen from the lips df her lover, were the turning of a new leaf, and oh! how dark a one Ms the book of life for the Springing Fawn. She saw at once as by in- teion what had driven the smile from his lip, and joyfulness from his tne. She knew that the signal for the confederated tribes to raise the tomahawk would be the signal of eternal separation between herself and wim who had saved her life, and in the first *-itterness of her anguish,- sire wished that he had allowed the dark waters to close forever over &amp;er head, rather than he should leave her now to a loneliness more ter- ;rible than death. It seemed strange to her now, that she had not 'sooner discovered the real cause of his change of manner, but a vague feeling of jealousy, she knew not of whom or what, had heretofore been like a thick cloud hiding the light of truth from her eyes. Na- desha had been anxiously, though covertly, watching her young favorite to see what effect, if any, the conversation might have upon her mind, -and it was with more sorrow than surprise that she marked the rich blood desert her face, and her features become almost gliastly 1h their epression, while the small taper hands trembled and grasped convul- sively the bird which she had been holding. She did not speak how- vew, and went on with her employment mechanically until Edward had leftthe lodge, and she was once more alone with Nades; then she traed, and after a few hurried words dof apology to her friend for leav- ag her before her task was done, stepped to the door without waiting for an answer, and seeing that no one was near enough to observe her, *fr the trunk of a large tree hid the Eagle Eye from her sight, she glideo   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGA. Gig swiftly along the side of the hill until her form was lost among the trees. In a few moments however, she descended to the plain, and carefully avoiding the vicinity of the huts,.soon found herself at her favorite seat beneath the branches of the old oak at the river side. She thought not of the keen frosty air of the autumn night, nor, of the cold damp ground on which she stood, but she threw herself down, and pressed her forehead oq the grass, already growing white and crisp beneath the cold moonlight. She did not sob aloud, but her- slight frame trembled like a leaf, as she lay on the bank hearing, though not listening to, the dashing of the water past her restnig place. How many an hour of happy reverie had she spent in that very spot, and, more lately, how many a one of anxious thought! She had believed that any thing was preferable to suspense, yet now that she felt rather than knew the truth, she thought her past uncertainty had been almost happiness, and more than once she was tempted to spring into the darr, deep water which edied and whirled almost beneath her feet, but the remembrance of her parents to whom she was so dear, a feeling of fem- inine pride which forbade,her to cast away her life for the desertion, as she deemed it then, of a lover, blended with a vagueindistinct idea that the Great Spirit would smile less kindly on her if she rushed uncalled into his presence, checked these wild thoughts; and after a time she grew more calm, and the bitter, the hopeless despair, not unmingled with indignation with which she had thrown herself upon the ground, gave place to a very different feeling. Again the Eagle Eye was all that was good and brave, and noble in her estimation. She no longer doubt- ed his love for her, and she regarded with admiration the more than In- dian firmness under suffering which led him to renounce all that he , knew or loved, every hope which had seemed to make the happiness of his life, rather than join the forest warriors, in the slaughter of his own kindred.  In arriving at this conclusion, the Indian girl might. have imagined that his resolution was taken more entirely from a sense of duty than it really was, for she knew nothing of Edward's meeting with the white man, nor the strange, mysterious stirring of memory in his heart, which seemed to call him away with a voice too mighty to be ra- mted.  ' As these thoughts passed through her mind, she gradua grew  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC8373-00000028"/> S6'          EDWARD WILTON? OR calmer, and remembering that her mother Aould be looking anxiously for her at this hour, she rose and with slow and thoughtful steps took her way home.  Her mother stood betre the lodge watching for her return, but her eyes were, bent in te direction of Sagito's lodge, and the maiden's light step was inaudible on the turf, so that she stood by her mother's side before the latter was aware of her approach. i F          ."  -s                  ,         "'   EARLY DAYS N MCOHGAN         5 r CHAPTER XVIII. The matron turned in some surprise. "My daughter is here at last," she said, "but the moon is very high in the heaven, and she comes not from the lodge of Nadesha. Has she been wandering with the village- girls in this frosty air "  "I have been alone, my mother," replied the girl, " but the lodge was too close and warm when I left it, and sought the river bank that the running water might sing to me, and the cool breath of the evening cool my head, and bring sleep to my eyes." She entered the lodge as she spoke, and commenced her simple pre- parations for slumber, but her mother noticed her damp garments, and dripping moccasins, and insisted on chafing with her own hands, the delicate little feet which were indeed more like marble to the touch than flesh and blood. Then she prepared with maternal anxiety some favor- ite prescription of the Indian matrons which her daughter must swal- low to avert the danger frff the night ramble. The Springing Fawn submitted with affectionate docility, for her heart reproached her with having, in her first wild burst of sorrow, forgotten even for a moment -d8 the mother whose whole happiness she knew was bound up it herself, and she felt that with such -love to depend upon, she could never be wholly wretched. These thoughts brought a more life-like glowto her clear cheek, and something of its natural light to her soft dark eyes, which the watchful mother attributed entirely to the renovating powers of her favorite medicine. More discerning people than the old Indian woman have sometimes made as great mistakes in their reasoning. At last, howev- er, the maiden was permitted to seek her couch, which was covered carefully with the softest skins the lodge afforded, and in the darkness and stillness of the night, her thoughts gained-fresh strength and calm- ness. She said to herself that the determination of the Eagle Eye never- to lift the tomakawk against those whose blood ran in his owns vein,was   &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC8373-00000029"/> 58          EDWARD WILTON, OR worthy of the noblest chiefs of her own race, and with the heroism of a loving and strong hearted woman, she resolved that-neither by word or look would she endeavor to turn him aside from his destined path. "The Great Spirit has whisperedin the ear of the EagleEye," she murmured, " he calls his son back to the home whsre he placed him at first, and he will be displeased with his red children if they speak in an- other tongue to the youth of the pale face." No sleep visited the eyes of the maiden that night, and yet the hours passed swiftly, and she looked with surprise on the increasing light within the lodge, which told that another day had dawned; for her soul had been filled with high andself-sacrificiug thoughts and purposes and the lapse of time had been all unmarked. And the Eagle Eye; the object of every thought in as true and gen- tle a heart as ever beat, how had the long autumn night waned with him?  He stood long in mournful reverie, gazing on the fair and familiar scene around him, but all unconscious that under the dark branches of the tree on which his eyes were resting, the soul of the Springing Fawn was wrestling with wild and bitter thoughts. He had not seen her leave the lodge, and he felt that they must not meet again until he had ( summoned oourage to announce to her the resolution which he had . formed.  Till now they had shared each others confidence for years, and I as he recalled the sad tone in which she had spoken to him that night, i his heart told him that she was only justly grieved and displeased at his I cold reserve.  lie remained still and silent as. a sentinel on the gentle slope of the hill, until the turning shadows on the grass warned him of ,the lateness of the hour, and then he noiselessly entered the lodge, and t sought his accustomed place of repose.               :i The morning rose brightly beautiful on the Indian village. . The rip- pling waters of the two rivers glanced and quivered like streams of dia- .  monds in the clear October sunlight, and the pure healthful breeze played i with the changing leaves of the forest trees, yet so gently that not one i fell from is parent bough to the still green grass beneath. The merry sound of children's voices, and the gay laugh of the Indian girls was heard as they gathered the golden ears of corn under the superinten. I dence of the older women. The men were issuing from their lodges,   I gun in hand, for the woods were well filled with game, and this was the *    EARLY DAYS IrN MHtmGA.      '   59 *srason for laying in their winter store of provision and skins. The Springing Fawn was silent, but as busily occupied as any of her young companions, as she labored alone in the rude Barden belonging to her father; and Edward Wilton was prepared to r eew the hunt of yes- terday, though now he proposed to seek his gam. among the pictur- esque hills west of the village. Otagimi's lodge was situated on the broad terrace-like plain which extends from the first low bluff near the river to the foot of the higher ridge. Edward was to call for his friend, and almost unconsciously to himself, took the path he had so often pursued on similar occasions, and which led him directly past the home of the Springing Fawn. Her light and graceful form moving among the dry and rustling cornstalks, reminded him of his resolution to avoid her for the present, but it was too late, for she had already per- ceived him and paused from her labor as if to receive and-return the usual greeting,  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC8373-00000030"/> 60          EDWARD WILTON, OR' CHAPTER XIX. "Does the Springing Fawn find the ears fall and plenty upon the stalks," asked Edward as he drew near. "The corn is very good," replied the girl "there will be no hunger among the children of the tribe in the winter. And the Eagle Eye, does he seek the deer again to-day?" "They are plenty among the hills," said the young man, " and the lodge of my mother must be well filled with' vension and skins when the winter comes-that she may feel neither hunger nor cold in the long nights, and the short cold days." "It is well," returned the Fawn, "for Sagito loves not the chase now as he was wont to do, and when the Eagle Eye has left the banks of the Kalamazoo to dwell with his white brothers, Nadesha will have no one to bring her skins to dress or vension to dry. It is well that her son should prepare for her comfort while he is yet with her." "Who has said to the Springing Fawn that the adopted son of Sagi- to would leave his red father and his home by the river side?" Edward asked the question in some surprise, though with a feeling of reliefthat the young girl had been the first to introduce a subject which he had dreaded so much. "She heard the chief talk with his son in the lodge last night, and through all the summer our warriors have spoken of going again on the war path against the pale faces, as our fathers did before them. The Eagle Eye will not stay at honme and hoe corn with the women and children, while Ws red brothers are gaining glory in the battle, and did he not say to Sagito that he could not raise the hatchet against his own people 8"  'Her dark eyes were raised to his face as she spoke, and her whole countenance glowed with the earnestness of her soul. Her lover had been gazing on her intently, and for a moment he felt that he could   *   r    '     .          O   EARLY DAYS IN MCHA.           61 sacrifice his kindred, his nation, all, and every thing for the sake of the beautiful girl by whose side he stood. But the feeling of temptation passedlaway as he listened to her words, for he knew he should then be unwoohy of her for whom he gave up so much, and something like the sentiment so beautifully expressed by a poet of a distant land, rose to his thoughts, though crude and almost undefined. "Icould not love thee, dear, so much, Loved I not honor more."           e "Does the Springing Fawn say that it is a bad voice which whispers in the ear of the son of the white man that he must not fight against his own nation. Nadesha tells him that it is. an evil bird, and Sagito says that he is too young to know the good voice or the bad. Let me hear the thoughts of the young maiden," said'he at length.) "Let the Eagle Eye listen to the voice in his heart," replied the Fawn, "it will tell him better than the words of .a foolish girl. The Great Spirit sends the words to call him again to his kindred, and he must go, but when he dwells in the villages of the pale faces, will he not think some- times of the river flowing through the oak woods, by whose banks he dwelt so long ."  "The lodge of his red father, and the dwelling of-the young Fawn will ever be dearer to the heart of the Eagle Eye than the villages of the whites," said Edward, "'but when he has found the home of his childhood, will not the Springing Fawn come from the woods and share it with him; it will be dark without her smile, and lonely and still if he cannot hear her sweet voice." The thought of accompanying her lover had never entered the mind of the mind of the Indian girl, and she could not summon words for a moment to refuse a request which brought such visions of happiness. Her voice sounded sadder than it had previously done as she said at last. "The Eagle Eye must go alone. He will not ask his sister to leave her mother and her people to dwell among strangers, wlhowill look with scorn on her dark skin. Since the day when the Eafle Eye drew the young girl from the rushing waters, they have trodden one path, and it has been very pleasant, and the same birds sang very sweetly in their ears, But now   their steps must tread in different ways. The Eagle  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC8373-00000031"/> Is A- 62           EDWARD WILTON, OR Eye will not again ask his sister to turn toward the white settlements, and she knows he may not dwell longer in the lodge of the red man. But see," she added hastily, as if desirous of ending a conversation which was becoming too painful, "Otagimi is seeking his friend, and the sun is high above the trees. The Eagle Eye will go to the hills, and let him remember that he and the Fawn are as brother and sister? She turned away as she spoke, to conceal her increasing agitation, and avoid Otagimi, who was now drawing near, after having waited for his promised companion till his patience was exhausted. Edward heeded not his railery on the cause of his delay, for he was recalling the last words of her with whom he-had just parted. He rebelled in his heart. against her decision, even thou'gh h3 felt it to be just, and never had he loved more fondly than when she had reminded him that " their paths must now be separate." Amid these conflicting feelings came a gleam of joy that she who was dearer to him/than all, had divined the struggle in his heart, and enootraged him in the course which he had determined to pursue.        , O         .    BARLY DAYS rI M6HXGA.          63 CHAPTER XX. The long dreary winter had worn away, and Spring in her fairest ar- ray was bursting upon the prairies and woods of the Peninsula. The anemone had heralded her approach, as it showed its delicate purple at the roots of the old trees on the hills, the snowy bloodroot and. the golden cowslip had expanded on the swampv ground below, the wavingo branches of the shade tree with its myriads of white blossoms, cast their gracefull shadows on the fresh green grass, and the notes of a thousanad birds made glad music among the forest trees, whose unfolding leaves foretold their coming wealth of foiliage. The months which had passed since we left Edward Wilton turning from the home of the Springing Fawn to seek ihe deer and the bear among the hills, had but confirmed his determination- to leave the Indi-- ans, and if possible rejoi'n his own kindred.. Through the winter there- had been constant intercourse with distant tribes. Emissaries from Tecumseh and his brother, the Prophet, had visited every/village on the Peninsula, and though the details of their errand were of course confided only to the ears of the older chiefs, the principal object of it was no se- cret among the tribes. Even the women and children, as the former planted their rude gardens, or the latter pursued their play along the banks of the river, spoke together of the day when the red man should again be lord of his own land, untrammelled by the leighborhood of the pale faces. Nor had the agents of the English government been idle; they had revisited the principal chiefs to renew their gifts, and exact fresh promi- ses from them, to be in readiness when' they should give the signal for the first blow to be struck. Little did the Englishin thbjnks he saw the fierce sparkle of the Indian warrior's eye, and hearthe stern deter- mination of his tone when he assured him that " they had not forgotten their white brother's words, their young men would be ready," that tae: \  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC8373-00000032"/> "      2    EDWARD WILTON, OR wily savage was playing even a deeper and more treacherous game than himself, and was contemplating with secret exultation the coming Xde- struction of the very nation at whose bidding he had promised to rush into battle. Edward had watched with an anxious eye the proceedings of the winter, as far as they had come to his knowledge. He did not share in X the belief of the Indians that the white race were now to be extirpated on the Western continent, for he had heard something of the story of progress from the old men of the tribe, and the more he thought of it, the more improbable it seemed that they .could now be driven from the land which they had so gradually and so surely acquired. He had said nothing more to Sagito on the subject of his departure. The mind of the old chief seemed filled with war-like plans and arrangements, but there was yet room in it for many an anxious thought of his adopted son, for whom he felt an affection he would have considered it quite de- rogatory to his dignity as a chief and a warrior to express. It was one lovely evening in May, as the sun was setting among the richest colored clouds, that Sagito was seated under a tree near his lodge with his pipe in his mouth, and wrapped in meditation, When the Eagle Eye drew near to him with a branch of a maple tree in his hand. "The leaves of another spring have come; does my father see them a" he enquired, as he presented the fresh green bough to the warrior. "I see the green leaves," said Sagito, " and my ears are open to hear the words of my son. Does the voice of the pale faces still whisper to him                       ,  "He still hears the voice which tells him to seek his own people," re- plied Edward, " and its sound grows louder and clearer; the spirit talks to him when he sleeps, and his dreams are of his white brothers whose faces he cannot remember, but they seem to stand around his couch, and call him back to his home." For a few minutes Sagito'did not speak, but there were marks of strong emotion on his usually calm and stern countenance. At length he said: It 'i well. Let my son .seek the villages of the pale faces, but let him remember that when the hatchet of the tribes is -once dug up, it will not be buried again till the blood of the last white man in our land. has reddened its steel,"   EARLY DAYS IN MOHGAN.          65 "Then the Eagle'Eye will fall with those among whom the,Great Spirit placed him when he first sent him upon earth," returned E dward, "and if his red father meets him on the battle field, he will see that his white son has learned the' duty of a warrior." "' Does my son know the path which leads to the settlements of the J palefaces?" asked the chief; "he is not like the bird -which can 4fly straight to the nest from which it has been carried. Will he go'alone, to find his home V" "He can find his way through the woods, towards the rising su n, replied the youth, "and the villages of the whites lie along the g reat river and the lakes., When he reaches the water he will find his peo- pie." Sagito paused. He had not supposed that his young compa nion had' so correct an idea of that part of the country from which he was broug ht. He had given his consent to his departure .reluctantly, aod solely from the superstitious reverence which the Indian feels forthe portents of a dream or the supposed admonition of a spirit. But though so many years -had passed since he bore the fair boy from the river Ra isin, he, had never yet forgiven or forgotten the fancied' insult he had receiv ed from Mr. Wilton, and his revenge would have been lost, hd he allowed Edward to return to the father from whom-he had been so long sepa- rated  \    A                           /  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC8373-00000033"/> 'B6j EDWARD WILTON, OR CHAPTER XXI. "Will my father tell me," asked Edward at length, impatient of the Silence, "in which one of the white villages I shall find the home from which he: ook me i" "Mysbn need not look along the banks of the broad river for his *early home, he must go farther South. If he will leave his red breth- ten, let him depart with Otagimi. The young chief goes with a belt to Tecumseh, and his path lies near one of the strong places which- the pale facesS have built to protect their soldiers from the tomahawk of the T Indion warrior, and to shelter their great guns. When they come with- in a days journey -of the strong house, let my son leave him, and seek ,the white men who dwell there. 'It may be that theyl can tell him of his 5ther or his brothers."   It tvin- vain that the yoiung man sought for some more particular diretions by, which he might discover his kindred. The wily chief art- full rmislead him with regard to the place of his- captivity, and professed entire ignorance of the name of the family from which he had been taken, -but all in suoh a manner that the suspicions of the Eagle Eye were not i for a moment awakened;. The apparent ignorance of Sagito concerning 'A:is name did not surprise him, for he well knew the habits of the sava- /ges, and that many an unoffending family of whites had been destroyed -by them in the mere wantoness of cruelty. His adopted father, from the comparative mildness of his temper, would scarcely have headed :such an expedition, but it was in no degree improbable that Sagito had -leen present at some scene of blood, like those of which he had heard, 'and had rescued him from the slaughter which awaited the rest of his family. The young man therefore willingly acquiesced in a plan which would give him the company of his most intimate friend for many days journey :through the wilderness, and sinace the struggle of leaving those whom - he loved must come, he wished that it might be over as soon as possi-   EBARLY DAYS IN McHdAN.        6T ble. He knew not how soon hostilities'between the two races might ,commence, and he regarded himself almost as a spy among those whom he felt that he must one day meet on the battle field.      For a long time he had said nothing to Nadesha of his plans, but since the snows had melted from the plain, and the first breath of apring had blown through the woods, the gentle,Indian woman had never seen her white son enter her lodge, that her heart had not throbbed; and her eyes watched him with a nervous anxiety, lest he should have come to announce his approaching departure. But there was Mother yet dearer to him than his adopted motherto whom all his hoe and fears had been confided. In the true and unelfish soul'of the Spring- ing Fawn he had found a depth of sympathy which others had denied him. She spoke with apparent calmness to him of the day whenir h should leave his woodland home, though she felt persuaded that, once separated, they should never meet again, and it was with a mournfiul smile that she listened to the visionary plans of Edward Wilton for a meeting at some future day, which should know no parting but death. His sanguine spirit could not brook the thought that "they could live asunder. War could not last forever, and the hatchet once buried, and as he fondly hoped, the red man being peaceably on -the same territory with his white brother, he would return to the Indian village, and bear hi forest flower to bloom among the lilies of another race. Or it might be that he should seek in vain for the home of his infancy, the kindred from whom h e had been snatched. Ha would only remain with" his own nation till peace should be restored, and then turn his steps ones more towards the green banks of the Kalamazoo, and end his life among those with whom so large a portion of it had been spent; and the Fawn, would she keep a place in her heart and memory for him, however long his absence might be? Would she trust in his love, and promise to share his home wherever it might be, when he again sought the In- dian village. An hundred times had the Eagle Eye asked these ques- tions of one who could not have forgotten him if she would, whose very existence was but a thought of him, and who would have considered one smile bestowed on another a sort of sacrilege towards the saviour of her young life.       . "The Springing Fawn can never forget him who drew her fromthe  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC8373-00000034"/> 68           EDWARD WILTON, OR dark waters," she replied one day to some such lover-like queries. It was one of the softest, loveliest days of early spring, that the pair was standing together beneath the old tree on the river's bank. The young maiden had 'eagerly returned to her favorite haunt as soon as the in- creasing warmth of the weather permitted her to escape with her work, from the close and confined air of the lodge, and Edward had sought the place in the hope of meeting her yet once more where so many hap- py moments had been spent. She had risen at his approach, and the basket upon which her fingers had been mechanically employed lay at her feet among the blue violets which looked as if flakes from the azure sky above had fallen on the soft green grass. Her slight figure leant against the rough brown trunk of the tree, and her dark eyes were raised to his face with a look of mournful tenderness. "The Springing Fawn can never forget him who drew her from the darkwaters" she repeated, "the image of the Eagle Eye will be in the heart of his sister when she sleeps and when she wakes, till the great Spirit shall call her away from earth, but she knows that when his steps are turned towards the homes of the pale faces, he will return no more to the vilage of Sagito." The young man vainly endeavored to combat this presentment of evil. It was too deeply implanted in the heart -of the Indian girl, yet she did not seem to fear his inconstancy, or to believe that the attractions of the home which he might find, would erase the memory of the pre- sent one. It seemed a belief so strongly impressed on her heart, that when,they parted it must be forever. o , ; /       /         fi  J \                   t           EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         69 -CHAPTER XXII. The sun was sinking slowly to the horizon, aS if unwilling to leave a scene so far as that on which his last rays were resting. It had been one of the most lovely days of early summer, and the scene was in one of the deep forests with which at that period, a vast tract of country which is now a smiling garden, was covered. The foliage had but just t unfolded to its full beauty, and the air was fragrant with the blossoms of a thousand flowering trees and shrubs, whose snowy petals contrasted strongly with the vivid green of the larger trees. Through this lonely and almost unbroken wilderness ran a rapid river, and just at this point - where a smaller stream swelled its waters, rose a fort, the only evidenee that man had ever intruded on the quiet of the woods. The building. in question, was not one of the noble structures of later days, the cost of whose erection is counted by tens or hundreds of thousands, but was composed principally of hewn logs, and rude in its appearance, though strong and capable of defence. Several officers were standing on the smooth turf outside the pickete, to enjoy the freshness and sweetness of the evening breeze, and their conversation which had been at ;first of a lively and jesting nature, i&amp;ad turned upon their Indian neighbors, who showed a growing disposition to become troublesome, when one of them suddenly pointed some dis, tance down the river, and exclaimed, "Look! there comes one of the red skinned gentry now. What should bring him to the fort alone, I wonder." "Are you sure he is an Indian, Ashey," asked another, my eyesight is not so-good as yours, but he has more of the figure and- air of a white man, I should think, than one of our copper colored friends." "You are right," returned Captain Ashey, "as far ashis general ap,- lpearance is concerned, but I can see his dress distinctly, and it is the full Indian costume. Hie is a splendid figure of a fellow too, but," he ex- * claimed, interrupting himself, "he is a white man after all. ASa heh A L  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC8373-00000035"/> o0          EDWARD WILTON', on comes nearer can you not see his hair 2 Nothing like that ever grew on an Indian scalp." "Yes," said another of the little group, which was now eagerly watch- ing the approach of the solitary traveller, whose firm, rapid step had now brought him fully into view, "yes his skin and his features are those of a white man, though the former be something of the darkest, and here is no mistaking that wavy dark brown hair. What and why can I be " "We shall know something about him soon," observed Ashey, "for he comes straight towards the fort. Some poor fellow escaped from the tender mercies ofthe savages, I fancy. He has borne his captivity well' however, if that is the case. One conjecture after another was hazarded as to who the young trav, der should be, who,well dressed in the fashin of an Indian warrior, weaong,instead of the ungraceful and unmanly blanket, a sort of hunt- ing shirt made of deerskin, and richly' embroidered with porcupine quill ;and carring in his hand a splendid gun, while his tomahawk was slung at his waist, bore no resemnblance either in his garb, or in his proud free bearing to an escaped captive. The wonder increased in no small measure, when as he came near the officers, and one of them addressed him courteously in English; the youngman's color deepened to crimson, and he asked in very imperfect English, for an interpreter. Fortunately there was one in the fort, and he was immediately sent for, and the commanding officer notified of their singular visitor. The stranger spoke rapidly and fluently in the Indian tongue, and the interpreter, who was a white man, listened with hdis;guised wonder. Every man off duty in the fort had gathered around the little circle, and most impatiently did all await the transla- tion of the short narrative. His own statement concluded, the young-  stranger stood quietly leaning on his rifle, and watching the group a- round him with an interest at least equal to that with which he was re- garded, while the interpreter turned to Colonel Hamilton, and repeated in English : story which he had just heard. "'The fyouifgeow says, Colonel;' said he, " that he cannot remem- ber the time when he did, not live among the Indians, and that he does not know how or when he was taken prisoner. He has been treated as /   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN. -  one of the tribe among whom he lived, and is the adopted so. of one .. of their chiefs. 'But they have never spoken to him in -his en lan - guage, and he has forgotten it all, though he says that some of the words he hears now, seem familiar to his ear." "Does he tell from whence he comes 2" asked Col. Hamilton. "He has not yet, sir," replied the man, "but I know by his speech, he has been among the Pottawatomies, off at the northwest. He says too, that his Indian father sent him here, to find if he could, some traces . of his family. A cunning trick of the old red-skin truly, for so longago- % as this boy must have been taken, there was not a "white settlement wihi-- in fifty miles." "But why has he been sent from them," asked an officer, "there i'. some other trick in this." "I think not, sir," replied the interpreter, " they would have sent an. older hand if they had meant any tricking ;- and he was not sent either- buthy some chance he saw a white man and heard him speak, and that made him anxious to know something more of his own people, and, when he heard some talk of the hatchet being unburied, he conclude&amp;d; to be on the side of his own color, for which I honor him, and though} he would have gone to one of the settlements along Detroit river, think:. ing his home was in that direction, his Indian father eent him off here, on what I reckon will prove a wild-goos e-chase. It is a good thing the boy has got among white folks at last, at any rate, and when he gets off that Indian ringing, and has learned a little of his mother tongue, Pll engage he'll be as good a white man as any one here." "Tell him that he is welcome to the fort, Johnson," said Col, Famil ton, "and assure him that I will assist him to the extent of my power in. discovering his friends. You must try to teach him English as fast as  possible, and he looks bright enough not to be long in learning. The young man will be no mean acquisition to our ranks, Ashey," he con- . tinued, turning to that officer, " if we may trust to appearances." i"You can hardly be deceived in him, I think, sir," replied Captain Ashey, "I never saw a finer looking man, or a more open, frank, yet resolute expression. I long to hear him speak his own language, how-  ever, for that savage gibberish is not worthy of him." "You will provide for his quarters among your men to-night," said&amp;                             7t -   &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC8373-00000036"/> t12         EDWARD WILnTON, OR Col. Hamilton as he turned away, " and tell Johnson to see that he has his supper, ad what else he may want. I will see him again to-mor- row."  i       EARLY DAYS Iyt MOHGAN. '3 CHAPTER     XXIII. Night settled quietly on the fort and those within its walls, but brought no slumber to the eyes of Edward Wilton. Neither' the novelty of his situation, nor the arrangements for sleeping, so different from those to which he had been accustomed, would have been sufficient to destroy the rest which comes so easily to the young and healthful, but since he had left Otagimi, he seemed to feel for the first time in its full bitterness, how far and how completely he was separated from the beautiful Indian maiden, on the distant, banks of the Kalamaioo. In obedience to the wishes of Sagito, whose will was law to his people, it was only under- stood by the tribe in general, that the Eagle Eye was to accompany Otagimi, and two or three other warriors, on their long and secret mis- sion to receive his first lessons in the art of Indian diplomacy, preparato- ry to entering on his career as a warrior, and perhaps a future chief. The two whose hearts clung most fondly to his, knew that-this could scarce- ly be, yet Nadesha at least had received no intimation of the truth; and she had prepared the parched corn and dried vension for his journey, and supplied the pouch or bag which he carried, -with fresh moccasins *to replace his own, when they were worn with long travel, in the full ex- pectation that when the leaves which were now so fresh and beautiful, were putting on the crimsom and gold attire of the autumn months, her adopted son would again stand before her. To the Fawn, her lover had ventured to hint the truth, and a hint was sufficient for the heart whose faculties had been quickened by suffering, but ever to her oldest friend, the wife of Sagito, no change in her manner betrayed the secret, A sad composure had now taken the place of the gentle gaiety of former days, and the step which had been as slight and almost as fleet as that of the beautiful creature for whom she was named, was now slbw and   thoughtful. Yet never had she seemed. more beautiful in the eyes of Edward Wilton, than when they stood for the last time together at heir old trysting place on the evening before he left the village. "Her  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC8373-00000037"/> "          EDWARD WILTON, OR image was before him as he tossed on his restless couch, and his memory retraced every word and look of that parting scene. He had sent mes- sages to her by Otagimi, the true and tried friend of both, and assuran- ces that they should meet again, yet now all that he had said seemed cold and unmeaning, and he would have given worlds for another inter- view with his friend. The thought of Nadesha also haunted him; he pictured to himself the bitter sorrow with which she would see the return of the young warriors without him who was the idol of her heart, yet he did not for a moment think of abandoning his purpose of endeavor- ingto'find his family, or learn something of his true history,-if, as he sometimes feared, he was alone on the earth. - There was something strangely familiar to him in the sound of the laguaeh e had heard that night, and in the faces of the white men on, whom he gazed. Something of the feeling which perhaps all have ex-- perienced, at some time in their lives, that the scene in which they are- that moment an actor is but a repetition of what they have known and felt before, either in a dream or in real life. The thought flashes across the mind that the same words have been heard, the same faces seen at some other period, nay, even the inanimate objects around are familir, though seen apparently for the first time, and every moment deepens the impression, while both reason and memory assure the dreamer that he has never been placed in a position precisely similar. Edward knew too little of himself how or where his early childhood had been passed, and the thought that he might have been a soldier's son occurred to him more than once. The courteous, dignified manners, and tall commanding figure of Colonel Hamilton, seemed to recall some slight rememberance of his own fahto his mind, and he longed for ithe morning to come, though he had alrsady been assured by Johnson, the interpreter, that there was but little probability of his search being successful in the region where he now was. He had related to this wan the little that he knew of himself, and Johnson;who understood the Wnmes of Indian intrigue as well as Sagito himself, had at once avowed his belief that he belonged to some part or settlement farther north, yet r he strongly recommended the young man to remain where he was for; the present, to learn for the second time his own language, and render himself more familiar with the customs of the whites, before re-com- mencing his search.   BARELY DAYS IN MOHGAN.        65 You will need a little time to learn to speak and dress like a Chris- tian, young man," said he, "and then you must have a white man's name found for you, till you recover your own. The savages showed some judgement though, when they called you the Eagle Eye, for rll engage those black eyes of yours can see as quick and as far as, any in the fort." i ?  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC8373-00000038"/> jIs          EDWARD WILTON, OY CHAPTER XXIV. By the kind thoughtfulness of Col. Hnamilton, the dress of a white man had been provided for Edward Wilton, before the usual hour for rising, and Johnson had assisted him in arranging the unwonted attire, which he declared was an infinite improvement to his new friend. A mere admirer of the picturesque would perhaps have preferred the rich- ly wrought hunting shirt to the blue coat, and the light moccasins to the heavy leather boot, but the inhabitants of the fort agree,1 with the inter- preter that the fine face and figure of the young stranger showed to much better advantage in the only dress which they considered befit- ting a white man.. It was not long before Edward was summoned to the presence of Col. Hamilton, accompanied of course by Johnson, as the -only medium of communication between himself and those around him. Several offi- eers were present, and all were surprised at the intelligence and quick- ness of observation shown by the young man in his answers to the nu- merous questions addressed to him through the interpreter. As we have said before, he had never been able to tame the buoyancy and viva- city of his spirit to the grave and solemn dignity prescribed by Indian etiquette, and the most severe reproofs he had ever received from Sagito, had related to this failue in his manner. His surprise was therefore equal to his pleasure at the sight of the animated faces and gestures in the group around him, and he felt at once that the manners of his white brothers, as he considered thei, assimilated far more with his own than the silence and reserve of the Indian warrior.    / But a few days elapsed before Edward Wilton had mastered several English phrases, under the kind tuition of Johnson, who, though an un- educated man, was both shrewd and kind hearted,while Col. Hamilton and his officers, interested in the young stranger thus suddenly thrown among them, and foreseeing the advantage which he might prove to them in the Indian difficulties which they had anticipated with but too   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         t much certainty, spared no pains in instructing him on those points of which he was now utterly ignorant, but which are so absolutely necessa- ry in civilized life.. The progress which he made in learning, or rather recovekng his own language, had astonished all who witnessed it, and with almost equal facility did he conquer the difficulties of reading and writing. His warm open-heart, and the interest attached to his story, soon rendered him a universal favorite at the fort, and all were eager to assist him in his ardent endeavors to atone for the years lost in his edu- cation, as well as in his search for some trace of his family and kindred, on which subject he only became more anxious as the time wore away; He had fully decided to remain with the army,for all his tastes and hab- its of his early life fitted him for the active and adventurous life of a frontier soldier, rather than any other employment, and he knew that the time was rapidly approaching when his country would need every heart and hand she could claim to defend her against her combined enemies. The summer passed away without any outhreak from the savages in that quarter, and before the cold blasts of autumn had scattered the leaves from the dense forests around the fort, Edward Wilton had be- come an adept in the duties of a soldier, and sufficiently familiar with his own language to bear his part in the conversation of the officers, with whom he associated. The manners of a white gentleman were ea- sily engrafted on the naturally frank and gentle temper, to which was added a slight and scarcely perceptible tinge of pride, belonging to the adopted son of a powerful chief, and few who had seen the youth for the first time six months after his arrival on the banks of the Maurmep, would have guessed that more than two-thirds of his short life had been spent in an Indian wigwam. During this period all possible enquiries had been made by his kind friends, in the hope of finding some trace of his home and history, but so far, had proved fruitless. In those days, news traveled but slowly, especially along the frontiers, and earnestly as the Wiltons still sought for some tidings of their lost one, no whisper of the dark eyed youth who had appeared so suddenly at the fort on the Maumee, had reached their anxious ears. It had of course been necessary to give him anoth- er name than the only on/ which he knew, the Eagle Eye, and at the- request of Capt. Ashey, ihose special favorite and protege he had be *   t         &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC8373-00000039"/> -8           EDWARD WILTON, OR come, he was now known and entered on the books as Henry Ashey. ( Borrow my name, I beg, my dear Eagle Eye," said the -captain when the subject was discussed, " and keep it 'till you find your own, or failing in that forever I will write to my sister if I am ever lucky enough to send a letter through this wilderness, that they have a new brother at the fort, and give them such a description that their hearts will be all impatience to behold their Unknown relation.". As Henry Ashey, then he was known, having taken only the sur- name of his friend, whose baptismal name was Walter, but to avoid using for our hero as many aliases as a city pickpocket, he will still be Edward Wilton to us, except in a few instances. '     EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          79 CHAPTER XXV. While Edward Wilton is regaining the habits of civilization within a hundred miles of the place where he first drew breath, let us turn for a time to those who had so bitterly mourned his loss, and who still so ten- derly cherished his remembrance. Mrs. Wilton received the news of Phillip's design to join the army with more calmness than her husband or children had anticipated, from one who had such terrible causes for anxiety. She had opposed her son's project for seeking his brother alone through the boundless wilder ness which spread around them, for she knew it to be wild and visiona- ry, but when she felt that his strong arm was needed for the defence of his country against the savages she so much dreaded, and their white allies, she would not by words or deed withhold him from his duty. "Go my son," said she, "if your aid is really needed, and if you and your brave companions can be the means of saving other mothers in the land from the misery I have endured, I shall feel repaid 'for my sacri- fice.  A heavy weight was lifted from the heart of Phillip Tilton, for he had feared that his mother would endeavor to dissuade him fom   his purpose, or if she refrained from that, that her grief would be so ex- cessive as to render it almost -impossible for him to fulfill it. "A thousand thanks, my dearest mother," he exclaimed. "We have all underrated your courage and patriotism. This war once over, our British neighbors made a little more reasonable, and our savage friends a little less saucy, our frontier villages will be more comfortable places of abode than they have been for years past." "You forget, PhiN,' said his mother, sadly, " how many brave hearts must cease to beat, and how many hearts must be made desolate ere that blessed time can come, if indeed with her small force, our country can contend successfully with the Briton and the savage." "Henry Effington would tell you mother," replied Phillip, " that the \   &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC8373-00000040"/> 80          EDWARD WILTON, OR battle is not always to the strong. We have right on our side, and does not God defend the right? Every man in our ranks will have th strength of ten of the foreign hirelings, when he feels that he is fighting to protect his loved ones from cruelty and insult. Some 4f us I know must fall, but, if you arc called to weep over the grave of your son, it shall be with proud tears."  "Remember one thing, my son," said Mr. Wilton, who had been standing by, an anxious listener to -the conversation, "Remember one thing: rashness is not bravery. Do your duty as a soldier, I need not say, shrink from no uifariecessary exposure; but do not rush needlessly upon danger. Recollect that your country asks for the lives, not the useless deaths of her soldiers, and never, since she wore a name among nations, has she needed those lives more than now. I will not speak of our own selfish feelings at a time like this, but when your impetuous heart is tempting you into some wild scheme, let ittell you also, that you Ae our only son, and that your death would break your mother's heart." Mr. Wilton's tone was grave, even to solemnity, but calm, and Phil- lip's spirit was hushed by his words. "Depend upon my thoughtful- nessw my dear father," said he, "you and my mother will never be ab- sent from my thoughts, but," he continued, quickly, as if to avoid the painful thoughts forced upon his mind by, his father's impressive words,. "do you not think, sir, it would be better for me to join the army now collecting at Dayton, than to wait 'till war is- declared? I can learn something of my duty in the time of peace that remains, however short it may be, and there are many of the young men around us who will gladly accompany me." Mr. Wilton hesitated for a time, but at last gave his consent to his son's departure, as soon as the necessary preparations could be made.-- Mrs. Wilton also allowed, that seeing Phillip must go, there could be no more favorable time for his leaving home. 'Phillip, with a number of his young companions, had been for some time past, quietly but ef- ficiently drilling themselves for active service; and it was a gallant lit- tle band which gathered to make their final arrangements, and pre- pare for a journey through the untrodden wilderness lying between the river Raisin and the little settlement bf Dayton, in Ohio.   EARLY DAYS fN MCHGA'N.         81 rPhillip Wilton, as the first proposer of the expedition, and as having devoted some time, among h other pursuits, to military tactics, was unaninously chosen their commander dltringlt their march. Many a mother's chleek grew pale, and many' a maiden's bright eyes were dim with tears, as the preparations went busily on, for the comgany who were about to leave them were the flower of the youth in that region, but their hands did not falter, and every hand that- could use a needle, toiled unceasingly, to add to the comfort of those tthey loved when they should be far away. The aged matron, for, even in that distant settle- ment, were some grey-haired women who had accompanied their sons or daughters from their eastern homes, plied her knitting-needles more busily than ever; while the young men, themselves, looked anxiously for the best arms and the most serviceable horses to be found in that part of the country, in order that they might prove a welcome addition to the ranks which they proposed to join.  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC8373-00000041"/> 82          EDWARD WILTON, OR CHAPTER      XXVI. The tears 'fell fast from the eyes of Josephine Duval when Phillip !' filton clasped her for the last time to his heart, and severed, with his dirk, one of the curls that fell in such rich profusion around her face and neck. The favorite grand-child of the kindpld Frenchman, who has been before mentioned in our pages, Phillip and she had grown up together, and the love of childhood had changed so gradually' to a deeper feeling that, perhaps, neither of the young lovers could have told at what pe- riod they had first considered themselves betrothed. As children, they had been pronounced a lovely little pair, a!,a their infantile attachment had amused the older members of the two families, before the mysteri- ous disappearance of her little Edward had banished the smiles forever from the life of Mrs. Wilton. After tha; miserable time, Phillip had sought the society of his young playmate oftener than ever, for his own home seemed very lonely now that he could no longer see the beaming smile of his brother, or hear his clear singing tones.- His sister was scarcely of an age to be playmate for him, and Madame Duval kindly permitted Josephine to share many of the play hours of the little Phil- lip, in the hope that the gayety of ,the two children might dispel some- thing of the gloom which shadowed Mrs. Wilton's brow. As the two grew older, the understanding between them remained unchanged, and she, who had been the little wife of Phillip Wilton, had renewed with more solemnity the pledge to be his bride, whenever their parents could believe that they had attained years and discretion sufficient to be uni- ted. This was rather a tacit understanding between the two, families, than a formal announcement and discussion of an engagement. Phil- lip was as much at home in the house of Monsieur Duval as in his father's; and Josephine Duval and Mary Wilton were as loving sisters, though so unlike in their temperaments, that the one resembled the lear brightness of a June morning, all freshness and animation, and -     - g  **    EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          83 the other was like the calm and pensive twilight. The young French girl inherited the sunny gayety peculiar to her own nature, and dearly did she ve, in the glittering moonlight nights of winter, to wrap her- self in her rich furs, and glide-over the smooth surface of the ice in Phillip's cariole. Never did her dark eyes flash more brilliantly, or the roses on her cheek glow more richly, than after her return from these exercises, which, at that time, formed a very prominent part of the amusement of the youn0o people at the different posts along the river. More than one of the young men of their circle had urged Mary to join the merry crew, butl, though seconded by the gay entreaties and laughing reproaches of her brother and his lovely companion, her gen- * tie and somewhat timiid nature shrunk firom so exciting an amusement and she listened to tho e mery laughter and sweet songs which floated to her ear over the frozen waters, without a wish to join the crowd. Per- haps, too, her intense love for her mother, had something to do with the constant refusal to join in the gayeties which winter brought in its train. She knew better than any one else, Mrs. Wilton's nervousness, when Phillip was absent on such expeditions, and she would not add to it by leaving her in solitude to watch for both her children. With all Jose- phine's gayety, she had both depth and strength of character, and though when Phillip had first announced to her that the permission' of his pa- rents was gained, and that he was to join the army immediately, her lip quivered, and her eyes filled with tears, she checked the rising emotion, and with a voice she meant to be even gay, she promised that he should be her knight, and that, since the days were gone for wearing embroi- dered scarfs, she would prepare for him some more'useful token of her affection. No needle was plied more busily than her's, no hand was more active than her own in preparing everything in the shape of com- forts which the young soldiers could carry with them through the for- est. At last, every arrangement completed, and as the young pair stood in the soft moonlight beside the roses which clustered around the piazza Josephine burst into a passion of tears which almost convulsed her slight frame. "Ah, dearest," whispered Phillip, " the plighted wife of a soldier should be more brave. Where is the firmness with which you promised to bid me farewell?"  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC8373-00000042"/> 84          EDWAR1D WILTON, OR The maiden strove to still the sobs that bur3Jt fro:n lhc rbo-o.)n, n ln ai soon as svhe couldl speak, replied: "I will b?, firm, Phillip; nay, I am so now, and T tholgv t to have seen you depart without sheldding one tear to sadden yorll' thoughllts of me in your absence, and I lhave struggled to repress mny grief that it mnilht not add to voulr mother's and Mary's, until they have thought I c)uld not feel; but, to-nilhit, nature must have. her ownvav for once. Bear with me, Phillip, for I am very-wretched " and again the thicl, gpspiirg sobs overpowered her sweet voice. A mnore tender caress was the only reply, for the lover dare;l not trust himself to speak, lest he should boh- tray more weakness than he would care to acknowledge. Gradually however, the young girl grew more calm, and raising her face to his said, quickly: "Go now, while I can speak quietly -to you; and take these roses, Phillip," she continued, gathering a spray from those that bloomed around her--" wear them for my sake, and God bless you and your cause."  One long, last kiss, and the young man sprang down the steps and hurried away, while Josephine, with one arm twined around one of the pillars of the piazza, watched his retreating figure 'till it was hiddlen by a turn in the street, and then returned to'her own room, to weep and pray for him she loved, through the bright summer night.    EARRLIY DAYS IN MCHGAN.        85 CHAPTER XXVII. The next morning shone fair and bright upon the little band of sol- diers, as they gathered for their departure. Singly, or in groups of two and three the company appeared at their rendezvous--an open space just without the village---where a little crowd was collected to see them off, and bid them God speed themon their perilous and toilsome march. There were fathers and mothers standing perhaps, for the last time, by their sons; maidens clinging to their brothers, their- cheeks wet with tears, or listening to the whispered farewells of those who were yet dearer; while the lads of the village had gathered around, looking wistfully at the unusual display, and lamenting that they too, were not of an age to swell the ranks of their country's defenders. Conspicu- ous in the crowd, stood the grey-haired Monsieur Dlval, with his fair grandchildleaning on his arm. She had forced herself to wear a calm . demeanor, that she might gaze once more upon her lover, and that he might see she had conquered the weakness  hich she had shown on the precedingl, evening, but the gay smiles which had seemed to have their home upon her lovely face, were fled. Nearly all the company were collected, but their young Lieutenant had not yet appeared. aIn the-privacy of his own home he had received his mother's last caress-- his father's tremulous blessing, and pressed his weeping sister fondly to his heart. "You must be their son, Effingham," said he 0to the young clergy- man who stood by, "I know I need not commend Mary to your care, and now, I must begone."                - He left the room quickly, followed by Henry Effingham. None of that sad family joined the coup who were waiting to see the band' de- part. Mr. Wilton would fain have seen his son 'till the last moment, but he would not leave his weeping wife and daughter for any solace to his own feelings. As Phillip Wilton, accompanied by Henry Effingham, approached \ .   r  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC8373-00000043"/> 86f           EDWARD WILTON, OR the rendezvous, the young men sprang upon their horses, and arranged their 'ranks to receive them. Another momenlt, and every head was uncovered, and every voice hushed, as the pastor rode into their midst, by the side of' Plillip.  The most thoughtless of the young hearts there felt the solemnity of the scene, and there was a look' of reverence and awe on every face, while the clear tones of Sle clergyman rose to Heaven in a petition for them and their cotmtry. The parting prayer had been made at the request of the mothers whose sons were now en- tering on so. new and perilous a career, and many a time during the weary march through the wilderness, in the silence of the midnight watch, or in the fearful pause which precedes the storm of battle, did those simple and beautiful words rise with increased solemnity on the memory of those who listened to them on that bright summer's day. A deep amen burst from every lip, as Mr. Effingham's voice ceased, and then, with one gesture of farewell to those who stood around, the cavalcade was in motion, and soon were lost to the eyes which followed them with such lingering looks of love. As their commander passed the spot occupied by Monsieur Duval and Josephine, he drew a cluster of roses, as yet scarcely withered, and raising them, for an- instant, quickly replaced them, but not 'till they had been seen by the eyes for which they were intended. One glance was given in return, telling all that words could have done, and" then the maiden turned away, her grandfather still at her side, and sought her home. "You are a brave girl, Josephine," said the old man, "and fit to be a soldier's wife one of these days. Our young Phillip may well be proud of his choice, and you have no reason to be ashamed of yours."' Josojle made no reply, and as her grandfather bent forward, he saw by the pale cheek, compressed'lip -and quivering eyelid, with what difficulty she maintained even the semblance of composure. With con- siderate kindness he forbore to speak agaiin until they reached their own dwelling, and then he pressed his lips on her forehead and whispered: i- Go to your own room now, my child, you need quiet and solitude, and I will go to enquire after Madame Wilton." ! The maiden gladly obeyed the injunction, and once more alone, gave way to the passion of grief she had subdued so long; while Monsieur Duval proceeded, ,as he had proposed, to enquire for the mother who L ,s ,       -                       .    EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          87 had seen her only remaining son leave for an indefinite period, and a dangerous service. He did not ask to see her, for, overcome by the sorrow and excitement of the morning, she too, had sought the privacy of her own apartment; but he spoke words of hope and encouragement to the scarcely less unhappy father, as he slowly paced the room which Phillip's presence had so often made bright and cheerful. The tears of Mary Wilton already flowed more gently, as she stood beneath a little arbor of honeysuckle, fashioned by the hand of him who had just left i , them, and listened, while she unconsciously plucked the coral tinted flowers, to the whispered consolations of her lover.  C  &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC8373-00000044"/> '8           EDWARD WILTON, OR CHAPTER XXVIII. Those who now pass so easily from one part of our country to anoth- er, in the swift steamer and velvet cushioned car, can have but a faint idea of the toil and peril endured by *ravelers in the wilderness at the period of which we write. The dense forests, and deep and dreary marshes have changed, as if by an enchanter's hand, to fair villages, with gay gardens, and noble meadows, whose peaceful tenants wander where- the bear and wild cat made their lair of old; and the bridgeless streams which delayed a journey and sometimes rendered it almost im"r possible, are now perhaps scarcely seen or remembered for a moment by the tourist who is whirled so quickly over them. Great, however as the change has been, 'there are many now living whose memories can bring back the day, when almost the whole region from Lake Erie to the broad and beautiful Ohio was an untracked wil- derness, inhabited only by wild beasts, or the yet more dreaded savage. Beautiful as that part of our country now is, bearing upon its surface the impress of civilization, it could not in a state of nature bear a com- parison with the wild and graceful loveliness of its sister State. The bright lakes, the emerald prairies, the beautiful openings which adorn the interior of the Peninsula, were wanting, and the heavy, dense for- ests, cast a gloom over all beneath its shade. Our band of volunteers had youth and the gay spirits which belong of right-to that blessed period, to aid them in bidding defiance to the darkness and loneliness of the wilderness, and though a thought of the home which they might never see again, would occasionally throw a momentary sadness over one of those light hearts, it passed away with the first merry jest from a comrade. With the advantage of a skillful guide, the route was made more di- rect and easy than it would otherwise have been, yet there was enough of weariness to allow a wish that their mar-ch was ended, to escape more'than one lip, and enoughL of danger at times to occasion some ex'   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         89 citement, and to bring a deeper shade of thought than usual to the brow of their young commander, for their path led them through are- gion filled with wandering bands of Indians, and the hostile feelings of the red man towards the Americans was too well known. At times they traveled silently and warily, stilling the gay song which at other peri- ods was allowed to break the monotony and weariness of their march, and a part of their number ever kept watch through the night, lest the savage should burst upon their slumber. But though they passed on unmolested, they were not unnoticed, and their precautions would have availed them little, but for the order of Tecumseh, which forbade that any important blow should be struck until their English brothers gave the signal for hostilities. It was but the stillness before the storm, not the sweet repose of nature. Steps more stealthy than those of the wild cat, tracked their every movement, and dark eyes, where deadly hatred to their race mingled with a natural love of cruelty, glanced un- seen upon them as they halted to refresh their weary steeds by some gentle stream, or prepared for their own repose when the deepening twilight of the woods, the melancholy note of the whippoorwill, and the wild, unearthly wail of the screech owl, warned them that the long day's travel was ended. At last however the long and weary march was accomplished. All day the path had lain along a river, at whose junction with the Miami their guide- assured them lay the army they had come so far to join, and when the party, just as the sun was settings came in sight of the white tents gleaming in the rosy light, of evening, the glad and simultaneous shout that burst from their lips, told how welcome was the sight to the little band worn with travel, yet eager to take their places among the defenders of their country. As they rode on towards the encampment, tt eir unexpected arrival was noted with pleasure scarcely less than their Svn. Thirty or forty in number, moun- ted on horses, which, at the ( ose of so arduous a journey, showed strength and spirit; well clad a id armed for service, and in the youth and vigor of their forms, giving pomise of good will and power of en- durance, the volunteers from the river Raisin were no mean accession to the ratlis of the army collecting on the banks of the Miami. They were courteously received by an aid-de-camp, who reported' their arrival to the commanding officer, and when Phillip Wilton as  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC8373-00000045"/> 90           EDWARD WILTON, OR their commander was shown to his tent, while the rest of the company were shown to the quarters pointed out for them, the frank and gentle- manly manners, and evident intelligence of the young man, deepened the impression in his favor which his bright and open countenance had O produced at first. At twenty, or even some few years later, acquaintances are easily made, and Lieut. Wilton, and his party were soon as much at home in their new quarters as if their lives had been spent in camp. Accustom- ed from their early boyhood to manage horses and handle arms, these young men required less drilling than many others of the new arrivals, and' coming as volunteers, they perhaps occupied rather a higher place in the secret estimation, if not in the publicly displayed favor of the superior officers, than those whose patriotism had been in some meas- ure compulsory. Preparations had already commenced for the march of the army northward, and-not many days after the arrival of our young friends found them turning their faces again towards home, though by a route somewhat different from the one they had previous- ly followed. But the march through the wilderness, which had been accomplished by a small party unincumbered by heavy baggage, with comparative ease, was far more distressing to a body of fourteen or fif- teen hundred nien with the artillery and baggage which were then nec- essary accompaniments. The increasing heat of the weather, and the damp debilitating air of the forest rendered that exertion every day more difficult which every day became more necessary. There were roads to be cut through the heavily timbered woods, and bridges to be constructed over the streams for the passage of the artillery, but there were willing and gallant spirits to accomplish the task, and after a time which now more than suffices for a voyage to Europe, every day spent in toil and hardship, the army reached a temporary resting place at Fort Defiance, the fort on the Maumee, where a little more than a year before, Edward Wilton had arrived, then a stranger to his own race but now considered one of the most promising of his young officers by Colonel Hamilton, who still commanded the little force stationed there.   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.         91 CHAPTER XXIX. The arrival of so large a body of men at the fort, of' course produced no small degree of excitement among its inhabitants. There were old friends to be sought, and new acquaintances to be formed, and warm and- welcome were the greetings that fell on the ears of many in both bands, while the weariness of the past march, and the prospect of approaching hostilities, were alike forgotten, or treated as a jest, in the mirthfulness of the moment. There were few among that little host who felt less interest in the arrival than Edward Wilton. It was not from the south that he hoped for any tidings of his family or'friends, and the eager pleasure which shone on every face he knew, only made him feel more deeply than ever how complete a stranger he was among his own peo- ple. The curiosity and interest with which he had watched the arrival of so large a force, was forgotten in the sad thoughts which the sight and sound of so much merriment called up, and his face. wore a grave, sadder look than was its wont, when Captain Ashey suddenly joined him.                  ! "Come with me," said that officer, "I have a dear old friend among the new comers, and I want not only to meet him, but to introduce my new brother to my trusty crony and comrade, George Fielding. I know you will be delighted with him.  Why do you draw back, chief," he continued, using a sobriquet which many of his friends applied to him; "why do you draw back so proudly, and with that sad gloomy look, which is not at all at home on your bright face?" "You forget, Ashey," returned Edward, " that I am a stranger to my own race, and the indifference of your comrades to one whom they have never seen, will only change to cold curiosity when they have heard the little there is to be known of my history. Go without me, for what should I do among them ". "I thank you for your opinion of my friend's courtesy and kindness," returned the other, " but I will not go without you shall accompany me,  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC8373-00000046"/> 92          EDWARD WILMON, OR and recant your heresy in half-an hour. Remember it is only by min- gling with strangers that you can make friends, and some chance word may lead to the discovery for which you are so anxious."' Edward could not resist the good natured solicitations of his compan- ion, and the two young men bent their steps towards the quarter where Capt. Fielding's company were stationed. As they passed along, Ash- ley met more than one old acquaintance, with whom he paused to ex- change the frank and cordial greetings of brother soldiers, and to whom he introduced his " brother, Mr. Henry Ashey." The striking face tnd fine figure of the young man attracted attention not only from those to whom he was presented, but even strangers noticed his appearance, and one of the officers remarked as he passed by, "t How very like that young man is to Phil. Wilton. Has he a broth- er in the army?" "I think not," replied the person he addressed; "and, moreover, I heard them call this youth Ashey. There is a striking likeness certain- ly; for though Ashey may be the handsomer of the two, the expres- sion of their faces and their fi ures are wonderfully alike. Some rela- tionship, I dare say. I will ask Phil. when I see him," and the subject was dropped for some other topic of present intent, and forgotten for the time. Captain Ashey, with his young companion, had now reached the 4 quarters of Fielding, and the meeting between the two comrades was warm and ardent as the meetings of those warmly attached to each other, but long and often separated, are wont to be. After the fst long Clasp of the hand, Ashey turned to his newer friend. "And now, George, allow me to recommend to your regard my friend and brother Henry Ashey." "I was not aware, Walter," said Capt. Fielding, after the first saluta- tions of strangers had passed," I was not aware that you had a brother in the army. Mr. Ashey must have josned since I saw you last." ("It is nearly a year since he reached the Fort," replied Ashey, "and some other time I will give you the history of his arrival and previous adventures, which you may work into a romance of two vol- umes at your earliest leisure." "Which leisure will not be at my command very soon, I fancy," said   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          93 lis f'iell(, "for p, resent aplpearanccs d) not prolmise any gie:at amount of time, for romance Writing, to the officers and sol die'rs o of or little army. We are liklely to d1-:-l with ro'liker t ol tols tla pen, ink alnd pa- per; but you have raisedi my curioiity to know throughl wliat perils dire your brother shouldl ha\ve p-tseil. You look young for a knight- errant, Ar. Ashey," he continued, "but I think he .would be a brave champion -vho would lightly venture to break a -lance with you." Edwa'rd smiled. "M y b:-other raises your expectations too higliy. Captain Fielding ; you would hear nothing in my story worth your at- tention, unless Walter chose to embellish it f)r your amusement." i"I should imagine you c(ul, relate ite quite as well, as I have no doubt you have acted it, and I shall ,depend upon knowing the tale from one of you before we part," replied Captain Fielding; then, as he re- marked that his young guest was not altogether pleased with being made the topic of conversation, with ready tact he changed the subject and in a few minutes the three officers were deeply engaged in the dis- cussion of military matters, and the campaign which all knew was ap- proaching. Edward was fully competent to bear his part, and as Field- ing listened to his eager enthusiasm, and watched the flash of his dark eye and the play of expression on his fine features, he could not but acknowle Ige to himself that his friend's young brother was in truth a hero for a romance. e ' ^ ,   &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC8373-00000047"/> "          EDWARD WILTON, OR CHIAPTER     XXX. Evening had fallen softly on the fort and on the camp, and many of the wearied soldiers had already given themselves up to slumber, but some yet lingered for the sake of the cool breath of evening, as well as to watch the picturesque effect of the camp fires, which cast their flick- ering, uncertain light, on the surrounding woods and the walls and buildings of the fort. Among the number of loiterers was Phillip Wilton, who, with one of his comrades, was lounging under al. immense tree, and exchanging a careless word with some passer-by, now talking earnestly together of their homes and the friends left. behind, and occasionally venting half angry, half sportive anathemas against the musquitos who continually invaded their retreat. A group of officers came slowly along; and as the bright fire-light gleamed on the figures resting on the grass, one of them exclaimed, "Tt certainly'is a remarkable likeness. Wilton-I beg pardon for interrupting you in your laudable efforts to annihilate that musquito- but pray, tell me, have you not a brother, or some near relative, at the fort 2" Strange, wild thoughts, flashed for a moment through Phillip's mind, at the sound of the word " brother," but he felt at once how unreason- able they were, and answered calmly, "No; certainly no brother, nor any relative that I am aware of-but why do you ask, Hardy?" "Simply because I never saw two brothers more alike than yourself and one of the, officers here whom I met an hour or two ago. I did not hear his name, but it seemed to me that you and he must claim kindred." "His name is Ashey," said another of the gr6oip. "I heard it spo- ken, and had it not been for that, I believe I should have taken him for Wilton himself."   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          95 "It is strange," replied Phillip, in a musing tone. "We certainly have no relations of that name, yet I should like to see this Mr. Ashey."' "Oh! you are talking of young Ashey," exclaimed a gentleman who now joined the group. "He is a noble fellow; and I have just been listening to his history from one of 'his brother officers-really, quite romantic, is not?" "We have not heard it," said half a dozen voices in a breath; and Phillip Wilton, who, in spite of his reason, was interested, even to anx- iety, asked eagerly, "Who is h1?  Whais s history? Let us have it!"  "Why, Phil., you are as anxious as a girl," replied the possessor of the story, with a laugh, " and it is not so very wonderful after all. I think I'll say nothing more about it, lest I should not tell the tale as well as it was told to me." "Nonsense! Miller," said Capt. Hardy. "Come, tell us your story, and let me be off before the musquitos have quite devoured me. I would rather face a regiment of his Britanic Majesty's red coats than these execrable little insects,"  "Yes, the story! the story!" repeated several of the-standers-by* "It must be a brief one, then," said he who had been addressed as Miller, " for I cannot endure this sort of warfare long. It reminds one too unpleasantly of the arrows of some of-our red friends; but I will abridge my tale as much as possible. This youth, now called Ashey, appeared at the fort abou: a year since, on such a summer's evening, per- haps, as this, in full Indian costume, except the paint; deer-skin, hunt- ing-shirt, moccasins, tomahawk and all--but could scarcely speak a word of/English. Luckily for him, there was an interpreter there, who could understand and translate the barbarous gibberish which he spoke; and he soon gathered from the youth that he had been brought up by the savages, almost from infancy, probably, as he had but the most vague and indistinct recollection of any other kind of life. He was the adopted son of a chief; but when he grew old enough to think for him- self, and heard thre was a possibility Jof some hard blows passing be- tween his red brothersafid his white relations, he determined very wisely to join the latter, and left his savage, friends. with their consent, though somewhat against their wishes, and-good heavens!  Wilton! what is f   - T  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC8373-00000048"/> 96          EDWARD WILTON, OR the imatter with you 1"I)e excJ limned, as Plillip started ftroml his seat, pale as death, and every nerve quivereld witlh excitclnect. , "Captidn Iardy,'9 said he qu licldy, without r 0plying'o tote interrog- atory, "yon klnow somre of, the ofcers at the fort, come with me11  an seizin'him ly the arm, he led him rapidly away, befoure lardy had time to ask the reason of the suldden milovement. " "Whlat the deuce can be the matter with Phillip 2" said the story- teller, " has he gone mad with curiosity to see my Indian hero?." The yoang man who had been sitting with Phillip when the fir st party joined 'ufi, was one of his comrades firom the banks of the Raisin, and per- ceivin t once the cause of Wilton's agitation when he heard that one bearing so marked a resemblance to himself, had been brought up in ignorance of his name or family, by the savages; he made the aston- ished group comprehend in a few words all that had seemed so strange to them. There was ready and eager interest shown by the listeners, and earnestly did they echo the hope expressed hy Phillip's friends, that he mi,2ht indeed have found his long-lost brothler. The singular story spread quickly through the army, and all waited anxiously for the re. turn of the soldiers from the fort, or for some news from them.   EArELY DAYS IN MCHGANN.       9 CHAPTER     XXXI. As Captain Hardy, with his eager companion, proceeded at a rapi6d pace towards the fort, Phillip told him briefly of his own early loss, and, the strong hope which he now felt that the Mr. Ashey who was the. hero of Mr. Miller's tale, mn n truth be his brother Edward There. seemed strong grounds tor su03 a supposition, and as Philllp glanced. rapidly over them, the hope iew almost to a certainty in his sanguine spirit, while his ctalmeir panion warned him of the danger of too. sudden belief. - "I acknowledged, my dear Wilton," said he kindly," " that there is much to encourage you, but at the risk of being called a croaker, I re- peat, do not build too strongly on these probabilities, and then be made wretched by a mistak;e."  "Do not talk- to me of mistakes or oubts now," replied Phillip. Ten words froin this youth will either confirm my-hopes or blast them;   but till they are spoken, I will believe that I shall have the joy- -of restoring my mother's lost treasure to her arms." Neither spoke ag;,in till they reached the fort, when a few words to, one of the soldiers of the guard, brought a  speedy invitation to the 'quarters of Col. Hamilton, with whom Capt. Hardy was well acquainted. "I would not intrude upon you at so late an hour, Colonel," said the latter, after the first greetings were over, "but my young friend, Mr. Wilton, wishes to speak to you of matters that will hardly bear delay2" "I shall be most happy to serve Mr. Wilton in any way," replied the. other officer, who had been earnestly regarding Phillip; " and, perhaps, in return, I  may be tempted to ask him some questions." "You  have a   young officer in your command, sir," said Captain Hardy, who perceived that Phillip was almost too much excited to speak, "who is now called Ashey." "I:have, indeed," interrupted Colonel Hamilton, "does Mr. Wilttit bring any tidings of his family, or may, :henot bea relative of hibl h. t rle0         lW  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC8373-00000049"/> t38          ]EDWARD WILTON) O0 "I hope, I believe so, sir," said Phillip, T but, till within this last half hour, we have never been able to conjecture whether my unfortu- nate brother was dead or alive; if I can see this Mi Ashey, as he is called, I can soon satisfy mnylclf. . "I will send for him n, t 'o;:) replied the commnander, who immedi- ately despaltched a mnessen ,r i o summnron the young m;l, " and I cannot buthope your enquiries will be satisfactory, as I Was so much struck with your resemblance to my young frieild, that. I intended asking you if you had ever lost any relative among tho Indians." A quick step wvas oon heard ia thie passage, and illn a monat the soi disant Henry Ashey, the real EdRward Wilton, stood again, after a, se- paration of so -many years, in the same room, and almost side by side with his brother Phillip, without a thought of recognition on his part, while the cheek and brow of the other flushed with emotion, and his lip quivered in spite of his manhood, for his memory had treasured faith- fully the image of his brother; and as he raised his cap, there were the same clustering curls around the broad, high forehead, only some few shades darker than in childhood, the same clear, flashing eyes and beau- tifully formed mouth which had distinguished the little Edward. We have said elsewhere that Phillip was less regularly handsome than his brother, yet the resemblance between them -was most striking, and as Col. Hamilton gazed at the two noble figures and bright faces before him, he was still more strongly impressed with the conviction that they were indeed brothers. "You sent for me, sir," said Edward, as he advanced. "Yes," replied his superior officer, " these gentlemen were making some enquiries of me with regard to the Indian tribes in the Peninsula - Will you assist my memory, and tell the name of the tribe with whom you spent so many years?" "I was with the Pottawatomies, on the banks of the Kalamazoo," re, plied the young man. "And their chief--who was he-your adopted father V" asked Phillip ' eagerly. Edward turned quiekly to the new speaker, in surprise at the tone -and manner of the question from a perfect stranger, but answered,   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAANl,        9 ** The name of my adopted father was Sagito. I have never known another?" "Edward! Edward! do you -not remember me?" cried Phillip, to 'whom the namle of the chief was tlte stronogest confirmation of hopes fthat were allnost certainty before, and who coullt no longer restrain his :impatio1nco to claimn tlis prize. Edward gazedt eag.,rly at the stranger, who had adlvanlced to his side, and addrlcessed himn by a name which. sounded stranglely, yet lie falnied faimilially to his eas.3, while Phillip re- peated in a tone almost of acony, "do you not know your brother .Phillip "  - "Phillip)! Phillip Wilton!" exclaimed the other, on whose mind the -name of lhis childhilool's playfellow and protector threw asflood of light when the sound of hii ow hald brougtlt the faint glimmering dawn of- memory.  The two brothers were clasped in each other's armns in an in- stant, and the strongr forln of the elder shook like that of a young girl, as he repelated; " my brother! my littte Edward!l" forgetful for a mo- ment of the manly figure to whom he applied the endealing epithet of old days.  "There can be no doubt, then," whispered Colonel Hamilton to his friend, asJhey gazed, not with unmoistened eyes, on the scene before them. '"lis memory of his brother's name is enough.?) - - "Certainly," said Hardy ; "and Wilton told me that Sagito was the name of the Indian who was suspected of carrying- off his brother. It is a most fortunate meeting." "Edward was the first to loose himself from the long embrace, but it was that he might graze with more earnest and wondering affection on his brother." "And you indeed are my brother Phillip," said he.- U How well I remember that name now!" "There cannot be a shadow of uncertainty," said Colonel Hamilton; "and now let me congratutate you both on sa happy a meeting. Mr. Wilton, you could hardly have hoped to recover, in the person of one of our most promisingr yng g officers, the child carried into captivity by the savages. Butcome, Iiardy, and take a stroll with me, while our young friends compose themselves somewhat. The whole fort will rejoice with" you, my dear boy," he added grasping Edward's hand warmly, as he left the 'room with his friend.  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC8373-00000050"/> 100           EDWABD WILTON, OR CHAPTER XXXII. There are few moments of such perfect happiness in life as now felt to the lot of the two brothers, so long Separated, so unexpectedly united In Phillip's sanguine dreams of Ids brother, he had never dared to think of finding him any thing, more than a savage; more easy, perhaps, to civilize and teach than the native denizens of the forest, but still igynor- ant and uncultivated, and he had often feared, imbued with the fierce and cruel passions of his associates. Hi. wildest hopes could never have soared to the present reality; and as lie gazed on the object of so mlany- fears, suchl unceasing sorrow and anxiety, his heart throbbed with proud and grateful jogy at the thought of presenting. him to their parents, allt and more than all their hearts could have wished. His impatient spirit. longed, like Imogen's, "for a horse with wings," that he might the, - sooner reach home with the long-lost treasure. And-Edward, who had now gained the knowledge he had coveted so earnestly. yet fearfully; who founld hiimself still fondly remembered by those, from hum he had been taken in his childhood, listened to his brother's answers to his eager qu, stions, till their forms and faces seem- ed to rise every moment more clearly and distinctly to his memory. Col. Hamilton soon returned. and after a few words of kind interest and congratulation from him, the young men took leave, and repaired. to Edward's quarters-for they felt that they could not be separated;: again so soon. The nigLt was a wakeful one to both, for their excited feelings could not-subgide into the calm of slumber; and there were constant questions  to- be asked, on one side or,the-other.       9  3orning,. brougkht them warm and eager congratulations from; the. friends of, both, and it was soon :arrrnged by their" superior officers that,. the two Wiltons should have leave, of Absence to :visit-the home whichi, th'ir arrival, would make so joyful Tihey! could not' wait for the -slow.: advance of the army, and made their arrangements as ;speedily as possivr ble for their departure. ,    i,   EARi  DAYS INs oMCoGAN.       101 Johnson, the interpreter, was to'be sent forward to Detroit with'lent ters from Gen. H., as he was an accomplished traveller in the w sodst and moreover a man of great sahrewdaess and undoubted veracity, and he proposed to set out at the same time with' our young friends , rne marking that, 6"Though the chief had. learned enough among the red akims to find a bee-line through the woods, as well as the best of them, the youngsters would be none the worse for having an older head along, and he liked good company on a lonig trail himself." ' The proposal was willingly agreed to, for Edward was strongly at- tached to the kind-hearted man, who had, in some measure, commenced his English education, and to Phillip every one was already dear who  had taken an interest in his brother, and he assured Johnson of a heaty welcome when they reached home. The sun was just sending  his first rays along the tree-tops onlihe banks of the Maumee, and  changing the dew-drops of the night into  glittering diamonds, which fell to the earth in showers as the leap of,:a squirrel, or,even the rustle of a bird among the branches; disturbed a portion of the thick foliage. Three horses stood ready saddled just be- yond the walls ofo the fort, and their nlasters werk butsil y odoupied in ar- ranging their arms, and the light baggage .and p roviso:os indispensable for a journey through the woods. The pistols were in thled holsters, the portmanteaus strapped on, and the experienced eye of Johnson had seen ' that all was properly " fixed" for the departure, amtl nothing now r mained but the final adieus from those who were gathered round S Ed* ward's friends in the fort, and Pllillip's comrades in the army.  " I begin to believe," said Capt. Ashley to his young friend, "what I have heretofore thought a very selfish saying, that it is more difficult to rejoice with those that rejoice than to weep with those who weep. I certainly am  not more than half -reconci    leaving us, even for the home and friends you are-so anxio to see, or to your discard- ing my name so uncerimoniously, tho' that o\Wilton may sound some- what better."               \ ' "No name can be dearer to mer" replied Edw  , "than that by '-  which I   have been known at the fort, if it were only that it belongs to . my earliest and kindes' friend among my own people, and I trust one - day to see you in my own home  "  )                    r  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC8373-00000051"/> 102         EDWARD WILTON, OR "Come, come, youngsters," called Johnson, who was already in the saddle, "leave the good-lyes for women. Every minute of this cool - Morning is worth ten after the sun gets a few hours higher, and we have no time to waste. Mr Phillip Wilton, you had better have taken another horse to carry all them letters you are crowding into your pock- ets," he Continued, as he saw the packets which Phillip's companions were hastily handing him to deliver to the loved ones at home. "Never .fear, Johnson," replied Phillip, "I their weight will hardly keep us back, and I should not dare to show myself along the banks of the Raisin without news from those who left them with me; but we will not keep you longer, for we must be thirty miles nearer home to- night." "Not if you stop there talking,",said Johnson; "I'm off, at all events," and he put his horse in motion, as the last hope of putting an end to the last words to which his fellow-travellers were listening.- The proceeding had the desired effect, and the young man imitated his example, followed by a hearty farewell-shout, and more than one last z message to be delivered by Phillip to some friend or relative at home, \ ,   E'ARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.'        103  OIC APTER     XXXIII. The little party had reached their encampment for the night on the, second day of their journey ; a clear spring which bubbled up niear the- roots of an immense beach tree, rendering it a convenient halting place. Johnson, who took upon himself the care of making the fires and cook- ing the simple repast, was busily occupied, only now and then pausing to address some piece of advice to his younger companions, as to' the most expeditious method of making a fire, or to impart to them some other portion of his woodland experience. The sun ,had set, but his . absence was scarcely felt in the unclouded light of the full moon, which threw a: sofened lustre on all around. Phillip's gay spirits were even hmore buoyant than usual, for he knew the same moon whose beams were dancing on the rippling water. at his feet, would shine, Scarcely changed, on the re-union of the long separated mother and son, and on his own meeting with Josephine Duval; and he hummed snatches of- the French airs which she loved to sing, contended gaily with Johnson for a rivalship in feats of hunting, or endeavored in vain to rouse his brother from the reverie into which he had fallen. But Edward's brow wore a graver look than his brother had yet seen upon it, and he scaroe- ly replied to the jests and gay reproaches with which his comrades at- tacked him. Something in the scene had sent his thoughts more ten-- derly than usual to his distant forest home, and the dark-eyed maiden with whom he had so often stood by the river bank in such glorious moonlight hours. The name of the Springing Fawn had never passed his lips since he parted with Otagimi, but her memory was fresh in his heart, and now he was pondering anxiously how his new found brother and the relatives from whom he had so' long been separated, woUld re- ceive the tidings of his attachment to one of the race they had so much reason to dread and dislike. He had already heard from Phillip of their tister's engagemaent to Mr. Effingham, and his own happy love, and the:  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC8373-00000052"/> A04          EDWARD WILTON, OB elder brother had wondered for a moment at the silence and reserve of Edward's manner, when he volunteered to find for him, if possible, a bride as fair and good as his own; but attributing it to his Indian edu- cation, or at most, to mere indifference, had let it pass unnoticed. Phillip and his guide had endeavored in vain to rouse, him from his moody abstraction, but at last giving it up, were now busily engaged, the one rel ating, the other listening, to a history of adventures on " the dark an d bloody ground" of Kentucky, where Johnson's youth and ear- ly manhood had been spent. So completely was the narrator absorbed in his own stor y, and so eagerly was Phillip listening to it, that they ,did not perc eive when Edward rose from his reclining posture on the; grass, and glided quietly into the deeper woods; nor had they seen his  slight start and suddenly raised eyes when the low long note of the whip-poor-will sounded several times apparently within a few yards of the encampment.  It was a signal which had been familiar to him for years, and words could scarcely have told him -more distinctly that Ota- gimi was awaiting him in the forest. A few cautious steps took him out ,of 'sight of the fre, and out of the ilnmediate hearing of his comrades, then the same long and melancholy tfote passed his own lips, and hard- ly had the sounds died away amonl; the trees, when a plumed and paint- ed warrior stood by the side of the young iAmerican officer. There -was no emotion shown by either at the meeting, for the savage would, have disdained any display of feeling as womanlyllt3 and Edward, after the first sound of the familiar call, h d- carefully controlled his surprise. "The sight of my brother is pleasant to the Eaogle Eye," said he, using A -the language which had been so long familiar to him ; " but it is a long path from here to the Kalamazoo. tlas Otagimi trodden it alone?" "There are hundreds of our young men gathering from the lakes to .iae side of their English brethren," was the reply, "but they are not mear to-night. Otagimi knew that there were pale faces coming through :Alah woods from the strong house on the Maumee, and he came forward ,on the path to find if his white brother were with them. He watched the Eagle Eye as he sat alone under the tree, and he tried if his ear 'were as dead to the call of the whip-poor-will as to the jests and laugh- ^r r:,f his companions." "The soul of the Eagle Eye had gone back for a while to the banh:- O            , '  *   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGA N*:".       O  of the Kalamazoo; and now Otagimi will tell him of those who dwell there-of Sagito and Nasheda." "And my brother would hear if the Springing Fawn yet weaves her baskets, and works her moccasins, under the spreading tree by the water side," said Otagimi, as a half smile played on his lip for a moment..- "Sagito is with his English brothers, at the head of his warriors, and Nasheda is lonely in the lodge of her husband. She mourned long and bitterly when the Eagle Eye returned with the young warriors at the falling of the leaf, and there has been ho smile on her brow since.- The Springing Fawn sits by her side in silence, or strives in vain to com- fort her for the loss of her white son. The young maiden looks sadder than was her wont in days of old, and she refuses the gifts which the young warriors have offered her, but she bade me tell her brother, the Eagle Eye, if I met him on our path, not to let his feet turn again to the woods, but to abide with his own people 'till the hatchet should be buried again. A  world of conflicting feelings passed through Edward's heart as he listened to the words of his early friend. His first wild impulse would have bid him turn his face at once towards the setting sun, nor pause 'til he found himself again in the presence of those he loved so dearly, but the next instant changed his thought. Could he abandon the brother but just recovered, desert the parents whom   he had not yet seen, or be a  deserter from the flag under whose folds he had sworn to stand against his country's foes. The struggle was a brief one, but his cheek - was pale as he replied to the young warrior by his side. "Otagimi will tell the Springing Fawn that the Eagle Eye-is with the brother who played with him in infancy; that their faces are even now turned towards the home from which he was taken. SHe must fight by the side of his own people now, but when the hatchet is again buried, the Fawn may look eastward through  the trees for her white brother; and tell Nasheda that her son will not forget in his new home the mother who cared for  iimn when he was aloneO among strangers."- He was going to add more, but the Indian raised his finger to his liph and Edward heard his comrades calling him, the' in careful tones, leat the sounds should be heard by other ears than those for whom they were intended.     &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC8373-00000053"/> - 10B6      ^S^:of 'EDWARD WILTON, OR 1           -06 "H is white brothers seek the Eagle Eye," said the chief, in a low voice, "let him not say that Otagimi has crossed his path ;" and as the footsteps drew nearer, he disappeared in'the, woods, and Edward rejoin-. ed his comrades, to whose questions concerning his absence he made some careless reply, and scarcely partaking of the meal which John- son's skill had provided, flung himself on the ground to live over again his interview with his friend.   EARLY DAYS IN MCH0         107 CHAPTER XXXIY.  It was a later hour than had been intended by the travelers that they rode slowly into the village where two of them were to end their journey. The day had been excessively hot, 'and their progress was necessarily slow; and even now, though the air was cool and refreshing, the gait of their horses was languid and weary, with the exception of Phillip's beautiful grey, who had recognized his vicinity to his own stable, and was pressing forward with ears erect and eager step,' while his master, though no less impatient than Himself, held him in to keep pace with the tired animals of his companions, who had no recollection of home to animate them. Poor Sultan, however, was doomed to make one more pause before he reached his own quarters. During the jour. ney there had been many consultations as to the best method of intro- ducing Edward to his friends withouta I great a shock to thp sensitive frame of Mrs. Wilton, and it had firrt been decided that the little party should call on Monsieur Duval on their way through the village, and act in accordance with his advice. It would scarcely be- fair to en- quire of Phillip, from whom the plan proceeded, allowed the thought of X f Josephine's glad surprise to have any weight with him; but however that might be, Johnson agreed with him that this would be the wiser course; and Edward, tho' his heart throbbed with impatience to feel his mother's caress and bear his father's blessing, acquiesced in their deoi- Sion. As the two rode through the principal street, in which Monsieur Du. val's house was situated, they -found it by no means so deserted as might have been expected. The cool breath of the evening, after a day of in- tense heat and lassitude, had tempted many a group abroad, forgetful or reckless of the danger that lurked in that sweet and refreshing breeze, and as they loitered along, the moonlight revealad to their astonished eyes the figure of their townsman, Phillip Wilton, in the foremost of the three horsemen. More than one called to him to greet him, and ask the-  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC8373-00000054"/> 108       VkDW   ARD WILTON, OR reason of his unexpecidl appearance accompanied by strangers instead of those who left their homes with him, but -the young man replied without checking his horse, that he was on urgent business, and his comrades were from the army. One of the enquirers confronted him just before he reached the little gate in iront of Monsieur Duval's mod- est mansion. The] familiar tones of the reply reached more than one pair of ears within its walls, for the words had scarcely passed his lips when a light figure flew down the steps, and gazed earnestly through the moonlight at the approaching riders, and "Men Dieu! Phillip Wil- ton returned!" was heard, as her grandfather followed, though lmore slowly, to greet his young friend. Sultan's bridle was thrown into Ed- ward's hand, and Sultan's master was within the gate, and by the side of the fair girl who had appeared so suddenly, almost before his compan- ions were aware that they had reached their destination. There was a joyful and hurried greeting between the lovers, and Phillip turned to the old man, who stood neal with a benevolent smile on his fine features. "I must ask a welcome for my companions too, my dear sir," said he as he grasped the hand so cordially extended to him. "We shall tres- pass on your time a few minutes before we ride on to my father's." "Certainly, mly dear boy," replied Monsieur Duval; and'advancing to the gate with Phillip, he invited th'e horsmen to dismount and enter the house.  Jolhnson was introduced to his host as they moved up the walk, but, somewhat to the surprise of Josephine and the gr'andfather, tie dis- tinguished looking young officer by his side remained unnoticed by Phil-  until reaching a lighted room, when turning -suddenly he said, "Must I introduce both my friends, Monsieur Duval, or can you r- call this face to your mind s. The old man gazed on Edward for a moment, then turned his eyes towards Phillip; and again, with an expression of increased wonder, on the young stranger. There was a dead silence in the room for a minute or two, Josephine gazing anxiously on her lover as if to ask an explana- tion of the mystery, and her grandfilther looking from one to the other of the silent group. At length he spoke, but in an uncertain and troubl- ed 'voice. "If it were a possible thing Phillip, I should say that that youth by your side was your lost brother, but that cannot be-"   EARLY DAYS IN MimO::         109 "Yet so it is," interrupted Phillip, " even our omn Edward, restored to his home and friends; and now the question is, how shall we plepare my parents to see him? Monsieur Duval did not answer, but he clasped the young man in his arms, and fairly wept in the exuberance of his joy, while Jasepline's dark eyes glistened with tears as she turned to congratulate Plillip. "This is joyful news, indeed," said her grandfather, when he could compose himself to speak again, and releasing Edward from his clasp, he held him at arm's length, and scanned every feature, as if to assure him-' self that there could be no mistake, and that the tall, graceful young sol- dier at his side was indeed the Little Edward whom he had once proph- ecied would return to gladden the hearts of hs friends. "Blut tell me TI'hillip, how it all came about.? I cannot let you go, even to your pa- rents, without hearing something of the story." In brief and hasty words Edward's history, or at least a sketch of it was related, only interrupted by ejaculations of joy-and wonder from the old Frenchman or his grandchild. "And now," said PBlillip, as he concluded, "Monsieur Duval must, if he will, tell us what 'to do. Shall we go home at once, or shall he, precede us, and prepare the way for our reception?" "That would hardly do," /eplied his friend, "lfor they would be startled at once, and fancy some terrible misfortune before I could tell them the truth, if they should find that you, Phillip, were in town and staying here instead of going home at once. You must go with me -at all events." "And   shall we leave Edward and my good friend Johnson here, while we go over and' tell them who is waiting for their greeting .?' "No, indeed," exclaimed Edward, who had till now remained silent; u I cannot consent to remain behind. Let me be presented as a stran- ger, if you please, but I must see my parents." "Very well, then," said Monsieur Duval, " we will go together, for I must see this happy meeting. Phillip, you shall introduce Edward as Mr. Ashey, and see how long it will be before Madame Wilton recog- nizes her lost son in this gay soldier. And let us be gone at once, for it is growing late, and you must accommodate your impatient young spirits for once to the step of an old man."  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC8373-00000055"/> "O         EDWARD WILTOei OR The party, with the exception of Phillip, who lingered to speak to Josephine, followed him from the room, andt Edward and Johnson were already in the saddle, and putting their horses in motion, and' the old Frenchman was a few paces in advance, and walking with an activity customary to him, but very unusual at his years; when Phillip appear- ed at the door, and in another moment he was on horseback and by their side.   BARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.      i  1" CHAPTER XXX V. At the same time that these eventl took place so near them, Mr. Wilton, with his wife and dawughter, were qitting quietly in their pretty parlor. Mary's graceful form was llhlf thidden by the light folds of the muslin curtain, as she sat by the window gazing out into the clear moon- light; while her father was reading talu t t ) moekr nither from papers which lay before hlm on the table. A mn:il ha;d arrived that evening, not an every-day occurrence in those tim s, when news not 'more than a fortnight old from the eastern cities was a matter of importance, and Mr. Wilton was deeply engaged, when Mary suddenly interrupted him with, "Papa, there are three gentlemen ridinog up to the house; what can be the mater ." Mr. Wilton laid down his paper, and hurried to the window, for such an arrival at that time of .night was unusual, and in the threat- . ening and uncertain state of the times, almost alarming, but before he had reached his daughter's side, she excllaimed, "It is Phillip ; one is certainly Phillip," and darted to the door fol- lowed by her parents. 'Quick, however, as their motions were, Phillip had already sprung from his horse, and was hastening up the steps, and in a moment he was cla--ped in his mother's arms, while his fataer and Mary stood by, impatient for their share of the greeting. "Is there any trouble, my dear Phillip, that you have returned so soon?" asked his father anxiously, as he grasped his hand.' "None at all, my dear sir; I have but come for a flying visit, and here are some friends for wholm I must ask a welcome. You are all well here, I see," he added, glancing at the familiar fae3s. Monsieur Duval now advanced and made his salutations to the ladies, and as he did so, Mary whispered archly to her brother, "You made a visit in the village before you come home, I fancy, Phillip.  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC8373-00000056"/> 112    ,EDWARD WILTON, OR ' It is true," said he, laugllig, "but there were good reasong, which I will tell you by and by; now I must attend to these strangers," and he went forward with his father to meet his two companions, who had fastened their horses, ald were standing, as if uncertain whether to join the group on the, piazza or remain -where they were. 'Johnson was named first, as a messenger firom the army, charged withll letter, to De- troit, and then Mr. Ashey. Mr. Wilton received both with the frank and ready hospitality which was habitual to him, but as Edward took his fathers proffered hand, his own trembled so excessively that Mr. Wil- ton could not but remark it, and wonder at an emotion so unusual in a young and active man, but he led him to the house, and presented Ilinm' with Johnson, to his wife and daughter, who received thellm courteously, though to say the truth, they scarcely more than glaniiccd at their new fieinds, nor did the blunt mannerof the guide, or t]ie very evident em- barrassment of the younger stlanger, make any ilnpression upon them', so entirdly were they occupied with Phillip, in whose manner there was a sort of hurried, nervous eagerness unusual to him, and which, in spite of his assurances that all was well, startled and alarmed them. Their old friend, too, seemed .by an unusual degree of vivacity, to seek to conceal some deeper feeling, and when they returned with the new comers to the room they had left so suddenly, Phillip saw that his moth-  er and sister loaked anxious and apprehensive, but before he could speak to reassure them, his attention was directed to another part of the room. Edward had endeavored in vain to subdue entirely the agitation which he felt at standing again beneath his father's roof and by his side  he gazed earnestly, but covertly, at the faces whose looks of love were turned on ]his elder brother, and he knew that they were indeed those which he had known and loved in his infancy; changed by time and sorrow, but still familiar to, him. The aspect of the room; too, was that of an old friend; the old-fashioned rhigh-backed sofa in a riecess near the fire, with:the small work-table before it; the large arm-chair, which. X: he remembered as exclusively appropriated to his father, the tall silver candlesticks on the mantel-piece, the landscapes on the wall, all bl'onghtf his, childhood. back in an instant. In one of the pictures were some horses bending their heads to drink at the side of a stream, and hereI   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.        113 membered well that he and Phillip had been accustomed to name them and call them their own. These recollections passed rapidly through: his mind, and when Mr. Wilton turned to him with some corteous're." mark, he saw that his young guest was piae as death, and scarecely shle to stand.   You are ill, Mr. Ashy," said he kindly, " what can I do for you?" The young man looked up without speaking, as Mrs. Wilton, hearing her husband's inquiry, advanced to offer her aid, and the appalling ex. pression of those dark eyes sent a thrill through the hearts of both husband and wife, so strangely were they reminded of their lost child. "Good God!" exclaimed Mr. Wilton, involuntarily, while the nfother left the room to conceal her emotion. "Pardon me," he continued, " but your face reminded me so strongly of one I may never see again, that I could not avoid an exclamation"-. but the young man made no. reply to the apology, and when Mr. Wil- ton looked to his son, as if to ask the meaning of so strange behavior, he saw that both he and Monsieur Duval were strangely agitated, and that the bluff backwoodsman was gazing at him-with eager interest, Mary had followed her mother from the room, and all eyes were di- rected towards himself and the young soldier with an air of anxiety 'and expectation for which he could not account. (In the excitement of the mopient, all had forgotten their intention of preparg ing th d of ' th  father to receive his son, and the old Frenchan 'teppigha lyfor, ward, laid his hand on his friend% arm, and exclaimied, .' Did I not tell you years ago that your son wiilyet returf to gladden your heart?  Am I not a true prophet? I':^. .   ' Mr. Wlton gazed wildly at him and on his so^ and gasped ou,:. "What do you say ? i What do you mean ? "' Imean" replied the other, "thaty ur SO son stad ^.,bef if:O yo ,tw,; Look-on him once more, and if you doubt it stili hear -his stoTbo The father gazed for. an :iuihtaAt then,     ?tgg:a   .i fallevnhad not .Fwa d-caught him:  aGod forgive me" said Monsieur DD, a"He bpf-beon too5 flS i rrpnaghtOp 'Iag'- ,4                WO'l   Pt apf  o th  ag  dtzihdt   &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC8373-00000057"/> "         EDWARD WILTON, OR filing a glass with wine, held it to his father's lips. The unconscious- ness was scarcely more than momentary, but Mr. Wilton roused, as if -Aom sleep, as he said, L EAnd I have dreamed again of finding my child!" "It is no dream, my father exclaimed Edward, "I am at home once more. I remember your face and my mother's, and the room in which we stand. All comes back to me clearly now." "Edward, my son! my son!" murmured Mr. Wilton, as he folded him in his arms, and breathed a fervent thanksgiving, then releasing tim that he might trace the well remembered features once more, he said, "i cannot ask questions now. I know that I see again the child for ,whom we sought so long in vain. I can only thank God that you are restored to us, and then call your mother to rejoice with me." The door opened as he spoke, and Mrs. Wilton, followed by her daughter, re-entered the room. She had subdued her agitation and hough still pale, was calm, until her eyes, which had first rested on Phillip, turned to her husband and the stranger on whom he was gaz- ingwith such deep affection, while MEonsieur Duval was alternately sob- bing like a child and shaking hands with all around him. Mr. Wilton held out his hand as she advanced, and Phillip drew near to aid the step s which trembled, as a suspicion of the truth flashed upon his mind. She did not speak, but passed eargerly forward, and passing her hands :thro ugh Edwtd's clustering curls, pushed them back from his face as she had been wont to do in his childhood, and gazing into his full dark eyes for a moment, clasped her ains' around his neck, and sunk into his arm s; but not unconscious, for as he exclaimed "Mother! mother, oh speak to nme,"' she whispered, "My own Edward, I should have known you among a thousand!" then raising herself, she drew her son close' to her, and pressed kiss after kiss upon his eyes aInd forehead, and wreathed her fingers again in his brown curls, as though he was still the child he was when she last saw him; while Mr. Wilton looked on, as if fearful that the happy vision would dissolve, No word from the standers by broke the silence of the sconce, but the tears fell fast from Mary's eyes, when her father called her to him, and said: ,  "Let me see all my children together once more. Ed ward, do you remember your sister?"                       I i"I remember well the pretty baby for whom I used to gather flowers,  and play bo-peep behind my mother's chair," he replied, as'he etm-z  b mated:htr'fliectionateley, "bunt can this fair.:girl be the same a I should . anot have known her or Phillip as I do my-father and mother." , I                 '  :   .     EARLY DArYS IN MCHGAN.        115 CHAPTER XXXVI. Gradually the re-united family acquired sufficient calmness to enquire how Edward had been so suddenly restored to them, and by what strange chance it was that he whom they could only have imagined the inmate of an Indian wigwam, stood before them an officer in his coun- try's service. Hours flew by unheeded, as they listened to all that Edward could tell-them of. himself and his forest life, and to Phillip's account of the circumstances which led to his discovery of his brother, and the night was more than half spent before they separated, and the happy parents, in the privacy of their own apartment, repeated once more their thanksgivings for a happiness for which they had never dared to hope; yet the early dawn found the party again assembled for, Johnson was obliged to reach Detroit as soon as possible,and Mr. 'Wil- tinii's hospitable habits would not. allow him to leave his house without a, substantial breakfast; while Mrs. Wilton, whg had been sleepless fogmt joy, as shtr had often been from sorrow, was anxious to have her recovered son again by her side, with the blissful certainty that it was no dream. .                      ' Early as it was, a message had been despatched to Henry Enffighamo which brought him to their breakfast table, to meet one ok whom he had heard so much, and to rejoice in the joy of those with whose sor- rows he had o ten sympathised.   He could scarcely believe, as he pressed Mrs. Wi ton's extended hand, that she was the sapae person he had seen butt th 3 day before; so wondrous is the transforming power of happiness/ There was a soft glow on the cheek lately so pale, and tremulous s/ilestole over a mouth still beautiful, but which for years had worn only an expression of pain and soow; nor could the young ' pastor wonder, as3'he gazed on Edward's ile face, beaming with ani- mation and affection, that his jnother's eyes rested -on him with such tearful joy, and his father listened to his voice as he feared its music would cease; and his son vanish from before his eyes. To Edward, the past seemed at times almost like a troubled dream, so vividly did he remember every thing that was unchanged in his early home; and he wondelred how he could ever have forgotten that which,  seen once more, was so dear and familiar. Even the old-fashioned sil- ver coffee urn, in which of old he had delighted to see the distorted-re- flection of his own face as hoe sat at the breakfast table, stood before his mother still, and lie could not resist the tempation of asking her in a low tone between jested earnest, if she still preserved the porcelain  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC8373-00000058"/> "6          ED WARD WILTON, OR mug in which he used to receive his morning draught of new milk. The cup, which was of peculiar workmanship and great beauty, had been kept sacred from the day of his disappearance ; no other lip had touched its rim, and no hand but his mother's ever removed it from its conceal-' ment. It was placed before him in an instant, and as he gazed on the graceful figures with which it was covered, it seemed to him that he was again a child at his mother's knee.            / In a secluded country village, or a frontier settlement, the old adage that 'ill news flies fast," applies equally to news of any description, and,the, sun had not half finished his breakfast of dew-drops, before the whole community were aware that Phillip Wilton had returned, br ng .ith I him his long-lost brother and at least an hundred versions of tij rcmnstances of Edward's life and restoration to his family, all froe tohe best authority, and each the only account to be depended up- onverepassing from lp to lp. Miss Smith had heard from Mrs. Joxnesiwhose husbamd saw the ,young .Wiltons as they rode into the ville :the precedig':evening, that the younger of the two was in a rel  Indian's dress, even to the blanket, withy long slit in his ears filled with silver rings, (dreadful! was it not?) and that he could scarce- ly ynaerstand or speak a word: of English; while Mrs. Martin ]knew, fromn a source equally reliable, that Edward Wilton had never been among;the Indians in his life, but having wandered far away into the forest at the time that he was lost, he was discovered by a small party from. the fort at Detr&amp;it, who, unable to obtain any direct informa- tion .wiwi regard to his home, had taken him with them, that he was immediately adopted by an officer, and educated for the army, where Phillip found him acting as one of the aids to the General commanding the' forBes now on their way north, and the silver rings which Mr. Jones sawtin his eA  werd only the embroidery on the collar of his uniform, glittering, in the moonlight-for Mrs. Martin knew postively that he was:; dressed in full uniform. How could Mrs. Smith believe such a ridic 9.los, story as the other . Various, however, as were the different stories, their narrators agreed most cordially in one thing, a most impatient curiosity to see the new- comers 2d which many of those whose acquaintance Mrs. Wilton per- mitted Miss Smith among the number--lost- no time in presenting themsves at the door, ostensibly to congratulate the happy mother andaiister, in reality to gain an mtroduction to the stranger, and decide for themselves which of -the many accounts of his adventures was most  lil y7 to prove true; others, with a truer sense of delicacy preferred  leaving the family toenjoy their own society and that of their most in-  itpant fieds*, amongwhom the Duvals rand firt.           /   I?  EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.          'i7 '       .        .: .-        . t ::         . CHAPTE R, XXXVII,           ' The brothers remained for a few happy, day son the banks of '!h Raisin, revisiting their childish haunts, many ofwhic wer;so ihcHlig- ed that Edward recognized themn at once. -Th'eiroseb still clusfere as luxuriantly as ever around the old tree beneath whose sl:Ldae hiiay when his infant beauty tempted Sagito to forego his dea dly puiipos for a revenge which he intended should beequally bitter' and even itore -lasting to the unhappy man who 'had offehndd .im. ' AS .the riiihed watudoer gazed on the rich masses' of flowersbliushimg^ aidst'the:d:rk glossy'foliage of the oak, the sudden conviction struck Mimthiatiith this spot were connected his last recollections dofihome,' Heiethm- bered well, as he told his mother, who .was' leaning on i h i i^ihow, wearied with friutless attempts to gather, some of the' roses 'whitcgrew h  beyond his:reach, he had thrown, himself down in thie sliade fo'!restt for a few moments, determined to accomplish his purpose before 'h^eenthred the house.   -                  .   i\e; "And there," exclaimed his mother you must have falln aseepjatid have been found by the savages, and this explains to me what has ever been one of, the greatest mysteries attending your disappearac, hodw you could have been carried away without making an alarm." i , i :"You havre been a long time gathering your fowers,- Edward, said Phillip; laughingly, as his brother broke Bff a spray of roses ' for -his mother, "but they will be scarcely less welcome on that acounit-will they, m*hier??      .                . Mrs. Wilton pressed the roses to her lips, but she6could not ireply to Philip's gay badinage, when she" looked back over the long period of sorrow and distress which had intervened between the promise of the child and its fulfilment by the man, For years hope had lain dead in. her heart; there -had been. only a That still and passive fortitude,  Which is but learnedfrom suffering." '   : And now, what a glorious sunise of happiness had burst on thatiibng night of misery! She almost feared she might yet awake, and find her new-born joy but a delusion of the night, as she had so ofteh :one Wefore, and she turned again to gaze Into elward's dark ey es, ^ Idart  the rih curls away from his brow to assure herself that this indeed,wa reality,  .           .  :; , The sob;er certainty of waking bliss." I ' '- To both Mr. and Mrs. Wilton the clockof time seemed, for, bile tuirned back to the early noon of their lives, and they almost :frgtthat ",g  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC8373-00000059"/> "8           zDWARD WILTON, OR the tall, vigorous young men, ol whom they could now lean for sup- port were not the children over Whose infant sports they had watched so long ago, and the walls rung more than once to Philip's gay laugh, when his mother unconsciously addressed Edward with some epithet of childish endearment, lovely in itf but ludicrous enough when ap- plied to the handsome and athletff young soldier at her side. But to none of the family did the change in Mrs. Wilton's looks and manners, seem so wonderful as to her gentle daughter. Mary Wilton had no remembrance of her mother, but as a sorrow-stricken woman, for whom even cheerfulness was too often a painful effort, and when she had sometimes heard allusions from their old friends to her early gaiety and vivacity of spirit, it had seemed almost impossible that those sad eyes could ever have been bright with happiness, or that smiles could ever have had their home on that pale cheek; yet now, when the sud- den and almost overpowering sensations excited by the return of her son had given place in some degree to a calmer happiness, Mrs. Wilton was indeed a different being. Her istep seemed to have regained the elasticity of youth, and sweet snatches of old songs flowed once more from lips whose music had so long been hushed. g    c"I shall groCjealous, mothers' said Philip gaily, as he entered the parlor one day, ad found his mother and Edward seated on the sofa, his hand clasped in her's, while she listened with fond anxiety to the de- tails of a life spent far from her, to the history of the gentle kindness of Nadesha, the war-like teachings of Sagito, and the sports and employ- ments shared with Otagimi; but' the dearest secret of his heart re- mained untold, and no allusion, to the dark-eyed Indian girl had passed his lips. "I shall certainly grow jealous, mother, for I think you have neither eyes nor ears for any one but Edward." The mother raised her eyes with reproachful tenderness to the face of her eldest born, but his bright, open brow showed no trace of the evil passion of which he spoke, and she replied in the beautiful lang- uage of the parable; "'Son, thou art ever with me, and all that I have is thine, but this brother was dead and is alive again, he was lost and is found.," These few days were precious .indeed to the hearts of both parents and children, succeeding as they did,} long years of gloom and doubt,' and soon to be darkened by the storm-clouds of war, the first crash of whose thunder, they knew, must be the signal for separation. And all too soon came the news, of hostilities commenced, and the-two broth- ers prepared to join the garrison It Detroit, in compliance with the or- ders received from their commanding officer when they left the army. i Bitter as the parting was, there Was far more of hope in the mother's ' heart than wheWlshe bade adieu to Philip but a few weeks previous;  she felt that the two would watch over and support each other, and she  trusted that the same power which had so wondrously preserved the younger during years of absence",would lead both safely through the ' new perils they must brave.  :                  j 4 ,ff/"   EARLY DAYS I  } MCHGAN.        19l .  ^. CHAPTER       XXXVIII. The young Wiltons, full of hope and glowing with patriotism, joined the army at Detroit, and bore their part fairly in the short-lived inva- sion of Canada Which followed almost immediately on the declaration of war. ' They shared, too, in the bitter put powerless indignation which., filled the hearts of that brave band, who, conscious of their ability to  keep their foes at defiance, were obliged to surrender without a single - blow in behalf of their country. In a work of so trifling a nature as the present, and one written by a woman, any attempt to describe the scenes of war would be unwise; yet, surely none, even of the daughters of America, can look over- that portion of her history which tells of the bloodless surrender of De- troit; without feeling the same glow of shame which burned on the brows of those brave men, as they cast down sword, rifle and banner, and saw the red cross of St. George streaming to the breeze, instead of the stars and stripes; and the fort and town they would have laid down their lives to defend, quietly given over to the keeping of their deadliest foe, and the tender mercies of allies yet a shade more cruel. There are some yet living who bore' a most unwilling part in the scenes of that day; whose chivalrous counsels had been neglected, and upon whose noble :hearts fell, like streams of molten lead, the disgrace they had vainly striven to avert. If these humble pages should meet their eyes, they may for a moment recall those feelirigs, but they will also remind them that the early degradation was amply atoned for in after days. As Edward Wilton, with a detachment of the now powerless army, left the fort, his eyes fell on a horde of dusky warriors, who were gazing on the scene with fierce and undisguised pleasure. One of the foremost groups was composed principally of warriors from the banks of the Kal- amazoo, and the dark faces 'in their terrible war paint were those which - had-been familiar to him for years. Sagito was at their head, and as his adopted son passed near him, he said with a smile of scornful tri- umph         "Does not the Eagle Eye see that the Yankees have the hearts of women? They do not even strike a blow when the red man and his, English brothers tell them to give up their gnns and strong houses. Will my son leave them even now, and join himself to men?" "The Eagle Eye will remain with his own people, and Sagito and the Englishmen will yet find there are hearts among them which are not the hearts of women." The chief did not notice the answer, but continued in the same'tone. ,      ,         ?  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC8373-00000060"/> 120        .  EDWARD WILTON, OR. of contemptuous triumph, as he watched the glances of anger and dis- like cast by- the departing army on him and his companions. "My son may tell his white brothers not to be afraid. The cowards who yield at the sight of an enemy, are not worth the rifle or the toma- hawk." Edward did not speak again, but his heart swelled almost to bursting, as he remembered that the only faint spirit which had breathed within the fort that morning, belonged to Him in whose hands were the desti- nies of thousands, and that the weakness of one man must bring the scorn and contempt of their enemies ,fpon a nation. The writer of these pages has neither the ability nor the inclination to depict the horrors of the campaign which followed, and rendered the western frontier a scene of desolation and wretchedness. The massacre at Frenchtown, where the savages, already maddened by the fire-water purposely provided for them, were loosed at midnight upon the care- lessly guarded troops and the unsuspecting inhabitants, is among the darkest pages in the history of this or any other war. With the bravery. of despair did the two brothers, and hundreds of others, young, brave and beloved as they, combat in the cold" and darkness of that bitter winter's night, against enemies a thousand times' more fierce and re- lentless than the elements in their wildest wrath, nor did the day when it dawned, bring any mitigation of their horrors. Those who still sur- vived were wounded or prisoners, and many of them fell a prey to the untameable ferocity of the savages, whose thrist for blood, once roused, is more untameable than the tiger's. Mr. Wilton's house, ferm its secluded situation, had escaped their ravages, but for days its inmates were unable to learn the fate of those who were dearer to them than,aught else in the world. Henry Effingham, however, who had been absent at the time of the massacre, but who had hastened home at the first intelligence of it, was fortunate enough to find that both Phillip and Edward were among the few who had survived the frightful march of the prisoners to Malden, and that, though both were wounded, their hurts were at least not mor- tal. Monsieur Duval's family had taken refuge with the Wiltons, at the first alarm, as their own house was much more exposed, and when the enemy left the desolated village, a heap of smouldering ruins was all that remained of the once 1happy home of the French trader. For months the two anxious and unhappy families remained together, lmak- ing vain efforts to communicate with the prisoners on the other side of the river; nor was it till the winter's ice had disappeared in the warmth of the spring breezes, that they received any further intelligence of those for whom they wept and prayed day after day. It was an unsually sultry night in May, and Josephine Duvai unable to sleep as she vainly strove to fancy whgre Phillip might be, if indeed he were yet alive, had risen, and throwing open her window, stood look- ing out upon the night. There was no moon, and though a heavy bank of clouds lay on the eastern horizon, the stars, which were still unob-   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN,         121  ' scured, gave a faint light, and the imaiden saw, with a throbbing heart, (   the tall figure of an Indian warrior approaching the house. He was alone, and before her terror allowed her to move or speak, he had paused a moment by a tree which grew near her window, and turned again towards the forest., Josephine watched him till his dusky form, disappeared in the, darkness, then lightly crossing the room, she bent over the bed and whispered to Mary Wilton, whose room she shared. The fair girls were at the 'window again in a moment, but there was nothing to be seen save the quiet stars and the gently moving trees. They hesitated for a while whether they would alarm the household, but at last determined to keep watch themselves, and allow the sorrow- worn family to rest, if rest they might, unless some new cause of terror shbuld occur. In silence, only broken by - an occasional low whisper, they, remained on their post till the faint streaks of light in the east,  and the first calls of the earliest birds, showed that the night was passed. As the lights grew stronger, the young sentinels could perceive that something was attached to the tree which had formed the limit of the Indian's approach. "It is some savage warning," said Mary: " there is an arrow." "Yes," replied het friend, " but there is paper too-a letter, I am sure--and the arrow has been placed there to secure it. There must ' be news of Phillip-of your brothers, Mary!" Even 'vhile she spoke, Josephine had throft her dressing ,gow4 around her, and before her companion could remonstrate, had glided Aiftly, yet silently, down the stairs, and- opened the outer door with a cautious hand. Mary gazed in terror from the window, lest the ap- pearance- of the young French girl should be the signal for the war- hoop and a burst of savages from the forest, but Josephine reached the tree in safety, and with a spring brought down the arrow by which the letter was transfixed, and around which was twined a rich string of va- rious colored wampum, and in another minute she stood by the side of! her more timid friend. "It is, it is- indeed from Phillip!" she exclaimed; " and see, here is the wampum to show the Indian's good faith." The missive was quickly torn open, and the two girls saw by the fast increasing light, the familiar hand and signature. There were but a few lines, but they were more precious than the mines of Golconda to his sister and his betrothed bride. "Edward and I are safe," so ran the note, "and nearly well of our wounds. One of Edward's Indian friends, (a fine fellow he is, by-the- bye, and one to'whom we owe your lives,) has promised that this shall reached you safely, my dear friends all. There is a rumor that. we 'are  to be sent to Montreal, but if our plans succeed, we shall be on our own side of the river in a week. ' "God bless you all. "PHLIP."  &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC8373-00000061"/> , " . 12  .       EDWARD WIION, OR -- '1". CHAPTER XXXIX.  The week after the arrival of Philip's letter, was, as may easily be conjectured, one of the most anxious suspense-to his friends. Ignorant as they were of, the nature of the plans to which he alluded, and know- ing his daring nature, every moment was one of watchfulness and terror. The whole frontier of Michigan was at that time under British rule and the. Wiltons felt but too surely that there could be nb safety among theim for fugitive prisoners. The week which Philip had mentioned in 'his hasty note had passed, and yet there were no tidings of him or Ed- ward, and Mr. Wilton and Monsieur Du;val had in vain attempted to learn if there had been any movement of the, prisoners at Malden. None of those they dared to ask could give them any information, and the hope which had animated their hearts'on first hearing from the young soldiers, was fast changing to that sickening suspense and dread far more difficult to bear than the certain knowledge of evil. More than two- weeks had rolled sadly and heavily away, and the evening of an excessively warm day had closed in with one of the terrific thunder storms common in the-western region. Heavy banks of black clouds had gathered in the west, and obscured the sun before his set- ting, and as they gradually covered the sly, the darkness became in- tense, only varied by vivid flashes of lightning, followed by the distant roll of heavy thunder; at last the storm burst in its full fury on the banks of the Raisin, lashing the river into foam ; the thunder no longer rolled majestically in, the distance, but burst in fierce and rattling peals, even in the instant that the mild glow of the lightning flashed as keen- Iy through closed blinds and drawn curtains as in the open air. Mid- night came and passed, yet the storm still raged with unabated fury, and there were but few sufficiently indifferent to its terrors to go to rest.  The Wiltons and Duvals were among the watchers, and in one of the short pauses of the tempest, Mr. Wilton had stepped to the door to as- certain if the clouds were breaking away. All was yet utter darkness, but. as he stood on the piazza, listening to, for he could not see, the de- scending floods, a sudden flash of lightning showed him the figures of two powerful-looking Indians almost at theifoot df the steps. To spring 'into the house and fasten the door was his first impulse, but the same light had shown him and his sudden movement to the approaching strangers, and before he could reach the entrance they were at his side, and the clear voices of his sons were ringing glad music in his ear., Forgotten at once were storm and darkness, as the overjoyed family crowded:around the seeming savages, whose dress and manner were so strangely at variance.   EARLY DAYS IN MCHGAN.        ,2 "You are to thank Edward's Indian friends for this meeting, sai Phii, when the first glad greetings were over, as his fahr equi3, the reason of their mas             fuh eraden" assacre last w  masquer, ade. "Otaimi saved our lives fter the The scvages are constantly goingand   the   of ca  now te  hieng extraord .inary that two of them should be dispatched b their h f on a pillaging expedition, even on such anigh t e p'ent indiffence to ourfae had rendered our guard comp Sve eglient, and once fiee fo  our prisonr we were soon savage enug in ou t appearance to bafflerdinary scutin.       enougk... Up o  and thanks to, the storm and darkness, we met none to 0uestion th  ut do you and Edward go now," said his mother, "and change ripping garments for your own; useful as they have been, I do- nohalf like to see you wear them."        have  I; They must stand us in good stead yet, my dear mother,' said Ed- "t fod, or with mccasins and war-paint, joined to my Indian edutc. ti, we shall reach  General arriason s ary in safety, while we cod i " remain here a day in our own dr'ess."; And this is war!" sighed Mrs Wilton, as the young men left the rao.  "Will such-horrors never ease?"      t  "I fear never," replied her husband, "'till they who fancy themselves the stronger shall have learned not to oppress and insult the compara tively Weak; but we must remember now that our wanderers need both  food and est after their midnight maach. When Philip and Edward W  7iltoil again entered the parlor, the war- paint removed from their faces and  in their usual dress, a substantial ( supper was awaiting them, to which they were willin  tdo full justice for the appetites of the youn  soliers eeded n  the previous zest- io fae to indu-c weeaea not the previous zesft':!? prison fare to induce them to do honor to the good things set before  "Are1 ousure you are so peefectly cured of you our wuds;y sons, asked Mr. Wilton, "that you dare venture on a journey now 2" "Perfectly, sir," replied Philip, all that we need i a nghts, o r rather a  day's rest-for we must tn day into n ight for once--and to m  orrow evening must see us on ou r w ay to the army." It was impossible to combat this resolution; all felt there was less danger in this plan than in any other, but it was heavy hearts that the \ assembled family, when darkness had fallen on  earth  the next night, saw the two young men appear again in the dress of Indian warriors. \J "o not weep, gosephbme, said :Pilip, trying to s ' the sobbing girl to his breast. When we me etsagleias, he lasp ed look, less ikle a savagee"Wgen w 'When we   meetsgain! Oh, when will that be Philip  " ; l   Icanot tell now, d earest, but depend upon it, there are bright days in store for us Met " ' "Godgrant it said M onsieur Duval, who stood near. : OWewh VV Wsi  &#xD;<pb n="124" xml:id="VAC8373-00000062"/> 124         EDWARD WILTON, OR --.                           : try to retain something of your hopeful spirit amongst us Philip, and look forward to happier days. Your young eyes may see the though mine do not." "Think happier things, my dear sir," said Philip, as he wi'uug the hand of his old friend; "we shall all live to-see them yet, I trust. Come, Edward, we must be miles on our way before morning. ' The young adventurers reached the American army in saf ty, and took no mean share in the scenes which followed, when Pery ori-  ous victory on the Lake had prepared the way for the relief of the Michigan frontier.' At the battle of the Thames, as Edward Wilton with his company was pursuing a portion of the routed army, be saw  splendidly dressed Indian fall, pierced with a ball from the u errinl rifle of a Kentuckian. As the wounded savage dragged himse f 'ith. difficulty to a tree a little out of the range of the fight and p . rsUit Edward recognized his adopted father, the stern and haughty ch eft o the Pottawatamnies. To spring to his side and aid him to raise hijmsel against the trunk of the tree, was the work of a moment, and a 1t g smile played over his featuies for an instant as he recognized his, ass, s tant. "My son was right," said he" when he said that the Yankees ^"ld  one day show the hearts of men." Fdward wouIr have had his old friend carried to a place tf satety, i bt'li he refused.,                      -  ' .i ' Tecumseh lies dead upon the field" he replied, " and Sagito will . follow his friend to the land of spirits." He had spoken with dfficulty, anid as he uttered the last words, a short convulsion passed over his'  face, and the high spirited and patrioti6 warrior of the woods was no -  more. The rush'and confusion of the battle field gave no time to greive over the dead; but, though Edward could not watch over the remains of his Indian father, he did not forget where they lay, and when the moumfu!l task'of burying the dead commenced, the old chief was ecaefully in- terred beneath'the tree where he breathed his last, in the same rich garb which he had worn in battle, and with pipe and tomahawk by his side, as became a chief and warrior of his nation.     &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>