<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8278">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Book of the Prophet Stephen, Son of Douglas, Vol. 1 </title>
            <author >White, Richard Grant, (1821-1885)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC8278</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Book of the Prophet Stephen, son of Douglas, vol. 1</title>
                  <author >White, Richard Grant, (1821-1885)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >48 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Feeks &amp; Bancker</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date >[1863-1864]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-09-20">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Book of the Prophet Stephen, son of Douglas, vol. 1</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8278-00000001"/>BOOK OF THE PROPHET STEPHEN, SON OF DOUGLAS. HERiEIN MARVELLOUS THNGS ARE FORETOLD OF THE REIGN OF ABRAHAM. NEW YORK: FEEKS &amp;' BANCKER, WHOLESALE NEWSDEALERS AND. BOOKSELLERS, No. 26 ANN STREET.    &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC8278-00000002"/> -.ENTERED according to Act of Congress, In the y'ear 1S63, by  FJlEKS .&amp; BANCKER, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States, for tho Southern '    District of New York.  W. H. TINSON, Stereotyper.               JOHN  . 118^,       .   PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, SON OF DOUGLAS. C IHAPTEE R I. 1 James the Eanich retireth and Abraham the Honest reigneth in his, stead. 3 King of Woolly-head-, a mighty statesman, splitteth rails and cooketh woodchucks. 4 He journeyetah from the Far West. 6 He resteth at the City of Gotham; offereth to kiss afair maiden. 9 His deeds of unknown valor. 10 lHe calleth Wfillicam to be his trumpeter. "Maketh a fish his puzrse bearer," who maketh precious coins out of green paper. 13 Simon the Just linister of Peace. 13 A Well he putteth over the sea. 14 Father of many children expoundeth the law according to the will of the king. 19 A great commotion in the land. 21 Th e inhabitants of Sunland strive for peace but the worsh7ippers of the wooqlly-headed Dragon refuse. 24 A man cometh out of the Tombs and smitetAhthe altars of the Temple. 25 A man gettet]i drunk and blowetIh up the king with afire- cracker. 24 Abraham coveteth the head of Jeff. 27 Sendeth the Pope to slay him 'with bulls. 28 Sends-is fiery dragon, Burnside. 29 Hooker the king's angler goeth forth. 31 Or- ders Park the Post Boy to blow off the heads of 40,000 with his-horn. 33 Abraham is deeieved by his cunning counsellors. I. IT came to pass in the eighty and fourth year of the Republic, that- James the Eunich having ruled all the days of his appointed time, retired to the shades of Wheatland, and Abrahamn, called the Rail-splitter, reigned in his stead. TI, Now Abraham   was a child of promise, and a wlan after the woolly-headed Dragon's own heart; full  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC8278-00000003"/> -- 4    PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, of exceeding cunning, and beautiful to look upon, as the skin of a sheep drawn over the' skeleton of a gorilla.    i  "I. Moreover he was a- mighty statesman, having, withal, had much experience in the matter of rail- splitting, flathoating, and cooking woodchucks in the Indian wars. IV. And behold it came to pass that, on his journey from the Far West to the seat of empire, even to the place that is called the Capitol, he made divers and sundry speeches, of great and marvellous power, inso- - much that the hills trembled at the sound of his voice, and vast scores of little pigs, and jackasses, and other beasts of the field, came and gathered about him, and were dumb with amazement at the beauty and majesty of the king. V. And, lo, when he was come to the place that is called Gotham, that is built upon the water that is over against the land of the Jersey she rested for the night. And the people came unto him, and took him up into the temple of the city, and there gath- ered about him men of high and low degree, who were curious to-look upon the king, to'see what manner of man he was. VI. And the great height of Abraham amazed the people, insomuch that a young and daring giant from the Aroostook in the land of Maine, boldly challenged the king to stand up and measure with him. But the king, looking down with pity upon the young man, said, No, I will not measure with thee, but if thou hast a sister, bring her hither, and her I will kiss. VII. And, lo, the people were dumfounded at the elegance and majesty of the king, and they fell down / and worshipped him. Vi11. And Abraham was also a great general, being   SON OF DOUGLAS.       $ a man mighty in battle, and of such exceeding strategy and invisible courage, that he cut his way, by night, ttirough?a hundred millions of hostile men in arms, that lay encamped in the region of country that is between the city that is called Harrisburg, and Washington, which is somamed from the Father of his Country.  IX. Now, having escaped the bloody legions of his imaginary foes, Abraham ascended the throne on the fourth day of the third month; and he summoned together the chiefs of his clan, even the mighty men of unknown valor and virtue, who gladly came unto him and threw themselves at his feet. X. And the king said unto William, whose surname is Seward, come thou and be my chief trumpeter to blow the fame of our kingdom to the four corners of the globe, and to make all other kings and poten- tates to tremble and flee away before the majesty of our power. XI. And then he called a fish from the great deep, ,which is also called Salmon, being named Chase among the natives of the wilderness of Ohio, and he said unto him, be thou my purse-bearer; and as we have neither silver nor gold, get thou engravers and printers, and blue ink, and red ink, and much green paper, and many mighty printing machines withal, and let us print money, to astonish the heathen, who think that nothing but silver and gold are precious metals.  XII. And next the king appointed Simon, who is called the Just, to be his minister of peace, and he said unto him, Do thou set up our comely black Idol, ,and bid all the people to fall down and worship it; lo, if any refuse, do thou draw forth thy sword, and smite them hip and thigh; for I say unto you that of  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC8278-00000004"/> 6      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, such neither man, woman, nor child shall live in my Ikingdom. And Simon bowed down his head, and kissed the hem of the king's garment, and said, My lord, I will. XTi. Then Abraham sent for one Gideon, whose surname is Wells, who is not deep, but is covered up with much hair, and he said unto him, Do thou be my ruler over the seas; and get thee speedily a hun- dred ships, and prepare thyself to lock up three thousand miles of the coast of the heathen who wor- ship white deities, lest it 'enter into their heads that they will not fall down before our comely black Idol. And Gideon lifted up his beard, and opened his mouth, and said, O king, thy will shall be done. -XIV. And after this the king sent abroad into the Far West, and summoned into his presence the father of many children; who is called Bates, and said unto him, Come hither, and sit by my side, and be thou the expounder of my laws, which thou shalt interpret according to my will, and not after the fashion of the books and judges which were before in this land. And the father of many children said, Yea, O king, -thy will is the law. XV. NQow there dwelt in the land the son of Blair, who was called M3ontgomery, and tha king said unto his servants, Send hither this man to me, that I may make him the, chief ruler over all my carriers, who axe to do my will in sending forth such papers as are pleasing unto me, and--in putting under their- feet whatever is opposed to the worship of the comely black Idol, And the father of the Blairs joyfully sent forth his son, even Montgomery, his youngest born, to do the bidding of the king. XVI. And, lo, when all theje things were done ac- cording to the pleasure of Abraham the king, he [   SON OF DOUGLAS.       7 again opened his mouth and said, Now let us. have one more man to serve in our name, in the interior of our kingdom; and again he sent forth into the West, and found him a man after his own heart; and when he had appointed 1him Minister of the Interior he journeyed so far into the interior that his name and his 'exploits have not been heard of, no, not even to this day.              . XVII. And it came to pass in those days that there 'was a mighty murmuring among the people that dwelt towards the South, and they loudly demanded of the king that he should make known to them; and to -all the land, whether they were to, be treated as equals in the family of States, or whether the religion of the woolly-headed Dragon /and the black Idol were to be the law of the land. XV1II. Whereupon the king was filled with exceeding dignity, insomuch that he swelled up to four times the size that was convenient to his skin. But he answered not a word, neither would he condescend to have any intercourse with- the heathen who worship white deities. XTY. And when the land was 'full of trouble, and the- hearts of wise men were smitten with dread, the mighty men of the nation came together, from the North and from the South, from the East and from the West, -and sat down in council together, as was the custom in those days. But the black fiend had taken possession of the people that dwelt in the Northland, so that they could do nothing to appease the fiery anger of the people that inhabited the region that lies to the south of the city that is called Washington. XX.' Now there were wise and good men in those days, who said, Let us go forth to s ve our pountry, that the men of the North and they of the Sot4 may *n,  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC8278-00000005"/> 8      - PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, still dwell together in unity, for our fathers were brethren. r XXT. And the wise men of the South stood up in the council of the nation, and said, I pray you let us settle this, our trouble, in peace. You men of the North take for yourselves and your black Idol, all the land that lies to the' west of the line that is called after the old name of Missouri, that runneth even to the shores of the Pacific Ocean; and we men of the South will take the little of the public domain that lieth to the south of that' line: and we will dwell to- gether as our fathers did, buying and selling and being one people forever and ever. XXTT. These things did John, surnamed Crittenden, a mighty man from the Southland of Kentucky, offer to the inhabitants of the North, in the name of the people of the South. XXIII. But, lo, the warriors of King Abraham all stood up as one man, and smote their breasts, and tore out their hair, and made such noises as time affordeth not to mention, swearing withall, that they would have peace on no terms that did not ensure the- universal worship of the comely black Idol. XXIV. And in those days came a man out of the Tombs, from the South, and smote the altars in the temple of the Nation with his fist, swearing that they of the South and of the North should be two people forever. XXV. And there followed after him a crazy man, who was called Wigfall, because he was often drunken, insomuch that he lost the natural equilibrium of his body, and suffered the artificial covering to his cranicum to fall prone to the ground: He, too, was full of wrath, and threatened to blow up the king with a fire- cracker,. 3   SON OF DOUGLAS.       9 XXVI. But the greatest of the chiefs of the South was the son of Davis, who was called Jeff, whose head the king coveted; for he showed himself great in skill to govern, and wonderful in the arts of war. XXVII. Insomuch that when the king sent forth the Pope to devour the hosts of Jeff, and to eat them up alive, according to the bulls he should publish against them, they neither feared, nor did they stand in awe, but came out in great force, and caused the Pope to flee for his life; and the place was thereafter called Bull Run, by reason of the marvellous flight of the Pope. XXVIII. And Abraham was discomforted; but, no- thing daunted, he commanded his fiery Dragon, which was called Burnside, to go forth and burn up the armies of the heathen, that worship white deities, root and branch. And, behold, when the fiery Dragon, even the all-destroying Burnside, was come into their coun- try, they threw great tanks of cold water upon him, insomuch that they utterly quenchedl him; so that he came back like a drowned chicken, and roosted in a chamber in the palace of the king. XXTX. Now the king bethought himself of a terri- ble and mighty angler among his warriors, which was called Rooker, because thathe knew how to hook; and him he sent forth, saying, Get thee over -into the land of the heathen, and put me a hook into the noses of all the rebels, and lead them hither unto me, that I maly kill them, every one, and be avenged of the wrongs that they have done unto me. XXX. And when he had- reached the southmost bank of the river that is called Chickahominy, the heathen looked upon him and saw what manner of man he was, and they laughed one to another; and, in their evil conceits, they sent forth an army of boots, 1*  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8278-00000006"/> 10      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, that kicked the hindermost parts of the king's fighting angler, and drove his rear guard even into the trenches that lie before the gates of the temple of the Dragon. XXXI. Now Abraham, the king, was sore oppressed, because the heathen had kicked the hindermost parts  of his mighty fighting angler; and he smote the earth until it quaked. And then he called unto him his faith- ful Post-boy, who is called Park, the son of Godwin, and he said unto him: The heathen have despised the Pope, and they have quenched my mighty, flaming Dragon, that is called Burnside, and they have kicked the hindermost parts of alooker, the king's own angler; now, therefore, do thou bring forth thine horn, and point its larger end straight at the heathen, and blow me a blast that shall blow off the heads of forty thou- sand. XXXTT. Now, the king's Post-boy was mighty of wind, so that he did even as he was bidden by the king; and, lo, he blew such a blast on his horn as astounded the heathen, yea, as blew the seat of his own nether garment into a thousand pieces, yea, inta a hundred thousand pieces; and the like of it was never known, no, not since the beginning of the world. XXXTTI. And, behold, when the king saw that his mighty, windy Post-boy had not blown off the head of a single rebel, but instead thereof had blqwn himself/ to pieces, he was fall of great grief, and of great wrath, and, lifting up his eyes to, the heavens, he ex- claimed: Art thou, then, in the name .of a thousand devils, on the side of the heathen? and is it thus that thou fightest for the comely black Idol, even for thine own cl ,jh of the woolly-headed Dragon? XXXTV, And Abraham was smitten with amaze- ment because his warriors had told him that speedily, t!  ,               /  .   SON OF DOUGLAS.         " yea, in ninety days, the hosts of the heathen should be, blown away, as chaff before a mighty North wind; and, behold,' nothing had come to pass according to the promise of his cunning counsellors and many mighty warriors. So Abraham hid his face-in his mantle and was ashamed. CHAPTER II. 2 Stephen the Prophet standeth up in the temple, and denounceth the worshippers of the woolly-headel Dragon--le showeth that they want war. 3 The worshippers of the Dragon gnash their teeth at the Prophet. 5 The warriors of thie king shed the blood of millions in their speeches. 6 Th:ey fain wqould destroy the Prophet by the blowing of rams' horns. 7 The Prophet showeth themt that war is disunion. 8 He chargeth, them with a design to destroy their country. 9 He pjroveth that all tyrants set up their claim to, prove that they have a government. 10 The Prophet showeth that a wzise nation goeth not to owar with its own people. "He showeth that the chief government hath no right to use the army, except according to -law, to aid the civil power. 12 He, tellath the truth concerning Fort Sumter. 13 [He proveth that Peace is the only policy that can save the country. I. Now  just before those days appeared Stephen the Prophet, who was also called Douglas, a mighty man in the councils of the nation, and beloved of the people; but hated by the king, because he had met him in" the mWestland, where the Prophet had proclaimed aloud the abominations of the woolly-headed Dragon, named by King Abraham-the comely black Idol. II. And Stephen the Prophet stood up in the coun- cil of the nation, even iin the Senate chamber, and, pointing his finger at the partisans of the king, cried out with a loud voice, saying: -You want war, because you  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8278-00000007"/> 12      PROPHECIES, OF STEPHEN,  thik that war will drive off the South and leave every- , thing here to the mercy of your h]ands. "I. And the partisans of the king, even Sumner, the pupil of Demosthenes, who stealeth the orations of his master, and Wade, called by Yallandigham the coward who wadetf up to his loins in the blood he hath not the pluck to shed himself, and all the hosts of the king, gnashed their teeth at the Prophet, and fain would have stoned him, but that they knew that the people loved him. IV. And the king was exceeding wroth, and sent for his chief warriors, even for William Pitt, who was called Fessenden, from the land of Maine, and said unto him, This seditious Stephen the Prophet is an offence unto me. H1e has been my evil genius even in the land of Thinois, where he proclaimed these infamous words in my own ears!"I old that this Government was made on the WH'E BASIS, by WErTE MEN, for the benefit of wait IEN, and their POSTERITY, forever." Therefore, O ye warriors of mine, be sure that some- how you bring to naught this stiff-necked prophet, him and his doctrines. V. Then all the fuglemen of the ki ng, even the val- liant warriors who shed the blood of millions of men in their speeches in the temple, put their heads together to see how they should confound Stephen the Prophet. VI. And, lo, they agreed that they would bring him down, as the walls of Jericho were brought down, by the blowing of rams' horns; and straightway they all began to blow at Stephen, until a mighty roaring wind shook the windows of the temple, and filled the spec- tators with fear, insomuch that fair women left the galleries in much trembling, and the old men said that such things had not been seen, no, not since the begin ning of the Republic.   SON OF DOUGLAS.         13 VII. Now, after all these things, Stephen came forth )and opened his mouth and said unto them, Do you think to confound the people with noise? Do you hope to save the Union by war? Verily, I say unto you that "War is disunion. War is final, eternal separation. Ifence, disguise it as you may, every Union man in America must advocate such amendments to the Con- stitution as willpreserve peace and restore the Unzio ; while every dis unionist, whether openly or secretly plotting its destruction, is the advocate of peaceful secession, or of war, as the surest means of rendering reunion and reconstruction impossible.   I have too much respect for any man, that has standing enough to be elected a Senator, to believe that ite is for war, as a means for preserving the U6nion, I have too much respect for his intellect to believe, -for one -mo^nmeMt, that there is a man for war whzo is not a disuniontst per se. Hence I do not mean, if I can prevent it, that the enemies of the Union-men plottin g to destroy it-- sh]all drag this country into war under t/he pretext of protecting the public property, and enforcing the laws, and collecting revenue, when their object is disunion, and war the means of accomplishing a cherished purpose." VIII. And while Stephen thus spake, the followers of the woolly-headed Dragon, even the warriors of the king, were filled full of anger as a coal, yea, as a live coal is of fire, and they raved at him; but Stephen heeded not their anger, neither did he fear them, but continued saying unto them: "The disunionists, therefore, are divided into two classes; the one open, the other serret disugm z onists. The one in favor of peaceful- secession and a recog- nition of independence  tfhe other is in favor of war,  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8278-00000008"/> "      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, as the surest mecanzs of accomplishing the object, and of making the seplaration final, eternal. I am a Union man, and hence against war." IX. Behold, when the Prophet had luttered these words, the Pitt of the Senate chamber was stirred up with exceeding wrath, and demanded to know if the king should not stretch forth his hand, even the hand of his powei', to show that there is a government in this land? And th6 Prophet answered the clamors of the Pitt, saying: I ' B]ut we are -told, and we hear it repeated every- owhere, that we must find out if we have got a govern- ment. ' Iacve we a government?' isqthe questiont; and we are told we must test that question by using the military power to put down all discontented spirits. Sir, this question, ' have we a government?' has been pronounced by every tyrant who has tried to keep his feet on the necks of the people since the world began. When the barons demanded Magna Charta from King JoAre^, at Runnymede, he exclaimed, ' hAave we a govern- ment g' and called for his army to put down the dis- contented barons. When C harles 1. attempted to collect the ship money in violation of the constitution of England; , and in disregard of the rights of the people, and was resisted by them, he exclaimed, ' have we a government  F We cannot treat with rebels; put dowr the traitors; we must show that we have a government.' WWhen James II. was driven from the throne of Eqng- land for tramnpling on the liberties of the people, he called for his army, and exclaimed, ' let us show that we heave a government!'  When George III. called upon his army to put down, the rebellion in America, Lord North 'cried  lustily, 'no conmpromise with traitors; let us demonstrate that we hoave a govern- ment.' When' it '1848, the peqple rose uPO   their   O8N OF DOUGLAS.         15 tyrants all over Europe, and demanded guarantees for their rights, every crowned head exclaimed, 'Ihave we a government ' and appealed to the carmy to vi ndicate their authority and to enfforce the law." X. Now these words of the Prophet Stephen only the more stirred up the worshippers of the black Idol to an evil and revengeful spirit, but he continued to rebuke them, saying: "Sir, the history of the world does not fail to con- ' demn the folly, weakness, and wickedness of that government which drew its sword upon its own people when tA/ey demanded guaranteesfor their rights. This cry, that we mnbust have a government, is merely follow- ing the example of the besotted Bourbon, who never learned anything by misfortune, never forgave an injury, never forgot an affront. .Must we demonstrate that woe have got c government, and coerce obedience, without reference to the justice or ij'ustice of the conm- plaints? Sir, whenever ten million people proclai m to you, with one unanimous voice, that 'they apprehend their rights, theirfiresides, and theirfamzily altars are in danger, it becomes a wise government to listen to the cppeal, and to remove the apprehenwsion. History does n ot record an example where any human government has been strong enougfh to crush ten million people into suthjection w'hen they believe their rights and liberties were imperidle without first converting the government itself into a despotism, and destroying the last vestige of freedom. "Let us take warning from, the examples of the past. Wherever a government, has refused to -listern to the complaints of the people, and attempted to put down their murmurs by the bayonet, they have paid the penalty.' XI. Moreover, said the Prophet, continuing to ex-  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8278-00000009"/> 16    !  f PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, pose the wickedness or foolishness of the unlawful plans of the king and his warriors:  "But we are told that the President is going to enforce the laws in the, seceded States. How?  By calling out the militia and using the army and navy! l These terms are used as freely and asfliippantly as' if we were a military government where martial law was the only rule of action, and the will of the nonarch was the only law on the .subject. Sir, the President cannot use the 'army, or the navy, or the militia, for any purpose not authorized by law. What is that.2? If there be an insurrection in any State against laws and authorities thereof, the President can use the military to put it down only. when called upon by the State Legislature, .if it be' in session, or, if it cannot be con- vened, by the Governor. He Vannot interfere except wrLen requested. If, on the contrary, the insurrection be against the laws of the United States instead of a State, then the President can use the military only as a posse comitatus in aid of the marshal in such case s as are so extreme that judicial authority and the powers of the marshal cannot put down the obstruction. The mvilitary cannot be used in any case whatever except in thve aid of civi process to assist the marshal to execute a writ." XII. And when Stephen had finished these words, he opened his mouth again to persuade the worship- pers of the woolly-headed Dragon,/ that they should make satisfaction to the men that dwell in Sunland,  aying:  "If we consider this question calmly, and make such -imendments as will conviee the people of the Southern States that they are safe and secure in, their person, in' their property, and in their family relations, within the Uniow we ooa restore andres eserve it. If we can-   SON OF DOUGLAS.         17 not satisfy the people of the border States that they may remain, in the Union woith safety, dissolution is inevi- table. Then the simple question comes back, what shall be the policy of t he Union men of this country . Shall it be peace, or shall it be war?  What man in all Americra, with a heart in his bosorm, who knows the facts connected, witlb Fort. Sumter, can hesitate it say- ing that duty, honor, patriotism, humanity, reTuire that Anderson and his gallant band should be instantly 'withdrawn?  Sir, I am not afraid to say so. Iwould scorn to take a party advantage or manufacture parti- san capital out of an act ofpatriotism." XIII. And thus the Prophet pleaded that they should be at peace with their brethren in Sunland: "Peace is 'the only policy that can save the country. Iet peace be proclaimed as the policy' and yobu  ill find that a thrill ofjoy will animate the heart of every patriot in the land; confridence will be restored; busi- ness will be revived; joy will gladden every heart; bonfires will blaze upon, the hill-tops and in the valleys, and the ch]urch bells will proclaim the glad tidings in every city, town and  village in America, and' the applause of a gratefulpeople will greet you everywhere.  Proclaim the policy of war, and there will be gloom an2d sadness and despair pictured uIpon? the face of every patriot in. the land. A war of kilidred, family and friends; father against son, mother against daughter, brother against brother, to subjugate one-half of this country into. obedience to the other half; if you do not mean this, if you mean peae,? le this be adopted, -and give the President the opportunity, through the Secre- tary of War, to speak the word 'peace;' and thirtq million people will bless Mhm with their prayers, and honor him, with their shouts of joy." XIV. And these were the lastwords spoken by the !  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8278-00000010"/> 18  '     PRIOPHECIES' OF STEPHEN, Prophet in the council of the nation; for he nevc returned more to behold the abomination of desolatio which should fall upoln its altars, by reason of th treason and- brutishhess of the worshippers of th Dragon'. CHAPTER      III. 1 The Prophet retireth to his own hired house and teacheth ti people that come unto himr. 2, The Angel of Peace apperet unto him and showeth the abominations of the woolly-head&amp; jDragon. 4 Heprophesieth of the desolation of the land. 7 TY Angel of Peace showeth him out. of the Prophet Jeremiah the an evil shall spring out of the North that shall spoil the who land. 10 He showeth from Jeremiah that the pastors of t: churches shall become brutish, and be destroyed. "He showe X  that the people shall take vengeance of the false judges. 12 1 showeth out of Jeremiah that the judges shall become facse az judge not according to the law, but according to the will of t) king. 14 He prophesiethl, that the abomination of desolatei shall last as long as Abraham ruleth. I. AND, behold, when Stephen had denounced t} strong men, and all the warriors of the woolly-heade Dragon in the temple, he went apart by himself into secret place, even into his own hired house. An there came much people unto him, such as were c pure heart and loved the land of their fathers, and 1 opened his moutli and. taught them, saying: II. Harken unto me, O ye people; for at mid-da the Angel of Peace ca le down with a great light or of the heavens, and said unto me: Stephen, the sc of Douglas, what seest thou? And I said, I see wo0lly-headed Dr/gon, whose tail and hindermost par are nm the!Northl but from his mouth goeth out forkc , ,   SO6N OF DOUGLAS.       19 lightnings and hot flame, that rageth even towards the South. "I. Again a great rushing light came -before my eyes, and the Angel of Peace said, What seest thou? And I said: I see a seething-not, and around about it standing the giants of Abraham, the mighty king of the Woolly-heads. IV. Then the Angel smote the cloud of smoke with / his rod, and said: Behold, O Stephen, the seething-pot is thy country, and the giants round about, even the warriors of the woolly-headed Dragon, shall ravage thy fields and bring desolation and famine upon ,all the land. There shall not be one stone in the foundations of the Temple of Liberty that shall not be thrown down. Neither habeas corpus, nor trial by jury, nor any other thing that thy fathers gave thee shall be left for thee and for thy children, so long as Abraham, the king of the Woolly-heads, reigneth. * V. And thy sons shall be slain in battle, their child- ren shall cry for bread, and the mourners shall go about the streets, when there shall be none to pityr them; for the woolly-headed Dragon shall harden the hearts of his- people, that they shall riot hear the cries of the; widows and the orphans that they have made. VI. And in those days 'beggars, and such as are,  called thieves, shall become rich men. They shall wax fat, and kick at whomsoever will not fall- down and worship thee black Idol. So they that were beggars and serving men shall dwell in palaces, and shall fill their bellies with strong drinks and hot meats, and swell up with great pride and much wind, until they shall be known in the whole region round about for their inso- lence and much stinking. VII. Then about the second hour of the third watch of the night the Angel of Peace came unto me the  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8278-00000011"/> 2 0O     PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, second time, holding a Bible in his hand, and he opened to the book of the Prophet Jeremiah, and said unto me, Read; and I opened my eyes and read these words: "Then said the Lord unto me, out of the North an evil shall break forth upon all the inhabitants of the land."  lIII. And the Angel turned over a leaf in thee book of the Prophecy of Jeremiah, and said unto me, Now open thine eyes and read what thou seest; and I be- held these words: "My bowels, my bowels! I am pained at my very heart; my heart maketh a noise in me; I cannot hold my peace, because thou hast heard, O my soul, 'the sound of the trumpet, the alarm of war. Destruction upon destruction is cried, for the whole land is spoiled; suddenly are my tents spoiled, and my curtains in a moment. - For my people is fool- ish, they have not known me; they are sottish child- ren, and they have none understanding; they are wise to do evil, but to do good they have no knowledge. And when thou art spoiled, what wilt thou do? Though thou clothest thyself with crimson, though thou deck- est thee with ornaments of gold-thy lovers will des- pise thee, they will seek thy life."  IX. And then I said in my heart, Behold, O my people, in these words of the Prophet Jeremiah, what woe shall be visited upon this our land, because of the rule of Abraham and the giants of the woolly-headed  Dragon. X. Again the Angel of Peace turned over a leaf in the book of the Prophet Jeremiah, and said unto me, Open thine eyes and read, and I read: "The priests said not, where is the Lord? the pastors transgressed against me, and the prophets prophesied by Baal, and walked after things that do not profit. For the pas- tors are become brutish, and have not sought the Lord     SON OF DOUGLAS.       21 therefore they shall not prosper, and their flocks shall be scattered," XI. And, lo, when I read these things out of the Prophet Jeremiah, my heart was sore within me, and mine eyes were full of tears, for I knew that the priests of this land should become brutish, that the blessed altars of peace should be changed into butcher's sham- bles, and war, revenge and blood should stream forth from the desecrated places of religion. By reason of these things I saw that the churches should be broken up, and that the sons of Anack and' Belial, who are also called after the names of Beecher, Cheever and Tyng, should corrupt the hearts of the pastors, until they all become brutish together, and walk in the fiery paths with the children of perdition. Verily I say unto - you, the end of these wolves in sheep's clothing shall be that of the ungodly, and their names shall be stricken out of the Book of Life. Their carcasses shall be devoured by the eagles, and the young eagles shall pick out their eyes; the bittern shall eat the flesh- of their bones, and the lizzard shall hatch its young in the hollow of their skulls. For they have not hiark- ened to the voice of peace, neither would they heed the commandments of the Prince of Peace.  l XII. And I lifted up my eyes, and behold, the Angel of Peace was still standing before me, with the first finger of his right hand pointing to another pas- sage in the book of the Prophecy of Jeremiah, arid he commanded me to read, and I read these words: "1 And they that handle the law know me not." And the Angel dropt his head upon his breast and wept. X1II. Then, ah woe is me, I knew that the judges of this land would also be led astray by the green charms of the woolly-headed Dragon, and that they would no longer judge according to the law and the  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8278-00000012"/> 22   .   PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, testimony, as was the custom of our fathers, but ac- cording to the will of the king. XIV. And when I lifted up my eyes, behold the Angel still was weeping, and his face was bowed even to the ground; which showed unto me that this the corruption of the judges of the land was the sorest calamity that could overtake a free people. Then I cried aloud in mny despair. I said: O Lord, is this people lost I How-long shall the perjured judges es- cape the vengeance of the peo!ple.? How long are these days of our humiliation and\ shame? And sud- denly there appeared a black cloud before my eyes, in the midst of which these words were written in let- ters as red as flame: 1"Behold, as lo ,g as Abraham and the woolly-headced Dragon bear rule." XV. And I said, How long, O Angel of Peace, shall it be to the end of these days of our abomination, even to the end of the rule of Abrahamz and the worship- pers of the black Idol Then the Angel lifted up his head, and I saw that his eyes were sad, and sorrow covered his face as a garment, but he answered not a word; and, behold, in the midst of a great and shining light he ascended up into the leavens, and I covered i my face with my mantle, for I was sore with grief and stricken in heart with much grief. stiAw                     .   SON OF DOUGLAS.          23 CHAPTER IV. 2 The Prophet showeth out of the Book of Jeremiak that the woolly-headed JDragon shall put a lying spirit into the minds of the people. 4 The worshippers of the black Idol shallper- secute and imprison the worshippers of the white deities. 6 The hypocrites shall leave the temple of the white deities, and go out into the temple of the black Idol, and come back loaded with the green jewels of the Dragon. 6 Daniel, the son of Dick, shall get into a den of thieves. 8 The building of the new Temple -of Janus half way betweeni the temple of the white deities and that of the black Idol-Peter, the son of Cagger, and the Dean of Richmond. 9 Elijah, the War Horse turned into. a donkey in the dirt-carts of the King. "The utler of the Knicer'bockers ascendeth like an eagle and lighteth lice a dove-The Dean. of Richmond buildeth him a chicken- coop behind thie Temple of Janus. 12 The people shall plot to destroy the Temple of Janus. IL Now it came to pass on the third day of the sixth month, at abo'ut the middle of the first watch of the night, that the Angel of Peace came unto me the third time, bearing in his hand the book of the Prophet Jeremiah, which was open 'at the seventh chapter, and he said unto me, Arise, O Stephen, the son of Douglas, for I have that for thee to read that shall tell thee what is to befall thy land before the end of the reign of Abraham the king of the Woolly- heads. II. Then I arose, and looked into the book of the" prophet that was in the hand of the Angel, and read these words: "But thou shalt say unto them that:this is a nation that obeyeth not the voice of the Lord their God, nor receiveth correction: truth is perished, and is cut off from their mouthb. And they bend their tongues like their bows for lies." "I. And then I kncw,   O0 ny people, that the fel   I  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8278-00000013"/> lowers of the woolly-headed Dragon should destroy and utterly spoil this land with their lying tongues, which should breed evil surmisings, and discontent, and slanderous reports, and all manner of lying abominations, until there should be no soundness, no, nor any truth left among the people. IV. Moreover, it appeared unto my vision, that the worshippers of the black Idol shall persecute and say all mzanner of things falsely against the wor- shippers of the white deities; insomuch that they shall be stoned in the streets, and be led to prison to be devoured of the vermin of the woolly-headed Dragon, and suffer violence?at the; hands of the Woolly-heads, because they will not fall down to worship the black Idol of the king.  Y, And in those .days fearfulness shall seize upon all the hypocrites that have crept for a cover into the temple of the white, deities, and they shall run out in the trayi' of the woolly-headed Dragon, and shall pros- trate themselves before the black Idol, and swear like that Judas whose bowels gushed out, that they never knew the white deities. And these shall come back loaded with the green charms of the woolly-headed Dragon. VI. And the greatest of the apostates from the temple of the white deities shall be Daniel, the son pf Dick; not that Daniel that was in the lion's dea, but that other Daniel, that got himself intd a den of thieves, and took the Scriptures down with him, and quoted them, to the great delight of the harlequins that dance before the black Idol in the temple of the Dragon.    I VIL. Now in those days many shall fall away from the'truth by reason of fear, who shall not gd over toi the temple of the woolly-headed Dragon, nor will they dare to remain wholly in the temple of the white g .      - ' /      .         *    osN OF DoaGLAs.       25 deities, but shall go out midway between the two, and shall mrake their benedictions first to the one and then to the other, looking two ways at the same time, like the hleathen gods in the temple of Janus. VIII. Among such as these shall be Peter, not that Peter vho0 denied his master once in Judea, but Peter, the son of Cagger, who denied his principles a thou- 3b' "'v u;Llthis1 principles a thou- sand times in the land .of the Knleckerbockers; and with him also the great Dean of Richmond, called the Profane, of whose riches and cunning manceuver- ing there is no end; and these shall build a new tem- ple of Janus, and many are they that shall come therein to worship. IX. And these shall take Elijah, called the War Gorse, and they shall turn him into a donkey, and shall make him to draw dirt inl the dirt-carts of Abrq- ham  the king of the Woolly-heads, whereby they shall get great gain to themselves, and Shall enrich themselves, even with the green 'ehams of the Dra- gon- X. Now   a great ruler shall arise in those days, to whom the people shall look for deliverance from the power bf the Dragon, and to lim shall be given the name of See Wore, because it shall be believed that he hath the gift of seeing further than other men even than the cunning king Abraham, of whose wis- dom no man shall know, no, not to the end of time. XI. And this great ruler shall rise before the peo- ple like a mighty eagle,'and he shall soar proudly up, and -fly very high, and spread his broad wings over the whole continent, insomuch that there shall be a great fluttering among the chickens of the Dragon; but when the king of the Woolly-heads, who is a cun- ning archer, shall come forth with his bow and arrow, this proud eagle shall subside as gently as a cooing 2  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8278-00000014"/> 26  'ROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, dove, and gracefully light in a chicken-coop, which the great Dean of Richmond shall cause to be built a hundred and twenty cubits back of the new temple of XII. Lo, there shall be great murmuring and much indignation among the people, and they shall smite their breasts and demanid, Who shall deliver us from the power of the Dragon, and from    the tyranny of Abraham  the king of the Woolly-heads.   And they shall plan among themselves how they shall destroy the new temple of Janus, by means of which soq many ,worshippers are drawn away from   the temple of the white deities, and carried  off half-way over to the temple of the black Idol. CtIAPTER V. 1 The Gothanmites shall nmurmur against their Watchmen becausd they take bribes from the King of the Woolly-heads. 2 They send for See Mlore to oome over and help them. 3 He sendeth is man Friday, Waterberry the Valiant. 5 The nan Friday gatheretl three shp loads of proof against the Watchmen, and See More sweareA that the Watchmen shall die. 6 Great joy among the Gothamites--every macn issethk his neighbor's soife for joy.. 7 The Watchmene escape the vengeance of the puler of the Knie7cerbockers. 9 The People murmur and smite the Blerr of the sKnickerbockers, because he deceived them. 10 The Prophet foretells the death of ail the worshippers in the Tem e :  oft Janus. 12 Be?warns the people to beware of The World hi  guideth he people intthehe Temple of 'Jants, and showeth that its heart- is like Marble, and its blood like that of a Halibut, 13 He wacrneth. against false Judges, such as Daly defilethe Temple of Justice. 14 He woarneth against Lazwyers woho plead for the blck Idol for hire. I. And in those days shall be great murmuring among the people of Gotham, a city that is builded by   J;       JON OF DOUGLA.         7 the waters over against the land of the Jerseys, because of the impurity and wickedness of their watchmen, who shall rebel against the people their masters, and shall take' bribes from t  he kingofthe Woolly-heads, by means of Which great and scandalous wrongs shall be committed against the liberty and peace of the Gotham-  ites. II. And they shall say to the lmigllty ruler of the KInickerbockers, who is also called See More, We pray thee to come over and help us, and to defend us and our children fromn the machinations of the evil dis- posed watchni, who have sold thlleselves to the worshipper of the woolly-headed Dragon. HII. And he shall send his man Friday, who is called Waterberry, by reason of his head looking like a small berry growing at the top of a tall water-weed, a man valiant in his own conceit, who shall never be kIown to covet anything that belongeth not to another, nor to take anything that lieth beyond the reach of his hand, whose honesty no man shall see, nor shall any man comprehend it to the end of time. IV. Behold, the mighty ruler of the Knickerbockers shall say to this man, Get thee down to the Gotham- ites, and bring me back a faithful record of the abomi- nations of the watchmen, that I may revenge the people of the wrongs that they have 'suffered at their hands. V. And, lo, the man Friday, even he that is called Waterberry, shall go down to the city of Gotham, and shall gather up testimony against the faithless watch- men, that, shall fill a hundred thousand volumes, and shall take them back in three ships to the ruler of the Knickerbockers, who shall swear in his wrath that the watchmen shall die.   YI. And he shall smite the mountains and they  shall tremble at his nod, and the sea shall roar, and the  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8278-00000015"/> 28      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, birds of the air shall fall dead with fright; and the - people of Gotham  shall rejoice with exceeding joy, insomuch that every man shall kiss his neighbor's wife, because they shall be delivered' fron the hands of the faithless watgchlmen. VII. But I say unto you, that the mountains shall tremble, and the sea roar, and the birds die; and the other men's wives shall be kissed in vain, for the watchmen shall not die, neither shall they be driven out by the inighty ruler of the Knickerbockers; for behold, he barketh like a dog, but runneth like a hare. VIll. And thie people shall become sick at heart, for they shall see their hopes perish, and shall find none to deliver them from the hands of Abraham the king, nor from the malice of the worshippers of the woolly-headed Dragon. IX. And they shall smite the rpler of the Klnick- erboclkers .until he die, so that he shall not be king, according to the promise of the worshippers in the temple of Janus. X. Moreover, I say unto you, that all who follow the hypocrites into the temple of Janus shall die; for they have forsaken the temple of the white deities, and turned their faces away from the altars that were builded by their fathers. XI. And all the men of this world shall die, because The World shall deceive them and lead them astray from the paths of truth, unto the temple of the heathen, even the new temple of Janus. XII. Give ear and hea/rken unto me, O ye worship- pers of the white deities, be ye not mixed up with the followers of The forldcl, for it is. a wolf in sheep's clothing; it hath been the herald of the king of the Woollylheaads, and was taken by the Bohemians, for hire, over into the temple of Janus, where it bowhth from afar to the white deities, while its heart is far from    SON OF DOUGLAS.          29 it. It knoweth not Democracy, neither understandeth it the worship of the white deities, for it hath a heart like Xarble, and its blood is like that of a Halibut. XTTT Beware, also, of false judges, and such as Day defile the altars of justice with sacrifices to the black Idol by reason of the green charmns of the woolly headed Dragon. XIV. 3Ioreover, I say unto you, shun the council of lawyers, who sell their country to the black Idol foi the green charms of the Dragon.     -Brade-he never so fair a web of cunningly devised falsehoods to hide his treachery to the white deities, believe him not; neither suffer thyself to be drawn into the ways of his foot- steps; for his paths are filthy with lucre, and he getteth fat with the fees of sin.  From  such turn away. CHAPTE R YI.        ' 1 The Prophelt showeth out of Jereminah that Benjamin, the king's IButler, Shall plunder the City of Orleans. 3 tHe shall be called ' the Brcit, and shall treat the mot/hers of c hildren like harlots. 4 His officers shall take concubines of the Ethiopians, and dwell in the mansions of the rich. 5 The Post-boy of Gotham shall trumnpet the praise of Benjamin tho Bruit. 6  The King is of ended at hie Butler becausoe he hordcth the gold which he steaeth--he putteth. Nathaniel the dancing-ma ter in Uis place. 7  The Arngel of Peace showeth out of Jeremiah that those who -have called green paper money sh7all die as the fool. "He shozoeth that those whob think they- have money as a dog hath fleas are without richlas. 12 He showoeth the people the moulntaein of debt which the kinzg's purse-bearer s7hall build. 14 He ahoweth that the                 woeopl shall scatter the riches *which the wor-shippers of the Dragon nude out of green paper, so ihat their children shall beg bread in the streets. I. Now  it came   to pass on the seventh day of the eighth month, the salne beinig the fifth month of the  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8278-00000016"/> 380      PROPHECIES OF STEPIEN, reign of Abraham, the son of Inlow, whose mother was of the Ethiopian tribe of Hanks, that the Angel of Peace appeared unto me the fourth time, holding in his left hand the book of the Prophet Jeremiah; and he said unto me, Arise, O Stephen, anid make thlne eyes familiar with these words of the twentieth chapter and twenty-second verse of the Prophet; and I. read after this manner: "Behold, the noise of the bruit is come, and a great commotion out of the North country, to make the cities desolate, and a den of dragons. .  When I had fed them to the full, they then committed adultery, and assembled themselves by troops in the harlots' houses. They were as fed horses in the morn- ing; every one neighed after his neighbor's wife. Shall I not visit them for these things? saith the Lord, and shall not my soul be avenged on such a nation as this?" II. And as I read these words out of the book of the Prophet, lo, the Angel of Peace was sore oppressed, insomuch that his whole frame shook with horror: and then I saw what must befall the city that is called New, and that beareth also the name of Orleans, that is built by the shore of the father of waters, afar off, in the land that lieth to the south of the habitation of the woolly-headed Dragon. i III. And I said, This is a doomed city; for the king of the Woolly-heads, even Abraham, the son of Inlow, shall send Benjainp, his Butler, who shall also be called " the Bruit,' as is given in the Prophet Jere- miah; and he shall enter in and dwell thgre, and the inhabitants thereof shall flee before his hand as from, a pestilence; for he shall order his soldiers to go out, every one of them, to plunder the people, and to treat all the fair women, even such as are the mothers of children, as harlots. / IV. Now, the officers and soldiers of Benjamin, w is called the Bruit, shall do even as they are b /    SON OF DOUGLAS. i      01 and they shall drive out the inhabitants from their own dwellings, and take to themselves comely black concubines of the Ethiopian tribes tlat abound in those regions; and they shall enter into the mansions of the rich and dwell there, eating and drinking and making merry in their hearts. V. And the king's Butler, even Benjamin the Bruit, shall flourish like a green bay tree, and shall become rich beyond other men by reason of plundering the people of the city; and his fame shall spread abroad throughout the land, even unto Gotham, where a Post-boy shall trumpet his praise afar to all such as love much stealing, and to every one that hath a lickerish tooth towards the fair and fragrant daughters' of Ethiopia. VI. Bat it shall come to pass thlat the king shall become wroth with Benjamin, his Butler, because, while he stealeth many hundred pounds of gold, he cunningly hideth it in his own house, and never bring- eth, not so much as e ven one ounce, into the temple of the Woollv-headed Dragon; therefore the king shall say unto his Butler, Now, get thee out of this city, for I will no more of thee; and I will put my faithful servant Nathaniel, the dancing-master, who is the son of Banks, into thy place, and he shall steal honestly, and shall bring the full half of all the plunder into the temple of tfhe Dragon. VII. Now While all these things, passed before my vision a great- and sudden trembling seized my whole frame, and! was stricken with much sorrow; for I saw tlat, according to the Prophet Jeremiahl, God will one day "' be avenged on such a nation as this-," and that the whole people will be made to suffer for the abomi- nations of Abraham the king and all the besotted wor shippers in the temple of the Dragon.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8278-00000017"/> 82      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN,  VIII. And in the midst of this affliction, even the sorrow that straineth the reins, and maketh the head like waters, the Angel of Peace opened the book of the Prophet J/eremiah, at the eleventh verse of the seven- teenth chapter, and commanded me to read. IX. Behold the words of the Prophet: "As a par- tridge sitteth on eggs and hatcheti them not, so he that getteth riches, and not by right, shall leave them in the midst of his days, and at his end shall be a fool." X. And I was sore afraid, for I knew not the mean- ing of these words, neither could I understand them; and I spake unto the Angel of Peace, and said: I pray thee to open mine eyes that I may know and under- stand the words of the Prophet. XI. Then the Angel opened his mouth and taught me, saying: The days shall come when the land- shall be full of green paper, and it shall be called money by. the worshippers of the black Idol. And every man shall have a bag fulll of such as is called money; yea, the woolly-headed Dragon shall measure out his money to the followers of the king by the hundred yards at a measure; and they that are drunken and such as spend their days with lewd women, and such as know not how to read, neither can they write, by reason of their great ignorance, shall abound with money as a dog with fleas, yea, as a-little dog with many fleas. ' XII. And verily I say unto you that the people, whose eyes shall be charmed so that they shall think the green paper to be money, shiall allow the king's purse-bearer, even he that shall, be called Chase, be- cause the imaginations of his heart shall be chased day and night by visions of the fair daughters of Ethiopia, to heap up a great mountain of debt, so that the people can never climb to the top thereof, neither can they   SON OF DOUGLAS. ;       33 dig under it, nor go round it, but it shall be there to devour the substance of them and their children for- ever and ever. XTTII. Behold, he that thinketh himself rich, by rea- son of so much green paper, shall be poor, for the day cometh that it shall be naught, and, as saith the Pro- phet Jeremiah, " at his end he shall be a fool." XIV. Then harken unto me, O ye fools! for the day cometh that shall burn as an oven, and all ye that have made gain by shoddy, and enriched yourselves by the robbing of the people, shall be burned up by the fierce anger of the people; for I say unto you that hunger breaketh through a stone wall, and that the wealth which you shall steal away from the people, as the un- lawful spoils of war, shall be scattered by the hand of the people, to -them and to their children, and your own, offspring shall beg bread in the street. CHAPTER VII. 1 The Angel of Peace pronounceth the doom of the worshippers of the black Idol. 2 Their sons shall be sent forth to battle and die. 3 The warriors of Sunland shall kill them man for man. 4 The Angel of Peace showeth that the woolly-headed Dragon had made his worshippers like swine, and not like men. 5 Their names shall stink inr the nostrils of the nations. 6 He foretell. eth the doom of the Loyal Leaguers. I. Tars saith the Angel of Peace: O ye followers of the woolly-headed Dragon, who hath hardened your hearts that ye cannot feel, who hath blinded your eyes that ye cannot see!  For have you not said one to another: Let us gather together our sons, even under 2*  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8278-00000018"/> 84;     PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN,- the banners of our fighting men, and send them down to the dwellers in Sunland, to slay all that will not bow the knee to the comely black Idol in the temple of the Dragon! II. And behold your sons shall go forth and they shall not return. They shall take the sword arid they shall perish by the sword. The mothers of the land shall weep for the slain of their offspring; your old men shall die, waiting for the return of their youngest born, and there shall be no eye that shall not weep, no, not from one end of the land to the other. "I. Now, therefore, harken unto me, and give ear to the words of my saying! To what end do you send forth your sons to kill the dwellers in Sunla d! For do they not slay your sons, pian for man? To what end do you burn their wheat-fields? To what end do you steal their' cunningly-wrought silver spoons? To what end do you lie down in the tall grass by the side of their black wenches? For is it thus that you would bring them back to sit with us in love as did their fathers a IV. O ye blind of heart and void of understanding, who hath delivered you over into this slough of fool- ishness? Who hath made you likeq swine, and not men? Who-hath taught you to forget that you are white men, and not negroes? Verily. I say unto you that'you have debased yourselves, and gone after other gods, wallowing about in blood and uncleanness. V. Therefore, saith the Angel of Peace, ye shall perish in your naughtiness. Ye shall be a by-word among the nations; yea, and your names shall stink in the nostrils of the nations; so that there shall be none that do not abhor you. They shall point at you in the streets, and shall say: There goeth a fool; yea, a very fool, and the father of fools!  b I  VI. And ye of the "Loyal Leagues' shall be in- flated with ignorance and pride, and shall swell up until ye crack with insolence and much stuffing, so that they of clean lives shall run from you, and hold their noses at your passing. Verily I say unto you that this shall be your reward in the world that now is; and in that which is to come ye shall be with the Ethiopians. CHAPTER VIII. I Abraham getteth in trouble with his officers of custom. 2 His servant Barney. 8 The Tribunes defend him. 6 Genaeral ay- mond of Solfering, organizeth a corps of liars. 10 The wicck- edness of the Times. 12 The great General Bust Steed cometh out of the Tombs. 13 Day Vis the Traitor. 14 Bust Steed drawheth a Curtin before him. 18 The great General Cock- Ran. 20 I)ix, who hath an. itch for office. 21 Daniel the Sic- kle. 27 JSfus, the king's merry-Andrews. I. AND Abrahain the king shall grow in trouble day by day; for they that serve him shall be of a corrupt heart, insomuch that they shall rob the strong box of the king, and bring his name into great contempt among  the people. Even his servant Barney -shall gather about him, at the receipt of custom, such as traffic with the heathen for their own gain, even Stanton, who is the weak male member of the body of that strong woman, who is the mother of the Bloomers. II. And they shall make the place of the receipt of customs a den of thieves, so- that the merchant men shall murmur among themselves, and shall say unto the king, We pray thee to deliver us from  the extor- tions of thy servant Barney.   &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8278-00000019"/> 36      PROPHECIES OF STEPEI9x, "I. Now the king shall have Tribunes in the city of Gotham, at the place of thie receipt of customs, which shall rule over the people in his stead;- and he shall say to his Tribunes, Now judge me of this mat. ter of my servant Barney, whether he lacketh any- thing, or hath too much of his own cunning to be use- ful unto us:.  IV. And the Tribunes shall say' unto the king, Thy servant Bacrey is a faithful and- just serving-man, inasmuch as he loveth the black Idol, and turneth out of the place of custom all whose grandfathers, yea, whose great-grandfathers were worshippers of the white deities. V. Then the king,shall say, Lo, Barney is a good boy. VI. Now Abraham shall be sorely vexed because of the want of great generals in the land. And he shall send out to the far land of Italy, and command to come unto him the mightiest commander of the world, even General Raymond, the immortal hero of the bloody field of Solfering, and he' shall say unto him, I pray thee to organize for me the second great army corps of my kingdom, even an army of liars, that we may meet and overcome the worshippers of the white deities, who think to put us down with the TRUTH. VII. And this- mighty general, even Raymond of Solfering, shall hasten unto the king to prostrate him- self before the throne; and he shall stand up before the king, in stature a mighty giant, full sixty inches in height.  VII. And he shall speak to the king, saying, Mighty monarch of the universe I brother to the sun, and first cousin to the moon! behold, both the world and I applaud thy wisdom and thy patriotism, in   SON OF DOUGLAS.       37 meeting the foolish hosts of truth with the proud and the resistless army of lies. Thou shalt see how I will scatter them to the four winds of heaven; yea, they shall be as dust under the wheels of my chariot, so that he that thinketh he standeth by reason of the truth, shall be trodden under foot of the legion of liars that I, even Raymond of Solfering, shall lead against him. IX. And the king shall embrace his liar, .even the terrible Raymond, and shall commission him to go forth at once, and smite the armies of truth hip and thigh, so that no man shall dare to tell the truth any more, lest he be thrown into prison, or have his bones broken upon a wheel. X. Behold, these shall be Times that try men's souls!         I XI. And Abraham shall appoint him a marshal in Gotham, one Murray, the grammarian, not the son nor the pupil of Lindley; and he shall have a nose like a hound, that smelleth afar the disciples of truth and all such as worship in the temple of the white 'deities. ,But he shall be a man without malice, which only executeth the will of the king. XII. In those days a mighty general shall come up out of the Tombs in Gotham, even the great and the invincible Richard the last, called Bust Steed, who is so named because he bursteth away from the ladies' chambers, and rusheth like an unthinking steed into battle., XIII. Him Shall the king send forth to meet the armies of Day Vis, the Cyclops, who shall be so called because, as his name signifieth, he shall be op- posed to the light, and shall seek to delude the minds of his people with sin, even with the darkness and de- lusion of treason.  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8278-00000020"/> 38      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEIN, XIV. But, lo, when this great general, even B-ust Steed, shall come into the land of the heathen, the dismayed soldiers of Day Vis, the cyclops, shall run before him as hares flee before a tit-moiise, and shall not stop until they have run a hundred thousand miles beyond the gates of 'their own city, even Jic Moeond, which is so named in derision, because of the great poverty of the place. XV. Behold, when the other generals of the king shall see these things, they shall wax jealous of Richard ' the last, surnamed Bust Steed, and shall persuade the king to send him back to Gothamn. XVI. And Richard the last, when he arriveth in Gotham, shall subside; and he shall seek to hide him- self behind a Curtain, which cometh from the executive chamber of the land of Penn, but which he findeth at a tavern, where the Curtist is wont to be. And this shall be the last of Richard. XVII. But the feast which Richard the last glveth in honor' of the highly illuminated executive 6urtin, of the land Penn, shall be remembered many days, because of the great and mighty men that shall be there. XVIII. For unto the feast shall come John, called the General, whose name shall also be Cock-ran, be- cause he goeth into battle like a fighting cock, and runneth out again like a chicken, that hideth itself under its mother's wing when it heareth the cry of the hawk.- X IX. But by reason of these valoidous deeds, the *worshippers of the Dragon in the land of See More shall make him chief officer of the law, because they shall imagine in their hearts that he who faileth as a general in battle, will make the braver general in peace; and though he knoweth not the law, they shall   SON1 OF DOUGLAS.       9 take him on their shoulders, and carry him up into the: temple of justice, and set. him in the chief seat before the judges. XX. And, lo, there cometh among the guests, at the feast of Richard the last, that other John, whose sur- name is Dix, who shall become a great general in the armies of the king, not, withal, because he believeth in the worship of the Dragon, but because he hath an itch for office, and is wont to run his head into-every open place where he hopeth to find one. XXT. Now in those days shall appear Daniel, called the Sickle, because he killeth a man; and he shall be of such evil report among men, that he seeketh the battle field that he may die, and be at rest, where he hideth his sins in the grave. XXIT. But, lo, when he cometh to the battle field, he shall fight bravely, even standing his ground against the hosts of the heathen until he loseth a leg; and he shall not give up until he falleth from his horse by reason of the loss of much blood. XXIII. Now when this Daniel returneth to his own city of Gotham, he shall be of great repute among the worshippers of the black Idol, insomuch that notwith- standing aforetime he was hated by the Woolly-heads, they shall think to put him into the chief seat in Gotham.        '    '       I XXJIV. By reason of this, great contention shall spring up among the Woolly-heads, and such as worship the black Idol in Gotham; and they shall wrangle among themselves, some saying, What! will you put this man into the chief seat, who aforetime was offensive unto us, so that no man trusteth him? - Other some- shall say, Hath the cunning vices of the Sickle's head also been lopped off by the losing of a leg? XX V. But the king's Tribunes shall come into the  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8278-00000021"/> '40      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, assembly of the Woolly-heads, and shall command them to cease wrangling one with another, saying, What mattereth it who sitteth in -the chief seat in Gotham, if he be a man withal which is void of conscience, so that he shall not stand up for the law, but willingly doeth the will of the king? XXVI. And there shall be silence in the assembly of the Woolly-heads. XXVH; But, lo, Rufus, the king's merry-Andrews, even the surveyor, shall stand up, as he is wont to do, and blow his own horn, until the people shall run out of the assembly and scatter themselves to their own homes. CHAPTER IX. 8 Stephen rebuketh those who cry war in hie name. 4 Be denounc- 'eth the Forney-cater. 5 He evposeth 'Martin, the son of Ryer. 6 And Jacob, the Apostate, surnamed Van Etta. 7 He showeth how they deceive the people in his name' 9 He prophesieth, their festruction. 14 The people shall break the black Idol in pieces. I. AND I, Stephen, saw that there shall be great tribulation as long as the woolly-headed Dragon liveth. And many are they that shall fall away from the truth, and shall speak all manner of lies, and do many un- clean things in my name, even in the name of Stephen, the son of Douglas. II. Behold, such shall go out into the highways, blowing the trumpet of war in my name. And they shall say that We are the followers of Stephen, the s6n of Dougias, because we are for war; but, verily I say unto you, that all such shall know that they are de- ceivers, for there is no truth in them; and they blas- W    SON OF DOUGLAS.        41 pheme, and in my name seek the destruction of the land. "I. For did not I say unto the people in the temple of the nation, that " eWar is disunion-war is AJral, eternal separation?"  Did not I proclaim it aloud that, "Peace is the only policy that can save the coun try?"  Did not I teach that, "Only those are for was who want disunion?"   Who, then, are these false teachers that shall go about in my name fanning the red flame of war? Verily I say unto you, they are de- ceivers, and the sons of darkness, neither is there any truth in them. IV. And of these deceivers shall be one that sat -with me, and break bread at my own table. By reason of his love of filthy lucre he shall sell himself to the king, to be a chief wrshipper of the black Idol in the temple of the Dragon. And he shall become fond of strong drink, and shall be given to gluttinous living, and be known in the whole region round about as one that catereth to the appetites of his own belly, insomuch that he shall be called Forney-cater ; and shall also be called the dog, by reason of his much barking for the king. T. So also shall that Martin, the son of Ryer, who was aforetime a great judge in the kingdom of Jersey, go out 'falsely teaching war in my name. Hini shall Jaek the giant-killer slay, so that there shall be heard no more of him, neither of him nor his lies, forever. VI. And Jacob, the Apostate, also of the kingdom of Jersey, the descendant of the mighty King Gambrenus, the inventor of lager beer, who is surnamed Van Ettaj shall bring much scandal upon me by reason of his war howling in my name. Him shall William, called the Wright man, by reason of his truth, slay in the Assem bly chamber of the kingdom of Jersey; and Daniel, .  t  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8278-00000022"/> 42      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, the Senator, who. shall be called Wholes-man, be- cause he- is whole and hath an undivided heart. for peace, shall bury the apostate, face downward, With his nose resting upon the first edition of the Helper Book, because in his lifetime he was a disciple of Helper, and a secret follower of the Dragon. VII. Now, all that go out to deceive the people and teach war in my name shall come to an untimely end, and perish in the midst of their days; for did I not stand up in the temple-and declare, in the presence of the traitors who urged the king to go to war, that "There is no law that authorizes it. To do the act, or attempt it, would be e o of those high crimes and usur- pations that would justly schject the President of the United States to imlpdeachmeent z VIll. For I saj unto you, as was taught aforetime by the founders of the Republic, even by the mighty men who framed the Constitution and the Union, and hath been taught by the Democracy from the begin- ning, that, ' The coercive power of the Federal Gov- ernment, as applied to States, is the coercion of law and not of arms." Behold, these are the words of the wise father, speaking in the convention of the States, even the convention that made the Constitution. IX. Come, now, hearken unto me; for who is he that seeth not that, if the chief Governinent can, of its own motion, collect 'an army and send it forth against the governments of the States, then our fathers were void of wisdom, nay, they were very fools; for they thought to form a government of coequal and sovereign States, when, behold, they made a despotism, even a military despotism, which hath power at any time to deluge the land- with blood, and bring to. an end the glorious principle of self-government which our fathers died to establish in this land.   soN OF DOUGLAS.       43 X. Verily I say unto you, tha  the day cometh that shall bring these men into judgment ; for the peo- ple shall- follow after them in the streets, and shall de- mand of them, saying, Where is the Union that was builded by our fathers? XI, And the chief worshippers of the Dragon, even they that aforetime called the Constitution a " lie and a cheat," shall answer them, saying, "The covenant with death" is broken, so that ye can no more have the Union unto yourselves, neither you nor your chil- dren, forever. XII. Behold, when the people shall understand these things, they shall gather themselves together in the market-places, and at the corners of the streets, and, with a loud voice, shall demand of the followers-of the king, Give us back the Union that our fathers gave us! XT1T. And  the chief rulers shall sneer in their , thoughts, and secretly rejoice in their hearts; for they shall think that, by reason of the war, they have sun- dered the Union, and put an end to the Constitution forever and ever. X1V. But the people shall grow more and   more violent, day by day, insomuch that there shall be great commotion throughout the land, such as never was before in these borders; and they shall rush into the temple of the Dragon and break the black Idol in pieces; and the worshippers of the Idol shall flee be- fore the mighty anger -of the people, so that they shall be in fear for their lives, and shall run to and fro, like foxes before the hunter.    -   &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8278-00000023"/> CHA PTER X. Copperhead, Black-snake, and Pattlesnake Indians, I. AND it shall come to pass in those days that the spirit of war shall spread abroad throughout the land, so that every part of it shall be at enmity one with another.      ' II. Yea, even the Indian tribes that aforetime were at peace with one another, and with all the world, shall be at strife by reason of the wickedness and violence of  the worshippers of the Dragon. "I. Lo, the Copperhead Indians are brave and gen- erous beyond all other tribes in the land, and seek peace above all things, both with such as dwell in their own land, and such as come from afar. IV.-But the Black-snake Indians are of a differ- ent tribe; full of all subtlety, yea, of maliciousness, bigotry, revenge, and all uncleanness, insomuch that- they can be at peace with no nation, no, not even with themselves. V. And they shall assemble in their secret places, even in their caves, that shall be called Wide-Awakes, because in them the evil eye never sleepeth; and they shall plot among themselves how they shall get hold of the government, so that they may oppress the CGop- perheads, 'and destroy the altars that they love, even the altars of the white deities that were builded afore- time by their fathers. VI Lo, they shall speak in the secret places to one another, saying, the Copperheads are a proud and stiff- necked people, which will never come down to worship the black Idol of our tribe, by reason of the pride of their own birth, and the caste of race, which growetl:   SON OF DOUGLAS.       i) among them day by day, insomuch that they despise even to enter the temple of the comely black Idol. VII. Now, therefore, let us make war upon the Rattlesnake tribe that inhabit the region that lieth to the south, which is full of riches, and easily tempteth the eye of the stranger, and such as are fond of gain, even of the plunder that cometh of war. VIII. And, behold, we will cunningly say to the young men of the Copperheads, who are brave, and full of a martial spirit withal, We pray ye to go down with us and help us against the Rattlesnakes, which threaten to descend with fire and sword upon all the tribes of the North, even upon the Black-snakes and upon the Copperheads, which seek to be at peace with all the world. IX. And, lo, when the young men of the Copper- heads shall go down against the Rattlesnakes, we will stay behind, even at home, and make ourselves agree- able, if happily we may, to their wives and fair daughters, even to them whose husbands and brothers' we have sent off to fight our battles against the tribes of the South. X. Moreover, when all the young men of the Cop- ) perheads are away in battle, then will we fall upon their fathers and brothers that shall remain behind, and scourge them, so that they shall not have any peace who refuse to go with us into the temple of the Dragon and worship the black Idol. XI. And they shall sigh for the Union that their a fathers made with all the tribes in this land; but we will mock at their desires, yea, we' will laugh at their expectations ; and when they shall say, let us have the Constitution as it hath been from the beginning, we will smite them, they and the altars of their white deities, so that none shall dare to oppose the new gov-  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8278-00000024"/> S46      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN, emment that the Black-snakes shall establish in the land.  CTTI APTER X.. Great battle between the Snake tribes. I. BEHOLD, I, Stephen, son of Douglas, saw in my vision the imaginations of the thoughts of the Black- snakes, that they were evil continually, and that they will do even as they plotted in the war-councils, in the secret caves of the tribe.  II. And it shall come to pass that the Copperhead tribe shall fall into the trap that shall be set for them by the Black-snake Indians; and their young men shall go out to battle against the .Rattlesnakes, even as it was plotted, so that the Black-snakes shall be left masters of the situation at home, even of the ballot- boxes, and of the altars of the white deities. -III. But the cunning chiefs of the Copperheads shall they bribe with emeralds, and with high posts of honor, both in the temple of fthe Dragon and the army that moveth against the tribes of the South. IV. So that these, even the Copperhead chiefs, which shall sell themselves for emeralds or office, shall be the most'daring and devilish of all the conspirators in the temple of the Dragon; yea, they shall be put foremost by the chiefs of the .Black-snakes, to smite the altars of the white deities wherever they shall find them, and to bring to an end both the Constitution and laws that have been in this land from the beginning. V. But it shall come to pass that the widows and orphans of the Cop perheads that shall be slain in the battles of the Black-snakes, shall be an exceeding great   SON OF DOUGLAS.        47 throng, so that they shall block up the streets, and hinder men and women from passing to and fro freely to the churches and market-places. VI. And these, even the widows and orphans, shall cry aloud in the streets, and shall demand of the rulers of the Black-snakes, and of the apostate chiefs of the Copperheads, Where are our husbands? where are our fathers?  VII. But the -rulers of the Black-snakes and the apostate chiefs of the Copper]heads shall answer them nothing. V Ill. And the flood of death, even the tide of blood, shall roll on until it hath covered the whole land, so that the angel of destruction shall sit at every man's door, and the bloody banner of the Black-snakes shall wave over the fallen altars of the white deities in the temple of liberty. IX. And it shall come to pass that ywhen the old men, and the virtuous youths., of the Copperleads shall see these things, they shall begin to murmur among themselves, saying, To what end is this sea of blood? and who hath bewitched our people that they join the Black-snakes against their own race? X. Then the riflers of the Black-snakes shall seize upon all such, and thrust them into prison to be de- voured of the woolly-headed Dragon. XI. Verily, I say unto you, that all this shall only make matters, the worse for the Black-snakes and .their Idol; for the Copperheads, though they be a peaceful tribe, shall be wrought .in the extreme by reason of these oppressions, and they shall begin to say one to another, Now, why have we permitted these things? XII. For is not this the land of our fathers? and this temple of liberty, was it not builded' by their hands? and these altars of the white deities, were they not established for us, and for our. childern forever? S  r . } * v  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8278-00000025"/> 48      PROPHECIES OF STEPHEN.      - XTIT. Now, therefore, why do we permit all these things to be destroyed under the cheat of making war upon. the Rattlesnakes of Sunland . XIV. For doth it come to pass that we cannot fight the R]attlesnakes afar in Sunland, without beating our own altars to pieces at home? Must we give up our own liberty and become the slaves of the Black-snakes, for the sake of depriving the Rattlesnake tribe of their freedom .' X V'. And, behold, when the Black-snakes shall hear and understand these murmurings among the Copper- heads, they shall wriggle, and squirm, and hiss, and begin to put themselves in the attitude to spring upon the Copperheads, and shall threaten to strangle them. XV1. Now the Copperheads are armed with a deadly weapon, so that when their enemies, even the Black- snakes, shall fall upon them, they will meet with swift destruction. XVII. And the battle when it cometh shall be short, and the end of the Black-snakes shall be as sud- den as the lightning falleth out of the clouds. XVIll-. For the whole tribe of the Copperh/eads are warriors; and when- their enemies shall fall upon them, who have, withal, few brave warriors of their tribe, they shall drive them like chaff before a mighty rushing wind, yea, and they shall be scattered as chaff to the four winds of heaven. XI X. And I, Stephen, Son of Douglas, see that the end of these things shall be that the Black-snakes shall be driven into their holes, and their Idol in the temple of the Dragon shall be- broken in pieces, so that the white deities, whose altars are in the temple of liberty, shall abide in this land forever and ever. END OF BOOK FIRST.      &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>