<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8060">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thrilling Narrative of the Lives of Sarah Sharp and Charles Edwards, the Victims of Crime </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC8060</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2499</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Thrilling narrative of the lives of Sarah Sharp and Charles Edwards, the victims of crime</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 p. l. 19-48 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>H.M. Rulison</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cincinnati </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1853">1853</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-06-23">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Thrilling narrative of the lives of Sarah Sharp and Charles Edwards, the victims of crime</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8060-00000001"/>THRILLING NARRATIVE OF THE LIVES OF    CHARLES EDWARDS, THE VICTIMS OE CRIME. PORTRAIT OF MISS SARAH SHARP'.  ALSO, THE LIFE, TRIAL AND EXECUTION OF FOR THE MURDER OF DAVID ROMER. CINCINNATI: PUBLISHED   BY  H. M. RULISON, NO. 34 EAST-THRD STREET. 1853.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC8060-00000002"/> 60865          ^ ^ PREFACAE' THE Publisher, in presenting to the eye of the public the follow. ing brief history of one of the most dreadful, heart-rending and inhuman tragedies that has ever been recorded in the annals of crime, together with a brief sketch of the life and private history of the parties, begs leave: t. state, that the information contained in the following pages may uinfhesitatingly be relied on. The early life of Edywards was obtained from a gentleman resi- ding in the town of Weibster, who had long been acquainted with him, and who had received it mostly from fhis own lips. The inci- dents contained in the narrative of the latter portion of his life have been kindly contributed by persons having a thorough knowledge of the facts, and of the greatest respectability, residing in the towns of Webster and Penfielt. The relatives of Sarah Sharp and Mrs. Edwards are persons of the highest respectability, and persons whose characters are above reproach-many of whom are also very wealthy, and so great was the fear of larcerating afresh their wounded hearts, that after the publisher had been to considerable expense and great trouble to obtain information, the publication of this book would have been abandoned, had he not entertained an earnestdesire to protect the living from calumny, as well as to shield the dead from mis- representation and falsehood, and that in no way: could this be bet. ter accomplished than by a correct, true and unvarnished publica- tion of all the -matters of interest connected with the horrible denouement of this fearful and appalling tragedy '   .          .*   ,* ,          THE HSTORY OF "f% CHARLES EDWARDS &amp; SARA SHARP. EPOCH I. EARLY LIFE OF CHARLES EDWARDS. CHARLES EDWARDS, one of these unfortunate victims of illicit love and jealousy, was born in Newhuryport, N. H., in March, I812.- His father, an industrious and respectable distiller of that place, had, in early life, married the daughter of a Boston merchant, by whom he had six children. Having amassed a considerable pro-  perty by honest industry and frugality he was, about retiring from business to spend the remainder of his days in ease and comfort with his family--but alas, how unaccountable ate- the ways of Providence ;---while this man, in the full enjoyment of health, and surrounded by the comforts and pleasures of this life, and with brightening prospects in the future, was attending to the construet tion or alteration of some of the machinery connected with his business, he, by one careless step, was precipitated into a vat of boiling'liquor, -and who, gentle and kind reader, is able to depict the horrible anguish attendant upon his death. The situation of Mrs. Edwards, thus suddenly deprived of the partner of her bosom, and his supporting and directing hand, was truly most distressing. She had been brought up in luxury and ease-had been reared as a  tender plant, being the youngest of five ehildren--she had been surrounded by all the delicacies that wealth could procure, her mind was one too, of no ordinary cast. Her education had been the best that could be obtained, and yet, gentle reader, left thus alone as it were with a large family to guide, sup port and direct, she was not equal to the task. Her eldest son was a fine, stout, athletic boy of fifteen years of age, and yet, not com- petent to take charge of his father's business even if his mother had desired him to do so. But she did not. That building, with its  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8060-00000003"/> 20    CHARLES EDWAIRDS AND SARAH SHARP. fiery apparatus, and hellish machinery for concocting spirits, had already swallowed up one victim, and no persuasion could induce her continue the business. . .  The business matters belonging to her late husband were placed ia thehands of Unworthy and ,dishonest agents for settlement, and in a short time that which would "hav e been a competency, indeed a fortune for herself and children, dwindled into nothing, and penury and want stared her in the face. Oh, the merciless villains that could thus swindle and -pocket the subsistence of unprotected widowhood. Thus reduced in circumstances, it was found necessary that something should be done for the children. Charles, then in his sixth year, was sent to reside withhis grandfather, in Boston.- Thebeldest son was sent to a forwarding house in Providence, R. I., where, a situation had been obtained for him. With her family -thus reduced in numbers, the widow, by industry and economy, was able to supply herself and them with the necessaries of life. Charles, being thus removed from a small, quiet village to the bustle and confusion of one of our largest cities, soon evinced a remarkable fondness for shows and play, and a supreme disrelish for his books, and even at this early age exhibited a strong love for -adventure and novelty-and it is not to be wondered at that love for play, adventures and novelty should have increased in an unac- countable degree in this boy, when it is taken into consideration that his grandfather was an old and infirm man, and unable to con- trol him. Thus situated the old man resolvedin his mind many and various means of furnishing some employment to keep Charles from mischief, and finally yielded to the earnest solicitation of a friend who was a member of a society of Shakers, near Boston, and placed Charles with them-but not until he had obtained a promise from his friend that he would watch over Charles with all the care and solicitude of a parent. Charles was subsequently adopted by the Shakers, and received as one of their number, and in this situation the character of the boy had ample space for development. He soon acquired a love for employment, and as he was not naturally of an idle nature, soon he was found first and foremost in any nece- sary undertaking, whether attended with danger and hardship, or pleasure and comfort. He made but little advancement in literary pursuits, although he had the advantages of good teachers. His   UvsIA Ji uW aJWASJl AND SARAH SHARP.;     1 mind was one of a peculiar make;--active employment of body was more congenial to him-so that with the exception of learn- ing to read tolerably, his education was by himself, almost wholly neglected -so much so indeed, that up to the hour of his death it was with difficulty that he could write even to keep ordinary accounts. His activity and usefulness gained him the good will of the entire society,--which, in the end, was probably injurious to him. As a natural consequence of his cleverness, and being withal a remarkable good looking boy, he was praised, caressed, flattered, and allowed to go wherever his fancy led him, and, although he was not considered a bad, vicious or troublesome boy, he at least must have, as a natural consequence, grown up without a just sense of the necessity of a controlling influence over his passions. Thus quietly, without any particular event worthy of note, passed ten years of his life. We now find him a man: he has passed the bounds of boyish life and fancy, and is seventeen years old; yet there is no marked change in his character, except a more than natural increase in desire for adventure, and a reckless and fearful impulsiveness to action. He was at this time a well formed and extremely handsome man- not effeminate, but with a bold, devil may care, daring and courage- ous appearance. He was about five feet eight inches in height, with dark brown-or auburn hair, bright blue eye, and full face, with a clear and rosy complexion. And even up to the time of his fear- ful and horrible self-destruction, he was considered by all who knew him to be a fine and noble looking man. He was not unconscious  of his personal attractions. This, together with a desire for adven- ture and novelty, determined him to cut asunder the tie that bound him to the Shakers. Acting upon impulse as usual, we find him on the road tot Providence, on a visit to his brother. He arrived at Providence late at night, destitute entirely of money, and with scarcely decent clothes. After wanderingabout the city nearly the entire night he succeeded in finding the object of his search. His brother, who had risen by degrees until he had become head clerk of the forwarding establishment in which he had been placed by his mother. His brother clothed him, gave him money and offered him a situation as under-clerk in the same establishment with him. self, This was unhesitatingly declined.  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8060-00000004"/> 5t22 .  qWOHARTFSB DWARDS, AND SARA r-. IAP, EPOCH   II. THE ADVENTURES OF CHARLES EDWARDS. CHARLES had already determined to see more of the world than the situation offered would allow of;, so after remaining with his brother a short time, he entered upon the paths which he hoped would make his- fortunes. Poor young man, what a world of evil might have been saved you, if, at the earnest solicitations of your kind brother, you had accepted the situation offered by him. Oh young men - you who: may read this book, reflect when you arrive at the age to make choice of profession for life and rush not head- long upon a reckless, wild and unknown path. You know not how slight a circumstance m y change the direction of the car of your destiny, and precipitate you, over a precipice into eternal, everlast- ing woe and perdition. Had Charles accepted the situation offered by. his brother, he might now, like him, be one of the wealthiest, most influential and respectable members of the Hudson Bay Fur Company; And thus his situation in life might have been very dif- ferent, and the fearful tragedy that closed his earthly career: preven- ted, and the young, interesting and lovely victimr of his passion saved from an untimely end, and her short life lengthened into years of usefulness ;and death, when I it did come, might not have come in so horrible a shape; and, instead of leaving behind a name covered with infamy and disgrace, might have left a name to be recalled and remembered with affection and pleasure. Edwards, after leaving his brother, traveled -westward on foot to the Banks of the Connecticut, and arriving at a quiet village about twenty miles above Hartford, he engaged himself to attend a saw- mill at so much per month. But his reckless, wandering spirit would not allow him to remain long quiet, and his desire for roving returned with greater force than ever before. He had filled his situation a month. And we find him again on the road -nor does hie remain long in any particular. place until he arrives at Roches- ter, six months from the time he left the situation above Hartford, In the city of Rochester he remained three or four months; in what   CHARLES EDWAERDS AND SARpAH SHTARP.     23 business engaged is not now known. His name can still be seen in the register of the then principal hotel of the city. Leaving the city of Rochester, he passed on towards the west, and after traversing Pennsylvania, Ohio, Michigan and other states we next find him at New Orleans. There he met with a misfor- tune which compelled him to stay at that city for a considerable time. He went, for some reason, into one of the many swamps in the vicinity of the city of New Orleans, and by handling a noxious weed was very badly poisoned, and obliged to go to the Hospital. Charles seems to have had the greatest abhorrence for human blood, although not destitute of couirage; and from the disposition then displayed, no one could have'believed that he was one that would ever engage in a scene of bloodshed and murder. In fact, the energy displayed in that last sad closing scene of his chequered life, seems unlike the bold resolution of the soldier, but to be the frantic outpouring of his despairing soul, torn by the varied pangs of love, jealousy and rage. When at the Hospital, at New Orleans, after he had so far recov- ered as to wander into the various apartments and passages of that vast and gloomy edifice, he accidentally happened to enter one of the dissecting rooms, in which several students were engaged in separating into its various parts a human body. So great was his horror and consternation at the bloody and disgugting exhibition which unfolded itself to his eyes that he left the Hospital and the city, and, in fact did not stop his headlong flight until the broad expanse lying between the state of Ohio and New Orleans' lay behind him. In Ohio he entered -once more a society of Shakers, with whom he remained until thoroughly cured. Thus was he for two years a wanderer in various parts of the west and southwest. He then returned to the state of New York, establishing his residence in Rochester, where he became acquain- ted with William Cheney, then a resident of the town of Greece. Cheney induced him to give up his wandering habits, and to become more steady. Seeing his gradual improvement, and sanguine of producing a greater effect, he gave him employment upon his farm, where he became acquainted with Polly Sharp, the daughter of Peter Sharp, Esq., of 'Webster, and became deeply attached to her.  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8060-00000005"/> 34    OHARTIL5 EDWARDS AND SARAH SHARP. EPOCH   III. HS MARRIAGE AND SETTLEMENT. Edwards lived with Mr. Cheney until sometime during the year 1832, and having satisfied himself that his affection was returned, he solicited in a formal manner the hand of Miss Sharp, and was accepted. The nuptials were soon after solemnized at the resi- dence of the bride's parents. Mrs. Edwards had two brothers and two sisters, Mrs. Campbell and Sarah, the unfortunate object of his future guilty passion, and who was destined for a sacrifice upon the altar of unholy love. Sarah at that time was a sprightly school girl of about eleven years of age, and already gave promise of that re- markable beauty and voluptuousness of form by which, alas for poor Edwards' peace of mind, she was afterwards so celebrated He saw her then, a beautiful child, and, happy in the affections of the wife he had just taken to his bosom, he loved her as the sister-- the lovely sister of his bride, without the thought of that threatening cloud which was soon to arise and obscure his bright prospects forever.      - The early part of Edwards' married life gave promise of long years of happiness. He settled in the town where his wife and her friends and relatives had so long resided, and engaged for about six years steadily in agricultural occupations, and, although he had no farm of his own, he managed, by a course of industry and economy, to support his family in comfort, and even to indulge them in many of the luxuries of life. The reputation thus acquired for industry and economy he maintained up to the hour of his awful death. The habits of strict honesty in mercantile dealings he had acquired from the Shakers, became a part of his being. With him honesty was made a matter of honor. He used to be proud of the confi- dence he had, von from his neighbors, and even to this day many of them will tel; you that no man was more worthy of confidence than Charles Edwards. If he wanted wheat, corn or flour he was allowed to take whatever quantity he chose and his word was ever relied upon as to the amount. If he had taken as much pains to school his heart and direct his affections as he did to be considered 9   CHABLES EDWARDS AmD SARAH SHARP.      25 a man of his word and an honest man, the sun of his earthly ex- istence would have set under very different circumstances. His case adds another to the many melancholy instances of men attempting to regulate their own career without any reference to the duty they owe to the Supreme Ruler of the Universe. His wife could not be said to be a woman of many personal attractions, yet it is generally conceded did every thing that woman could do to render his home happy and to become the polar star of his exist- ence., His family began increasing; his eldest daughter, now a young lady of great personal attractions, was born about three years after their marriage, and was a fine child, of a sweet disposition and was always his favorite ;' besides, his wife had presented him with one or two others. Things continued in this manner until the fall or winter of 1838. EPOCH   IV. COMMENCEMENT OF THE INTIMACY BETWEN CHARLES EDWARDS AND SARAH SHARP. About this time, as Mrs. Edwards was soon to be confined, Sarah, at her request, came to reside in the family, and assisted in taking care of her sister and the children. Sarah at that time had just reached the age of eighteen years, the age when the blushipg, reserved and beautiful girl becomes the loving and confiding woman. She, since the marriage of her sister, Mrs. Edwards, had re- mained at home with her parents, now somewhat advanced in years, and being the youngest daughter, had enjoyed advantages of education possessed by few young ladies in the country. Besides, as is generally the case with the youngest child, she was almost idolized by her parents who gratified every wish of her heart. She was also exceedingly handsome. A gentleman who recollects her well at this time, describes her as lovely in the extreme. She was slightly above the middle height with a finely chiseled neck and beautifully developed and well turned bust, delicate hands and feet, jet black hair, clear brunette complexion and a dark hazle eye of peculiar lustre. It'was the fire of her eye. filled with love and animation, that made her so extremely interesting in conversation. She had been the centre of attraction in the litle world in which  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8060-00000006"/> 6 i  .OCIqARTFS. EDWARDS AND SASAH SHARP. she moved. She had- been praised for her beauty and sprightly powers of conversation, and flattered by all the gentlemen of her acquaintance. All this she might have resisted and come forth like gold from the refiner's furnace, brighter for the trial, had her heart, in the days of her childhood and youth, been properly dis- ciplined and educated. Had she been early taught to look beyond this world for guidance, and to pray to .God for direction, rather than to rely upon her own strength of character for safety, the flatterer's poisonous words would, have passed her as the idle wind; and can it be surprising that she became vain, self-willed and proud? Instead of taking the bible for her guide she had formed liews of her own in regard to matters of religion, and it may be supposed, from some remarks that she was heard to make at a later period in her life, that even before this time, she had come to the falacious conclusion, that the highest law of being was self gratification. And here let me say that her life of shame and awful death of in- famy afford to the parents of our land a terrible warning of the danger of being so much engrossed in the mental education of their children as to neglect the far more important duty of their moral cultivation. At the time she entered the Edwards family, her sister was too much out of health to spend more than a small portion of her time with the family, being obliged to keep her room.- Sarah was thus thrown almost constantly into the society of he brother- in-law. He assisted her about many of the duties of the house, and sought to render her situation in the family agreeable and happy. Not an evening passed without their being in each others society; sometimes on a visit to a neighbor's house, at:others chat- ting by the pleasant fire-side, during the long winter evenings. She found pleasure in his society, for he was gentlemanly in his deport- ment and agreeable in manners and conversation. She admired him for the good temper and kind disposition always displayed towards his wife, and for the uniform respect and affection with which he spoke of his family. She was capable at this time of the exercise of right reason; for the tempter had not yet poisoned her whole mind. On his part the relation that existed between them was pleasing Probably at this time Edwards had not for a single moment indulged a thought that was in the least calculated to cast reproach upon the fair fame of the yoang lady, or that was in any degree inconsistent   CHABRL-a S ,aWARD A,  ARA; SHAs P,    it with his duty to his wife. Having for some time been deprived #f her society by sickness, he found his hours gliding-away pleasantly ' in the company of the sister. Her presence afforded him a pleasant: and agreeable companion, and undoubtedly with such views only, he regarded her; but it cannot be denied that like most young mar.: ried men, when deprived of the society of their wives, he allowed himself too easily to become- attached to other ladies, We would gladly allow the veil of oblivion to intervene, and cons. ceal this guilty pair from the world. We would gladly leave them before the tempter found them, and won them from the fields of in- nocence and peace. But the duty of a true historian, compels us to cast aside the curtain of silence which kindness and respect for the anguish of others would have allowed to remain, and show you plainly the distruction of two of your fellow beings. This fondness for each others society gradually ripened into a deeper feeling, and the closest intimacy sprung up between them, They became so attentive to each other, that Mrs. E. (and she was not a woman of a jealous disposition) became alarmed; and some of her friends remonstrated. But this only seemed to increase their flame. As a fire at first easily managed, when but partially check. ed, and allowed still to pursue its' work of destruction, became a mighty conflagration. So what with them had been only a deep, feeling, under the blast of opposition, became a black passion, ready. for its own gratification to dare high heaven, and risk the flames of bhell. Finding themselves closely observed, they met in secret. - {Many were their stolen interviews, and many the- moonlight walks- they enjoyed together. They were as devotedly attached to each- other, as love could- bind them. And could they have been legally united, their many crimes would have been prevented. But that I  could not be; and as Edwards could not bring himself to think of deserting his family even for her sake, they were in a most deplora- 5  ble condition. Overcome by the devouring fervor of passion, in one rash, unguarded moment she yielded to his solicitations, and' , lost. that gem that ornaments the female character more than earth- ly power or queenly robes. Thus she fell, and thus the way was paved for all her future follies and her death of shame. As care- fully as their places of clandestine meeting were selected, and'as secietly as they contrived to gratify their guilty passions. they could not long conceal from the eyes of neglected and slighted love, their At. -   &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8060-00000007"/> 28     O TjAJCARIJT EDWARDS AND SABAU  WARP, amours. And one morning detecting them in acts of the grosses impropriety, the injured wife took her youngest child, then little more than a week old, and told her inhuman husband and unnatural sister that she would remain in the house no longer, She had de- termined to carry her child in her weak state of health across the fields to her brothers, a distance of two miles. Edwards struck with the forlorn appearance of his wife and child, melted by her sobs and tears, and overcome by a sense of his own guilt and out- rageous conduct, suddenly relented, and promised his wife on his knees, that he never again would give her occasion to doubt- his honor. Upon. his knees he asked her forgiveness and received -it freely, for, Mrs. Edwards still loved her husband with all the ferver of' her early devotion; notwithstanding he had proved so unworthy of a pure minded woman's love, Edwards was truly penetent, and desired Sarah also to ask his wife's forgiveness, but she after the first false step in sin, seemed v, lholly infatuated, and incapable of repen- tance. In reply to this request she said " she had not done anything she -was ashamed of in the sight of God or man, and should ask no one's forgiveness." In consequence of this discovery, Sarah left the family and went home to her fathers. - Notwithstanding his re. gard for Sarah continued the same, his respect for his wife was so great, that he did not see her again during the winter. And she seems even to the time of her cruel murder, to have entertained for him the same entrancing passion. In the spring following, Edwards again went west to see if he could not better his fortunes, and no doubt with the intention of moving his, family, and thus placing himself. beyond the reach of temptation. He returned in the following autumn unsuccessful. He could not escape his fate. The spell was again upon him. The precise nature of the intimacy that existed between them up to the time of his removal to the town of Irondequoit in 1841, is not dis- tinctly known; but it is probable that very little regard was paid to the rights of Mrs. Edwards, by either of them. He resided in the town of Irondequoit four years, and then returned to Webster. Nothing of importance seems to have occurred during this intdrval. Although he saw Sarah several times, it is not thought any farther improper -intimany occurred between them. He provided with his usual care for all the .necessities of his family, and discharged the duties of a kind husband and loving father. Upon, his return to   OHAARWi  EDWARDS AND SARAH SHARP,     29- Webster he seems again to have returned, to the embraces of his paramour, and to have continued his life of shame up to the 27th of May, 1847, when the community were astounded with -the intelli- gence, that Sarah Sharp had given birth to a female child. 'The public at once turned towards Edwards, and he was regard, ed as its father. The town authorities attempted to compel her to disclose the name of the one who had wronged her. But that woman of iron firmness land pride refused. She had endeavored to conceal her shame from every eye, and was even about the neigh- borhood the very day before the little stranger was thus cast among the peltings of this pitiless world, its hopes shipwrecked even in the hour of its birth; and now that exposure became inevitable, she de- termined to bear the weight of public censure alone. Although it was not known to a certainty to whom this child of shame owed its existence, it was the cause of some difficulties in Edward's fam- ily. He was charged by friends of the family with the young woman's ruin, but he steadily denied the charge. In later times the child's features and appearance have put the question of its pa- rentage beyond a doubt.' The little girl's name is Viola DeLove, and she now lives with her grandfather. Edwards and Sarah con- tinued to live near each other, both suspected but nothing known absolutely concerning their continued guilt, she at her fathers and he appeared to remain in all respects the same kind father and hus- band that he had always been. During all these exciti'g times he was never heard to speak disrespectfully of his wife or family, but on the contrary with terms of affection. About six weeks before the tragic termination of their, lives, Sarah went to visit and take care of her sister, Mrs. Campbell, who lived about three miles from her father's house. Edwards remained at home, and nothing un- usual happened until about a week before the murder. He had not even seen or heard from Sarah from -the time she went to William Campbell's until about the last five days of his life. EPOCH V. "AST WEEK OF THE LIFE OF EDWARDS. , During the last week of the life of Charles Edwards, he was a gisting one of his neighbors. They were chopping, and throughout  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8060-00000008"/> O ARIT   S E bDWARDS AMN SAITAR STHARP, the entire week, he seemed as cheerful and happy as usual On Tuesday, his wife visited her sister, Mrs. Campbell, And Sarah, at the house of the former. She remained with them two days, and returned ot Thursday, the 23d day of January. During her visit, she had observed a young man of the neighborhood, named Daniel Thompson, frequently at the house, and several times had found him in conversation with Sarah. Wheln she returned home, she either had some reason td think that Satah was about to be mar- ried, or which is more probable, thinking that such information might have a tendency to break off the intimacy between her husband and Sarah, she tld 'Edwards that Daniel Thompson was paying particular attention to Sarah, and that they were goiing to be mar. ried. This was undoubtedly a mistake, for it is not generally sup- "psed that Thompson had the slightest idea of marrying her, nor is there any evidence that he had paid her either particular or im- 'proper attention. The presumption is, that Mrs. Edwards told her hiteband this with the intention of reforming him. ' Daniel Thomp- son is a young farmer, and a man' of uncommon respectability, living in Penfield. Edwards did not-:ait to enquire into the truth of the story, still loving Sarah Sharp With all the fervor of former years, his soul was racked with jealousy and despair. On Friday, he went to his work as usual, and did not disclose to any one the state of his mind, which subsequent events have so fearfully reveal- e. In the course of the day, he spoke of getting his boot mended, and remarked that his feet were wet. His neighbor told him he had better get another pair, and go over to a neighboring shoemaker and have his mended. He accordingly called at Mr. Aliens' and borrowed a pair of boots, and left his own to be mended. Saturday morning, he called for his own boots, and returned the borrowed pair. During the whole day. he worked at the chopping, and seem. ed as cheerful as ever, although he appeared at times very thought- ful. He came up to the house and partook of a harty supper; put his axe in the wood pile; and after promising to come up the next day and grif so as to be ready for Monday's work, and bidding his friends and family good evening, lit his pipe and started in the direc- tion of his home. But he did not go home. After proceeding as he thought, too far to be ol served, he got over the fence, and went di. v*otly 'across the fields and through the wood, in the direction of Wm. Campbell's house. He did not go to Campbells that evening,   C AW^ID. W WAFW#1) AND SW4   NoAr, oK but probably for the purpose of satisfying himself in regard to the report, remained outside; and from certain-appearances in the snow about the house, it is quite certain that some one was about there that evening. That night, as if by a' singular fatality, Thompson was at the house, and. left about 9 o'clock. It is evident from the letter found on the body of EdwardS, that he must have fancied something like marks of esteem and affection between them that evening. But he allowed Thompson to go home unmolested. It was not hislife he sought; but the life of the woman, who had been the former partner of his guilty love, and whom he believed had proved untrue to the bonds of darkness that existed between them; Edwards returned home at a lete hour, and slept till morning as quietly and gently as a peaceful child. It is truly a strange and wonderful power of self-control that some men can exert over them- selves, who can thus compose themselves to gentle slumber upon the, very eve of premeditated murder and self-destruction-and Charles Edwards was one of those men. We say, he composed himself to a gentle slumber; no doubt dark visions came up thick and fast before his bewildered brain; no doubt the form of that ruined woman, whose "unpflpared soul" he was about to usher in- to the presence of an injured and offended Deity, to stand at his bar to answer " for the foul deeds done in the body," came before him ;-:no doubt he once again saw her, as when first he knew her, pure as the driven snow, and no doubt former innocence rose up before him, as a horrid mockery of the course of sin that had thus reduced her to infamy and disgrace. No doubt; he saw in dreams his wretched wife and'children with tearful eyes, disheveled hair and downcast, reproachful look, as if to warn him from his course of evil, and upbraid him with the terrible act he was about performing. If so, he had sufficient command of himself to pre- vent any physical emotion, even while sleeping, He rose on the morning of the day that was to close his earthly existence ;,he seemed very thoughtful; but with no signs of emotion or of hesita. tion. In fact, he seems to have resolved upon and planned the deed under the influence of his old habit of-impulsiveness. The plan once conceived, he pursued it to its consummation with fright- ful certainty. After taking breakfast with his friends, in reply to his wife, he  said he had been to the shoemakers to get his boots mended, and   &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8060-00000009"/> 32     CHARLES EDWARDS-, SBA)   ARA  &amp;TIARP. that that was what had kept him from home to so lateni hour s He , then showed his wife the soles that had been put on thinem. It will be recollected by our readers that Edwards-got the boots mended on the Friday previous, unbeknown vto his wife.' This story allyed all suspicion -on her part. He was about the. house :all the' fore part of the day, and seemed-buried in thought. A little after noon, he asked his wife for-his pencil,: and when she asked what lhe was going to do with it, replied in the following omnous language - ' My dear, you will know sometime'" He went up stairsi and it is supposed that at this time he wrote the following lines, which were fot id upon his body after his death:-:-  My God Sarah could I ever believed unless I had seen with'my own eyes Never did I think of seeing you letting such a man that is so diminutive take my privilege that you have promised me so much My God Sarah I had rather he dead twice- Hoe will drive me mad you dont knowmy feelings I see every motion I see when you parted I see that kiss You made my feelings rack my bosom Andfor this I die." These lines were evidently intended for Sarah, and owing to his agony of mind, and want of skill in penmanship, his ideas were not clearly expressed.  The intelligent reader will see, that they were undoubtedly'writ. ten, to give her an idea of his 'agobof mind, in a moment when he was intending to spare her life,          - only sacrifice himself-but his original intention seems to have- been to destroy her as well as himself-and when he saw her so near the object of his jealousy she acted upon his original plan. After writing these lines he laid 'doWn on the bed in one of the chambers for a short time, but not to sleep.-,ah; no! His eyes were destined never again to close until celosed ii death. He couldnot remain long in one place; the awful deed he was revolving in ,his mind, would give him no rest. He arose and paced his chamber in terrible agony of mind. So great was his mental' anguish,' that great drops of;sweat stood upon his forehead, and blood seemed bursting from his veins. His family were alarmed about him, and to pacify them he said he was unwell. He went into the yard attached' to the' house, and there walked 'about in the same manner. .-He then went into; the house, and after lighting his pipe, informed the family, that he was going -to one of the neighbors. He took up the youngest child, and said " what will become of poor little Messey," (the childs' name was Messey,) and A seeing that such: an expression wis calculated to create alarm, he qUickly added," poor boy, he has no shoes." After leaving home   CHARLES EDWARDS AND SARAIr SHARP.      33 at about 3 o'clock, he went to the house of Mr. Fosdic, and staid a considerable time, conversing cheerfully with the family. In a short time he said he was going to Stephen Meeker's--Meeker's house is about one half mile from Fosdic's. After a short absence, he returned to Fosdic's. At Meeker's he was as sociable as usual, and told Mrs. Meeker, that his wife was out of health, and that he wished she would come and see her. He finally left Fosdic's at about half past four o'clock, saying, "he was going down in the woods where he:haa'formerly been chopping, to get the beetle and wedges. The house of Canipbell is in a south westerly direction from Fosdic's. This was the last seen of him until found dead under such appalling circumstances. EPOCH VI. CLOSING SCENE OF THE DRAMA. Campbell's house, to which our scene now changes, was situated on the north side of an eas and west road, in the town of Penfield, about five miles from Pereld village, and a little more than three miles from Edward's housh a south-west direction. It is a house built of rough logs, with awindow and door in front, and a door and window in the rear. The back door opened out of the north side of the house, into a small dilapidated stoop at the left of the door on that side; and towards the north west corner of the house was a small pantry. It is sabbath evening, January 26th, 1851. The house contained five persons, besides a young child of Mrs. Campbell's; William Campbell, his wife; Daniel S. Thompson; Sarah Sharp, and the little Viola DeLove. It is six o'clock, and the short twilight of that season of the year, had already been succeeded by pitchy darkness. There was a small quantity of snow, on the ground, which had been blown by recent winds into drifts -but notwithstanding this, it was a remarkable dark night. The family had partaken of their evening meal, and with the exception of Sarah, had gathered around the fire to protect themselves from the inclemency of the weather, which was indeed bitter cold. Sarah had been engaged in removing the tea dishes,and had commenced washing them at a table near the north window, between it and the door.  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8060-00000010"/> 8a 4   aOHETIARMLES EDWARDS AND SARAH StAURP. -No noise was heard, nor signal given from the outside, to Sarah by any one, as far as the knowledge of the other inmates extends. She washed a part of the dishes, took down the towel, wiped her hands, went to the stove, thence to the cupbo9ard, back to the table, telling her little girl Viola that she would be back in a moment; she then passed out of the door and closed it. That child never saw its mother again alive. Not five minutes from that time, she saw her stretched on the snow, cold, lifeless -- dead!  In from one to two minutes from her exit, the inmates of the house heard a low noise, like some persons engaged in low conversation. Mr. Campbell asked what was the noise, and his wife thought that it was the tea kettle. At that moment they heard a shriek, clear and piercing as the wail of a lost spirit. Thomnpson ran to the door; it was so dark that, as he expressed it, he could not see his hand six inches from his face; but he heard a singular noise like dogs in a scuffle, and he was so much impressed with the idea that it was dogs, that he called to scare them off. He went into the house, procured a candle;and rushed into the yard again; a violent gust of wind extinguished the, candle, but not till he- had been able to see the prostrate form of a woman, and a Jin apparently stooping over fher. He called aloud upon the name o lrah, and heard a noise, not like a human voice, but an unearthly guttural that was without doubt produced by her attempt (being still sensible) to answer before the spirit took its final flight. Thompso:n by this time considerably alarmed, ran into the house, and as quick -as lightning seized a fire brand from the stove, and called on' Campbell to follow, in less time than it can:be recorded, beheld the awful scene, illuminated by the unearthly light of the blazing torch, and stood over the prostrate form of Sarah Sharp, from whose body the vital spark had fled. While making a hasty examination ,to see if she was dead, the body of a man fell heavily at his feet, within a pace of the murdered woman! The blood was still spurting and gurgling from his throat! That tnan was Charles Edwards! The scene was awful beyond description. The little Viola was runing about bare loot in the snow, almost phrenzied with terror, Mrs. Campbell was in hysterics; andsthe men left with scarcely strength to summon assistance. -Our artist has succeeded in giving you in the accompaning en. grairig, alas! but too correct a representation of the terrors of that scene. Would that truth might permit us to soften them. 'The   CHnARLES EDWARDS AND SARAH SHARP.      35 rear of the house as discovered by the flaming brand is singularly correct. Assistance was at last obtained; and before eleven o'clock a crowd of several hundred persons had assembled. Edward's boots were found standing as represented in the engraving; he being in his-stocking feet. The snow gave -evidence of a severe struggle; it appeared from the marks on the body of the woman, -that Ed- wards had put his left arm around her neck, taking violently hold of her nose, thus confining her in a measure, and horrible to relate, had cut her throat from ear to ear, and- then after dragging her some distance from the spot, had consumumated the horrors of the night, by his own destruction. His own head was almost entirely severed from his body! His pocket knife was found under his prostrate form, covered with blood. The knife was an- ordinary white handled one, such an article as every one carries, with one large blade in it about two and a half or three inches in length, and slightly worn in the middle. It had evidently been ground or sharpened by whetting very recently and had a remarkable keen edge. The shrieks of the affrighted females; the glare of the approach- ing torches and the tall forms of stalwart men, approaching in every direction. The hoarse voiees of the few whose presence of mind had not entirely deserted them, were heard giving orders! The blood stained snow for many yards around, and the gloomy- house, illuminated by a hundred torches, and in the midst lay the mangled, distorted and ghastly faces of the murdered woman and the self destroyer, standing out in bold relief, wrapped in their winding sheet of snow, all combined to make one of the most dreadful and unique representations of terror. As soon as anything like order could be obtained, the bodies were both placed in a sleigh and conveyed to the house of Edwards. Although the family had been previously apprised of the afflicting stroke, no words could pacify them. It was indeed a terrible thing -to look upon the grief of that mother and her three fatherless child- ren. A messenger was immediately sent to Rochester, that being the nearest place where a coroner could be procured; but owing to the state of the roads, coroner Pullis did not arrive until about eight o'clock the following morning. The coroner was accompained by Dr. Montgomery, a skilful surgeon of Rochester, who made a minute  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8060-00000011"/> 36    C3ACESR EDWARDS A-ND SABAH S[ARP. and accurate post mortem examination of the bodies, and testified to-the result of the examination at the inquest. EPOCH VII. CORONERS INQUEST HELD BY T. V. P. PULLIS, ONE OF THE CORONERS OF'MONROE COUNTY. At an inquest indented and taken on the 27th day of January, in the year 1851, in the town of Webster in the County of Monroe, before T. V. P. Pullis, one of the coroners of said county, a jury were regularly summoned and. sworn, and upon a view of the body of Sarah Sharp, then and there lying dead, at the house of Charles Edwards, the following testimony was then and there produced before them: William Campbell, being duly sworn says, in substance, as follows: That he resides at the house where the murder was committed, and knows the person murdered. - The house is in Penfield about 5 1-2 miles form Penfield village. The woman, Sarah Sharp, was in the house about six o'clock. WNVe had been to supper, and she was washing dishes at the table before the- window, near the north door. She washed a few minutes and then went out doors on the north side of the house. There was a candle on the table. We heard an unusual noise out doors. I told Daniel Thompson to go out and see what was the matter; he went, and immediately returned, say. ing there is somebody out here. Thompson took a candle and went out again and I followed him. The wind put out the candle. We returned, got a torch and by the light of it I saw the bodies on the snow. I then ran to Mr. Eldridge's and told them. Daniel re- mained during my absence. They came down, and then we saw the deed was done. I thought I heard a gurgling noise out doors before Daniel went out. I knew the man; it was Charles Ed- wards; I did not hear any noise that could have drawn her attention out of doors, before she went out. Sarah Sharp was a sister of my wife'; she was at work at my house; she had been there between five and six weeks; the wife of Charles Edwards is a sister of my wife.  Daniel Thompson being duly, sworn, deposed, in substance, as follows: I was at the house of Wm. Campbell last evening; Sarah   CHARLES EDWARDS AND SARAH SHAP.       37 Sharp was there; Sarah went out of the back door; after she went out I heard a noise; Campbell asked what that was; Mrs. Campbell said she thought it was the tea kettle; I then thought I heard voices, like some one talking to her; I soon heard a scream; I then went to the door; I heard a noise west of me like a dog chewing something; I said get out, and went into the house; I took a light and went out again, but the wind extinguished it; I again returned. got a brand of fire from the stove and took a candle, and saying to Campbell "'Come out, for something is not right," went out again; I went to the comner with the brand and saw the woman lying still on the snow, and a man was also lying near her; I then went towards the 'door near Campbell and told him Sarah was dead; (I thought she was dead because I saw blood on the snow,) he asked me where? I said on the snow; I heard blood spinning from the man's throat at that time; I told Campbell to go to some of the neighbors and give the alarm; he went to Eldridge's; some persons came with him from Eldridge's; they had a light; I then went to George Hibner's and Peter Harris' and told them; I was acquainted with Sarah Sharp and Charles Edwards; I think I have heard her say she was thirty years of age; the first time I went out I heard something like a dog chewing; I called Sarah's name aloud, and -heard a noise, not like a voice, but which I now think was an attempt to answer with her throat cut; they, from appearances on the ground, had been scuffling; she had been dragged a short distance; Edwards was in his stocking feet; his boots were found standing near the corner; she, went from the table to the cupboard, thence back to the table before she went out of doors. Charles Eldridge being duly sworn, said Mr. Campbell came running up to my house and said he thought somebody was mur- dered down at his house; we ran down and I saw this woman lying on the ground with her throat cut; the man lay on his nose with his throat cut also; they were both dead; I never saw him until that night; I had seen the woman a number of times. P. P. Cheneye sworn, ('witness was shown a knife) and testified that the knife was found under the body of the man, near his right hand. Witness'concurred with the other witnesses in regard to the situation of the bodies; there were tracks where he had stepped about in his stocking feet; their heads were about eighteen inches-  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8060-00000012"/> Ua    U ;nAK^.IllJ EDWA; VIJUP  A1DL ObAsAo BurAKr, apart; it seemed from the appearance of the snow that she had. - been dragged a short distance from the house, in the scuffle. D. C. Hammond was sworn and concurred with the testimony of the last witness. Norman Allen sworn.-I know the knife shown to the two last witnesses; it belonged to Charles Edwards; Edwards was a sober man; I always took him to be a sane man: I have heard him speak of some trouble; he said he had been accused of having connection with this-lady; he said he was no more guilty than the ones that reported the story; it seemed to work 'on his mind. A. Bushaw sworn.-Edwards seemed to be regular in his mind; he once told me he should be forty in March; there had long ex- isted an intimacy between Edwards and Sarah, Sharp; she was a single woman. Benjamin Randolph sworn.-I should think this paper was in Edwards' hand-writrig; (The paper found in his pocket was then read to the jury, for which see page 32 ) he was of a melancholy disposition to a certain extent. P. P. Cheneye recalled.-I requested Mr. Carlton to search Edwards' pockets; we found a wallet and a piece of paper. Mores Fosdic sworn.-I know Charles Edwards; he was at my house yesterday at 4 o'clock; he staid some time; he went up to Stephen Meeker's, about 1-2 mile from my house, and soon returned; he finally went off in the direction where the murder was com- mitted; he made a few inquiries about Campbell's family; I think he was perfectly sane; it is two or three miles from my house to Campbell's. Doctor Montgomery being duly sworn, says: I should think this knife would make the wound on the woman's neck; I have ex- amined her body; I examined her with reference to the question of pregnancy; she was not pregnant at the time of her death; I discovered a cut in the fore finger of the right hand - also one on the little finger of the same hand; a slight cut on the back of the left hand; -. slight scratch on the right wrist; the wound across the neck extended from the back ot the right eat across the wind pipe down to the spine, and not quite to the ear on the left side; the wound would produce death in a very short time. After some impressive remarks from Coroner Pullis, by way of a charge, the Jury retired, and after a few minutes brought in their   verdict that the said Sarah Sharp came to her death by the hands of Charles Edwards. Coroner Pullis then proceeded to hold an inquest on the body of Charles Edwards; and the jury after hearing the same testimony in substance as above recorded, rendered a verdict, that Charles Edwards came to his death by cutting his own throat, with his knife  CONCLUSION. THE bodies of this most unfortunate man and woman, were in- terred in Mason's Burying Ground, not far from the residence of Edwards. The usual funeral solemnities were observed, and a most touching, beautiful and pathetic discourse was delivered by a worthy clergyman of that vicinity, to the largest concourse of people ever beheld in the town of Webster. The worthy man did not fail to use that most melancholy occasion, to impress upon all, the neces- sity of looking to our Heavenly Father, for that support and direc- tion which He alone can give. Indeed their unhappy lives, and tragical death, was most fitted "to point a moral or adorn a tale." No event ever cast a deeper gloom upon society than this. No family was ever left in a situation more forlorn, than the family of Mr. Edwards. He left his wife with six children the oldest only ex- cepted, unable to make a single step in the world without a father's guidance, and a father's care, without a place to look for bread, save to Him "who hears the young ravens, and feeds them when they cry." Mrs. Edwards too, at the time of his death was enciente, and thus another helpless little one has been ushered into the world, and added to the number, who will through life too bitterly lament a father's follies. No family ever had more right to claim the gen- erous sympathy of our citizens than they. No family were ever more worthy of friendship, and kind encouragement than they. Mrs. Edwards it has been said, is a woman of more than ordin- ary excellence, and the oldest daughter, Miss Jane, is a young lady of superior good sense and intelligence, and having been her father's favorite child, and he having been her confidential adviser, would feel his loss under any circumstances to be a calamity scarcely en- durable, but when the Angel of Death visited him in such a treic  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8060-00000013"/> 40     OaHARi,  EDWARDS AND SARtAH SHARP. form, surely she must be inconsolable. And the other little ones, deserve the kindness and commiseration of all their neighbors, and will doubtless receive from hands incited by religion and charity, many favors, And she, most helpless of them all, the worse than orphan; the little Viola L)eLove, deprived by this double stroke of him who was her father by nature, though not by law; and the tender mother, who had watched and protected her infant years, what tongue can tell, or pen portray her agony? Reader, our heart sickens at her destiny. The child of shame; this tragic tale will follow her even to the last step in this weary pilgriniage of life. Innocent herself, she bears the fruits of other's follies. Let her take warning from the fate of those near and dear to her-the authors of her existence. Let her learn from their lives, the necessity of grounding her hopes for a life of peace and usefulness, upon the promises of God. Let her ponder upon the glory of the future world, and seeking early the feet of the Savior, she may be saved from all the temptations and trials which always prove too strong for mere mental resistence. Go thou, in life's fair morning, Go in the bloom of youth, And buy, for thy adorning, The precious pearl of truth.- Secure this heavenly treasure, And bind it on thy heart, And let not worldly pleasure E'er cause it to depart Go, while the day-star shineth, Go, while thy heart is light; Go, ere thy strength declineth, While every sense is bright: Sell all thou hast, and buy it  'Tis worth all earthly things, Rubies, and gold, and diamonds, Sceptres, and crowns of kings. Go, ere the clouds of sorrow Steal, e'er the bloom of-youth; Defer not till to-morrow- Go now, and buy the truth. Go, seek thy great Creator, Learn early to be wise; Go, plaeu iipon his altar :-A morning sacrifice. The house where the murder and suicide above related was per   CHARLES EDWARDS AND SARAH SHARP.       41 petrated, is now wholly uninhabited, except by a large cat, that still remains sole occupant of that lonely, and long to be remembered spot. When we visited the spot in company with the artist, who took the accompanying design, this faithful animal leaped upon the window sill, and looked through the window at us. The very window that Sarah Sharp looked through, but X few short moments before her spirit took its flight to be judged by the Supreme Ruler of the Universe. The grounds about the house are covered with a fine crop of buckwheat. And dark spots in the soil, together with the singular luxuriance of the grain, not far from the corner of the house, plain- ly point the visitor to the spots where the victims fell. The author in thus narrating a simple, plain and truthful history of those fearful passions; which even Shakespeare has depicted with all his glowing fancy; does not lay claim to :any merit, in its pro- duction, but only strives to do his duty, in holding up a warning ex- ample to mankind, of .the evils that flow- fromtunguarded passions: Mian still remains subject to them; but never, reader, should you search the annals of history, could you find a tale so appalling in its denoument; so terrible in its details; and taken as a whole, so black and fearful, as this ow'er true tale of love, jealousy, murder and suicide.  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8060-00000014"/> THE LIFE, TRIAL AND EXECUTION OF MATTHEW CARRIGAN, WHO WAS EXECUTED AT ANGELICA, ALLEGANY COUNTY, N. Y., JULY 18, 1851, FOR THE              , MURDER OF DAVID ROMER. IN presenting to the public the memoirs of the unfortunate individual who is the subject of this detail, we are not dictated by a desire which is too commonly the mo- tive of pamphleteers, of mere pecuniary compensation, but rather to exhibit to our readers the rapid progress by which persons are often precipitated to their ruin. The subject of this little volume, Matthew Carrigan, commenced life with as bright prospects and under as auspicious circumstances, as usually fall to the lot of those who are born in the humbler walks of life. So far as we are able to learn from the most reliable authority, his ancestry, though in humble circumstances, were all persons of respectability. His parents were persons of more than ordinary respe-tability, for those who held the position which they did in that country, the land of want and op- pression. We havB an assurance of this fact from the authority of the most influential men, now living in the immediate vicinity of the place where he was born, and the place in which he lived till he left the home of a widowed mother, with nothing but his good name, and a praiseworthy desire to benefit his family. He left the land of his sires to seek an asylum in this land of promise. He left his home, accompanied with the blessings of all who knew him; and by the assurance of persons in high standing, with a characteruntarnished by any previous act which could throw the least shade of disgrace over the days of his youth,   W       JMAT'THEW UAKtIGAfS. '            X. Matthew Carrigan was born in the county of Mayo, in the town of, Newport. His ih&amp;er, Iugh Carrigan, died prior to the emigration of the subject of these memoirs to this ountry, leaving Matthew, the eldest son, as the supporter of the family. It was thought by the family that if he should migrate to this country, he would easily provide a future home for hiisfamily. America wasthe Eldorado of their hopes. Mat- thew had resided in this country some six years whenthe fatal occurrence took place that ended his mortal career, and was at hisdeath twenty-two years old By a petition to Gov. Hunt, which was sent from Ireland, numerously signed by the highest dignitaries of church and state, living in that portion of Ireland where Oami- gan was reared, we are assured that e-was not only free from the commrtc immorali- ties incident to the characters of those young men who have the misfortune to be ed- ucated amidst a dense population, where vices of all kinds seek a home; but that he was from his youth notorious for his mild and peaceful disposition. In that petition, asking for a commutation of his punishment, it is asserted that he was never known to have been engaged, directly or indirectly, in any quarrel; and we have his own as- surance to the same fact, and that too when prevarication could not avail him anything and at a moment when the awful realities of an untried future would dictate to him honesty of confession. He assured all those who conversed with him immediately prior to his dissolution, that he had neverngaged in a quarrel with his associates; and so far from having any experience in the use of fire arms, he had never discharged one inhis lifeprevious to the time when the fatal occurrence took place that made him a felon, amenable to the laws of the country which he had adopted, and for which his life became a forfeiture.       -  Such was the character of M. Carrigan at the time of hisemigration to this country, when he left his family for a- fordign land, where he hoped to provide a home for his widowed mother and-family. In this land of strangers, he had a few of his early companions, with whom he could seek an association. He sought them out, undoubt- edly with the expectation that he should. find-in them the 'same moral integrity, the same sobriety that he had been wont to see in them when, in, the halcyon days of his youth, he had roamed over the green hills of his own "native Isle of the ocean." He therefore placed confidence in them, and trusted them ashisguides in a land where to him allwas new and strange; He knew not the danger into which he was precipi- tating himself. He knew not that those friends of his youth, who in "bye-gone" days had sported with him in the palmy innocency of youth, had changed their whole moral natures, and had become the debased subjects of the demon Rum. Such was, however, the fact. No sooner-had be found these old assoeiates, employed as they nostly were, upon our public works-places Synonymous with degradation and crime--than the poisoned ehalicewas presented tohislips by those in whom he trusted. He drank, and from that day may be dated the loss of all control over himself.-. Though unlike most persons, he seemed not to be rendered more passionate or malicious when under the influence of intoxicating drinks. Even when Rum had the most per, feet control over his physical and moral man, he was mild and inoffensive, and was never known, as we are assured by an intimate friend of his, to commit an act of violence, or to show any disposition to injure any person. His associations not only intirduced him to the accursed bowl, but urged him onward, and still onward, in his career of degradation, but rendered him daily more the subject of his vile passion for drink. At length so habitual and constant had become his use of ardent spirits, that the whole man was lost in that intoxicating cup which buries in fell ruin all the moral qualities of our natures Great excess of drinking followed close upon the heel qf acquired habit, till that most degrading and appfling disease, "&amp;deiriun treme ns," attacked him. Recovered from thia attack, he came in company with some sincere friends, who assured him that unless he ceased to use intoxicating drinks, his life, at an early day, would be the forfeiture. He heard their admonitions; and for some time, was a sober and industrious young man. But the demon that had once consid- ered him his sure prize, again returned, and again he became an inebriate. It is here worthy of remark, as it appeared by the evidence of one of his associates, that young Carrigan had in his youth received a hurt upon the back of his head, and that this was supposed to render the effects of stimulants more deliterious upon him. In fact, there could be little duibt that the use of intoxicating drinks had an unusual effect on him in stupifying his intellectual faculties. Even to the last moments of his life, the faculties of his mind were extremely variable. At times, he would seem un- commonly brilliant for one of his class of persons. He would converse with much spirit anid propriety. At other times, he seemed exceedingly stupid and senseless.   &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8060-00000015"/> "          3IATTHIEW    CARRIGAX. These seeming parorisms were of constant occurrence till the time of his death. C the eve of his execution, he requested to be shown the gibbet upon which he was 1 die. He examined it with, perfect composure, and did not seem torealize the awf event so soon to follow. By his own request, the lady of the jailer showed him h grave clothes. He examined them with perfect coolness, and gave her many thanl for maklng so apipropriate preparations for his burial, observing that it would be hil y gratifyllg tohis friends. Notwithstanding this apparent coolness andseeming .r diai, lonce, previous to his trial and after his condemnation, there were times when t keceneat sensibility was apparent; yet, at no time during his confinement, either to th jailol; whom he considered as a friend, or to his associates, or to the clergyman wh vrisited hiin, did he acknowledge a recollection of the crime which he had committed and whic  he was at:out to expiate with hls life. But at all times he would admit th fact, that he supposed that he had killed Romer, inasmuch as the evidence so said, bu denied his consciousness of the act. Such Werle the prominent circumstancesof his life previous to the enactment of th, murder of Romer, and such the general state of his feelings from the time of the mur der till his execution. We now propose to go a little back in the thread of our rela tion to the time immediately preceding the commitment of the act. Some two or three days previous to the murder, he was residing at Portage, Wy oming county. Some young associates of his, with whom he had been acguainted i, other places, came there, and, with all the open-heartedness of a son of Enn, he prof. fered them the social cup, as a pledge of friendship, and drank freely with them. He continuedl to drink to great excess for several days, and at length wVas again partially attacked with the Delrium Tremens. In this state of health and mind he took from a friend's trunk a brace of pocket pistols, and with a few associates started for Cuba, in Allegany county, where there were many of his countrymen engaged upon the public works. From all that has ever appeared, either from witneses at the trial, or friom his own confessiorns, we have yet to learn that he had any object in removing his location. True, some of the witnesses had heard him, in this state of mental aberla- tion, make some  threatening speeches against the Yankees, but no one ever thought that such words were any thing more than the mere ebulitions of a present disordered mind  He left Portage, in February, 185t, and, in company with two others, came that night to Belfast. On his way he rode in a wagon with a Mr. Adams, the same person who was with Mr. Romer, the murdered man, at-th time of the tragical act. Mr. Adams' testimony is to the amount that Carrigan was civil in all his acts and words during their travel from Portage to Belfast, but that he was evidently under the influence of intoxicating drinks. Carrgan staid in Belfast during the night, and ariose somawhat early on the follow- itg morning--the morn on which the murder was committed. The landlord where he staid was not conscious that Canigan drank but one glass of spirits during the m6.ning. Ca rigan, with his two companions set out for Cuba, at about sunrise. On their road, not far from the house at which they staid, they encountered the wagon of Romer, and in it Messrs. Romer and Adams, the man with whom he had ridden the day previous. Carrigan stepped up to the wagon, which was immediately stopped, when (,aprigan requested a fide to Cuba. Whereupon, Romer pointed to a mill not far distant, and said to him that he was going no farther than to that mill,' and it would be no object for him to ride thus 'far. Carrigan left the wagon and it pagaed on for some few yards; meanwhile, Carfigan had taen a  pisto from his pocket, and, ap pal   Hently without any special aim, fired at the peros in the wagp. - t was a fatal :l-hot, and caused the death of Romer some twelvehonrs'afterwai dn. What malice afore-thought there might have been in this act, we are unable to divine, for neither the murderer nor murdered had ever hald any intercourse with eaelL other-. they were perfct  strangers. Mr. Adams, on the discovery that the shot had taken eflectupon  :mer leaped froln the wag on, and seizing, one of the comparnions of Cardigan, held him till assis- trauce arrived, which was nearat hand. Carrigan, with his other companion fled, but welre minediatrely pursued by the sheriff, Mr. Hughs and others, and were taken some half a  mile-from the spot where the nurder was committed. The evidence as to the facts was conclusive identifying Carrigan as the man who fired the pistol, which caused the death of Romer. The pistol was found in  aligan's possession. There could be no doubt in the cake that Carri,gan did killRomer. Such werethe facts that appeared on Ihe examination for commitment, with an additionlal part, to wit: that airg an, as he walked towards the wagon, appeared to witnesses to be somewhllat intaxieato   MATTHEW CARRIGAN.                45 Upon tlis testimony Carrigan was committed for trial, which took place in the following April term. As the prisoner was not in circumstances to employ counsel, the court assigned him counsellors Peck and Grover;, two of the most prominent counsel in the county.' The prosecution on the part of the people was conducted by 'District Attorney Davidson, assisted by counsellor Champlin. In opening the case to the jury, Mr. Champlin remarked that the evidence in proof of the criminality of the accused would be Brief, but pointed and positive, so as to leave no doubt upon the minds of the jury of the facts criminating the prisoner, and identifying him as the murderer of Romer. The counsel then proceeded with some pertinent remarks to the jury on the many violations of the public peace, which had been perpetrated within this county during the past year, and exhorted the jury, however disagreeable it might be to their feelings, not to shrink from their duty, but by their decision to show to the wilful violaters of the public peace, that the maiesty' of the law would interfere to secure the rights, and protect the lives of the citizens. It should here be observed that a more impartial jury could scarcely be imagined. In , selecting this jury the regular pannel was exhausted, and only six jurorswere obtained - all of those who were rejected having consctienious scruples on the subject of capi- tal punishment. A new tally was collected and the pannel completed. The evidence which was brought forward by the prosecuting attorney proved the criminality of the prisoner so far as related to the overt act, beyond the possibility of a doubt, as we have previously stated. * The defence was opened by counsellor Peck. He commenced by saying to the jury that since the court had assigned him as counsel for the prisoner at the bar, he had had opportunity to converse with him, and that he had no hesitaaLcy in saying that he believed the prisoner to be at present unconscious of the act of which the evidence proved him guilty, but from a confirmed state of idiocracy to be morally incapable of appreciating the nature of the crime which the counsel admitted the prisoner had com- mitted. - Hence, the counsel contended that the prisoner was rather a fit subject for the lunatic asylum than one to be tried for having -committed wilful murder with malice afore-thou ht The evidence adduced by the defence went to prove that the prisoner was subject to aberations of mind, during which he appeared entirely unconscious of all around him, and apparently not capable of exercising his moral functions, and therefore, not accountable criminally, for the acts done while in this state of mental incapacity. Such was the substance of the facts that were submitted to the jury, and commen- ted upon by the able counsel for the defence, and we have no doubt from our personal knowledge of the facts, as well as from the general expressions of those who heard the trial, that the unbiased opinion of the jury, as well as the congregation, would have been that Carrigan had killed -Romer when in a state of mental aberation. The jury retired and in a'AiSt time returned and gave their verdict of guilty, in accordance with their declaration. Eight of the jurors, however, recommended the prisoner to the mercy of the court" These jurors have since assured us that they were mistaken in the nature of the verdict which they rendered, not supposing that -their verdict would, of necessity, subject the prisoner to the death penalty, and some of these jurors have since assuredxus that had they have known the true nature of their verdict they would not have rendered it in that form. Had I wanted any further confirmation of the mental imbecility of the prisoner, I had it in the most perfect indifference and stolidity manifested by him on the rendi- tion of the verdict Not a muscle moved, and the prisoner seemed as unconcerned in the whole affair, as though he were a block of marble. On the following morning, wnhen he was brought into court to receive his sennce, to the usual question of the court, as to whether he had anything to sy why judg- ment should not be pronounced, he replied, ." That he had no knowledge of having committed the crime of which' he now stood condemned -that he had never seen Romer before, and had no ill will against him I or any other living person." A soli- tary tear coursed down his cheek, the only evidnce of sensibility exfhibited during the entire trial. Judge Marvin then proceeded to pronounce the sentence of the law upon the" pris- oner, in a very brief, feeling and pertinent manner. He said:--"You, Matthow Car- rigan, have been tried for ] avying committed an offence against the laws of your coun- try, and your God, for which you tiow stand condemned, by an impartial jury of that country. Every care has been take..that that jury should consistrof such men only,  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8060-00000016"/> "          , MATTHEW CARRIGAN as were notprejudiced for or against you, men of candor and integrity. The court, in consideration of your inability to provide counsel for yourself, appointed for your defense two of the most able advocates of this bar. - Those counsellorshave did all that could be done to present your case in the most favorable point of view, in which the law and evidence in your case would possibly permit The court have granted, both you Pnd your counsel, all the leuit y and indulgence which they have deemed consistent with the nature of the case. Yet after the fullest and most patient investigation of your case, that jury have rendered to the court a verdict of guity of the charge of your indictment. It now only remains for the courtto-affix the penalty of the law and tlia' death. The court have no choice left to it We are but the organs of the law, to pronounce its sentence. You have violated its injunctions and it demands of you a relaration for your transgression. You have trampled upon the rights of a fel- low being, who had in no way injured you, by taking away his life. In this you have violated the laws not only of man, but of God, and must suffer the penalty which the law demands. However painful it may be for the court to pronounce upon you the sentence of the law, it has no alternative. The court, in pronouncing your sentence, are (deirmos ,if giving you all that lenity, which the circumstances of the case will pei nt. We fully appreciate the relation in which you stand to an untried future, and are, therefore, desirous of .lengthening out that little span which intervenes between you and eternity, and hope that you will spend that time in making prepara- tions -to meet that God whom you have offended. In man you can have no further hope. Repentence and trust in the merits of a crucified Savior is all that is now left to you." SENT'TE NCE. The sentence of the law is, that you Matthew Carrigan, be taken hence to the place cf your confinelmenlt,and to remain there unto the 20th day of June, 1851, and that on that daj, between the hours of ten o'clock and two o'clock P. M.. you be thence taken to the place of execution, and be hung by the neck till you are dead. As soon as convenient after the adjournment of the court, one of the judges of the court, the sheriff, and deputy sheriff several members of the bar, together with other persons, feeling 'that the condemned was not a proper person on whom to inflict the extreme I:ena4y of the law, wrote communications to the Governor, stating the facts of the case, as they appeared to them, and suggested to Gov. Hunt the propriety of commuting hi. sentence to imprisonment for life, The strong inducement which caused those pelrsos to make these representations to the Governor, originated from the fact, that llnee of the'jury had represented to them, that they did not know that their verdict was of necessity a death penalty verdict, or they should not have given it. A petition was. also sent to the Governor from the place of Carrigan's birth, signed hy many of the leading men of his native place, requesting a commutation of his pulniIshent, giving hin, in all his previous life the best of character. The Governor reftusd to grant the petition, but granted a reprieve from the 20th of June to the 18th of July. This reprieve, through the untiring exertions of his clergyman, Rev. John Doran, reached the sheriff some twenty minutes before two o'clock, on the day upon which he was to have been executed. At the same time he was assured by his clergy- man, that lie must give up all hopes of any further grace from the executive. From that day lie renewed his preparations for a coming eternity. He was aided ia his devortional exercises almost constantly, -by the Rev. J. Doren, of the Catholic Communiron, of which faith Carrigan was, and also by several of the Protestent clergy of the place, for whose attention le ever expressed his warmest gratitude. His de- portment during the whole of his confinement, up to the moment of his dissolution, was mild mnd respectful. To the many who visited his prison he was ever polite. We should do ourselves injustice if we should close this narrative without the single remark, that unlder ordinary circuristances, we have not the leastdoubt that Carrigan's punishment would have been commuted to imprisonment, but for the excitement of the people, in the county where this tragedy was enacted. Many depredations, with- in the year, had been comnitted by those operating upon the publtc works, passing through this county, by countryn en of Carrigan, and I have not a doubt these facts influenced the decision ,of Govr. lutnt not to commute his punishment I will now close this narrative, with the single remark, that if in presentiig those memoirsto the public, I shall have convinced any young man that 'evil comnmni- eations corrpt good morals," and throw around the young those inducements, which   MAITHSW OARRIGAN.               47 in all cases lead to the gates of death, I shall have accomplished all my hopes on this subject, and shall feel myself filly compensated for the time which I have spent in this compilation.  THE :EXECUTION. The day fixed for the execution of this unfortunate individual, to wit; the 18th of July, 1851, having arrived, it found our worthy sheriff and his efficient deputy in per- fect readiness to fulfil their duty as executive officers; a task every way disagreeable to be peiformed by any person possessing even the ordinary feelings of common hu- manity. The apparatus by which this unfortunate being was, at the appointed hour, to be launced into an. untried state of existence, was all in readiness, and got up in the most approved style. His clergyman had been with-him most of the time during the day preceding the fatal hour; giving to him as the embassador of Christ, the " extreme" consolations of his office. At half past 1 o'clock the sheriff admitted into the yard, where the prisoner was to be executed, the witnesses required by law, together with a few other invited witnesses. The prisoner was then conducted from his cell to the yard of the jail. His step was firm nas the very feeble state of his health would per- mit, and whatever inward emotions he may, and probably did possess, his outward ap- pearance was that of calm resignation to the awful fate which awaited hinm He took his position and submitted to the adjustment of the fatal cord with but little apparent emotion.  Opportunity was then given for any remarks which he might deem proper to make. The substance of his remarks was summed up in this: That he was not conscious of having committed the crime, for which he was about to be sacrificed - that he enter- tained no ill will against any human being-and that he desired the prayers of all at this awful moment. - His clergyman then offered for him hislast prayers and pronounced his last blessings. A death like silence pervaded the assembled witnesses, while the voice of the sheriff counting the moments of existence to this unfortunate subject of the majesty of the law, broke with solemn import upon the ears and hearts of the assembly. The last moment arrived - the fatal cord was touched, and a young man, flushed with the vigor of twenty-one - far from the land of his sires- from the home of a widowed mother, who had consented to his emigration to a land of strangers, with the hope that in that far off land he would be enabled to afford her that assistance which the destitution or her circumstances needed, was launched into eternity. As the drop-weight fell, a few convulsive moments succeeded, and the ' silver cord" was broken, although signs of life were observable for some fifteen minutes His friends were all allowed, at a proper time, to receive his coffined body, which they conveyed to Portage, and buried in the consecrated burial grounds of his church, and who shall say less than peace to his ashes. Thus ended the solemn scene which the laws of our land demand to be enacted upon all those who willfully shed man's blood. The law is satisfied, forthe sword of justice is dyed with the blood of the criminal But, reader, is this all that a moral and religi- ous community ought to think or say upon this similar occasions? We think not. If it be " a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God," how fearfully responsible is that community which sends, uncalled for, a human soul into the presence of its God. These questions naturally arise in the mind of every thinking person. By what authority was this extreme act done? Is the taking of life for life in accordance with the will of heaven?  So far as the act relates the action of the judicial and executive officers in the case, no blame or error can be attached to them. The law of the land demand life for life, and compel her executives to take it. But the question still occurs, is that law requir- ingthis sacrificeof liferight? The advocates of our crimialcode answer tiumphautly yes. The bible demands it in the most emphatic language, when it says: * An eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth. He that shedeth man's blood, by man shall his blood be shed," and numerous other passages might he quote  This, at first blush, might seem to put a quietus upon the whole argument Not so. God seeks, in the govern- ment of his creatures, that expediency which the exigencies of the times and the con- ditions of his subjects demand. His government is one fitted to the exact condition of the governed -.and if the Bible, His oricles, be true, then does not the Almighty delight in either the physical or moral death of any of his intelligent subjects Th0 whole tenor of divine inspiration is repent and live. The whole design of the pun- ishment threatened and inflicted is intended for the improvement of the subject. So  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8060-00000017"/> / 48           MATTHEW CARRXG;AN should human laws be-so they are intended to be. Are we asked why God commad- ed life-to be taken, we answer, that the condition of mankind, at the periodsh hen such commands were given, rendered it impossible to secure the lives and right of communities from the assassin's knife, or from the depredations of the wilful violators of human rights. Most of the inhabitants of the world, at that period when the com- mands were given, were existing in wandering tribes, their dwellings the tent, or some temporary buildings. They had no penetentiaries in which the depredator .on the rights of man could be confined, and thus be prevented from further injuring his fellow man. Hence the necessity of the death penalty. There are undoubtedly, nations whose barbaric conditions compel them in defence of individual rights, to conduct their criminal processes in the spirit of the Levitical code. But we ask, most emphat- ically, is such the condition of our own country? Have we no places of safety where the criminal may be secured without the hope of pardon-where he will not only not have the power to injure his fellow man, but will be permitted to have a day of grace in wlich to prepare for the solmreali ties of a future state; and may be compelled to be useful to his fellow man, by exercising his industrial powers. If we have such places, then in the name of all that is sacred, and in obedience to the commands of a crucified Savior, let usl cast aside the relics of barbaric ages, and no longer stain the sword of justice with the blood of victims slain to satiate the vengeance of man, and leave to God what he claims as his right, when He says, "Vengeance is mine, and I will re- pay, saith the Lord." But it is said that were the death penalty abrogated, our country would be filled with assassins. lThis we deem a mere assertion, without the least item of proof. On the contrary, wherever any section of the Union have abolished the death penalty, al those crimes, punishedhere by death, have decreased. (See report of Sec. of Michigan and of otherStates.) And this decrease of crime tales place where the country is becoming more densely populated, and of consequence,more subject to crimes of all kinds. Besides, the influx of people from the o!d world, sent hiter, from the sewers and from all the sinks of iniquity with which that world abounds, would of necessity increase the boundaries of crime, and yet the ratio of the death penalty crimes is lessened It is a false position that the severity of punishment diminishes the amount of crime. It is the surety of the punishment In connection with this idea, I desire to call to mind the fact, that about one-half of those persons who are indicted for murder, escape punishment altogether. This originates, undoubtedly, from the fact that the public mind is so far averse to the death penalty that it seeks to clear, from the abhorent penalty, the guilty wretch, in many instances, when if the penalty was imprisonment for life without the hope of pardon, that same wretch, who is left to roam through the land unpunished, a terror to all, would have been confined within his cell and made to subserve the interests of his abused fellow men by the labors of his hands. Viewed in all the light of the 16th century, the death penalty seems to us but a hideous relic of by-gone days, when the "lex talionis," was justified by the conditions of men, and the revengeful spirit of the age; for whodare say that the spirit of the gospel dictates that vengeance which bathes the hand of justice in the blood even of the murderer. We have long possessed the foregoing opinions, and we are gratified by the dawn- ing appearances which give an assurance to our hope that the day is not far distant, when the statute books of our country will no longer be stained by legalized com- mands to sheath the sword of justice in the heart's blood of humanity, thus assuming the prerogative of heaven.                SPECTATOR.    &#xD;<pb n="50 (Illustration) -51" xml:id="VAC8060-00000018"/> I MATTHEW LARRIGAN Was executed at Angelica, Aliegany county, N. Y., July 18, 1851, for the MURDER OF DAVID RoOMER.  This murder was caused by rum drinking, and the history of poor Carrt- gan speaks in thunder tones to the man who "mixes strong drink," and should prove A VALUABLE TEMPERANCE ARGUMENT TO ALL READERS     &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
