<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8382">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Corner Stall </title>
            <author>Wright, Julia McNair, (1840-1903)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC8382</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2805</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The corner stall</title>
                  <author>Wright, Julia McNair, (1840-1903)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>257 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Hoyt</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1868">1868</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-10-14">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5. Inserted OCR text. Linked image files</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The corner stall</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8382-00000001"/>NEW YORK STORYk&#xD;
a%-                                       ?&#xD;
HET&#xD;
N.MPS. JMNAIR WRIGHT.&#xD;
i PUBLISHED BY HENRY 110Th&#xD;
--0.^bCORHflL.&#xD;
r  t  1.F.,  .".S~av, . td  . :jeu   "  i~...Wr.+:  e  ^' g 'v'''&#xD;
"  s".;y. "1,,: (rF'   r'yhr  ,,  }!h i    L, 'iI&#xD;
&#xD;
.:. :&#xD;
'+&#xD;
'&#xD;
: ?&#xD;
,+&#xD;
;&#xD;
,&#xD;
' :;;&#xD;
. ,&#xD;
,_ ,  1&#xD;
,&#xD;
. *w&#xD;
' '  ' a   ' '&#xD;
.    '&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n=" (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC8382-00000002"/>&#xD;
-SS -&#xD;
I  # $&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER L&#xD;
Tnonus Twtcac          -        -  -&#xD;
CHAPTERit .&#xD;
Tx r Wor     --           --&#xD;
Jrtz fltssa&#xD;
TUQXS$ Tlidc s  cw, ma r.4I&#xD;
CIAPTtE&#xD;
cI PTu T&#xD;
tmsit Twt Ex ATr E. ---..&#xD;
CHAPTER VUL-&#xD;
Lrw (rcc orarcts, -a35&#xD;
CHAPTER i&#xD;
floTnrsc O,  -  *-  -  a -&#xD;
CHAPTER L&#xD;
Taso vna Loai At 1116 Won&#xD;
&#xD;
8 t.&#xD;
r&#xD;
.A&#xD;
&#xD;
i_   K&#xD;
n     a&#xD;
' -j_  .&#xD;
M _&#xD;
-  t7&#xD;
&#xD;
a&#xD;
c?&#xD;
8r-&#xD;
&#xD;
NL#%&#xD;
&#xD;
U&#xD;
&#xD;
'I&#xD;
&#xD;
/r; _ ,&#xD;
iij&#xD;
&#xD;
T      J4      "~a} "       umnr&#xD;
L'&#xD;
&#xD;
4n",&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC8382-00000003"/>&#xD;
LVH                                      CHAPTER 1    TA&#xD;
TUOMAS TWIGO.&#xD;
ALITdawn,thchlgrywtC&#xD;
tAIL   ~looked it a  upe1&#xD;
her," almost -as salasta4bitW&#xD;
the Shanuite w  e&#xD;
or Elisha, years ago.T&#xD;
t was supposed o e&#xD;
hl C its corners being one There w&#xD;
hen depatent -gIRatnyirpaeov-&#xD;
oppositeachi4nacoe&#xD;
*/&#xD;
&#xD;
"_            ,-      -   . _                         '"x" ""41         _s"°"°,. -    _, ~ ..t.:      _    -                      ._- - _           _  -,      .&#xD;
Pon&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8382-00000004"/>&#xD;
r,       _ -  _.f f .M-  - l~tY" ~i :  Y' JlS&#xD;
Erw =&#xD;
&#xD;
IR wah ** **4      a   eening the  ba    -a&#xD;
third angle had a square v&#xD;
carpet, a yelow chair and a. stand covered&#xD;
with a ao'ildoth, whihgreu       uns.&#xD;
4s idicated a parlor,-and lastly, a cot&#xD;
covered with two brown blankets was te&#xD;
eK pnent of the bedroom, under the two&#xD;
Thomas Twigg, mater,&#xD;
and sole occupant, of this residence, which i&#xD;
almost called aerial, inasmuch as it over-&#xD;
e nearly all the adjacent chiuneR&#xD;
oming in through thec       n&#xD;
er window, albeit not         rosy&#xD;
ted as thpoets             h&#xD;
ebutdull&#xD;
as-if disappoint  in her P&#xD;
Twsgg, who rose anddree&#xD;
soon asehiseeswere&#xD;
was short, wiry1 a little grey, a&#xD;
4enkind, put on patched clothes, but wasbei&#xD;
and combed his hair w&#xD;
tinhineiyorpk&#xD;
&#xD;
to00&#xD;
&#xD;
This                       hisr...psde  yn  10&#xD;
nearly ito the center of i. e ad ei&#xD;
irresolute -he turned his chair&#xD;
attempts to kneel down; he had     t&#xD;
pair of knees which    were all&#xD;
bowing.&#xD;
The fact was the man was    yi   no&#xD;
indeed he had learned a prayer a&#xD;
to ofer it; he had a   Xon that to&#xD;
the best posturefor. these. h i Gra&#xD;
devotions; he was not rheumati lit his&#xD;
the hackof his chair with an iron grip Pa&amp;amp;&#xD;
bean to repeat hisnew form IO. =e&#xD;
somehow it would not do-he went&#xD;
one    e,e       the seat of te chair&#xD;
could see him          e solid wai&#xD;
jiu anly h  led tedwe~erinth&#xD;
&#xD;
-r&#xD;
&#xD;
.3&#xD;
i&#xD;
a&#xD;
TJ&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8382-00000005"/>&#xD;
a   cont sTALL&#xD;
&#xD;
nberation ;,he wsahmd&#xD;
o    le               y ashamed of this,&#xD;
Oneof hebest moves he had ee    ae    n&#xD;
deesniitt..ever made, and&#xD;
 cuyroom he brok    nto  Seat&#xD;
at  s unusual undertakja                e&#xD;
and muttering fast&#xD;
andindistinawofor ess than two minutes, rose&#xD;
spng, as if' punged to his neek in the&#xD;
Rwt      iver, just then floating -down huge&#xD;
He had fuunish-A&#xD;
Unsatisfactory devotions&#xD;
- they were Uflsatisfacwrl because while the&#xD;
ande wld not bow the heart was unbowed,&#xD;
ad wle  the ips attled over what the head&#xD;
bd lerne  t heart was silent as a corpse&#xD;
k dead    es Toaswig' heart was&#xD;
h  wouldad d   in trespase  and sins, and&#xD;
nt cae Unto Jeks that he might&#xD;
e knew very little about&#xD;
As Thomas std.i up to recover himself&#xD;
at prying methinks had hi&#xD;
&#xD;
vision been made clear like that young&#xD;
who stood with Elisha in Dothan, he   g&#xD;
like him, have seen a strange spect-&#xD;
terng spirits doing His servi, wlite winced&#xD;
messengers from  the skies, looking on wel&#xD;
phased. rejoicing over their Master's plans fw&#xD;
1is poor Thomas Tw.gg, pie-man, and keeper&#xD;
aa Corner Stall, where those who 'pick up&#xD;
a living' bought the unusual n aaies of *&#xD;
dughnuts and muddy cofee.&#xD;
Thomas set his chair away, smoothed his&#xD;
bed, took one book from his shelf and put it&#xD;
in one of two lage wicker hampers, wW&#xD;
l together by a broad leather strap,&#xD;
anging against the wall.- He put the saa'&#xD;
n some 4terous way across his breast so that&#xD;
'Th hamper hung over his strong $   d&#xD;
and then he went down two flights of t&#xD;
In the gloom he stumbled against a frgment&#xD;
of humanity, which fragment sobbed.&#xD;
Wv, Mw" cried Thomar"oha&#xD;
gone wrong'&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8382-00000006"/>&#xD;
S   ma&#xD;
&#xD;
Wtcold*andiseary      , and F&#xD;
smam   ays an' I dom   sell mor&#xD;
y nor I did yesterday shell whip me,"&#xD;
maige, running over a&#xD;
quite enough to overwhelm a tear old.&#xD;
"Chik up and sell your picks lirelv" said&#xD;
Mr.           and ma&#xD;
Tw ,ra       yiny if you get up by&#xD;
Union  aq                     gix4 von a&#xD;
alitte, hut inalessrtch&#xD;
ed        ent dawn another pair ofa stairs&#xD;
side the pie-man; then she wenton toward&#xD;
street, while Thomas struck a door with&#xD;
hi hard knuckles. An oldw    an&#xD;
e stuck in a turnip, opened the door.i&#xD;
Pardner, said Thomas, "are you ready&#xD;
for buinss?&#xD;
Sorra a day am I behind,"   a the old&#xD;
gve a the hamper man," shed',&#xD;
aStePpmolf~ back fo Thoaw&#xD;
p  tlafor Thomas to enter ther&#xD;
Sh  s not an looking old lady, ther cap&#xD;
&#xD;
wh its wian                        Was&#xD;
strpe4apron.&#xD;
She had several chairs in the rolt a&#xD;
one wasa oiled ham, on another a&#xD;
biscuits, on another a number of pies.&#xD;
Th      put his baskets on the for, and&#xD;
sat down on the foot of the bed.&#xD;
"Get out wid ye," cried the old lady,&#xD;
mussing up the bed F' just u       akg&#xD;
and me best quilt on it&#xD;
Thomasseeing no chair, posted himmdf a&#xD;
the corner of the small table.&#xD;
" A  lazy lummox," said Mrs. Ki*a&#xD;
cani ye no stand a bit?&#xD;
I stand all day," ejected Thomas.&#xD;
"Thrue for ve" said Mrs. Kiligan,  fsly&#xD;
packing the baskets;  is is settg upnM&#xD;
books ye are, Thomas? here's a bit of a&#xD;
n the basket."&#xD;
"Its a spelin' book," said To&#xD;
Howly Moses " cried Mrs. SKligan,&#xD;
spelling' book I an whatiitkr?"&#xD;
&#xD;
_&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8382-00000007"/>&#xD;
SA&#xD;
Thomas looked abished, but when his part-&#xD;
ner in business demanded anew, "What will&#xD;
ye do wid it, Thomas?" he replied, "'m&#xD;
studyin'2"&#xD;
"The saints help ye, man, who ever heard&#xD;
the like?" said Mrs. Iiliigan, stopping with&#xD;
the han half in one of the baskets.&#xD;
"It isn't justly what you might expect,"&#xD;
said Thona,       ! rtcoring his composure, "hbut&#xD;
'm favorable to it. There's a gentleman, a&#xD;
real out and outer too, he's up in the Sem.&#xD;
nry getting hisseif made into a minister, and&#xD;
he's teaching me and I shall know the books&#xD;
rightly soon."&#xD;
"An' slackin' up the business, an' Il lose&#xD;
money by yer airs," said Mrs. Kiliigan, wrath.&#xD;
fudly, putting biscuits wherever she found&#xD;
room in the hampers.&#xD;
"It's 'idle time I take and I'll not los a&#xD;
stiver by it," asseverated Thomas; "my luck's&#xD;
your luck, Mrs. Killigan, and you'll never find&#xD;
a better pardner than ThomdTwic&#xD;
&#xD;
" That car be," sadMrs. Kifliga, "but I&#xD;
isdouht the books. Can ye read?"&#xD;
"Right smartly," said Thomas, wh&amp;amp;- was&#xD;
onl of adverbs. " Next week I'm going inno&#xD;
c Testament.&#xD;
And what may that be, Thomas ?"&#xD;
SWhy it's piece of the Bible, pardner.&#xD;
" May the  intakepTyonaye heTihlom;&#xD;
the ible  a heretic book and an invention&#xD;
of the evil one himself," cried Mrs. Kiigan.&#xD;
"I know bater, said Thomas; "my grand-&#xD;
mother read it, and she had no dealings with&#xD;
the evil one: ;your speaking by your priest,&#xD;
pardner. and they'd take the last penny you&#xD;
earn byv your baking.&#xD;
- They won't get much out of me, mavrom&#xD;
neen," said Mrs. Iilligan, shutting the baskets,&#xD;
with a chuckle like the rttle of loose coppers&#xD;
in a purse: "but let well enough alone, and&#xD;
don't tempt thrial by the Bible."&#xD;
"Did you put in the book?" askedThomas,&#xD;
takinguphis lot&#xD;
&#xD;
:^&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8382-00000008"/>&#xD;
h! Iid. Sorra teday that ye wouldn't&#xD;
take good advisement."&#xD;
"I take better," said Thomas. "Ill hang&#xD;
on to the directions of the Sem-S-nery chap;&#xD;
he's an out and out zentleinan every inch of&#xD;
him."&#xD;
Away went Thomas. hendinz under the&#xD;
weight of the baskets on his back; as he went&#xD;
Out of the doorway, fr he door had been&#xD;
surreptkiody carried off and converted to&#xD;
fuel by the denizens of a neighboring alley,&#xD;
upon whom the aristocratie inhabitants of the&#xD;
house where Mr. Twizz lived, Lioktd down&#xD;
with vast contempt. Mr. Twist: e neountered a&#xD;
woman caring a little bundi of kindlings,&#xD;
for which she had paid two cents.&#xD;
"Good morning, Mrs. Dd'" said our&#xD;
friend; "you're out early."&#xD;
rI have to be. I got a morsel of washing&#xD;
to do, and must make the rent somehow; the&#xD;
old woman daunders over her knitting so oky&#xD;
like, that I'm  dreaming shell get to the&#xD;
&#xD;
m  C  U TALL&#xD;
rSylum herf afore she gets work to the&#xD;
shop."&#xD;
" Poor soul!-" saidThoma, "and you've&#xD;
set up little Maggie with picks to sell.- She's&#xD;
small for the street."&#xD;
She don't make her lirin' by no means,"&#xD;
sai Mrs.Dodd. " Itold her I-bate her the&#xD;
night an' she didn't earn more for ne."&#xD;
I wouldn't do it" said Thoma, "she's&#xD;
little and timid for the street; you don't know&#xD;
what it is, Mrs. Dodd, you never had to do it&#xD;
"No more I didn't'" cried Mrs. Dodd.&#xD;
Srra the Jay I left dull Ireland for this&#xD;
tiresome land. an' married a man wid chider&#xD;
to ;ns±-r rme&#xD;
Mazfe's a znod child; I wouldn't whip&#xD;
her" -ur:ed Mr. Twizg.&#xD;
You know yourself that I rate her right&#xD;
decent in the main.&#xD;
" So yon do, better than many do their own&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8382-00000009"/>&#xD;
and blood, but I wouldn't he hard on her&#xD;
for not earning much ; she's not six year old,&#xD;
v-mn."&#xD;
"Thrue for ye, it's hard lines, but other bits&#xD;
of childer earns more."&#xD;
"Steal it more likely, and you wouldn't&#xD;
want to drive her to that by being hard."&#xD;
"No more I wouldn't," said Mrs. Ld.&#xD;
"I want no thieves nor hieveries around me&#xD;
-drnken ones is enough-- Dodd sucks up&#xD;
the whiskey like a sponge the weather, bad luck&#xD;
to him. I'm clean discouraged."&#xD;
"I-believe it," said Mr. Twigg, heartily.&#xD;
"I m sorry for you, woman. I wish I knew&#xD;
ome comfort for you, but I reckon there ain't&#xD;
any for poor folk, but /to drudge it out as siff&#xD;
as we can, and die some day"&#xD;
t     "Arrah, the time is long," said Mrs. Dodd,&#xD;
climbing the steep staircase toward her room,&#xD;
while Mr. Twigg went off bent, but brisk of&#xD;
tep toward tnion Square.&#xD;
&#xD;
As Mr. Twigg went on he soliloqi    -&#xD;
The world's put together right queedyisb,&#xD;
t's not me nor me pardner hat to compbin; I&#xD;
aakes my living and fills my bank, -he I he!I&#xD;
[homas Twigg, banker, who knows it?  I'm&#xD;
directors , Fm  President, Fm  Cashier, I'm&#xD;
icad and tail in my bank, but here's Dodds&#xD;
an hardl keep their souls in their bodies-&#xD;
fl Land 0' Goshen, there's the Alley, Jug&#xD;
Uny what did all those people come into the&#xD;
Vrd fo r? or why should there be Jug Alley&#xD;
nd Fifth Avenue, there's a punier for you,&#xD;
Fhom as Twigz: why should there now? I&#xD;
alls it a Problum. Here's bricks andfg%&#xD;
mxd stuns, and there's more tears nor all of&#xD;
hemr,, other he, and I swan there ain't the&#xD;
lightest morsel of. comfort for them, nor&#xD;
10 hodv to give it."&#xD;
Solomon, sitting in his house of cedar, '&#xD;
troned on gold and ivory, builder of the&#xD;
nest magnificent of temples, grand Magia&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8382-00000010"/>&#xD;
11    nRt- -&#xD;
&#xD;
'whbo bad evoked rb the rods of power and&#xD;
gold, fair Tadmor, like a vision of beauty in&#xD;
the wilderness, had written, "So I returned&#xD;
and csdr  ed j all the oppresionshat are&#xD;
done under the sun ; and behold the tears- of&#xD;
such as were oppressed, and they had no cen-&#xD;
forter?"&#xD;
He who had seen Jesus in gory as he wem&#xD;
to Damascus, who had keen lifted up to tdx&#xD;
"third Heaven "      the .rapturous love&#xD;
the Saviour, had caught up the refrain of&#xD;
Solomon, and spoken of  God that comforttf&#xD;
those that are cast down;u" hut while Mr&#xD;
Twigg took the same view of the case of the&#xD;
poor as Solomon, setting forth his wonderment&#xD;
in homely phrase, he had never heard of&#xD;
God as "God that comforteth," nor of -the&#xD;
"Holy Ghost the Comforter," nor of Jesus&#xD;
who invites the "weary " to his Rest.&#xD;
Thomas thought earnestly and walked quick-&#xD;
jy, and at last reached his place of husineM&#xD;
&#xD;
on Union Square; he never got to it be&#xD;
loked at it with pride.   Weather stained&#xD;
boards made up the bark and two sides of his&#xD;
stall, also the sloping roof; in front, sheltered&#xD;
by the roof was a kind of counter, at the bark&#xD;
a few shelves, and the place to stand between&#xD;
the shelves and counter was narrow exceed-&#xD;
ingly; it was a good thing that Mr. Twigg was.&#xD;
not a larger man.&#xD;
Mr. Twigg got behind his counter, lifted up&#xD;
the i d which had been fastened with a s&#xD;
padlock. and began to arrange his stock in&#xD;
trade. He had two little furnaces on whih&#xD;
he heated coffee and water ; he had also a litd&#xD;
green tub wherein he washed his dishes,&#xD;
a brown towel to wipe them. He had&#xD;
jars of eandy, some nuts and apples, a&#xD;
stock of crockery also. He set his merchan-&#xD;
dise on the shelves, put his dishes in&#xD;
the ham,  iesLLC th    e&#xD;
~of the ham, pies, and other edibles, be bad&#xD;
&#xD;
-.&#xD;
&#xD;
zs  W .&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8382-00000011"/>&#xD;
411gtntheamper. Nexthetmndeafln&#xD;
in each lite furnace, and put water to heat in&#xD;
apot,and madecoffee in a kettle in a fashion&#xD;
that b et 'ise     and hanseleepers fat dL~&#xD;
fane.-&#xD;
Then, as passers by began to multiply, Mr.&#xD;
Twigg, for his own refreshment, and the better&#xD;
advertising of his humble restaurant, poured&#xD;
out a cup of black coffee, sweetened it with a&#xD;
black sugar, the deposite of molasses barrels&#xD;
cut some bread and ham, and proceeded to eat&#xD;
his breakbst.   He ate with   great gasto,&#xD;
kia'his lips, eyeing his coffee like aCon-&#xD;
lisseur, and lovingly regarding the ham; thi,&#xD;
prtly because he was hunzrv and hearty, and&#xD;
 s ishedwhat he ate, and partly because it was&#xD;
a      nhe had got as a sort of cheap adver-&#xD;
tt of his edibles. Mr. Twigg being too&#xD;
poor to patronize the newspapers, and most&#xD;
ofT his estomers not knowing how to red a&#xD;
newspaper puff for    Corner Stal of Mr.&#xD;
&#xD;
Thoma   Twigg     .,"  would late bwa&#xD;
superfluity.&#xD;
As he ate, a new thought struck Iha;&#xD;
he got down under his shelves to rummage a&#xD;
minute, and emerged with his spelling book&#xD;
rescued from the basket. He opened the book,&#xD;
and skSwly moved his fing*er down the pages.&#xD;
"Ah," he said "1 knew it; b-r-ea-d-&#xD;
bread,. there you are," and he poked abc&#xD;
in a jocular way ; "e-o-d4e-e - cofee,then&#xD;
you are,  and he put his cup to his&#xD;
Then he walked his cup and plate, looked&#xD;
about for a customer, sold two mites of&#xD;
cakes for a penny, and turned to a little&#xD;
er sewed into the leaves of his book ; it&#xD;
a Track Society Primer, hut Thomas was&#xD;
ightfulv oblivious of that Tract Society, far&#xD;
wi h a Christian people has so much cause to&#xD;
thark God. Mr. Twigg again looked in erery&#xD;
Aidnit  witk a   eye  t     hen'an&#xD;
to spell to himself and pronounce aloud, "God&#xD;
nt - his -Son - to -save -lost - men."&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8382-00000012"/>&#xD;
1$&#xD;
&#xD;
ORN  lE  nx&#xD;
&#xD;
Gracious," said Mr. Twigg, "it must have&#xD;
been Jug Alley people ;' then he read on,&#xD;
We are all-sinners -but.- Christ- died -to&#xD;
save - our - souls."&#xD;
"That was doing a mighty sight," said Mr.&#xD;
Twigg;    wonder if it means everybodyx;-&#xD;
herein running npon a Theological snag of&#xD;
serious dimensions, but quite ignorant of the&#xD;
weighty' discussion that had hinged thereon,&#xD;
he concluded to read further. "Herein - ,&#xD;
love -not that we -ovei - Gd - bt that - he&#xD;
first -loved u&#xD;
"-That's powerfMh talk," saidl Mr. Twigz;&#xD;
hilo  hors' hre I am ready with your&#xD;
kfast; how's buines?  Sold out. Tr.&#xD;
bwze?   What's your luck Tines ? Hwled&#xD;
yourself hoarse, herald? there ain't such&#xD;
another pair of lung in the trade as yours.&#xD;
World, what's the news?     Thus cordially&#xD;
.hnrn.n-        linr-  mwn .n.rnrdia  tao&#xD;
their usual custom, came to his stall for their&#xD;
nmorningme&#xD;
&#xD;
;,,, _&#xD;
f  Jh     "      _&#xD;
' _,&#xD;
tY   a&#xD;
&#xD;
"Ain't no news," said 'World,' who took&#xD;
his title from the paper he carried.&#xD;
"Ain't, now," said Mr. Twigg, setting out&#xD;
tour cups and putting in sugar; "sakes, I&#xD;
eard von running over a list of things round&#xD;
the corner.&#xD;
- That's to sl," said World, watching the&#xD;
black. smoking stream pourgitas cup&#xD;
9lper  Ra  asdi hwater's L'I!"' =&#xD;
"That's your go and you'll break on it,"&#xD;
sai R Timen; -Slast night ye were yowling&#xD;
about a man was elected , when he wus'nt ;&#xD;
w il bur of ye agin when onet ve're cheated&#xD;
There's lots of folk's," said World, "and&#xD;
ai Eve fooled 'em all I'll be rich?&#xD;
v I say, Herald, said the Tribune boy,&#xD;
- was you at the meeting last night? "&#xD;
" Well, I was," said Herald.&#xD;
-What does you say to the speaker?&#xD;
askedl Tribune, stuffingr his mouth with biscuit.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8382-00000013"/>&#xD;
"He's a brick," said Herald, eating a tough&#xD;
doughnut.0&#xD;
"Who's heb? whar    he talking tout?"&#xD;
asked Mr. Twig.&#xD;
"He's called Aliston, and he's a  achin'&#xD;
man:; gracious, don't he give out the doetrim2&#xD;
why, I felt as if I was a precious rasal I did,"&#xD;
said Herald, a loud voiced Lv. iarer than&#xD;
the rest.&#xD;
"Ye wus'nt fur wrong" said Times, gri-&#xD;
ning.&#xD;
"I know him   ' cried Thomas Tw niz;&#xD;
,r when's he going to have a preachment&#xD;
jain?"&#xD;
"To-night," said World.&#xD;
"I'll go " said T -,;i  be sure I will -&#xD;
~'.... C.liet  fere tfi  r ! ,&#xD;
dWh I knows him; - h'coe heever darl&#xD;
be does?&#xD;
"Take his diner    setered Tkmes-&#xD;
No ; but he don't de spi- to stand by the&#xD;
counter helping me read, he don't'&#xD;
Well," said Herald, "he puts it out right&#xD;
&#xD;
lively about sinners and getting saved 1&amp;amp;.a&#xD;
-  t       o "&#xD;
I'm going to-night.&#xD;
The news boys went off shouting their&#xD;
respective papers, Thomas Twigg washed his&#xD;
dhes, and s' had a p.e of shoe blacks to&#xD;
serVe ;aS he attended to them, a stubbed&#xD;
ti ure. lie the oid woman in the picture&#xD;
h.' xdn. witi sAir dr   ld country blue&#xD;
etokN, flide cap ruXZUe d closet quitedu bLLIa&#xD;
1r. cJamet Up.&#xD;
'il. pardner, what's to ja'? " cried Mr.&#xD;
-N ar a thing saidi Mrs. Killizan, re&#xD;
rin the row of hungry hors with evident&#xD;
ta"    .-ut the bo      mad mte naisy&#xD;
ie. al  1 just trolkl u  t see were ye&#xD;
uving the business pretty decent?&#xD;
Never fear," said Thomas perfectly good-&#xD;
;atured under this suspicion of neglect; "g&#xD;
ne t  , your cooking pardner; I'll run the&#xD;
sta1 haudsnme. Thomas TwNi is the&#xD;
for me."&#xD;
&#xD;
w&#xD;
T-166&#xD;
Y  ' tl&#xD;
1Y .n h  t&#xD;
r&#xD;
J^&#xD;
it&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8382-00000014"/>&#xD;
"Troth, but maybe he ain't the man for&#xD;
other folks" said Mrs. Killigan.  "I'll keep&#xD;
an eye on him, Thomas."&#xD;
"Two if it isn't to deprive yourself," said&#xD;
Thomas, cheerfully.&#xD;
Mrs. Killigan, with another sharp scrutiny&#xD;
of the- stall, and the money the boot blacks&#xD;
were handing in, turned to go.&#xD;
"Hill, bold on, parluer,  cried Thom.as,&#xD;
"here he come, and I'll make you ae&#xD;
qusinted.&#xD;
Mrs. Killiian stopped. and for occupation&#xD;
ate one of her own singerr snaps, while a ta&#xD;
young man dressed in black, drew near the&#xD;
stall savin, "Good morning. Thomas."&#xD;
-'Morninz, sir. morninz, hope your well,&#xD;
sir; here's my pardner, sir," said Mr. Tigg.&#xD;
"A  line dar to vou, said Mrs. Killigan,&#xD;
with an old country curtsey.&#xD;
"Thank    ou," said Mr. Allston; "your&#xD;
wife, Thomas?"   he asked, turning to the&#xD;
pie-man.&#xD;
&#xD;
cona flALL&#xD;
&#xD;
"Faith, no:" interrupted Mrs. Kuipu,&#xD;
briskly, "never a man of them all would I be&#xD;
bothered wid, respects to ye all the same."&#xD;
"Business partners,"  explained Thomas    yi&#xD;
loftily.&#xD;
"I think, ma'am, that you have a very&#xD;
edicient partner in Mr. Twigg," said the gen-&#xD;
IL. alwiz did well," said Mrs. Killigan,&#xD;
- hut I have my doubts ince he's afther book&#xD;
]arman.&#xD;
Tlhoms has   very praiseworthyr desire to&#xD;
read the best of ooks. tihe: 1Vb1e" said Mr.&#xD;
The saints preserve as" cried Mrs. Ki-.&#xD;
gae. with evident horror.&#xD;
vou ever read that book, ma'am?"&#xD;
aked Mr. Allston.&#xD;
The Virgin be praised, cried M:'rs.  -&#xD;
an, "there's never a line of any book -that I&#xD;
can read at all at all?&#xD;
&#xD;
A)-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8382-00000015"/>&#xD;
Mr. Allston drew a little black book fom&#xD;
his coat pocket. "If you wil listen a mo-&#xD;
ment, ma'am, I wdl read a few words that&#xD;
wll show von tat the flinl is no Iok to-&#xD;
make Mr. Twit~ nezect his business? said&#xD;
he.&#xD;
Mrs. Klliga# crossed herself, retreated a&#xD;
step and .htened, whle Thomas was evidently&#xD;
u   cleasd.  Mr.. A. '1ren turned  er s3me&#xD;
leaves and read here and there in Proverh,&#xD;
pausing a nmment at the end of eah verse -e&#xD;
" He becotumth   or that eaU-n with a slack&#xD;
h a n d ,  b u t  t h e   4 a n dl  o f  t h e   d i lb.e n t  mu a k e t h&#xD;
rich." Mrs. Kjidt aa nVFd led apiproivingdy.&#xD;
"Mind that.Thonmas," .id Mrs. Kihligan.&#xD;
He that is slothful in busines- s brother&#xD;
to him that    meatwaster?   r&#xD;
&#xD;
8a&#xD;
&#xD;
s const an-&#xD;
&#xD;
Thrue for ye," said Mrs. Killigan.&#xD;
Slothfulness casteth into a deep sleep; and&#xD;
an idle soul shall suffer hunger," read Mr.&#xD;
Aliston.&#xD;
Sure it's a proper good book Im think-&#xD;
imz: what's better than to mind one's business&#xD;
and lay up the pennies?" said Mrs. Kiligan,&#xD;
approbativelv.&#xD;
What profit hath a man of all his labor&#xD;
h ch he hath labored under the sun ?  One&#xD;
eration passeth away - and another genera&#xD;
an 4"ncometh:" continued Mr. Aliston, look-&#xD;
keenly at the old woman.&#xD;
OXh hone, but you''e spoiled it all," said&#xD;
Mr.. Killizan ; "it's ever a sore thought to&#xD;
r that man like a head of wheat that ills&#xD;
iu: to be cut down. Shure there's little satis-&#xD;
faction after all ; we go down to the grave&#xD;
whlsere w1c can take e: ve r a inig of ale&#xD;
saved up ; " and turning away, she was soon&#xD;
lost in the crowd of passers by.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8382-00000016"/>&#xD;
m         STALL                                      STALL&#xD;
&#xD;
"She's right," said Mr. Twigg; "it's quite&#xD;
aeous to think of what will be the end&#xD;
of al, to die and - who knows what"&#xD;
"I'm  sorry von feel .that way," said Mr.&#xD;
Aliston ; "are you afraid, or in anxietv about&#xD;
each night as it comes?'&#xD;
"Be sure not said Thomas ; "its quit&#xD;
omfortabie after :he racketh and worriti;&#xD;
of the day, to get a resting speli and then -&#xD;
the morning won't be long in coming.&#xD;
If von were a Christian," said Mr. Al&#xD;
ton,  vo would feel sure that dying was but&#xD;
going home to God's good rest: and that the&#xD;
- morning of the Resurretion would soon comou&#xD;
and Jesus, your Master, would bring your&#xD;
body from the grave to His glory"&#xD;
Then," said Thomas. seriously, "I wish&#xD;
I was a Christian.&#xD;
o    grant that     mayrbe ne; anA n&#xD;
be a Christian is to feel that you area poor&#xD;
helpless creature, and Jesus is your Saviour."&#xD;
&#xD;
a That's a matter," said Thomas, "which I&#xD;
hain-t by no means looked into as I ought to."&#xD;
"I'd like to know something of your his-&#xD;
tory. Thomas said Mr. Aflston.&#xD;
Dear knows I haven't any," said Thomas.&#xD;
" Where were yoU born?" asked Mr.&#xD;
A1:ton.&#xD;
Up in 'Hampshire? said Thomas,&#xD;
Ar o;ut o the world.&#xD;
- I Qhouid think then you'd long for the&#xD;
country. ;ometimes"&#xD;
No sir. said Thomas, emphatically, "I'm&#xD;
a Utiss man. Thomas Twig likes folks&#xD;
mo re titan he do fieds. Thomas Twigg likes&#xD;
s4W an -bustle, and up and down trading, that's&#xD;
wha: he likes."&#xD;
SAnd who brought you up. Thomas?"&#xD;
-I brung myself up inostlv," said Thomas.&#xD;
A . 1  ' ,.&amp;amp;il  3.#  i 11  V  l  C'X . UAId S- d1  A.C&#xD;
- .L'Vi e withS grannies  a g 'nld so'ut sa&#xD;
were too, till' she died, clean of old age, I&#xD;
gue%, and folks says, 'here's this ten year old&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
4        LL.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8382-00000017"/>&#xD;
shaver, let's put him in the poor hus.' I were&#xD;
a stubby little chap, but I had sperrit ; says I,&#xD;
no poor hus for Thomas Twig'       SoI&#xD;
slipped off, walked to the sea coastgot on  a&#xD;
vessel, and said  4I'd be a sailor.'  One bld&#xD;
took the sail out  IIfnm. I was tat sick&#xD;
wouldn't go on salt water again fr no rnony.&#xD;
I slipped the Capn when we m l- New Y&#xD;
and here I v-   i n ev' a  ."&#xD;
'Bu hw di   - ou make ta9ivin at first ?~e&#xD;
I hadI an eye twr Irade, ,ir. .I had ad  -&#xD;
Jar I'd saved up iwme I zwt a lbake , sir, at. t&#xD;
some fruit fro.m tihe dck; sometimes I wa&#xD;
&amp;amp;cliated, sometimes I drove zood barzams ;&#xD;
sometimes I went hungry -makes me feel&#xD;
for hung bov4 now - other times I had&#xD;
money clear. I riz litle by little, sir, got a&#xD;
big basket, got a stand, got a -tal, gut a part-&#xD;
7        . rs.- a~r .. s        u-  nv~&#xD;
and, sir, them's the adventures out and in aP&#xD;
Thomas TWIgg.&#xD;
&#xD;
ian         sat.-           37&#xD;
"Well, Thomas, I can see that the Lord&#xD;
has watched over you and blessed von. What&#xD;
have you done for him?"&#xD;
Not one thing$ said Thomas, looking&#xD;
down and twisting himself about&#xD;
Did you ,pray this morning as von prom&#xD;
ised?&#xD;
"When I promises I performs," said Thom.&#xD;
as.&#xD;
"WelI Thomas, what is yoar opinion of&#xD;
pnayingC?&#xD;
Sir, I says, says I this is just the tougher&#xD;
bn of business ever you got into,Th     s&#xD;
wi_ gg&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8382-00000018"/>&#xD;
THE comaALs&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER IL&#xD;
&#xD;
TfL'E    1W  I t3}7F   1? 11&#xD;
&#xD;
(    A  'I. ALLtTON turni and loked&#xD;
towvar I ra:, ;the fiw ti at&#xD;
-...r4.4 r _ ; t - 1 V  iiat' -&#xD;
smile on it ;   'n-um' au Idit  causetl for&#xD;
a momnent a mirthful . ature t: uverthow, but&#xD;
the face that presently turned to Thnlas, was&#xD;
kind and grave as ever, as Mr. Alton asked&#xD;
"What made it hard work, Thomas?"&#xD;
"It seemed -queer and awkward, and I&#xD;
thought somchodv was joking at me; all the&#xD;
room seemed full of yS. uny 1 ai promscu,&#xD;
I wouldn't have done it, sir, but I never grs&#xD;
bck on my word. I hated to, dreadful."&#xD;
34&#xD;
&#xD;
Opt&#xD;
&#xD;
a_&#xD;
&#xD;
Rp&#xD;
&#xD;
"Why, Thomas," said Mr. Allston, "this&#xD;
int at all as it ought to be. God bids us&#xD;
cosme to him freely as children to a father ; he&#xD;
bids us say 'Our Father.' He is so willing to&#xD;
less us that he gave his own Son-to die for&#xD;
our sakes, that * we might be saved from wrath&#xD;
b  Him' When you were a little boy did&#xD;
v n ate to) ask yoar parents for anything?"&#xD;
Tiannas w as silent ;he leaned- hack against&#xD;
 ,b4lve-, his eyes (awt d own and rubbing his&#xD;
am .,i  t wthr.  Mr. Allston watched his&#xD;
r.   face with interest ut was like watching&#xD;
: at lighting slowly up in the cmv dawn&#xD;
-  ur Northern latitudes, Jowly sfteuing and&#xD;
rowingg clearer; so Thomas Twigg's face re-&#xD;
laIxe and grew soft, as he mused - like a&#xD;
little child's face, for his mind was busy with&#xD;
hi childhood1 which had gone away like a&#xD;
- These ain't all new things to me, sir," said&#xD;
Thomas, his voice quieter than usual; "why,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8382-00000019"/>&#xD;
m CO     SAL.&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
as you spoke, and as you said  Our Father,'&#xD;
and as von went over that' ware, why, sir,&#xD;
the days when I were a shaver come back to&#xD;
me as clear as clear can be. Seems like I can&#xD;
see that little house, the vines on the front&#xD;
porch, the kitchen. clean and bright as a new&#xD;
pin; and old Grannie, always knitting sock-&#xD;
ings. Wasnt no schoJ nija, and    rarn&#xD;
was lame ; she taugh trm a hit. but like I tiI&#xD;
you I never got onl a liztle in:to  pe!%n', and&#xD;
soon lost it in this here bi'ness place. But I&#xD;
mind she talked to me and she braved, and I&#xD;
used to go down on my knees by a chair, not&#xD;
minding what I said pretty much, but I re-&#xD;
collets' Our Father,' and I learned that very&#xD;
ware one Sunday. Onet and a while I went&#xD;
to church, but it "as too far for o1d folks and&#xD;
lttle chaps. I've about lost all grannie Kod&#xD;
me, onlv enlouzf' smki      yha    th   -&#xD;
never could steal nor swear, sir.  I mind&#xD;
grannie took me to a grave yard    e -&#xD;
&#xD;
showed me where my folks was buried. She&#xD;
wiped her eye on the corner of her apron, and&#xD;
stooped down and patted the graves, like she&#xD;
was smoothing a bed ; 'they're gone to glory,'&#xD;
says s, 'mind you goes too, Thomas.' Ind,&#xD;
sir . that's full tifty year gone, and instead of&#xD;
ato glory 1ve never thoauht a word of&#xD;
iii glad to hear all this, Tomas, said&#xD;
ir. Abston.&#xD;
Glad to hear I'm so far out of the road to&#xD;
s r s; itCs quite discourageous, I think,"&#xD;
tdThomas.&#xD;
-I did not refer to that part of your re-&#xD;
r," said Mr. Allston. " I mean I am glad&#xD;
u u ead pious relatives. I am sure that they&#xD;
entI prayed for vou, and that God has an&#xD;
.ered their prayers b  keeping vou from&#xD;
open sins, and I hope be will do yet more for&#xD;
u by bringing you to the knowledge and&#xD;
love of Jesus Christ."&#xD;
&#xD;
;--        _&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8382-00000020"/>&#xD;
42&#xD;
&#xD;
ras coaEs STALL&#xD;
&#xD;
"  don't see how he can do that much for&#xD;
such a careless old fellow as Thomas Twigg,&#xD;
said the pie-man.&#xD;
" There is nothing in any of us to com-&#xD;
mend us to God," said Mr. Aliston,.* but&#xD;
herein God commendeth his love to us, that&#xD;
while we were vet sinners  irst iedorLus&#xD;
" Titais more than ever I heard of before,&#xD;
as I remembers, said Thomas.       We must&#xD;
be powerful bad off to need dying tor; ain't&#xD;
many sins a man loses his lift for, let alone&#xD;
needing somebody else's life to be took."&#xD;
"Well. now, Thomas, while Jesus has felt&#xD;
your sin and misery enough to die for- you,&#xD;
what have you ever done for your fellow fmen,&#xD;
for Jesus, or for vurself?"&#xD;
"As to your first two questions," said&#xD;
Thomas,   I ain't a word to say  but as for&#xD;
myself, sir, I've done pretty well by myself.&#xD;
I've laid up two hundreds dAlarso "&#xD;
This closely practical dollar and cent an.&#xD;
&#xD;
swer took Mr. Aliston so completely by sur-&#xD;
prise,-that he again turned away, and watched&#xD;
fbr a minute the tide of comers and goers&#xD;
that ebbed and flowed along Broadway; then&#xD;
turning back, he said,  In a hundred ears,&#xD;
Thomas, where will be your two hundred&#xD;
dollars, or what vou have bought with it?"&#xD;
" That's a case I've put to myself, sir,"&#xD;
said the pie-man.   I've said what will be&#xD;
the good or it all, as much as a thousand&#xD;
times. and to give a clear answer, sir, will take&#xD;
a lt:ter scoliard than Thomas TI wg.&#xD;
can tell you one thing, Thomas," said&#xD;
Mr. Allston, am@t sternly,  if you do not&#xD;
get an interet in the Blood of Jesus, if you&#xD;
dn~ ~east yourself on him, in one hundred&#xD;
years it will make little matter about your&#xD;
money. and you will be a lost soul.&#xD;
Thomas dropped his head and loked di&#xD;
treed. Mr. Allston saw tiat the arrow had&#xD;
gone home,    h  sai,- I'll read a little to&#xD;
&#xD;
', : '&#xD;
,., _ r&#xD;
. - "&#xD;
..&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8382-00000021"/>&#xD;
V~flvs TALLai                              WALL&#xD;
&#xD;
yOU Thomas,nd then you shall hre your&#xD;
Thomas sold some lemonade to a nurse maid,&#xD;
and some painted candy which she wanted to&#xD;
keep her little charge quiet, while she gossiped&#xD;
with her cronies in Union Square. Mr. Alls-.&#xD;
ton looked at the delicate little ones, and won-&#xD;
dered what their mother would say to see&#xD;
the eain .the ;nfe4rir ndy trom the~ stall&#xD;
of Thomas Twig. He then read a little to&#xD;
Thomas, and Thomas read too; they were&#xD;
reading the Gospel according to Mark. The&#xD;
lesson being finished, Mr. Allston went away.&#xD;
The next visitor, at the Corner Stall, wasb&#xD;
little Magie Dodd. She looked very forlorn,&#xD;
aying she had sold but three picks. She held&#xD;
out her little box to Thomas; it had in it about&#xD;
thirty picks. made of white bone, with two&#xD;
little blades to them.&#xD;
"They're fire cents apiece," said Maggie,&#xD;
"an' nobody won't buy any. I wisht I was&#xD;
&#xD;
like them children in the Square.   dont&#xD;
have no good times; home pappy's drunk, and&#xD;
grannie's mourning, and the baby squa a&#xD;
straight streak. I wouldn't mind so much&#xD;
onIy I don't never get enough to eat;" and&#xD;
Magie eyed Thomas' wares, remembering&#xD;
the promise of the turnover.&#xD;
Thomas was not stingy, neither was he&#xD;
forgetful; he gave Maggie the turnover, and&#xD;
ste ate it with as satisfaction, never thinking&#xD;
of finding fault because it was several days&#xD;
old, had a tough crust, and was scantily fu&#xD;
nished with sugar.  Apple turnover wa a&#xD;
ra'ity that did not come to Maggie every days&#xD;
and he accepted it accordingly.&#xD;
"Now. Magie,     said Thomas, when the&#xD;
last crumb of the turnover had disappear&#xD;
"Eo into the Square, and ask every grown up&#xD;
one vou meet to huy a pick, then walk all&#xD;
round the Square and do the same."&#xD;
"Tm afraid, folks look so sharp at me, sa&#xD;
Maggie.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8382-00000022"/>&#xD;
4as com STALL&#xD;
&#xD;
"Come, now, you'll-never get on in trade&#xD;
if you mind that!" cried Thomas; "runoff&#xD;
like a little woman ; hold up that long frock&#xD;
of yours, voull tumble on it; your mother&#xD;
ought to take a reef in it."&#xD;
"She ain't no thread nor needle," said,&#xD;
Maggie; "she wants to buy some."&#xD;
"Go earn the money for her then; trot&#xD;
along you poor little toad; vo'1 sell a heap&#xD;
of picks before you get round the Square,&#xD;
sure's my name's Thomas Twxgg, said the&#xD;
pie-man, cheerfully.&#xD;
Maggie gathered up her long frock in one&#xD;
little brown hahd, pulled her hood farther on,&#xD;
and clasped the corners of her shawl in the&#xD;
hand that held the uncovered box of picks.&#xD;
Thomas looked after her, going timidly up to&#xD;
one and another, generally turned off with a&#xD;
gnick shake of the head. One old gentleman,&#xD;
with a gold headed cane and gold rimmed eve&#xD;
glass, seemed quite angry at being asked to&#xD;
buy.&#xD;
&#xD;
. --              =.,&#xD;
---      -&#xD;
&#xD;
,s&#xD;
&#xD;
"Like's not he' got a gold pick in his&#xD;
pocket," said Thomas, watching his little&#xD;
friend's progress, "hbut land o' Goshen ! he&#xD;
must have a stun for a heart, to refuse such a&#xD;
poor weazen faced little toad as that, out hunt-&#xD;
ing her living.&#xD;
It was noon, trade was more brisk at the&#xD;
ts' rer Stall,. for a little while; some street&#xD;
Zweepers were eioying such financial success&#xD;
:Lha they=hought a bottle of zinzer beer, a&#xD;
pi and I om)rne biscuits, from which they dined&#xD;
iuxuriuly.&#xD;
Mag..e came back after her rounds, With a&#xD;
Jan face; she had sold five picks, wonderful&#xD;
pr perity in al hour and a half, she thought;&#xD;
m: having made her report trotted off toward&#xD;
lhoadway, her long, soiled frock, twisting&#xD;
Camp and ragged about her ankles as she lon,&#xD;
nd her h.'ht hair blowingr about from under&#xD;
her tAd worsted hood.&#xD;
Maggie hurried along toward the "The St.&#xD;
&#xD;
,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8382-00000023"/>&#xD;
48&#xD;
&#xD;
Nicholas$" where she had fhquently sold picks&#xD;
to those who congregated about the door after&#xD;
the dinner hour. She did not mean to stop&#xD;
one moment until she got to this hotel, whose&#xD;
grand white front always filled her poor little&#xD;
heart with a sort of awe, but she did stop,&#xD;
right near a fine window full of beautiful&#xD;
French china. It was not the beauty of the&#xD;
china that attracted Mazie, but looking into&#xD;
the window was a little girl of her own age,&#xD;
dressed in green velvet from her hat to her&#xD;
gaiters; a cloud of wavy golden hair was&#xD;
comled down over her shoulders, and her face&#xD;
was fair and sweet as a moss rose. Behind&#xD;
this little nurslinz of wealth stood a maid&#xD;
ervant, holding the child's doll, a splendid&#xD;
waxen affair, that seemed to Maggie almost as&#xD;
beautiful as its owner; the child herself held a&#xD;
mne Cornucopia, and was dividing her time&#xD;
between looking in the window, and picking&#xD;
out of the Cornucopia dainty confections such&#xD;
nulease d her taste.&#xD;
&#xD;
"Goody gracious, don't that gal have good&#xD;
times!" said Maggie to herself; and just then&#xD;
little miss looked at her, and cried out, "Janet&#xD;
what a funny little girU why donut her mother&#xD;
give her some god clothes?"&#xD;
Never mind her, Miss Mar'," said Sane,&#xD;
I ain't no good clothes, said Maggie,&#xD;
tears sprinzinz to her eves, there Was such a&#xD;
Sctrast between heseif and this other child.&#xD;
What i in your box ?   asked the little&#xD;
'Pikt, wont vou buy one?" said iMaie,&#xD;
Co me, Miss Mar"4" said Jane, scornfully,&#xD;
don't be stopping to talk to such trash."&#xD;
I shall see what she's got, said Mary,&#xD;
tryv: and taking a pick Maggie held out she&#xD;
crit, "in't it funny, Jane, only look at it.&#xD;
How much is it?" she asked Maggie.&#xD;
"Five cent," said Maggie.&#xD;
&#xD;
7RIW&#xD;
TAX CONJMR STALL-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC8382-00000024"/>&#xD;
"Do coae on, Miss Mary," cried Jane,&#xD;
if you want such a thing your pa 'Il get 'em&#xD;
from the store; such beggars ain't fit for your&#xD;
talking to, right here, too"&#xD;
"I shall buy the pick," said Mary, "so you&#xD;
can pay for it, Jane: do you like candy,&#xD;
girl?"&#xD;
Maggie nodded, though such candy as Mary&#xD;
was eating se had never tasted1. Jane re-&#xD;
lactantly paid fir the pick, which Mary pock-&#xD;
ed with much deiht.&#xD;
4'Hold out your box, girl," said Mary, "Il&#xD;
gi1ve you some candy."&#xD;
"Indeed, Miss Mary," cried Jane, "such&#xD;
candy is not to be wasted on begars."&#xD;
You keep still, Jane." said Mary, quickly,&#xD;
"Ill do asI like to;" and she poured half her&#xD;
candy into Magge's box, saying,  Tell me&#xD;
yelr nae, girl"f&#xD;
"It's Maggie," said the little street gi&#xD;
her eyes full of gratitude; "thank'ee, Miss "&#xD;
&#xD;
4 Now, Miss Mary!" exclaimed Jane, "we&#xD;
must go on. I'll leave you, Miss, if you don't&#xD;
Come."&#xD;
The girl went, on, and her pretty charge&#xD;
f slowed her slowly, while Maggie, putting&#xD;
some candy in her mouth, and some in her&#xD;
pocket. ran down the street.&#xD;
While Maggie Was thus seeking her fortune&#xD;
r alon  Broadway, Thomas, in his stall, on&#xD;
Union Square, had another guest. The pie-&#xD;
man kept his Testament in his hand, and when&#xD;
not 1 u s with customers, studied it carefully;&#xD;
L*vking up from his hook, he saw not far from&#xD;
nim a pair of dark wolfish eyes, glaring upon&#xD;
him in a way that made him quite uncom-&#xD;
fortable. Of course the eves were set in a&#xD;
c and that face was bleached and haggard,&#xD;
U:ti the grim  genius of &amp;amp;mine might have&#xD;
taught it was his very self. About the face&#xD;
hung shagy unkempt hair, and to be sure the&#xD;
head was mounted on a body, and that body&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC8382-00000025"/>&#xD;
was lank and loose jointed, and  eed cad in&#xD;
a heterogeneous collection of old rags; here&#xD;
looked out a sharp elbow, here a shoulder;&#xD;
and there part of the side was bare, while&#xD;
knees and feet and ankles were the prey of&#xD;
every sleety wind that blew.&#xD;
"Land Co Goshen'" cried Thomas, " Ratty,&#xD;
is thatyou?"&#xD;
"AYes it be," said the boy, shuffling a little&#xD;
nearer.&#xD;
"Why, Ratty,. what are you doing up here,&#xD;
so far from the wharf?"&#xD;
"I'm beat out " said Ratty, or rather Jer-&#xD;
miali Hocknev. "Sumudy stole my money,&#xD;
an' I got dared out of the house, an' Ie&#xD;
slept in box'n, an' dodged the perlice, an' Ive&#xD;
rigged a little, but ain't 'ad no luck, an' I'm&#xD;
done beat out I are."&#xD;
o swthat tieo b wanted something&#xD;
to eat, but selfishness suggested that the profits&#xD;
a( the Corner Stall were small, that he had&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
given some     toMaggie, and that to fed&#xD;
Jerry, was only to encourage him to come&#xD;
again ; he knew him forahbadoy, -but just&#xD;
here conscience put it quite plainly, whether&#xD;
the lad had ever had any chance to be better.&#xD;
Memory, coming to the aid of conscience, hint-&#xD;
to Thomas how bitter it was to be hungry.&#xD;
Ri        ..po. where will all your savings be&#xD;
a hundred' year' ? and soft and earnest the&#xD;
Spiriz cried to him.- Jesus died for sinners."&#xD;
-"What do you want, Ratty?' said Thomas.&#xD;
Won't you let me come an warm by yer&#xD;
furnis?" whined the boy, called '-Ratty' be-&#xD;
cause he was a Wharf Rat-that isafelow&#xD;
picking up his living, generally dishonestly,&#xD;
ab+ut the wharves.&#xD;
Now, Rtaty," said Thomas, "I know you;&#xD;
y-a want to get behind here to grab some&#xD;
thin : 'nit is the word, ain't it, Ratty?  I&#xD;
puts it to you square."&#xD;
.W No 'ta'r" said Jerry, ut he   Led&#xD;
guilty, and began to edge away.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC8382-00000026"/>&#xD;
m conssa ertat;&#xD;
&#xD;
"Hold on," said Thomas, "you're   ni&#xD;
in here, Batty, but you'll fnd no need to&#xD;
'nig'. Here's a kag," says I; "sit down,&#xD;
latty; warm yer toes, and eat a meal. Thom-&#xD;
as Twigg will give you a first fate A. No, I&#xD;
dinner, Jerry Hockner, so walk in."&#xD;
The boy seemed hardly able to believe the&#xD;
word, but when Thomas. held open the little&#xD;
gate that he mizht zet into the stall and cower&#xD;
by one of the small furnaces, he darted to it&#xD;
quickly, as if fearful of such good fortune&#xD;
slipping from him.&#xD;
Thomas took out of the counter the ham&#xD;
bone which he had reserved for his own sup-&#xD;
per, and Jerry receiving it began to gnaw it&#xD;
voraciously; a cup of the black coffee was&#xD;
next offered by Thomas, and then a  m oth&#xD;
biscuit.&#xD;
-. :ow, na, sata ..nomas, atas wnar&#xD;
calls a good square meal. Pardner makes a&#xD;
good biscuit sure as fate; and if there's a man&#xD;
around as can beat that coffee, or a barn a&#xD;
&#xD;
can raise such another bone, my name ain't&#xD;
Thomas Twigg."&#xD;
"I's good, it ar," said Jerry, eating.&#xD;
Thomas' eyes fell on his book, and he bent&#xD;
down and began to read something that had&#xD;
caught his attention ; the wind had turned a&#xD;
few leaves of the little volume, the wind doing&#xD;
the will of that Master, without whose kindly&#xD;
notice not a sparrow fails 'With care and&#xD;
labor Thomas read, re-read to make it plain,&#xD;
and much delighted, cried. "Hark here, Ratty,&#xD;
what do vou say to this 'ere?"&#xD;
' Wo ?" said Jerry, his mouth full.&#xD;
Thomas read slowly, skipping the word&#xD;
'fragments ' as too hard.&#xD;
"'When I brake the five loaves among five&#xD;
-thousand - how many baskets fall of'-.-&#xD;
well, it means bits, I guess, Ratty, 'took ye&#xD;
up ---They say to him twelve.'   There,&#xD;
now, Ratty !"&#xD;
"They must a bin powerful big loaves ef all&#xD;
the filkses was as hungry as I be," said Jedy.&#xD;
&#xD;
«.,. ter...  ~A yye&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC8382-00000027"/>&#xD;
56&#xD;
&#xD;
TfE CnflnRm&#xD;
&#xD;
"Feedin' fre thousands! cried Thomas,&#xD;
with anination1, "that beats all nater ; 'pose&#xD;
somebody did that here,at&#xD;
once a week, say?"&#xD;
Wisht the       p    aid Je&#xD;
done - now; y    o 3"&#xD;
doneflo; I'l g, Mster Twigg ; reckon&#xD;
Wharf Rats a          e   flks, ai     our&#xD;
sort -offcom-      m:-3&#xD;
sort-'ofv - ;  to Ve; what to&#xD;
pay    he       , with an attempt at  in&#xD;
jocular-&#xD;
"There's a gentlemen as  d like to menion&#xD;
you to," said Thomas; mayb he'd g      you&#xD;
a lift, Jerry; you're no: doing well. lad."&#xD;
amt," said Jerry; "but no&#xD;
gentleums fur rnee T'd&#xD;
ic       b  d wn  on me&#xD;
-  d   down on me; good be, Mister&#xD;
Twigg, wislit I was as well off as you he, I&#xD;
do;" and Jerry shambled along the chilly&#xD;
street, a little refreshed hr Mr. T-i-&#xD;
re 'r       r. Twe- ,&#xD;
bountr. but a ver.2   d   h -&#xD;
Jane! cried a clear. chi!djsh Yven-&#xD;
me my ten cent piece!"&#xD;
&#xD;
TEE     SL-Lsra.r&#xD;
&#xD;
"What now, Miss Mary?" said Jane-&#xD;
"Give it to me, Jane," said Mary, imperb&#xD;
ousiy; the maid handed over the money, but&#xD;
just as Jerry was wondering if he could&#xD;
snatch it and run off uncaught, the little lady&#xD;
in green velvet ran up to him crying, "poor&#xD;
boy, here's some money for you ! Come on,&#xD;
Jane, IL go howe now. I've done some good&#xD;
to-day, I've done some good to-ay ;" and so&#xD;
to this sweet tune Mary danced home, her&#xD;
heart as li: as her feet.&#xD;
MagTie, too, went home as evening closed&#xD;
inm; she carried with her part of her sugar&#xD;
plums; she wanted the people at home to&#xD;
share what she thought so nice, and maybe&#xD;
there was a secret feeling that the candy&#xD;
might appease her mother, and avert the&#xD;
threatened whipping, if the money for het&#xD;
Jar's work was-not satisfactory.&#xD;
Maggie need not have feared the whipping.&#xD;
Mrs. IXdd was not a hard woman, and Toma&#xD;
&#xD;
41&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
40OLdwm .&#xD;
nll r&#xD;
ww W-&#xD;
&#xD;
A&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC8382-00000028"/>&#xD;
as TWig's plafor thervender of pickshad&#xD;
been effetual; as Mrs. Dodd bent over her&#xD;
wah tab rubbing with might and main, she&#xD;
soliloquized. "Dear knows it's a hard life for&#xD;
us alL  Maggie is born for rough imes, poor&#xD;
thing. I'll not make it harder, but it's more'n&#xD;
I can tell how we'll live if she don't earn&#xD;
more."&#xD;
As the day closed, Mrs. Dodd got ready her'&#xD;
supper -a cup of weak tea, minus milk and&#xD;
sugar, for herself and prandma Dodd, some&#xD;
cold Johnnie cake,. and its of fried bacon;&#xD;
these, with water in a broken nosed pitcher,&#xD;
made up the supper; just as it was ready&#xD;
Ma   in e in, timidly.&#xD;
"Come to the fire, and warm. child, said&#xD;
Mrs. Dodd, in her usual quick tone. "Here,&#xD;
Teddy, come to mom," she added to her&#xD;
screaming babe; where's your money, Mla-&#xD;
Maggie handed it over, trembling;j her.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
.1&#xD;
&#xD;
mother counted it without a word. "Are ye&#xD;
hungry?" she said.&#xD;
" es'm," said Maggie, "only Mr. T&#xD;
give  nE a turnover, an' such a picter of a&#xD;
little gal give me some goodies, I brung some&#xD;
home ; " and standing near the small fire, she&#xD;
drew out her candy. "Some for Teddy, an'&#xD;
you, u granme,   he said.&#xD;
Mrs. Dodd looked at her keenly.&#xD;
"Tell me the truth, child ; did ye stal it?"&#xD;
she demanded.&#xD;
"No, I didn't steal; I'm afraid of the per-&#xD;
lice to steai,'" sobbed Maggie ; "it were give&#xD;
to me it were, by a little picter of a gal all&#xD;
dressed splendid, it w:ere.&#xD;
"Where did vou see her?" asked Mrs.&#xD;
Dodd.&#xD;
Up Br'way. by a winder, an' ge thunk&#xD;
the picks were tuany, an she buyed one, she&#xD;
did."&#xD;
V Weli, well, nuh  up crying. I b'lieve ye.&#xD;
&#xD;
r-p&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC8382-00000029"/>&#xD;
-s  N wrxt..&#xD;
&#xD;
TUE CO RE STALL..&#xD;
&#xD;
Teddy take his pretty candy from Maggie.&#xD;
Give grannie a bit; there th&#xD;
meb; make Wy with the rest fore your dad&#xD;
comes in.&#xD;
was Maggies home coming, and short-&#xD;
Jy she was asleep by Teddy&#xD;
When Mary gave Jerry Ilockney the ten&#xD;
cenit pice h eoo&#xD;
open mouthed wonder.&#xD;
";Here's a run of luck  said Jerry; there's&#xD;
are centttaa&#xD;
flvecen, thf, AA11, ere's tire cent, thar's&#xD;
breffu  -jolr r me&#xD;
Of course nith  th              e&#xD;
&amp;amp;st were very i  airs, but the Whaff Rat&#xD;
Was not OVer particular.&#xD;
Thmas Twi-in,&#xD;
s sa, ate his supper&#xD;
a any small remnants that had been left that&#xD;
day," and menwil          v-&#xD;
aMry Stuyvest and her&#xD;
laid got home, and Mary ate   r six o'clock&#xD;
dinner.  Then it was dark&#xD;
.;"tedtheparor~, a ra , th  g"&#xD;
h hted, the parlors were Warm and bright; at&#xD;
r.S   i't'e't'. s necoud hardly remember.&#xD;
&#xD;
that poverty and misery were any where in&#xD;
the world.&#xD;
Mr. Aliston was a young man, and early&#xD;
that evening went out to call on a young&#xD;
lady; he was ushered into Mr. Stuyvesant's&#xD;
parlor, and presently Miss Laura Stv esant.&#xD;
came down to see him.     Miss Laura was&#xD;
Mary's aunt, and Mary, who always ctimed&#xD;
the. privilege of aing Mr. Alton, came into&#xD;
the drawing room   with her.  While Miss&#xD;
Laura occupied a luxurious chair conveniently&#xD;
near the drop ght and register, and conversed&#xD;
very easily and agreeaiby Mary went close to&#xD;
Mr. Aliston's ide and stood with her dark eyes&#xD;
fixed earnestly on his face; shc knew he would&#xD;
talk to her presently.  Sure enough Mr.&#xD;
Aliston said, "Well. Mary, hW is it to-day ?&#xD;
have you done ango&#xD;
r4   n "  x2ar1 ,-0IV-  7== -&#xD;
a  tes," ried Mary, ju ously,  &amp;amp; g ave some&#xD;
andy to a poor little girl, a very poor girl all&#xD;
rags, and it made her look so gad. I wish I&#xD;
&#xD;
p,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC8382-00000030"/>&#xD;
Ta                                                                isaewmsraLw&#xD;
&#xD;
w who she was; can't your tell me, Mr.&#xD;
Ailston. She wasjustas big asIa nsand se&#xD;
bad an old hood, and a box of little picks.&#xD;
Do you know her?"&#xD;
"    ,Mary thinks yon know wall thoor peo-&#xD;
ple," said her aunt Laura, smiling.&#xD;
"Do you know who she is .t" urged Mary.&#xD;
"Yes, and n," sai Mr. Aiistun.&#xD;
"That is a funny answer; what does it&#xD;
mean ?" said Mary.&#xD;
"I know she is one uf God's poor," said&#xD;
Mr. Aliston.&#xD;
" tavbe she's had," said Mary.&#xD;
"The Lord makes no exception; he says&#xD;
Comfort ye the poor my people,' he does nut&#xD;
add, 'if they are groud".&#xD;
Then she isn't trash," said Mary.&#xD;
"Certainly not," said Mr. Allston.&#xD;
"Jane called her that, and made her cry,"&#xD;
id Mary,&#xD;
"Jane," said aunt Laura, to Mr. Aliston,&#xD;
&#xD;
S      exemplifies the Proverbs of Solomon, con-&#xD;
cerning the things which the earth canm&#xD;
bear, 'a servant when he reigneth,' 'and a&#xD;
maid that is heir to her mistress.' I find ner&#xD;
vants are apt to be very hard on that ame&#xD;
poor class from which they themselves came."&#xD;
.I hope you told Jane bow to speak more&#xD;
properly, Mary," said Mr. Allston.&#xD;
I told her to -hush up,'" said Mary.&#xD;
Perhaps I can find out the child's name&#xD;
for you, said Mr. Aliston.&#xD;
"I'gave ten cents to an awful poor boy,"&#xD;
sad Mary.&#xD;
"Im  afraid von are teaching Mary r&#xD;
miscuous and thoughtless giving, said aunt&#xD;
Laura.&#xD;
To cultivate the generous impulse is a&#xD;
great thing," rejpied Mr. Allston; "we shall&#xD;
have to teach her next how to dd good judb&#xD;
ciouslv. How would you like to take some&#xD;
poor little girl for your protege, Mary, to help&#xD;
her and he kind to her."&#xD;
&#xD;
1&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC8382-00000031"/>&#xD;
Uk AKsna&#xD;
&#xD;
vim AoSS-sa,£&#xD;
&#xD;
Oh, splendid!" said Mary, dancing about;&#xD;
"I'd give her clothes and pennies, and send&#xD;
her tochool V"&#xD;
"Miss rMar," said Jane, kooking in the&#xD;
oor, " will you please come to bed, it'E timie."&#xD;
"Good night!  cried Mar-; "be sure fand&#xD;
find me a lite girl&#xD;
How is your pupil on Union Square pro-&#xD;
gressing?" asked Miss Sturvesant.&#xD;
&amp;amp; He improves; he is quite an oddity, and&#xD;
interest me a good deal.&#xD;
"I mean to walk up there and see him,"&#xD;
said Miss Laura.&#xD;
"1 daresar you would be amused with&#xD;
him.&#xD;
"To tell the truth,' said Miss Laura, "I'm&#xD;
tired of doing good just bysubscriptions to&#xD;
iharmti, and by a visit to a  il or hospital&#xD;
cow and then. There must be active work-&#xD;
ers in the workd, and I want to be tne of&#xD;
them.  ttur  Saviour w alk d  a d  p&#xD;
the gospel to the -poor, binding up broken&#xD;
&#xD;
N&#xD;
&#xD;
spirits, and ministering to suffering bodies, but&#xD;
how very few of us follow in his steps. To&#xD;
day I have thought what an idler I am. I&#xD;
hare health, strength, money and time, and&#xD;
what do I for my Lord. I mean to go out&#xD;
into the bre-places of the earth to labor for&#xD;
the king.   Yet - I don't know   where to&#xD;
be i&amp;amp;n&#xD;
'Concentrate your energies on some special&#xD;
w ork, find some particular corner and labor in&#xD;
said Mr. Allstn. "1, thank the Lord&#xD;
that it has been put into your heart to labor&#xD;
zealously for him.&#xD;
Tell me where I shall beg:n' said Miss&#xD;
Laura. "This morning I came     this verse&#xD;
in my reading. - \Vhy  tand ye Lure all the&#xD;
td   _ idle. awl I have resulrvd to be idle no&#xD;
loger. ftr I know the i:me will come, when&#xD;
the Master of the Vineyard shall take account&#xD;
of his servants. Tell me of some place where&#xD;
I can go among the poor and teach and help&#xD;
them."&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC8382-00000032"/>&#xD;
'Tn x SAL&#xD;
&#xD;
Mr Allston thought a mnoent, then said,&#xD;
"It has come quite strongly into my mind,&#xD;
MissLaura, that you may find good work to&#xD;
do in the house where my Union Square&#xD;
pupil lives. I will visit the house and bring&#xD;
you my report."&#xD;
"Thank von, I wish vo would do so," said&#xD;
Miss Laura.&#xD;
"II am to preach in a newsboy's room, at&#xD;
nine o'clock this evening,"- said Mr. Allston,&#xD;
rising. " I find the boys run the streets until&#xD;
pretty late, with their papers. and I appointed&#xD;
some late meeting this week to get in a few&#xD;
fellows that think they have no: time to come&#xD;
early."&#xD;
"I hope rou will tave an attentive audi-&#xD;
ence," said Miss Laura.&#xD;
"I hope I shall have a benefitted audience,"&#xD;
replied Mr. Aliston.&#xD;
"At all events you will be benefitted rour-&#xD;
self," said Miss Laurz "for we read that 'he&#xD;
that watereth shall be watered also himself.&#xD;
&#xD;
$4&#xD;
&#xD;
As in the buds of some powers the leaves&#xD;
are rolled and twisted one upon another from&#xD;
the inmost to the outmost, so in human l,&#xD;
from lowest poverty to highest station, the&#xD;
individuals touch upon each other, the poor&#xD;
man's misery grazing the edges of the rich&#xD;
wan's abundance. There are two promises fir&#xD;
always' one, "So I am with you always,&#xD;
the other,  The poor have ye away with&#xD;
you." Let us succor the poor for his sake&#xD;
whose presence our souls desire.&#xD;
&#xD;
WAMW&#xD;
&#xD;
,"&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="68" xml:id="VAC8382-00000033"/>&#xD;
CHAPTER     III.&#xD;
ALL Fox .JESUS.&#xD;
T   r.    bn    n   service might&#xD;
hjavl bee      ;;;t, in a corner. Thomas&#xD;
Twigu, his hampwrs dp lt1e at his&#xD;
feet, hiamelf Vat forward, Is eager eves fixed&#xD;
on the speaker. The serc . enled. home&#xD;
went Thomas ; his baskets, bein2 nearly empty,&#xD;
impeded hima but little.&#xD;
Once ii his attc, the hamprs hung up with&#xD;
his hat abve them, the pbian walked abuut&#xD;
his room, kooking at -all his little helmjging,&#xD;
and then, rubbing his hands, said to himnef&#xD;
with a chuckle, "Its banking hours. I gues&#xD;
68&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="Illustration-69" xml:id="VAC8382-00000034"/>&#xD;
L                _-     r             e-C :=S&#xD;
r^w                                  m ° . .,&#xD;
y          _-~&#xD;
eC; "A  4,. yie&#xD;
S Y I' E&#xD;
'u r..%^.x     -&#xD;
od&#xD;
&#xD;
raktng Bwm.rsgr w-&#xD;
&#xD;
..y cor  er&#xD;
&#xD;
U&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
we'll unlock the vaults, and hau  over the&#xD;
silver and gold."&#xD;
He took his poker from the ehimiey and&#xD;
pried up a briek from  the fire place,th&#xD;
removed another easily with his hand, and Jo!&#xD;
revealed a little square tin-lined space, Thomas&#xD;
Twigs hank     of deposit, where were  h&#xD;
careful savings, the well loved two hundred&#xD;
dollars.  His Tee glowed with satisfttion&#xD;
heholdi:nz it; he felt like a rich man; he was&#xD;
not a sinner; he liked to be comfortable in his&#xD;
own way, and as we have seen, he could an&#xD;
ocasin rive away a meal to a hungry chld,&#xD;
but he loved his money next to himself;&#xD;
taken what was a large sum to him to s'a.&#xD;
Corner Stall with all its equipments; and h&#xD;
realtv this, what he had in hand, was the&#xD;
saving of Ufty years. it gave him a feeling&#xD;
of importance, and what wonder that he val-&#xD;
ued it. He counted it over, dollar by dollar,&#xD;
delighting in the clink of the pieces against&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC8382-00000035"/>&#xD;
each other, for this was before currency times.&#xD;
"Two hundred dollars, them's your finances,&#xD;
Thomas Twi       - your a moneyed man von&#xD;
ae --         a.-u  s  Fsa  r ar&#xD;
are ; yocould buy ot tis establishment 'n&#xD;
could; yes, two hundred good solid donars,&#xD;
and -now I see my war to Iavin  Up a little&#xD;
more every week.    Whcn pardner and me&#xD;
dmde  th   :mnti    i  a i a  yive to that?-&#xD;
Then ito h     md caen the text of the&#xD;
e veing, othat sermn n :he valuec of the&#xD;
soul,$-- What Ihal2 a man  v :n e"xchanze for&#xD;
his soul.&#xD;
He put the :noher safev away, and sat with&#xD;
hbis hand&amp;amp; rn I: knexw andI hi' head drope&#xD;
forward. lHe :1uaht a I n; time, then with&#xD;
a sigh he roe, Iavin: half aoud  Xell ifi's&#xD;
all true, Thomas Twio'&amp;amp;s soul mut be an&#xD;
uneeamon yo.r ca#.&#xD;
Mr. AllSton had not asked him to renew the&#xD;
promise to pray, out the Spirit f God was&#xD;
strivim  with him. and overpowered by a sense&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
'I&#xD;
I.&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
bf hishelpess need, T   a   l    L&#xD;
lifting up a prayer very much like that of the&#xD;
publican of ol; he cred, Lord, help Thomas&#xD;
Twig; ' and upward sped his prayer into the&#xD;
ear that is never heavy.&#xD;
Thomas had cried for" help ; so Peter tried,&#xD;
smkimg, and help eame at once ; the cry for&#xD;
help is a cry that Jesus delig  to hear and&#xD;
answ r: hep came to Thomas from that hour;&#xD;
his wImeo nature seemed quickened his ener-&#xD;
received a new direction, he bent his&#xD;
mind earnestly to the study of the word of&#xD;
Go     and Mr. Allston, his faithful teacher,&#xD;
was surprised and deizhted at the quicknen&#xD;
ith whin he became a very tolerable reader,&#xD;
and the readiness with which he appreciated&#xD;
and applied the Divine Truth. The Bible&#xD;
was no longer a sealed book. Thomas had no&#xD;
more to skip words because they were hard or&#xD;
long ; to be sure he miscalled many proper&#xD;
names,: but he could re and understand.&#xD;
&#xD;
,.&#xD;
&#xD;
)&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC8382-00000036"/>&#xD;
Mr. Alston helped him, and explained to him&#xD;
some, hut he had a more efficient teacher,&#xD;
even the Holy Teacher, who dwells in the&#xD;
hearts of the chosen.&#xD;
Of Saul of Tarsus the Lord said "he is a&#xD;
chosen vessel unto me: ;' so was Thomas Twigg&#xD;
a chosen vessel. Saul was chosen 1for a high&#xD;
and shining track, like that of some grand&#xD;
planet set in heaven, but Thomas was like the&#xD;
little lamp chosen to shine clearly and steadily&#xD;
in an bumble place. Star and lamp alike ful-&#xD;
flling His will who ruleth all, shall alike be&#xD;
set-around the brightness of the. Land above.&#xD;
He who penned the Chronices of Israel&#xD;
and Judah, dwells not always on the names&#xD;
of the mighty; he writes -- There were pot-&#xD;
ters, and those that dwelt amid plants and&#xD;
hedges; there they dwelt with the king for&#xD;
his work."&#xD;
Like these lowly servants of Solomon, who&#xD;
labored in may, and in hedging and  itching,&#xD;
&#xD;
I1&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
is&#xD;
&#xD;
are some men of little worldly knowledge or&#xD;
station, who toil for Jesus among the outcast&#xD;
and the vile, who succor paupers and criminals&#xD;
and world-forgotten ones  they labor for the&#xD;
King. Jesus himself is with them. Despise&#xD;
not one f these little ones, for Jesus sets their&#xD;
good names in the Chronicles of Jerusalem&#xD;
the Gaden. The Lard will not forget the&#xD;
labors of love in the lowliest places: let no one&#xD;
say he can do nothing, for the Lord "increas-&#xD;
eth strenzih to them tht have no might,"&#xD;
and give:b more aun lant honor to those that&#xD;
lack. Here is Thomas Twigg, uulearned, un-&#xD;
kuu.vn, ol poor,but he goes from strength&#xD;
to strength, doing the work of Jesus, an hum-&#xD;
ble uncommissoned evangeist. But not yet.&#xD;
A week passed away; Maggie went on as&#xD;
usual, only that twice she and her old grand-&#xD;
mother had to fir out into the cold dreary night.&#xD;
from the drunken rage of George Dodd, the&#xD;
son and father. Jerry came nomore to Thom&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC8382-00000037"/>&#xD;
IL&#xD;
&#xD;
T&#xD;
&#xD;
,' cons stL&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
ER,&#xD;
&#xD;
as. Mrs. Kiligan, as she had promised, kept&#xD;
an eye on Thomas," but the result of her&#xD;
superrision was conveyed to the pie-man5 in&#xD;
he remark, "0th, but re're a jewei of a e&#xD;
to the business. Thumas-, me man. Shure, its&#xD;
a mortal pity ye rant let well enough alone,&#xD;
and not be takin' after books at your time of&#xD;
Never fret, pardner7. said Thomas grave-&#xD;
yu t Im ,juas!tettingV myiV ee .&#xD;
Holy Virit !' cried Mrs. Kllican "is it&#xD;
so?  Fur a blind man Ye ve iia'ie yr way&#xD;
most amnazing hat yer worse rir the little pup-&#xD;
pies, Thoma ; they gets their eves open in&#xD;
ten Jars, an' er goiu on for sixty years."&#xD;
Its better late nor never, savs Thomas&#xD;
Twig.    It' no use crying for spilt milk!&#xD;
What's done's done, pardner; but new ways&#xD;
for me now. This very day I read in the&#xD;
Psalms of David, Open my eyes that I may&#xD;
behold wonderous things out of thy love ;'&#xD;
that's the talk for Thomas TwiggY&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
Ii&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
iE COfNER STALL.&#xD;
." Faith," said the practical Mrs. Killigan,&#xD;
"if ye'll lock down Broadway, ye'! see plenty&#xD;
of wonderous things widoat fashing herself&#xD;
to do fhirde."&#xD;
" Pardiner," said Thomnas. sulemnnlv, " thats&#xD;
a big word,  eternity.'&#xD;
S Oh  but it  i  ;  ig t:or  Becky  Kiligan&#xD;
to 5peM. It's mnesel will have nune of it."&#xD;
- Thre waS a yung2 lady by yr stall to-&#xD;
dlay, "aid Thoa  ;  he wast one of the zrand&#xD;
folk. I u     by her way and her dress ; but&#xD;
am u' (odeen i. hner voic   wxer n't sweeter&#xD;
man any iusic lever heard, ani her lace was&#xD;
that lr 'aut iul-&#xD;
Never uiid th2 bauty. Thoumas," said&#xD;
Mrs. Kiigain. - What did Ah tuy&#xD;
"She didn't buy anything,  begar Thomas,&#xD;
Sbuit--&#xD;
'Iii care nnue for her, then," interrapted&#xD;
Mrs. Killigan.&#xD;
but she said, 'You're reading the best of&#xD;
&#xD;
t  n&#xD;
I  'i&#xD;
&#xD;
.1&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC8382-00000038"/>&#xD;
S&#xD;
&#xD;
Tarconstt&#xD;
&#xD;
Mr. Tw4     I hope the Lord will bkss&#xD;
it to you.'"&#xD;
"Pooh, pooh," said Mrs. Killigan.&#xD;
"Say she, ' Mr. Twigg, I think Hi call on&#xD;
your partner, some day ; what is her name?'&#xD;
She's Becky Kihligan, pardner is. says I-"&#xD;
"Well, let -her come," said Mrs. Killigan,&#xD;
"an'Ill tell her my victuals is good enoughi&#xD;
for any body's buying."&#xD;
"You wont tell her anvthing but what's&#xD;
nice, when you see her, I"ll be bound," said&#xD;
Thomas.&#xD;
"What's to hinder." said Mrs. Killigan. deo&#xD;
6antly, setntm  her brawny arms a-kimbo,&#xD;
"The good Book tells me, 'a soft answer&#xD;
turns away wrath, so I'll not answer you back,&#xD;
pardner," said Thomas, caml.&#xD;
"Saints alive, man, you'll know the book,&#xD;
whatever it is, bh earth soon," cried the old&#xD;
woman.&#xD;
I wish I might. I read it is -'a lamp t&amp;amp;&#xD;
the feet and a light to the path.'&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
I.&#xD;
Si"&#xD;
T:&#xD;
&#xD;
k&#xD;
&#xD;
ft&#xD;
&#xD;
"Turrul lurul" said )rs; Kligr&#xD;
"I'd rather have a lanther - or the gas."&#xD;
"I daresay von might, until the Lord&#xD;
opened your wind, Pardner, but the 'enter&#xD;
ance of His worse gives light,'i&#xD;
ple folk like us wonderful&#xD;
says, * the words are sweet&#xD;
'Give me the honey,"        rs Killigan.&#xD;
"I've lived my own way with none of your&#xD;
nonsense this fifty year, Thomas Twig, and&#xD;
it's a god enough way to live by.&#xD;
But is it a good enough way to die bys?"&#xD;
said the $e-mnan.&#xD;
rrab I cannot tell ; the word ' die' is&#xD;
miserable.&#xD;
So I thought, but dyings got to come; so&#xD;
be a man, ad get ready. Says I to Thomas&#xD;
Tw'i---Thomas, me man, You can't live for.&#xD;
ever iii this world. But if there's a life after&#xD;
dying and a god road to it, look about and&#xD;
put yourseII to-get in u, Tunas.&#xD;
&#xD;
4:&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC8382-00000039"/>&#xD;
Tao&#xD;
&#xD;
THE        STA&#xD;
&#xD;
"And what is the raad ?" asked Mars. Kl.&#xD;
ligan-&#xD;
"The book tells me," said Thomas,   that&#xD;
Jesus Christ is 'the life, the truth, the war,'&#xD;
and he that uets in hihn shall dwell safev and&#xD;
be  . from fear of evil."&#xD;
"Land alive,   said Mrs. Killigan,  how&#xD;
can Vou remember it all?&#xD;
"1 set my  into it; when I read a b, I&#xD;
say Lord, help Thomas T wi: to remember&#xD;
that and 1I can't justy explam how it i but&#xD;
those words I read sticking my in  when I«&#xD;
get to  b di a:  night I  ovr  jt all, and  fit this&#xD;
and that to everything about me. Seemb iUke&#xD;
as if  A ead was full of lt  pes, and I1&#xD;
bang up the idees on thorn, ard there is each&#xD;
one fitr and square, ready fo use just when&#xD;
there Wti.&#xD;
"  none of your pecs I want in Inmr&#xD;
head, said Mrs. Kiligan; "get out wid ye,&#xD;
yi   ermug crater tar ye are; lye. my baking"&#xD;
to do.&#xD;
&#xD;
V&#xD;
rs&#xD;
I&#xD;
Ik&#xD;
I&#xD;
jj?&#xD;
a5&#xD;
&#xD;
..- s&#xD;
&#xD;
Thomas was quite in despair over hi rrt-&#xD;
&#xD;
ner.&#xD;
It was now the end of May. Miss Laura&#xD;
had not been able to visit the house where&#xD;
Mr. Twigg lved, and try to help ana&#xD;
the inmates, for her sister-iaw, Mary's&#xD;
mother, had been very ill, and home duties&#xD;
had muiplied. But now the invalid was eon-&#xD;
valesei, ishe sat Up in her chair, and -talked&#xD;
Of  "ok n  ginI  into the  country  or  th , - n&#xD;
So ne day Miss Laura and her little niece set&#xD;
out t viit No. :27 the house where Th&#xD;
lived.&#xD;
Mary Stuyvesaint hadl been sorely disap-&#xD;
oted about her little " pick girl7.  She saw&#xD;
her no more on the streets, and Mr. AlIston&#xD;
had not boon aide to find out the poor child's&#xD;
name ; he had nut thought to speak to Thomas&#xD;
about it. Now Mary was soon to go into the&#xD;
country- and though she was trying,    an&#xD;
L   -t An all the cood she could,&#xD;
earnest conn ~ 14  ~ - -    e&#xD;
&#xD;
A&#xD;
&#xD;
MM&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC8382-00000040"/>&#xD;
she wanted very much 4i nd some special&#xD;
object for her charity, and she had set her&#xD;
heart on the little " pick girl."'&#xD;
On this afternoon Mary' went cheerull&#xD;
with her at on he 1r errand of love, and as&#xD;
she went she said, -Oih, aunt Laura, wouldn't&#xD;
it be nice if I could find njy little girl to-day&#xD;
Yes it would, but if you do not, yon will&#xD;
fnd some little girl to be kind to, for Jesus'&#xD;
sake. See, Marv, what a dreadful looking&#xD;
place it is down that narrow street."&#xD;
That is Ju; Alley," said a podiceman, who&#xD;
stood on the sweet corner. and hear .Miss&#xD;
ura speak.  -I hope von   are nat ginug&#xD;
there, ma'am; they're a rough set.&#xD;
"We are looking for No. 2T," said Miss&#xD;
Stuyvesant.&#xD;
6       --&#xD;
Two doors below, na'am, that aint so&#xD;
bad," said the officer, who considered it a very&#xD;
refreshing incident in his day's work to see&#xD;
and spek With such anelegant young&#xD;
Miss Laura Stuyvesant.&#xD;
&#xD;
A'&#xD;
F&#xD;
* j&#xD;
&#xD;
Miss Laura and her little niece went a&#xD;
few steps, when Mary darted any from&#xD;
aunt's hand, crying, "Oh, here she is, ant&#xD;
lAIy, here is mr very own little girt  Oh,&#xD;
what's the matter with you! look at her poor&#xD;
little face ;&#xD;
Pappy did it," sobbed poor Maggie, who,&#xD;
when discovered 'y Mary, had been leaning&#xD;
against a lamp post, looking absently at the&#xD;
sluggish black water slipping along the gutter.&#xD;
"Oh, aunt Lolly, do look at my poor little&#xD;
girl," cried the compassionate Mary; "why,&#xD;
girl, ve furzut roar name, but I've looked&#xD;
for von so much. Where have yon ken, and&#xD;
where are your pretty picks ?"&#xD;
Thev'r all broke,' said Maggie, crying&#xD;
bitterly now, as her misfortanes came up fully&#xD;
before her.&#xD;
"Tell us all about it," said Miss Laura,&#xD;
kindly.&#xD;
"It's the whiskey did it," said Maggie- "it&#xD;
&#xD;
VI&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC8382-00000041"/>&#xD;
U     tatCeaNn eral&#xD;
&#xD;
4=&#xD;
&#xD;
does every thing. I wish there wasn't any I&#xD;
do. Pappy got raging' drunk, an' he knocked&#xD;
Inc with a chair and made this," and Maggie&#xD;
pointed to her discolored cheek. "He turned&#xD;
grannie out o doors. an' he fu't nmom, an' he&#xD;
threw down mv box and stamped on all my&#xD;
picks, an' he grabbed Teddy an' broke his&#xD;
little arm--oh dear, oh dear:s&#xD;
Over Marys soft cheeks the tears f svmpa-.&#xD;
thy were fbowinv fXst while  Mis Laura's&#xD;
brilliant eves flashed with indination at the&#xD;
man who would thus make a brute Sf himen,AK&#xD;
at the deal  iealii villians% wii sell the&#xD;
prison. at the ind which cannot frame laws&#xD;
that shall be an egis of defence fr weary&#xD;
Wires, helpless babes, and aged mothers.&#xD;
"And have vou no friends?" asked Miss&#xD;
Laura-&#xD;
" Mr. Twigg he come an' cot pappy, an' the&#xD;
perlie nabbed pappy too, but he broke ol an'&#xD;
ain't been back sin'. It's three dars now.&#xD;
&#xD;
x&#xD;
14&#xD;
-  ;F&#xD;
a..r&#xD;
6&#xD;
It&#xD;
3ri&#xD;
&#xD;
C .&#xD;
&#xD;
tilt MiRESflALI___           z_&#xD;
Mr. Twigg give mom s           ya&#xD;
grannieS knitting to the store. Mr. Twig's&#xD;
very kind, Miss, bat mom's cean wore&#xD;
"We will be your friends ; take us into we&#xD;
our       t    said Miss  tuvesant whie&#xD;
the kind Mary, not despising to take Maggie&#xD;
t tile hand, whispered, "you'll have some&#xD;
money, and some clothes, and lots of nice&#xD;
things now.'&#xD;
in the hal of. .. ., A.s LaUrIa met an&#xD;
old woman whom she at once recognized, from&#xD;
the description given by Mr. Allston.&#xD;
Is this Mrs. Kiliican ? she asked.&#xD;
True fr ye," said the dame, "an' Pm&#xD;
thinkin' this is the beautiful young lady Thom-&#xD;
as tells about."&#xD;
Miss Laura blushed crimson, and Mrs. Kil-&#xD;
lgan, looking at her in undisguised admira-&#xD;
tion, said,&#xD;
"Share it's a true tale he's after telling ;&#xD;
' oudd ye plase to walk in, my room's tidy if it&#xD;
ain't fine."&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC8382-00000042"/>&#xD;
 kyou  said Mis Laura, "I would&#xD;
ke to get a little advice from you. Coimen&#xD;
y     Mar this little girl come in, too, Mrs.&#xD;
"Indeed she may." said Mrs. Killigan, but.&#xD;
hug about for chairs, her heart completely won&#xD;
by the young lady's gentleness.&#xD;
"I have been taIkmn to his little irl, said&#xD;
Miss Laura, and te tells me a very ri tonrv,&#xD;
 I     ntt in n.&amp;amp; Vn v4at kind o naren&#xD;
she has, and what had better be done for&#xD;
them"&#xD;
Faith, miss, it's a sorry case, said Mrs.&#xD;
Kiligan;  her grannie has seen pretty good&#xD;
days, but she's simple now ; and the child's&#xD;
step-mother is a hard-working, honest body as&#xD;
is to be found. The father is. lazy, but when&#xD;
the drink ain't in him, he's that mild and&#xD;
meek as a sheep ; but once the whiskey gets&#xD;
hold of him, he's like a ragin' lion. He made&#xD;
bad work dh other nght. The woman is just&#xD;
heart-sick, for her baby's arm is broke. They&#xD;
&#xD;
'4&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
I&#xD;
I,&#xD;
S&#xD;
4    4&#xD;
- C&#xD;
U&#xD;
&#xD;
would hare been turned out, only fir&#xD;
He Pad the tent and got a bushel of coaL&#xD;
said he was a fool to be after giving his money,&#xD;
but I give them a couple of loaves meeseif, af-&#xD;
ther "at"&#xD;
n ; n.. fose there need most everything ? "&#xD;
They need cheering up and' encouraging,&#xD;
most of all, miss. A gC-d word from. ye would&#xD;
do a weift of oodx; and thrue for ye, Victu-&#xD;
als tor mo.ey would n't corn amiss, but it's&#xD;
work she wanVts mosYtly.&#xD;
Thank you, Mrs. i i; :11 lgo in and&#xD;
see her    ,   1aid Mi  Laura:; and  e followed&#xD;
Magie into the rionm above,. Mrs. Killigan not&#xD;
hesitating to couLe after.&#xD;
Thie room of Mr. Ddd was clean, hut its&#xD;
broken furnitureA. and the sd faces of its suf-&#xD;
tvring inmats w.~:e tcaken of the stonn of&#xD;
drunken wrath:. tat had i.swept through it. The&#xD;
distressed infan t ar mnoaninz  n his mother's&#xD;
lai by the wiiwbiw the old grandmother knitw&#xD;
tinz and sghing.&#xD;
&#xD;
9 i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC8382-00000043"/>&#xD;
'St&#xD;
&#xD;
ie"nidlittle M            , "here's&#xD;
best young lady, and this was Mrs. aura's&#xD;
Miss Laura did not hold herself loftily aloof&#xD;
1h  some nnopsuprtIr  rtrea' th 'nfer rn-°&#xD;
merited favors; but with a woman's tender&#xD;
sympathy for a sister woman, she sat down byr&#xD;
Mrs. Dodd, looked ftanklv in her eves. laid&#xD;
her soft hand on the restess baby's head, and&#xD;
path'. protkrcd ther aid in the war of one&#xD;
who finds highest happiness in making others&#xD;
bappy: and cheered the despondent heart with&#xD;
he hope of higher things to come.&#xD;
"IWe usen't to be iike this," said old Mrs.&#xD;
Dodd, catching the word of better days,&#xD;
"when pappy Dodd war livin'; he was a right&#xD;
straight. go ahead. up and down business man.&#xD;
He kept a stand by the wharf, and he made a&#xD;
good living for us, but George's got astray. he&#xD;
drinks, and pappy Dodd never touched a drop.&#xD;
Pappy Dodd give good evidence and -died lik&#xD;
&#xD;
I'&#xD;
*a&#xD;
&#xD;
. _      ..,  ,&#xD;
&#xD;
ej:&#xD;
&#xD;
a good man; he's got to glorylknow; hope&#xD;
%i rget there t.&#xD;
"I hope you will," said -Miss Laura, well&#xD;
pleased ; "and I hope in al then tradda van&#xD;
will turn to Jaesus who can feel for you, and&#xD;
comfort von. He will not suffer vou to be&#xD;
* tried more than vou can hear. Trust in him."&#xD;
"I ain't going to trust in nnthinz else;&#xD;
pappy Dodld didn't" said the old lady, wh&amp;amp;'&#xD;
Iin'rr r  'tr Liat.  h ~ n&#xD;
* r -     tI.;.% ,twX - aaz'11 -4 ~''t^4-1' 1 _  s&#xD;
Don't do you much good," said Mrs. Kit-&#xD;
Iian4 in a wh ijper. as h stood in the door.&#xD;
Mrs. Kiiligan. ~aid the delightful Laura,&#xD;
I want you to bring up some of your good&#xD;
meat and bread for Mrs. Dodd, that much,"&#xD;
she added, holding out a dollar till; "and now&#xD;
*        Mrs. Dodd, let Magzie come home with us for&#xD;
Sa while  Good bye," - and as Miss Laura&#xD;
rose, she put a folded bank note in the lady's&#xD;
I      hand.   On the stairs she met-sMrs. Killigan&#xD;
laden with provisions.&#xD;
&#xD;
'&#xD;
&#xD;
_-  .&#xD;
_  _;&#xD;
: . :&#xD;
.... .=&#xD;
. ..&#xD;
- '   -   4,&#xD;
- - -.  ;&#xD;
_    _        °&#xD;
hV-  . .&#xD;
.      I       r&#xD;
-     Y&#xD;
rti&#xD;
f       i.&#xD;
"          ' .   1{'yvl5j&#xD;
+ '&#xD;
&#xD;
R,-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC8382-00000044"/>&#xD;
TxE STALL&#xD;
If ye'T give me yer numbes Miss," said&#xD;
the dame, "Ill step up that way an' walk&#xD;
home with the bit child; she's too young to&#xD;
come back with what ye might give her&#xD;
there's folks might snatch it."&#xD;
Home went Miss Stuyvesant and Marv&#xD;
Maggrie following .&#xD;
If Maggi' went out with her new acquait-&#xD;
ances feecin: lhet'uh 2he rvzurned with Mrs.&#xD;
Kilhgau teihn: y~vytui. Cingi jtme 'Aue had&#xD;
on a dress that had lbenr Mary, fcarrwd unidr&#xD;
her arm her A I itrk wrapp I up, an] in h r&#xD;
hand a lb   t. xn rem were AI:1 1 m+te  .:ht-&#xD;
gowns and ,mrts fr -Teday.  n iy .mn fouIr&#xD;
tandae    ttr the aikdtcd arm,  a viai . Lax&#xD;
water to bae the lIttl   uferr' had,, and&#xD;
crackers, oran  , rwe and I )  1  telnpt hjs&#xD;
appetite. M   . Kan;an very winnv Ieied&#xD;
Ma   ',:b car;yin  a handle wherein was a&#xD;
Van'ett  t 'ot:s for Ma xf, and, thou;a.&#xD;
unknown It Mrs. liian, a Bible, which&#xD;
&#xD;
'I&#xD;
F'a&#xD;
&#xD;
s&#xD;
k&#xD;
4 '&#xD;
/.&#xD;
0^h&#xD;
w&#xD;
&#xD;
Maggie was to tel her mother and grand-&#xD;
mother to read.   Mrs. Killigan was kind&#xD;
enough in her way, and she heartily rejoiced&#xD;
in tis succor for the Dodd family, especially&#xD;
as she flattered hersif she had some hand in&#xD;
bringing it about.&#xD;
She was a Zrssipv old body, and must needs&#xD;
wavTh Tm       w     'zg, when he came hone&#xD;
from his stall, and tell him the events of the&#xD;
dax. Sitting on the lowest step of the third&#xD;
flight of stairs he had to traverse, Mr. Twig&#xD;
listened attentivelv to Mrs. Killigan's evidence,&#xD;
and cave his v erdit as tfixws:-&#xD;
"That's religion, pardner ; 't ain  north x&#xD;
else.&#xD;
Fiddie-dedee, man," said Mrs. Killigan,&#xD;
ve lay evvrythinc, any wars  oodto reli&#xD;
-Y   -   -    .  -       -4W&#xD;
And there's very little decent that isn't to&#xD;
Le laid to it, parduer ; not much good comes&#xD;
"at of the natural heart. Did you ever a&#xD;
many rich folks like this young lady?"&#xD;
&#xD;
1/&#xD;
&#xD;
__&#xD;
%,;'&#xD;
r .,,&#xD;
;., ;&#xD;
&#xD;
~ ,'a&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC8382-00000045"/>&#xD;
M    CORNERL sm-&#xD;
&#xD;
"Thre for ye, I didn't; she's a jewel, ev-&#xD;
"And she's one of the Lord's jewels, mind&#xD;
 ye, ardner. She's tot religion in her heart,&#xD;
and that's the way it grows out."&#xD;
",And have you religion, - Thomas, me&#xD;
man?"&#xD;
*I can't jusy tell, parduer," said Thimas,&#xD;
dubiously. "Mr. Aliston says it's just -look&#xD;
and live;' believe on the Lord Jesus and be&#xD;
aved; hut there's sumnat in the war of Thou-&#xD;
as Twi eg.&#xD;
" Faith, Thomas, you'd better take advise-&#xD;
ment of Becky Killigan, and not be meddlia'&#xD;
wid things too high for ye"&#xD;
r0, parder !" sihed Thomas, picking up&#xD;
his hampers, " I need something high, to lift&#xD;
'r Thomas Twizz up to Heaven;- and be&#xD;
went on up to his attie, and there casting him&#xD;
self on his knees, cried out, ".Lord, help&#xD;
Thomas Twiair'&#xD;
Then helit his candle, and topk out his Bi-&#xD;
&#xD;
tle, and his iron-immed spectles, which be&#xD;
needed when he read at night, and turned to&#xD;
the thirteenth chapter of Matthew, and begin&#xD;
nine at the twentyrfourth verse, read slowly&#xD;
along through the fifty-second. Then he went&#xD;
to his bed, and all night long those Parables of&#xD;
the tares, the mustard seed, and the net cast&#xD;
into the sea, followed him through the world&#xD;
of sleep.&#xD;
The next day, as far °as business was con-&#xD;
cerned, was one of the worst days Thorns&#xD;
had ever known. It was sudden and fiere.e&#xD;
Sl hot, and customers were almost as scarce as&#xD;
rain in Egypt. But of all the days that Thom-&#xD;
as had ever lived, this was the crowning day,&#xD;
the white da,-thc day that should in all his&#xD;
life never suffer eclipse from any othet day;&#xD;
but that one most blessed which should usher&#xD;
Thomas into the sanctuarY abuv. And the&#xD;
good was on this wise. Thomas, idle from his&#xD;
usual work, read, pondered, prayed; the Lord&#xD;
&#xD;
"&#xD;
&#xD;
AOL.&#xD;
rf yeti&#xD;
low&#xD;
4r+&#xD;
J t r&#xD;
9&#xD;
1a&#xD;
&#xD;
IL -&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC8382-00000046"/>&#xD;
TMl'  C'YZ' F a         U ITifl a  i  ,d r 6A&#xD;
&#xD;
£4 2  +r LE i  1 '" :.  a,. *_.I±  K.    ,'  '" . °   w4..&amp;amp; w  -: h .&#xD;
y 222  2  h4±       2 422222&#xD;
1  1 r ,  7  M  4  Y      0&#xD;
_" t     is       ++ 2 . 2  2 -   -~&#xD;
&#xD;
21   1°  $1 wn&#xD;
M22  .  ,2.  S, i   r  , t r:  2  .#7.2r d  "t*  2424&#xD;
.4 _ 2y. '  7 -_  72 - .   :: a  '  2 2 44"°y   fl: 2  "  M . k  2  Y.'.   !&#xD;
4242!t a+ 2J22  e' -  1  -2  d4 k 222.2.2 .  Y722&#xD;
x  -2&#xD;
All2  2   2'     '' 7&#xD;
gy.  4 x"_                      w  2.-2i&#xD;
2.. 1&#xD;
j2\V   A   Ia  22     .2. 1+.&#xD;
... -A  2x.  1'"  r 'w x+4 X !,3 S'zsw,  1.2 .'-a1 2r&#xD;
j    t r1 y     4     1X . {  :     4.22&#xD;
4)2.22  122  2 17:  724.42,2a"&#xD;
_      s a s R  6 s tt ;2 7 2&#xD;
R.:2&#xD;
2."222     2    .. J '       2&#xD;
&#xD;
rin: eN:&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC8382-00000047"/>&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
e're all better," said Mrs. Dodd; "how&#xD;
do you fin yourself Mr. T&#xD;
"Jesus hat fluad me," said Thomas, "and I&#xD;
lwpe les made a new man of me ; this is a&#xD;
good day for Thomas Twig."&#xD;
"That's just the way Pappy Dodd talked,"'&#xD;
said ld grannie, lifting up her head from her&#xD;
pillwr. for she had gone to bed.  Pappy&#xD;
Dodd said l'id get safe1y over the river of'&#xD;
Jordan, and I hope I wi too.&#xD;
Do wyo  love Jesus and trust in him?"&#xD;
said Thomas&#xD;
Yes I d   replied the old lady. "Pappy&#xD;
Dodd alius did.~&#xD;
t*Slhows what a blind old sinner Pve been&#xD;
never to mention the matter before."&#xD;
There ain't nuold to talk to me  since&#xD;
Papipy Dodd's gone." said the old lady.&#xD;
I'll talk to vo," said Thomas. "I'm&#xD;
Muehly to blame that I've been dumb as well&#xD;
as blind.&#xD;
Well, Pappy Dodd said that if folks was&#xD;
&#xD;
,&#xD;
&#xD;
m            coat t&#xD;
right they'd talk what the Lord had dn&#xD;
for 'em."&#xD;
 He's done a heap for me," said Thms&#xD;
"seems like I want to tell it all over town."&#xD;
"That's just what Pappy Dodd said," cried&#xD;
the old lad.&#xD;
And thlen Thomas climbed up to his attic,&#xD;
feeling as if indeed old things had&#xD;
away and all had bene w&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC8382-00000048"/>&#xD;
TaE co       STLL.&#xD;
&#xD;
dR             Rh&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER IV-&#xD;
JEitRI Y 'AOC K N E Y.&#xD;
&#xD;
:'&#xD;
&#xD;
nn   wseatUer  ew  Verr warm, he&#xD;
tlursan.t s were readv to : into the&#xD;
country. Miss Laura had been often&#xD;
to No. :2, and counld se  iiood resuhts from her&#xD;
labors -in the DoddI famil  but while Mrs.&#xD;
Becky Ki igan grea1Wy admired the young&#xD;
lady. and always received her warmly, all re-&#xD;
ligious instruction seemed to avail as little for&#xD;
her as tears shed upon a tomb. Miss Laura&#xD;
was not diaoraged; at the close of the after-&#xD;
noon bore she left the citv, she sought the&#xD;
r   T oml"nshe saiguarew.&#xD;
"Thomas," shewsid,. I a     gong away,&#xD;
&#xD;
and it will be sometime before I can. cR at&#xD;
Na. 27 again. I want you to help Mrs. Dodd&#xD;
all you can."&#xD;
"Indeed, ma'am, I will," said Thomas.&#xD;
"For yourself, Thomas, remember the word&#xD;
in Revelation, ' Hold fast that thou hast, that&#xD;
no man take thy crown.&#xD;
A* Wont you mark it for me, ma'am," said&#xD;
Thomas, eageriy taking out his Bible,  and&#xD;
I'll read it every Jay.&#xD;
Mliss Stuveant marked the verse, and then&#xD;
ake    -  Thomas, what efforts are von mak-&#xD;
in fr your partn.'s con veri.n ?"&#xD;
The truth i , maam, I don't sav much to&#xD;
pardner any mnire. She' o   t agi Scripter,&#xD;
an so rul  of her own war it ionht do any&#xD;
ood. I thought I'd leave the Lard to work."&#xD;
" But, Thonas, the Lrd works hy means.&#xD;
And one chief instrument ib the Scripture;&#xD;
'The word of the Lord is quick and powerful&#xD;
sharper than any two edged sword.' I have&#xD;
&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC8382-00000049"/>&#xD;
tar rl                        rncnt r t&#xD;
&#xD;
been reading the Bible to Mrs. Kflianand&#xD;
as yet I have seen no good results. I am now&#xD;
-        about to leave town, and I want you to read&#xD;
the Bible to her as nearly every day as posi&#xD;
ble, and with it drop what good word the Lord&#xD;
puts into your heart."&#xD;
If you hav'n't done any good to her, how&#xD;
can I?" said Thomas, mournfully.&#xD;
Let me tell you a little story" said Miss&#xD;
Laura. "A little brd. retin: on a fir-tree,&#xD;
aot one of the ir-seeds in its win s. As it&#xD;
flew on, the seed drlppeJ, falln: own, down,&#xD;
into a narrow crack in a .zreat rock. The&#xD;
winds had carried there dust and dead leaves ;&#xD;
they brought vet more. The suns smote on&#xD;
the rock and warmed it, rain trickled down the&#xD;
crevice, the fir-seed grew.  A  long. weak,&#xD;
slender shoot at first. but gaining vigor and&#xD;
thriving; it e spanned. shot down aionz the&#xD;
crack touzh roots, an by its strong life it tore&#xD;
the stubborn rock in two, found the rich soil,&#xD;
&#xD;
and lifted its head up to the sun, and stood for&#xD;
years a landmark by the sea."&#xD;
"1 take your meaning," said Thomas, bow-&#xD;
ing his head ; " you've told me a parable, like&#xD;
our Saiour used to tell. I'm muchly ashamed,&#xD;
that after the Lord's done so much for that old&#xD;
gray-headed sinner, Thomas Twigg, he'd go to&#xD;
despairing of Becky Killigan, or any other poor&#xD;
creature. I see the point, ma'am; if I ain't&#xD;
no more than a poor, ig'rant little bird, if so&#xD;
be I've lit on the Tree of Life, I can carry&#xD;
good seed somewhere, and the Lord can give&#xD;
it rooting, even in a rock. Thank c,  a'am,&#xD;
I'l not forget that lesson very soon."&#xD;
" I fear, Thomas," said Miss Laura, kindly,&#xD;
that Nou hare been resting satisfied with the&#xD;
good work in yourself, and have forgotten that&#xD;
the first rule of the Christian life is Christ&#xD;
ian labor. If you would lire, you must grow,&#xD;
and you grow by activity'&#xD;
"Indeed, that is the clear truth," said Thom-&#xD;
as. "ni' pray over that."&#xD;
&#xD;
!Jul&#xD;
AIM&#xD;
&#xD;
; -&#xD;
_                ? _h  ^' _&#xD;
&#xD;
.&#xD;
,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC8382-00000050"/>&#xD;
9&#xD;
&#xD;
- I&#xD;
&#xD;
Tsms&#xD;
And Thomas did not forget Miss Stuyve-&#xD;
wit's words. With renewed earnestness he&#xD;
nayed that he might be wholK consecrated to&#xD;
the Lord's work; that if lie had but one talent,&#xD;
he might be preserved from hiding that ; and&#xD;
houly  entup iscry. ' Lord, what wo uldst&#xD;
hourly wente P      -&#xD;
thou have me to ds 7"&#xD;
IfV we look fr work well find Punzy  it U&#xD;
and daily Thoma found something to do for&#xD;
Jesus. Eachi .venilf, wh;&amp;amp;n be came1 Ih#me1&#xD;
from mi  alh -      t down in Mrs. Kliian's&#xD;
root'. and riad a t:\\w vcrcS mfAn  uAZnI&#xD;
quaint and t   "'iF4 i  E414u--- in ot the \lrM .&#xD;
Kiiam grex weary i: makin jc4., or disput-&#xD;
jun he  i 4  en ;  e heart! ini tonyV 4ilec0e-&#xD;
Geor~D I) td er is drunken up roar-&#xD;
when he broke te iabl's arm. had  entirely&#xD;
disappeared ;  n WUC a1&#xD;
no-n  itt 1m -and concluded that hie Vo a&#xD;
nothing   . from.mn&#xD;
dead. Ma::.e, who had known her either on,&#xD;
to dread sme whiky outbreak and    ho&#xD;
uld charge him wi man 'a chily night and&#xD;
&#xD;
hungry dy, and blows that she had suffered&#xD;
felt glad that he was gone. But old grannie&#xD;
uaundered on, about how different George was&#xD;
from a  Papyi DTd4  what a .ice ritte boy&#xD;
George had been, how his hair had curled, and&#xD;
be had loved pav and hated school ; and she,&#xD;
por soul, had spodt Lim; humoring in place&#xD;
of        :.vrning, until he wh) mii  hare been&#xD;
h  e fort f her ag., became its curse.&#xD;
Alas the comm nstory.&#xD;
Paur Dud I warned me." said she to&#xD;
Th"mas : --   $ heaid I was zoin rizht azin' the&#xD;
L'rd : bu4 h  were a peaceable man, an' he&#xD;
ne ver 1 In mor than talk. The Lord for-&#xD;
lvK' that I splied the hor. ~\Vhen I think&#xD;
of dyinO the Lord will be asking why I ruined&#xD;
Georze. And Papry Dodd 'l be asking for&#xD;
his bor; so I ll b  clear ashamed to go.into&#xD;
Heaven, and I don't want to go no where&#xD;
else.     da&#xD;
"ts bad -e enough," said Thomas, shaking&#xD;
&#xD;
4It&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
t    4 i      Nr',&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC8382-00000051"/>&#xD;
his heal over the wreck George had made,&#xD;
but mind, neighbor, the Lord can abundantly&#xD;
pardon, and he will heal all thy backslidings,&#xD;
so you repent, neighbor;"oldontotha.&#xD;
The missing mans wife said nothing, a&#xD;
gloom  hunr over her, but the family must.&#xD;
have 'Fod, so  he left her ik hbb fur rannie&#xD;
and Mazre t: nurse ar wel~l ats :hey could, and&#xD;
wernt to thL O )ter Stall on te wh art; whre&#xD;
her tnt--andI hal p reten 1led to dAbsne;&#xD;
andI as tEre.; was no call I 3r oysters this hot&#xD;
weather,  -   Y had  oter  refrehmn ts;  and&#xD;
wshinG a -. erubing her -t1ai, an1 its fuirui-&#xD;
m1 i i   f  z   ia      ~  t 4 1  l:&#xD;
tWure, andaa    e     t ---    ,:Wh wat&#xD;
prrn'i.  y Wharf Ra:s the lower casse5&#xD;
5:".&#xD;
ofbo:ha ,    ad.s nw  grw dmarond&#xD;
7} V          yyher  w antq lamp!a gaih red, to buy foo  .%d andY&#xD;
cotl   a   range Iode of human bat and&#xD;
Owls, who~ f ear the lih of day. Then, when t&#xD;
ten o'clWk camh. the sturdv woman made al&#xD;
safe, ta k her ba kct on her arm, and sought&#xD;
&#xD;
A&#xD;
4&#xD;
4I&#xD;
&#xD;
4-&#xD;
&#xD;
her bome and the helpless ones there, with a&#xD;
heavy heart to be sure, but with enough hou-&#xD;
-stlv earned money to give them food and&#xD;
shelter and some poor raiment.&#xD;
Amonz the days of heat and glare came a&#xD;
-A rainy dar. rather a relief, as it washed the&#xD;
s'rc:-ts and houses clear from dust. and gave a&#xD;
chaice fr. frer breathing .&#xD;
T~ma  stU  in his ituli that morning;&#xD;
about ten' el2ock he tunnd b-isuru for washing&#xD;
hi    h hunter and dishes. and settinl things in&#xD;
order; he kept the Corner Stall quite clean,&#xD;
andI':thimrning a little flower girs imploring&#xD;
eves had won him to hurca small bouquet, and&#xD;
tis. set consieuuly in a brown muz. lent to&#xD;
his little establi!tment that charm which leaves&#xD;
and trowers forever brina.&#xD;
Thtas could sing. he had always loved to&#xD;
SIng, l, d had once known plenty of street&#xD;
hailads; 'whaps he bad forgotten these, for&#xD;
lately lhe   otherr things; now as he washed&#xD;
&#xD;
.k&#xD;
gin&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC8382-00000052"/>&#xD;
.;';&#xD;
h&#xD;
T&#xD;
'     Yt&#xD;
f  t&#xD;
..  r&#xD;
.   3&#xD;
w   'rt&#xD;
-     y&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
TED O.fl&#xD;
&#xD;
his cups and plates, he sang, "There is a foun-&#xD;
tamnfilled with blood." Mr. Aliston had giVen&#xD;
him a hymn book, which Thomas c      d to&#xD;
the Mission Church where he attended &amp;amp;rrice,&#xD;
and erery Sunday he committed one hymn to&#xD;
memory. He was catenmng -some strains of&#xD;
Sunday School musk too, for every LorIs&#xD;
day, he took little Mawie and, the uwent to&#xD;
Mission school.&#xD;
Thomas hal op ned his li4tle  o or :at,&#xD;
whicheverit mar be cale.i when 'sme crea-&#xD;
ture sprung around the. er, coming bowed&#xD;
down and 5wiftlv, and taking refuge umdr his&#xD;
counter lay panting breathle~ssy at  i et&#xD;
The intruder was fo other than Jerry Hck-&#xD;
ney, the Wharf Rat. who, like a hunted ani-&#xD;
mat moaned and (ung at the feet of Thomas&#xD;
Twing.&#xD;
"Why, Jerry, is this you'? what's up?&#xD;
said Thomas.&#xD;
Hol on, groaned Jerry. "Go on with&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
_  ,&#xD;
k ,.&#xD;
----T-&#xD;
. :&#xD;
-&#xD;
&#xD;
CE[&#xD;
L&#xD;
_.&#xD;
C&#xD;
{&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
your dshes Mr. Twigg     don't look at me,&#xD;
don't speak to me!           ketch me they&#xD;
[wilL "h&#xD;
Areyou runninv nth nlfIr"9a&#xD;
aked&#xD;
Thomas.&#xD;
Yes I are ; don't let em nat me don'&#xD;
SMr. Tw&#xD;
"flare you been nii --ist now, ther&#xD;
i xv' emet --...azd Tum          a rnct~   wit hi&#xD;
rt                         ueawnym&#xD;
dbi c.  a ru:±le  o rHemen, coming&#xD;
at     crner and o    n   n adreedons&#xD;
tCr: ier fuKdve, xwi;d lheir ho: tanes, and&#xD;
you up for..day,"     1&#xD;
Thomas        .Jerry    cn      tell mn fa r&#xD;
and square wha lx:you're been doing. .Out&#xD;
with it now honet true."&#xD;
"  uied a matter of some old junk," said&#xD;
Jrrv, su   werin" '  de   i&#xD;
Je-y s:t C    eri  under thle COUnter. " I&#xD;
had to, did   I  twer starvni"&#xD;
ihy didn't you come here for a meal ?"&#xD;
&#xD;
.        x&#xD;
w _.&#xD;
105&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC8382-00000053"/>&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
"os" - leJrry&#xD;
"That's no reason," said Thomas, sharply;&#xD;
stealing seems to come natural to you,&#xD;
Jerry-'&#xD;
aI can't help it," whined Jerry, "' don't&#xD;
o body care for me, I al:us had to look out&#xD;
furmyelf  4 don't gire me to 'em, Mr.&#xD;
-ur  my  *-e              m       -.,   r&#xD;
Twigg dont now, 11 never db it no more.&#xD;
3!How uld arc yua, Jerr- .&#xD;
'l duAn." saiI Jerry.&#xD;
4 imatter of ide;~a "r twel Vc I sP450s&#xD;
sadTVinas.     OF#4 N1" :vux1,soe   o&#xD;
turn over a flew  it.&#xD;
--I can' read, said Jerry, n5,understan-&amp;amp;&#xD;
mg                      unul-&#xD;
inkfhies.&#xD;
'Spose you be a zod hoy"&#xD;
"I can't," sail Jerry, "ain't never had no&#xD;
folks, no  courag:ement. nor no shiners, like&#xD;
other flks.&#xD;
"That's'true, vv  weren't mor'nu fire  ear&#xD;
od when I fir-t knew you, and you were&#xD;
&#xD;
r:&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
:&#xD;
.&#xD;
;rr,',&#xD;
-&#xD;
' :&#xD;
--V - ---&#xD;
°. .&#xD;
&#xD;
knocking about Lot yourself then, more shame&#xD;
to me,- Thomas Twigg might have made a&#xD;
man of ron hr thi umt "&#xD;
'Twant morn fire cent worth," said&#xD;
Jerry, fmusterinz courage, and venturing to&#xD;
swvear a little to strenicthen his afirmnation,&#xD;
Tue~u anc&amp;amp; iueked d9own and grKi d hi&#xD;
ViJ couev say x, -t Dn :    ze another such&#xD;
'ur1   U o' ysvn'ar rmun::1 Jery-,- tr IM take&#xD;
au e neared tii&#xD;
ap ardon, dn t hn w youd         eet to&#xD;
n       A wrnpreOd  Jrry, reP ase ! frmin  Mr.&#xD;
Twi     a --w  - b&#xD;
p,?  hut INwas so    --eokiu&#xD;
ha -k an oth with etlert, " starim  Mister&#xD;
Twig4. I could pretty near eat the ;unk itsel&#xD;
I could."&#xD;
i: up, -sati Thomas shortly, and Jervry&#xD;
sat up as well a ihe could under the counter.&#xD;
Thomas hande d hian a good suppdy of meat&#xD;
and bread, and a cup of water savin,"hee&#xD;
make your meal and then str ch at, Jerry,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC8382-00000054"/>&#xD;
noew I: eel&#xD;
&#xD;
jV,&#xD;
Y                                                                      c 1&#xD;
tk-l-&#xD;
\         r.i 1 r&#xD;
AV,&#xD;
&#xD;
iUg&#xD;
&#xD;
and go to sleep, you're safe, and I want to&#xD;
think."&#xD;
usy -te, an then lyig down on the hard&#xD;
pavement under the counter, his head dropped&#xD;
ack, and his arms in their raged, dirty&#xD;
es, folded over his breast, he slept pro-&#xD;
div. Meantime Thomnazs attended to his&#xD;
customers, thought eDarnestly, seayhed h i-&#xD;
le, and   e  l     I ugi heart in  raver to&#xD;
his Master.  ie wI   erd very much to See Mr-&#xD;
Aliston, bu: he dii not cen and Thomas had&#xD;
to make his pans aLone. What the plans&#xD;
were became eid   t at niht. for about eight&#xD;
J'elock he woke Jerry, gave him a doughnut,&#xD;
and lidding han ta. e a small ba ket filled w:ith&#xD;
different articles, said,&#xD;
"Now, Jerry, it you likes, come home with&#xD;
me. If yoU bolt with my basket, I dont say&#xD;
one word, nor take one   tep after you, but&#xD;
never come a nar Thomas Twig again. If&#xD;
so be von come home with me, I reckon you&#xD;
&#xD;
uma  ensna emit109&#xD;
won't be sorry in the end. He fastened up his&#xD;
stall, and walked leisurely homeward, Jerry&#xD;
following him, dodint into the shadow of&#xD;
Thomas' big hampers, and going in fear and&#xD;
trembling because of the police. They reached&#xD;
No. :7safely, and climbed the stairs. At  r.&#xD;
Kili;..a's dooir, Thoas called out.&#xD;
S-Ain't comig to read to-:Jht, pardner."&#xD;
Glad of it," said Mrs. Kiiligan, Iarpi.&#xD;
Ptng away id baskets, whie CJerry lin-&#xD;
zerc i: trh lt!. attie hal. Thomas next car-&#xD;
i. on  :, hm a mall tub has ul  water, a&#xD;
brown tow 4 and a pcew ot soap.&#xD;
-MSrip off themn ra. Jerry." he said, "' and&#xD;
t, work and keep scourin4 g yvourseit, till I&#xD;
gets back." Then shuttu.: himselIf int his&#xD;
room long enoash to draw 1ive dollars from&#xD;
his bank, he locked tlhe dor, set a iighrea ranr&#xD;
die in ote corner of th entry, and went ff$&#xD;
leaving Jerry splashing away in the water with&#xD;
ae zt&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC8382-00000055"/>&#xD;
110&#xD;
&#xD;
THE         WxLLL.&#xD;
&#xD;
In the course of half an hoar, Thomas re&#xD;
turned with two bundles ; he put one down in&#xD;
the hail, saying, "There, ow, there's clothes;&#xD;
put them on decent?   He then went to his&#xD;
room, and unrolling the quit contamed in the&#xD;
other parcel todd it in the idie, and put it&#xD;
drin oni the floor in one corner. Next, taking&#xD;
his candle in hand, he surveyed .erry in thet&#xD;
clothes he had bough:, and reumarked, - J.rrv,&#xD;
my man, vou're imprvina." lie atain 'eked&#xD;
his roon, and1 bidding the lad  undle up his&#xD;
old ra:   , an " t:hrow th7m out in the street, he&#xD;
escorted him to a f arth rate barber's estab-&#xD;
lshment, where Lt ha ua Jerry  Lair cut cdose&#xD;
to his head, and his LeaI thuorongIy scored.&#xD;
Jerry submitted in wognderi  hsilece to all&#xD;
theset proceediings, andi wheii he nad been adi-&#xD;
mited to T'hmas' rroom, our friend sat down&#xD;
a his " parlor corner -on the fellow chair,&#xD;
stood Jerrr in front of him, and holding hni&#xD;
° irmlv hy both vlbow, l#'ked straight into his&#xD;
eyes, saving,&#xD;
&#xD;
m  cos srn..&amp;amp;&#xD;
&#xD;
11&#xD;
&#xD;
bide by me, mind what I say to you, keep&#xD;
scot free of your old rowdy mates, leave the&#xD;
wharfs, quit your games, and make an honest&#xD;
Yes I be," said Jerry.&#xD;
' Then Jerry Hockne   you can't nig, you&#xD;
can't tell is, yOU can' loaf about, von can't&#xD;
Use Io Pal talk.&#xD;
-I won't." said Jerrv.&#xD;
S V ou will," said Tao mas. "and then I&#xD;
e ne dw I vilo\u. liut if vu stands being'&#xD;
ete downI on, iand it you takes to "ood vars,&#xD;
and woxxrks ike a mnr, then PNI be a father to&#xD;
yu sre my name's Ihomas Twig.      You'll&#xD;
iVe here wi:hme, yu'ah have 'oUIugh to eat&#xD;
'nagh clotes place to sleep, you Iearns y'U&#xD;
-1 4k, you govs to church and Sunday sch 401&#xD;
and bv-an'-by xmebbv youll1be took in&#xD;
in my stall and her money in your pocket."&#xD;
-- That's so," said Jerryaprobativelyv.&#xD;
&#xD;
:&#xD;
' -&#xD;
'  ,&#xD;
:&#xD;
nl&#xD;
_  /fAl  _ _ ,&#xD;
-____ '-&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
u.~&#xD;
&#xD;
77,&#xD;
.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC8382-00000056"/>&#xD;
11,&#xD;
&#xD;
nrEEfcomek4 ,.---&#xD;
&#xD;
"There's your bed, Jerry, and there s the&#xD;
door,-if you bolts yu bolts, an' I don't run&#xD;
afrrn, lnt sn tin' yon turns yoar back on&#xD;
agood chance."&#xD;
Shan't bolt," asserted Jerry. "I'l go to&#xD;
No 'vou don't, Jerry, there's more to be&#xD;
done.   There's a chair, sit down my SonI.&#xD;
lit nint L rutr Lea ts, Jerry we've .got ,aoul,&#xD;
and we mdust look a:vr 'em.- Listen now&#xD;
while I read the cript:r. then we 'H aU go (&#xD;
on our knee and LI $ ray&#xD;
4         Jerry  at d1wn   quite  rerawel, \ ile&#xD;
Thomas coniduetedI his irst taily~ devotinn.&#xD;
Risin a fromt  their  knecy,   T a  a ain  took&#xD;
Jery'Lsthe L v  ,'x iti r. "-MLt lad, lit,, sn&#xD;
of mines goin :o he in fear o: the p llee.-&#xD;
They won't know me :w", said iTrry.&#xD;
, "You'll start Iair and qaare. T"o-oit.rrow&#xD;
jpru we    f to the wharf and pay tor that&#xD;
bit of junk, and yon beg pardon and mkes&#xD;
&#xD;
rutMILL&#xD;
&#xD;
1i&#xD;
&#xD;
tour nrorisumforegood&#xD;
conduct in future"&#xD;
Jerry looked dubious.&#xD;
"Them's my terms, said Thoms.&#xD;
I' l do it, said Jerry, and undressing went&#xD;
to i quilt.&#xD;
(irrat was~ the amazement of Mrs. Killigan,&#xD;
xx    1 next liv  hmas mtrodueed to her his&#xD;
ai s. Gratwas the a mazement of the&#xD;
x arf  i, whini the xhim n" rat   came&#xD;
anad decendy clad,  e av- for h' last&#xD;
-!-                 "   .{    an&#xD;
ttxin: an]d prunmie amendment, Great was&#xD;
amazement of paser bv the stall on Union&#xD;
Square. to see an apprentiue under Thoma&#xD;
Twig   bi: induted int) the mysteries of&#xD;
ee   an Lemonade makin.. and instructed&#xD;
halfQ a  zen times a day in speilinz-book intri-&#xD;
cacies; and ret greater astonishment was it to&#xD;
see Thomas ounce upon his boygrasphim by&#xD;
the collar, and shake him with great zeal, ...--&#xD;
Jerry. with rolling eyes and quick gasps, sub-&#xD;
&#xD;
",&#xD;
&#xD;
°;&#xD;
&#xD;
to&#xD;
On,&#xD;
4 _ "+"  t    _iM ar,&#xD;
iv'3i!  R  fi^P     '&#xD;
171&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC8382-00000057"/>&#xD;
rturnin.1g to his tzbtTi      a   Lur&#xD;
wa  f"onhrav ~on Jerrr Lw sct r "&#xD;
1  e  $, . G:  4  +. a.. aF.e j $' ~t4&#xD;
3°.  Ea 4 4 M.  M r^ ,yb4&#xD;
4L j&#xD;
'Lid  '  1   4 "  -   1       ''  'u "!   a..'- yRa , u 4 1&#xD;
4-   -   ---S&#xD;
-~ 14A-                 4' W4&#xD;
"  tz  'c M   :y  . -N. ,  -u44i..  :  .. 1A  c te"  A&#xD;
-  t 2: N L   I  z*:  c~n TX u3 - IL&#xD;
nl:U~: " tL ~ tI-at 1;::  o   th'L:2 ixe&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
4&#xD;
a&#xD;
*T&#xD;
&#xD;
xtt-: L I ~ ; M ~   h n   Ji ~ e h is  -s h 2 n , y t z   i   : gwl&#xD;
teYA x ofI&#xD;
1u-44444Ty 4  I  4  1  *    -T   #.T  r.  vM 'W- kpYf:y YS&#xD;
,z  .--   "  w    d  _ - mw  ''g ' 4   F   4 ^"+      9'  i._ s'  P&#xD;
'. &amp;amp;.  Y  3a+k s-  -4             4&#xD;
J411&#xD;
*       Aw'mY&#xD;
-              44 +4 R  .A,'.r.4  4,Y'   . i' -  r a f  _ '-w .-&#xD;
V         4      -  ,ara  r  ea  M-a iGXa    '6  w _-  .  rt ',-  '  +"&#xD;
k443  414'  44 444444  44 .44  :]  4&#xD;
ac-i                *14-&#xD;
1)-                a,',Ftq.-- 4:&amp;amp;.Aix  nJ 444  r¢  k w ,,,-  u -&#xD;
)am434cC4&#xD;
., Wp,  4  .  '+  t :  i  a1 c  5#  *ici w-  ".   r:;    ;":  s1&#xD;
+F - -:x&#xD;
X 4$ 2 .  A&amp;amp; , J U 4 xw - a: P ;  --&#xD;
J i+      9y ' MM  4'ta           4 Y&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC8382-00000058"/>&#xD;
What is the matter," said Thomas one&#xD;
evening, as he found her sitting on the door-&#xD;
sill, with her arms crossed on her knees, and&#xD;
7 0t'h lnn     ed Mrs K$i.it!n with a&#xD;
sigh   this is a vVar  wa r riud  i  !cky&#xD;
Killigan is wa-taive it. The da I  urn&#xD;
up a Laf, an a re~wt i: 4'nru : ti t  lta&#xD;
r an&#xD;
an' yisterdar mt; 2rCea i I  ike a lm&#xD;
o7Af lead, thuEI. thalz .ve  ..-so  -oUd&#xD;
Silligan before, ine wa2 n *r rae--&#xD;
"Never fxtG       Th :uas, -Ta    halves&#xD;
on the lss.§&#xD;
"No xouN wo dsid Becky;     the bye's a&#xD;
burden' -  mnakinz a poor man of ve, now.&#xD;
The Iand    -  "    Thomas suddenly&#xD;
elapsed his baud over his mtnh.&#xD;
W fhat's the mattr "asked MrsL. fIiuhgan&#xD;
"hae ye the tooth-ache. Thoma"s&#xD;
"No,    an1 Thomas, "but I'm   tryngtO&#xD;
stop usinz bye-words. 1 read in the Scripter,&#xD;
&#xD;
m uu&#xD;
&#xD;
' Let your vet be yea, and your nay, nay; fit&#xD;
whatsoever is more than these comet of evil,'&#xD;
and I'm trying to live up toib but it's tough&#xD;
work."&#xD;
"I should think so!" cried Mrs. Kidiigan;&#xD;
what would I do couldn't I say 'Holy Peter,'&#xD;
or' Blessed Yirmix,' to reieve me mind a bit."&#xD;
Ysu:oI better by far spend your breath&#xD;
pravmr ,aid I Tiomra.&#xD;
And wtn should I prayi for?" asked Mrs.&#xD;
That the Lord would change your heart,&#xD;
and forgive your ns sad Thomas, promptly&#xD;
eOh hone,   said the old lac,  B&#xD;
Khgan s alsIs I een a decent body and has no&#xD;
great weight of Ins on her mind. It's not&#xD;
often I trouble the acnfessional, for 've little&#xD;
to confess. Burnmu up them tooa d rittils, an&#xD;
arm  the sodv out A me ilngerbread's the&#xD;
worst ive done tlon% While!&#xD;
"Oh, pardner, said Thomas, "You'll never&#xD;
&#xD;
S:&#xD;
&#xD;
i       Ti -.per ,   ^"   -'  '&#xD;
&#xD;
^      4&#xD;
.- IS&#xD;
&#xD;
f _i  -&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC8382-00000059"/>&#xD;
TM cn srw.&#xD;
&#xD;
A  a&#xD;
r&#xD;
~   °T _  _&#xD;
&#xD;
rat COzg sra.&#xD;
&#xD;
get to glory at that rate ; ask the Lord to let&#xD;
you feel yourself the chief of sinners!"&#xD;
Iwon't for I am't," said' Mrs. Kiliigan&#xD;
T I I      i.ue * j ona ady use tf) talk like&#xD;
man  to  to  truir"tr* dttup       to&#xD;
Peter that         _ia    n$    i-#    kIlinws&#xD;
spoke ancK 4u      a '-'&#xD;
his b''..  ,uU':. .+a  :-  aw:;;:: Wr&#xD;
There's :nv one natr-  art . A&#xD;
it's the &amp;amp;ne th pUb  an  the. ;-n:tnt :hief&#xD;
got in at. -rv n Out lir diet.e to xmgne'-"&#xD;
T6-4-                      --&#xD;
The summ nr pa-.d away-, Ti 'mas had doe&#xD;
a g4od wark rt :; e had been the counsellor&#xD;
and friend of thE D1dd famnlt :  hl tna&#xD;
&#xD;
*&#xD;
&#xD;
'memo-&#xD;
&#xD;
118&#xD;
&#xD;
lit&#xD;
&#xD;
wonders for Jerry Hockner; the goodma&#xD;
felt no self-gratuation, but he wgladto&#xD;
working for his Master, and longed to do yet&#xD;
more.&#xD;
ne Sunday evening, -while old Mrs. Dodd&#xD;
ay the window er:  nin an od time hymn,&#xD;
an  heIr -auuter-m-lax  in a   eCond-hand&#xD;
rnr-vmz -.a:r which -he ±ad manad. to par-&#xD;
. j trn  -  mhA1  T y to sleep&#xD;
a :ange ;aj; -ion :ipared i n the doorwa.-&#xD;
n urt      - a t,  ii rI, tL n theked&#xD;
'i  JJ ..La.k in. Lanin4 iL head&#xD;
a:    4:dirmz to  hold  ort hi  hand, and made&#xD;
B-war toa a corner.&#xD;
rile        4&#xD;
"Ge'orge, is, i you t" aid is wile.&#xD;
Hads lime b1y    im mfe I "said the old&#xD;
ai , hending ttrward and IPet ring, with her&#xD;
wak, cleared esruh the twiiizht&#xD;
Y QU'   been long away," said the wife,&#xD;
going towxar i the returned prodigal.&#xD;
&#xD;
'x&#xD;
"       i^&#xD;
s          ?&#xD;
r                 Y^&#xD;
i&#xD;
_[Z y&#xD;
-4 ^ wal3r'&#xD;
&#xD;
_  .&#xD;
-.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC8382-00000060"/>&#xD;
=  _      __&#xD;
&#xD;
I was ashamed," murmured George.&#xD;
George, ye nearly killed the babyu!" s&#xD;
the old mother's shrill, quavering tones.&#xD;
I didn't mean to do it," said George.&#xD;
SYounever mean to do anything." said :&#xD;
younger wonan, in a despondent war.&#xD;
"It's the whiikeyv does it " said Geo1 ;e&#xD;
groaning.&#xD;
All tis summnr ther s Wen bread and&#xD;
quiet here. (iGere, but never a drtp of Jhi -&#xD;
key," said hi; wife.   --HIeret +y r{- Loy,&#xD;
George, y Ubrake hi arn. ad t  i  m.-end&#xD;
right, an1d h ere  i t is  2d  hjejp  Na nd  ank,"&#xD;
and he crippled 14r lik; "there v re t rs in&#xD;
the woman's Voide, but she had Zuflvr'ei too&#xD;
much for them to be in her eves The man,&#xD;
however, was or a weaker natu.  hBowedl&#xD;
hIlishe .and sobted.&#xD;
WhV'iere have you hee'n? ".asked Ihis wil,&#xD;
impatienti v.&#xD;
Traveii, the country, and I've been six&#xD;
week sick in The poor house."-&#xD;
&#xD;
*U&#xD;
&#xD;
Mrs. Dodd groaned.&#xD;
-Well, George," she said, "I've eared for&#xD;
your mother, and your child, and my child,&#xD;
and I could take care of you, but I c't take&#xD;
care of the whiskey."&#xD;
SI knw vyou can't, ;sobbed George, "yet&#xD;
I knw III be at it azin, sure as I can see it&#xD;
and ct a cent. Kill me. Bridget, and put me&#xD;
out f the wa.  I've tried to kill mysel hant&#xD;
Fm too much of a coward; kill me for . hate&#xD;
mvse f. and you hate me, and the whiskey&#xD;
rules me;" and he dropped on the floor&#xD;
moaning.&#xD;
Then his old mother tottered over to him,&#xD;
with the Only human love that did not fail the&#xD;
wretch, and sitting down on the floor, drew&#xD;
his head to her worn old breast, and mambled&#xD;
uch endearing words as she had soothed him&#xD;
with thirty years bfore. The wife stood by,&#xD;
catching her breath quickly, but she held in&#xD;
her arms the babe he had maimed, and for a&#xD;
while she could not speak ;nally she said,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC8382-00000061"/>&#xD;
T ens    STALL,&#xD;
&#xD;
TU CO RSEt  $ LL&#xD;
&#xD;
Get up, George, rI'l give you your supp-r,&#xD;
and you can go to bed."-&#xD;
So at last she had the babe and Maggie&#xD;
asleep in the trundle bed, the old lady in her&#xD;
cot, and George too was asleep. Then she&#xD;
went - softly out, and up to the attie, and&#xD;
knocked at the door f Thomas Twi-n.&#xD;
That's wanted?" said Thomas.  Im in&#xD;
bed."&#xD;
" Get up and come out, Thomas for my&#xD;
heart is breaking," was the answer.&#xD;
Thomas ;ot up and tuxuhhed about with his&#xD;
clothes for a while, t:en came out into the&#xD;
entry, and found his poor neighbor sitting on&#xD;
the top step, gruaninz and rocking herelf to&#xD;
and fro as one in sharp distrss. Thomas&#xD;
heard poor Mrs. Dodd's story of her sorrows&#xD;
and fears, as the call of his Mster ordaining&#xD;
him to another lab.r of lve.&#xD;
Cheer up, neighbor.' he said, " don't -ve&#xD;
way ; the Lord helping us, we'll save George&#xD;
yet. Go to your room contented, to-morrow&#xD;
&#xD;
you must tend your stand and make George&#xD;
bide at home all day, and after that PIl have a&#xD;
plan laid out for him."&#xD;
Mrs. Dodd went to her room comforted.&#xD;
The succeeding day, as George was feeble,&#xD;
and aho ashamed, it was not very hard to&#xD;
keep hum at home. ejspealyi as Mrs. Kiigan&#xD;
agzree o ook harm a good dinner. " Arrah,\&#xD;
Lu:tit's a pity that iver lie conie home to de..&#xD;
tr  all, and make a aste or himself," she&#xD;
if Beeky iligan was his honor the&#xD;
r, shure as preachin' se d rut out all&#xD;
n wusk- shops and cellars, an Ishe applied&#xD;
2 en:ta and towel with new zeal.&#xD;
That aero      .an Beekr anclUd-a  to take an&#xD;
airing. anl as ;here was but one place in all&#xD;
e w  York that she esteemed of particular&#xD;
interest, and that the Corner Stall on  Union&#xD;
Square, thutner sue bent her steps.&#xD;
As Thomas had powerfully considered Jer-&#xD;
ry s case, so now le did (eor'e D  ..u ; all&#xD;
&#xD;
J&amp;amp;P&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC8382-00000062"/>&#xD;
1&amp;amp;4nna-  ~&#xD;
&#xD;
day long it had occupied his thoughts, but as&#xD;
Becky drew near he stood in front of the stall,&#xD;
lookinganxiously about the street-&#xD;
"A   good day's work to  e ! " cried the&#xD;
"Yes, I have had a busy day," said Thounas;&#xD;
"would you mind watching the stall for a bit,&#xD;
pardner.&#xD;
"Och, no," says Mrs. Kiliigan, "but what's&#xD;
nnu   "&#xD;
"1 sent Jerry off on an errant," said Thom-&#xD;
anxiouiv, "and it's time I was looking for&#xD;
him."&#xD;
"'Go, thin," said Beckky, taking her place&#xD;
with dignity behind the counter, " its not well&#xD;
to be trusting bye's, Tho:nas."&#xD;
Thomas walked along a square or two feel&#xD;
ing quite distressed, when, confirmation of all&#xD;
his fears, he saw son Jerry sitting with several&#xD;
raged urchins on the sidewalk, playing pitch&#xD;
penny, the parcel of sugar he had been sent&#xD;
&#xD;
70C         B&amp;amp;i Lt         125&#xD;
&#xD;
for lying on the ground beside him; his back&#xD;
was toward Mr. Twigg. Instantly, without&#xD;
any warning, Thomas pounced upon the young&#xD;
renegade, and while the penny Jerry had just&#xD;
tossed up was yet ringing on the pavement,&#xD;
Jerry himself was shaking and spinning about&#xD;
in the strong hand of the indi :ant Thomas,&#xD;
like a rat in the mouth of a .aiff. Jerry's&#xD;
companions in evil were too much stupefied by&#xD;
the swiftness and violence of Thomas Twigg's&#xD;
descent to do more than sit and stare, open&#xD;
mouthed. at his proceedings.&#xD;
' Where is your change ?" said Thomas,&#xD;
hiding his ward at arms length. Jerry point-&#xD;
d to the han ul of coppers on the sidewalk,&#xD;
gasping.&#xD;
Thomas stooped and sorted out five pennies.&#xD;
"Are these what you had?" he asked. Jerry&#xD;
choked and nodded. Thomas picked up the&#xD;
sugar, and bidding Jerry "walk on,   they&#xD;
proceeded to the Corner Stall; by the time&#xD;
&#xD;
so&#xD;
&#xD;
r.&#xD;
&#xD;
F&#xD;
&#xD;
,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC8382-00000063"/>&#xD;
they reached there Jerry was somewhat re-&#xD;
vived after being " come down on," and&#xD;
Thomas bade him make some lemonade.&#xD;
"Jerry makes good iimnmonad," said Becky,&#xD;
sipping some. "Did he bring von the change,&#xD;
Thomas?" and she eyed Jerry, sharply.&#xD;
Here it is' said Thomas, putting the&#xD;
cents in the moneyc drawer-&#xD;
- ;l al4i alon2." saidtBeky.  -iWaat can&#xD;
-I do for yrn Thomas  '&#xD;
You mi.h: stop and speak for more zadv&#xD;
for toi-m or  the tray's about Aut, &amp;amp;said&#xD;
Thomas hA now Thomas was left alone&#xD;
with Jerry.&#xD;
Jerry. my sn. said Th.mxs. gravely,&#xD;
v. flu , 41  sa'    V--  l  1&#xD;
"you're fell away -bd"&#xD;
Jerry lo k  down 1fand rubbed i eves with&#xD;
his list .&#xD;
" Y ou've fLl a;av in diverse wars, Jerry.&#xD;
continued TAona; ; "you've disobeyed, thatX&#xD;
one, you've tbeen gamnbiing, tiiats two, you've&#xD;
took my money, that's three.&#xD;
&#xD;
U&#xD;
&#xD;
I didn't g for to keep it," cried Jerry,&#xD;
I knew I'd win more, and, certain true, I&#xD;
was goin' to bring back yourn.7'&#xD;
" How did you know you'd win more?"&#xD;
asked Thomas.&#xD;
aI allus does,' said Jerry.&#xD;
Tfen von eheas," said Thomas, decidedly.&#xD;
- w. Jerry, who saw. yon when you fell&#xD;
You di?, whimpered Jerry.&#xD;
Who elsV?&#xD;
Godi did." whisperedI Jerry.&#xD;
Yes, my son, VoU've sinned again the Lord.&#xD;
Lay -that to heart. Stand up here, Jerry,&#xD;
ile I deal out a Scripter for you to learn.&#xD;
-My sau, it sinners entice thee consent than&#xD;
n* t.'"  When Jerry had learned this, Thomas&#xD;
sNow I shan't talk to you any more,&#xD;
Jurrv, but von goU to thinking of your sins, and&#xD;
z)\ your mind- so when I asks the Lord to&#xD;
forgive vou to-night, wd'*1 both mean it?&#xD;
&#xD;
p&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC8382-00000064"/>&#xD;
That night, when Jerry and Thomas were&#xD;
at home and ready for devotions, what an&#xD;
earnest,'soulfull prayer the good man put Up&#xD;
for the erring boy; that prayer, following such&#xD;
a train of kindnesses, and such conscientious&#xD;
coming down on sin, Jerry never forgot- he&#xD;
recognized that higher power from whence all&#xD;
goodness flows, and Jerry's progress was there-&#xD;
after from race to grace.&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER V.&#xD;
&#xD;
THOMAS TVIGG IN TROUBLE.&#xD;
&#xD;
j   H~tIEN Jerry had gone to bed after&#xD;
lh failin; away in tlw matter of&#xD;
t't up." Is ad1opted father&#xD;
went 'a to Mfr'. 1ls rom. The old&#xD;
laI lld he chIdr'n wcrte in hed, ut George&#xD;
and hi ife wetre waiting hr Th.mas. Mrs.&#xD;
Ddd rcked1 in her little chair, sizhing now&#xD;
and thcn a if in despair .f any thigin, while&#xD;
George had bowed his he ad on the window&#xD;
sill, evidently even more dejected than his&#xD;
wife.&#xD;
Well, George,' said Thomas, in his usual&#xD;
&#xD;
iT r&#xD;
&#xD;
to                Is                                         I I.,&#xD;
&#xD;
:.  ,&#xD;
_"&#xD;
._ ;&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC8382-00000065"/>&#xD;
c coam STLL&#xD;
&#xD;
=cott  STALL.&#xD;
&#xD;
blithe way, "we're going to see what can be&#xD;
 man; here's Tour wife such&#xD;
done for you, ymaO&#xD;
Si hand alminess that she's taken the&#xD;
'standwAy from you.&#xD;
Le Georc   "I never can&#xD;
"Let her, r.anet eo e&#xD;
do anything, whskeS    t the upper hands&#xD;
of me, von know it..r. Twcz&#xD;
SCome, come,"4 aid Thomna', br ly, " you&#xD;
,wtt wlet.whi4;o   wh4o You out of&#xD;
buines ; stand up asairt t&#xD;
an   Jc IG    re     I've sail I&#xD;
4vold  t I\tii hunli ~t 4tms&#xD;
ped4 ait   h  na&#xD;
II&#xD;
Bridcet, there, bat juot et me et the ah or&#xD;
the smel o f it, anl E m don fr- Sonwhody&#xD;
says c eme, treat or, comt-e Il treat yQou;&#xD;
1- s all  n th&#xD;
and I v ;tright on. leave th  stll  pe,  h&#xD;
the end of it. I hal saha ini' arnd agod&#xD;
chance, -and it all goes ior nothing."&#xD;
h s knew all this before George told&#xD;
Ti0Umsgm&#xD;
&#xD;
him: theya had none          heard of an&#xD;
inebriate asylum. If Mr. Allston had been in&#xD;
town he might have mentioned such a refuge&#xD;
to Thomas; as it was, the pier-man had to&#xD;
manage all his ownl wva.&#xD;
Wht's to be done for you, GeorgeW" he&#xD;
N ot~i  'ng  aml (eorce,  mnoodiiy; "if some-&#xD;
ibodiy was at hand always. to knock the glass&#xD;
out  nmw fin s.  or knock me down. I mijt.&#xD;
standI a chance.&#xD;
dmself ready to d ot:h   sai&#xD;
Tihomat with a grimn smile.  II come down&#xD;
ny. e I do on Jerry, and ftch von right&#xD;
p to the .mark."&#xD;
Geor Ie Ahok his head. "You can't," he&#xD;
said;  wih I was a boy again, so you could ;&#xD;
but now I'm bent on going to ruin ; there's&#xD;
deny' to tempt, and none to save.&#xD;
"Don't go to ruin, George; piped a shrill&#xD;
voice from the bed.. "What 'II Pappy Dodd&#xD;
say if you do?"&#xD;
&#xD;
130 /&#xD;
&#xD;
131&#xD;
&#xD;
9&#xD;
&#xD;
..&#xD;
&#xD;
_.     -&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC8382-00000066"/>&#xD;
Tint.    :.-LL&#xD;
&#xD;
"Never fear," said Thomas; "George is&#xD;
going to do better now. George, here's my&#xD;
~,. inconstable Tswigg. I takes you in&#xD;
carge. - Where I goes von goes ; vou do&#xD;
business long side o' 'me.  We goes and&#xD;
comes.  I looks after you, George, till you&#xD;
van stand a zlass of whikeyv right under your&#xD;
nose, and not want it.&#xD;
 -he  said George.  Wish&#xD;
it would. I am a ruined man, Mr. Twiz, all&#xD;
-   .&#xD;
along of wmisike'.&#xD;
", George," implored the hitherto silent&#xD;
wife; do. what Mr. Twicz sav ; see what&#xD;
ho's done for Jerr.&#xD;
" TIll do it, lbut it wou': do any g.od," saidl&#xD;
George.&#xD;
"Well. Georzr. von iitry and Ut try ; an&#xD;
we'll leave the ret to the Lord," said Thoma,&#xD;
cheerily.  Let your wife keep the stand ,o&#xD;
the wharf; she can make a living there, an&#xD;
you can't. Old Polly Kepple has got a strike,&#xD;
&#xD;
I,&#xD;
&#xD;
and went to the hospital, an' there's nobody&#xD;
on the square selling tape, needles, shoe gs,&#xD;
soap and suth like. You get a basket and a&#xD;
stook, and nail together a little awning to stick&#xD;
up to the fence, and you sets up in a new bud-&#xD;
ness rizht lonz side of me."&#xD;
"0. Mr. Twig, that's a good offer, but I&#xD;
ha   t a red cnt to set up with."&#xD;
WelL George," continued Thomas, with&#xD;
the air of one resolved to carr through what&#xD;
he nronosed, to a happy completion, -" I'll&#xD;
lend you twelve dollars to start like a man,&#xD;
and v4I1 pay me  ack twenty-five cents er-&#xD;
err week f£r a rear out of your profits. That&#xD;
w      ill be my money and a good interest on it."&#xD;
"I'l get whiskey spreeing, and make no&#xD;
rorit,' groaned George.&#xD;
No you won't, said Thomas, "'and if pm&#xD;
do, why, Il take in all your stock to sect re&#xD;
myself."&#xD;
g - George, do it," cried his wife.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC8382-00000067"/>&#xD;
":Il do itsMr. Twigg, and I hope you'll&#xD;
hold on to me pretty tight ; hut when I do go&#xD;
wrong, you know I warned you a-head of&#xD;
time."&#xD;
It's time we went'to bedj said Thomas,&#xD;
"but before we does, just kneel down here.&#xD;
and we'll Lay out our plans before the Lord,&#xD;
and asksa blessin.&#xD;
They all knelt, and when the pntyer was&#xD;
ended, a tremulous "Amen.   came from the&#xD;
old lady as she lay in her bed.&#xD;
The next morning Thomas left his stall in&#xD;
charge of the p nitnt ant thoruughlv subdued&#xD;
Jerry, and taking Georz who had aeccompa-&#xD;
nied him from N. £7.: le bout a second&#xD;
hand Stotl, a Lrze basket, a goofd assortmet t&#xD;
of small wares. a little frame covered witil&#xD;
canvas to fasten against the fence, to shelter&#xD;
him from the sun or rain. Thus he set up&#xD;
George in busines a few feet from himself.&#xD;
Providing the new merchant with fifty cents&#xD;
&#xD;
E:&#xD;
I&#xD;
'a&#xD;
&#xD;
'itt ---   -&#xD;
&#xD;
in      coin to make change with,   oma&#xD;
also gave him a knife, a piece of wood, and a&#xD;
square of sand-paper, saying, "San gets idle&#xD;
folks in mischief; so, while you're waiting for&#xD;
customers, you 'whittle out picks and rings and&#xD;
reels, any traps you can, and mind vou takes&#xD;
my Bible and reads a chapter twice a day;&#xD;
that' the Street Anehor. man, to tie yoar&#xD;
oad resoutions to.  That's the Looking&#xD;
(ilas, holds up all one's own meanness; that's&#xD;
the Treasure house, tells all we can get for&#xD;
the asking; that's the Gide Book to Glory,&#xD;
,George, mind vou reads it?&#xD;
Besides teaching Jerry to read and to make&#xD;
lemonade, coffee and sandwiches, and sending&#xD;
him ;on errands. Thomas now sent him each&#xD;
niorning, to a Confectioner in a small way, to&#xD;
learn how to make taffy, cornballs, peanut&#xD;
candy and mint sticks. "You'll have a shop&#xD;
of your own, Jerry, one day," Thomas would&#xD;
say encouragingly. Thomas meant to send&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC8382-00000068"/>&#xD;
Jerry to night school as soon as it opened, and&#xD;
to find some way of learning to write and&#xD;
cipher himself. Suddenly it occurred to him&#xD;
that George Dodd could be their private in-&#xD;
structor in these arts, and forthwith they&#xD;
began at once.&#xD;
Thomas faithfully kept George in his sight,&#xD;
going to and fro between LUnin Square and&#xD;
No. 27. How often -George strove to hldt,&#xD;
into some groger. and just as often Thomas&#xD;
dragged him along hy main strenzti   At&#xD;
times, when the thirst was furious, patient&#xD;
Thomas would furnish a pail full of coffee, and&#xD;
lock the demented Gegorge ito his own private&#xD;
attic, while himself slept on the entry floor.&#xD;
Georze's wife blessed Thomas, and took what&#xD;
courage she could, though her maimed, miser-&#xD;
able child was a sad sight to a mother.&#xD;
Often on Union Square such scenes as this&#xD;
were enacted.&#xD;
"What ails you, George1? You look like&#xD;
running away ; what are you uneasy after?"&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
"Oh, whiskey, Thomas,&#xD;
just one taste, or I'll die.&#xD;
don't hold me; I'll knock,&#xD;
do"&#xD;
&#xD;
Imuss nave t ;&#xD;
MI-&#xD;
'm going for it,&#xD;
you down if you&#xD;
&#xD;
I m the tougher man, George, and you'l&#xD;
go down first. Come on -Eth me."&#xD;
"I'm going after whiskevy if it kills"me.&#xD;
"Come along," said Thomas, seizing the&#xD;
arm of George. and taking a cup as they&#xD;
passed the stall, he led him to the hydrant&#xD;
"Have a drink, George?"&#xD;
Noft water, whiker..&#xD;
Drink, I tell vou.'&#xD;
I can't. I hate water. Im raging thirsty&#xD;
Thomas tilled the cup, and taking George s&#xD;
hand, and feehig his forehead said "Yon ain't&#xD;
overly hot, water won't hurt you, drink," and&#xD;
he pushed the cup to George's lips-George&#xD;
drank.&#xD;
"Another;" that went too.&#xD;
"I've had enough," said George.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC8382-00000069"/>&#xD;
"Drink more," said Thomas, the inexorable.&#xD;
George was growing meeker, he denied the&#xD;
Cup again.&#xD;
Another, and you'll be like a lamb," said&#xD;
Thomas.&#xD;
Im chock full,"' said Georze, yet took the&#xD;
"fRere's more." said Thomas.&#xD;
"0, I'll burst," zroaned Georze-&#xD;
Do you want whiskey now ? " asked DK-&#xD;
tor Twigg.&#xD;
No, nor nothminz -ese to drink. I'm ful&#xD;
to the teeth."&#xD;
Thus azain and again did Tihomas conquter&#xD;
George's toe. " For it stands to reason." said&#xD;
Thomas. "-that George won't crave whisrkey&#xD;
when he's full of water.&#xD;
Never did Thomas' faithful watching fail or&#xD;
grow weary, and yet that Evil One who was&#xD;
playing with IhiM for the stake of this so u&#xD;
sometimes very nearly snatched away tie&#xD;
&#xD;
-      co a   san..          18&#xD;
prize. As for instance, whea one day, one&#xD;
of George's bad days it was, as they came&#xD;
home arm in arm, Thomas stopped to help a&#xD;
child that had fallen down, and George seizing&#xD;
the brlrortUnity bolted down Jug Alley, and&#xD;
into a dram shop; at once Thomas was after&#xD;
lim, and neither too soo  ntr too late, he&#xD;
gra-pedi him just as the reeking glass was at&#xD;
 in site of the struggles of the&#xD;
:ntrzuated Gerge;, and the oaths and exposta-&#xD;
atis of the rumsellers and his hangers on,&#xD;
ise iragged him to a piaee of saiety.&#xD;
I Confess  "said ThoImas to Mrs. Kiligan,&#xD;
that ennig " that tile ncae  George do look&#xD;
mt dubsersotsme.&#xD;
I wouldn't worrit myself about the rap-&#xD;
scailion." said Mr1. KillcGan ; "you ain't his&#xD;
kper.&#xD;
That's just what Cain said," replied Thot i-&#xD;
a shaking his head. -but the Lord made it&#xD;
out to hin right air and square, that he was&#xD;
&#xD;
It&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC8382-00000070"/>&#xD;
pna        I'll do my duty, pardner, and let&#xD;
the Lord take care of the rest"&#xD;
Miss Stuyvesant came back, and was soon at&#xD;
the Corner Stall, and No. Q7. Little Mary at&#xD;
once gave her friend Maggie suftient clothing&#xD;
to go to school looking decent, and promised&#xD;
Mrs. Killigan a trifle a week for looking in on&#xD;
the old woman and the baby now ad then."&#xD;
"-How are you, Mrs. Killigan?" asked&#xD;
Laura.&#xD;
"Och, bonney, I'm the same woman I was&#xD;
bast spring,' was th" reply.&#xD;
"1 hoped you would be a new woman by&#xD;
this time "said Miss Laura.  I prayed the&#xD;
Lord to ehanze yon.&#xD;
" VWel, He ain't " said the obstinate Mrs.&#xD;
Killigan.&#xD;
"Then I must pray harder," said Miss Law.&#xD;
ra, calmly.&#xD;
"Indeed, miss, I hope you had a pleaMsnt&#xD;
time the summer ; you desarve it," said Mrs-.&#xD;
Xilligan, touched.&#xD;
&#xD;
ST t&#xD;
&#xD;
*&#xD;
&#xD;
Tan    you, said Miss Lamr, i've en-&#xD;
joyed it very much."&#xD;
The case of Jerry greatly dighted Miss&#xD;
Laura and Mr. Allston, and they at once took&#xD;
great interest in Geurze. Mrs. Stuyvesant&#xD;
and Mary promised to patronize his basket, and&#xD;
gtve him a Bible and Hymn Book, and made&#xD;
him promise to go to church with his wife.&#xD;
The old lady revived a httle, as things grew&#xD;
better, and spoke less dolefully of 'Pappy&#xD;
The rush down Jug    Alley after George,&#xD;
stirred Thomnas' heart with pity for the wretch-.&#xD;
ed inhabitants of that quarter. He saw them&#xD;
traded, miserable and friendless, and he&#xD;
nged.,to earrv 'h  igh of God's word to ii.&#xD;
muine their darkness, and to tell them of the&#xD;
Friend of sinners.  As Mrs. Kiligan had&#xD;
grown quite restive under what she appeared&#xD;
to consider the infiction o hearing the Bible&#xD;
remd, Thomas concluded to take Jerry, his B&#xD;
&#xD;
_                          _&#xD;
;'&#xD;
&#xD;
r 'Y&#xD;
&#xD;
fl&#xD;
^ .L&#xD;
i   w&#xD;
rr U&#xD;
4&#xD;
v +&#xD;
&#xD;
=;&#xD;
'&#xD;
"&#xD;
&#xD;
,s. .....                                 Mw XNkKYR&#xD;
VYM1 ' :ffi' ' ^'i_&#xD;
fie{ t&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC8382-00000071"/>&#xD;
ie, and a few picture ards and te, and o&#xD;
into the Alley, after Sanday school, and taking&#xD;
possession of the door-step, read and talk, and&#xD;
nay-be pray with whuver would listen to&#xD;
him. Once, twice, Thomas did this, several&#xD;
women, some half-grown children, and a man&#xD;
or two were his auditors, lis:tning more from&#xD;
curiosity than any better moiwe.&#xD;
But all unconseiou lv Thomas hal fierce&#xD;
enemies in Jug Alicy.    They called him&#xD;
" Methodist     Parson,  and many other&#xD;
names, and spoke to each thiler of - t witing&#xD;
his neck,"  c racking is head," and -brain-&#xD;
ing       - him. That Thomas was tryng to rescue&#xD;
George frgma bondage tz whiskey was anp Un-&#xD;
pardotia~e uJmnee; the Alley had its code&#xD;
of laws, and its tut-ive Slave Law against all&#xD;
helping the bandsmen of whiskey to treedomn.&#xD;
The grugzery keeper. frm whom Thoma% hads&#xD;
carried off George, was partieularly loud andl&#xD;
violent against our pie-man, and the third&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
Sabbath, when Thomas, with Jerry at his&#xD;
side, was sitting on the front steps of a Jug&#xD;
Alley domicile, and talking in his ourn enaint&#xD;
way about lost men and their Redeemer,&#xD;
Paddy McClure had     his wildest followers&#xD;
gathered in his low groggery, while himself&#xD;
stood treat in strychnine whiskey. Yet a little&#xD;
while and Paddy McClure, and his so called&#xD;
triends, came roaring and gesticulating about&#xD;
and Jerry, upsetting the children,&#xD;
rou2..vyipumhingz the women, and swearing.and&#xD;
thr ate.ing a: a Pearfu   t. rte  Stones were&#xD;
th rowni. a door cera hed in, tme windlows were&#xD;
broken : a1  while TiimaS, dholdin  fst to&#xD;
Jerry trid to parley or escape, louder rose&#xD;
the yellS, - hild the b'ye   Pour whiskev&#xD;
down the :hrats or 'em: Clear ou the hiri-&#xD;
tics : Give u their Bible. man, we'll bile the&#xD;
kettle tour hot p   Winch wid it."  And while&#xD;
one party tore off Thuas coat and hat,&#xD;
another dragcd off Jerry, and served him in&#xD;
the same manner.&#xD;
&#xD;
71&#xD;
&#xD;
o.&#xD;
_&#xD;
;   ..&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC8382-00000072"/>&#xD;
The echoesfthisc"            r       the&#xD;
Police, and two or three blue coats ctain&amp;amp; tc&#xD;
the rescue. Thomas, seeing entreaty and ex-.&#xD;
potltion vain, was raianthy defending him-&#xD;
self, and as the rumorof the ajpruach of the&#xD;
"Stars" Came about, Paddy Me~ure yelled&#xD;
"finish  the hiritiei  and the men   about&#xD;
thomas, wh a Ifew parting Llows, Ieft him&#xD;
almost senseless on the pavement. With that&#xD;
keen direction tha: characterizes the modern&#xD;
police, the real rioters Were puiery allwed to&#xD;
make ;a whie. Jerry wh,, wit a brui d arm&#xD;
and bieedu~snr  w i ,was. struglng 'vit  &#xD;
tOrm entor ai fi&#xD;
bleeding tEwe andi Trained arm, was lv 1n r&#xD;
te pavemnt'i  were arrewzedI a-' di~turLbers oJ'&#xD;
the public pseae-, and charged with ritiig aud&#xD;
drunkennes%, were hurried off to the $tati s&#xD;
House and Bee up-.&#xD;
Jerry bvege to be put with Ar. T igg&#xD;
sceued i getting a pail of water where-&#xD;
&#xD;
jin to  tba their wounds. A doleful ending&#xD;
. this to the bUessed Lord's day.&#xD;
"Thank the Lord you're here. Jerry, my&#xD;
son," said poor Thomas, faintly, "and not to&#xD;
he led away with them bad ones. '&#xD;
"Oh, o    &amp;amp;' blubbered Jerry, "we're in&#xD;
jail, and all our decent close is torn, and there&#xD;
amt noboy to mind the st:alL nor Mr. Dodd."&#xD;
ItNevr mind all that." said Thomas, who,&#xD;
very aint and fUll of pain, was lying down.&#xD;
S The Lord can take care of all'that."&#xD;
But we're in jail,' ybbd Jerry.&#xD;
-"Wei. sonnv. when we're wrongfully ae-&#xD;
eused we must take it patiently,    replied&#xD;
Thouma ; "jt in:think how many wrong thing&#xD;
our Lord and Ma:er wvas 'eusel of."&#xD;
O-o--o-' moaned Jerry, "a jail's such an&#xD;
awful bad place to be, o-o-o-o.&#xD;
"Come, come. sonnur  said Thomas "Paul&#xD;
and Silas in prison sang and gave thanks and&#xD;
so can we. A jail wa'n't too bad a place for&#xD;
&#xD;
I4&#xD;
&#xD;
e R m&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC8382-00000073"/>&#xD;
ma  mn nw r&#xD;
&#xD;
an angel to go to, to see Peter, and John and&#xD;
Peter went to prison a time or two. What&#xD;
wasn't too had for them ain't to be grumbled&#xD;
at by as; cheer up, Jerry, me boy, the Lord&#xD;
will make it all go together for good ret."&#xD;
There was a long silence.- Jerry watched&#xD;
Thomas, and saw that he was in a deep&#xD;
rCer,    o a neI tht was not paijnfu±. "Don'lt&#xD;
you feel bad at all?" he said.&#xD;
"   cir 1.QerY.  repned Tmmnas, -  I feel&#xD;
like David did in the Valley.  I will fear no&#xD;
evil fr Thou art with me. ThyA rod and ty&#xD;
staff they comfort me.&#xD;
SRut.? sait errv, -suppose we gets Zent&#xD;
up to-morrow stid of bein let go.&#xD;
That won't be," said Thomas, decidedly,&#xD;
"for the Bible says ie shall bringr forth thy&#xD;
judgment as light and thy righteousness like&#xD;
noonday,' or words to that effect, son Jerry."&#xD;
"But the perlice don't know nothin' 'but&#xD;
you," persisted Jerry-&#xD;
&#xD;
14$&#xD;
&#xD;
Jr47&#xD;
"Th   i Lord do," said Thoa;" and the&#xD;
Lord knows the magistrates, and has their&#xD;
hearts in his hand to turn where he will; don't&#xD;
you fret, Jerry; we're in prison, 'tis true, hut&#xD;
hles the Lord, he ain't ashamed to come to&#xD;
prison 'iong with us, and He says 'all thing&#xD;
hll work together for good to them that love&#xD;
the Lojrd;' and I know I do. Now, Jerry,&#xD;
vo ugive Ut the Commandments. I want to&#xD;
M#ee :haz vou ain'  oro them since last Sun-&#xD;
day."&#xD;
Meaunte the new of Thomas' ignobe cap-&#xD;
ture "as :riumphatcyreported b Juz Alley,&#xD;
and 4Ju: Aiyvs vron of the atfuir sPeedily&#xD;
rach   te tars of Mrs. Kiicn. The dame&#xD;
qui     tted       t prCeiv the rights&#xD;
el the matter a: once. She rushed into Mrs.&#xD;
Dods.-room,her best cap-s:rirg  fimg and&#xD;
her Sunday calico rustling in high indignation,&#xD;
and her tongue pouring forth a torrent of bh&#xD;
a.%rat, without let or hindrance&#xD;
&#xD;
,Y&#xD;
ti.=&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
F  \! Y-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC8382-00000074"/>&#xD;
40&#xD;
&#xD;
illa&#xD;
~-nw~flStLL&#xD;
&#xD;
. Have ye heard the news of our Thomas?&#xD;
dSe cried.  Here's Ju  Alte  be   l&#xD;
and mauninz hun and th         an  then gets&#xD;
tem taenr up  r iotn   Bad      t   xwrv&#xD;
mother son   ue    Sur      t&#xD;
as nice a man as Iaer trttr&#xD;
has molntev Li  up a:               rr.2r~   at~&#xD;
Sa     I a&#xD;
tuuse mar neX&#xD;
sapleen, 11hat       t~  8&#xD;
nor wa.&#xD;
La em m t:e auu       U     Srra :a d&#xD;
tht Thouta hk.nam ;u ov :  uKn   * a:&#xD;
took to loukini' uit  fir o her filkN us. It&#xD;
yer taul: Gieerg  D   d;i     arn'     'e&#xD;
has Set foiks azn  Thaa ant ht&#xD;
glowerim aKn uaki.' :radr t: run to Jut2AP&#xD;
for whiskey-, to bV a baqe wid, after im tha:%s&#xD;
gone can no moirc zuard ye&#xD;
After this tiradto M1ri  Kimfbn 'topiwed for&#xD;
breath, and her feartui eitnas about George&#xD;
""" fn~~~    rasriek of dimay fromn Mag-&#xD;
&#xD;
TE   oa    STAL--&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
k&#xD;
L&#xD;
V&#xD;
&#xD;
149&#xD;
&#xD;
r  gie,and a groan  Mrs. To4d the ou   r,&#xD;
while the "old woman'" broke forth in this&#xD;
wise : --"O, it's sin to wish Pappy Dodd&#xD;
out ofm or; but pears like he could do some-&#xD;
thinz for Thomas if he were here ; and what'lI&#xD;
he say to George ?  Oh. dear, Pappy Dodd&#xD;
was such a main hand - but' suddenly break-&#xD;
nz off her lamentation, seein' Pappy Dodd's&#xD;
cone where we can't get no good ohim,&#xD;
there's the Lord can -lork after Mr. Twigg,&#xD;
caa t he?&#xD;
I dnt know,    sail the unrighteous Mrs.&#xD;
KUIan,    Lu: there's Geo-r;, arah, he's&#xD;
. zgad ot the throube and will run for Paddy&#xD;
McClure that did the wicked trn for Thomas&#xD;
bad cess to hiun&#xD;
I won':, said George, stoutly, "less I g&#xD;
to knock his hea!i Ju   Allev's abused Mr&#xD;
Twizz, Illnever utn a- mf oot-th1ere again,&#xD;
Mrs. ith an."&#xD;
wishJu" A!Ig'v was burrntsaid"Mrs.&#xD;
K iW-hiu               UiLr&#xD;
&#xD;
°SS4'&#xD;
'_   x&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC8382-00000075"/>&#xD;
Tir CflgSTALL.&#xD;
twat&#xD;
can We do for Th&#xD;
irs. DodJ, reieved of -xe  a     ,   i&#xD;
staring 'Ole Mt anCetS aout (heorge's&#xD;
What ThaT! W d   ure&#xD;
ed George.as                    de&#xD;
"0Oeh1" said 31t  . ,.l an"ibuh&#xD;
and k-              Adra,&#xD;
shallnot e deerte, aly, al asbsies&#xD;
s       ft tit tu k&#xD;
Stall eh  I        u-         the Coirner&#xD;
IN- rr&#xD;
t o  ri s e   T h e n -  r           u s&#xD;
she said .. tir.iderat4            i v&#xD;
and   n. :    ur -       s        r&#xD;
t  r       ai                     t ri&#xD;
ti Airm Atup o-    him a bo-ut Thom.. and&#xD;
ihi 1 nd up tuqn# and See J-ustice d900&#xD;
Georg anJ  once   k 1.&#xD;
_"., .        aril  Ii&#xD;
Geur.  ~ t- c ~hat and&#xD;
old ia!                 a re41~s into his&#xD;
quit  coL:  (4*:tnk -j aj    r-  K~&#xD;
t for thalt&#xD;
"a  ealdn&#xD;
1k w  t-ar- ark -h- Georger returnd&#xD;
&#xD;
he had missed Mr. Allston, and then followed&#xD;
him to church, and at last had seen him and&#xD;
obtained his promise to look after Mr. Twigg,&#xD;
early in the morning.&#xD;
Mrs. Killigan regarded George suspicious-&#xD;
lv.   Is it the thruth y're telliu, se said;&#xD;
SonicM a near  e. and let me see if vevve been&#xD;
at the drink. .Arrahbiut I b-lieve ve've been&#xD;
dU' the riht thin: had luck to the day&#xD;
Thom" a  .T wU: o ot into throube; it' Becky&#xD;
.K i:awi.lave n" rest till  s out ain-&#xD;
34 u n    had growxn dark in the little&#xD;
I      w  '   T  g&#xD;
\ wLre Ti mafland 4JerryV were loced up.&#xD;
Jerry, boy ," said Tihomas,- we'l say our&#xD;
ran get to leep, to Cee if my head&#xD;
will quIt aching.  That is a fine thought,&#xD;
Jerry. -the eet of the Lord are in every&#xD;
lace.' Anw what a text that was this morn-&#xD;
ing, Jerry - The Lord shal deliver me from&#xD;
every evil and bring inc into his 1eaveIely&#xD;
Kingdom.&#xD;
&#xD;
'&#xD;
ip&#xD;
°fxi&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC8382-00000076"/>&#xD;
159&#xD;
&#xD;
Now Jerry had in himself so much of the&#xD;
"old leaven," that he was not duly Comforted&#xD;
by Thomas' quotations, but now. his gathered&#xD;
wrath broke forth as he exclaimed, "Well,&#xD;
hope old McClure and his bummers will never&#xD;
get there, 1 d1: ll's knocked and kicked me&#xD;
a grst of times, the old wretch  Don't I&#xD;
wish his rascaiyx grrog shop, wo uld burn, downi&#xD;
on his head, and :hey  all break their latefid&#xD;
old legs and........&#xD;
Jerry, Jerry '" cried Thomas, hold up,&#xD;
while I deal von our a verse ----- - Lay aide al&#xD;
M a  liee.  al  guile,  and  y poersies,  and  env msi&#xD;
and all evil SpeaJking.' £Larn tha JWrry, and&#xD;
then mind it.?&#xD;
&#xD;
lo&#xD;
&#xD;
F&#xD;
t&#xD;
C'&#xD;
&#xD;
tRl  OUT OF DARKNESS.&#xD;
&#xD;
y the next morning, and found&#xD;
themseve locked up in the Sta-&#xD;
tnin Ilouw. instead of being in their snug attic&#xD;
all rady for a btrt to teie Corner Stall, Jerry&#xD;
brIke ;orth into renewed lamentations, bt&#xD;
Thomas. after a moments thought, said,&#xD;
Here's a verse fr your comfort, son Jerry;&#xD;
My soul is escaped as a bird out of the snare&#xD;
of the owe, he narei         ena&#xD;
escaped.' The Lord's done higcr things fo'&#xD;
rhmas Twg      than to get him out of thi&#xD;
Station House."&#xD;
&#xD;
nfl&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER VI.&#xD;
&#xD;
77&#xD;
x&#xD;
F m&#xD;
i&#xD;
a            dip&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC8382-00000077"/>&#xD;
154HEmC&#xD;
&#xD;
All this did not console poor Jerry, and&#xD;
Thomas said, " Come, son, we'll have wor-&#xD;
ship, to cheer us up a bit."&#xD;
Jerry listened while Mr. Twig read'a&#xD;
chapter, and then both knelt while the worthy&#xD;
man prayed ; but it came to pass that Thomas&#xD;
was much more exercise.I about other people&#xD;
than about himself. and his supplications were&#xD;
chiefly for forgiveness for McClure &amp;amp; Co., and&#xD;
for protection for Geory  Dodd. Jerry rose&#xD;
from his knees quite dissatisfied, and began to&#xD;
complain in this fashion&#xD;
"say you paint hardly said one word 'bout&#xD;
Us. You spent all the time taikin' bout Paddy-&#xD;
McClure an' Geor-re Dodd."&#xD;
"Well, son Jerry, don't you care for&#xD;
them"..&#xD;
"   1es       care more for us.   Why&#xD;
didn't you tell the Lord what sort of fis we d&#xD;
got int?&#xD;
" Whyi. Jerrv -the TLord1 knows i.Srig.r&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
I -&#xD;
&#xD;
LN&#xD;
&#xD;
ter says *He knows what things ye have need&#xD;
of before ye ask Him'_&#xD;
"Wtat's the use of prayin' then?" says&#xD;
Jerry.&#xD;
"Because, son Jerry, it's the Lord's ap-&#xD;
pointed means of getting blessin's."&#xD;
- Ten," says Jerry, briskly, "why don't&#xD;
yon axen what Von wants?&#xD;
" Well, Jerry," said Thomas, "I'm sorry&#xD;
yudon't like my prayer mostly 'eause the&#xD;
promise is to two or three that are agreed.&#xD;
IHtwsomever, Jerry me boy, I hopes the Lord&#xD;
wiLl be better to us nor all our fears, and that&#xD;
e li d  for us over and above what we cn&#xD;
or think."&#xD;
i  e dn :," said Jerry, with a sniffle,&#xD;
he won't do much for us this time.&#xD;
Thomas took refuge in the little Bible that,&#xD;
havin: been in Jerry's trousers pocket, had&#xD;
not been  C4niieadby     ,. 1 Ju  Ally ritters.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC8382-00000078"/>&#xD;
the window as possible, for his sight was dim,&#xD;
and his spectacles had been destroyed the day&#xD;
bfore, when he cried out joyfully,&#xD;
"Come here, Jerry, and let me deal ou&#xD;
out a Scripter that just comes pat to what&#xD;
you've been faulting me for -. And the Lord&#xD;
turned again the captivity of Job, when he&#xD;
prayed for his friends.t  There, don't that hit&#xD;
your case extactl, Jerry ?  Now mind my&#xD;
words, Jerry, the Lord's guing to bring light&#xD;
out of darkness for us, or I'm  mucdy mis-&#xD;
taken."&#xD;
The hour for the appearance in court of&#xD;
Thomas Twig; and Jerry Ilockney, charged&#xD;
with assault and battery, and rioting, speedily&#xD;
arrived.&#xD;
The two had washed as well as they could,&#xD;
and combed their heads with Thouas' wooden&#xD;
pocket comb, but despite this care they had&#xD;
certainly  a very  disreptable appearance.&#xD;
Neithr had a coat, their shirts were torn and&#xD;
&#xD;
15t&#xD;
&#xD;
a&#xD;
e&#xD;
r&#xD;
.T SST.&#xD;
i&#xD;
1aTM'k&#xD;
&#xD;
spotted with blood, their trousers were well&#xD;
da hed with the black slime of Jug Alley, and&#xD;
their black eyes and swollen faces made them&#xD;
hook like a wretctkd pair of prize fighters&#xD;
Public sentiment was evidently against them.&#xD;
Anler the uffences of tie two prisoners had&#xD;
b    rapid1y inflicted, and the uproarious&#xD;
character of Jug Allev adverted to, ax4 the&#xD;
necessity of -xmakin  an example," or that.&#xD;
quarter set forth.- in ans er to a question ad-&#xD;
dresed to TEomas, our friend r plied:-&#xD;
N.your 1h mr. I've asked n counseL but&#xD;
oifthe Lord ; and the Lord' couwsel is to tell&#xD;
tetru:n. s:raigzht to the pint. IEve never&#xD;
lived in Jug Alk-v.y your honor, and I don't&#xD;
jusly know a I've ken there more than a&#xD;
time or two. I goes t1ere. your honor, to read&#xD;
a bit of Scripiter, and to give a little goo ad-&#xD;
vi..int to a tet of iost iuner , your honor,&#xD;
that I jaindv  ee was a living' without God,&#xD;
and without hope in the world, which I leave&#xD;
&#xD;
-S&#xD;
&#xD;
;,,,&#xD;
.T_.&#xD;
':&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC8382-00000079"/>&#xD;
TEE CORNER StAL1&#xD;
&#xD;
to your.honor is a bad case for anymanto be&#xD;
"His Honor'" winced, and a broad smile,&#xD;
passed over the faces of -those gathered in the&#xD;
court&#xD;
"But how did you get into such a row?"&#xD;
was the next query.&#xD;
lour honor, the natral heart is agin the&#xD;
Lords work. Tve no doubt but that the Evil&#xD;
One led en those Jug Alley folk to set agin me&#xD;
and the boy. The boy, your honor, is my&#xD;
adopted son, and I am hoping to make a decent&#xD;
sugar-baker of bim. I account for the fight'&#xD;
thusdy :- twat I'm dead seteagir whiskey, and&#xD;
they're dead et for it; an 1- they pitched. into&#xD;
me pretty Lvely. your honor, and I didn't fight&#xD;
no more than I cotul possibly h , not consid-&#xD;
eri' tig tin is a Christian work for Sunday&#xD;
nor any other day.&#xD;
Have youl any blv to vouch for the truth&#xD;
of thee statements?" asked "His honor,"&#xD;
who was quite taken with Thomas's oddities.&#xD;
&#xD;
r vedone an honest business in thi city,&#xD;
sir, kbr near fifty year. For five year .'ve&#xD;
a Corner Stall on Union Square, sir, and&#xD;
I 2:1 think pretty nigh every body knew&#xD;
1huas Twigg, and would say a good word&#xD;
Sr  Iim. hoWs, your honor. that mosly we&#xD;
a    1 a:  much account a we th ink wei."&#xD;
Tie smile lthat was Qing about deerned&#xD;
ie a laugh in some case, ; and just here&#xD;
;cared a friend in need, who turned the&#xD;
scals  f justice fairly in favor of Thomas&#xD;
T vig. Mr. Aliston came upon the scene,&#xD;
and s on Uhowed Thomas to be a victim d&#xD;
iereCUtioni a good man abused for doing goo,&#xD;
and the .cases of Georze Dodd and Jerry&#xD;
beinz menio ned, Thomas was honorably dis-&#xD;
missed from custody. His honor highly corn-&#xD;
mened him for his benevolence, and remark-&#xD;
ing that in making decent men out of George&#xD;
and Jerry, Thomas was doing ,good service for&#xD;
the commonwealth of New York.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
A-,777777--&#xD;
&#xD;
Tim&#xD;
&#xD;
.1&#xD;
,,,=A&#xD;
&#xD;
....&#xD;
-         '  "'&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC8382-00000080"/>&#xD;
#TU VeRER STLL&#xD;
&#xD;
Sympathizing with Thomas's mortification&#xD;
at his unseemly appearance. Mr. Allton pro.&#xD;
cured a hack and took him back to No. 27.&#xD;
Mrs. Kileigan, George and Mrs. Dodd had&#xD;
gune to business, but Thoai  aon Succeeded&#xD;
in making himself and Jerry coitrtable with&#xD;
bath, Itod and clean clothes. Mr. Ailston&#xD;
bought a lotion for their wounds and bruises,&#xD;
and then went home promuiwiwg them a visi--&#xD;
from Miss Stuyvesant.&#xD;
The misrtunes of Thomas TwXi    worked&#xD;
for the uphuildin: of the strength of George&#xD;
Dodd ; he wa: of leading strznzs. he could&#xD;
go after whiskey if le would, but all at once&#xD;
he was resolute against it. That king whiskey;&#xD;
should make a bea t f Gieorze was one thing,&#xD;
but that it shuuhl make a martyr ot Thomafl&#xD;
Twigg was quite anther. Now that Thomas&#xD;
was in trouble, Gere woUld not make mat-&#xD;
ters worse by proving recreant himself.&#xD;
In a few days Thomas and Jerry were back&#xD;
&#xD;
at their business. Thomas had replaced their&#xD;
Sunday coats, and Becky Killigan was busy&#xD;
baking for the stall, and making new shirts to&#xD;
supply the ones destroyed by Jug Alley.&#xD;
The matter of the uproar in the Alley had&#xD;
not been allowed to drop, some attention bad&#xD;
been turned to the place, and to the perform-&#xD;
anees of its denizens; and the result was that&#xD;
Paddy McClure and his two most sigorons&#xD;
supporter; were arrested and sentenced each&#xD;
to s months in the penitentiary, the McClure&#xD;
r    rv was tiloed, rent xva duei. and the&#xD;
Clure taily were turned into the street,&#xD;
The 5ther families were quite destitute. Pad&#xD;
dy and hij friends had made matter' -worse by&#xD;
reis:inc :h-ir arrest. amli knvvhin: dTown one&#xD;
of the emeers who made it. Al! tis did&#xD;
Jerry report: t' Thoma, with triumphant look&#xD;
and voice, on returning to the stal trom the&#xD;
hunmbe establishment where he had been to&#xD;
learn the hih arts of making taffy and mint&#xD;
stiek.&#xD;
&#xD;
__.  -&#xD;
&#xD;
w00&#xD;
&#xD;
i1L lull. Irsr&#xD;
&#xD;
lam&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC8382-00000081"/>&#xD;
YAte&#xD;
&#xD;
"Now, Jerry," said Thomas, "here's what&#xD;
I want you to take notice to. Just look how&#xD;
Scripter comes true. 'The wicked shall be&#xD;
taken in his own pit - His violent dealings&#xD;
shall come down on his own pate.&#xD;
I'm glad of it," said Jerry.&#xD;
" Now, Jerry," said Thomas, " don't rejoice&#xD;
over them that fall. Mind vou don't do it,&#xD;
Jerry,. or you'll get into trouble.&#xD;
having said this, Thomas bad derry mind&#xD;
the stall and not Iegiect CUstomCS. and put-&#xD;
ting on his knit jacket. Thomas went as fast as&#xD;
possible to Jug Alley. Not surely to triumph&#xD;
over the fallen - no, he went to help the helip&#xD;
less and cheer the unhappy, He got Mrs.&#xD;
McClure, her children and her mali lot t&#xD;
furniture, into a room near No. 2T, and tave&#xD;
her such good advice and encouragement that,&#xD;
lxking forward to °ix :months' freedom  from&#xD;
whiskey tyranny, he made everything about&#xD;
her as (ican as possible. and went out for some&#xD;
work whereby she Might buy bread for her&#xD;
(&#xD;
&#xD;
u;n&#xD;
&#xD;
£uuilv. Not less did our friend Thomas do for&#xD;
the other women, happily relieved of their&#xD;
drunken husbands, and having finished hii&#xD;
wOrk for them, by asking Miss Stuyvesant to&#xD;
k after them a little, he slept that night&#xD;
with a quiet heart.&#xD;
Good deeds as these did not go unrewarded.&#xD;
Jug Alley was amazed at this new method&#xD;
ut revenue. Thomas. from  being hated and&#xD;
desired. was hated as their patron saiut, and&#xD;
nabazh afternoon a delegation, composed&#xD;
o a raged woman, a ragged baby, and two.&#xD;
ragged btys,waited upon him at No. :., re-&#xD;
questng that he would "come baa and read&#xD;
the bok and give them a bit of a peachment;&#xD;
suure wasn't vthe all wlli to hear him.&#xD;
o on those very sttps whence a fortnight&#xD;
before he had been so ignomniously expelled,&#xD;
stood Thomas, with Jerry at his side, Thomas,&#xD;
with his new Bible in his hand. and his heart&#xD;
glowMg with new love and -ta,. and t...enmg in&#xD;
&#xD;
a&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
:  ,&#xD;
-   _.   r        -&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC8382-00000082"/>&#xD;
isown earnest, queer, simple way, "just the&#xD;
thing they wanted to know." So for Thomas&#xD;
the light had coe  ut of the darkness&#xD;
But for other than Thomas, light came out&#xD;
of darkness. Becky Killigan was one of those&#xD;
in "gross darkness   upon whom   light did&#xD;
shine. Shining, it revealed so much of irrate&#xD;
corruption, as made Becky first angry. and&#xD;
then unlappy, and 2ettin desperate nuder the&#xD;
smarting of the wounds of sin. she set to work&#xD;
to heal them herself. But One Good   Ihv-&#xD;
cian, with th true Bah of Gilea. can heal&#xD;
-   the si-sick soul. Becky Killian. setting up&#xD;
for a spiritual quack, and calling th;er spiritual&#xD;
quacks to her aid, Only made matrs worse.&#xD;
On the evening of a stormy tail dar. Thom.&#xD;
as closed up his stall earlier than usual, and&#xD;
goin  home, Jerry ;as wo n s sound asleep,&#xD;
while Thomas sat hr his stand reading his&#xD;
beloved Biibie. A slow step came all along&#xD;
the stairs, and there was a knock at the door&#xD;
&#xD;
"come in, said Mr. Twigg, and Mrs. Kiligan&#xD;
entered. Thomas handed her the fine yellow&#xD;
chair and closed his book, saying, "Well,&#xD;
prdner, do you want to settle accounts, or&#xD;
count over the money .&#xD;
Och, no it's. not-the money that threubles&#xD;
me V said Mrs. Kidigan, with a deep sigh.&#xD;
have you had bad luck with yor bak.-&#xD;
Sa  akied Thomas.&#xD;
"Faith. I haven't, it's all goand she&#xD;
si hed again.&#xD;
Have ou lost -anythig ?"&#xD;
I have. an I haven't," said Mrs. Kiligan.&#xD;
"Are von siek ? persisted Thomas.&#xD;
Och, hone, but I am."&#xD;
Why do..'t you go see the doctor, pard-&#xD;
ner&#xD;
"lowly Virzin don't I know it's a sick-&#xD;
ness none or 'em all can cure.&#xD;
Why, pardner" cried Thomas, now real-&#xD;
ly alarmed. "Is it consumption, or mebby its&#xD;
of the heart."&#xD;
&#xD;
.;&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
,  s&#xD;
M 8&#xD;
,&#xD;
,a :&#xD;
it -&#xD;
a&#xD;
=+ i&#xD;
_~ '1 i&#xD;
:4 - '&#xD;
= ,,++° _&#xD;
' a^.,.&#xD;
'Cir&#xD;
&#xD;
;&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC8382-00000083"/>&#xD;
1.1 coas0a SA             167&#xD;
&#xD;
"Troth, but you've hit it now. Thoia"&#xD;
"But the doctor could help you, pardner&#xD;
or mebb vo are deceiving yourself; -o see&#xD;
the doctor, pardner."&#xD;
' The doctor i: it:.' cried Mrs. Killign,&#xD;
angrily,  and what will the doctor do for me!&#xD;
What can I teE him over an' above that I fe&#xD;
sick over the war' Thomas Twi2.. and Mis&#xD;
Stuves.1.ant ra an i alkd anl prayed over&#xD;
me. tti aLl t  comfTr,"t isclean ar out of&#xD;
me li. at. I    :t Thnmas, and sorra the&#xD;
dayv he sayvse the d eb r&#xD;
Thomas; dronpi'd i ihead for m-rv shame.&#xD;
lie i= prye I r Mrs. JKm'a this mani&#xD;
months, a::. yI  Low      of heart to uind c-&#xD;
stand the- b?-:mnn Af t:e :acious answmc&#xD;
lit Ia pryed I: was, it wa,.      lih e had&#xD;
ezp'ck d :Uais reply  he took hiinself severely&#xD;
to :ask. II w 'asily he had becon discour-&#xD;
aged, Lai harted4 over Becky's resistance to&#xD;
the truth ;he had fadlen into a mere sform of&#xD;
prayer for hers It is truly wonderful what a&#xD;
&#xD;
very small amount of faith can be sifted out&#xD;
cf all the prayers that are uttered. No won-&#xD;
tr dnt so often they go no higher than our&#xD;
leads. Faithless prayers have leen among&#xD;
the clogs of the church, from its earliest age.&#xD;
Thomas was so long sent, that Mrs. Kill-&#xD;
pan aid hiarflv, Ii dbe goinz back agi; it's&#xD;
Lul ye care for -the trouble v-ve made me,&#xD;
Lid luck to you."&#xD;
)h. pardoer   cried Thomas, - In too&#xD;
gad. a1:. too ashamed to know what to say.&#xD;
An you ought to be ashamed; a man that&#xD;
a disturbed :e peace and quiet of a well-&#xD;
de in' wo man like Becky iliiean.&#xD;
(Oh. pardner, it's the best thing that ever&#xD;
happened " yoAu to be anxious and troubled&#xD;
or y our peace was just like floati -easy along&#xD;
iii a little boat, bound to zo over a bi; fall and&#xD;
destroy vou. It is the work of God's spirit&#xD;
that disturbs you, pardner; and not the work&#xD;
of Thomas Twig;. And there's but one way&#xD;
for yon to gtit ato d, s UreSa pace-&#xD;
&#xD;
-Y V.&#xD;
a"i6  t ,&#xD;
&#xD;
-a~*Iur&#xD;
&#xD;
Ull, 1 01&#xD;
&#xD;
.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC8382-00000084"/>&#xD;
-H  - F" ttLL.m&#xD;
&#xD;
16          in ciltii&amp;amp;si irat&#xD;
"And what may that be?" demanded Mrs.&#xD;
Killigan. "Shure, Eve tried fifty and none&#xD;
would do. Did n't I try to drive thorn dol.&#xD;
drums away for weeks, and they wouldn't he&#xD;
drK    Didn't I mark my ways, and they never&#xD;
to do a wrong thing, hut be as innocent as a&#xD;
new born babe, andit wouldn't do at all at all.&#xD;
And then didn't I go to the praste, and he&#xD;
said do penance ;. and I did it ? Share it was&#xD;
ila  ~     .T        .'          r&#xD;
~4$ t  e amtw 4 ue IIL  maUI  t do) it. ien 1i&#xD;
confessed, an I got absolution. Shure, says&#xD;
he, your sins are all done away cane ; but I&#xD;
knew in me heart they wasn't, fur I felt em&#xD;
like a red hot burden weighin' down me souL&#xD;
Then, Thomas, I paid out me money, and if&#xD;
I paid one dollar I paid ten, Lthough each one&#xD;
came like me heart's bood, and sorra a hit of&#xD;
good did it do me.&#xD;
"No," said Thonnas, eagerly, "and the&#xD;
priest deceived you when he .said it would;&#xD;
doesn't the Bible say itself, 'Thy  money&#xD;
&#xD;
peTnsh with thee, because thou thoughtest the&#xD;
gift of God might be purchased with money!"&#xD;
T"3.            !D ;F at.z zmu S a  arnto fl&#xD;
"and clean in the face of it he tell't me to buy&#xD;
me pardon! Out on him for a rapscallion ;&#xD;
is me money clean thrown away ?"&#xD;
Indee it is, and if vn'd~ spent ahudd&#xD;
it had been all the same."&#xD;
"L flut I'd spent a 1hundredAyes andi Auv&#xD;
LtFUi.  2xILIS j in a  4L .1ti .4   v- an.&#xD;
hundred, which is just al! I hare, to zet aisy!"&#xD;
kIt wuld have dIone no rod pardner; it is&#xD;
not mnney.r but lood that takes away sin.&#xD;
Ti:ank tlhe : d Lord, I've got peace and I&#xD;
ever paid a penny for it it was a free gift&#xD;
bought with the blood of 1te Lord Jesus&#xD;
c h .o                         d   e u h o n e ,"  z r o a n e d  M r s.  K illig a n ,  r o  k -&#xD;
to and fro.  was hver a woman that un&#xD;
fort'nit as Becky Killigan. The work and the&#xD;
sorrow and the time ndtl ihn throuhl' that&#xD;
fve spent and all fr nothing&#xD;
&#xD;
1     ; r                                   7144++,f,,as&#xD;
1&#xD;
&#xD;
;, ;&#xD;
_ ;&#xD;
.. °=s r&#xD;
.r£&#xD;
K_&#xD;
&#xD;
-_  .;&#xD;
&#xD;
+  _              _ u..+1&#xD;
...}-   -"-"- ---nv.nrl.. -rte  M+ -C e       +.vy,&#xD;
1 R'                           Y   m'       -  .&#xD;
'   .,f&#xD;
&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC8382-00000085"/>&#xD;
1M 0,  STALL&#xD;
&#xD;
tUEcora TAL.171&#xD;
&#xD;
"The Bible tells of just such a case," said&#xD;
Thomas; "you listen and Il deal it out from&#xD;
me mind. A poor woman was sorely sick, and&#xD;
k suffered a      tmearA snt alshe had&#xD;
on doctorin', and was nothing made better but&#xD;
only zrew worse."&#xD;
aidi, its just me own ease intirei!&#xD;
cried Mrs. Killan;  and did she iver get&#xD;
help ? "'&#xD;
"  es. she found a Phwirian at last who&#xD;
Cured her.&#xD;
" Truth :and whIpbat di hIe charge ?'' aked&#xD;
the bniihted IMr~. Kii an&#xD;
-   an     ai Thas, - it was the Lord&#xD;
Jesus, an  he cured her and bid her go in&#xD;
peaw.&#xD;
hen po  Mrs. Kilig an, here in the nine&#xD;
teenth century. :ook up the ery that Job lifted&#xD;
when the world 'as voung, " ), that I knew&#xD;
where I       fih: find hin ' and Thomas straitty-&#xD;
responded,  Hie i not far from every one of&#xD;
&#xD;
/&#xD;
&#xD;
as;" and in his own plain, heart-taught and&#xD;
heart-touching way, he preached to her-Jesus.&#xD;
'rk, ntdx   Mn Killiaan- rt hold of one&#xD;
glorious truth, the willing power of Jesus ; to&#xD;
that fact she clung.   No longer rebelling&#xD;
aainst 1earmI the word, she sought intruc-&#xD;
turn rcontnuiV     -&#xD;
UnIr heclear shining of the Truth, the&#xD;
tt p s :r gtii  and the black niht ofS oh-&#xD;
sanaCy cicaredI awayx , an1 at 1at she, te3Uld&#xD;
  up that  ter .aying  f Jo,  I have&#xD;
beard~ a e by tihe hearing uf thet ear; but&#xD;
I w :ner eve Seet   thee: wherefore I abhor&#xD;
n   0 and repent in dust and ashes.&#xD;
-- Idccd," said Becky Killigan to Tho'mas,&#xD;
'the diucrence is curi . WViy, bere Sunday&#xD;
is nut 7t~  bong, and the Book is lie&#xD;
muic. IHow did I iver star away rumc auth&#xD;
that Ib . Ye mut4  hgear the chiller ay thir&#xD;
qlestons and their ctecrhize in my  om now,&#xD;
T Ii     Mt I.a- .. El  el   It  wonduefu&#xD;
&#xD;
170&#xD;
&#xD;
11&#xD;
"  L    a.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC8382-00000086"/>&#xD;
172&#xD;
&#xD;
Ta    tt i&#xD;
&#xD;
how I never, took no more comfort in hearing&#xD;
the ould woman talk. Shure I can't laugh at&#xD;
her, Thomas, I think she's going' to get into&#xD;
Heaven, what ever Bcky Killigan does; but&#xD;
praise God, Thomas, Il get in too.&#xD;
CHAPTER vii.&#xD;
E GOSPEL T) THE POOR.&#xD;
A')j   D Ml o many changing scenes winter&#xD;
:    . (04Meh on apace.&#xD;
Tihrou,   the kindness of bright&#xD;
- Mary Stuyvesant, Maggie Dodd was&#xD;
Oi   everV day to school, weji wrapped up&#xD;
In woolen hood and shawl, a plid dress of&#xD;
Mary' made over. and carried a primer in her&#xD;
hand. bught with some of Marfs pocket&#xD;
money.&#xD;
Every Saturday morning, Maggie, made as&#xD;
clean as poile, and looking  e    happy,&#xD;
went to see Marv for an hour, and the little&#xD;
1I3&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC8382-00000087"/>&#xD;
4TEE COR tAL.&#xD;
&#xD;
patroness gave her small protege much wise&#xD;
advice (second-hand from mamma or Aunt&#xD;
Laura), many childish treasures of sugar&#xD;
plums, pennies, or pictures, and always some-&#xD;
thing to carry home to Teddy. Teddy, poor&#xD;
bv, grew but slowly ;hi left arm hung down&#xD;
weak and helpless, he walked about a little,&#xD;
but preferred to it still and look at pictures;&#xD;
Mary gave hum a little clair which he ke pt&#xD;
close to his old rav another's first and econd&#xD;
chidhood acreein  very well together, and the&#xD;
ok lady to  qmtue as much com.rt i  Jrop-&#xD;
~ remarks aboeu: the veneratedap)&#xD;
Dodd to her -siek!; grandbabv, as to any&#xD;
*       other peCrsn whatsoever.&#xD;
Thomas arranzei hs stall for a little larger&#xD;
f             -x&#xD;
cook  apparatus. and had a corner for George&#xD;
and Iha small wares: Por said corner George&#xD;
fairiully paid rent; he wvas aa  payiz hack&#xD;
SThmass loan. Thmi were prospering with&#xD;
the Dodd , they had ired a smal room open.&#xD;
&#xD;
K&#xD;
&#xD;
as&#xD;
&#xD;
174&#xD;
&#xD;
[  on the one they were living in, and this&#xD;
itde room was furnished for grannie and&#xD;
agzie; they had a new cooking 'stoie, a new&#xD;
table&amp;amp; and some gay paper curtains. George&#xD;
had still many secret and some open inclinings&#xD;
toward whiskey; to quell these Thomas tried a&#xD;
e w'ailone r day when theground was winter&#xD;
xvwhi ed ;   forced his patient to eat nearly&#xD;
a     of the new tallei snow, and then ad-&#xD;
anto *ep 'i mn  ea   by takig. i&#xD;
LI 11and ilndin al the verses he could about&#xD;
ByMr. A*ton alviwe, Jerry Mwas sent to&#xD;
° 82 eh 'A during the winters; ou: of school&#xD;
1 urs he wxas buvv learning his humble part&#xD;
5-2co niectiunerv husiness. MrLs. lli54J,&#xD;
in- at tinas in a new L:ii h ecame ver&#xD;
zealou . for the comfort of Jerry anid Thomas,&#xD;
and was very nebbldsrly to Mrs. Dodd. She&#xD;
was a firm friend also to Mrs. M-Glure, and&#xD;
the two other families whom  Temas    ad&#xD;
ished up from the depths of Jug Alley.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC8382-00000088"/>&#xD;
176&#xD;
&#xD;
T               L C==fl A&#xD;
&#xD;
As to Jug Alley it was getting too cold and&#xD;
stormy to have meetings on the ricketty, tum-&#xD;
ble-down  door steps; attendance on the&amp;amp;&#xD;
formal meetings now amounted to thirty or-&#xD;
forty every Sabbath, and Thomas was sorely&#xD;
puzzled what to do for those strar sh4e with-&#xD;
out a shepherd. One dar lie sat readin: in&#xD;
his stall during a eIU'ure  hour. when Mr:&#xD;
AiLton came up.    - What do von find cool&#xD;
t- a homa  h ?" he d.&#xD;
"0,"  repli N  the i e-man.   i t" s a ummw  as&#xD;
is awayy. turndinZ up umna: choice, but here's&#xD;
bit as has et m thinkin, -to t  ir the&#xD;
gospel :s preAehet and hi ed  Lwt wh tOC  r&#xD;
shall not +e o  iled in te.' Now Mebb&#xD;
that had some    ec iai mn anirn; te Johni, hut&#xD;
here's a meanlin; it has to Th'iozma' Tw:-&#xD;
tha I&#xD;
We ain't to set ourselves above bri an the&#xD;
gospel to the poorest, when it's touch work to&#xD;
do it. and takes a he;p of outlay mehbv. We&#xD;
aiu't to be ofiendd at no call whatsumexver.&#xD;
Sow, sir, says I to Thomas Twigg,* There's&#xD;
&#xD;
Jug Alley is as heathen a place as can be;&#xD;
by it's a flock without a sign of a shephe&#xD;
and the whiskey wolves forever yowling after&#xD;
hom  they may devour.    And A say   to&#xD;
Thomas Twigg, there ain't no     y else a&#xD;
working in that stony corner of the Vineyard,&#xD;
mbv the Lord's left it to yon, and you to&#xD;
find vaur own, tools.&#xD;
Can von do it?" sal Mr. Aliston.&#xD;
- J canj try.7 repdied Thomas.&#xD;
Jug Alley on his mind, Thomas stepped&#xD;
at evening to see how Mrs. McClure was&#xD;
comn  on. lie found her Sewing at blue&#xD;
I. -&#xD;
pvraiN ni poor but tidy rooml the chdren&#xD;
eating their supper of muh and masses and&#xD;
the baby sound1 asleep i its cradle. Mrs.&#xD;
McChure was. unusualy cheertu. Miss Laura&#xD;
had been there and offered to clothe the two&#xD;
little boys so they could go to school, and had&#xD;
found a place for the eldest child, a girl of&#xD;
tw   e Iwher she was to begin service the&#xD;
nest day.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
K I&#xD;
:j&#xD;
it&#xD;
-4 1&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC8382-00000089"/>&#xD;
178  Tn  rnr~~                     UN      fZL    ~   I&#xD;
&#xD;
"We'd do well enough," said the woman,&#xD;
"if McClure was never coining back ; but&#xD;
yet   I must remember old times, and I sort&#xD;
of want to see him.  But I knows so well&#xD;
how he gets to cuttin'up. Dear- rue, McClure&#xD;
was a decentish felow before he took to drink-&#xD;
.  Che'r up. sai  Thuomas, " who knows&#xD;
but he'll comn r'und all riht-t. There&#xD;
aint no     ttcLr        m             ,.&#xD;
Iam pravi t"r MI lure, and a:ter w ar t&#xD;
Lord's done for me and pardner, I am t a mite&#xD;
faint-hearted of gcttin: wha: I asks f'r.'&#xD;
ho pevoull  t it, said Mrs. McClure.&#xD;
a fair teeimen of many New York heathen,&#xD;
" if it's only on account of the children."&#xD;
During the watches of the night, whEe&#xD;
Jerry slept the sound sleep of byhotod care&#xD;
to Thomas his plan for the help of Jug Alley.&#xD;
"Pardner," said Thonas the next morning,&#xD;
while Becky was fming the hampers, 4'&#xD;
&#xD;
getting to be an old m, and do you know&#xD;
what it's set me to thinking of?"&#xD;
Och  ' said the pnctical Mrs. Killigan,&#xD;
"iebbv it is that ye ouzht to be iayx up&#xD;
mor' of the coppers.&#xD;
No -a'd Thomas, "just contrarywise.&#xD;
I -as to Thomas Twigg, you're od, Thomas;&#xD;
step about IVly now and lay up some treas-&#xD;
uireS ave i  yo v.mu have done but little in all&#xD;
n lif for the zoo  kingdom. ~o. pardner,&#xD;
SI   n     nk to lay up more but to give&#xD;
v   r f he Lord's work  while I&#xD;
-41 H&amp;amp;v Peter'  Cried Mrs. Killigan, drop-&#xD;
.- - 'pate full of douhnuts in her amaze-&#xD;
m hut that's a square notion&#xD;
ar ner," said Thomas, slhakin  his head&#xD;
wTh all due solemnity, -I'm afeard that while&#xD;
yu Ihave been sumat converted, yon ain't&#xD;
prikrIY converted in that long stocking where&#xD;
U U.cps your nye hundred &amp;amp;oLars.&#xD;
&#xD;
179-            4DIONSM  wt.. .&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC8382-00000090"/>&#xD;
a     mw2sZa rn-&#xD;
&#xD;
" Moses   m "id Mrs. Ki'li, collecting her&#xD;
doughnuts, "but there's many a one that ain't&#xD;
converted where the money is"&#xD;
"Tore shame then, said Thomas, " and no&#xD;
excuse to you    Iputs it to you, iair and&#xD;
square, when the Lord didn't hold Lack his&#xD;
own Iife, and when the Farth-r zave his Seo,&#xD;
isn't it a  in anIdiamne that w\etl h:Utd on to a&#xD;
little miserabe zm cy, andl lok at a dollar ten&#xD;
times btfre we Vrt with it.&#xD;
I 1ook at it a .hdre i :m ," said Mrs.&#xD;
Killiga-,  and maye it's a Sin as you say.&#xD;
Thomas.    Il study on it. Ah, well its a&#xD;
grana mang over rehgen Ls reprin       -&#xD;
And oughtn't it to be." demanded Thom-&#xD;
as; " what was \here of old Thomas Twigg or&#xD;
Becky Kiligan that was worth taking into the&#xD;
kingdom: And here's another thin;. pardner ;&#xD;
don't call on Peter and Moses, the Virgin or&#xD;
the saints in your talk., Its again Scripter. and&#xD;
you ought to get beyond it-."&#xD;
&#xD;
4THl thrarel fast if Igets beyond all yua&#xD;
sets for me to," said Becky, stoutly ; " but Il&#xD;
do my endeavor, with the Lord's help, Thomas&#xD;
and as for five hander- well, Thoma-eii,&#xD;
dear me, man -if the Lord wants it -he&#xD;
can have the whole of it -andi Ill haul it&#xD;
over. man; if you say so&#xD;
It's not me, pardner," said Thmas, "keep&#xD;
vaur money till you have a call, and then hand&#xD;
over whatwver conlSCienfCe andi LteSrptrd&#xD;
you.&#xD;
When Thomas came home that night, Mrs.&#xD;
Ki1icans do or was alar, an1 she bade him&#xD;
cone in.&#xD;
lyEe hbee watching   o f ur vo, Thomas," She&#xD;
said: have you done anything like you talked.&#xD;
of today!"&#xD;
Yes," said Thomas.~4 The Lord has&#xD;
helped me. I made up my mind that Id hire&#xD;
. a room where we c'l have zood meetings,&#xD;
all we wantd..    -' al  ni      on'tlay&#xD;
&#xD;
101&#xD;
&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
MIAM&#xD;
&#xD;
ALT&#xD;
AW&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC8382-00000091"/>&#xD;
-n&#xD;
&#xD;
_ _  - T-LL.&#xD;
&#xD;
up another cent. Pl pay the rent of it for&#xD;
this winter. I left the stall with Jerry, and&#xD;
away I goes to Jug Alley, and what did I find&#xD;
!aated this morning but poor McClure's grog-&#xD;
gery. At once I think this is of the Lord,&#xD;
awl of1 I oes, and Ipardner  that very whiskey&#xD;
den, where the Lord was abused and defied..is&#xD;
the very one wh8re now w     praise his zood&#xD;
name: 0, pardner, it makes my heart jump&#xD;
for joy to thik  o  tre Stan's going to get&#xD;
ousted for the go o~ the kingdo~mn"'&#xD;
Te7ars o ette  ::1f linz hon~e in old IThom-&#xD;
3$ ee, and  Mrt WUlzau smote her brawny&#xD;
hands together. crvinz out,&#xD;
"G  od  fo r.r you,  T homas,b  lure  it will  be a&#xD;
blessed sight, the BiLes for the whiskey turn-&#xD;
tilers, andI paim  instead of swearing. It is&#xD;
aeseh will   o  own when iver there is a&#xD;
mateing, to wonder over the doing's of the&#xD;
Lord."&#xD;
I~l et a stove and some deal benches and&#xD;
&#xD;
a table, and I'll ask Mr. Aliston to come down&#xD;
and give us a preachment," began Thomas -&#xD;
SIndeed," interrupted Becky, "you'll not&#xD;
dit alone; share it is a pitt it an't oie&#xD;
the matter a lift.  Now, Thomas,--she&#xD;
a lon  breath, for the proposal was a&#xD;
scru .one  to her -"you go and get them&#xD;
benchem and the txble and stove, an share,&#xD;
you- : 1at a ehazr or :wo; get 'eta  heap,&#xD;
Tmmar at econd-han d; don't go and get&#xD;
e ated on -emnd itfs me will fot the bill,&#xD;
Tima t r Shaure that's but little to do for&#xD;
Iwan a, paid tlor me with~ lte. -&#xD;
1Tma, was so elated at this bringing forth&#xD;
ofgo fruit in Mrs Killigtan, that he sprang&#xD;
up atmI shook hands with her, sat down, and&#xD;
reconsidering the matter, ros s and shook hands&#xD;
'You're right, pardner," he cried, -an&#xD;
Tm coming to the notion, pardner, that to do&#xD;
trind is all that ln worth lining for:!"&#xD;
&#xD;
p        L&#xD;
115"1&#xD;
&#xD;
lox&#xD;
1             Sw&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC8382-00000092"/>&#xD;
" Be quick about doing this business up,&#xD;
Thomas," urged the cautious Becky.    "If&#xD;
you're groinr to g:ive the money, itsn use let&#xD;
ting it go so slow as to get rusty. Kape it&#xD;
moving, man, and we'l see whiat'lI come of&#xD;
it."'&#xD;
Thomas rose to leave the r o.m, but pausing,&#xD;
with is hand on the- latch, said, -- I meant to&#xD;
tell you, partner, tfr a 'ure token that the&#xD;
Lord was wit   me, tit the Iad todk in eigt&#xD;
dollars whie I was gtone to Juc A1iy, which&#xD;
Is more taI e;ve was took in th lie tune 0YS&#xD;
fore. lie is ni great business chap. pardlner,&#xD;
nor was thir eCia0 reaon  4such!en.-i a re&#xD;
of business; *1J I take it as a token that the&#xD;
Lord was making al work for :tvd."&#xD;
-That a mnty be, Tuomnas," replied Mr'-&#xD;
Ki±:Kgn ; - but if your going brings in the&#xD;
pennies like that, you had better g pretty&#xD;
otten.r&#xD;
To hire and faPrpish a room tor religious&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
i-uv conma srax-                -&#xD;
was a great urdertakilng for two people&#xD;
lieor pie-man and his partner, greater in-&#xD;
Aeed than themselves imagined. All work&#xD;
that is dictated by humble zeal, designed by&#xD;
living hearts, and made the subject of earnest&#xD;
l   God gives his pec-&#xD;
will at la  sc&#xD;
he thel Ap they dot) fIknow they?) need. While&#xD;
Thma'w      ' TwiC was ma'fully making ready to&#xD;
Shtdun~f be could not bear. Mr. Aliston&#xD;
was 2et his waY.   Of course, as soon as&#xD;
Thomas saw his friend. he began speaking of&#xD;
1 - 1  -the reformation&#xD;
tu     t o near his heart.terfomto&#xD;
-f Ju; Alley. His plan of a room for service&#xD;
Mad  nP-ton w-as askei&#xD;
was mae known, and     r. -   o      a&#xD;
if he would not give "Jg Alley folks a reg-&#xD;
'ar  ; .reach e t '"&#xD;
"Go and get your room turnished as you&#xD;
~n, Thoma.' said Mr. Allston,~ "and I&#xD;
will think over the matter,aw  ee VOaai&#xD;
aboutit.&#xD;
Thomnas -hired the room, Mrs. Dodd and&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC8382-00000093"/>&#xD;
-H  ORUfSt&#xD;
&#xD;
Becky Killigan cleaned and. whitewashed it,&#xD;
George Dod, who was handy at everything,&#xD;
A  te renter work. and Becky, according&#xD;
to her promise, paid for what furniture was got&#xD;
at second-hand. It was not a very large sum&#xD;
that this furniture cost, to be sure.b ut it was&#xD;
large for one whose whole fortune was five&#xD;
hundred dollars; neverthe's, the night that&#xD;
Becky Killigan aid for it, and siw it at! set&#xD;
up in the whilom groggery. she fei richer- and&#xD;
happier than sheever had before.&#xD;
Little Mary Stuyvesant came- down to Mrs.&#xD;
Killigan s, one morning, in the carriages under&#xD;
the care of the nurse-naid and coachman, and&#xD;
brought some cards with illuminated tests, a&#xD;
few large colored cards of Scripture scenes,&#xD;
mounted on stiff card board. a Bibie in large&#xD;
type, and a dozen hymn-books.    This .was&#xD;
Mats contribution to the Jug Alley reforma-&#xD;
tion; the dear chilb'shirth-day had just passed,&#xD;
and her fatter had given her a twenty-dollar&#xD;
&#xD;
lac&#xD;
&#xD;
O&#xD;
&#xD;
1s&#xD;
&#xD;
rS0&#xD;
AP,&#xD;
,{ n&#xD;
r r r   yrn '&#xD;
f-k&#xD;
&#xD;
1-M&#xD;
t~&#xD;
Y'.' ra&#xD;
&#xD;
z&#xD;
.&#xD;
&#xD;
g iea she h)a     in t7&#xD;
thes th   ssebogato Becky's-' Mary's&#xD;
radiant face bore bright wits  at it is more&#xD;
radelaedlwas&#xD;
than   m ree ~-r&#xD;
becky th iry's glft, that she couldhard&#xD;
c ecky loinga   the different articles long&#xD;
okg ath&#xD;
oftto attend to&#xD;
eNo M   tr                 the Jug Alley&#xD;
Mr.s tosne    o          that he enliste&amp;amp;&#xD;
eisonandt *&amp;amp;fl means in the&#xD;
enerarge- ad they agreed to help hold £&#xD;
Snder Scool there, to furnish fuel and lights&#xD;
sunday        a~nd proside  oki&#xD;
and hire a teacher.,n  -r~i' hoos       enf&#xD;
it  4     id be organwed.&#xD;
'       T   g had hw the Lord was pros&#xD;
p §i ewundertaking he fet tlen years&#xD;
plerm                             blcsto&#xD;
treated three bankrupt shoe&#xD;
yhot dinners and al that night was too rapp&#xD;
k ~   4ei s layawake~ reflceting1 what the Lord&#xD;
h-d n      While the arran.;etl-&#xD;
in don for  u-&#xD;
&#xD;
. ~_&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC8382-00000094"/>&#xD;
188&#xD;
&#xD;
w c-a fAjz&#xD;
&#xD;
_   'Y&#xD;
&#xD;
going on, Thomas left the stall for several&#xD;
hours each day with Jerry, while he scoured&#xD;
Jug Alley. explaining to the residents the&#xD;
intents of the new inission, getting recruits&#xD;
for night school, Sunday School and preach-&#xD;
ment. He went with his heart full of love,-&#xD;
his pockets fall of little pictures and biscuits,&#xD;
and winning the hearts of little ones by his&#xD;
small zifts, and of grown foLks by his simple,&#xD;
hearty speech. he .got a good many to promise&#xD;
to attend to his various neetinzs. While go-&#xD;
ing about in this way, be gained the appellation&#xD;
of ' Daddy Twigg" from the children of the&#xD;
unfortunate quarter upon which he had had&#xD;
compassion.&#xD;
And now, before this chapter cl ses, let us&#xD;
look on a goodly sight.   Un a Saturday,&#xD;
Thomas had taken down. the tawdry, dilapidated&#xD;
sign, --"Liu&amp;amp;AR D WXN I B PADDY McKua4'&#xD;
which had hung thu  .ong, and breaking it&#xD;
into tuel by rtigrou lvwV, ie had given it to&#xD;
&#xD;
a poor woman to cook her supper. Then&#xD;
came Sunday, the inaugural Jug Alley Mision&#xD;
ov                      U -n  -wLwn pap&#xD;
were going to fine churches, Mr. Allston and&#xD;
his friends, and Thomas and Becky, with all&#xD;
the Todds, rannie, baby ard all, went to tle&#xD;
e 5  misio m r  ai    met th~&#xD;
Juz Alley foks of all sizes, a dirwan,&#xD;
TflCfl3x a% flfirrnfirrer7RWC&#xD;
ro- nnarn      ---asa            nz&#xD;
made, hmns were sunz, and then the rejiicin&#xD;
Thomas, and all 1is hublte friends. listened to&#xD;
Mr. AiLston' preachment.&#xD;
It must have seemed strange to see and hear&#xD;
those solemn, tender  words in that room;&#xD;
strange to Mrs. McClure with her habe on her&#xD;
knee, and her children on either side: ;strange&#xD;
tco the men an Iwomen who had drank and&#xD;
cursed and rioted in that very room. - Come&#xD;
Unto    al's ye that labor and are heavy laden,&#xD;
and I wil gve von rest.&#xD;
Thus in Jug Alley   to the poor the gospel&#xD;
was preached.&#xD;
&#xD;
IFU&#xD;
I  h&#xD;
.k 4&#xD;
bif&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC8382-00000095"/>&#xD;
Tn    LL ?151&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER VHI.&#xD;
&#xD;
THE OFFENCE OF THE CROSS.&#xD;
&#xD;
S the winter advanced, so advanced&#xD;
thre prosp*eritv of enmrchi services,&#xD;
Sunday school and evening school, in&#xD;
Jug Alley. Thomas had become so interested&#xD;
in his work among 5s humble friends, and&#xD;
found he could do them so much goods that he&#xD;
spent from  four o'clock to sx. every day&#xD;
among them.&#xD;
During these hours he left the stall in charge&#xD;
ot Jerry, and Jerry, virtually in charge of&#xD;
Dodd, who, sitting under the same little roof&#xD;
with Thoms nnrerafltile ventures, gave an&#xD;
eye to all that was ging on. George was&#xD;
1no&#xD;
&#xD;
getting quite steady; he could go about the&#xD;
streets alone, and though he might not yet he&#xD;
able to resist the fumes of a glass of his favor-&#xD;
ite poison, if held under his nose, was yet es-&#xD;
tablished sufficiently in good purposes to avoid&#xD;
temptation. Old. Mrs. Dodd was flourishing&#xD;
in clean caps and dreses, and spent her time&#xD;
in talking cheerfully of the sayings and doings&#xD;
of her deceased husband, anw  in ftebly media&#xD;
taking on what Scripture was read to her by&#xD;
ThomGa and George. Under the vigorous ad-&#xD;
ministrati-u of the younger Mrs. Dodd, the&#xD;
Oy ster Stall by the wharf was quite decent&#xD;
and  uccessul, and the nearest policeman had&#xD;
ceased to feel uneasy about it.&#xD;
But now we must put on record a very&#xD;
eaISant circumstance about friend Twigg.&#xD;
From the day he began to give, and actively&#xD;
labor for the Master, affairs of business at the&#xD;
Corner Stall took, what is called, "a start"&#xD;
Trade increased, profits increased, and while&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
I91&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC8382-00000096"/>&#xD;
'.&#xD;
&#xD;
I .                   -cii af&#xD;
Thomas provided for himself as before, and&#xD;
took care of Jerry, and gave away as the Lord&#xD;
prospered himhe vet laid hy as much as ever,&#xD;
the more he gave the more he got. He fre-&#xD;
quently spoke of this with surprise to Becky&#xD;
and George, and in his ow   o odd fashion of&#xD;
counting fingers and strokes, and making on&#xD;
his slate scrawvr figures lake the tracks of a&#xD;
drunken spider. he went over his accounts&#xD;
of income and outlay, ever with the same&#xD;
result.&#xD;
One dat however, sitting in his stall reading&#xD;
his Bible, while George, in his own corner was&#xD;
carving some chess men, Thomas cried out,&#xD;
there, now. George, it's all as clear as a&#xD;
streak of daylight; give us an ear man, while&#xD;
I deal out what I've been turning over to in&#xD;
my reference Bible:  He that giveth unto the&#xD;
poor shall not lack.' He that hath pity on&#xD;
the poor lendeth unto the Lord: and that&#xD;
which he hath given will he pay him again.'&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
Do you take the sense of those verses, George?&#xD;
t He that soweth bountifully shall reap also&#xD;
bountifully.' Don't that make all pain to&#xD;
yon, George? I'll mention it to pardner this&#xD;
evening. Why, man, it's the Lord's appointed&#xD;
way of doing business; we give and it's like&#xD;
dropping seed into ploughed ground, we get&#xD;
a crop like we sowed."&#xD;
So also Thomnas explaned his new light to&#xD;
Becky, and true to the minzlinz of old leaven&#xD;
and new, .  replied. A Arrah, Thomas. but&#xD;
san iiant war of gettin' rich.&#xD;
No:   : alter this Tomras found Mrs.&#xD;
Kiisman- :ne evenxinz, very mvlana-cdv, and&#xD;
" sighi; like a furnay." T   talk her into&#xD;
cheerful interet in ier fellow creature., Thoim&#xD;
as hg an t tell of a siwk woman h Lad visited&#xD;
that dar in Jug Alteyr; he had h'tn ill of a&#xD;
fever, and had two small children who were&#xD;
wandering the streets as beggars.&#xD;
"It's full time, pardner. that von wer un&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC8382-00000097"/>&#xD;
mnd doing for the Lord your Master,?' said&#xD;
Those.&#xD;
"And what can I do ?" asked Becky Killi.&#xD;
777--&#xD;
gan- groaning&#xD;
You can do a power of good if you're a&#xD;
mind," retorted Thomas; "wly, partner, go&#xD;
to that woman, wash her kee, comb her head,&#xD;
make her bed and tidy up her room. I telt&#xD;
when I went in there as if I wished you to&#xD;
work there for an hour.   What a change&#xD;
mizh: yournake, parilner. Then there's mores&#xD;
you might do: you could give her a thrifty&#xD;
notion or s . and make her muchlv more care-.&#xD;
ful than she is. And more'n alL partner, you&#xD;
could just tell straight ahog what the Lord&#xD;
did for vou. Tll justly how you felt and&#xD;
what the Lord did for von it's the truth hit's&#xD;
home, pardner. not .o much the larnin', though&#xD;
ihat's good in is place; but rizht out solid&#xD;
truth of the Lord's dealing. th  s the talk for&#xD;
Thomas Twigg. There's many a nands ta n&#xD;
&#xD;
arm&#xD;
coulddofor theLord,        r, if you set&#xD;
"Could I ?" said Becky, eagerly, leaning&#xD;
rnrd,her strong arms crossed on her knees;&#xD;
are ye shure on it Thomast"&#xD;
That I am," said Thomas; "why not?&#xD;
don't the &amp;amp;'ripter say for its self that out of&#xD;
e mouth of habes the Lora perets praise,&#xD;
d it ain't aiwa; the high and mizhtv and&#xD;
noble that are called.&#xD;
"Och, but yere lifting a load from   me&#xD;
heart " cried Becky. "Shure iss Struve&#xD;
san came here to-dar, and what is she goin'&#xD;
to do but to hire a Bible woman for Jug Alley.&#xD;
o hone, Thomas, when she set out before me&#xD;
how the Bible woman would go about from&#xD;
one house and room to another, reading and&#xD;
yin&amp;amp; and teachin' and eomfortin' : whin she&#xD;
me how they did good to souls and bodies,&#xD;
was fit to die that I couldn't do that goo&#xD;
rk mer-4 It's neA the inonev, Thomas-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC8382-00000098"/>&#xD;
+Y&#xD;
&#xD;
77,&#xD;
&#xD;
__&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
for I makesasmuch byme ba        butwhin&#xD;
on Sunday I hear 'em holding' forth about&#xD;
working for Jesus, and lovin' him, and living'&#xD;
(or him, my heart is breaking to be about it.A&#xD;
Nothing ekse .seems worth livn' for. What is&#xD;
Becky Killigan to b caring for herself and&#xD;
not laboring for the kingom.&#xD;
That's true,' said Thomas,  we oughtn&#xD;
to grumble at spending and bin' spent in t&#xD;
Lord's service, we needn't set out to- sav x&#xD;
how we can't do so and how, fr fear we'll&#xD;
tired or sick, or made poor ; what did Jesus&#xD;
for us?  What do the saints sav. but ' for thy&#xD;
sake we are killed all the dtw lonz; and thC&#xD;
killing isnt to be noticed it it coms i&#xD;
war of dut-, ardner. I don't ask no m&#xD;
nor no less than to do what the Lord wa:&#xD;
of me_; ki   rno   it's all oe to Thou;a&#xD;
Twi."&#xD;
"True for ye." said Becky, eag rv;  bu:&#xD;
make   plain man. whaNNi 1 an d1res&#xD;
&#xD;
r*+ 4.&#xD;
&#xD;
f......_.        -   --      -     -..,.,.,.......&#xD;
&#xD;
InmgE Brai&#xD;
&#xD;
Have you any time you can spare for this&#xD;
work, pardner ?&#xD;
Troth, but I can spare two hours every&#xD;
day hut Monday.&#xD;
"That's what I spatres" said Thomas; " and&#xD;
how much do you think Mr. Aliston laid out&#xD;
to me that it was .&#xD;
How can I tell: if t aint two hours, what&#xD;
Wh. pardner, in a year its three weeks,&#xD;
five days and two hours, more or less, if I&#xD;
ain't disrveembered."&#xD;
TI Tatw jhemt. mtiev, Thomas. but what&#xD;
shall I do. said Beekv. impatiently.&#xD;
"Why, pardner. go- about, I'll tell you where&#xD;
y   r r t needed inot, andl how 'em how to be&#xD;
clean and savin.&#xD;
indeed, them  two things I know intire-&#xD;
l, cried Mrs. Killican. in a lively tone.&#xD;
Show em how to make the best of what&#xD;
they've got. Cheer 'em up, talk to 'em of&#xD;
&#xD;
--&#xD;
'              °-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC8382-00000099"/>&#xD;
Tu~zu tt&#xD;
&#xD;
Uw&#xD;
&#xD;
a   a                  Inw&#xD;
&#xD;
the meetings in our room. Make mention to&#xD;
Miss Stuyvesant of depret cases. and 'bore&#xD;
al. pardner. tell what you feel in your own&#xD;
heart of the goodner of the Lord. 0, pard-&#xD;
ner, thaf's the  ld kev that unlocks shut&#xD;
heart;it's the tire that thaws out icy hearts;&#xD;
it's the hammer that treak up stony hearts;&#xD;
itsf the mlIcine For sjek lhearts."&#xD;
Tr:h, 1aid Mrs. Kiliivm,  but that's as&#xD;
goodYI a pr-atln': as ier I heard, Thomas,&#xD;
from Mr. A:1H tn, 'r ere a man v 'emt all."&#xD;
And non   L hi~ the Bli*  women commis-&#xD;
sioned - by  d Miss Laura Stuyvesant, went&#xD;
ravelv and faithfuly about Jug Aley, Mrs.&#xD;
Killigan, not interfering with any other labor-&#xD;
er, went abou: that helpless alley too; and&#xD;
while the little untortunates there called our&#xD;
pie-man    Daddyr Twizz" they called her&#xD;
Mammy Killigan." She did a good work,&#xD;
and the Lord was good enough to let her seed&#xD;
time and grape gathering touch each other in&#xD;
&#xD;
some cases, that she might be thereby encour-&#xD;
aged, yet the "offence of the cross" has not&#xD;
ceased, and under gross ingratitude, under&#xD;
bitter revilings, under such personal asntdts&#xD;
as stones and mud and gutter water cast upon&#xD;
her Becky felt her Irish choler rise betimes,&#xD;
and was sorely tempted. to use her brawny&#xD;
arms for other ends than the performing of&#xD;
her legitimate duties. Neverthe less Becky&#xD;
was helped not to render raiingfordrailing,&#xD;
no'r to commii~ assault and battery on any body,&#xD;
ad       grace her profeion, and Thomas, at&#xD;
home, made it plain to her that if she was not&#xD;
willing tu bear this cross of eontumei  after&#xD;
Christ, she was not worthy to be his disciple.&#xD;
I ain'tnater that Satan could see you&#xD;
fightin' his kingdom  without his setin' in and&#xD;
tighti' yoU. You can't expect him to do less&#xD;
than kick a little mud and some bad names&#xD;
unto you, pardner.-&#xD;
it makes me fel like  ihutin', me nma"&#xD;
said Becky, ruefully.&#xD;
&#xD;
't&#xD;
3:&#xD;
n7&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC8382-00000100"/>&#xD;
_   4&#xD;
&#xD;
x         -   _      _&#xD;
yy   ,......_,....4- - m,_-      ..  III- A    ..aAi__ __         _ : _       _&#xD;
&#xD;
HuTe(-lfERl sTai-.&#xD;
"And what would that be," cried Thomas,&#xD;
kly, "but turnin' right agin your own&#xD;
colors, and doin' justly what old Satan wanted.&#xD;
Be'd laugh so loud at the advantage he't&#xD;
got that I muchiy believe you'd hear him,&#xD;
pardner."&#xD;
I shan't do it, thien," said Becky. -I&#xD;
keep quiet as - as lnz as the Lord heil&#xD;
me.&#xD;
That'!! be as long as you pt4ty god and&#xD;
strong," said Thomas.&#xD;
Those who  ppose evil are uluualV for d&#xD;
to suffer persecution from that ev2: the offence&#xD;
of the cross never ceases. The were those&#xD;
among Georze Dodd's olden companions who&#xD;
took high exCejtion to hi separating han;el&#xD;
from then, and taking to decent ways.  When-&#xD;
ever they saw him they followed him witi&#xD;
jests and jibes. and names which he need not&#xD;
have been  shamed to have applied to him, but&#xD;
yet as he knew they were used as reproaches&#xD;
they disturbed him greatly. They called him&#xD;
&#xD;
TUE conr snt.x..        131o&#xD;
long coat," parson,"" priest," "cold water,"&#xD;
aTwigg man," and tormented him with being&#xD;
under Thomas's authority, or "tied to the&#xD;
apron strings of the old women." They of-&#xD;
fered to treat him, and invited him to go to&#xD;
shows and -.rat fights. "&#xD;
One lay two of them met George going&#xD;
I me earlier than usual. and getting him by&#xD;
ithe r arm they drew him down Jug Alley to&#xD;
a Srgery Auch as McClure's had been, and&#xD;
¢utrig h  1glad they were to see him -him-&#xD;
41 asain. and a "man like the rest," they&#xD;
rd :rel a glass of hot wiskey, and pushing&#xD;
him :' the reeking tar pressed it into his&#xD;
hand.&#xD;
No Caithful friend, no anxious wife. not even&#xD;
J err.y .with voice of warning, or Maggie. with&#xD;
en"trating eye, was near.&#xD;
In a dim corner of the vile shop, standing&#xD;
cme to a smoky, foul lamp, a glass of gin in&#xD;
., big, shaking hand, was a coarse, bloated&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC8382-00000101"/>&#xD;
7  y ry                   .&#xD;
-,,,.          -&#xD;
,"                       ._&#xD;
- _____-        -      rs          _-       ---&#xD;
PT             :f&#xD;
"                          a ,&#xD;
r                         '     n&#xD;
y       II               _&#xD;
-                           _ _    i&#xD;
r&#xD;
^&#xD;
&#xD;
.  .&#xD;
, .&#xD;
u'"&#xD;
., =&#xD;
5&#xD;
-&#xD;
4&#xD;
JY.&#xD;
dal.._,&#xD;
"p -.&#xD;
&#xD;
4T&#xD;
&#xD;
woman. She wore no garments but a ragged&#xD;
petticoat and a dirty, torn sack ; her hair, un-&#xD;
mbed   and rough, hung down     over her&#xD;
shoulders, and about her purple throat was&#xD;
loosely tied a red cotton handkerchief; she&#xD;
looked the very genius of the wretched place;&#xD;
yet from this poor helpless creature came a&#xD;
voice of warning. She turned her blood shot&#xD;
eyes. gkeamng yet with the frequent fires of&#xD;
the drunkard's delirium, upon George, and&#xD;
cried in a harsh, shrill voice,&#xD;
If I were as near being' saved as you are,&#xD;
George Dodd, I wouldn't go back to ruin  If&#xD;
I stood where I could be somebody fit and&#xD;
decent, I wouldn't go down to the ditches&#xD;
agin, not 1.  Are you ashamed of daddy&#xD;
Twigg for saving you!p It's a  ity he ain't&#xD;
here now to keep his work from 'falling&#xD;
though!&#xD;
Sn many and such honest words had never&#xD;
been heard from drunken Jane before; they&#xD;
&#xD;
roused what slumberng honor andg       s&#xD;
was in George Dodd; he looked about him on&#xD;
the haggard and bloated faces, the trembling,&#xD;
ragged figures, the bkared eyes of those who&#xD;
crowded about him; a viIson of their beggary,&#xD;
their misery, their wild riots and their horrible&#xD;
tteazies rose before him, and putrins down the&#xD;
untouched glass and clearing his way between&#xD;
his erowdin: tempters, he dashed out of the&#xD;
do r and homeward through the' keen, cold&#xD;
winds, and the rising winter storm.&#xD;
It was a day or two after that he told the&#xD;
ta- 0f this escape to Thomas, giving Jane&#xD;
h r due. Thomas had sometimes spoken to&#xD;
Jane, and. tried to influence her, but without&#xD;
any success but -this story of George's gave&#xD;
him hope for the woman; he resolved to seek&#xD;
her out and try and reform her. He sought&#xD;
her for two days, and ound her at last - but&#xD;
where? drawn out of the river from amid&#xD;
blocks of ice, her blue lips  uA  ad her e-yes&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC8382-00000102"/>&#xD;
tH . wan__ __&#xD;
&#xD;
}"-  ,&#xD;
.&#xD;
q,&#xD;
'&#xD;
aV .&#xD;
Mr&#xD;
_..m-'..._      _&#xD;
&#xD;
an.&#xD;
&#xD;
ptaingstonily in death ; stiff, still, forever un-&#xD;
doe ; so he found drunken Jane, one of the&#xD;
wrecks that daily go down among us to infinite&#xD;
despair-&#xD;
On one. of those gray, chill, winter after-&#xD;
noons, perhaps it was March, but winter still,&#xD;
Paddy McClure came from the six month's&#xD;
confinement, to which he had been condemned-&#xD;
and walked slowly down Jug Alley; he had&#xD;
not a penny in his pockets, and wits perfect&#xD;
sober, preferring to get home and get drunk&#xD;
on his own premises. He was cleaner, stouter,&#xD;
straighter, than when arrested for assult and&#xD;
battery; his time in the penitentiary set apar&#xD;
from rows, and bound to honest labor had done&#xD;
him good. When Lie came to what he con-&#xD;
sidered his own door he found it fastened, and&#xD;
the windows were losed with strong shutters&#xD;
and barred ; the sign too, was gone. He&#xD;
struck the door with hi; list; a small boy, a&#xD;
professed pickpocket, a sharp-wined little vl-&#xD;
&#xD;
ian, who bore McClure ill will for sundry&#xD;
kicks and curses, dodged out of a cellar, cry-&#xD;
ing, "hi. yi, what you doin' there wn"&#xD;
bI want .to get into my house," said&#xD;
McClare.&#xD;
'Taint ours no more. Thomas Twigg&#xD;
hs it for schools and preaching, an' it's all&#xD;
furniIhed up, and - -seeian McClure was&#xD;
about to kick the door violently,. he added,&#xD;
"- yo' better look out. he's got some rich&#xD;
nien to back him and they come thre every&#xD;
"Where's my folks'?" demanded the man,&#xD;
d 'gediy.&#xD;
iReekon they're dead," said the boy ; "got&#xD;
turn  into the street, and the old wonan's&#xD;
dead, and the children got took to the Home,&#xD;
an vour big gurl is bound out fr her ivin,"&#xD;
continued the remorseless urchin, drawing&#xD;
ia rgly on his imagination.&#xD;
There was a remnant of decent feeling in&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
11-01     "1   -   ORO&#xD;
iWORIORK&#xD;
&#xD;
mmm&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC8382-00000103"/>&#xD;
ThU    STALL&#xD;
&#xD;
l-&#xD;
&#xD;
:&#xD;
," ^.&#xD;
;-&#xD;
.&#xD;
. .&#xD;
&#xD;
Paddy McClure, not yet burnt out b whiskey,&#xD;
He had hitherto had some den be called home,&#xD;
and clung to it as the wild beast to his lair.&#xD;
He leaned against the side of the house a&#xD;
minute, looked about for a place to get a glass&#xD;
of liquor, but seeing none hut that kept by his&#xD;
olden foe and rival, concluded to go to another&#xD;
street for whiskey, and, stumbling blindly&#xD;
ang, dazed by the blow he had received, he&#xD;
plunged against a woman carrying a bundle&#xD;
of work, a thin, half-satternlr woman, the&#xD;
same who had used his sign for fuel, and to&#xD;
whom, when she was sick. Thomas had sent&#xD;
Mrs. Killigan-&#xD;
"  , Paddy, are you out?" she said; "have&#xD;
you seen the old woman?"&#xD;
"How should I ?! asked McClure.&#xD;
" Mebby you'd better not, she's better off&#xD;
without you. Jane's dead, bin drowned, and-&#xD;
where's them fellows got sent up with you?"W&#xD;
-"Bill's sick, in 'ospital, 'and Dick's gone&#xD;
tramping."&#xD;
&#xD;
"Glad of it," said the woman.     Bil's&#xD;
wife's taking in clothes to wash, and doiW'&#xD;
pretty good at it, and Dick' woman is hired&#xD;
out to a restaurant; her children is put out to&#xD;
places. Im doin' pretty good myself-so's&#xD;
your old woman."&#xD;
".MV woman ain't she dead ? "&#xD;
No, in course not, why should she die?&#xD;
She's living nice. and your big girl is out to&#xD;
place  and the boys goes to school, and the&#xD;
babv' grown like gas."&#xD;
-Your chaffing," said McClure.&#xD;
aNo I ain't : she was turned into the street,&#xD;
the hoys was sik, she hadn't a cent, they were&#xD;
crying with cold, and Daddy Twigg got 'em a&#xD;
room and work, and helped 'em amazing. It's&#xD;
all along of him them other women got above&#xD;
board, and he did all for me or I'd be dead&#xD;
afore now.&#xD;
"Thomas Twig, him as we thrashed and&#xD;
pounded*'&#xD;
&#xD;
.LB.y,                _      _         _&#xD;
vp                                    ,&#xD;
w&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="208-209" xml:id="VAC8382-00000104"/>&#xD;
A-&#xD;
&#xD;
208             C0   {  -40.a lt&#xD;
"Just him."&#xD;
"I don't believe a word of it."&#xD;
"Go see," said the woman, tartly; "round&#xD;
in the street, No. 29, third floor, back; there,&#xD;
now, if them ain't your folks, and helped on&#xD;
just as I said, pitch me into the river."&#xD;
She walked on with her bunile, and M-&#xD;
Clure, half convinced. ititowed her directions&#xD;
though slowly, and just as it grew dark, stool&#xD;
before the door indicated. le was about to&#xD;
knock, but recogcnizing . his wife's voie, open I&#xD;
the door ; tor a moment le was unnotice. iHe&#xD;
had a full view of the room; it was comforta-&#xD;
bly warmed by a small store with a coal tire,&#xD;
The bed and cradle were properly made, some&#xD;
cooking utensils stood on a box, by a pine table&#xD;
stood his two boys. while On one side sat their&#xD;
mother, with the bah on her lap. The fai&#xD;
Swereeatintheir supper. The boys had&#xD;
mush and molasses. in blue bows, the mother&#xD;
a cup of tea, and in the center of the table&#xD;
&#xD;
A&#xD;
&#xD;
K          Sy&#xD;
&#xD;
ood a plate well supplied with good bread.&#xD;
McClure moved ; the group at the table looked&#xD;
up, the little boys gave a cry of dismay and&#xD;
fled behind the bed. The mother rose ; she&#xD;
felt somewhat like welcoming her husband. but&#xD;
she glanced about her comfortable room, and&#xD;
felt as if he brought desolation, then she checked&#xD;
te feeling and went to meet him. McClure&#xD;
wa4 softened by the afternoon's experiences;&#xD;
ie rete his wife cordial, cald pleasantly&#xD;
hchlee asked for his daughter, and sat&#xD;
n tO eat 1s .u;pper. The    a  yain&#xD;
cx urr : the  ile told of her prosperity. and&#xD;
h r rindss  - The boyS go to  chook," she&#xD;
said p roudly.&#xD;
SAnd to Daddy T wigg's "unday school 2&#xD;
said one ro.&#xD;
"And to Daddy Twigg's church ! said the&#xD;
other.&#xD;
"SaM1y's got a new frock: said boy one.&#xD;
And a new bonnet' said by two.&#xD;
&#xD;
n  ^  }«&#xD;
+«1?law r b4    ,.&#xD;
S' ,&#xD;
yw,&#xD;
i 'S'(&#xD;
n&#xD;
&#xD;
t3,&#xD;
&#xD;
:&#xD;
&#xD;
a&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="210-211" xml:id="VAC8382-00000105"/>&#xD;
InM&#xD;
&#xD;
It's all along of that good man, Mr.&#xD;
Twiow" said the wife.&#xD;
Then there came a knock at the door, and&#xD;
on opening it, in came Thomas Twig himself;&#xD;
when he saw Paddy McClure, he walked up,&#xD;
holding out his hand, looking him squarely in&#xD;
the eye, and saving.&#xD;
"I'm glad to see vou home, my man.&#xD;
Thomas Twi"zz "t cried Mcire, "you're&#xD;
the last man I'd bnked for this, from: TNA&#xD;
fed m' wvife andI bovs,&#xD;
"And why noft if they neededI?" askxu&#xD;
Thomas.&#xD;
Didnt-   set diem on to pounding y.&#xD;
that time?&#xD;
So you did, but I cared for your folk all&#xD;
the same," replied Thomas, looking him full in&#xD;
the ere,  but I haven't got done with yas,&#xD;
yet."&#xD;
"Wel" said McClure, "if you want t*&#xD;
have a regular set to, have it; hitoutas hard&#xD;
&#xD;
.aaflMi&#xD;
&#xD;
as you ken, but I ain't the   to hit back&#xD;
after this."&#xD;
What I want of you is to take you square&#xD;
along to our temnperance meeting to-night, a&#xD;
meeting in your old wuskey shop, man, and&#xD;
have you sign the pledge .&#xD;
-"I can't write" said McClure.&#xD;
--     -                -  °       w&#xD;
Yo can make your mark," said Thomas,&#xD;
But '--- said Paddy, "all the fliers wil&#xD;
atwiat me."&#xD;
e ide,  said Thomas, afterwards, to&#xD;
Becky.,. the idee of him getting ashamed of&#xD;
ding decent, that wasn't ashamed to pizen his&#xD;
ir ighors, and lie in the gutter like the swine."&#xD;
What he said to Paddy that night was,&#xD;
"And this here woman, and these ixbos, will&#xD;
laugh too, a good, loud, happy laugh, too.&#xD;
Here's a home for you, will you drink it up?"&#xD;
No;' said McClure, slowly. The coals&#xD;
fir Thoma had carried burning as the wise&#xD;
&#xD;
--sr&#xD;
&#xD;
r        ,&#xD;
L'&#xD;
&#xD;
: _&#xD;
:A&#xD;
: ,  -&#xD;
.&#xD;
' t' ,&#xD;
L,&#xD;
vs"&#xD;
,-".&#xD;
. _&#xD;
"  Y,.&#xD;
; ;        .,&#xD;
,,      ;;, u&#xD;
_&#xD;
;_ 4&#xD;
' .&#xD;
:,&#xD;
&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
- -77&#xD;
&#xD;
.J&#xD;
e&#xD;
rl{&#xD;
-  1&#xD;
i r  '&#xD;
. - i  .&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="212-213" xml:id="VAC8382-00000106"/>&#xD;
'It    ~TMoam     a&#xD;
&#xD;
men promised. "No, Mr. Twigg, I'll go with&#xD;
you and I'll make my mark, and the man tat&#xD;
sets out hereafter to pound Mr. Twigg 's gut to&#xD;
pound me first 2 bet you a dollar."&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER IX.&#xD;
&#xD;
HOLDING ON.&#xD;
&#xD;
H AT was a grand temperance meeting&#xD;
in Jug Alley ;zrand not so much from&#xD;
force of numbers or from the power&#xD;
and intellizence of those who gathered to it,&#xD;
" from the fact of information that permitted&#xD;
it to be there at al. It was a grand thing&#xD;
atc the o1 whiskey shop was turned into a&#xD;
r" m ftr the temperance lecture, that the&#xD;
X  W key seller put his sign manual to the&#xD;
"Total Abstinence Piedze, and the whiskey&#xD;
drinkers eme out to listen and wonder, and&#xD;
on  -them te sign also.&#xD;
&#xD;
-t&#xD;
&#xD;
Akio&#xD;
mwo"w&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="214-215" xml:id="VAC8382-00000107"/>&#xD;
r    ctULNE  STALL.&#xD;
&#xD;
214 R cof&#xD;
r. Mlston made a speech, two gtlement&#xD;
w   caewith him made speeches Thomas&#xD;
who  c e-   a  unconsciOusi y to&#xD;
Twigg got up to sjawo                r&#xD;
lj and to the surprise  all who hrd&#xD;
1     uer adquait       a&#xD;
him, was eloquefti queran   uanto   an&#xD;
S tru  but chrxlft because&#xD;
I'9&#xD;
o As lt uWoa     1cpil   f tears that&#xD;
lie so nefrm&#xD;
conrcame the er %&#xD;
ardent alm&#xD;
'Three chx      Dadil i  Twe , and&#xD;
r" fl n  ;r   1bv ft. ~aaflc iL catut w&#xD;
wityiw:c an t n   w eer Jz oe reada por?&#xD;
Sl Ta    iens f ht&#xD;
T"S  a~rall  t'  s n h a1W ginu tug "^. '    Bless " d&#xD;
L   a                  t not al&#xD;
wfitsinSty&#xD;
adv     w ure   inwrs a&#xD;
efitsr1                    -heaver&#xD;
&#xD;
on die wharf; such hard labor might be sup-&#xD;
posed enough to work off any extra physical&#xD;
excitement, but less than two months after&#xD;
sgnnvthe pledge, Paddy McClure was arrests&#xD;
ed on the old charge of assault and battery.&#xD;
t was a nod war from her house to Union&#xD;
SquareK but poor Mrs. McClure dropped the&#xD;
Lue verAd  he wvas xnaking and went almost&#xD;
on a run t- Thomas whom she deemed her&#xD;
.. Mr. Twign," she cried, wringing her&#xD;
hand;   hip Paddy, or they'll have him in the&#xD;
et4 ar for a year or two, this time, and him&#xD;
dIn s weI; it will be the ruin of him, por&#xD;
bybe.&#xD;
Tas hurriedly inquired into the trouble,&#xD;
an fPand at what p'e station Paddy was,&#xD;
ani biling George mind the stall, he went to&#xD;
the an  Place and before the same "His&#xD;
ll.nr where he himself had been tried after&#xD;
Ithe J   Alley riot.&#xD;
&#xD;
AA,&#xD;
&#xD;
aif&#xD;
a   ' .&#xD;
Gi&#xD;
_    -&#xD;
_  ,&#xD;
iti&#xD;
f , --&#xD;
' '    . y:&#xD;
'S.1' 'h   ..  ..&#xD;
_}'. y&#xD;
^.&#xD;
;f' _,..&#xD;
i{ -;-&#xD;
i&#xD;
'   i&#xD;
&#xD;
mow:,&#xD;
Y&#xD;
^"&#xD;
+&#xD;
F.:&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="216-217" xml:id="VAC8382-00000108"/>&#xD;
tie&#xD;
&#xD;
ME :  w It&#xD;
&#xD;
74&#xD;
&#xD;
The acts concerning Paddy were these;&#xD;
ome of his olden boon companions had for&#xD;
some time been tanning hi for his new tex-r&#xD;
peance ways, and had sought by every means&#xD;
to make him drink; on this day five or six&#xD;
of them  surrounded him  and proceeded t&#xD;
estremitits, holding him, throwing whiskey in&#xD;
his face, and so on. Paddy had always been a&#xD;
-bi.     f   w adt est a        ness&#xD;
Digstrng, hi--         s---&#xD;
coal heaving had tended to muscular develop&#xD;
met     Driven  o bay, he turned on    i&#xD;
rsecutors and, striking vigorously right ad&#xD;
left, he soon cleared the field, his foes inglor-&#xD;
ously retreating with wounds and bruises.&#xD;
Paddv however, was arrested, and past e-&#xD;
perience taught him better than to resist -&#xD;
officers. The court Looked on him as an ok&#xD;
offender, and had not the honest, well-remem-&#xD;
bered face of Thomas Twigg appeared on the&#xD;
MPay mast have one to the Island.&#xD;
With Thomas to certify to recent good conduct&#xD;
1                                   _&#xD;
&#xD;
11 ago                         Fes";       _ _&#xD;
&#xD;
-&#xD;
4,&#xD;
A&#xD;
'I&#xD;
_  I:&#xD;
&#xD;
f '&#xD;
L-&#xD;
a&#xD;
:ti&#xD;
h&#xD;
A&#xD;
__-&#xD;
,y&#xD;
s'&#xD;
.5&#xD;
, 4&#xD;
^N 3&#xD;
. b&#xD;
&#xD;
and tempernce principles, with Thomas, who&#xD;
had learned from Mrs. McClure what witnesses&#xD;
there were to testify to the truth of the pri-&#xD;
oner's statements, and with Thomas, valiantly&#xD;
rea lv to go bail for Paddy McClure, the ae-&#xD;
cased was simply bound over to keep dt&#xD;
peace, a:d was dismissed with a portion of&#xD;
goA ad ice from "I:  Honor."&#xD;
- . Nwmy man, sa4 Thomas W Jrinl&#xD;
away trom the Police Court with Paddy,  o&#xD;
rn: .earn to take radinz patiently, and not t&#xD;
b tau: when voh gets mad. Can't vou stand&#xD;
a little tazzng or ill talking?"&#xD;
--. hut it's tourh to be flited and hooted&#xD;
au male t.very manner of fun of, bedad,&#xD;
reyp id Paddy.&#xD;
Ksfor that you ought to be proud to give&#xD;
occasion for such kind of persecuting," replied&#xD;
Thomas ; "if you went on like the rest they'd&#xD;
ut set on you, but what for a decent mar.&#xD;
uld4.youL be ?-"&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="218-219" xml:id="VAC8382-00000109"/>&#xD;
218&#xD;
&#xD;
'='    .&#xD;
, s  _&#xD;
,,  :-&#xD;
r,&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
Share I dont want to turn .to dhrinkin'&#xD;
.i  sad Paddy, "but it makes me ashamed&#xD;
.A to :ma&#xD;
like, to be singier;g&#xD;
down to his place of work.&#xD;
That evenmlt' Tomas an  d Becky were n&#xD;
dulging in a little social chat, and Thomas&#xD;
recounting  a     a&#xD;
me. he sail- to see the way things woni&#xD;
folks ainft a mie asaw dt ~    rn   t&#xD;
there mrtal shamed t&#xD;
tere's - Paddy. never P'ared ' 1r a e~  m&#xD;
make a unsee of ijnsi.wnatt&#xD;
braztn as could    but here t&#xD;
gnou i of  in: 'Uer and hard work&#xD;
all ot a piece, Vk  amut asuam  e t    t&#xD;
devil butt they're put:otebuhathn&#xD;
o r t Lord who made em.  p&#xD;
hty clear how  machly the world'5 goun&#xD;
wron:.&#xD;
"Well,  d B~ckv "I might as well say&#xD;
the thruth and done wid it, I have them sinai&#xD;
&#xD;
r.&#xD;
co&#xD;
&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
kr .;r&#xD;
.r  °+&#xD;
}&#xD;
-  'C&#xD;
,&#xD;
!&#xD;
+ ".. _&#xD;
.       _   .&#xD;
p' f '&#xD;
.&#xD;
.y&#xD;
,.&#xD;
,&#xD;
&#xD;
:ri&#xD;
A&#xD;
:ar&#xD;
.°&#xD;
_&#xD;
&#xD;
feelings meself. Shure Pm tired of not know-&#xD;
ing how to reax but I am getting Maggie to&#xD;
teaeh me, and troth I puts me book nuder me&#xD;
apron or under me pillow, if eve a body comes&#xD;
tat all at all. And shure whin Mrs. Dodd&#xD;
walks in. and me sayin' me prayers, I felt like a&#xD;
j'.nW-Thomas. Indeed. if ever&#xD;
ter  waR a crooked stick in the builin of&#xD;
QL:; fDWckv Killcan, an it s ew morning&#xD;
#r  k O.     eh, Beckyi, youre that&#xD;
+::um&amp;amp;ey clner ov ye, mor ye re tit for noth&#xD;
at as -a: all.&#xD;
We1L  ardner. said Thomas. after a mn-&#xD;
nis mesta U     - that may he as you say,&#xD;
:-myalief tha theLod'        nerful&#xD;
a: straight  nml .&#xD;
Buthere come to our quiet study an echo&#xD;
tauouter w:r. ada we pause a noment.&#xD;
e  s   that sueh tales as this we are so&#xD;
w;H tamnr are -intresing," arnd yet&#xD;
&#xD;
";&#xD;
,,&#xD;
.    :..       -&#xD;
_ _..&#xD;
- ,&#xD;
:&#xD;
.,: -&#xD;
&#xD;
,wve- j.          _ F,&#xD;
tiA                                      -&#xD;
N+      f&#xD;
n  r;^ =r&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="220-221" xml:id="VAC8382-00000110"/>&#xD;
ma cosrat mat.&#xD;
&#xD;
a'&#xD;
&#xD;
" we do not   itessuch results fromats&#xD;
which we ourselves or our neighbors may&#xD;
perform" This is a cry often repeated -and&#xD;
still, dear friends, what are you saying ? Are&#xD;
such results as these, indolence, vice, drunkem-&#xD;
ness, self-serving, abandoned from the preach~&#xD;
ing of the gospel, old things passig away and&#xD;
all becoungz new from- Christian iduence,&#xD;
exceptions to a commnal rule ? Is not this the&#xD;
legitimate eifet of religious ife and iabor?$&#xD;
No wonder that Vyiu d? not see cthe&amp;amp;.e thin&#xD;
when youl do not etrpct to see umm.n Xou&#xD;
mast work with ;Ui al' Are vou so wo.rkin&amp;amp;&#xD;
are vou toiling onl in God's wide vineyard re-&#xD;
lying on his promniscd reward ?. Are you giving&#xD;
until von feed it, working until the desh gows&#xD;
weary, praying in -faith, nothing wearering.-&#xD;
Ali, there is the key note of success ; those&#xD;
who so work and give and pray,  shall doubt-&#xD;
zess come again rejoiclig, bringin their zsaeave&#xD;
with them?&#xD;
&#xD;
-C&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
4&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
V&#xD;
&#xD;
0, earnest, whole-hbearted laborers, we p-&#xD;
peal to you for confirmation of our words-&#xD;
we point to some of your sheaves.- Was not&#xD;
the work of good constable Lyons, in "Battle&#xD;
Row,"' wider and more etieetual than this of&#xD;
pie-man Twigg in Jug Alley ? What can be&#xD;
said too. much for the seed sowing and har-&#xD;
vetngz in the Five Points ? Who will forget&#xD;
the work of one good woman in Russiter's&#xD;
aileyr; loo~k at the tull sheaves of one Bihie&#xD;
Sweman's harvet !Verihy, great is the Labor&#xD;
and greater the reward, for God has said --&#xD;
- A the rain coethl down, and the snow,&#xD;
trom TlEaven, and returneth not thither again,&#xD;
so shall my word be that gcoeth forth uut of&#xD;
my mouth, it shall not return unto. me void,&#xD;
but  hall accomplish the thin whereunto I&#xD;
SentU&#xD;
-lBe not faithless but believing.&#xD;
lBnt while we are thus discoursing and say&#xD;
ing some things and leaving thers unsaid,tis&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="222-223" xml:id="VAC8382-00000111"/>&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
coaffMaSta-&#xD;
&#xD;
-u  c'n== r--&#xD;
&#xD;
for instance, any mention of the Wynd Mis-&#xD;
the daily ife of our friends about Jug&#xD;
si fd tn with plenty&#xD;
S   Alley isbem, s ua --- 'e-- ,-     -   -&#xD;
of work and many little cares and pleasures-&#xD;
Of these last was the stp  g o&#xD;
dandily dressed lack bor at the CAll,&#xD;
31 4               llhaan-. and e&#xD;
and at Mers.  i&#xD;
place a small parcel i&#xD;
sai dparce1 iaiK&#xD;
1       i-&#xD;
(rOV ~nnc ~-~~. ct-~x.~i awhite r'ib,en.&#xD;
band   e    th~~eI\~~  a niqnuraml j .elegant .&#xD;
tt ncth r ThIn :a~ nr Becky could deciphier&#xD;
.                                        ---  -&#xD;
Th~ey reo ad enr cxtanuf  ieo&#xD;
diuz leaicd&#xD;
theacopaniym    k  to ~e ~    ay&#xD;
thiw  bBe ee.bti~cky told hin he c&#xD;
nnrt tkc'a tsteIcrdecencs a  kc; ,o&#xD;
ut: the ea-usl    bieand gave Jerry&#xD;
t     hs,&#xD;
tT 4&#xD;
an I-                 a     .+A&#xD;
&#xD;
another, and then put the box with the rest&#xD;
of the cake away in a multiplity of wrap-&#xD;
pings, and, for all I know, be has it yet, among&#xD;
his most sacred treasures.&#xD;
"A.nd so' said Becky, "Miss Laura ain't&#xD;
M11s Laura any more at all Troth, I hope&#xD;
m 4 bc as a 2  pF  aMrA Aiston, as she's&#xD;
S         aie  c  aute a twopeas&#xD;
m. au, S     nme wx     glad or it, for she&#xD;
u bn 1c tcer.&#xD;
t1 n' doub: hut wiat M s7 Mary~ll grow&#xD;
-Th  I-.t  pa   x .  .2   :  serx t r  has  it,&#xD;
n~' c~d i Inc"z~  heKw~d go and&#xD;
xxbn I,. is old he w.nut depart frux  t&#xD;
\V K Ith bi c%#, ' y!  fT  xe1. es  ben'  trained&#xD;
up r::ht, for it'S nut a wSeek, Tbhomas, smn ahe&#xD;
ah&#xD;
w t into Dodd's, with her nurse, taking the&#xD;
Kd Iady a double 2uwnl and a basket of good-&#xD;
i-   The 01d ladd's feeble.&#xD;
Yes she'ss feeble, is Mrs. Dodd" repid&#xD;
&#xD;
222t~tf&#xD;
&#xD;
-n&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="224-225" xml:id="VAC8382-00000112"/>&#xD;
ca&#xD;
&#xD;
_-Sa  n T S&#xD;
&#xD;
Thomas, "and I don't think she'll live much&#xD;
longer. She's always been a weakly minded&#xD;
Wa, but, as I retadSeripter, the Lord is&#xD;
merciful and tender, and don't despise any.&#xD;
That's reasonable too, pardner, if you look at&#xD;
it, for if He took to des piing any He might&#xD;
easy despise us all, for what any one in&#xD;
comnriaan. Thcres a tine book I got of Mr.&#xD;
Aistn, PiT gIULs Prgress 1t'$ cde,adit&#xD;
shows up how earetu, like a Good Shepherd,&#xD;
4W  the Lord is over weaKIy onets.&#xD;
Old Mrs. Dodd was growv4ing weaker, but as&#xD;
her bodily strev nh decayed i+r mind brigh-&#xD;
ened up a lttie. She said one day to her&#xD;
daughter-it-law, ' WVli, Bridgtt, Pappy D  d&#xD;
told me to hold on to the promises, and 1ve&#xD;
been holding ou a fast as I could, and now&#xD;
seems as I htld on stronger and stronger, the&#xD;
Lord says, a fear not, I will help thee,' and&#xD;
Thomad read   e - wiie  ave thy edudren&#xD;
arnd I hold on to them, and he says 'come,'&#xD;
&#xD;
and I tink  ve come, and he says, take&#xD;
freely,' and it's just what I want to do."&#xD;
She asked her son one day, "George, have&#xD;
yon put your name to paper not to tech no&#xD;
more whiskey?"&#xD;
" Yes, mother," he replied.&#xD;
."Well, now, George, just bold on to that;&#xD;
hold on to it and I won't feel onpicasant when&#xD;
I gets to glory and meets Pappy Dodd. I'll&#xD;
not fear to make mention of youif I know&#xD;
your holding on to   ways,&#xD;
Mrs. Killigan looked after Mrs. George&#xD;
DtJP' feeble ones, the old lady of eighty, and&#xD;
the young baby of two, but after a while the&#xD;
old lady  otdso helpless that she needed&#xD;
constant -care, and Mrs. Dodd said she must&#xD;
stay at home and take care of her, but what&#xD;
would become of the stand on the wharf&#xD;
which was half their living. Thomas offered&#xD;
to sell George's small wares at the Corner&#xD;
Stall that George might go to the wharf.&#xD;
&#xD;
4g&#xD;
k&#xD;
&#xD;
L&#xD;
\-&#xD;
&#xD;
;i_&#xD;
_       ,  '&#xD;
..&#xD;
&#xD;
.'&#xD;
..&#xD;
.i .:&#xD;
_                          v&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="226-227" xml:id="VAC8382-00000113"/>&#xD;
As       41&#xD;
&#xD;
Tn  co-a r   ai&#xD;
&#xD;
"It's a bad tempting place for Geor,'&#xD;
said the wife, uneasy ; but here, with a sudden&#xD;
gam of intelligence, the old woman spoke,&#xD;
"Let him go, Bridget: I want to know if he&#xD;
can stand temptation and ain't a-going to fall&#xD;
away any more, so's I can tell Papp  Dodd,&#xD;
for I know he'll ask. I want to be sure. of&#xD;
George.'&#xD;
t sI n'  eea there s any other way t&#xD;
do." said the youngettr woman.ttfll nxioul v;&#xD;
she. had sufTfred much fromn hem r hul.and's&#xD;
drunkenneS. and nowA if he   ouldIfadl I 'ak&#xD;
into the old, evil habit, how dreadful it would&#xD;
be; she was not o sure of him as to be wiling&#xD;
he should be far awav from Thomas Twigg.&#xD;
Again the old woman spoke, mingling in her&#xD;
reeling brain the past and present. -Georgie,&#xD;
sunny, do you say your prayers "&#xD;
George stammered and hesitated.&#xD;
"Speak up, sonny, don't be ashamed of it&#xD;
if you do, but oh, be afraid if you don't; you'll&#xD;
&#xD;
surely fall away if you don't say your prayer.,&#xD;
you will, sonny; folks can't stand alone, and&#xD;
they must ask the good Lord to hold on to&#xD;
em. Do you say your prayers, Georgie".&#xD;
George bent his head, and, touched by the&#xD;
w words that brought back his childhood and&#xD;
tbis weak, over-fond mother's love, the man&#xD;
4ept. and as The repeated drearily, "Georgie?"&#xD;
he replied, " Yes, mother, I will."&#xD;
as the fall passed away, and the winter&#xD;
cecddly on, she, whose life had long since&#xD;
into It' desolate winter, was goingrby&#xD;
evident steps to that fair land where sweeping&#xD;
st nns of sorrow and Chillinz winds of disap-&#xD;
tument mar never come, and where they,&#xD;
wh. are weak and feeble-minded, are kindly&#xD;
wel com  and nurtured and dowered with the&#xD;
;-4 things of the Better Life.&#xD;
'WIhen for Jars she had been too helpless to&#xD;
leave her pillow, and it was evident, that the&#xD;
end was near, Thomas bent over her, and&#xD;
&#xD;
IL&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
"  y&#xD;
}y&#xD;
5   4&#xD;
;  w-%     I&#xD;
d   i&#xD;
r    _&#xD;
n i&#xD;
" y'1M&#xD;
. ~y&#xD;
"    '&#xD;
d.&#xD;
r&#xD;
nw&#xD;
s -&#xD;
'  ° _ _&#xD;
2&#xD;
.&#xD;
~' ._&#xD;
&#xD;
I7t1&#xD;
3 4:&#xD;
4   4&#xD;
&#xD;
M  ,&#xD;
,&#xD;
; -~&#xD;
,&#xD;
;    .&#xD;
-'&#xD;
;;&#xD;
^. y'&#xD;
°&#xD;
rK"&#xD;
&#xD;
AIL&#xD;
i   law. P, w3l M.IJ 5 - C -02 X_ MIAM&#xD;
&#xD;
. j&#xD;
I =&#xD;
.;  ?&#xD;
r&#xD;
&#xD;
;&#xD;
.&#xD;
: =,&#xD;
r.&#xD;
'~,&#xD;
i&#xD;
_ .&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="228-229" xml:id="VAC8382-00000114"/>&#xD;
ngloudly to reach her dulled sense, he&#xD;
"Do you know you are soon to die?"&#xD;
Well;"   e said, dowly, *I ain't sory for&#xD;
that -I've been waiting -a long time."&#xD;
After a while, holding out her wrinkled,&#xD;
trembling hand. she said, Good bye, Georgie,&#xD;
the  Lord's  been  good  to  me, many  ways -Io&#xD;
ain't a bit afeared - mind yu get to glory,&#xD;
George, Scriptrr' te  yn how ''--and in a&#xD;
few minutes She ;was goe trom among them.&#xD;
The old lady 'was laid in her grave ; it wr a&#xD;
weary ife well ended ; they all felt that it was&#xD;
a thing to thank the good Father for, that she&#xD;
was buffeting the whirling storms of this life&#xD;
no longer, like a poor, faded leaf clinging to&#xD;
the branch beyond its time: all felt so but the&#xD;
baby, who missed the chattering occupant of&#xD;
the big chair, and made some pitiful complain.&#xD;
wings after "(Grannie.'&#xD;
The mission room in Jug Alley was like the&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
"little leaven leavening the whole lump;" its&#xD;
influence spread through all the miserable&#xD;
tenant houses, from slimy, reekv cellars to&#xD;
sting and leaky attic. Here was a     n&#xD;
rescued from  a drunkard's grave, there a&#xD;
woman taught to work and hope, there a child&#xD;
brought to school, an embryo pickpocket taught&#xD;
to read and make an honest living, and often&#xD;
nel cted hahit were, by the watchful Bible&#xD;
woman. ganed fur the fosterinz cares of the&#xD;
children's Home, or the Island Nurseries; but&#xD;
while these things encouraged some of the&#xD;
poor folks to hope for better things, and while&#xD;
the hearts of many of God's children were&#xD;
strengthened in seeing how he prospered the&#xD;
work of humble instruments, the adversary&#xD;
of sout and his like-minded servants greatly&#xD;
raged.&#xD;
First there were rumsellers and inveterate&#xD;
frum-drinkers, who wanted nothing so much as&#xD;
liberty to kill and be killed in their own war. -&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
ITV&#xD;
.1_&#xD;
MK!&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="230-231" xml:id="VAC8382-00000115"/>&#xD;
Net came the zealots of Rome, who, hitherto,&#xD;
had given the cold shoulder to Jug Alte&#xD;
inasmuch as there was there absolutely north&#xD;
ifgt to tDe extorted:; but nocw that gospel light&#xD;
was beginning to 4hine, and Thomas Twi&#xD;
was as a steadyc -:l iamp Ae :y free gaeii&#xD;
that darkc    : Int 4iine true" tfa&#xD;
Laste to bim   a bu h    to cov   up&#xD;
Up an II;xci dA      v. went a  re:&#xD;
bi  -akr M a' si   "ath     aeT&#xD;
inirk rv -.       The-~ tries di the p&#xD;
mu m t church and eounk a:&#xD;
theyv were:                    - za~  n addd ha&#xD;
o turn                  ur  de:ruenq ;&#xD;
ThXma   T~              n:ao ed as an ar:h&#xD;
there-t:c. and  a true n-i   e ~         d :--  n&#xD;
Bec-kxy Ku::1: onwar     A a s"a xiki&#xD;
renegade,. list, herNeC U1 Lid in wat for thl:&#xD;
seoS o: olp--r  and c~xrezW&#xD;
The priet: x tsia d B cky, idd in2 h Y.f  .  1  'Y 1 e re6 T&#xD;
&#xD;
T&#xD;
R&#xD;
5C&#xD;
&#xD;
[itcona ews&#xD;
Swnt, and turn to the bosom   of the true&#xD;
Church.&#xD;
I wouldn't do it for fire under dollars,"&#xD;
was the characteristic reply.&#xD;
Then you'll be excommunicated with book&#xD;
and Wen&#xD;
What  that: asked Becky.e&#xD;
Turwed ut afthie true Caurch."&#xD;
Arrah. said BWnk, -that can't be done,&#xD;
 '  1nemyself outlu  .ago;it'sno place for&#xD;
oe. IIw can ye turn out her as amtin .&#xD;
"An Iitis dehvering you  ver to the evil&#xD;
cne  went on the priest.&#xD;
ut tat. repied Beck       1 ju  ieto&#xD;
 vur any  her man     the world, do&#xD;
ta' at aU at all. Don': the Bible say -him&#xD;
that ceeth unto me I will in no wise east&#xD;
on::' and whin Becky Killgan' s heart was&#xD;
broke intirely, and she went to the good Lord,&#xD;
do you think ere a one of you is going to east&#xD;
&#xD;
w&#xD;
l&#xD;
rt J       {   .  Q&#xD;
-l       r&#xD;
}lr a e&#xD;
w      -&#xD;
r  -&#xD;
1            .&#xD;
i _    y&#xD;
-+iX =&#xD;
&#xD;
I_&#xD;
., ..&#xD;
. .;.'&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="232-233" xml:id="VAC8382-00000116"/>&#xD;
n           ta corn     sno&#xD;
stick. Faith, you aint, for Thomas read to&#xD;
me that the Lord is 'able to kape what is&#xD;
committed to him,' and that's, Becky Kigan&#xD;
sure and certain.&#xD;
The priest had been dumb before the rapid&#xD;
flow of Becky' Irish eloquence, but now, as&#xD;
she paused.&#xD;
The church cats vou ot, and wil no&#xD;
more help you, tPreve'r?&#xD;
SI want none of her help' said Becky.&#xD;
a"so long as I have the Lord, and I aig' t s&#xD;
much trusting to me holding on to hun as to&#xD;
his holding on to me. Share. I'd hold to that&#xD;
doctrine if it took ivery emt  have in tae&#xD;
wuarrld."&#xD;
A similar ebrt at reCon vrsonI was rade&#xD;
with the stalwart Paddy McClure, and wi&#xD;
no more success and a plot was quietly lail&#xD;
to make a personal assault on Thomas, and&#xD;
punish him for his meddling.&#xD;
This plot was confided to Paddy McClure&#xD;
&#xD;
it,&#xD;
&#xD;
Arm&#xD;
&#xD;
w . c .TALL&#xD;
&#xD;
by a brother coal hearer, who was too tipsy to&#xD;
know that Paddy was not "'one of his bovs."&#xD;
The fact was, olden passions were strong in&#xD;
Paddy, and he really relished the idea of a&#xD;
melee in which he resolved to make his burly&#xD;
ure a shield for little Thomas Twigg. and&#xD;
1e giVe as g-ood as. he cot.&#xD;
As Thomas left the MLsion room on the&#xD;
evenin of t!O proposed a       Jsault, Pi1Ad t&#xD;
hi pace b hi  ide, and whiwering what was&#xD;
cmng, a:3idkartilv,  s  vtick v me ani don't&#xD;
lear Cef ;Tll stand by You, and I' hew 'em&#xD;
down le a  vtV:" and he smote his arms&#xD;
around hi bro ad chest, exultijnu in his strengthi.&#xD;
I Hld n," said Thomas. "that ain't Scripw&#xD;
tr way, and 'll not be false to my doctrine.&#xD;
Xeep your hands in your pockets, Paddy, I&#xD;
bid you."&#xD;
And is it Scripter to run, or to get pound-&#xD;
ed man:"&#xD;
" The Scripter is, *'A soft answer turneth&#xD;
&#xD;
AL, I&#xD;
7-41&#xD;
2^&#xD;
Sw,&#xD;
sK   _                                      _&#xD;
«hy                                 '&#xD;
j  ifm&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="234-235" xml:id="VAC8382-00000117"/>&#xD;
234&#xD;
&#xD;
at CORNE SALL&#xD;
&#xD;
away wrath,' and 'leave off contention before&#xD;
it be meddled with ; and now, Paddy, I mean&#xD;
to tr those words,. and be. yoU sure tey&#xD;
come good.&#xD;
"There they come      cried McClure, n-&#xD;
Where is the heretic? where is Daa I&#xD;
Twig; ?  was the cry from a dozen voi&#xD;
Here I am:  rmcid Tiomas, ceary&#xD;
And he re I anm,  *." roared li McCiur..&#xD;
" I   : land to  e air pay;w&#xD;
XV  * 3.  i  tS' s 1.1sk  p  r  3A ':U tdi.i a+lIJ uis a A5'dt:an"-&#xD;
eried the n.-&#xD;
\VL4    'x.  °Pl 'Cri$ed  T him a,   in  a  sh&#xD;
1'        I       .  t-    i 7 #1    a (t  LIet t&#xD;
plan oie.-   r. I 4ti. and nw   I * V&#xD;
man -vu ver  urt r ijured comew out fir-t&#xD;
manpIr                  y rnu&#xD;
Here I and to anwet sor the fly'I mi&#xD;
've done in Jun Aleyx&#xD;
"aThat's fair; come  u   cried MCiur;&#xD;
but not a man came.&#xD;
&#xD;
. Where is the man I've ill-treated !" es-&#xD;
claimed Thomas, uncnsciously vemulatig the&#xD;
.-  -  2    - a  a   man  I  have&#xD;
challenges   raai,-                -     .&#xD;
oa treated like a brother, in the fear f God.'&#xD;
I have gone about here trvinz to help you-&#xD;
an  vour women and children, and so I wil,&#xD;
et last.&#xD;
You've hurt me." cried onec; iyou re&#xD;
ntmyv trauc.&#xD;
*.iM Fillin? sai M31Ciure, int a whit-&#xD;
t* u r  ne or   t r m&#xD;
-           -           : your baby&#xD;
Mr. Twi:    L id i- hoorx~  fur Dddv&#xD;
T i  «4 U c -i-d -jv en   J ak  a  n w ;  ja r  id  eru tch -&#xD;
t Iltray: cried oe. recring arurnd with&#xD;
runRen tacmU y.&#xD;
--G(ve hin three -ier  an z'tncw&#xD;
y, cried McClure -. it- him s it a findn&#xD;
to every mother a 0  x y.  D&amp;amp;     e  r&#xD;
one set ye  o2e him.  ±Tnree clcer5, flOW *&#xD;
&#xD;
It'n&#xD;
&#xD;
A71&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="236-237" xml:id="VAC8382-00000118"/>&#xD;
TE COUR STLa&#xD;
&#xD;
The men gave one good cheer, and then,&#xD;
with a laugh, walked off, leaving Thomas and&#xD;
Paddy to go home.&#xD;
" My way was the best, found it in Scrip&#xD;
ter," said Thomas.&#xD;
a proper good guide 1"iI be&#xD;
bound," said Pa dy.&#xD;
&#xD;
CHAPTER X.&#xD;
&#xD;
TAKING THE LORD AT HI1 WORD.&#xD;
&#xD;
v HREE       years have gone by. Let s&#xD;
again to No. 27. Workmen have&#xD;
been busy -at the lower rooms. and&#xD;
have fitted up one for a very comfortable shop;&#xD;
back, of the shop some one has been white-"&#xD;
wahin and scrubing, and in the room across&#xD;
the entry. from the shop. are Mrs. Killisan&#xD;
and Mrs. Dodd.&#xD;
"i Mrs. Killigan's cap rates are as stiffy&#xD;
luted, as wide. and as white as ever; her&#xD;
dress is as dlean, and one would think she had&#xD;
on the same striped apron as when we begun&#xD;
53&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
_&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
F&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
Jj,&#xD;
&#xD;
_                        Alp&#xD;
&#xD;
236&#xD;
&#xD;
Ll&#xD;
zm-&#xD;
iR&#xD;
,fiy    W&#xD;
i        t"&#xD;
_ "++yyyrg y     _&#xD;
M-F&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="238-239" xml:id="VAC8382-00000119"/>&#xD;
TE COMMSa STLL.&#xD;
&#xD;
23&#xD;
&#xD;
TEE CeOflR STALt&#xD;
&#xD;
7'&#xD;
&#xD;
this tale ; she had just entered the room; over&#xD;
one hand was a woolen stocking drawn for&#xD;
airing, inothe othr Ler yar 1ha1 atnA darn-&#xD;
inl needle. - She took a chair by one well-&#xD;
cleaned window ; the other window was occu-&#xD;
pied by Teddy, tidily dressed, and occu py ng: a&#xD;
high chair: his face D kdas it he was oier&#xD;
than four; his nirure .was much smaller than&#xD;
L   .4I  ,-            t .  I,&#xD;
sickly; yet had a center1 look, marked on&#xD;
his slate a if his li  dep!ndd on the curly-&#xD;
cues  he  was  m$JnL u,  ant iy  V''  on&#xD;
window sill, were tw pot  _ ioK:,:n: Lwers.&#xD;
MIrs. Georg~e Dodd nt pped, Udser in hand. to&#xD;
eztet her fi I Bechy.&#xD;
Troth, v'Y.I e m t K in ordern.i said Mrs.&#xD;
Kilizan : ile, y 4, ou   n 'lk mee. Them cur-&#xD;
tamins is verv fne. and 4hure. tat s an iiiant:&#xD;
bed quilt if I did help make it. And what a&#xD;
camfoirt it 1s to have new table and chairs and&#xD;
beds' how much might you have spent tixif&#xD;
it all up?"&#xD;
&#xD;
"Well, thirty dollars, with some bits we&#xD;
got for the kitchen."&#xD;
" Troth,  s a mint of money, but ifs well&#xD;
spent hei' decent and tidy, and making a&#xD;
home for the children. It's meseif wishes ye&#xD;
well in your new shop; cash pay., good, honest&#xD;
dealingS, and smalt steady profts, them my&#xD;
ru.  and Thomas   and we've turned a pretty&#xD;
rT-r-    An 1Mr. Dodd. which is iver&#xD;
S   er o     bu: which Thomas says is no&#xD;
wcndermnnnto himu Anr' we ;ive a sharec, and&#xD;
our tie    vw     rsesmost&#xD;
ors&#xD;
ama/nm&#xD;
4WeI i iN't George who will drive hard&#xD;
-ri  with h  poor for wv knows what&#xD;
,aramins  W a  4B .  .&#xD;
povrt i. I Ba ild day to nw who have&#xD;
toiled in cold andi heat and  torm_, so many&#xD;
l:gdaysand have been sore put to get a&#xD;
bite for the children, it is a glad day to me to&#xD;
he .d George able to set&#xD;
have a eroom hoes, a   ne-      fo the&#xD;
.up  decnt, onetotmperance shop, forth&#xD;
&#xD;
s&#xD;
1&#xD;
r&#xD;
sY:S  x&#xD;
Ott;  pt&#xD;
a&#xD;
;t l33&#xD;
't&#xD;
&#xD;
I1&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
t'&#xD;
&#xD;
s&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="240-241" xml:id="VAC8382-00000120"/>&#xD;
,&#xD;
&#xD;
1.&#xD;
&#xD;
2 5 COONE SAL&#xD;
poor folks about here. And, indeed I knows&#xD;
well he could never do it only for such friends&#xD;
as he's had."&#xD;
" Yes," said Mrs. Killigan, "Thomas has&#xD;
been a good one to him.&#xD;
SHe'd be in a drunkard's grave, and me&#xD;
heart broke over him now, and it wasift for&#xD;
Thomas Twiggz~ said Mrs. Dodd, earnest2y-&#xD;
And there's that bilesed chiti aia i m.&#xD;
Eilligan, thus indicating Mary StuyvesanL&#xD;
Indeed she is a blessed etutd. .ot one&#xD;
penny of expense has Mazic b tto us&#xD;
three year, getting her bok and he-r clothes&#xD;
from Miss Marv, and then the nice manners&#xD;
and idees is better than all ;an to  .k at the&#xD;
sight of clothes and toy s. and good things She's&#xD;
bought Teddy. When I see her many i the&#xD;
time Iye sad,1 there is a born angel without&#xD;
the win  inded&#xD;
, Shes like her aunt, Sut M- Kihigan;&#xD;
" aiver in the wurruld did anything go to me&#xD;
&#xD;
M con, sra.&#xD;
&#xD;
*Y&#xD;
&#xD;
4.&#xD;
I E&#xD;
&#xD;
..&#xD;
_:&#xD;
-&#xD;
. £&#xD;
x-&#xD;
, . -,&#xD;
, , ,&#xD;
=',&#xD;
-, : ,&#xD;
&#xD;
_&#xD;
&#xD;
a&#xD;
&#xD;
heart like having her sind them wedding' cards&#xD;
and cake to me and Thomas. Share, it was&#xD;
the Christian spirit ov her made her think of&#xD;
it, for what to her were two such poor creatures&#xD;
as me and Thomas, saving she see in us two&#xD;
folks on the road to glorvo"&#xD;
HereZ XUg8i came ;i fr-om  corl with Mrs.&#xD;
McClure's hearly, barf-ot, but clean and&#xD;
whole-clothed hors&#xD;
" When' our shop z    g to open. Mrs.&#xD;
Dodd ?" cried one: -"mamnmy says we're going&#xD;
to buy all our things at it ;ain't you gdad ?"&#xD;
Tell Mr. Ddd t keep somane crackers for&#xD;
the Fourth. I wVan: vem to; shoot" c ried the&#xD;
other boy.&#xD;
" See the long -al of the child, looking on&#xD;
two Months: said Mrs. K   in, approvingly.&#xD;
"W   i are you so late, Maggie?" asked the&#xD;
mother.&#xD;
Instead of repIying, Magi laid her head&#xD;
on the table and began to cry violently.&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
, 7. --, - T-F&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="242-243" xml:id="VAC8382-00000121"/>&#xD;
curears SALL&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
"Where have you been?" urged the&#xD;
1  V4&#xD;
mother.&#xD;
"T   M M Ailson's, sobbed Maggi&amp;amp;.&#xD;
Sure, there's no crvinz matter in that,&#xD;
only  ye ought to ask." interposed   Mrs.&#xD;
Killigan.&#xD;
"What did you go for ?  asked Mrs.-Dodd.&#xD;
"I heard." sobbed Mazzwe in mn ucwief,&#xD;
thz she wante' a nurs cghi, and, and- I&#xD;
wanted the piaes, andI -  he I -I was too&#xD;
little, anI mug: co t sdhoo inger-but I&#xD;
want to g there,. the baby 's jut like pretty&#xD;
Miss Mary, it is:; and Ahe gt Mrs. McClure's&#xD;
girl, and I wilh it w me."&#xD;
Here a fresi,-aced girl of sixteen put her&#xD;
head in the door: ;she was neatly dressed, and&#xD;
her rounds smiling countenance prepossessed,&#xD;
in her favor, every one who saw her.'&#xD;
"I'm going to live with Mrs. Allston" she&#xD;
eraimed.&#xD;
"So Maggie says, and she's crying after the&#xD;
&#xD;
s%~ta&#xD;
&#xD;
place herself," said both the women,a   .&#xD;
"Don't cry, Maggie," said the girl; "do&#xD;
your best to grow and learn, and some time&#xD;
you shall go and live with Mi ss lary "&#xD;
"She's only nine years old," sniffed Maggie,&#xD;
"So arc you only nine years old," said the.&#xD;
girl, merrily, "and she'll grow as fast as you&#xD;
will ; but I must run and tell mother, she'll be&#xD;
so glad; she grieved enough when my mistress&#xD;
went West, and now for me to go to Mrs.&#xD;
Aliston's, will make it all up.i'&#xD;
She's a  lony girl9" said Mrs. Dodd, as&#xD;
her youthful neighor ran off.&#xD;
"Aid Thnomas T wig'% been the savin' of&#xD;
all that family? said Mrs. Killigan, with much&#xD;
pride in her old friend.&#xD;
" Well, I pray he may be blessed on earth,&#xD;
and sure and certain there's reward laid up for&#xD;
him in Heaven," said Mrs. Dodd.&#xD;
You ought to step down Jug Alley," said&#xD;
Mrs. Killigan; " the health men hare cleaned&#xD;
&#xD;
F&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
- , ,-&#xD;
.  '&#xD;
hT&#xD;
-  .&#xD;
n&#xD;
r   -N&#xD;
&#xD;
1&#xD;
&#xD;
r  y&#xD;
y'&#xD;
N&#xD;
e&#xD;
4&#xD;
'r&#xD;
&#xD;
'1&#xD;
US&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="244-245" xml:id="VAC8382-00000122"/>&#xD;
240.&#xD;
&#xD;
SCOR e STALL.&#xD;
&#xD;
at(threeorfour cellars, and drairA the&#xD;
street, and some other men have torn down&#xD;
those two worst houses, saying they wasn't&#xD;
safe no longer, ana gladamd  N   Ny&#xD;
as you're alive, me heart was in me mouth&#xD;
erye time I walked troo '&amp;amp;m this three month.&#xD;
They've strtightened up the pavIn' too, in a&#xD;
place or so;   as she s     Je, err, a well-&#xD;
grown, lvely lad, burst into the room without&#xD;
any cereinonv, errm:, -n-&#xD;
up stairs for you  I got let to come home for&#xD;
t    from the stall, to tell you tIe jolliest&#xD;
news.&#xD;
And troth what is it: are you runnin' for&#xD;
Congress' or is Thomas nominated for Presi-&#xD;
dent"?: asked Mrs. Kilizan, jocularly&#xD;
Oh, no, but - nlo  ain' it :ood. Mr.&#xD;
Aliston stop-d lw the stall, and told us how&#xD;
them rich ones, who've been helpin: here in&#xD;
Jug Alleys have bought, where the housts&#xD;
weretor -0,furaIchAeand seh&#xD;
were torn dwn fr-3ch V-ad chol oo%;&#xD;
&#xD;
a&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
s$&#xD;
Ir&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
*    '&#xD;
&#xD;
C'&#xD;
c(&#xD;
&#xD;
they're going to make a mission of it, have an&#xD;
industrial school, and a night school, and Sun-&#xD;
day school, no end of schools."&#xD;
" Well, that's news, and good news, shire&#xD;
added the thrifty Mrs. Kdhian, never forget-&#xD;
ingthe interest of that center of all attraction,&#xD;
the Corner Stall,   how's business to-day?&#xD;
doin we.&#xD;
Yes, fr:-rate; we'll want p anr Ieakes&#xD;
to-morrow, aU I Im to  dnw to the wharf,&#xD;
now, for :mnqs : andI -2 mht I'm to make a&#xD;
lUad t4 Iar and m -&#xD;
And what U t- l'nva saV to tne Mission&#xD;
liouse?  am ' Mrs. Kim ran, her anxieties&#xD;
about the' 'tal rehexad s  that she could re-&#xD;
turn to the tnr-t t-pw.&#xD;
WeIh, safd Jerrv,  l: said hs,' he'd&#xD;
taken the Lord at his went the Lord said,&#xD;
'fear not, I will help thee,' and he'd taken&#xD;
hm at his word an' gn   on for Jug Alley,&#xD;
and here the help was coming.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="246-247" xml:id="VAC8382-00000123"/>&#xD;
b, r          Y:&#xD;
e             y&#xD;
tV&#xD;
r                 -&#xD;
'      $w&#xD;
1        Y&#xD;
. 2n&#xD;
3          ^&#xD;
r             -&#xD;
r                       5&#xD;
f     Av.&#xD;
Fs           i&#xD;
&#xD;
"True for him; could you fnd me that&#xD;
erase, Jerry?" asked Mrs Killgan, reaching&#xD;
for Mrs. TohAs -a ;_- was very proud&#xD;
of her new accomplishment of reading.&#xD;
"I don't know where it i    said Jerry,&#xD;
after a little search,** bat I'l tell you what&#xD;
more he said: One never loses by taking the&#xD;
Lord at his word;' and he bid me keep it n&#xD;
It's a good word," sail Mrs. Killgan,&#xD;
"but run now to the wharf for the lemons,&#xD;
and mind you make a good bargain ; there's&#xD;
many a scripter about bem' diligent in basic&#xD;
Meanwhile, active as ever, a little more&#xD;
wrikled of face, and grided fA hair, Thomas&#xD;
Twigg stood in the Corner Stall. It was&#xD;
about six &amp;amp;ch=ek. and newsboys and shoe-&#xD;
blacks were gathering about him, eager for&#xD;
their  p     moA of them having eaten-nth-&#xD;
ing since breakfast. There were those called&#xD;
&#xD;
AToes," "Herald,"    " World," "Tr,"&#xD;
not the same boys as three years ago, for moat&#xD;
of those had outgrown the business, and found&#xD;
other work to do.&#xD;
Of all these hors Thomas was the adviser&#xD;
and confidential friend. " Times c onfided to&#xD;
him how much he had put in the Saving's&#xD;
Bank, and "Herald" asked his advice about&#xD;
getting a home in the country 'Tiser " was&#xD;
roundly reprovea for selling apers on SUna,&#xD;
and several Scripters, suitable to the occasion,&#xD;
were dealt out to him.&#xD;
Here was a boot-black whose sick mother&#xD;
was inquired after. here another with a little&#xD;
humpbacked sister, &amp;amp; deftrmity, alas. fearfully&#xD;
common among New York poor, and to this&#xD;
little unfortunate Thomas sent one of his best&#xD;
cakes, a trifling gift, to be sure, but what a&#xD;
sunny ray in that poor little one's existence,&#xD;
To a homeless boy, new to the shoe-blacking&#xD;
business, Thomas heartily recomrnendA the&#xD;
&#xD;
ammm&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="248-249" xml:id="VAC8382-00000124"/>&#xD;
248E'CORNER STALE.&#xD;
Boy's Lodgig House," and, indeed, offered&#xD;
to take him there as soon as Jerry got back.&#xD;
Thus daily was Thomas, sowing good seed&#xD;
beside all waters; he found even m that hum-&#xD;
ble sail, on the corner of Union Square, a&#xD;
wide field of labor, and plenty to occupy heart&#xD;
and.hand a ine commentary his active, useful&#xD;
life on those who have a nothing to do.&#xD;
On a hot simmer eveig, Thomas went&#xD;
home, after a iong day of 'tandm in the -stall,&#xD;
and two hours of labor through t   stifling&#xD;
tenant houses of Jug Alley. A  he came to&#xD;
No. Q7, he saw McCluie, and hs wile, sattm&#xD;
on the door-sill of No. 29, and stopped to talk&#xD;
with them.&#xD;
where are the ehilder?" he aed.&#xD;
"Thevre un' for a walk, por thigs,&#xD;
where it's eoderY said M\rs. McAyure.&#xD;
OkI tell vou  hat, Mr. Twis+." Said P addy,&#xD;
"I'm a big, strong chap, as can earn m ihi&#xD;
anywhere, and here-s - the woman could do&#xD;
&#xD;
a&#xD;
a&#xD;
&#xD;
better at day's work, now and then, than at&#xD;
shop sewing. Tve nigh made up my mind to&#xD;
walk off into some of the Jersey villages, and&#xD;
hire a bit of a house with a yard tu rams uur&#xD;
own vegetables, and engage work, and come&#xD;
back to brinz the fatniir. Tve laid up forty&#xD;
dollars, and that  l make the more; tell us&#xD;
what von think of it?"&#xD;
"We won't be worrited about the girl,&#xD;
wnen she's with Mrs. Alston; sad the mother.&#xD;
"It's a good plan. and you'd better follow it&#xD;
up soon; it Will be better for you and the&#xD;
ehilder, only,. wherever you go, take the fear&#xD;
of the Lord with ou, and 'whatever you do,&#xD;
do it as to the Lord and not as unto-men'-&#xD;
iot with eva service as men pleasers, but&#xD;
with singleness of heart as unto God;' them's&#xD;
Scripter as nigh as I can recollect. Be sober&#xD;
and industrious,  Here's another Seripter,&#xD;
Not sothfu in business, fervent in Spirit,&#xD;
serving the Lord,&#xD;
&#xD;
, ,t%  ,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="250-251" xml:id="VAC8382-00000125"/>&#xD;
Thank you, kindly," said Mrs. McClure.-&#xD;
Il go next week and look out a place,"&#xD;
said the husband, decidedly.&#xD;
Thomas went up stairs, weary but encour-&#xD;
aged, and humming a hymn tune; as he went&#xD;
through the lower entry, he saw Mrs. Dodd&#xD;
in her room, rocking her little sick boy to&#xD;
sleep, Maggie, making patchwork, at the win-&#xD;
dow, and in the opposite room.. a snug, tidy&#xD;
shop, George waiting on two otthree custom-&#xD;
er. who had come for sixpences worth of&#xD;
soap, salt, matches, or tea. Up stairs, and in&#xD;
her room, door and windows open, sat Mrs.&#xD;
Killigan.&#xD;
"Did ye leave the boy to lock up?" she&#xD;
asked.&#xD;
Yes,"' said Thomas.  I thought he would&#xD;
do well enough alone."&#xD;
And does he lock up safe. and bring things&#xD;
home in gooA order?"&#xD;
Yes, pardner, hes very trusty."&#xD;
&#xD;
--&#xD;
&#xD;
'1&#xD;
&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
.ms''&#xD;
&#xD;
o narn sAt r&#xD;
&#xD;
'&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
.C&#xD;
&#xD;
"Och, well, then, come in and rest in me&#xD;
big chair, Thomas, me man, yon look clean&#xD;
done out ; and ye mast quit going to Jug&#xD;
Alley.  Share, ye're getting an would man,&#xD;
Thomnas$'&#xD;
"That's no excuse for nittinz work," said&#xD;
Thomas Twigg. * When it pleased the Lord&#xD;
to convert my sea., I was bound out to&#xD;
him body and soul, to b his servant and do&#xD;
his work. He  never given me back My in-&#xD;
dentures, and I'm of the opinion that he never&#xD;
will. Indeed, pardner, don't the Lord justly&#xD;
say ' watch,' and  blessed is the servant whom&#xD;
his Lord, when he cometh, shall find so doing.'&#xD;
Not blessed is the servant whom  the Lord&#xD;
shall find lyinz by from work, and saying,&#xD;
aLord, I'm old, and I'm tired, and I've done&#xD;
my share' but han. the Lord rinds up and&#xD;
doinz, and civin2 to all their meat hn season."&#xD;
3S eem to me it ct:n  pretvt Hd on you,&#xD;
Th ucomas, andtwi wear you out," saa Mirs.&#xD;
&#xD;
A&#xD;
&#xD;
.4&#xD;
&#xD;
;P*&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="252-253" xml:id="VAC8382-00000126"/>&#xD;
Killian, in whom nature continually warred.&#xD;
evidently, with grace, ana often very nearly&#xD;
got the upper hands.&#xD;
"No, tain  hard, Tor its sausactory, and&#xD;
if it is hard, we can't expect tig wages with-&#xD;
out hard work, and I'm looikngto big wages."&#xD;
And what may they he ?" asked Mrs.&#xD;
Kiliizan.&#xD;
phy, ar  rA I y ou putsyour mind on&#xD;
these things on            . know yourseu: it is a crown&#xD;
of life which the Lord, the righteous judge,&#xD;
shall give n at that Jay.&#xD;
.A,. ye." said Mrs. nialhsan. with a sigh,&#xD;
that is a price worth getting. But." she&#xD;
added. after a pause,  ain't it better to work&#xD;
easy, and save yourself a little,. and not wear&#xD;
out.&#xD;
"    .No fear ofwearinfg tut,' a iThima ,&#xD;
setting his over is no-e. and reach.-&#xD;
i  tnfr the i Rib  un the- tabl, a present to&#xD;
Beckr from Mirs. Alistun. . Let me deal ymu&#xD;
&#xD;
416&#xD;
44&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
TR  Cfl~kSTALL.&#xD;
&#xD;
23&#xD;
&#xD;
odt a Scripter on that head, pardner;" and&#xD;
turning to the fortieth chapter of Isaiah, he&#xD;
read, 'But they that wait upon the Lord shall&#xD;
renew  neir sreng; meV snt uui up&#xD;
with wings as eagles; they 'shall run and not&#xD;
he weary, there shall walk and dhall not faint:&#xD;
there. now. pardner, ain't that a promise well&#xD;
worth trusting m ; amrt it good just to take the&#xD;
Lord at his word, and zo ahead whatever work&#xD;
ZI1  IZ I L  ''" I&#xD;
"Well. mehbyl  it is Thomas. von see into&#xD;
things clearer than I do.&#xD;
"aAnd now. pardner. In't vou want to giv e&#xD;
them something :tward building' their Miionl&#xD;
House, round in the Al V  nody ha men-&#xD;
tioned it. but I thought meb you'd nwl it a&#xD;
privilege&#xD;
l How muci.if you gi, T1.   mas ?"&#xD;
asked the wary Mrs. K siigan,&#xD;
I gave 'em tifty dhIar it it ain't breaking&#xD;
o.rni 7F.s,.1   s a ;,&#xD;
Thomas.&#xD;
&#xD;
I:&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="254-255" xml:id="VAC8382-00000127"/>&#xD;
2t      it  o~~&#xD;
&#xD;
twatt-&#xD;
&#xD;
N '&#xD;
( r&#xD;
j x&#xD;
k_&#xD;
&#xD;
"Fifty  dollars!"  cried  Mrs. Kifigan.&#xD;
"Now, Thomas, that was too much for a poor&#xD;
old man; you'll miss it, see if vou don't."&#xD;
SI see I must deal you out another Scrip-&#xD;
ter," said Thomas, with a sigh over the "old&#xD;
Adam," in Becky.. and opening the Bible&#xD;
again, and holding it to the ight, he read,&#xD;
'Verily I say unto you, there is no man that&#xD;
hath left house, ar parents, or wife or children,&#xD;
for the kingdom of God's sake, who chal not&#xD;
receive manifolh more in this present time.&#xD;
(note that. pardner) -and in the world to&#xD;
come life everlasting.  Now. pardner, ain't it&#xD;
best to take the Lord at his word on such a&#xD;
promise. to the valley of fifty dollars. I felt&#xD;
like giving every penny I had when I dwelt&#xD;
on that word nlife everiastingv Rot that I could&#xD;
buy it. but just to show how I 'preciated it-.&#xD;
But 'Mr. Alstion  aid no mre than fifty, so I&#xD;
give ine w&#xD;
"4hr was a long silence, the shadows of&#xD;
&#xD;
evening gathered in the little room; at last&#xD;
Becky rose, took a key from under her pilow,&#xD;
opened her blue chest, drew from the bottom&#xD;
I I     of it a long and well-filled black woolen stoek-&#xD;
ing, and asking Thomas to light a candle, she&#xD;
deliberately counted out, in hills and coins,&#xD;
fifty dollars.&#xD;
&amp;amp;  "There," shemaid, with a loig; deep breath,&#xD;
" I    "1"vc got just even six hunder. Thomas, and&#xD;
thermes fin  of 'em, and may the Lord nelp&#xD;
Ie to give not grudgingly, but of a ready&#xD;
mind, as Vou've often told me."&#xD;
We think our friend, Becky, was getting&#xD;
converted in" that bg sticking.&#xD;
What shall we ay more? We know that&#xD;
they, whom God hath chosen, zo from strength&#xD;
to strength, and every one of them in Zion&#xD;
appeareth before God.&#xD;
It may be that as the rears have passed,&#xD;
friend Thomas Twigg is seen no more in the&#xD;
Corner Stall on Union Square, perchance he&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb n="256-257" xml:id="VAC8382-00000128"/>&#xD;
has prospered unto the attaining of a shop,&#xD;
with Jerry for his confectioner; it may be he&#xD;
bs gone where good men -Rest from their&#xD;
labors and their works do follow them."&#xD;
Earlk this morning the roar of cannlO and&#xD;
the snap of fire-crackrs aw)ke mue to the con-&#xD;
seiousness that patroie Aaerica, big and&#xD;
little was eelebrain the Natons birth-day&#xD;
If the most that patriotism did to show its&#xD;
zeal, was to use umn uua amtants of powder&#xD;
and Lager, ouIr land would be poor indeed.&#xD;
The true Criian is the best patriot. Re-&#xD;
lizion is the Palladium or our  rnes-&#xD;
Yong friends, he best serves his country&#xD;
who beat serves hi' Gd. Remember right-&#xD;
eons meni wo uld have sav  SAodom, and the&#xD;
Christialn i America are theV- whe- 1y earn-&#xD;
est labor andI tai;M  ri&#xD;
largest hiad;nZ trom the ling of Natmin.&#xD;
Many men have built in New York mar e&#xD;
&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
-I&#xD;
F&#xD;
*$&#xD;
&#xD;
TECO + gnUA&#xD;
and hotels, and palatial residences;&#xD;
many men have dowered public buildings, and&#xD;
. beautified public grounds; but I hold him a&#xD;
truer patriot, a more useful citizen, who, moved&#xD;
by love to God and fellow beings, rescues men&#xD;
from vice and iznominV, and gives to the state&#xD;
honest workers who might have been out-&#xD;
rageons criminals.&#xD;
He who spreads ;ospel lizht, temperance,&#xD;
industry and education, even in one&#xD;
home, s brter to  is country awl h  native&#xD;
-a than he who sets on hizh a: splendid&#xD;
piece of statuary, or rears a lofty done.&#xD;
To such, as Thomas   es the gd com-&#xD;
uiendiation, " lie wIho conerteth a sinner from&#xD;
the error of his wa,  hali rave a sul from&#xD;
death, and cover a multitude of ins."&#xD;
&#xD;
:4&#xD;
&#xD;
.a&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
 &#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD; &#xD;
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
