<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8397">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Gem of the Lake </title>
            <author >Wright, Sarah A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC8397</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The gem of the lake</title>
                  <author >Wright, Sarah A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >vi 3-60 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >American News</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1868">1868</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-10-20">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The gem of the lake</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8397-00000001"/>THE   A NOVEL,   BY  MRS. SARAH A WRIGHT:    AUTHOR OF "MEDORA," "BEAUTY OF FAIRFAX," "MPROPER USE OF THE TONGUE," ETC., ETC.   O, Love, thy flashing, thrilling flame, Affects the wisest head, And oft times levels in the dust, The living with the dead. For, like a flash of lightning, thy Electric smiles entrance, Till hopes are withered in the soul, And sorrow doth enhance.   NEW YORK:  AMYERICAN NEWS COMPANY,  Nos. 119 &amp; 121 NASSAU STREET. 1868  &#xD;<pb n="0-iii" xml:id="VAC8397-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1868, by MRS. SARAH A. WRIGHT, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York.   O, PEFACE.   A THE public are always curious to know something of the history and origin of a work of, fiction, especially when it professes to be founded onl fact. To gratify this natural desire, we may state that the present work, THE GEM OF THE LYaE, is founded on incidents furnished by a legal gentleman who resided near the scene of he story. He stated at the time that he was a married man, and had four little daughters, and if the story should be written he would like his children to read it, hoping it might have a good effect on the fe- male mind.  We know that woman is .the "weaker vessel;" there- fore, the stronger sex should not .abuse and decoy her away from the strict paths of virtue. Man was created to love and protect the being who was given him in the garden of Eden. The Great Power, who brought all things into existence, never made " the help-meet of Adam" to be tortured.  Eve was placed by the side of the lordly son of God to cheer and comfort him    through the vicissitudes of life. At that time man possessed the genuine spark of affection or love, congeniality or affinity, or whatever term we might use. Adam must have loved the woman the Lord had given him, or she never could have persuaded him to have eaten of the forbidden fruit.  But it seems, in the Nineteenth Century, woman has lost much of her powe,; as, perhaps, the reader may see by perusing the GEM OF THE LAKE. There is a great deal of misery arising from inconstant lovers and husbands of this age, but we would not say for A moment that women are infallible, neither would we state that-they are never to blame when the dark clouds of misfortune hover around them, yet we know that it is too often the case that men, after entangling them in'rthe ;    iii k * *   &#xD;<pb n="iv-v" xml:id="VAC8397-00000003"/> iv             PREFAOE.            i fatal web which is termed love, have destroyed the very being whom they have professed to worship. True love never injures its object, and when a man would lead a girl on to ruin, she may rest assured that he does not love her. The heavenly flame, the word love, should never be applied in such cases. This the readers of our story may perhaps discover ere they -finish the perusal of it. The heroine of our story was the eldest daughter of a practitioner at the bar, in one of our States, which it is not necessary to name. She was a beautiful blbnde, with blue languishing eyes, light hair, a small mouth, a little dimple in the chin, and always looked as happy and was as mirthful as the little lamb that skipped upon! the plain. And not only beautiful was this sweet girl, but intel- lectual and amiable, and always relieving and pitying the misfortunes of the poor; yet fate, fate! how cruel are thy mandates, and how often they fall upon the most' confiding of our sex. The father of Eleanor resided near the capital of the State, and lit was there amid the beautiful shrubbery in 'the silent valley, where nothing was heard but the warbling songster of the grove as it flitted from tree to tree, and the little busy bee that buzzed among the flow- ers, that the sacred vows of love were pledged and there the fatal step was taken. We have stated that our story is founded on fact; we again reiter- ate the sad tale. The hero of this story, Egbert, was a minister, and a first cousin of the heroine. He was handsome, talented, and just the man to captivate the heart of a young and innocent girl.  His pa- rents had omitted the advice of King Solomon: "Train up a child in the way he should go, and .when he is old he will not depart from  it." '  Perhaps some very nice, scrupulous, sensitive mind, may be shocked at many little expressions connected with our story; but, if they should take offence, we trust they will excuse us for trespassing, as our inten- tion is pure in bringing this work before the public, hoping it may have a good effect on theyoung and innocent maid who is unsophis- ticated in the arts and wiles of men. Our gentlemen readers njust not think for a moment that we would infer that there are no good men; far be it from us -to assert anything so incorrect, for we know to the contrary.  There are hundreds and thousands of noble souls, whose              ,          *   PREFACE.              V pure spirits would never permit them to infringe upon the laws of God or the rights of woman. Yet there are too few who place woman upon the pinnacle where she should be. We also hope that every doting mother and iond father may remember the story of Eleanor Cropper. She was once as fair and unsullied as/their Own little daugh- ter, with bright eyes, and flowing curls falling over her alabaster shoul- ders, who, while gazing sweetly into their faces, lisps the name of mamma and papa. But, alas! thorns may be growing in the path of their beautiful child, as was previously the case in the life of our heroine. Let us follow her, from the day of her birth through the happy days of courtship, then on--on- ion, and see where the evil, decoying spirit of Egbert, her cousin, leads her, and how the lives of the hero and heroine end. We have not written a long and tedious story; therefore, to read this tale will not embrace much time. We have been brief, trying to pen it in language that every person may understand. The different characters in our story are portrayed as accurately at our power enabled us, and as they acted on the stage of life. Clara Seward, afterwards the good Mrs. Dr. Holland, was worthy of all that has been said of her. She was in girlhood a school-mate of Eleanor, and by mere accident met her in after years in the most mis- erable condition. Sarah Jacobs, the woman in red and white, who kept a boarding-house in the city, was one whose character can better be imagined than described after the reader has perused the book. The father and mother of our heroine were pure-minded, good, re- ligious people, whose hearts were so far from evil that they could not suspect others of committing crime. Thus it was that the serpent-de- stroyer was permitted to entwine itself around the heart of the innocent girl before her devoted parents suspected wrong. The beautiful Julia, the incensed avenging wife, may, perhaps, be blamed by many for the course which she pursued, but she was not so much depraved as she might have been, for she lived a true woman with the little doctor, who married her as soon as the report was put forth that Egbert was dead. The poor Irish woman, Mrs. Gallagher, differed from many of her coun- try people, for instead of torturing and inflicting pain upon others, she pitied and aided the sufferer when she 6ame to her door. Time heals' i^ many wounds which have been probed to the quick. This, perhapsi, may be the case with many characters we have introduced in our work.  &#xD;<pb n="vi-3" xml:id="VAC8397-00000004"/> Vi             PREFACE. After a storm there is generally a calm; and although the horizon is darkened and the tempest rages, and we almost imagine that the foun- dations of earth are shaken, yet in a short time the beautiful sunlight bursts upon our vision, and Nature once more re-animates our souls. Thus it is in real life; when we have passed through many storms and shed many tears of bitter repentance, hope again sits upon its throne, the troubled scenes of life become tranquil, and our lives pass gen- tly on as the rippling waves upon the -summer sea. Our readers will, no doubt, detect the paste and appreciate the diamond ere they close our story.   T-H 8] GEM OF TH :'LA KE.   CHAPTER I.   THERE dwelt, some twenty years' ago, on Lake Michigan, two brothers who, having lost their parents at an early age, were, from their orphaned condition, warmly attached to each other. "Lord of themselves, that heritage of woe," happily, was not their sole legacy. A moderate competence, properly cared for by conscientious guardians, and judi- ciously invested when the steady and-in- dustrious young men became their own masters, in the course of a brief period resulted in the acquisition of handsome fortunes. Deprived from childhood of domestic ties, each early sought a partner with whom to travel through this "vale of tears." Here again a lucky star prevail- ed, and it would seem as though Nature had been in a most genial mood when she formed the fate of the orphans. An easy fortune, excellent health, together with the best of wives, combined to fill the cup of happiness to the brim: there seemed not- even reason or room for a rose-leaf to float upon the surface of the overflowing vase. Eden, in its pristine beauty and innocence, had come again. A Miss Dorson, of Ohio, early consented to exchange her maiden gladness For a name, and for -a ring," the name and ring having been bestowed upon the blushing recipient by Charles Cropper; whilst a certain Miss Toliver, of his native State, did hot hesitate to render Theodore equally happy.   And now, indeed, the sun of their pros- perity and happiness seemed without a spot. And thus would it oftener be on this terrestrial ball were hearts and hands always joined in the holy bonds of matri- mony. Alas I too frequently are false vows on the lips of those who stand to- gether before the altar; too frequently indifference, and worse than indifference, is in their coward hearts. Diamonds out- weigh hearts in the matrimonial mart. The most powerful passion known to the human heart is love. Ambition is mighty, avarice is strong, revenge is deepr and bitter, but love is omnipotent I What laid in ashes ancient Troy? What caus- ed king Ahasuerus to spare the Jews? "What lost the world Marc Antony?" 7 Woman-and woman is but another name for love; at least it ought to be. "Ah I listen, love, I read to-day A sweet conceit of my own name-- How in the language of Malay Woman and flowers mean the same." But to return to the picture of sweet domestic happiness which induced this digressive paragraph, and which, never- theless, was enjoyed by the two brothers for many invaluable years. Lake Michi-' gan, with all its rural scenery, was a para- dise to those young husbands. But, alas I man -is born to trouble as the sparks fly, upward. There can be no real, uninterrupted happiness that hath its root on earth, otherwise it would not be earth, but heaven below. The Peri gained Paradise but by the passport of a mortal's tear I 88  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC8397-00000005"/> Charles Cropper having been admitted to the bar became quite an eminent prac- titioner, and steadily increased his for- tune; whilst his broter Theodore was quite as successful as a western planter. As previously observed, some years of almost perfect domestic felicity, "- --- that only bliss Of Paradise that hath survived the fall," fell-to the lot of the brothers. In due course of time two rose-buds were added to the- parent stem and filled the cup of joy. A blooming son and' daughter came to perfect the family pic- ture. Great were their rejoicings. To Theodore was born an heir, to Charles a fair little heiress. The grateful happi- ness awakened by this last greatest boon in the hearts of the young parents was a fair type of the joy'of Sarah and Abra- ham. of old. Ah, could these parents have lifted the curtain and looked forward but fifteen years! Well, indeed, for us is it that the future is always veiled. Our hero is yet a small boy, a bright- eyed lad whose name is Egbert. An only child, his mother, once the beautiful Laura Toliver, sees in him no imperfec- tion. A good, sensible woman in every other respect, she is blind to the faults of her son. Indulgences are lavished upon the youth; nothing is denied him. The advice of King Solomon was un- heeded by the doting mother to whose guidance the boy was almost entirely left. Several bright summers had passed over Eleanor's head before her little sis- ter Emelia was born.   Charles Cropper, naturally disappointed in not having had an heir, was yet proud and fond of his fair little daughters, and Eleanor's rosy lips oftened challenged kisses from her handsome   cousin Egbert, which, however, were never gained until after a wild romp. There never lived on the beautiful lake two friends who dwelt in greater harmony than these children. In-   timate from childhood, yet they were to be separated whilst quite young.  A promising business opening induced the senior brother to remove to Pennsylva-. nia, in which State he was soon estab- lished as a fourishing and influential member of the bar. - Nothing marred his happiness but the necessary separation from Theodore. Scarcely, ever in their lives had a day passed without some in- tercourse occurring between them. Mar- riage, though it too often does, had not made any difference in this daily com- munion. They still loved each other as fondly as when, years before, they cried themselves to sleep in each other's arms. Deep as often is the friendship between man and man, the affection of these brothers was more than usually sincere,' for Charles' happiness was far from com- plete thus separated from Theodore; and when year after year brought no adequate consolation, he wrote to his brother, hold- ing out every inducement to come and reside and test his fortune in Pennsyl- vania. Theodore, to whom the unwonted sep- aration had been equally painful, after due deliberation and conjugal consulta- tion, concluded to follow in the wake of his brother Charles. Accordingly a fine plantation, situated about five miles from the seat of government, was purchased, and thither Mr. Theodore Cropper and family removed. Vain are words to adequately describe the meeting of the long separated broth- ers. In the language of Scripture, " they fell upon each other's neck and wept." How much there was to see, to heaffand to tell. Since the families had met years ,had passed, bringing many changes. The children, who when separated were quite young, were now nearly grown. Egbert had been for some time a student of theology, and was about to graduate, and his fond parents hoped to witness his ordination. They were all members of the Protestant Episcopal denomina- tion, which they were so fond of calling the "Established Church."   Young Egbert was looked upon as a pattern of piety. The indulged boy had to all outward appearances changed into the studious and religious youth. Hand- some in appearance, and prepossessing in manner, he seemed already to have ac- quired an art apparently essential to a graceful young divine. At the advent of this spotless young canonist, there could not be found in the vicinity two buds of fairer promise than his cousins Eleanor and Emelia Crop- per. The eldest, aged fifteen, who had far out-stripped her years; was already an acknowledged belle, whilst Emelia, quite as prematurely developed as her sister, promised fair to follow fast in her footsteps. Nothing except the care be- stowed upon their moral culture could exceed the pains taken in the education of these two idolized girls. , As a matter of course, the families were on terms of the closest intimacy. Young Egbert was considered by his fair cousins a paragon of perfection. Adolescent, ar- dent, innocent of guile, they believed him to be all he so evidently appeared. Nor were they the sole worshipers at the feet of the young priest. Many a beating heart bowed before this shrine it would seem of more than earthly perfection. This theological student divided his time and attention between his library and the frequent resort to the fashionable residence of his uncle. The cousins were never but a few hours at a time deprived of each other's society. They rode to- gether, walked together, and sang to- gether, "- --- and love Hath no interpreter like song." Daylight, moonlight, starlight, all alike looked upon these interviews. To the parents this intimacy was a source of the purest delight; and to have suggested that this unrestrained intercourse was in- discreet, would have been to make them, open their eyes in amazement. Never a thought of marriage had entered their minds, or troubled their hearts. But neighboring gossips had found a subject,   an inexhaustible subject for discussion, and not the slowest among the busy tongues were those of the young ladies who had been overlooked by the young candidate for orders in favor of his irre- sistible cousins. Of course those most interested in these flying rumors were the last to hear of them. The neighbors were expecting a gay wedding. * Clara Seward, Eleanor's most intimate friend and schoolmate, at last heroically determined to venture a word to Elea- nor's mother. "A word to- the wise is sufficient," she whispered to her trem- bling but faithful heart. That heart sank a little at the reception her intelligence met. The happy, unsuspicious mother laugh- ingly replied, "Oh, my gentle, affection- ate, mistaken Clara! your faithful little heart has been uselessly troubling itself. Egbert and my children have been inti- mate from childhood, and during their separation have constantly corresponded. That Eleanor and Egbert should'Bver feel for each other more than a cousinly at- tachment 'is impossible.   If either Mr. Cropper or myself suspected such a con- tingency, we should at once put a stop to this intimacy. Anything but this inter- marriage of relations-of- cousins 1" and the mother held up her hands in aston- ishment. Miss Seward had introduced the sub- ject with great finesse, very distantly alluding to the on dits in circulation. "Forgive me, my dear Madam,for hav- ing presumed thus to interfere," cone ' tinued Miss Seward, "Eleanor is veryt' dear to me," and simultaneously tears started to her gentle blue eyes. "All that concerns her, even remotely, is of importance to me; I greatly fear, dear Mrs. Cropper, that she is becoming too much interested in that handsome young clergyman, and," with hesitancy, " evena ministers, you know, are not invulner- able." "Nonsense, Clara," interruptedthe mo- ther, "why you forget yoirself; Eleanor is but a child 1"  4.&amp;^s  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC8397-00000006"/> "In years, I grant you, Madam; but not in stature. Even you will allow that in altitude she is fully a woman, and, to my belief, her heart has grown with her growth." "Well, Clara, what would you have?" rather pettishy said Mrs. Cropper, never much accustomed to argument at any time. "The poor child cannot help her j growth, can she?" "Alas I no, nor her beauty!" replied the youthful sage. A moment her pretty cheek rested upon her hand, then looking up she said, coaxingly, "I am about visit- ing Richmond, Mrs. Cropper, and the delight I anticipate in meeting my rela- tives, and in the enjoyment of -that city, is only dampened by the coming separa- tion from my beloved Eleanor. Will you not lend her to me for a little while? Permit her to accompany me; oh I do, if you please. I do not intend to be long absent; a few weeks, at farthest, will see her returned to your arms, and a brief absence from this place may be more im- portant than either of us dare dream." And in her eagerness the speaker clasped her hand fervently. "A pretty statue of Persuasion, truly," uttered a deep, musical, and, at the same moment, sarcastic voice. "Why, Miss   Seward, where did you study attitudes? Your posp, so comme il fant, certainly betrays practice."          \ Miss Seward started violently, and turn- ing, confronted the speaker, a tall, elegant young man. Their looks met, and for a moment Egbert looked full into her un- shrinking eyes. From this mutual re- connoitre each deduced silent conclu- sions. Clara Seward read in his counte- nance that shed beheld an enemy. To Egbert Cropper it became patent that he was known; that this innocent girll had rightly construed him. And to this correct conclusion had Clara been led rather by a fine instinct than by her reasoning powers. She did not stop to ask herself how she came to know that the' seemingly irreproachable canonist was other than he appeared to be. Yet Clara had a strong and determined will with which to cope. "I will it!" with these words, and a quiet, unreadable smile had Egbert been wont to bear down all opposition. Great power to work one's will is some- times given, power to a degree jtlhat 7 astonishes us. But the Almighty tries His creatures to see how far they will go, either for good or bad, for woe or weal. His power is over all. )   CHAPTER II.   IT was evident to Clara that the young student had overheard her last remark. Nothing daunted she was about to reply when two other persons entered the room. A richer color mounted to the blooming cheek of one of the intruders, as she met the glance of Egbert Cropper. - The gamboge face of the other seemed of too permanent a cast ever to deepen under any circumstances; and yet its yellow became almost green in the vio- 'lent contrast it offered to a little bright blue bonnet. "Well met, friends; well met i " said this creature in a high falset- to voice, and performing innumerable   little bobbing curtsies. "Why, Mr. Crop- per I " pretending to have perceived him for the first time, although her little gray eyes had espied him before she had fair- ly entered the room. "And pretty Miss Clara Seward!" holding up her hands. "Here is an encounter I Who would have thought of it? quite a little party, to be sure. I met my charming friend Eleanor, who insisted upon my accom- panying her home; delighted, of course. "And how are you Mrs. Cropper? and you, Miss Clara "Mrs. Cropper was speak- ing in , low voice to Eleanor, so Clara re- plied:   "In excellent health, as I hope we see Miss Grey," said Clara kindly, while the faces of Egbert and even Mrs. Cropper were lighted with satirical mirth. "And how blooming our lovely Elea- nor is looking l" the little visitor went on, quite disregarding the hope expressed concerning her own sanitary conditiona "Eleanor certainly exhibits an unusual- ly brilliant complexion," observed Miss Seward. All eyes turned upon Eleanor, which of course did not tend to create pallor- all eyes excepting those of Egbert; his were turned away. "Is Eleanor not well? i She certainly has the appearance of per- ; feet health," said Miss Grey, seemingly struck by te tone in which Miss Seward had uttered this simple remark. "I am   very well indeed, Madam," stammered the blushing and embarrassed Eleanor, following Clara who had retreat- ed to a distant bay-window. "What do you mean, Clara?" with averted eyes said Eleanor to her friend when they were at a safe distance from the others. "Your words are simple   ] enough, but your manner is so strange. I am very well, I assuire you." . "Physically, perhaps you are; but for- give me, Eleanor, if I remark that your spirits are not what they once were: they vary too much to denote peace of mind. You are at times wildly happy,  and then in a moment too sad. An ex- pression of melancholy, altogether unusual n and unnatural for one so young, now too 1 often pervades your countenance. Some- E thing weighs upon your mindI am  con- e: vinced. What is it Eleanor, my- dear friend; what can it be? Confide in me; have you not ever found me true?"   r "True  as truth itself!" murmured d Eleanor,  struggling  with  her tears. h "But you are mistaken; nothing troubles st me.   Why, what cause can I have for a sadness?  Your friendship renders you w over-anxious, Clara."         a Miss Seward's clear eyes intently read lI the face of her friend.  What she saw w there seemed to pain her, for she sighed tl   e as she said, "Dear Eleanor, you are not e entirely frank with me. But I have not. r told you the motive that brought me here this morning." Here the girl started, - quite unnecessarily as Miss Seward- t thought. "I wish you would go with " I me to Richmond, Eleanor." The girl opened her languishing eyes. - Miss Seward had a persuasive tongue, and after half an  hour's conversation Eleanor promised    to accompany her friend, if possible, and would give a de-  cisive reply in the course of the day. They turned away from the window, and again Miss Seward encountered the dark eyes of Egbert; they seemed to say, * IYou are playing against me. 'Tis of no use; the trump card is in my hand." 'Decidedly profane language for the eyes of a student of divinity I Ere they separated Miss Grey repeated these lines, although it is doubtful if even she understood the full amount of application contained therein: "When the belle of fifteen gets sight of a beau, She scarcely can peep thro' the sticks of her Ihn; Her heart all a-flutter, her cheeks all a-glow,  She tremblingly simpers out-- Who is the?an ' "Sweet twenty has brought her to years of discre- tion; She blushes no longer, but alters her plan: She thinks of the pocket, the place, the profession, And looks round the circle with-' What is the man? '" "I will spare you the rest," says Miss Grey, dropping    curtsies, and  as she  makes her elaborate adieux the comprel hensive looks that she cast upon Miss Seward, Eleanor and the young student, expressed volumes indeed. It was night, dark and stormy. The roads and pathway had been long since deserted, save by the poor traveller who: hastened  homeward   with- quickening.  step.  In the window of a large mansion a light was gleaming. The draperies were turned aside, and disclosed within a spacious apartment adorned with every luxury  that taste could call for, and: wealth furnish.   Seated at this window, though the hour was midnight, might  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC8397-00000007"/> be seen a fair young creature of, perhaps, eighteen summers. She seemed to be in deep thought, and her jeweled fingers were nervously locked together. Dark auburn curls fell in graceful confusion over a faced beautiful and sad as Desde- mona's in her woe-worn moments. An- other hour passed; still the beautiful statue moved not. The clock struck three. At the sound she started quickly, glanced hurriedly around, while a death- like pallor overspread her features. "O God, must I in this moment de- cideJ "Starting up, she rapidly paced the floor and exclaimed: "Oh, my dear parents, forgive an erring child I Let these lips speak but one word and I am happy.  But no,-- no; they may never again behold me. I have 'vowed a vow, and must perform that to which I am sworn I "          , At that instant .a low tap was heard at the window, and immediately the door leading from the balcony opened to ad- mit a young man. Exceedingly hand- some, manly in appearance, and dignified in his mien, he seemed just the man to captivate the senses of an inexperienced young girl, and, alas, such was she whom he came to seek. His mesmeric eyes spoke a deeper language than his tongue could utter-language that far sooner Reached the heart. But when he spoke bis voice stirred the depths of her inner- most soul. "Come, Ella, are you in readi- ness r" Eleanor hid her face in her hands. He was silent a moment. When he spoke again, a touch. of impatience betrayed itself in his tones. "Your father, your father," said he," might awake. Then all will be over. He has said that he will never consent to our marriage. But I will out-wit him," muttered he in an undertone. "Why Eleanbr, my darling, I hadhoped to see you ready and waiting." A A choking sob was his only answer. He put his arm about her; She stepped backward as if she could not go. "' My father I sheA whispered again. "-What  my sweet angel, weeping!   Dry your bright eyes, and come to the arms of one who loves you better than life. Come, my love; the carriage waits at the foot of the hill. Your parents are dear to you, but, my sweet one, is not Egbert dearer still?" Eleanor moved not; she could not move. He was silent for a moment, and gazed earnestly upon her. Was his bet- ter angel pleading with him?   The weeper made a slight movement 'mid her sobs; the motion threw back her heavy sleeve and -revealed an arm exquisitely beautiful and white. A light shot up into those eyes, and fixed itself upon her; she saw it not, poor girl, her face was covered with her hands. In a voice whose melody might have won an angel, he murmured: "Eleanor, my Eleanor; my own and only love, do you cancel your promise; do you refuse to go with Egbert? ," "No, no, no;" she said, sinking into the arms open to receive her.  "This sorrow, these tears are for my parents; my sister, my father, my mother, this will break their hearts. They have forbidden our union." "It will soon be over," said Egbert,. softly. "We will then return.  They love you too much to remain unforgiv- ing."- And soothing, wooing, caressing, Egbert soon put everybody but himself out of Eleanor's mind. Amid a shower  of soft kisses he tied on her bonnet and arranged her shawl. Over one arm he took her portmanteau, and with the other about her waist, giving her no more time to think, he bore her rapidly on. Down  the winding stairs, down the well-known L hillside path, she was fleetly borne by his [ strong arm. 'In an instant-it seemed [ but an instant-she was'seated in the 1 carriage with her cousin and lover by her I side. Wildly throbbed Eleanor's heart, , though it beat against the-heart of Eg- bert Cropper, though his bewildering i. voice was breathing in her ear vows of y ardent love and unceasing tenderness; trembling, weeping, speechless, she only ! clung closer to him.   They were travelling at a most rapid rate, yet Egbert called to the driver to hasten his speed. The fair face lying on his bosom was still moistened with tears. The struggle between love and duty had been violent: love had conquered, and weak and helpless she lay in the arms of the victor. As is too often the case with women, love had overcome her- better judgment. One inconsistent course had been taken, and now, she thought, there is nothing for it-but to go onward-on- ward.   Oh, simple, weak-minded wo- man, take warning! Trust not to man's honor! Where there is one who will per- form all that he so ardently promises, there are thousands who swear but to perjure themselves. "The humblest lover when he lowliest lies, But stoops to conquer, and but kneels to rise." Eleanor wept, but Egbert kissed the tears from her cheeks, and begged her to compose herself for his sake, whispering that in a few hours more .they would be safe from detection. She sighed and smiled in one breath, and resigned her- self to coming events. "My sweet little dove, have I not promised everything, and will I not perform? Do you, can you, doubt my sincerity?" "No, no, no; I do ,not, I could not; it would kill me to doubt you!"  Then, after, a pause, "Egbert, you are all to me now. I have fled from my father's house." "My sweet girl, be not thus troubled. If I fail to perform my promises may the powers of darkness overshadow my life, and may the gates of Heaven be forever barred against my immortal soul I " Eleanor shuddered. Infatuated girl I why did not her soul shrink from the man of God who dared to make use of such blasphemous language?"Do you still doubt me, Eleanor?"- whispered that persuasive voice.            1 "Ah, no 1" answeringly murmured the i trembling girl.             } ) "We will be so happy, my own love." Travelling. with such rapidity, sunrise 1 found them many miles from home. They   I had taken a direction least 1ikely to he D followed. They topped to change horses, I and breakfast was. ordered at4 the quiet hotel. Morning, the serene and beautiful [ morning, somewhat cheered the drooping l spirits of the innocent and too confiding maiden. Having been conducted into-a private parlor, she sank exhausted upon the sofa, and, while Egbert absented him-  self to give some orders, fell into a troub- led slumber. She dreamed that they had been successfully pursued by her father, who had carried her back home. That Egbert had drawn a pistol upon her aged parent; that she had frantically inter- ceded, and the weapon fell from his hand; that her father became so much enraged he even endeavored to kill his own childi In her fright she awoke trembling and in tears. Beside her stood Egbert, be- wildered and alarmed. She exclaimed, "What has happened?" "Nothing, my love," replied Egbert, in . a soothing voice. "I have been watch- ing your awakening; you have beein troubled in your sleep, my own. Break- fast is in readiness; come, dear, we Will refresh ourselves, and then proceed on our journey." "Oh, Egbert!" answered the still frightened and trembling girl, "I have had a dreadful dream. Something fear- ful is, about to befall us." !"My little trembler!" said that voice so potent to soothe, "you must not per- mit yourself to be troubled by mere dreams. The days when Joseph dreamed of the sheaves are passed away. But tell me, my own, what frightened you so much; you started and murmured and even wept in your sleep, and I was just about to awaken you."    - "I dreamed," said Eleanor, "that we were pursued by my father, and that you endeavored to shoot him," and looking up tearfully into his face, she met a smil- ing glance in return. "Egbert," %he said, hesitatingly, "nothing, no provocation, would tempt-you to that," and she Rem- bled at what she had said. .      - Egbert Cropper permitted a few mo- . * b               i,* t  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8397-00000008"/> ments to pass in silence before he replied; then kissing her, said: "My little self- tormentor, you have nothing to fear. Come, let us to breakfast;" and they left the room. Unquiet were the lines of Eleanor's face. Regard of Egbert, mingled strong- ly with her love for him,-and attach- ment forced her to endeavor to partake of the meal which had become distaste- ful. Struggling to suppress her agita- tion, she became outwardly calm. Na- ture partook not of the secret gloom which pervaded the heart of Eleanor. The morning was clear and unclouded. The heavens were never more resplendent than on the day Eleanor and Egbert Crop- peleft the hotel and started for Cape B   May. He thought that at that fashion- able resort they might remain unnoticed amid the crowd. Still wearing the garb of his holy office, the Rev. Egbert Crop- per gave more to carry out his designs than did Crcesus to secure the exalted opinion of the Romans. He gave only money and time'; but the minister gave character, integrity and conscience--all were thrown into the scales; It was not long before our heroine and Egbert found themselves at the fash- ionable watering-place, amid -crowds of gay and thoughtless beings--gay and thoughtless, apparently, but who dare say what thoughts agitated their bosoms, what untold griefs were hidden under the joyous laughter and the merry jest?   CHAPTER III.   WHEN Eleanor was first missed from home, her unsuspecting parents imagined that she had gone on a visit to a nearO ,neighbor, at whose house she was in the habit of making frequent and unpremed- itated sojourns. But when an unusual time elapsed without her having returned to them, or reported the reason of her continued absence, they sent to inquire. Alas they had seen or heard nothing concerning the missing girl I Miss Seward, having returned from Richmond, was now on a visit at the resi- dence of Mr. Cropper. More enlightened on the subject of certain rumors than were the unsuspecting parents, like a rev- elation it flashed upon her mind the ex- planatibn of Eleanor's strange absence. In the most delicate manner she sug- gested the propriety of inquiring con- cerning the present whereabouts of Mr. Egbert Cropper. Accordingly, a messen- ger was sent to his residence. He was not at home; his parents supposed him to be at his uncle's. Consternation reign- ed supreme in every heart. What strange thing was about to be revealed I Slowly the conviction forced itself upon their   minds that the two had eloped. The grief of the respective parents can be kbetter imagined than depicted; no pen is adequate to the tasl of such a descrip- tion. It were simplyfan impossibility to describe the anguish of these parents. But the first care was to keep all, quiet; in this case publicity would be additional disgrace. The heart that is obliged to smother grief suffers more than one which is free to give full vent to its ebullitions of sorrow. But the father of Eleanor was a keen lawyer, and well knew how to de- tect and punish villany even in a nephew. XWe will, for a season, leave this suffer- ing family, and return to Egbert. Elea- . nor was surrounded with all that money and love (?) could give her. Rides, drives, the invigorating sea-breezes and bathing were for one short day enjoy- able; but a melancholy, tender and sweet smile prevailed and sat upon her counte- nance. She became more cheerful, firmly believing that they would be soon mfr- ried, and that she would be restored to her parents. Her fears, which in her in- nocent heart had never taken any defined form, were lulled by subtle arguments,   and with the confidence of a loving wo- man she believed and loved on. Oh, woman I woman! inconsiderate, blind, confidingI Man shows but the cowardice of his heart when he deceives a woman. If he were a brave warrior he need not practice deception at all. He is certainly able to fight the battle of love with the sword of truth. Then, if they gain the field by honorable means, they are saved from that terrible scourge- self-reproach.  And virtuous, virtuous women-have been brought to destruction by the machinations of love. He whom we left in the enjoyment of all Cape May afforded, dreamed not that his uncle was so near at hand. But ah, instantly came an inundation which almost swept away the foundation of hope. Fast, fast was approaching the avenging father of his innocent child.   Mr. Cropper, the father of Eleanor, pursued the footsteps of his daughter. But a brief period had elapsed after their arrival at Cape May, when Eleanor was sure that she. heard the voice of her father in the hall. " Where is she? Is this the room?" said an agitated voice near her door. "Oh! Egbert, Egbert I 't is the voice of my father I What will become of me? Whither shall I fly?" She sank into a chair; a chill suddenly benumbed her whole being.    She was alone, and the door was locked. Egbert 1 was absent from  her side. A loud rap ( repeated upon the door, and the distinct ( tones of her father's voice recalled the i scattered senses of the almost distracted t girl. Regaining her feet she tottered ' across the room  and opened the door. i "Father, father, forgive, forgive I " she I cried, amid hysterical sobs, and endeav- oring to throw herself into his arms. He c repelled her embrace, but she was unable r to stand unsupported, and he placed her d upon the sofa.  Silently and sternly he e regarded her. "Prepare to return with  p me," he exclaimed, with sternness.   c he was only answered by heart-break- v ing sobs. Th6 eyes of the father filled t: with tears as he looked upon the shrink- s   - ing form before him, but he dashed his hands before his eyes, and struggled to , suppress all signs of emotions. "I find ? you alone," he said, in a voice so cold tand stern that Eleanor could scarce be- , lieve it to be the voice of her father. "I l find you alone. How is this? Where is the man who stole you from me? Has he, after his kind, already forsaken you? Where is he? Let me have his blood." She sprang up with extended arms; she shrieked "Father, father, injure him not. I will return with you; I have dis- obeyed you; in that alone am I Iguilty. Oh! father, forgive your erring child:" and as she uttered these words, her head fell upon her bosom, and the hot blood rushed over her neck and face. "Do the angels blush to own their pu- rity?" solemnly said the old man. - "Father, dear father!" in an awe: stricken whisper she said, "I have spoken the truth." Gazing upon her, he could not but be- lieve in her innocency. And she was innocent: but, alas, she owed her esaape to Egbert's feeling of security, not to his sense of honor. He -believed her to be entirely in his power. A few hours had, however, somewhat opened the eyes of the innocent Eleanor. Without an in- stant of hesitation she prepared to ac- company her father home. Tying on her bonnet, she was hurried weepingly out of, the room. At that moment Egbert entered the hall. Seizing the arm of his uncle, he threw himself against the wall, and forbade the departure of Eleanor, "This day she is to be my wife," he said, in a voice that trembled with suppressedt passion and disappointment. "You villain; you execrable villain!" cried the old man.  "Do youdare forbid me to take my child? Marry her, in- deed; you scoundyel Had you intend- ed honorable marriage would you have permitted all this time to elapse, you petty coward?   Thank God she is not your wife; and while there is breath left in this body, aged as it is, your wife she shall never become.  The son of my M   &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8397-00000009"/> brother, and a minister of the Gospel as you are, I had rather behold my daughter dead at my feet, than wedded to a scoun- drel such as you. You too well knew that my consent would never be given to the union, and for revenge you have sto- len her away." So saying, he attempted to drag Eleanor away. Egbert seized the girl in his powerful grasp. In an instant her father drew a pistol from his breast, and leveled it-at the clerical nephew. Quick as lightning Eleanor dashed the weapon from his hand, and it exploded as it fell. Egbert was unarmed, having left his pistols in his room; that room was near at hand, and into it he dashed for the weapons, determined to kill his uncle, and secure Eleanor at all hazards. But the noise of the exploded pistol, and loud talking, had attracted a crowd. The gentlemen protected Mr. Cropper's retreat to his carriage, and in another moment Eleanor and her father were rapidly driven away. Brief time elapsed before Mr. Charles Cropper bore his almost fainting daugh- ter across the portals of her lately desert- ed home. The scene that occurred when Eleanor met her mother and sister will not be here related. We will let the cur- tain fall upon the anguish of a devoted and Christian mother. What has the unfeeling world to do with such a scene? Those whose ready hearts can sympa- thise with sorrow such as this, can, with- out description, let fall: the pitying tear. The mother pressed her prodigal child to her heart, guilty as she had imagined her to be. But that faithful maternal heart was soon relieved of a portion of its burden. The reader may wonder at the salva- tion of Eleanor. Slowly, and, as he thought, securely had Egbert worked his plan to gain his beautiful and accom- plshed cousin. But the end was not yet. Poor, deluded girl I Ah, love, love, the elixir and tie poison of life I the passion that has caused its thousands to fall; the passion that occasioned the blindness of Samson. Delilah, Delilah, thou treach-   erous woman, thou hast left thy effect even upon this remote generation I When woman loves "Not wisely, but too well," what but dire consequences can follow? Woman should ever let reason govern her feelings. Pride, principle, self-respect, self-government should teach the sex to spurn as a deadly viper the man who would break -his first marital promise. But it is difficult to convince women of man's treachery. Women are apt to be very credulous when he whom they love vows the vows of constancy, and swears oaths of eternal allegiance. But, oh, had they a magnifying glass which would enable them to view the heart of these. false individuals. Oh, what did the vain and deceived Olivia sing? "When lovely woman stoops to folly, And finds too late that men betray, What charm can soothe her melancholy? What art can wash her guilt away? "The only art her guilt to cover, To hide her shame from every eye, To give repentance to her lover, And wring his bosom-is to die 1" We will inquire what has become of the lover? Eleanor had escaped him. He could not believe it. Was it for this that he had so long and so patiently waited? He dashed the loaded pistol from his hand. "I am undone I -All is over; and not a sign of success," he mut- tered between his closed teeth. Curses "not loud but deep" rankled in his heart. He gazed wistfully around the deserted room which but a little while before had contained the form of his fair cousin. She was now beyond his reach, and he had thought her so secure.  "I was a fool [!" he muttered. He threw himself upon the sofa and buried his hot face in his hands. Where, oh, where was the cooing dove whose soft fingers had but lttely caressed his burning temples? "Beyond your reach," said a voice in his heart; and he cursed that voice. He re- called her beauty, her grace, her tender- ness. He heard again her gentle voice, murmuring, "Egbert, will you always   love me? always care for and protect me?"And now, madness I she bad left him forever I In these moments of excitement Egbert fancied that he really loved his cousin. But he was incapable of feeling sincere and lasting affection for any woman. His was a temperament that would have wearied of the most charming, the most perfect woman that ever lived. Neither a Helen, a Cleopatra, nor a Catharine de Medici could long have chained him to her side. The reader wig find him just what we have described. Now that she is gone he fancies that he loves her. For an hour or more he lay motionless upon the sofa. At the end of that time he arose once more a resolute man; determined not to be defeated, but to conquer. Were men but as courageous in war, as are some when they are bent upon carrying their own selfish views into effect, how many battles would be won The hero of this tale would have made a brave general during the late war, and had much better have been fighting for his country than engaged in ruining the peace of his un- cle's family, and sealing his own fate with destruction. The pleasures of Cape May were lost upon him. At that place' he remained but a few days after he had lost his cousin. Then he left for the West. But in the meantime he met a zwoman in ohite; frequent and secret were their interviews; earnest and con- fidential were their conversations, whose subjeet never changed, and that subject was Eleanor: ah! ill-fated Eleanor I The tin that bore him away from Cape lIay, took him "westward, ho!" In that broad country he found abum- dance of room to brood over his dis- appointment, and perfect his future schemes.' After an absence of some months he returned to his father's house; guilty in his heart, but the boldness of innocence on: his brow. To the numer- ous questions of his parents he returned strange replies. "He had only taken Eleanor over to the Cape6 for a pleasure trip," he said. "His uncle had made a   great fiss about nothing. Eleanor he loved as a sister."  "But, my son, I fear that your charac- ter as a minister of the Gospel is blasted. Strange reports have gone abroad. It is your duty to make Eleanor your wife." "I may do so, but at some future time. If people object to me as a minister, the are not compelled to hear me preach." The saddened, subdued, heart-stricken mother said, "My son, would I had died ere this occurred I I agree. with your father; your character is impeached, your usefulness as a minister will be for a long time retarded, if not entirely destroyed." But Egbert would listen to nothing. He went on his way with a face full. of innocence, with a heart full of guil]e, de- termined to live down reports, and to have his will. The families were sepa- rated, no intercourse existing between them. Eleanor dreaded to meet Clara Seward again, but that faithful friend received her with open arms and tender kisses. Soon their tears were mingling. "Oh I! my dear Eleanor, I am so happy to see you again safe under your father's roof." Tears choked her farther utterance. "Yes," said the weeping Ella, "I am thankful that I am at home again; but v Clara, what, what do people say of, he?!" "Very, very unkind things, my dear Eleanor," replied this brave and truthful friend; "but by a rigid, excellent life you may recover the past. By so doing you may yet be happy." "Happy! alas I no, never again; hap- piness is no more for me, Clara. I love Egbert!  Separated from him, I am miserable. Do not start and look so shocked. I only said, I love him. That is true. It is just so true that I do not expect ever to see him again. I desire to obey my parents. I am reconciled to being unhappy- to learn to live without happiness, as Carlyle expresses it. My dear old father has been too kind, too, forgiving for me, ever again to distress him." But- soon she resumed, evidently glad to relieve her over-burdened heart,  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8397-00000010"/> for Clara was the only one to whom she could talk unreservedly. "I Clara, I have a blessed, good father. He has so gently detailed to me the con- sequences of my imprudence. 'My child;' said he, ' what induced you to leave home with your cousin?' ' Father,' I replied, with a burning cheek, 'I loved him, and he wished to marry me:' 'Marry you, simple girl I did you really believe that he intended to make you his wife when he stole you away from your father's house? ' 'Firmly, father,' returned I, 'and why not believeihim? He loves me.' My father turned away; and wiped some tears from his eyes before he answered me; then said, 'Eleanor, my daughter, I thank God that you are once more safely at home, safe from the grasp of that villain. My dear, he did not intend to marry you. I am a man, I know the programme he had marked out. And now, my dear child, hear and remember these words. If ever you leave again your father's roof clan- destinely with Egbert Cropper, or any man,- remember, oh, remember, that you leave it FoaMV ;.K. Bear this well in mind. The first offence is forgiven; the second, NEVER. You have now erred through ignorance, but the second time you for-   sake the home of your parents, you for. sake it forever.' Oh I Clara, as he uttered these words my heart turned cold within me, I felt faint even unto death. Why, was it, Clara?" "God knows, my dear Eleanor. Let Him teach you how much, how very much you have to be thankful for. The truth, the wisdom, the piety of your most excellent father, Eleanor, ought to keep your heart alive and warm. Treasure up his words; his noble, his forgiving words; never forget them; never again grieve him; he has forgiven in you what would have incensed some parents be- yond forgetfulness - beyond forgive- ness." "I do love him-I am most grateful to him. I will never, never again grieve him," murmured the tearful girl. Alas I how little she dreamed of the weakness of the human heart; and alas t just as little did she dream of the deceit, the sin, the corruption rampant in this weary world in which we dwell. ) The hearts of human beings are queerly con- structed organs, each one playing a dif- ferent strain; a different key-note to each varied scale. We are each a mystery to ourselves.   CHAPTER IV.   THE courageous and faithful Clara re- turned home after many and long con- versations with her friend. She cherish- ed in her affectionate heart a firm belief in the discreet future conduct of Eleanor. Little dreamed she that a second tornado, tenfold more destructive than that which had passed," was even then brewing in the horizon of the future. Eleanor had declared to her kind father, "Oh I father, forgive, forgive, I will never again grieve you." He kissed her, gently bidding her good-night, and she had retired strug- gling between filial affection and the wild love that had possession of her soul. Yet it gave, her happiness to know that 1   she was still beloved at home. Alone in her room she could- not sleep. Her wan- dering thoughts found their type in her restless movements. The fragrant flowers that graceher windows were unnoticed. Now  nothing charmed  her, nothing awakened a feeling of secure happiness, nothing aroused her. Too much for her good thought she of Egbert. Oh, why was man rendered so fascinating? Her loving thoughts dwelt upon his eloquent language, his impassioned voice, his man- ner of indescribable tenderness. She sighed, she wept, she mourned, and, worse than  all, she remembered. She really and truly desired to do what was   right. She tried to think that her pa- rents best knew what was for her ultimate good. She struggled hard to conquer her feelings. But, reader, she was eight- een, and, in love. Oh, innocent bird in the net of the fowler I Slowly dragged along the weary weeks after her return home. Sleepless vigils werekept by our heroine I The mournful ticking of the clock was heard until the light of day beamed again into  her window.   The early birds; as they chirruped, busily flit- ting from bough to bough, taught her that even the feathered tribe were happy, that unfettered by hapless fate, they wooed and won wherever the heart listed. "Ah I "  thought the sleepless girl, "Wherefore is it that- I alone am miser- able? Never again can I be happy; no, nevermore."  And   despondingly she turned away from beautiful Nature, "'from all it brought to all it could not bring." How often she murmured some such lines as these: "Across the waves, away and far, My spirit turns to thee I I love thee as one loves a star, The brightest where a thousand are, Sadly and silently: With love sustained by hopes and fears, Too deep for words, too pure for tears I "My heart is tutored not to weep; Calm, like the calm of even, When grief lies hush'd, but not asleep, Hallows the hours I love to keep For only thee and heaven; Too far and fair to aid the birth Of thoughts that have a taint of earth. "I love to think on thee, as one With whom the strife is o'er; And feel that I am journeying on, Wasted, and weary, and alone, To join thee on that shore Where thou, I know; wilt look for me, And I, forever, be with thee." At times a better, less selfish spirit would prevail. Blushing as she felt her pillow wet with tears, she Would mur- mur, "How foolish I am   to grieve in this manner!1,ePerhaps Egbert loves me not as I love him. -I cannot believe all that they say against him. I cannot, can- not believe that oiie so false as they think him could be so dear to mel He-must   be good, he looks so noble; and if he loves me, ah I we may yet be happy." I She stood by the window looking out into the bright morning; the brightness of every thing seemed to taunt her with her misery. Wearily she completed her toilette, wearily descended the stairs. At the foot stood a woman, a stranger to Eleanor, into whose hand was thrust a letter. Eleanor bewildered, had yet suf- ficient presence of mind to put the letter into her bosom, for a hasty glance had shown her that the superscription was in the handwriting of Egbert Cropper. As  soon after breakfast as possible, she locked herself in her room, and with a throbbing heart perused this precious epistle. "Ma owN BELOVEDV,-- Long before this would I have written you, angel of my heart, but for the fear of distressing you by the expos6 of intercepted letters; and, beloved, you have already suffered enough for me. She who delivers this to you is our friend. You can trust hr. The day  upon which your father tore you from me was the saddest of my- life. Despair tempted me to fire upon your parent, but love for you restrained my anger. When you were gone darkness fell upon my soul. The light of mine eyes had- de. 'parted; naught but despair was left me.; I threw myself upon the sofa so lately pressed by your dear form, and gave vent" to my uncontrollable emotion. Ella, I cannot live without you. Could you but know the anguish I endure, your gentle heart would swell with pity for your un- happy cousin. I think of your precious smile, your still more precious caresses and tender words, until my heart is on fire. ' Never to see you again iP It can- not, must not, 8sall not be. My brain reels, my nerves tremble; forgive my im- petuosity. I must see you once more, once more, darling Ella, these arms must embrace you, these lips must meet thine. Come to meet me at, the hour I shah name, at the place I shall mention, and, I swear, you shall never have cquse :to re.  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8397-00000011"/> pent it. I will marry you at any time you appoint, my own beloved. Or, if you do not wish now, just at present, to become my wife, I will be faithful to thee unto death. Come, my Ella, come to the heart that is throbbing to greet thee. Only let me again gaze upon you, only let my heart once more feel yours beating against it I Beloved treasure, I love but thee, and I love thee to madness. Meet me on Sat- urday at the time and place mentioned on the card I enclose. Write me, dear one; the bearer of this will manage to secure your note unsuspected by any one. If she bring me good tidings from you, my angel, my Peri, my Bird of Paradise, she will have rendered herself invaluable. Au revoir, dearest Eleanor; I hope soon to say, beloved wife. Wife I tender, beau- tiful word. Ever thine,  EGBERT." The receipt of this letter threw Elea- nor into a state of great excitement. She had just succeeded in calming her mind into comparative repose, as she thought; it was rather the apathy, the reaction at- tendant upon former excitement. Fully aware how much her parents had suffered upon her account, she had determined to give up all thought of Egbert. Yet this attempt, she feared, would cost her her life. This man had mastered her affec- tions. A woman of her temperament loves once, and onch only. But then it must be love; genuine, true attachment, and not mistaken youthful ardor. No change of circumstance, neither woe nor weal, can extinguish the flame when it is once kindled in a true woman's breast. Even the cold clod of the valley, and the winding sheet, find her "faithful unto death." O man why then art thou so cruel as to trample under foot such genu- ine affection't Such love would brave the sting of poverty I\ Such love would survive ills the most dire I Let the reader call to mind Lady Harriet Ackland.. She followed bhr husband through the war, with four darling children by her side. The roaring of the cannon, the smoke of sulphuric gunpowder, could not drive her   from the side of the man she loved; and following him, she was enabled to soothe the dying throes of many a poor soldier who suffered in his country's cause. Think also of the Empress Josephine after she had been divorced by the insatiable Napoleon. Only her death deterred her from following the banished ambitieu to the barren isle of St. Helena. Oh, charm- ing woman I But it appears that the heart of man is less captivated when wo- man adores him than when she coolly re- ceives adoration; her ardent love seems rather to congeal the ardor of his! A queer compound of contrarieties is often found in the honorable sex! And just such an one of these (queer beings was the minister, though, fs yet, like too many, he continues to wear the mask. Eleanor read and re-read the letter which had so unexpectedly reached her hands. To reply, or not to reply-that was the question. She hesitated, and Bulwer declares that when a woman hesi- tates she is lost. - The result of the de- bate in Eleanor's heart was a reply to the epistle. Oh, woman I woman I will the scales of blindness never be torn from thine eyes? Will reason never assert its reign in thy mind? Will self-respect never be as po- tent as it should be in the feminine breast? We fear never--never. Could we only be instrumental in saving our sex from the pain and misery that lies hidden beneath the veil of sin to which they so often expose themselves, the writer should then feel that her life had been spared for that special purpose. Yet we fear that no one is adequate to the task. However, when this tale is con- cluded, and the heroine is exhibited to the reader in her real state, we think that it must have some effect upon the tender," youthful maid, who may take warning by Eleanor Cropper, and'that some may henceforth obey their parents, and trust not to heartless deceivers. We repeat that Eleanor replied to the letter. :Had she been ill, dying, or incompetent to write, how much better would it have   been for her I Could she have felt as Nero did when the first death warrant Was brought to him to sign t He exclaimed, "Oh that I had, never learned to write!" Had Eleanor never answered that fatal letter, her life might -have' been strewn with' roses instead of prickly thorns. But like an impassioned, inex- experienced, loving girl, she followed in the footsteps of many others who had gone before. And, alas I how many will hereafter tread the same stormy path I She wrote as follows: "DEAR EGBERT,--What to say to you I scarcely know. You have been grieved upon my account; our separation is an- guish to you; you love me, and my heart beats with delirious joy. All that is bright fades in comparison to this great thought, The prospect of seeing you again makes my innermost heart throb almost to suffocation. Yet I have oft- times wished that we had never met; forgive me this; but that we love each other is at once to me the joy and the misery of my life. "You are fully aware of my father's insuperable objections to our union. Yes, Eleanor is miserable; she grieves that she is parted from Egbert; she grieves, that she seems fated to bring sorrow to the hearts of her parents. I have tried, forgive me again, I have tried with all my strength -to forget you-but that is impossible I To love you is my fate. Love I rather call it adoration. I some- times feel convinced that as your wife, I could better do my duty to you,-to my parents, to the world, than while I live I thus isolated from him who rules my  ( heart. To see you once again I now   ] consent. Therefore, expect me at the appointed place and time. Remember your sacred promises. Your confiding "ELEANOR."  0 This letter was moistened with her i tears. Not long after its transcription, the door bell of Mr. Cropper's mansion 1 announced a visitor. The master of the t 2   house, happening to be near: the door, opened it himself. Before him stood a strange woman,- who, rather startled to be tlih s confrontedwith the very last per- son she wished to see or be seen by, did not at once announce her business. "What are your comman'ds, Madam?", politely inquired this gentleman of the old school. A voice, sweet and lady-like, replied, "I am sent by Miss Matilda Potter with a message to Miss Eleanor Cropper; Miss Potter is quite ill this afternoon, andher mother, compelled to be absent on busi- ness, requested me to call and beg your daughter kindly to come and sit a few hours with the invalid." What a charm is there in a sweet and gentle voice! Mr. Cropper, subtle lawyer as he was, heard with pleasure these words spoken in tones "like the chafing of silver pebbles in a pearly brook "Call- ing a servant, he desired the lady to be shown into Miss Eleanor's sitting room. . This was a species of good luck un- looked for but welcomed by Egbert's messenger. She followed the domestic with a step that was as light and airy as her voice was sweet, not forgetting though, before she went, to express her' thanks to Mr. Cropper with a smile and a manner that he thought the most grace- ful he had ever beheld. But Mrs. Jacobs determined to risk nothing. Brief was her stay, and few the words spoken in Eleanor's pretty boudoir: "You have replied?" Eleanor silently placed in her hands the -letter which it had cost her so much to indite. It was hastily and dexterously concealed. "You will not fail to meet him?" "No," in a voice weak and smothered. "Be punctual!" and she disappeared. Eleanor wrtng her hands, and cast an appealing glance to heaven-yet all the while intended to keep the appoint- ment. Mr. Cropper retired to his library, sus- pecting nothing, and inwardly concluding that a pretty, sweet-voiced, graceful wo-  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8397-00000012"/> f man was not at all a disagrqsable sight. And she who had brought him to this original decision was indeed a fair picture to look upon. Her white cashmere dress, her elegant drapery, her tasteful bonnet, all pure and white, were exceedingly ele- gant and becoming, and bespoke the wearer So be at once a lady of taste and refinement and affluence. She looked like an immaculate creature, and she woas one of the Rev. Egbert Cropper's acquaint- ances. These two had for a long time been well known to each other. She ac- cidentally happened at Cape May just in the nick of time; and, knowing her to be capable of full as much stratagem as himself, Egbert employed her to aid him in the recovery of his lost prize--prized all the more for having for a time es- caped his grasp. At the various places of fashionable resort no lady presented so beautiful, so recherche, so elegant, and   so invariable an appearance as did Mrs. Jacobs. Subject of wonder, of discus- sion, of marvellous conjecture, she al- ways was wherever she presented herself, but she calmly pursued " the even tenor of her -way," apparently as pure as the spotless robes she wore. And who would dare to think that " aught of evil could dwell in such a templei"Let nobody say that appearances are nothing! It would be quite as sensible to declare that -eey-sight were a vain and useless gift of nature. So long as we look around with the physical eye we will, in a measure, judge and be guided by it. How sad then to think that appearances are oft- times deceptive; that what looks so fair without is sometimes so false, so'very false within!, AhI when will virtue reign supreme, and vice 'become un- known? Not, alas  while human na- ture yet remains.   CHAPTER V.   MR. CROPPER was aware of the illness of Miss Potter. Eleanor was in the habit of frequently visiting her school-mate; thus, when a few hours after the advent of the strange woman, she was seen to leave the house, nothing, of course, was suspected to be wrong. Indeed, her pa- rents rejoiced that something had oc- curred to rouse the listless Eleanor, the ,darling of their hearts. Her trembling feet bore her to the first gate of the grounds. Oh, why did she not obey the impulse that tempted her to fly back to her father's house? But she ascended the hill, and stood on its summit. In the rear of the building, in the valley, she beheld a manly form pacing to and fro; her heart beat fast, as she recog- nized him whom she had come thus clandestinely to meet. Descending the hill, she was soon in view, and in an- other moment he was beside her. How the .warm ardent pressure of his hand   made her heart palpitate! How his ex- pressive eyes made her own fall beneath their gaze! How the remembrance of father, mother, and duty was fast for- gotten in the joy, the deep joy of meet- ing him again  Sitting beside him. where was the grief that had so long oppressed her heart? Oh, that long, anxious, pleading, impassioned conver- sationi! Oh, that rapturous, dangerous interview! Oh, the subtlely, the art, the strategy of that man! which was only equalled by-a thousand just such be- ings I "I must now return home, Egbert," said Eleanor softly, after two hours had elapsed- "Whither " t To my father's house." "And never see me again--" "Nay, Egbert; not so, to see you again frequently, I hope. But our meetings must be blest with the permission and   cognizance. of my father. We must be patient; Egbert." "Eleanor I "-there was both entreaty and reproach in his tone. '"Ella I "--Oh, the dangerous melody of that voice  He clasped again the hand, which, just now, in masterly acting, he had yielded. There was magnetism  in his touch!" "Eleanor, you do not love me I " Ah I the potency of that accusation I How much, how .very much, woman will venture to prove it a false accusationI And  Eleanor blushingly, tremblingly whispered that she did indeed love him, ah! better than all the world beside. "Then, Eleanor; you will not leave me to despair, and to  "  A well pro- duced action of hysterical demonstration and uncontrollable emotion choked the rest of the sentence. "To what, dear Egbert? What dread- ful thing do you mean?"    cried the equally agitated girl. Alas I her emotion was most sincere, his, only simulated. His vehemence of manner far more than his words alarmed her. "To destruction, Eleanor I am but mortal. Without you, I am lost; I will not answer for myself. Ruin is before me. Despair-Madness-Suicide " Oh I credulity of woman! Eleanor be- lieved him. By a superhuman effort she stifled the shriek which rose to her lips. They were in a spot entirely secluded from observation; she threw herself into his arms. "Egbert I Egbert I Egbert!" she exclaimed passionately. He rained kisses upon her brow, her eyes, her lips. "Beloved, I cannot live without you," he murmured in a voice of unutterable tenderness. Again Eleanor believed him. Too young, too innocent, too loving and sincere herself to doubt, his passionate, ardor filled her with new, ecstatic delight. She grew dizzy with i happiness. The face that bent over her watche4 with eagle eye the traces of the various emotions that chased each other over her expressive countenance. Re- newed vows of undying love and con- stancy were poured into her willing ear.   Eleanor, with resolution growing feeble, tried to nerve herself for the coming separation. "My heart's treasure I it will drive me mad to lose you again. I cannot, cannot be separated from you; not for a week, a day, nay, an hourI  What to me is life without my angel in the house? Your- father will not consent to our union;, consequently it were useless to beseech him." Still Eleanor struggled against those emotions which were fast mastering her. The sense of duty was too strongly im- planted in her heart to yield without a mighty struggle. "Egbert, my father- my mother-my sister I " "Eleanor, my w0ifel"  The tone in which these words were breathed shot like electric influence along every nerve of her being. Still she did not utter the words which he waited impatiently to hear; still she murmured not, "Eg- bert, I am yours I " He waited, waited, outwardly calm, in. wardly chafing at the delay; literally chafing at the delay; he knew well that it was only delay, not defeat; chafing to see the sun shine brightly, chafing to hear the birds warbling unmindful of his torture. At last, unable longer to en-. dure her silence, he said, "Eleanor, this is killing me I You love me not; shall I say farewell, farewell forever?" With a passionate burst of tears, Elea- nor threw herself upon his breast; she was clasped in an embrace that threatened to suffocate her in its intensity. At that instant a shadow, a white shadow, fell across themI Egbert started and looked up. Before I him stood the woman, his friend; a look full of meaning passed be- tween them. "Is this Miss Eleanor Crop- per?" inquired the substance of that shadow. "Yes," replied, Eleanor to the gently- spoken querist. "A carriage awaits at the foot of the hill. YourSmother has been suddenly. taken ill; a, i your father has sent me for you to convey you home." - '. *  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8397-00000013"/> "Good heavens!" exclaimed the credu- lous girl. "Let us go; let us go imme- diately ;" and she clasped her trembling hands in an agony of grief and appre- hension. "How did you discover that we were here?" asked Egbert, for the purpose of still further blinding his deluded cousin. "I happened to be passing the resi- dence of Mr. Cropper; he saw me; the household was all in confusion; he re-\ ' quested me to call at Mrs. Potter's, and beg Miss Eleanor to return home imme- diately. I recognized you as I passed these grounds andtcame to seek you." The absurdity of these assertions, Elea- nor, in her agitation, failed to notice  Turning to Egbert, she held out her hand; smiling faintly, she said: "We must part now." "I will accompany you a portion of the way." Drawing her arm within his they descended the hill, and entering the car- riage which still waited, were driven rapidly away. The blinds of the vehicle were closed. The woman, having taken the front sqat upon entering the vehicle, affected to be deeply occupied in the pe- rusal of a letter. Egbert seated himself beside his cousin, drew her head upon his bosom, and whispered dulcet words of tenderness and consolation, words so potent to charm that Eleanor was in dan- ger of forgetting her mother's indisposi- tion. Suddenly the whistle of a locomo- tive sounded in her startled ears. She raised her head. "What does this mean? This d6pot is in an entirely opposite direction from the house of my father. What doesit mean?" "It means," said the lady, with the gentleness of a subtle woman, " it means, beautiful Eleanor, that we are to have a wedding at my house." "It means, beloved," bhispered Egbert, "that I cannot again part with you; that I have you now, and that I intend to keep you. .You can but see how much, how sincerely I love you. 'This lady is my friend; she will be yours also. Per-   ceiving how dear you are to me, and how difficult it was to persuade you to make me happy, she has volunteered her as- sistance to save my life-for without you I cannot live." "But, my mother?" "As far as my knowledge extends, is in the best of health," said Egbert. "My Eleanor, ' all is fair in love and war.' " She, bewildered, fascinated girl, gave herself up to Egbert. Laying her sweet face upon his shoulder, she wiped away the tears that would come, and trusted implicitly that his love and his cloth would be her protection. Egbert Cropper, as the cars sped on, looked down upon the still pale face resting so quietly upon his bosom, and a feeling of compunction entered into his soul. .On the opposite seat one sat in- tently watching him. He looked up, their glances met. The language of her eyes was potent: a minute they gazed full at each other. When he looked down again upon Eleanor there seemed to be no pity in his impassioned eyes. The woman who sat opposite gazing upon Egbert with intent eyes, was once as fair and pure as she whom he held upon his bosom. In a few hours the travellers reached Philadelphia. 'Eleanor was very quiet, scarcely lifting her eyes. In the smile that lighted the face of her cousin, might be detected a gleam of triumph. He left them a moment to procure a carriage; this woman followed him a few steps; some words in a tone too low to reach Eleanor's ears passed between them. "Perhaps it is the better plan," Eleanor heard her say, as she released Egbert, and returned to her side. "My dear," she sweetly said, taking Eleanor's hand, "I had hoped to take you at once to my house, but your cousin has decided it is best to go to a hotel. I am under the necessity of accommodating boarders for a livelihood, and he thought that it would perhaps embarrass you to be taken among so many strangers. At a hotel, on the contrary, one can remain as   quiet and as private as one pleases. As soon as you are married you must come to me." Eleanor blushingly thanked her, and just then Egbert returned. Mrs. Jdcobs kissed her, and, in going, said: '"Mr. Cropper, you will let me know when you are to be married!" "Certainly, and that shall be at once, just as soon as the bride elect has found again her power of speech," looking smil- ingly down upon Eleanor. They separated at the depot. Egbert following his cousin into a carriage, or- dered the coachman to drive to a hotel near'Eleventh street. Supper was soon dispatched, and that night the weary girl lay her head upon the pillow in the firm belief that the next day would find her the honorable wife of Egbert Cropper. Leaving her to the last weak slumber that she was to enjoy for a long, long pe- riod, we will return to the home she had so lately deserted. "Where is Eleanor?" asked Mr. Crop- per, when during the evening the family were seated in the luxurious library.? "She has not yet returned from Mrs. Potter's," replied his wife. "Matilda must be very ill, indeed." "Nothing serious is to be apprehended, I hope? '? interrogated the preoccupied lawyer. "I trust not. Matilda was always de- licate, and everybody when ill, loves to have Eleanor about them, she is so tender and gentle." ;' Her husband, already deep in the eve- ning paper, made no- reply. Another hour passed. "Marnma;" cried Emelia,' "I have concluded learning all of my lessons; may I summon Robert, and run over for Eleanor?" ' Yes, child; I wish you  would; and by no means permit Eleanor to re- main with them all night. She is far from being well herself, and I should not be satisfied to have her away.' Emelia had been absent but a Short time, when she again entered the library. She entered hurriedly, and her quickened o    respiration evinced that she had walked  rapidly. "Why, Emelia, how flurried you are I Where is Eleanor? What in the world is the matter with you?" "Nothing is the matter with me," said Emelia, in a strange tone. "Mother, Eleanor has not been to Mrs. Potter's to- day I " "Not been to Mrs. Potter's to-day  My dear," anxiously said Mrs. Cropper to her husband who had not heeded what had passed; " my dear, did you not tell me that Eleanor had been sent for by Mrs. Potter?" "Certainly, my love; is there anything extraordinary in that?" "Mr. Cropper!" rising hurriedly, "Emeia has just returned from Mrs. Potter's, Eleanor has not been there to- day, neither had they sent for her; they have not seen her during the week." A dead silence fell upon the little party. By a mysterious species of intui- tion they at once surmised what had oc- curred. "The woman, the strange wo- man!" gasped rather than articulated the mother of Eleanor. Not three hours before had her husband described in glowing terms this woman, this mysteri- ous woman. "That devil incarnate has bee/n again tampering with her!" cried the old man in stern tones, and while his eyes flashed, he turned to go. "Charles 1 whither go you? I must fol- low," said the stricken wife and mother, tottering to the side of her husband. "I go to Theodore I It is many a day since I have entered his house. I know that Egbert was there this morning; if he is now absent-" his utterance was choked.   The despairing look of his wife made his stern heart ache. "Let me go with you, Charles 1 " she whisperingly entreated. "No, no; better remain here; I will soon return." Taking her in his arms he laid her upon the sofa.- She seemed stunned with grief. The strong old man groaned, as he kissed her, and departed  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8397-00000014"/> upon his sad errand, Quietly she lay for a long time; at last, "Eleanor, Elea- nor, my child, my child!" burst in agonised tones from the mother's lips. "Mother, mother, you have not lost all I am here; your daughter, your own Emelia!" and mother and daugh- ter were locked in each others arms, shedding bitter, bitter tears. Two hours elapsed before Mr. Cropper returned. When, at last, he came, his steps, even before he entered the house, told to the watchers that he brought with him no glad tidings. He came into the room. He walked up to the sofa; stand- ing with folded arms, he silently regard- ed the grief-stricken faces before him. Soon his lips quivered; suddenly he dropped upon his knees, and laid his gray head on the bosom of his wife and gave vent to an outhurst of his almost   breaking heart. Noiselessly Emelia stole from the room I Alone she sought her chamber, desolate as though death had stricken all she best loved. Ah I it was her first sorrow, and with the unreason- ableness of youth' she thought that it was to last forever, that never in her life was she again to know happiness. She, innocent maiden, had a very dim idea of what had occasioned this grief and consternation. She only knew, she only, felt that it must be something dreadful, because she beheld her parents so over- whelmed. So she wept-herself to sleep, to sleep at last, dreadilig to awake, dreading to-morrow, and all the days that were ever again to dawn upon her. Innocent maiden, tender girl I she little knew the power, the astonishing power of renewed life and happiness in the hearts of the young I A\    CHAPTER VII.   MR. CHARLES CROPPER had sought the house of his brother Theodore. Its master happened to be out, away-from home. "Say to Mrs. Cropper that I de- sire to see her for a few moments." The wondering domestic who had been whnt to see the families on the most intimate terms, departed to convey the message to his mistress. She, equally lost in conjecture to -hat to attribute this unexpected call, unless to a renewal of cordiality, hastened to make her ap- pearance. ." Where is your son?" was the quick and peremptory inquiry. ("Absent from home." "When did he leave?" "This morning.;' "For what place?" "It would be difficult to tell, Egberts movements are quick and sudden. We do not subject him to inquiry." "It. would be better for you, perhaps, had you granted him less license. Where - is he gone? I demand a reply."   "Indeed, Mr. Cropper, it would be impossible for me to say, with any. de- gree of certainty, but I think he took the cars for Harrisburgh. "And that is all the information you have to give?" "That is all I know about the matter." Silently and sternly Mr. Cropper re- garded her; then without a word strode from the apartment. His return to his desolated home has been  described. When the first storm of his grief had abated, he arose from his wife's embrace, determined to seek out and punish the man who had given all this trouble. In a few hours he was on his way to Phila- delphia. Days were passed in a fruitless search. Hotels and boarding houses were besieged by the desperate father. The very house at which they were stop- ping was overlooked in the idea that that place would never have been patronized by the aristocrat. All in vain I Mr. Cropper returned to his heart-broken 1   family to whom his coming was at once a relief and a crushing disappointment. Grateful were they to see him again, but, alas I he came alone. Like all whose lot it is to dwell upon earth they had to suf- fer and to endure. - By means worse, far worse than death, they had lost a child who, from her birth, had been an idol. Her beauty, her intelligence, ,and her many amiable characteristics had drawn all hearts to her. We will not attempt to delineate the sufferings of this afflicted family; our pen i's inadequate to the task, the sorrowful task i The parents of Egbert for a long time refused to believe him guilty. But, at last, the scales fell from their eyes, and they were compelled to view him in all his naked deformity. The city had now a ripe nut to crack. The families occu- pied a position which rendered them known far and wide; and gossip had now a fruitful theme. Jealous women spared not Eleanor. They knew, dis- criminating creatures, that divine Mr. Egbert Cropper had been inveigled by that artful creature; while the men blamed and pitied the lost girl, they were equally alive to the audacious vil- lany of the minister. A certain set of women were willing to cast the blame en- tirely upon the shoulders of Eleanor. The men were more just. They better knew to what deception their sex will re- sort, and they understood the freedom that a minister enjoys in the community; he can associate with his congregation under all circumstances, and in all places, and it is all allowable in the eyes of the world. We again return to Eleanor. She awoke; her eyes rested upon sur- roundings unfamiliar to her gaze, For a moment she knew not where she was; then recollection returned, and she buried her burning face in the pillow. It was a long time ibefore, she could gather courage to rise and perform her toilette. Soon she was summoned to breakfast. During the meal, and- while he remained with her, nothing could ex- ceed the tender and respectful. -attentions   of Egbert. After several hours had elapsed, he gently told -her that indis- pensable business would compel his ab- sence for several hours.. A soft, reproach- ful glance was his answer, to which he replied by a tender embrace, which when he had gained the door he returned to repeat. Wearily passed the hours to the solitary girl. Late, not until late in the evening did Egbert return. With pro- fuse and tender apologies he endeavored to excuse his prolonged and unavoidable absence. But Eleanor met him with un- usual dignity. A gentle reserve had taken the place of girlish abandon of, manner. She did not return his caresses which she evidently did not wish to re- ceive. i Once more he repeated the oft- recited tale, how much he loved her, how very, very dear she was to him. "There is a way by which to prove that," she replied in a firm voice, while a crimson torrent covered her face land throat. He remained silent. "Egbert." she exclaimed interrogatively. How ex- pressive was her glance, and the very tone of her voice. "It is now too late to-night to have the ceremony performed. Eleanor, your evi- dent distrust distresses me." "There is but one way by which to dis- pel it." He had not thought she could be so brave. The girl, or rather the woman, was roused. Egbert perceived that a struggle must take place, and that it was now to come off. This did not dismay him. He rather liked it than not. He could see "No charm in trophies won with easel I' He advanced towards her with extend- ed arms, and languishing eyes. "Elea- norl beloved!" "Leave me, oh, leave me!" "Eleanor, I love you to adoration! Come to me." "I will not!-I will not HLeave me, oh, leave me " She wrung her white hands; her voice both menaced and pleaded. "Egbert-go; go; for God's" sake, go!"  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8397-00000015"/> With one bound he reached her side; he enclosed her in his arms; his mad ca- resses overwhelmed her. She was pow- erless; a mortal languor stole over her frame; then, with a mighty effort, she broke away from his embrace. Almost bereft of strength, yet she flew across the room towards the door. But he reached it before she did, and grasping her hands as she touched the lock, he stood with his back against the door. Holding both her hands in his, he compelled her to look at him; his glance magnetised her. For some minutes they looked full into each other's face; then leading her gen- tly back to her seat, he bent over her a moment; his breath played upon her cheek, but he did not caress her, but -bade her a formal "Good-night "  He was gone. The girl remained motionless, stunned, bewildered, bewitched. She had trusted to his honor. His honor! Alas! alas I How long she oat there she never knew. At length she rose, and feebly dragging herself across the room, locked. the door. After a time the flood-gates were unlock- ed, and bitter, bitter were the tears she shed. Oh, consummate actor I Never was there a more perfect one than Egbert Cropper I Oh, weak, weak Eleanor I mis- guided, deluded girl I Upon her mem- ,ory came the advice bestowed upon her by her dear father and mother. - The words of her wise young friend,' Clara Seward, rushed into vivid recollection. Eleanor I Eleanor I Alas I she wept but she remained. She groaned in agony of spirit, yet she made no motion to depart. Eleanor had never been taught self-de- pendece!  Every accomplishment de- signed to perfect woman had been mark- ed out to take its place in the routine of ,her education. Nature and art, wealth and genius, vied with each other to be- stow upon this girl their best and most charming gifts. But alas I she has never been obliged to think for herself. Had some ministering angel been allowed to enter that room, and audibly ex-   claim, "Eleanor, misguided girl I fly, 1y, while there islyt time!" then would she have rushed from the impending danger; as it was, she never thought that it was in her power to escape; it never occurred to her that it was her duty to speed away for self-preservation. Already Was she tasting the bitter wages of sin. But what is this to what must follow I Oh, that our pen could write this tale in words of liquid fire! Oh, that eloquence the most persuasive could invest the words we in- dite! But, alas 1 we must pen this story in plain and simple language, such as every woman on the globe can under- stand. Towards dawn Eleanor fell into a troub- led slumber. The renewed bustle of a busy city aroused her. The bells rang to announce the morning repast. Half an hour after a gentle rap at the door was heard. With a trembling hand she unlocked it; he whom she feared, yet longed to see, was not there: but there' stood a waiter, who brought in a nice breakfast, and then respectfully with- drew. Eleanor could not taste a mouth- ful of food, but eagerly swallowed the fragrant coffee. Any liquid-was grateful to her feverish thirst. When the waiter came to remove the breakfast service, he was the bearer of a little note.' Eleanor held it passively until the domestic had left the room, then eagerly tore it open. Of course it was from Egbert; who told her that he was obliged to be -absent dur- ing the morning, but that all she wished should be accomplished that afternoon. Blind, infatuated girl I she still remained, and still believed him. It was, dinner- time before her cousin deemed it expe- dient to return. a Again a tempting little meal was sent to her room; as at break- fast she could eat nothing, and only or- dered a cup of tea. Again the mulatto messenger bore her a missive. This time a few lines were traced upon an enameled card. They merely desired her to be in readiness to accompany him; ia the course of half an hour he would call for her at ner door. Eleanor's heart was re-   lieved of a load of anxiety. Her's was a temperament which, to use a " sprightly" phrase, was prone to jump at conclusions. it He is going to take me to a minister!" her willing heart whispered, and that same fond, foolish heart smote her for the doubts she had just now harbored. Too ready to excuse his conduct, she now felt sure that for some good and valid reason he had been obliged to delay the per- formance of his promises. Thus, when, at the appointed moment, Egbert came to her door she met him with a manner, reserved, it is true, but softened almostto tenderness by the self-reproach she had just undergone. He was gentlemanly, far from ardent. Well, for him, she did not see the triumphant gleam of his eye. He conducted her down stairs, they en- tered a carriage which, after a rapid drive, drew up before an elegant house. ("This is the residence of our friend, Mrs. Jacobs," he said, in answer to Eleanor's inquiring glance. "If you do not object, we will be married here." They ascended the step, entered the elegant vestibule, and the door of that house was closed upon the retreating form of Eleanor Cropper. Leaning upon the arm of her cousin, she was ushered into an elegant drawing-room.       I "Mrs. Jacobs will be with you imme- diately," said the very gentlemanly wait, eC as he bowed and withdrew. In a few moments that lady entered the room. Sweetly apologising for being still in demi-toilette she gracefully welcomed Eleanor, who almost forgot her embar- rassing, situation in admiration of the splendid creature before her. Mrs. Ja- cobs extended her white hand to Egbert, and languishingly said: "You naughty man I why have you not sooner brought her to me? Ah, I see I you selfish adorer, wanted to keep her all to yourself, eh?" Then turning to Eleanor, said, 'Come, my dear, let me remove your things." You, must remain with me this afternoon. And when were you married? Naughty children, not to let me know anything about it."   Eleanoi colored violently, and hastily withdrew her hand from the gentle clasp of her hostess. "We are not yet mar- ried," said Egbert.      ) "Not yet married 1" with a well-simu- lated start of astonishment, and knitting her fair brows. "Imprudent, inconse- quent man I why, what do you mean?" Her well-assumed indignation imposed upon the credulous Eleanor, who felt at once as if in the presence of a friend and a protector. "Dear madam, kind friend!" -said the smooth voice of Egbert, "I feel almost'" deserving of your just indignation. But, indeed, circumstances beyond my con- trol have compelled me to act against the dictates of my heart. A man cannot always be the pilot of his own actions. But now, determined to delay this cere- mony no longer, I have taken the liberty, my dear, good friend, to bring to your house this little girl, who has begun to be afraid of me." And stepping to her stfe, Egbert put his arm gently about Eleanor. "And you wish it to take place here?" asked the lady, wonderfully affected. "With your permission, and with E1- la's consent." "Will Ella trust me?" asked Mrs. Ja- cobs, in her most winning manner. Eleanor looked up wistfully. Mrs. Ja- cobs led Eleanor off into an elegantly fitted-up chamber, which opened into a cosy sitting-room. Here she detained her in pleasant converse for an hour;* then declared that she must really teat herself away in order to attend to her do- mestic duties. Eleanor was left alone. With a heart lightened almost of every burden, she leisurely examined the pic- tures which decorated the walls; they  :' were exquisite specimens of art. But even while Eleanor gazed, her thoughts wandered. Why did Egbert avoid her?  Why did he not come to her?. Was he offended? He certainly did not seek her with the eagerness of the ardent lover; and with the intensity of a loving na- ture, she yearned to see him.  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8397-00000016"/> The afternoon fled away-; it was now near dusk. Eleanor, with a strange feel- ing of loneliness oppressing her heart, leaned out of the open window. This window looked out upon a garden fra- 'grant with myriad flowers, but deserted by human occupants. Eleanor leaned over the casement, involuntarily murmur- ing a faint, sad melody. Suddenly and softly an arm was passed around her waist, ad -her weary head was drawn down upon the resting place it so much loved.  "My sweet little tyrant! what a weary time has elapsed since I had you in my arms ;" and soft kisses were pressed on her lips. Eleanor felt too happy to reply. A long, long silence followed, during which the heart of the girl revelled in sweet thoughts! Oh I what were those in which her companion indulged? She started up, as drawn back into another   world, when a bell resounded through the house to call its inmates to the even- ing meal. Just then Mrs. Jacobs entered the room. ," I have taken the liberty to order tea up here, and have invited my- self to partake with you. Am I wel- come?' she gaily inquired. She was assured of her welcome pres- ence. She bestowed upon Eleanor - kiss and ordered lights. Supper was soon-pro- duced. As far as Eleanor was concern- ed, it was a silent meal, but her com- panions supplied all deficiency by keep- ing up a brilliant and witty conversation. Seated in that luxurious room, beside the man she loved, with the scent of flowers stealing in through the windows, with the sound of Egbert's melodious voice, and the silvery laughter of Mrs. Jacobs in her ear, her senses seemed confused, and she did not see the secret signal made by that lady to Egbert, who soon after left the room.   CHAPTER VIII.   MRS. JACOBS seated herself beside Elea- nor, and a long dialogue, or rather mono- logue, ensued, for our heroine had but little to say. Oh, the conversation of that woman 1 In her way she was a genius. All the concealed subtle evil of the worst and most wickedly fascinating French novels was rampant in her nature. What strange sensations crept over the girl as she listened to the syren. Why did it not seem a far less reprehensible act to have stolen away from the house of her father than it seemed an hour ago? We will not attempt to repeat, we could not do justice to that conversation. Suffice it to say, that without having heard ut- tered one exceptionable word, Eleanor acutely felt that she was considered fool- ishy fastidious. The weak Eleanor, per- ceiving that she was thus considered by another, began to think that it must really be so, and that she was making a very silly and provincial appearance in   the estimation of others. Alas I Eleanor had never been in the habit of thinking and deciding for herself. The woman stealthily but unceasingly watchedthe girl. Once she deemed her work done, and that the ripe time to act had arrived, but some sudden remark made by Elea- nor determined her to delay yet a little. Once more the stream of talk went on, thd subtle, artful merging of words into ideas that bewildered the unsuspecting girl, and made her feel as she never be- fore had felt. Another half hour elapsed, then, unobserved by Eleanor, Mrs. Jacobs touched a spring which communicated with a signal in another apartment at that time occupied by the minister. Three moments after Egbert Cropper entered the room in which sat Mrs. Ja- cobs and Eleanor. As if overcome with chagrin and disappointment, he threw himself into afauteuil. "What has occurred to disturb my   young friend?" inquired Mrs. Jacobs with sweet equanimity, while Eleanor turned pale, her thoughts instantly re- verting to her parents and the home she had forsaken. "'The greatest disappointment in the world," replied the minister. "I had set my heart upon having the -marriage cer- emony performed by my old and valued friend, Dr. Suydam; and, as ill luck would have it, he has been compelled to leave town suddenly, on account of the severe illness of his wife who had gone to visit her parents. 8 He may not be able to return until to-morrow, or perhaps later. It is to me the greatest disappoint- ment in the world." "But, my dear Mr. Cropper, there cer- tainly are numerous other clergymen in the city," remarked Mrs. Jacobs, depre- catingly. "Very true, Madam; 'but you cannot understand how much my heart was set upon having the ceremony performed by no other than my venerated and esteemed friend. But I suppose my peculiar feel- ings must be set aside, and I must go seek some other;" and, with a sigh, he lazily rose, as if about starting in pursuit of another clergyman, who would prove as imaginary as his dear and esteemed friend, the Rev. Dr. Suydam. "My dear boy, do not be in such extreme haste," said the silvery voice of Mrs. Jacobs, the touch of sarcasm in which made Egbert wince a little, although Eleanor perceived nothing but the kindness of the tone. "I repeat, no need to be in such frantic haste. 'Tis really too bad that you should be so dis- 1 appointed. Indeed, I can truly sym- I pathize with you. I know just how you 1 feel. I deferred my own marriage for a  whole year, for no other reason than that 1 I was, like you, determined to be mar- 1 ried but by one person, and he was then 1 absent on a mission to the Sandwich  t Islands. My intended generously per- t mitted me to follow out an inclination so i strong in my heart."          t Eleanor was gazing up into the speak- r   es ers face with moistened eyes; her breath Dr came quick and'tumultuous. "Did you e- love him very much?" she softly asked. e "   Who, child?" asked Mrs. Jacobs shortly, in strange contrast to her former e placidity. "t "Your husband," replied Eleanor tim. r. idly, and with a blush. hung  down her d head.   For a moment the serene Mrs. k 'Jacobs looked disturbed.   The color o mounted to her white brow, not so much, e perhaps, on account of the mal-apropos e question, as at the amusement visible in e the satiric countenance of Egbert. He s could scarcely smother a laugh. But the woman quickly recovered herself. "Oh I exceedingly --ex-ceed-ing-ly!" - she said, looking at Egbert with blazing eyes. Egbert looked at Eleanor; her large eyes were luminous, her cheek fiushed. Rising, he said, "I will go seek some one else.?' bMrs. Jacobs also rose, not quickly, but with a slow luxurious motion, that Egbert, with the eyes of a Sybarite, liked ' to see. "Remain here," she said. "I will attend to-this matter. Make yourself easy, my dear "-this to Eleanor, and with a grace- ful bend of her superb head, she swept out of the room. Egbert allowed full ten minutes to pass before he approached Eleanor.  Then' with slow, easy movement, as if not ins the least ardent, he crossed the room, and sank beside her on the sofa. "Is my pretty bird weary of all this?" he asked, tenderly. I The low reply was inaudible to all but the ears of a lover. With gentle-fingers he stroked her hair, and caressed her fair brow. What made his touch so danger- ous? After a while a servant entered the room, bearing rich goblets, and a silver pitcher which contained a cool, delicious beverage. Eleanor, while tasting it from the goblet that Egbert held to her lips, thought it must resemble the nectar indulged in by the gods A Long, long they sat together, until, at last-what made the lighA alternately so pale and so  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8397-00000017"/> dazzling before her bewildered eyes?  What made the fragrance of the flowers so wondrously sweet, and yet so oppres- sive? what made her respiration so rapid and tumultuous? what made the voice of her lover sound like rapturous, un- hallowed music in her ears? Alas 1 alas I We will drop the curtain, and pity the deluded girl l Oh 1 think of her fate, ye parents of youthful daughtersl think of her fate, and take a lesson to heart I Remember, oh I remember that ignorance is not in- nocence. Teach your children self-re- liance. The love of father, mother, sister, friends, has been forgotten. Alas I weep for the lovely Eleanor! "Oh I weep for the hour When to Eveleen's bower The lord of the valley with false vows came; The moon hid her light From the heavens that night, And wept behind the clouds o'er the maiden's shame. The clouds past soon From the chaste, cold moon, And heaven smiled again with her vestal flame; But none will see the day When the clouds shall pass away Which that dark hour left upon Eveleen's fame:" Such were the words-whether from her own thoughts or the warning voice of some ministering spirit who had. watched over her and bewailed her un- fortunate fate--Eleanor heard  as she awoke from  a .feverish sleep late the next morning. Whence they proceeded she knew not, but they brought rapidly and vividly to the mind of the bewildered  girl the recollection of what she was. Alas I unhallowed was the remembrance that blanched the quivering features of Eleanor, and caused her to close her eyes, praying in her despair, that she might never open them again. It is sometimes a cruel punishment to be obliged to con- tinue to exist! It is often harder to live than to die I Weeks passed away. Eleanor became pale and dejected, and was often found in tears. Egbert's friend showered upon her merciless sarcasms. "Do not weep yourself quite away, my gentle Niobe!"   she would say, in her pitiless voice. "Rachel weeping for her children, and refusing to be comforted, because they were not! ha I hal hal But, seriously, my pretty bride, is it your desire abso- lutely to disgust your liege lord and master? If such is your laudable pur- pose, you have certainly chosen the most effectual method. Bahl a snivelling, drivelling, weeping-willow of a woman I The best man in the world would hate a crying woman were she as beautiful as an houri, and versatile as Aspasia. And you know, my dear, that our ministerial husband is not exactly immaculate, not- withstanding his cloth. It was your bright eyes and rosy lips that he loved. He loved you in your joyful beauty, he will cease to care for you in your sorrow. I tell you he will hate you if you continue to be like those cherubim and sera- phim that continually do cry. If you do not cheer up he will leave you to return home in the best manner you can man- age it."  "Get home," murmured Eleanor, as if' a new hope had entered her bursting heart. "Oh could I but go home  Egbert has promised me that we shall be married this week, immediately upon Dr. Suydam's return, and' then we will. leave for home." "4-Nous verrons que nous verrons /" said Mrs. Jacobs, a strange smile lighting up her pale face as she left the room. How wonderful that " evil could dwell in such a temple" of perfect physical love- liness. For once in a way Mrs. Jacobs had uttered the truth. Eleanor plainly perceived that the minister was fast wearying of her unceasing grief. He told her one day that it would seem she had truly found this world "a vale of tears." He had removed her from the house of Mrs. Jacobs, and for a few days passed much of his time with her. Then his absences became long and frequent. Eleanor, while in his presence, tried to stifle her sorrow. It was a bitter strug- gle. Gaiety, cheerfulness, had departed at once and forever. She felt noW that   life was too bitter to endure, and that her   earthly prospects  were forever crushed. No mortal could have suffered more. She began to fade fearfully. In five weeks she looked as though a greater number of years had passed over her head-that once proud, erect, queenly head, now drooping in hopeless grief. At the door of her heart was written, in letters of scorching fire, Dante's inscrip- tion on the portals of the abode of the lost: "Hope which comes; to all dwells not here." Sharp lines began to show themselves on her fair face- "Those furrows which the burning share Of sorrow plough'd untimely there." Haggard, faded, grief-stricken  Fled forever were the rosy cheek and lip. The sparkling eyes no longer shorne; a' dead languor showed in her gaze, as though the ghost of departed joys looked out of each languid ball. Continually she re- peated to herself-"Here^nly refuge is to die!"Yet like many others who before her had trod the same thorny path, she never to her deceiver uttered an oral complaint. He could see the misery, and that he had, almost broken her heart; yet- ,' She never blamed him, never; But received him when he came With a welcome kind as ever, And tried to look the same." But she had now become less fascinating to Egbert. In less than three months her presence had become distasteful to him. Had she been but sufficiently de- void of heart so as to have evinced some cheerfulness, or sprightliness of manner she might have retained his favor for a little longer-we were about to say love, but angels forbid such desecration of the word, the holy word I Eleanor saw no one excepting her cou-   ; sin, and him far less frequently than r formnerly. She feels that he has destroyed her, and yet she dreads to be forsaken by him. He is not, cannot be her friend, and yet she feels other than he she has none-no one in the world. He soon ceased, even ceased to caress her when they met. After a few mouths a kiss from him became an unknown thing, a remembrance only of what had been. She had urged marriage upon him until his sternness frightened her, and she dared no more broach the subject. She plainly saw that her fate was sealed-- that the lawful wife of Egbert Cropper she now never was to become. Six months rolled round, and Eleanor knew that greater troubles were now to come. Her very soul almost died within her; and when, after a long delay and a violent struggle, she at last ventured to impart the intelligence to Egbert, he : received the information in ominous silence. Not many days after this he announced that he would soon be obliged to absent himself from Philadelphia for an indefin- ite period of time. ^ "Oh I Egbert," cried the terrified girl, " you do not intend to, cannot, shall not leave me now!"- She was almost beside herself with terror, and, sinking back on the sofa, gasped for breath. "Eleanor!" was the stem and only answer in return. "If you must go, you will soon retqmrn," she replied, pleading faintly. "I do not know; it is impossible for me to state definitely the term of my absence, or for me to anticipate what may prevent my coming at any given time;" and compelling her to swallow a glass of water which he coldly handed to her, he left the room.  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8397-00000018"/> CHAPTER IX.   EGBERT CROPPER hadrecently become acquainted with a young lady of fashion, Miss Julia Harwood-a tall, elegant lady whose beautiful dark eyes and distingue manner entirely eclipsed the confiding, distressed, lost Eleanor. In the society of this new flame the minister almost for- got the very existence of the girl whom he had so basely deceived. Almost every evening was passed in the society of the fascinating Julia. The young divine-- young in years, but old in iniquity-had been introduced into the family of Mr. Harwood by a mutual acquaintance. Eg- bert's family were highly connected, and f well-known affluence. His evil conduct Lad, of course, never reached the ears of his Philadelphia friends. Little dreamt they that within the limits of the city of Brotherly Love dwelt more than one soul lost by means of the undisciplined princi- ples of one whom they deemed as imma- culate in conduct as his stainless mouchohi'. Ah I none could be more irresistibly cap- tivating when he chose. The heart of the proud Julia Harwood was touched. For the first time she loved, and to love was with her the event of a lifetime. Not, like Eleanor's, was her's a facile, yielding, weak temperament. And Egbert? He had seen her but a few times when he fully made up his mind to marry her. She was wealthy, and of high lineage, and,' more than all, she was most beautiful. Neither timid, tame, nor weakl, she could be gained but at one price, viz., the price of his liberty, and that price he was determined to pay. Dearly did he prize this liberty; but to gain pos- session of this new love he was determin- ' ed, and thus he was fain to convert him- self as soon as possible into "Benedict, the married man." His marriage, he thought, would alter all things for the better. It would place him among con- nections of the highest social position. It would be a sort of pledge for his future   proper conduct, and a kind of respectable pawn for the past. By means of this mar- riage, finding that he was immediately tied, the parents of Eleanor might be per- suaded to take her home again. To know that she was safely located and kindly cared for would be a source of great relief to him. Ah! and then the beautiful, peer- less, imperial Julia I To think of having her all his own. Oh! the very anticipa- tion made him dizzy with rapture. One evening he entered Eleanor's room unannounced. She did not expect him, and he found her in tears. "Eleanor!" he exclaimed, angrily, "I am weary of this, completely weary. Six months of weep- ing have entirely exhausted my patience and-and-my love." Eleanor sank back, almost fainting. Her hysterical sobs, and the heavy foot- steps of Egbert, as he hurriedly paced the room, were the only sounds for sometime heard. The heart-broken girl wept until the fountain of tears seemed entirely ex- hausted. Every now and then a shudder- ing sigh shook her frame. A half hour elapsed in which no word was spoken; then Egbert ceased his unsatisfactory promenade, and seated ihimself at the ta- ble. "Eleanor; will yyu listen to rea- son?" The terrified, over-tried girl fell sense- less on the sofa. Not a ray of pity ap- peared on Egbert's face as he coldly re- garded her. He indifferently awaited her recovery. After some time had elapsed, with a sigh she opened her eyes. As she  beheld the form of her cousin herthoughts seemed to wander to happier days, she smiled, and whispered faintly - "Egbert, do you love me?" "Love you?"Pen cannot describe the intonation of contempt in which these two words were uttered I The hot blood rushed into Eleanor's face. She sat erect. What little spirit she possessed was touched to the quick.   "Egbert Cropper, send me home. I ask but one thing of you: Only make me a lawful wife, and send me to imy father's house. I freely promise never to seek your face again, Oh!" clasping her hands piteously, and gazing upon him with   wildly beseeching  eyes,' Only marry me! give me once more an honest name, and send me away from you." "And you really believed that I in- tended to marry you?" was all he said. "Believe that you intended to marry me! Great God! what else would have induced me to accompany you here?" Eleanor's voice and heart were falt los- ing their firmness, and her limbs were as though afflicted with ague. "There is nothing so easy as to be mistaken, Eleanor," said Egbert, in words so cold that they fell upon the heart like ice. "When I choose a wife she shall be a woman whom no man could-clandestine- ly decoy from the home of her parents. She shall be one in whose virtue I can place complete and unlimited confidence. When a woman forgets and fails to do her duty, when she strays from the right patli, she may be certain that a man will not be too strict in his own conduct." "In heaven's name, what mean you?" "Why, you suffered me to persuade you to elope with me; nay, not once, but twice you forgot your parents, your sis- ter, your honor. You must have known what you might have expected. "No-no-no I " she wildly ejaculated, "Ididnot; O God! Ididnot. Thatwoman declared that mamma was very ill; you, you hurried me into the carriage, to-" "You simpleton 1" exclaimed this ele- gant gentleman, " common sense, a mo- ment's reflection, a particle of that might have shown you the transparency and the danger of the plot. Listen! that woman, as you style her, is a   ." He bent down and whispered a word in her ear. She shrieked aloud; she wildly clasped her trembling hands. "Egbert I Egbert I you declared to me that she was a friend of yours." i               IF   The heart-stricken tones in which these words were uttered, startled, and almost touched the obdurate heart of the minister. It was but for a moment.' Again he bent down, and whispered a sentence. "Oh I great heavens I Egbert Cropper, you did not dare to take me to a  ," she cried, qnable to repeat the word, horror in her every aspect. "Yes, I did," he calmly replied. "You women are fools where you love. Perhaps there was a time when I might have married you. I believe I loved you very much once; but that time has passed, forever passed. We can henceforth be friends only." A dead silence ensued. "Oh!" she moaned in her breaking heart, " pitying Death I -come and take me to thy cold embrace; thou wilt be kinder than he who has destroyed me!" Strange that in such a scene Egbert's thoughts should have wandered to Julia. He was for some time lost in meditation, and without being aware of it murmured aloud: "I should like to see the man who could decoy Julia clandestinely from the, house of her parents!" "Who is Julia?" exclaimed Eleanor, involuntarily, but in a peremptory man- ner. Egbert looked at her in amazement. "Can she have divined my thoughts?" he asked himself, hardly knowing that he had spoken aloud. "Who is Julia?" repeated Eleanor. "A lady whom I knew once upon a time," he said coldly, and walked away, Paler became the already pallid Elea- nor. With closed eyes, rigid features, and tightly clenched hands, she seemed almost to have ceased to breathe. With woman's intuition she saw and knew her fate. After a long period of wretched silence, with a desperate struggle she forced herself to speak. "Egbert Crop- per I I plainly perceive that this Julia, whoever she may be, has supplanted Eleanor. This accounts for your contin- ued absences. Remember that when you  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8397-00000019"/> cast me off you destroy more than one life. I have no home, no friends, no money. Do not forsake me quite yet; wait a little while, a few months longer, and I shall be no more. Only, I beg you, take care of--  ," and the words died upon her lips; but again catching her breath, she whispered, "should it sur- vive its wretched mother. Your love is gone, and I can no longer live. Welcome, death I death t death I Oh, I am lost 1" Her distracted words and mien thor- oughly alarmed him. He went to her, he tried to soothe her. He even took her in his arms and told her that he still loved her, loved her fondly; that the story of Julia was but a fable, invented to tease her, and excite a little jealousy. She leaned her aching head upon his shoulder; she gazed upon him with a strange expression, she, was evidently scarcely sane. "Egbert, may I repeat a song to you?" she said, dreamily. This  consummate  hypocrite  softly kissed her lips, as he murmured, "( Yes, my beloved." Wildly sad, mournful, was the voice that whispered the following lines. Eg- bert, as he listened, found it in his heart to wish that he had not broken hers. "Mustit be? Then farewell, Thou whom my woman's heart cherish'd so long I Farewell, and be this song The last, wherein I say "I love thee well "Oh I if in after years  The tale that I am dead shall touch thy heart, Bid not the pain depart But shed over my grave a few sad tears. U For me, my days are gone; No more shall I in vintage times prepare Chaplets to bind my hair, As I was wont: oh 'twas for you alone. "But on my bier I'll lay Me down in frozen beauty, pale and wan, Martyr of love to man, And, like a broken flower, gently decay.1" A silence ensued after the mournful cadence of the closing line. Egbert caressed the exhausted girl. She seemed to realize that he was near her, was again kindito her, qnd that was all she seemed to know  At last she fell into a slumber, and when sixty seconds had run their   round upon the little French clock that stood on the marble mantel the minister laid the sleeping girl gently upon the, sofa. The next day Egbert again entered the sitting-room of Eleanor, bearing in his hands a fragrant cluster of violets. In spite of himself he had been haunted by the sad line of the poet- "And, like a broken flower, gently decay." Eleanor's faded eyes brightened some- what as she took the violets, and thanked him in a voice-as sweet as though he had not crushed the life out of her young heart. To his inquiries concerning her health, she gently replied that she was feeling much better. "All on account of a dream," she said, smiling, with some faint resemblance to former girlish vivacity. "Ah I I dreamed that I was once more at home, and that my father and mother had forgiven me. And, Egbert,"-hesi- tatingly, but with a singular absence of fear and jealousy that had formerly trou- bled her-" and, Egbert, I dreamed that you were married to Julia Harwood 1" "Julia Harwood!" he echoed, in utter amazement. "Yes; and it seemed to me that you loved her very much." Egbert, the consummate actor, was embarrassed, amazed, confounded. "Dreams are of but little account in these latter days," he said, at last, in a confused manner, that did not escape the sad eyes watching him. . "No,"' she replied, softly, "I am no believer in dreams, but I wish that a por- tion of this one, might come to pass, that my parents had forgiven me, and that I was once more at home." Inexpressibly affecting were her voice and manner. "Does Eleanor wish to leave me?" asked Egbert, tenderly. "No-no-no; but Egbert will soon leave Eleanor. Of that I am certain,- my heart cannot deceive me." "It does deceive you, Eleanor. I will not leave you while my presence can be of any comfort to you; while you need my care."   Strange that Eleanor's heart beat. no quicker at words that once would have been inexpressible joy and comfort to her. Strange that she was calm enough to wonder at her own apathy! A few days! passed on as usual, when, one evening, Eleanor, sitting sad and alone, was startled by a rap at the door. Opening it what was her astonishment to behold the woman who had aided in her ruin. She was accompanied by a gentleman, or, rather, one of the mascu- line gender who passed himself as such. At the sight of this woman Eleanor staggered and almost fell to the floor. "What is the matter, Mrs. Cropper?" inquired the insidious Mrs. Jacobs, en- deavoring to render some assistance. "I am not well!'"Eleanor gasped, scarce knowing what she said, and strug- gling to escape the touch of her visitor. "Where is Mr. Cropper?" inquired Mrs. Jacobs, with a manner as placid and languishing as ever. "He has not yet returned; he is out," she who was addressed as "Mrs. Crop- per" managed to reply. "AhI I regret his absence.  This gentleman wished to see him particularly. When is he likely to be at home?" "I cannot say." After a few more observations, both with her tongue and her eyes, Mrs. Ja- cobs took her leave, concluding it wisest not to thrust herself where she knew her presence would not be tolerated. As she went she wondered if Egbert had yet re- vealed her real character to their victim. The sight of this woman almost mad- dened Eleanor. She had been the assist- ing wheel that turned her to destruction. Oh, what a dangerous creature is a wo- man entirely destitute of virtue! Such an one rushes headlong and fearlessly on to ruin, involving many, innocent and guilty, in her 6wn misery. We wonder 3   from whom and from what. such can have descended. Rather from a source dark and unknown, than from that Eve who has been the mother of so many true and virtuous women. Alasl that such fe- male fiends as Mrs. Jacobs are allowed to cumber with their presence this fair earthI Such as she poison the minds and lives of men. Such women are hid- den. in crime. They cloak their vllany, and put on smiles to decoy the innocent into their black nets, in which, when once caught, they are forever destroyed. Their venom, says King David, lies hid- den under their tongue. They, are also well compared to serpents whose deadly poison utterly destroys. Eleanor thought many times of writing to her parents, but dared not hope that they would ever again forgive and re- ceive her. Her courage failed, her heart beat fast-she trembled when she recalled to mind the stern, emphatic language made use of by her father. In-fancy she wandered again to her little room at home, which she had forsaken t&amp; find supremest happiness, as she fondly dreamed. But what, alasl had been her portion e'ver since she had fled from the sanctuary of home? What, indeed, but griefs more bitter than "gall and wormwood."  Ohl the rapturous im- aginings of the young heart that has given itself to another I Wondrous strange and sweet are its dreams. They picture to themselves joys as sweet and lasting as the joys of Paradise. Oh, Sor- row! that such dreams should fade. Oh, Fate I that ' the trail of the serpent is over all." Alas, alas I the world, for some, changes into e dismal Sahara, where the weary travler finds not a single oasis upon which to rest his way- worn feet I Such is life; and yet we cling to it I  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8397-00000020"/> CHAPTER X.   VERY late one evening Egbert abruptly entered the room of Eleanor, and coolly said, "Here is my purse; it contains but a small sum; however, it is all I can at present spare. I am'compelled to leave the city to-morrow, and shall not be able to return for sometime. You had better make an effort to return- home." "Return home!" repeated Eleanor me- chanically. "You are well aware that my parents would not receive me. I will go to the house of your father, if you say so." Egbert bestowed on heri a keen, stern look. Was the weak-minded Eleanor about to turn sarcastic, rebellious on his hands?"Were you -to do that, I'd make you rue it forever," he said, in tones that froze the blood in her veins. "What am I to do then?" she help- lessly asked. "Prepare yourself for a-separation," he said indifferently. "I shall, probably, not see you again for a long time." Eleanor was too much stunned to give way to tears. The dreary night passed, and day dawned at last. The poor girl had never moved from her seat. Egbert awoke, and beheld her motionless, just where she had thrown herself the night before. "Why are you up so early?" he peevishy asked. He had been hoping to steal away while she still slept. "I have not been sleeping," she said, in a strange hollow voice. "Well, I am obliged to leave early, and will not be able to remain for breakfast. Good-bye, Eleanor. I shall take care you want for nothing." Despite his bravado, his heart troubled him as he looked at her. Eleanor's gaze was fixed  and  glassy. "Good-bye, Eleanor," he repeated, anxiously and hurriedly. She looked like one just risen from the dead, as she fastened her strange eyes upon him, and said, in a voice that   sounded far away, "Egbert, farewell for- ever!"           I He turned quickly and left the room, but never, to his dying day, did he for- get her look and voice as she muttered-- "forever!"After his departure she re- mained motionless for hours. No one came to inquire after her welfare, and she summoned no one. The sun was declin- ing towards the west before she aroused herself. A little circumstance restored her to recollection; a tone that struck her benumbed senses, and thrilled her weary heart. It was a voice in a distant room singing a hymn her mother loved: "Just as I am-without one plea, But that thy blood was shed for me, eslus, I come 1" Like a message from heaven floated those tones on the ambient air. She listened intently until the blessed sounds died away; then, rising she locked the door, and, falling on her knees beside the bed, offered up a prayer such as brings from the skies quietness and hope. She besought God to forgive her, and restore her once more to her father's house, then' to take her from a world which. was too dark for her to live in longer. No one was forgotten in her petition. Strangely quieted she arose from her knees. Exhausted from her long fast, she rang the bell, and ordered a cup of coffee, which she forced herself to drink. Another weary night came on. Oh! the suffering of the over-burdened, oppressed heart I We can no longer de- pict the cruel scene. It chills our veins to think of the sorrows of one who had, loved, as have many, many others, to their- destruction.  OhI that woman Would take warning from this case. It is not all fiction, but melancholy facts. Were it simply fiction, then our heart would not beat so strangely. When  a few months had   passed,   Eleanor's funds became exhausted. She had sold her watch, pawned her elegant- clothing and her jewelry. When her last ring was carried to the pawnbroker's, she felt now, indeed, her time on earth was short. Out of many, she had re- tained but one ring. It was one which had been given her by Egbert, two hearts curiously interwoven in braided gold- the only emblem of has lost love that she permitted herself to retain. She determined to leave her present abode, and on the morning previous to putting her intentions into execution, sat in her room listlessly looking over the daily paper. How suddenly, and at one fell swoop comes the blow that destroys our happiness I Thus, this announce- ment met the horror-stricken gaze of Eleanor, the announcement of the mar- riage of the Rev. Egbert Cropper, to Julia, only daughter of Livingston Har- wood, Esq., of Philadelphia. She fell senseless to the floor, and recovered but to rave for hours in wild delirium. When her senses returned, she found herself alone in her room. Renewed recollec- tion almost set her brain on fire. It was late at night before she gathered strength to rise; then she tied on her bonnet, put a shawl about her, and with a small bun- dle in her hand, left the house. Out into the wide, unknown streets, she walked on, not knowing, scarce caring, whither she went.  Her funds were quite ex- hausted; not a cent in her purse. On, on, on, forward, backward, she wandered, until bewildered, she sank from exhaus- tion on the steps of a fine stone mansion. Gazing apathetically around, she thought that the surroundings appeared familiar. Suddenlyitflasheduponhermind; itwas, it was the residence of Mrs. Jacobs. She started up to flee in terror, but sank down again through sheer physical ex- haustion. Suddenly the thought occur- red to her, and she murmured:-- "Per- haps she can tell me where he is. Ah I perhaps it was a mistake; after all, he may not be married. I will inquire; that cannot injure me now."   Dragging herself feebly up the spa- cious steps, she rang the bell. In a few moments the door was opened by the very genteel usher. "' Can I ee Mrs. Ja- cobs?"The man eyed her closely, but at length concluded to usher her into the reception-room. Eleanor shuddered as she entered, and sank helplessly upon one of the luxurious sofas. A short inter- val elapsed, and Mrs. Jacobs entered. Eleanor scarcely recognized her.  She had always beheld this woman with fear, who now appeared in a magnificent robe of garnet-colored velvet. Superb dia- monds glistened in her hair, and on her white throat and rounded arms. Her. red costume seemed to Eleanor like drops of blood oozing from her own heart. Mrs. Jacobs took the hand of the fainting girl, and, in her cooing voice, inquired if she were ill.. "Almost unto death," burst from the pallid lips of Eleanor. "You are suffering from exhaustion," was the composed rejoinder.   "Come, follow me!"She led the way to another room, where she bestowed Eleanor com- fortably upon a sofa, and compelled her to swallow a glass of wine. When the girl had somewhat recovered, she man- aged to murmur: "Mrs. Jacobs, I have called to inquire the whereabouts of Mr. Cropper. Be kind enough to inform me where he can be found." "And he is not with you?" interroga- tively said Mrs. Jacobs, whose serene countenance darkened visibly. "I have not seen him for a long while," uttered Eleanor, no longer able to sup- press her hysterical sobs. "Shall I reveal to you the truth?" asked Mrs. Jacobs, keenly regarding the grief-stricken girl. "Eleanor-he is married!" "I read the announcement in the pa- per this morning," said Eleanor, with strange apathy. "I wish to obtain funds to enable me to return to my friends." "1 And you intend to ask the means of Mr. Cropper, Eleanor?" iYes."    A  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8397-00000021"/> "I do not believe that he will furnish them, Eleanor. He has wedded a woman whom  he madly loves, and he cares nothing whatever for you or any one else." Eleanor suppressed a shriek, and quiet- ly replied, "I tknow it,-I know it; but what can I do? Perhaps he has some sense of manhood remaining, and will assist me to return to my parents." "But suppose that they refuse to re- ceive you?" "Then I am forever doomed to mise- ry 1" "Eleanor, I am not ignorant of Mr. Cropper's address, but he charged me not to give it to you. ' Iwill not be an- noyed by her,' he said. But, if you really desire to seek him, I will inform you where to find him. My advice is, go not near him; it will only expose you to repulse and mortification. Your parents, I am sure, will never receive you. Re- main with me, I will give you a home." The blood rushed into Eleanor's cheeks, then rapidly retreated, leaving them even paler than before. In a quick tone she said, "Let me first rather die4 a beggar on the street." She rose from her seat, and tottered to the door. Let me out; let me out; oh, let me out?" shrieked Eleanor. "Sterne's starling cried, ' I can't get out,'" said the strange woman. "Here is the address of Mr. Cropper. Call upon the reverend gentleman, do,; a bridal call would be -quite apropos,-very re- freshing, both to you and to himself. And do note down a description of the high-born bride I Oh I here, I have a trifle or two for her. She thrust into Eleanor's hand a card bearing the street and number of her cousin's residence, and the almost senseless girl staggered out of the house. ,Out upon the wide, unknown streets again. Where to go, sloe knew not. ' Alas I for the rarity Of Christian charity Under the sun. Oh t it was pitiful, Near a whole city full, Home she had none."   It had commenced to snow when Elea- nor again entered the street, but such was the distraction of her mind that it was some time before she discovered the fact. The weather had become bitterly cold, as is usual at that season. "Whi- ther, whither, shall I go?" murmured the unfortunate being, who had been so ten- derly nurtured. On, on, she walked, slowly dragging her weary self along. At last she fell against the steps of a de- lapidated house, which she afterwards learned was the home of a hard-working laundress. Feeblyshe knocked at the door. A hard-featured, but kind-looking woman answered the feeble rap. "May I stay here to-night? I am ill-I am very ill." The woman held the candle as near as possible to her, and peered into the face of the applicant. She saw something there that irresistibly appealed to her sympathies. "Yes, yes; come in, come in, poor cratur. - Ye are welcome to stay, if ye can put up with our poor 'commo- dations. We have no feather beds, sure; and we live moighty poor to entertain the likes of ye. You look so delicate and tender, that I'm thinking you won't rest well in this poor abode." "Only let me in!" pleaded poor Elea- nor. The rough but kind wolian "took in and cared for" the almost dying girl, whom, she declared, sote oce, "looked like a raal angel. Holy Mary, mother of God, an' it's true, she does care for ye. Whativer she is, she'll niver come to want, while it's meself that has a home." She proved to be the Good Samaritan, as have others. Eleanor, firmly determined never again to deceive any one, firmly stated the whole truth to her hostess, who, it would seem, determined never to do anything by halves, made her un- expected guest as comfortable as her scanty means would allow. Jeemes, her husband, was forthwith despatched for a physician, who, when he arrived, was in turn astonished at the beauty, elegance, and present situation of his interesting   patient. During the night Eleanor be- came the mother of a darling boy. After a long and warm consultation with her husband, the Irishwoman deter- mined to retain, and take the best of care of the sick girl until such time as she should have recovered. "And the Holy Virgin will reward us!" she piously con- cluded. The physician also became par- ticularly interested in his lovely and gentle patient. He privately sent stores of delicacies to Eleanor, and gave Mrs. Gallagher carte blanche at a neighboring provision depot. A load of wood was also sent to the house. "Don't ye talk of dy- ing," Mrs. Gallagher would say to Eleanor. "Yer friends will come to ye after a time. Upon me sowl, yez are the most perfect piece of wax-work me ould eyes iver beheld; and the man who would injure the likes of yez will be well singed when the d-- 1 gets him-arrah, now!" The physician inquired of Eleanor if she would permit his wife to call upon her. Longing, and yet dreading to mingle once again with the pure and refined of her own sex, from whose society she had been so long debarred, Eleanor gently replied that she " would be only too glad to see Mrs. Holland." The next day the Doctor's lady was announced. Full of kindness and sym- pathy she entered the darkened room, and leaning over the invalid, was about to address some gentle remark to her, when suddenly she fell back, with a startled exclamation, "O, is it possible 1 can it be her; no-yes," she cried as she recognized the lost girl, her own dear friend. "And what ails ye? Wad youi the lady intirely bereft of her senses?" and the Irish woman hurried the visitor out of the room. ' Fortunately Eleanor had sunkeinto a doze, and did not, there- fore, recognize the friend of happier days, Clara Seward,' now Mrs. Dr. Holland. Poor Clara I her sorrow was pitiful to be- hold. She cautioned the woman to take the best-of care of Eleanor, to whom, in her weak state, she dared not yet reveal   herself; and depositing a sum of money that her friend might want for no com- fort, she hurried home to communicate the sad and startling intelligence to her husband. Great was the surprise of Dr. Holland to discover in his reduced pa- tient the once affluent and elegant Elea- nor Cropper of whom he had heard so I much. "O Herbertl" said his loving wife, "it breaks my heart to see her in that house, and in that condition; brought up as she was in the lap of luxury, and now reduced to such misery." "The result of her own conduct," ad- ded her husband emphatically. They were at first inclined to write im- mediately to the parents of Eleanor, but concluded it advisable to await the fur- ther recovery of the young mother. As soon as practicable she was to be removed to their own home, and they could from thence communicate with her parents. It was three weeks before the Doctor considered his patient in a proper state to bear an interview with his wife. At the end of that time the anxious and impatient Clara found herself at the bed- side of- her who was once the happy Eleanor Cropper, and who was still her dearly loved friend. That interview we will pass over in silence-it can be bet- ter imagined than described. In a short time Eleanor nerved herself to write the following letter to her pa- rents : "MY DEAR PARENTS,--Feeling that I shall not survive the affliction which dis- obediefice has brought upon me, I make the feeble attempt to pen you a few lines ere I pass into another state of existence. Oh, my loving father and mother I how I could throw myself at your feet and clasp those dear hands in mine, and hear your trembling  lips pronounce the word- forgiveness. I should die much happier, but that is a boon I need not expect as I am ill, very ill, and may not live. "I know if you were to see me it would open the wounds afresh which have al- ready given you so much pain. "You can better imagine my situation  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8397-00000022"/> -and the cause of my illness than I can describe it. I am too feeble to say much, and my physician has forbidden that I should write a line;- yet I should not die happy unless I should receive a few lines from your hands, pardoning and once more recognizing your unfortunate Elea- nor. "I have suffered but too keenly since I left you-I, misguided, deluded girl, seri- ously regret the fatal step which led me on to ruin. "Yet I hope to enlist your sympathy, not for myself alone, perhaps, as I shall soon pass away, but for my innocent babe who is the offspring of a mother's weak- ness and a father's treachery. Oh, God I forgive an erring daughter's disobedi- ence. My child is a boy, and is three weeks old, and if you should forgive and forget the past and take him as your own, never tell him of his father's folly or his mother's shame as the' grave will cover all. Oh, father-mother--sister-fare- well! and let one pitying tear fall upon the cold earth which may soon cover the remains of a thoughtless, yet repentant daughter. I am now trembling from over-excitement. I am too weak to write much more; but I must once again plead for the little darling which is now nes- tling by its mother's side. It knows not of the gloomy, cheerless abode of its un- happy mother. You will hear all after I am gone through Mrs. Dr. Holland, my dearest friend and schoolmate. Clara has been with me, and by mere accident her husband is my physician, and they have been the most faithful and devoted of friends, notwithstanding all that has transpired. My last words are praying for forgiveness, and that you will not too sadly grieve over the fate of your lost ELEANOR." After sending the above, physically ex- hausted, yet mentally relieved, she sank upon the pillows wishing only to see her parents-and die I Clara showered upon her kind words and actions, until gently composed, she sank into a slumber quiet as that of a little child. As Clara Hol-   land sat watching the pallid face of her once blooming friend, what thoughts, what varied thoughts rushed into her mind. Only too years ago how bright were the prospects of her who now lay ,before her a broken-hearted woman. She compared the then fond attentions of Egbert Cropper with his present brutal- ity, and she exclaimed, "What is man that thou art mindful of him, or the son of man that thou visitest him? The Past and the Present. "The sad, the irrevocable Past," and the uncertain Present-uncertain in its effects-were " weighed and measur- ed" until she was ready!to say with' Solomon, "All is vanity and vexation of spirit." Nothing, beyond heaven, seemed substantial. The mind of Clara Holland was clear and unclouded. She had seen the unreality of earthly grandeur, the folly and hardness of the rich, and the misfortunes of the poor, and her purified soul admitted that there was nothing worth living for but Heaven; Heaven was the only means by which to secure interminable happiness in life-and that heaven was the pure thoughts and actions of mortals in this world. Clara was happy, with the happiness of one who, with heart and mind, unceasingly endeavored to do her duty to all the human family, even to the suffering being who lay be- fore her. Had she treated Eleanor Crop- per as so many women-would have done, there is no telling what would have- be- come of the erring girl. There are many who would never have acknowledged the acquaintance; nay, who would have spurned) a woman who had thus fallen  There are thousands of such false-hearted women, whose sins are as scarlet; yet they would fain appear to the world as though they were immaculate as wool. Alas I to say it, and yet there are women in the world who even rejoice to hear of the downfall of their sex. Clara Holland was a true woman; she encouraged the virtuous. upheld the unfortunate, pitying their misfortunes. Would to God that there were, in this sad world, a greater   number like her I Then there would be many a Magdalene saved from degrada- tion, who, for want of a kind hand, are plunging deeper and deeper into the vor- tex of misery into which one false step has plunged them.   Leaving Clara, in the midst of her own happy home; the pride and joy of a beloved husband, and Eleanor slowly recovering her health, we will review the present circumstances of the young min. ister.   CHAPTER XI.   EGBERT CROPPER had wooed and won the peerless Julia Harwood. She was his wife, and yet he was not happy. Al- ready her fascinations had begun to pall upon his depraved taste. The memory of Eleanor haunted him. She had dis- appeared as completely from  him as though she had gone to another world. He knew that by this time she must be either in the cold grave, or a mother. He knew also that he had left her destitute of means. He was a wicked man, and " - Conscience Makes cowards of us all." He feared that she had died. He was thrice a villain, yet he felt -some sympa- thy for Eleanor., His dark-eyed bride, with her ever brilliant fascinations, and her imperial will, alternately wearied and irritated him. Her very charms became irksome, her- caresses unwelcome. He had not been to the home of his parents since his marriage. He now proposed to visit them. His restlessness demanded continual change of scene; he desired to be ever on the wing.    - Yet the visit home had now a secret motive, though he scarcely confessed it to- himself. He determined to go more to discover whether Eleanor had returned to -her parents than to manifest filial , duty to his parents. He felt that to know her comfortably situated in her fathler's house would be to him an inexpressible relief. A few days after found them ar- rived at the homestead.! They were warmly received, and his father and mother could not but be charmed with the grace and beauty of their elegant daught- er-in-law, yet they felt indignant on ac-   count of poor Eleanor's terrible condition. On the day following their arrival it was announced to Mr. Egbert Cropper that a visitor, a gentleman, awaited him in the library. He entered the room, his non- chalent air deserting him, as he found himself face to face with the father of Eleanor. The old man gazed upon the young minister with eyes of fire; that gaze seemed to burn into the very soul of Egbert. It so happened that only a few hours previous to this interview had Eleanor's letter been received at home.' "Villain I dastardl I demand my child -where is my child?" "-I know not." "And care not, now that your purpose is accomplished"--and e'er the words had well escaped his lips, he discharged a pistol at the miscreant. The ball struck the fleshy part of Egbert's arm, who fell  to the floor more from horror than from hurt, and the noise brought the en- tire family into the r6om. The fattier of Eleanor, unable longer 4 to restrain the burning rage that filled his breast, levelled another weapon at. his brother. A gentleman who had rush- ed in, struck his arm upward crying, "Would you-become a fratricide?"The weapon discharged itself in the air. The same friend with greadfficulty, suc- ceeded in persuading the^ ged father to leave the house. The sight of Egbert extended upon the floor, pallid, covered with blood, and ap- parently lifeless, greatly alarmed his pa- rents. As for his wife, her enthusiastic passion had greatly cooled since the late carelessness of her husband regarding He   &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8397-00000023"/> her, nay, she was not without her suspic- ions, and she looked on, at last, with eyes more curious and inquiring, than griev- ed. The truth was, that Egbert had-been for once horror-stricken, and the life blood which curdled around his heart had not yet begun again to circulate free- ly. Servants were despatched for physi- cians, and three happening to arrive at once, almost came to a quarrel among themselves. The wound was found to be but a flesh wound, and the world was not yet to be deprived of Egbert, the elo- quent minister. Julia wearied him with inquiries as to the reasons of any one fir- ing upon him. The replies which she re- ceived were evidently unsatisfactory. At length her impatient husband remarked with considerable asperity, "Why, Ju- lia, you seem to attach much more im- portance to the discharge of the pistol, than to the wound received." "  Oh I " she answered in that careless, imperial, potential manner that was high- ly irritating to the invalid; "Oh! the one fact you know is intimately connect- ed with the other. The solving of the problem of the discharged pistol, would enable me to see daylight through your wound." "- Heartless I " muttered Egbert, but not so low but that the quick-eared girl over- heard. Her dark eyes flashed, the thin nostrils expanded. "Heartless, indeed I I wonder at your using that term. Mr. Cropper, I must say at once that I do not understand you. iReverend Sir, did you marry Julia Harwood, or did you marry her money? Your affection has cooled mightily since a certain ceremony was performed. Yours is a species of love quite beyond my comprehension. Per- haps, were weto part now, we Gould bbth be haptier." Of course, Egbert\ did not believe the wilful girl to be in earnest, yet these words cut him to the heart. In the lan- guor of illness he longed for gentle foot- steps, soft caresses, low words, sweet tones; these he never had from the brill- iant Julia. She entered his room rust-   ling in silks, and decked in jewels; the one grated upon his sensitive ear, the other dazzled his weary eyes. She flung down a book, or overturned a stool in her impetuous advance; she asked concerning his health, in her full unsubdued soprano voice, and often amused herself by loud- ly humming  some dashing .bravura. There were moments when the memory of Eleanor's gentleness and sweetness of manner came vividly to the mind of her deceiver. He was now competent to judge between the true and genuine affec- tion, such as his heart told him was Elea- nor's, and the flying fancy of the meteo- ric Julia. His parents were quite bro- ken-hearted. As soon as it was expedi- ent for Egbert to travel, they returned to their Philadelphia home, where once more settled in their elegant mansion, the newly wedded pair became daily more indifferent toward each other. Mrs. Eg- bert Cropper plunged with renewed avid- ity into the gaities of fashionable life. A young physician, Le Fevre, just return- ed from Europe, seemed very much dis- posed to renew his allegiance to the fair queen of society, as the beautiful bride was denominated. This ci-devant ador- er was found constantly at the side of the brilliant young creature, who had scarce yet ceased to be entitled to the interest- ing term of bride, and than whom no no- ble lady of blood and fashion could have been more utterly indifferent to her " liege lord and master." Julia Cropper, nee Harwood, could have been no sensible man's ideal of a wife. She was essentially a woman of society, of which she was the life and soul wherever she went. 'Her reputation for beauty, wit, and fashion was firmly established on a golden foundation.. Yea! wealth, like charity, covers a mul-s titude of sins. ,Even the caprices of Mrs. Egbert Cropper were pronounced charming by all excepting her husband. Brought up only to the exercise of grace- ful accomplishments, accustomed to ser- vile attendance and to every indulgence, occupied solely with herself, and her   gaities,: she was fundamentally but a "parlor companion."  Even Egbert, that worldling, asked for more than this in a wife. His egotistical nature demanded affection deY )ted even unto death. The love he requil ed he measured not by the scantiness of his own transient passion. He desired a love that would be willing to "die for him, or live but to prize him;" a love that would be satisfied with him only, ask for and prize but him alone through life and after death. "Wilt thou espouse my memory, love, When I no more can brand thee base, land trle in thy devotion prove, 'Mid scorn'd despair, and shun'd disgrace?" Let us now direct the mind of the reader to the family of Mr. Charles Crop- per. The hearts of the afflicted parents of Eleanor had bled afresh at the receipt of her sad and touching letter. For a time Mr. Cropper endeavored to steel his heart against his still fondly loved, but erring child. But the mother and sister yearned to fly instantly to aid and console their suffering Eleanor. Oh  since the advent of this trial how rapidly had whitened the locks of Eleanor's father, and mournful were the signs of trouble upon the patient face of her mother. The fawn-like -tep of the sister had changed. Ah I change was written upon all within the desolatedhouse. Gentle reader, if you are a gay, thought- less girl, r  nember Eleanor Cropper, and pray for aid and power to shun the quick- sands that engulfed that pitiable and for- saken woman. If you should be a parent, and wish to cultivate a blooming flower, you must destroy the worm that nestles near its heart. Nip an unwise affection in the bud. When it has once taken rootyour efforts to eradicate it will all be in vain. No parents were ever blessed with two more lovely and gifted daughters than were Mr. and   Mrs. Cropper.  Their whole hearts and minds had been ab- sorbed in the fuiture of their children-- in their education and their happiness. Behold the hapless, hopeless fate of the one, the oldest, whose destiny could   not but throw a Upas shadow over the career of the sister whom she so fondly loved, the youngest of the house, the pet, the plaything of the family. The serpent had entered this Eden, and pierced hearts whose pulsations were once so full of hope and joy. Disgrace and despair had usurped the place of innocent and unmarred happiness. Can it be wonder- ed at that their very souls and energies were utterly crushed under these circum- stances? Now how vain seemed much and many things that they had once so passionately desired I Each one was fain to exclaim: "It is the past that maketh my despair- The dark, the sad, the irrevocable past." AhI among the many melancholy re- cords of life, surely there can be no sor- row like to this: "Iivery woe a tear may claim Except an erring sister's shame," That is a woe too deep, too burning, too eternal to be assuaged with tears, how- ever bitter. * 'Tis a dark labyrinth-the human heart." Still the stern pride, the rigid principles of Mr. Cropper withheld him from send- ing for his unfortunate child. He yearn- ed to yield to her appeals. She was his child although she had "erred and strayed like a lost sheep." Should he, could he bring her back again, sinful as she had  proved herself, into her pure home? And with what an incumbrance! Here was misery, here was anguish I "If there 's a tear that's pure and sweet, That might not stain an angel's cheek; 'Tis that that pious father shed Above a duteous daughter's head 1" And if there are tears that fall like drops of molten lead upon the heart, it must be tears shed for a daughter's shame. The heart of Mr. Charles Cropper groaned with- in him, as one day he heard a little urchin shouting, with a pretty lisl, "Grandpapa, Grandpapa!"  AhM there are woes that make it, hard to live.. How varied our emotions under different circumstances I What a strange thing that what occurs  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8397-00000024"/> at one time, and under certain circum- stances, fills our heart with ecstatic de- light, while the same occurrence, taking place under different auspices, becomes the source of unmitigated woe I Thus   it was that the brave old heart of Charles Cropper shook and trembled within as the innocent little boy, in his glee, shout- ed "Grandpapa, Grandpapa!" for his mind wandered to a little one far away. # A   CHAPTER XII.   ONCE more we will glance at the couple whom the papers had announced as " the happy couple!"Their indifference was fast merging into mutual hatred. Egbert was frequently absent from his home, and Dr. Le Fcvre still continued devoted to the young wife, who seemed subject to frequent illnesses during these absences of her husband: Strange to say, for one, so really indifferent to him, Mrs. Egbert Cropper's health seemed always in a state of improvement when her husband was at home. Mr. Cropper was too acute to fail to notice the strange and increasing caprices indulged in by his lady wife; but, it would seem, he deemed them of slight importance; certainly of not sufficient moment to merit an appeal to words, for he passed them over in silence. Strange sensations concerning Eleanor troubled his mind. He had been made acquainted by Mrs. Jacobs, the woman in alternate white and red, with what had passed in her house. His visit to his home had made him aware that Eleanor had not returned to her father's house. The re- membrance of his cruelty and cowardice began to be a haunting demon to him; all the more unendurable because there was not a creature on earth to whom he dared speak about it, in whom he dared confide, to whose sympathies he dared appeal. Nay, he dared not even call for aid upon Him whoe- laws he had so daringly outraged. One afternoon in March, Egbert sat alone in his luxurious library. It was about dusk, and the dreariness without, occasioned by the new-fallen snow, ought to have enhanced by contrast the comfort   within. A cheerful fire burned in the grate. Luxuriously reclining in a velvet fauteuil, Mr. Cropper's poetical fancy lim- ned pictures in the glowing anthracite. He heard not the sound of the street door bell, nor saw the entrance of a female who elapsed a young babe in her trembling arms. "What do you wish?" roughly asked the footman, who was accustomed to see that massive door roll back only for the admittance of elegantly clad visitors, con- veyed thither in well-appointed equip- ages, whose approach was heralded by pompous attendants. "Is this the residence of Mr. Egbert Cropper?" uttered a sweet voice, which seemed to falter as it articulated the name. "'Tis supposed to be," answered the lackey, with an impertinent leer. "Say to him that a lady desires a brief interview," said the stranger in a firmer tone, and in a certain manner that the shrewd domestic saw at once could only belong to a lady indeed. "Will you please to enter, Madam?" "No; I will remain here until you de- liver my message." The man disappeared on his errand, and the stranger sank, apparently e,- hausted, upon a chair in the hall; a low half-stifled sob escaped her pale lips. "A woman with a child in her arms l" echoed Mr. Cropper, as: the servant de livered the message. His heart silently throbbed. What if it should be Eleanor I and yet impossible! Every day women begging with-children in arms assailed that grand mansion for charity; yet few had the temerity to ascend the marble steps. The area was generally the thea- c   tre of their appeals. Yet Mr. Cropper did not respond to this call. He meas- ured with slow steps the length of the apartment. 'Absorbed in thought he for- got the presenc of the domestic. For some time the lacIey stood in respectful silence: at length impatience got the ascendant of his manners, and slyly taking a book from the table he dropped it with a loud crash upon the floor. The noise of the concussion aroused his ab- sorbed master. "Well, sirrah!" he said. impatient of the presence of any human being. "The woman with the child in her arms-she waits your pleasure," said the man, demurely. "Go; inquire her business: and do not trouble me needlessly," he replied. The domestic returned to Eleanor, for she it was who sat trembling in the hall of her cousin's elegant mansion. "The master is after wishing to know your business," the man began as he reached her side. "His time is awful took up, and he can't be bothered grant- ing interviews to all the paupers that wants to see him." "I am no pauper!" said Eleanor, too weary and despairing to evince or feel much indignation. "I wish particularly to see Mr. Cropper. If he refuses me an audience, say to him that I shall demand one of his wife." "Whew!" half aloud ejaculated, the servant.   But he went upon his new -errand, saying  to himself: "Richard Holmes, here is a muss in purspective." t Mrs. Cropper ordered the woman to be v brought to her dressing-room. The ser- t vant stared, but proceeded to obey. Mr. Cropper had refused to see "a woman  t with a child in her arms," who anxiously h plead for an interview  with him, and t who, upon being refused, had demanded I to see his wife. This was enough   to t rouse the  curiosity of the fine lady t and   gained  for  Eleanor what she h might otherwise long   have sought in c vain, an admittance to the private room li of Mrs. Egbert Cropper, she who reign- M   ir ed in Philadelphia, the,acknowledged i- queen of beauty and of fashion. e  The trembling Eleanor was conducted - into an elegant apartment. At first the r blaze of light'dazzled her vision; 'but ere 1 long she became sensible that she was e within a splendid room, and in the' g presence of a superbly beautiful woman, t upon whom she gazed with strangely ex- e pressive eyes. They conveyed so much in their keen glance that Julia said,with a smile, "Well, what do you think of me?" "That you are very beautiful." Elea- r nor slowly replied, with a long drawn sigh. The spoiled beauty smiling showed two rows of pearly teeth. Here was a new species of adulation, and novelty was now about the only thing that could charm or interest Mrs. Cropper.  Half amused, half flattered, she curiously regarded her unexpected visitor. "Can I do anything for you!" she inquired in a kinder tone, than few so apparently far beneath her had ever heard from this proud woman., "'And you are %Mrs. Cropper, the wife of Egbert?" "Yes-I am that particularly fortunate and distinguished person," she replied in her silvery and sarcastic voice. Eleanor struggled to speak again. The, attempt 4eemed futile, the words died on her lips. . Among the many virtues of the- beautiful Mrs. Cropper, patience was not numbered. Her little satin-shod foot be- gan to tap the floor repeatedly. "Is that the amount of the sum of information you : wished to obtain from me?" she impa- tiently inquired. "I wish to present this infant to its fa- ther, and to ask him to provide for its helplessness." Up shot the hot blood to 4 the fair temples of the wife of the Rev.. Egbert. The mother of his child stood " there as pallid as a statue of death. A terrible silence ensued. Apainter should have beheld that scene. The one an in- carnation of despair, the other a roused lioness, a beautiful, outraged, avenging woman.  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8397-00000025"/> "Its mother?" she asked at last, in those suppressed tones that come from the depths of the heart. Eleanor's reply was eloquent, but inar- ticulate. She bowed her meek head, and put her lips to the brow of the sleeping infant. Another long silence. "This is a grave charge to bring against the Rev. Egbert Cropper. Are you fully prepared to substantiate the ac- cusation?" at length asked the wife. The tones of her clear voice were firm, her coolness was admirable. "I am his cousin, and his victim. This innocent creature is the result of his de- ception, and of my weakness," murmured Eleanor.   o Julia relapsed again into thought; then "rising," she mechanically drew alaoe shawl about her perfect shoulders. "Re- main here until my return," she said quietly, and with the tread of an em- press she swept from'the room. Again was the gentleman startled by a low knock on the door, and this time it opened to admit his lady wife. Oh what an interview was that which followed I We pass it over in silence. It far sur- passes our weak powers of description. Suffice it to say that when Mrs. Cropper at length returned to the room where Eleanor awaited her, it was to announce on the part of her husband a complete denial of the accusation. Was the light that gleamed in the dark eyes of the lady the result of a belief in this repudiation? Eleanor's over-wrought feelings occa- sioned a dreadful shock upon the receipt of this intelligence; and in agony, her brain whirling, her blood almost con- gealed, she staggered forth toward the elegant Julia to prove her story; then faltered, the babe dropping from her arms, f but caught by the lady. She at last faint- ed and fell heavily to the floor exclaim- ing, " O, base wretch." The white jew- eled hands that administered restoratives to Eleanor and the babe, did not tremble in the service. When Eleanor had some- what recovered she feebly rose, anxious   to leave at once the abode of this unfeel- ing and wicked man. "Mr. Cropper de- sired me to send you away," said his wife. "He at once pronounced you an imposter." "God is the witness of my truth," was all that Eleanor could utter in reply. Mrs. Cropper seemed about to make some further remark, but desisted. Evidently she had a secret purpose in view. She accompanied Eleanor to the door, thrust a purse in her hand, and bade her good- night. The poor girl descended the steps; bewildered, faint, she dropped the purse and dragged herself wearily along. After walking a long distance, she enter- ed the cold house, which she had so re- cently left, where she remained all night deprived of fire or bed. The reader may wonder at her deso- late condition, after having seen that she had met with friends. We will explain. The Irish family which had so charitably and opportunely befriended Eleanor, were about to remove to another residence when she had fallen into their hands. Her illness had delayed their removal for five weeks. That day they had conclud- ed to go. Eleanor had the address of Mrs, Holland, and was to go to her house, Clara desired to send a carriage for her, but Eleanor had left the cottage of her lowly friend before the arrival of the ve- hicle. She had a secret purpose in view, Her frenzy induced her to attempt to see Egbert. Her reception has been related. She left his elegant mansion, a despair- ing, a hopeless outcast. In her excite- ment she had for gotten both Clara's ad- dress, and whither her Irish friends had removed. Behold her dreadful positionl "Cold, bitter cold 1 No warmth; no light I L  Life I all thy comforts once I had; Yet here I crouch tlis freezing night, T will drive me mad-'t will drive me mad." How many women on God's fair earth  have shared the fate of Eleanor Cropper I 3 Trust not to the honor of man after you D have forgotten your own. Cold and bit- - ter was that night, while on the bare 3 floor lay the once beautiful Eleanor Crop-   per, shivering with her darling babe in her trembling arms. The day at'length dawned. A bright sun came out to relume the chilled world. It conveyed no gladness to the desolate heart of our heroine, but it beheld her subdued and quieted, although she con- tinued to shed hot, scalding tears. Was it the apathy of despair, or the spirit of resignation? Eleanor strove to think of her Creator-to remember only His omni- potent power, and his inscrutable pur- poses. She'believed herself reconciled to her fate, and willing to trust entirely to the mervy and wisdom of her God. The outer world appeared very beautiful upon this clear, cloudless morning. The calm, the serenity of nature aided to tranquillize the mind of the troubled girl as she open- ed her eyes and gazed out at the window and viewed the brilliant sun in all his meridian grandeur. Suddenly, as by the lifting of a curtain, the remembrance of the addresses of her friends returned to her recollection. Both the number of Mrs. Holland and of the Irish family flashed upon her -" like a wave of light." She arose from her crouching position upon the cold floor, and commenced her ] long and weary walk. In the course of L an hour she found herself at the door of E Mrs. Holland's residence. When she- l gained admittance, Clara was affrighted n at her appearance. Perceiving her ex- a hausted state, she forbore to question e the weary woman. Bearing her off into a warm, comfortable room, Eleanor was c put to bed, and she soon slept the sleep p of exhaustion-all the sweeter, because- T ere she closed her eyes a feeling of seren- cc ity, long unknown, had .entered into e her soul. She had seen her half frozen g: babe fed and cared for; he smiled up  ro into the face of Clara as though he was sa aware that she had saved his life, and re the thankfulness of Hagar, when she found he water, gushed into Eleanor's heart.   fa Is there a soul that refuses to sympa- m thize with the broken-spirited, poor, in- en jured Eleanor?   s there one that would ey   in not detest the hypocritical Egbert, and the false-hearted, insidious Sarah Jacobs? it There is something disgusting even in/ I. the name of Jacobs I ;e  Oh I is it not inscrutable why the A!- a mighty permits such women to live] i- Yet there is wisdom in all things; and s thus He permits the wheat to fall into the f same -field with the tares. It is said that. f the English have exhibited one mark of i- wisdom, energy, and virtue above all '- other nations. After so great, so dan- o gerous, so wasting a revolution as that of Cromwell, they seemed to rise, not like e Samson after he had lost the secret of L his strength, but like one who is made , virtuous by affliction, strong- by exertion, i and wise,by experience. Just so was it with our heroine. She had become wise r by experience.   Coleridge has said- "Experience is like the dead-lights of a ship, it only illuminates the way that is passed." Brought again into the companionship of a woman virtuous and strong-hearted as was her friend Clara, all that was good in Eleanor rose again into the ascendant. She determined to approach her parents like the prodigal son, willing to eat the husks, and to fall prostrate at their feet. "God   is very merciful to me," humbly said Eleanor, as she again clasped to her breast the infant that so lately had been near death. "I shall yet live to return and receive the'forgiveness of my par- ents." Some benignant spirit whispered the comforting thought that her letter to her parents would soon be acknowledged. This reviving belief was fulfilled in the course of a few days. Eleanor clasped the letter from her mother to her full and grateful heart, and in the privacy of her room  devoured the contents. It was a sad, but a forgiving epistle, and as she read each line gave renewed strength to her qver-tried heart. The sweet, pale face, to which  an expression- of deep  melancholy had become habitual, bright- ened as she read, and tears, to which her eyes had at times been strangers, relieved  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8397-00000026"/> her oppressed brain. A balm as of Gilead was shed into her heart. The letter contained a heavy draft for Mrs. Gallagher from her mother. Eleanor, with. glad tears in her eyes, put it into the hands of the astonishedwoman. "You shall have more-you shall have more," murmured the grateful woman, "money can never repay your kindness to me." And moneyit was difficult to prevail on Mrs Gal- lagher to accept. She was, however, at length, prevailed upon to appropriate the sum to the educational advantage of her children. '"I shall ever feel under many obligations to you," said Eleanor, "I am going home," how her sad eyes brighten- ed at the word--home. "Probably we shall never meet again, dear Mrs. Gal- lagher; but, believe me, you and yours shall never, never be forgotten." She conveyed her precious letter to Clara for her perusal. "Eleanor!" said that excellent lady, "I rejoice with you that you are going home again; but ever remember that, had your parents never received you, you should ever have claimed a home with me. .Cheer up, my dear; you will be happy'yet!" "No-no-Clara; never happy.   I must learn, as one writer expresses it, to live without happiness. But, by the grace of God, I humbly hope to do my   duty in whatever state of life it may please Him to call me. Happiness, Clara, is not the portion for such as I am. - I have done wickedly, and must abide the penalty. Unmindful I wandered from the right path, unheeding, the many warnings of my friends, and the secret monitor within. Oh, Clara! my friend, I thought that Egbert was a minister so pure that he, could not think evil, far less practice it. But I was deceived." The friendsumingled their tears-tears of grief for the past, and of hope for the future. After some time Mrs. Holland rose to prepare to go out. It was a very cold, disagreeable day, but Clara had some visits of charity to perform, and although she felt greatly inclined to re- main with her guest in the warm, com- fortable room, yet she was one who never neglected duty for personal convenience, and cheerfully donning her street attire, she was soon on her way. Clara, with her steadfast principles, her clear judg- ment, her cheerful temper, her unfailing sympathies, was just the wife for a phy- sician; and every day, in his inmost heart,' Dr. Holland blessed the good Being who had bestowed upon him his excellent helpmate. Cheerfully they walked the path of Jife, mutually assist- ing, sustaining, and blessing each other.   - CHAPTER XIII.   ELEANOR, unfortunate Eleanor, was evidently somewhat unsettled in mind. After Clara had left the room she sat for a long time with her fair head resting on her hand. How full of woe was the ex- pression of her young face I At length she arose from her seat with a sort of shuddering sigh, wrote a note and put it upon Mrs. Holland's work-table.  The, purport of this note was to announce her intended departure for the home of her parents; should they refuse to receive her, she dared not think of the conse-   quences. Ten thousand thanks were ex- pressed for'the unexampled andlunmerit- ed kindness of Dr. Holland and his wife, and a myriad blessings invbkld in their behalf. The paper bore'evi'denee of the tears it cost the writer.   ' : Eleanor robed herself, wrapped up the child, and started for the depot. She felt her blood chilled before she reached her destination. She purchased her tidket and entered the car. It was late in the after- noon and she did not reflect until after she was seated that it would be farin the night   before she could arrive at her long desired home. But a sort of contentment relieved her mind as she repeated over and over to herself, "I am going home-I am going home!"   This was the burden of her soul's song as the locomotive rapidly hur- ried the passengers over the ground. She had been sitting quietly an hour or two when a sudden fear entered, her mind, the fear that she might be recog- nized. Rapidly her glance took in the inmates of the car., In an instant she beheld and she recognized a form that made her heart almost cease to beat. It was Julia, the beautiful wife of the min- ister-the cousin and the deceiver of our heroine-the absorbed Julia who saw not Eleanor, nay, who saw no one in the world save him who sat beside her; nay, again, beheld not him even, for her dark eyes drooped, and a warm 'flush mantled her cheek. Her hand was clasped in his; this Eleanor could not see, nor could she hear the words his lips were murmur- ing; these words were inaudible to all ears save those of the deluded woman who sat beside him. The instinct, the intuitive knowledge of a woman's heart, told Eleanor that those lips, that attitude, that reception, could breathe, could mean, could receive but one language--and that language was love. Eleanor, who could see Julia plainly, and whose companion was almost hidden from her view by intervening figures, thought, of course, that manly form could I belong to none other than Egbert, the F husband; he alone should dare to look i thus upon the wedded Julia. "Yes; it 1 is he," murmured her beating heart, with  accelerated pulsations. How benumbed became her limbs, how her brain whirled I E But Eleanor was mistaken. It was not 1 the Rev. Egbert Cropper who now sat ] beside the brilliant JuliaI Who then could be journeying with his wife? Ye c pitying angels! it was the young physi- f cian, Le Fevre. Misguided, deluded, miserable Julial Here was the woman s ,of wh'ose immaculate principles Egbert s Cropper had so lately boasted, "I should d L   l like to see the man who could decoy Ju- lia from her father's house 1"Egbert had  once said to his cousin. Had he but been "' in presence there,'"to him it might have been said, "Behold the manul" Choose between these two, oh, ye critics of virtue I Who was the pure? who the impure? Eleanor, not wishing to be re- cognized, turned away, and drew her veil more closely over her face. The hours fled, as hours will flee, and they arrived at their destination. The heart of the- young mother beat strangely: so near home, and no one to meet her ; she who once was sought after, flattered, admired I lNear home at last, and no one to greet her; she the beloved, the prized, the treasured of many hearts, but now so desolate I She left the car, and with her burden in her arms, commenced her slow pro- gress. The weather was intensely cold, and Eleanor was still weak. Walking on, on, she at length found herself near her father's house; she tried the' gate which opened on the lawn; it- was locked.   She walked on further, and obtained a view of the place where she had met Egbert. To her excited fancy it seemed as though she could behold the very tree beneath which they had sat when she had suffered herself to be be- guiled bythe serpent's tongue. She sank to the ground overcome by her feelings, by sad recollections, by cold, and by fatigued As she thus crouched in the snow, sae was approached by an old man. "What do you here at this late hour on this freezing night?" said he, bending down to obtain a view of Eleanor's face. "My home is near this city," replied the girl; " but I fear to venture to my father's house, although now so near. The nearer I approach, the more my fears assail me." "You appear young and delicate. Rise, do not remain quiet, inactive. You will freeze if you do not exert yourself." The infant wailed, and/would not be stilled. "A child, too!" exclaimed the strange old man.   "What could have driven you out at this time, and in such  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8397-00000027"/> weather? The veriest wretch deserves shelter on such a night as this!" "Misfortune, disobedience, -have de- prived me of a home," replied Eleanor, feeling compelled to speak she knew not how or wherefore. "Have you a father, child?" "Yes; and he dwells not far distant from where I am now perishing I But, alas I I fear, I fear to approach him." "You must not fear to humble yourself if you have been disobedient." "I am willing to become anything if my father will extend to me his forgive- ness." "Go; seek it l" he said, extending his arms, and then speaking in an oracular manner, he repeated these lines: "Daughter of the stranger, would'st thou take O'er you blue hills thy lonely way To reach thy still and quiet home, Along whose banks the west winds play- Let no vain dreams thy heart beguile, Oh I seek thou not the fountain's isle. "Lull but the mighty serpent king, Midst the grey rocks, his old domain- Ward but the Cougar's deadly spring, Thy steps that home's green shores may gain; And thy bright cottage, when all is past, Shall vainly meet thine eye at last." These beautiful lines of Mrs. Hemans were so mutilated and so incomprehen- sibly recited, that Eleanor had much ado to recognize them. The harmless lunatic departed, seemingly forgetting the pres- ence of her to whom he had been speak- ing. He had evidently escaped from the asylum, and was also a wanderer on this cold night. Eleanor cheered up, she knew not why, gathered up her waning strength, and proceeded on her weary way. It was past midnight when she reached the home of her happy girlhood; A freezing misty rain had commenced to fall. A dim light shone from her father's hall. ' Elea- nor was completely overpowered. She sank on the steps and almost ceased to breathe. She could only articulate, "Thank God, I am even here," and she pressed her cold lips to the marble steps. "If I were now to die, my spirit would   pass more happily away to know that I am so near my mother's arms," and here I leave my babe. Within the house the family had not yet retired. Since the disappearance of the eldest daughter, sad, nightly vigils had been kept by the old couple. The r*n had now commenced to fall rapidly, the temperature of the weather having become somewhat less cold. "What a dreadful night-!" said Mrs. Cropper shivering,- although the Liver- pool coal in the grate warmed and illu- mined the room.  "The storm  has come up suddenly; a few hours ago the moon shone brightly, and now how it rains." Mr. Cropper merely replied with a melancholy shake of the head. "Oh, dear!" sighed his wife, " how the wind blows!" "Yes," replied the husband, "these rapid and stormy changes that nature undergoes, truly depict the stories of our lives." "You speak truly I These storms of blustering winds and wintry rain fill me withl melancholy forebodings. My dear, lost Eleanor!" she added hesitatingly, anxiously reading her husband's counte- nance, "My dear, lost Eleanor!- Ah I would I knew where she is to-night." A silence ensued. Mr. Cropper rose, and slowly paced the room;- he suddenly paused behind the chair of his wife, placed a hand upon her shoulder, and said: "Anna, I can no longer endure this suspense, this misery, this 'separation. To-morrow we will leave for Philadel- phia, and bring the wanderer back." Mrs. Cropper clasped his hand and drew it over her eyes; tears of mingled pain and gratitude prevented herspeech. "I will go and examine the appearance of the weather," said the iunhappy, but proud old man, still too proud to reveal how much he was affected. He went to the front door, and for a moment felt not the driving rain. While casting his eyes about he beheld on the steps the figure of a human being. He startled; he also thought that on such a night the , *     poorest creature on earth ought to be housed. He went into the room exclaim- ing: "Anna, here is some poor soul exposed tz all the tempest. Prepare something, while I bring her in, for if my eyes de- cOivWq e not, it is a woman." Mrs. drojper hastened to perform the charitable purpose, while her husband descended the steps towards the crouch- ing figure. At his approach it held up a trembling hand, and in a feeble voice murmured: "Forgive- forgive-ere I die!" Oh, merciful God! did his ears deceive him? or was not that the voice of his child, the voice of the erring, lost, but still be- loved Eleanor? His heart throbbed; the strength of a Hercules seemed to have come to him; he gathered up in his arms the stray lamb with her burden, and bore them into the house. He laid her upon a sofa; she was again at the desired haven-at home; but Eleanor was insen- sible of it-she had fainted. They took the infant from her arms, and amid a death-like silence administered restora- tives and changed her wet garments. Gradually Eleanor came to herself; at first her mind wandered, she evi- dently knew not where she was, and piteously begged of them not to detain her, but to aid in sending her home. She murmured, '"Oh, why did I leave my home, disobey my kind, kind parents, and bring their gray hairs with sorrow to the grave?  Why break an only sister's heart and mantle her fair cheek with shame? O God, forgive Thy erring child?"Opening her eyes slowly, and with a dreamy look, she cast them around the room; then started up, and reclining, exclaimed, "Home! home I am Ham I here?  No; yes-it is, it is, my own sweet home.' Oh  home of my inno- cence and of, my brightest thoughts. And-my babe; where is it?"; looking around. The mother, who had held the babe in her arms silently, for her grief was too great for utterance, held the infant near T,   her. She passionately kissed it, while the aged father, bursting with profound- est grief at the wreck of his child, fell on her neck, exclaiming, "Eleanor, my own sweet child, you are home, forgiven, and shall still be loved and cared for." With a sweet, yet mournful smile, Elea- nor threw her arms around her father's neck and kissed his mournful brow; while her mother, with the babe, sat quietly by her side, the tears, like rain; falling " without measure." Instantly a figure presented itself-it was Emelia. With one uncontrollable burst of anguish she threw herself upon the bosom of her long absent, but still beloved sister. "Oh! dearest Eleanor!" was all she had power to say. Eleanor returned the simple words, "My sister, my sister, my own sister!"They mingled their burning tears and mourned the past. The great blessing of forgiveness had been accord- ed to her-that, at last. She was again at home. The whole family now aroused, the dawning hours beheld them at last reunited, if not happy. In the morning Eleanor awoke in her own room. Her lacerated heart could not be sufficiently grateful. The purity of her girlhood seemed to have come again. It was difficult to believe that she had, indeed, been absent so long. Nothing seemed changed in this dearly loved home. Her canary was still in its little cage; it did not sing on that morning, but jumped from side to side as though conscious and glad of her return. Day by day Eleanor improved in health and appearance; yet a visible melancholy had marked her as a prey. Her boy, whom she feared would be an unwelcome guest, became the pet lamb of the house- hold.' They were far too wise and too good to visit so speedily on its innocent little head the sins of its parents. The world would do that goon enough. Mrs. Cropper inquired the name of the little unfortunate. "He is not yet named,!' said Eleanor, turning pale. ' "My own kind mother, I wish you to name him, and to adopt  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC8397-00000028"/> him as your own. I shall not long sur- vive." Mrs. Cropper sighed as she endeavored to dispel these gloomy fancies; fbut Eleanor remained silent and unconvinced. She felt that she was not long for this world, and she could not regret it. "Life is so sorrowful here; oh I it were swelet to escape it at last." All that she had lived of late to effect had been now ac- complished. Her babe was in the hands of those with whom she would best like to leave him. Her peace was made with her parents, and with her God-into His hands she longed to commit her spirit. Of this she spoke but little, perceiving that it only distressed those about her. After -due discussion it was concluded that the child should be called Frank Dorson, the name of her mother's father. We will now, for a season, leave Elea- nor in the peaceful enjoyment of her home, and the society of her parents. Returning to Philadelphia we behold the consternation of Clara Holland, when she   - found that Eleanor had again disappear- ed. She had hastened home. Not a L sign of her friend was to be found, ex- ; cept a short and incoherent note. She mmediately penned a letter to Eleanor, directed to the care of her father, and anxiously awaited a reply. In a few days she received the welcome intelligence of Eleanor's safe arrival and happy recep- tion at her father's house. "Ah!" thotight Clara Holland, " the upright in heart are not always to suffer. They who put their trust in God shall be brought out of all their trials." And this tried and true friend sincerely rejoiced with Eleanor; for the friendship of Clara Hol- land. was that of the purest and most en- during description, alas! rarely to be met with in this weary world. The good news was also conveyed to the poor Irish woman, who had so opportunely befriend- ed the unfortunate girl; and she was as ready to rejoice with those who rejoiced as she had been to weep with those who wept.   CHAPTER XIV.   ONE morning Philadelphia was aroused by a piece of startling intelligence-the wife of the Rev. Egbert Cropper had eloped with Dr. Le Fevre! Mortification and rage contended for mastery in the bosom of the minister. Tenderness he had not recently felt to- wards his guilty-wife; his heart was not so much wounded by her elopement as the public scandal it brought upon him. He feared the gibes of society, the finger of derision pointed at him. But he soon fbund that their seemingly irrevocable misfortune had only served to add to his popularity. Society pitied the outraged husband; lovely women pitied him, and could not sufficientlydcondemn the guilty wife. Consolations abundant, substan- tial, unceasing were heaped upon him; he was in danger of something beyond mere tokens of sympathy. Female homes and hearts were thrown open to him.   Gentlemen who wear a white necktie gain much sympathy when misfortunes over- take them. But the distress of the family of the ruined wife was pitiable to behold. The: aged father seemed bowed to the grave with grief; the invalid' mother seemed smitten by the hand of death. Julia had rushed into ruin. -Egbert had not imposed upon her credulity when he had invented the tale that the stranger with the infant was an impostor. Julia had from the first believed the story of Eleanor. Not for an' instant had her husband succeeded in deceiving her. That night, the witness of his heart- less conduct had sealed her fate. On his head fell the onus of her sin. "l When I leave my husband, I forsake not man but a devil!" she had said. The minister could. now compare the two women. Ju- lia, of whose steadfast principles he had   boasted to the gentle Eleanor, and she who had loved him better even than her life. Now the conscience of Egbert Crop- per commenced its work. Restlessness pursued him by day and by night I Ad- ulation, so undeserved, maddened him. He hurried away from Philadelphia. He travelled everywhere, but the recollec- tions of Eleanor and the infidelity of Julia haunted him. He could not close his eyes but she came to him in dreams. Waking or sleeping his cousin never left him. She never accused, she never criminated him, but her piteous eyes made his very heart ache with madden- ing pain. He was wretched. Oh, the conscience, the guilty conscience! The hell into which all such men fall! Truly, there is no peace for the wicked. His parents, too, how wretched were they I! Disappointed in all that pertained to their idolized son, they asked but to close their aged eyes in death. They no longer believe him to be a guiltless man; the scales had fallen from their eyes. Six months of sorrow such -as this put an end to the earthly sufferings and existence of his mother; death happily relieved her of the burden life had be- come.      - Egbert traveled far and wide, thus a long period had elapsed after the death of his mother before the melancholy tid- ings had reached him. He hastened home to, his inconsolable remaining parent. The poor old man I In all past troubles ;he had had the blessed comfort of the presence of his brother Charles. Now they were divided, even by the hand of his only son. Egbert's deed had des- troyed the two families. And in the eyes of the world, Eleanor was considered the most guilty, the irrevocably lost of the two.  After Egbert's arrival he heard of Elea- nor's return home, and of the quiet, good manner of life she led. Those who had seen her described her as possessing a saintly appearance. Egbert longed to see her. He acknowledged to his proudheart that to obtain her forgiveness would give   him more peace of mind than ought earth could afford. But he darednot approach her. In dreams she came to him    still, and almost distracted him by her moon--  light, despairing eyes.- He departed for Europe, thinking that a wide sea of waters rolling between them would stay the sight of the nightly vision. But con- stant as death was the beautiful, unearth- ly visitant I "Alone I Oh, no; I am not now alone; Forever with me is a shape divine, Which my fierce soul pursues from zone to zone, And knowledge of its living truth is mine; 'Till of my heart Its image forms a part, Immortal as yon stars, which silent shine. O beauteous comrade I Shadow, which I call From thy more beauteous substance, at my will, Brief is the spell, and yet to me 'tis all That gives me strength stern duties to fulfill, Herself in vain My worship would disdain; Her charm is mine, altho' her scorn might kill 1" In vain he wandered from scene to scene. Memory, conscience pursued him wherever he went. Like the author of the above sad lines, he was tempted to perpetrate suicide. The poet died by his own hand, but the minister lived to endure still greater remorse. While en- deavoring to drown sorrow in the gay scenes of Paris, a letter reached him giv- ing intelligence of the dangerous illness of his father. He immediately sailed for e America. Oh, that long miserable voyage I It seemed interminable to the wretch- ed man. He had been at home not a day, when his aged, broken-hearted par- ent breathed his last. He died with words upon his lips that sunk like shafts of iron into the heart of the young man. "Repent, Egbert," murmured the hollow voice of the old man. "I die broken- hearted by your evil conduct, as was your mother before me. Repent, and seek forgiveness of God, even as I accord you mine." The hero of our story felt as though death would be a great relief to him as these piteous words fell from the cold lips of his dying father. Egbert Cropper followed his aged father  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC8397-00000029"/> tod the grave, and would gladly have laid himself down in the damp vault which, contained the senseless clay of his par- ents. But, like Cain, he was to be cursed for his sins. The tortures of conscience pursued him. He who has injured a fel- low being needs not to pass into the other world for torture. This life often affords both punishment to the guilty, and atone- ment for those who have suffered! When the will was read it was discov- ered that a large portion of the property had been left to the son of Eleanor. Al- though this considerably curtailed his income, yet Egbert offered no' objection; indeed, he thought that this act of jus- tice executed by his parent would some- what assuage the tortures imposed upon him by a remorseful conscience. But he was mistaken. The very fact of existence was a torture to him. We will leave him, writhing in the halls of his father, and turn to another scene. Three years had passed away, Eleanor had become a pure woman,..and a balm had been given to the wounded heart. One fine morning in spring she entered the grounds whence she had eloped with Egbert. A servant walked beside the little Frank who clapped his hands and gabbled at all he saw, evidently conclud- ing that everybody and everything had 1been created for his comfort and his especial diversion. The mind of Eleanor reverted to the past. Here was the scene 'of her trioa and of her temptation. Deep waters were again stirred in her heart, although she had often since her return visited these grounds. Rousing from a fit of deep abstraction, she noticed a per- son seated at some distance. The crea- ture was evidently in distress. Her dress had once been of good material, but was now worn and discolored. Something withheld the charitable Eleanor from ap- proaching this object of pity. "How strange it is," thought she, "whenever I see a person in distress I always wish to aid them, but this person seems to strike terror to my heart." She then   called to the servant, and prepared to re-  turn home.   i "There is a woman ma'am, and looks as if she was crying. She is the most wretched lookin' cretur I ever saw in my life," said Jenny, the nurse. "Did you approach her?" inquired Eleanor. "Close enough to see her, and she look- ed at you, ma'am, and extended her hand, but you did not appear to notice her. "I I caught a glimpse of her face, and it appeared to recall some strange, unwel- come memory. I did not care to look again." They left the place and wended their way home. As they were about entering the house, Jenny glanced back, and be- hold, the forlorn woman had followed them. Jenny looked at Eleanor, whose absorbed face deterred her from attract- ing her attention to the circumstance; and, soon busied with gossiping with her fellow servants, the fact escaped her rec- ollection. During the afternoon the tingling of the front door bell was heard. Jenny happened to answer the call, and now stood before her the woman whom they had seen at the foot of the hill. "Is-Miss Eleanor Cropper at home?" "Yes-an' what is it the likm .of yez wants of her?"  "I wish to see her for one moment." Eleanor was called, she came and was astonished to behold the apparition, of the morning. "And this is Miss Eleanor Cropper?" questioned the woman. "a Yes--can I do anything for you, my good woman?" she answered softly. "You can; I have come to beseech your pardon for my crime, my sin toward you," said the woman in a trembling voice. "Toward  me!"  repeated Eleanor. "Surely you mistake. I never before be- held you, that I am aware of." "Do you not recollect her who was en- gaged in decoying you from your home?" Eleanor started, an almost inaudible "Yes " escaped her pallid lips.   "I am she whose false heart aided and abetted your attempted destruction. Ever since I turned you from my house in Phil- adelphia, I have'become more and more unhappy. Misfortune has pursued me; now, no one can be more miserable than am I." "I pity you," burst involuntarily from the lips of our heroine. "Pity me, me," echoed the surprised, wretched woman, to whom human sym- pathy was an unknown thing. Eleanor took the outcast into her own room. Food was placed before the fam- ished woman, and amid tears of gratitude * and contrition she sobbed. "Oh! you are an angel I I, who have injured you beyond repair, have come to you hungered, and you have fed me. On that dreadful night when you came to my house in the city, you had no money, the " filthy lucre" was abundant with me, yet I gave you none. Can you, will you forgive me?" "It ill behooves me to institute myself a judge," answered Eleanor meekly. "I have freely forgiven all of my enemies, even as I hope to secure that priceless boon from the Almighty! Turn to Him, Hisl everlasting arms will never fail you. Remember that those who seek to destroy others, succeed thereby in bringing des- truction upon themselves." "That mercy I to others show, That mercy show to me." continued Eleanor pathetically. The eye of God is awake to every thought and every act of the beings who people his worlds. Through eternal changes his vigilance sleepeth not, For a time the wicked may flourish as a "green bay tree," but at last they will parch up as the scorched grass in the burning heat of summer! Ahl would we but give Him all our love and faith, how far, far happier would we be! Eleanor sent her enemy away less des-  pairing, and with the means to render herself comfortable. A well of gratitude was opened in that wicked heart. Months rolled round, and Eleanor i   heard no more of her. Qne afternoon she went out for a drive with her mother, About six miles from the city they beheld a funeral train issuing from a cottage on the road side. An old woman, whose hair was white with the frost of many winters, stood impotently weeping in the door way. Eleanor ordered the coach- man to draw up until -the procession should have passed.  The body was borne away to its long home; Eleanor followed its disappearance with a strange interest. "Who is dead?" she said at length, somewhat abruptly, turning to the weep- ing woman in the door-way. "Sarah Jacobs," was the unexpected reply. A chill ran through the heart of Eleanor as this name fell upon her ears. "Did she ever live in Philadelphia " inquired the astonished girl. "It was there she lived for many years," answered her mother."  "Qh I you Egbert Cropper!" cried the old wo- man, throwing up her arms toward heaven. Eleanor almost shrieked aloud, but with a violent effort restrained herself. "He, God forsake; he destroyed her, then abandoned her to her fate. Reck- less she became, and wicked she lived, and you see the result-an untimely grave! Woe's me! woe's me 1" and the speaker dropped upon a chair, covered her face with her apron, and rocked her- self to and fro, overwhelmed with grief. It was some, moments before Eleanor could speak again. What a terrible les- son was this! A mental prayer of grati- tude for her own redemption ascended from her overflowing heart to heaven. "Had she parents?" at last she inquir- ed in a trembling voice. "I am her mother, her father has been dead a long while," said the old wo- man, uncovering her face, and articulat- ing with evident difficulty: "and but six months ago she came home distract- ed, and here she died." "Did-did--her deceiver-was he not gware of her illness '"  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC8397-00000030"/> X"Don't mention him' don't mention. him," hurriedly exclaimed the bereft mother; her aged eyes gleamed, the very suggestion of the name of this man seemed to infuriate her. "Woe's me I woe's me I Poor Sarah I Do you take an interest in her sad life? She recited to me one circumstance in her wicked career which seemed to haunt her tormenting conscience more than all beside." "What was that?" inquired Eleanor faintly. "She aided that-that deceiver to de- stroy a beautiful girl-his cousin. Had she not sought this unfortunate girl, and succeeded in attaining her pardon, I fear to think of her death-bed." Eleanor and her mother listened and looked, filled with astonishment. Could it be possible that the degraded woman who had so lately visited them, belonged to such respectable people and surround- ings? After some further conversation, they drove on. Eleanor desired to be- hold the last resting-place of one whom the world had so little cause to regret. They descended from the carriage, and approached the newly-made grave. The few who had gathered to witness the burial had already dispersed. Sarah Jacobs was interred in the family grave- yard. No tears were shed for her ex- cepting those "natural" drops which flowed from the eyes of the miserable   mother. A grave-stone leaned against another, blackened by time, ready to be erected in its place. It had been ordered by the repentant Magdalene, and bore this inscription: "I came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance." Beneath were to be seen these Words, added by the mother: "Let him who is without sin among you cast the first stone." With an oppressed heart, Elea- nor followed her mother into the carriage; few words passed between them during the drive homeward, where, having ar- rived, their meditations were interrupted by the noisy little Francis, whose childish exclamations of glee awoke a smile upon the most thoughtful countenance. Eleanor Cropper has loved as deeply, as truly as woman is capable of loving, but her affections had fallen upon stony ground, and could not take root. Her false step had blasted all prospects of earthly pleasures ; yet she began to feel again a degree of happiness. Peacefully glided the stream of life which was darkened, nevertheless, by one dark shadow. Need we say what that was? The little Francis seemingly was des- tined for the ministry--to become a mis- sionary. It was a beautiful and a touch- ing sight to see him standing at his mother's knee, listening with eager eyes and quick although infantile mind, to her holy readings and pure teachings.   CHAPTER XV.   IT is some time since we have referred to the career of our whilom minister. And a long time since any one had heard his eloquent words from the pulpit, as he had not preached since his trouble with his wife. His prospects darkened from day to day. From his utter negligence of pecuniary affairs, his losses became fre- quent and great. Peace of mind, of course, he knew not: and never could he forget the dying words of his father.   These, with the memory of the injured Eleanor, haunted him unceasingly. Since that freezing night which saw her turned upon the street with her babe in her weak arms, her soliciting, despairing cry had ever rung in his bars. His gray- headed, broken-hearted father and mother visited him in frightful nightly visions. The torture of a guilty conscience had materially impaired his health. One morning in a fit of desperation he   ordered his horse. Mile after mile he passed on, the noble animal he bestrode was urged on to its utmost speed. Ah I miserable, there was no peace for him. All the morning a depression greater than usual had weighed down his heart. Presentiment, with its clammy touch, was on his heart., Evil was about to befall him. Unhappy as he was, an impression of added misery about to occur pursued and almost maddened him. He had al- ready become quite a hermit, seldom leaving the desolate house.  ow many hours he was absent he knew not; he knew not even when he turned his horse's head towards home. The reader will iemember that the ele- gant mansion of Mr. Cropper had been built at some little distance from the city. As Egbert gained an elevation in his homeward progress what met his vision? His home, the elegant mansion; which was the envy and the admiration of all, was in flames. Madly he urged on his horse, to save if possible this lordly piece of architecture. Vain, vain was his mad career, his frantic efforts when arrived. Nothing could save the property, the greedy flames were too far advanced. Behold!  All that Edward Cropper had in the world was in that smoking pile of ashes! Deeds, important papers, all, everything was consumed!-and the day that had seen him the miserable pro- prietor of a princely hall, beheld him, ere its close, reduced to poverty. Homeless, friendless, what was to be the after fate of the once haughty Cropper? Brought up to the pursuit of knowledge which had proved distasteful and of no avail, what was now to become of the elegant theolo- gian? Few thought of him, and no one car- ed. All the world had become to him a peopled solitude, a desert, a wilderness. It was not unusual for him to hear strangers speak in high terms of the beau- tiful devotee, Eleanor, his cousin. Her charities were queenly, her life that of a meek Christian. She well deserved her meed of praise, and it was yielded in no unstinted measure.   His heart sickened: at th% name of mother or child. What now were they to him who were so near, and might have been so dear? Ah I that merciless " might have been." How he now cursed the evil purpose which had tempted him to ruin instead of marrying his cousin! Misera- ble as mortal man could be, was Egbert. In the entire extent of his acquaintances could not one be found who cared for or respected him. His wealth gone, neither good nor bad men thought of him. He now saw himself as others saw him, a poor, deserted fugitive. While all the world slept Egbert Crop- per lay awake, tossing on a bed -of thorns, or pacing wearily about. Sleep, which which brings joy to even desolate hearts, had no comfort to bestow upon him. All the night long he cursed the hour in which he was born; and yet, whom had he to blame but himself for his conduct and his consequent sufierng? What was to blame but his own evil pas- sions? All the visions which he saw and heard were the phantoms of his troubled conscience! The powers of darkness ap- peared to be let loose upon him. I He lived on in this way, until he was so reduced in circumstances that he had not even genteel clothing to wear. The pangs of hunger subdues even the proud; est heart. Egbert possessed a natural taste for drawing, which had been well cultivated. This, which he had pursued, only as an elegant accomplishment, served now to gain him bread. So abject had he become, that lie went from, house tob house sketching any suggested scene for a mere pittance. Beholdthe destiny of the iniquitous man! Wherever he wan-. dered he was known by the name of the crazy artist. His long neglected beard, and altered appearance rendered him an object of pity I How frequently did he wish to fall at Eleanor's feet, and beseech her forgive- ness! Daily he knew that his "final end" became more legibly visible-nearer and nearer approaching the grave. He bat- tled with ate-&amp;and a guilty conscience as  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC8397-00000031"/> long as strength allowed, but at length he was compelled to give way; he be- came very ill, for for many months was confined to his bed, and a report was ex- tensively circulated that Egbert Cropper, the crazy artist was dead. This news reached the ears of Julia, his wedded wife, and of Dr. Le Fevre, and was a matter of great rejoicing to them. On the very day of the receipt of the "melancholy tidings," they appeared before a clergyman, and were joined to- gether in the holy bonds of wedlock. Julia, as deeply as her nature permitted, was attached to the man for whom she had "given up all that a woman holds dear." And on his part, Dr. Le Fevre truly loved the beautiful though guilty wife. Eagerly Dr. Le Fevre made repara- tion, as far as in 'his power lay, for the evil of which he had been guilty. Origin- ally, his was an honorable, manly nature, inclined toward and greatly preferring to follow the good path, but not strong enough to resist the temptation. Egbert Cropper, the dying man, the deserted husband, took one morning in his hand the daily paper. The light sheet shook in his tremulous fingers, but, alas! soon from another cause than phy- sical debility: This marriage announce- ment fell upon his glaring and almost dying eyes. Reader, can you imagine what this estrange announcement was? Terrible, shocking, were the facts I The marriage of Julia and the Doctor had been announced. Terrific was the news, but, alasI it was truel  The husband clasped his cold hands together, and tie paper fell from his grasp. " O God I be merciful to me, a  sinner!" he whis- pered.  "I deserve it all. My wife has been false, but no more so than I have : been to others." The blood   seemed to curdle in his f veins, his face grer Vpale, and he whis- pered, "Eleanor-Eleanor!"      E Long dwelt the deceiver upon   those i few words which  entered his heart, j and penetrated to the inner depths of  his nature.  Then he murmured, "I de-    L serve all-everything!"A long period of time he continued in this miserable state of mind. At the end of that time it became patent to him that the moments of his life were numbered. Then his feeble fingers traced a note to Eleanor, beseeching her forgiveness. She, in the midst of comfort and tranquillity received these brief lines. Even now the well- known characters made her heart trem- ble on its throne. "MY DEAR, MY LONG LOST ELEANOR :- On the verge of eternity I dare again to trace your name, a name too sacred and too pure for my contaminated lips to utter-but death awaits me; its cold fingers already clutch at my heart. Death is terrible! Eleanor, deprive it of half its terrors by according me your forgive- ness--without that, I cannot, cannot die. To see you, saintly girl, would be too much for endurance long I Once more to feel thy gentle hand upon my heated brow, or hear thy silvery voice murmur again, "Egbert," would seem but to tran- sport me to the other shore. I have suf- fered what mortal has never known, save my own heart. Sin has stamped upon my frame that which only eternity can erase. Oh! Eleanor, dear cousin, I have atoned for my cruelty. I hope, I feel sometimes that I am forgiven by my Ma- ker; but then, again, I fear that my crimes have been too great. Yet I can trust in the goodness of God, and believe that He is merciful, although I deserve it not. My dying   body is fast sinking: soon, ah! soon I shall be laid in the tomb. Poverty and disgrace will cover my re- mains. Yet I hope that you will pity me and forgive my crimes, and the injuries inflicted upon you, noble girl. My last prayer shall be offered for your happiness and that of my  child.  Had I married you instead of the false-hearted Julia, I should have been happy. But, alas! all is over. I  can write no more-death glazes my eyes, and palsies my hand. Send me your forgiveness, then let me die, dear Eleanor.    EGBERT."   When Eleanor received- and read and re-read the letter, she thought of all the suffering to which he had been subjected, she whispered," Vengeance is mine, and I will repay,"-- She hastily threw on her hat and shawl and. hurriedfrom her home, and in a short time she had reached his abode. Oh lAmisery of miseries! He was lying on a miserable pallet of straw, and was in the most wretched condition. As Eleanor approached his bedside he raised his languid eyes and exclaimed, "Oh I forgive, forgive, thou angel of mercy sent to me in my last moments to soothe this burning brow and beating heart l" and at the same time declaring that he had suffered the tortures of a guilty conscience until it was killing him. Starting up he would exclaim, "Oh! what frightful visions I have seen." The once injured girl looked upon him with pity. She laid her tender hand upon his fevered brow; she breathed into his ear consoling words of forgiveness, and shed tears of true feeling over the man who had crushed her every hope. But, ah woman-like, she forgave. He had repented in his last moments, and we draw the curtain of charity over his exit into another world. The very touch of Eleanor's cool hand upon his burning brow seemed to recall his scattered senses, and all he could whisper was her name, her dear name. Egbert Cropper lingered but a short   time ere he passed away, whispering, " God bless her, and my boy." The gen- tle girl saw him breathe his last, She forgave and tried to forget the past. Egbert Cropper owed his decent inter- ment to her whose enemy he had been. She had the body conveyed to his family burying ground, near the dust of his parents and the ashes of the late dwelling, and upon -his grave not a tear was shed. Eleanor could not weep; the oppression on her heart 'was denied the relief of tears. Dreary was the scene at the inter- ment of the hero of our story. There were no flowers blooming, no birds sing- ing; only the cool October winds rustled through the trees; all was dreary, silent, and all turned from the grave, as though none pitied, none grieved. When she reached home, and was seated in her lit- tle chamber, all her former life came so vividly before her, she could no longer suppress her grief; her silent bedroom witnessed the anguish of her' who had been so basely deceived, and so sadly injured. The land once owned by Egbert Crop- per had been sold into the hands of strangers, and, in dourse of time, the very recollection of the locality of his grave was lost. "' Death is the port where all may refuge find, The end of labor, entry unto rest, Death hath the bounds of misery confin'd, Whose sanctuary shrouds affliction best"'   CHAPTER XVI.   ELEANOR  had seen those who- had injured her fall one by onel There now seemed not a cloud above her head; the bright sun glimmered over the very mounds where once the pelting storms had beaten upon her fragile form. The atmosphere seemed to be perfumed with the aroma of peace, joy, and tranquillity, so much was her life changed in a few years after the death of Egbert, "None knew her but to love her; None named her but to praise."   Mrs. Holland and Eleanor sustained an unbroken correspondence, and a yearly exchange of presents passed between them. They often visited each other. It was upon one of those friendly visits to Eleanor, and to beguile the tedium of conversation, Ms. Holland, in a hilarious mood, knowing Eleanor's musical talent, requested her to sing one of her old fav- orite pieces of music. Eleanor gently dis- sented; but urged by her friend, her sis- ter, and parents, she at last consented.  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC8397-00000032"/> "Sing something lively," cried Emelia. "Yes, do," echoed Mrs. Holland; all, all joined in the request. Eleanor shook her head and said, "I cannot-I cannot; not now." Drawing near the piano, she ran her delicate fingers along its keys, and while great tears came to her dreamy eyes, she broke out in a plaintive strain in the fol- lowing words: "A child sat by a-limpid stream, And gazed upon the tide beneath: Upon her cheek was joy's bright beam, And on her brow a blooming wreath. Her lap was filled with fragrant flowers, And, as the clear brook babbled by, She scattered down the rosy showers With many a wild and joyous cry, And laughed to see the mingling tide Upon its onward progress glide. '"And time grew on-and flower by flower Was cast upon the sunny stream; But when the shades of eve did lower, She woke up from her blissful dream. "Bring back my flowers!" she wildly cried, 'l Bring back the flowers I flung to thee 1" But echo's voice alone replied, As danced the streamlet down the lea; And still, amid night's gloomy hours, In vain she cried: "Bring back my flowers!" "O, maiden I who, on Time's swift stream, Dost gaily see the moments flee, In this poor child's delusive dream, An emblem may be found of thee I Each moment is a perfumed rose, Into thy hand by Mercy given, That thou its fragrance might dispose, And let its incense rise to Heaven: Else, when death's shadow o'er thee lowers, Thy heart will wail, "Bring back myflowerm." As the last words died away, such had been the  simplicity, pathos, and inten- sity of Eleanor's feelings that Mrs. Hol-  t land, Emelia, and her parents had crowd-  E ed  around her and stood   struck with s amazement and    were silently weeping. I * Poor Eleanor had been singing    her own f sad experience; and as it is said that no  t great artist has ever become   such with- 1; out experience of the passions, she   had A proved her artistic skill in her own   sad a history and present ability in music.    S "Oh, my   poor, dear child 1" agitatedly I cried  her mother, "will you, can   you so never forget the   dark past?  Eleanor," v she   continued, "my  child,"  and  she E   a. threw her arms about her neck and kissed 1, her, " we have all forgiven you, dearest, Heaven has blessed you, your dear boy I is our joy; forget the past, think only of the future." r  Eleanor embraced her/ mother, and e mournfully returned, " es  mother, I e know all, and am happy inlite thought; - but memory and sadness sometimes, in spite of all, will throw its dark jolds over my thoughtful soul."    t Mrs. Holland broke in, "Eleanor, my dear, for me, just -for me, sing now one of our old time songs when we used to laugh and romp as school-girls and play- mates; when we both painted the future with the rosy light of happiness. Elea- nor bent her head once again to the in- strument, and after some time, at the suggestion of Mrs. Holland, sang-it was but mechanical, for her heart was not in the matter-the following world wide song-"The, Dashing White Sergeant:" "If I had a beaux for a soldier would go To war, think I'd marry him? No-no-no." As the song ended they all \reseated themselves and a brief silence ensued, broken only by the appearance of a gentleman who had been listening out- side to the plaintive airs of the song- stress. Mr. Leicester had been a frequentvisitor at the house of Mr. Cropper, but no one at that time suspected his feelings. 'Whenever Eleanor would sing, he seemed charmed. This evening, when she had yielded to urgent solicitation to repeat the song, "Bring back my flowers," as soon as she thought herself unperceived, she stole out upon 'the balcony. The beauty and the perfume of the night filled her heart with rapture as she thought of nature's God, and made it bound with a sense of earthly pleasures. As she sat viewing the starry heavens, and musing upon all that had passed, she heard a soft footstep approaching. In an instant a touch came upon her shoulder, a voice breathed her name.. It was the young and handsome Leicester! He caught her hand in his, and murmur-   ed words of purest love. This manly voice, whose every word was truth, vowedto:take her to his heart, anclove and cherish her forever. ReaSer, can you imagine the feelings of flanor Cropper at that moment? gfy had been'the hours which she had. passed in his society, but she had never -for he had been an old lover-sus- pected his intentions. Now she knew all; when he ceased to speak, a deep silence prevailed. She felt a strong arm passed around her waist. Eleanor struggled to crush the feelings which made her alternately flush and grow pale at his touch. Why did she so well know the sound of his ring- ing footstep upon the porch? Why did he seem to her the personification of all that was worthy in man? Yet, as much as possible, she avoided him, remember- ing the pain she had previously given him. "To love and to be repulsed is surely the worst pain a person can endure! I have given pain to ath who truly loved me," thought our heroine, " let him at least escape." But after numerous overtures had been made as time had elapsed, Mr. Leicester found to his satisfaction that Eleanor loved him as devotedly as he could wish. Her heart once more bounded with joy, her eyes sparkled with the animation of a deep and lasting happiness founded upon true and worthy affection. She found, even here on earth, rest and happiness. The marriage, after several months had elapsed, was solemnized in the pre- sence of her parents and some other friends. Eleanor was to return to the spot which gave her birth, delightfully situat- ed upon the Lake, where the happy days of her infancy had been passed. What more could she desire? The little Francis Dorson remained with hs grand-parents at their most earnest solicitation. After Eleanor's marriage, and on their wedding tour, she made a visit to Phila- .     ..   delphia, and next, to her friend Clara Holland. Mrs. Galagher was sought for. The meeting between Mrs. Leicester and the woman who had taken care of her, we will not describe. The reader must conceive that there was great joy. The first words uttered by the poor woman were, "The Lord be praised, if there ain't the lady who came to my house in the storm; and shure, and yez don't look like the same! .but, faith, I never could for- get a face so heavenly." Our heroine was truly happy to meet again one who had befriended her when so much in need. Eleanor was now hap- py and wealthy, and she. wished to share it with her friends. "A friend in need, is a friend indeed!" she whispered. Therefore Mrs. Gallagher received some very valuable presents from the bride, The friend of the Green Isle declared that the money that Eleanor had given her before her return to her father's house, had set up her husband in business, and since then they had never known want. After a few days spent in the city, Eleanor and her husband returned, but not without the blessings of these good people. At their parting, Mrs. Gallagher invoked the blessings of the mother of God, and her beloved son, Jesus, upon the bride. The hurricane which had been blowing over our heroine abated; life again be- came precious; once more she enjoyed' the song of the forest warbler, once more looked upon the flowers admiring their beauty and fragrancei and once more she gazed upon the pebbled stream  with pleasure, and adored the hand which had brought all things into existence; and felt even more grateful for the deliver- ance from him she had once so tenderly and devoutly loved. Quietness and sweet repose sat upon her countenance; no one taunted her with thepast, but all encour- aged her to forget by-gone days and be happy.  Anmid the scenes of domestic life, with the love of Mr. Leicester, her days glided happily away.  &#xD;<pb n="60" xml:id="VAC8397-00000033"/> But, oh, reader . even a less apprecia- tivey heart than that of Mr. Leicester would have loved Eleanor to adoration. Her eyes, her soft loving eyes, expressed what she felt far oftener than did her lips. Did he feel all the love and allegi ance they ever so silently and timidly spoke? She had reason to think so I In the language of the immortal Jane Eyre, she could say, "I know that I live entirely for and with what I love best on earth.. I iold myself blest, blest beyond what language can express, because I am my husband's life as fully as he is mine." Mr. Leicester at this time lived at his father's old homestead on Lake Michi- gan, surrounded by all the luxuries of life, with no one to share his happiness previous to his marriage. This kind and devoted husband spared no pains or money to have everything around his fu- ture home completed with the utmost ele- gance and taste. In a few days after their arrival, hoping to afford her a joyful sur- prise, he invited her, one beautiful moon- light night, to stroll down to the shore of the lake; upon so doing he called her at- tention to a new and beautiful yacht which 'he had expressly procured and had equip- ed in the most elegant manner for her use. Upon beholding it she expressed her admiration in the most enthusiastic manner; after enjoying her surprise for   - a few moments he requested ir to name it and regard it henceforth as her espec- ial property and as one of his bridal pres- ents.  After a few moments consideration, she bestowed upon it the appellation of GEM oF THE LAKE This elegant pleasure- boat could only have been surpassed by that which contained a band of hidden musicians constructed and floated upon a miniature lake by the Earl to afford gratification and amusement to the Royal Queen, Elizabeth. The misfortunes and vicissitudes of Eleanor had so influenced the mind of Emelia that she determined never to marry, but divided her time be tween the homes of her father and sister,  devoting herself and means to relieving the wants of the poor and needy. The beautiful little Frank Dorson favored his father, but had inherited his mother's amiable disposition; and it seemed he was to fill the position his father had so unwisely disgraced. He beae a useful and exemplary minister, and as a de- voted son to his mother and aged grand-parents. In after years a bright- eyed boy and interesting girl blessed the family circle of Mr. Leicester. Many were the pleasant excursions which this happy party enjoyed on clear moon-light evenings, floating over the calm pellucid waters in the GEM OF THE LAKE.   THE END.   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>