<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8279">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Book of the Prophet Stephen, Son of Douglas, Vol. 2 </title>
            <author >White, Richard Grant, (1821-1885)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC8279</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Book of the Prophet Stephen, son of Douglas, vol. 2</title>
                  <author >White, Richard Grant, (1821-1885)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >48 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Feeks &amp; Bancker</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date >[1863-1864]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-09-20">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Book of the Prophet Stephen, son of Douglas, vol. 2</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8279-00000001"/>  THE BOOK   STEPHEN, SON OF DOUGLAS.  NEW YORK:' FE , .}'tJBLmHER BOORSE UEl. NO. 2 ANN BTREETs  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC8279-00000002"/>   STEPHEN THE PROPHET. 4 The King's conscience an Iron-C'lad Monitor. "TI. Kinghaveth a Dream. 12 Sewarddrinketh Pophesyitg ohisky. 15 The Devildelighted at his su ccess with Abra.  h m. I. Behold, O my people I war shall continue inthe  land, and shall desolate it; yea, it shall destroy it, so that they that knew it and loved it, shall flee (from it and know it no more. II. But a remnant shall be left, even the Demoen - racy which descended from the mighty Chiefs of -the'a Revolution, who aforetime had fashioned the laws, and made the name of their country to be feared to the uttermost ends of the earth,  Ila , But these shall suffer great tribulation by rea- tson ofthe'vi'olenee of the followers of the Woolly- Headed aDragon; and shall be reviled, and cast into prison; for the King of:the Woolly-Heads shalle reign for the space of a thousand and four hundred days; and all the days of his rule Shall be counted as a scourge upon th e people for their sins. IV. For beholdc the ing's conscience even his tm- Hede rao ;ad hllbervie, n    Gs it  &#xD;<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC8279-00000003"/> - Z4H EN TIE PROPET. rio ward monitor, shall be an Iron Clad, so that it- shallbe impeneirable, and shall be proof against the-clamors Of theft Wno Iothe conktitution *b the tohb had take n anoath to support, but which the worshipers of the black Idol shall swear he shall not keep, for they will have him to trample it under his feet.  v. And the wrath of Abraha'm the King shall be kindled against the people because they love the Con. stitution and the laws of their Fathers ' I. AndC he sall call unto him his purse-bearer, h oiscalled ffa/mon because he is sea/y, even as a afisahchzll- co'mialnd him saying, do thou counci Ti' the clxef rulers in thetemple of the Dragon, how -; ' ca w  u punlsish: the People because they ill not worship the comelyblack Idol, E:i' And they said one with another, Behold we 3Jwi11$..thelan -fuji of GreenbackLocusts which shall vj- 'the tane  th Be peo e , ad shall Causo every little thing to be of an exceedi' gre- priaut 'S3o0 thatnone but such as we will feed from the temple {,iithepDragon shall ;have the wherewithai:of life. Y'::1:. AU :these thinas sh"l]: delight the lig, so half ht. t ;,ing, so) tha he shallebae '--; tat he a embrace his Ucry purse-bearer, even he that is called Saimon; and the worshipers of the black Idolishl smite themselves for joy, because of ck lddoh, ' i     r joy ., , .bee the suffering of the worshipers of the White deities. JXIX. Lo, in the midst of these revelries a sound shall be heard from-afar coming up from the North, a dm the Eat, and:rom the West, like the noise of many waters, and Abraham; the King, shall be seized with wonder and fear, and shall send forth his faithiul: trumpeters to search out the cause of so great a commotion.   BOOK- SECOND.        5 X. And they shall return quickly to tell the King how the worshipers Qof the White deities are gathering in the mountains and in the vallies, like the leaves of the forest, crying aloud that the altars builded by their fathers shall remain for them and for their children forever and ever! Lo, these things shall trouble the heart of the King, so that his countenance shall change, and his looks shall become like unto that of a buzzard that is sick, The hair of his flesh shall stand on end. His meats and his drinks shall not nourish him ; even his jokes shall become dry and husky. XI: But when the eventide cdmeth "the govern, ment" shall sleep, and in a dream the devil shall appear unto him,. even the King, saying--"The Constitution. is not equal to the exigencies of the case ;" "the dogmas of the quiet past are not suffi- cient for the stormy present;" " the situation is pile-d high with difficulties, and therefore we must rise with the occasion." XII. Now when the morning cometh, the King shall summon his faithful Fuglemen, even him that is called Sumner, the same being the descendant of a comely black wench from the land of Demerara; and Seward, the prophet, who drinketh much Prophesying Whiskey, and foretelleth the times and the seasons when war shall end, and when the " irrepressible con- flict " shall bring peace, even the peace that blesseth the dead after the battle; and Stanton, not he that fingereth the King's money in the House of Customs; but that other Stanton, who w as aforetime a Demo- crat, and selleth himself to serve in the temple of the Dragon.  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC8279-00000004"/>    Br STVEPHEN THE PROPHET, UTT. All these and other some shall the mighty King of the Woolly Heads summon into his presence and shall open his mouth and speak unto them say- ing:  XIV. O ye my Fuglemen, hearken unto me, and give ear to the wonderful things which the Lord hath done, for yester-night, at about the second hour of my slumber, the angel of the Lord appeared unto me in a dream, and shewed me the things that appertain to a wise and just reign over my people. XV. And Abraham shall tell his faithful Fuglemen the dream, and all the words which the devil speaketh unto him in the vision, and the fuglemen shall look one in the face of another, and shall marvel among themselves, saying, it is surely the Lord's doings. XVI. Now the devil is cunning above all things, and vain withal, so that when he perceiveth that the King taketh him for the angel of the Lord, he shall take delight in his own heart, and shall say unto him- self, Behold this King of the Woolly-Heads is the covey for me, and,I will make him my servant, and he shall help me in the work of my hands. CHAPTER    II. 1 The King falleth into a deep Slumber. 4 The Devil tip. peth himselJ a Wink, and teacheth the King. 4 He show. ietlk that the way to Save the Union is to Destroy it. 23: Tihe Devil leavethi a blue streaw behind himn, which smelleth like the Itch. , I. And behold when darkness covers the earth, and   BOOK SECONDO. night cometh on, a aeep slumber shall fa u pn the eyes of Abraham the ing.        e aeth ey   mhen the devil seeth him asleep in to !I. And when the ,*^        hi w the form of th comely black Idol, and goeth in unto him, ano sah unto him in a 'oud voice, but soft h., n satut   ibAraham I     Araham! withal as Ethicpio musoo,--  .S           -  ---   Abraham 1 iII Brehol &amp; the King turneth in his sleep, and an- swereth the devil with reverent speech, -rIhat, my dear lord t?"          self JV. The devil tippeth a vilk     -wose I pray thee, 0- K ing, listen to the words of 0isdom. thatcometh from thy fathers, and hearken unto the that^^oine truth that theLord sendeth to thee.  t or verily I sy uto , that he way to save the Union is to destroy it. If thou wouldst have it i lourish like feen Tay tree gluck Up its roo  the roots are heavy, holding much earth, hi drag geth its top lownwards and stoppeth its growt I. Mioreover,t O  ing, thou knowest that all men "VI, Mworeover,) I 92 them  e ot African de- are born equal, especially them tha soentL                That,ior- Yoi. ttol&amp; this truth to be self-evident, That,inor- a H. Sol this tat^iGovernment, anl aer to preserve a      epublian form of Government, all power must be der"ve from them thac govern, an6 not, as the wickea teach, from the consentof the gov, ernedoeth                tae erneI. now also, that the Union made the States; nd not the States te Union, as is held by themtha ' IX. A-people that   I arIX Apowke thtat WOuld be free, inus b oend not by the law, but by milit arynceito interpreted, signiffeth the will ofheano the con sent of the people, as say  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC8279-00000005"/> "*:- 8    STEP'HEN THE PROPHET. X,- The people have no part nor lot in government but to submit to the will of them that govern. XI. Beware! -O righteous ruler, of the ballot, for it- is::the device of the. enemies of freedom; and if thou, in, thy weakness, destroy it not, it will hang thee. -XT. Follow thou after the counsel of the great Douglas; but be sure it be that Douglas which spell- ethhis name with .an F. XTT. Beware of all such as say, "The privilege of the Writ of Iabeas Corpus shall not :be suspended," for they are enemies of human freedom and foes of the gov ernment. XIV. The right of a people to keep and bear arms for self-defense is a device of the wicked, not to be tolerated by a righteous ruler. XV, .Ee that saitlh that the people "' shall be secure in theirpersons, houses, papers, and effects, against - unreasonable searches and seizures," is an enemy of the State, and should)be disposed of speedily. X I. Shui the councils of all suchtas declare that ,o shearches or arrests ought to be made except on warrants supported by oath, and "particularly de- ,$.uching the place to be searched and the person or th gs to be seized."  VII. Set thly face aainst them that say, "The *tria .of tatl crimes shall be by juty, and such trial shall be held in the State where the said crimes shall have beoen: committed," and against them that say, "No person  I shball be h lelld to anc swer for a capital, or otlher- wise infamous crime, unless on presentment or indict- ment ,of angran j'ry." :V!III. And against those other seditious and gain- yfing distnrbors of the peace of men who go aodnt yen    ,        ... .  g *t   be   BOOK SECOND.         9 I to declare that "In all criminal prosecutions, the ac- cused shall enjoy the right of a speedy and public trial, by an impartial jury of the State and district wherein the crime shall have been committed, which district shall have been previously ascertained by law, are to be informed- of the nature and cause of the ac- cusation; to be confonted with the witness against him; to have compulsory process for obtaining wit- nesses in his favor, and to have assistance of counsel for his defense." XTX. Turn thou also a deaf ear to those sons of darkness who declare that, "No attainder of treason shall work corruption of blood, or forfeiture, except during the life of the person attainted." XX. And also to them that say, "No new state- shall be formed or erected within the jurisdiction of any other state, without the consent of the legislature. of the state so concerned." XXT. Pray that the wrath of heaven fall upon all who declare that, "No ex post facto law shall be. passed," and who insult both God and map by affirm- ing the damnable sin of "freedom of speech 'and of the press."                 , XXII. But above .anl, just and mighty ruler, tub thy feet out of the paths of such ask declare, "the- Constitution shall be the supreme law of the land ; for thou knowest that all the-- danable things herein named are found in that peisn    Gold defying instrument worshiped by thei;opperheads, and by all the followers of the White deitieiscalled among them the wicked Constitution. IXT I, Behold when the devil shall make an end of breathing these things into the ear of the King, he ? .---- . -- ---*  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8279-00000006"/> 10      STEPHEN THE PROPHET. shall tip himself a wink, and vanish, leaving a blue flame behind him, that smelleth like a country school house in that season when the itch prevaleth I CHAPTER    III. 1 TIhe King thinketh the Devil's stink to be the pleasant odors of the contely black Idol. 2 The IEing calleth a council of his faithful Fuglemen. 5 He promiseth to make an end of thte Constitution. 6 Willianm the Prophet speaketA. 7 Sumner the'Plagiarist, speaketh. 8 Benja: min the Coward, speaketh. T'laddeus the Crafty, spear- I. Now, when the King awaketh he smelleth the stink of the devil, and he throweth up his eyes for oJy, for he shall say, "Of a truth I perceive that the comely black Iddl watcheth over my sleeping, because he leaveth-his pleasant odors behind him." II. And the King, when he getteth up and washeth himself, calleth a council of all hisFuglemen; yea, of the mighty men of the Woolly-Headed nation, and: breaketh to them the joyful tidings of the wonderful things' delivered to him in the vision. "I. And he ;shall say unto them, Hearken unto me, for the things which have been revealed shall do away with the dead past, even with the Constitution and the laws, whichi joretime were made by our fathers, who , were oppress:l with blindness, and all uncleanness, in that they denied to- our dear brethren of African  descent the equality which maketh -them as one of ourselves.   BOO0K SECOND#.  1V  . Neither allowed they their sons to marry with the daughters of negroes, nor their daughters to take into themselves comely black husbands, for they were proud and lifted up after the manner of the wicked. V. Now, therefore, Alet us make an end of their  Constitution and their statutes, even of the laws which we had from the beginning, for they are an offence unto the saints that worship in the temple of the Dragon. VI. Whereupon William, the prophet, calle d Sew- ard by the generation of the Woolly-Heads, shall stand up before the King and open his mouth saying, it is well, O King, that we straightway make an end of the Constitution and the laws, for if we do not, they will make an end of us.  VII. Then Sumner, the Plagiarist, he that afore- time had his brains knocked out in the Senate Chamber, because of his much lying about the in- habitants of Sunland, shall come forward, and stand close to- the King, saying, To what end O King, do VIII. Behold Benjamin, the Coward, surnamed Wade, because he had once wished that he ight wtade up to his knees in the blood olthe: slaveholdersb, standeth up, saying-Why talk ye hiere of the Consti  tut   ion and the Union, for know. ye not that they are dead, and their carcasses stink above the ground? ow; therefore, let us, if happily we may, bury hem  a,:!-.;; thll,8 out of OUr sihlt. up to h*s knees in the blood oI - a ' - h .l,dors  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8279-00000007"/> ia      BTEPBHN THE PROPHET., I. Then Thaddeus, the Crafty, the same whos   mother was a white woman, but whose concubine, even she that liveth in his own house is a free person ,of African descent, proclaimeth aloud that, as long as the organic laws of the States survive, the Union and; the, Constitution are daily liable to be dug up out ofiI their graves; neither is their any safety to our ow neeks as long as the governments of the States shall stand.    -      . X:. And Abraham said, in due time the States shall be no more.  CHAPTER IV. 1 -The King-rebuketh: hs Fugemen. 5 le showeth that the, people. must earn by degrees to bear their new burdens. 6 He showet that while destroying the Union they must retend to besaving it. 3 ie showeth how to split rwais. 9   le', sheth how the Democrats help him. f1 Htanni. ,bthe ;Ethpioadn, trietih to speak,. but cannot by reason of Itedirt 'Pon ius face. ,! oQlad, w hen Abrahahm the ing shall hear leoseo urmn,ngs and misgivings among his faithful. Puglemen, he shall rebuke them, saying--O y short  -of sightt and of little pluck, do ye not perceive that all  ese objects I will compassin due time.  ':I, :Of the old dispensation, that dates from the pro- slavery 4as of George, surnamed Washington, there is to be left' Aeither the Con-t itution nor States, nor, ny other thing that lieth in 'the way of our power. UI, B ut what would ye, defeat ourselves by much    BOOK SECOID.        1: iaste? 'When a man splitteth rails .ut of a greatlog lofth he foolishy drive the wedge in at the middle? o, he beginneth at one end, and by degrees worketh up to the centre, until at last he splitteth the log in Lwain. IV. Even so work we at our task, compassing the mnd by little and little untilour workis done. Yerily [.say unto you, the old foundations, must be taken way liftle by little, lest the people smell what is, in khe wind, and get up in their ungodly strength and overthrow-the holy revolution:which we have begnns for the glory of the comely black Idol. V. Know ye not, that the people must learn by de- grees to bear the 'new burdens, which theyare to wear evermore, lest by feeling the whole load at oncethey throw it off, and restore again the Union and the laws, which we have sworn by an oath to the Dragon, that we will destroy forever and ever. VI. For these reasonswe must be wise as serpents, and pretend that we are saving the Union, while de- stroying it, VII. Did I not aforetime declare that I had no right and no intention to disturbthe domestic institu- tions of the heathen in Suniland, who -worship White deities? even so did not our -own faithful Congress proclaim thatthe war shoild not be used'for any in- terference with slavery, but only to enforce the laws; whereby we deceived many of the foolish worshipers of the Wlhite deities in the North, and gained them over to our own side, to help us destroy their own temples, even the temple of the White deities which were worshiped by their fathers.        D VAII. Now, therefore, be of good cheer, for in due  A - I r , ,.., e;f   &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8279-00000008"/> le"     RBIEN THE PROPHET.  time we will bring all things to pass according to the  desires of our own hearts; but beware that ye drive not on too fast, so that ye lose the support of those foolish but useful democrats, whom we happily use to fill up our armies and to scourge the Copperheads, who cry aloud in: the market places and plot in secret for the Union and the laws. IX. Verily I say unto you that without the support Of the Democrsats we t fail, and the temple of our co:ely black Idol would be destroyed, andthe tem. ple of the White deities would flourish forever and ever.  X. Behold, have we not the great ruler of the nicekerbockers, and he of the kingdom  of Jersey, for tais to our kite? Do we ot proft by the cowh .ri dice and foolishness of their friends il our own Congrei who vote supplies to the powers that Strangleth them and their doctrines? Doth not even Jack, the Giant-killer, while he condemneth our own policy, with the same breath offer to make us still stronger to carry on our policy-unto the end? XI. Therefore, see ye not that we must use the blindness of these, our enemies, to compass our end? The things revealed to me in the vision I will do, so that there shall not be left one stone upon another in the temple builded by our foolish ancestors, that Sha not be thrown down. But I say unto you again, beware that ye spoil not all by much haste.  XII. And when the King shall make an end of .his sayings, ohannibal the Ethiopian, the same who is ex o the Eng m the temple of the Dragon, shall  get up and try to speak.  :ISI. But when he openeth'his mouth, he shall not F * . .   be able to shut it again, nor-to move his jaws a tittle, by reason of the much dirt on his face; so that his eyes shall roll in their sockets, and his tongue shall wiggle about between his jaws without his being able to utter as much as one syllable. XIV. And when the King seeth it he shall laugh and say that it reinindeth him of a story, which he telleth, thesame being not decent even to be repeated. XV. But the-fuglemen shall all confess that the King speaketh wisely, and that it is the better part to keep on, as they began, compassing their object by craft and lies, which shall deceive the foolish, of which there are many, and shall give such as can be bought with the green charms of the Dragon an excuse for their treachery to the White deities. XVI. So Abraham   and the Woolly-Heads shall flourish; and day by day the foundations of the white mans liberty shall crumble; yea, the white man shall recede from the glory of his fathers, and the negro shall stand in his place as long the Woolly-Heads bear rule in the land. CHAPTER V. I TVie Prophet showeth the speed of' Loyal Leagues. --The King instructeth the Leaguers how to destroy the ruler oJ the Knickerbock-ers. 6 The King's liar killeth Seynmotlr with a Resolutioz n. 7 The Post Boy tric th to speak. 11  Sey/motur blown to death by a Bellows. He  ifive tima killed by Resol1ution. i6 Anna Dic/dinsozn killeth hitm. I. And it shall come to pass that loyal leagues  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8279-00000009"/> shal ab'on  rHEN THE PnOri,;LC .  .  . . .  shall abound in those days, in so much that women shall forsake their own houses to go about after the young men who gather together -for the purpose of drawing the people into the temple of the Wcolly. Headed Dragon. II. Behold these shall be sore oppressed by reason ,of the stiff-neckedness of the ruler of the Knicker. bockers who is called Seymour, who because he is a worshiper of White deities, hateth the black Idol, and worrieth them that follow after it continually. "I. So they of the Loyal League shall go apart into a secret place to speak one with another pri. vately, and to see how they shall overcome the ruler of the Knickerbockers, and happily bring his councils to naught. IV. And they shall council with the King how they shall destroy the ruler of the Knickerbockers. V. Ad he shall speak unto them  saying-KInow ye not how I conquered the rebels in Sunland, and utterly destroyed them, by proclamation; now even so may ye overwhelm and confound the ruler of the Knickerbockers, and make him to worship the black Idol, by resolving against him, even as I proclaimed against the in-habitants of Sunland. VI. Then a  mighty warrior from Solfering, even Raymond, that was aforetime called the King's liar, shall stand up and open his mouth, saying-As the Kig   commandeth so be it Resolved, That the sole cause of the heart-sickening failures before the city of-the heathen, which is called Charleston, is the cul- pable, the audacious and treasonable practice of .the notorious, infamous, and shameless sympathiser, the ruler of the Kinickerbockers, who is called Seymour. ,     r   I   BOOK sEcoNM.        17 And the whole assembly shall clap their hands for joy. VII. Then shall arise the King's Post-Boy, even Park, the son of Godwin, who aforetime blew himself to pieces, as is recorded in the first Chapter of the first Book of the Prophet Stephen. VIII. But the Leaguers shall murmur among them- selves, and refuse to hear him, because they know him not, as he appeareth with a clean face. But when he speaketh they shall know him, and they shall laugh among themselves, saying-"Who hath washed thee?" IX. But nothing daunted, he shall cry with a loud voice-Be it Resolved, That to Horatio Seymour is due all and singly of the innumerable "irregulari- ties " and " botherations," even the defalcations, rob- beries, thefts, plunders, and stealings, which have be- fallen the Administration of Abraham the King. X. And when the Leaguers shall hearthe King's Post-Boy, they shall greatly rejoice among them- selves, insomuch that their chief scribe, Horace- not the poet, but the philosopher of Ethiopia-shall be moved to open his mouth in wisdom, saying--Re- solved, That the unreasonable, the unrighteous, the inhuman prejudice of the people against negroes is solely on account of the rebel sympathies of Horatio Seymour. XI, Whereupon one of the Chief Priests in the temple of the Dragon, who is called Bellows because he is given to much wind and bloweth hard at the worshipers of White deities, shall stand up and open his mouth, saying-Resolved, Thaat the deplorable ig- norance of white men, which causeth them to believe that amalgamation would .not produce a greatly [J-  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8279-00000010"/> Sl -81 EN THE PROPHET. proved type of humanity, is chargable upon thealari. asg treason and devilish sophistry of Horatio Bey- cmour, XII. And when the commotion is stilled, the son of Tilton, so called because he hath an itch to be ever on a tilt, who is mighty withall in his own conceit, shallrebukethe brethren, saying, of a truth I perceive  that ye go not to the root of the whole matter, which I give unto you after the manrner of wisdom-Re. soloed, That the vulgar popular error which teacheth that the negro is a negro, and that the white man is a white man, and also affirmeth that black is not White and white not black, ometh of the ignorance, infidelity 'and treason of Horatio -Seymour. XTIT. Then ariseth John, surnamed Kennedy, who is also called the Just, and who is, withall, chief of the watchmen in the city of Gotham that is built byX the waters of Manhattan. The same shall utter these words  saying--Resolved, That the Woolly-Headed police of Gotham who are given to assisting burglars, cut-throats, and those that live by swindling, are moved thereunto by the God defying   treason of Horatio Seymour.  XI. And behold a mighty warrior, even John the  Great, surnamed Dix, who hath the skill to shun the deadly dangers of any battle-field, shall stand up pro- claiming that it is a military necessity for the people to be still that he may speak, saying:--Resolved, That the damnable condition of the Park Barracks whence cometh contagion and death, ariseth alone from the subtlety and treason of Horatio Seymour. XV. Then shall come forth awclamberer from the placeof Commerce, who is called :Low, because he l ed L o w ,  e c a u s e h   BOOK SECOND.        19 hath nothing that is high in his nature, and the same shall utter these words, saying-Resolved, That the vicious character of the Police Commissioners, the high price of gold, and the worthlessness of govern- ment shinplasters, all comeof the rebel sympathies of Horatio Seymour. XVI. And in the end cometh forth the Goddess' out of the temple of the Dragon, even Anna that was called Dickinson, and sayeth-Resolved, That igno- rance, incompetency and drunkenness among our generals, discontent among the conscripts, small-pox in Washington and weak-backs in men, all spring from the duplicity, treachery and treason of Horatio Seymour.  XVII. Behold, after this manner shall the Loyal Leaguers, following the wisdom and the justice of their King, squelch and utterly exterminate the ruler of the- Knickerbockers. And it shall be said by the genera- tions that are to come, that the ruler of the Knicker- bockers was resolved to death by the Fuglemen of the King, who killeth millions byproclamation. And the nemory of the wisdom of the Woolly-Heads shall lescend from generation to generation. ,. ,          '  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8279-00000011"/> 20 S'HEN THE. PROPHET, CHAPTER     VI. mIansou   de stroyed "by rrocdanation. 2 A strane I Wn called Gallret, not John Smitho epoun tha a f the Dragon. 16 Garret the F righty o a the g.. of hs sayings 1   .j..y maketh an end Sfm hik YM93. 17 The Jtng isg roubled and doubteth which way he shallgo. 18 rtendel th ro1 i expoundeth and sleweth that thesna, o o h ps, sz22h fugitiv slaves,; Yea, even the bond , ,ix . . .. e .a i,' s - Ylet Garrt, a .se womaf n 'i Sari Cabeldesthfro-d ' : ;- roclamation that the Bible may adestyed, som   o thathe peol e may be misled no more. I. And it shall come Co Pass in the days than a great throng of the orshper o f the Dragon o sha go in before rehe Kin to persuade him to send forth an edIct even one of his exterminating proflamahp on, fgains the Bible.         ro  tos II. And a shrange man, surnamed Smith, not John, buto he that is called arret, becauseof a ighty ind, sharl stand upland pro]aim [hose words, saying-- mighty and sublimte mon arc broherof the conra. band, and cousin -o the moon ,thy pofpe have Coraise thy wo derful dolngs, in making an end of the accursed slaver--protecting the Constitution of'hisland, and of the laws and stautes that sdanl ' the way of the jut punismen of all who, by reason of heir stub borns'T ref             otr stub II. Bu   1sena, O in to the voice of thy people, for they would have thee to go to the root of this matter, so that our proud and boastful white race shall know in their hearts that they are inwardly ne- groes, and that their white skins are a deception and th offense idnol h oatinl in the temple of   BOOE SECO)D.   '    21 IV. Now therefore we beseech thee to hearken unito us, for as iong as the Book .that is called the Bible liveth to be a guide to the minds of men, there re- maineth no safety to the worshipers of the Idol, for it hath been a stAmnbling block to the weak,- in that it endorseth the doctrines of slavery, and teacheth men to be subject unto the laws that protect the damnable institution. V. Thou knowest that the Idol teacheth that slavery is a sin ag sin st- God and a Crime against man ; and that this is the foundation of all our doing, even of the war that we have amade in the land. VI. But behold how the Bible contradicteth us, and would, if men trusted it, bring all our Work to naught. VII. For do we not-read at the beginnirg, even in the seventh chapter of the Book of Genesis, tht t the Lord took a most notorious slaveholder, even Abraw ham, and the'slaves that were "bought with his money " into covenant with himnself, without so much as once rebulring slavery as a sin; but otherwise, authorizing him to retain his- slaves, even them that were "bought with his- money," while he-took him, into covenant with himself. VllI. Now Abraham was  a great and wicked slave- holder, and he did wickedly arm (Gen. 14: 14,  15,) three hundred and eighteen  of his slaves to pursue certain Kings who had offended against him. IX. Know we not tiat this wretch, who was the owner of more than a thousand slaves is called in the Bible "  the friend of God," and " the father of them that believe." X. Behold also how we are forbidden by the Bible  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8279-00000012"/> 22      STPHEN THE PROPBET. (Exodus 20: 17,) to covet a man's maid-servant or man-servant, nor anything that belongeth to him, or -that is his property! I XI. Now, doth not this 'forbid us to take the ser. vant or slave from his master? Yea, doth iti not even establish the right of property in the slave, and affix the seal of condemnation upon every one who runneth off the contraband, which was "bought" with his master's " money." XII. Furthermore, doth not this book that is called the Bible proclaim this dreadful law as one that de- scended from the Most High--"Both thy bond-men and thy bond-maids which thou shalt have, shall be of the heathen that are round about you; of them ye shall buy bond-men and bond-maids. Moreover, of the children of the strangers that do sojourn among you, of them shall ye buy and of their families that are with you, which they begat in your land, and they shall be your possession; and ye shall take them as an inheritance for your children after you to inherit them for a possession. They sha -llbe your bondmen forever." (Lev. 25: 44, 46.) A XITT. Moreover it is known unto all of us, and to the whole world, that all through the Bible, the slave is called his master's ' money ;" so that all the people must see and believe that if this Book be true, the teachings that we have taught, yea, even the doc- trines of the Woolly-Heads are false above all things, and abominably wicked. , XIV. Yea, then also are we thieves and murderers, for behold we have robbed our fellow-men of their t" money," and murdered them; even them and their wives and children, that he might establish the reli- r \       I.   23 BOOK SEECOND. gion ot the comely black Idol over them forever ana ever. hoe - to XV Li lod therefor O King, we beseech thee tog destroy this book, eve he Bible, with a prolama- tion, so that it shall be uterly destroyed, to the end that i may no more be a prop to othem hat will not worsh ip in the holy temple of the Dragon. k fltit Loom toal etmalaa weorhpl" te,   Garr -et t edta   eKig XVI. And when Grre the Flighty shall make an AaU gofg, he sh sihllown, ant the   th rong ena of h is saymgear            at othabt orshp the black IdoArl sa m  ak eaby ^obXstou Of hiug$oht noise, even of approbtion of things pr o Garre ehe Flight fy  An/[ the King shall be greatly troubled, for he knoweth tha the people love the Bible, and her ish it as a lamp to their feet; h ie e s o perceiveth that ib dooms to eternal death the doctrines of his people, the Woolly-H  eads. '    tl XVII. So when it is percehvei tha th   e ]ins is trouble&amp; in lhis mind, and dabteth   -hich lay he hall go, the great Wenuel, those surname ts Phil- lips, 4 ho cometh from a city of the Eas[ that hath a frog pond in its centre,'even he wto aforetime boastea that he haa labo red nineteen yearsto destroy he 'Union, shall get up and speak before Abraham, :saying:- why aoth th, FUng     elay to send XVriii..lok,whyich,  forth his prodlamation against the B ook,  which is the bulwark o1 the doctrines of the worshipers of mite XIX. For know ye now - haY I his pesfi lenBo o and only justifieth the holding Of men as " money afr maketh them even as other property, but the frst damnable fugitive slave law the world ever b held is Also found in the statutes 0f the Bible.  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8279-00000013"/> '24      S'IriH:EN TH E PEOPHET.  XX. For it is recorded in the sixteenth chapter of Genesis that, when Hagar, the fugitive slave of Sarai, -the wife of Abraham, was Mnissing, the "Angel of the liord" went to seek her to drag her back into slavery Again., And when the " angel of the Lord" had found the poor slave in the wilderness he said - Hagar, Sarai's maid, whence amrnest thou? and whither wilt thou , :go? And she said, I flee from the face of my mistress Sarai. And the angel of the Lord said unto her, Re- turn to thy mistress, and submit thyself under her iands. XXt. Verily, O King, how shall the temple of the black Idol stand, if such a book as this abideth? Do Ihot we teach that, if a slave runneth away we shall eltp hiim run? Yea, and if he will not run of his own accord, we shall coax him to run, and if he-is stil obh stminate we shall steal him i XXTT. Ho6w then shall we allow the Bible to con- tinue inAthe land, when it telleth- the people that the Lord sent forth his angel to bring back afugitive slave to hed mistreiss-? For will not the' people ask if it is the part of mortals to set themselves up? above aihe Lord?- arid shall we go to war to steal slaves, :when the Lord sent his angel to bring them back into slavery? XXIII, Of - tria; truth in, I perceive that- either othe Bible must be false or we must be rascals; and :as we cannot be rascals it followeth that the Bible is false. Thlen we pray, send forth thy proclamation and destroy it, so that it slall mislead tihe people no more 1!   25 IBOOK SECOND. CHAPTEI   VI1 '1 The bieg driven to his v wits'd. 2 Sendst for he man ,o God, evei tl Bi. the A .tr u, t ne ,ont'abad. s 6 Heny ale; Yea, even like minto a sick eo ab i 7 ese h. aseNnuhly f I .haithfl Beecher, propo e syeth tter he Naughty;  y  tres of the  Oled 'Iestainent the' showeth t     hat the ScO iPt., a 1tI hinys tteaOl. '"'  s a r t     a. as aye t "t hou shalt not s fea.        . I. KNo when the ing heae all hese thfogs he shall bR anriven o his Wits ends, eor he shall sea h  stt if the Bible be tr te, theen he and his foower gh  o be hang ed in the life .that now is, and damned in that which is comee  II. And in the midst of his great gyief, I e thethings that appestin to he B dst dst  he .ordof 'o, a thl s ea wAlonizo, ,. oc is aot ' r bi, f ai ul oe'iaevA )-' by' t, rte, aonde-d  3       i"bisho -r by, P'l s all sa'y fugfilnst tihe good           on A  Bhing old wen ,ii aucllwe tessed ehin of tGo Old Testamen- re not- aboog tea in condemned by Christ and his followers. II Th Aonzover CbtheTotter shall -core-beforre t6he fessed that if th e tey ,fwerae con- dispensation, so ,.'bat he came not to destroy 'a..Behold whenu Araham-shal makethis answer,  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8279-00000014"/> 26      STEPHEN THE PROPHET. the King shall turn pale, yea his countenance shall blanch like that of a sick contraband, because he shall perceive that the whole Bible is against him, and against the doctrines of the Dragon. VL. Then shall come forward Henry, the Naughty, i whose surname is Beecher, who hath a church of job-i x bers and swindlers in' a city that is built at the oppo- site side of the water from the city of Gotham. VII. And Henry, the Naughty shall say, Behold the time hath come when the truth must be told.' The Bible is a pro-slavery book. I never take a text -from it that my heart does spt smite me in the face. VIII. I trust that the loyal friends here gathered together in the presence of our mighty King, will bear in their minds the propriety of not repeating in the -ears of the ungodly beyond this solemn council of the faithful, the words herein spoken-in as much as the people of my charge, of happy confidence, pay me seven thousand dollars every year of grace for preach- ing from the Bible. IX. But here, beloved brethren, let truth be spoken -though the heavens fall; and as our good King seek- eth light, let it plainly be expressed that the Bible is a pro-slavery book. X. To what end do we seek to hide the truth from ourselves, and from the loyal worshipers of our most comely black Idol? XI. Hath it not been shown unto, you already how the Scriptures of the Old Testament would condemn us all as thieves, in that we steal what in that book ils declaeril to be a man's" noney,' and the "inheri- ' 'an-ce -of his ch;ildren forever?" ' XUI. Yen, brethren, doth it not convict us of murder,   BOO0 SECOND.        27 Iinasmuch as we make war upon men and kill them in order to deprive them and their ofspxing of their i money " forever? XIII. Harken unto me, brethren, and give ear, 0 King, for it shall be made plain unto you, that the New Testament is as pernicious as the Old, against the loyal doctrines of our most righteous party. XIV. Suffer me a little, whileI speak what isknown to the learnedt everywhere, that the word translated servant in our English text means a slave, even one that is the property of another, as in the Old Testa- ment he is called his " money," and when it hath not fhis damnable meaning, the word " hired" goeth be- tore it, so that it readeth " hired servant," in distinc- tion from one that is " bond," or as the Greek read- eth, doulo.  XV. Be it known unto you, O King, and be it I spoken with shame, that when Christ came on earth there were even more than twenty millions of slaves in the Boman Empire. XVI. And Corinth, in Greece, called "thb city of the Christians," was the chief slave market for the whole eastern side of Italy; in so much that there were at one time four hundred thousand slaves in thiat ity where Paul planted his church. XVII. Now it is known unto us that, notwithstanad- ing the Savior taught in the midst of a country and a people where slavery was as common as the air and the light of heaven, he never so much as hintedthat it was a sin, nor warned men against it as an eviL XVIII. Moreover, the Apostles founded Churches of slave-holders, without so much as rebuking them for this great, yea this damnable shame.  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8279-00000015"/> 28      STEPHEN THE PROPHET. XTX. Bear witness, beloved, that had we been the shoes of Christ and his Apostles we should have been so remiss in our duty-for verily I say you that we would have sounded the alarm Corinth to Brundisium, and from the rivers to mountains; yea, we would have split the world twain, even as we ,have split our country, before would have suffered a slave-holder to live in peace XX. Nor is this the worst, beloved brethren, f the Savior in his teachings repeatedly referred to slavery, by using it for illustrations in the most beau- tiful of his parables without even so much as once leaving upon the minds of his hearers the least im- pression that it was a sin. XXT. Did he not profess that he came to declare the whole council of God, and did he not rebuke the whole catalogue of sin, except this one, the most damnnable of all sins! XXTT. Beloved brethren. how shall we read these words of the Savior without a burning cheek-"For the kingdom of heaven is like unto a man traveling iato a far country, who. calleth his servants (slaves) il delivered unto them his gCods, aend to one he gave five: talents, to another tWo- and to another one, according to his abitli y, and straightway took 'his journey,  h  XX-T'. Behold, in these words the kingdom of, he:/v&amp;is likenetdlito a slve establishment. ,These, slaves had novlnUntairy will or choice, as to the ofaty they wire; required to -perfform. It was demanded ttiAd t hey should take and iniprove the. sum-they re- iedadred tu rn it again tow their master with the increase, and if' they did 'not do-as commanded, they   BOOK SECOND. were severely punished. Their e  anin gs nwent not to thlemselves but to their master. (See Bible.) XXIV   . Even so, O hing", does the Son of man use the institution of slavery, without reLke; for an illus- tration, in the nineteenth chapter of the book of Luke, wh   eehe describes a certain nobleman about to go into  distant country, hllo called his servants (slaves) and delivered'unto then ten pounds, commanding theM to occupy till e returne I And when he re- tuired he called them to an account, and punished -the one who had failed to obey his directions. vXX  . ,Now men and brethren do nwe not perceve that, not only did the Savior not reb uke the institn- -tion of slavery, but he used it faliliarly, mit hout leaving the faintest shspicon of sil upon it, to illus- trate the kingdom Of h eaven, XXVI. M:oreover, brethren, the Apostles taght the slaves subulission to their master, even as Timo- -thy. (I T . : 1  L-5.)-"Let as many servants as are under the yok9e count theirownmasters orthy -of all honor, that the lname bf Gocl and his doctrine be neot blasplhlemed. And they that have believing masters, let them not despise them, because they are brethren ; but rathe' do theln service, because they are faitlful and beloved, partakers of the benefit. -These things teach and exort. If any man tac- otherwise, and consent not to wholesomue words, even the words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to the doe- trine which is accrclill to godliness, he is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about questions and strifes of words, whereof cometh envy, strife, railings, evi: sumaisings perverse disputings of men of corirupt -'-i"u m sn s .   &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8279-00000016"/> 30       STEPHEN THE rOPHST. minds, and destitute of the truth, supposing that gain is godliness : from such withdraw thyself." XXVII. Behold wha t the Apostle here teacheth; even that if any man teach otherwise than reverence and submlission on the part of slaves to their masters, lhe is yp;roud, 7kowing nothing, but doting alout ques- tions and strifes of cocrds, -zhereof cometh envyr, sltti/fe, razings, evil surm7isings, pertver'se disputings of men of coriulpt nmids and cdestitute of truth /' and the Apostle warns the christian--"fron szuch zmthdraw thysel^." Now, therefore, O Kihg, if this Book be allowed to stand, how know we but that the people will say that this scripture is like a prophesy of us, even of the abolitionists who make it our boast- that we teacli those under the yoke to " despise " their masters, and to refiuse "to do lthem service, yea, to run away from, and if need be to murder tuhem! XXVIII. Verily it maketh a man's bones ac1he to think of the character the Apostle driweth of such as we make our loyal boast to be! XXIX. Moreover, what better than this abomina- ble teachincg is that of the Apostle Paul to the slaves in Ephesus. (EPH. VI: 5.)-"Servants, be obedienk unto them that are your masters according to the ? flesh, with fear and trembling, in singleness of, your heart as unto Christ." XXX. Even so did Paul command the slaves that  were among the Colossians (CoL. n : 22.) saying :- ' Servants, obey in all things your masters accord6ing to the flesh, not with eye-service as men-pleasers; but in singleness of heart, fearing God." XXXI. The same things said Paul, in his Epistle to Titus. (TITUS, I: 9.)--"Exhort servants to be   BOOK SECOND.        31 obedient to their own masters, and to please them in all things; not answering again; not purloining, but showing all go:-d fidelity ; that they may adorn the doctrine of Go I oar Savior in all things." Now brethren, the Apostle commands slaves not only to be obedient to their masters in all things, but he enjoins it upon them that they do not steal; whereas we teach the slave both to steal and to murder, and finally make an end of the matter by ourselves robbing the master of his slave. Verily, how can we stand, if we destroy not this teaching of the Apostle? XXXII. Moreover, the Apostle teacheth by impli- cation that such as teach the slave not to obey his master do not "adorn the doctrine of God our Savior." What then are we, brethren, if this teaching be not false? XXXIII. Even the same commanded the Apostle Peter to the slaves in Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia. (I PETER, II: 18.)--"Servants (slaves) be subject to your masters with all fear; not only to the good and gentle, but also to the froward. For this is thankworthy, if a man for conscience toward-God endure grief, suffering wrongfully." XXXIV. But even further, O King, the Apostles do not stop with enjoining slaves to be obedient to their masters, for they also instruct the masters in their duty to their slaves, thus at once recognizing the lawfulness of the institution. (EPH. VI: 9.) "And ye masters, do the same thing unto them, for- bearing threatening: knowing that your master also is in heaven." XXXV. Behold the Apostle teacheth not the mas- T .Behold the Apos,.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8279-00000017"/> c)P      STEPHEN TRE PROPHET. ter that it is lis duty to Owancipate lis slave, but that he shall be kIind to him, and merciful, ven as h exects lmerc of 'heaven, wherel he also hath a mas- XxXV  . BretldelnIet us have the whole olter I for the apostles not only teach the slave submission but even contentment with their lot, even as Paul when writing to those whom he had converted in the great slave mart at Corinth. (Con. vn: 20, 21.)- "Let every man. abide in the same calling whereill le notfoas clled. Art thou called being a se,'vctnt? cae  nor for" it, u if hoe majyest be nmade free, use it rather.", XXX;VI. Behold the Apstloe teaceth slavce to  to e content with whatever lot, lichever it mray be. X- VIII. Even so the Apostle of the Lord Jesus Christ made hlnself the execfutor of tihe f-ugitive-sla veG law tiat was in vogue in fliose days. For whlen a good:for-nothing  slave, nameil nesinus, had ruln away from Philemon his master, he went to Rome, where he heard Paul preach and was conerted, XXXTX. Behold rhlen fle Apostle lnew e his case he sent him directly back to his master; which tiling we should not do, for, verily, tlme Lord kinoreth tfiat we should- sed him on his way to Canada, or help him to go back stealthily to poison his master. XL. Know also bLrefLren, tlat this slaveholder Ph2ilemon, had a church of believers in- Christ wlfich met in his own house. And the Apostle calls this slave-holdr a "cfellow beloved" and a "dearly be- loved brother ; and upon the believing Slave-hoders  who met for worsiip in Philemon's house he pro-  hous hep   nounced the benediction-"Grace to you and peace, fr:om God our Father and our Lord Jesus Christ." XTUT. Behold, brethren, such is not the benediction we pronounced upon the slave-holding professors, but that other one, even the baptism of fire, sword,-star- vation and death!         - XLTTT. Verily, this false teaciher, even Paul, and his slavery-defending epistles must be squelched, or we must go down to our grave with the word of infidel and assassin engraved upon our name. XLIII. Even so, brethren, did the Son of Man, even rafter the same fashion that his Apostles received - slaveholders; for when a slave-holding Centurian came to him, beseeching him to heal his sick servant,' ;slave), the Lord immediately restored his slave, and turning to his disciples, said : "Verily I say unto you, I have -not found so great faith, no, not in Israel," (MATT. VIII: 10.)  I XLIV. Now, brethren, is this the way  to treat slaveholders?  O mighty King, thy true and loyal subjects beseech thee to hear us, and destroy, even with thy fierce proclanzation this Book, even the Bible, which is the bulwark of slavery, and a stumbling block to the feet of many. And when Henry Ward the Naughty had said these things, he subsided, remind- ing the brethren that his- speech was entirely confi- deltial. XLV. So whllen HenWy the NTaughty shall subsfid a great man among the Woolly-Heads, even he th is called Garrison, because he hath'set himself for defense of the temple of the Dragoa, shall come for- ward before the King  aad rejoice with a lbud voice, savin : * - *  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8279-00000018"/> 34      STEPHEN Tre PROPHET. XLVI. Noi is the day of my triumph! for did I not declare, even twenty years ago, that te only oe of the save was over thegrave of the American Glurch? Now then, O mighty King, make the Bible to follow the Constitution, that they may both rot together in the same grave! VZII   And the grand Council of Loyal Leaguers shall rejoice with joy unspeakable at these things. CHAPTER     VIII.        1 bram promise&amp; to issue a procdamation against te I Bible. 4 He tellet a story of a man whose sons killeth A2kknls,  10 He -shozweathat tke Bible hai o Eect?*/ he od W02iY nds. .13. e shoeWth that the Bible is no aore in he way of a Loyal League, than a small corn i on the toe of a strong man. 16 Stephen, surnarad Aos. t, showeth that1the Ten Commandments recognize the right of slavery 19 He shouoeth tat ChrisA el- rs *. the same. 21 A :.aha. ssatisfied..  I. And when the King heareth this counsel of hi"  faithfl, he shall answer them saying, I am persuaded of the truth of all that these men of wisdom fhave uttered; and in the fullness of time it shall be even as you desire. IT. But, as for the present, it is yet too soon o I break to the whole world the marvelous tings revealed in the divine temple of the Dragon. "I. Have I not already done as much as the peo- ple will bear? Even so let us wait a little, until the people get a back strong enough to carry the whole  load that we shall lay upon it. IV. And the King telleth a story of a man who had    three sons who had a great desire a-d knack, withal, at killing skunks.    t- V. One day the three Sons addressed their Faerat five o'clock in the morning, W e beseech thee, Father, to let us go out into the field and kill slknks. The Father said yea; and they went out, and behold they killed six skunks before breakfast, so that all the ar,- for miles round about, was loaded with the suffio cating stink of skunks. VI. And at the sixth hour of the- day, the--three Sons again besought their Father to let them g ing skunks, and he said yea; and they went:o :itfaa . 'killed ten skunks, so that the whole neighbodorod was choked almost beyond the power of mortals to endure. , VII. And at eventide the three Sons again be- sought their Father to let them go killing skunks. But this time the old man said, Nay,. my boysy you Mave made stink enough for one day. Vill. Now behold, O  my friends, have not my proclamations made stink enough for the present; and sha tl- we not more wisely wait a little before I ut- ter my proclamation against the Bible. IX. Verily I say unto you, if the Bible supports slavery, educate the people to hate slavery, and then you will, with greater ease, persuade them to hate the Bible. X. Besides, my friends, your King perceiveth that tI'e Bible, is of no account'with them that are willing' to worslip our comely black Idol. XI. For has not brother Henry the Naughty, Iroved to us that it is no stumbling block to his feet. 2Even so with our dear brothers, Cheever, Tyng, Vin-  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8279-00000019"/> 36      STE'P'AM"If THE PROPHETO ton, Bellows', 'and almosAtthe whole throng'ofpreaeC- era-do not they all show that the Bible is as nothing to6them, whenever it :comethin the way of the doc- trines of the comely black IdolJ. :XIL: What availeth-it that tley read that[ the Sou of man healeth the sick 'slaveskof slave-holders, andl then prpionounceth: a benediction upon their masters? or wha aimle'th it;,that Paul, the Apostle, teacheor slaves to' obey:,their masters, and calleth the slave- holders ".v'ell beloved brethren;" verily I say u t) y[offi:t1 hse miniisterts wiM steal a slave-cand; cut his :-na:ster troat JUSt as readily as -though they had never r6ad th 'Bible.- ill. e' L      rhr n ta XIIL"Even so you perceive, beloved brethren, that the:Bible, like a small :corn on the toe of a strong maan, hurteth not much. When we find that it does, '- w -shal- prloclaim against it, and. send it headlong after 'the remains of the Constitution which was so long its"twin bulWark of slavery. XIV. But saith the King, after the manner of his joking, we will spare the Ten Commandments, in or- der that our dear friends, the preachers, may have left unto them a few texts to preach from. XV. And when Stephen-not he that was stoned, but that stoneth all who are not worshipers of the slack Idol, and whose surname is Foster-heareth the King, he shall spring up in great anger and open his mouth, with a loud voice, saying- XI. Behold, O King, if you spare that accursed decalogue which is called the Ten Comman dments you give up all, and we shall one day be hanged as thieves --for know you not that- both tho Fourth anpd Tenth Commandments include the rolation of master atd   BOOR BECONDS.       37 slave, wherein we are forbidden to covet a maun'im an- servant nor his maid-servant?  XVII. Verily this admitteth not of doubt. We are commanded not to covet what belongeth to an- other, that is, what is his property, in the list of *wich things are his man-servant and his maid-ser- vant, which we know were slaves, for they belonged to XVIII. Now this is a part of the organic law of the people of Israel, which it is claimed, God delivered to Moses on Mount Sinai. There is no blinking the matter--if they are God's Commandments, we are forbidden to disturb a man's property in his slaves, aust as much as we are forbidden to meddle with his propery in his cattle. This is the law of the Deca- logue. God forbid that an anti-slavery man should ever stultify himself by admitting such an accursed Decalogue to be divine!    XIX. Furthermore, men and brethren, Christ most fully endorsed and confirmed these odious slave-- holding laws of the Jews and the Decalogue, for he declared that he "came not-to destroy but to ful- fill" them-yea, he said that "one jotor one tittle shall in no wise pass from the law 'till all befulflled." He makes no exception. He swallowed the Deca- logue whole, slavery statute and all. XX. Behold therefore, O Abraham, thou must not think to put off this matter with thy jokes about skunkls; for I say unto thee, that if the Bible be the Word of God, and thou allowest it to stand, the day shall come when we shall be held a genrati of skutnes; yea, and our very names shall stink in the nos'trls of me, froa geoeroti on to generatiOn.  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8279-00000020"/> - 38     ISTEPHEN THE PROPHET. XXI. And when Stephen sayeth these things the lKing shall tremble, and he shall sit stupified, so that  -the water droppeth from his under lip, for he knoweth not which -way to turnm.     - CHAPTER IX             1 A m1rry Andrews comneth from a city that hrth a fIog. pond 2n its centre, with a delegation of a hundred Minis. ters. 2 }e beseeck Abraham to utter a proclamation against crtan ooks. 6 They shtow tiat the 2issionaries in Africa lie about the negroes. 13 Aorace, the Tribune, ieth about the Jfricans. 17 Showeth that certain books nust be suppressed or, the Wooly teads be damned. 19 Te 100 Ministers sfcream sr &amp;led that they sli the King's I. Behold while the King remaineth in these  straights, a merry-Andrews from that city of the East, that hath the frog-pond in the centre thereof, riveth in the city of the Dragon, even in Washing. ton, at the head o a delegation of an hundred minis-  ters from the tribe of the Puritans.  I. And straightway they go in before the King, and, having chosen a spokesman,-even one Kirk, who celebrateth with the negroes, and maketh himself as  one of them, standeth down close to the King and beginneth fto barrangue, saying-We have 'come, an hundred ministers strong, to beseech thee, OAbraham, to utter thy proclamation and suppress all of certailn mischievious and damnable books, both of histories and travels, which reveal the condition of the negro in his native land, even in Africa, the place which tih e  Lord gave him and made him what he is, even as tfieo hiltteman hath his native clime, and inheriteth the character which he weareth.   BOOK SECOND. S "I. For know then, thatthese pestilent books of histories and travels, give such an account of the idolatrous and damnable state of the-negro in his own land that persuadeth the people that it were a deed  of Christian charity, yea mercy to take him therefrom and bring him even to servitude in Sunland. IV. For they say, verily the negro is a thousand fold better off even in slavery in Sunland, than in his own native country. V. Now, let us see what sayeth these books, which we would have thee to exterminate by proclamation., So be it that they all agreed that the negro hath never made one step of improvement, while left to himself, without the white man's aid, no, not since the beginniv g of history-verily showing that the race is, of its own forces, unimproving, and naturally with- out any of the great marks of the Caucasian man, who is his master in Sunland. Behold how camel reason then declareth that in- stead of its being a wrong to bring the negro from his natural beastly state, and place him at service in Sunland, it is the greatest blessing that can befall him.  X VI. What sayeth oven the Rev. John Leighton Wilson, a Secretary of the Presbyterian Board of Foreign Mission, the same who was for many years a missionary in Africa! Even thus he slandeoreth the poor negro: "It is a common remark of the present day, that "the heathen world is as depraved now as it was in "the days of Paul. But: this does not meet the case. "It is worse now than it was- then. There are but "few- modern missionaries who cannot testify to the  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8279-00000021"/> - 40     STEPHEN THE PROPHET. -'existene of forms of human depravityamong-them, "'of which there is no mention in the Apostle's cate- "' gory, and of which perhaps there was no existence w"in his day. . . The depth of infamy and pollu. "tion to which the African tribes have already re- -' duced themselves, can scarcely be conceived." Behold how this vile traducer of our comely black Brethren -proceedeth to revile the Lord's anointed- for he sayeth that " they worship devils,' and then goeth on after this fashion: .. ." If it be true, and -it undoubtedly is, that our ' moral- characters constantly assimilate to the char- :' acter of the Being we worship, it follows as a neces- ' sary consequence, that African character has been ' approximating for. centuries to a model the most "hideously .immoral and depraved the human imagi. ' nation can conceive. And here is at once the secret ' cause of all that cunning, duplicity, and cruelty that "have ever characterized this people. Theelinea- -'ments; of 'the divine image have been effectually ' effaced from their hearts, .whilst those of the spirits ' of the infernal pit have been drawn with too bold a "' hand to be mistaken or misapprehended." VYll. Moreover, this blaspheming missionary, speaking of what his own eyes hath seen, exhibteth our brethren, as Without natural affection, implacable, unmerciful. A mother, for rum or for a few yards of cloth, will "' sell her child, and -a husband will sell his wife. Theo "inhabitants of one village, without having received any provocation, will attack at midnight the sleep- "ing inhabitants of a neighboring village, and sell *" 'o Gare y ball wh*a they eaa eaptro, whila &amp;baey   BOOK SECOND.        1J. "nmurder every one who resists them, and destroy the "village."            '    - IX. Behold also what sayeth Carnot, who had twenty years experience in Africa-he telleth of two towns at Dighy, governed by two, cousins who had always lived in harmony, until some slavers established a d(pot for the purchase of slaves in the town of the younger cousin, iwhich so offended the elder through jealousy that they became at enmity one vath the  other, and immediately put t-heir towns in a state of defense. X. Now when the slaver came again four months afterwards they ewent to the settlement of the elder brother, which produced such rejoicing that they danced and caroused until long after midnight, " when all stole off to maudlin sleep." Then proceedeth the narrative as followeth, in these words: "About three o'clock in the morning the sudden "( screams of women and children and volleys of mus- "ketry aroused him. The town awas attacked by the "younger cousin, aided by buslmnen, headed by a fe- "rocious scoundrel, who, with his chiefs, were canni-. "bls, ' and never torod the war path wilthout a pledge "-to retun laden with human flesh to gorge their "households. These savages rushed with shouts "through the town, murdering every one whom they "encountered. After the first massacre was ended "and the day had begun, they assembled around "their leader at the Palaver House, and there was "scarcely one of them who did not bring the body of "some maimed and bleeding victim, who- were M tum- "bled on a heap in the centre. -Immediately after, "a procession of women, whose naked linibs were  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8279-00000022"/> 42. STEPHEN THE PROPHET. "'mearedl with chalk and, ochre, poured into the "Palaver House to join the beastly-rites, each armed "with a knife and bearing in her hand some cannibal trophy. Tlhen came the refreshment, in the shape "of rum, powder, and blood, which was quaffed by "the brutes till they reeled off with linked hands in "a wild -dance around the pile of victims. As the "women leaped and sang, the men applauded and "encouraged. I forbear to transcribe his account "of the revolting scene of lasciviousness and cruelty "which followed.*" XII. Behold, O King, there is not a book that toucheth on this matter that slandereth not after the same fashion our comely black brethren-setting forth how in their own land they live in holes, and in caves of the rock, eating snakes and worms, and even eating each other as no beasts of the forest will eat their own kind.  XTTT. And even our own brother Horace, thy M3a- jesty's-Tribune, in a late writing, in his own paper, useth his pen after this fashion, to the great shame of our holy cause: (His Blood-smeared and Mud-smeared Majesty of "Dahomey,:nitescent in all the glory of green feath- "ers and red oche, has recently been pathetically re- "quested by a Christian officer to give up that diver- "sion of wholesale murder which has for so many s" ages been the delight of African Royalty, and has, "indeed, constituted the chief charm of Coronations "and Funerals in those parts. We regret to say that "this Royal Personage, being of a highly conserva- , ftive nature, and satisfied that the true happiness of *See frnot, oh * ,-.  *    . ,   BOOK SECOND.        4: "his subjects depends upon the killing of a largo "number of them annually, declines to abandon the venerable custom, as we suppose, both upon political "and religious grounds; and has given the benevo- "Ient remonstrant to undertand that his benevolence "is impertinent and untimely. 'I must,' says this "fraternal Prince,' have a certain number of skulls to "garnish my stockades withal.'"  XIV. Behold, shall we destroy our country, and murder our countrymen for such a race as this! 0 King, if so be it that these things are true, how shall we say that the African has been wronged by being brought' into Sunland? For then verily it were a mercy if all Africa could be made as well off as the wretchedest negro who serves in Sunland! XV. Now, therefore, these books must be de- stroyed, yea, all of them, or we are without excuse before men. For we know of ourselves that, in'the country that is called San Domingo, the negro, by reason of his emancipation, hath gone back to the re-  ligion of his native land, and worshipeth the green snake, denying the gospel of Christ which he was taught and did obey in his servitude!* XVI. Now of these books, even of histories, travels, and -missionary reports, there are many; yea more than a thousand, which are pestilent fountains of in- formation for the people; the same being used by the worshipers of White deities to convict us of being fools or knaves, to turn the world upside down about nothing, and to deluge the land with the blood of our kindred, in the main effort to make the negro even that which Jehovah hath denied him the power to be!           .  Rce Report of the London Bapt ist Miionry Soeiety.  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8279-00000023"/> {41      STEPHEN THE PROPHET. :XVII. Verily, O King, these books must be sup- pressed, and the mouths of such as have read them and wickedly repeat the same, must be stopped; else -wre, of all men, shall receive the greate dcamnation. - XVIII. Therefore we beseech thee to utter thy deadly proclamation 'against them. Proclaim them to be lies. Make thou the travelers, the historians, and the missionaries all to be liars, so that we mtay silence the idolatrous nation that worshipeth at the altars of the White deities. XIX. Lo, when the spokesman uttereth these say- ings, all the other ninety and nille ministers shall cry out with a loud voice Amen! so that the King thnk- eth the drum of his ears to be cracked. XX.- Then each one of the hundred ministers shall shalke hands with Abram ; and thereafter they shall all return to the land of the Puritans, the chief city of Which hath the frog-pond in the centre, of the which it; inhabitiants are- so proud that they sing songs about it conitilually.. CHAPTER X. i Abrahamn is overwhelmeedl y- Co zomnzittees. 2-. The Doctor driveth them away by spreading that the King ,zath the Small-Pox. 7 A Committee of Ministers goeth to the King to ask a Proclamation to put Blacks and Whites to Oed together. 8 The King refuseth. 9 He showeth that this Good Work is already providedfor. 1 1 - Hedeclaret -that Copperheads shall not mix'with the, Wenches. He wanteth a. pure breed of Negroes and Loyal Leaguers. 16 One Vinton trieth to kiss the King's toe.  I. Now, Abraham' shall sgrow more, and more op- pressed day -by daYv. by reason of the Committees that   BOOK SECOND.        45 ,ome before him demanding proclamations. So great an anxiety shall prey upon his peace of mind that it. throweth him into a spotted fever which the doctors think to be small-pox, and thereby a great alarm spreadeth among the Woolly-Heads froim one end of the land to the other. II. And when the King at last findeth himself to be getting well, he shall begin to dread the Committees, and he shall say to his physician, Doctor, do thou give that which shall sicken me again, that I may be kept even here out of the reach of the Committees; for of a truth I perceive that they will kill me. "I. And the Doctor shall spread abroad a report that the King hath a relapse, and that the small-pox spreadeth alarmingly throughout the city, so that ten thousand committee-men that came to see the King shall suddenly flee back to their homes whence they came. IV. And Abraham shall laugh at the cunning trick which his physician putteth upon the Committee-men. But verily I say unto you that his joy shall be short, for soon there, cometh a Committee which will not be put off, for they would speak with the imng about a matter that is like life and death unto them. V. So when Abraham perceiveth that they will not be turned away, he giveth himself up to his fate, and receiveth them. VI. And they sliall come in unto him, a great throng; the chief leader being one Theodore, sur- named Tilton, and a certain Divine, who is called Bellows because he bloweth much, and that Stephen who is called Tyng, because he goeth on, ting-a-ling, like a bell continually about everything, and one  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8279-00000024"/> "-     STEPHEN THE PROPHET. Vinton, called the sozer-faced, because he vainly trieth to put on a godly look when he prayeth, for by these means he getteth a living, and among them also com- eth Henry Ward, the Naughty, the same who afore- time harrangued the fKing about the Bible. VII. And when these shall stand before Abraham, the man Theodore shall open his mouth saying: We have come, great and mighty Monarch, to ask of thee a proclamation declaring the prejudice against people of color to be' unreasonable and sinful; and also to make it proper and fitting for a white man to go with a black, woman, and for a white woman to go with a black man, that they may miscegnate one with another whereby a new and improved type of the American man may be produced. , Vll. Then Abralham shall answer them, Where- fore do you ask me to establish by proclamation what is going on well enough already! For have not my Generals and my Chaplains in the -army done this thing to an amazing extent? Moreover, during my reign, have not five thousand of this improved tpye of the: American man been born in this our -beloved  city alone? IX. What would ye  Have I not sent ministers and school-teachers, and a; whole army of so-called agents, to follow up the success of our legions, whose business it is, not only to teach the old contrabands, but to ,ns;ceYgncef with' the younger,- that they mnna raise up a new genertation of the American man 1 X. Moreover, you learned and pious men, do you not shoW that you understand, and have no doubt tasted, the benefits of m iscegnation with the comely daughters of Ethiopia? And have we not good news   BOOK SECOND.        47  from every part of our kingdom that the good work is going on well, in as much as our Loyal Leagues are all devoted to the same great and glorious end ? XI.L Then they shall answer the King, even as thou sayest, so it is true; but the Copper2'eads are a stff- necked and a proud people, who not only refuse to mix in our perfect and loving equality with the blacks, but they wickedly laugh and sneer at us withal. 'XII. And the King shal say, What! would ye have the veins of our new and improved generation poisoned with the blood of the Copperheads ? Verily no! Unto you of the Loyal Leagues, belongeth the happy monopoly of miscegnation with the blacks, and would ye share it-with Copperheads? Not if the court understand herself, as she thinks she do. XTTL Then they shall answer, saying, But the Copperheads are men given to the subtlety of science, -who publish many books to show that the offspring of the blacks and whites run out after the third gener- ation, so that they cannot propagate their species, the which, if the people believe it, showeth that they are not of one race, and that at last our new and im- proved type of the' American .man would, become' ex- tinct, so that we should have no posterity in the land of our fathers? XIV. And Abraham shall answer them, Now why trouble yourselves about posterity? What has pos- terity ever done for us, that we should sacrifice our happiness in its behalf ?  erily I say unto you that long enough before the time of three generations, we shall be done with the country, and let those who follow us do the best they can with what we leave, even as we will make the best thiOng we can for our- selves in our day and generation.   &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8279-00000025"/> 48$ STEPHEN THE PROPHET. + ' ' '              J  ' ' XV. Then the' Committee shall look one in the face of another, and say among themselves, The King speakethwisely, and asbeseemeth a patriot; therefore let us retire, even to our own houses, and follow the council of the King, and let the Copperheads content themselves with the foolishness of science, and hug themselves with the proud memories of their ances- tors; but as forus, we will make ourselves merry with greenbacks, and with the fragrant daughters of Ethiopia. XVI. But before they retire from the presence of the King they shall, one after another, kneel before him, tokiss his hand; and one, even the man who is called Vihton the Sour-faced, shall entreat the pleas- are of kissing the King's toe; but when Abraham seeth what a face he hath, he shall decline, for the reason that he hath on dirty stockings, saying, My wife hath not' been at home for these two months, so that my household fixings are, even as the rebel army, which is, telegraphically, in a demoralized con- dition XVII. Here endeth the Second Book of the Prophet Stephen, Son of Douglas.    &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>