<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8042">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Catharine and Clara, or, The Double Suicide </title>
            <author >Thompson, George, (d. 1893)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC8042</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Catharine and Clara, or, The double suicide</title>
                  <author >Thompson, George, (d. 1893)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >46 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Federhen</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1854">1854</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="AEL Data" when="2003-04-28">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-08-19">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <pb  n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8042-00000001"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>CATHARINE AND CLARA,</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">OR THE DOUBLE SUICIDE:</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">A TRUE TALE OF DISAPPOINTED LOVE.</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="desc">This thrilling narrative is founded upon the recent suicide of Catharine B. Cotton and Clara C. Cochran, at Manchester New Hampshire. The terrible effects of disappointed love are depicted with startling eloquence and power, by a writer who came into possession of all the true facts of the case.</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <epigraph > 
               <q>
                  <lg type="quotation"> 
                     <l>I shall soon in death be sleeping,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Far away where strangers dwell</l> 
                     <l>Far from all those haunts of pleasure,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">That in youth I loved so well.</l> 
                     <l>Flow'rs shall not be o'er me planted,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Nor shall willows o'er me wave-</l> 
                     <l>Marble columns decked with grandeur,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Ne'er shall mark my humble grave.</l> 
                  </lg>
               </q> 
            </epigraph> 
            <docEdition>COPYRIGHT SECURED ACCORDING TO ACT OF CONGRESS</docEdition> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>BOSTON.</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >PUBLISHED BY FEDERHEN &amp; CO., <address> 
                     <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">9 AND 13 COURT STREET.</addrLine> 
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint> 
            <docDate>1854.</docDate> 
         </titlePage> 
         <div type="frontis"> 
            <pb n="3 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8042-00000002"/> 
            <p>
               <figure> 
                  <head>MISS CATHARINE B COTTON.</head> 
               </figure>
            </p> 
         </div> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Catharine and Clara, or, The double suicide</head> 
            <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC8042-00000003"/> 
             
            <head>CATHARINE AND CLARA,</head> 
            <head type="sub">OR THE DOUBLE SUICIDE:</head> 
            <head type="sub">A TRUE TALE OF DISAPPOINTED LOVE.</head> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head> 
               <p>KIND reader, on the wings of fancy accompany us to Biddeford, in the State of Maine. It is summer, and the air is full of music and perfume-the melody of birds, and the ordor of flowers. It is the Sabbath, too, and the very atmosphere, so soft and sweet, seems full of the sanctity and holiness of the occasion. The church-bell chimes out its gentle invitation, and a throng of the piously inclined inhabitants are wending their way towards the house of prayer and praise. Observe that neat white cottage, which modestly half conceals itself amid trees and shrubbery. How tastefully the little garden is laid out in front, and how prettily the snowy curtains are arranged at the windows! Surely, that beautiful spot must be the abode of contentment, and the home of loveliness and virtue.</p> 
               <p>Let us put on our invisible caps, and enter. A small parlor, exquisitely furnished, meets our gaze. Everything announces the presence of an elegant, delicate, and femenine taste. But where is the presiding divinity of this gem of comfort? There she sits, upon the sofa; and we shall now attempt a brief description of her personal appearance, for the gratification of our lady readers, who are always supposed to be curious about such<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC8042-00000004"/> matters, and also for the benefit of our male friends, whom we presume to be admirers of female beauty.</p> 
               <p>Miss Catharine B. Cotton is about twenty years of age, although she looks somewhat younger. She is what the world would call a very lovely woman; and a close observer would be charmed with the peculiarly melancholy and tender expression of her dark eyes, which indicate the depth and intensity of her soul. It is easy to perceive that if she once places her affections upon an object, the slightest disappointment will break her heart. Who can be so base as to tamper with that pure, confiding heart, and destroy its hopes of peace and happiness forever?</p> 
               <p>Catharine is perfectly formed, and her wavy hair falls in rich masses over her ivory shoulders. She is dressed in a style of simple elegance; and, although she is nothing but an humble factory girl, she is, in education, in manners, and in appearance, a lady.</p> 
               <p>She is not alone. By her side is seated a well-dressed young man, of prepossessing appearance. We can see, at a single glance, that he is her lover, and that she adores him. Her head reclines upon his shoulder, in a confiding and affectionate manner, and his arm encircles her waist. Occasionally, she gazes up into his face with looks of ardent love; then she blushes, and casts down her eyes; and then his lips meet hers in a "long-drawn kiss of ecstasy."</p> 
               <p>But love scenes are always tedious, except to the parties principally interested; and, therefore, we shall not dwell upon this interview between the lovers. After a little harmless dalliance, which the reader will have the kindness to imagine, and save us the trouble of describing, Catharine remarked, as she partially withdrew herself from the close embrace of her companion,-</p> 
               <p>"Dear Cyrus, the church-bell is ringing, and the sound seems to reproach me for failing to attend divine worship. Are we not very sinful in thus neglecting our Christian duties?"</p> 
               <p>"No, Catharine," replied her lover, "the passion of love is holy, and the Sabbath is just as appropriate for its indulgence, as any other day. But come, give me another kiss, and I must then tear myself away, for I have an appointment with a gentleman, in relation to matters of business."</p> 
               <p>The kiss was given, and repaid with twenty: and as the lovers prepared to separate, Catharine remarked,-</p> 
               <p>"Cyrus, you know that the time appointed for our marriage is near at hand. <emph>The ceremony must not be delayed.</emph> But are you content to become the husband of a poor factory girl?"</p> 
                
               <p>"You are dearer to me than you would be, if you were the heiress of a princely fortune," was the reply of Cyrus; but, as he spoke, a slight and almost imperceptible smile curled his lips-a false and mocking smile, that announced a cruel and an inconstant heart.</p> 
               <p>"To-morrow," said Catharine, "I am going to Pownal, to make preparations for our wedding. I shall return here one week before the day appointed for the performance of the nuptial ceremony that will make us <emph>one,</emph> and sanctify our mutual love. Farewell, dearest Cyrus, and remember that the happiness of my whole life depends on you. I do not believe that you are capable of deceiving me; but, if you <emph>should,</emph> I never would survive the blow!"</p> 
               <p>Again that hollow, contemptuous smile! Cyrus, if thou art not false, then was <emph>Iago</emph> true, and <emph>Benedict Arnold</emph> a patriot!</p> 
               <p>"I never shall deceive you, Kate," said the hypocrite, as he drew on his gloves, and having once more kissed his unsuspecting victim, he departed.</p> 
               <p>Catharine gazed after his receding form and her bosom swelled with agitation, for a strange presentiment of evil took possession of her soul.</p> 
               <p>"I love him to distraction," said she to herself, "but I cannot help mistrusting his strange, peculiar smile! O, would to heaven that to-morrow were our wedding-day!"</p> 
               <p>Catharine, plunged in melancholy thoughts, seated herself and drew from her bosom a miniature of Cyrus. While she was contemplating those handsome but deceitful features, Miss Davis, her friend and companion in the mills, entered. Miss Davis is a young lady of superior manners and appearance, and possesses a mind of extraordinary acuteness and cultivation, for one of her social position. To her is the author indebted for many of these facts.</p> 
               <p>The two young ladies saluted each other affectionately, and then entered into conversation.</p> 
               <p>"My dear Catharine," said Miss Davis, seriously, "I just now saw your friend, Cyrus, leaving the house, I candidly confess to you that I do not like that young man. As your particular friend, I wish that you would entirely relinquish his society. I do not desire to interfere with your private affairs, but I really cannot refrain from advising you to beware of that man. He may be handsome and agreeable, but his countenance is full of treachery. Depend upon it, if you place any confidence in him, he will deceive you in the end."</p> 
               <p>"You must be prejudiced against Cyrus," said Catharine,<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC8042-00000005"/> with some severity, "pray has he ever injured you in any way?"</p> 
               <p>Miss Davis blushed scarlet, as she replied,-</p> 
               <p>"I once regarded Cyrus as a friend-as a brother. He insulted me, and when I treated him with scorn, he used language which displayed a corrupt heart, and a deficiency in moral principle. That is why I dislike him, and that is why, as your friend, I am opposed to your intimacy with him."</p> 
               <p>Catharine sighed deeply, for again did that mysterious presentiment of evil arise within her breast.</p> 
               <p>"Tell me, Catharine," said Miss Davis, earnestly, "have you been indiscreet-have you forgotten yourself so far as to-"</p> 
               <p>"O, ask me not," interrupted Catharine, bursting into tears, "I am the most miserable being on the face of the earth. Yet I think that Cyrus will marry me-I <emph>know</emph> he will!"</p> 
               <p>"Poor girl, I pity you from the bottom of my heart," said Miss Davis, in tones of sincere compassion.</p> 
               <p>After some further conversation, which it is unnecessary to repeat, Miss Davis left her friend, with the assurance of her constant advice and sympathy.</p> 
               <p>Catharine, being alone, abandoned herself to her sorrowful reflections. Yet hoping that her lover would prove true, notwithstanding what had been said against him, she began to prepare for her next day's journey to Pownal, her native home, where she intended to make arrangements for her anticipated wedding.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head> 
               <p>"THE silly creature loves me dearly, that is plain enough; but how can she help doing <emph>that,</emph> when I am such a good-looking and fascinating fellow? The girls of these factory-places all adore me; and at this moment I have a dozen, each one believing that I am hers exclusively. Poor Catharine! I like her well enough, and she certainly is a charming girl, but then I can't marry her. What! throw myself away upon a poor factory-girl! Never! No, Cyrus, you must become the husband of some rich heiress, whose wealth will enable you to live like a prince! I have my eye now on a fair damsel, who has money, as well as beauty; and if I can but succeed in winning <emph>her,</emph> I am a made man! Catharine is going to Pownal to-morrow, to prepare for our wedding. Ha, ha! What will she say when I in form her that I never <emph>intended</emph> to make her my wife? However, she'll soon get over the disappointment; for a woman's heart is not so easily broken as some people imagine. While Catharine is away I shall have a splendid opportunity to flirt to my heart's content with every pretty girl in Biddeford and elsewhere."</p> 
               <p>It was with such cruel, selfish thoughts as these that Cyrus left Catharine's abode, and wended his way along for the purpose of enjoying a solitary walk in the country. His statement to Catharine, that he had an appointment to keep with a gentleman on business, was an untruth. That statement was an absurdity; for people in puritanical New England are not apt to transact business on the Sabbath. Cyrus had become tired of Catharine's society; her presence seemed to reproach him, and therefore he avoided her as much as possible.</p> 
               <p>The young man walked along, enjoying the salubrity of the air and the fair prospect around him. He had reached a retired and lonely spot, when suddenly a strange, wild-looking figure darted from behind a tree and confronted him.</p> 
               <p>The figure was that of a young female, worn and wasted almost to a skeleton, yet retaining in her face and form traces of beauty and of grace. In her eyes blazed the fires of insanity, and her garb, language, and actions, all announced a "mind in ruins." Her raiment was tattered, and carelessly put on; no shoes protected her feet; and the only shelter for her head was a fantastic wreath, formed of flowers and leaves.</p> 
               <p>This poor creature placed herself directly in the young man's path, and greeted him with a loud shout of maniac laughter, that made the blood run cold in his veins.</p> 
               <p>"<emph>You</emph> here, Mag!" said Cyrus, in a tone of assumed compassion, while his agitated countenance betrayed fear, and a desire to cut short the unpleasant interview. "Poor, foolish girl, why does not some one take care of you? Why are you not provided with a home, instead of being permitted to lead this life of privation and misery? You ought, at all events, to be placed in the Lunatic Asylum, where your shattered intellect might possibly be restored to reason."</p> 
               <p>"Ha, ha!" screamed the maniac girl-and, reader, is it not strange that laughter, the offspring of mirth and delight, should be the favorite sound of those unfortunates who are bereft of reason?-"ha, ha! How very benevolent-what a great philanthropist you are! You'd like to see me in the Lunatic Asylum, so that I might be whipped and chained by men as heartless<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8042-00000006"/> and as cruel as yourself! Who made me the wretched thing I am?-who caused my reason to be destroyed?-who broke my poor mother's heart, and made her die of grief on account of her daughter's fate?-who made me homeless, and transformed me from an humble, but happy factory-girl, into the gibbering maniac I now am? an object at which some look with pity, others with contempt. Margaret Willford, <foreign xml:lang="LAT">alias</foreign> 'crazy Mag Wildfire,' asks you to tell her, who did all this?"</p> 
               <p>"Come, come, Margaret," said the young man, soothingly, as he gently laid his hand upon the arm of the maniac, "why do you so continually recall the past, whenever we happen to meet? Let by-gones <emph>be</emph> by-gones, as the saying is. I am sorry for your misfortunes, but I do not think that I can justly be accused of being the author of them. True, we did once consider ourselves as engaged to be married, but <emph>circumstances beyond my control</emph> rendered that marriage impossible. This sad disappointment somewhat affected your intellect, and your mental malady has been greatly increased in violence by your neglecting to take proper care of yourself, and by your unnecessarily exposing yourself to the most terrible privations. Your mother died of old age and decrepitude; a 'broken heart' had nothing to do with her death whatever. A hard-hearted landlord turned you out of your cottage, and made you houseless. Therefore <emph>I</emph> am not to blame for your misfortunes. There are plenty of kind-hearted people in this place who would be glad to give you a home, my poor Mag. I will use my influence to procure you a comfortable one without delay. Come, let us be friends."</p> 
               <p>"Ah!" cried the unfortunate girl, as she burst into tears, and sobbed in a manner that would have affected a heart of stone, "you speak kindly to me now, just as you used to in the old happy times. Do you remember, Cyrus, how, upon a fine Sabbath like this, we used to sit upon the grass beneath this very same tree, in this beautiful and quiet spot, and form plans of future happiness? O, what were the circumstances that prevented our marriage? I was true to you, and loved you better than tongue can tell. That cruel letter which you sent to me, on the morning of the day appointed for our wedding-that letter that coldly announced to me that the ceremony could not take place, and that I must relinquish the expectation of ever becoming your wife-that letter, Cyrus, broke my heart, and crazed my brain. I was nothing but a poor factory-girl, Cyrus, supporting myself and my invalid mother by the labor of my hands-but I loved as truly, and suffered as keenly, as the finest lady in the land. O, Cyrus, it was very cruel in you to desert me thus, at the very moment when I thought my happiness complete!"</p> 
               <p>Margaret, who was now in one of her lucid intervals, wept with renewed bitterness; while the young man gazed at her calmly, his countenance wearing that peculiar smile.</p> 
               <p>"You say," continued Margaret, after a short pause, and making an effort to dry her tears, "that there are benevolent people who would willingly give me a home, and that you yourself will procure me one. But, in my miserable state, I cannot go among happy and rational people, to horrify them by my insane ravings. I am unfit to dwell with my species, and prefer to live alone. Near this place, yet quite secluded from the gaze of passers-by, is a little cave which I inhabit. Dried leaves form my bed, and food is brought me every day by several kind young ladies, with whom I formerly worked in the mill. Among these friends are Miss Davis and Catharine Cotton. You started, Cyrus, at the mention of Catharine's name, and I know the reason. It matters not how I became acquainted with the fact, but I am aware that you are paying your addresses to Miss Cotton, and that a time has been appointed for your marriage to her. Do you mean to deceive <emph>her</emph> as you deceived <emph>me?</emph> Do you intend to break <emph>her</emph> heart, as you broke <emph>mine?</emph> Beware! Cyrus. There are some women who are capable of doing desperate deeds, involving the destruction of themselves and the betrayer, when they find that they have been made the victims of a <emph>heartless male coquette,</emph> who engages the affections of an unsuspecting, too confiding female, just to enjoy the <emph>triumph</emph> of casting her off; who laughs over the misery he has created, and tramples on the heart which he has broken! Again I say, beware! Do not deceive Catharine, that amiable, that excellent girl. Deal with her truly, I implore you, and I will forgive and bless you."</p> 
               <p>"You should learn to mind your own business, Mag, and not meddle with affairs which do not concern you," said the young man, in a tone of severity, "what do <emph>I</emph> care for your forgiveness or your blessing?"</p> 
               <p>This harsh, contemptuous language produced an immediate return of Margaret's insanity. Her eyes flamed with fury, as she sprang towards Cyrus, and cried in piercing accents,-</p> 
               <p>"I will make you care, then, for my <emph>hatred</emph>-my <emph>revenge!</emph> Die, thou false and cruel man!"</p> 
               <p>As she uttered these frantic words, the poor demented creature drew from her bosom a knife, with which she aimed a des-<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8042-00000007"/> perate blow at the breast of Cyrus, who, however, sprang aside, in time to save his life. Margaret, impelled forward by her sudden movement, fell to the ground, with a violence that rendered her insensible, her forehead having struck against a stone, causing a wound, from which the blood flowed in a copious stream.</p> 
               <p>On beholding this melancholy sight, something like pity entered the breast of Cyrus. He raised the form of the poor girl in his arms, bore her to a neighboring brook, and bathed her head in the cool, clear water. Then he bound up her wound with his handkerchief, thus stopping the flow of blood. After a little while, Margaret slowly opened her eyes, and as they fell upon the countenance of Cyrus, who was bending over her, she shuddered, and by a painful effort released herself from his arms. Making a sign to the young man to indicate that he must not follow her, she walked away with slow and uncertain steps. Just before disappearing, she turned, and placing one hand upon her heart, and with the other pointing towards heaven, she murmured, in a faint and tremulous tone, which was, however, perfectly audible to the person addressed,-</p> 
               <p>"I forgive thee, Cyrus. We shall never meet again. Do not deceive Catharine; and now farewell, forever!"</p> 
               <p>Slowly and thoughtfully the young man left the spot, and walked towards his boarding-house. Margaret's last words still rang in his ears; and in future years, during the solemn hours of night; those sad, forgiving tones will thrill through his soul, mingled with another voice, at the imagined sound of which, his eyes will try to penetrate the darkness, and he will almost expect to see, emerging from the gloom, a pale form, dressed in white, with dripping hair, whose blue lips move, but speak not, and whose glazed eyes freeze the soul with their supernatural stare!</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head> 
               <p>WE now come to a portion of our narrative which reveals, in all its hideous deformity, the moral aspect of a heart that is capable of deceiving a loving, gentle, and trusting woman.</p> 
               <p>One year ago, last June, as we find by a careful reference to our notes, Miss Catharine B. Cotton left Pownal, and re- turned to Biddeford, one week before the day appointed for the nuptial ceremony. It was with contending emotions that this excellent and ill-fated young lady resumed her abode in the little white cottage, which we described in a former chapter. Her heart glowed with happiness and joy at the prospect of her approaching union with the object of her love; but then that <emph>strange presentiment of coming evil</emph> would arise within her breast, casting its dark shadow over her soul and making her miserable.</p> 
               <p>Cyrus had written very sparingly and coldly, in answer to Catharine's frequent and ardent letters. But she tried to excuse his negligence and seeming indifference, by supposing that a press of business prevented him from being a more attentive correspondent.</p> 
               <p>Had the poor girl suspected the distressing fact that Cyrus had all along been paying the most devoted attentions to a wealthy and beautiful young lady of Biddeford, it is very probable that she would <emph>then</emph> have terminated her sorrows by a voluntary descent into the cold, cold grave.</p> 
               <p>"He may be fickle," thought she, "but I do not believe him false. He knows that I have returned to Biddeford, and he will of course call upon me without delay, to assure me of his undiminished affection, and to make the final arrangements for our union. With what joy I shall gaze into his countenance, and listen to his voice once more! He will visit me to-day; I know he will! Away, dark shadows of misgiving and fear! Let nothing enter my bosom but the golden sunshine of joy!"</p> 
               <p>Thus thought Catharine, on the day of her return to Biddeford. The day and evening passed away, but Cyrus came not to see her who so soon expected to become his bride.</p> 
               <p>Catharine passed a sleepless and a wretched night. On the second day after her return, the agony of suspense which she suffered became too painful for endurance, and she resolved to have an interview with Cyrus, and learn the worst, at once. Accordingly, she addressed him a few earnest and affectionate lines, entreating him to come and see her without delay.</p> 
               <p>This note reached the young man towards evening, just as he was preparing to go out, and pay a visit to Miss Templeton,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-2480-NOTE001" n="*"
                        place="foot">
                     <p >For certain reasons, which the intelligent render will have no difficulty in understanding, we have here given a fictitious name.</p>
                  </note> the lady whose wealth and beauty-the <emph>wealth</emph> more than the <emph>beauty</emph>-had attracted him and inspired him with a sordid sentiment which <emph>he</emph> imagined to be <emph>love.</emph> How often is the divine<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8042-00000008"/> passion of love libelled and outraged, by its sacred name being applied to motives the most selfish and dishonorable!</p> 
               <p>We will here remark, that we have good reasons for believing that Miss Templeton never cherished any warmer feeling towards Cyrus, than that of mere <emph>friendship.</emph> She thought him agreeable, and respected him-nothing more. We do not think that she ever would have married him, under any circumstances. Had he proposed, she would have rejected him at once; and we will do her the justice to assert, that had she been aware of the fact that he was capable of engaging the affections of a lady, promising to marry her, and then cruelly deserting her;-had Miss Templeton, we say, known this of Cyrus, she would have rebuked him severely, and then dismissed him, with an injunction never to enter her presence again.</p> 
               <p>Cyrus carelessly glanced his eyes over Catharine's note, and then tossed it from him with an air of impatience, as he muttered,-</p> 
               <p>"I expected this! Well, I will go and see Catharine at once, to save myself from future annoyances; and, as I have fully made up my mind to dissolve my acquaintance with her, I may as well speak plainly to her first as last. I hope she won't take the disappointment very deeply to heart; <emph>I</emph> can't help it if she does!"</p> 
               <p>As the heartless young man wended his way towards the home of the much abused Catharine, he continued to soliloquize as follows:</p> 
               <p>"Having got rid of Catharine, I must turn my whole attention towards Miss Templeton, who is both rich and lovely; but, even were she as ugly as sin, I would gladly marry her, for gold is a magical talisman, that can render the most repulsive face charming. But Miss Templeton, as yet, has given me very little coquettish, and wants to plague me. I must push the warfare with vigor, until she surrenders the citadel of her heart. She must be mine, or I shall begin to lose confidence in my powers of fascination, with reference to the fair sex."</p> 
               <p>Cyrus soon reached the little white cottage. Catharine, who had been awaiting his arrival with the utmost impatience, sprang forward to meet him with a cry of joy.</p> 
               <p>"You are come at last, dear Cyrus," said she; "all, then, is well, and I am <emph>so</emph> happy!"</p> 
               <p>And how acted <emph>he</emph>-the man whom she loved better than her own heart's blood? Did he not at once dismiss his cruel intention of deserting her, confess his meditated fault, implore and receive her entire forgiveness, and make her supremely happy by the assurances of his undying constancy and love?</p> 
               <p>No, he did no such thing, for such a course of conduct was altogether foreign to his nature. He coldly repulsed that warm hearted girl, and said to her, in a tone of freezing politeness,-</p> 
               <p>"Miss Cotton, excuse me, but it is both proper. And desirable that we should come to a definite understanding. <emph>I have changed my mind and concluded not to marry!</emph> This is my unalterably decision. We can never be more to each other than friends. I need scarcely say to you that I shall always wish you well. Don't suffer this trifling disappointment to cause you any unhappiness. You may feel badly for a little while, but the great physician, Time, will soon cure you. Now, consider, and look at this matter calmly-dispassionately. We are both poor, and were we to marry, nothing but a life of poverty would be open before us. I, a young man without fortune, or brilliant prospects, hope to wed a lady of wealth; while you, although nothing but a poor factory girl, are possessed of beauty and accomplishments that may win the love of some rich man. Our remaining apart, you see, will be to the advantage of us both, while our union would entail misery and hopeless poverty upon us. <emph>love in a cottage</emph> is all very well in its way, no doubt; but I, for one, greatly prefer <emph>solid comfort in a palace.</emph> Tell me, Miss Cotton, as a rational woman, don't you think that our engagement should be cancelled?"</p> 
               <p>No reply came from the lips of that forlorn and broken hearted girl, whose fabric of happiness, reared by hope, and sustained by the strong prop of her own truthful love, had thus suddenly crumbled into dust, overwhelming and crushing her as it fell. She could not speak, but, burying her face in her hands, she moaned in all the agony of her lacerated spirit. A sense of complete desolation swept like an avalanche over her soul, forever destroying every green and flowery thing that had every bloomed there, and producing a desert, dark, gloomy, and peopled only by images of sorrow and despair.</p> 
               <p>"Answer me, Miss Cotton, if you please," said the immovable Cyrus, after a long pause, as he gently placed his hand upon the unhappy girl's shoulder, in order to arouse her from her seeming lethargy.</p> 
               <p>Catharine slowly raised her face, which had assumed the hue of marble. The few moments of mental agony which<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8042-00000009"/> she had already endured, had done the work of years in changing her appearance, and Cyrus was almost frightened at the alteration. She gazed at the deceiver with the rigid look of a statue. No expression was in her face-neither surprise, nor reproach, nor sorrow, nor rage. All was cold, calm, immovable as the face of the dead. Could she have wept she might have experienced some relief; but the fountain of her sorrow was frozen, and she could not shed a single tear.</p> 
               <p>"Can she be dying?" thought the alarmed Cyrus; "<emph>that</emph> would be really too bad. Poor soul! I actually <emph>pity</emph> her. She must have been very fond of me, much more so than I thought, as she exhibits such intense emotions on my informing her that I cannot, marry her. Well, the worst pang is over now, and she'll soon recover her usual composure. I hate this sentimental interview, and shall make my escape from the house as soon as possible."</p> 
               <p>This <emph>matter-of-fact</emph> young man-this <emph>hater of sentiment</emph>-whom, we presume, the reader admires as much as we do, now said to Catharine, in a loud and pompously benevolent tone-</p> 
               <p>"Miss Cotton, you do not appear to be well. Shall I call for assistance? Perhaps I had better, as I wish to go, having a particular appointment to keep."</p> 
               <p>Catharine struggled to break the spell that seemed to have thrown its frozen chains around her. In this, she only partially succeeded. Her pale lips moved, and Cyrus could see that she was vainly endeavoring to pronounce the word "<emph>go!</emph>" Her hands were clasped with convulsive energy over her heart, which felt to her as if it had been rent in twain. A wed by that pale and spectral figure, and frightened, in spite of himself, Cyrus left the room; and, having told the inmates of the house that Miss Cotton appeared to be very unwell, he precipitately departed from the premises, and hastened toward the elegant mansion occupied by Miss Templeton.</p> 
               <p>Catharine was found by Miss Davis and others of her friends, lying upon the floor, in an insensible condition. Several weeks elapsed before she was able to sit up, and her illness, her despair, and the terrible disappointment which she had sustained, enlisted universal sympathy for her; while remark were made, with reference to Cyrus and his conduct, that were not always complimentary.</p> 
               <p>When Catharine had recovered her health sufficiently, she determined to leave Biddeford; for after she was abandoned by one upon whom all her affections were placed, it was to her like a deserted home, and therefore she left and went to Lowell, where she stayed a few weeks and went to Lawrence. She remained at that place but a short time, and went to Manchester. But there, as at all other places where she lived, after the silver cord of her existence was broken, she could think of nothing but sorrow; clouds and thick darkness were continually about her.</p> 
               <p>From Manchester she went to Lynn, hoping that a change of occupation might bring relief to her mental distress. But wounded affections, caused by the desertion of a lover almost at the bridal hour, cannot be healed by mere worldly cares, nor by diverting the mind by travel. About seven weeks before her tragical end, she returned to Manchester, unable to find peace anywhere. Then, for the first time, she became acquainted with <emph>Miss Clara C. Cochran;</emph> and, being possessed of kindred feelings upon one subject, the young ladies became intimate friends.</p> 
               <p>The following letter, written by Miss Cotton, and addressed to Cyrus--, Biddeford, Me., has been found; and its language is, to our mind, peculiarly simple, eloquent, and affecting:</p> 
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="letter"> 
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>MANCHESTER, August 14, 1853.</dateline>
                           </opener> 
                           <p>"I now, for the last time, will attempt to scribble you a few lines, and, ere these few lines reach you, I shall be sleeping in death. Think not that I shall ever trouble you again with a letter, for I shall not. No, this is the last. You will receive this with anger, perhaps; but, Cyrus, forgive me for troubling you. I have forgiven you long ago, but have not forgotten. I suppose you are in Biddeford now, happy and contented, and I hope you are. As for myself I am not happy, but in a few moments I shall be free from the sorrows of this world, and I cannot be more unhappy in another. When you read this, think that I am cold in death, and shall one day meet you in another world. So farewell, Cyrus; go, and be happy.</p> 
                           <closer>
                              <salute>From your friend and well-wisher.</salute> 
                              <signed>CATHARINE COTTON.</signed>
                           </closer> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <p>Miss Cotton also left the following poetry, and a postscript, which gives a clue to her state of mind. These simple, unpretending effusions of her pen are far more touching than if they possessed all the polished elegance of the highest order of composition: <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>Cyrus, dear Cyrus,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">It was for loving you,</l> 
                        <l>That makes me so unhappy,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">For you have proved to me untrue.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8042-00000010"/>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>How many times you have promised</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">That you would marry me,</l> 
                        <l>But how little did I think</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">That I should ruined be.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>I know you have tried to ruin me,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">But now I'm far away,</l> 
                        <l>And, perhaps, we never shall meet again,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Until the judgment day.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>I have strayed far from friends and home,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">You for to forget,</l> 
                        <l>But you are ever present,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And you I think of yet.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>Now you and I are parted,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Perhaps never in this world to meet,</l> 
                        <l>Remember there is a meeting,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">It will be at the Judgment Seat.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>Pray, think how you have wronged me,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And remember what you have said,</l> 
                        <l>And may it not escape your mind,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">When on your dying bed.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>And when our bodies, they are laid,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Beneath the cold, cold clod,</l> 
                        <l>Our spirits will return unto</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">A just and holy God.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>And then to be judged</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">By the God that rules on high;</l> 
                        <l>The judgment's fast approaching-</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">The judge he will not lie."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <p>This is the postscript:</p> 
               <q>
                  <p>"CYRUS:-Several months have elapsed since I saw you, and how many sad hours I have seen within that time, and I often think, O, that I had never seen you, for you have destroyed my happiness, I fear, forever. Now, while you are enjoying yourself in the gay world, remember that you have been the destroyer of one's happiness-one that loved you sincerely. If you had treated me as you should, you would have found in me a devoted friend. What is passed cannot be recalled. I am now far from those that I once prized as friends."</p>
               </q> 
               <p>
                  <emph>Miss Clara C. Cochran</emph> was, at the time of her death, about nineteen years of age. She belonged to New Boston, and, for a time, lived with her brother in Hopkinton. She was, had she reached the age of twenty-one, to have come into possession of several thousands of dollars. She left behind her the following scrap of poetry, which, no doubt, expressed her feelings at the time of writing: <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"I shall soon in death be sleeping,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Far away, where strangers dwell-</l> 
                        <l>Far from all those haunts of pleasure</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">That in youth I loved so well.</l> 
                        <l>Flowers shall not be o'er me planted,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Nor shall willows o'er me wave,</l> 
                        <l>Marble columns, decked with grandeur,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Ne'er shall deck my humble grave.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>Friends will shed no tears of sadness,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">When my dream of life is o'er,</l> 
                        <l>For around me all are strangers-</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">I am on a distant shore.</l> 
                        <l>Hear me, then, O! friends of childhood,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Hear an exile's dying prayer,</l> 
                        <l>When I soar to climes Elysian,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Let me meet my loved ones there.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>My heart now droops in loneliness-</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">My misery's perfect now;</l> 
                        <l>For dark Despair his seal hath stamped</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Upon my throbbing brow,</l> 
                        <l>No voices, in affection's tones,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Upon my ears now fall.</l> 
                        <l>Alone I tread the path of life.</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">I am the last of all.</l> 
                        <l>I would not have proud marble piled</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Above my grassy bed,</l> 
                        <l>One simple stone to mark the spot,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And one to weep me dead.</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>Miss Cochran, in early life, became strongly attached to a young man with whom she went to school. Although they did not see each other afterwards for six years, up to last March they kept up a regular and affectionate correspondence, begetting in <emph>her</emph> mind the belief that he was her lover, and would be her husband. It may be that the young man considered these letters merely as the offspring of <emph>friendship,</emph> and had no idea of ever marrying her, Last March, he wrote to her, saying, that she need not write to him again until she received another letter from him. She, however, sent him<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8042-00000011"/> several letters, which elicited no reply; and from the moment that the full conviction flashed upon her mind that she was abandoned, her life became desolate. "Hope deferred maketh the heart sad," and dreary, dreamy, almost unreal, were the hours after that conviction came upon her. Her tears were more bitter than those shed for the dead, and yet not so consoling. As she read, "do not write to me again," she seemed to lose all consciousness of who she was, and where she was, and the meaning of what she had read, reminding one of little Mary Lee: <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"I put my hand upon my head,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">To think what it could mean;</l> 
                        <l>I knew I never had been dead,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And come to life again.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>''Twas long before I understood</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">The words that I had read;</l> 
                        <l>And then, an overwhelming flood</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Of burning tears I shed."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>It was very natural that Catharine Cotton and Clara Cochran should have become warm and sympathizing friends. It is true that their cases were not precisely alike; yet there was a sufficient degree of similarity between them to unite the young ladies by the most tender, affectionate and eduring ties. In private they mingled their tears together; and their poor bruised hearts may have derived some consolation from such interviews of mutual sorrows and sisterly love. They roomed together at No. 24 Manchester Corporation; and, secluding themseives as much as possible from society, they were almost constantly in each other's company. Oh, that must have been a dark, a dreadful hour, in which these two amiable and interesting young ladies, throwing themselves into each other's arms, and weeping bitterly, resolved to terminate their sorrows by resigning themselves to the icy embrace of death. The public mind, as is natural, is anxious to know the <emph>true cause</emph> of such strange, such tragical proceedings. Was it disappointed love? Was it shame for past acts? Or was it fear of bringing disgrace upon themselves and friends? A tattling, surmising, evil-minded class in a community, simultaneously cry, the last. But we are authorized to say, and feel warranted in saying, that such surmises are all false. <emph>Disappointed love</emph> was the cause, and the only cause, that brought about such sad and fatal results. Not a <emph>late</emph> disappointment, but, in the case of one of them, wearing and preying upon the mind for some fourteen months, so that almost nightly her pillow was wet with tears. She (Miss Cotton) told Miss Davis that several times, once at Lowell, she went to the bank of the River to drown herself, but her courage failed her. Miss Cochran once, while she was at Fishersville, threatened to commit suicide by drowning, and repaired to the river for that purpose; but she was followed by some friends, and restrained. These facts show that both the unhappy young ladies, before they ever saw each other, had thought of committing the desperate act of suicide.</p> 
               <p>On Sunday, three weeks before the commission of the double suicide, Miss Cotton and Miss Cochran remarked to their room-mate, Miss Davis-</p> 
               <p>"We have made up our minds, and nothing on earth shall dissuade us from our purpose. <emph>In three weeks from to-day we shall die!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"Catharine-Clara!" said their friend, in a tone of mild reproof, "I know that you are only jesting; but then it is very wicked for you to speak so. Do not, if you love me, pain me by repeating such expressions. You must have been reading some romantic or melancholy book. Dismiss your sorrows, my dears, and look forward to brighter, happier days. You know, it is said, that the darkest hour comes just before the dawn of day."</p> 
               <p>"We are perfectly serious, and mean just what we say, for we cannot bear the pain of living," rejoined the young ladies, seriously; and they persisted in saying that they were determined to put an end to their existence, but their remarks were not taken in earnest by any one. Their friends endeavored to cheer them up, but these well meant efforts were all in vain; they grew more melancholy and solitary every day, and, in secret, deliberately prepared for the awful tragedy which they were determined to enact.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head> 
               <p>LET us now, reader, pay another visit to Biddeford, Maine. There stands a splendid mansion, whose grand exterior denotes that it is the abode of aristocracy and wealth. It is approached by means of a noble avenue, bordered with lofty trees, whose spreading branches, meeting overhead, formed a vast green<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8042-00000012"/> arch, through which the soft breeze rustles musically. This mansion is the home of squire Templeton, an old gentleman of princely fortune, but he is an incurable invalid, and seldom, or never leaves his chamber. With him resides his only daughter, Julia, a beautiful girl of eighteen, the sole heiress of her father's immense wealth.</p> 
               <p>It was evening, and in a splendidly furnished parlor of Templeton Hall, as it was called, two persons were seated-a lady and a gentleman. Not to keep the reader in suspense, we will state at once that the lady was Miss Julia Templeton, a creature of ravishing beauty, fully qualified to adorn the highest spheres of society, possessed of the rarest accomplishments, and dressed with exquisite taste. Altogether, it was no great wonder that Cyrus-the young man who had so basely deserted poor Catharine Cotton-had become ambitious to gain the hand and fortune of the heiress of Templeton Hall.</p> 
               <p>Julia's companion, as the reader has doubtless anticipated, was Cyrus himself. He, too, looked remarkably well, but his face indicated uneasiness, and, we may say, agitation. Was this the result of remorse for his heartless conduct with reference to poor Catharine? No; for he had almost, if not quite, forgotten that wronged and unfortunate creature. His discomfort proceeded from the unaccustomed coldness of Julia towards him. She had always treated him in a cordial manner, at least; and upon this occasion the coldness, the reserve, the aversion which she manifested towards him, utterly confounded him; for on that evening he had intended to make her an offering of "heart and hand," as the common jargon goes.</p> 
               <p>An awkward pause succeeded some common-place remark, and Cyrus at last ventured to say,-</p> 
               <p>"Miss Templeton, will you not favor me with a little music this evening? An air or two on the piano, accompanied by the tones of your own unequalled voice, would oblige me much, and have a cheering effect upon my spirits, which are somewhat depressed."</p> 
               <p>Cyrus, not withstanding his coldness of heart, knew the softening influences of melody; he thought that, as "music is the food of love," its divine charm might possibly awaken in the heart of Miss Templeton emotions favorable to his hopes and aspirations.</p> 
               <p>"When she has become warmed up a little," thought the cunning and fox-like young gentleman, "I will throw myself at her feet, and refuse to rise until she has consented to elect me to the position of husband, and the sharer of her fortune." Julia darted a rather contemptuous look at Cyrus, as she replied,-</p> 
               <p>"I cannot grant your request, Sir."</p> 
               <p>"You do not seem to be well, Julia, that is, Miss Templeton," said Cyrus, fearing that his familiarity might offend.</p> 
               <p>"I am quite well in health," was the cold rejoinder.</p> 
               <p>"Then you are low-spirited; something must have occurred to annoy you."</p> 
               <p>"Something <emph>has</emph> occurred to annoy me," observed Julia, emphatically; "but do not question me further."</p> 
               <p>Another awkward pause. Cyrus began to grow desperate, and said,-</p> 
               <p>"Is my visit an intrusion, Miss Templeton? If so, I will retire."</p> 
               <p>Julia answered not; and as silence is supposed to imply consent, Mr. Cyrus began to arrive at the unpleasant conclusion that his absence would have been preferable to his company.</p> 
               <p>"What the deuce ails her?" thought the perplexed and mortified young man; "she never treated me so before. She's got some crotchet into her head, I'll be sworn. Perhaps, after all, this is nothing but female coquetry. Now, of all things in the world, I do hate a coquette. To trifle with any person's affections is a despicable piece of business. Whatever may be the cause of Julia's conduct towards me to-night, I shall not retreat from the field of battle without making another effort to gain the victory. But what shall I say next? Her confounded coldness has completely frozen up my powers of speech. Let me reflect a little."</p> 
               <p>Mr. Cyrus proceeded to reflect accordingly, while Julia traced out imaginary figures upon the rich Turkey carpet with the point of her delicate slipper. She was evidently laboring under a considerable degree of embarrassment; sometimes she seemed on the point of making an important observation to the aspiring youth, who was so ambitious to become her husband; then checking herself, she appeared to shrink from making the communication that occupied her thoughts.</p> 
               <p>After a little while, a sudden, and, as he conceived, an exceedingly acute idea took possession of the mind of Cyrus, who said to himself,-</p> 
               <p>"O, ho! I see it all now, and I was blind not to have seen it before. This excellent but weak-minded young female, whose wealth and personal qualities certainly entitle her to some consideration, having become tired of my bashfulness,<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8042-00000013"/> and wishing to get married without any further delay, is affecting all this coldness and reserve merely to drive me to a declaration of love, and into a demand for her hand in mantrimony. She thinks herself shrewd and sagacious; but her design is so transparent that I can easily see through it. I have before heard of such 'artful dodges' on the part of ladies who have been anxious to urge matters to a crisis. Why, Julia might have known that I am as anxious as she can possibly be for our union; and a few words of encouragement on her part, or a smile even, would have been quite as effective in bringing me to her feet as all this manuvring. However, women will be women all the world over, and I suppose that I must humor this whim. Now for a love scene, got up in the most approved style of delicate art."</p> 
               <p>Reader, have you ever seen the "walking gentleman" of a comedy or farce, in the character of an ardent, impetuous, but impoverished lover? have you, we ask, ever seen that individual in the act of casting himself at the feet of a wealthy heiress, and imploring her, in piteous but honeyed accents, to bestow upon him just one look, one smile, one word, to assure him that his love was reciprocated, that he was not wholly an object of indifference to her, entreating her to murmur that little affirmative monosyllable that should render him the happiest of men; and warning her not to think of making a negative response, unless she desired to make him food for the fishes, or a suspended ornament from a beam; or, as we might say, a gentleman in the act of accomplishing an aerial hornpipe; declaring to her upon his unsullied honor, that her wealth was no object to <emph>him,</emph> none at all; he merely being anxious to possess her person alone, to live exclusively upon her smiles as an article of diet, and so forth? If the reader has ever seen this, he or she can perhaps form something like an adequate idea of the manner in which the enthusiastic and disinterested Mr. Cyrus laid siege to the heart of Miss Julia Templeton.</p> 
               <p>This young lady, with ill-concealed disgust-for she despised the theatrical manner in which her admirer was urging his unwelcome suit-requested Mr. Cyrus to rise; and Mr. Cyrus <emph>did</emph> rise, rather chopfallen it must be confessed; for Julia's tone and manner convinced him that he had made a failure, instead of a <emph>hit,</emph> and he felt painfully assured that he would never succeed remarkably well as an <emph>actor,</emph> especially if Miss Julia Templeton was to constitute his audience.</p> 
               <p>"Let me hear no more such language," said the lady, with severity; "for I will not listen to it."</p> 
                
               <p>"Then you reject my proposals?"</p> 
               <p>"Most decidedly."</p> 
               <p>"May I inquire your reasons?"</p> 
               <p>"You may, and I will answer you. In the first place, I never loved you, and never cherished towards you a warmer feeling than that of friendship. Your circumstances in life I do not at all regard; for, were you the possessor of millions, my sentiments with reference to you would be the same. I am entirely my own mistress; for my invalid father, having implicit confidence in my discretion, has often told me to marry the man of my choice, whoever he might be; and therefore, should I meet a man in the humblest circumstances, whom I might think capable of making me happy, I would unhesitatingly marry that man, provided, of course, that he would marry <emph>me,</emph> even if he were not worth a single penny in the world. Therefore, you see that neither parental restraint, nor your own poverty, has anything to do with my rejection of your proposals. I have two other good and sufficient reasons for refusing to accept you as a lover."</p> 
               <p>"Will you be pleased to name those two other good and sufficient reasons?" said Mr. Cyrus, in a tone of bitter mortication.</p> 
               <p>Miss Templeton, who spoke with an energy and a decision that were among the most prominent elements of her character, replied,-</p> 
               <p>"Certainly, sir. I have but to mention the name of Catharine Cotton, to remind you of-"</p> 
               <p>"Ah!" interrupted Cyrus, "then you know all about that affair?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I <emph>do</emph> know all about it, having just learned all the particulars of your desertion of that excellent girl, whose heart you have broken, and of whose death you will be the cause. Your heartless conduct towards her was related to me to-day, for the first time; had I known of it sooner, I would have told you that our acquaintance was at an end. I now inform you, sir, that hereafter your visits will not be received by me, and that you must not attempt to intrude your presence here again. I cannot endure the sight of a man who is capable of such baseness. Henceforth, and forever, we are strangers!"</p> 
               <p>Trembling with suppressed rage and shame, Cyrus faltered out,-</p> 
               <p>"Now for your other reason."</p> 
               <p>"You shall have it if you insist; but I warn you that it will not please you."</p> 
               <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8042-00000014"/> 
               <p>"No matter, let me hear it."</p> 
               <p>"Have you ever known such a person as Margaret Willford?"</p> 
               <p>Cyrus started at the mention of that name, which painfully recalled to his recollection another poor girl whose heart he had broken. He replied, with assumed composure,-</p> 
               <p>"Why, yes, I <emph>have</emph> heard of such a person. She was a factory-girl, who being disappointed in some love affair, became insane, and has ever since been wandering about without any settled home. She is, I believe, known as <emph>Mag Wildfire.</emph> But what of her?"</p> 
               <p>"What of her!" repeated Miss Templeton, bitterly, as, with flashing eyes and heaving bosom, she scornfully surveyed our discomfited hero, "can <emph>you</emph> ask 'what of her'-<emph>you</emph> who disappointed her in that 'love affair,' to which you so carelessly allude-<emph>you,</emph> whose cruel desertion made her insane, and caused her to become a homeless wanderer? Your agitated countenance proclaims your guilt. I will tell you 'what of her.' That poor, forsaken creature is dead!"</p> 
               <p>"Dead!" echoed Cyrus, as for a moment-but only for a moment-a feeling of pity took up its unaccustomed abode within his icy breast.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, poor Margaret is dead," said Miss Templeton, who was now profoundly affected, and from whose brilliant eyes the tear-drops fell bright as the gems that adorn the robes of an angel; "her sorrows are over, and she has gone to a world where her poor bruised spirit will be healed, and made supremely happy by the Redeemer's smiles. Listen to me, and I will tell you how she ended her earthly pilgrimage. A few days ago, I was taking a walk not far from here, when, in the course of my rambles, I accidentally discovered a sort of cave, which I entered. Judge of my surprise, when I found, stretched upon a heap of dried leaves, the emaciated form of a young female, who was clothed in rags, and who was evidently not long for this world. Full of sympathy and pity for the unfortunate creature, whose faded countenance still exhibited the impress of beauty, I asked her a few questions, which she answered with extreme difficulty, for her system was completely prostrated by her life of privation and suffering. She was perfectly rational, and replied to me with clearness. Informing me that her name was Margaret Willford, she related a few of the events of her life, and then I became aware that she was the poor crazy <emph>Mag Wildfire,</emph> of whom I had often heard, but whom I had never before seen, although I had frequently at- tempted to procure an interview with her, for the purpose of administering to her comfort. I had heard that her troubles arose from her having been abandoned by a man upon whom she had placed her affections; but I had never suspected that <emph>you</emph> were the cause of her deplorable condition. Feeling a deep interest in her, and being much affected by her artless tale, I caused her to be removed as speedily as possible, to this house, where she was immediately provided with every comfort. A skilful physician was sent for, and every effort was made to revive the spark of life, which was fast dying out. But her system had received too severe a shock to admit of her recovery. Up to the very moment of her death, her reason remained unclouded. Just before she died, and while her head was pillowed on my bosom, she faintly whispered your name, Cyrus, and said that she freely forgave you; and then I knew, for the first time, that you were the author of her misfortunes. May Heaven forgive you, Cyrus, as <emph>she</emph> did! Her gentle spirit passed away like a summer cloud-and she is happy now!"</p> 
               <p>"Where is she buried?" inquired Cyrus, in a hoarse whisper, which proclaimed that even <emph>his</emph> hard heart was a little softened by this touching recital.</p> 
               <p>"She died but yesterday afternoon, and her remains have not yet been consigned to the tomb," replied Miss Templeton, mournfully; "would you behold, for the last time, the face of her who once loved you so well? Follow me, then."</p> 
               <p>Cyrus would gladly have declined this invitation, but some mysterious and irresistible influence urged him to follow Miss Templeton into the adjoining room, where his eyes encountered a spectacle that caused his heart to stand still within his breast.</p> 
               <p>In the centre of the apartment, on a table, was a mahogany coffin partly covered with a sable pall. Several wax candles were burning on the table, and shed a ghostly light upon every object in that chamber of death. Seated at the head of the coffin, was an old and faithful servant, who had been appointed to watch the corpse during the night.</p> 
               <p>The most profound silence, and an air of deepest solemnity, prevailed in the room, which seemed to contain the visible presence of the King of Terrors.</p> 
               <p>"Her funeral will take place to-morrow morning, and she will be buried in our family burial place," whispered Miss Templeton, as she glided to the coffin, and removed the pall that covered the face of the dead.</p> 
               <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8042-00000015"/> 
               <p>Cyrus gazed long and fixedly upon those pale and delicate features, which seemed to have been restored to all their pristine beauty, as if Death, in striking down his victim, had kindly obliterated every trace of hardship and sorrow from her face, and left there all the loveliness of an angel. A smile rested upon her pallid lips, like a sunbeam upon snow; and no one who gazed upon that serene smile, and those plaeid features could help observing that the spirit which had once inhabited that frail tenement of clay was then in heaven.</p> 
               <p>"Poor Margaret!" murmured Cyrus, after a long pause, during which he had stood over the coffin, with folded arms and moistened eyes; and a sigh came up from the depths of his bosom-a sigh which indicated that remorse and sorrow had achieved, at least, a temporary victory over his hard, unyielding nature.</p> 
               <p>The scene was a very imposing and striking one, as dimly revealed by the light of the unsnuffed candles. The corpse and the paraphernalia of death-the old gray-haired servant, who sat as motionless as the corpse itself-Julia Templeton, with her pale, but gloriously beautiful countenance, and soul-speaking eyes-the form of Cyrus, who stood in the attitude of a culprit-all these combined to form a scene that would have deeply impressed an observer, especially if he had been acquainted with the peculiar circumstances of the case.</p> 
               <p>"Let this be a lesson to you, Cyrus; and remember that a woman's heart is too delicate an organ to be trifled with. Had you been kind and constant to this poor girl, who now lies here, cold in death, she might at this moment have been alive, well, and happy. Cyrus, I have no harsh feelings against you, whatever; but it is my wish that I may never behold you again. Go, sir, the world is wide enough for us both. I trust that you may be prosperous and happy, and that you never may experience the pangs of disappointed love, nor the anguish of a broken heart. Farewell, forever."</p> 
               <p>Cyrus went forth from the young lady's presence, and left the house, with feelings which he had never before experienced, and which we have not the power to describe.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head> 
               <p>The remains of poor Margaret Willford were consigned to the tomb, and many were the tears shed by compassionate eyes on account of her melancholy fate.</p> 
                
               <p>Before dismissing Miss Templeton from these pages, it may gratify our readers to know that she has just been united in marriage to a worthy young man, after a short courtship. The young man was poor, but he possessed many shining qualities, which attracted the attention, and won the admiration, and then the love, of the elegant and brilliant heiress, who, in accordance with her intention of marrying the man of her choice, no matter how poor he might be, bestowed her hand and her fortune upon Mr. Ray, with the entire consent and approval of her father. The manner in which the young couple became acquainted was quite singular. Mr. Ray, who was a common mechanic, happened to be employed, by Squire Templeton, to make some repairs about his mansion. While thus engaged, the young workman attracted the notice of Miss Templeton, who could not help admiring his manly beauty, which shone even through the coarse, rough garb of the mechanic. She was also pleased with his industry, his skill, his good-humored cheerfulness, and his perfectly respectful deportment. On entering into conversation with him, the young lady was surprised and delighted to find that his intellect was of the very highest order, and that he possessed an excellent education, which he had acquired by self-application. He was exceedingly well informed on almost every subject, and the splendidly accomplished Julia Templeton found him a match for her, and thought that she had never enjoyed the society of a more congenial companion. Mr. Ray regarded the superbly beautiful girl with a feeling of positive adoration, and, when he was in her presence, it seemed to him as if he were holding communion with an angel. The idea of ever becoming the <emph>husband</emph> of that peerless creature, of possessing the legal right to press that glowing and voluptuous form to this throbbing heart, and to banquet upon the nectar of those rosy lips, where lingered the perfume of a thousand flowers-that bold idea never entered the mind of Mr. Ray, and, if it had, he would have scouted it as the offspring of a madman's brain; for would she, a young, lovely, accomplished, and rich lady, occupying the very highest rank in society-she, who might reasonably have aspired to an alliance with the noblest gentleman on earth-she, whom he regarded as almost belonging to a superior order of beings-would <emph>she</emph> descend from her high estate so far as to wed a poor carpenter, whose sole dependence was on the labor of his hands, which were hardened by toil? Preposterous thought!</p> 
               <p>"Ah!" said poor Mr. Ray to himself, with a sigh that came<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8042-00000016"/> up from the very bottom of his heart, "poverty may be no disgrace, but it is certainly very inconvenient, and it becomes a curse when it debars me from the enjoyment of the greatest earthly felicity I ever dreamed of! Now, if I were the owner of a few piles of paltry yellow gold, I could woo, and perhaps win, that glorious creature, whose angel presence thrills my heart with a strange rapture, and whose voice, with its exquisite melody, lingers around me even now. I wish that I had never seen her, for she has destroyed my happiness forever. Did ever sculptor, or a painter, or a poet, in their moments of inspiration, conceive of a being so ravishingly beautiful as Julia Templeton? No, that were impossible! What eyes she has-lustrous as stars; what cheeks-glowing with the hues of a ripened peach; what lips-like 'wet coral;' and then her hair, which falls in such rich masses upon her neck and shoulders of dazzling whiteness! I can scarcely look at her, without feeling as if my heart were about to leap out of my bosom; and I fancy that she sees my emotion, and pities me on account of my hopeless passion, for she is goodness itself. The qualities of her mind are not inferior to the graces of her person. She seems to combine the most masculine learning with every feminine accomplishment. There is a nameless charm in her conversation, that holds me as if spellbound; and then how kind and condescending she is towards me! Why, she treats me as if I were her equal in every respect. Well, to-morrow I shall finish my job of work, which I have protracted until I can do so no more; and then I must pack up my tools, and bid an eternal farewell to Julia, who will forget me before a single hour has passed. But shall I ever forget <emph>her?</emph> Never-never!"</p> 
               <p>This soliloquy will show Mr. Ray's feelings with reference to Julia Templeton. The next day, the young carpenter reluctantly completed his job of work, and, with a heavy heart, he repaired to the library of Squire Templeton, for the purpose of receiving his pay. The Squire, by the way, is a fine specimen of the "gentleman of the old school;" his countenance indicates benevolence, and a love for the good things of this world; but, alas! that infernal plague of the generous liver-the <emph>gout</emph>-has crippled him, so that he can scarcely move; and he is obliged to be wheeled in his chair, from one room to an other, by a stout servant.</p> 
               <p>Having paid the mechanic most liberally, the Squire said,-</p> 
               <p>"You have done your work well, sir, and I thank you. Whenever I need the services of a carpenter, I shall be happy to employ you. Help yourself to a glass of brandy; there stands the decanter, on the table. Excuse me on account of not rising, for I am a cripple. The devil take the gout! that last twinge nearly wrenched my leg off!"</p> 
               <p>"I am sincerely obliged to you for you kindness, sir," said Ray, respectfully, "but I never drink."</p> 
               <p>"Ha! you are a temperance man, then?"</p> 
               <p>"I am proud to say that I am. I never drank a glass of liquor in my life, and never intend to. My father died a drunkard, but I am determined that his son shall never come to such an end."</p> 
               <p>"Give me your hand sir. I respect a man, no matter what he is, whose conduct is based upon <emph>principle.</emph> You are a fine young fellow, sir, and I like you. Are you married?"</p> 
               <p>"I am not, sir."</p> 
               <p>"Ah, that is a thousand pities. A bachelor is a miserable dog, while matrimony is the greatest blessing in the world. I have been through the mill, as the saying is, and know all about it. You should select some fine girl for a wife to comfort and take care of you, and hand down your name to posterity. You are a good-looking fellow, and almost any girl would be glad to have you. But perhaps you can't find one exactly to your liking-eh?"</p> 
               <p>"I <emph>have</emph> found one exactly to my liking," observed Ray, with a sad smile.</p> 
               <p>"Then why the devil don't you marry her?" demanded the good-humored Squire, whose constant confinement made him delight in conversation.</p> 
               <p>"Because, sir," replied Ray seriously, "I do not believe that she cares a single straw about me; and, another thing, she is very rich, while I have hardly a dollar in the world."</p> 
               <p>"Bah!" cried the bluff old Squire, "what matters if she is rich? You're as good as she is, I'll be sworn; and I'm quite certain that she <emph>does</emph> care about you. Take my advice, young man, and make her marry you without any delay."</p> 
               <p>"But, sir, she has a father who might possibly object to the arrangement."</p> 
               <p>The Squire snapped his fingers derisively, and exclaimed,-</p> 
               <p>"A fig for her father! What do you care for him? Pay no attention, whatever to the old fellow, but run off with the daughter, if necessary, and make her bone of your bone, and flesh of your flesh. That's the way I did with <emph>my</emph> wife, who is now dead and gone, poor soul! Her father objected to me, and so I eloped with the girl. The old man soon forgave us, and all was right. Follow my example young man."</p> 
               <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8042-00000017"/> 
               <p>"I will think of it, sir," said Ray as he took his leave of the old gentleman, who little suspected that he had been strongly advising the youth to run away with, and marry, his own daughter.</p> 
               <p>The carpenter could not help smiling, as he thought of the amusing scene that had just taken place; but this merriment was of short duration, for he reflected that now, in all probability, he was about to part forever from the idol of his soul. As he passed down the stairs, he looked eagerly into every apartment, in the hope of obtaining a glimpse of Julia Templeton; but she was nowhere to be seen. Ray sighed deeply, as he left the house, and entered the magnificent garden that was situated in the rear of it. This garden which was of great extent, was full of flowers and ornamental trees, and contained many classical statues, fountains, and arbors. Our "love-sick swain" strode along one of the gravelled walks; and, as he approached an arbor, he was delighted to see it occupied by Julia, who was seated in a listless attitude, holding in her hand a book which she was not reading; though her eyes were fixed upon its pages, her thoughts were elsewhere.</p> 
               <p>Ray thought that she had never looked so charming, as upon the present occasion. A single white rose was carelessly entwined amid her luxuriant tresses, and a plain white dress, wholly without ornament, revealed, to the very best advantage, all the graces of her form.</p> 
               <p>She looked up, when she heard the sound of Ray's approaching footsteps, and greeted him with a radiant smile of welcome. He returned her cordial salutation in an embarrassed manner, and said,-</p> 
               <p>"I am sorry to be obliged to bid you farewell, Miss Templeton, for my work is finished. I regret to go, very much, for you have been very kind to me, and I feel that I am about to lose, forever, a true friend. Farewell, and may you be happy!"</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Ray," said the young lady, with that charming frankness, that adorable candor, for which she was ever distinguished, 'do not be in a hurry, but sit down here in this agreeable shade. Let us converse freely; I am sure that you will not misinterpret my motives. I confess that you have inspired me with a deep and abiding interest in you; and I regret, for your own sake-but <emph>only for your own sake,</emph> remember-that fortune has not, in a pecuniary sense, bestowed her favors upon you with more profusion. Yet you possess personal and mental advantages which should reconcile you to a lack of wealth. O! what is gold, compared with worth-with intellect-with education-with the sacred pleasures of friendship, and the celestial joys of love!"</p> 
               <p>Miss Templeton's enthusiasm had hurried her into the use of language which, in her cooler moments, she would have considered indiscreet. She checked herself, cast down her eyes, and blushed deeply. Ray looked at her with surprise; but not for a single moment did he doubt the angel purity of that elegant creature, whose bosom now heaved with the agitation produced by her own chaste, but ardent emotions.</p> 
               <p>A delicious hope began to arise within the heart of the young mecahanic; and he said, softly,-</p> 
               <p>"Pray, proceed, Miss Templeton; your words are like balm to my despairing soul!"</p> 
               <p>Julia recovered her ordinary composure, and looking up with a frank smile, she said,-</p> 
               <p>"I see that we perfectly understand each other, Mr. Ray. There are many congenial points between us, and it is natural that we should like each other. There is no impropriety in that. So let us be friends, let us be like brother and sister. You are poor, and I am rich; but need that insignificant circumstance separate us? Let us see each other frequently, and continue to derive instruction and amusement from each other's conversation and society. Does not this arrangement please you? Don't you think that I am a very singular young lady, to talk in this free and open manner? Well, I confess that I am singular, and I glory in it, for I despise the hackneyed forms and customs of the world. I am a decided <emph>original;</emph> and, so long as I am assured of being right, I care nothing for the opinons of other people. The world may frown, and shake its head, and shrug its shoulders, but it shall not frighten me into the abandonment of any line of conduct I may choose to adopt. My father will approve of our friendship, for he resembles me exactly."</p> 
               <p>The mechanic, carried away by the violence of his feelings, could not help saying,-</p> 
               <p>"Ah, Miss Templeton! I wish to Heaven that you were as poor as I am!"</p> 
               <p>"That is a strange wish," observed the young lady, with an arch smile, "pray what prompts it?"</p> 
               <p>Mr. Ray, with the courage of a hero-knowing that "faint heart never won the fair lady,"-threw himself at the feet of the beautiful heiress, and in burning, passionate and eloquent languge, poured forth the story of his love. We shall not<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8042-00000018"/> dwell upon this scene; suffice it to say that the young man acquitted himself remarkably well, because he <emph>felt</emph> just what he <emph>uttered.</emph> And what reply did Julia Templeton make? That we conceive to be none of our business; but we feel bound to state, as a faithful chronicler of the truth, that a very few moments after Mr. Ray had "finished his speech," he was seated by the side of Miss. Julia, with his arm around the waist of that young lady, whose head rested confidingly and affectionately upon his shoulder, and whose countenance proclaimed the intense happiness that filled her soul.</p> 
               <p>"The course of true love" <emph>did</emph> run smooth in this instance, at least. Squire Templeton readily gave his consent to the marriage of the lovers, saying, as he turned towards Mr. Ray,-</p> 
               <p>"Well, sir! you have followed my example with a vengeance! But I am very well satisfied, and I hope that you and Julia won't quarrel more than half-a-dozen times before the honey-moon is over. There, go and make love, and let me enjoy my afternoon's nap!"</p> 
               <p>The marriage ceremony was performed without delay, much to the astohishment and dissatisfaction of the neighboring gossips, who declared that no good could possibly spring from such an "ill-assorted union." Heedless of all this, Mr. and Mrs. Ray, accompanied by Squire Templeton, removed to New York, where they now reside in an elegant "up-town" mansion, surrounded by all the comforts and blessings which wealth and virtue can give.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head> 
               <p>EVERYTHING throwing light upon the last hours of Miss Cotton and Miss Cochran, or tending to show what contributed to their melancboly fate, is read by the community with great avidity. A thousand and one stories are in circulation, most of them having no foundation on fact, and calculated to injure the feelings of the friends of the two unfortunate young ladies, whose sudden, deliberate, self-possessed act of taking their own lives, has caused such a sensation in our midst.</p> 
               <p>The statements which we give, were made to us by Miss Davis, in the presence of two other ladies, one of whom was also a room-mate of Miss Cotton and Miss Cochran, and all three of whom saw them when they committed the fatal deed.</p> 
               <p>Miss Cotton, as we have before intimated, was a particular friend of Miss Davis, with whom she has conversed freely about these matters for a year or two past, and in whose company she was during the greater portion of that memorable Sunday. Catharine, left all her affairs in the charge of her friend, declaring her intention of drowning herself; but Miss Davis did not believe she was in earnest until she saw her jump into the fatal stream.</p> 
               <p>Catharine left a letter for her father, and another for her sister, bidding them adieu, and stating that she should not be alive when they received the letters, which contained a small sum of money, (fifteen dollars,) and which we here present to the reader.</p> 
               <p>To her father she wrote thus:-</p> 
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="letter"> 
                           <p>"DEAR FATHER:-While your eyes are scanning these few lines, your unhappy daughter will be lying cold in death. This is to bid you farewell, and to hope that we may meet in another and a better world. I and a chosen companion, have concluded to quit together a world which has nothing in store for us, but sorrow and grief. We have both been disappointed in love, and both of us are broken-hearted. Forgive me, my father for this rash step; you may condemn my conduct, and the world will judge me harshly, but no one is aware of the distress of mind that drives me to self-destruction. If you ever see Cyrus, tell him that I forgive him, and that with my dying breath I blessed him. Farewell, kindest, best of fathers; never again on earth shall you behold your unhappy daughter,</p> 
                           <closer>
                              <signed>CATHARINE."</signed>
                           </closer> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <p>The reception of this letter naturally filled the heart of the father with grief and consternation. Who could have helped compassionating that sorrowing parent, in the dark hour of his affliction?</p> 
               <p>To her sister, Catharine wrote the following letter:</p> 
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="letter"> 
                           <p>"DEAREST SISTER:-I am going to write you a very long letter, but you must not complain, for it is the last one which you will ever receive from me. My earthly career, which commenced under such a bright sky of promise, is about to close in gloom and darkness. Start not, but read this calmly to the end. Do you not remember, when we were little girls to wander away into the depths of the shadowy forest, to listen to the music of the birds, to gather wild flowers, and to talk of the future years of happiness which we supposed ourselves destined to enjoy, when we should become grown-up women? Ah, my sister, those golden hours of my innocent childhood were full of<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8042-00000019"/> felicity, and, as I think of them now, the tears come into my eyes, land almost blind me. Those dreams of happiness have not been fulfilled, for the fondest hopes of my life have been blasted, my loving heart has been rent in twain, and here I now stand, a trembling soul upon the shores of the vast, mysterious ocean of eternity! Pray for me, my sister, pray that my spirit's shattered bark may be safely guided to that serene land where sorrow is unknown, and where angel music soothes the wearied soul. Yes, I have fully made up my mind to die by my own free, voluntary act, and, while your tearful eyes ere perusing this, my lifeless body will be an object to be gazed at by curious and unmoved spectators. You know very well the cause of this suicide, for my former letters have explained everything to you. I have been deceived and abandoned by the idol of my love, and existence has become a burden, which I am desirous of shaking off. Desperate diseases require desperate remedies, it is said; and <emph>my</emph> distress can only be alleviated by death. Poor Clara Cochran, whom I have so often written to you about, intends to be my companion to the spirit-land, "where the wicked cease from troubling, and the weary are at rest." Clara, like myself, is a victim of disappointed love; a young man from whom she had been accustomed to receive affectionate letters, and whom she regarded as her lover, abruptly terminated the correspondence, and broke poor Clara's heart. She is a sweet! girl, nineteen years of age, while I, you know, am twenty-two. I have tried to dissuade her from joining me in this terrible business; but she is resolved. She is determined to go with me down into the dark valley. After my death, people may assert that I was insane. I wish it to be distintly understood, that such is not the case. While I write these lines, which I do with a steady hand, my pulse is as firm and regular, and my brain is as clear, as ever they were. I send you a lock of my hair, to keep as a memento of me. I have just written a short letter to father, informing him of my intention, and bidding him farewell. And now, in conclusion, dearest sister, let me entreat you not to grieve too much on account of my sad fate; and may <emph>you</emph> never know such pangs as I have suffered. Give my love to all our friends, and tell them not to weep for me when I am gone, but rather to rejoice, for I shall be released from all the anguish of spirit which I have endured. Farewell, my sister! and in future years, when you are happy-surrounded, perhaps, by a troop of rosy children, and made the joyous recipient of a husband's tender love-then sometimes think of poor</p> 
                           <closer>
                              <signed>CATHARINE."</signed>
                           </closer> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <p>The reader will acknowledge that the foregoing letter is a most beautiful and touching one; and no literary lady who contributes to the pages of our fashionable magazines, could surpass the poor factory-girl, in the eloquence with which she depicts the miseries of a broken heart. We have reason to believe that the false Cyrus also received a most affecting letter from Catharine; and we regret that it is not in our power to give that letter to the world.</p> 
               <p>Clara Cochran, on the day of her death, addressed the following letter to the young gentleman whose coldness and indifference were the cause of her mental distress, and fatal resolution to put a period to her existence:</p> 
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="letter"> 
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>MANCHESTER, N. H., Sunday, Aug. 14th, 1853.</dateline>
                           </opener> 
                           <p>"I write you this letter, and thereby disobey your, request, for the last time. This evening I am going to die. <emph>You</emph> will not care-<emph>you</emph> will not even weep-no tear will dim your eye on account of poor Clara-no sigh will arise from your bosom; you may perhaps smile and say, 'She was a foolish, an infatuated girl.' You will also say, 'I never gave her any encouragement to believe that I loved her, or intended to marry her. My letters were merely those of friendship; and, when I found that she was becoming affectionate, like an honorable man I immediately discontinued the correspondence, instead of taking advantage of her strong partiality for me.' This you will say when I am gone. Well, be it so. I write not this to reproach you, but to bid you farewell, forever. I hope you may always be happy, and select a bride whom you may consider worthy, of you. As for myself, I am in a few hours to become the bride of death, and the cold grave will be my nuptial couch. Oh, my dear-(for I must call you so once more), could you not see that your kind letters were calculated to make a lasting impression upon my poor susceptible heart? Why did you not cease writing to me before you had excited my tender regard-why did you tamper with the happiness of my life? I must give vent to my feelings, even at the risk of arousing your displeasure; but I do not think that you can be <emph>very</emph> angry with me, for, while you are alive and happy, I shall be food for worms. Excuse any wrong expressions which I may make, for I am only a poor girl, having no knowledge of the world. <emph>My</emph> world would have been a quiet, happy home, and I should not have cared how humble it might be, if that <emph>dear one,</emph> whom I so fondly love, even at this moment, were with me, to cheer me with his ever-welcome presence-to warm my heart with his beaming smile-to delight my ears with the music of his voice-to say to me, 'Clara, I love thee.' But this was not to be. That happiness would have been to great for <emph>me.</emph> I am doomed to die a disappointed, a broken-hearted girl. Life can afford me no further enjoyment, and therefore I am about to relinquish it. And yet I tremble as I approach 'that dread bourne from whence no traveller returns.' What is to come hereafter? Is not the act of suicide a terrible-an unpardonable crime? Will it not be punished by eternal banishment from Heaven? I ask myself these questions, but I am unable to answer them, Nothing, how-<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8042-00000020"/> ever, shall induce me to give up my determination. Oh! it is hard, after all, to leave this bright, beautiful world, with its green fields, its sunny skies, its million avenues of pleasure and enjoyment, which are open to those who are light-hearted-it is hard to exchange such a world for the darksome tomb! <emph>But I must go!</emph> I must nerve my heart up to a great pitch of courage, to enable me to perform this act of self-destruction. I must not let another rising sun find me in the land of the living. But you are perhaps impatient for me to conclude this unwelcome letter. I must at all events close now, for I have preparations to make for my self-sacrifice. Let not my death cast a shadow o'er your life-forget me, and be happy.</p> 
                           <closer>
                              <signed>CLARA."</signed>
                           </closer> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <p>This letter will show that Miss Cochran possessed literary abilities of a very respectable order. She was frequently in the habit of beguiling her leisure hours by writing compositions, both in poetry and prose. Some of these productions she caused to be published in different magazines and newspapers. As everything connected with her must be of interest to the reader, we will here insert a piece of poetry written by her a year or two ago. It is entitled-</p> 
               <div type="poem"> 
                  <head>THE FRIENDS OF OUR YOUTH.</head> 
                  <lg type="stanza"> 
                     <l>The friends of our youth have departed,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">No longer their voices we hear;</l> 
                     <l>The joyous, the gay, the fond-hearted</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Have closed their short earthly career;</l> 
                     <l>No more shall we listen in gladness</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">To their footsteps, so lightsome and free-</l> 
                     <l>They have left us in sorrow and sadness,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">To sleep 'neath the cypress tree!</l> 
                  </lg> 
                  <lg type="stanza"> 
                     <l>Alas! that the music of voices</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Of those that are dear should be hush'd;</l> 
                     <l>That the heart, which in fond hope rejoices,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">By the cold hand of death should be crush'd</l> 
                     <l>That the flowers of beauty should languish,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Depriv'd of their sweetness and bloom-</l> 
                     <l>Bright gladness give way to cold anguish,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Joyous earth to the darksome sad tomb!</l> 
                  </lg> 
                  <lg type="stanza"> 
                     <l>The friends of our youth-ah, what sweetness</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Doth dwell in that beautiful sound</l> 
                     <l>When Time, on the wings of his fleetness,</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Shall scatter his frosts all around,</l> 
                     <l>Still, still shall the fond recollection</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">Fill our hearts with its freshness and truth,</l> 
                     <l>Of those objects of early affection-</l> 
                     <l rend="ti-1">The long-cherished friends of our youth!"</l> 
                  </lg> 
                   
                  <p>How melancholy is the reflection that the authoress of these lines, while in the very flower of her youth, descended, of her own accord, to the "darksome, said tomb!"</p> 
               </div> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head> 
               <p>WE now approach the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">denoument</foreign> of the appalling tragedy-the closing scene in the lives of Catharine Cotton and Clara Cochran.</p> 
               <p>During the week before the commission of the fatal deed, they did not mention the subject to any one, and seemed to act as if they had forgotten it.</p> 
               <p>On Sunday, one said to the other-</p> 
               <p>"I did not speak of our drowning during the week, because I wanted to leave your mind uninfluenced by anything I might say."</p> 
               <p>The other responded-</p> 
               <p>"I have been silent about it for the very same reason."</p> 
               <p>Miss Cochran worked on a dress until a late hour on Saturday evening, and on Sunday they both appeared as usual till nearly noon, when they began to pack their trunks.</p> 
               <p>After dinner, they devoted most of their time to writing letters and giving directions apout their affairs, seeming all the time to be in such good spirits, that no serious apprehensions were felt by Miss Davis or others, who had received itimation of what they had said and done. They ate a hearty supper, and seemed to be in a cheerful frame of mind, until they went up stairs for the last time. Then a friend said to them, good-naturedly-</p> 
               <p>"You foolish girls, what do you think <emph>now</emph> of drowning yourselves? I have a great mind to give you both a good scolding, for talking such nonsense. Don't you think you deserve it?"</p> 
               <p>Catharine and Clara both burst into tears, and for some time, remained apparently lost in thought.</p> 
               <p>Miss Cotton gave Miss Davis three letters, and asked her to put them into the post-office the next morning, and also gave her labels for her trunks and boxes, showing where they were to be sent.</p> 
               <p>A little after dusk, Catharine and Clara came down stairs,<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8042-00000021"/> dressed in white. Miss Davis and another lady asked them to go out and walk, thinking that thereby their minds might be diverted from the subject, which had become so awful. They refused rather coldly, and, leaving the house, walked quietly around the corner and up the street towards the canal, which was but a few rods off. They proceeded hand in hand, and with great apparent cheerfulness to the bridge crossing the upper canal, leading to the Manchester Mills.</p> 
               <p>Miss Davis and two other friends, feeling a little uneasy, thought they would follow after at a distance. They did so, and, upon inquiry, found that the two young ladies had gone up a short street, and turned to the left, towards the canal bridge. They followed as fast as they could, and had just got to the bridge, when they saw Catharine and Clara hurrying to the side of the canal, some three rods above, and leap into the water together, without a word, or a scream, or a particle of hesitation. The act was seen by several persons, and the alarm was instantly given. Miss Cochran sunk to the bottom, and was not again seen until her body was taken out, three quarters of an hour afterwards. Miss Cotton sunk and then arose, gave a gurgling sound, and floated down the canal. Great excitement was instantly created, and a young man, named James Hall, boldly jumped in and caught her by the dress as she was sinking again; but she was so heavy, and he so light, that he was not able to save her. Boards and rails were thrown to her after she came up the second time, and though they came within her reach, she made no effort to touch them. She was taken out in about ten minutes, and every effort to resuscitate her failed. <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"One more unfortunate,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Weary of breath,</l> 
                        <l>Rashly importunate,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Gone to her death.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>Take her up tenderly,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Lift her with care,</l> 
                        <l>Fashinon'd so slenderly,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Young and so fair?"</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>Thus perished these two interesting and most unfortunate young women; and it must be a hard heart indeed, that can deny the tribute of a tear to their memory. May their sad fate convey a useful lesson; may it teach thoughtless young men to beware how they trifle with the affections of loving and tender-hearted women; and may it be the means of urging the latter class to <emph>bear up</emph> under disappointment, and never yield to despair, for, as the hymn says, "there is no sorrow that Heaven cannot heal."</p> 
               <p>The body of Miss Cochran was carried to Grafton, Vt., on Monday, (the day after the suicide,) under the charge of Mr. John T. Moore. She was born in New Boston, but requested to be buried by the side of her mother, at Grafton, where some of her relatives reside. Her funeral took place on Tuesday morning, at 9 o'clock, at the house of Jonathan Sherwin, and was attended by a large concourse of people. John H. Sherwin, the person to whom she wished her property to be given, was present at the funeral. Miss Cochran was of an excellent family, and had a superior education; and her melancholy death causes deep sorrow. Her father and mother both died of consumption; and she formerly had the impression that such would be her fate.</p> 
               <p>We are tempted to give another specimen of this young lady's poetical abilities. The following was found among her papers, after her death:-</p> 
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="poem"> 
                           <head>THE EXILE'S LAMENT.</head> 
                           <lg type="stanza"> 
                              <l>O, talk not to me of the beauties of spring,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Or the pleasing enjoyment of summer's gay hours,</l> 
                              <l>Of the warbling of birds, as they joyously sing</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">On the leaf-covered branches of nature's green bowers,</l> 
                              <l>Of evening's soft twilight, of bright rosy morn,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">As it comes in its glory o'er valley and hill;</l> 
                              <l>Of the emerald mantle that carpets the lawn,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Or the sweet, gentle, sound of the murmuring rill!</l> 
                           </lg> 
                           <lg type="stanza"> 
                              <l>"Sad, lone, and forsaken, an outcast on earth,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Far from the loved scenes of my childhood I roam;</l> 
                              <l>An exile I am from the land of my birth,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Bereft of friends, kindred, and dearly-loved home;</l> 
                              <l>No more shall the accents of love in my ear,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">To my care-stricken breast consolation impart,</l> 
                              <l>Nor shall the kind voices of those I hold dear</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Shed comfort and peace o'er my sad, broken heart!"</l> 
                           </lg> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>We envy not the feelings of <emph>Cyrus,</emph> with reference to the fate of Catharine Cotton. He must, as long as he lives, reproach himself for having been the cause of her untimely death. We have, throughout this narrative, dealt as lightly with him as possible, and have by no means depicted his conduct in as strong colors as we might have done. Our motives have been most disinterested and honest, for it has been our sole object<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8042-00000022"/> to lay before the public a <emph>true statement</emph> of all the facts connected with the affairs, in order that justice may be done to the memory of the deceased.</p> 
               <p>The young man, whose indifference was the cause of Clara Cochran's death, was far less to blame than Cyrus, in our opinion; for we have no evidence that he ever engaged to marry Clara. It may be that he merely corresponded with the young lady as a <emph>friend;</emph> and that on discovering her increasing tenderness towards him, he deemed it advisable, and necessary to secure his own happiness, that the growing intimacy should be broken off at once. We charitably hope that such was the case, and that he had no idea of the depth and intensity of Clara's love for him. He must have been terribly shocked when he heard of her melancholy end.</p> 
               <p>From a <emph>journal</emph> kept by Catharine Cotton, we take the following interesting extracts. We omit dates, as being unnecessary:-</p> 
               <p>'Last evening I attended a very agreeable party, at which many of the factory-girls were present. A beautiful time we had of it, music, dancing, and other innocent enjoyments.-How superior are such simple, harmless amusements, to the pursuits of the wicked! Innocent pleasures leave no sting behind them, while guilty joys result in sorrow and remorse. I had the satisfacrion of becoming acquainted with Mr. Cyrus--, a young man of prepossessing appearance and superior address. I took quite a fancy to him, and he paid me particular attention, complimenting me on my good looks, and assuring me that he never flattered. Indeed, I am vain enough to believe that I <emph>did</emph> look remarkably well; for I wore a new silk dress, brought by the proceeds of my own industry. I am poor, and work hard, it is true, but then a clear conscience, and bright hopes of future felicity, render me very happy. I would not change places with the richest lady, who has not purity and virtue on her side. But I sat down, not to moralize, but to keep a journal of events. When the party broke up, Mr.--, accompanied me home, and asked permission to see me again, requesting that we might be friends. I assented, and we separated. How strange that I should have dreamed of this young man last night! He has certainly made a deep impression upon me. How natural it is for the heart to seek some object upon which to bestow its love! But, do I already love Mr.--, whom I have seen but once in my life, and of whose character I know nothing? I certainly feel very strangely about him, and long to see him again!"</p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
                
               <p>"I have see him again, for the second time, and much as I liked him after our first interview I find that he improves upon acquaintance. We went together to the concert, to hear the Hutchinsons sing, and their simple, touching melodies deeply affected me, and moistened my eyes with tears. On our way home, Cyrus-I prefer calling him by that familiar name talked in a manner that made my heart beat almost audibly. His language was strictly proper and respectful, yet he spoke of love, and the blessings of matrimony, in a very pointed and significant manner. How I blushed and trembled-he speaks with such eloquence! When we parted, he pressed my hand, and-shall I write it?-kissed my cheek, and my tongue had not the power of reproving him. I am to accompany him to meeting next Sabbath. How happy I am!-but shall I always be so?"</p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>"This is Sunday evening, ten o'clock. I am writing in my chamber; my room-mate is fast asleep, and all is still, yet I am so deeply agitated that I can scarcely hold my pen. My agitation, however, is of a pleasurable character. Cyrus has just left me-we parted in the garden. I went to meeting with him this afternoon. After meeting, we took a long walk, during which Cyrns frankly told me that he loved me, and asked me to become his wife. His declaration and proposal were so abrupt, that I was taken all aback; yet what a flood of delicious happiness gushed to my heart, on hearing him speak thus! I trembled from head to foot, and would have fallen to the ground, if Cyrus had not supported me. He repeated his offer with increased tenderness of tone, and I became his affianced bride-his betrothed wife. This happiness seems to be too great for me to bear. My brain is dizzy-I can write no more.'</p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>"To-day I went with Cyrus on a very pleasant excursion, and enjoyed myself highly. It was a pic-nic party, got up by the factory-girls and their friends. We had singing, and dancing, and such a nice dinner! Cyrus was particularly kind and affectionate. When we are married, I must repay his kindness by the most constant devotion. He says that we are to live in a beautiful little cottage, surrounded by vines and honeysuckles. How delightful! Yet I could live contentedly with Cyrus in a hovel."</p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>"The day for our marriage has been fixed upon. But a<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8042-00000023"/> singular presentiment of coming evil oppresses me. This is very foolish, and I must banish such feelings. What have I to fear? Is not Cyrus as devoted and as affectionate as ever? Can he prove false? To suppose him capable of such baseness, is doing him foul injustice. Yet why am I unhappy at this moment? Alas! I cannot tell."</p> 
               <p>"To-morrow, go to Pownal, to make preparations for my<milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> marriage with Cyrus. Still that odious presentiment! My friend, Miss Davis, does not like Cyrus. She tells hard stories concerning him-but have I a right to believe anything to the discredit of my beloved? No, I will not-I <emph>must</emph> not. Where is all my accustomed strength of mind, that I cannot drive these gloomy shadows from my soul?"</p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>"Last night I dreamed that I was in the water, strangling and drowning; and I thought that Cyrns stood over me with a mocking smile. I awoke, feverish and unrefreshed. What should cause such a horrible dream? It seemed that I had thrown myself into the water, that I had committed <emph>suicide.</emph> Then I thought how a coroner's jury would surround my lifeless remains, and coldly record their verdict without caring anything about the poor creature whose body lay before them. To pass away my time, I write the the following lines:</p> 
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="poem"> 
                           <head>THE SUICIDE.</head> 
                           <lg type="stanza"> 
                              <l>"Assembled in grave conclave</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Are six men of portly mein;</l> 
                              <l>A woman has found a suicide's grave,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">And her dripping corpse is seen.</l> 
                              <l>Near the rough, unpainted bier</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Stand these 'good men and true,'</l> 
                              <l>And a gaping crowd is near,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">All scrambling for a view.</l> 
                           </lg> 
                           <lg type="stanza"> 
                              <l>'Tis hurried quickly through,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">The verdict's easily made;</l> 
                              <l>'There, gentlemen, that will do,'</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">The burly coroner said.</l> 
                              <l>He takes a hugh pinch of snuff,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Then looks benignly round-</l> 
                              <l>The Jury have heard enough</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">And they render the verdict, '<emph>drowned!</emph>"</l> 
                           </lg> 
                            
                           <lg type="stanza"> 
                              <l>'Now let there cheaply be</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">A coffin quickly made;</l> 
                              <l>And he pocketed his fee</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">As the heartless words were said.</l> 
                              <l>In a suicide's hated grave,</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">The unwept was spedily laid-</l> 
                              <l>The compassionate, soothing wave</l> 
                              <l rend="ti-1">Knew alone the grief of the maid."</l> 
                           </lg> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>"I am distracted-mad-deranged! My brain is on fire, yet my heart is a lump of ice! Come down, ye thundetbolts, and crush me-come down, ye lightning, and pierce me! Would that an earthquake would yawn and swallow me! Those words-I will try to write them:-I <emph>have concluded not to marry!</emph>' Was not his tongue blistered as he spoke? O, it is cruel. I have not deserved this. Cyrus ought not to treat me so. Well, let him go-but do I hate him? No-no-no! That were impossible. I love him still. Yes, I can forgive him. I hope he will be happy; but, as for myself, there is no happiness left for me in this world. Death alone can end my misery; and death will soon come to my relief.</p> 
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>"This is the last Sunday-the last day-that I shall ever pass on earth. My mind is fully made up; I shall die this evening. Poor Clara Cochran will die with me. My friends are very kind, but they cannot win me from my purpose. All my preparations are made. Will my fate excite any sympathy-will my death cause any sorrow-will Cyrus shed a single tear on my account? Will he regret having so coldly abondoned me, almost at the hour appointed for our marriage? Oh! if I thought he <emph>would,</emph> happy would be my death. . . . Miss Davis is in the room, looking at me while I write. She smiles, because she thinks that all my threats of committing suicide, meant nothing. When she sees my cold, wet corpse, this evening, she will believe me. How strangely calm I am! Not the slightest agitation-not a flutter of the heart-not the least confusion of mind, do I feel. It is like the terrible stillness the precedes the fearful elemental war that follows. .... And I am about to rush headlong into eternity. I shall soon be before the throne of my Creator! Oh! Almighty God, in thy bounteous mercy have compassion upon me; and the crime I am about to commit against nature, do Thou! in the plenitude of Thy goodness, thinking of the depths of my heart's great sorrow, oh! do Thou visit not upon my head thy just displeasure.". . . .</p> 
               <pb n="46-47 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC8042-00000024"/> 
               <p>Here ended the melancholy and despairing lines, every word and sentence of which was laden with misery, despair, utter hopelessness, and yet reliance for forgiveness on the mercy of a God, whom she was yet fearful of offending, yet totally unable to bear the dreadful load of sorrow which was pressing upon her devoted head.</p> 
               <p>Talk as you may, of the sinful and wicked act of cutting the frail cord of life, but when it is considered that here were two of humanity's purest and brightest creatures, who have been given to the world for man to love and cherish, and who look up to him by right as a protector, and one, on whose strong arm they must look for reliance; when all these are considered, how can it be wondered at, that their loving, gentle trusting hearts should break, at the infernal deception, and heartless villainy that men, forgetful of themselves, practiced against their confiding and weak natures.</p> 
               <p>If suicide can have an extenuating cause, here surely was one; and few, we think, can have the heart to blame the deed of the heart-broken, wretched, and forsaken girls.</p> 
               <p>And the great Judge of all mankind will visit on the despoiler's head, his just and fearful displeasure, and we trust and believe will not deal wrathfully with the victims of heartless desertion, and disappointed love.</p> 
            </div> 
         </div>
      </body> 
      <back> 
         <div type="advertisement"> 
             
            <head>JUST PUBLISHED, AND FOR SALE BY FEDERHEN &amp; CO.,</head> 
            <p>9 AND 13 COURT STREET,</p> 
            <list> 
               <item>ADOLENE WILMONT, Being the Confessions of a Girl of Spirit-written by herself. Price 20 cents.</item> 
               <item>KATE CASTLETON, The Beautiful Milliner-By Greenhorn, Price 15 cents.</item> 
               <item>GAY GIRLS OF NEW YORK, Or, Life on Broadway. By Green.horn. Price 25 cents.</item> 
               <item>MY LIFE: OR THE ADVENTURES OF GEORGE THOMPSON, (alias Greenhorn), written by himself, (a great book). Price 25 cents.</item> 
            </list> 
            <p>Any of the above books will be sent by mail, on the receipt of the price of the book.</p> 
            <p>Agents are wanted to sell them, to whom a large discount will be made.</p> 
            <p>Federhen &amp; Co. are Boston agents for Harper, Putnam, Godey, Graham, Peterson and Leslie's Magazine.</p> 
         </div> 
      </back> 
   </text>
</TEI>