<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8321">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Flying Arrow, or, The Pirate's Revenge </title>
            <author>Williams, Henry Llewellyn, (1842-)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC8321</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2746</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The flying arrow, or, The pirate's revenge</title>
                  <author>Williams, Henry Llewellyn, (1842-)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>100 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R.M. DeWitt</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date>[n.d.]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-06-03">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-08-12">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8321-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE FLYING ARROW;</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, THE PIRATE'S REVENGE.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>MATT. MIZZEN,</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF "BLACK CRUISER," "WILL WATCH," "SUSAN WYLIE," "DELAWARE DICK," "BINNACLE JACK."</byline>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>ROBERT M. DE WITT, PUBLISHER, <address>
                     <addrLine>160 &amp; 162 NASSAU STREET.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The flying arrow, or, The pirate's revenge</head>
            <pb n="7" xml:id="VAC8321-00000002"/>
            <head>THE FLYING ARROW:</head>
            <head type="sub">OR, THE PIRATE'S REVENGE.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <p>IN former days when our whaling ships returned from the Pacific Ocean with full cargoes of sperm oil, there was an opportunity open for ambitious and energetic youth to lay the foundation of a fortune, and but a few voyages in a subordinate capacity qualified them to take command of a ship.</p>
               <p>It was a foggy morning. The mist was heavy on the waters where one of the Pacific cruisers lay, without other motion than that occasioned by the heave of the sea, though could we penetrate the surrounding vapor, we should perceive that all was life and activity on board that some thirty human beings, canopied by the cloud, moved about on the plank, full of life, and bouyant with the most agreeable anticipations, while near the summit of the tall masts, the look-outs held their lofty vigils, though it would seem that the extent of their observations must have been exceedingly limited—their view being circumscribed by a circle of some two hundred yards in diameter. On the quarter-deck lay a boat which had evidently suffered from some cause or other, and, the captain of the ship, with the tool-box by his side, was carefully inspecting.</p>
               <p>The sharp chisel moved through the soft wood in beautiful style; and whoever could have seen the pleased expression of the workman's countenance, would have instinctively perceived the reason that Martin Luther and Thomas Jefferson were partial to the turning lathe. When the Captain had cut away all the broken wood, he seized a long boat-board and fitted the pieces to the aperture. A boy went under the boat and held up a hammer to the points at which the Captain drove in the nails. As the Captain saw his work gradually improving under his hands, the moroseness of his manner softened.</p>
               <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC8321-00000003"/>
               <p>In a couple of hours, the strange sail was distinctly visible from the deck. Much speculation was agog concerning her. Some pretended to know her. A boatsteerer who had been in the Rambler declared it was that vessel. Another felt certain it was the Golden Farmer. The heads of the men were already visible on deck, and those stationed at the mast heads loomed up against the clear sky. On came the stranger, rising on the wave, then sinking down until nothing below her tops was visible: then again her head was thrown up until the new copper shone brightly on her bows, and her flying jib-boom pointed to the sun.</p>
               <p>Already had the Captain of the Maro called for the trumpet, and the crew had stationed themselves at convenient points for listening, when the approaching vessel was observed suddenly to come to the wind—the main yard was squared and the topsail lay hard against the mast.</p>
               <p>The captain of the Maro sprang from the taffrail to the deck, and screaming at the top of his voice, addressed the men on the look out—"Hey, there! Are your eyes made of marble stones, there aloft!"</p>
               <p>"There she blows," responded the boatsteerer on the main.</p>
               <p>"Hah! You leave it for others to tell you of it."</p>
               <p>"There she blows!" exclaimed the boatsteerer on the fore-top-gallant head.</p>
               <p>"Where away?" inquired the mate flying into the rigging.</p>
               <p>But he need not have made this inquiry, for the other ship had lowered her boats, and the rowers were springing to their oars with might and main, while all the boats were heading to leeward of the ships.</p>
               <p>"Come down, Mr. Barnard!" cried the captain to the mate, who had only reached the leading blocks—"Lines in the boats! Tompkins!" said he to the ship-keeper, "keep near us—that's all."</p>
               <p>In a moment the three boats of the Maro were skimming over the waves. But the boats of the stranger had the advantage. They had first discovered the school of spermaceti whales, with their low bushy spouts, and the boats of the Maro were far in the rear. The officers of the several boats, however, urged on the rowers with the most enthusiastic exclamations.</p>
               <p>In general, the crew of the Maro were sufficiently happy to fall in with the objects of their search; but now, when they were in momentary expectation of hearing from their friends at home, and enjoying some gossip with those who had recently arrived from the father land, the disappointment considerably damped their ardor: nor was it sufficient to kindle their enthusiasm that others were on the ground to witness their prowess. The spirit of emulation which had so often carried their boats like arrows through the waves, did not assert its power on this occasion.</p>
               <p>The boats were very near each other, when the captain gave orders to lie on their oars. The three boats ceased their motion.</p>
               <p>"Those whales have been frightened, Mr. Barnard," cried the captain. "They are heading all faster than we can follow them."</p>
               <p>The mate replied by standing on the thwart and looking after the school. They were indeed at some distance, ahead, and it was even doubtful whether the stranger's boats would come up with them. The wind had died away. The hot sun shone upon the sparkling waters. On the clear blue of the ocean the nautilus spread his sail in vain; there is nothing so much like death as silence on the ocean.</p>
               <p>While lying on their oars, the boats' crews of the Maro had an opportunity to examine the strange ship which, following her boats, had run down very near them, where she lay becalmed, rolling about on the billows.</p>
               <p>One glance convinced them that no tidings of their friends were brought by this ship. She was doubtless an Englishman. Indeed, there were some letters on her stern that looked very much like the word London; although they were not yet in such close proximity to the ship as to be able to decide this point. There were other marks, however, that could not be mistaken.</p>
               <p>The dark hue of her canvas, her black hull, and a general heaviness in her whole aspect, betrayed the country in which she had been built and rigged. An English ship like an English woman is substantial and enduring.</p>
               <p>The fact that she was an Englishman was first perceived by a youth—or, young youth as the English term it—in the mate's boat. This was a stripling not more than seventeen years of age whom the Maro had taken on board at Woahoe, one of the Sandwich Islands. He had deserted from some vessel in the mountains, and when brought on board was so weak that he could scarcely stand. He had lived among the mountains, and was one of the runaways that had escaped the pursuit of the officers and the hireling natives who successfully pursue all that prefer starvation to bad usage on board ship.</p>
               <p>The young fellow was an Englishman, and appeared to be well acquainted with every art of his native country. Sometimes he thrilled the hearts of his listening ship-mates with tales of Scottish life, adventures of smugglers, and other lawless manners; and anon he made them roar with laughter as he drew more comical sketches, and imitated the provincial dialect of good man Darby.</p>
               <p>He was also an excellent singer.</p>
               <p>"Will Watch, the Bold smuggler," The Bay of Biscay, "Water loo," and many other favorite songs were sung by this young stranger with great effect. His personal beauty and varied accomplishments rendered him a great favourite with the crew.</p>
               <p>Rosy cheeks, a slender frame and bright sparkling eyes might have created a suspicion with regard to his sex, had not the young whiskers began to make themselves visible, at an earlier age than common, upon his fair and ruddy cheeks.</p>
               <p>This lad pulled the tub oar in the mate's boat, and he had been observed to look somewhat earnestly at the strange ship, and evince a degree of uneasiness which was wholly unaccountable; but when the mate discovered that she was an English vessel, he said to the youth:</p>
               <p>"So, John: I saw you looking at her very sharp. It is you then who will be likely to hear from home, while we must wait for another opportunity."</p>
               <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8321-00000004"/>
               <p>John's bright eyes did not evince so much pleasure at the idea of hearing from home as might have been anticipated. The mate continued.</p>
               <p>"How is it John, on board them English whalemen, the boys are apprentices there—are they not!"</p>
               <p>John colored deeply as he replied in the affirmative. "Perhaps," said the mate, "that you were an apprentice at the time you left your ship. In that case, I suppose that your Captain would like to get hold of you. But, tell me, how in the name of common sense, could a boy like you contrive to escape?"</p>
               <p>John bent down to peak his oar, which had got loose that moment but a negro who pulled the midship looked mighty wise—</p>
               <p>"You, Johnson—" said the mate, addressing this negro—"You did not escape so well. You were not gone from the ship three days before we caught you." "He was glad to come back," said the boatsteerer laughing. "We found poor Johnson starving upon sago, and poe he would not taste at all. The kenackers set him to work carrying wood from the mountains."</p>
               <p>"Why, Johnson," said the mate, "would they not even treat you to a baked dog after a hard day's work?"</p>
               <p>"When?" cried the negro, his countenance expressing strong disgust.</p>
               <p>"As for John," continued the officer, unmindful of the torment he inflicted—"he was as lean as a snake and as weak as a rat when he came on board; but he made out to weather it three months among the mountains, it appears. Perhaps he was hid in the hole of a rock. They say that toads will live a great while in the heart of a rock."</p>
               <p>The negro looked at John, and showed all his white teeth as he grinned from ear to ear.</p>
               <p>"Come, come, you know something about it, Johnson," said the mate to the negro. "How did John contrive to hide himself from the search of his master, for he must have been an apprentice, and I'll warrant there was a close search made for him."</p>
               <p>The English lad contrived to steal a glance at the negro behind him, when the latter suddenly assumed a serious aspect, and not a word did he utter afterwards.</p>
               <p>In a moment one of the British boats was observed approaching them. The mate was the first to hail.</p>
               <p>"How fare ye, neighbor?" cried he.</p>
               <p>"Good day to ye," answered a voice in the English accent: "These fish have been gallied. They run like race-horses."</p>
               <p>Our Englishman changed color several times, at the sound of that voice. It came from a short, stout individual, in the stern of the approaching boat, and as he drew near, his look and manner sufficiently evinced that he was the English captain. He probably mistook the mate for the captain of the Maro; or perhaps regardless of the stiff etiquette; the monotonous attention generally paid to the petty rank by the American captains; he I ad no objection to chat with his in ferior.</p>
               <p>A few strokes of the oar brought him alongside of the mate's boat. The first thing observable in the boat of the stranger was the contrast in the appearance of the men. The boatsteerer was no doubt, sixty years of age: and the bowman was as much as fifty—a little man in corduroy knee breeches, with ribbed stockings, and buckes in his shoes. The countenance of the rowers differed still more widely than their apparel, while the Captain was a regular John Bull, with red cheeks, high breast, and a voice like a cataract.</p>
               <p>The crews of the respective boats looked hard at each other, so interesting is a new human countenance to those who have been many months excluded from the walks of humanity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <p>THE Captain of the Royal George jumped into a boat, and was seen moving over the billows towards the Maro. The captain stood by the ladder to hand him the man-ropes and receive his visitor, with all due honor. The English captain, however, was not so ceremonious. He sprang into the main chains and clambered up like an ordinary tar. In a moment, he bounced upon the deck of the Maro, with a hearty cheer, and was followed by a petty officer. The latter went forward and was received by the boatsteerer, while the former met the captain of the Maro on the quarter deck. The mate of the Maro let himself down into the Englishman's boat, which pushed off and conveyed him on board the Royal George.</p>
               <p>"Relieve the helm, here," cried the captain. "Eight bells have struck. Who's helm is it?"</p>
               <p>The second mate went forward to repeat the order, and demanded whose turn it was to take the helm.</p>
               <p>"Edwards," replied one of the lads.</p>
               <p>"Edwards! Where is he?"</p>
               <p>In a few moments a young negro came up from the forecastle and said he would take the helm.</p>
               <p>"I don't care who takes it," said the second mate, "but it is very strange that Edwards should want to skulk in this way, and should keep the helmsman waiting. I never knew him to play the old soger before."</p>
               <p>"Edwards has gone to the mast head," said the negro.</p>
               <p>"He must be uncommon fond of going aloft," returned the second mate; "I think he was aloft before we lowered the boats."</p>
               <p>Mr. Bunker returned to the lee side of the quarter deck, when the Captain who was standing on the weather side, with his visitor, said, "What's the matter, Mr. Bunker?"</p>
               <pb n="12-13 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8321-00000005"/>
               <p>"It was John's trick at the helm, sir, but he has gone aloft."</p>
               <p>"What, John Edwards, the young Englishman?" said the Captain. "We have one of your countrymen aboard, sir," addressing the English captain.</p>
               <p>"That's not usual, I think. Where did you take him up?" inquired the Englishmen.</p>
               <p>"At the Sandwich Islands."</p>
               <p>"Indeed! how old may he be?"</p>
               <p>Before the Captain could answer, the second mate, who had begun to smell a rat, interposed: "He's old enough to keep better run of his trick at the helm, sir. He is called <emph>young</emph> indeed; but to judge by his whiskers——"</p>
               <p>"Whiskers!" said the English Captain: "then it is not my apprentice: for he is not over seventeen."</p>
               <p>The American captain looked wond'rous wise, and the other changed the subject.</p>
               <p>Although the English Captain had appeared satisfied, yet as he descended the companion-way, at the invitation of his host, he cast his eyes aloft and fixed them upon the top-gallant-cross-trees, with a keen scrutiny that did not escape the attention of the negro at the helm.</p>
               <p>As soon as the two captain's had reached the cabin, the captain of the Maro opened a sort of mahogany chest which he called the case, in which were several decanters and large wine glasses curiously gilt. A little sugar and water and a couple of spoons were produced, when the gentlemen wet their whistles with something "very nice," as Mrs. Child had it.</p>
               <p>The Captain of the Royal George then asked the captain of the Maro what ships he had spoken. After these questions was answered, the two gentlemen looked at each other a moment, and then the captain of the Maro said, "Shall we go on deck? The other captain said "Yes." Therefore they went on deck, and walked about, looking at this thing and that and trying to get up a conversation; but what could men so situatedfind to ask about?</p>
               <p>Pretty soon, however, the Captain of the Royal George discovered that the negro had abandoned the helm, and a new man stood between the ropes.</p>
               <p>He, therefore, cast his eyes aloft again and now he saw the young fellow descending from aloft by the fore-top-mast-stay. By this arrangement, the youth must alight upon the bowsprit, as far as possible from the quarter deck.</p>
               <p>In the mean time a couple of long, black heels hanging down from the fore-top-gallant cross-trees assured the captain that the negro lately at the helm, had exchanged places with the youth aloft.</p>
               <p>Just as the youth reached the bowsprit, the British captain became interested in the cook's cabouse on the larboard side of the forecastle. The captain of the Maro could not help asking him to walk forward and examine it.</p>
               <p>At the moment that John Edwards—the English lad—had reached the knight-head at the inner end of the bowsprit, and was about to<figure>
                     <head>THE HAND-TO-HAND-COMBAT.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8321-00000006"/> leap on the forecastle, the two captains turned the corner of the wind lass The English captain stepped directly up to John, jerked off the cap that he had pulled over his eyes, and exclaimed——</p>
               <p>"This is my man, sir! So, you rascal, I have caught you, My falling in with you is providential Captain G——. This fellow, for whose capture I had paid a hundred dollars, is now restored to me by a miracle. He is an apprentice. He ran away at Woahoo and hid himself among the mountains, I suppose, where they get sandal wood. You shall go on board," continued the captain turning his eyes in the direction of his own ship, "hah! what's the matter there. They've hove the main-top-sail aback; the man at mast head is pointing to windward!"</p>
               <p>The mate of the Maro came running forward exclaiming—"Here comes a boat from the other ship for her captain! Mr. Barnard is in her." "Ay, ay!" cried the American captain, "What do you see aloft!"</p>
               <p>A long loud cry was at that moment heard from the mast head of the English vessel.</p>
               <p>"There she blows! there she blows! there she blows!" "Do you see nothing there aloft?" cried the captain of the Maro. The men addressed were silent a few moments, when suddenly the boat-steerer at the main sprang on his feet and cried, 'There she breaches! only a mile off—right abeam! there she blows! there she lop-tails!" "Hey, there!" cried the captain, running to the quarter deck, "lay down there aloft! Hasten in the boats! Back the main yard! Man the boat falls! Stand by to lower away the boats!" We will not attempt to describe the hurry and confusion which now prevailed on board the Maro.</p>
               <p>The British captain seemed to have one eye on his captive and the other on the boat that was approaching.</p>
               <p>In this agitation he lost sight of John just as the second mate lowered away his boat, then he immediately detected the lad in climbing over the side to get into the boat as it struck the water. He sprang to the rail in order to intercept the lad, but he was too late.</p>
               <p>"You have got my man in your boat!" cried he. "Yes, sir—but see the whales yonder!" cried the second mate, heaving with one hand against the after oar as he guided his boat with the other. The light vessel shot away from the ship's side like an arrow, and the sturdy subject of George IV. was instantly summoned to get into his own boat, which waited for him under the counter of the Maro.</p>
               <p>With a sweep of the eye we now behold the two ships slowly filling away in order to keep as near as possible to the boats: while the billows of the ocean are dotted with half a dozen black specks, which, at a distance, resemble drowning flies moving their arms and legs to keep afloat. These little specks are drawing nearer to some five or six hundred black masses which resemble huge logs on the surface, with a misty cloud above them. Now these little black and moving specks have reached those shapeless masses.</p>
               <p>All is quiet for a few moments: when suddenly something resembling<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8321-00000007"/> bling a huge black fan is thrust into the air—it is in violent motion—the water underneath begins to foam. Now we see a huge blunt thing projecting into the air like the bows of a bilging ship. All is now in motion; six boats are in the centre of a school, completely surrounded by whales; the harpoons and lances glitter in the sun—the sea is lashed into foam by the tails of more than fifty monsters.</p>
               <p>Here the open jaws of a whale are thrust up within a few feet of the boat; there two whales rushing upon either side of a boat threaten on to crush her to atoms. Farther off a whale leaping entirely out of water, his huge bulk is, for a moment, painted against the blue sky, when he falls, spanking upon the water, with a sound like the discharge of fifty cannons at once.</p>
               <p>Here, a boat attached to a whale by the line, is drawn, like an arrow through the very heart of the school, over crimson foam and waves of blood, while the companions of the wounded fish, as if determined to avenge his wrongs rush after the boat, snapping their jaws and thrashing their tails till the frail vessel is half deluged with clotted blood and hidden in a cloud of mist.</p>
               <p>This was the boat into which the English lad had scrambled when flying from his capturer. It was commanded by the second mate, who had placed himself in the how of his boat, lance in hand, and eagerly watched the opportunity to use his weapon. But the whale ran so fast, that the man could not hand in the line and bring the boat nearer to him.</p>
               <p>Mr. Bunker was therefore content to tell his boatswain to bold the line at loggerhead on the stern-sheets, which he did by the aid of a piece of old hat that saved his hand but, ever the an on, as the whale leaped out of water and jerked the line, it flew round the timber, cutting into the wood until it smoked.</p>
               <p>But John, who was at the tub oar, threw water on the line, with a little bucket, to prevent it from taking fire. The boat was drawn with great rapidity through the water, directly to wind-ward leaving the main school and the other boats in the distance.</p>
               <p>A pod of whales continually surrounding the boat, some snapping at the steering-oar, then thrusting up a jaw by the side of the boat, and anon sweeping their huge tails, like a cloud, over the heads of the rowers.</p>
               <p>At the same time, the sharp fin of a large shark cut the waters near the side of the boat.</p>
               <p>At length, the whale began to sound—to desend in the depths of the ocean. The boat steerer held on the line to check the whale as much as possible, which brought the nose of the boat nearly to a level with the water.</p>
               <p>The line ran fast from the tub. Nearly all the line was out, when the boatswain's aching hand slipped: a flake of line went like lightning round the loggerhead, and in a second, it wound itself round the body of the tub-oar's-man.</p>
               <p>"Take care!" cried the second mate, seizing the boat atchet—Bang! The line was severed, at a blow, and the freed whale went off triumphant with nearly a tub full of whale-line dragging after him.</p>
               <p>The whale was lost, but the man saved.</p>
               <p>"We should have lost the whale at all events!" said the boatsteerer, "for there are not half a dozen fathoms of line left in the boat.</p>
               <p>The officer looked into the tub and was appeased. He perceived that the misfortune of the boatsteerer had served only to save a little two-line, which would have been lost had no accident happened.</p>
               <p>The second mate turned the head of his boat towards the school where the war still raged with unabated violence.</p>
               <p>Heads, flukes and fins were to be seen in violent motion, and every boat appeared to be fast to a whale.</p>
               <p>As his line was gone, Mr. Bunker thought best to assist the other boats with his lance; but as he ran down to the scene of action, he did not perceive that the whale to which the English captain was attached, was about going in his flurry.</p>
               <p>It was a large fish. The captain had drawn in his line and was near the animal as he run rapidly round in a circle. Mr. Bunker perceived his heedlessness too late.</p>
               <p>He ordered his men to pull with speed, but he was in the path of the dying whale, and before his boat's crew could take any measures to save themselves, the fish came rushing, with his head out of water directly upon the boat.</p>
               <p>In a moment nothing was to be seen of the second mate's equipment but a fragment of the stoven boat, and a few men struggling in the water. The Englishman's whale having turned up his fins, which gave sufficient evidence that he was dead, he immediately went to pick up the men whom his whale scattered on the waves.</p>
               <p>The boatsteerer was picked up first; then the second mate, who looked anxiously around to see if all his men were afloat. He discovered all of them excepting English John. They were taken into the boat, and then the English captain gave orders to his men to pull toward the floating fragment in order to see if the missing man might not be clinging to it. When they reached this piece of wreck, they did indeed find John upon it; but he appeared to be just letting go his bold, his eyes rolled back in his head, and the spectators believed that he was dying.</p>
               <p>"I was afraid of that," said the second mate—"he has been hurt undoubtedly. The whale's head struck the boat about opposite to this thwart."</p>
               <p>John was gently lifted into the boat. He appeared to have no power to move.</p>
               <p>He was laid down in the bottom of the boat.</p>
               <p>"There is no appearance of injury," said the Captain—"he is, no doubt, hurt inwardly."</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir, I think he is killed," returned the second mate of the Maro. "I wish we could get him on board the ship."</p>
               <p>"We had better take him on board the Royal George," said the British captain, "for all our whale ships have a doctor; whale yours do not."</p>
               <p>As these words were pronounced, a shudder passed over the prostrate youth.</p>
               <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8321-00000008"/>
               <p>"Life is in him," continued the English Captain, "did you not see him move?"</p>
               <p>"I saw him open his eyes," said the boatsteerer bending over him with anxiety; for no man in the Maro could have elicited deeper sympathy than English John, the general favorite.</p>
               <p>The captain of the Maro having killed his whale, and thrust a pole, with a black flag, in the eye of the fish, so that he might not be lost, now approached the boat of the English captain.</p>
               <p>"Is anybody hurt, Mr. Bunker?" cried he.</p>
               <p>"Yes," answered the other—"John is hurt."</p>
               <p>"Let your men come on board of my boat. I am going to the ship," said the captain.</p>
               <p>The American Captain then ranged up along side of the other boat, and the men began to get into the boat of the former. The second mate and boatsteerer then lifted up the insensible body of John to put it on board; when the English captain ended—"No—no. I will take him on board of my ship: we have a doctor."</p>
               <p>"But, sir," returned the American captain—I am going immediately on board, and it is necessary that the lad should be attended to. Your ship is at a great distance and you are not going to her yet."</p>
               <p>"Never mind that," said the other. "He is my apprentice. It will do him good to suffer a little. It will teach him that in going on board an American ship, he has not bettered himself."</p>
               <p>"A man is not a brute!" exclaimed the captain of the Maro, and "Americans do not sport with the lives of their poor. Every man counts one in my country, and your bluster will frighten nobody here. Bring him into the boat, Mr. Bunker."</p>
               <p>The Englishman sprung between Bunker and the American boat and stared at the young officer in that peculiar manner by which the insolence of rank or wealth endeavors to overawe persons of humble grade. Mr. Bunker pushed the captain aside and the latter fell into the bottom of his own boat. In a moment, John was safely put on board the Maro's boat; and before the English captain could regain his feet, the boat of the American captain was gliding over the waves towards the Maro.</p>
               <p>Had not the American captain believed that John required immediate assistance, he would probably have surrendered up the youth to his old master; but the brutality of the English captain towards a lad who apparently had not many hours to live, very soon decided the destinies of the young apprentice. John was conveyed on board the Maro. He was immediately taken into the cabin and restoratives were applied which revived him a little. The captain in vain searched every part of his person to discover a wound or braise. He finally had a cot prepared and put John into it. In the mean time, he waited for the doctor: but no doctor came.</p>
               <p>The two ships began to cut in their dead whales, by stripping the blubber from their carcases. This task was completed before night, and it was then observed that the Royal George had made sail, and was fast separating from her companion. "He cares nothing about the lad's life," said the captain of the Maro. "His talk of a doctor was a mere artifice to get the boy into his possession."</p>
               <p>"I thought as much," said Bunker in reply: "but the lad is strangely affected. He lies perfectly still and appears to suffer no pain."</p>
               <p>"Let us go down to him," said the Captain, "and see what we can make of his case."</p>
               <p>This conversation took place in front of the try-works, where the second mate was engaged boiling out blubber. The officer dropped his skimmer—a sort of iron for removing scraps from the kettles—and followed the captain into the cabin. They discovered that the cot was empty, and in a moment John came down the companion-way with a pitcher of water. Both stared as if the dead had risen untimely from his grave.</p>
               <p>"Well, John, you are better," said the Captain approaching the youth. "How long is it since you recovered your recollection?"</p>
               <p>"Ever since I heard that the Royal George had parted company with us," said John, turning away his face to conceal a smile.</p>
               <p>"What!" cried Mr. Bunker, not knowing whether to smile or frown; "then you have not been hurt at all!"</p>
               <p>"No, sir," returned John.</p>
               <p>The captain looked at the mate for an explanation, and-the latter said—"He was afraid of being carried back to the Royal George, and he pretended to have been hurt in order to avoid going back."</p>
               <p>"Well, I'm glad it's no worse," returned the Captain who felt his mind relieved of a great burden; for he had entertained fears that the lad would die, and in that case, he would have found it difficult to justify himself, the British captain having insisted on furnishing him with medical attendance on board his own vessel.</p>
               <p>Still it was so difficult for the captain to divest himself of the idea that John was hurt, in some degree, that he made him sleep that night in the cot which had been prepared for him.</p>
               <p>The light from the try-fires of the Royal George became more and more indistinct, and when morning broke, nothing was to be seen of the British whaleman.</p>
               <p>Greatly to the surprise, and much to the joy of the ship's company, John Edwards, as he chose to call himself, came on deck and went to his duty in the morning. The secret of his manœuvre was confined to himself, the captain and mates.</p>
               <p>"Well, my boy," said old Tompkins, as he tossed up the horse-pieces—junks of blubber—from the main hold, "I'm glad to see you about so soon—but you must not work too hard at first. I was saying to Russell last night that the Captain would cure you if any doctor could."</p>
               <p>"Doctor," said another of the crew. "If he had gone aboard that ship, the doctor would have kept him sick a mouth with his <emph>poison</emph> physic. But where were you hurt, John?"</p>
               <p>"No where in particular," returned John; "as much in one place as another, I think."</p>
               <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8321-00000009"/>
               <p>"So I was saying," said Tompkins; "the whale's head struck the boat and cut it right in two. Now the gunnel of the boat broke the force of the whale, before he struck you, or you would have been smashed; but as it was, you did'nt get the whole force of the blow—but jarred your <emph>intervals</emph> and that knocked you up for a little while, till the blood got to circulating again. Then the captain has given you all the grog you could drink, I'll be sworn, and there's nothing like that to bring a man round. A man will never die while the liquor is in him; for no man can be dead till he's cold; and the heat of the liquor prevents him from going cold."</p>
               <p>"You seen to have a good idea of these things, Tompkins," said one of the boatsteerers, who had been leaning over the hatch and listening to this medical lecture.</p>
               <p>"Oh, no, I don't pretend to any great learning," said Tompkins, meekly: "but I've seen some service—yes, I've seen some experience, too, and I take notice. There are some folks that don't take notice. We had a marine when I was in the Constellation, along with——"</p>
               <p>"Horse pieces! horse pieces!" cried the man at the try-works, which out short the yarn of old Tompkins, who began to toss up the junks of blubber with a pike, and use extra dilligence to make up for lost time.</p>
               <p>In the centre of the mind of man, there is a high observatory, furnished with lens that to "the utmost bounds of the everlasting hills!" We have but to turn the instrument in any direction we please, and the eye of the mind falls upon any distant part of the universe to which it points. We have hitherto glanced over the Western Continent and across the Pacific Ocean. We will now whirl the instrument around and look nearer home.</p>
               <p>The dust blew from the shore of Cape Cod towards the sea. The waves recoiling from the strand, launched their foaming tops back upon themselves. The waters rolled on chased by the north wind, until they encountered the island of Nantucket. Checked by this isle of the ocean, they thundered angrily against the shore, beneath the cliff that overlooks the Bar—a dense bank of sand stretching far beyond and across the mouth of the harbor, and so near the surface that loaded ships could not cross until lighters had deprived them of the greater part of their cargoes.</p>
               <p>It was at the time when, in the far Pacific, the Royal George had fallen in with the Maro, that a ship just arrived from "round Cape Horn," lay thumping on the Bar of Nantucket exposed to the northern winds. The white caps were seen off the harbor, by the islanders, and some concern was felt for the ship and cargo. Old Mr. Pinkham, the pilot, was consulted by the owners and his reply was such that they saw the shades of night settle around their exposed vessel without much alarm.</p>
               <p>This was the case, however with a company assembled in a decent wooden house on Wescot Hill, overlooking Beebe's Bakery. This house was not a hundred yards from the tower, where parson Swift was wont to hold forth.</p>
               <p>In the front room of this dwelling were a middle-aged woman, a lot of girls, and several young men. The matron was quickly engaged in knitting stockings, and occasionally looked up when a remark worthy of note was made by one of the young people around her. Several of the girls looked rather serious, and it was reasonable to conclude that they had lovers "round Cape Horn." The rest were as lively as crickets and the young men stole kisses unreproved.</p>
               <p>A rap was heard at the door. One of the youths went to open it, and soon returned bearing in his hands several letters.</p>
               <p>"Now who's got beaux around the Horn?" cried he. Two of the letters were addressed to the woman of the house. Before she had perused one of them, a blue-eyed girl made question—</p>
               <p>"Is there anything there from Barzilla, cousin Merab?"</p>
               <p>The lady replied by putting the letter into the hand of the questioner requesting her to read it aloud. All the young people became instantly silent, and she read as follows—</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>"WOAHOU, ——, ——</dateline>
                              <salute>"Dear Parents—</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>"Before I say anything to you about this voige, I want to tell you what has com to my ears—that Jane is false"—here the poor girl turned as red as fire: she hung her head, attempted to go on——</p>
                           <p>"I have—have—heard that she is corting with Ben Raymond"—"Oh! what a lie!" cried the reader turning pale and hiding her face in her hands, she burst into tears.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>"To be sure it's a lie," cried the youth alluded to in the letter, and who chanced to be present. "Every body in Nantucket knows that it's a lie!"</p>
               <p>"Certainly it is," said they all: and now all the girls set themselves seriously at work to comfort the love-lorn damsel.</p>
               <p>"He'll find out better when he falls in with a ship from home," said one of them, attempting to take her hand.</p>
               <p>"But who could have told him?" inquired one of the young men. In vain did they ransack their memories. They could think of nobody recently from home that would have carried such news to the mariner lover.</p>
               <p>It was then suggested to the desponding fair one, that, at least, her lover could not pay his addresses to any other girl until his return, and that long before that time, he could be undeceived by letters from her and others.</p>
               <p>"It is not that!" cried the blue-eyed fair one weeping afresh, while her plump bosom moved as if her heart would break. "I am not afraid that he will <emph>always</emph> think me false; but when he went away, he told me that when he found himself off at sea—living on salt junk and hard biscuit—that when he went below cold and weary from his hard night-watch, it would be a sweet relief in the midst of his hardships to think that there was one on shore, that there was one in Nantucket who—who"—here the poor girl overwhelmed by the picture she had drawn, could go no farther, but wept aloud.</p>
               <p>The other girls glanced about them timidly as if unwilling the young<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8321-00000010"/> men should be let so fur into the secret of a woman's love, while the latter silently cast their eyes to the ground, as if too conscious that such were not the feelings which they entertained for the opposite sex.</p>
               <p>"Don't take it so much to heart," said the mother of the absent youth: "when he gets on whaling ground, he will have so many things to take up his attention, that he will not be unhappy on your account."</p>
               <p>This was an unlucky speech, and the tears of the maiden continued to flow.</p>
               <p>"What else is in the letter? Perhaps it tells who carried the news," said one of the girls.</p>
               <p>The mother then took the letter from the stand on which it had been placed and read on—</p>
               <p>"When I first heard this news, i was at mast-head, and had such a death-sickness seize me that I came near falling from aloft. But i can rite no more on this subject, as i am sick at heart, whenever i think of it."</p>
               <p>The rest of the letter gave an account of the voyage.</p>
               <p>The blue-eyed girl, still weeping, put on her bonnet and without saying a word, set out for home.</p>
               <p>A silence of some moments ensued after her departure.</p>
               <p>At length two of the girls began to whisper, and the mother overheard the name of <emph>Ruth Willard.</emph>
               </p>
               <p>"Caroline," said she, to the speaker—"tell me whether you suppose there is any danger of another such rash action—"</p>
               <p>"Oh, no, I think not—but when Jane went out, she was as pale as a sheet, and her looks put me in mind of Ruth when her lover suspected her in the same way. But Jane has more sense than that."</p>
               <p>"How long is it since that tragedy happened?" inquired a young store keeper from 'off Island,' who had recently set up in town.</p>
               <p>"It is something like three years as near as I can tell," answered Caroline. "Ruth was an orphan; very pretty, with deep blue eyes and yellow hair. She was not tall not large, but of a light build, and the men said she was well formed."</p>
               <p>"So she was," interrupted one of the youths. "She had a fine bosom—small waist—wide, round hips, and little feet, and she was as quick as lightning. She would talk of a dozen things at once, and talk well on everything too."</p>
               <p>The storekeeper smiled, inquired where she had lived.</p>
               <p>"Down in Eunice Mitchell street," was the answer—"but, perhaps, you don't know where it is. You go from here right down into Main street—then you turn to the left, and go along by George Cannon's and Mark Coffin's till you come to the end of that street. Then you turn down a jog, and the first street on the left is Eunice Mitchell street, and Eunice Mitchell lives in a white house, with high steps, on the corner of the lane that leads up to the Quaker meeting and school-house. It is she that owns the ship Maro, which Jane's lover is in."</p>
               <p>"Maro! that's the name of a poet!" cried the shopkeeper, smiling.</p>
               <p>"Very like," answered Caroline, for the ship was named by Miss Lydia dia Mitchell, and she is one of your poetry folks. Well, Ruth Willard lived in that street."</p>
               <p>"You say that this young lady was jealous—"</p>
               <p>"No, but her lover was. He came here from Boston, where he had been clerk in a store; but he took a notion to go to sea. So he went out in one of our Nantucket ships, and while he was out, he heard that Ruth was courted by somebody else. He wrote a terrible letter to her which broke her heart; and he never came back in the ship. Nobody knows what became of him."</p>
               <p>"And the girl?"</p>
               <p>"She killed herself—poor creature. She was in the habit of going out upon the cliff all alone, to watch for her lover. But she got a letter from him—the letter which I mentioned. It almost broke her heart, for it was as false as Lucifer, and never did a girl love anybody as she loved him. But she waited for the ship which was then expected every day. At last the ship came—but her lover had not come home in the vessel. He had left the ship in foreign parts, and that is all the satisfaction the crew could give her. In two days afterwards, her bonnet was found on the cliff, and in about a week after that a shawl soaked with sea-water was found on the beach after a Norther. The waves had washed it ashore; and that is the last that was ever known of pretty Ruth Willard."</p>
               <p>"What sort of a person was her lover?"</p>
               <p>"Alexander Merrill! Oh! all the girls can describe him. He was a great favorite here. Everybody thought him handsome excepting me; but I did not like his high Roman nose and coal black eyes. I like softer looks in a man."</p>
               <p>"He must have looked like a Jew," said the other.</p>
               <p>"I don't know. They say Jews have long beards."</p>
               <p>"He was too young to have much beard," said another girl.</p>
               <p>"So much the worse for John Brock—one customer less," returned Caroline, laughing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8321-00000011"/>
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <p>AT the mouth of Conception Bay, which spreads out before the the little Spanish town of Talenhana, is a small island called Karakeena. When the wind blows violently from the North, this island breaks the force of the wave's as they roll in from the Pacific. Therefore, the harbor is a tolerably good one. At about the time these events occurred which we have recorded in the preceding chapter, several seamen might have been seen wandering over the desolate heather, tasting some strange berries that they found in their way, or gazing out towards the sea, and conversing about the barrenness of the plain.</p>
               <p>At length they reached the sea-shore on the Eastern side of the island, and as they talked of the recent gales which were reported to have done some damage, a mulatto man, whose speech betrayed his Cockney origin, came up from the beach, to the promontory on which they stood, and signified that the two Spaniards who were lost the other night lay beneath them on the sand.</p>
               <p>The whole company descended the hill together and in a few moments they stood around a couple of skeletons which lay embrined upon the beach. Although scarcely three days had elapsed since those individnalss were drowned by the upsetting of their canoe, there is nothing remaining to show they once existed but the light frame work of bone that gives form and consistency to the human body—save here and there was a small bit of flesh still cleaving to the skeletons, as if the bird had been instructed that it was had manners to take the last piece.</p>
               <p>The Cockney lifted one of the skeletons by the neck, turned it over, examined it, remarked on its lightness, and then threw it, rattling, upon the pebbles with which the shore was lined.</p>
               <p>Some remarks were made by the seamen upon the nothingness of man, and the Cockney quoted a few extracts of Scripture in a style more original than correct, then the seamen turned and retraced their steps, evidently feeling that if the island afforded no other prospects than such as they had just witnessed, it was hardly worth the trouble of exploring. The Cockney, who served an Englishman that owned the island, also turned away, and passed over the hills.</p>
               <p>When the coast was perfectly clear, another descended the promontory, and advanced rapidly towards the beach. He started as his eyes fell on the two wrecks of humanity, and walking up to the spot where they lay, he examined them with increasing curiosity. The arm of one of these skeletons was partially covered with the sand: he disengaged it, and after eagerly examining the hand, he cried—</p>
               <p>"It is then so! Poor unfortunate Pedro! Your poor wife will be doubly miserable. Wretched as was her existence before, she will now be beggared indeed! All the earnings of her husband could not keep sufferings out of her little hut—but now—Ah! why should these calamities fall so frequently on the poor!"</p>
               <p>He stood a moment as if lost in sad reflections. The wind blew open his jacket and revealed a shirt of check and a perfectly modelled neck and breast.</p>
               <p>His attire though coarse, was scrupulously clean, and his showy neck ribbon fluttered in the breeze.</p>
               <p>His features though considerably embrowned, were intellectual and rather more bold than handsome. It was evident that he had scarcely arrived at manhood.</p>
               <p>After standing a moment, gazing sadly upon the bony frame at his feet, he stooped down and took a plain ring of no great value, from the dead hand.</p>
               <p>"Here was a creature with affections," said he. "He is gone—the air is emptied of him, as of a thing annihilated. Who that looked at these few bones could believe that the former owner of them was still in existence? Who ever read immortality on the face of the dead?"</p>
               <p>The youth sat down upon a rock, clasped his hands, and looked out upon the bay. The shores of the main land were at some distance, and it was scarcely possible to discern the few huts that were scattered along the coast. In the midsts of the bay were several whale-boats, one of which had made fast to a humpback; and while the fish ran towards the main sea, thrashing the waters with his tail, and even leaping above the surface, the others vainly endeavored to keep up with her as she was drawn by the whale. But the young man was as one with the dead, and on the island all was silent, save the breeze that crept through the grass and stinted bushes. The waves hoarsely complained on the beach, and the far off seal cried from his black cavern open to the sea. "What boots it," said he at last, "if such is the end of man? Shall I continue here to struggle on, to live a life like the fishes—to exercise first one passion and then another, to gratify my appetites till they are lulled by age? And what is the issue of it all? Here it is. In a few years I shall begin to grow old; well, I shall continue to eat and drink—to sleep and to wake—and time will add nothing to me. It will only diminish my enjoyments; would it not be better and nobler to—finish all with this?"</p>
               <p>He took a short and very sharp dagger from his bosom. "Shall I give the buzzards another dinner?"</p>
               <p>He laid his dagger on the sand beside him, and once more approached the skeleton of his friend. He lifted the slight frame from the ground.</p>
               <p>"Ought philosophy to regard this skeleton as an object of terror?" said he. "Surely every part of it is as well adapted to its purpose as the frame work of a ship. Here are the ribs, which were planked up<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8321-00000012"/> with flesh. The flesh cleaves to the bone and is kept in shape by it. Then this foot is there, anything frightful in that? Behold this beautiful arch made up of several bones, intended for strength, because the foot endures the weight of the whole body. If an arch is so strong, well may it be said that the promises of God stand sure, which rests upon the many hued arches of the heavens—what better sign of substantial hope could have been given to Noah? This skull contains the brain. It is intended to receive the most precious parts of the human body—the birds have not carried away the brain of my friend."</p>
               <p>Quick as thought, he made sure of this fact. With this dagger he burst open the skull, and plucking out the brain, he held it before him in one hand.</p>
               <p>"Here is a red, pulpy substance which——thinks! Aye they tell us that this is the seat of thought. From this, as the centre, a number of threads pass to every part of the human body. At different points they all receive different impressions, and this constitutes the five senses. The impressions run along these conductors to the brain. But what part of the brain? Much brain may be removed without touching the head quarters of intelligence. Now that I look upon this brain, I cannot perceive any part that looks peculiar, as if it were more excellent or wonderful than the rest. Yet surely the sensorium must be far more wonderful than all the rest. Lo! my friend Pedro! is your sensorium <emph>here,</emph> and does it now perceive me present with you? Or has it passed away to gather to itself other substances which have a natural affinity for it, and become the cognomen of another being with other affections, other hopes—and while the tastes which you have cultivated in this world cause substances more or less excellent, to attach themselves to your sensorium—so that if you have improved your few talents, you will next be rewarded by a nature a hundred fold more excellent, more capable of refined and exquisite enjoyment. Ah! Pedro! you were a man of humble occupation, little gifted with intellectual power: but you were hospitable, as I too well know: now then I will dig a grave for you, for your wife must never see your bones stripped of all she once loved to embrace."</p>
               <p>With a large shell, the youth scooped a grave high up on the beach, and laid the bones of Pedro and his companion in the sandy sepulchre. He piled the sand upon them and rolled a stone of peculiar configuration upon the grave to mark the spot.</p>
               <p>"Now to bear these tidings to his wife and poor lame brother, who depended on him for support,' said the youth.</p>
               <p>He walked away. He continued his route along the beach, until he had arrived at a rocky cove, and from a cavern, he launched a little canon upon the waters.</p>
               <p>At this time, two whale-ships were lying under the lee of the Island. Their topmasts were housed, and they had evidently designed to make a considerable stay in that place. The boats of both ships were out on the bay. Several of them were moving along the Eastern shore, in company, and the officers of those boats conversed freely with each other.</p>
               <p>"I hope," cried one, "that we shall fill up soon. If I were the old man, I would not have stopped for hump back oil; I would have gone right round Cape Horn with a flowing sheet."</p>
               <p>"So I think," said the other—'It's hardly worth taking—but what's that?"</p>
               <p>The last speaker clambered up and stood upon the stern-sheets. He saw, at no great distance ahead, something above the level of the water which resembled a little black island, rounding up to view.</p>
               <p>"There's a hump-back, by all that's holy I fast asleep!" cried the mate. "Now, boys, spring to your oars. Lay back to it, if you want to see Nantucket—go it—my darlings! Buckle, you dogs! Spring!"</p>
               <p>The boat shot through the water and the white wave roared around the prow.</p>
               <p>The boat had already touched the long fin of the whale.</p>
               <p>"Stand up! give it to her!" cried the mate to the boatsteerer.</p>
               <p>The boatsteerer took the harpoon, lifted it—and the whale, startled from his sleep, wheeled, rolled over, lifted the boat from the water, and spilled all the men, who rolled out like green peas from an open pod.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, the other boats were not idle. One of them was very near the first when she was overturned, and her men sprung on their oars, and reached the whale before he commenced running towards the mouth of the harbour. Two irons, or harpoons, were put into him, and he instantly begun thrashing the water and running.</p>
               <p>The men in the water succeeded in getting upon their boat which they turned over, and partly bailed: but they thought best to go ashore, the beach being distant only half a mile.</p>
               <p>When they reached the shore, the boat was hauled up, and the crew looked about them for some house in which they could dry their clothes. From the beach, they walked up a ridge of rising ground and began to walk over the plain, interrupted occasionally in their progress by dells, underwood and rocks.</p>
               <p>At length they reached a little hut, built of mud, with a thatched roof. Everything here bore the appearance of extreme poverty. They, however, perceived smoke, and concluded there must be fire within. Upon entering the miserable dwelling, they perceived it contained no floor but the ground.</p>
               <p>A few stones served for seats, and two or three tattered rags supplied the place of beds. A middle-aged woman, cheaply attired, with the lines of care and anxiety deeply traced on her countenance, sat before the fire caressing a couple of half-starved children, who turned up their sad eyes, as if glad to see somebody enter their solitary domain. A poor crippled man arose from one corner of the fire-place to welcome the visitors.</p>
               <p>The mate and his men scarcely noticed the inmates as they seated themselves before the fire, compelling the occupants of the dwelling to retire to another part of the room.</p>
               <p>They piled upon the fire all the fuel that they could find on the premises, the woman rendering them what assistance she could. The<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8321-00000013"/> children sat down together shivering in a distant corner, not daring to approach the men who had taken possession of their homestead, and looking up to them as superior beings.</p>
               <p>The lame man evidently perceived that all was not right, but he dared offer no impediment to their course.</p>
               <p>Their clothes having become dry, the men turned towards the women and demanded something to eat. She shook her head and declared that she had nothing in the house. Indeed, the aspect of the dwelling sufficiently corroborated her statement.</p>
               <p>The sailors then rose up and with lond threats demanded that she should produce something to eat and drink. Her children then approached their mother, as if they feared that the strangers would offer violence to her.</p>
               <p>Finding that nothing could be got from the woman, the men began to rummage the house. In a nook on one side of the chimney they found a horn tumbler half full of bran and meal mixed with water. As they drew it from its hiding place, they loudly charged the woman with deceiving them.</p>
               <p>She said it was only a mouthful that she had saved for her children and the little ones looked up, with their emaciated faces and with wisitul eyes, as they saw their scanty supper borne off by the invaders, of their lonely dwelling.</p>
               <p>The woman could not avoid making an attempt to recover the precious morsel. She advanced one or two steps towards them and begged that they would return it for the children's sake.</p>
               <p>"What! are you not satisfied with deceiving us? cried they, and snatching up a sharp stick they thrust the point against her breast. She fell back, dropping a few tears, extorted by the anguish this occasioned her, and the children clinging to her frock set up a scream when they saw that she was hurt.</p>
               <p>The lame man then hobbled up as if he would protect the woman, but one of the boatsteerers knocked him back with his fist. All resistance appeared useless and the wretched family remained passive.</p>
               <p>In a moment, however, and before the woman's eyes were dry, the sound of footsteps was heard without. A youth entered—the same that we have described above. He had just arrived in his canoe from the islands. A boatsteerer sat on a large stone before the fire devouring the meal, with a wooden spoon. The rest were standing about him. The former looked up with that sort of hoggish impudence which some men assume when they belong to the strongest party, while the rest looked at him as to demand his business. The woman and her children immediately ran towards the new comer, and the lame man smiled through the cloud that rested on his countenance.</p>
               <p>"Pedro! where is Pedro?" said the woman in Spanish. The youth evaded a reply by bowing to the strangers.</p>
               <p>They did not bow to him in return: but began to whisper and grin to each other, in a manner extremely offensive to the youth. The latter dropped the courteous manner which he had assumed, and carelessly observed—</p>
               <p>"You appear to be enjoying yourselves, men; you doubtless belong to Nantucket."</p>
               <p>"Yes I belong there. I am chief officer of the ship——" said the mate folding his arms complacently, as if he supposed the announcement of his dignified station would put an end to all further question on the part of the youth.</p>
               <p>The latter scarcely stopped to hear him finish the sentence: but turning aside, he said a few words to the lame man in Spanish. The cripple glanced at the intruders, as he replied to the youth in a low voice.</p>
               <p>The fellow who had eaten up the children's supper gathered up his long legs, which he had spread out before the fire, and placing his elbows on his knees while he leaned his chin upon his palm, cried—</p>
               <p>"He's telling you I eat some hog wash out of a horn, I suppose—well, what have you got to say about it?"</p>
               <p>The youth looked at the brutal visiters very much as Ulysses looked at the rival princes who devoured his substance; and my meditated dire revenge upon the plunderers of the poor.</p>
               <p>He replied not to the taunts of the whalemen: but one by one the family left the house. The youth went out after them, leaving the house in the sole possession of its ruffian invaders. The boat's crew then began to crack their jokes at the expense of the departed youth, and their chief observed—"He soon had to haul in his horns when he found that he had the mate of a ship to deal with;" but while he spoke, the mate became sensible that the room was filling with smoke.</p>
               <p>"Something is burning—don't you smell it?" said he to the others who had risen from their seats. "When! let's have fresh air!" cried the gentleman who had eaten the meal, as he hastened towards the little aperture which served for a door. But lo! this aperture was closed, and firmly too, for he in vain endeavoured to push away the stones that barred his egress. He turned to address his companions, but the hot smoke blinded him.</p>
               <p>"Make way there! go out! Quick, or I shall be smothered!" exclaimed the mate.</p>
               <p>"Hullo! without there! Open the door!" cried they all, as the red flames burst through the combustible roof. Cinders, brands, and live coals now rained down upon the heads of the imprisoned men. The mate roared aloud for help, and the others shrank close into one corner, which was still free from fire, although even there the heat from the rest of the building was so intense as to blister the skin in some places.</p>
               <p>At length the roof fell blazing at the feet of the terrified whalemen. They could no longer endure the smart of the fire, and rushing desperately against one side of the hut, they forced their way into the open air.</p>
               <p>As they emerged from the burning pile with their faces peeled, their hair singed, and writhed and capered about in their anguish, they might have been mistaken for a party of wild Indians dancing around the death fire of a burning captive. Their wounds were not serious, how ever; but the smarting of their skins rendered them frantic.</p>
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8321-00000014"/>
               <p>As soon as they had recovered from their terror, they plainly perceived that the insulted youth had strongly, fastened the door by piling up large stones, and had then heaped some rubbish against the side of the hut. This, having been set on fire, and thence their disaster.</p>
               <p>To add to their mortification, their clothes began to drop from their bodies, and they had not walked more than half the distance to the boat, before they found themselves naked as they were born. The wind was chill, and they ran to keep themselves from freezing; notwithstanding which some parts of their persons were suffering a burning pain, and the limbs of the mate began to blister.</p>
               <p>At last they reached the shore; but what was their consternation when they discovered that their boat was gone!</p>
               <p>The mate ran to a high cliff near the shore, from which he could discover his boat just turning a point of land, at a great distance, towards the mouth of the harbor. It was pulled by two oars—doubtless the lame man and his youthful friend.</p>
               <p>"What shall we do?" said the mate, as he came down from the cliff.</p>
               <p>"They have gone off in our boat, and we cannot hail the ship as we are a dozen miles from her. No boat is to be seen from this place, and if we set a signal, it will not be seen—indeed, we have none to set!"</p>
               <p>"If there is no where we can go," said the boatsteerer, "we might as well stay here and die."</p>
               <p>"We must look for the inhabitants," said the mate; "come let us be going."</p>
               <p>In melancholy plight these naked men set out upon their travels. They ran nearly a mile over the rugged plain before they came in view of a human dwelling. A little hamlet, consisting of mud houses, was concealed by the trees that grew around the tenements. The boat's crew had penetrated the heart of the settlement before they discovered that the inhabitants were gazing at them from all points, doubtless surprised at six foreigners appearing before them in a state of undity.</p>
               <p>As soon as they perceived that they were in the neighborhood of human dwellings, they ran up a little hill, on which were a couple of houses, for the purpose of demanding aid at the hands of the inmates. Several women ran off screaming at their approach, and three stout Spaniards advanced a few paces and demanded what they wanted. The mate could speak a little Spanish.</p>
               <p>He very humbly signified that he was mate of a vessel, and that the rest formed part of the ship's crew—that they had lost their boat and desired succor, for which a generous reward would be given by the captain of the ship.</p>
               <p>The Spaniards stared at the naked man, with his hair half burned off and his legs blistered, and evidently doubted his story. They conferred together a moment, and then replied that they did not understand the story; that was very strange; that he and his men looked like rogues; that there were a great many foreign vagabonds prowling about the country, and that a Spanish gentleman had recently been robbed and murdered by some of the Yankees on shore.</p>
               <p>This reply was interpreted by the mate for the benefit of his companions nions in distress, and it gave no encouragement to the shivering crew It was the more unsatisfactory as, by this time, several of the base sort of the natives had evinced a disposition to trifle with the unfortunate. The boatsteerer received a patch of mud on his naked back which had been thrown by some scapegrace from behind a tree; while a rotten apple smote the cheek of the make himself.</p>
               <p>Nothing remained, but a speedy retreat. They had inland, but the whole village was now raised and every cholar was armed with missiles, following closely in the rear of the routed whalemen. In this way they fled half a mile further, when they caught sight of a handsome dwelling surrounded by a thicket.</p>
               <p>They plunged through the hedge and found themselves in a little garden, at that moment occupied by a Spanish gentleman and several ladies.</p>
               <p>This party was startled at the sight of six naked men, covered with mud, and bounding through the enclosure that surrounded their pleasant habitation.</p>
               <p>The Spaniard drew out two pistols, exclaimed that they were robbers, and bade the assailants to advance no further. The made told his story as well as he could, when the Spaniard put up his weapons and beckoned them into an apartment of his house, and closed the door upon them.</p>
               <p>They had not waited long before he returned with a number of old Spanish trowsers, short and wide like those worn by the peons, and ponchos rather the worse for wear. A few sugar-loaf-hats were also handed to them as they passed out the door.</p>
               <p>He then conducted them to an obscure path which led to the beach, and motioned them good day. All this he performed without uttering a word, and when the mate would have thanked him for his aid, he held up his finger to impose silence.</p>
               <p>Dressed in the Spanish gear, the discomfited crew arrived at the beach. Fortunately for them, there was a large canoe within half of the shore. An old man with two girls were taking up muscles. This operation was performed by means of a pole which the man held up-right in the water: and the girls descending by the pole to the depth of three or four fathoms, brought up the muscles from the bottom in bags tied to their waists for the purpose.</p>
               <p>This old Spaniard they hailed. The old man could not be prevailed upon to approach the shore, until the mate pretended to hold up money to him. Then did he slowly paddle towards the beach. When, however, he discovered by their speech that they were not his own countrymen, he moved with more alacrity.</p>
               <p>When he was fairly within hearing, he leaned over the bows of the canoe, leaving the two we girls shivering in the stern with their knees drawn up to their chins.</p>
               <p>The mate promised him money in abundance if he would convey them on board the ship which lay at a great distance, under the lee of the Island. The Spaniard at length consented to leave his muscles and girls on the beach and undertake the job. The men entered the<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8321-00000015"/> canoe and the old man paddled them over the waves. Their progress was necessarily slow. The old man toiled until dusk, and he became so completely exhausted that it was a matter of doubt whether he would be able to return to the place from which he started. The captain and second mate looked over the ship's side, and seeing a canoe approach, filled with men in Spanish garb, cried out—</p>
               <p>"Stand off! You can't come on board! Get you gone."</p>
               <p>The mate replied, and the canoe continued to approach. But the wind was blowing in the teeth of the mate and his words were lost.</p>
               <p>Then the captain began to swear and to order the canoe, in a tone of thunder, to sheer off and not presume to approach the vessel. It was sometime before, the captain could be made to understand that one of his boat's crew was in the canoe. Great indeed was the surprise of the captain and the crew on board, to see their shipmates thus habited—and coming aboard in a fisher's boat instead of their own. The mate told his story, and the captain so far from evincing any sympathy for their sufferings, flew into a boiling passion, charging them with misconduct on shore, neglect, and pusillanimity.</p>
               <p>In the meantime, the poor Spaniard remained under the chains in his canoe, looking up wistfully at the ship.</p>
               <p>"What does that man want?" cried the captain to the boatsteerer, the mate having gone below to change his dress.</p>
               <p>"We agreed to pay him five dollars for bringing us on board—"</p>
               <p>"Pay him five dollars!" exclaimed the captain. "Indeed! that would be a fine day's work that you would make of it." Then leaning over the ship's sides, he bade the aged boatman to make himself searce immediately.</p>
               <p>The old Spaniard looked up amazed and could scarcely reply that he was waiting for his reward.</p>
               <p>"Yes, I'll pay you!" cried the captain grasping an harpoon and threatening to transfix the old man in his canoe.</p>
               <p>The old boatman slowly paddled away—turned back his streaming eyes to look once more at the vessel, and then betook himself to his weary task. The shadows of night descended upon the waters and he was seen no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <p>THE morning sun shone bright upon the broad expanse of water already introduced to the notice of our reader under the name of Conception Bay.</p>
               <p>The breeze was light, and the season was opportune for two whalemen to put off their boats, and pursue the great fish, that roamed about those waters in quest of food.</p>
               <p>A couple of boats did put off from one of the ships: but this time, the harpoons and lanoes, could not be discern glittering in the sun; and in lieu of such gear, the crimson edging and short feathers of Spanish soldiery could be discerned mingling with the duck shirt and red caps of the seamen.</p>
               <p>The object of this array might have been surmised had you seen the Captain of this company point with his sword towards a small black brig, at that time slowly cleaving the waters, with all sail set, and heading towards the mouth of the Bay.</p>
               <p>"Are you sure," said the mate whose forlorn wanderings are recorded in the preceding chapter. "Are you sure, Captain, that the fellow is on board that brig?"</p>
               <p>The Spanish soldier curled his moustache with his left hand, as he sheathed his sword with the right, and sat down by the site of the mate.</p>
               <p>"Yes, yes, sir—We have looked for him in that vessel. These foreigners give us a great deal of trouble; because they are not Christians: they are mere brutes."</p>
               <p>The mate who understood part of this trade against Protestants, endeavoured to turn the conversation by remarking that the brig could not escape them, as the wind was light.</p>
               <p>The men continued to put their oars, with long strokes, that swept the boats ahead with surprising rapidity.</p>
               <p>"That's right my lads—go ahead!" cried the mate, springing on his feet. "We will teach the rascally beach-comoer what it is to insult the mate of a ship and steal his boat."</p>
               <p>"You won't get the boat back," said the soldier, "It was sold to a vessel bound to Coquimbo, and the thief made sure of his money."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps he left the money or part of it, with that woman and the lame fellow."</p>
               <p>The brow of the Spaniard grew dark, but he said nothing.</p>
               <p>As the boat came within hail of the brig, she hove to and waited for them to come up.</p>
               <p>"Brig Bio, Bio!" cried the Captain of the guard—"have you got a young Englishman on board of you?"</p>
               <p>The Captain of the brig who was a native of England, came to the side and answered in Spanish, that there was nobody on board<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8321-00000016"/> but himself and mate, three or four natives, and a negro from Brazil.</p>
               <p>The mate of the whaleman told the soldier that this was probably a lie, and insisted that the brig should be boarded and searched. The soldiers seemed to feel very little interest in the matter, and mechancally obeyed.</p>
               <p>On going aboard, they found the deck lumbered with various articles of merchandize. There was a poop deck, and directly before the cabin door was the wheel where stood a tall cholar, who began to handle the helm very vigorously, although the vessel was lying to, in order to display his seamanship to the soldiers. In the cabin was a tall, delicate gentleman playing upon the piano, who did not deign to break off his music, or pay the least attention to the individuals who had interrupted the voyage. The other native sailors were lounging about the windless, and the negro from Brazil, stood on the poop deck looking down with sullen dignity upon the interlopers.</p>
               <p>The brig was pretty thoroughly searched, and then the seamen descended to their boats followed by the soldiers. As soon as they were gone, the Brazillian negro descended from the poop, washed his face and hands, and leaving his ebon hue in the bucket, stood forth the youth of the hut—the very man of whom the soldiers were in search. The brig continued her course, and in a few hours she had doubled the northermost point, and was lost to the crew of the whaleman.</p>
               <p>On their way to the ship, the Captain of the guard threw out some hints to the mate about an attack having been made upon a defenceless native family by men from the Yankee ship; and he also hinted that the two men found dead on Karapeiua might have been murdered.</p>
               <p>Improbable as the latter suggestion was, the mate well knew that the prejudice against foreigners was strong enough to beget suspicions which might be dangerous. He now recollected that when the last whale was cut in, and crowds of canoes surrounded the ship to take possession of the carcase, there were strange glances cast at himself, and whisperings among the boatmen, accompanied with gestures more auimated than friendly.</p>
               <p>The mate suggested these things to the Captain, when he got on board, and the result was that, on the next day, the top-gallant mast was sent up, and everything made ready to sail on the ensuing morning.</p>
               <p>On the next day, the ship weighed her anchor, and sailed for home.</p>
               <p>About a week after these events, a number of seamen might have been seen standing together on the beach at Valparaiso. Boats belonging to the different ships in the harbor were hauled up, or lay off at a short distance from the shore waiting for Captains or officers who had landed on business.</p>
               <p>At a short distance from the water, stood several buildings and among the rest, a little grog-shop called the "Hit or Miss," illustrated by a sportsman taking aim with his gun at a flock of birds. Farther off, but within a few steps of the beach, was a wide, low building surrounded by a plazza and tenanted by the Captain of the port—a genteel young Philadelphian with a very showy military cap.</p>
               <p>On a promontory overlooking the harbor was a building with piazzas, green blinds, and all that renders a place pleasant and agreeable in a hot climate. This was an aristocratic boarding house for the higher classes of society, kept by a woman who had come out to Valparaiso from England in the humble capacity of a menial; but who by perseverance and good fortune had been enabled to become the proprietress of the finest public house in town. It is true that the lady's crockery was occasionally broken by an earthquake: but she soon become accustomed to such trifles, and made up her losses by charging an enormous price for board.</p>
               <p>The crowd of seamen were all well dressed in blue jackets with duck trowsers—the former ornamented with small eagle buttons. They wore neither suspenders nor vests, and their white shirts were ornamented with blue facings, and stripes of the same were on the collars Their shining, black tarpaulin caps were begirt with wide black ribbons, and their slippers nicely fitted to the foot were fastened with strings of the same material. Among them were individuals of all ages and sizes. The appearance of some was very inferior, while others were specimens of manly beauty exceeding that of the pampered youth in our cities who are favorites with the fair, and who owe their fine proportions almost wholly to their dress.</p>
               <p>A youth, long and slender, and whose proportions appeared to disadvantage in the simple attire of a seaman, was holding a discourse in Latin with a Spanish priest, while his shipmates surrounded the interlocutors and listened to his companion as he Interpreted the replies of the priest.</p>
               <p>"He says that St. Jago is a hundred miles off—in the interior, you know, and we can walk it in three days; and as we have just been paid off from the frigate and have a great deal of money about us, there will be some danger from the robbers on the road."</p>
               <p>A burst of laughter from his companions was all the reply that the interpreter received. Just then a Spaniard on horseback rode up to the seamen who respectfully made way for him, until he was in the midst of the throng. While they waited for him to tell his business, he elevated his hands and eyes to heaven, and asked aims in the name of the Blessed Virgin.</p>
               <p>"You are able to ride on horseback," said one of the men, "and do you come to beg of me?"</p>
               <p>"Sheer off," cried another. "Sell your horse and go fight, before you come to beg of sailors."</p>
               <p>Although this was unintelligable to the mounted beggar; yet he could perceive that his petition was rejected and changing his suppliant and devout attitude to one of defiance, he rode off cursing the heretic pirates.</p>
               <p>It was evident that these seamen, newly discharged from an American frigate in the harbor had resolved to travel on foot to St. Jago—a large inland city, where but few of their countrymen could be found. Having been for many months confined on shipboard, this adventure presented many attractions.</p>
               <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8321-00000017"/>
               <p>Before "taking their land-tacks on board," the man-of-war's-men thought best to lighten themselves of a portion of their money on the Main Top, a hill in the vicinity of the town occupled by dancing-halls and other places of public resort. Accordingly they passed through the principal streets, ascending the hill and found on its summit the Main Top Dancing Hall, kept by black Sam, formerly a servant to the celebrated Dr. Nott of New York. Sundry Spanish lasses lingered about the place, and gazing with longing eyes upon the new comers, listening, with hope on tip-toe, to the jingling of the coin in the pockets in many dancers.</p>
               <p>Leaving these gay wanderers of the deep to the two great blessings of life—wine and women—we must turn our attention to one of the principal characters in the story.</p>
               <p>On the same afternoon that the discharged seamen landed on Valparaiso beach, a solitary seaman wended his way up the long hill at the bottom of the Main Royal or lower part of the town. The path which he took to go over the Cordilleras, a ridge of mountains near the sea-shore. Although dressed as a seaman, this was evidently a man who had chosen his profession for the simple purpose of making money. Though more desperate and reckless of consequences than the hardiest sea-men, he possessed none of their coarseness and levity. While meeting danger and hardship, with an unblanched cheek, his soul was alive to the tenderest sympathies of our nature. Although, in this age of the world, he was not calculated to distinguish himself, the character given of Cæsar by Byron, was, in some degree, applicable to him— <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l rend="ti-2">"But the Roman's mind</l>
                        <l>Was fashioned in a less terrestrial mould</l>
                        <l>With passions fiercer, yet a judgment cold,</l>
                        <l>And an immortal instinct which redeemed</l>
                        <l>The frailties of a heart so soft yet bold;</l>
                        <l>Alcides with the distaff now he seemed,</l>
                        <l>At Cleopatra's feet, and now himself he beamed</l>
                        <l>And came and saw and conquered—"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But he was not calculated for distinction in a society organized like ours; for he carried out those principles which so many talk about and which so few put in practice. He would not be great, excepting in his own way; and "sink or swim, live or perish," he would have nothing to do with the sordid cunning which leads to wealth and preferment. From his cradle the coldness of the world's breath had chilled him, and he had learned in his infancy that grown up men could be pleased with toys—much more that they could be proud of them. He had early learned that all men must die, and from that moment and ever afterwards the world was his prison-house, and the thought of placing his affections upon anything which can perish was repulsive and degrading to his immortal nature. He knew there were those that looked contemptously upon his apparently aimless life, but he never permitted them to know with what utter indifference he regarded their opinion of his character; for his indignation was vanquished by godlike pity for the wretches whom he scorned.</p>
               <p>With such sentiments, he was not likely to make much figure in the world. The desire of fame, of wealth—some motive is requisite to obtain eminence. His nature was too simple for the tortuous course of modern greatness.</p>
               <p>Such was the character of the individual. It is not our business to admire or defend it, but simply to portray it as it was.</p>
               <p>He began to ascend the long hill that overlooks the lower part of the town, and before he had gone many steps, he saw an old man and woman wallowing in the land. These he addressed——</p>
               <p>"I am a stranger in Valparaiso," said he, "and I have set out for St. Jago, a large city in the interior. Tell me, if you please, whether this is the right road, and whether there are stopping-places on the way, where we can procure lodging and refreshment."</p>
               <p>The old man sprang up like lightning, and drew his forefinger across his throat, intimating by this motion, that he would be robbed and murdered if he travelled alone. The old woman uttered loud outeries, brandishing a bottle of aguadiente, and making many gestures indicative of threatened danger. The youth, at length, prevailed on them to say that he was in the road to San Jago, and he left them.</p>
               <p>He continued to ascend the hill, and had walked more than a mile, when he came to a house—low but wide—built of stones and mud, with hollow tiles on the roof.</p>
               <p>Two or three rough looking native, with long dirty hearts, lowering brows, and sugar-loaf hats, shrunk behind the corner of the house as he approached.</p>
               <p>"Come here, John!" cried a voice in broken English, and our traveler perceived several young women in front of the house with little tables, upon which were several kinds of fruit, little pies, auguadente, and <hi rend="i"/>chee chee—the former the ardent spirits of the country, the latter a beverage between wine and cider. He immediately obeyed the call. The girls made room for him, and he sat down beside them. They began to talk and laugh among themselves, and occasionally passed a joke upon their guest, evidently wishing to make him talk. They pointed at the articles on the tables, and expressed a wish that he would purchased something.</p>
               <p>Before he could make up his mind, the noise of horses' hoofs were heard, and in a moment several men drove up at full speed, leaped from their horses, and each one took a Spanish lass upon their knees. There were English and Americans. Our youth told them whither he was bound. They charged him to put up at the house where he was, that night, and to travel always by day-light.</p>
               <p>"This," say they, "is St. John's day, and the natives have very generally got drunk in honor of it, if they meet you on the road, you will find them troublesome."</p>
               <p>The youth observed that these men were all heavily armed, wearing the poncho and splatter dashes of the country. They stated, that they were mechanics belonging to Valparaiso. He had been led, by their bearing to suppose that they were men of higher grade; but in a country where the great mass are paupers, a man who can get a living without begging or stealing is an important character.</p>
               <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8321-00000018"/>
               <p>After taking something to drink, the strangers leaped on their horses and went off with the speed of the wind. The sun was low, and the evening breeze was cool among the hills. The youth asked the girls if he could spend the night at their habitation. They called on an old man by the name of Pedro. He came forth with his wife. He was a little old melancholy Spaniard, with a night-cap on his head. He told the youth he could lodge there for three rials and could have supper for half a dollar. The charge was exorbitant, but the youth had several dollars in his pocket, and did not hesitate. Pedro proceeded to prepare supper, by catching a hen. He held the body of the her firmly with his left hand and pulled of its head with the other. It was awkwardly done, putting the poor animal to much torture; but the executioner appeared to suppose this a matter of small consequence. The youth reprimanded him for his cruelty, and instructed him that he should have chopped off the fowl's head with a hatchet. The Spaniard bore the reproof very patiently, and his wife hastened to cook the fowl. The supper was scanty in the extreme. A few skins were spread on the earthern floor, and the youth lay down to rest. He was awaked about midnight by the entrance of half a dozen armed Spaniards. They sat around a charcoal fire, drinking auguadente, and talking with such of the family as chanced to be awake. They made very particular inquiries about the youth who feigned sleep. They asked if he had much money.</p>
               <p>"A little, not much," was replied by one of the girls.</p>
               <p>Owing to his scanty covering, the youth felt cold. He arose and approached the fire. He took up a glass of augundente that stood on the table and drank it off. The Spaniards looked at each other and muttered, for the liquor belonged to one of their number. He heeded them not, for he was in his reckless humor, and having passed some satirical joke upon these fierce mountaineers, he retired to his place of repose and fell asleep again.</p>
               <p>He arose with the sun. His entertainers desired him to stay to breakfast; but he told them he liked not their charges, and immediately sailed forth.</p>
               <p>Our traveller having emerged into the open air felt himself relieved by the mountain breeze. He passed over a wide tract of country during the day, meeting nobody but a few teamsters, and men driving asses laden for the Valparaiso market.</p>
               <p>The deep vales between the mountains filled with trees and every variety of shrubbery, with water sparkling at the bottom, engaged his attention; and occasionally in those mighty abysses the human figure might be seen, stealthily treading a wooded path, and at so great a distance as to appear no larger than a Lilliputian.</p>
               <p>At length, the evening shades began to descend again, and the youth succeeded in finding a little dwelling built of mud and thatched. There he applied for lodgings.</p>
               <p>He was permitted to lie on the floor with the rest of the family and charged one rial for his entertainment. His fellow-lodgers comprised, among the rest, several rough natives, armed with long knives and of very ferocious aspect.</p>
               <p>In the night, he felt them fumbling at his pockets for money. He seized an unseen hand that was moving over his person. The individual broke away, and as it was totally dark, he could not discover the thief.</p>
               <p>In the morning, he again addressed himself to his journey.</p>
               <p>Our youth was in no hurry. He pursued his journey leisurely, and with an observing eye. From the moment that he commenced his enterprise, he had been continually warned that danger beset him on every hand—that he would be robbed and murdered, every alarmist, ending his prophetic exhortation by drawing his finger across his throat in imitation of the manner in which he should arrive at his death. On this morning, he discovered a solitary traveller at a great distance ahead, but his gait proclaimed that he was no Spaniard. He walked very fast and soon encountered our youth. He was a young Mulatto.</p>
               <p>"In God's name, where are you going?" said he to our traveller.</p>
               <p>"To St. Jago," was the reply.</p>
               <p>"You must have urgent business, or you would not go there."</p>
               <p>"I am going for pleasure."</p>
               <p>"Pleasure!" cried the mulatto, eyeing our youth as if he doubted his veracity. "Turn, and go right back to Valparaiso with me; for the city is in an uproar. A revolution has broken out and all the English and Americans are massacred in the streets and in their own houses. I have just come from St. Jago; I have killed my horse by hard driving, and left him at Castle Blanco. Your life is in danger, even now. Come then, shipmate and go back to Valparaiso with me."</p>
               <p>Our traveller told him that if there had been a revolution when he was there, it was probably over by that time, as South American revolutions never amounted to much.</p>
               <p>Thus they separated, the mulatto continuing his rapid course, towards Valparaiso, and the other making progress towards the inland city.</p>
               <p>On this day, our adventurer passed through Castle Blanco where were a post house, one or two taverns and stores, and a few dwelling-houses.</p>
               <p>On the next morning the travelled a sort of road studded with buildings at the distance of two miles apart. At about ten in the morning he saw antique gate-posts with a house in the rear. An eagle had alighted on one of these posts, and an old man sat underneath, in a chair placed by the sides of the gate. The old man rose and presented his hand to the youth.</p>
               <p>He invited him into the house, and introduced him to the women. The latter were, by no means, so hospitable as the old man. They however yielded so far to the persuasions of the latter as to roast an egg which they presented to the youth with great ceremony, and from whom they seemed to expect unbounded gratitude. He received the present with mock gravity and offered to pay for it, but the old man would not permit this, although the women seemed perfectly willing to accept a liberal compensation.</p>
               <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8321-00000019"/>
               <p>He departed, followed by the blessing of the old man. During the forenoon, he stopped at several houses to procure food; but was informed that they had no victuals cooked.</p>
               <p>At about two o'clock in the afternoon, he stopped at a farm-house which stood a considerable distance from the road. Nobody was visible save five or six girls, who sat round a pot, out of doors. Of them he purchased a plate of baked meat for one rial, and they presented him with some <hi rend="i"/>chee chee to drink.—These young women were not remarkable for their beauty, although they were wholesome, active girls. They were very sociable with our youth and he remained with them about two hours, contributing, in various ways to their amusement. One of them mounted a very skittish horse, and pretended to be ignorant of the art of riding.</p>
               <p>She made the animal rear and plunge, and pretended to be afraid of falling off.</p>
               <p>When the youth sprang forward to assist her, she gave the horse the rein and set off at full speed. Then the whole bevy set up a laugh at the expense of our traveller.</p>
               <p>At about four o'clock in the afternoon, he bade adieu to these wild nymphs, and travelled on until dusk, when he saw the smoke of a cottage rising above the tree-tops at a little distance from the road. He took a path which led through the woods, and soon came to a large fire ill the open air, around which sat a man, his wife and nine or ten girls of various sizes.</p>
               <p>He sought to purchase a supper; but they were very poor, and although extremely good-natured, and disposed to accommodate him to the utmost of their power, had nothing to offer but a little farina in a horn tumbler. He paid them for it, and then selecting the prettiest girl, he kissed her with great severity.</p>
               <p>The old man seemed highly amused at this, while the girl herself seemed to wonder whether the business was going farther.</p>
               <p>Again he struck out into the road. Night soon overtook him. The road was very bad, and the sloughs and streams of water rendered it difficult to pass. Late at night he found a cottage into which he entered without ceremony.</p>
               <p>It contained the man and his wife, three very homely girls, and two or three course young men. They insisted that he should pay for his lodging before retiring to rest. He reached a rial to the woman, who pretended to drop it, accidentally, into the ashes. They all began to grope in the ashes for the precious coin; until the youth asked one of the young men lift his foot, under which the rial had been concealed.</p>
               <p>In the morning he set out again. He soon met a Spanish gentleman on horseback.</p>
               <p>The latter reined his horse, and after some conversation, suggested that the youth was a deserter from an English man-of-war, and that if he would get up behind him on the horse, he would carry him back to Valparaiso and deliver him to his captain. He also agreed to give the youth the money which he should receive for restoring him.</p>
               <p>"I am no deserter; but am a traveller bound to St. Jago," was the reply.</p>
               <p>The Spaniard said he did not believe him, and ordered him to show his discharge. The youth shook his stick at the Spaniard, saying, "This is my discharge—go out of my way, or you may have a chance to peruse it."</p>
               <p>The Spaniard then put spurs to his horse and calling our traveller a "damned heretic," made himself scarce.</p>
               <p>The youth was now near the case of a high mountain upon which the clouds rested. The road was winding and he passed through green woods where the foxes, rabbits, and birds boldly played in his path. Nothing could exceed the audacity of the birds.</p>
               <p>They would scarcely get out of his way when he came amongst them, and two large eagles sat proudly perched upon a tree, who refused to stir until he was within ten feet of them when they spread their wings and flew off to a short distance where they a alighted again.</p>
               <p>He then commenced ascending the mountain that had been repeatedly pointed out to him as the resort of banditti and wandering things. A zigzag road led to this mountain for the convenience of teamsters and travellers. The dells and deep gorges on either side of the path were filled with scraggy trees and every variety of underwood. From these deep chasms singular noises ascended.</p>
               <p>It was difficult, very difficult to declare whether they came from men or brutes.</p>
               <p>Long before he reached the summit, he passed through a cloud. Its nature was that of a cold mist, like the spray of a sea-wave, and so dense that he could not see more than twenty feet before him. He kept in the path, although he would occasionally find himself on the brink of a high precipice; and at another time he would be stopped by a great rock that the mist had hidden from his vision. At length he had passed through the cloud, and approached the summit of the hill. The air was clear and he could find his way without difficulty. But he saw another cloud resting on the summit, above him, while the cloud under his feet shut out the plain from his view. Thus shut up between two clouds, he felt himself an insulated being—separated from the world; and his soul throbbed with the wildest pleasure. He wished it was in his power to dwell there forever—but meat and drink were not obtained on that elevated spot. Feeling very little desire to change his situation, he clambered into a high rocky seat, like a throne, and looked down upon the world, or rather, upon the cloud far beneath his feet that shut the world from his view.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8321-00000020"/>
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <p>IN the midst of his 'lofty cheer,' the mind of the youth recurred back to his past experience in life. An orphan at the age of twelve years, he had been left the artificer of his own intellect—his own sentiments. A married sister, proud and selfish, with whom he could hold no feeling in common, was all the relative left him. He thought of her no more. But his imagination pictured another.</p>
               <p>"Now," said he aloud, "I am alone—alone physically as well as mentally. "Tis glorious to be alone, to those who never imagined themselves otherwise. Bright dream—flash of light in the midst of the dark terror I saw her—I imagined her such an one as I had never expected to see. That falsehood could dwell in that bosom—that she could have assumed feelings which never had place in her bosom. Ah! she was like the rest of the world. I left my native country in a whaleship. Disgusted by the artifices of trade, set out to visit distant lands, to lend a more simple life, and she fell in with a shop keeper during my absence. Doubtless they are united by this time. Yes, married, and pursuing the old monotonous track which their ancestors pursued before them. This then severs me forever from the world. This renders me solitary. It restores me to the solitude I had before I knew her—nay—not to that solitude, but to a deeper solitude, as one flash of light increases the gloom of midnight. Is it then possible, that if I visited Nantucket again that girl—that woman—could look upon me with a cool and indifferent gaze? Hah! the thought almost makes me man! I could almost laugh at human nature when it renders itself so ridiculous. She with her profession—her enthusiastic profession of congeniality."</p>
               <p>For a moment he seemed bewildered at the idea of so much baseness—so much deceitfulness, united to so much apparent candor. "Oh! Ruth! Ruth!" said he: "How unlike the Ruth or old! How unlike her who said, where thou goest, I will go; where thou diest I will die!"</p>
               <p>He pondered a moment in silence, and then, under the influence of violent emotion, leaped from his throne, and began to ascend into the top of the mountain.</p>
               <p>He had reached the very summit and was preparing to descend, when he heard the sound of voices—in the midst of the cloud. The mist was so dense that he could see no person for several moments; but as he continued to advance, the dark outlines of the human form became visible. A number of natives were seated on the ground engaged in roasting a large pumpkim. This was the most wretched sample of chilians that he had seen. Their mustachios and beard stuck out in every direction. Their eyes were sunk deep in the socket, and the hair hung out through the rents in their shapeless hats. These seemed to be mountaineers without house or home who dwelt in the open air. Their clothes were filthy and full of holes, and their ponchos were of the coarsest stuff that goes by the name of cloth. They all wore long knives at their sides, and a pair of pistols lay on the ground near the fire. Our hero felt no fear whatever. The adventure exactly suited his romantic turn of mind. Therefore with more than his natural ease of manner and boldness of bearing, he approached the ruffian group. One of them started up and approached him—</p>
               <p>"Where are you going?"</p>
               <p>"To St. Jago"</p>
               <p>"Are you travelling all alone?"</p>
               <p>"Yes."</p>
               <p>"When did you leave Valparaiso?"</p>
               <p>"Several days since. I have travelled slowly."</p>
               <p>"We are going to Valparaiso," said the man; then turning to his companions, he said—</p>
               <p>"This is a gentleman!"</p>
               <p>Then drawing out his knife, he approached the pumpkin, chopped of a slice, and taking it on the point of his knife, presented it to the young man. The latter received the timely gift with thanks and commenced descending the mountain, saying to himself— <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>When man meets man, a stranger in the wild</l>
                        <l>The man to man is always kind—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>He might have added—Except the stranger betrays doubt, suspicion, or fear, when man to man may be unkind.</p>
               <p>He now imagined that when he emerged from the cloud, he should have an opportunity to see the country beyond him, to a vast distance, perhaps to gaze on the glittering spires of St. Jago. But when he came out from the thick mist that covered the summit of the mountain, he saw, far beneath his feet, clouds spread over the whole of the surrounding country, so that he seemed to be standing on an island in the midst of a boundless ocean. He could, therefore form no idea of the plain which he was about to visit, until he had descended beneath this lower cloud, and then a prospect opened before him, which beggars description.</p>
               <p>The country through which he had passed on the other side of the mountain, had been more wild than beautiful; but now the most charming scene presented itself. He, at length, reached the bottom of the mountain, and travelled on over green lawns, through shady groves, among waterfalls and wild flowers for nearly two hours. He then arrived at a house, just as the evening shades began to fall. A middle aged black eyed woman—much resembling a lady ship owner whom he had seen at Nantucket—was cooking something over a pan of charcoal, under a shed near her dwelling.</p>
               <p>He had occasion to remark, as he had often done during his journey; the strong resemblance which many of the natives bore to persons whom he had seen in his own land.</p>
               <p>He was almost led to believe that the people of one nation were copies of people of another bearing close resemblance to each other in their features and in their dispositions.</p>
               <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8321-00000021"/>
               <p>This woman received him very kindly and immediately gave him something to eat.</p>
               <p>By her side was a daughter not more than nineteen years of age—a plump and graceful little creature with very small and delicate hands and feet.</p>
               <p>He asked for lodgings, whereat there was a pause in the conversation for a few moments. As the woman occupied a very respectable house, he supposed that she hesitated about admitting a poor traveller under her roof, but the cause was soon explained. With an inclination of her head towards her daughter, she demanded, in hesitating accents, whether he would sleep alone, or share his couch with another.</p>
               <p>Acting upon a hint which he had received at the outset of his journey, he carelessly replied that he would sleep alone; for he supposed that the woman and daughter being the sole occupants of the house wished to test his character before they admitted him. He soon repented his answer; for a crimson blush gradually suffused the countenance of the lovely damsel, and she hung her head with evident looks of mortification at having been rejected by the youth at her side. He would have given much to take back his rash answer; but could he do so now without appearing to accept one from motives of pity whom he had repulsed from choice? Afflicted at the thought of having wounded a woman on so tender a point, he followed his conductress to a door in the front of her house.</p>
               <p>The room into which he was ushered bore the appearance of having been a store. The bed destined for him was formed of several thick rugs laid upon a board frame or broad bench, with skins and blankets for covering.</p>
               <p>It was the first comfortable bed, he had found during his journey. The hostess locked his door on the outside, and he slept well and soundly.</p>
               <p>Early in the morning, his door was unlocked, and he paid his land-lady and set out on his journey. He called upon the peasants occasionally during the day, and at dusk he reached the margin of a broad river, not more than ten miles from St. Jago.</p>
               <p>While he was wading this river, two girls came out of the hovel on the opposite side and called to him.</p>
               <p>As soon, therefore as he had crossed the river, he repaired to their humble habitations. He found several girls within—one of whom was quite pretty.</p>
               <p>They began talking with him as well as they were able—partly by signs and partly by words—when they proposed to take a walk. He rose up and accompanied them to a sort of hostel and store on the banks of the river, surrounded by a high wall, with an open gate. He bought the girls some cakes of sugar, called Jon-kak, and cheese to eat with it—the cheese being about as large as the crown of an ordinary hat; and they returned home. He slept at this place, and started for the city in the morning.</p>
               <p>There was now a wide plain lying between himself and St. Jago, nearly as level as a marble floor. He had walked about four miles, when he came to a clump of trees, behind which were several houses.</p>
               <p>A horseman rode out from behind these trees and came at him, at full speed, as if with the intention of riding over him. Perceiving that this ruffian was backed by a number of companions, who regarded him from behind the cluster of trees, our youth contented himself by walking leisurely forward, as if he did not perceive the object of the intruder.</p>
               <p>Accordingly the latter reined in his horse, and rode along by the side of the youth.</p>
               <p>"Give me your money!" cried he pointing at the knife in his belt.</p>
               <p>Our hero replied that he had none to spare, where upon he drew out his knife and brandished it with great pomposity. Our youth lifted his cane and threatened to use it if the robber did not withdraw to a respectful distance.</p>
               <p>He then sheathed his knife and rode along by the side of our youth, acting in so friendly a manner as to lull suspicion. The youth, was, how-ever on his guard, thinking only of preserving his money. Suddenly however, the robber stopped and plucking our traveller's cap from his head, rode off with it in triumph. This was a seal skin cap of imposing dimensions which our hero had obtained of Valparaiso from some English sailors, who gave it to him in exchange for his tarpaulin.</p>
               <p>As soon as our hero perceived what had been done he turned to-wards the thief, and kept his eye on him till he saw him go into a little shop behind the trees.</p>
               <p>He then advanced to the place; but the comrades of the plunderer had given notice of the youth's approach, and he came out of the house and mounted his horse with the seal-skin cap on his head. The youth broke through until he reached the horse of the chief. The latter endeavoured to ride over him; when the former struck his horse on the head with his cane and kept him at bay. Then the confederates of the thief all rushed upon our hero with their horses and he was compelled to retire.</p>
               <p>As the youth slowly gave ground, they cut at him with their knives, and the thief rode off with the cap. The youth, seeing all attempts at recovering his cap useless, again addressed himself to his journey. He stopped at a house on the road, told his story, and procured an old straw hat.</p>
               <p>When within about two miles of the city, be met a number of gentlemen on horeback, and several carriages filled with the elite of the country.</p>
               <p>One old Spanish gentleman, richly dressed, and riding a handsome steed, drew out a pistol as soon as he saw our youth, and kept the muzzle pointed at him with his finger on the trigger, until he had passed by, which seemed to imply that robbers lurked near the city.</p>
               <p>At about eleven o'clock in the forenoon, our traveller entered one of the avenues of the city. Ladies on horseback, carriages, and foot-passengers now became frequent.</p>
               <p>He penetrated into the heart of the city—to the large square called The Plaza, without having found a single person who could speak English. He made many inquiries of the Spaniards who told him of<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8321-00000022"/> English persons, but could give him no intelligible direction to their place of residence.</p>
               <p>Having made inquiry of some soldiers in the public square, they told him they knew of no Englishmen in the city: but they invited him to him their guard-house. There they made many inquiries about Valparaiso, and gave him some chee chee to drink. He borrowed one of their swords and a sash and gave them in return, several passages from Shakspeare, uttered with great vehemence and with the most spirited gestures—knowing that they could gather nothing from the language. This induced them to go and call their officer, who seemed pleased with the performances.</p>
               <p>Having rested awhile in the guard-house, he went forth and continued his wanderings about the town.</p>
               <p>While thus employed, at about three o'clock in the afternoon, he heard a gentle voice, in broken English—</p>
               <p>"Come here, John, and tell me the news from Valparaiso."</p>
               <p>He looked across the street and saw a Spanish girl in the door of a house, who now Leckoned to him, and earnestly requested that he would enter her abode. He was about crossing the street, when he heard another voice from a piazza overhead—</p>
               <p>"Don't go there, shipmate! Come up here and rest yourself and take a bit of dinner with us."</p>
               <p>He accordingly crossed over, and then the girl ran out and entreated him to come in: but the Scotchman ran down from the piazza and laid hold of him, saying, "No, no; don't mind her! Walk up stairs <unclear>with</unclear> me, and I'll introduce you to as guid a set of fellows as ye ever set your twa een upon."</p>
               <p>He went up stairs with the young-man and was ushered into a large room containing a couple of beds a bin of burning charcoal, and a great variety of English books, with a few apologies for chairs. In the room were also several Scotchmen, one Englishman, and a Yankee with a large nose.</p>
               <p>He was informed that there were only seventy persons in that large city who spoke the English language, comprising Scotch, English, Irish, and Americans.</p>
               <p>"Then," said he, "you can tell me who was the mulatto fellow that I met on the other side of Castle Blanco, fleeing as he said, from the revolution."</p>
               <p>"Yes, yes," said one of the Scotchmen, "I ken well wha it is what you mean. 'Tis a yellow bit of a body that lifted about ten doubloons from his master, and run off to save his bacon. There has been a revolution here; but it is all over now. Men were shot dead in the streets like wild ducks; and they stuck up some of the richest merchants in the place, to be pelted with and lead in the Plaza."</p>
               <p>The occasion of the late disaffection was—that some of the citizens wished to remove the Chief Magistrate, whose name was Pinto, and to introduce a man into office who was violently opposed to foreigners. But the rebels were discomfitted, and Pinto remained at the head of affairs. So bitterly hostile was the minority to Europeans, that, during the disturbances, they sought out English and Americans, with great deligence, to put them to death. They told him that nearly all the English, Scotch, Irish and Americans in the place were <emph>temporarily married.</emph> When they saw a girl who suited them, it was only necessary to hire a room, and invited her to enter it. She would remain with a man as long as he would maintain her. But the room in which he then was, belonged to a Scotchman and Yankee, who hired it of an old woman in the other end of the house, who also furnished them with three meals per day—charging them but two dollars, a week for the whole. This old lady and her husband preserved with great devotion, a picture of Ferdinand: and their attachment to royalty was not more remarkable than their devotion to the ancient church. Whenever the old man met a priest in the street, he would raise the hem of his robe to his lips and kiss it devoutly.</p>
               <p>On the next day after the arrival of our hero, he was informed that the old man and woman had gone to church, with all the devout Catholics, to pray for the deliverance of three Spanish gentlemen who lay in prison, under sentence of death, for taking a part in the late rebellion. A few days afterwards, an immense crowd assembled in the suburbs of the city to see the sentence of death executed upon these prisoners. Our hero was among the spectators. A file of soldiers with loaded muskets, were drawn around a rough post to which a plain board seat was attached. After waiting sometime for the appearance of the prisoners, the crowd were informed that they had been pardoned, at the intercession of devout men and women.</p>
               <p>As our adventurer walked away, intending to return home, he passed by a church, on the steps of which stood an image of the Virgin Mary dressed in the most fascinating manner. A priest said to the youth—</p>
               <p>"Englishman, have you not a rial to give the Mother of God?"</p>
               <p>Our hero looked up and saw that Our Lady held a box in her hand, with a hole in the lid. He was about to refuse this trifling boon, when he recollected that others had been saved from death by these very devotions.</p>
               <p>He stept up and dropped a piece of silver into the box.</p>
               <p>As he turned away, his eyes met one in the street. This man seemed to be about fifty years of age, and was dressed like a Spanish horse-man. His form was tall and athletic, and his flaxen hair hung over his shoulders. At the first glance, our youth perceived he was an European. The stranger beckoned to our adventurer in a familiar manner.</p>
               <p>"Well," said he to the youth, in a Scotch accent, "I perceive that you are beginning to learn the fashions of this place. When you are in Rome, we must do as the Romans do."</p>
               <p>The youth looked up in some surprise.</p>
               <p>"Oh! I have heard of you," continued the stranger—"My name is Barney. It is all the name I have at present. I have seen a Cholar who knew your story—or a little of it—in Talcahuna where you burnt up a ship's company, and ran off with the boat. It was very well<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8321-00000023"/> done—served 'em right—" the man's eyes shot fire. But he checked himself and immediately added, I have lived in this country a number of years. I have a family about a hundred miles back in the interior."</p>
               <p>"Is it possible? Is there a settlement there?"</p>
               <p>"None but mine. I have several daughters, two of whom are married. The youngest is about your age—perhaps, she is two or three years younger than you, I will warrant. We have a snug little family there all to ourselves. We saw logs to make boards, and I visit this place occasionally to dispose of my merchandise."</p>
               <p>"I should much like to see your place—"</p>
               <p>"And my daughter—ha! ha!"</p>
               <p>The eyes of the youth fell, and his countenance became pale as death.</p>
               <p>"Well, good bye. I'm in a hurry," said the old settler, moving rapidly away and clanking his spurs as lie walked.</p>
               <p>The youth looked after him a moment, and then returned to his lodgings.</p>
               <p>In the evening, when his companions were all assembled, he related his adventures with the old settler.</p>
               <p>"Ah! that Barney," said his host—"don't you listen to him. He is a gude mon enough. I don't spake aught against the mon, ye ken. Oh no—not I—that's not my way, is it Jockey?" turning to a Scotchman at his right—"but when one goes by only one name, though I'm not that man to be speering into another man's mess: but what did he tell ye—Come, now, lad, what did he tell ye?"</p>
               <p>"He said he lived about a hundred miles off—"</p>
               <p>"Amongst the wild Indians and ravenuous lions—that's it, isn't it, Jockey? Don't ye stir a step after him, and his daughters must be as ignorant as bears, brought up in the wilderness. You've got a very guide hame, now—"</p>
               <p>"But I can't stay here, certain, my money is nearly gone, and I have never paid you a rial yet."</p>
               <p>"There, now, no more of that, Oh! to hear him, as if we were not all brithers here, English, Scotch, Americans—"</p>
               <p>"But your brothers must not eat up your dinner from you—"</p>
               <p>"Never a bit! O, hear him. He's found out that I'm free-hearted! well, they're all welcome, for that is the ruin of me, I'm too freehearted, and I always was."</p>
               <p>"Therefore, if this man will let me go home with him, I'll go."</p>
               <p>"You will! O no—that you won't. You are not afraid of the lions then?"</p>
               <p>"No, I think not."</p>
               <p>"You are not? well, the lions are not very dangerous, neither. This old Barney has met with 'em often: but never a bit did they ever snatch a piece of him."</p>
               <p>"To be sure not. They say, indeed, that—"</p>
               <p>"But the wild Indians, lad. Maybees that ye'll have a grapple with them. They don't spare anybody that get's into their hands."</p>
               <p>"No matter. He has lived there many years and has never been killed yet."</p>
               <p>"Never been kilt! well, the lad is right. He never has been kilt, for I saw him this blessed morning with never an arrow sticking in his rump."</p>
               <p>"Then I will certainly accept his offer, and will—but when does he start for home?"</p>
               <p>"There now, to hear the lad talk, one would think he was in earnest, truly! can't Nathan and you and me sleep in one bed, as we have done, though it crowded me so, last night, that I could'nt sleep a wink; but what is that to one that's free hearted like me? and, as for the dinner, there's not enough for Nathan and me when you are not of the mess; and so it's all one thing whether you are here or not, lad. But I'm so free-hearted. I hurt myself for other people."</p>
               <p>Our hero pulled out all the money he had and threw it on the table.</p>
               <p>"Here!" said he—"take this to buy you more to eat, and I will go in search of old Barney."</p>
               <p>"O no—I won't lift the money. So, now, lad, ye may just put it into your fob again."</p>
               <p>"Yes, you shall take it!" cried the youth.</p>
               <p>"Well. I like to see any one free-hearted—give us your hand, lad sit's so much like me! Pick up the money, Jockey, and go and buy—let's see—it will buy just three bottles. Go and get the liquor right away, Jockey, and we'll drink to his success amongst the lions and the savageous, ferocious Indians.</p>
               <p>Our adventurer went to bed that might with the firm determination to go home with the old man—</p>
               <p>"Why should I return to the habitations of civilised man?" said he, as he lay awake and listened to the melodious cry of the Penora or city watchman—"the only individual whom I had supposed to be mentally constituted like myself, is worse than lost to me. She has put the finishing stroke upon all my earthly hopes; for if I was mistaken in her, then I shall seek no further. Yes, I will go into wilds with this old man, and there I will abide my time. Something tells me that in another state of being, I shall meet with more congenial spirits!"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC8321-00000024"/>
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <p>THE sun poured his searching rays upon the sheet of water that was spread out in front of the little town of Honululu. The inner harbor contained one or two brigs that were busied in taking on board sandal wood for the East India market.</p>
               <p>In the outer harbor were a number of whale ships, some of which were hoisting out their oil to cooper it; others were repairing the rigging, painting ship, or preparing to go to sea. Boats were continnally passing between the ships and the shore, some of them laden with pumpkins, cabbages, sweet potatoes and other vegetables suited to the necessities of the crews.</p>
               <p>All was bustle and activity, without any appearance of comfort. The only exception to this general state of things was the presence of several native girls, who either wandered about the decks of the vessels or floated alongside in canoes.</p>
               <p>Not a few of them, however, were swimming about the habor, a custom taught by nature to the inhabitants of warm countries, and which seems to promote health and cleanliness. The natives sailed about the harbor in their light vessels, and occasionally a large double canoe, full of Indians, put to sea, bound to another island.</p>
               <p>All this time a ship was lying at anchor off Punch Bowl Hill, at some distance from the mouth of the harbor. The ship had not begun to perform any of the operations for which she had come to the islands.</p>
               <p>It was necessary to enter the inner harbor before the crew could proceed to business.</p>
               <p>The hands had, therefore, considerable leisure, which they employed in mending and washing their clothes, reading, and conversing with the native women who had flocked to this ship in great abundance.</p>
               <p>The captain from the inner harbor visited this ship to inquire what news she brought, and to chat about the state of thing in Waanoo—yes, and the state of things at home: for, these men, though several thousand miles from their native shore, took as lively an interest in all that transpired there, as those who spent their days by the firesides of their ancestors.</p>
               <p>It was on a windy afternoon, when the swell ran high in the harbor that a boat from one of the ships inside reached the vessel of which we have spoken.</p>
               <p>The captain, boatsteerer, and all the crew save one, left the boat alongside and ascended the deck. The two crews greeted each other with great cordiality, as they were, for the most part, acquainted with each other.</p>
               <p>"Where are you from last?"</p>
               <p>"From Japan."</p>
               <p>"We got a thousand barrels. We staid as long as the weather would let us. It came on to blow one night—a regular typhoon—and all our sails went out of the bolt-ropes. On the next morning we left the ground."</p>
               <p>"Have you heard from Nantucket lately?"</p>
               <p>"No, we spoke only two ships, and they had been out almost as long as we had."</p>
               <p>"Very well; we have received late letters from Nantucket. They came in the Ploughboy."</p>
               <p>"Well, what is the news?" inquired the crew of the newly arrived vessel.</p>
               <p>"Oh! they say there is a new Universalist church built on the spot where old Dickson used to live, near Mrs. Plum's house, opposite Noah Coffin's Mary J—has got married to Sam S—and Love M—has got married to Isaac B."</p>
               <p>"That's all the news then, I suppose," said a slender and somewhat precise youth, who leaned against the fife-rail of the main-mast.</p>
               <p>This question caused a little sensation in the group, and the second mate, who was lingering near, nodded and winked to the boatsteerer from the harbor, and said in a low voice—"He has lost his girl, you know."</p>
               <p>"No?" said the boatsteerer, by way of question and surprise "Jane cannot have done that. She loved him too well."</p>
               <p>"It is true, though," returned the second mate, "Barzilla has never been the same being since. He has lost all his ambition. Jane is married to Ben Raymond by this time."</p>
               <p>"Ben Raymond!" cried the other, so loud that Barzilla overheard him: "pshaw! Raymond is on board the Ploughboy. He is second mate of her, and I know he is not married <emph>yet.</emph>"</p>
               <p>"What," cried Barzilla, rushing to the speaker; "is Ben in the harbor, and are you sure that he is not married?"</p>
               <p>"True as Luke! I know it!" was the reply.</p>
               <p>"Then I will see him. I will know—I will get leave from the captain to go in your boat, and I will board the Ploughboy. No, I won't; I'll go in one of these canoes alongside."</p>
               <p>He ran to the captain, who replied, "Go, my lad, for God's sake, for you will be good for nothing on board the ship until you have learned the truth. A sailor in love is a sad devil any how."</p>
               <p>If the reader has perused the third chapter attentively, he will not doubt that Raymond gave his friend Barzilla such an account of Jane as set his mind at rest on the subject.</p>
               <p>When Barzilla had left the ship and departed in the canoe, conversation began to flag, and the crew of the ship, going to the side, asked who was in the boat.</p>
               <p>"Nobody that you know," was the reply. "It is a young Englishman<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC8321-00000025"/> man that we shipped when we were in Waahoo before. He calls himself John Edwards. We call him English John. He is a great singer."</p>
               <p>"Is he?" was the quick exclamation, "than let him come on board. Let the boat be dropped astern."</p>
               <p>This was soon done, and English John was permitted to come on deck, although he was a stranger to all present excepting his own shipmates. He was cordially welcomed by the ship's, company who were at once pleased with his appearance. He made himself at home, and on the invitation of the crew, he descended into the forecastle where he sang a few songs in such a strain as delighted all present.</p>
               <p>When he had concluded, one of the crew said—</p>
               <p>"As you have been on the shore at Waahoo and have lived on the mountains, perhaps you can tell us something about Red Mary, a very curious Indian girl."</p>
               <p>The face of John became crimson, and he turned away his head. In a moment, however, he recovered his self-possession and replied—</p>
               <p>"What is this? who has told you about any such person? There are a plenty of Indian girls on shore, and a few on board your ship."</p>
               <p>"Now I know that you can tell something about her," said the cooper of the ship, throwing his arms over John's shoulder, and looking him in the face in a coaxing manner. "Come, you know who and what she is, perhaps. Several of the crews from the other ships have spoken of her. They say that she can speak English—that is, if she pleases—what makes you start so?"</p>
               <p>"Because you tell me of a native girl that can speak English. I know that they can all speak a few words."</p>
               <p>"But I tell you that a man on shore—Jack Crown who keeps a <hi rend="i"/>oulperee and sells liquor—once overheard her talking with somebody, not far from the missionary house, and she spoke excellent English."</p>
               <p>"He overheard her! How long since?"</p>
               <p>"Oh! about six months ago, in the evening, when she thought nobody heard her except the person she talked with."</p>
               <p>The English youth bit his lips and appeared to be both vexed and agitated.</p>
               <p>"It is probable then," said he, with assumed carefulness, but with rage in his eyes, "that Jack Crown was listening? We have a law against eavesdropping in England."</p>
               <p>"Then you know there is such a person as Red Mary. Why do they give her that name?" inquired a Nantucket youth.</p>
               <p>"They say it is on account of her complexion, which is not like that of the other girls; but it is more red—more like the North American savages, I have heard say."</p>
               <p>The rest kept silence, expecting John to continue: but he ceased.</p>
               <p>"I should like to ask another question," said a listner. "Is it true that she never holds any intercourse with men—that is—you know what I mean."</p>
               <p>"Yes!" cried English John, with sudden energy, "I can swear that she is as pure as snow!"</p>
               <p>"That is strange!" cried they all in a breath. "I should suppose that she would be sought after, as well as the other girls."</p>
               <p>"But they would not find her," replied John.</p>
               <p>"Yes, they say," was the answer; "that she lived here sometime without being known—that an old chief supplied her with food."</p>
               <p>"But this is very old!" interrupted Barzilla, who had just returned from the harbor. "I have just heard a great deal about this girl, myself, from the crew of the Ploughboy."</p>
               <p>"Give us the particulars," cried the rest, making room for Barzilla to sit down in their centre. He seated himself, and every one gathered closely around him to listen. It was observed that English John was quite as eager to listen as the rest.</p>
               <p>Barzilla said, "I have heard several persons speak of that girl.</p>
               <p>There was a fellow on board the Ploughboy who belonged ashore. and who 'tends here for Jack Crown. He says that Red Mary lives in a subterranean passage——"</p>
               <p>"Aha! then she is under deck?" cried one. John was now all attention, and watched the lips of the speaker.</p>
               <p>"But," continued Barzilla, "nobody knows where this cavern is. Some pretend to say that it's all yarn, without truth or foundation, I went aft to the water butt, to get a drink, and I overheard the captains joking about her. One of them said he had looked for her until he was tired. He had hired a Kanackur (native) to hunt her up; but the fellow soon afterwards brought him back his money and said she was taboo (forbidden to be approached.) Another of the captains said that the chief might be bribed, and he added that it had never been tried."</p>
               <p>"At any rate," said the boatsteerer of the Maro, "she must have been acquainted with English or Americaus—otherwise, how should she have learned our language?"</p>
               <p>"Pshaw: it is some cast off mistress of some North-west captain, and she must have come from North America, that's the most likely—"</p>
               <p>With sudden violence, John started on his feet and exclaimed, "I have once told you—" he then abruptly stopped, sat down, and remained silent.</p>
               <p>The crews looked at each other, and each man felt persuaded that John knew more about the girl than either captains or publicans. They were awed by the manner of the youth, and the subject was suddenly changed.</p>
               <p>About three days after these transactions the captains of the various ships in port were observed to attire themselves in their best dress.</p>
               <p>The crew of one ship started on seeing their captain, who had worn nothing but tarpaulins for the whole voyage, make his appearance at the companion way in a snuff colored surtout and rolling velvet collar. When I add that the weather was remarkably hot, this attire will appear extraordinary.</p>
               <p>Indeed, nothing can be more vulgar and awkward than a superfluity of broadcloth in a hot climate! But the crew, who had regarded their captains as a water god before, now hung their heads in his presence as if Jupiter stood in his boots. The additional importance<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC8321-00000026"/> which these winter vestments gave him, was obvious in his gait and the tone of his voice.</p>
               <p>He looked down upon his men as if they had been so many, "whelps of low degree;" and when a boat's crew pulled him ashore, he deigned not to utter a word during the passage, but kept his eyes fixed upon the clouds, as if things of earth had suddenly sunk beneath his notice.</p>
               <p>As he did not give orders to his boat's crew to go on board, they made fast the boat to the little wharf and stepped on shore. They paused a moment near the spot where a native family were roasting a dog with heated stones in a little pit.</p>
               <p>Here they were met by one of the men from another ship who gave them to understand that all the captains in port were assembled on shore for the purpose of devising means to put a stop to desertion. A few men had run away and seated themselves on the island, and the whalers were determined to take such measures as should put a stop to these proceedings.</p>
               <p>The boat's crew walked up to the building in which the grand council was held. This was one of the thatched houses common in Waahoo, and of unusual size. It stood but a stone's throw from the water. Here sat a number of captains dressed in citizen's apparel. In the centre sat a fat chief, and before him stood a missionary.</p>
               <p>The latter was a small man attired in black, with a thin, pale countenance. The captains addressed this missionary, told him that their men had facilities for deserting at Waahoo, and that several of them had taken advantage of these facilities. They added that the white men who lived on shore secreted the runaways, and they, therefore, prayed that all foreigners should be expelled from the Island. This very reasonable request was then interpreted to the chief by the missionary. Much was said on both sides, when the conference broke up and the spectators were informed that all white men would be forthwith banished from Waahoo.</p>
               <p>Among the spectators were several white residents. One of them addressed the missionary, in pathetic terms, represented to him that he had lived many years on the Island, owned a house and land, and was married to a native woman, by whom he had several children. He therefore requested the missionary to intercede for him with the chief. The missionary would not, at first, listen to him at all. At length he so far condescended to say half a dozen words to the chief, merely to tell him that the petitioner desired leave to remain on the island. As there was no argument in this, the chief shook his head and said that all the foreigners, excepting the missionaries, must quit the place. In vain, this unfortunate man requested the missionary to speak a few words in his favor. The latter said he could do nothing for him, and hastened away. In this way was this simple chief urged to an act of the grossest injustice.</p>
               <p>The man who had informed the boat's crew of the council was English John.</p>
               <p>On the next day, it was reported that John had deserted from the Maro. It was not yet certain that such was the case, as he might have staid on shore over night, with the intention of returning in the morning. But the morning boat came on board, the next day, without bringing the young Englishman, and when the sun went down upon his absence, the captain thought it time to take measures for the recovery of the runaway. Several natives, acquainted with every part of the island, were employed to go and hunt him up. The natives went and returned, and went again: but they brought no news of English John. Every one was struck with surprise, as it was supposed no foreigner could clude the vigilance of the native runners. It soon became whispered that as John had been in Waahoo before, he doubtless knew of some secret den, or hiding-place, and had means of support and bread to eat, which the public knew not of.</p>
               <p>On the next day the search was renewed for John with great rigor, and in the meantime, the different boats in the harbor went out to tow the ship into port—the newly arrived vessel of which we have spoken. The anchor was weighed—a short thick man, called Jack O'Clubs, stood on the knight-head of the vessel and gave directions to the men in the boats. This was the pilot. The ship moved slowly along toward the mouth of the harbor, the men in the boats occasionally cheering with great uproar, and the pilot bawling—"Show a leg! show a leg!"</p>
               <p>The Maro's boats were near the centre of the line, and the crews had a pretty fair view of the people on the deck of the ship. The boatsteerer in one of the boats happening to look behind him, suddenly exclaimed—"who is that standing near the pilot on the forecastle of the ship? If that is not our John it looks very much like him."</p>
               <p>"I know who you mean," said the man at the bow oar. "I have been looking at him. I saw him a few minutes ago, in the waist, talking very earnestly with Barzilla——"</p>
               <p>"As sure as fate, that must be John!" cried he; "Hullo! Lincoln!" added he, addressing another boatsteerer behind him. "Look at that slender figure looking over the bow of the ship!"</p>
               <p>"It looks like English John," replied Lincoln.</p>
               <p>"It is certainly he. We ought to secure him," said the first boatsteerer.</p>
               <p>"We can't cast off now, you know very well," said Lincoln. "But as soon as the order is given to cast off and go aboard, we will go to the ship and seize upon him."</p>
               <p>Having taken this resolution, the boatsteerers remained satisfied: but, just as they were entering the mouth of the harbor, they saw a light canoe push off from the ship, and beheld John standing in the stern.</p>
               <p>The crew of the Maro's boats turned their heads to look at him. He recognised them, and taking off his hat, he waved it in the air, and gave them three cheers.</p>
               <p>The boatsteerers stamped with rage, which was increased by the malicious nods and smiles of the men under their command. But what could they do.</p>
               <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC8321-00000027"/>
               <p>The ship was now in the middle of the channel, and it was necessary for them to remain in the line. They gnashed their teeth in vain. They saw John reach the shore. They saw him leap out of the canoe, and walk leisurely towards the town, until he was lost to view behind a sand-hill.</p>
               <p>The ship was now towed safely into harbor; and as soon as the crew got on board, the officers of the Maro were informed of the mysterious apparition of John on the forecastle of the other ship. The Captain of the Maro was on shore, but the chief mate instantly sprung into a boat and ordered the boat's crew to pull him on board the other vessel.</p>
               <p>He found the captain of the ship busy in mooring his vessel, and could not obtain immediate access to him. The men had carried out the ledge anchor and dropped it on the flats, and were heaving at the captain. But the mate shook hands with Mr. Gardner, and kept up a running conversation.</p>
               <p>"Mr. Jinkins, I have called to see—"</p>
               <p>"Grind coffee! run round, boys!" cried the other to his men at the captain.</p>
               <p>"If," continued Gardner—"you could tell me anything about a young fellow—"</p>
               <p>"In a minute, Mr. Gardner—come on board you, in the boat—what are you waiting for—"</p>
               <p>"He ran away from our ship—"</p>
               <p>"Run away from the Maro! Who do you speak of? None of our men I'm sure."</p>
               <p>"No—no—he was board of you a little while ago—"</p>
               <p>"On board of us. Run round, boys—"</p>
               <p>"Yes, he went off in a canoe."</p>
               <p>"Oh, you must mean—mind those captain panls, you boy—don't let the rope slip round the capstan—"</p>
               <p>"Yes, Mr. Jenkins, he was talking with Barzilla——" He probably knows all about him.</p>
               <p>"Then, the best thing that you can do, Mr. Gardner, is to ask Barzilla all about it; for I was so busy in getting the ship into port that I took very little notice of the young man. I took him for one of the men who lived on shore."</p>
               <p>Mr. Gardner found Barzilla at the captain, and as the labor was nearly over, he drew him forward to the forecastle and said—</p>
               <p>"Barzilla, do you know that we have lost a hand—a young Englishman who ran away from us a few days ago?"</p>
               <p>Barzilla looked surprised. He was for a moment puzzled, when he said—</p>
               <p>"There was a young fellow on board of us outside of the harbor—I now recollect that he came on board the other day in one of the Maro's boats. I was trying to recollect where I had seen him before."</p>
               <p>"Yes, he is one of our men!" cried the mate with indignation "and just tell me where he keeps himself, for we have hunted for him to no purpose."</p>
               <p>"Do you know where Red Mary is? You will find him at her place," returned Barzilla.</p>
               <p>The mate colored with anger: for he had heard of Red Mary and had supposed her an imaginary character. Therefore the answer of the honest youth was equivalent to saying—go look for your man among the mountains of sugar and rivers of rum discovered by Mr. Nobody.</p>
               <p>"You ought to know better than to answer me in that way," said the mate bridling his temper. "Are you a blackguard, to assist runaways in making their escape?"</p>
               <p>"I do not understand you," returned the youth. "It is said that this young fellow knows Red Mary. That was the talk at the time that he visited us in one of your boats."</p>
               <p>"Nonsense!" said the mate: "but I thought you was trifling with me. No matter—you will then just tell me what English John came here for, and what he had to say to you."</p>
               <p>"He came to pick up some information. I don't know how he came to know anything about me; but he made particular inquiries about a number of persons in Nantucket—"</p>
               <p>"In Nantucket!" exclaimed the astonished mate—"what does he know about Nantucket? He was never there in his life. Pray who did he inquire about—in Nantucket?"</p>
               <p>"A number of persons. He wanted to know whether anything had ever been heard from that Alexander Merrill who was in love with Ruth Willard—the girl that threw herself off the cliff and was drowned for love of him."</p>
               <p>"I recollect," said the mate—"that Merrill! I have seen him. He left a ship around here somewhere. He had heard that Ruth was false, and he swore he could never go home again. He sent home a letter to Ruth that broke her heart, and she drowned herself!" The mate put his hand to his forehead, scratched his head and seem much puzzled.</p>
               <p>"I'll tell you what, Barzilla," said he—"there is something very mysterious in all this; and you are sure it was our John that asked you all these things? Perhaps that, after all, it was some fellow who lives on shore, who came originally from Nantucket. Eh?"</p>
               <p>"No, sir, I know that it was the same John who came on board in your boat, a few days ago, while we lay off Punch Bowl Hill."</p>
               <p>"Then it is English John! But what should he care about the folks in Nantucket? Oh! I think I know all about it now. He was here to beg something to eat—he had heard us speak of people in Nantucket, and he wanted to pretend to you that he was one of us."</p>
               <p>"No—no—that is not it," returned Barzilla. "He did not ask me for anything. He inquired about Nantucket people as if he knew them," and when he asked about that Merrill, he looked into my eyes as if life and death depended on my answer. When I said that nobody had ever heard of him, and that he was supposed to be dead, then your man turned pale as death, and walked away from me to the forecastle, where he stood by the side of the pilot till he was ready to quit the ship.</p>
               <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC8321-00000028"/>
               <p>"This is very strange," said the mate. "But how did he come on board of you?"</p>
               <p>"He came in a small canoe, sir. An old man and a girl came with him. They did not appear to know him."</p>
               <p>After a little farther discourse with Barzilla which threw him no light upon John's conduct, the mate slowly retired, puzzled and bewildered.</p>
               <p>At night when the captain of the Maro came on board, Mr. Gardner told him all that he had heard.</p>
               <p>At first, the Captain opened his eyes with astonishment on hearing that John had ventured to make his appearance in the fleet; but when the mate went on to relate his conversation with Barzilla, the Captain maintained that it must be some other person.</p>
               <p>"It is doubtless some beach-comber who resembled our John," said the Captain—"but it cannot be John himself. Well, I shall give up the search. It is of no use to look for him any more. Let him go—He will stay on land until he gets starved out and then he will he glad to ship on board some other vessel." The Captain turned away to go down the cabin, when he caught sight of a ship coming in from sea. He ordered a few men to get into a boat, and went off to meet the vessel and get the news, hoping that she was just from home.</p>
               <p>She proved to be the Enterprise, seven months from Nantucket, but before we give her news, it is necessary to look after the youth whom we left in St. Jago.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <p>WHEN our hero arose the next morning, he found his hospitable entertainer over the charcoal fire cooking breakfast.</p>
               <p>"Hah! boy—you was a little draft last night," said the Scotchman, "do you know what you talked about?"</p>
               <p>"Very well," said the youth "I proposed to Barney that I would go with him into the interior."</p>
               <p>"Hout tout, man."</p>
               <p>Our adventurer stopped the, mouth of the Scotchman by assuring him that he was in earnest, and refusing to taste any breakfast, he sallied forth immediately. He soon found the place where the old man put up, but learnt that some unexpected event had taken him from the city. He started early in the morning for home. The youth felt disappointed, but he was not discouraged.</p>
               <p>"I am alone in the world," said he, "No one depends on me for happiness, since Ruth has broken her plighted vow—vow did I say! would I hold her in thraldom by the vow when her <emph>inclination</emph> prompts not to our union? No, I leave such contemptible conduct to those who sue for a breach of promise. Let her choose whom she may; I would not now consent to take her. It was not a mere woman that I desired. I thought her a congenial soul though all immortality—but that is vain; such an one dwells not in mortality, and this immortal spirit can never be satisfied with anything short of it. Yes, I am alone. If then there is danger in my course, who is left behind to weep for me—to grieve on my account? Not one."</p>
               <p>He repaired immediately to a spot where a carpenter by the name of Mundy worked, and with him several Englishmen and Americans. Here he inquired the way to the old man's secluded villa. They could give him but little information on the subject and could do little more then to point in the direction of his little settlement and tell him it was a hundred miles off, and that the wolf and the lion would stand in his path.</p>
               <p>When he abruptly left his companions to go on his journey, they stood still—the smooth plane ceased to slide, the broad axe rested in the cleft wood, and the hard plank ceased to murmur at the incursions of the screw-anger, the file ceased its harsh gratings, the saw no longer fore its way through the quivering board, and the hairy-armed artificers looked at the youth whose daring so much resembling that of the celestial<pb n="60-61 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8321-00000029"/> lestial messengers that fear no injury from the elements of the lower world, and amid the howling tempest, war's alarms, and the withering pestilence pursue their missions, unscathed by the arrows of death.</p>
               <p>That he would leave his dead body on the plain was regarded as a certainly which required no argument. Therefore they said nothing. They looked after the young man as he took the shortest way to the mountain, and then drawing a long breath, discoursed as people of ordinary clay always discourse upon such occasions. There can be no doubt that they magnified the danger. The old man often travelled that way alone. Why could not our adventurer do the same? These carpenters were not cowards; for from it; but in vulgar natures there is always a dread of unaccustomed adventure. They are brave as lions while they travel in their accustomed path, but the shaking of a reed in an unknown, wilderness is as terrible as a wizard with ten horns.</p>
               <p>Soon after our youth set out on his unknown way, the denizens at Santiago were visited by a rain which lasted several days the Scotchman and his friend Jocky believed that this storm would bring their late <unclear>guest</unclear> back to his old quarters. The brooks must be swollen into rivers, and the torrents from the hills and mountains must be formidable to the solitary traveller. But weeks passed on. "A lion has <unclear>eaten</unclear> him up," said they, "we shall see him no more."</p>
               <p>We must now introduce the reader into the interior.</p>
               <p>Several mud walled houses and shops surrounded by a wall, a little superior to the original defence of Rome, as few men could have jumped over it, stood on the border of a deep ravine, one hundred miles to the S. E. of Santiago. On the side of the settlements were dense woods receding as far as the eye could reach, on the Southern side was mountains; but between the settlements and the mountains were deep valleys and ravine into whose depths the sun looked about as often as a rich man looks into the house of a poor relation. At this period, the rains had washed many gulleys in the hills and the ravine at the side of the hamlet was half full of water which ran and roared in a furious manner. Flinging the broken surges upon the banks and almost threatening to undermine the foundations of the settlement.</p>
               <p>The settlement itself might be mistaken, when seen from the summit of one of the adjacent mountains, for a little old man in russet garb, with a broad-brimmed hut, squatted on a stone and abiding patiently the peltings of the storm. The howling of the fox was heard in the distance, and the scream of the iron-beaked bird pierced the thunder of the cataract, and the tall trees half enveloped by the misty curtain of the mountains bent their heads to the winds and the whole forest was agog with their harlequin dance.</p>
               <p>The lower settlement was quiet. The inhabitants appeared to be securely housed from the storm, and thick smoke issued from the chimneys of the little dwellings.</p>
               <p>At length, a living being might have been seen to emerge through an aperture in an outhouse and take her course to a neighbouring grove. She was a damsel not more than fifteen years of age, of fine proportions, and rosv face. Her eyes were black and sparkling, but her dress was<figure>
                     <head>THE SOLITARY PRISONER.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC8321-00000030"/> calculated to obscure whatever charms had fallen to her lot. She wore on her feet a pair of heavy <unclear>men's</unclear> boots which harrassed the motion of her youthful limbs. Her hat was of a kind worn by the poorer class of Spaniards. Over her shoulders was a large horse blanket, leaving exposed a handsome arm and tapering fingers which exposure had rendered somewhat brown. By the time she had reached the grove, half a dozen dogs had espied her and approached on a brisk trot. She stooped to gather sticks, the dogs began to jump up and rest upon her shoulders with their fore paws. She drove them off as a maiden generally does a disagreable youth when he attempts to kiss her. The dogs ran off in a tangent and returned. She drove them off again, and this time they took a wide circuit, they were gone so long that when the maiden set out for home, she turned her head to see what had become of them.</p>
               <p>She discovered these faithful animals at a little distance off clustered under several large trees whose mighty black arms were stretched forth to grasp the flying tempest as it passed. She then knew that some unusual event had happened, and hastened home with her bundle of sticks, and having met an elderly man at the door of her dwelling, they talked together and then set out for the spot where the dogs were congregated.</p>
               <p>The girl just reached the spot, and then she heard a piteous howl from the base of a tree under which the dogs were gathered.</p>
               <p>"Father! I see something lying on the ground, and the dogs are smelling it," said the girl.</p>
               <p>"Perhaps it is an Indian," said the father carelessly. "But we will see what it is."</p>
               <p>They two ran until they reached the spot and the object which they now beheld awakened the interest of the young girl. It was a youth of no ordinary beauty stretched upon the ground, but whether dead or alive, did not at first appear.</p>
               <p>His countenance was pale and his eyes were closed; yet the features were of a noble cast; the forehead was not only high but handsome, with a mystic expression that those mechanical creatures called phrenologists, would probably have overlooked—but the eyes of the maiden felt its spirit.</p>
               <p>She was surprised at the alacrity with which her father prepared to remove the youth from his damp resting place; for the man had generally evinced such indifference to human suffering.</p>
               <p>When the youth was raised up by the man and his daughter, he momentarily opened his eyes, looked round him and then closed them again.</p>
               <p>By degrees he seemed to feel the ground under his feet and was partly lifted along until they reached the aperture in the wall. He was now introduced into an area containing a saw mill and two humble tenements, with several hovels and other out houses. Tools and utensils of various kinds were scattered around.</p>
               <p>The youth was carried into one of the houses and laid upon a few bullock's hides covered with rough blanket. He was soon restored to consciousness; but appeared to be suffering much from exhaustion.</p>
               <p>On opening his eyes, he saw around him, several individuals—the<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC8321-00000031"/> old man, the daughter, and two married women and their husbands. An elderly Spanish woman was busied in preparing food in another part of the room. The youth fixed his eyes upon the old settler.</p>
               <p>"Do you know me, my lad?" inquired the latter.</p>
               <p>"I've got here at last," returned the youth closing this eyes and almost immediately dropping into a slumber.</p>
               <p>Every one looked at the old settler for an explanation.</p>
               <p>"I saw him in St. Jago. It is the lad I told you about who defended a poor woman against the rascally whalemen and burnt the house over their heads. I see through it all. He has come out here to see me. If he will stay with us—but we must take care of him in the mean time."</p>
               <p>By the use of nourishing food, the youth soon became sufficiently strong to sit up and give an account of his journey. That we must omit, as a walk of seven days through the wilderness, almost without food, and several hair-breadth escaped for the Indians would afford nothing new or remarkable to the reader of travels and voyages.</p>
               <p>It was several weeks before our adventurer was strong enough to assist in the labors of the old man and his sons. But the old man considered himself more than compensated for the loss of his services in the mill by the attention which he paid to his daughter.</p>
               <p>It had long been a source of regret to the old settler that he possessed not the means of giving an education to his daughter. His own education was limited and his time was too much occupied to impart even the little which he possessed to others.</p>
               <p>He soon made the discovery that the young stranger was a good scholar, and it was with pride and pleasure that he saw him devote several hours every day to the instruction of the young Rosina Pamela—for such was the high-sounding appellation that he had bestowed upon his youngest born.</p>
               <p>We have said that Rosina Pamela had bright black eyes and a rosy face. Her mother was Spanish; but her daughter spoke the English language more fluently than that of the country.</p>
               <p>She could read a little, and our youth was pleased to perceive that she was quick of apprehension.</p>
               <p>Before he enjoyed a familiar acquaintance with any other females, he thought of Ruth Willard only as one that was lost to him—a heavy weight rested on his mind—a cloud unrevealed obscured his spirits: but now comparisons between the two maidens would intrude themselves, and his darkness, became visible.</p>
               <p>He felt the difference between Ruth who had—as he once supposed—preserved her innocence and simplicity in the midst of artificial society, and Rosina who, although cut off from the civilized world, betrayed many of those little arts that disgrace the acquette of fashionable life.</p>
               <p>He was not so great a dupe as to attribute the <emph>ignorance</emph> of Rosina to native simplicity, a mistake that is frequently made by poets when they sing of <emph>artless rural maids.</emph>
               </p>
               <p>The artless lasses, when transplanted to the city, generally prove, like Esop's flies, worse suckers than the sated broad.</p>
               <p>But our adventurer could not be insensible to the charm of finding a maiden who could talk his native language, and who had heard of American and English customs, so for from the land of his birth and surrounded by foreigners.</p>
               <p>He looked with a lenient eye upon her foibles, and they seemed to diminish every day.</p>
               <p>When the rains had ceased to fall, he went abroad with her, carrying books, paper, and pencil, and he taught her to sketch the romantic scenery which environed her father's settlement.</p>
               <p>It was quite evident to every one that the maiden prized the society of our hero very highly, and it was evident to the youth that her father beheld her growing attachment without alarm.</p>
               <p>Several months had passed away, during which Rosina made great progress in her studies: and her father's eyes glistened with pleasure whenever she exhibited her proficiency by reading aloud, or producing her drawings.</p>
               <p>"Ruth, is lost to me forever—there is no such congenial spirit in the world for me, and could I do better than to wed this pretty flower of the desert——"</p>
               <p>He started! while these ideas were passing through his mind, he sat by a pine table in an inner apartment carelessly turning over the leaves of an old bible, and his eyes suddenly rested on these words, written on the inside of the cover——"</p>
               <p>"<hi rend="i"/>Barney Dougal, his book—ship Bounty. He had board of mutiny which had occurred some years before, on board the Bounty; and he had understood that one or two of the guilty survivors were still living on some obscure island of the Pacific.</p>
               <p>An attempt had been made to scratch out the word, Bounty: and if the light had not fallen upon it from the direction in which it did, he would never have discovered the faint traces of the word.</p>
               <p>He took up the book to examine the words more closely, and the name of the ship ceased to be visible.</p>
               <p>He turned the volume in every direction, but could find it no more: It was, however, traced—indelibly traced in his memory.</p>
               <p>"Then my Scotch hero in St. Jago was correct," said he; "the man is not to be trusted—and the daughter—</p>
               <p>He paused a moment, before he continued—"Circumstances made this man a mutineer, or murderer. Circumstances make other men oppressors of the widow and the orphan. Napoleon killed more men than did the mutineers of the Bounty—to give himself <emph>a name.</emph>" But the girl is not to be censured for all this'—</p>
               <p>From that moment, Rosina was a heroine of romance in the imagination of the youth. In this way, an ordinary girl, pretty but not beautiful, became invested with powerful attractions. She was the daughter of the outlaw; she spoke his native tongue in the wilds of South America.</p>
               <p>He was not, however, prepared to be her lover. He felt that he could never love more; but she seemed to be devotedly attached to him. She had neither eyes nor ears for any other individual in the settlement<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC8321-00000032"/> Their walks were long and frequent. They penetrated the woods to gether; they climbed the mountains, and explored the deep dells.</p>
               <p>Her father was every day becoming more attached to his literary guest; and no one in the settlement dared to make mouths at the acknowledged favourite of the master.</p>
               <p>One day when the youth was walking over the plain with his docile pupil, she suddenly stopped, laid her hand on his arm, and looking up, with a peculiar expression in his face, said—"Will you ever go away from this place?"</p>
               <p>The youth hesitated, and as he saw a tear starting to her eye, he answered—"Perhaps not. Why do you think I should go away?"</p>
               <p>"Because you have told me about so many fine things in your country, that I am sure if I were you, I should want to live there."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps I shall go—what then?"</p>
               <p>The maiden looked down for a moment before she replied: "I should like to go too."</p>
               <p>"What would you leave your father, your mother; all your relations."</p>
               <p>"But <emph>you</emph> would be with me," answered she, "and you know more than they do. Besides, I should be lonesome here without you."</p>
               <p>This led to an explanation, and Rosina confessed that the dearest wish of her heart was to become the bride of her preceptor.</p>
               <p>From this moment they talked of love. Whether sheltered from the sun under the branches of the grove, climbing the hills, or plunging into the deep ravines. Rosina gave vent to the admiration which she entertained for the favored youth, and overwhelmed him with praises.</p>
               <p>On his part, the lover was less communicative. He knew that what he felt for Rosina could not be termed love; but a marriage of convenience was in prospect for him. He believed that he could be as happy with her as with any other woman.</p>
               <p>While affairs were taking this direction, old Barney went to the city. The young couple enjoyed no more freedom in his absence than in his presence; for he never discouraged the intimacy of his daughter and her preceptor.</p>
               <p>On his return, the old man brought with him a stranger. This was a young fellow of the same age with our adventurer; but of a character very dissimilar.</p>
               <p>He was quite tall and slender, and stooped much in his gait. His face was thin and his eyes of a light blue. His chin was long and sharp, and he wore his dark brown hair long behind.</p>
               <p>This young man had just arrived from Valparaiso where he had followed the trade of gambling at all the sailor grog shops. He also knew several tricks of legerdemain. He could read and even write. He had thrust himself upon the old settler in St. Jago, and had talked the old man into a belief that he was a very important personage.</p>
               <p>This hopeful adventurer had discovered that <emph>blunder</emph> passed, with a certain class, for extraordinary merit, and he always continued to put his best foot foremost, if one could tell which that was.</p>
               <p>The old settler led his new guest into the house while the family were eating supper, and our youth was seated, as usual, by the side of his devoted Rosina.</p>
               <p>"Well; my boy," said the master, "I have brought a man here that can be company for you. He is a knowing one, I can tell you."</p>
               <p>Rosina and her mother looked up, as the young men saluted each other, and the eyes of Rosina continued to rest upon the stranger for several moments. Her lover observed this; but was not surprised, as it was only the second white man—with the exception of her relatives that she had ever seen.</p>
               <p>After supper, the old settler proposed that his guest should go to bed.</p>
               <p>"You must be tired after your long journey," said he politely.</p>
               <p>"You're right friend." cried the other yawning, "I did have a notion of taking one game with your bully there (pointing to our adventurer) before I turned in; but I can try him in the morning. Do <emph>you</emph> every try your luck at cards, my pretty flower of the valley?" continued he, staring with his stoney eyes at Rosina.</p>
               <p>The maiden blushed, fidgetted, and then with a gracious smile, replied—</p>
               <p>"A little, sir. Sometimes."</p>
               <p>"Oh! well—time enough for that," cried the young man, pulling off his muddy shoes. "Time enough—eh! Mr. Barney? ha! ha."</p>
               <p>The stranger then lifted up his arm, looked under it at Rosina, and gave her a sly wink. She looked up in the face of her lover and smiled, wondering that her preceptor was not as much amused and delighted as herself.</p>
               <p>On the next morning, our youth went out to walk alone, leaving Rosina behind with the stranger who had challenged her to a game of whist. Our adventurer strolled about thinking every moment to see Rosina tripping over the lawn to meet him. She did not come, and he returned to the house. He found Rosina talking with the new guest. He was showing her some curious tricks, at which she was highly delighted, and as her lover entered, she exclaimed, "Come and sit down by me, and see these things done. Cannot <emph>you</emph> do such things? I wish that you could put a pin through your leg without hurting you, as he can!"</p>
               <p>"But, Rosina, you have not looked into your book to-day. Shall we take our walk into the woods."</p>
               <p>The other youth started back, glared as if astonished at our adventurer, and then bursting into a loud horse laugh, exclaimed—</p>
               <p>"In the woods, eh! Is that the way you do it! You're a sly one, ahem! is there any chance there, eh?"</p>
               <p>Rosina looked up at her preceptor with a triumphant smile, which still more encouraged the saucy gambler who approached to steal a kiss. Her lover walked away towards the door. He heard a loud smack, and turning round, saw Rosina blushing and smiling, and heard her say—"Oh! foolish fellow! Is that the way they do in Valparaiso?"</p>
               <p>Our youth walked out the door, and was followed by his pupil.</p>
               <p>"Don't you think he is very handsome?" said Rosina, as she over took her lover.</p>
               <p>"Who? the man in the house?"</p>
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC8321-00000033"/>
               <p>"Yes! He is so noble looking!"</p>
               <p>"Noble"' cried the youth, looking at Rosina to see if she was in earnest.</p>
               <p>"Yes, and then he knows all about playing cards. He taught me two games—and, oh! such curious tricks and then he is so polite."</p>
               <p>The youth made no reply. He heard her repeat her lesson, and then proposed a long walk. She consented: but he observed ever and anon, she looked back as if expecting some one to follow and overtake them. At last she complained of fatigue, and insisted on returning to the house.</p>
               <p>When they reached the house, the new guest immediately proposed a game of all fours, with the master, our adventurer, and Rosina. They all consented and played several games. Our hero now perceived that Rosina kept her eyes on the new comer and seemed to relish all his vulgar speeches, second hand witticisms, and coarse attempts at flattery.</p>
               <p>A week passed in this manner. Rosina almost neglected her books and her pencil, and seemed happy only in the presence of the stranger. On one fine afternoon, our hero engaged her to walk out. They had been out nearly half an hour, when they unexpectedly encountered our new guest. He immediately joined them, walking by the side of the maiden. He kept up a steady conversation, our adventurer gradually fell back, and finally he left her to go on with the gambler. He returned to the house.</p>
               <p>In about an hour Rosina and her companion returned. As soon as they were alone together, Rosina said to our hero—</p>
               <p>"Why did you leave us to-day? Was that polite? I was willing you should walk with us."</p>
               <p>"Willing!" cried our hero. "But are you also willing that our private consultations shall be interrupted by this man?"</p>
               <p>"Well," said she, "I have read that when there are two rivals, they decide the question by fighting for their true love."</p>
               <p>"Rivals! I have no rival, Rosina. I never can have one; because the question must be decided by you or by nobody."</p>
               <p>"By me! If a woman is not worth fighting for, she is—"</p>
               <p>"Just like <emph>you!</emph>" cried he with energy. "Be assured that you have already proved yourself unworthy of my regard."</p>
               <p>He walked hastily away, and Rosina was soon afterwards joined by the new corner. He saw her look back at him several times, as if she thought his jealousy would be aroused, and expected him to come and fight for her. He avoided Rosina during the whole of that day. In the evening, he walked out alone to the grove and having bared his brow to the breeze, he murmured—</p>
               <p>"Am I destined never to please woman? How devoted—how enthusiastically attached to me she appeared to be! How strong were her professions of never dying constancy. But this poor trickster appears. She sees another man who can speak English, and who was born in the United States, and anon she falls in love with him. Let a man beware how he weds a woman brought up in obscurity until she has endured the test of society! But Ruth! there is the mystery—Ruth Willard!"</p>
               <p>"What of <emph>her?</emph>" cried a voice at his elbow—</p>
               <p>He turned and saw the stranger.</p>
               <p>"So, my sly one! I've found you at last. I come to ask you into the house—to make up the number for a game. But how did you ever hear of Ruth Willard?"</p>
               <p>"Let me ask you what <emph>you</emph> know of that person, sir?"</p>
               <p>"Just this and no more. I was on board a Nantucket ship just before I left Valparaiso. It was the—I forget her name—no matter; and they were telling about a pretty girl at Nantucket that jumped into the water and drowned herself—"</p>
               <p>"Pshaw! this one—the Ruth Willard of whom I spoke is married—</p>
               <p>"No—no—it was reported that she was married, and her lover who was around here somewhere heard that lie. He sent her a letter that broke her heart; for she was as true as steel—never such a girl in the world. She would have waited all her lifetime for him. But he has done it. He wrote her a savage letter, and she run mad, and drowned herself."</p>
               <p>"Great God!" cried the youth—"were this possible"—</p>
               <p>I'll tell you who told me. It was a fellow from Nantucket named Royal Starbuck.</p>
               <p>"What! he! the son of the man I boarded with! You are right! It must be true. He knew all about our courtship. Oh! that I could see him!"</p>
               <p>In pronouncing these words, our youth staggered—he grasped the trunk of a tree, and held himself up a moment. Then he sank senseless upon the ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC8321-00000034"/>
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <p>THE sun looked down upon the harbor of Valparaiso. It was midday, and the waters were calm. The pennons of the various vessels in the haven hung listless on the masts. There stood upon the hot sand of the beach a well proportioned youth, but whose face was pale and whose restless dark eyes appeared to be sunk with wearing grief and anxiety. He watched a whale boat that had just put off from a vessel in the harbour. Suddenly a foreigner dressed in the garb of a Spanish horseman approached the youth, and having bent down and looked him in the face exclaimed—</p>
               <p>"Upon my honor, it is he! Why, my lad I am as glad to see you as a if I had found a bag of ounces."</p>
               <p>"Ah! Barney, are you here?" said the other endeavoring to be cheerful.</p>
               <p>"But why did you leave us. You went off so suddenly we had not time to bid you good bye. Come, come, you must return. Rosina was crying her eyes out when I left."</p>
               <p>"Rosina! well, she has a comforter. The young fellow you carried home'—</p>
               <p>"Ah! you have not heard then! But, first, tell me whether you have seen the rascal or not in any of your travels."</p>
               <p>"Certainly not. He is at your settlement, I suppose."</p>
               <p>"Not he! He left about three days after you. He went away in the night, and carried off a little trunk containing all the money that I had earned the last six months."</p>
               <p>"What! has he robbed you!" exclaimed the youth.</p>
               <p>"Certainly he has. I was a fool for to trust him; but I do not think he will escape. I have scouts abroad in every direction, and I have come to Valparaiso to look for him. Now that Rosina has found him out, she despises him. Come, come, girls will be notional, you know. You must forget and forgive. I did not know what was going forward between Rosina and the thieving rascal, or would have made her drop him like a hot potato; for I had always intended you for my son-in-law. Assist me in finding the villian and we will go home together. You shall be married to Rosina as soon as we reach the settlement."</p>
               <p>"You must excuse me, sir. I do not wish to marry Rosina. Understand me. I loved another before I saw Rosina. She was not only a paragon of beauty—of charming womanhood, but was also incapable of deceit and double-dealing. She was the being whom destiny had designed for me. In an evil hour, I cast her from me. Some villian spread the report that she was false. I wrote her a letter, upbraiding her for treachery, and assuring her that she should never see me or hear from me again. She received the letter and in a fit of despair, she drowned herself! I have heard this story from the mouth of only one individual. I am now determined to go to the Sandwich Islands where I shall find at least one man who can tell me the whole history of her grief and suicide. As soon as I have heard all I can glean respecting her I shall"—</p>
               <p>"You shall what?" said the old settler grasping his arm, and betraying more emotion than the youth had thought him capable of. The latter replied—"There are some few things that you can neither understand nor appreciate. The vast majority of mankind, in all countries, live but to eat, drink, and sleep, and procure property. They love (as it is called) and marry with an eye to such matters. If one of them dies, the surviver take another companion. That these people do not believe in immortality, however loudly they may rave about it, is very evident. 'By their fruits, you shall know them.' Now, sir, I look for other pleasures than those which flow from the possession of money or property. That is all the answer I can make you."</p>
               <p>All this was an unknown tongue to the settler. He stood a moment looking at the young man. The whale boat arrived. The youth jumped into the boat, waved his hat at the old man, and the rowers pulled off to the ship. This ship was the Enterprise of Nantucket. She sailed for the Sandwich Islands in three days after the youth went on board of her. He shipped under a feigned name, and continued a stranger to all on board until the Enterprise reached Wooahoo.</p>
               <p>We stated at the conclusion of a former chapter that the Captain of the Maro went off, in his boat to the Enterprise immediately on her arrival.</p>
               <p>The captain of the Maro greeted the captain of the newly arrived vessel, and inquired the news from Nantucket, while his boat's crew sauntered about the deck chatting with the crew of the Enterprise. Suddenly, the boatsteerer of the Maro pointed out one individual on the forecastle, and said—"who is that? his countenance looks quite familiar."</p>
               <p>"That," replied a boatsteerer of the Enterprise, "Is a young man who came on board of us at Valparaiso. As we had lost one hand, who was killed by a whale near the line, the captain was glad to take him on board. He seems to be a person of first rate education; but he cares nothing about this world or anything that is in it."</p>
               <p>"It strikes me that I have seen him in Nantucket," said the other. "Coffin!" continued he, as he addressed a lad at short distance from him, "don't you recollect that young man?"</p>
               <p>"He reminds me very much of the fellow that was courting Ruth Willard," replied he. "It must be the same."</p>
               <p>"He has made some inquiries about Ruth Willard," said the boatsteerer of the Enterprise as if struck by a sudden recollection. "But there was nobody on board of us who knew anything about her—only that she drowned herself."</p>
               <p>The boatsteerer of the Maro then walked forward to the place where our adventurer was employed in repairing some part of the rigging.</p>
               <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC8321-00000035"/>
               <p>"How fare you, shipmate," said he. "Perhaps you don't recollect me, but I have seen you in Nantucket. Your name is Alexander Merril, I think."</p>
               <p>"Yes, you are right, and this, I believe is Gardner. You know a little of my history. I have come to Woahoo on purpose to make inquiries about a certain person."</p>
               <p>"Yes, I understand you. But where have you been so long, and why has nobody heard of you? There have been a great many strange stories circulated in Nantucket. As to the young lady, there is nothing said of her, only that she is dead. Her hat and shawl were found on the beach, and she was never seen afterwards. That ought to satisfy everybody that she drowned herself. But it was a great mistake of you to suppose her false. She never dreamed of any person but yourself. The mischief then is in the blackguard that raised the false report about her."</p>
               <p>Merrill, as we must call our hero, entered into conversation with Gardner, and very soon became fully satisfied with respect to the constancy of Ruth. Gardner was alarmed at the singular expression of his countenance, for he seemed to have taken some desperate resolution.</p>
               <p>Before the captain of the Maro left the ship, the news had been circulated through every part of the vessel that the man whom they had taken on board at Valparaiso, under an assumed name, was the renowned lover, Alexander Merrill. Every one respected his sorrows; for the history of Ruth and her lover had been regarded as a romance. Already two or three Nantucket bards had invoked the Muse in their behalf, and the Inquirer had published the lofty "rhymes."</p>
               <p>A few hours after the Maro's boat had departed, the crew of the Enterprise beheld a canoe, pushing off from under the Punch Bowl Hill. It was watched until it reached the ship. The little vessel contained a couple of natives, and a young white man, with dark eyes and rosy cheeks. As the greater part of the crew had never beer in Woahoo before, a white man from the shore was an object of some curiosity. Even the officers gathered around the youngster to make inquiries about the state of things on the Island.</p>
               <p>After he had answered all their inquiries, the youth began to question them in return.</p>
               <p>"Has anything yet been heard of one Alexander Merrill?" said he.</p>
               <p>The crew looked at each other and smiled. One of the officers drew Merrill forward, and confronted him with the inquirer.</p>
               <p>"Why do you all laugh?" said the youth from the shore, "I only inquired after Alexander Merrill. If you know what has become of him, I wish that you would tell me."</p>
               <p>Merrill looked at the inquirer attentively before he replied. "You have the advantage of me; for I certainly never saw you before. I am that Merrill about whom you inquired."</p>
               <p>The other started, turned pale, and seemed hardly able to support the tidings. He looked around upon the bystanders, and earnestly cried—</p>
               <p>"I hope that you do not deceive me. I hope that this is the identical Merrill who loved Ruth Willard."</p>
               <p>"But," said the mate of the Enterprise, "there is something very strange in all this. You make particular inquires about a man, and when he is placed before you, you do not know him. You do not seem to be a Nantucket-man. Were you ever in Nantucket."</p>
               <p>"Never; I was born in England, and my name is John Edwards."</p>
               <p>"Then I am at loss to know what interest you can take in me," said Merrill walking away gloomily.</p>
               <p>The officers and crew of the Enterprise took no farther notice of the young Englishman: but he after one earnest look at our hero, hastened into his canoe, and the two natives plied their paddles with unusual diligence until they reached the shore. The crew of the Enterprise saw John leap from the canoe, and no sooner had he struck the land, than he ran towards the town as if bearing some extraordinary message.</p>
               <p>In the meantime, the crew of the Maro, on returning to the harbour had spread the news among the fleet, that Alexander Merrill was alive, and that he had been discovered on board of the newly arrived vessel. Towards night, a number of visitors reached the Enterprise, and among the rest came the youth through whose means our hero had first learned the tale of Ruth's constancy, and her melancholy doom. Merrill now had an opportunity to satisfy himself to the full. While discoursing with Royal Starbuck, with whom he had been well acquainted in Nantucket, the rest of the crew were busy conferring with their visitors on the subject of Red Mary, the great topic of conversation in the fleet, and who seemed to inspire every new comer with singular interest and curiosity.</p>
               <p>"The Captain of the Maro said something about that girl," cried the mate of the Enterprise, who had been listening to the conversation of a group assembled near the mainmast.</p>
               <p>"He knows nothing about her," was the reply. "She never sees any white person, except there may be one—a young Englishman that ran away from the Maro, and who is said to have been secreted by her, as nobody could catch him after he deserted."</p>
               <p>"Then it must have been the lad who was on board of us to-day, and who made such particular inquiries about Alexander Merrill; though when Merrill was brought before his eyes, he did not know him!"</p>
               <p>"But this is strange!" cried one of the assembled boatsteerers. "Has Red Mary sent this Englishman to inquire for Merrill? Perhaps she has seen him! Perhaps that Red Mary is an old acquaintance that he has met in his travels on the South American coast. Let us inquire of him."</p>
               <p>"We will," said the mate. "Merrill! Merrill!" cried the mate, "step this way a moment!"</p>
               <p>Merrill broke off his conference with Royal Starbuck and walked towards the group. Every eye was fixed upon him. His countenance was, indeed, changed. It was evident that the tidings which he had received at Woahoo, had made fierce inroads upon his health. His eyes were dim, and appeared to be fixed in his head—like a living being whose heart was dead within him.</p>
               <p>"Do you know?" said the mate—"that the English lad who took so much interest in you to-day lives with the celebrated Red Mary among the mountains on the other side of the Island?"</p>
               <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC8321-00000036"/>
               <p>"I have heard something of this woman—or North West Indian girl, I believe," said our hero, "but is there really such a person, or is she an imaginary character, like a wood-nymph or a mermaid?"</p>
               <p>"Oh no, no, there is such a person," returned a boatsteerer belonging to the Ploughboy, and she is under protection of a chief who knows something about her, and who supplies her with food."</p>
               <p>"Well, it concerns not me," said Merrill walking away and rejoining his friend Starbuck.</p>
               <p>"There goes a strange man!" said the mate. "He can think of no female but Ruth Willard, and while so many mates and masters of ships would jump at the idea of exciting interest in the heart of this strange girl, he hears of his good fortune without a smile."</p>
               <p>"Ah!" said another, "they were true lovers. Did you ever read the piece in the Nantucket Inquirer headed. "The wandering Lover?"</p>
               <p>"Yes," said the mate, "Every man in the fleet must have read it."</p>
               <p>"By the by," said another, "did you ever know who this Ruth Willard was, and where she lived before she came to Nantucket?"</p>
               <p>"No," returned the mate, "She came from off the Island somewhere but whether she came from Boston or from New York, I never could learn. She was not a Nantucket girl, for she had no relations on the Island."</p>
               <p>"No, she was an orphan," said the boatsteerer from the Ploughboy—"she did not look like our Nantucket girls: besides she had different ideas from any other girl that ever I saw."</p>
               <p>"They say," continued the mate, lowering his voice, "that she and Merrill used to walk out by moonlight when everybody else was asleep, and they would go to the South shore and sit down and listen to the breakers as they came roaring in upon the beach. Nobody could talk with her except Merrill. They were made for each other; that is very certain."</p>
               <p>But now, behind the far waters, the sun gradually withdrew his beams, and the visitors retired to their boats for the purpose of returning to their vessels in the harbor. The farewell of Starbuck and Merrill was more solemn than the occasion seemed to require.</p>
               <p>"I shall see you again. Your ship will be towed into the harbor, and then we shall meet often," said Starbuck. "Remember that there are many girls in Nantucket who will rejoice to see you come back again."</p>
               <p>Alexander Merrill pressed the hand of his friend as he replied—</p>
               <p>"There are many fine girls in Nantucket. I know it well. But, you will bear me witness that I never swerved in thought from her who died for me. Had she married another, I never would have loved again, even if I had married; but as she was true—farewell, Starbuck."</p>
               <p>Starbuck dropped a few words of condolence, and then retired to his boat. In a few moments, the Enterprise was deserted by her visitors. The sun went down—the shades of the evening glowed around; and all the crew of the Enterprise, save the lonely anchor watch, descended to their berths.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <p>WHEN the day broke on the ensuing morning, the few men on the deck of the Enterprise saw that the waters were covered with a thick mist. The harbor was curtained from their view; and even after the sun rose, nothing was visible but the dark top of Punch Bowl Hill, down whose sides rolled the watery fleece.</p>
               <p>At length the lonely watchers, as they sluggishly paced the deck, became sensible that some one was approaching the ship. The stroke of paddles was heard; and yet so still was the morning, that they knew the boat must be at a great distance. One of the watch who had been commissioned to call the first mate in the morning, then crept down the companion-way and summoned that officer to the deck. Several minutes elapsed before he made his appearance. By the time he had reached the deck, the thick fog had began to seatter and to roll aside its huge volumes beneath the rays of the ascending sun.</p>
               <p>"Do you say that somebody is coming?" inquired the mate, of the man who had waked him.</p>
               <p>But scarcely had he spoken before a huge mass of vapor rose slowly from the waters on the starboard beam and disclosed, at the distance of a quarter of a mile, a large double canoe, manned by some forty or fifty natives, and moving towards the ship. The mate started at the suddenness of this apparition. He had not supposed that the visitors were so near. There was a something peculiar in the appearance of this large canoe. It had a royal look; and the boatmen appeared to move with that cautious deliberation, which denoted the presence of a person of consequence.</p>
               <p>The canoe contiued to approach, occasionally obscured by a tongue of mist that stretched across the prow; but, very soon, the fog was all gone, and the approaching vessel was distinctly visible. Then the mate beheld a majestic and corpulent chief standing up in the stern, and by his side was a beautiful female dressed in the garb of an American lady, who was also standing. This seemed to him so much like a dream that he looked round at his companions to convince himself that he was awake. In the next moment, the idea shot through his mind that the female could be no other than the renowned Red Mary!</p>
               <p>The watch instantly conceived the same idea.</p>
               <p>The mate ran down the cabin and summoned the Captain who hastened<pb n="76-77 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8321-00000037"/> ened on deck, at the same time that the crew came pouring from the steerage half dead with curiosity to see the heroine of their waking dreams.</p>
               <p>The canoe was now very near the ship. The Captain and his officers prepared to receive their visitors, while the crew stood in the waist and looked at the chief and his charge with wonder and awe.</p>
               <p>But that young female was now the object of the closest scrutiny. She was beautiful, and her form was perfect in feminine symmetry; but, the lookers-on knew not why, they felt singularly affected by the expression of that countenance. Tears were even seen to roll down the cheeks of the hardy seamen. There was on that radiant and youthful countenance a mysterious expression of patient and enduring grief mingled with extraordinary resolution, that seemed to etherealize her nature, and to convey the idea of a suffering angel instead of a mere sorrowing mortal. But when she had ascended the deck of the Enterprise when the Captain had assisted her on board and she stood confronting the seamen—Oh! then the earnest and <unclear>piercing</unclear> gaze which that <unclear>frail</unclear> and gentle being bestowed upon the <unclear>crew</unclear> and the sweet and melancholy tone in which she pronounced the <unclear>name</unclear> of Alexander Merrill thrilled through every heart.</p>
               <p>English John followed the chief to the deck, and placed himself by the side of the fair visitor.</p>
               <p>"It is Red Mary!" cried the mate, as he told the crew to summon Alexander Merrill to the quarter deck.</p>
               <p>"Will you not walk down into the cabin?" said the Captain of the Enterprise to his visitors, "Merrill can come there to see you."</p>
               <p>The Maiden shook her head, apparently unable to make another reply; and when a couple of men came up out the steerage followed by Alexander Merrill.</p>
               <p>The fair stranger turned pale and trembled in every limb. She stood a moment as if transfixed to the spot. Her eyes wandered over the form of our hero as he approached, and the captain looked in her face and now he recognized the features of <emph>Ruth Willard</emph> whom he had once seen in Nantucket.</p>
               <p>Merrill did not so soon perceive who stood before him, nor was it strange, for he had been assured of her death and could not have been prepared to meet with her alive and well. It was not till she spoke that he looked at her face. The voice of the maiden aroused him from his melancholy stupor and he gazed wildly into her eyes.</p>
               <p>"Alexander.!" cried she "Oh! Alexander!" and would have fallen to the deck had not English John caught her in his arms.</p>
               <p>Merrill sprang forward with a loud cry of astonishment and joy, and having seized the fainting girl and pressed her to his heart, while English John turned to the Captain and mate and replied to their eager inquiries.</p>
               <p>Ruth Willard soon revived and clinging to Alexander as if fearful that he should be again separated from her, she gazed into his eyes to satisfy herself that it was not all a dream.</p>
               <p>While the two lovers draw aside for the purpose of mutual explanations<figure>
                     <head>THE LAST HOPE!</head>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC8321-00000038"/> tions, which were indeed, required by the bewildered and enraptured Merrill, we will hear what English John says to the officers of the Enterprise.</p>
               <p>As soon as John was sufficiently composed to speak he acknowledged that he and Ruth Willard were brother and sister. They were born in England. Their father was a gentleman of fortune who had suffered a total loss of property through the treachery of a friend in whom he had confided. He soon afterwards died.</p>
               <p>As his wife was also dead, John and Ruth were left orphans at a tender age. John was bound apprentice to an English sea-captain; while Ruth came to the United States in search of an aunt who died a few weeks before her arrival.</p>
               <p>Poor Ruth was therefore under the necessity of using her needle in order to obtain a livelihood, but this did not prevent her from improving her mind.</p>
               <p>She read and studied much, and when Merrill found her at Nantucket, she was esteemed a young lady of great natural endowments and very respectable acquirements.</p>
               <p>The history of Merrill had somewhat resembled her own. He too was the child of misfortune. We need say nothing of the strength of their mutual attachment. That is sufficiently proved already.</p>
               <p>When Ruth received the fatal letter from her lover, she immediately resolved to go to him, since he had declared he should not come to her.</p>
               <p>In order to do this, she must ship on board a vessel as cabin-boy. To avoid suspicion, she left some parts of her dress on the cliff overhanging the sea. This gave rise to the story that she was drowned.</p>
               <p>She attired herself like a sailor, and the Captain to whom she offered herself was so delighted with the <emph>beautiful boy</emph> that he eagerly embraced the opportunity to engage him in the proposed capacity. The ship went to the Sandwich Islands.</p>
               <p>Ruth soon perceived that this was the great depot for whalemen, and here she determined to wait until her lover should come. She at first hoped to find him on the Island, or in the fleet.</p>
               <p>But having been disappointed in this, she went to the house of the head chief, and confided to him her secret, preferring to trust the Indian rather than the white man.</p>
               <p>Her confidence was not misplaced. He guarded her secret with the utmost care, and never bored her with <emph>prudent advice.</emph>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time, John came to the Island in the Royal George. The brother and sister accidently encountered each other. He then deserted from the ship and spent some weeks with his sister at her subter rancan home.</p>
               <p>Finally, he took a cruise to Japan in the Maro, and left her when he returned to Woahoo. Since then he had been with his sister, using the utmost diligence to discover when Allexander Merrill should arrive at the Island.</p>
               <p>He had at length discovered him on board the Enterprise, and hastened to communicate the intelligence to the chief and to his sister who lived at some distance from the town. As soon as possible they came on board the Enterprise.</p>
               <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC8321-00000039"/>
               <p>Long was the interview between Ruth and Alexander. They were, indeed, a fine looking couple; young, noble, and beautiful, while their animated features and the deep feeling betrayed by their looks and gestured drew upon them the observations of all on board as they stood apart holding intercourse at once sweet and said; for what had not they suffered! what heart breaking accounts had they not a relate to each others and the chief and English John stood patiently waiting by the side of the Captain.</p>
               <p>A close observer—and there are many such among the Temperance people—might have detected in the countenance of the Captain, as he glanced towards Alexander and Ruth an expression that could hardly be denominated friendly, a disturbed and dissatisfied look which seemed to stay "that a common sailor" like Alexander had no right to the prize which had so unexpectedly presented itself on board <emph>his</emph> ship. He was Captain, and his claims were paramount, and what right had the young seaman to the smiles of Ruth Willard, the lovely English girl?</p>
               <p>It was indeed, a rare thing to find a white woman in that part of the Creation, and much less, a young, beautiful and refined one. So, the selfishness, the baseness of man was exhibited in the looks and glances of the Captain of the Enterprise. Although the latter possessed not one quality that would have recommended him to Ruth, yet he thought that from the mere fact of his being Captain, he had the best right to her. It must be remembered that he had never seen her before. Ruth had kept herself so much secluded that even the existence of such a person as "Red Mary" was doubted by many persons who came to the Island.</p>
               <p>When Ruth Willard, at length, made a sign to the chief to return to the shore, and Alexander walked towards the gangway with his loved one, the Captain came up to them in a blustering manner and said to the Chief—"You don't calculate to carry off my man, I take it?" Then turning to Alexander, he said—"Go to your duty, you sir!"</p>
               <p>Alexander then reminded the Captain that when he shipped at Valparaiso it was with the understanding that he might have his discharge whenever he chose to call for it.</p>
               <p>"Don't answer <emph>me!</emph>" cried the important commander of the Enterprise. "I'll let you know whose jurisdiction you are under, with a rope's end, you mutinous rascal!"</p>
               <p>Ruth started with astonishment and looked at the Captain, who perceived that he was not helping his cause with <emph>her,</emph> and therefore continued—"Miss Willard you must, know that we're obliged to have rules aboard of a vessel, and besides you don't know this man as well as I do: he is very hard to manage; and let me tell you, young lady, you can do much better than marrying <emph>him</emph>—Don't you see he is only a common, sailor—there's mates of ships—yes and masters of ships to that would show themselves friendly to you if you'd let 'em. So you'd better drop this fellow quickly, and look high."</p>
               <p>Ruth could scarcely believe that a man capable of commanding a ship was so great a fool, so mean a fellow, as to address her in such strains. She made no reply but by a look of astonishment at the Captrain tain, and then quickly descended into the canoe—but not until Alexander had whispered something in her ear.</p>
               <p>To his astonishment, Alexander saw the Captain about to follow the chief into the canoe, doubtless for the purpose of trying his hand at seducing Ruth when they should get to the chief's dwelling place! He pretended not to observe this, and going forward, over the bows, he let himself down into the water by the cable; and as the great canoe came by the prow, he slid under the stern, and holding on by the vessel, reached the shore as soon as the others.</p>
               <p>He did not immediately show himself, however; but kept out of sight till he should discover the object of the Captain in going on shore in the same canoe with Ruth Willard.</p>
               <p>When the canoe came to land the Chief and Ruth got out, with all who were in the canoe, Alexander saw that the Captain kept close to the side of Ruth, who clung closely to the Chief and evidently wished to avoid all intercourse with the former. At length the Captain tried to snatch the hand of Ruth, and quite a struggle ensued between them. While that was going on Alexander came hastily up, and just as the Captain succeeded in getting hold of Ruth's hand, he dealt him a blow under the ear which laid him sprawling on the strand. This was witnessed by several Captains and officers who were loitering on the shore and who come running to the assistance of the discomfitted Captain. Several natives also came up who took the side of Merril, and during the skirmish the Chief made of with Ruth and escaped.</p>
               <p>The fight was quite brief as the natives surrounded the whites in great numbers, and the enemies of Alexander were fain to beat a hasty retreat.</p>
               <p>The youth then looked about him, and saw a native beckoning to him from the corner of one of the native houses. He ran thither and the Kenacker made motions for Alexander to follow him. The youth did so, and passing through the town came to a hill against the side of which rested a large but flat him stone. This the guide removed with ease and disclosed the mouth of a cave. Both entered and found a well furnished room, with many mats on the floor and upon a pile of which was seated Ruth Willard entirely alone. Having pointed towards Ruth with a peculiar smile, the native withdrew and left the enamored pair entirely alone.</p>
               <p>"At length," said Alexander, pressing her to his heart, "I may enjoy your conversation without interruption. But what must not your sufferings have been since we parted at Nantucket!"</p>
               <p>"This hour repays me for all," cried Ruth gazing lovingly into the bold, dark eyes of her lover.</p>
               <p>One long embrace, one earnest kiss, and they were interrupted by the entrance of the Chief under whose protection Ruth had so long been. Alexander arose respectfully to salute the Chief, while he observed that Ruth looked at him with a singular expression. In a few moments the Chief retired. As he went out Ruth shook her head.</p>
               <p>"What mean you?" said the youth.</p>
               <p>"Something is wrong," returned Ruth; "I know these people, or, at<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC8321-00000040"/> least, the Chief better than you do. There's a sinister look about him that I do not like. His eyes avoided mine. Something has gone wrong—"</p>
               <p>"Then we had better leave this place as soon as possible," cried Alexander springing to his feet. "If there is treachery, no time should be lost."</p>
               <p>Even while he spoke, a dozen natives entered the apartment, and while some of these endeavoured to keep back Alexander, two stout savages seized upon the girl.</p>
               <p>With the utmost distress depicted on her countenance, Ruth Willard held out her hands to her lover and cried, "Death before separation."</p>
               <p>Alexander struggled desperately with the natives. He knocked three of them down and would eventually have mastered them all had not the false hearted Chief glided in through a secret passage way and struck Alexander on the head with a massive club. As the blow came from behind, and Alexander had not even perceived the entrance of the Chief, it was impossible to guard against the blow. Alexander was stretched senseless upon the ground, and when he recovered his recollection, he found himself in a sort of fort near the beach, where runaway sailors and other offenders were confined. At first, he could remember nothing; but on looking about him and discovering several sailors in irons lying upon a pile of old mats, he gradually recovered his recollection.</p>
               <p>His first thoughts was of Ruth who was, doubtless, in the hands of his and her enemies, but who were they, and why had the chief in whom Ruth had trusted and who until now had treated her with great kindness—why had <emph>he</emph> turned traitor and delivered her over to her foes.</p>
               <p>While puzzling his brain to discover the meaning of this, one of the seamen drew close to him and said, "Was it you who was found with the girl they call Red Mary?"</p>
               <p>"I am the same one," replied Alexander, "why do you ask? Do you know anything about her or what has become of her?"</p>
               <p>"Yes," was the reply, "the Captain of the Enterprise has got hold of the gal. I saw him with the old chief that she used to live with, and a missionary was with them, and the natives told me that an old woman and two Kenackers had carried off the gal to a house at the foot of the mountains where they get sandal wood, and where the Captain can see her."</p>
               <p>"Then I will go there—you will direct me, will you not?</p>
               <p>The man looked at him surprised, "How can you go there?" inquired the sailor—"Don't you see that you are a prisoner, and that as soon as they perceive you have come to your senses they will put handcuffs on you, just like us. You say that you are a deserter from the Enterprise and they'll serve you as they serve us."</p>
               <p>"Ay, ay," said Alexander, "then I must go before they put me in irons." and he began to look about him for some mode of egress. He saw a small square window behind him, some distance from the floor, and secured by iron bars, he begged two of the men to let him climb on their shoulders, to which they readily agreed. Standing erect upon the shoulders of the men he could reach the iron bars, which he worked vigorously and to the surprise of the manacled seamen, they very soon became loose and was finally wrenched out entirely away by the determined youth.</p>
               <p>In another moment, Alexander had sprung up to the aperture and darted through it. On the other side was a low mud wall upon which a native sentinel was marching to and fro with a musket upon his shoulder. Alexander dropped upon the ground, which was some ten feet below the window, and alighting upon a muddy spot escaped all injury, but the native sentinel looked hard at him, and was about to give the alarm, when Alexander made a motion to him that he could give him money. The native looked anxiously about him in every direction, and seeing none of his superiors at hand, nodded acquiescence. Alexander had no money with him: therefore he walked deliberately up to the sentinel, wrenched the musket from his hand, leaped from the wall into the path outside and made the best of his way to the mountain.</p>
               <p>He found the musket was loaded and resolved to use it, if Ruth Willard could not be otherwise rescued from her capturers.</p>
               <p>As he ran, he heard the noise of pursuers; but they were far behind him, he had very little fear of them—therefore he went, with a moderate pace, towards the spot indicated by the prisoners of the fort.</p>
               <p>As he approached the mountains, the long shadows denoted the approach of evening. He met several natives carrying sandal wood on their shoulders who surveyed him closely and seemed particularly interested in the musket which he carried. At length one emaciated white man crossed his path.</p>
               <p>He paused, with a heavy stick of sandal wood on his shoulders and addressed our hero.</p>
               <p>"Halloo, shipmate," said he, "what ship have you left? you'l find it hard work here, my good fellow and very little to eat."</p>
               <p>"I don't intend to stop long," returned Alexander, "but can you tell me of a house out here where the captains of the whalemen visit?"</p>
               <p>"No—stop—yes—I recollect there was a girl brought down yonder, the other side of those bananas that you see growing, who was put in some house, and I saw the Captain with the missionary and some natives go there afterwards; if that can be what you mean."</p>
               <p>"Exactly." cried Alexander, "just direct me if you please."</p>
               <p>The man pointed out the place where the house stood, and Alexander stole cautiously over the grass and through the field of bananas, till he saw on the side of a rock a large house built in the usual style, with poles, thatched and in some places plastered with mud.</p>
               <p>That, then, was the house that contained Ruth Willard! All was quiet as he crept towards the building, inasmuch that he doubted her presence. He forgot that her persecutors imagined him to be secure in the fort, if, indeed, the blow from the chief had not entirely disabled him.</p>
               <p>Alexander reached one end of the house; it contained a window over-looking a thick tuft of bushes. Creeping through these bushes, he looked in at the window, and there he beheld a sight which shocked him—an elderly man chained, almost overgrown with hair, and covered with<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC8321-00000041"/> filthy garments. The poor man appeared almost stupefied, and seemed, by appearances, to have inhabited that den for years. What was singular the narrow apartment in which this man was confined was walled with large stones of a loose texture like those used on the Spanish Main. Outside, the house was an ordinary native building. The question arose in the mind of the youth whether Ruth was confined in the same manner, within stone walls. He then examined the priming of his musket and passed around to the front of the building. The door was pushed open easily. He entered and saw an old woman also seated upon a mat. She looked at the youth with the fierceness of a wild cat, and started up to bar his entrance. He pretended not observe her unwillingness for him to enter, and bowed very politely with the usual salutation of "Aroohah."</p>
               <p>She then pointed to the door and bade him depart, he pushed the woman aside and entered the room. She became furious and made a great noise, but evidently without hope of receiving assistance, the employers were too far off. Alexander struck against the side of the apartment till he found a door which yielded to his touch—"Ruth! Ruth!" cried he aloud, and at that instant, he heard some one stir within.</p>
               <p>"Can it be? who calls?" exclaimed some one as he entered a little dark apartment, "It is I, Ruth, where are you?"</p>
               <p>"Oh! my God I saw you hunted down—killed—and the missionary told me that now I must accept of the Captain's protection as you were in an another world.</p>
               <p>"Liar!" cried Alexander, dashing a hole through the side of the house to let in the light—He will find that the dead man will—but how, how is this? Handcuffs on you!" Tied to a post—wretches! they will pay dearly for this."</p>
               <p>In an instant, Alexander had freed Ruth from her bonds, and led her out of the house. As they emerged from the building, they saw the old woman flying over the plain, doubtless to apprise the missionary or the chief of what had occured.</p>
               <p>They saw the necessity of escaping from that spot as fast as possible; but whither could they go? The chief and the missionary—not to mention the Captain—could put natives on the scent who would hunt them out of the most secret recesses they could find.</p>
               <p>"We will try to escape from the Island: said Alexander, as he led Ruth over the plain towards the town of Honolula. It was now dusk, and the darkness would favor their escape.</p>
               <p>On they hurried towards the town, Ruth briefly related to Alexander the events which had occured during their separation. The Captain of the Enterprise together with the missionary and the false chief had conveyed her to that house near the mountains, where they endeavored to convince her that she ought not to throw herself away upon a common sailor like Alexander, but should give her hand and heart to the Captain. The absurdity of such proceedings was sufficiently apparent to the poor girl and she resisted all their arguments. They then secured her person in a dark room and left her to the care of an old native woman, a creature of their own.</p>
               <p>Alexander begged to know who was the aged prisoner enclosed in a living tomb, in the same house where she was immured. Ruth replied that she did not know any such person was in that house, though she had several times heard of an old man who was kept a close prisoner somewhere, through the influence of the missionary, who charged him with insanity; but she had never heard of any proofs of such disorder except the fact that he undertook to preach a different doctrine from that of the Puritan missionaries, should be regarded as a proof of insanity. His name and country were kept a profound secret. He was only known among the natives as "The man of the Devil," this name they had probably learned from the missionaries. But what chiefly concerned Ruth was the unaccountable absence of her brother. "English John," who had not been seen since her landing with the chief. That he had been spirited away and confined in some dungeon by her persecutors appeared very probable. They now approached the shore and as they did so, Ruth recognised an old native who had always evinced the greatest regard for her. To him she called. He came up and uttered an exclamation of surprise when he saw her. She bade him be silent, but told him her straight,—that she must get away from the island under cover of night, as her absence from her prison was doubtless known already to her capturers.</p>
               <p>Even as they talked, the tramp of men was heard, and the loud voice of the false chief. The friendly native lost no time in ushering Ruth and Alexander into a hut close by, and stood guard at the door till the pursuers had passed. From a loop hole, Alexander thought he distinguished the Captain of the Enterprise among them. In a moment, he levelled his musket, but restrained himself. The charge might stand him in stead when more needed.</p>
               <p>As soon as the pursuers were gone, the native represented to Alexander and Ruth that hunters would be on their track before morning; but he also stated that a friend of his was going in a canoe with two others to another island, a few miles distant, at the first streak of dawn.</p>
               <p>This satisfied them well. Ruth was profuse of thanks to their deliver, while Alexander, not knowing the man; eyed him closely. He knew that a reward would be offered for their capture, and that natives were fond of dollars. The event proved that Ruth was correct and that the youth's suspicions were unjust. The native kept them safe till daylight when he led them to a secret part of the beach and put them on board a small canoe in which were five natives hound to a neighbouring island.</p>
               <p>Alexander lifted Ruth into the boat, and was about pushing off, when several men started up from behind an old wreck and approached them with pistols. They were hailed and ordered to stop by the head chief of the island. At the same time, the officers and their aids presented their pistols.</p>
               <p>Alexander saw that nothing was left but a desperate defence. Calling upon the natives in the boat to aid him, he rushed upon the assailants and discharged his musket. One of the officers fell, and the rest, took to their heels, among them the missionary, but not till three or four, pistols<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC8321-00000042"/> tols was discharged at Alexander. He escaped unhurt, but a cry from the water convinced him that Ruth had been wounded. A ball had pierced her heart, and she fell into the shallow water at the end of the canoe. With a cry of agony, Alexander rushed to the spot, and dragging the lifeless body up high on the shore, endeavoured to recover Ruth from what he, at first, supposed to be a swoon. Too soon was he convinced that her eyes would never open more—that a hall had pierced her heart, and that her noble spirit had flown to Him who gave it.</p>
               <p>With a deep vow of vengeance, he sank upon the beach by the side of the dead girl, and tore his hair in rage and agony.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
               <p>THREE months after the above events, a cluster of men were gathered on the high bluff, near the harbour of Woahu, known as Punch Bowl Hill. The greater part of them was seamen, but there was also several natives among whom was a couple of chiefs.</p>
               <p>"Well," said one of the former, "you big double canoe comes in pretty quick. I guess they've seen something of the Arrow on their way from Hawai."</p>
               <p>"D—n the bit!" said an old tar hoisting up his trousers by his waistbands. "She is not on the coast now."</p>
               <p>"Don't be so sure," cried another, "what do you spose these Kenackers and the old chief there are arter."</p>
               <p>"Don't know, do you?"</p>
               <p>"Well, I'll tell you, then. They expects a descent from the Flying Arrow upon this ere d—d hole, every hour. Merrill, the pirate, you know, who commands the Arrow, is sworn to take revenge on the chiefs and the missionaries of Woahu."</p>
               <p>"Yes, and many a canoe has he sunk already, and got all the money and fruit which they had on board, and were taking from one island to another."</p>
               <p>"Ah, well—we'll have a States' vessel down here arter him."</p>
               <p>"Yes—you may say that. Mad Jack is on the coast of Chili now, and when he hears of this Flying Arrow he'll be down upon her in less time than you can say 'Jack Robinson.' But its a hard case, arter all, the way that young fellow was sarved."</p>
               <p>"Is it? Well I've hearn something about it," was the reply of the old Jack, "there was a petticoat in the case, I believe. They generally makes all the mischief."</p>
               <p>"Yes, Jack—a woman or a priest is generally at the bottom of all mischief."</p>
               <p>"As I knows to my sorrow. But I've heard the gal was shot by the captain of a whaleship."</p>
               <p>"I dare say he shot her, or it may have been one of the chief's men, or the chief himself. At any rate, it was a hansume gal, they say, who had a mind, and knowd how to 'spress it too."</p>
               <p>"Well, what cum on'em all then?"</p>
               <p>"The young fellow, you mean? Oh! he was brought up all standing when he seed the gal laying there a dead corpse before his eyes, and her beautiful yaller hair a streaming on the sand, and they took him easy enough, and dragged him away from the corpse, and put him in the fort in double irons."</p>
               <p>"My eyes, but that's hard! To have one's own doxy shot down before your eyes, and be took up and put in prison for it too."</p>
               <p>"But he didn't stay there long. He got the irons off of himself and off of all the other chaps that was confined in the fort, and then they cut and run."</p>
               <p>"What next?"</p>
               <p>"The next was one of the daringest things that you ever heard of. There was a clipper schooner here, of Baltimore build, called the Flying Arrow. What does these chaps do—for it was in the night—but goes right aboard of her, and ties her crew hand and foot, for the captain and mate was ashore with the <hi rend="i"/>Wyheenas, and they gets her under way and runs off with the vessel. She had small arms and powder on board, with two or three loud talkers on swivels, and away they goes out to sea."</p>
               <p>"How soon did her captain find it out?"</p>
               <p>"Why, it was a dark night, and he left his gal just afore daylight, and come down to the beach, and hailed his schooner, and told 'em to send a boat. He bawled till he was hoarse, but nobody answered his hail. Cause why? There wan't nobody there."</p>
               <p>"Ha! ha! You're right."</p>
               <p>"To be sure I am. When daylight come, he found that out for himself."</p>
               <p>"And looked d—d cheap when he see his vessel was nt there."</p>
               <p>"Cheap as a spoiled codfish"——</p>
               <p>"Or a bank-note without no writing on it"——"</p>
               <p>"Yes, or a teapot without a spout or a handle"——</p>
               <p>"Or a soger's coat without sleeves."</p>
               <p>"Well, he looked sheepish enough, I take it."—</p>
               <p>"Oh! I should like to have borrowed his face to have gone to a funeral just about that time."</p>
               <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC8321-00000043"/>
               <p>"Well, Jack, it seems that the captain and mate never got their vessel again. Cause why? The young fellow turned pirate, in revenge for losing his gal in that onscroopulous kind of a manner."</p>
               <p>"And he had a few to join him that come with him out of the old fort; but not enough, I should think."</p>
               <p>"He picked up a good gang more—fellows that were adrift on the islands, and went off to him in canoes, whenever he appeared in sight with the black flag at his fore. He picked up a lieutenant for his craft—a devil of a fellow—that he found floating on a raft at sea."</p>
               <p>"How came he there?"</p>
               <p>"He belonged to a Nor West trader, and stuck up for his rights like a man. But the crew all joined with the captain and officers, and they seized him up and gave him a devil of a flogging. He said nothing, and pretended to be very humble after his flogging. But when the brig drew near this port, he goes to work and kills every living soul on board of her"——</p>
               <p>"How could he do it?"</p>
               <p>"He put laudanum in the tea which went down the cabin, and that stupified the captain and mates, and as for the crew he took 'em unawares while they were asleep on deck and below."</p>
               <p>"But the man at the helm?"</p>
               <p>"He was a big nigger, and the mutineer had hard work with him, but at last he got the darkey overboard."</p>
               <p>"He was a bold fellow, but what became of the vessel after that?"</p>
               <p>"Why, the brig was just off this island, a few miles. So he made a raft for himself, and scuttled the vessel. He meant to drift down to the island and report that he came from a whaleman that was stove by a whale and sunk, like the old Essex, of Nantucket, you know."</p>
               <p>"A good story, too! Well I glory in his spunk. And how did he get aboard the pirate?"</p>
               <p>"The Flying Arrow happened to overhaul him on the raft, and took on board. He had no occasion to tell the cock-and-a-bull story about being stove by a whale there, and so he just gives them the true history of the case."</p>
               <p>"And how did you hear about it?"</p>
               <p>"From Davis and Goodenough, two follows that the pirates' put on shore at Owhyhee, for cowardice I s'pose, though they pretend it was for mutiny. They tell about the Flying Arrow, and everything that was happening on board of her."</p>
               <p>While they spoke, these two men saw a white speck on the horizon. The people on the hill seemed to hail its appearance with pleasure and doubtless believed it to be another whaleship. The natives liked to see it because it spoke of increased traffic, and the whites because they could hear the news.</p>
               <p>The breeze freshened, and the vessel was soon made out to be a three masted craft.</p>
               <p>"Another whaleship!" cried a seaman.</p>
               <p>"Yes—now from the States?" cried another!</p>
               <p>"How she walks!"</p>
               <p>"Like a duck on the water!"</p>
               <p>At this moment two of the natives began to point off in a direction a little to the windward of the ship, and to talk loud and earnestly together.</p>
               <p>The sailors were not slow to perceive this movement on the part of the natives, and upon looking carefully they were, at length, able to discover a speck of white in another quarter.</p>
               <p>The natives cried out that it was the pirate vessel, speaking rapidly in their own tongue, and insisting that she was in pursuit of the ship. The latter was now in plain sight. Her hull was distinctly visible. She had evidently descried the other vessel, had spread all her canvass and was making all speed for the harbour.</p>
               <p>"Out goes her fore-top-mast studding sail!" cried a sailor.</p>
               <p>"Her royals are set—now she hoists her fly-jib! all they can stretch on her? Them spars wont hold on much longer with this breeze it he don't take in sail."</p>
               <p>"But see how the tother one looms up! Lord! is'nt she walking!" cried a seaman, holding up his hands in admiration at the wonderful speed of the smaller vessel.</p>
               <p>"It is the Arrow, by all that is holy!" exclaimed an old resident of the island, who was more than suspected of supplying the pirate with fresh provisions.</p>
               <p>"The Flying Arrow!" was passed from mouth to mouth, and the greatest excitement prevailed.</p>
               <p>It was evident that the ships in the harbor had taken the alarm as the crews were seen climbing the rigging and gazing sea ward.</p>
               <p>Then the old fort. As the two masts of the schooner became distinctly visible, and the distress of the whaleship in the offing was shown by the reckless display of canvas at a time when reefed topsails were demanded by ordinary prudence, the natives flew to the fort.</p>
               <p>Now the ship is in full view. Her boats are seen, and no doubt exists that she is a whaleman.</p>
               <p>She is light—just from home. The seamen on board the various vessels in the harbor prepare to get their news and letters from home.</p>
               <p>But the schooner, also, has become more distinctly visible. She is following the ship—in her wake—and gaining rapidly on her. Still no one believed that the ship was in danger, as she was too near the harbor.</p>
               <p>She would soon be able to let slip her anchor in the outer harbor, and then she would be under the protection, not of the fort to be sure, but of all the seamen and natives who could arm and go out in boats and canoes to assist the new comer against the pirate.</p>
               <p>"The Arrow is too far astern—can't overhaul her," said one of the men on Punch Bowl Hill.</p>
               <p>Just then a piece of bunting appeared at the mast-head of the whale ship.</p>
               <p>"To a pilot! She signed for a pilot!" cried the seamen in a breath.</p>
               <p>"Good God! She don' think herself safe in the outer harbour! She expects to be attacked <emph>there.</emph>"</p>
               <pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC8321-00000044"/>
               <p>"D—n! the pirate would'nt dare to attack her there."</p>
               <p>"But why not? You see that nobody is on the move to assist her All the Captains in harbour are as mum as mice."</p>
               <p>"It's too late to help her now," cried another. "Before the boat could get outside, the Arrow would be through with her business. Lord! how he walks! Hah! what's that?"</p>
               <p>From the bows of the Flying Arrow came a flash, a puff of smoke, and then a detonation, which was followed by a shriek faintly heard by the men on the hill, who looked at each other in amazed silence. The hall had evidently taken effect on board the whaleman. Somebody was wounded. But the ship kept on her way, though her bending spart threatened every moment to snap off under the powerful press a canvass.</p>
               <p>Just as the main-top-mast of the whaleman snapped with a noise like a cannon, and was distinctly heard by the spectators on the hill, as it fell over the side, the schooner rounded to and fired several cannon at the chase. The latter was now so near that the people on the hill could plainly see the distress and confusion on the deck of the whaleman—men running backwards and forwards and trying to clear the boat for the purpose of escaping to the shore and leaving the ship to her fate.</p>
               <p>Gun after gun was now fired by the schooner, and the shrieks of the wounded went up from the deck of the whaleman.</p>
               <p>To add to the horror of the scene, the large black banner of the pirate now rose to the mizen peak of the Flying Arrow, displaying in its centre the terrible death head and narrow bones, the sight of which strikes a chill to the hearts of the peaceful merchantmen.</p>
               <p>The fort, near the the beach, now began firing its sluggish guns with the vain intent of intimidating the pirates.</p>
               <p>The schooner came on like a shark roaring through the waves, eager for his prey—The disabled whaleman moved very slowly along the deep, and the crew labored to get out their boats which was no easy matter, as they had been all secured but one for the passage of Cape Horn".</p>
               <p>Into that one boat, they finally rushed, taking their wounded with them. They put off from the ship which was now left to drift upon the beach or wherever the winds and waves might convey her.</p>
               <p>When the crew of the ship got into the boat, they were about two miles from the shore, and the pirate schooner not more than a quarter of a mile from the ship. Slender hope for the crowd in the whale boat! But they imagined that the pirate would be satisfied if the ship was given up to him for plunder.</p>
               <p>They reckoned without their hoast.—He did, indeed, seek for booty, but <emph>vengeance</emph> was his main object. The murder of <emph>Ruth Willard</emph> he was sworn to revenge, not only upon these who killed her, but upon the officers and commanders of all whaling vessels.</p>
               <p>The Flying Arrow, therefore, tarried not at the ship, but continued right on in chase of the whale boat. Had there been a few pieces of cannon on the hill, the boat would have been finely protected, but there was not even a musket among all the spectators, who had now increased to hundreds, upon Punch Bowl Hill. On came the terrible schooner with her black banner waving over her stern; and loud were the cries for aid—for help—for mercy—from the crowd in the whale-boat. Indeed, they were so closely packed as to impede the motion of the rowers, and when within a mile of the shore, the pirate came upon them.</p>
               <p>The boat was ordered to come alongside the pirate, and they could do no better than to obey. <emph>One man</emph> was seen to leave the boat and ascend to the deck of the schooner. Then the boat was seen to leave the schooner and make for the shore. We need not say that curiosity was on tiptoe, not only to see what the schooner would next do, but also to get all the particulars from the boat's crew as soon as they should land. For the latter purpose many rushed down the hill and sought the beach, while others remained above, intently watching the motions of the schooner.</p>
               <p>The pirate vessel made directly for the ship—While a part of her crew went on board of the whaler, the rest remained in the schooner and kept at a little distance from the ship. These whose eyes were fixed on the ship suddenly saw a man run up to the end of the main-yard by a rope affixed to his neck! They saw him struggle a moment in the halter, and try to clutch the rope, for his hands were not tied and his face was not bandaged. In a moment all was still. The man was dead. A murder had been done in broad daylight, in view of the whaling fleet and the inhabitants of Honolulu.</p>
               <p>Soon after the pirates left the ship taking with them whatever was valuable. The schooner them made sail and rapidly departed till she became a speck in the distant horizon for a moment and then wholly disappeared. Long before that time, however, the boat had reached the shore.</p>
               <p>To the hasty inquiries of the people on the stand, the boat's crew returned for answers that the ship was the <hi rend="i"/>Warrior Chief of Nantucket, commanded by Tristram Hussey. The pirates had wounded three men and injured the ship with their cannon shot, and upon coming up with the boat had ordered them alongside.</p>
               <p>When they went alongside the pirate, a young man armed to the teeth came to the gang way, and looking over, said, "My men, who is your captain.?"</p>
               <p>"I am" replied Captain Hussey.</p>
               <p>"Come on board, sir!" was the quick command.</p>
               <p>As soon as the captain had left the boat, the Pirate Captain said—</p>
               <p>"The rest of you may go. I have a debt to settle with all whaling captains. Push off."</p>
               <p>The boat then came ashore as we have seen, while the Captain was hung upon the main-yard arm of his own ship. The pirate left him hanging there when they left the ship.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC8321-00000045"/>
               <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
               <p>As soon as the whaling captains in the harbour became convinced that the Flying Arrow was actually gone, they ventured to peep like rats from their holes, at the departure of the cat! There was not a ship that did not send a boat, to, visit the disabled and plundered vessel. They reached that unfortunate vessel an hour after the pirates had left her. They took down the corpse of Captain Hussey and conveyed it to the shore for burial. The first mate took charge of the Warrior Chief.</p>
               <p>In the afternoon a bring arrived at the island from the main land, and reported having been boarded by the captain and part of the men of a piratical schooner, who took all the money and part of the provisions, and having thrust the captain and first mate into a large sack, flung them overboard.</p>
               <p>The brig entered the port with her flag union down, as a signal of distress.</p>
               <p>While the captains and officers of the vessels in the harbor were filled with consternation; the crews showed signs of rejoicing. They perceived that these pirates of the Flying Arrow never offered injury to common sailors nor to their property, but only to the captains and officers of vessels, whom they killed and plundered without mercy.</p>
               <p>Many of the sailors on board the whalers ardently desired an opportunity to get off to the Flying Arrow, and become one of her crew.</p>
               <p>This exasperated the captains and mates greatly, for they could perceive how the minds of the seamen were affected, and they became far more tyrannical than ever.</p>
               <p>They would patch up something against a man occasionally, as an excuse for sending him on shore to be flogged in the fort, and sometimes took the liberty to seize them up in tho rigging of their own ships, and flog them with a rope's end.</p>
               <p>On one occasion a Captain Barker, of the ship P——, took three men on shore, to have them put in the fort and flogged.</p>
               <p>It was yet early in the morning, there had been a fog all night, and it was not yet cleared away.</p>
               <p>One or two ships, lying in the outer harbor, could not be seen from the shore, and when the boat came up to the strand with the captain, second mate, and the oarsmen, for the purpose of bringing the three victims on shore, they mistook a group collected under a shed, only one hundred yards distant from the spot where they landed, for the native officers whose business it was to take charge of the prisoners.</p>
               <p>Accordingly the captain approached the shed, ordering his men to bring forward the three victims, who were handcufied.</p>
               <p>The group under the shed stepped out, and came near the men from the ship, when the captain discovered his mistake, speaking in an an gry manner to his boat's crew, and ordering them to move towards the fort with the prisoners.</p>
               <p>Then there came a voice out from the mist—</p>
               <p>"Stop' what are you going to do with those men?"</p>
               <p>Captain Barker looked around before answering, to see if some of his friends, or some native chief, was not at hand.</p>
               <p>He could see nothing but his own men, and a slender, but well-formed youth, armed with a sword and brace of pistols, who now stepped out in full view, and confronted Captain Barker face to face.</p>
               <p>"Who are you, and why do you interfere with what don't concern you?" said Captain Barker.</p>
               <p>The other answered in the words of a song well known to seamen. "Young man, don't think your on board of your ship."</p>
               <p>"What are you doing with them pistols, young man?" said the second mate of the P——, now speaking in his turn, "I'll be bound you stole them from some ship."</p>
               <p>"Too true for a joke!" cried a little rosy-cheeked fellow who had placed himself by the side of the armed youth, and who carried a dagger in his own belt.</p>
               <p>"God." cried the mate, "I could almost swear that yonder young chap with the dagger, was the fellow they called English John, and whom I saw on board the Maro."</p>
               <p>"It is the same!" said Captain Barker, "I recollect him well. I saw him when we were in company with the Maro, on the Off-shore-ground—and he must be a deserter, and so are all the rest of these fellows—deserters from whaleships, I'll warrant you."</p>
               <p>Then, addressing the armed youth, the captain said: "You'd better give up your pistols, and go back to the ship that you've run away from, or you may get taken care of pretty soon, and catch a flogging into the bargain."</p>
               <p>The young man took no notice of those observations of Captain Barker, but having kept his eyes fixed on the three men in irons, he now stepped towards them, saying, "What are you going to do with those men, who are handcuffed?"</p>
               <p>"None of your business," said the Captain sternly, and preparing to pass on with his prisoners.</p>
               <p>Drawing out a pistol and levelling it at Captain Barker, the other said:—</p>
               <p>"Let them free or you die at once, on the spot where you stand.'"</p>
               <p>"Seize him, men!" said the Captain to his party, and the second mate stepped forward to obey the order, when the youth fired. The Captain fell dead. The rest fled, with the exception of the three men in irons. They spoke up at once and said, "You are the Captain of the Flying Arrow?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, my men. You have seen some suffering at the hands of my enemies. As for me, I live for vengeance; all that I valued on earth exists no more, and those who deprived me of happiness here, I seek the wide world over. You will go aboard the schooner with me, we can find you something to eat and drink and better ways than you will in a whaler."</p>
               <p>The three men embraced the offer with joy, when Merrill introduced<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC8321-00000046"/> them to half a dozen of the schooner's crew who were in his company. He then led them to a little bay or notch in the shore where was secreted a light and fancifully painted boat. They all entered it, and the pirate sailors sat down to their oars, Merrill setting in the stern. In this way they pushed out of the harbour within gun shot of the ships which lay there at anchor.</p>
               <p>There was a noise on shore, however. The second mate of the Pirate had aroused the Chiefs—he had told them of the murder of his Captain and demanded that the boat containing the pirates should be instantly pursued. But when they looked off upon the waters, they saw that the mist had swallowed up the pirate skiff. It was no longer visible! The Chief refused to set out in pursuit of an invisible object.</p>
               <p>But when a few minutes afterwards, the mist lifted partially from the face of the water, they behind a man dangling from the fore-yard arm of a Nantucket whaler, and then they knew that the pirate had not left the harbour without leaving his mark behind him. A boat that came speeding from the ship, soon afterward brought the tidings that Alexander Merrill had been on board with his boat's crew, and after a fierce contest, in which one of the pirates, and the mate of the ship, steward, and two seamen were killed, the pirates were victorious, and immediately hanged the Captain to the fore-yard.</p>
               <p>The mist lifted still more, till at length, the sun chased it entirely away, when could be seen a schooner in the offing, standing out to sea, with all sail set.</p>
               <p>Then they knew that the Flying Arrow had taken advantage of a fog to approach very near the shore—sufficiently near to land the captain and several of his men.</p>
               <p>But what had been their object on shore? One of the principal chiefs found slaughtered in his own house—his head cut off, and placed on a pole before his own door—told the whole story of their secret expedition.</p>
               <p>The slain chief was the same who had sold Ruth Willard to the Captain of the Enterprise, and who had been the cause of her death.</p>
               <p>Merrill had taken vengeance on the false chief, and gone off to his schooner. Before noon, the Flying Arrow had again passed out of sight—but she had left sorrow, amazement, and wailing behind her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head>
               <p>WE must now transport our reader to the West Pacific, the coasts of Japan, the Ladrone Islands, and the Chinese Seas.</p>
               <p>At the time when the events recorded above transpired, the Western portion of the Pacific Ocean was new whaling ground; and with an ardent hope of finding plenty of whales there, and realizing quick fortunes, the whalemen rushed to those seas in vast numbers.</p>
               <p>The whole whaling fleet were now in the West Pacific. Not a ship remained in port.</p>
               <p>In the low latitudes of the Ladrone Islands, where the weather is always hot, a large number of ships were engaged in hunting for the mighty monarchs of old hoary ocean.</p>
               <p>It was night. The day had been prosperous to several of the whalemen, and now amid the darkness could be seen the fires of half a dozen ships, as they boiled out the oil during the long watches of the night—The watch on deck of each ship thus engaged could see the fires of the others, looking like stars on the surface of the ocean, owing to their distance.</p>
               <p>A curious observer would have been interested in watching those lights, seeing one occasionally grow larger as the ship came nearer then become scarcely visible as she receded, while one or two would be entirely swallowed up in the darkness, as the vessel ran off to seek some other ground where less rivalry afforded more ample means of success.</p>
               <p>We may as well listen to the conversation on board of one large vessel, whose fires blazed high and brightly, and which had been unusually successful in obtaining whales. It was the starboard watch with the second mate on deck.</p>
               <p>"Strike two bells!" said the officer. "One o'clock already. Who'd have thought it? Come, boys! pull up—show a leg—we must take<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC8321-00000047"/> advantage of this run of luck, and not let blubber spoil on our hands."</p>
               <p>The second mate was standing before the try-works at this time, fork in hand.</p>
               <p>'Horse-pieces, here!" continued he. "Bible leaves, Gershom—pass 'em along. Mince fine and fast too. Heave down some scraps here, you boy! Starbuck," said he, addressing the boatsteerer at his elbow, "Do you see the Maro now?"</p>
               <p>"No, sir," was the reply, "she was off the lee bow about two points a few minutes ago. I could but just see her light."</p>
               <p>"Off, I guess. It seems to me that her captain and the old man did not agree very well together."</p>
               <p>"Did you think so, sir," asked the boatsteerer.</p>
               <p>"Well, yes, Starbuck; I noticed something of the kind from the moment that the girl named Red Mary was killed."</p>
               <p>"What do you suppose that Captain G—— cared for that?"</p>
               <p>"Well, you ought to know, Starbuck, that Captain G———, of the Maro is or pretends to be something of a gentleman."</p>
               <p>"Isn't the old man the same way. Why should not our Captain, be a gentleman too."</p>
               <p>"The devil!" cried the mate impatiently—"You know there's a difference between the Captain of the Enterprise and the Captain of the Maro—at least every body says so."</p>
               <p>"Well, I don't want to say nothing against my own captain"—commenced Starbuck.</p>
               <p>"Oh! I forgot!" interrupted the other contemptuously. "You expect to be first mate under him next voyage."</p>
               <p>The boatsteerer bit his lip in anger. "But no matter." continued the second mate. "We won fight about that. I only say that ever since our Captain had a hand in the death of that girl, Captain G——, of the Maro, has been a little shy of him. I don't know any particular reason for it, though a fellow called 'English John,' who turns out to be the brother of Red Mary, was on board the Maro awhile."</p>
               <p>"And now he is aboard the Flying Arrow that they tell so much about."</p>
               <p>"Well, they think so," said the mate curtly.</p>
               <p>"I wonder how much longer they'll let that pirate blockade Honolula, and take everything he pleases from the vessels which go in and out that port," said Starbuck.</p>
               <p>"Guess they'll have a States' vessel after him soon. They'll squeeze his neck before long; you may depend on that."</p>
               <p>"Not before he's squeezed some more necks himself, I'm a thinking, muttered a boy who was flinging down scraps from the strainer.</p>
               <p>"Silence! you rascal! Who put you in spokesman?" said the mate. "Speak when you are spoken to."</p>
               <p>The man at the mincing-horse looked up slyly and grinned to the youth and there were others present who mightly relished the bold speech of the lad, though prudence kept them silent, for it is a maxim with sailors that when your head is in the lion's mouth you'd better draw it out as quietly as possible.</p>
               <p>"Well, our watch is most out," said the officer—"It lacks but ten minuter of four, and the other watch will take our place soon, glad of it. I'm sleepy. Do you see anything, Starbuck, that looks like a small white cloud off yonder"—and the mate pointed to some object far away on the weather quarter.</p>
               <p>"I see nothing, sir. Stop: there's something like a little light there."</p>
               <p>"Well, no matter. Call the watch."</p>
               <p>"Larboard watch, ahoi! Turn out—bear a hand there!"</p>
               <p>The first mate's watch came up grumbling. The Starboard watch retired to their bunks, laughing at the former <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"For some must watch</l>
                        <l>While some must sleep</l>
                        <l>So wears the world away."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The first mate went forward to the try-works. The mineer went to the horse, and the skimmer to the side of the mate, on the platform before the works, while the helmsman went aft to the wheel.</p>
               <p>A hand forward—an Indian of some experience in nautical affairs, was coming up the ladder, and scarcely got his head out of the hatch when he cried out, "Sail O!"</p>
               <p>"Where?" said the mate.</p>
               <p>"Just here, on the quarter," replied the man, pointing out the object with his extended hand.</p>
               <p>"Ah! yes—I see it, what clumsy fellow is running down so near to us, in the night? Is he blind? Guess he's just come on the coast and don't know how thick we are here."</p>
               <p>"But, sir," returned the Indian—"it seems to me that is no whaler. I see but—but two masts: she is fore-and-aft rigged!"</p>
               <p>"The devil!" cried the mate, Jumping to the side of the ship and then getting into the main rigging for a better view. After looking a little while, he cried—"She must see the light of our fires. Why don't she luff? Here, Brown, bring a lantern and set it in the mizen-rigging.</p>
               <p>We'll give 'em every chance."</p>
               <p>The lantern was set, and still the strange crew came driving down upon the quarter of the Enterprise!"</p>
               <p>"Call the Captain! Quick!" cried the mate, who maintained his position in the main rigging—"Call the Captain up, right off!"</p>
               <p>The Captain came on deck in his shirt and trousers—"Hullo, there!" cried he—"why don't that fellow keep off?"</p>
               <p>Down came the schooner.</p>
               <p>"What ship is that?" cried a stern voice from the taffrail of the schooner.</p>
               <p>"The Enterprise of Nantucket!" shouted the Captain as loud as the other.</p>
               <p>"All right!' was the muttered reply. "I'll see you as soon as it is laylight."</p>
               <p>The Schooner then came to the wind and ran along parallel with the ship, shortening sail to avoid shooting ahead of her.</p>
               <pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC8321-00000048"/>
               <p>"We are all dead men!" said the Captain gravely to his mate.</p>
               <p>"How so, sir?"</p>
               <p>"Did you never hear of the Flying Arrow?"</p>
               <p>"Merciful God! can this be she?" cried the mate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>A weary hour passed. When morning dawned a row of cannon and the American flag at the mizzen showed the people of the Enterprise that they were in company with the United States schooner Dolphin.</p>
               <p>With a mountain load removed from his heart, the whaling Captain saw a boat lowered from the dolphin. He backed his main yard, and the boat came to the ship. As he handed Captain Percival over the side, the latter said.</p>
               <p>"Have you seen anything of a piratical schooner about here, know as the Flying Arrow?"</p>
               <p>"No, sir. Is she on the coast?" inquired the captain of the Enterprise.</p>
               <p>"We have every reason to believe she is," said <hi rend="i"/>Mad Jack, as Captain Percival was universally called by his sailors.</p>
               <p>After a little more conversation the naval officer left the Enterprise went on board his schooner, and then went on his way in search of the pirate.</p>
               <p>At the same time a vessel appeared to leeward, supposed at first to be a ship.</p>
               <p>But the men at the masthead soon made her out to be a fore-and a vessel.</p>
               <p>Rapidly she came beating to windward, and before noon the black banner of the pirate was seen waving its sombre folds over her stern.</p>
               <p>Then was seen to windward the other schooner returning.</p>
               <p>With everything set; the Dolphin sped towards the ship.</p>
               <p>But she was still at great distance, and the pirate was close at hand.</p>
               <p>A gun from on board the Flying Arrow commanded the Enterprise to heave to.</p>
               <p>Emboldened by the approach of the Dolphin, the Enterprise kept on her way.</p>
               <p>Then a shot from the pirate struck the plank shear and bulwarks of the ship, and sent a dozen splinters over her deck, severely wounding two men and an officer.</p>
               <p>The pirate then ran into the quarter of the Enterprise; her captain sprang on board with a dozen armed men.</p>
               <p>A terrific contest now ensued, but it was of short duration.</p>
               <p>The whaling Captain was out down by Alexander Merrill, and when he cried for mercy, the latter thrust his sword through his heart, as he shouted "Ruth Willard!" in his ears with a voice of thunder.</p>
               <p>But now the Dolphin came up.</p>
               <p>Her crew boarded the ship, and met the pirates, whom they fought hand to hand.</p>
               <p>Desperately did Alexander defend himself, but the contest was far too unequal.</p>
               <p>Just as he was about to transfix Mad Jack with his sword, a Quarter-master came up behind, and split his skull open with an axe.</p>
               <p>He fell and died without a groan.</p>
               <p>Most of the pirates were then captured.</p>
               <p>English John leaped into the sea, and swam to a boat that was adrift, and made for the land which was not far distant.</p>
               <p>Exhausted by the extraordinary fatigue he had undergone, he sank upon the barren earth in a state of insensibility.</p>
               <p>He did not revive to consciousness till the morning, and then he looked around him with despair.</p>
               <p>The ships were gone; he was left alone, and as far as his eyes could stretch all was desolate, wild, and dreary.</p>
               <p>Nothing could possibly be more fearful than his situation, the place he was in, was evidently uninhabited; a frightful lingering death stared him in the face, and bitter were the curses that escaped his lips.</p>
               <p>One moment he was half resolved to plunge into the sea, and thus at once end his existence.</p>
               <p>But still the hope of rescue and future vengeance, arrested him in his deadly purpose, and he endeavoured to become more calm.</p>
               <p>The principal portion of his property was lost in the Flying Arrow, but still he had a large sum of money secured about his person, and he hoped that it might yet prove of service to him.</p>
               <p>He now made an excursion into the island, with the hope of finding some inhabitants, or meeting with any of the pirates who had made their escape, but without success, he returned in the evening, tired, hungry, and half mad, to the sport from whence he had started.</p>
               <p>That night, and a portion of the following day, he passed in the same state of misery. But in the afternoon, he espied a vessel at a<pb n="100" xml:id="VAC8321-00000049"/> distance and half frantic with sudden joy, and the prospects of deliverance, he shouted aloud, and played all the antics of a lunatic.</p>
               <p>He stood on the very verge of a rock, and waved his handkerchief as high as he could in the air, with the hope of attracting their, observation; but at present the ship was too far off for those on board to notice his signal, and he began to fear that he should again be doomed to disappointment.</p>
               <p>However, the wind bore her swiftly on, and at length she had arrived so near, that he felt satisfied his signal must be seen, which supposition was soon confirmed, for he saw a boat put off from the ship, and make towards the rock on which he was standing.</p>
               <p>What a relief was this to his mind and again he shouted with delight.</p>
               <p>The boat arrived and he was released from his perilous and awful situation, and received with every kindness on board the ship, which was an English merchant vessel on her passage home.</p>
               <p>To the questions that were naturally put to him by the captain, he replied that he was an India merchant and was on his way to England in a ship called the Enterprise, which was wrecked in the storm which had occurred three days before.</p>
               <p>That every soul on board but myself had perished, and he had succeeded with great difficulty in reaching the barren rock on which they had found him.</p>
               <p>His story was a plausible one, and of course, he was believed, and much sympathy was expressed for him.</p>
               <p>Thus, "English John," was the only one of the pirates that escaped an early and a bloody death.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>THE END.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>