<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8280">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Chronicles of Gotham, Vol. 1 </title>
            <author >White, Richard Grant, (1821-1885)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC8280</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The chronicles of Gotham, vol. 1</title>
                  <author >White, Richard Grant, (1821-1885)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >43 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >S. Low</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London </pubPlace>
                  <date >1871-1872</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-09-21">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The chronicles of Gotham, vol. 1</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n="Advertisement (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8280-00000001"/>BY THE SAME ,UTHOR,  TH{E   FALLj3 OF O F, OR, THEI LOVES OF THE GORILLAS, U,-     A  SATIRE,      lection. Upon the Darwinian Theory of Development by Sexual Selection. -;    BY THE AUTHOR OF THE NEW GOSPEL OF PEACE." BOOK FIRST. NEW YORK: G. W. CARLETON &amp; CO., PUBLISHERS, LONDON: S. LOW, SON &amp; CO MDdCCIXXT.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC8280-00000002"/> In the Oilice of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington,          Enee a odn to ,c of^ I oges in'^ th year 18*1 b. IF AN G3 ^SSLILMAN;                . S3teamr nters and Stereotypers, iO8 tol l4 Wooater St.,    X - NEW YOBK                  X   THE CGIRONICLES OF GOTHAM. CHAPTErR L 1. The latter days of Gotham. 3. Cornelius. 10. Carrieth cucurm bers to Gotham. 12. Taketh money on the' road. 14. And in Ouahlstrete. 16. The Almighty Dahl. Lar. 18. The image of Cornelius. 25. Daniel the Pharisee boweth not down to it. 30. The Query road. 1. HERE begin the chronicles of Gotham  in the latter days, when Ulysses ruled the land of Unculpsalm. 2. For after the days of the New Gospel of Peace which was preached by Phernandiwud, and which prevailed not, and whereof Benjamin the scribe wrote when the war was in the land of Unculpsalm, and after the days of Andrew, whose surname was Jonsing, Ulysses was made chief ruler. 3. In those days there was an image set up in Gotham, of i man whose name was Cornelius. 4. And this Cornelius was chief of a band called the Scent-rule band, which took money on the -way as thou goest from the river Hutzoon to the great lakes. Now men who ;6ok money from wayfarers on the road were called Dur- rektahs. And sometimes he and his band took money ia Ouahlstrete. 5. And he was a devout man, and prayed many times every day, praying for all things and chiefly for the souls of them that withstood him.  &#xD;<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC8280-00000003"/> ' , i                 ?! 6       THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.        e 6. And the manner of his prayer was in this wise, dahmiz- - ize and dahmrizole; for such were the prayers of the devout men of Gotham. , 7. And albeit they were not Pharisees, they prayed thus not only in their houses and in their chambers, but at the  corners of the streets and in the market places, and in the  temples where they worshipped the lgod of that city. In all X these places dahmizize and dahmizole were heard continu- ally.            : 8. And they called the name of their god Almighty Dahl Xi Lar. And all men worshipped him, and of women not a , few.  i                        9. Now Cornelius had come to be one of the chief priests 0 of this god in the city of Gotham. But in his youth he was : a shipman. For he loved the water; so loving it to sail : upon it, that he would in no wise diminish the quantity ,: by drinking thereof.                  - 10. And having a little ship, he carried the fruits of the earth, even corn and cucumbers, from the country round about Gotham up to the city; for that city stood upon an island..  ". And as the city grew, and Cornelius grew therewith, he X made unto himself larger ships, even ships that were moved ;: by the boiling of water in a caldron, very marvellous and i terrible, according to a device of Satan, who was Cornelius's :i familiar spirit.  \      : 1l2. And Satan helped Cornelius, and he got great gain f by the ships that were moved with caldrons; and he made unto himself more of them, and sent them into far countries, and took money from travellers by sea.         ! 13. Now when he saw that he got great gain by taking , money from travellers by sea, he said within himself: Are i not the travellers by land an hundred-fold more in number i than the travellers by sea? Go to, then; shall I not get more !   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.       7 by taking a little daily from these, than by taking much from those? Behold I will be a Durrektah, and take money on the land. (For is it not written that the Durrektahs were robbers?) Wherefore he sold his ships and began to take money on the roads which ran by the river Hutzoon, and from the Hutzoon as thou goest westward to the great lakes. For he was wise in his generation. ". Likewise he took nmoney in Ouahlstrete; and there also he was helped by Satan. For Satan went to and fro in Ouahlstrete every day, and up and down therein. 15. And Cornelius was a great man, and a mighty, and a goodly man to look upon. And he had sons and daughters, and sons-in-law and daughters-in-law, and men servants and maid servants, and men which were not of his household to whom he said, Go, and they went, and Come, and they came; so that there was a multitude to do his bidding; for he had a great following.  16. For so it was in Gotham that men gave themselves day and night to gathering unto themselves images of their god, the Almighty Dahl Lar, and he who had gathered many was called worthy of so many images, and he who had gathered most was deemed worthiest and greatest. And him they worshipped, even as he had worshipped the Dahl Lar. 17. Therefore, when the men of Gotham saw that Cor- nelius had gathered to himself a great number of the images of the Almighty Dahl Lar, even a multitude like to-the stars of the firmament and the sands of the sea for number, they said one to another, 18. Lo, Cornelius is worthiest and best among us. Let us therefore set up his image, that we may bow down to it and worship it. 19. And Cornelius shall pay for the image. 20. For it was so in Gotham that when men said, What By e    -  &#xD;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC8280-00000004"/> 8       THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.  shall be done to the man whom the people delight to honor?  that they answered: Let us give him vessels of silver or  vessels of gold, or let us set up his image, even a brazen j image, or an image of stone, or a painted image, and let-us J grave thereon his name whom the people would honor, and - moreover our own names, for so shall we be set up before the $ people, and' seeming to do honor unto him, we shall get : honor for ourselves, and seem to be chief men that speak for the people.  21. For this was the manner of men in Gotham; and men when they did this thing of themselves, not being asked to ! do so by others, called themselves a committee, because noth-  ing had been committed unto them. 22. And the man whom they delighted to honor paid for the image and the vessels of gold and of silver; and when they were given to him, he received them with humility, anrid made an oration, saying he was not worthy of such honor. And so it was that Cornelius paid for his own image. 23. And the image was set up in the temple of the Hut- zoon, that great river that floweth between Gotham in the country of Mannatton and the Jahrzees, even the temple which Cornelius himself had builded to the Almighty Dahl Lar, on the outer walls thereof, on high that it might be seen : of all men. . , 24. And when the image was shown to the people, there!^ was the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, dulcimer, and all kinds of music; and the governor of the ^ city made an orationi which he spake unto the people, but verily addressed to Cornelius; even as a priest made a prayer which he spake unto his god, but addressed to the people. And the people worshipped not their god, but bowed down before the image of Cornelius and worshipped it.   : 25. But one man bowed not down before the image of  i   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.       9. Cornelius, nor worshipped it, and the name of that man was Daniel. 26. Now Daniel was a Pharisee. And he also prayed daily; but not in the manner of Cornelius, nor yet in that of Daniel of old, who went up into his chamber to pray. But this Daniel prayed always in the'congregation, and sang psalms and hymns and spiritual songs. 27. And when he was not praying and singing, he was taking money on the road or in Ouahlstrete, like Cornelius; for he also was a Durrektah. 28. And Satan helped him likewise. For when he was praying and singing, he thought about taking money from wayfaring men, and from the men of Ouahlstrete, and when he took money, he seemed to think of praying and singing. And this manner of man findeth favor with Satan. 29. And so it came to pass that Daniel, that had been an herdsman, driving sheep and oxen to Gotham, and after- wards had kept an inn for other herdsmen, became rich and mighty, and took money on the road, even the road of iron that goeth from the Jahrzees, by the river Hutzoon, over against Gotham, northward and westward to Laiquery. 30. And men called the name of this road Query; partly for the shortness thereof, and partly because Query, being interpreted, is, Who can tell anything about it? For no man ever knew anything about this road, of a surety, save Daniel; and- he was the treasurer' of the Query band, and, like Judas, carried the bag. 31. Nevertheless, the Query road was a great road, and Cornelius strove to get the rule pof that road, and to take money on it; but Daniel withstood him. Wherefore,. Cor- nelius and Daniel were at enmityy,  &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8280-00000005"/> 30      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. CHAPTER II. 1. The Durrektahs and, akkawnah. 5. Daniel maketh one. 8. Laym.  duz. 11. Satan, Daniel and Cornelius. 15. Daniel joinethi hmself unto Cornelius. 21. And they make akkawnnh. 28.  Which cometh to naught. 31. Daniel's righteousness.  1. Now the Durrektahs took money not only from  the wayfarers on the roads of which they had taken possession, but from each other also!                ! 2. And the manner of the latter taking they called making akkawnah. For is it not written in the New Gospel of Peace, in the third book thereof, how the men of Ouahlstrete busied - themselves in buying and selling dreams and wishes, and in i? paying for them with promises; and how, when the dreams vanished, and the wishes were come to naught, he whose  : promises were the greatest paid the overplus in money. -:J 3. And the manner of making akkawnah was in this  wise, for a man to sell dreams and wishes, and take promises , therefor, and, himself to cause the dreams that he had' sold to ! vanish, and the wishes to come to naught, and then to de-,  mand full payment, to the ruin aof them that had put faith  in his delusions.  4. And the men of Ouahlstrete saw each other making   : akkawnah daily; but they went on buying and selling the  dreams and the wishes, each man hoping that it would not : be his dreams and wishes, but his neighbor's, that would come to naught, and not his promises, but his neighbor's,  that would come to be paid.                : 5. And Daniel made akkawnah, a great one, and he made  it on the Query road; and he seemed unto all men to be , ,                       ::i,,%g   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.       " buying promises and wishes- for the success of the Query. And the men of Ouahlstrete said within themselves, Lo, Dan- iel the Pharisee, the great Durrektah of the Query road him- self, who is treasurer thereof, and beareth the bag like Judas, buyeth these dreams; let us, therefore, buy them, and we shall have good success with him. 6. But when the time came for the dreams to be true, and the promises to be paid, behold, Daniel had caused Query to come to naught, and he had bought not dreams but promises ; and all they that had bought the dreams fell into this snare, and there never had been so great akkawnah, no, not in Ouahlstrete. 7. And Daniel gained thousands and hundreds of thous- ands; and on the next Sabbath-day, he prayed in the congre- gation, and sang psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, and gave thanks that he was not as other men were, even as those laymdux in Ouahlstrete. 8. For in the tongue of that country, where men had paid for dreams with promises, and could not keep their promises, they were called laymdux. 9. And it came to pass, that forthese things, Daniel was hated of the laymdux; and all men feared him, but they also envied him, and many woiild have joined themselves to his congregation. For in Gotham, men would even pray and sing, if they might hope to gain thereby. 10. Now the time had come when the Query Durrektahs should be chosen; (for every year, they who had possession of the roads chose Durrektahs;) and Cornelius sought to have some of his following chosen, so that by their means he might get the Query road into his own hands, and take money thereon. ". And Cornelius said within himself: Lo! Satan helpeth Daniel more than he helpeth me ; peradventure, because I can do better without his help, but chiefly because Daniel is a man  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8280-00000006"/> 12      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAJH. more after his own heart: for when he is making akkawnah he seemeth to be thinking of praying andsinging psalms, and when he prays and sings in the congregation, he thinketh of of making akkawnah. 12. Now I fear not Satan, and am a match even for Daniel  but he is not a prudent man who would undertake to fight the Devil and Daniel together. And if Daniel is left to work . out the devices of Satan by the craft of his own heart, he will triumph. 13. Wherefore Cornelius called unto him one of his law- yers (for he kept some lawyers) and caused him to write a complaint and a petition, which being read before a judge, and put into his hands with a persuasion (for in Gotham the  Judges weighed causes by taking the pleas in one hand, and.  the persuasion in the other), the judge might give him ade- cree forbidding him to work out his devices against Cornelius. ". Moreover, Cornelius -caused that Daniel should hear thereof. And when Daniel heard thereof, he saw that Comrne-  liushad been too much for him. Then he considered the matter, and in the craftiness of his heart hewent straightway unto Cornelius and said unto him:  15. Wherefore should there be enmity between thee and me? Are we not both of one mind and one purpose? And have  2 we not, both of us, Satan for our familiar spirit? Go to,  now, let us join ourselves together, and if thou wilt we shall  both of us be Durrektahs of the Query road, and we shall both of us take money on the road, and make akkawnah in  Ouahstrete together, and get great gain, we and our follow- ing. Let us, that have been at enmity heretofore, be hereafter J friends forever               .      v  16. Then Cornelius prayed inwardly, after his manner, for Daniel and said: Dahmizize, doth he think that I see not the craftiness-of his soul, and that I can be deceived with the smoothness of his speech? Nevertheless, if some of my fol- ,                      .   ..   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.       13 lowing may become Durrektahs with him, this will give me a vantage ground, and I shall not only take money on both roads, but, peradventure, I may be too much even for the Devil and Daniel together, and I shall drive him from this Query road, he and his following, and they shall no more be Dur- rektahs. 17.f Moreover Cornelius hid all this in his heart (which was not according to his wont, for he was an outspoken man, but this time he thought to fight Daniel with his own weapons), and he welcomed Daniel, and smiled upon him, and said: Let it be s thou sayest, and we shall prosper together and be friends brever. 18. Then was Daniel pleased; for Cornelius was a lordly man to look upon, and his smiling became him; and it lighten- ed the cloud of Daniel's perplexity, and he thought that his de- liverance was at hand. So he bowed himself before Cornelius, and made obeisance unto him; and they joined themselves to- gether. 19. But Daniel said unto Cornelius: Let not the friends of my lord and the friends of his servant seem be made Durrek- tahs together, lest, peradventure, the men of Ouahlstrete be mistrustful, even as when a dog smelleth a rat: But let anoth'er man be made Durrektah in my place; and it will seem as if my lord had obtained a victory over his servant, and the hearts of my lord's following shall be 'lifted up, and those of my following shall be cast down; and the former will buy dreams and wishes, and the latter will sell them, and we shall get gain. And after we have gotten the gain, let the man who is made a Durrektah give up his place, and let thy-servant be placed therein, and carry the bag again. So shall the men of Ouahlstrete be confounded, and those of my following shall buy dreams and wishes, and those of thy following shall sell them. And because we know what is to happen, we shall get gain again; for thley will be in darkness and confusion. g i  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8280-00000007"/> ----u-zPVIF OTvcWXHAAL O. And it was so, as Daniel had said, and he justified him-   n he eyes of Cornelius,"and of them that followed him* f also in the eyes of his own following Thi. ^^ m,'      i ie craftiness of him soul; for meantime hep 1  reven to his own friends, tod his own felloe  h* n the sanctuary.         n "oling, as'e1 For Daniel made a covena"t with Coeli, and with  - y for ^"T   *theat they should make akkawnah on Y fortheother meja of Oaahlstrete; and they made     Wi. to -do it withal.  NNlow in the to'ngue Spoken by the men of Ouahistrete ike appubl, was toput to-aether money, every man his  tob buy wherewithal to make akkawnqh;  and all the Iat were in appuhl together, weie bound' in bonoj-, even IPLh among thieves, to stand, by their covenant ^S:^h:tther., And because Daniel was treasurer, and carried th bag, Tas he  ^ wasue an mar    mr Qr 4 ,caue h wasa mn of much expe'rience' in this busi- 'nd because, they said, be, is a er'afty man and bath Fbr his f'amiliar spirit, and is the ma t oe ut the matter into hi'shands. matoesee appuhl 30 tey wnt ito Oaahlstrete, and did According'to, )venant; ttnd they glorified ihe Que'ry' road, and they  dreams and wishes for the glory thereof, and gave omises in payment therefor. 3ut 861t w 't as that when they looked that all the m1 en hlstrete should believe 'in the Coming glolry 4f the road,should bug' th   ^^Z8^        T Poad ehbd hg teir dreams an"d keep them unto   i vTes, they found, that all m -     Hetthmele wo. de appuhl and we're making akkawnab, weie ready heir'.C'6ams and wiyhes, and were not ready to buy. werte astonished. len theysaid', 1Lo this is because, we have ni'ye ,the Q uer- 'oad e'nough, -and have not bought'   fh. And they glorified moreand bought more, and of them, who had spent ailtheir money, went to Dan- ecause he carried the bag like Judas, and borrowed y of him, and he lent it to them, at usury. And they said among themselves, Behold what it is to covenant and in appuhl with the great Daniel who (s the bag, and who is a righteous man, and hath bowels, ompassion for his friends, though he be hard with his ies. We shall get riches. Great is Daniel the treasurer I Nevertheless, the thing changed not, and the time nigh when their long promises should be paid. And said among themselves and to Daniel, Lo! we are all in il, and yet we have not made akkawnah. Who hath this thing? And Daniel, looking upon them, said also, hath done it? And they employed cunning men to inquire into the er. And it was found that Daniel had done it, and that they did openly, he who was in covenant with them aindone secretly. And terror fell upon them; for they saw that they betrayed, and that where they had laid snares for rs, they were taken themselves in snares, even the snares aniel. Thus did Daniel gain much, and they who were in, nant with him lost what he had gained. And he re- d in his hearti and said, See what it is for a man to be a^a rektah, and also a treasurer, and to carry the b-ag like is, and to keep his own counsel. And on the next Sab- day he prayed in the congregation, and gave thanks, i the thanks of the righteous; and he sang psalms and ns and spiritual songs, and m ent down to his house, and, odor of his own sanctity was in his nostrils'.  &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8280-00000008"/> 16 -TMI B ONICS 011'. GOTHAM, i, .Th oatA o/6Yornelus X4. 2epmakel akkawn8hah for Danie I  9, TjudgeAbrnah. 11.Die 'shemi. D. ah    myq- tery of ouahterinstog. 13. Govne iis #oth agaii to ebarnak thejudge. oeS. 17. teometh r w      of a- iel b 19.      own blozoeth his own tum e? adci of -Da- i25.    Gorneli    tump .  - .ad . Da?, - s2oils.                t    di. 1. TaE  a Corelius wroth, and his angerburne d h t  i against Daniel, and even against himself Farhe said, Tht  ind. Bat am I not evenie T.  was only doing after his knoiving homy eyes open, have been  betayed by: this s.           open  e been e aking, pharisee?. :2. And Cornelms also- prayed devoutly -fo Da:el hI manner, and cried out. dahmizizelad dahmizz   after times daily.  And the sons and daughtorsof CoreliUs, and his men servonts, and his maid          s feared to come before him, because of his anger.  :"  An     /i'fnei ".And  Ooinelms npodered the matter, and said: This man shall repent him of this thig in dust and ashes. For I will darive him from his oe, and e shall     or I  :: Durrektah and a treasurer, and arry th  e bag , althogh he will ever be like Judas; and I will drive hi from the ue road, that he shall no more be known thereon, and Iill   : take his possession from him.         n 4. Then he gathered together his follo Us make appuhl together, and let us make akkawnah, and 1 akkawnah, saidlld;I   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTiHAM.      17 will tie this psalm-singing Pharisee hand and foot, and will cast him into it; and we shall take this Query road out- of his hands, and take it unto ourselves; and we only shall take money on it, and get great gain, and our horn shall be ex- alted, and he shall be cast down; and this Judas shall know what it is to betray Cornelius. So they made appuhl, and began again to make akkawnah.   5. And, it was told to Daniel, Behold, Cornelius maketh akkawnah for thee. Then he lifted up his eyes and said, The Lord is gracious, and he will help his servant. (But when he said the Lord, he meant Satan.) And he was not troubled. 6. For Daniel said within himself, have I not many sheers laid by me, even fifty and eight thousand? 7. Now Daniel trusted more in sheers than he did in the Lord, or even in Satan; for he who had a multitude of sheers, could, by scattering them in Ouahlstrete, bring to naught the devices of them who would make akkawnah. 8. And when Cornelius saw that Daniel was not troubled because of his making akkawnah, he said, Behold, he trust- eth in his fifty and eight thousand sheers, (for Cornelius knew that he had them); but I will be too much for him and for Satan,. 9. Then he sent his lawyer to a judge with a plea to put into one hand, and a persuasion to put into the other; and the judge made a decree that Daniel should not use his sheers to prevent Cornelius in making akkawnah. And the name of the judge was Abarnah. 10. But when Daniel read the decree, he was yet not troubled;" for in the room where  the Durrektahs met together, there was a sheer-mill, which would make sheers as fast as Daniel and the Durrektahs had need thereof. ". So the next day, Daniel and the other Durrektahs met together, and worked the sheer-mill, and made a hundred 15  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8280-00000009"/> 18      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. thousand new sheers, and they kept the making of them secret, and told no mani thereof. 12. Now, Cornelius foresaw the craft of Daniel, and feared that he would make new sheers; for he had been there him- self, where the sheer-.mill was, and the working of that mill was called by the men of Gotham, the mystery of ouah- terinstox. And Cornelius understood well that mystery. 13. Wherefore Cornelius went again to Abarnah, the judge, with a great persuasion; and Abarnah made a decree  that Daniel should do no more about the Query road, and that nothing more should be done about it in the room of the Durrektahs; and moreover, that Daniel should come before him, and show cause why his candlestick should not be removed out of its place, and he be no more a Durrektah. ". Then Daniel, when he read the decree, laughed within himself, and said in his heart, It is too late; Cornelius and Abarnah, his judge, are a day .behind me and Satan; for  have not the hundred thousand sheers been already ground I! -out of the sheer-mill?,                : 15. And Cornelius .knew not of the hundred thousand new  sheers, and he and his following went on making  akkawnah.       .  -  : 16.' Now among the Durrektahs that, had been chosen when Daniel and Cornelius joined themselves together, was Jeems, the son of Phrisc, whom men called Jemphrisc. 17. And -Jemphrisc was a disciple of Daniel, and was also a devout man, but .not after the manner of his master: X for he followed Daniel in his craft, but in his praying he followed Cornelius, and said dahmizize and dahmizzole many times daily. 18.-Now Jemphrisc was a Iangkie, and had come to Gotham from Bosstown, the chief city of the Iangkies, and "X he was of the tribe of Peddullah, and in his youth he had gone to and fro in the land of the Iangkies, sitting in a X ' "-      THE CHROEICiMu v ....---. chariot, and blowing a trumpet, and selling merchandise. And he found favor in the eyes of the women of that land, and sold them much merchandise, even garments of silk and andof woollen and of them uc ine linen, and jewels, and name- less little things that in the Iangkie tongue are called noshins: albeit among the Iangkie women both shins and noshins are nameless. 19. But i n Bosstown h e had joined himself unto the tribe of Jobbah, and sold merchandise unto the Peddllahs. And when he came to Gotham he left the Jobbahs and went into Ouahlstrete, and became a money-changer. But he ceased not to sit in a chariot or to biw a trumpet, and he blew his own trumpet daily. 20. For he sa idt If I blow not mine own trumpet, who Will blow it for me?       a 21. And he went to Daniel andblew his  trumpet, and moreover, he blew Daniel's trumpet before him, and the sound thereof was pleasant in the ears of Daniel; and he took Jemphrise unto himself and made him one of his following And he taught him how to work the sheer-mill; and Jem- phrisc remembered that teaching forever after. 22. And it came to pass that when Daniel had made the hundred thousand new sheers with the sheer-mill that he said, I will use one half of these myself and the other half will I give unto my disciple Jemphrisc; and when the time is come he shall use them to prevent Cornelius in making akkawnah.              ' 23. Then Cornelius said to them that were in appuhl with him, and to his sons-in-law, and his officers and his servants, and all his following, Move forward and make akkawnah, and put Daniel therein. And they moved forward, and they filled Onahlstrete with the noise of their shouting. 24. But Daniel scattered abroad his sheers, even fifty thousand new sheers, ground from the sheer-mill by the   &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8280-00000010"/> 20      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. mystery called ouahterinstox, whereof no man had knowledge save himself and Jemphrisc his disciple; and in the face of these no man could make akkawnah.  25. Then did Ouahlstrete look 'or Cornelius to be discom- fited; for the sheers of Daniel had, spoiled Cornelius and his following so that there was no more appuhl when the sun. went down upon the strife. But Cornelius stood fast, and said unto his following, The sheers of Daniel cannot last for- ever, for the sheer-mill is stopped by the decree of Abarnah. Move forward on the morrow again to make akkawnah for Daniel. ' Behold, I myself will be appuhl. (But he know not of the fifty thousand sheers in the hands of Jemphrisc.)  26. And they moved forward to make akkawnah, and it seemed that day as if Ouahlstrete was thronged with men each of whom was possesed of seven devils; and the place was filled with the noise of their striving and their shouting. 27. Now when-Jemphrisc saw that the battle was hot, and that Cornelius had given orders to his followinglto stand fast, even until all was lost, and also that Daniel had no more  sheers, he scattered his fifty thousand in Ouahlstrete. 28. And men saw that there were many thousand new   X sheers fresh from the sheer-mill, and looked upon the sheers, and behold they were the sheers of Jemphrisc; for they said, !! The mark of the Beast is upon them. 29. Then Daniel trembled and his heart sunk within him; for he saw that he had been taken in his own snare. And likewise the lmen of Ouahlstrete were dismayed. And the followers of Cornelius ran to him and said, There cannot be a akkawnah. Daniel we can meet and Satan we can meet; but there is moreover this Jemphrisc, and he is Daniel and Satan . together.                         X 30. But Cornelius rose up before them and said, Fools that : ye are and blind! because we have failed in one thing shall   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. -we bring ruin upon all? Owls and bats, againI say unto you, stand fast.! 31. And they stood fast, for they feared him and trusted him; and his courage became their courage. Butwhenthe sun went down on the second day Cornelius was spoiled again even as he was upon the first. Likewise Daniel was spoiled not a little. Yet was he not cast down; for he saw that Cornelius was beaten, although not destroyed. Then was Daniel comforted. 32. So Jemphrisc was victorious, he and the other Query Durrektahs that were with him: And he gathered together the spoils, aud they were great, that they had taken from Cornelius, and he put them in a chest and sat himself down upon the lid thereof. 33. And with the breadth of himself rearward he covered the lid of the chest; for he grew large from his feet upward and from his head downward, and, spread abroad. And when he saw that he covered the chest, he looked upon it and said, It is safe.  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8280-00000011"/> CHAPT ER IV. 1. The Judges in Sotham. 6. 6The r junctions, 9. The worath of Abarnah. 14. Jemphrise and Daniel flee into the Jahrzees. 20. Daniel seeketh Cornelius. 25. 25Jempris consideret h how they may return to Gotham. 29. The law-givers of the province and their lobbeepheeze. 831. Staycool goeth with persuasions to the lawgivers. 36. Cornelius goeth backward on the lawgivers. 40. And releaseth Daniel and Jemphrise for a consideration. 1. Now in the city of Gotham were many judges; and they -were just and upright: for being chosen by the people  (and in Gotham the Pahdees were the people) they said, Shall we smite the hand that feeds us, and overthrow them that are our bulwarks? Far be it from us to do this thing.  2. Wherefore, when one of the Pahdees had tried to con- vert his neighbor to his own belief by laying open his head or by ripping up his bowels (which manner of conversion was contrary to the law in Gotham), and the Pahdee was- brought before the judges, they let him go free,and punish- ed the man whose head he had opened or whose bowels he had ripped up, because he had so hardened his heart that he had made this unlawful manner of conversion needful, 3. Likewise in causes which concerned houses and land and cattle and goods, if any man came to them without a persuasion they did- nothing for him, were he as wise as Sol- omon, as just as Noah, or even as rich as Dives. 4. For they said, If we have not a persuasion, how can we weigh the cause? So they put the cause in one hand and the persuasion in the other, or if both the men brought a persuasion they weighed both the persuasions, and gave   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.       23 their judgment each of them, for that which on his honor he thought was the heaviest. Wherefore a judge in Gotham was called His Honor. 5. And so it came to pass that because of the Pahdees and the persuasions no man feared the law in Gotham, except the poor and them whose fathers were born in the land. 6. And when a Gothamite that was rich, or a great one among the Pahdeea feared that another man was about to hinder him from doing his will at the cost of the other, he went to the judge with a persuasion or a threatening and asked the judge to stay the other from hindering him by a decree that would unjunct him; and the judge unjuncted him, and that decree was called an unjunction. 7. And it came to pass that when one judge had unjuncted a man from doing one thing, he went sometimes to another judge with a great persuasion, and the latter judge unjuncted him from the unjunction of the former. 8. Then went his adversary to the former judge with a greater persuasion than before, and got from him a decree that no other judge should make any decree about that mat- ter, and that all other decrees than his own should be-void and of no effect. And so the judges unjuncted one another. And this was the manner of doing justice in Gotham, and it was thus that it was done between Cornelius and Daniel, and Jemphrisc, Daniel's disciple. 9. Now when the judge, whose name was Abarnah, that had made the decrees against Daniel, saw that -he and Jemphrisc and their following had made a junction to set the unjunction at naught, he was wroth, and he commanded the chief officer of Gotham that he should take those men .and bring them before him, to be cast into prison. 10. And the chief officer sent his under officers secretly with the decree of Abarnah the judge, to the place where Daniel and Jemptirisc and the others were gathered to-  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8280-00000012"/> 24      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM, gether, reckoning the spoils that they had taken from Cor- nelius. ". And as they sat together, one came -to them running, and said: Why sit ye here?- Behold the officers are com- ing upon you, because of your contempt of Abarnah, to take you before him that he may cast you into prison. 12. Then did the soul of Daniel quake and his knees smote together, and he said to Jemphrisc and the other Durrek- tahs, Brethren, let us pray. 13. And Jemphrisc rose quickly and prayed after his fashion, saying, Dahmmizole, he was a publican, and he is a sinner, and he always will be an hypocrite. Men and breth- ren, let him pray, but let us flee, for the officers are upon us. ". And there: was a great commotion; and they gathered together their books and their writings, and the sheer-mill,\ and Jemphrisc took the chest containing the spoils of Corne- lius (for that was the thing his soul cared for), and they fled, some in chariots, and some on foot, to the river Hutzoon, that they might go over into the Jahrzees, for there the de. crees of the judges of Gotham were of no avail. 15. And as they fled, the garments of them that were on foot stood out straight behind them, that a man might have sat thereon; and when the garments of Jemphrisc stood out, men saw as he fled, how it was that he had covered' the top of the chest that contained the spoils of Cornelius. 16. And Jemphrisc outran the officers (for he was a fast man and good at running, as will. appear here after), and he came to the river, and he got a little ship, and he and the others went over into the Jahrzees; and when they were there they gathered together again and laughed at Abarnah the judge, and wished him good success in his unjuncting. 17. And they dwelt many days in the Jahrzees; for they   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM       25 dared not go back to Gotham for fear of Cornelius, and for fear of Abarnah the judge whom Cornelius had persuaded. 18. But on the Sabbath days they could go over, because no officer could take a man before a judge on the Sabbath, except he had tried to convince another by laying open his head or ripping up his bowels. 19. So Daniel said, I will go over into Gotham on the Sabbath days, and I will go into the sanctuary and pray and sing psalms and hymns and spiritual songs. Peradventure the Lord will hear me and will soften the hearts of Cornelius and of Abarnah the judge, that they shall repent them of this decree, and that we may go and dwell again in Gotham and make appuhl and akkawnah, and get gain. 20. And Daniel went. But he said in his heart, I have gone aforetime to Cornelius, why should I not go now, and I will take with me the spoils, becavre like Judas I carry the bag, and I will bow myself doWto him, and make restora- tion unto him; and so shall his anger be turned from me, and I will offer a persuasion unto Abarnah the judge, and I shall be released from the officer, and I will turn my back upon Jemphrisc and join myself unto Cornelius.- 21. But Jemphrisc knew Daniel of old, because he had been his disciple, and he said, Dahmizize, he goeth to pray not to the Lord, or even unto Satan, but unto Cornelius. And Jemprisc set watchers upon Daniel; and found that it was 22. Now Daniel had possessions in the Jahrzees, and Jem- phrisc went before a judge of that country, and the judge gave him a decree that he might hold all Daniel's possessions that were in the Jahrzees until he brought back the spoils of Cornelius. 23. And-when Daniel returned and saw what Jemphrisc had done, he said, Verily, this disciple of mine is too much for nme; for I have taught him to fight me with my own weap-  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8280-00000013"/> 26  .    THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. ons. So he brought the spoils back in the Jahrzees, and then was Jemphrisc content, and he triumphed over his mas- ter, 24. Now Daniel and Jemphrisc, and all their following, sojourned in the Jahrzees and were strangers in that land, because of Cornelius and because of Abarnah the judge; and they could not go to Gotham. And Daniel mourned because he could not pray and sing in the congregation save on the Sabbath ; and Jemphrisc wearied' of his life in the Jahrzees, where there was neither money-changing men nor dancing women; and he said within himself, My soul lusteth alter the flesh-pots of Gotham, and its Ouahlstrete, and its concu- bines. 25. And Jemphrisc considered the matter, and communed with himself, and on a day when he and Daniel and their following were gathered together, he said unto them: 26. Go to, now, why should we continue to be sojourners and strangers in this land of the Jahrzees, for fear of Corne- lius and his judges, this weary land, where there is neither Ouhalstrete, nor dancing women, nor singing women, nor con- cubines, where we can neither get the money of other men nor spend it after it is gotten? 27. And Daniel answered and said: What shall we do? Shall we go back to Gotham to be cast into prison? 28. Then Jemphrisc answered Daniel saying, Fear not, Daniel; cleave unto me and thou shall not be cast into pri- son before thy time. Yet, verily, thy time is now; for thou deservest to be cast into prison, for because thou hast been faithless, even unto thy friends, from the beginning. But Zagain I say unto thee, Fear not. Cornelius hath persuaded Abarnah, the judge that administers the law; but-we can go one thing better; we can persuade them  that make the law. 29. VFor in the .province of which Gotham was the chief   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.       27 city, the lawgivers met together once every year to make laws and to receive persuasions, and the persuasions of the lawgivers were called lobbeepheze. And so it was that law- givers came to the council poor men, and paid for their living at the inns more than they were paid for making the laws ; and after a season they went each man to his home, having the prayer of Agar granted to him, neither poverty nor riches, but food convenient for him. 30. Now Cornelius had the lawgivers under his rule by reason of his persuasions. But Jemphrisc said: Have we not the spoils of Cornelius? Why should we persuade the ministers of the law, when we can persuade the makers of the law? Let us send a man to the lawgivers that will go one better. 31. And the thing pleased them, and they sent one of them- selves, named Staycool, who was Jemphrisc's companion and familiar friend. And men said that when they dwelt togeth- er, Jemphrisc provided the flesh, and Staycool the spirit. 32. And Staycool went to the city where the lawgivers were assembled, and there he set up his tabernacle. And Corne- lius was there also. And the lawgivers went to Staycool, to receive his persuasions, and they saw that his persuasions were good. Then, because they were just men, and would know both sides of the matter, they went to Cornelius, and they found that his persuasions were good also. 33. Moreover, for because that- the lawgivers were upright men, and justice prevailed among them, they went back and forth between Staycool and Cornelius many times, and the persuasions of him with whom they were last seemed always the best and the weightiest. 34. Then it came to pass that some of the lawgivers said: Let us make the doings of Daniel and Jemphrisc in the mys- tery of ouahterinstox lawful. And they gave it to seven men prudent in business, and cunning as to persuasions, to  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8280-00000014"/> 28      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. consider the matter. And the chief of the seven came to Staycool, and Staycool laid his persuasions before him an( said: Art thou content? And he said, I am content. Ther Staycool went to his'house and slept the sleep of the right eous.            , 35. But, behold, the next day the lawgivers made a law against Daniel and Jemphrisc, and in favor of Cornelius And Staycool was astonished, and his soul was troubled, and he went back to the city of the lawgivers. 36. And the lawgivers knew it, and looked eagerly fox more persuasion from him against Cornelius, and from Cor nelius, against him. But Cornelius said, there has been enough of this. Do they think me, again, one of the simple ones? I will offer no more persuasions. And he shut up the book, wherein he wrote his persuasionps, even that which, in the tongue of the Hebrews, in the land Unculpsalm, is called the shekbook, and which is the most persuasive of all books, and he girded up his loins, and shook the dust of the city ol the lawgivers from his feet, and went home to Gotham. 37. Then were the lawgivers wroth because of Cornelius and because of the ceasing of his persuasions. And they said: Who is this Cornelius that goeth backward on his his friends, and expecteth to get a law made without per- suasion? We will have naught to do with such a fellow. And straightway they made a law in favor of Daniel and Jemphrisc, and of their sheers that were ground out of their sheer-mill by the mystery of ouahterinstox; and the law was against Cornelius.       .  38. But Cornelius took not the matter to heart; for he said: It will' cost me less to persuade Daniel and Jempbrise than to persuade the lawgivers; for their stomach is bottom- less, and their name is legion. Moreover, when I persuade Daniel and Jemphrisc, there will be no man on the other   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.      29 side persuading them against me, and saying: Behold, thy servant goeth one better. 39. Then Cornelius said unto Daniel: What wilt thou give me, that I cease to pursue thee and thy following at tlhe law- for thy doings, and that Abarnah the judge shall withdraw his decree against thee, and against Jemphrisc, and the other Query Durrektahs, and that thou and -they may return to Gotham and live therein? 40. And Daniel said: Verily, that I may not be pursued at the law, and may return to Gotham and live there, and go unto the sanctuary, and- hear the Scriptures, and pray, and sing psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, I will give thee five millions of the images of thy god, even of the Dahl Lar, which profane men do call almighty; and, moreover, I will make two of thy following, whom thou shalt name, Durrek- tahs, that they may take money on the Query road. ". And the thing pleased Cornelius and he took the Dahl Lars, and lie stayed from pursuing Daniel and Jemphrisc and the others of his following, at the law, and he caused Abarnah, the judge, to stay his decree against them. 42. Then did they all return to Gotham, and Daniel went to his devotions, and was heard of no more in Ouahlstrete; and Jemphrisc went unto his also, yet not likewise; but of him all men heard thereafter, and some women.  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8280-00000015"/> SO      THE CEBONICLES OF GOTHAM. CHAPTER   V. 1. Bihltuede. 7. Joineth himsefunto the PPhyarmen. 10. Seeketh an office. 13. And is made an Overseer. 14. Jtisuprightnness. 20. Becometh a great man among, the Pahdees. 22. Peter and E ,lipridic.  24. oaxumall. 26. Becometh Governor of the City. 27. Thur Ing. 29.- 81iridic is made Treasurer. 31. And ihltumed e a Lawgiver. 33. Thur Ing prospers. 37. nd Jem Shri.A There was a man in Gotham named Bihlttede, hose olo t am nal t"ee wla e surnamewas Bigzhics, and some men called him Boss, which being interpreted is master. i2. And he was a just man, and a righteous,' for he' had been a disciple' of Phernandiwud; and in the days of the war,in the land of Unculpsalm, he was one of the sect of Smalphri among the Dimmichrats. 3. And before that time he was a poor man, and for his living he had made chairs, and many of the men of Gotham had sat upon his handiwork. /But he gained little, and was a man of no substance. Then he cast about to see what he should do that he might prosper. 4. And he said 'within himself: Behold, I am a man of no substance, and of no account, and I cannot carry on this little business and handicraft of chair-making to my profit; I am not learned in the law, nor have I studied how to rule men nor read what has been written concerning rulers that have lived aforetime, therefore will I cease making chairs,'and set myself up 9to be a ruler and a lawgiver in Gotham. - 5. PFor do not the Pahdees make the rulers of Gotham? and have they not come to this lalll ill ship-loads by thousands   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.      31 and tens of thousands to make rulers for this city? And I will recommend myself unto the Pahdees, and join myself unto the men that are leaders of the Pahdees, and unto the Bougheribois; for they are they that rule in Gotham. 6. Now in the days before the war in the land of Uncul- psalm there was a sect in Gotham called Phyarmen, and the most of them were of the tribe of Bougheribois. And these Phyarmen ran about the streets shouting like men possessed of devils, and they fought in the street with each other, and killed each other with stones and clubs and shooting-irons; and some of them were thieves; and many of them were drunken with a drunkenness that had neither beginning nor ending, for before one drunkenness had well ended with them another was well begun. 7. Wherefore to the Phyarmen it was given to do much in the choosing of the men who should govern the city and the province wherein the city was. So Bihltuede joined himself first unto the Phyarmen and unto the sect of Bunkahs among the Phyarmen. 8. Now the Bunkahs were men that slept in the temple of the Phyarmen and watched over their god, whose name was Dummasheen, acnd who got their lodging by their watching. So Bihltuede commended himself unto the Phyarmen, and after many years became some man among them. And it was of the Phyarmen that he was first called Bigzhics. 9. And it came to pass that after he had gained favor for himself with the Phyarmen, and with the rest of the Bougheribois and with the Pahdees that he spake with some of them in secret and with stammering speech (for Bihltuede was a meek man and a modest), saying: 10. Give me a little office in Gotham: I ask not to be a lawgiver, or a judge, or ruler of the city, or even one of the council, for I am meek and modest; but make me, I pray you, -one of the overseers.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8280-00000016"/> , ." 82      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. ". Now what the overseers in Gotham oversaw was the spending of the money of the city. And it was a great city and a rich, and its streets were filled with traffic, and its mer- chants were great merchants that stretched out their hands to the ends of the earth, wherefore it was the custom in Gotham to make overseers of men who had failed in their own affairs, or who had no affairs wherein to fail. 12. And because the greatness and the wealth and the merchandise of the city caused much money to be spent, it was likewise the custom to give the spending of the city's money and the keeping thereof to needy men who had no money of their own to spend., 13. So they made Bihltuede one of the overseers, and all the money that was, spent for the city of Gotham was known upto him; and without him could none be paid out of the treasury. ". And he took no money out of the treasury for him- self, because he was a just man and an upright.' But when a man came to him and said, Give me work for the city; for thy servant is a cunning workman, and skilful in his handicraft, that Bihltuede answered and said, What is thy cunning work to me, and thy skill in the mystery-of thy craft? under'- standest thou the mystery of pursentojobbs? 15. And if the man said, Yea, verily, I understand that mystery, and in this work there is a goodly pursentojobb, as thy servant will make manifest unto thee, then Bihltuede gave him the work to do, and they took counsel together as to the pursentojobb., 16. So the carpenters and the masons, and the men who were cunning to work in iron and in lead and in brass, and in plaster, and the men who made roads came to Bihltuede, and if they were Pahdees or Phyarmen, or Bunkahs among the Phyarmen, or were of the sect of Smalphri among the   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. Dimmnichrats, and understood the nmstery of pursentojobbs, he gave them the work to be done for the city. 17. And without the knowledge of that mystery no man had work given him by Bihltuede. And it came to pass always that the more a man knew of the mystery of pursento: jobbs, the larger were the payments he received from the city tS. So did the city prosper while Bihltuede was overseer, because he was just and upright, and wise in his gener- ation. t19. And after a season he became a great man among the sect of Smalphri, and had a great following amongst them, and he and they gave themselves up to the mystery of pur- sentojobbs. And that mystery became the occupation of Bihltuede and his following, and they studied it by night and worked at it by day. And because it was a great mystery and a blessed, it brought blessings upon all them that pro- duced it. And Bihltuede grew apace. 20. For he had made unto himself friends among the Pahdees, and chiefly of the Phaynyuns among the Pahdees, and had bowed himself down unto them, and pr'actised upon them another great mystery, even the mystery of blabknee. And if he met a Pahdee- he would go with him to a house where they poured out drink offerings and made schyndees, even a pour-the-rows, or a jinnmihl, and give to each man there a portion of the drink offering called in the tongue of that country inanshuger or of that other drink offering called ouiskhee; so that there was not a pour-the-rows or a jinnmihl in Gotham where Bihltuede was not a great man among the Pahdees. 21. And after he had become a great man among them, he joined himself Unto two other men of the sect of Smalphri among  the Dimmichrats, Peter whose surname was Beezoueni, and Khonnullee who was called Shpridic,  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8280-00000017"/> 34      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. 22. Now Slipridic was a Pahdee, and Peter whose surname was Beezoueni was the son of a Pahdee wlich had kept a pour-the-rows in Gotham where the Pahdees and the sect of Smalphri among the Dimmichrats were used to g'ather them- selves together. And Peter and Slipridic were likewise great men among the Pahdees. 23. Now these men were not Pharisees, neither were they Scribes. And they said among themselves, Behold, we need a man who is a Scribe that he may write proclamations for us and make speeches to the people, and that he may be a counsellor to us, so that we may break no law whereby we might be cast into prison; for they said, it would be a wick- ed thing for us to do that; whereby we might be cast into prison. 24. And -they found Abraham whose surname was Hoax- umall that was a scribe and a lawyer. And they said, Lo, here is Hoaxumall, who is a scribe and a lawyer, and cun- ning to' write proclamations and to make speeches, and whose counsel will keep us out of prison; let us take him. 25. And Hoaxumall had not been of the sect of the Smalphri among the, Dimmichrats, but of another sect of Smalphri which-waged war upon the Dimlmichrats. But they said unto him, Join thyself unto us, and it shall be for thine advantage. 26. And he joined them. And they told the Pahdees to make him  governor of the city; and they made him -governor. And this Hoaxumall was that governor of Gotham which made the oration when the statue of Corne. lius was set up. 27. Now when Bihltuede, and Slipridic, and Peter, whose surname was Beezoueni, and Hoaxumall saw that they were great men in the eyes of the Pahdees, they, said one to another, Let us conspire together to keep the city in our  hands, and in the hands of them that are of our following. ' \        THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.      85 And they conspired together and made a confederacy, and they called the name of this confederacy Thur Ing; and they and their following, and whoever would conspire with them to keep the governing of the city in their hands only, were all in Thur Ing together. And so it came to pass that the people of Gotham, and the houses and the lands, and the goods of the merchants, and the artificers, and the lawyers thereof, and chiefly the treasury of the city were in the hands of the men of Thur Ing. 28. And thev looked for one among themselves who should be treasurer, and who should pay out the money of the city to the men who understood the mystery of pursento- jobbs. And Bihltuede said, Lo, here is Slipridic, who can tell the truth when that is for his own profit, and that which is not the truth for a like reason. Let us make it his profit to tell the truth to them who are in Thur Ing, and that which is not the truth to them which are not in Thur Ing, and let him be treasurer. 29. So Slipridic was made treasurer of Gotham: and he paid out the money from the city treasury to them that were in Thur Ing, and that understood the mystery of pur- sentojobbs. 30. And the blessing of heaven was upon the men that were in Thur Ing, and chiefly upon Bihltuede, and Peter whose surname was Beezoueni, and Hoaxumall, and Slipri- dicl because they were just men and upright, so that whereas they had been poor men, they increased in substance and waxed rich, although they were neither merchants, nor artificers, nor husbandmen, and neither toiled nor spun, and did nothing but rule the city and say who should receive money from the treasury. And when men saw this they said, Lo, here is a mystery. These men give themselves to governing the city, becausA they love the people, and they wax rich thereby. Behold the rewr4d of the righteous!  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8280-00000018"/> 36      THE CHRONICLES OFP GOTHAM. 81. And it came to pass that allthe affairs of the city and of the country -round about fell into the hands of the men that were in T'hur Ing, and it was through them that many lawgivers and the governor of that province were chosen. And after a time the men of Thur Ing made Bihltuede one of the chief lawgivers of the piovince.  32. And when the merchants, and the altificers and they that took money on the roads and the men of Ouahlstlrete. saw this, they sought to be friends with the chief men of Thur Ing, and to have them joined unto themselves in their business.                      i 33. For they said, These men are wise, and jnst, and up- right; and peradventure if they join themselves unto us, a blessing will follow them. And do they not make the law- givers and the governor? and is not Bhiltuede himself one of the chief lawgivers of the province? and if wejoin them unto us, the laws will be made for our advantage. And so it was that all they which joined the chief men of Thur Ing unto them did prosper, and the laws were made for their advan- ta g e .   -    - -aI 34. And whereas in the City of Gotham all these things were wlrought chiefly through the mystery of pursentojobbs, in the city of the lawgivers they were wrought through the other like mystery of lobbeepeze ht through  35. Wherefore it was that when Jemphrise saw these things, he said unto Daniel, Hearken unto thy servant. Seest jthou not that when one of the chief men' of Thur Ing is joined unto any undertaking, a blessing follows? Let us therefolre make Bhiltuedeand Peter sunamed BeezoLeni as, * one of ourselves, even Durrektahs. 36. And the thing pleased Daniel (for he loved a bless- ing), and he smiled upon Jemphrisc, and said, Let ithe as thou sayest. So Bihltuede andPeter Beezoueni were made DIurrektahs. Likewise 0ls did many other men who took   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM..      37 money on the road and in Ouahlstrete. And blessings fol- lowed, and they all prospered; and Bihltuede and Peter and $lipridic waxed richer and richer day by day. 37. And Jemphrischecame chief ofthem that took money on the Query road; and whereas, other Durrektahs, which were robbers, were content to take money from the people on their roads, Jemphrisc took the road itself from them that had made it, or had bought it, and kept it unto himself and his following. 38. So that after not many days, he that had been of the tribe of Peddullah, which is a small tribe, and of little account, and he that had been one of the laymdux in Ouahl- strete, came to have silver and gold without end, so that in all the land of Unculpsalm, there was no man that spent the silver and the gold of other men like Jemphrisc.  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8280-00000019"/> it8      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. women ofl otham. 7. Because of their garments.  9. Butfind favor in the eyes of ta e men. 10. Jemphrise e onsidereth what he shall do with his posessions. 17. ollowet the eanole of olo- mon. 19. But maketh exceptions. 24. He and Bihltuede and the others of Thur Ing are supreme in Gotham. 1. And after these things, there came certain women to the city 'of Gotham, singing-women and dancing women froln the land of the Pahvoos, and from the land of Jon- wmen were comely -and fair to look upon; and they all painted their eyelids like Jezebel,and they that came from  the land of Jonbool stained their hair yellow, 2. And theirgarments began low and ended high. 3. And whereas other singing   women  and dancing women sang at one time, and danced at another, and some would sing, and others would dance, these women all sang and all danced; and they sang and danced at the same time dancing When they sang, and siangie when  they danced. ' 4  And Fwhen  they sang, they lifteB up their arms, and clapped their hands, that men mighp see that they were comely from the waist upward; andf when they danced, aen miight see that they werh, comely from the waist down- 5. And the words of theil ,iinging. no mab could under-   THE CHRONrCLES OF GOTHAM.      39 stand; for verily they meant nothing; but their dancing meant a great deal, and was understood of all men. 6. And they found favor in the eyes of the men of Gotham. But in the eyes of the women of Gotham, they were naught; and they said, What are these women, that the men should set so much by them? 7. Do they not wear garments that begin low and and end high, which is an abomination, and worketh confusion? Verily, we ourselves, when we go unto a feast, where there are many men to look upon us, wear garments- that begin low, but likewise they end low, even so low tlat a womanfl raiment continueth long after the woman is ended. 8. And this is the rightful fashion of a woman's gar- ments, that the ending shall be conformable to the begin- ning, and the beginning unto the, ending. For when we are by ourselves, in our own chambers, with no men, or only our husbands, to look upon us, our garments begin high and end higher than when we are at a feast. ' But these women that the men of Gotham run after, wear raiment the end of which correspondeth not unto the beginning; and of a truth it seemeth to have neither top nor bottom, but to be all middle. Verily, it is an abomination; and these men of Gotham are possessed of devils. 9. Notwithstanding, the men set none the less by the dancing and singing women, and when they played before the people, the houses were filled with men, young and old, shouting -and clapping their hands, and casting flowers and jewels of gold at their feet; such was the delight that they took in the singing that meant nothing, and the dancing that meant a great deal. Even so, also, did the men of the land of the Pahvoos, and of the land of Jonbool. So that the whole world was filled with the uproar of these women; and their singing and dancing was called, in the tongue of  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8280-00000020"/> 40      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTrAM. the ahioos, as it is spoken in the land of Unculpsalm, 10. Now when Jemphrisc saw the chests full of silver and gold that he had taken from men on the Quer8 y road, and from them that had made that road and had bought it with a price, he said within himself? What shall I do that I may live as becometh a man of such great possessions? ". And JemphQeisc pondered the matter. And he said, I will buy houses, and lands, and ships,and cha'iots, and horses, and precious stones, and I will fare sulloptilously every day...       12. And he bought the houses and the ships, and he dwelt in both; and he went down to his ships dressed in the lai- ment of an officer of the land of Unculpsalm. And albeit he was not an' officer, no man gainsaid him, because he was Jem. phrisc, and because he had great possessions. 13. For in Gothamn if a man had great possessions he might do what was right in his own eyes, even if what was right inl his own eyes would have been wrong in the eyes of other men, if he had not great possessions. 1'4.' And. ',he bought chariotsand horses, and drave about Gotham seated on high in a' great chariot, and with many horses, placed one beforethe other. And the people of Go- tham said, Lo, there is:Jemphl ic riding in a chariot, and with horses that he hath bought with the money which he hath  taken on the Query road, and from them that made the road. 15. And'he bought jewels of gold and precious stones, and wore a breastplate of precious stones, even of one precious stone. And the shining of that stone was seen afar off, and told of the coming of him that wore it. 16. Likewise also did Bihltuede and others of: them in Thur Ing, so that men knew them thereby; and When they saw a man with a breastplate of pr':cions stones, and he was   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.      41 not Jemphrisc, they said, Lo; he is one of them that are of Ihur Ing. 17. Yet was not Jemphrisc content with all these things; and he communed with himself upon his doings and his possessions, and he said, Lo, I am like unto Solomon for my wealth and my wisdom. For have I not shown myself wiser than Daniel and his counsellors, and than Cornelius: and his counsellors? And are not my proverbs better than the, proverbs of Solomon?- And have I not gold, and silver, and precious stones, and chariots, and horses, and all the possessions of Solomon, except the ships that brought him apes and peacocks; and them I need not, for there be apes and peacoaks to be seen of all men daily in the Fifth Heavenue. Moreover, I have the righteousness of David, for have I not taken this Query road even as he took Na- both's vineyard?  18. Howheit in one thing Jemphrise saw that he was not yet like Solomon; for Solomon had seven hundred wives, and three hundred concubines. And he said, Why should I not be like unto' Solomon in all things? Verily I will be like unto him in this matter also; like unto him, but wiser. For after a man hath once had one wife, how can he that is not foolish ever desire to take to himself another'? Wherefore I will skip the wives and begin with the con- cubines.       -             - 19. Yea, verily, I will skip six hundred and ninety and nine of the wives, and begin with three of the concubines. one for every thousand. And I will choose me concubines of dancing women, and singing-women, and women that play before the people. 20. So he bought him an house, even a great house, for the women to dance in, and sing in, and play before the people; and he, filled this house with dancing women and singing women from the land of the Pahvoos, even of the women  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8280-00000021"/> 42      THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM. * whose garments began low and ended high; and' out of these women he chose his concubines. 21. And in one part of this house he had his offices where- in he did his business, and wherein were his scribes and them that kept account, so that he might be near unto the dancing women and the singing women. Thus did Jemphrisc join his business to his pleasure;'for he also was wise in his generation. 22. And he drave through the streets of Gotham, and round about it in the gardens thereof, with his concubines in his great chariot, and with his horses one before the oth- er. , And the people said, Lo, the men who made and bought the Query road, and from whom Jemphrise hath taken it, even as David took the vineyard of Naboth, are paying also for these concubines, for their houses, and for their fine raiment, and for their jewels, and for their feasting. 23, Wherefore men said of Jemphrisc, that he had the righteousness of David, and the wealth, and the wisdom, and the magnificence of Solomon. 24. And Jemphrise was as a king in Gotham; and he and his following, and Bihltuede, and Peter Beezoueni, and Hoaxumall, and Slipridic and their following, ruled in all the country of Mannatton, and there was nothing done in the city but by their sufferance. " 25.' And the men of Gotham, even the merchants, and the lawyers, and the artificers, said unto their sons, Behold Jemphrisc, and Bihltuede, and Peter Beezoueni, and Hoax- umall, and Slipridic, and consider their ways if ye would learn wisdom and prosper. For these be the great ones and the notable, to whom it is given to rule in Gotham, and be the chief men therein. 26. And the young men did so, and considered the ways of Jemphsc, and of Bihltuede, and of them who were of   THE CHRONICLES OF GOTHAM.       43 Thur Ing, and verily so likewise did the young women, learn- ing wisdom and the way wherein to prosper. 27. And the rest of the doings of Jemphrisc, and of Bihl- tuede, Whose surname was Bigzhics, and Peter, whose sur- name was Beezoueni, and Hoaxumall the governor of the city, and Slipridic the treasurer, and theirfollowing, and of the other great ones of that city, and of the Pahdees, and of the riot that they made in Gotham, and of the breaking of Thur Ing, are they not written in the Second Book of the Chronicles of Gotham? END OF BOOK FIRST.   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>