<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8356">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Life, Adventures, and Elopement of Emily La Croix, the Poisoner ; Also, An Account of Jean La Croix, Her Brother, Better Known in California as Leon Gabralli ... </title>
            <author >Withbeck, Trebor R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC8356</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The life, adventures, and elopement of Emily La Croix, the poisoner ; also, An account of Jean La Croix, her brother, better known in California as Leon Gabralli ...</title>
                  <author >Withbeck, Trebor R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >50 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >M.A. Milliette</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Baltimore </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1856">[1856]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-10-08">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The life, adventures, and elopement of Emily La Croix, the poisoner ; also, An account of Jean La Croix, her brother, better known in California as Leon Gabralli ...</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (Cover) " xml:id="VAC8356-00000001"/>   ;1$s '  1TH TEE P R. . *EM !r LIFfl ADYENTraGES, AS]):EJ-QiPEMEE V I     - ON - o DIVrI ** 11. *^ EI SM owe An d  it:w^ '.c        : I ** ' eli gi i s 1     O i S;B, ;, f-t  i'1 . B ^EtPR%:NEW     X I' n God "X 71^ ^' TTi" BA          TAL L o   &#xD;<pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8356-00000002"/> THE LIFE, ADVENTURES, AND ELOPEMENT OF EMILY LA CROIX, THE  POISONER. ALSO, AN ACCOUNT OF JEAN LA CROIX, HER BROTHER, BETTER KNOWN IN CALIFORNIA AS LEON GABRALLI, AND WHO WAS POISONED BY HIS SISTER, IN ORDER TO SECURE THE IMMENSE REWARD OFFERED BY THE AUTHORITIES FOR HIS HEAD. ALSO AN ACCOUNT OF HENRI LA CROIX,         1 THEIR FATHER. THE SMUGGLER CHIEF, WHO RECEIVED HIS DEATH  FROM THE HAND OF HS OWN DAUGHTER.  In WHOLE- COMPLETE IN ONEB VOLX7      I B EDITED BY THE REV. TREBOR R. WITIIBECK. PUBLISHED BY M. A. MILLIETTX, BALiTIMORE, PHLADELPHA, NEW YORK AND BUFFALO  &#xD;<pb n="0Illustration-21" xml:id="VAC8356-00000003"/> ENTERED according to the Act of Congress, in the year 1856, by M. A. MLLIETTE, -in the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States in and for the Eastern District of Pennsylvania.   THE "FE, ADVNTURES, AND ELOPEMENT OF  EMLY LA CROIX, THE POISONER. WE PRESENT TO THE READER, A short sketch of the Life of EMILY LA CROIX, the manuscript of which was found in her trunk, at  Hotel, San Francisco, and is supposed to have been written on the voyage to America. That the reader may takewarning by her fearful fate, is the ear- nest prayer of the editors and it is this reason alone that induces him to present the work to the public. Trusting that it may do some good,- he takes his leave, and with a sorrowful heart, he re- mains,-Your humble servant, TREBOR R. WITHBECK. "France, la bielle France! again I leave your shores, perhaps never to return," were the words I uttered, as the gallant ship spread every sail to the breeze, and " walked the water like a thing of life." In a few hours we bad lost sight of the land; and as I turned to descend the steps to the cabin, a small locket fell from my bosom to the floor. H picked it up, and with a heart filled with emotion, I rushed into the cabin. Tlere, seated at a table, which was screwed down to the floor to prevent it from upsetting I re- viewed my past life. Suddenly the idea struck me, it would be well to write it down, and obeying the impulse of the moment, I drew out the paper and ink; and the following short chapter is the result. I was born in Paris, France, in thb year 1832. Till the time I reached my eighth year I met with nothing worthy of being noted dlown in this place. I attended the village school, and received what most people would call a good education. -Suddenly, my bro- ther, who had been absent for some years, returned home. He 21  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8356-00000004"/> 22        THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES was both an atheist and a republican, and he soon led me to adopt hIis opinions. lie remained with us for several years; but one day he suddenly disappeared, and when he returned, I had reached my sixteenth year. I was very beautiful, both in form and feature, and 1iknew it. I was proud of my beauty, and this pride ruined me. The young men of the neighborhood came to my father's house very often on purpose to see me, although they pretended that they had business to transact with him. But I was not to be deceived thus, for I noticed that they usually came when he was absent. Several offers were made me, but I refused them all. It was about this time that my brother returned. He was accon- panied by a young man, whom he introduced as Count de Boume. The title won me; for when, a few days afterwards, the Count re- quested me to return with him to Paris, as his mistress, I did so. We lived together for about three months, when the Count grew tired of me, and one day after a violent altercation, he threatened to turn me over to his valet de chambre. I laughed at his threats, and this only made bimn the more enraged. The only weaipon that a woman has is her tongue, and I used it incessantly. Suddenly, and unable to restrain his passion, he sprang from his chair, and struck me to the floor. When I recovered Omy senses, I found my- self in the arms of his valet. It was enough. Fired almost to madness, I sprang up, and seizing a pistol I entered the Count's room. He was no longer there. I waited a few hours, hoping, tevery moment that he would return; but he never came. At length I resolved to seek him. I put on' a. suit of his clothes, and as he \':s about my size, they fitted me very well. Thrusting the pistol in my pocket, I left the house and directed my steps towards a club of which he was a member. I soon reached the house, and ascending the-stairs, I entered the club-room. The Count was st.#nd- ing in the centre of the room, talking to several persons. I walked to the window and listened. Hearing the Count utter my name, I turned round and watched him. "What will you take for her?"I heard one of them say. "Why, I value her at ten thousand francs, and you well know that Emily is worth it. Come, there are four of us here. Let us play at dice. Each of you will pay me three thousand francs, and the winner shall have her."     . "Agreed!" they cried, and walked to the table. "One word," said I, approaching them, and laying my hand on C the dice box. "If, Count de Bournte, you value your mistress at ten thousand francs, at what price do you value your worthless life?" "What, Emily! You here?" exclaimed the Count.   OF EMLY LA CRObL.         23 "Aye, here!" was my reply; and drawing the pistol firom my pocket, I pulled the trigger: The powder flashed in the pan, and that was all. "Murdress!" cried the Count, and he struck me. The blow was immediately returned by one of the young men, and the Count fell bleeding to the floor. I turned to the young man to thank him; and his appearance so pleased me that I requested him to go home with me. He did so, and remained all night. In the morning he received a challenge from the Count, and was obliged to leave me. I cut off a lock of his hair, and told him that I would neter forget him. He smiled as I said this, and then left me to prepare for the- meeting. At noon the parties met, and both, fell dead at the first fire. Thyj perished the Count de Bourne and Henri Chappell. As soon as I heard the result of the meeting, I resolved to leave France. My brother engaged a passage for me to America, and with his assistance and a ladder placed at the window, I actually eloped with my own brother and soon was in New York. For-three years I remained in that city, without meeting with any thing wor- thy of notice. At length I became acquainted with a young man by the name of Robert Bramwell.-But I cannot write more, and if I could---  Here the manuscript abruptly breaks off. The remainder of the story will be found in the following pages. v          , .s-  &#xD;<pb n="24 (Illustration) -25" xml:id="VAC8356-00000005"/> 24L    MTHE LIE AND ADVENTURES ELOPE N  OF EMLY LA -  *1 HE'.,  ELPEEN OF EML LACOXWflHKBOHb   OF EMLY LA CROIX          25  CHAPTER I. THE STUDENTS--THE DECEIVED-THE BLOW-THE BROI2HER-THE DUEL AND ITS RELULT. Truly in my youth I suffered much extremity for love."--SHAKSPEARE. ts The ways of Providence are dark and intricate, Puzzled in mazes, and perplexed with evils; The understanding traces them in vain, Nor sees with how much art the windings run, Nor Where the regular confusion ends." "HERE'S to the health of Robert ramwell! May he live to see a bright old age; may he never know what it is to want a dol- lar, and may he always have kind friends to help him spend it, as they have now helped me to spend a fortune. To your health, \ Robert Bramwell ;'- and the speaker raised the wine glass to his lips, while with a slight sneer he bowed his head to the subject of his remarks, who -was eyeing him with a sarcastic smile, as he sat leaning back in his chair, and kicking against the legs of the table with his feet. The above words were spoken by one of a party of young men, six in number, who were seated in one of the private rooms of IIotel, Broadway, New York.  The table was covered with bottles of wine, wine-glasses, and baskets of cigars. The windows were wide open, for it was a hot, sultry afternoon in July. The speaker was Thomas Livingston, a member of one of the mnost aristocratic families in the Union, and a Southerner by birth. He, as well as his companions, was attired in the most rich and fashionable stvle; and what was somewhat remarkable, their clothes were all of the same colour and cut. Their features showed marks of dissipation, and two or three of them  showed by their quick restless manner, that the wine was beginning to affect them. As-- he concluded, Livingston turned his-glass upsidedomwn on the table, and seated himself." "Many thanks-same to you," said Bramwell, a  tall dark fea-  tured man, of about twenty years of age; and without drinking he laid the glass on the table.               . "'What is the matter? Why don't you drink?" cried another, William Ashton by name, and whose rolling eyes showed that the wine was rapidly making an impression on him. "You are not quarrelling, are you?"  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8356-00000006"/> 26        THE LIFE AND cADVENTURES I N Quarrelling, Indeed! said Livingston; bah we have never! quarrelled-, have we, Mr. Robert Bra'mwell?" *t ^ Of course not. Why should we quarrel Y9 -r 1' Come, come! no mistering here," exclaimed another, u Don't We all belong to  college! Haven't we dined at the same ta- ble, and slept in the same house, for several years, and don't we all separate to-night, never, perhaps to meet again?" , "Some of us will meet again," said Bramwell, "aye, and to- morrow, too; although one at least does not suspect it/' and he darted a rapid look at Livingston, who returned it with one ofide- fiance. It was plain to all that an ill-feeling existed between the two young men, and that something serious would take place before they parted. The cause of that ill-feeling we Will endeavor to ex- plain. Thomas Livingston had come to New York some five years be- fore. to nattend college. There he met Robert Bramwell, who attended the same college, and a friendship had sprung up be- tween them which promised to'last through life. For three years they remained firm friends, but suddenly a coolness arose' out of an introduction to a young lady, a native of France, 'Whom Bram- well had been visiting, and they ceased to visit each other's room. For some eight months Bramwell kept away from the house in which the young lady resided, and perhaps he would not have en- tered it again, had she not sent for him. From her own lips he then -learned that she had been seduced by Livingston, and induced to elope with him; and now finding that he would not fulfil the promise he had made of marrying her, she wished to enter a con- vent. From this step she -was dissuaded by Bramwell, who took her to a farm which a friend of his possessed on Long Island, and there left her. None knew where he had been, but all noticed that his few weeks' absence-had wrought an entire change in him. His laugh appeared forced, his step was more firm, and long after the midnight the lamp was seen burning in his chamber. From avoid- ing Livingston, he now sought his society, and though they never visited each other's room, all but the closest observer took them to be the best friends in the world. Livingston never alluded to his victim save once, aid that was to express his surprise at her mys- terious disappearance. He did not notice the" errible look that passed over Bramwell's features as he mentioned, her name, nor the shudder that shook his frame when he left him. Matters passed on, and at length the day approached when the college doors should be closed'to them for ever. At the examination the"-students formed a resolution to meet at some private place, where they could   OF FMTL-Y LA CROIX.         27 drink each other's health. and take their leave over-the.,wmne-glass. Six, among them Livingston and Bramwell, separated from tho others and went to   Hotel, wherewe now find them. -  ' H-Ia! ha! laughed Bramwel, again emptying his glass, " alft-r all I was the only one that gained a degree Thomas ivingston, do you remember our wager-if one of us failed to obtain a degreu, he was to pay to the other five hundred dollars? What good haJ all your boasting done you? Your father's wealth could not bribe, the committee; your learning was not equal to the task ;-and 1, in Spite of your malice, sneers, and pretended friendship, have gained what you could not-the prize of superior scholarship-a degree. Come, my hand is eager to clutch-the five hundred dollars. Would it were your heart!" l He is drunk'!" cried several of the students in astonishment, for they could hardly believe their ears. A scowl, black as the midnight sky whenthe storm fiend is marching across it,-rcovered the features of Livingston; but hoping to return back the scornful words he repressed his anger, and drawing forth-his pocket-book he flung several bank notes across the table, and said:- "For a smaller sum than that I won the affection ,of Emily La Croix,your best friend." "'Liar'" cried Bramwell, starting to his feet; "the wealth of 'worlds could not have won, her affections, unless her heart went with them. Had the wealth of the Indies, the riches of Peru been offered ber, she would have spurned. them all. You curse, you, Thomas Livingston, who love to boast of your desceent from an Indian princess, you seduced, her under, a promise of marriage. More-you told her that H who loved her more than life itself- that I was married to another. False friend! deceitful villain! the woman vou seduced, and of whom you speak so lightly, is now my wife! Take that, and return it if you dare; and seizing his wine-glass he dashed it with all his strength into his face, and with- out waiting a moment, he bent over the narrow table, and struck him a tremendous blow on the forehead, which felled hbm to the floor. The blow was given with such force that Bramwell fell for- ward, and unable to gain his balance, he fell to the -floor, carrying the table -with-him.                 , In a moment the whole room was in confusion. The table, was flung aside and Livingston, his face covered with blood, raised to to his feet, and seated in a chair. In a few minutes he recovered somewhat frotm the effects of the blow, and wiping away the blood with his hand, he glared fiercely around the room until his eye met those of his enemy's. Hastily staggering to his feet, he drew  &#xD;<pb n="28-29 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8356-00000007"/> 28        THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES a glove from his pocket and flung it into his face, saying at the same time in a voice hoarse with passion:- "To-morrow, Elysian Fields, Hobpken, at six in the morning.' "I will be there," said Bramwell, picking up the glove. " gay your prayers-ere you meet me, for just so sure as we meet, just so sure still you die." - At this moment the door opened, and a young man whose air and features proclaimed him to be a Frenchman, entered the room. For a moment he gazed around him with curiosity; then suddenly stepping forward he asked:- "Which of you gentlemen answers to the name -of Thomas Liv- ingston?"  There was a moment's pause ere Livingston, who had fallen back into the chair, replied, "That is my name." The stranger drew a card frotm his pocket and threw it into his lap. " 'My name, as you will perceive, said he, " is Jean La Croix, I amn the brother of the girl you seduced, and I have left my native land to take a brother's vengeance on the seducer of his sister." "And I am prepared to give you satisfaction," said Livingston, whose face was very pale. "Not till after our meeting," said Bramwell, stepping forwar(d. The young Fr-enchanwt grasped his hand. "Ah," said he, - vou are the generous, noble-hearted man that-" His emotion would not pelrmnit him to say more, and he turned aside to conceal the tears which flowed down his cheeks. Bram- well seized his arm, and led him to the door - "Remember," said he, pausing'a moment, ' to-morrow at six. -You second will find mine at my house this evening."  Livingston made no reply-he Was insensible. -    *    *   *   u At six o'clock in the morning they met, and Livingston fell severely wounded. The bullet had passed through his side just above the heart; an inch lower and he would have been a corpse. "The first turn of Fortunes's wheel has been favourable to you," he muttered as Bramwell approached him. ' The next turn will be mine. Beware our next meeting, Robert Bramwell beware!" A,    O EMLY LA CR:IN.        29 JEAN LA CROIX.  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8356-00000008"/> 80         LIFE AND ADVENTURES -CHAPTER II. FARM-THE CONVERSATION-A BROTHER lS   VENGEANCE-THE COMMAND.  "It was a chosen spot of fertile land, Emongst wild hills set, like a little nest, As if it had by Nature's cunning hand Been ehoycely piclked put from all the rest, And layed forth ensample for the best."--SPENcIRi. ABOUT one mile from the town of H   ,Long Island, stood the little farm-house in which Emily La Croix-or, as we should now call -her-Mrs. Bramwell, resided. It was a beautiful little place, but one story and a half high, and stood somewhat retired from the road. - It was surrounded on all sides by trees, whose huge branches effectually protected it from the heat of the sun in summer, and the terrible storms in winter. - Here, two days after the duel between Bramwell- and Livirigston, we find Jean La Croix, his sister, and Bramwell. "What news?" inquired Jean, as Bramwell eagerly perused one of the New York daily papers. "Any thing relating to that little affair?"  "Not much," said Bramwell.  ' The paper merely states that Livingston will soon be well. I don't see how it was that the bul- let did not pass through his heart." - "You aimed an inch higher than you should have done," said Jean. "It is now my turn to meet him. Nothing but his life will satisfy me, and that I'll -have, if I have to fight him breast to breast."  Emily shuddered. She alone knew her brother's daring spirit. "I have been thinking of going to Europe," said Bramwell, " but I intend to remain here until Livingston has recovered from his wound, and then to meet him again." 6s I beg your pardon," said Jean, coldly. "-It is my turn next. What, would you rob me of my right to meet him?" he added, as Bramwell shook his head. "I tell you, I must meet him." "Well, well," said Bramwell, who knew the speaker's hasty tem- per, "have it your own way. Emily, the weather is very fine; suppose we walk in the garden." "Not now," said Emily.  "Go," said Jean, in a tone wlich sounded like a comnmand. ' Come, I will go with you.'   OF EMLY LA CROIX.          31 CHAPTER IIT. THE SICK CHAMBER OP THOMAS LIVINGSTON--REVENGE-THE ITALIAN DI)OCTOR-A TALE OF BLOOD-THE PLOT AND ITS DEFEAT-BLOOD FOR BLOOD. "Throughout my brief but changeful life, With error and misfortune rife; I ardently have sought to find In the world's crowd some kindred mind. ^*      *       *e Le X  A But I have learned the bitter truth, Which early chlls the hope of youth, That it is wisdom to repress The gushing tide of tenderness Which the young soul would lavish round."--AN-oN. ( Wheresoe'er the shrieking victim hath Poured forth his blood beneath the assassin's knife, Some hand erects a cross of snouldering lath." a "ET us take the reader to the chamber of Thomas Livingston. At the moment we enter, the wounded duellist is lying on his bed, and by his side stood a tall, fierce-looking man, whose dark fea- tures and air proclaimed that he was an Italian. Mark him well for he is a doctor, and is possessed of mnore knowledge than any physician in the country. His name is Luigi Giotto, better known perhaps as Doctor Glotto.-Let us listen to their conversation. "Well, what do you think?" exclaimed Livingston, iimpatiently, and throwing his arms restlessly about. The doctor- made no re- ply, but stood for a moment calmly surveying him. "Come, come! are you dumb? You do not suppose I hired you to play the part of a dumb statue? What do you think?" "That in a month you will be able to go out, providing you fol- low my advice." ' And that advice- what is it?" "That you make no attempt to stir until I tell you to." What!" exclaimed Livingston, " would you have me remain- motionless like a corpse, while that accursed Bramwell is walking the earth as happy as a bird! I cannot lay quietly here when I think of him. I tell you, doctor, that you must cure me in a week. Why, man, there is money to be earned, and I have not yet to learn that the Italian god is gold. A thousand dollars if you put me on my legs in a week.'" "Impossible!" replied the Italian; "but in i fortnight-" Ah! I have gained tmw wee-ks out of the month," said Living-  + a  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8356-00000009"/> 832       THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES ston. "Come, say that .you can cure me in a week, and if you keep your word the money is yours." "Again I say, itis impossible," said the Italian, firmly, although - his eyes glistened at the large amount offered him. ' Well, well, I suppose I must do as you tell me," said- Living- ston, after a moment's pause; but every hour will appear a cen- tury to me." "But why are you in such a hurry to get well?" inquired the doctor, after a moment's pause. "Why?" said Livingston, sternly; 'because I have received a blow, and I do not want it to be said that any man struck Tho- mas Livingston and lived." "Ah, you seek revenge," said the Italian, his eye flashing like lightning.           + - "Yes, and I will have it," was the reply. * But how?" inquired the doctor. "If you know not, T can tell you. There are a hundred ways by which you can kill him, with- out any one suspecting the means of his death. I can send death to him by a peach, or by placing a few grains of a certain powder in his favorite book. I can kill him by sending him a letter, or by touching him with myihand If you would be revenged, pay me my price, and I will lend you my aid." "Ahy you would have me play the part of de Med--" "Silence!" exclaimed the doctor, gazing rapidly round the room. "Is the death of Robert Bramwell worth ten thousand dollars?"     v  '  ' You-charge high, doctor!" "But consider the risk I run," returned Giotto. "We will speak of that to-morrow," said Livingston. ".I little thought two years ago, that in so short a time I should be plotting the death of one whom I always looked upon as my best friend." "'And do -you believe in friendship?" said Giotto, sneeringly. Yolung man, I have seen more of the world than you have-have moved lobnger on the stage of life, and during that time I have dis- covered that there is no such thing as true friendship. Every one in this world is moved by self-interest if " "Spare me your sermon," said Livingston, witlHa yawn. "Were you ever married?" ' Married!"' exclaimed the Italian- ay, and to a lovely crea- ture. You might have searched the broad earth in vain to find her  equal. The poets of my native land- used to write her name and place it under their pillows, and painters were proud to paint her as the Madonna. Oh! how- I loved her. - But she deceived me- mark you, Thomas Livingston-my best friend won her affections   OF EMLY LA CROIX.         33 from me, and-they fled together. I went to the church, and knee- ing down before the altar Iswore the Italian's oath of vengeance, lnd dipped my dagger in the holy water. For weeks Ahy search was in vain; but at last I learned that they had joined the banditti led by Cascotto. - A large reward was offered for the arrest of the chief, and his most bitter enemy was Count Julian. The bandit chief heard of the reward, and with that-daring peculiar to him, he offered ten thousand Venice sequins for the head of the Count. I must tell you that I was one of-two twiins, and that my brother had disappeared wpFtn -but five years old. Well, I knew how to reach, the heart of the chief, and I resolved to do so. One dakr night I went to the Count's palace, and in ten minutes-I left it with his head in a bag. In two hours I was at the foot of the mountain, and quickly ascending I was Qon challenged by the sentinel. "Who goes there?" he asked. "A friend," said jE. '4I wish too see your chief." " The chief is asleep, and it would not do to disturb him for a trifle. Is your business of importance?'" Yes. Lead me to him."  The sentinel obeyed, and in a few minutes I stood by his side. -He .was lying on the ground, but as we approached he sprang up, and drew his dagger.  ' What seek ye here?" he asksd. "You-have offered ten thousand sequins for the head of Count Julian."     '      '     . ' I have."                            l "You have a member of vour band by the name of Jules Carles." "He is my lieutenant."              - "Would you give his head for the Count's?" Yes." Enough," said I; and opening the bag I suffered the head to fall to the ground. "Here is the head." "Tell Carles to come here," said the chief, to the sentinel; "and hark you, breathe not a word Of what has occurred." X In a few minutes we heard a step a pproaching; and in obedience to the orders of the- chief I concealed myself behind a tree. "Well, captain, your orders," were Carles' first words. ' Give 'me your arms." Caries, with a look of surprise, obeyed. K 'Kneel," said the chief. He did so. I approached, and drew my dagger. Caries started up as he saw me, but with a cry of joy I plunged the dagger through his heart. The chief stood with folded arms looking sternly on. As Caries fell, I turned to him. "Will you let me join your band?"I asked. "With pleasure. Can I do any thing else for you?" WU . 1 U5 sk. .;.  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8356-00000010"/> 34        THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES "Yes; by giving me Teresa." "She is-dead. You can have her body, if you wish. "I do not want it," said I. "I want to tell you a secret. Is there any one near?" 'No one. What is it?" ' This," said I; and I plunged my dagger into his side. In a moment his head was in my bag, and I proceeded to search his person. By the light of the moon I saw a small strawherry on his right a'rm, and with a low cry of horror I started up. I had slain my twin brother."  "But what did you do with the head?" "Carried it to the authorities, and got the reward," was the re- ply. "Was I not fearfully revenged?" "Fearfully," was the reply. "And you would aid me to take Bramwell's life?"   -  "I will if you pay me my price l14 "And that is  "Ten thousand dollars." "You will have to wait for it then." "How long?"    .  "Till my father's death." "But what security shall I have that you will pay me at hia death , "My word of honor?" The Italian threw himself back in a chair, and laughed. "Your word?"*  "Why not?" said Livingston. "I am a gentlemaln." "Say rather a would-be murderer," was the--reply. "To my mind, at your father's death you would forget that such a person as Luigi Giotto ever existed." "B Put what better security ,can I give you? "A written one, which will be returned to you on the receipt of the money." "But how are we to proceed?' e "Leave that to me," was the reply. "Have you any objections to my occupying this room a few days?" *"For what purpose?" "As a labratory." "Pah, would you-poison me with your villanous compounds?" "Well, never mind, then, returned the doctor. I must leave you now, but you may expect me to-morrow. Good day;" and the Italian left the room.  "  Ah," he muttered, as he entered his own house, "he will pay me at his father's death, will he? I must see the old man, and it   OF EMLY LA CROIX.         35 would surprise me if he were to die a few days after my visit. And now -to prepare the poison." Saying this he passed up the stairs, and entered a small room on the second floor. After making a fire in the huge fire-place, he took from a small iron safe several bottles, and laid them on the table. Then fastening a glass mask carefully over his face, he.  proceeded to pour the contents of the bottles into a small iron bowl, which he placed on the fire. In a few minutes the room was filled with a powerful perfume, which ascended higher and higher. The doctor now took a small glass rod and stirred the contents of the iron vessel rapidly for several minutes. Suddenly, one of the legs of the stool broke from under him, and the Italian fell, striking the mask against the corner of the fire-place with such force that it was shivered to atoms. Instantly he clapped his hand to his / mouth, and rushed towards the window. Before he could reach it 2 he fell, and in a moment he was a corpse. The soul of Luigi Giotto was standing before his Maker's throne to answer for his fearful misdeeds-        - Performed in life's dark journey."  8 &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8356-00000011"/> 36        THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES CIIAPTER IV. TE CONVERSATION-MUTRDER OP -ROBERT BRAMWELL, AND THE ES- CAPE OF THE MURDERER-THE BROTHER AND SISTER-T- HE DE- PARTURE. "It is concluded:-Banqluo, thy soulls flight If it find heaven, must find it out to-night."- MACBETH. THREE months have passed away since the conclusion of our last chapter. Again we take the reader to the farm-house, and in the same room where we saw them last, we find Emily, Jean and Bram- well. Emily's features wear a scornful expression, and occasion- ally she turns her dark eyes to her brothelr, and addresses him in French, a language with which Bramwell is unacquainted. The latter person is seated in a chair, near a table, upon which lay several lettelrs and newspapers. His fce is very pale, and his lips tremble as he speaks. Let us listen to their conversation. "I tell you, Emily," said her husband, " that what you ask is impossible. You lknow that I love yom, and you- kn-ow that I awn always ready to do aniy thing that is reasonable. Were I to tell mny father of our marriage, he would stop my allowance at once and cast me adrikupon the world. -Then, dear Emily, let me ask you what would Wcome of us?" "Ask him, EnEmily," said Jean in French, "what property he will possess at his father's death." "Three plantations, two thousand slaves, a number of shares in the Pacific bank, and a very large amount in ready money," re- plied Bramwell. "I have heard my father say, that he owns more property than any other man in the country. Now were I to dis- close our marriage, he would will all this property to his relatives, and leave me nothing."  -  "( But your father may live many years yet," said .mily. "Heaven grant he may," said the young man, fervently. "And why should I wish his death? He allows me five thousand dollars a year, and surely that is enough to supply -our wants." At this moment the door opened, and a servant entered the room. "What is the matter?" cried Bramwell, who saw from his man- ner that something had happened. "Nothing as yet," was the hurried reply. "I come to tell you' there are several men prowling around the house .and I am sure they are here for no good purpose."   OF EMLY LA CROIX.  Perhaps they are sportsmen," said Bramwell. "And-what should( you fear. I have not an enemy in the world,. a You forget Livingston," observed Jean. "Anld y o forget that he has gone to Europe," said the young man. "Leave   the room, William." Tle servantadic so, but hardly had the door closed behind him, The :ervn     -but har when a man sprang through the open window into theroom. He was inmmediately followed by two others armed with rifles. ; You here?T' cried Bramwell, springing to his feet, as he recog- nised in the features of the first his deadly enemy, Livingstn. "Ay, Thomas Livingston your humble servant,' replied the other, bowing mockingly  - "I told you that we should meet again, ana you see that I have hcept my word." 'Scoundrel!" cried Bramwell, "leave the housethis instan t or I wh call my servants, and have you flung through the windo ivingston drew a pistol from his pocket and levelled it atthe speaker. W'ould you murder me?" cried the young man, starting. Why not? This world is not large enough for both of us, and one must give place to the other. But words are- but empty air. I came here to take your life, and intend to do so." Yor  u must fight for it then " said Bramwell, and he rushed forward. Livinagston suffered him to approach within three feet of him ere he fired. With a low groan of anguish he staggered and fl into Jean's arms, and at the same moment the three men sprang through the window and darted of. A^re you hurt?" asked Jean, his face pale with horror. "H am dyfhg," replied the voung man; and hardly had the words passed his 'lips, when his mouth filled with blood, a shiver shook his frame, and Robcl t Bramwell was a corpse. 4'Run' for the surgeon, " exclaimed Emily; and as the servant darted into the room, her brother added, "It is useless-he is dead." Dead!" said Ernily; and for a moment she was silent. But strange to say. no tears of grief filled her eyes and if she was Si- lent it was because the eyes of the servant were upon her. Send-him away," she said in French*. Her brother wa ed his hand, and the servant left the room. "But three months married, and a widow," said Jean. "This ends all our schemes at once, Emily. We must fly." II Flv! an4 why." 6, Of what use *ould it be for us to remain here?" answered her brother. "Know you not that when the father hears of his son s death, he will come here, and we shall have to undergo a long cross  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8356-00000012"/> 38        THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES examination before him and the coroner. You cannot prove your marriage, for the certificate is lost; we know not the name of the clergyman who united you, and there were no witnesses. Being foreigners we shall be looked upon as suspicious characterl, and -" * "Be it as you say," said Emily. "Let there be no secrets be- tween us. You are an apt pupil of the forger Louis Heart, my dear brother; and, to tell you the truth, I am almost glad that Bramwell is dead; for I was growing tired of the Marriage state. Brother, have I not played my part well. "You have indeed," replied Jean, with a look of admiration. -In France the mistress of Count de Bourffe; a cast-off mistress, you come to America, and assuming the guise of a virtuous young -female, you become the mistress of Thomas Livingston; growing tired of him, yu marry Robert Bramwell. My dear sister, I con- gratulate you on your address." "Many thanks," said Emily. "You too have played your part well on the stage of life. In our youthful days we knew the stings of poverty, and we vowed to stifle every good feeling in order to gain wealth. But come, we must prepare for oilr departure." "And the- sooner we set about it the better it will be for us. Here is Bra nwell's pocket-book. Let us see how much it contains" and he rapidly counted the bills. "Eight hundred and fifty dol- lars," he added; " that will be four hundred and twenty-five dol- lars a piece. His watch I take to be worth albout two hundred- dollars; but if we sold it, it would not fetch more than one hun- dred and twenty-five dollars., I will keep the, watch, and give you eighty dollars for your share. This diamond ring and breast-pin I will keep, and give you in return fifty dollars. O Are you satis- fied?" "Perfectly satisfied," replied his sister, thrusting the bills into her pocket. "We must now call the servants, and bid them watch by the body till morning. You will tell the coachman to get out the carriage-or stay, suppose you play his part to-nivht?" "I'will," said the young man, and he left the room. - In-a few minutes the servants entered, and under the direction of imily, whose eyes were filled with a few crocodile tears, they carried the body to the bed-room in which the deceased slept. Hardly had they done so, when Jean entered. "Every thing is ready, and fortune favors us," he said in French. "The coachman is lying drunk in the stable, and the carriage is at gate. Are you ready?" "But the servants -" "Have already promised to watch here all night. D Come;" and casting one last glance at .the body, they left the room.   3U OF EMLY LA CROIX.' e In a few hOnrA they reached New"York, and on arriving at'the ..Ib onrithey racedNew"Y Astor 11ouse they learned that a vessel was to leave for London Whe for lowing.dav. HereEmily learned that Jean intended to re- main in the ct, and that if she Went she would be obliged to re- turn as she came-alone. But why remain here ?" she asked, as her brother handed her the passage ti hicthI he had just purchased. '  "Oh, I shall not remain here long, was his reply.' I intend to leave in a few days for California. I shall see you safe on oard, however," he added,  and will wite to    breyou as soo as I rrive in San Francisco. There is the bell ringing: let us to breakfast, and thenho, fr the ship which is to carry you to England, and from thence to Frdince      ndi  orwek   iiY  a  aea At noon-the vessel sailed, and in four eeks Emly w safe t her father's house.       ,   -.- CHAPTER V. IBE BMUGaGLR CulEM'a, -TII SPY THE MUR  nEII-in  DEPARTURE SMUGGLERS   FOR CALIFORNIA.  When, in the vale of years, I backward look, Ald miss such numbers-numbers, too, of such, Firmer in health, and gree in teir age, And stricter on their guard, and better far, 'ho play ife's subtile gamne- scarce believe still -survive.71 ON AG1T THO0UGHTS. you have'done gloriously, said the father of Emily La Croix, as he listened to his daughter's rcital of what had happened to her in America. He was al old, gray-headed man, and as old in clime as in years. He was a smuggler by profession, and umor even hinted at something For e Stories were told of a richly dressed hintravelledr who had entered his ouse one stormy evening, and whose body was  found a few hours afterwards, at the foot of a precipice, with the pockets turned inside out. His wife, strange to say thea a true Christian, and spent the most ofer time i visiting the poor. She loved her husband as oman only can love, and though she received much brutal treatment from him nomurur ever reached the ears of the neighbours. Ir duhter looked upon her and with contempt, and her son hated her. She had suffered much, and was still doomed to suffer more.-If you ivish to find a true wo-  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8356-00000013"/> 40    -    THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES man's heart, look not for it'in the palace, but fatler search the dwelling of the poor, and there you wl find -it' Is this not so, Reader." i a " Bravely done-you are indeed my daughter, and your father is proud to own you as his child," said the old man, as his daugh-: ter concluded her narrative. 4 "But you must not tell your mother what you1 have told me, for she would be sure to blab it out to tile priest. "Where is she now?" asked Emily. "Out visiting some of the neighbours as usual, instead of attend- ing to her own business," replied the old man. "Do you knom, Emily, that I have almost made up illy Rind to leave this place " "What! and give up smuggling?' said Emily. "If I leave this place, I suppose I shall have to give it up," sai the old man.  "'Besides it's getting rlather dangerous, and I am afraid they are placing spies to watch my house. If so, I pity the first that falls into my hands. Hallo'! what's that? ltRain? I thought we should have a storm. Whlat a glorious night this would be for landing a cargo " "But tell me father, if you should leave this place, where would you go to?" "Well, I don't know. I haven't made up my mind yet. If I lhad as many brave hearts as were with us three years ago, I would exact toll from every traveller that passed through the mount lins." But you have several men with you yet," said Emrnily, who was pleased at the idea of being the daughter of a bandit chief. Ay, but all of them are young, and therefore not fit to be trust- ed. All of my old comrades are gone. There's Jules C el-Blacck Jules, as we usedl to call him-the smuggler of the hills-he Dot shot three years ago by one of the village guard. Jcanll Caelr, Iis brother, shared the same fate. - Then there was Snaky Louis, the man that could run faster than a race horse, he is serving his time in the galleys. Henri Calvani Jules Cousin, and seven or eight other brave hearts perished in the fearful storm of the eighth of February. Ah, I  can't help thinking of them. . Eighteen years ago 1  had over fifty men serving under me, and to-day I have got but five, andgarcon at that."  " Checr up, father cheer up," said Emily. Who knows but what in Californil you may become the captain of as brave a band as-" "Who talks of California?" said the old man. "I do, father; it is just the place for a man of your genius." And do you wish me to go there?" I   do. -'  ' And will you accompany me." 4   COF EINMLY LA CROIX. : On one condition--Yes.;" ' And that is?" -' That you leave your wife behind. "Well," said the old man, slowly, "I'1l think of it.  And when am I to have your answer. '( To-morrow." "Perps-ny I    m almost sure thatthe answer will satisfy you. .Good heavens ! what a   E  storm !f -rk how the wind blows " said Emily. "Throw a few more logs on the fre, father, and put the bar over the door." (t But your mother may return  What matter if she does?" "IIush ! here comes some one. The door opened, aid one of the smugglers entered. e was a yung an about twenty-five yes of age, and armed to the teeth *  l' Ur'loke iaenl     aron  him, and then benin Scarcely had he entered, when he mae a sign to the oldman tht e had som-ething of importance to communi cate to him alone. The "1e h'adno skno n that afobe      fth  e  rt  hoieri latter turned to his daughter, and hinted that it-was time for her -"Good night," said Emilv, and taking one of the pine wood torches from the wall, she left the room. r What is it?" inquitel La Croix, as the door closed behind her. "Wheae is it? inuie t "ut A r iten  tog" aniwas the instant reply. ( "Isnro is to be landed to-n. " " Is that all'?            'and then bendi Tile smug,ler looked carefully around him, and then bentling his liead low down he whispered:-, "You are watched."' "4 I knew it before." AY, but you do not know that a member of the secret police is within thirty feet of the house." La Croix st"Uted.  " ,n(. even nowj" whispered the young man, the eyes of tho t re upoa you. Don't move your head." "iCan I see him without being seen myself. "He is looking through the window. Are thou aood shot . "Few cin surpass me with the rite" said the old man proudly. Whilre is it?'" t' Hanging over, the mantle-piece." C; Is it loadled?" "Now listen to me. Iwill sk you to go out with me to-mor- row after a wolf, in a tone loud enough for the spy to hear. You will answer that the lok of yiur gam wants oiling, and. you will  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8356-00000014"/> 42        THB LIFE AND ADVENTURES take it down and pretend to clean it. When you are ready spring up suddenly and fire." "I will," said the old man, while a grim smile passed over his features. "Traitor," he muttered to, himself " you world have me kill him in order to procure the informer's reward. We shall see- i we shall see." "M. La Croix," said the young man, in a loud voice, "will you go with me to Avigne-forest to-morrow, to kill a wolf?" ' With pleasure," said the old man, a smile hovering around-the corners of his mouth. ' Hand me my gun ;-the lock wants oiling. The smuggler took down his gun and handed it to La-Croix. "Draw your dagger and holdit -over my head," said the old man. ( Why?" was the suspicious reply.  "It will attract his attention." The young mane drew his dagger, but hardly had ho done so, when La Croix sprang up and raising his rifle with the rapidity of lightning to his shoulder, he fired. With a loud cry the smuggler sprang several feet from the floor, and fell back a corpse. "So perish all traitors,' muttered the murderer; and he glanced towards the window. The officer was no longer there. He had hardly-withdrew his eyes when the door opened, and Emily entered. "What have you done?" were her first words. "Rid the world of a traitor," was the stern reply. "I heard all that passed between you," said Emily. "But how will you account for his death?" "By saying that I slew him in self-defence," was the quick re- ply. "The officer saw him draw his dagger, as if about to kill me. Was it not gloriously done, Emily. I was told to beware of himn a few days ago," he added, spurning the body with his foot, " and I heard that he had already given information as-to the lIniding of several cargoes. The information he brought me this evening was false, and he has paid for his intended treachery with his life. 'But come, girl,it is time for you to retire."  Th'ihext morning when Emily awoke, she found that all traces of the deeds were cleared away. The storm still raged with un- abated fury; and her mother had not yet returned. As soon as the morning meal was over, during which not -aword was spoken she drew a chair to the fire, and seated herself by her father's side. "Well, what is your answer?" she inquired. "I have decided to go to, California." "Good! and wien will you start." "This morning." 'So soon!"               -  "Yes. If I am slow in glvnug miy decision on any subject, I am always prompt in executing it. If you have any thing to pack up,   -43 OF EMLY LA CROIX. do so sno; but let me tell you that the smaller your bundle is the better it will be for you." 4 And mother  e-what of her?" ic She wiill liave to remnain behind.1 "Bu t hhat wh she think?" "Whatever she pleases." In two hours they lvere plep"ared to depart, and ere nicllt closed in, they were man miles on their w ay toe seaport, from which they were to tmbark for t le ltr1y of pronlmise. When the smuggler'svi-fe returned, she was surprised , t the un- usual silence which reigned throucrh the house. A note on the table in her husband's tand-writing c:tu ;it hkr attention. It merel  containe thcsc wods-  "I hne left you for ever.   Th read, and a lorrible laluch, brlok;e fioui her lips. Reason forsook its throne, and to t le day of her death she remained a ravng maniac. t * - CHAPTER VI. A6AN FRB ISCO-TIIE PRETENDED COUNT-THE ROBBER CHIEF- SAN FRANCISCO  D3ATH OF-THOMAS LiVlNGTSTON, THE SEDUCER. Home of the free! Land ofthc great and good, Whose he'ritagffe is glory! Rail toee,! Thou oft, undaunted, nobly hath withstood Europia's best and proudest chivalry; And; conquering, won a miglty destiny First amnid the nations; and thy flag of light Gleamrns on all climps; a brifiaft oalaxy, To auide to gulide to Freedlorn fro oul -Slavery s nialt; Tlyping thy. lero-sons' apotlveosis b iallt."--Gouis 1FOUmmE T1ONAS. "HAVE YOU heard of tAie MnClv arri  -a, M Lrston," inquired l- iam n  , the eldest son of one of the first merchants in San Francisco, as he and his frien stood listlessly gazing down the baowhich gives to the noble city its name, and enjoying the beauty of t-e -sencry. "No who is it?" replied his friend. 'Arn   h count and his dauglter," replie* R. ' (n crrLtu- late, me, my dear fellow; thlley lveot been her thre hors, ;et I have been introduced to therni "And what kind of a looking nian;is tho Count?" inquired arston. "w0Tell, I can't praisc his appearl"nce much," was thc reply "but then, his dalutriter! By Jove but she's a keauty. Do you Lhow that I navo already fallen in love wiith her?"  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8356-00000015"/> "       THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES "Malting, I suppose, the fifteenth lady with whom you havo fallen in love, during the last fortnight. Really, R , the beau- ties of San Francisco will have to keep a good- watch over their T hearts while you remain ,lahere." - But I am really in love with the Count's daughter," said th- young .m'an -, seriously. "You saidr the same of Lucy Smith." "Marston you are a bore," r eturnecld hiis friend, " and I am afraid that I shall have to cut you." "Now don't go so far as that," said Marston, with a laugh, in which his friend joined. "And have you really fallen in love with this fair stranger?"  "I have, seriously," replied the young man.  "What is tho Count's name?" La Croix." "I should like to see him." "His daughter you mean," said R--, with a smile. "Both-the father and daughter." "Well, come to the hotel, and I will introduce you." *          TIC *  * * * - As the reader may have already suspected, the Count La Croix and his daughter were no other than the smuggler chief and Emily. Knowing that titles were much looked upon in America, he had prefixed a Count Ao his name, in order to gain an entrance into society. The plan succeeded to a charmn, for they had -not been more than three hours in the city, ere invitations to balls, parties, &amp;c., pouted in upon them, until the large dining table was covered. They had already received several visitors, but at the moment we now speak of them, they were alone, and congratula- ting themselves on their success. 4*' Every thing worlks well, Emily," said the old man, rubbing his hands with great glee. "Why, it will take us a month to answer allt these invitations." "And to do it in that time, we should be obliged to hire a secre- tary to heip us," said Emily, glancing at the table. The door opened, and the landlord entered with a large bill, which he proceeded to tack up against the wall. "There," said he, as soon as he had finished, and pointing to the; bill, 'just read that bill. Stay, perhaps you can't read English; I'll read it for you."-;The bill read as follows:- '$1000 will he paid by the. Mayor of Stan Francisco for the capture of Leon Gabralli, the mountain chief, who is supposed to be lilrking near the city. He is about five feet ten inches in height, has dark clrly hair, and very light complexionl. His name is sup-   OF EMLY LA CROK.'.         45 posed to be an assumed one, and it is stated that he is a French- man by birth. Thqe above reward will be paid by the Mavor for his capture. "April 8th, 185-." "'That man's body I. take to be worth its weight in gold," said the landlord. "Why, every village in the state has offered a re- ward of one thousand dollars for his capture; and if you reckon them up, you will find the amount to be about two hundred thou- sand dollars. I only wish I could catch himn, that's all: and the landlord left the room; but in a fesw rminutes he returned. "I beg your pardon," said he; t' but there is a young man be- low whlo wishes to see you. Shall I show him up? "iYes," was the reply.  The landlord turned to leave the room, when the door opened, and a mnan entered. "Stranger, it seems to me you are in a deuce of a hlurry," said the landlorld. " -Couldn't you have waitedl- " "Certainly not," replied the stranger "This man is my fatner, and this lady is my sister." "Phew!" whistled the landlord; anid hle left them. "And so you have arrived at last," said Jean, throwing himself into a chl-air. ' But what's thlat?" he addled, glancing at the bill. ,Another reward for the arrest of Leon GraTbrali? Why9 what fools the Yankees are.  Here sits the object of their search, his hair, figure and complexion answering, word for word, with the adver- tisement, and yet they do not arrest me. "What!" cried Emily, starting, " surely you are not Leon Ga- brai V' "I have the honor to be that- very individual," said Jean, tap. pig hiis boots with his cane. "But I must go now-rather a short visit ain't it?-but I have something of the utmost importance to attend to. I shall take tea with you this evening. Good day, Count La Croix;" and with a laugh the young man withdrew. "Who would take that head of his to be worth two thousand dollars?" said La Croix as the door closed behind him." "'Tis a large sum," muttered Emily, "and were ne not my brother, I would try to win it.* a And what matter if he is your brother?" muttered the old gLn. Their eyes met, and they understood each other.  "He showed no affection for you," said Emily. "And did not even shake hands with you," said her father. "And did not even ask after mother." "Two thousand dollars," said the old man again, "that would be one thousand dollars a piece." "Shill it be ours."  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8356-00000016"/> "       THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES ' Yes." "Enough. He will be here this evening, and I have a bottle of prussic acid in my trunk." ' If he had but showed some affection for We," muttered the old man, "I might not have thought of this; but as he did not-" ' Well?" said Emily, seeing that the old man paused. "Well he shall die," was the reply. "Emily, I ain going to take a short wallk. You will remain here to receive visitors." Here is your hat and cane," said Emily. "Do not forget that you are a count."  "I will not," said. La Croix, and he left the room. About two hours afterwards as Emily was looking out of the window, the landlord entered.-"Velel," said Emily, inquiringly. s The Reverend James Smith is below," said the landlord, and he wishes to see you." "For what purpose?" n Merely a-visit, I believe," replied the landlord. Emily bowed her head, and the landlord left the room. -In a few minutes the door opened, and Thomas Livingston, alias the Rev. James Smith, entered the room. Emily recognised- him at once, ( Villain what brought you here?" she exclaimed. "My legs," was the reply. "Well, daughter of Count La Croix and once nmistress of Thomnas Livingston, how wags the world with you?" Emily made no reply, but sat glaring at him with her beautiful features distorted with passion.  ^ Murderer!" she exclaimed, after a moment's pause. "Soft fiords, if you please," said the young man, throwing him- self into a chair.             - " b Why are you here?" inquired Emily. "To say that you arelooking more beautiful than ever, and that our former friendship must be renewed." ' In plain words you wish me to become your mistress?" "Exactly," replied the young man; " and your reply is-" ' That even I, steeped to the lowest dregs of poverty and degra- dationI would refuse your offer as I do now" . "By heavens! but you shall be mfne," said the young man, rising an ezing her hand. gack!" cried the young lady, endeavoring to shake off his grasp. "Unhand me, or I will alarm the house." - You darte not," said Livingston, throwing his arms around her neck.- "Dare utter a cry, Iand I will proclaim to those who enter, that the daughter of Count La Croix was formerly the mistress of. Thomas Livingston."             -    OF EMLY LA CKOIX.         47 "Villain!'" exclaimed Emily; and she uttered a slighf scream. Instantly, as if by magic, the door opened, and Jean La Oroix alias Leon Gabralli, the mountain chief, entered. He started with sure prise as his glance fell on Livingston, who still retained Emily in his grasp, and turning round he locked the door, and then with folded arms he confronted them. - "So ho, Thomas Livingston, we meet again," said he with a hoarse laugh. "You do not appear, pleased at seeing me." Livingston released Emily's hand, and with a haughty step stalked proudly up to him, until they stood face to face.-"Hark ye Jean La Croix," said he, " if you have the spirit of a man you will-" And having thrown him as he thought-off his guard, he suddenly drew a dagger, and aimed a -fearful blow at his. heart. Jean caught his hand as it was descending, and giving it a sudden twist, he tore the knife from his grasp, and threw it out of the window. "Ycu cannot escape your fate," he exclaimed, seizing him by the shoulder. "And that fate is-" "To die by the hand of Leon Gabralla';" and Jean drew his dagger. "What! the mountain chief!" cried Livingston, starting. "Aye," said Jean, and he plunged his dagger into his body. Without a groan the young man staggered'and fell a corpse upon the floor. - Jean bent over him a moment to make sure that he was really dead, and then placed the dagger in his belt. "But what are we to do with the body?" inquired Emily, as soon as she had somewhat recovered from her alarm.- ' Throw it into the closet, and lock the door," said Jea "Stop, let me see if he has any valuables about him;" and he rap ly rifled the Sockets of the deceased. When he had finished he took the body in his arms, and flung it into the closet. He had scarcely done so, when the dooropened, and La Croix entered. "Has any thing occurred?" he asked, glancing around. In a few words they informed him of what had happened. "I am glad he is dead," said La Croix; and he had hardly spoken when the door opened, and several waiters entered, bearing trays. "Will you not join us?" inquired Emily of her brother. "With pleasure," was the reply; and he seated himself At the table. As he was doing so, Emily went to her trunk and too out a small vial, which she thrust into her bosom. Then, with a smile she seated herself at the table.  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8356-00000017"/> 48'       THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES CHAPTER VII. THE DEATH OF TEE ROBBER 0HiEr-4THE DEATH OF THE SMUGGLER  BY THE HANDS OF HSIOWN DAUGHTER-REMORSE AND SUICIDE OF EMLY LA CROIX, "For seven long years I ve borne this load of guilt, This knawing consciousness of dreadful crime. I now tear off the maslk, and stand before you  A self-acknowledged wretch."--OLD PLAY. ' 6 AND so you have left France for ever?" said Jean, inquiringly. "Do you intend to become an American citizen?" and he laughed loudly. "Eat, brother," said Emily. "Yes, we have left France for ever. I wonder what Madame La Croix is doing at present?" "Tending to the poor, I suppose,' said Jean, as he helped him- self to a cup of tea. "Sister, do you- know that you are looking  handsomer than ever?" "You are indeed beautiful!" said Jean with a sigh. ' I almost wish that you were not my sister," "And if I were not, Jean, what then?" "Why then I would, make you my wife.' Emily laughed again.       \  "But what is that in your hand?" inquired Jean, suddenly.' "Guess," said his sister with a, smile. "Something you mean to give me, is it not?' Yes.", "I ariTmpatient to see it. What is it?" "Something to eat. Now, Jean, open your mouth and shut your eyes, and you shall have it.?"'  Jean did as she desired, and hastily drawing the cork, she emp- tied the contents of the bottle into his mouth. With a horrible cry, the robber started up, and caught hold of the-edge of the table. "Poisoned, by G-d!" he exclaimed; and fell back a corpse. "The two hundred thousand dollars are ours," said La Croix, rising "Mine, you mean," said Emily. "that do you not Mean to give me my share?" 'Certainly not," was the reply. "I will give you one quarter of the reward, but as to giving you half, you are foolish to think it."' (' But half I mean to have," said the old man, firmlv. "And half I do not choose to give you.' * And who will prevent mre."  "'I will."          i   -  Pooh I you are but a woman.'   OF EMIY LA CROIX, "And if I am," said Emily,in an angry tone, "I have moreo epirit than you have."  The old man gazed at her steadily for a moment, and then said- "I do not see what is to prevent me from havinD- all." ci Ah! and woqld you take all?" said Emily., "This will preve n t you; and drawing a dagger she plunged it into his bosom. Help! cried the old man; and he staggered against the wall. Mep! 'help  ,  Emily opened the door and looked out. "If I am taken," -she muttered, " they will han me " "Help!" cried the old man faintly Without even "glancing at him, Emily sprang down the stairs, and left the house. In a few minutes she reached a mllliner's shopt and hastily entering, she purchased a bonnet and veil. As she was going out, she saw-several men running past the door. One of them stopped a moment to rbest himself. "Is there a -fire?' she asked. "Fire! No," was the reply. "What is the matter, then?" she asked. "'Murder is the matter," was the reply. ' Count La Croix and two young men have been murdered at   -Hotel." "And by whom?" "The Count's daughter." "What makes you think it was her?" "Because the Count told us so himself. I was sitting in the bar-rcom with several others, when we heard cries for help, and on going to tie room  from which the cries proceedled, we saw the o0n1 beaning against the wall, and a stream of blood flowed from a wound in his side. In the midst of the room lay the Count's son his body still warm. 'What has happened?' I asked. ' iy dsugh- ter has poisoned her brother and stabbed me,' was the reply. 'There is another of her victims in that closet,' he added, and then with a groan he fell dead. .We searched the hoaseo for the murderessi but she was not to be found.  But she can't escape; for the landlord has sent all his servants out in pursuit of her; and in afer minutes the news will be all over the city." "Andwhat' said EmI;ly, will bethe fate of the murderess if she is taken. "Death!" was the reply. "But I must go ow." Drawing-her veil still closer over her face, the murderess walked on until she came to the river. Suddenly a voice exclaimed-- "There she is now!" Emily turned her head,and saw the landlord rapidly approach- ing. Behind him followed a  large number of men bearing arms. t               &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC8356-00000018"/> X "          *  -       .           J O     LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF EMLY LA COOLS. "There she is now!" he exclaimed, and he rushed forward. With a cry of despair the murderess sprang to the edge of the pier, gazed for a moment at the water, and then started back. - I cannot-dare not die!" she muttered; and she ran rapidly  along the pier. There was no escape. On one side was the water, on the other a crowd of excited men. A brig lay a few feet from the pier. Suddenly mustering all her strength the murderess gave one spring, and landed safely on the vessel's deck. Then, with a shout of exultation she began to ascend the rope ladder, and in a few minutes she was far above', her pursuers. But they were not to be baulked of their prey. Hundreds sprang on the shrouds,and Emily seeing her danger, endeavored to ascend'higher. Suddenly a piercing shriek rang through air; and the men who were ascend- ing the shrouds involuntarily paused. Another shriek-aloud crV- of "My brother's spirit! God! I=cannot look at it! . Hell! receive your victim!"-One spring and the body of ,tlhe murderess lay upon the pier a senseless clod. A loud shout burst from the crow-d. Among many of the men that surrounded her was myself. I was both a surgeon and clergym n, and as soon as the crowd would per- Ulit me, I knelt,down by her side, and took her hand. Her pulse beat, but so low that I could hardly feel it. Requesting the crowd to step aside, I bore the body on the brig, down into the cabin, and closed thie door. It, was some hours before she came to, and during that time I remained seated by her side. As soon as she was able to speak, she inquired whether I thought she would recover. I shook my head. A smile of joy lit up her features, and for a few minutes she remained silent. I then asked her if I should pray for her. She made no answer. I then questioned her about the fearful deed she had committed, and then questioned her as to her past life. She told me that there was a small manuscript in her trunk, in which she had written the incidents of her life up to her seventeenth year. I sent for the manuscript and read it. She then commenced at the point where it left off, and in two hours she had told me her whole history. She had hardly concluded when she sank back, and in a few minutes *her eyes closed for ever. Thus perished Emily La Croix, one of the most beautiful beings the world ever saw. May she rest in peace, and may all who read this little book take warn- ing by her fate, and learn-  "That the shortest surest road to Heaven, Is-to forgive and be forgiven." THE END. 1    &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>