<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8237">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >We by Us. That is to Say, James Yellow and John Blue : Their Travails </title>
            <author >Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC8237</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >We</title>
                  <author >Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >196 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Baker Godwin</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1854">1854</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-09-08">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>We</head> 
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8237-00000001"/>  WE, BY US; THAT IS TO SAY, ,amnes Belloi an}tr loa i te: THEIR TRAVAILS, BY THEM. ' NEW YORK: BAKER, GODWIN &amp; CO., PRINTERS, OOBEB NEASSAU MAOD BPBUC 6BEfB. 1854.  &#xD;<pb n="0" xml:id="VAC8237-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1854, by J. J. WHTE, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States, for the Southern District of New York.   "Ihi! man, dme O rhean di,  Ori an dhe, It,-ell nol,--ie Fory ell, owand blu e. O rust wo ;- Wcw!--rot, eth isbo 6k: IT ow, wed id."  &#xD;<pb n="0 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC8237-00000003"/>  r CONTENTS.  ER..                    PAGE. I., WAE DON'T SET OU',   .   .      9  T. WE DO,     .       .  JI. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,   .     14  V. WE CONTINUE OUR TitAVAILS  .   .   21       - f. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,    .     25 I. WE CONTlINUE OUR TRAVAILS, .       32  I. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,       .  38  I. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,  .   .   43  C. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,         49  C. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,    .     55       I I. WE CONTiNUE OUR TRAVAILS,    .   .  60  I. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,  .      68 I. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,     .   '73  Y. WE CONTLWE OUR TRAVAILS,   .      82  r. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAIL S,   .   .  89       j I. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,  .   .   98 [. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,    .   . 105 [I. WE CONTINUE OUR, TRAVAILS, .   .   120  K. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,     .   130       - C. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,  .      135 I. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,    .   .148 1. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,  .   .   152 [L WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS       . 160       i V. WE CONTINUE OUR TRAVAILS,  .      170  [. BENGi TzE LAST COMAPsty    .   . 1n APPENDIX,   ..         .   179  &#xD;<pb n="0-9" xml:id="VAC8237-00000004"/> CHAPTER I.   WE cannot forbear laughing when we think how, at the outset, we dignified our prosaic trip with the title 'of "Adventures on the Wild Prairies of the West;" that is to say, we spoke of it as such to our friends. We commenced our preparations a month before starting. We dreamed frightful dreams of tat- tooed savages scalping us on the lonely prairie, or bearing us away in triumph to the neighboring forest; there to be danced around in a war-dance, and then led to a tree, fastened thereto, and have forty or fifty Native Americans firing hatchets at us. We imparted these dreams to our fair friends, and terrified their souls till they froze within them. We tracked out our course on the map, and dwelt with frightful emphasis  o6n Wisconsin and Minnesota. There was to be the principal scene of our exploits. Then, too, we spoke of the frequent explosions of western steamers, and spoke, in a reckless way, of taking state-rooms directly   &#xD;<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC8237-00000005"/> 10 over the boiler, so that, if we were blown up, we'd go off with a pop into atoms, and not linger out a long life with broken legs and arms. But, in the event of having gone through all these vicissitudes, and reached the, prairies in safety, we were to chase and capture the wild horse or shoot down the bison, to hunt the prairie-hen, to revel in the long grass amid the beau- tiful flowers of the prairie, and to fish in the Falls of St. Anthony. In short, James Yellow and John Blue were to go through a glorious course of adven- tures, unparalleled by any of the past or present, which, indeed, would henceforth be deemed unworthy the name of adventures, so glorious a light was to bec thrown around their own career. ' -  Whether these dreams of James Yellow and John Blue were realized, we leave to the reader to de- termine.   CHAPTER II. Tim day fixed upon at length arrived. James Yellow's old nurse who was still retained in the family to take care of the little Yellows, was full of prognos- tics and vague forebodings of evil. She had heard the death-watch the night before, and that morning had put on her stockings inside out, and seen herself up- side down in the looking-glass. James. Yellow, who had never ventured far from home before, began to feel nervous and wretched; but John Blue laughed off his fears, and having called the nurse "an old granny," quite re-assured, by this contemptuous epithet, the spirits of his friend. But as James Yellow rose, John Blue fell; for the day had opened with a misty driz- zling rain, and when they started there was every pros- pect of a long northeasterly storm. The manner of starting was well suited to the present time. In days of yore, when a travel was to be made, the man started, booted and spurred and mounted on a favorite steed, with his belt stuck about with daggers, and his  &#xD;<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC8237-00000006"/> *-   12 saddle-bags:full of pistols. He generally began his career by entering upon a barren moor, and always reached a dense, wild forest, just as the shades of night began to fall, accompanied by a heavy shower of; rain. Robbers were lying in ambush, and the first night'generally opened with a bloody conflict. Now, alas, how changed! James Yellow and John Blue order a carriage from a livery-stable, have a porter to put on their trunks, ride, well sheltered from the rain, through a densely-popuatedcity to a ferry boat; fight their way through a crowd of small boys, asking to carry their trunks, pay two cents fare, to cross the river, and, having reached the Jersey shore, walk to the depbt, a smoky old building-enter a car crowded with people-rush, whizzing, through the country, and reach Philadelphia late in the evening. Then, instead of passing the night in some robber's cave, covered with glorious wounds won in a noble fight, they go to a comfortable hotel-are conducted to "Room No. "," with two beds in it, up in the fifth story-go to bed tired and have a good night's rest. James Yellow and John Blue wake up-the next morning, indignant, and tell one another they might just as well have stayed home+; look out of the window, and, finding it rains pitchforks, exclaim that they had better have staid at home. John Blue, discovering that his throat   13 is very sore, sees only a domestic day before him, and heartily wishes he had stayed home; and James Yel- low, who is bound. to stick to John Blue 'through thickand thin, sees that he, too, is housed for the day, and wishes he had stayed home.  &#xD;<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC8237-00000007"/>  WE spent the morning in gloomingly lookiig at the rain, as it came down in a steady drizzle. Oppo- site the window was a low building, used as a circus. in the front was'an immense picture, decorated with red and blue designs around the border. We mention the border of the picture more particularly than the picture itself,inasmuch as it was the most striking ob- ject of the two, the picture merely representing a man balancing himself on a horse tha- was running round a ring with most remarkable velocity; at least that was evidently the design originally, but the rain had washed away one of the rider's -legs, and the horse was pursuing his mad career without a head. There was an old tin spout, too, that irregularly vomited forth small volumes of water on the pavement. Alto- gether, it was a most dreary prospect; and John Blue and James Yellow, both, felt that the, very leaden clouds overhead were laden with gloon. In the after- noon, however, a ray of sunshine made the prospect a   15 little more cheerful, and we sallied forth to explore and observe, John Blue having been first muffled up in the tippet of James Yellow and a French k'haban. But the spirits of James Yellow had yielded to th e depressing influences'of the morning, and his reflec- tions were of the most sombre hue. We wandered silently through Chestnut street; and, to a remark ven- tured on by John Blue that the houses looked neat and tidy and clean, James Yellow only responded with a most savage grunt. Intimidated in nowise by this unfavorable opening, John Blue added, that the houses looked as though they were cut out of'cheese; to which remark James Yellow volunteered a ghastly, malicious smile--"Cheese!" said he, in a most sar- dopic manner, "I see nothing like cheese; they are mad' of as common brick and mortar as I ever saw." To which John Blue, with the veins all distended on his forehead to bursting, answered, "When I say cheese, I mean of the nature of cheese. If you take a cheese and cut out a square, the edges and corners are sharp; and these houses have been built with-so 'much care, that their edges and corners are sharp. Besides, how do you know of what substance the house is made? You only see the paint that covers it: some houses are painted to imitate brown stone, so that the inexperienced are frequently deceived and &#xD;<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC8237-00000008"/> 16 think it is brown stone, whereas it is merely brick and mortar. You might take cheese," continued he, in an exasperated tone, "and. paint it to imitate brick and mortar;" and ending .this eloquent speech with so 'brilliant and triumphant a finale, John Blue stopped to take breath and wipe his face, which had become quite warm during his harangue.  To all this, how- ever, the invincible James Yellow merely replied, "But cheese is full of holes; "' at which John Blue became speechless, and sank into a moody, indifferent silence. But this state of things, fortunately, lasted but a shorttime. We had both reached the lowest ebb of misanthropic feeling, and the tide of good fellowship soon began to rise again. We noticed the plain, unostentatious appearance of the houses, and. the white stoops without railings, and playfully re- marked, that Philadelphiq was no place for roaring blades to go home early in the morning, as they would be very apt to fall off railingless stoops. But what astonished us most was the nomenclature of Phila- delphia streets.. Were, names in reality the actual embodiment in language, of things, we would have believed ourselves in some vast forest; for the streets, wherever we went, had trees for namesakes-Poplar and Chestnut, Walnut, Cherry and Oak, Hemlock, Pine and Beech, &amp;c., &amp;c., until you have exhausted           .f   17 the whole vocabulary of trees. At length, meeting with a Cranberry street, we began to entertain sanguine hopes of finding Grass street, which we thought would be exceedingly funny to behold; but after fruitless endeavors (par parenthesis to our readers- par paren- thesis again, that is, if we have any-we wish to call- your attention to the word "fruitless;" knowing the bad reputation that travelers have of not being strict adherers to truth in their narrations, we wish to defend ourselves from any such' imputation as the word "fruitless" may afford a basis for. We acknowledge that appearances are against us. Having, but a mo- ment before, spoken of encountering a berry of the species cran, we say in the very next breath that our endeavors were " fruitless;" but we solemnly assure you that we employed the word in but one sense, the fig-urative, not literal; in fact, we would not be guilty of that vile habit of punning, under any circumstances, as you will plainly see for yourselves it the perusal of this book-but to continue), after fruitless endeavors, we concluded to discontinue our search for Grass street, and content ourselves with the mint, before which we now find ourselves. The Mint--a granite building, whose dimensions, and style of architecture, you will find described in guide-books of this city. As this professes to be a 2*  &#xD;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC8237-00000009"/> 18 book of travails merely, it would be beyond our prov- ince to go into such details; but we entered the door, and were immediately regarded with a suspicious eye by a man in a white cravat, and requested to give our names and residences. We were then consigned to a fat man's guardianship, who conducted us about and pointed out various objects of interest-"Do you see silver in boxes? it resembles lime." Saw silver, but couldn't discover resemblance. From here went to the " engine-room "-big-wheel, big strap of leather, and strong smell of oil. From here to "stamp-room," see what are apparently little bits of tin turn out silver sixpences. "This is all, gentlemen-ahem!" fat man feels in his pocket and looks .knowing. We leave to the charity of our readers the determination of the important question as to whether he was adequately compensated for his trouble. For our own part, we frankly confess that we have never felt as though we had adequately compensated the individual called " the guide," under any circumstances. We left the mint, much to the satisfaction of the man in the white cravat, as well as olir own. The evening of the first day was spent in the hotel. On retiring at night, John Blue's throat was soaked in spirits of camphor, and a gargle of alum-water endured. Almost suffocated by the fuimes of the   19' camphor, he passed a night closely approximating to delirium.  .  The next day opened warm and pleasant, and tho Fairmount Waterworks received our first visit, The grounds are pleasantly laid out; but who that has seen the Croton Reservoir, can speak of the two in the same breath? From Fairmount we went to Girard College-met a tall, thin woman, who volunteered as guide. Were led first 4o the dormitory-a long room with two rows of small beds. Then to dining-room- "accommodates 312 pupils"-made pupil of eye dilate. Then to the wash-room-long room, with row of tin basilas along the walls-imagination revels in spec- tacle of 312 pupils washing. Then to 312 pupils' closts,for clothes-312 jackets on 312 shelves, and 12 times 312 brass buttons on 312 jackets. &amp;' magnificent building is Girard College, and a noble end is the education of poor orphans. We: next went to Independence Hall, to see the room where "The Declaration" was signed. A chair, portraits, statue of Washington, and piece of stone on which the secretary stood when he read the Declara- ;  tion to the people, 4th July, 1776. While lost in 'pleasant reverie, we were startled by a cold, sepulchral vdice, saying, "Come, I must shut up the room." . So we, returned to the hotel. Tired of Philadelphia, we /i e*  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8237-00000010"/> 20 determined to start that afternoon for Baltimore-so took an early dinner at I P. M. "What do you wish?" says the waiter. "Bill of fare." We have no bill of fare; but anything you want, yoi shall have." " m!" says John Blue, "month of April- should like a pheasant, with green corn, and straw- berries and cream." Waiter slightly staggered, "We have none of those, I'm sorry to say;" and finally becomes himself the bill of fare, by enumerating "mutton, roast-beef,-and chicken;" and that is whence John Blue derived his habit of calling all the waiters Bill, having noticed their unconquerable [ aversion to the name "John," or " waiter."   : , , CHAPTER IV. Ou, road to Baltimore lay through a pleasant country, though flat. We crossed a river two or three times, over such a very narrow bridge, that, in looking out of the window, it seemed as though we were runhiing over the water itself. This was exces- sively cheering; especially as we were quite a long time in crossing it. John Blue startled James Yellow by suggesting the idea of an easy upset, and con- siderably increased the sensation, by conclusively demonstrating that in such an event, there was no way of escape. We, however, reached Baltimore in Safety. Had a very vivid first impression of that city, in the coach from the depot to the hotel; the smells from  the filthy streets we passed through, being almost insupportable. Were, received very courteously at Barnum's. The probable cause being-two Kos- suth hats, one French k'haban, and one incipient moustache, that gave John Blue quite an air (the o ; ^3  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8237-00000011"/> 22 indulgent: reader will please be charitably disposed here, and not suffer the slightest suspicion to float in his mind, that we intended a pun on the word "aiir'") We remained in Baltimore two days; but the reader eager for information will be disappointed; for, in consequence of John Bluets sore throat, we were unable to see much (more of Baltimorei than the limited -view of it obtained through 'the 'window. That view consisted of the brick houses-opposite, and a monument between, called the "Battle Monument." James Yellow made a little excursion on. one of the two days, and returned with glowing accounts of Baltimore beauties, but John Blue has doubted the truth of them to this very day. He persists in saying that he saw no beauty in Baltimore; but then he withholds at the same time the fact that he did'nt stir out of the house while he'was there, with the exception of one evening, to be sure, when we both ventured out for castor-oil, ini the hopes that it might cure Blue's sore throat. 'James Yellow recommended this proceedig; and professing to be a connoisseur in that article, to him was entrusted the responsibility of purchasing it. The difficulties we encountered in procuring good castor-oil may in some measure account for the disgust that had strengthened in John Blue's mind against Baltimore-a disgust that o   *23 even to this day remains with him that he never thinks of that city without fheiass of nausea. W  visited at least a half-dozen of the principal 'druggists wirthout successthe  rancid; but what most amused John Blueir oil was the mode of inquir y adopted by Tames Yellow. Having professed whimself a connoisser, he assumed an air of impotance entirely unprecedented, and entering the druggist's said, in a slow, solemn, manner, "lRave you got any fesh  astr-o that comes in little bottles      casthat o rilll ,ittle bottles ith that (making a vague motion with his fingers through the air)around it The replywas invariably, "No, sir." "Well, that"is the kind I am in the habit of t  aking, ad I want to try and find it." Disgusted with druists, he has recourse to a grocer. Grocer; disgusted with inquiry, refers disgusted Ye6low to "apothecaries, for such articles." We rangedthe streets of Baltimore without success. Finally, limiting the inquiry to fresh castor-oil without any mention being made of that   ' being'md of that   around small bottles," we begin to have a ray of hope. A druggist pro- duces a bottle.; Jmes Yellow holds it to the light, then slowly inverts it, and exclaims "That looks good, but I should like to smell it." Now, -the idea of any man liking to smell castor-oilas such a startling development to the mind of John Blue  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8237-00000012"/> 24 who had never before heard it spoken of but with disgust, that he burst out into a loud roar of laughter, much. to the indignation, of the apothecary, who was eyeing Yellow's movements with astonishment. Nevertheless, Yellow smells it, and John Blue gags at the sight. Yellow finds it good, and having purchased sufficient for six'adult men, we return with our treasure to the hotel. John Blue, however, hasn't the stomach to take the oil after what has transpired, and contents, himself with bathing his neck in volatile liniment, till his eyes start out of his' head; and they end this episode of their stay in Baltimoreby going to bed. Such is one of the many prosaic realities of the present age. The traveler in days of yore must have been ignorant of sore throats, or uncomplainingly have suffered them to ripen into putridity; for we find no mention of them. in old romances, and yet read of tales of exposure that would have wilted the healthiest of men:. kf.    CHAPTER V. WHAT a rattling, rickety, old house that was at Baltimore! Our second morning there was passed in our room, which being full of chinks and cracks, the wihd hot only whistled outside of the house, but also had the audacity to come whistling into our very chamber. John Blue and James Yellow spent this second morning in continual efforts to avoid sitting in a draught;' but at length finding them ineffectual, John Blue retired to snug quarters, beneath the bed-clothes, while James Yellow retreated down stairs, leaving his friend to the companionship of rattling doors and casements, and whistling draughts. As John lay with his throat swathed in flannel, and soaked with liniment and camphor, dismally reflecting on his mournful condition, the door suddenly opened, and there entered one of those vigorous specimens of female humanity, denominated - "chambermaids." With red hands, solid red arms, red checks, and red nose that had a snivel in it, her hair sprinkled with dust, and a broom in her  &#xD;<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC8237-00000013"/> 26 hand, her very entrance seemed to act as a tonic upon John, who immediately began to feel stronger. "Don't be alarmed, my go6d girl," cried he, for seeing him in bed, she was about to leave the room, "you might as well put my room in order now, for if you wait till I get up, you'll have to wait a long time; you see 'm what they call sick a-bed;" and feeling very communicative, went on to inform her what "a very sore throat" he had, and ended by asking her if she'd ever had a sore throat. "Oh, many a time," she said; and the old doors and casements rattled, and the wind whistled, about the room, as if perfectly delighted. "And what do you do for it?" continu'ed John. "Nothing, I don't have time." "The deuce you don't," says John, "why, how long did one ever last you " "Oh, I had one for two weeks once." "And you did nothing for it?" "No, sir," said she, dusting the furniture with so much vigor, that John seemed to feel stronger and stronger; "I went'about my work, as usual."  "So will I," said John, springing out of bed, to the great horror of the startled chambermaid, who, raising a small scream, started for the door. John was, however, too much in earnest to pay attention to any thing except dressing, and shortly after astonished James Yellow in the sitting-room below by his company.    27   L One of James Yellow's characteristics was a sim- plicity of nature that constantly led him into scrapes. A great aim of his was to see "a slave;"' but he experienced great difficulties in thiF pursuit, inasmuch as he had no guide or standard by which to determ- ine who was a slave. "In this Southern countlry, says James (for he was under the delusion that be- ing in Baltimore was being "South"), "the colored people do not differ in appearance from those at the North." Having delivered himself of this mighty axiom, he began to revolve in his mind, in what way besides by mere looks, he could accomplish this desire of his heart; and he adopted the most direct, as will be seen.  Shortly after John Blue's unexpected appearance below, James, who had been quietly pondering on this slave question, which ha'l of late haunted him, arose and said he would take a short walk, and return soon. John being left alone, began after a time to feel ennuyed (or as a French acquaint- ance of ours once translated it into English, "to annoy himself"), and went to the window to gaze gloomily at Battle Monument and the opposite houses, when his attention was attracted by a crowd collected beneath the window; and in the midst of it, to his amazement, he beheld James Yellow, his friend, decorated with a black eye, and red spots  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8237-00000014"/> 28 evidently occasioned by a bleeding at the nose, while near by was a powerful negro, violently gesticulating, whom the people could hardly restrain from making ai attack on the quarter where Yellow was stationed. The crowd, meanwhile, seeming very merry, presented a strange contrast to Yellow's lugubrious visage. It afterwards appeared that James Yellow, whose mind had been wrought up to a state of desperation at his unsuccessful attempts to see a slave, had finally concluded to make the inquiry of 'oe of the colored population themselves.' "Are you a slave, sir?" asked he of the negro already mentioned, in the most open and confiding manner possible; when, to use his own words, he had "suddenly found himself knocked down, contrary to all established principles;" for argued he, " if a man be a slave, he is a slave, and being a slave is not his fault, buit his misfortune; why, then, should he knock me down, who had sympathized with him in misfortune, and had more- over shown respect for him as a man, by addressing him as 'sir' "To which Blue only said, "You're a queer bird, Yellow; but I'd advise you to go and wash your face, and get something to take the stain out of your eye, for the black and blue, added to the natural yellow of your complexion, gives you an uncommonly discolored appearance."   29 Now, this James Yellow was in reality a very singular person. Johri Blue had always thought so, dating his opinion from his first visit to Yellow at home, after their acquaintance commenced at college.  On this first visit, he had found James in a roofl in which every chair was covered with some article of clothing. Over the back of one hung a pair of  pantaloons. turned inside out, the linen lining of  which gave them a very sepulchral and unfinished appearance; on another lay a coat covered by a newspaper; a vest hung over a third; while Yellow himself, so astonishingly transformed by a change of clothing that Blue hardly knew him, occupied the remaining chair. He was arrayed in a coat of faded yellowish green plaid; his pantaloons were faded too, and when he rose, had that peculiar hang about the knee, and draw-up over the calf which distinguish pantaloons that have been worn for)a very long time. As he rose up suddenly and whisyd round to remove the clothing from a chair near him, a new development in the seat met the astonished Blue's gaze; a large ;spot of white was disclosed, which led himn to conjecture that the pantaloons had been worn through in that quarter, but the coat- tail didn't remain in the air sufficiently long for him  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8237-00000015"/> 30 to determine positivelyo whether it were so or tot. A pair of boots lay on the floor in front of a hard- coal fire, and a bandbox stood on his desk. Had it not been for the well-filled book-case in one corner of the room, and a cabinet of minerals"and other curiosities in the pther, Blue would have thought he had invaded some clothier's apartment, and that Yellow, in his blue stockings and slippers, was the tailor. Havyng spent the afternoon together in this t room, they both concluded to take a walk for exercise, and Yellow commenced preparations. He first pro- ceeaed to turn the pantaloons outside out and change them for the faded pair, then drew on his boots, and, in short, made a complete exchange of outer garments. This having been performed, he proceeded to the band-box, and to the increased astonishment of Blue, produced his hat. On a better acquaintance Blue .discovered that these manceuvres were of every- day occurrence, as well as a habit of carrying an old, green cotton umbrella out/with him in all seasons. His clothes always had an old-fashioned cut, and at tea-time, when he was seen to drink tea without either sugar or milk, he had the appearance of an antiquated gentleman of the old school, although he was then but nineteen years of age. But these peculiarities did not in the least diminish the good   31 qualities of his heart; on the contrary, they rather served, like the shades in a picture, to make them still more prominent. His very manner of doing a kindness was sometimes peculiar. On one occasion, he had been known to carry a bowl of rice pudding, tied up in a napkin, through Broadway, to a con- valescent friend. This is mentioned as peculiar, as in the circles in which he moved, such a transaction (though it might not be noticed by men who are accustomed to regard rather the things themselves, than the surface of things)' would be regarded by the so-called "first society," as a flagrant violation of decorum and propriety, and sufficient to excom- municate forever an ordinary offender. Extraordinary offenders, by which .class is meant, that small "set" whose position is fortified by great wealth, were of course beyond censure. Such a proceeding on their part would be regarded as a "delightful eccentricity," and even imitators would have been found. O, how thankful should we be that James Yellow (though moving in the first circles) was not a leader therein! for how know we but Fashion might have compelled us to stroll through the street with a bowl slung in a napkin in our hand-a custom   that might, perhaps, be more ridiculous, but certainly not so odious or horrible as boring holes through one's ears for the purpose of hanging trinkets there.  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8237-00000016"/> CHAPTER VI. ON the morning following the transaction between Yellow and Black, and which had been recorded on Yellow in characters of red, Yellow was as ready, if notnore-so, than Blue, to leave a spot where a black had taken such liberties with his person. James, who had left the North with a most unbiased mind, was now so much a slaveholder in disposition that he was as wicked as one in will, if not in deed; so much of a slaveholder, indeed, was he, that he expressed great anxiety to be able to hold that "vile slave," as he called him, and pommel him till he was partly blue, in other words, to make him appear of the color of his eye-black and blue. That stain-was not yet effaced, so it was deemed advisable to cover it with a blind of green silk, which being done, they proceeded to conclude their other arrangements, and in due course of time found themselves on their way' to Washington, and rapidly leaving Baltimore behind. As John Blue, however, said, he for his part had "left Battle Monument, and the houses opposite the hotel   33 windows," that comprising all that he knew of Balti- more, "except, indeed," nudging Yellow in the ribs, "that black men there wouldn't endure slavery ques- :tions, and that Baltimore druggists didn't keep castor- oil with that (making vague motions in the air around the bottles." To divert Yellow's mind, which seemed settling into gloomy despondency, Blue drew his at- tention to the scenery out of the car window. The storm had not yet passed over, and the prospect was a most dismal one. A young man in a shaggy over- coat now opened a window and let in a draught of cold damp air directly upon an old gentleman who occu- pied a seat near him. This, old gentleman, by his frightful wheezings and gaspings had attracted the at- tention of several of his imediate neighbors, who ex- hibited their sympathy/for him by curiously, inquiring I into his circumstances, nation, and station, in general, *and in particular, as to what he was doing in the cars, and where he was going to, with numberless other like inquiries. This species of cross-examination, well cal- culated to put even a healthy man opfe rack, had by no means a soothing effect on the old gentleman's complaint. On the contrary, it so exasperated its that he was threatened with .a speedy suffocation, which would soon have put an end to all his troubles. A benevolent individual, however, interposed, and, hav- 3  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8237-00000017"/> 34 ing quieted these buzzing inquisitors, asked the young man in the shaggy coat ;to close the window, and wrapt up the old soldier, as he proved to be, in the remnant of the old cloak, which scantily covered his shivering limbs, aided by a warm shawl that James Yellow kindly offered for the purpose. He was an old soldier, having fought in the American Revolution, and his head was now whitened with the snows of ninety winters. There before us, in a rusty old velvet vest, with eyes bleared and watery, and water running out of the corners of his poor old mouth, and cough- ing away his little remnant of life, sat an old hero, who had once breasted it bravely against the op- pressor, and whose sturdy sinews and determined will had formed part of that combination of sturdy sinews and determined wills that were once the bulwark and defense of the nation's infancy-likesome old castle that has successfully withstood many a vigorous attack, but at length crumbles away beneath the insidious advance of age. James Yellow and John Blue both considered themselves very common-place, and decidedly modern, by the side of this old hero. They felt insignificant, and by no means inclined to push too far the self- inquiry that rose as to what they had done for their fellow-beings, or their country; and they could not   835 help wondering why they, who had done so little, should have so many comforts, while this old soldier, who had done so much, should have so few. They were very glad when they, at length, reached Washington, and parted company with the old soldier, for whom they could do nothing, but who had done so much for them; it being human nature to wish' for benefits to be bestowed, but to dislike being under a sense of obligation for them. On leaving the cars, our two friends found them- selves in Washington, in the midst of a heavy shower of rain; and, while John Blue, whose throat was still sore, remained beneath the shelter of the depot, James. Yellow waded through the mud, with an umbrella, in search of a coach: the which, having been, at length, found, was also found to be full, according to our ideas; but, the driver persisting in saying there was room, \  James Yellow made the first essay to enter, despite the lowering looks that met him from within; and John Blue following closely at his heels, had barely got his head into the coach when he experienced a sudden im- petus from the rear, and the next moment- found him- self jammed into a fat man, and only prevented from tumbling out into the street by the fastening of the door, and, before the driver could be expostulated with, they were rattling to the hotel; that is, if a coach  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8237-00000018"/> 36( could be said to rattle that rolled quietly through mud sIix inches deep. In books of travels, the coach is al- ways said to rattle over the stones of the city, and the Clear crack of the whip is generally heard; but in our case the only crack we, or rather John Blue, was con- scious of, was the crack in the door, which he was fearful might be extended indefinitely, and thus result in a general expos6 of the party in the coach and a particular one of the party nearest the door. His fears, however, having somewhat subsided, he next found himself haunted by the remarkable similarity he bore to that race of beings, with fur for hair, incarcerated in small boxes, and who greatly amuse children by sprnging suddenly out on the pressure of a spring. As he was sadly ruminating on the remarkable manner in which he would burst on the astonished view of spectators at the hotel windows, on the coach's arrival, his nerves received a sudden shock'from the sound of a shrill female voice, close in his ear, the owner of which was congrattilating herself on having "so fortunately stumbled" on him. To this, a response was given in another female voice, of a suitable accompaniment of congratulations; whereupon, a weak, piping male treble, coming as if from a drlstance, like the voice of one, about Toing smothered, was heard to say "how delighted he was at this unexpected honor." Curious   37 to see, as well as hear, John Blue, much to the disgust of his fat neighbor, whose wind he had been for some time exploring with his elbow, turned his head and beheld-two immense women, and, between them scarcely visible, a little, meagre man, in a white cravat and with his hat knocked over his eyes, and evidently trying to look cheerful, without success. These ladies, having once unloosed their tongues, gave them a free rein, and the coach was much edified by such an enu- meration of matrimonial alliances that one would sup- pose the sole business of the world consisted in marry- ing and giving in marriage. We at length reached the hotel (it is a very long ride from the depot to Willard's); and the handle of the  door having been turned, and John Blue having gone through his performance as anticipated, James Yellow was discovered in a most deplorable condition; for he had cramps in both legs, and both of his feet were asleep. By poking and punching them, however, they were; at length, awakened, and James was enabled to come forth. 'It rained steadily the whole of the afternoon, which was spent, within doors, in gazing gloomily out of the windows.  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8237-00000019"/> -     X         ( CHAPTER VII. THE prospect from our window at Washington was inferior in grandeur to that from the window at Baltimore, but far surpassing it in rural simplicity; the background consisting of an irregular row of -small houses, and the foreground of a wide level of deep  mud, occasionally enlivened by a few straggling cows, who waded along with apparently the same contentment as if they were grazing in rich pastures, notwithstanding the rain which kept pouring down on their smoking backs. We both agreed that the cow was the stupidest of animals. The idea of their complacently chewing the cud,' under such .dreary circumstances, was positively exasperating to us':discontented travelers, whom the ' gloomy leaden skies seemed to follow everywhere. Even night, which .generally casts a veil over human woes, by the sweet oblivion that it brings, neglected, on this occasion, to perform that comfortable opera- tion for -ns. At an early hour, we retired to our       '   39 room, eligibly situated directly beneath the leads of the house, in the hope (vain, alas!) of forgetting our little miseries. On being shown to our apartment, we entered it with our minds so completely wrapt up in the- pleasant anticipation of rest and sleep, that we failed at first to notice that our bodies were enveloped in a dense mist, which filled the room, and which almost extinguished the dim light of our tallow- candle. The mind cannot always rise entirely above the sufferings of the body, as the sequel will show; for no two unlucky wights ever had a more determined. g will to 'fall suddenly asleep" tha we, that night. James Yellow, fearing damp sheets, coiled himself up in his shawl, while John Blue, after extinguishing the light, went in between blankets. The monotonous patter of the rain on the roof, ordinarily so soothing a sound, had- lost its wonted effect in the dreadful dampness of the air, suggestive of miasma and other horrors, and productive of an oppression in breathing almost unendurable. Each of us, at first, concluding the cause. to be in his own respirating apparatus, refrained from disturbing the 6ther. John Blue, who found breathing almost impossible with his head outside of the. clothes, drew it in, as a turtle does his, when he finds things adverse to his comfort  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8237-00000020"/> 40 at work outside. As he lay perspiring beneath the clothes, he heard James Yellow; in a muffled tone of voice, exclaim, "Oh, I can't stand this ;" and thrusting his head outside, heard a rustling in the dark, and then James Yellow again, "There, now, I've got no matches ; they're all locked up!" JOHN BLUE. "Don't think of it ' (a modern degraded species of the ancient Stoic Philosophy). JAMES YELLOW (in agony). "But I shall catch a dreadful cold." (Unlocks trunk-finds matches- strikes a light, and proceeds to dress.) JOHN BLUE. "What are you going to do?" JAMES YELLOW  (hoarsely). "I'm going down stairs; Ill catch a dreadful cold up here!" JOHN BLUE. "What'll you do down stairs?" JAMES YELLOW (dressed, and enveloped in his large shawl, and looking vacantly about). "I don't kinow; sit up all night, I suppose." JOHN BLUE.  "Sit up!  Vhere? Lights all out by twelve-fires, too-sit up in the dark 2" JAMES YELLOW  (dreamily).: "Yes, that's true. Oh, isn't this awful! I. shall have a horrible cold to-morrow." (Snuffs through'nose with effort, and talks hoarse.)  JOHN BLUE. "We might take some brandy, and   * *     '     -    * " smoke. That'll keep off the cold, and give us some- thing to breathe besides damp air." JAMES YELLOW (brightening): "That's a capital idea! Reach me the flask." (Silence for some time, only broken by an occasional peculiar noise, caused by drinking out of -a bottle--uddenly choking); "My stars! what's this ." JOHrN ILUE.  "Why  - What? Why, brandy, isn't it?" (frightened lest it may be "poison"). JAMES YELLOW.   "Why, it tastes like  (shudder runs through frame). JOHN BLUE (tasting).' "By George! our folks must have made a mistake; that's the brandy the baby was washed in!" A  picturesque tableau-vivant now follows, in which both parties take similar parts, consisting in the exhibition of an energetic inclination to turn one's self inside-out. This performance having been gone through with, to the mutual satisfaction of both parties, JAMES YELLOW (breaks the silence of the panto- \ mime). "Oh! isn't this awful?" JOHN BLUE (silently smokes). I JAMES YELLOW (alio waxes grum, and no more "breaks the silence,' but is soon seen in bed, with 83*  &#xD;<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC8237-00000021"/> -         'w         .    - 42 clothes, collar, and boots on, and  wrapped  up in his eternal shawD. The room  fills 'with smoke, which soon shows its sedative influence on our two heroes, and they begin-very vulgarly-to snore. \                       ' %  ' ,   CHAPTER VIII. THE next day opened-dismal, rainy, and un- pleasant, again. After breakfast, we went to the Reading-room, and looked out of the windows. What wonder that John Blue began, piteously, to commence his moanings?-"And is this to be the amount of adventure we are to experience? Have we come forth to encounter nothing but storms? to buffet, with nothing but an umbrella, against nothing but rain? to fight damp air with brandy and cigar-smoke? to' explore cities only from win- dows? Are these the prospects before us? Algs! alas! , Oh, miserable beings that we are!" "Yes," echoed Yellow, "miserable, indeed. Here I have a letter to write, and nothing to write about but rain-water." As he said this, he turned away from the window, and looked, drearily, about the apartment in which they were sitting; when he saw- a small dog, under a chair, violently wagging its tail, while a man, seated on the chair, deeply interested ' ' .              I  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8237-00000022"/> " in a newspaper, was scratching his leg, which the dog's wagging tail tickled. Truly it is wonderful what small things create revolutions. Both John Blue and James Yellow, it was evident, had ceased to repine; for two merrier countenances never left a hotel than theirs, as, un- furling an umbrella to the blast, they sailed, in , india-rubbers, through the mud, to the capitol. The grass was green and beautiful, and contrasted strangely with the dry, leafless trees, and the white building that rose up like a monument before us. We ascended the steps, had a fine view of the city and "'White House," entered the "Rotunda," and then the "Senate Chamber." James Yellow had a letter of introduction to one of the senators, so he advanced boldly within the railing; while John Blue seated himself on one of the benches- against the wall, and wondered what was meant by "the honor of a  seat on the floor," an expression that he remembered to have heard somewhere.  Hie was soon partially enlightened on this point, however, by an austere- looking individual, who advanced, and with a clumsy but sufficiently expressive movement of his right hand in the direction of the door, intimated that none but distinguished strangers were allowed " the honor of a seat on the floor." Now, John flt that this was   45 wrong-that it was doing him great injustice, besides using him  very inhospitably. "Was he not a stranger in Washington? And, as to the 'distin- guished' part of the qualification, wasn't he, at that very time, in the act of commencing a tour of general observation, exploration, and discovery, which, for its beneficial results on the world in general, and on the vast and varied interests of his country in par- ticular, was to make his name as immortal as the names of some of the 'distinguished senators' them- selves? And were these senators so blind as not to see this future greatness plainly foretelling itself to them in the fire of his eye, in the roughness of his outer appearance, and in the majestic silence which he preserved! o And were not these senators , wantonly sacrificing the interests of their country, in thus neglecting the proffered opportunity of making friends with him? Could they be aware of the highly impolitic and discourteous conduct of this gruff porter? And was it not his duty to inform them who and what he was?"   While these thoughts had successively chased each other through John Blue's mind, they had not in the least disturbed his composure. No, eye could have found in his placid countenance, the slightest indication of the storm of contending feelings which raged within.  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8237-00000023"/> " He had by this time fully convinced himself that he had0 a right to keep his "seat on the floor ;" but immediately calling to mind how it would disturb the equanimity of those grave senators, to appeal to them, and the length of time, and the number of speeches, and the possible senatorial duels, and the general excitement throughout the country, which the due disposition of so weighty a question would necessarily involve, all personal considerations van- ished in an instant. He rose from his seat, and, for a while, stood aghast at the frightful scene he had pictured, until, seeing the right hand of that perse- vering porter still waving doorward, he magnanimously, determined to waive his right, too, for the good of his country; and being of a retiring disposition, he with- drew from the "floor of the senate." But'what of James Yellow, meanwhile  Let us return to him. Almost immediately after the perusal of his letter of introduction, his senatorial friend, with a brilliancy which, in its progress, irradiated his careworn features until they assumed a kind of lurid, unearthly aspect, bethought himself of " a very important engagement" with some committee outside, ! bade Yellow a hasty, but very affectionate adieu, and vanished, leaving him to his reflections. These, though many in number, and generally of a melan-   47 choly cast, were too quick and brief to become very pps; and he, therefore, favors the reader with a few of them, in the appendix, A. He had been offered "the honor of a seat on the floor," but declined accepting it, fully sympathizing with his friend Blue, who, not sufficiently appreciating such honors, cast an audacious eye, as he left "the floor," towards a seat by one of the small desks, as if looking forward to the day his instinct smelt out some distance a-head, when he should occupy such a chair voce Patrice. How absurd it is, that neither the world nor the United States Senate, will honor a great personage' until he proves himself sucht. A man may have all the necessary qualifications and powers to become distinguished i.-case he should at any time desire it); yet, if he lack present ambition to call those powers into action, he remains one of Ot .ro Aol Lforever. (Ergo, distinguished greatness is a compound of actual inherent power and personal ambition). Thus was it with us (as our modesty suggests) in our present circumstances. One of us unceremoniously turned from the floor of the senate; the other's acquaintance but slightly valued by one of the senators! Such is the blindness of the greatest and most far-sighted of men!  They cannot read any part of the histories or biographies of the -future!  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8237-00000024"/> 48 To return once more-not that we did so lower ourselves as to return to the ground floor, bodily- we next find ourselves in the gallery, amongst the ladies. Now we can breathe more freely, and are better enabled, by reason of our elevated position,  to "look down upon" the senate beneath. ^  .  .  . ' -   CHAPTER IX. SEVERAL members now came in and took their seats, and shortly afterwards the session was opened by prayer. A short senator now rises and says something about "Bill," which seems, to have an electric effect upon another senator, who springs to his feet and wishes to know " the reasons." Short senator, enraged, sits down, rises again, and makes remark, but so choked with choler (?) that the remark is inaudible. The other senator now rises, and wishes again to know "the reasons " (word "reasons " in a voice of thunder). Short senator rises, purple in the face, and shouts out, with rage, "I'withdraw my motion;" looks around, makes a flourish of contempt with his hand, and then sits down, looking daggers at the other senator: two men hate one another. Other senator now rises, puts his hands in his pockets, assumes a lofty mien, and walks magnificently up and down the main passage. Another senator now rises, and wants money from     ,  .  &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC8237-00000025"/> 50 Government to build a house f6r somebody-cost, $17,000. Another senator objects to "somebody" having a house at all. Another one makes facetious remark about "$17,000 for house; " "And then," says he, '$17,000 for furniture 'for house," pursing up his lips with contempt; "and then," continues he, elevat- ing upper lip till it reaches end-of his nose, " he'll want $17,000 to furnish furniture." Here James Yel-p low looked at John Blue, inquiringly, for the point, but receiving no reply, and noticing a thoughtful ex- pression, asked him the cause; whereupon, John Blue replied that he was still wondering in what consisted 4' the honor of a seat on the floor." Nothing interesting came up to-day, nothing -be- sides making motions and presenting "bills." Some of the senators, seated before their desks, were reading newspapers, one looking over Punch, another par- ing his nails, another squirting tobacco-juice about; and some, evidently newly elected, seemed completely absorbed by the important topics before-mentioned, and looking "as Cicero saith of Piso, that when he answered him he fetched one of his brows up to his forehead and bent the other down to his chin." John Blue still continuing to look abstracted, James Yellow again asked hiln what he was thinking' about; to which he replied, that he was thinking   51  . what a splendid hunt they might have "on the floor;" "for," said he," look over this list of senators' names; and you will see that to make a hunting scene, the DODGE would be to make HUNTER CHASE BADGER into UNDERWOOD; BADGER, finding PEARCE in his side, would rush on DOWNS; BADGER now feels a RAE of hope, and makes for a neighboring mill-pond, where he disturbs FISH; MLLER, near by, knocks BADGER on the head; all WADE in the water, and  capture stunned BADGER; JAMES carries hirm to 'the table,' and lbrings likewise FISH and RusK; the BUT- "ER now brings in (H)ALE; and, at the noise of BELL, all rush in to demolish FISH, RUSK, and (H)ALE." We both now felt frightened, and expected to be immediately arrested for treason. We felt, too, as though we had almost brought ourselves, by this ebul- lition, to a level with "the floor" itself; so we con- cluded to take a hasty departure. From the Senate Gallery we went to "the House of Representatives." Here, a man, in a voice of tlun- der, was reading a long, prosy, paper. We left "the House of Representatives." We next went to "the Supreme Court Room." This apartment is eligibly situated in the cellar; and, being naturally damp, we announced our entrance by  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC8237-00000026"/> 52 violent fits of sneezing, and short, choking coughs, which the formidable array of solemn, motionless figures on the bench, before us, could not in anywise repress. These figures, seen, but indistinctly, puzzled us considerably at first, their backs being towards the light, whi they themselves, concealed in roomy silk gowns, sat stolld and immovable; but, as our eyes became accustomed to the obscurity, we discovered that they were living Judges of the Supreme Court, In the center of the room stood a small, thin man, screaming at the top of his voice, sometimes banging books about, sometimes slapping his hands vehemently together, and sometimes jumping up and down in his excitement, and twisting his body in all directions. Now he would be heard in the loud, hoarse voice of pas- sion, now in the subdued tone of feeling, now the elo- quent outhreak, now glass of water to quench thirst. "If," said he (raising his forefinger slowly, and then bringing it down rapidly to meet his hand; missing his hand, and losing equilibrium, he recovers himself and repeats), "if the judges would read the Reports of Cases" (points, to ten immense volumes before him, and brings down his hand violently on the back of one of them), " they would see  ' (what they would see was lost in the deep:intensity of his tone). Ile then drew an affecting picture of "a slain man,"   durin which we left the Supreme Court Room, left the Capl, and returned to the hotel. The next day, the weather. making a slight demon- stration of an intention to clear up, by a small exhibi- tion of blue sky, we felt our spirits rise a little. We went to the President's house, at which James Yellow gazed with longing eyes, and, at length, actually ex- pressed an ardent desire to be its occupant, as the head of the nation; in which ambition John Blue sympathized not the least: John thought that it would be a sufficient bore to be the head of a family, a catastrophe which, he solemnly declared, he should avert in his own case by every means in his power. It was wonderful how confidential, and yet how mys-  terious John Blue always became on this subject. During our walk over the grounds, we came to the stables, and were much impressed by the republican simplicity of the menage of the President of the United States-an ordinary wooden stable, which, at the time, was occupied by only two horses, while a negro outside, in shirt and trowsers, was cheerfully singing as he rubbed down an old gray nag. In Eng- land, you must have a ticket to visit the "Queen's Mews," where you see horses and carriages enough to supply a whole village, and a small colony of men, dressed in the queen's livery, to take care of them.  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC8237-00000027"/> 54 We were sufficiently impressed with the outside appearance of the War Department, the Treasury, Post-Office, and other public buildings; and not ex- periencing any very strong desire to see their interiors, we didn't seek admittance-; excepting the Post-Office, which, we believe, we did enter to see if there were   , any letters for us, but were referred elsewhere. The streets of Washington are very wide, but their names struck us as being rather comical. There was F street North B; D street South C; H street East P; X street West J; &amp;c. '^.   CHAPTER X. ONE egg-one mouthful of steak-one cup of -offee-and one bite of brown bread, was all the )reakfast Blue got one morning, after having been ulled out of a warm bed into the cold darkness of 2 A. M., by James Yellow (it was the morning we eft Washington). Both were hurried into the car- iage, the door was slammed, the driver scrambled nto his seat, and the horses were lashed and driven nto a perfect foam; and all for the ultimate purpose, s it proved, of reaching the depot to find that we rere half an hour before the time, and that we were ed to the depot to wait for said time; whereas, me and tide never waited for any man. We found the cars, on starting, a fair type, as we supposed,  f a Western character. He had on light yellow owsers, a bright blue vest, a gray coat,and Kossuth at; his hair was long, and his face had an open, Ald, resolute, independent, look. On reaching Baltimore we changed cars; and now  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC8237-00000028"/> 56 commenced' a most extraordinary railroad ride; some- times we'd drive a-head with fearful velocity, and then suddenly pull up, and' move at an intolerably slow pace ; and then as suddenly tearing on again, as,if mad, we'd'skie around hills-then down, and then up-and then skie around more hills. We were very glad when we reached Harrisburg; and the first thing we did was to jump out of the cars; and having had nothing to eat since we started, the second thing we did, was to ravenously seize upon an old woman, who was peddling dirty oyster-patties. James Yellow had barely got one of the oysters in his mouth, and John Blue one on his fork, when we heard the confounded locomotive whistle; so we paddled off, patties in hand, for the cars, which we reached safely, to find that our oysters. had all dropped out, and left us nothing but dirty pie-crust. The country, from Harrisburg to Hollidaysburg, is 'a beautiful one.' James Yellow said it strongly reminded him of the road from Laibach to Murz- zenschlag, in- Austria. The resemblance consisted in there being a similar turbid, uneasy stream rolling by, and similar high hills rising on either side. The ears were dreadfully hot, being heated by a stove, which looked, to John Blue's heated imagination, like a red devil. We were verymuch struck by the   57 great number of fine churches, with green blinds, that we passed; but could not see into the necessity for so many in a country where the majority of inhabitants seemed to consist of the cattle grazing near these edifices. We afterwards discovered that they were intended for those same cattle; being what are com- monly called " bars." A man in the cars attracting our attention by the loud tone of his conversation, we learned by that conversation that he had been abroad-had been to Italy-had known a man who preferred staying in a station-house, to walking a short distance to the house in which Sallust once lived, merely because the weather was cold and unpleasant. He, himself, was once a State senator in Wisconsin and "when he was in the. senate" doud voice) "he presented a bill" doud voice). Some incoherent remarks now followed in an under tone, in which the words "currency" and "par" frequently came into play; the whole being concluded by a very loud remark, that "he having been unable to carry it, the resuit was" (of course), " that everything went wrong." We reached Hollidaysburg late in the evening and found ourselves in a lonesome place consisting, as far as we could see, of a solitary house at the foot of the Alleghanies. This h]ouse, solitary as it seemed 4  &#xD;<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC8237-00000029"/> 58 outside, was, however, any thing but solitary within doors. A multitude of famished travelers rushed resistlessly into the eating-room, to secure seats at a long table; and among the number we, James Yellow and John Blue, who had almost lost our individuality in the throng. We, however, rapidly recovered it at the sight of the viands which, though meager in quantity and poor in quality, were not rejected by our palates, whose sensibility and fastid- iousness had been considerably blunted by that demo- cratic leveler, IIunger. Having at length reached a state of comparative sanity, we bethought us of securing a room for the night; but upon application, which was both confidential and conciliatory in words and tone, were coolly informed that they could stow us away in a room with twelve others. These twelve others proved, on inspection, to be twelve of that dyspeptic, nk, lantern-jawed, bilious-looking, race of beings who, as we afterwards learned, haunt our Western country. Now, John Blue would no more think, for an instant, of trusting himself alone in a room  with suckh beings as these, than-James Yellow. Visions of such apparitions as these, stalking about in disturbed slumbers, flitted before our weary eyes; imaginary bowie-knives were already smoking in our vitals; loud snorings and louder nightmares,   59 the natural concomitants of such disordered diges- tions as these men appeared to enjoy, were all antici- pated, and the prospect didn't please us; so, in sullen despair, we walked back gloomily to the bar-room, and there seating ourselves on a trunk, ornamented with large and exceedingly comfortable brass nail- heads, we prepared to smoke the night through. Some insist that tobacco is one of the deadliest of poisons. Our cigars, however, killed time very slowly that night. As we sat moodily puffing away, about 12, P. M., the barkeeper, moved probably by the sight of so much misery, approached us, and said he had found a room with a double bed in it. It was intensely cold, but we had only four hburs to sleep; so we covered up as well as we could, and set to- work to sleep it all up. John Blue'said he was a very long while commencing, but at length became unconscious; and James Yellow remarked now very strange that was, inasmuch as it was precisely his case.  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC8237-00000030"/> CH APTER XI. AT half-past 4, we were both startled out of bed by a terrible racket in the entry. We found, on nquiring, that they were " only waking us up." The noise was indescribable; but whatever its nature or. its cause, it certainly had the merit of being decidedly effective in its result. We were told to hurry, as brealfast was ready, and the cars would start soon; but that was all superfluous, for the intense cold hurried us sufficiently, without any other motive being called in as an auxiliary. In the cold cars, at this time in the morning, and ascending mountains, James Yellow and John Blue were excusable for priming themselves so heavily and"repeatedly as they did with brandy, We went over by means of the inclined-plane system, an exceedingly slow process. The passengers 1were all very cold, very wretched, and very silent with the exception of one croaker, who repeatedly informed the whole car that he "hadn't had any breakfast that   " morning; and that he was very much troubled with being afraid of accidents on inclined planes; and, also,. that he had a bad rheumatism." A pale, thin man next to him, turning on him a pair of wild, haggard eyes, ,earnestly asked him if he really thought there was any danger. "Danger," replies he, "to be sure there is; why, I was traveling up . one of these inclined planes, as they call them-I believe it was in this very car-and a man sat next  to me--he looked something like you; you're the  kind of fellows that always get hurt, when all of a sudden-don't be alarmed, my friend,-but'all of a sudden, he said he thought something was going to happen; my stars! how; much you do look like him! I should think you were brothers; and what do you think lie did? why-see here, my friend, if your eyes keep starting out of your head in that way much longer, I'll do what he did; he jumped through that window, to save his life as he thought; and, it proving afterwards a false alarm, he came back again; but he hadn't a tooth left in his head-,when lie talked, he showed nothing but gums. We all thought he'd lost his teeth from fright; but, you see, he had false teeth-how much yours look like themr! why, I'd almost swear they're the very same teeth, only I know he lost them," Here all in the neigh.  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC8237-00000031"/> 62 borhood, who had heard this account, were in a roar; and what followed was lost in the noise, which at length subsided, when he added, "and that's what I call an accident." He now wanted to know how fast we were going. Answer. "Twenty miles an hour." "Oh, my I you make me dizzy," replied our facetious friend; at which the whole car- was in a roar again. A big, clumsy fellow, who was standing up, now suddenly fell back, and thrust his arm through a pane of glass. The stream of cold air let in, by no means mollified us in favor of the clumsy clown; especially as our nerves were somewhat- disturbed by the cracking of the glass; and the car again became silent, even 'to oppression, when our facetious friend again breaks the silence, by a story of a representative to the Assembly in Vermont, from a small place containing only five persons. During the session, he was asked if he were the best man they had; "Wall," said ho, "I reckon there was two others smarter, but they hadn't clotlhs fit to come." Meanwhile, the day thad advanced, and we found ourselves passing slowly through a wild, romantic country, with. lofty mountains rising around us, not very aspiring ones-not exactly scaling the heavens,   63 nor very much resembling that piling of mountains on top of one another, in which Pelion, Ossa, and Olym- pus were involved-but respectable mountains, that would stand muster in good society, rnd find a position on the map. There was a mountain torrent, too, that raged and boiled and bubbled, quite creditably for its source. Near the torrent, we saw a solitary house with a broken chimney, from which blue smoke was curling gracefully upwards. Some huge trees, lately felled, were lying motionless and silent, like dead giants on a battle-field; and large gnarly roots, that looked as though they'd struggled, and resisted being pulled up, to the death. A snow-storm now set in, and began to hide these wild beauties, and we began to feel our ride very tedious. At length we, reached the place where- we were to take stages. It was so intensely cold, that we all rushed into the little house that stood near the track, and let our baggage take care of itself. John . Blte had always asserted, in contra- diction to James Yellow, that to travel was nothing more than to go about from place to place, for the express purpose of superintelnding a trunk; James Yellow's definition being, that traveling was not- merely going about for such a purpose. On this occasion occurred a practical exemplification of James  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC8237-00000032"/> ": Yellow's theory; and he was not slow to take advan- tage of it-a circumstance which James Yellow's friends ever after applauded, inasmuch as John Blue has never been known since that day to bring forward that favorite theory of his, which he used to boast was the fruit of deep and painful speculation. The time soon arrived when we were obliged to issue forth, shivering, into the cold. Our very trunks seemed shivering on the outside of the coach, the inside of which was crammed with shivering mortals, to the number of nine. James Yellow and John Blue occupied one-third of the front seat, the remaining two-thirds being filled by an immense individual, who put us both awfully into the shade, but whom we soon afterwards reduced to a most abject state of subjection, by means of cigar smoking. The smoking and riding backwards combined, soon put to flight all romantic visions he may have enter- tained of his dinner giving support to his unwieldy  carcase; for that dinner, in a short time after our start, rapidly disappeared through the window. Facing us on the middle seat of the coach, were three more poor miserables; and on the back,. three others, blue with cold. To our joy, we recognized among the number the facetious man of the cars, and with him his nervous friend.   65  Our road Was called "The West (something) Plank Road Route, running by the Youghiogheny river," and was worthy of its title, all except the ' plank." If twenty-seven miles of stony ground and rocks, and one mile of plank, constitute a. "plank road" of'twenty-eight miles in length, then, indeed, was ours "a plank road." We were jolted about for the first mile in the most unmerciful manner; and our facetious friend immediately commenced his experiments on the nervous one's system, by sud- denly suggesting "easy upsets on such a road." This miserable, nervous individual, was already worn to a skeleton by his past anxieties; and he now thrust his head out of the window, and, fidgetting about, commenced boring a hole in John Blue's leg, with one of his sharp knees; while the facetious man added, "that a great many accidents happened on this road, especially when the coaches were heavily loaded; and now I think of it," continued he, " we're uncommonly heavily loaded." Shortly after, in a doleful tone, "Since coaches do upset in great numbers on this road, what chance is there for us, who are so uncommonly heavily loaded 2"The only resource left for the nervous man, was to go crazy, which he seemed in a fair way of doing. His eyes gleamed so wildly, that both James Yellow and John 4*  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC8237-00000033"/> *.ii '66 Blue produced their cigar-cases, and proceeded to smoke, notwithstanding the remonstrances of the pale, fat sufferer. What were the fat man's sufferings to lunacy in a stage-coach, and the lunatic on the seat directly opposite you, and armed with sharp bones! The smoke actually seemed to have a sedative effect on the nervous man; and though the fat man suffered greatly, still, of two evils, we, in common with other people, always prefer the least. Although the Youghiogheny river rolls near so barbarous a road to ride over, it yet waters a fine country; and the views from our window consisted of such beautiful landscapes, and-so frequent, that we felt ourselves amply repaid for the jolting. We did not 'reach Turtle creek, the end of the plank-road route, until dark, and thence took the cars for Pittsburgh. Our facetious friend, from whom we had been separated for a 'short time, now made his appearance. He said that there was a fine car in front, but nobody in it; that he had sat there alone for some time, but nobody coming in, and hearing the engine whistle, he felt "skeered," and so thought he'd go where there. was more company. "I say, little boy," exclaimed he abruptly, "don't cough so much-you disturb my   67 nerves;" and, "You Dutchman, you, turn: that gun the other way." Dutchman. "It ish not loaded." "I tell you it is; I smell it; it's loaded with sour- krout." But if we should go on enumerating his eccentricities and stories, we should need the patience and pe^l of a Boswell. We reached Pittsburgh about 9 P. M.   The air was so full of smoke, that we were unfavorably impressed by the place; and we determined, even before reaching the hotel, to leave Pittsburgh the very next morning.   &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC8237-00000034"/> CHAPTER XII. BOTla John Blue and James Yellow had, an in- stinctive desire to escape from the soot and smoke of the city called Pittsburgh, especially when they found that on the morning after their arrival they had been r obliged to re-shirt themselves twice before 10 o'clock, and to perform their ablutions, not only once before breakfast, but constantly afterwards; so that being in Pittsburgh became, in short, nothing but a constant state of wash and change of linen: wherefore, they sighed uncommonly loud for green fields, and took the first boat for Cincinnati. This boat was called "Messenger No. 2." What had been the fate of "Messenger No. 1," was a mys- tery that we dared not attempt to penetrate; but there was a mournful air about "No. 2," sufficiently suggestive of the-probable termination of its predeces- sor; so, with a shudder, we selected- a state-room directly over the boiler. We say "selected," for, we were asked to "select;" but after having selected   69. every other one, we discovered that this was the; only one to select, itheing the only one that remained un- taken. We breathed more freely, however, on opening our window and looking out; and our spirits were quite restored when we beheld; near us, a steamboat labeled "Pike Jo. 9." We could conceive of no state more inconsolable than that of being in "Pike No. 9;" and it was with most unfeigned comnmiseration that we regarded that individual who was also at the time re- garding us, from the window of the state-room directly over the boiler of "No. 9."' What has since become of him, we have never learned; probably, for the reason that he has become nothing, as that would well account for the fact of our having heard nothing. Arriving at Pittsburgh in the night and leaving it the next morning, our acquaintance with that city was not a very long-standing one, and our knowledge of it not very profound. Viewed from the deck of the steamer, it presented the extraordinary appearance of a cloud, the edge of which was lined with steam- boat pipes. And this is all (but quite sufficient as we deem) that we know of Pittsburgh. The boat having commenced locomotion by mnak-  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC8237-00000035"/> 70 ing a tremendous noise, we thought it advisable to retreat to the shelter of the cabin. The "Ladies' Cabin" was separated from  the "Gentlemen's" by folding doors, which, however, were sufficiently far ajar-to allow us a peep at the bliss- within. John Blue, whose objections to the married state had always been insurmountable, now acknowledged that that state did possess one advant- age in the facilities it afforded of a snug berth in the ladies' cabin of 'Western steamboats. His greatest objection to marriage had been the condition, in- separably annexed to it, of feeding and clothing an- other body beside his own; and not, perhaps, merely one, but also other little probable contingenoies, in unforeseen numbers. He contended that it makes man too material, consuming all his best powers and time in making bread and clothes (or, what is the same thing, making money to buy them), an occupation not at all consonant with the character of a college grad- uate. But this objection now seemed almost balanced by the advantages offered to the married in the seclu- sion and remoteness of the ladies' cabin, especially as the noise continued fearfully to increase, and the boat sensibly to tremble,while the heat of the floor over the-boiler was very uncomfortably perceptible. We soon, however, became accustomed to these alarming   71 phenomena, as we at first considered them, and finally ventured to enter our state-room, and even to open the door which looked out upon the water, for it had two doors, one opening into the cabin, and the other upon the deck, near the bulwarks. We had no sooner, however, opened this door than all our fears vanished before the magnificent view presented to us, and we entirely forgot the heat of the floor, high-pressure steam-engines, and "No. 2 Messenger" boats. There are in this world some savage natures who delight to clothe themselves in shooing jackets, buck- skin trowsers, and long cowhide boots, and then, with slouched felt hats jammed carelessly on their heads, guns slung over their shoulders, knives in their belts, and pioneering hatchets in their hands, to penetrate the darkest and most hidden recesses: of the most ap- palling and terrific-wildernesses of Nature. Neither James Yellow nor John Blue were of this stamp. Their peaceful natures infinitely preferred to forego the knowl- edge of such mysteries, when they were to be purchased at such a price; and, consequently, they may not be supposed capable of that pure enthusiasm requisite to the full enjoyment of such scenes. We deny the truth of the conclusion, We do not believe that any one ever did or could have enjoyed more intensely than we did, the beauties we saw that day. Without the  &#xD;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC8237-00000036"/> 'iz , necessity of being clad in shooting jackets and buck- skin trowsers, or being otherwise equipped as before- mentioned, we yet had, opened before us, all those delicious sources of delight which are usually sought for in such an equipment. The beautiful river Ohio (beautiful from its associations and scenery, though turbid in itself) was our pioneering hatchet, clearing a broad pathway for us through the center of our Republic, and showing us the types of our political liberty in the freedom of our own noble forests and boundless prairies. We could not, for the world, have used guns, had they been slung over our shoulders, to shoot out of our feathered companions that life which they seemed to enjoy so intensely, as they whirled around in circles over our heads, or floated luxuriously off towards the shore.            ' The quiet beauty of the landscape, or the wild grandeur of the bliffs, we do not pretend to describ : we lay no claim to fhe pen of the poet: we onlyjfelt the beauties and the grandeur that we saw, and that this faculty, alone, was a sufficient gift to call foithl our gratitude; for we marked that day with a white stone,  - . zr Ad   CHAPTER XIII. WE reached Cincinnati at 10, P. M. Our arrival was attended by the disgusting circumstancesof dark- ness and gloom, while the rain" fell in torrents. The flickering light afforded by a bundle of pine sticks blazing in a wire basket, and which illumined a soli- tary cab on the wharf with its solitary driver, only added to the spectral feeling we had already begun to experience. We lit cigars to soothe our nerves, and entered the cab as rapidly as possible, which soon rolled noisily through the silent streets to the hotel. On Yellow's writing our names in the book, the proprietor, who was leaning over him, asked if he were any relation of Josh, Yellow. James hesitated, didn't know, but finally thought he must be, as the name was familiar.  The proprietor stimulated his memory by the name of Tayleure. "Oh, yes," said Yellow, L" why, to be sure I do; why, that's my father." "Oh, ah, indeed!" said the proprietor. "Waiter, con- duct these gentlemen to No. 147," a fine room, as it  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC8237-00000037"/> 4p proved to be, in the, third story (heretofore, weve been up in the sixth or seventh), where, as soon as the door was closed, Blue expressed his deep obligations to Yellow for having been the means of procuring such elegant accommodations. Going out the next morning to view the city, we stumbled unfortunately into the business quarter, and consequently detested the place: we passed nothing but dirty drug stores. On extending our stroll, how- ever, we reached a more pleasant -quarter, where were some neat, quiet dwellings, and were better pleased. As Cincinnati is the great depot of slaughtered hogs, we felt emboldened to reply to a person asking us where Mr. B---- lived, that we were strangers in the land of Ham. It was here that the celebrated mas- sacre of 400,000 hogs took place in 1848, and which stain has not yet been wiped out. A canal ruiLs through the city, which (the city) is bounded on the north, east, and west by trees, and south by steamboat pipes: beyond the canal, the houses look as though they were running up hill. We drank some of the native wine, the "Catawha," which gave our faces a vinegar aspect for some time afterwards. We would recommend, however, the " sparkling Catawha," which tastes somewhat like champagne, though more acid and bitter.   - 75 To reach the Cincinnati Observatory, which John Quincy Adams called " the light-house of the skies "- though why the deuce he did bothers J. B. and J. Y. to this day-we were obliged to climb a steep hill. On reaching the top, in a prouse perspiration, we dis- covered, to our disgust, that we had chosen the wrong day for admission; so were obliged to content ourselves with the view from the hill, which was truly beautiful, comprising the city at our feets the Ohio river winding round the city, and an extensive prospect of the coun- try beyond. We wore determined not to be poetical in this description, and we flatter ourselves that we have admirably succeeded. A rapid succession of cold shivers admonished us to retreat out of the cold wind that whistled over the top of this hill; so we descended again to the city; and the next morning, anxious to move on, and reach something more excit- ing than we had yet experienced, we took the boat "Telegraph, No. 2," for Louisville. Here was "No. 2" again, which set us to wondering again what No. 2 meant-wondered if No. 1 burst her boiler- felt uneasy, and shifted our seats, which began to feel hot; felt very anxious to know whether No. 1 did actually burst her boiler; but forgot our anxieties at the sight of a pretty woman in a blue josey, who now made her appearance in the ladies' cabin. We both  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC8237-00000038"/> detested blue joseys, but admired pretty women. Blue immediately commenced forming schemes to make her acquaintance, but his ardor cooled considerably, when on her having entered a state-room she shortly after re-appeared with a small child. Alas! crushed hopes! pretty woman married! Blue said he didn't admire the western women, they had such big mouths, and bad figures, and broad, flat backs, and then their shoulders seemed up to their heads, and they walked with such a ricketty motion-except the pretty wo- man; but she was married; and then what was one among so many, especially when she's married? Two  small boys now began to fight, and one small baby fell down and cried? Blue vowed he'd never marry: with two small boys who fought, and one small baby who cried, he'd go wild, and how did he know but, such might be his lot. The banks of the river presented a strange con- trast; on one side was Kentucky, with green grass and trees in full foliage; on the other, Indiana, with bare, brown hills, and the leaves of the trees but just budding forth. Having sufficiently admired this con- trast, we looked again into the cabin, where a man with a glazed cap on and seated on a chair, was bal- ancing himself on its hind legs, and darting forth electric glances at a woman with whom he was cvi- -  '               *  '   " dently attempting to commence a flirtation. On the termination of their interview, the man rose red and triumphant, and his eyes gleamed with an overflow of joy; regarding not sublunary things, he fell over the stove, recovered himself, and walking off, proudly looking back, fell over a chair. At length subdued, he slunk out of the cabin, and was next seen outside, smoking as if for a wager. A beautiful night and bright moon lighted us into Louisville. We took a hack, and for the first portion of our ride to the hotel felt joyous and in high spirits; b ut the streets proving in a dreadful condition as we proceeded, we went ricketty, hicketty, bump against the roof; and, having barely escaped knocking out our brains, at length descended the hack-steps in a bruised and battered condition; entered the hotel, and being ushered into a room, with the walls yellow- washed, but with a smell of fresh linen, we soon slip- ped in between the clean, white sheets; and John Blue the next morning asserted that he had never slept better in his life; to which James Yellow added a " ditto" for himself. We were still luxuriating beneath the bed-clothes, in that species of dreamy reverie expressly Invented for morning snoozers, when a loud knock at the door grated on our nerves, and a voice shouted out " Here's  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC8237-00000039"/> 78 card for 82." Yellow, being nearest the door, rose and received it, at the same time sending down word that we were both sick a-bed, and couldn't be dis- turbed. James, looking sleepily at the card, read "Mat. Muggins, Louisville Hotel" (and, in pencil) "For John Blue." "Here, Blue, it's a challenge: I thought something of the sort would come out of your staring at that married woman." Blue didn't recognize the name, so after breakfast he went to the Louisville Hotel to solve the mystery; but it was only deepened, when, on sending up his card, he received, for reply, that "Mr. Muggins was sick a-bed."  ' Blue having rejoined Yellow, who had been waiting the result, and the air in the city feeling hot and stifling, we took an omnibus, and rode into the country. The omnibus stopped at a point on the Ohio river, where there was a ferry-boat, which we took, and were steamed over to New Albany, Indiana. This town presenting no very peculiar attractions, and our only object in going there being, to sat that we 'had been in Indiana, we immediately returned by the same boat to Kentucky again; not, however, before Yellow had been seen grubbing in the dirt by the captain of the ferry-boat, who seemed very much astonished at 'tie proceeding. Yellow's object was   79 to preserve a memento of Indiana; and the best article for the purpose, that was here accessible, was a dirty piece of rock, which he put into his pocket. Going back; the boat was crowded with wild 'horses-a circumstance which rendered our return trip quite a pleasant one. The horses were fifty or sixty in number, all united by the neck by means of a long rope. On the way, this rope became entangled in the horses' feet, and upset some of them. which accident by no means tended to soothe the riotous disposition of those excitable animals, who seemed to dislike such a crowded mode of boating very much. The ferry-boat was open-decked; and James Yellow and John Blue being jammed in among kicking, rearing, and falling horses, and having been unfortunately separated from each other's counsel and sympathy, were kept wide awake during the passage; and at its termination, James Yellow's nervous system seemed to have been irreparably shattered. Having miraculously arrived in safety on the Kentucky shore, we extricated-ourselves from the horses' feet as speedily as possible, left the boat without any reluctance, and taking the omnibus again, returned to Louisville. On the way, we passed a woman With a pet pig,  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC8237-00000040"/> 80 This pig would run forward after butterflies, then run back and look up in its mistress' face, and then bound back again after butterflies, his corkscrew-tail vibra- ting like a spiral wire. It was a very curious spectacle, and only confirmed the truth of the old saying, that "Education makes the man."  This pig's instinct, by education, had been elevated to that of the dog. The ride was very dusty, and when we reached the hotel, we looked like travel-stained wayfarers, much to the astonishment of the host and waiters. The' afternoon being pleasant, we walked into the country, infinitely preferring it to the hot town, and again returned covered with dust. --Our host now regards, with bewildered amazement, two young men who frequently sally forth, and invariably return begrimed and covered with dust. Finding another card at the offico "for John Blue," we became frightened by tie rapid increase of acquaintances, and therefore straightway booked ourselves in the first coach, to start the next morning for the Mammoth Cavet If any one feels curious to know what we thought of Louisville, wewould say that we consider it a pretty little town; but that we liked it better in the afternoon ihan in the morning, the probable cause   81 being, that it was then after dinner, and the sun seemed to shine pleasanter, and there was less bustle and less appearance of business, and it wasn't so dusty in the country. Our readers have most likely noticed, ere this, our particular disinclination to remain in cities, so long as it was possible to get out of them. The season of the year at which we reached Louisville was peculiarly favorable, being the latter part of April; and, since reaching home again, James Yellow looks back to Louisville as the pleasantest city lie ever visited. ,5  ffi^  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC8237-00000041"/> CHAPTERT XIV. O, ye sluggards, who snug in bed, waste the eshness of the morning, unclose now those gummed- up eyelids of yours, and regard, as patterns worthy of imitation, John Blue and James Yellow, removing the comfortable coverlids, and valiantly exposing their warm limbs to the outer air! We dresse4 uselves hastily by the spasmodic rays of a miserable tallow candle; and without the preliminary of breakfast, took our places in the coach, whichwas waiting for us at the door. (Apendi, B.) Oh, ye writers who expatiate on the delights of early rising; who, in glowing colors, depict walks before breakfast, and the 'enviable vivacity of men with empty stomachs; we unhesitatingly proclaim you as impostors, who, with air-castles, delude the weaker brethren. We always did prefer the deep mystery of midnight to the cold rqality of morning air, before breakfast; and neceisity alone ever induced us to test the soundness of our belief. , -                1   83 The only result of that test has always been with us,-1st, eyes feeling full of sticks; 2d, a general frigidity of body and rigidity of countenance; 3d, rumblings in the alimentary canal, and a sinking of the diaphragm; and lastly, a decided inclination to have something to eat. We rode nine miles in -this dreadful condition, and our mental and physical energies seemed completely paralyzed. But oh! the glow after those first two cups of coffee, and the subsequent ham and eggs! We, who before breakfast had felt as though we had not even energy sufficient to lie down and die, now began to look wakefully about, and regard passing events. Our companions consisted of a gawky countryman; a stupid ugly-looking Dutchman; a young fellow with a bold, bright eye; and a cheerful, gold-natured, though dissipated-looking individual. Shortly after this general survey of the contents' of the coach had been made, we experienced an accession in the persons of a very thin woman and a very fat man. This event so happened by the indiscreet stopping of the driver at their hail. We, within, had seen them in the distance, ad our only chance lay in the hope of the driver's not seeing them; but that perverse individual was wide awake, for we soon found ourselves in the horrible position we had anticipated;  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC8237-00000042"/> viz., cramped and squeezed out of all shape, ald comfort. To relieve the tedium of our new situation, the young man with the bright eye related adventures and stories of such magnitude, that we were both compelled secretly to suspect him of being a great 'blower. (We employ the expression" great blower," because it was the one used by James Yellow and John Blue, when whispering to each other in the :coach their opinion of this story-teller.) The day rolled-slowly on, and so did the coach. We crossed Salt river on an old mud scow, propelled by long oars; and, after passing through a fine country, the beauty of which was subsequently heightened into grandeur by the dark shades of a terrific thunderstorm that sprang up, we at length reached Elizabethtown and dinner., How Elizabeth- town is; situated-the number of its inhabitants- its character, prospects, and resources-are all matters of which we are still as profoundly ignorant as we were before reaching there ; for, on the huried demolition of portions of ham and eggs, we were called upon to resume our seats in the stage, and nere soon on the way again. One circumstance, however, was a cause of rejoicing, viz., the absence of the thin woman and fat man, who remained at. Elizabethtown. After a long ride, we stopped at a place con-   85 tainilg three log-houses, and left the mail there. The name of this place not being put down in any map or guide-book, and both of us being somewhat curious to ascertain it, we made numerous zealous inquiries for that purpose, but no one could give us the desired information. James Yellow asked the postmaster, a man of a saturnine and bilious com- plexion, with a paper of tobacco in his cheek, "What town is this, sir " In, reply, the postmaster looked solemnly at him for about the space of half a minute, then turned deliberately on his heel and walked into the house; and that, we can declare, is the last we ever saw of that man. Reaching Mumfordsville (which lies on the Louis- ville side of Green river), we were politely invited by the driver to "get out," and walk down a steep hill before us. The time seized on for making this request was opportune in the extreme. In the first place, it was pitch dark; in the second place, there was a terrible thunderstorm going on; and in the third place, this thunderstorm was accompanied by a heavy fall of rain and hailstones. But, as there was danger in the coach, we concluded it would be better to get out of danger by getting out of the coach. We had not proceeded far in advance of the stage, when we were so completely drenched as heartily to repent  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC8237-00000043"/> 86 having heeded the driver's request. A flash of light- ning revealing a shed near by, instinct took us with one accord beneath its roof, where we waited till the coach came on, when we left and followed close behind it.  Mem.-The hill was very steep, and covered with sharp stones. On reaching the bank of the river, we-saw nothing, but heard the rushing by of a roaring torrent. We now entered the coach, in silence, at length broken by the driver saying "that it wouldn't do to cross the river in that gust, as :it would frighten the horses ;" so we all sat in the coach and listened to the rain as it came down in torrents, and to the hail as it dashed furiously against the window-panes. Our driver now seemed to be in a complication of difficulties. He said if we waited much longei, the river would be too deep to cross at all; and if we went on now, the horses would probably be frightened, and upset us in the river. We here, for the first time in our lives, saw some little' advantage of a collegiate education. We analyzed the two propositions placed before: us, and saw that one contained a certainty, and the other only a probability; and we concluded to embrace the probability, as being the lesser evil of the two. In other words, -we decided to 'cross, and run the risk of the horses' probable fright. No sooner had the   87 coach entered the Water than the bold, daring adventurer--he who had astonished the company during the day by 'the relation of his deeds-that courageous, hardy individual seized one door, while the big Dutchman seized the other. As we advanced, the daring youth flung open his door, crying, "Oh, driver! hold on-hold on; we're afloat-we're afloat." We all felt the water now coming through the bottom of the coach. The brave young man could hardly be restrained from jumping into the river " to swim ashore," but his coat tails were fortunately of good strong cloth, and undoubtedly saved his life. At last, 'the coach keeled over a little, the hind-wheel sank deep into the water; we all felt extremely wet; a vig- orous pull by the four horses; and a moment after, we were safe ashore. We stopped at the tavern at Woodsonville, where we dried ourselves and had an excellent supper, during which our hardy friend kept up such a continual "blowing" (we refer again to the whisperings of. James Yellowand John Blue as our authority for the use of 'this word), that it became positively laughable* \ As may be supposed, the danger was abundantly ex- aggerated, while his fears were entirely left out; and it was only by his directions to the driver that the coach and all on board were saved. The storm hav- f,          e   &#xD;<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC8237-00000044"/> ' - /   " 88  " -  ,  -l S S ing cleared, a bright moon shone out from the clouds, and we gaily started on again. About midiight, we stopped to change horses, and, after much calling, routed out a darkie, who appeared, half-naked and half- awake. On being asked if it had hailed there, he said "No." "(Why," said we, "you must have been asleep,  for it's been hailing 'partridge-eggs below." The darkie caught thew word " sleep," mumbled it over- "Sleep, sleep, no, sir, we don't have theni things- sleep-here; I don't know what them is." On we moved again, and at two o'clock in the morning we found ourselves at Billy Bell's.   CHAPTER XV. V                 . WE had often heard of "Billy Bell," and won- dered who or what he or it looked like. We now saii before us a lone-looking house, amongst trees and fields, which we immediately entered, as it was too cold for any external speculations that night. A bun- dle of rags, in a corner of the room, first attracted our attention, which, on closer inspection, was found to consist of a small negro-genus, boy-asleep, like a log, on-the floor. We were wondering whether this could be Billy Bell, when we heard a shuffling noise, as of a man walking in slippers; and turning round, we beheld the original Billy Bell, an old man of about seventy, who had lived, he said," for forty years with- in seven miles of the Cave, and never been in it." 1Iospitalities were commenced by an offer of peach and honey. Not knowing what "peach and honey" meant, though ashamed to show any ignorance in the matter, the inquisitive John Blue was determined, nevertheless, to find out; so he boldly said, as though 5                   '  &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC8237-00000045"/> 90 he had been particularly intimate with that article- "of course, by all means "-whereupon, a tumbler was shortly afterwards handed to him, who soon, however, repented his temerity; for, at the first swallow, the ears of the company were edified by a spirting noise, while their eyes were witnesses of the extraordinary and unexpected conduct of a ypung pan who had hitherto carried himself with great propriety and de- corum; the said John Blue now rendering himself exceedingly disgusting and offensive, by hawking up and spitting about the room, long, gluey strings of saliva, the getting rid of which seemed to be attended with great difficulty and manyexertions. James Yellow apologized very prettily for his friend, and concluded by taking up a dirty tallow candle and conducting the said John Blue to bed. The bedroom was clean and fresh, but the beds had a lumpy feeling, as if they had been indiscreetly stuffed with small boards. The next morning we had a very good breakfast; but old Bell kept boring us all through it, with "Now wouldn't you like a piece of spring chicken " poking a wing inder the nose of one, and then nodding inquiringly at the other, " or a nice piece of beefsteak 2" "No, I thank you, sir," responds the one whose olfact6ries have ,been addresed. "No, I thank you, sir," says the one who was nodded at, inquiringly. "Have some ham?"   " "Thank you, I have some."  "Here are some eggs, would you like one of those " "Thunder and Mars, no," answer both, in a voice of thunder. After break- fast, we took a wagon for the Cave Hotel, which we reached about half-past ten. Those who go there with the expectation of realizing the picture that represents that hotel, will find themselves about as near to it as the antipodes are to each other. In the picture is a tall edifice, surrounded by beautiful trees; and, in front of the door is a magnificent barouche, with spirited steeds, and in which is seated a fashion- able lady with a fringed parasol, and by het side an elegant gentleman with beautifully brushed hair and an open waistcoat, who sits facing the spectator, with his hand admiringly pointing to the building, and with such wonderful effect, that, while his legs appear to be inside, his body seems to be outside of the barouche. Young gentlemen, with very long caneb, are lounging through a street that apparently runs along one side of the house; and the whole picture wears an air of fashionable gaiety. With minds pre- pared for such a scene, one can imagine how com- pletely bewildered we were at finding ourselves in as lonely and wild-a spot as ever crow cawed in, or screech-owl gave utterance to lugubrious sounds. As these imaginary cries floated through our brain, we,  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC8237-00000046"/> 92 were startled out of our bewilderment by the fiendish, tom-cat scream of a ridiculous peacock, who now strutted into view, while a long Kentuckian, appearing at the door of the habitation, gave us an honest, open-handed welcome, that did our hearts good, and quickly convinced us that savage sceneryand warm- hearted humanity are by no means incompatible with one another. The building is long, low, two-storied, irregularly shaped, and of singular appearance. At right-angles with it stands a row of about a dozen cottages, built in the log-cabin style., These cottages are all covered by one roof, and look very cosy and pleasant. In front of the main building, and on a level with the ground, is a portico, two hundred and seventy feet long, by fifteen wide, with pillars, around which the :honeysuckle naturally and gracefully entwines itself. From this portico you step directly upon the grass; or,- if you choose to sit beneath its shade, a cool, pleasant breeze, laden with sweet perfumes, constantly refreshes you. There are no houses near; you are alone among the trees, with that immense Cave but a few rods dis- tant, and yawning as if it would like to swallow, you. You descend to its entrance by rude steps, cut irregu- larly in the earth, and there is a smell of cold, damp air, as of a cellar. Two or three delicate streams of Ix   93 water fall from the top of the opening, Entering, you walk a short distance over uneven ground, when you come before a black hole, large enough for a man to walk through. Looking in, you see an arched way towards the right, and involuntarily turning back to the light again, you see John Blue scampering away as fast as his legs will carry him. Great as John Blue's curiosity was, we (that is to say, James Yellow and a couple of new-made acquaintances) could not prevail on him to go in with us. He said he ex- perienced a species of spectral feeling, and an irresist- ible desire to get back into the open air again. "Add to this," continued he, " the black color of your guide, and the party with lanterns, and it wouldn't require a very strong imagination to conjure up the idea of being in the infernal regions. Darkness is always, of itself, unpleasant to me, without the addition of being underground. Do you go in, while I, in the open air, will content myself with an imaginary picture of the Cave, quite as satisfactory to me, and probably much more unnatural than the Cave itself." His im- pressions of the grandeur and sublimity of the Mam- moth Cave, he said, were already rendered sufficiently forcible by the appearance of the entrance. We tried to overcome these feelings, but to no purpose. He had heard that the Cave was the residence of sundry  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC8237-00000047"/> " bats and rats, of whch he had an especial horror; epossums and coons, too, he said, had been seen in there; and if others had seen them, why might not he? So-we were obliged to go in without him. We reached the open air again just in time for dinner, and perfectly enchanted by what we had seen, of which we kept no single particular a secret from John Blue, but diring dinner' ve continued steadfastly to stimu- late his curiosity, that he might not leave unvisited this wonderful cave. The only visitors, besides ourselves, consisted of threeyoung Englishmen, who sat opposite us at table, and who were all dressed in suits of large plaid. They were also " blowe'a--although of a different species from that heretofore mentioned--and carried large tin horns, with the sounding of which they delighted themselves in spending every spare moment. These frequent blasts were very loud, and not altogether eu-  rphonious; but wevconsoled ourselves by the thought that this evil removed a greater by drowning the pea- cock's screams, which had repeatedly brought to our very tongues' ends some very naughty words. These three Englishmen had been all through Europe, Asia, and Mexico, blowing their three tin horns wherever they went; and although they had not molested every- neighborhood with entire impunity, still, to every one   95 of their dilemmas there being three "horns," they had hitherto - ontrived to escape without loss of limbs or lungs. Notwithstanding that they were so noisy, we regretted their departure, which was shortly after din- ner; for we then found ourselves alone with the land- lord, and foresaw a dreary evening before us. We were agreeably deceived, however, for he talked enough for twelve men, and we found him very intelligent and entertaining. His orthoepy was a little defective, which rather added to the charm of his originality than otherwise. He transposed the pronunciation of the words "air" and "are;" for example, he would pronounce "hair," "tear," and " scare," "i ar," " tar," and "scar;" and "scar" he called "scare." We were kept awake the whole night by those diabolical peacocks, who screamed from "dewy eve" till "dawning morn;" but on cominng out into the open air before breakfast, we had the satisfaction of seeing one of them, who was unfurling his tail and turning round like a wa-ivoman in a barber's shop, to display all sides we had the delightful satisfaction of seeing him upset by a strong wind that was blowing at the time. At breakfast, John Blue asked, James Yellow what he supposed peacocks were made for, when the darkie behind us brought a fly-brush, made of the tail. He also told us of the singular manner X  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC8237-00000048"/> b96 of the peacock in walking down chickens. If he sees a chicken that he takes a fancy to, he walks solemnly -after him for about a week, at the end of which time ' the poor chicken generally gets used up, when the peacock seizes him and makes him his prey. After brekfast, the company was augmented to three, by the arrival of a solitary man, whose only pculiarity seemed to consist in wearing a small velvet cap at meal-times,'which made him look very much like an imitation buccaneer. -Our darkie waiter at dinner was very facetious. Having tarts for dessert, Yellow told him he wanted "peach," and asked him if they were all alike. "No, sir." "Is this apple . " "No, sir" "Peach?" "Yes, sir." '"How do you tell the difference " Darkie (beginning to snicker). "Don't, sir" (suppressed chuckle), "there aint no difference, they'm all alike, sir." Whereupo lihe suddenly withdrew to enjoy a small horse-laugh in the entry, which he was unable to suppress; and at the expiration of about five min- utes he returned in such a profuse perspiration, that, standing so near us as he did, we were unable to finish our dinner. The remainder of the afternoon was spent in fruit- less attempts on the part of Yellow and the stranger to X induce Blue to consent to go into the Cave on the fol-   97 lowing day; a thunder-storm and peacocks combined, making, meanwhile, a terrible noise. To conclude the chapter, we may say that our most lasting impressions of the interior parts of Kentucky (excluding, of course, the great Cave, which is worth traveling a thousand miles to see), are that they. have there some very noble and interesting specimens of man-both black and white, wilds tur- keys, mournful doves, horrible peacocks, good roads, bad ferry-boats, unrivaIed "peach and honey," plenty of wild romantic scenery, and first-class thunder and lightning.  &#xD;<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC8237-00000049"/> CHAPT-ER XVI.  WITH next day we started again to explore the mysteries of the Cave, when, to our astonishment, John Blue was seen to quietly take off his straps, roll up his trousers, put on a thick overcoat, and, with an oaken stick -in his hand, accomipany us to the mouth of the Cave, where a close observer might have seen him quietly endure a quiet shudder. He then followed our example, took a lantern, and said nothing till he was so far in- that he couldn't return without, the guide, when he informed the company that he was going through a rapid, series of small shudders-ex- tremities icy cold-pulse high-eyes wild. There was now a horrible, spectral silence, suddenly broken by our darkie guide giving a .wild whoop which made John Blue almost jump out of his skin, and he cried in a voice of extreme passion, "Halloo what are you about, you rascal?-don't you do that again!" Darkie. "Yah,yah! I only thought I'd amuse the genelmen." Then such dodgings about, down, down,   " derry down into deep holes, through narrow passages, bumping of heads and scraping of backs; slipping over slippery mud, and nearly falling into " the Dead Sea;" feeling covered with goose-flesh, as we walked over a frail bridge that crossed "the Bottomless Pit;" going very zigzaggy through "the Fat Man's Mis- ery;" stooping till one's back is broke, to crawl through the long "Valley of Humility;" emerging then into a large open space called " the Hall of Re- lief," which you feel to be rightly so called, until, see- ing a large rock, cracked, and almost ready to fall over the small passage through which you have just come, "relief" changes to horror and consequent re- turn of paroxysm of shudders; looking through a small hole in the wall, as the darkie advised, "up and down and all around," into " (orin's Dome," till your head is giddy; climbing rickety ladders; visiting the houses where sixteen consumptives dwelt for three months, without seeing the light of day; hearing bats wheeze in all directions; sinking down with terror as the darkie tells you that, "Now, genelmen, you am three hundred and thirty foot below de surfams ob de earth," that you "mought" go lower, if you want, only we think we "mought" better not. Then, such windings, and twistings, and turnings; such a con- fused notion of being somewhere and nowhere at one  &#xD;<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC8237-00000050"/> 100 and the same time; such ,a horrible feeling as the thought strikes you, how entirely youare at the mercy of that s4the individual on ahead; such a benevolent regard you suddenly (now, perhaps, for the first time), feel for tie welfare of a fellow-being!  Wandering on thus, with a vague impression that we were loafing about in a damp cellar, for some un- accountable reason, we followed our guide until we suddenly came into a place ("The ,Star Chamber") where we could almost have sworn we were in the open air. The darkie set some combustibles on fire in the center, and took away our lanterns while we stood at the sides of the chamber. Looking-upwards, we saw huge cliffs towering above it on either side, and overhead was apparently the sky, crowded with stars. The appearance of the sky was precisely as we have seen it on a dark night when the stars look small and shine dimly; and, around the edges of the rocks was the light appearance usually seen there at such times. 'The whole scene was truly grand, and the illusion perfect. It was as if we were in some wild regions, at the bottom of a chasm, around a fire, of a dark night. The :ti;s appeared to be an infinite distance above us; and as we steadfastly gazed at them, they seemed to twinkle, like real ones. We felt very unwilling to en- ter as it were, the Cave, again,   ,    101 We now walked on, and reached the river "Styx" and " the Dead Sea," some -fifty feet below us, into which we splashed stones, until, passing on, we came to "Echo River," where we embarked in a dirty flat-boat, and'were paddled along for some distance. The river wound through sand-banks, and over head was a most beautiful and spacious arch of rock. At length we landed, and, walking through the mud, reached another part of the river. Here arose a diffi- culty-there was no boat: "Mat," our guide, said, too, that if there were, the river was rising too rapidly to allow our crossing with any certainty of a safe re- turn. We were therefore compelled, very reluctantly, to retrace our steps, leaving unseen some six miles and more of the main avenue of the Cave. The guide told us that beyond the river was the most beautiful part of the Cave, that is, the finest mineral formations; But as he also assured us that we had seen "the grandest part ob de Cave," we the more easily resigned ourselves to our unlucky fate; and, having visited "the Smoke House," where stone hams hung down in great profusion, and paid our respects to " the Devil's Arm Chair," and "the Gothic Chapel," in which a couple had very recently been married (being the first marriage on record in the' Cave), we pioceeded to "Lake Purity," where we saw a solitary eyeless fish,  &#xD;<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC8237-00000051"/> 102 who seemed, nevertheless, very jolly, and rushed about through the water at a great rate. From "Laki Pttrity," we were conducted to " the Giant's Coffin,' which John Blue began to imagine might contain the genius of the Cave, and straightway moved that we should strike for the open air, which, soon after, we reached, and, with grateful hearts drew in long- draughts of it, to drive out that smell of the cellar, which still seemed to haunt us. We must 'not, however, omit to record the plar. which the darkie hit upon to find his way in the Cave. At. the entrance of each avenue that we explored, he placed the provender for lunch. We then went in as far as we pleased, and when we wished to return, thl darkie, who has a strong smell, wheeled about, snuffed the provender, and followed his nose. John Blue's afternoon was spent in sleeping off the fatigue and excitement of the morning's tramp. James Yellow, meanwhile, paid  a visit to the "sanctum" of the guides; and having purchased several "eyeless fis" (preserved in a bottlefof spirits), and some beautiu  mineral specimens, taken from the interior of the Cave, passed a very pleasant after- noon in listening to the endless stories of the darkie guides, one or two of whom are very intelligent. V    103 James had also, before leaving the cave, filled his brandy-flask, with water from "Lake Lethe," upon which he seemed to set a superstitiously high value; and the bottling of this, and the packing up all,- fish, minerals, and waters of oblivion,-in a suitable manner to send them home by express, formed sub- jects of such nice and intricate calculation, and such delicate manual skill, as to leave him no time for sleep. When all this weighty business had been duly dispatched, James Yellow felt unspeakably relieved; and on waking John Blue, at tea-time, the latter found him so unusually jolly, that, while he as - yet lay in a half-awakened, stupid statk, he enviously hinted a suspicion thathis friend Yel ow had been some- where imbibing artificial spirits. In the evening, our good host entrtained us with various stories; and, among others, the wonderful one of a Scotchman who was very fond of hunting, and who once shot a wildcat by mistake, thinking it was a coon. He was so proud of this wildcat, that he hung him up in his bedroom, and kept him there till he couldn't keep him, any longer; for the cat itself' didn't keep, and the cat-astrophe of decomposition ensued ; so he was obliged to throw him away, which he was loth to do. But he also loathed the smell;  &#xD;<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC8237-00000052"/> 104  and of the two loths, he chose the one he considered least. And this is the style of narrative in whichl our host told his tales, and in this style he greatly delighted, for he was an inveterate punster. {      , :   \ CHAPTER XVII. THE evening following found us at Bell's Tavern again, where we took tea with that veteran, and where our eyes were delighted with the spectacle of a beautiful girl-fresh and blushing-whom James Yel-' low justly compared to a peach, so soft was the down, and so luscious the bloom on her cheeks. After tea, we went directly to bed, to get some little sleep before the arrival of the stage in which we were to journey up to Louisville again. We were outed out at 10, P, MX- the coach had come. We found it' empty, took our seats inside, and in a few minutes our second long stage-ide had commenced. The road for some distance was quite rough, and though we had the whole coach to ourselves, and felt very drowsy, the jolting effectually prevented -any sleep-worthy that name.  About 34, A. M., we reached Green river, which had risen so much since our stormy passage across it on our way to the Mammoth Cave, that we were O-  &#xD;<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC8237-00000053"/> 106 now obliged to cross in a scow, rowed by darkies. The moon' shone beautifully in a -clear, starlit sky, and the' banks-on either side were romantic and wild. It was a subdued grandeur, which seemed to sleep in the silvery moonbeams. We could not help remarking on the striking contrast between Green river of a black, stormy night, illumined at intervals by angry flashes of lightning, and the same scenery on a quiet, lovely night like the present. John Blur leaned pensively on one of the. rough, wooden sides of the scow, as it moved slowly onward, scarce breaking the solemn silence of the night, and asked the darkie in the stein, who seemed to be working hard at his oar, "Do you do this kind of business every' night?"  "Everry night, twyst," said he; "I wouldn't care if I got anythin' for it, but don't get nothin'-one dime--half a dime -a stage; I'm goin' to give him up!" Having landed, we again took our places in thQ coach, and rode to the top of the hill-the steep, sharp-stoned hill-the hill where our troubles commenced on the night of the, stoim. On the top of this hill sleep the inhabitants of the little village of Mumfordsville. As James Yellow, on reentering the coach, after crossing Green river, enveloped himself in his eternal  a  ..   107 shawl, and then immediately fell asleep, no other alternative remains for John Blue, who still kept wide awake, than to resume here his individuality, and totally divested of James Yellow; continue the narrative on his own responsibility. The reader must have noticed (if indeed, he have read thus far) how inextricably we have been mixed up, during the whole course of the narrative; with what a Siamese-twinship we have continued so far; but some mysterious Fate having chosen to break up for a season the sympathetic bond that existed between us, we have only to bow, submissively, to the sad necessity. Deprived, then, of the support and counsel of his dear friend Yellow, with a very red face, and with feelings of great diffidence, John Blue now stands forth alone before the public. At the top of the hill, the coach stopped at Mumfordsville, to leave the mail. The postmaster came out in nightshirt and trbwsers, and asked if there were any passengers. "Yes, two -," said the driver, and hesitated; when, showing my head at the window, he added, "gentlemen."  I wondered why he hesitated, and have never, to this day, been able to account for it satisfactorily. "Ah, Mac," said the postmaster, "you'll murder them before you reach --" (namning some place that  &#xD;<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC8237-00000054"/> 108 I didn't hear distinctly); and then they both dis- appeared into the house, laughing. The reader can, perhaps, imagine my horror on hearing this declara- tion. I let down the window, which had been closed to keep out the cold air. We were the only passengers in the coach, else it would have been undoubtedly opened long before. I now looked out, and saw that there was no one on the box, and  the reins were fluig loosely on the horses' backs; whereupon I turned to Yellow, who was still in a state of stupefaction, and facetiously remarked, "Wouldn't it be a lark if these horses should run away with us?' The words had barely passed my lips when the horses started. The driver, hearing the 'coach rattle off, rushed out of the house; and, after much running, succeeded in catching, the hinder off-horse by the bit, and hung stoutly to him. Meanwhile, not apprehending any real danger, I thrust my head out, and w^vs admiring the strength of the man in being able to' cling on for so long a time, when I saw him suddenly flung off about two feirtand the horses ad coach went rattling at a mad pace down a steep hill. I now, for the first time, saw our danger; and turning to Yellow, said, "By George, they've run away with us!"Yellow made no reply, but, wrapped up in his immense shawl, ?   109 sat staring vacantly at me, like an Egyptian mummy. I immediately began to pull off my overcoat, and told him to get out of his old shawl as soon as possible. I made use of the expression "old," as applied to shawl, because he looked so completely swaddled up in its folds, that I felt exasperated with it. As I stood up, pulling off my coat, the rapid motion of the coach flung me backwards on the seat, my legs flew into ite air, and for a time I was as powerless as a beetle on his back. Yellow, mean- while, continued to sit still, without making any effort to rid himself of his -shawl, and advised me "not to fall for'ard." At length I succeeded in getting my coat off; and then, after much shouting, contrived to get the idea into Yellow's head that his shawl must come off. By turning him around again and again, and after a great deal of untwisting, he was finally unrolled. Then, divested of all incumbrances, we each took a door; I opened mine and looked out; the four horses were at the top of their speed, going in a straight line, over a straight road. I turned to see what Yellow was ab-ut, and found that he also 'had his door open, and was leaning out as if about to jump. I looked out again, and saw a bridge on a-head in the distance (which I recognized as a certain narrow one, without sides, that we had crossed  &#xD;<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC8237-00000055"/>  10  on our way to the Cave). "Now," thought I, ' is our time, if ever "I put my left foot on the lower step, placed my coat-tails under my arms, and waited till we- reached a comparatively soft part of the road, when I sprang forward, and in a line with the coach, intending to run on, the moment H touched the ground,- so as to break the impetus; but I had no time for the latter manoeuver, for no sooner did I touch the ground, than my feet bounced off as if they had been two india-rubber balls, and I was flung headlong into the dirt. Picking myself up im- mediately, I involuntarily ran on after the coach. I now heard Yellows voice, and felt horribly, as the thought struck me that, in jumping out, he might have fallen under the wheel. As I ran, I looked on either side of the road, but his voice growing fainter with the receding of the coach, I looked towards that, and saw him still in it, with his head thrust out of the window. I now felt sick at heart, but still ran on. Suddenly the coach turned off the road, ran a short distance on the- grass near the fence, and then dis- appeared. I now gave him up, but redoubled my speed. Reaching the place where the coach had disappeared, I saw it a short distance before me, stopped, and Yellow out and at the leader's head.   "1 I had just sufficient breath to ask if he were hurt, - and received a welcome "i No, not a bit."  Yellow being now wide awake, too, I am rejoiced at being able to renounce my individuality, and again become merged in the " we." We stood  looking at one another until Blue recovered his wind, when he returned to the road and hallooed for the driver. After shouting till he was hoarse, and no driver making his appearance, Yellow now took his turn at shouting, having first, however, enveloped himself in his eternal shawl. Here was an interesting situation! In a strange country, among trees, at 4 o'clock in the morning, with a stage-coach and horses!. We didn't know whether to laugh or cry, and so concluded to do neither. The driver still continuing to remain behind the scenes, we found ourselves in an awkward predica- ment; for, independent of the fact that we had nothing to say, the huskiness of voice occasioned by much shouting, was by no means adapted to the carrying on of a lively interchange of ideas; so that we were reduced to the disagreeable necessity of playing the part of dummies, till it suited the driver's convenience to make his appearance. Besides, not being at all versed in the resources of Kentucky  &#xD;<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC8237-00000056"/> "2 forests, how did we know but, at that moment, bears, panthers, and other beasts of a like ferocious nature, might be spectators of this dummy scene, and snatch i s, collectively or individually,off the stage without a witness.  But our attention was now diverted from such doleful reflections by a new feature in the case. There were but three horses visible, whereas we had been run away with by four. Now, what had become of the fourth? Yellow, at this sudden inquiry of Blue's, came towards the coach, and perched himself on a high stump, whether for purposes of wisdom or to keep his feet dry, Blue could never ascertain. There, however, he remained, enveloped in his im- mense shawl, and solemnly, looking out; and in this position was seen by the startled driver, who had at length made his appearance. He was closely followed by all the male inhabitants of Mumfordsville, amounting in number to five, but in powers of loud talk-to a host. -(Mumfordsville is a very small town.) They seemed very much puzzled, and somewhat inclined to doubt whether they were awake or not; for, instead of finding two individuals lying on the ground with broken legs and arms, they beheld an apparition in a shawl perched on a high stump, and another one at the leaders head. The driver,   "3 being one of the most wide awake of the party, first broke the silence by shouting out, "Where's the 'other 'Torse?' "Damn the other horse!" said one of the villagers; "is any body hurt?"John Blue immediately went up And shook hands with that man, and right cheerfully responded that "no one was hurt." Search was now made for "the other horse," but he could nowhere be-found. Morning had not yet dawned, and it was still dark. At length, hearing a grunting noise from underneath the stage, we looked to discover the cause, and there we found the poor missing horse, lying against one of the fore wheels. He had fallen, been run over by the horse behind him, aid had acted as a scotch to the wheel, thus saving Yellow's life. All said that had it not been for this lucky accident, Yellow must undoubtedly have been dashed to pieces; for the horses had run into a by-path among the trees. We both felt exceedingly thankful for our escape; but as the air was growing still more damp and chilly, we went to the road again, and ran backwards and forwards; Yellow telling, meanwhile, how that, when he found himself alone in the -coach, he first examined into the feasibility of getting out on the driver's seat, as he had hopes that some one or more of the reins might be there; but finding the window R*k  &#xD;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC8237-00000057"/> "4 too small, he next directed his', attention to the horses. He first addressed them in the mild tone of entreaty, but he soon fully, satisfied himself that they were deaf to all "moral suasion." Then he changed to a loud, hoarse voice of command-so stern and savage, indeed, in its tone, that he says it was what frightened the horses, and made them turn off abruptly from the road, just before coming to the bridge; in the performance of which sudden turning, the leader so fortunately lost his center of gravity, and saved Yellow's life, bringing at the same time a healthful return of blood to his face, which, he was well aware, had been for some time past, the center of gravity with him. At the end of about half an hour, the coach was ready for another start, when, bidding the inhabitants of Mumfordsville farewell, and thanking them for their kind sympathy, we were driven rapidly on to make up for lost time. It seemed very strange to us that the poor, fallen leader, whom we had supposed to have been nearly killed, and whom we had felt sure must have been quite disabled for a long time to come should hold up his head; look as lively and well as ever, resume his former place, and trot along with such remarkable briskness. IIs foreknees and back presented a-lreadful spectacle, being all raw and   "5 bloody. We wondered, but said nothing, contenting ourselves with scratching down in our note-books a "mem," to the effect that Kentucky horses are game to the backbone, and don't yield to any pressure of external circumstances; and that they axe capable of coming up lively to the scratch, without heeding the scratches, even after scotching the wheel of a heavy stage, containing a heavy heart and a very heavy shawl, in rapid motion. Wie breakfasted at a place called "Noynn," which name, some say, is derived from the fact of there being no linden trees there. A curious reason, indeed, for, with equal propriety it might have been called Nohamandeggs, as we were there, for the first time since our departure from Louisville, denied that luxury. Others say, with more probability, that a tribe of hunters having settled here, one of the party, named "Lynn," was lost; and, as the others returned-from their unsuccessful search for him, they would say, "Vo Lynn." At all events, it was easy enough to imagine how one might lose himself, without much effort, in such a place. Our driver now lay by to rest, and was succeeded by a man of pleasanter physiognomy. The runaway horses were also taken out, and supplied by four feeble and meek-looking animals, one of whom continued sound asleep through all the rough process  &#xD;<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC8237-00000058"/> ;           .1 IG ,by which the Nolynn hostlers are. wont to "put 'em before;" being apparently something like James Yel- low in this respect, that is to say, not particular how roughly you handle, cuff, or kick him, so long as you don't carry matters so far as to wake -him out of a comfortable morning nap. Here, while waiting for the drowsy horse to awake (a preliminary indispen- sable to making a proper start); the matter of the run- away was talked over ;and our new driver offered us a J. somewhat too late consolation for the unpleasant ex- citement from which we were just recovering by the aid of coffee and cigars, in the assurance thatt our night driver, who had gone into the tavern at Mum- fordsville, "to see what time it was," wlen the horses, being left alone, had started off so wildly, was " the most careful driver on the whole route from Louisville to Nashville;" that his horses, too, were "perfectly t gentle," had never acted thus before but twice; and that the reason, undoubtedly, was, that "t they knew they were considerably behind their time." Thus did they try to cajole us into the belief that the sagacious animals were only impelled by a laudable ambition to be punctual; whereas, it had clearly appeared to us that the coach was propelled by infuriated fiends. However, it was certainly a very comfortable thing to know that those horses were "perfcctly gentle," and ,  .        .   the driver such a "careful man," and that it was alto- gether a mere piece of pleasantry on their part-a perfectly good-natured, well-meaning runaway. On this ground we forgive them, although we couldn't much enjoy their joke while it was being perpe- trated. But the sleepy steed is beginning to open one eye; the driver has clambered into his box, and taken the whip. The usual notice, "All aboard," has already been given, so we must hurry into the stage, and bid "a last farewell " to Nolynn. The remainder of the ride was rendered sufficient- ly stupid from the fact of Yellow's having become so -hoarse with a cold he had taken, that he was abso- l1utely speechless; so we rode on-Yellow in. silent suf- fering, and Blue in silent wrath at having been thus deprived of all conversational pastime, by a wretched catarrh. The miles were therefore doubly long and tedious; but in course of time we reached "West Point," on "Salt River," wheie Yellow, at length, opened his mouth-to receive his dinner. A black woman now increased our number in the coach to three. She was exceedingly affable; and, Blue having asked her if his cigar interfered at all with her comfort, she unhesitatingly replied, " she must confess it did," whereupon Blue moodily threw it out of  &#xD;<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC8237-00000059"/> "8 the window. In recompense, however, foir his courtesy, she pointed out many interesting parts of the country, as we passed themand seemed to dwell with peculiar delight on those places productive of chills and fever. She likewise informed us that she was "a denizen " of Louisville, and occupied the position of nurse in "a high, private family," in Chestnut street; and that Chestnut street and Broadway were the fashionable streets of that city, where we might see pretty girls in any number. We reached Louisville towards night-fall, tired and sleepy. On the following day, having first engaged our state-room on the steamer "Fashion," for St. Louis (to leave the next day), we took a stroll through Chestnut street and Broadway, where we saw one or two pretty girls, lho did not, however, give us a very satisfactory impression of "the beauties" of Louis- ville," of whom we had heard not a little; and to aggravate Blue's disappointment, Yellow kept declar- ing that he "ought not to have been sick in Balti- more, if he liked to see real, first-class female beauty," that "the prettiest girls he ever saw were in Balti- mnore," etc. On reaching the hotel again, Yellow received a parcel, which, on opening, proved to be a plaster that f   "9 a kind friend at home, learning by one of his Wash- ington letters, that he had a bad cough, had sent on to him, and which now arrived very 'opportunely. Blue applied it "hot," according to directions, and soon had the satisfaction of hearing Yellow's voice again, in all its wonted strength, as he roared out the moment the plaster touched his skin.  &#xD;<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC8237-00000060"/> CHAPTER XVIII. l;+t\ WHAT a ridiculous thing it is that a man must take off his clothes every night, and do what is called "going to bed," only to get up the next'morning and put them on again! We have heard of a man who cut his throat to be rid of so great an annoyance; and although we cannot commend his wisdom in so doing, we do certainly agree with him that it is a most grievous bore. All this process had to be gone through with last night and this morning; and then, after breakfast, we went, at an early hour, on board of the "Fashion," for St. Louis. On the list of passengers, we found the name of "Julia Dean." What a strange beauty there is in that simple name alone! Joy immediately took possession of the hearts of John Blue and James Yellow; and they forthwith proceeded to reconnoitre eyatall girl that passed them, but without success, until, a gth,                       121 they caught a glimpse of her in the ladies' cabin, eat- ing cake, very talkative and full of spirits. We are free to admit that we have butl little sympathy with that species of "refinement" which professes disgust at the idea of a lady eating or drinking; and so long as there is nothing indecorous in the mode of doing it, we are in no wise disposed to criticize the act itself In the present instance of Julia Dean, we should not have objected to seeing her eat cake all the voyage-- she got it into her mouth somehow so beautifully! She was continually surrounded by a host of friends, and' seemed so natural and lively, that we always longed to join the party. Blue declared he was in love with her, which Yellow believed more fully be- fore the declaration than fter it; and we defy any- body to look at her without loving her, that is, any one who has the least love of simplicity and refine- ment.  An additional charm, too, is her acknowl- edged purity. She bears an irreproachable character, and that, for a woman following a profession so full of temptations, is no trifling merits. A small poodle, thin as a rail, nervous, and hardly able to see out of his eyes on account of the quantity of wool with which he was furnished, was also a fellow-passenger with us on the "Fashion." lIe now made his appearance, and we were just recovering   &#xD;<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC8237-00000061"/> 122 from the effects of a too hearty laugh at his eccen- tricities, when the bell rang for the starting of the boat, and we left the "Saloon" for the "Promenade Deck." On the map, the Ohio river, from Louisville to the Mississippi, is very crooked and zigzaggy to look upon, yet we suffered no perceptible incoivenience from these sudden and numerous bends and turns, but, puffing with high-pressure, were lazily jerked along on our way over the waters: We say waters, for the Ohio is made up of so many tributaries that it seems to be ratlir of a mongrel nature, than exclusive and distinct, like the noble Hudson; so that, as we moved on and saw, in turn, the ' Kentucky," the  "Salt," the "Green," the "White," and "Wabash" "Cumberlandthe   "Tennessee," and other innu- merable streams without a name, all emptying into us, we lost, in a measure, the idea of being borne along by any particular stream; for any one verily formed but a small part of the forces that carried us on. Why it should be, called "Ohio '" we cannot imagine, It takes its rise in Pennsylvania, but the origin of its name is in no wise made any clearer by a knowledge of those of its parents, the "Alleghany" and "Monongahela." In its subsequent flow, it forms the boundary line of Ohio, separating that State from   123 Kentucky and Virginia. The fact of separating those States cannot be of sufficient importance to give it the name of Ohio, for a much larger portion of it also divides Kentucky from the States of Indiana and Illi- nois as well. On this account, and also because it is more freely and fully supplied by Kentucky, it ought, by good right, to be called the Kentucky River. 'It cannot then, we conclude, be named from the State, but that must rather derive its name from the river. It is very possible that in discovering this river, some worthy may have exclaimed with joy "Heigho!" and then, in revolving what name to call it, some other worthy, struck with the idea, may have suggested, "O! Heigho! call it that;" whence it is easily contracted to  Oheiho. Elide, now, the "h" and the superfluous "e,"^ and Ohio finally appears. We make these suggestions, as the only derivation we have met with is that of Heckewelder, who derives it from "Ohiopekhanne," which is perfect nonsense on the face of it; for Ohio- pekhanne means a white stream, whereas the Ohio is as turbid and dirty a stream as one could wish to see; infinitely more so, in fact, than we desired, when, on sitting down to dinner, we discovered that we had to drink that very water, the mere looks of which had so much disgusted us. The manner of taking meals was a very curious  &#xD;<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC8237-00000062"/> one, and must be unparalleled in the records of gas- tronomy. We were first made acquainted with the preliminary preparations by a mere chance; happening to open our state-room door, two men, to our surprise, suddefly fell in backwards upon us. On emerging into the saloon, a novel spectacle met our view; a row ,of men were ranged along either side of the room, and each man behind a chair. Between these two rows stood a table, which the waiters were covering with dishes. A quarter of an hour was occupied in this pantomime, when a bell rang, and we beheld all the women issue forth in a string, from the "Ladies' Saloon," and these were first seated. At the same time there was a disorderly rush, from the outer deck, of a gang of men, who had been-so improvident as not to have secured seats beforehand, and who were conse- quently obliged to wait for the "second table." While the ladies were getting properly settled in their seats, and the men who had come too late were gazing eagerly at the viands, and painfully scratching their respective heads, we, who, fortunately, had grasped a couple of chairs in season, had ag opportunity to inspect the table which was spread with all the gim- cracks of the modern style of cookery;-gothic archi- tectural erections of peanut candy, covered with a gauze of frosted sugar;-lobster-salads, concealed PM.   125 beneath a covering of yellow, interspersed with red spots;-aspects of oysters, seen through jelly;-pieces of beef, with erect bits of pork sticking out all over "Iike quills upon the fretful porcupine;"-pyramids of macaroons, with artificial boquets of flowers at the apices;-and numerous other airy decorations. Our admiration of these many ornamental beauties of the table was not unmingled with distressing doubts as to whether we should be able to find enough substantial victuals to sustain life. While, lost in these contem- plations, the tinkle of a second bell was heard, the instantaneous effect of which quite startled us, for we thought a general fight had that moment commenced, so great was the noise and confusion with which the men darted forward, chairs in hand, seated themselves, and plunged indiscriminately into potatoes, asparagus, bread and butter, pie, jelly, &amp;c., without the slightest regard to their own stomachs, or those of their neigh- bors. We distinctly recollect one comical-looking man, whose hair stood tp like horns, finishing his dinner before the covers were off.-After somewhat recovering from the shock of our sudden initiation into this novel and riotous method of getting seated, we immediately saw into the necessity of some active movement, on our own part, in order to obtain something to eat. A hard struggle had just terminated, with partial success--for   &#xD;<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC8237-00000063"/> 126 we had just got some turkey-legs and potatoes on our - plates when-to our great surprise and horror, we saw - the cloth begin to move; and before we could recover sufficient presence of mind to determine what was best to be done, our plates, turkey-legs, and potatoes, were irreclaimably beyond our reach: We kept our eyes steadfastly and anxiously fastened upon them until they disapthe disappeared in the distance. The cloth, it seemed, had been thus drawn off to empty the crumbs, preparatory to setting the "second table. This deli- cate hint caused us to notice that we were the only two left at the table; so we arose and returned, in angry mood, to our state-room, as empty as when we sagely took our seats for the purpose of securing them. We resigned ourselves, as we best could, and found ourselves reluctantly forced to resolve, that next time we must try to fight and gormandize like the others, the only alternative being actual starvation, which we mighlt, indeed, have preferred, had the days for which 'we were doomed to this mode of life been so many months. We never before had worked so hard for a living, and never!to so little purpose. The glowing accounts we had heard of the excellent accommoda- tions, good living, and general comfort of these- wes- tern steamboats, proved to be without good foundation -at least, we found nothing good about them.   127 We passed Cairo as the sun was setting, but saw nothing, that city being under water; and having turned a corner, now found ourselves going, up the Mississippi. The effect of passing from the Ohio to the Mississippi river is similar to that of, after having sauntered leisurely and securely on the sunny side of a sytreet, well sheltered from the wind; to then find, on crossing the first street that intersects it, your hat knocked off by a strong gust of wind, and all your powers suddenly called into play to catch your hat, and to resist also being blown away yourself; so that, from the most passive, lazy, luxurious being in the world, you are instantly trans-  formed into a most active and energetic member of society. A strong horth wind, sweeping down the valley of the Mississippi, compelled us to retreat to the saloon. When we rose the next-morning and issued into the open air again, we found ourselves enveloped in a mist that concealed the neighboring shores, and dampened all our prospects; a mist that we could not penetrate, but which penetrated us so effectually that we were again obliged to retreat before this second hostile element. Yesterday, air; to-day, water. By noon the mist had cleared;, but the scenery did not differ much from  that of the Ohio river.  &#xD;<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC8237-00000064"/> 128 Thef only/difference, in fact, appeared in the water, which was .even more turbid, and in which large logs were floating down-stream at a terrible pace. Oceasionally one would catch in the wheel, at which times Yellow made a point to start and look wild; and, Blue acknowleiges, with some reason, for there was a frightful cracking and smashing going on till wye got rid of the log. We had been on board a day and a half, when we began to feel very gaunt, and as though we were just about half starved; but by dint of thinking of Julia Dean, and smoking, and watching the scenery, we contrived to appease these gnawings of hunger. We were especially on the qui vive at the landings, in hopes of new and larger supplies of provender, but were always miserably disappointed. One of the landings was modern Herculaneum- though why so called, it would be difficult to tell; the only similarity between the two cities, that we could discover, consisting in their both being buried out of sight-the one by lava, the other "submerged beneath the wave." A colony of Frenchmen, how- ever, may have settled here, and this would satis- factorily account for the origin of its name; for, the waters constantly washing over the city, and "to wash" being in French "laver," there is no very   i1-9 marked difference between it and lava. Now, both the ancient city, Herculaneum, and this modem town of that name, being out of sight, and both being lavee'd over, the similarity appears complete. What perceptible difference can there be between the two? None, whatever, we concluded, as we paddled past and perhaps over it. Shortly afterwards, we were boarded by the St. Louis health-officer, who, when he leaped upon our deck, was decidedly the most unhealthy looking man on the whole steamboat, and, as he advanced, *aa smilingly suggestive of cholera, yellow-fever, and all the other ills of humanity. 7 ".  &#xD;<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC8237-00000065"/> -CHAPTER XIX., , ONE Sunday afternoon saw us crawling through the slimy mud of the dirty, narrow streets in St. Louis that lead from the steamboat-wharf to the Planter's Hotel.. There, however, we soon found ourselves com- 'fortably established in an airy room, from the ceiling of which actually hung a gas-burner. Our joy was as great as our surprise; and we immediately lit the thing to make sure it was a bona-fide affair, and not mere pasteboard. A bright light dazzling our eyes, so long deprived of the accustomed glare of gas, soen convinced us of its reality, and we fairly reveled in the brilliant glare which had at length supplanted the miserable glow-worm tallows that had heretofore been greasily thrust upon us, and made our rooms smell as if they had been previously tenanted by soap-fat men. We were soon obliged, however, to put out the gas; for we found St. Louis hot, even to steaming, and those huge jets of flame by no means tended to cool the air; so, opening the windows, we went sweating to bed. We -  . \    131 sweated the night through, and arose, next morning, with sodden faces and debilitated bodies. We were thoroughly disgusted with St. Louis before we' had been there a day. The mud in the streets was knee-deep, and the heat almost insupport- able, exceeding that of a usual New-York midsummer. This was the early part of May, and we were told it had been " much warmer " in St. Louis " last week." We started to deliver some letters of introduction, but paused at the threshold of the first victim, and turned back, positively ashamed to present ourselves, for we were spattered with mud from head to foot, our faces steaming and red, and our boots so overlaid with clayey slime that they strongly resembled drab gaiters, and, at first sight, startled us considerably, as we could not recollect possessing, in our own right, a single pair of those articles. To present ourselves in such guise, was by no means our intention on starting out, so we came to the conclusion-.that, mud having dis- figured our vestments, "circumstances had altered cases,"-and accordingly changed our minds. We returned to the Hotel, stripped 'and cleaned, and then restlessly asked each other "what to do next." As neither could satisfactorily answer that inquiry, we looked out of the window, and smoked away the languid hours, When night came to extin-  &#xD;<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC8237-00000066"/> 132 guish the sunlight and substitute oil, camphene, and gas-burners, that dignitary found us still smoking and drenched with perspiration. In this wise did we pass the first day in St. Louis. The theatre was open that night, but we doubted much about going, on account of an apprehended risk of suffocation by the heat and crowd. "Julia Dean," however, staring at us in big letters everywhere, the temptation proved stronger than our fears, and we went. There was a baby at the breast in Tier No. 1, who, on being removed from that point of attraction, burst out into tears, without number, and kept up such a con- tinued sobbing and gasping, alternated with occasional screams, that the attention of the spectators seemed rather directed to that tale of woe, than to the one enacted on the stage. The mother, unable to pacify it by jumping it up and down, now lost all patience, and, turning it over, spanked it, to the great horror of the whole audience; and the babe now giving way to the most distressing paroxysms of grief, cries were heard of "put her out,"-"put her out," when the box-keeper advanced, and the offending objects were removed. Our attention was now drawn to the stage again, and Blue asserts that Julia Dean recognized him and modestly 'blushed. She certainly had very   133 red cheeks; but, then, so did the audience; and no wonder,-who wouldn't be red in such a heat? We left, exceedingly pleased; by no means, indeed, con- siderifig her one of the most perfect of actresses, although certainly among the most lovable and natural. Our hearts warmed toward Her so, that when the curtain dropped and separated her from us, everything about us seemed cold and repulsive. (See Appendix, C.) The next morning was spent in prosecuting dili- gent inquiries, as to the shortest and safest way of getting out of St. Louis. To reach Chicago, two routes lay before us,-one via the Illinois river and canal,--the other via the Mississippi to Galena, and then across the prairies. We first went on board the "Amazonia," an Illinois river boat, but, finding her loading with rosin, we felt unutterable things, said nothing, but departed, and immediately took passage on board the "'Dr. Franklin, NoV. 2," for Galena, feeling confident that the Doctor could never be brought to act upon the modern "drive-ahead-and- damn-the-consequences " system. We then returned to the Hotel, and spent the afternoon in celebrating the birth-day of a certain young lady, whose wit is only equaled by her good- ness of heairt. The manner in which we celebrated it,  &#xD;<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC8237-00000067"/> 134 must ever remain a mystery. The secret was alone revealed to a darkie waiter, who, on entering our room late that evening, for a certain purpose, discov- red himself enveloped in a dense smoke, that smelt strongly of tobacco, and beheld, in the dim twilight, a table covered with bottles, and, beneath that table, all that remained of Yellow and Blue. IV   CHAPTER XX. WE sat on the promenade-deck of the "Dr. Franklin, No. 2," surrounded by barrels. The boat was so heavily laden that her lower deck was on a level with the water, and yet they continued to pile up articles on her decks with almost super- human activity. Rough men, in flannel shirts, were busily throwing up around us an alarming barricade of trunks, tables, cradles, cribs, and other truck; and every moment our prison-house was growing percepti- bly smaller. We felt disheartened: but with the skill and courage of cornered rats, we planned and success- fully executed a series of "lofty tumblings," which finally set us free. Having now taken our station at another part of the boat, where there was less bustle, and consequently  less danger of being suddenly immured, we looked out upon the busy quay with greater ease of body and mind. Among a great variety of other interesting objects, we saw a long, thin, yellow dyspeptic, in a  &#xD;<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC8237-00000068"/> 136 w lita~    - danip g over the steamboat-plank, with a fwer-pot in one hand and a bandbox in the other, and at the same time vainly endeavoring to use- those members of his body to hand two fat women on board:  Wlile thus engaged, the hack they had come inwhich was apparently about to drive off with his trunts still strapped on behind, caught his eye, ' when both flow6r-pot and bandbox rose rapidly in the air and nearly displaced the two fat women. Leaving his human charge, he ran roaring after the hack-man, -convulsively pointing, now the flower.pot and now the bandbox, at the receding ttmks. The driver stopped at length, convinced that something was wrong, lis- tened to the appeal, looked knowingly, and soon after was- seen staggering beneath one of the trunks, which he took on his shoulder, while he lugged the other along over the stones.-Once started, the boat creaked dismally wvith its heavy burden, and moved so slowly that t seemed. a though we should never get out of sight of St, Louis. A stranger, near by, hearing us express appebhensions of such a calamity, broke in on the conversition by-telling us of a boat that was once actually two dayp in getting out of sight of that place, and then was so rotten that it broke in two. We were leaning over the railing in the darkness of the night, watching the black waters as they rushed;   rapidly by, when we heard "puflf-puff--piff,' in the the distance, and looking out, saw two bright fires approaching us, before which the distinct outline of the man tending them was occasionally visible. As- they drew nearer, we saw that they belonged to the "Yuba' bound for the Missouri River, a iboat cele- brated for racingS-'" Come, fire-up, fire-up," grumbled out the gruff voice of her captain; and it seemed toas' then as though we had at length seen the ".Flyingr Dutchman," or some other infernal craft. Our cap- tain was a very sensible man, on this occasion at least, for he rang a bell and we "lay-to" till the- "-Yuba " passed, and she rushed fuming by like a dis- appointed demon. Before reaching Galena, however, we frequently found ourselves envying passengers on fast boats, for we went at such an intolerably slow pace that it actually tired us. On rising, the next morning, we asked the way to' the wash-room. This was delightfully situated next" the wheelhouse, and was extensively furnished with. two dirty cracked basins, whose bottoms wore thick  with the sediment of Misssppi water; one small towel hung on a nail, for the avowed purpose of giv- ing three hundred persons an opportunity to dry themselves, while a beautiful mirror reflecting a very  &#xD;<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC8237-00000069"/> ' 138 dirly face,'was discovered to the delighted spectator,  )i:: the water in which he had just washed himself,  ; :We were four days on the "Dr. Franklin, No. 2," and that small towel was only changed once the whole passage  Having performed our ablutions, we went" through the ordeal of breakfast, and then issued forth to con- -template "the romantic beauties"' of the Mississippi. We were, on the whole, disappointed. The scenery was not so fine, to our eyes, as that on the Ohio. We saw a wild, luxuriant country, on either side, but few of those high, romantic bluffs, we had expected. We passed what- were, probably, beautiful little islands, but the rise of the river had transformed them into clumps of trees, growing out of the water. Many of :.the inhabited places were half under water, and looked sufficiently desolate, without the accompaniment of the crows-Whieh hovered over them.. We passed, among other places, modern "Gilead," and, to our surprise, when opposite it, somebody, near by, cried out "Dain,-I say, Dan," and, turning round, we saw a lank; yellow dyspeptic, in the act of being addressed by this ancient appellation. "Can this be Dan"r thought, we, "and that scurvy little place 'Gilead." We immediately conceived tha, horrible desire of throwing Dan overboard, in the hope of his   139 being swallowed by some fish and then vomited up again into Gilead, for we were confident no stomach, whether of fish, fowl, or beast, could long hold such a morsel. Gilead was the only fit place for such a man. As we proceeded on our way, and the boatnext-grated harshy on the shore, "facnibal" was shouted out- "O Yellow!" said Blue, "can it be that we are at college again for ,they are 'continually ringing the changes' in my ears of those ancient names we used to read about:-but let us go forward and see this Hannibal, whether he be like unto a man, or only another yellow, dyspeptic stick, like Dan;" and we went and saw that Hannibal was a place, most curious- ly construoted of roofs and chimnies, at least, as far as we could see, for all else was under water. The next place, Marion City, we- fondly hoped would break the spell of ancient places, but, on inquir- ing, discovered that Palmyra was but a short distance inland. "Quincy," that followed, did not surprise us; on the contrary, our only surprise was that we had not met with more quinsies in such a wet country; but, when "Tully" followed, we groaned again, and "Warsaw " next coming, we were utterly confounded. Niver before had we met with such a mixture of an- cient, modern, and medicinal names. Next came the' Mormon city (that was), "Nauvoo," which rose up  &#xD;<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC8237-00000070"/> "O before like some anaent city of tie East as seen in panoramas;? silent and red it loked, and the Temple in the distance strongly reminded Blue of the trinum plE areTh ok the " (hamps. .yses."-We're detep *r ned, to let you know that Blue's "been abroad."- eaving. Nauvoo, we next passed ".Fort .Madisow," &amp; o sipposit '4t panXose; ' which we tink must be a. typographieal'error, and intended for .Hapminess', as, this town is comparatively on dry land, and the in abitans seemed to possess a degree of cheerfulness. Afte ti^s^s4 kuA River' i's seen "to pour its foul trean ito: the Mississippi, and then having reached  "Oquawka," we began tq snell for nl ians, We say we began to snell for them; e, of course mean meta- phoically. We are compelled to use this inelegant xpXesson ,by the fact that we once did smell one, liteally bwhen we were immediately made acquainte with a doggy, musty smell, of a slightly suffocating n4ature since .whch time .our ideas of Indians have always bheenassocited with the sense. of; smell .But, though we smelt for them, we did not see them; no! ao one of tihat persecuted race appeared, to stalk aiajStitclly and reprovingly before us.. There are 5om ptesons ian the .world wh oprofess to have out- liypdastonisbhnent,and we remember at one period of r livestO have thought that the same ievent had )   "1 happened to-us; but not to meet the- red man -so -near his own home would move, we should think, even tihe red man himself, to astonishment.( We had verily run- greater risks of being scalped, during sundry little excursions made to ]Hoboken, than on this expedition of ours to the West,-unless, indeed, they were all the while lying in ambush. We lamented, however, this- omission of the red nin among the other dramatis per, sonce, for we had hoped to benefit the cause of science by successful inquiries into the origin of those Indian names, which, one would think, are alone sufficient - to strike terror into their enemies-such, for instance, as Piankeshaw, Kickapoo, Quapaw, Puncah, Chickasatw, and many others. Chippewa is easily accounted for.  The number of that tribe has dwindled to thirty.' The only alteration we would suggest, is the substitutic of "d "for the second 'p," which would make it Chij'd ewa. In a Universal Gazetteer, for 1852, we see 'under  the head of ' Indian Territory," the following imposing prospects for the Indians :- "This Territory was set apart' by Congress for the permanent residence of the Indian tribes. Here *they are secured a refuge from the progressive encroach. ments of the white races, and allowed to live under governments of their own- choice, suject to no other   &#xD;<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC8237-00000071"/> "2 control of the United:. States than such as may be lecessary to reserve theeae of thefrontier, and har- -mony amohn the several tribes," By referring to a Report of the Commissioner for Indian Affairs, that appeared in December, 1853, it will be seen what degree of reliance may be placed on a nation's faith. O ye Piankeshaws, Kickapoos, Quapaws, Puncahs, Ohickasaws, and others of your race, your destiny is so plainly written that "he who runs may read." The time is not far distant when those scalp locks of yours will be darkening the billows of the Pacific, for you will soon reach "the end of the log," and then, plunp, you drop,one after the other, into, the waves, where you r   will swim about- for a short time, finally to disappear forever, and take your places, perhaps, in the list of Fabulous Nations that were once dreamed about."' It will be folly, ye dear red brethren! to talk about your wrongs. + A-smooth veil of sophistry will sufficiently satisfy the white man's views, when -his selfishness : -will it to be so. But you have two courses before you. The 7one is to do as we did on a former occasion, whichwe: yearly celebrat--Rise against your oppres- : sor . You will undoubtedly be completely extermin- :ated :in the attempt, but it will be at least in that brave struggle against wrong, where the death of the   "3 right is more glorious than the victory of the oppres- sor. The other course is to wrap yourselves up in the mantle of stoicism or resignation, and unresistingly submit to your fate. But, don't talk; it will be of no avail, for selfishness already knows how to deaden its ears to the cry of others' woes. Whichever of the two courses you choose, die bravely and uncomplaining; and it will be for you rather to pity and mourn over a nation who can part with its honor for the premature possession of a little piece of the earth, the whole of which God made for all. Tyranny may be able to destroy the poor red body, but it can never reach the free spirit.  On the third day the milk gave out, and we were obliged to content ourselves with a vile black liquid which they dignified by the name of " tea." We began to doubt whether we should ever reach Galena, we plodded on at such a slow, monotonous rate. Our passengers consisted chiefly of specimens of that glorious, noble western race that you hear so much about, and whom you are fortunate in seeing so little of,-lank, uncouth, clumsy, and rough, they are unpleasant beings to meet with; but yet, inde- pendent, enterprising, and hardy, they are- just the men to open a new country. Whether they were made expressly for that purpose, or whether the  &#xD;<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC8237-00000072"/> "4: coantry itself has made them so, is a matter of doubt; still, one could hardly bring himself to belevee o looking at them, that those tough, robust bodies, were once tender, delicate babes. They look rather as if they must have sprung directly from their -mother earth, and been suckled by bears and wolves. . The discipline on these boats was of the most orderly character. About meal-time, two waiters were seen to walk, with great formality-and precision, towards two tables of the kind known as "extension." Seizing hold of the part to be drawn out, they ran backwards with a short, rapid step, until, coming in collision with each other, back to back, the shock doubled them over upon the tables; then, sliding out at the sides; they joined the two lend laid the spread. -The' chairs were always standing in a r6w, in the most precise manner, against the tides of the sa- loon,; giving it that stiff, cold, cheerless appearance that you meet in the parlors of persons in moderate circumstances, who use their parlprs only for tom- pany. We were at first astonished at their remaining so long in the same precise order and position. More than once, on drawing out one from its dreary society of other empty chairs, and then leaving it to get a book or something else out of our state-room, we   "5 would return and find 'it mysteriously occupying its former place amongst its dreary chair-mates. We were curious to witness the process of return, for we could hardly believe it was a voluntary one on the part of the chair. It was a wonder, at least, that we had never heard of; so we repeated our former movements, and again emancipated a chair. from the stiff, cold, and silent company of ane- bottoms; and then, returning to our state-room, lay in ambush and looked out for the result. We had barely taken our position, when we saw a waiter, heretofore invisible, suddenly appear and remove the chair back to its former place. So we sagely came to the conclusion that there were always certain persons on the look-out for every opportunity to preserve order; a pleasant reflection, truly,-to think that while you are sitting in a chair reading, or otherwise employed, you are the subject of a system of espionage, ad that the moment of your rising will be the signal for rushing forth and restoring order among the chairs. Among the passengers was a Methodist parson, who was continually preaching disipline, and talking about the wonderful influence his wife possessed over two miserable, demure-looking little bundles of akin and bones, whom  he was pleased to denominate  &#xD;<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC8237-00000073"/> "6 hii children. The secret of her influence, we soon ::i^dovered, lay i spanking them at stated intervals. To use the rod- is, Solomon's injunction, but he does not tell us to make it a regular employment. This parson made his appearance every afternoon, -with very sleek hair, a smooth, sanctified face, and a white cravat, and spent an hour in reading. Some- times he: would knit his brows, then bend over the book and look keenly up at the ceiling, as if strug- gling with a mighty thought; at other times he would read on calmly and placidly, with a beatified air; always it was "whiz-er, whizser, whiz-er," then a satisfied swallow, Ad then  "whiz-er, whiz-er, whiz-er," again. Our last day ion board was Sunday, and this genius had been exceedingly restless the preceding evening for a call. His anxious wish was gratified. On the Sabbath morn he appeared pale, solemn, and precise; and just as we entered Fever river, the captain invited him to "hold forth" in the cabin. The exercises began by a singular noise made in a nasal, monotonous twang of voice, which grated so unpleasantly on our ears, that we were compelled to leave the cabin and seek refuge in the open air; and were soon lost in admiration of the loveliness of nature in general, and of the beautiful bends   "7 and turns of Fever river in particular. A chilliness in the' atmosphere, however, -soon drove us back again to the shelter of the cabin; where, the "singing" having just subsided, the parson wasg setting his teeth and bracing himself as for a mighty effort. A horrible tirade of canting slang again drove us forth; and this time we wrapped ourselves up as warmly as we could, and remained outside until the bell rang for dinner.  .   &#xD;<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC8237-00000074"/> CHAPTER XXI. WHEN we returned after dinner to the outer-deck, our eyes were greeted by the welcome sight of the nd of our long and tedious voyage--G alena rose before us; a collection of hills, with houses perched on the tops and scattered over the sides; -a dismal, dreary, dirty-looking place, the desolate appearance of whbih rather modified the excess of joy with which we had contemplated our escape from the old steam- boat. ! While James Yellow watched our trunks on the landing, John Blue set out on a voyage of discovery fr, the; hotel, and also for a wagon to carry our luggage thither, as no conveyance could be found near the:quay. On returning, after an absence of }. abouttwo hour, he found Mr. Yellow blue, shivering with cold, and regarding, with ineffable disgust, a dog that had just thrown up his dinner on one of the R truinls near by. Returning together to the hotel which Blue had   "9 discovered, we found dreary discomfort and a dreary dinner there awaiting us. W6 were that day very much' like the weather,-dull and muggy; and the prospect before us-that stage-ride to Chicago-was any thing but cheering. In the afternoon Blue, sallied forth in search of a friend who resided here. There being no directory in the place, he was obliged to trust -to the verbal directions of strangers. After asking several persons, who could give him  no clue, he at last found : man who seemed to have a very clear idea of the geography of Galeta, and of the number and names of all its inhabitants. By him Was Blue kindly instructed to "go this way, then that way, then round the corner, then turn to the left, and then to the right, and then-down a bit, until he should see a white house, and that was in Geer Street; then he was to go up Geer Street -to Prospect Street, and in some of the houses there he would probably find some one who would know where his friend lived." Thanking the man for his time and trouble, Blue followed these minute directions as closely as possible, and though with little hope, did actually stumble' at last upon Gfeer street. He found Geer street to consist of a high, steep, and precipitous hill, well wooded, and I  &#xD;<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC8237-00000075"/> ldeA O0uiit,    ith-  or two  nds ofI provided, on the summit, with one or two-ponds of waters, Pretty well blown,' he asked some boys who were-pllaying ball there-on Sunday, too-where Pros- peet street was, and, to his great disgust, received for answer, that it was "but one street from the bottom of the hill." Nothing remained, however, but to stumble down again (for the hill abounded in stones). He finally reached a tract of land comparatively level, and this he found to be Prospect street. After knocking out all the people in Prospect street, he finally en- countered a very pretty girl, who gave him the desired information. Next followed a series of rapid descents and toilsome climbings, which brought him suddenly upon Bent street,-in safety, much to his surprise;-- passed five churches, from which he concludel Galena was religious;-climbed another hill, and, at length, reached his friend's residence. We've not the slightest doubt but that some indi- vidual will here ask, "Who's your friend?"-but we'd rather not give his name, as he may not wish to appear in print. - We had intended going to St. Paul's, but, on learning that a delay of two or three/ days was neces- sary,-no boat leaving till then,-if will not be won- dered at, by those who have read the foregoing that 9     151- we left Galena in the stage-coach on the-following morning, at the early-hour of six, after a sojourn, n. that execrable place, of sixteen hours, the majority of which was spent in hunting out bed-bugs, and smash- ing them when found.  &#xD;<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC8237-00000076"/> CHAPTER XXII. THE first hour or two in a stage-coach, in com- pany with half a dozen strangers, is extremely discouraging. There is a silence and embarrassment brooding over all, which is ten-fold increased by the very consciousness of it, and the sense of one's utter impotence to escape from it. We, James Yellow and John Blue, in common with other fellow-mortals under the like circum- stances, felt oppressed and uneasy. At one time we made an attempt at conversation, but the sepul- chral tone of our voices, breaking the dreadful silence, fairly hushed us up; and there was, too, a vivid impression on the mind of having said something very weak and absurd, that made one feel dreadfully insignificant. About the middle of the second hour, however, something generally occurs to break the spell; and it our case it was nothing less than the rolling of a kegover the roof of the coach, in company   153 with a tin pail, which had such a ludicrous effect, that our countenances began to warm-into a little geniality. First, we heard the keg Tumbling surlily along; then suddenly strike the tin pail; then a clatter immediately ensued, and both rolled and rumbled off together. This occurred with such regularity and frequency, that, at length, human nature could stand it no longer, and there was a general laugh through the coach.  After this, it seemed as though some heavy storm had cleared up, and the sun had come out shining again; every- thing went on so pleasantly; there was an atmos- pheie of repose and luxurious abandonment; and we soon found ourselves chatting cozily and familiarly together, as though we were the oldest and best friends in the world. We 'were astonished at the mean appearance of the lead mines; which, to the eye, seemed nothing more than holes sunk in the earth, as if one had been digging for wells; and this especially after having seen them designated on the map by blacker spots, and larger, than those usually allotted to towns, and "EAD MNES" distinctly printed, in the northwest corner of Illinois. Crossing the boundary line into Wisconsin, we admired the boundless prairies that now stretched before us; and discovered a sublimity in them even 8.  &#xD;<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC8237-00000077"/> 154 surpassing that emblem of sublimity, the ocean, itself. On our sensibilities at least, the quiet, im- movable boundlessness before us, had an intense effect- which the restless motion of the ocean had never inspired. After dinner, the afternoon sun -shone pleasantly into the coach; and having asked the- permission of the only lady traveler with us, who professed to be very fond of the smell of the cigar, we produced our cases, and under the influence of that pleasant narcotic, dreamed away the remainder of the daylight. We should not feel justified, however, in omitting to make mention of that young man, who, during -an- interesting philosophical discussion that arose respecting the origin of those. distinctive appellations which divide our western citizens into the several classes known as hoosiers," "suckers," "pukes," etc., indiscreetly propounded the following problem: "If an Illinois man should marry a Missouri woman, what would the progeny be called "  Whereupon the lady, with her quick wit, immediately replied, "A puke-sucker." - Not, however, till the words had left her mouth, did she discover how much they signified; and then, suddenly struck with shame and confusion, she drew a veil over her blushing features; while we, with risibly indignant A               \   155 countenances, severely rebuked the audacious ques- tioner. The heinousness of his offense lay in the covert manner of putting the question. Had ,he openly asked, "If a sucker should marry a puke," &amp;e., he would have been met with by an indignant silence; but concealing it, as he did, was the occasion of the lady's indiscretion--a gross breach of con- fidence on his part, which, while it by no means destroyed the hilarity of the company, deprived us, nevertheless, of the pleasant oecupation-of beholding the' delicate features of our only lady companion, who, for the remainder of the jouney, kept herself closely veiled.  The day, that had passed so agreeably, was suc- ceeded by a night of horrors, sleeplessness, and gloom.  As night advanced, it became very cold; not a. bracing, healthy cold, but a- damp chilliness that kept one constantly covered with goose-flesh. It was becomiig very dark, when we found ourselves leaving the open prairie, and entering into the deep obscurity of a patch of wood. called '"'ratiot's Grove." This, one of our more experienced com- panions seemed to regard with particular horror; and with good reason, as we discovered, for we had no sooner entered it than all our difficulties commenced,  Plunged in Erebian gloom, it -was by -  &#xD;<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC8237-00000078"/> 1565. our sense of feeling alone that we became acquainted with the terrors of "Gratiot's Grove." The first sensation was as if the two front wheels had suddenly sunk down, while we found ourselves suddenly pitched forward upon' those occupying the front seat. Then ensued a tugging of the horses, who, were evidently  being very much whipped and stimulated by the driver. Then the, door of the coach opened, and we heard a voice say (for we could see nothing), "Come, you must all get out;" whereupon, one after another jumped out into the darkness, when each found himself up to his knees in mud. At length the fore-wheels were extricated, when- we were allowed to reenter the coach, which, after much feeling, we finally succeeded in finding; not, how- ever, before James Yellow and John Blue had both found themselves two or three times, in the confusion of ideas, climbing a rail-fence, which they had mis- taken for the coach. It was the hind-wheels' turn to suffer next, which they did by going through precisely the same manoeuvres that the fore-wheels had; and now the occupants of the front and middle seats- found them- selves precipitated upon those on the hind seat. John Blue was fortunate enough to find himself in the embrace of the veiled lady, and had an indistinct   idea of having his mouth stuffed with woman's 4othes, which effectually prevented him from begging pardon for his sudden and involuntary obtrusiveness. The wheels being now stuck very deep, we recovered our proprieties as speedily as possible, and all jumped out, one after another, into the mud again. In tugging away at the coach, one of the traces broke, when there proceeded such a volley of oaths and execrations on the part of 'the driver, that even the men were obliged to put their fingers to their ears. This having been patched up, we again proceeded on our soggy way; and by a long series of such transactions, passed the' night. When morning dawned, we found ourselves rolling -smoothly over prairie-ground again.- We saw the darkness slowly retreating before the dim gray dawn; the eastern sky now became gradually red; and at length the sun itself appeared, and revealed haggard eyes, pale faces, and muddy garments, while the cool, fresh air fanned our fevered cheeks. For relief and variety, we languidly got out of the coach, and attempted to take " a morning walk," as we called it, "before breakfast;" but we soon discovered that we were too much fatigued to enjoy pedestrianism, so scrambled in again. The horses were very much  &#xD;<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC8237-00000079"/> 1S8 tilad also, as might have been expected ; and before eaehiing the place to breakfast, they all four on one occasion fell down at once, when our ears were again regaled by a repetition of the driver'shorrible oaths. A more forlorn and be-draggled party never dragged themselves in-to a breakfast-table. That meal con- sisted of coffee that tasted as though brown soap had been dissolved in it, eggs that smelt rank, and ham which stuck in our throats, being made, as we do verily believe, of thick red leather. Our only resource was the unfailing cigar, and puffing away, we con- tinued our journey, cheered with the unexpected assurance of the driver, that we had traveled, between sundown and breakfast, seven and a half miles! A good night's work, that, surely. ! (not the "Oh," sentimental or rapturous, but the "O" of anguish. We detest "Oh;" and, to borrow an expression from one of our New-York would-be-exquisites, "generally always" throw aside the book in which it occurs), but O! what a tedious, dismal ride we had to Cherry Valley, nodding and bobbing about in the coach, from fatigue and jolting! and when we did at last reachf that place, and took our seats in the cars, James Yellow asserted that he never liked the looks of a locomotive so much in his   159 life before; and immediately followed the example, of;, John Blue, who had fallen fast asleep while Yellow's remark was in process of enunciation. When we awoke, it was to find ourselves in Chicago.  &#xD;<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC8237-00000080"/> CHAPTER XXIII. WE were not particularly struck with the appear- ance of Chicago or its inhabitants, on our first arrival in that city. Everything seemed misty and vague, as was very natural to persons just waked out of two (not "too," but the numeraD sound slumbers. We rode dreamily to the hotel, went through a dreamy tea, and then dreamily dragged ourselves to our room and threw ourselves into bed, where we -slept much too soundly to dream at all. On the following day we found Chicago the flattest of inhabited :places. It was so flat, that it - looked as though you could slap it. The streets and sidewalks were all boarded, like the floor of a vast toom, and afforded unusual facilities for runaway horses. A canal runs through the city-the great canal which joins Lake Michigan to the Illinois and Mis- sissippi rivers, and thus cuts a very big piece out of the continent of North America, and makes an   161 island of it; that is, when the locks are all open- an island being, According to Webster, "a tract of land surrounded by water."   Having sufficiently dwelt upon this grand idea, we wandered through the city. We say " wandered," because we strolled listlessly along, without any guide or any fixea aim, until we found ourselves looking out upon Lake Michigan; which, for all we could see, was boundless as the ocean, only there was very little wind, and the X waves, white-caps, and foam of the ocean were not there. We here amused ourselves by picking up shells on the shore, and- thus enjoyed the feeling that Newton speaks of, when he likens his acquisitions of knowledge to that employment. We must say, however, that if Noewton really felt so, he must have found it very unsatisfactory business; at least, if he were any thing like us, for we soon tired of it, and strolled back into the heart of the city again. We passed a church built of a very curious kind of stone that is dug out of the prairie. This stone is of a gray color, with black, spots, and gave the building a very antique and chequered appear- ance, which greatly delighted us. The next day we took the steamboat to MiliVaukie; of which city we have nothing especial to record, except that we considered it a very pleasant place'to $-X  &#xD;<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC8237-00000081"/> 162 live in; that the streets were all paved with planks, as in Chicago; that the houses were nearly all frame buildings, of a dark yellow color; and neat and uni- form in appearance; and that dast, but by no means least) there it was that we met the prettiest, the jolliest, the most gushing beauty that ever crossed our indi- vidual or collective path. The thought of her stirs up our blood even now. Truly, "a thing of beauty is a joy forever!" Here, too,-- we had our first experience in rat- hunting, and we hbpe also our last. How we did corner that fellow in the "reading-room" of the City Hotel! and how we jumped on chairs when- ever he rushed by!. and how we slashed about, in a perfect agony of shudders, those files of newspapers two months old! How glad we were to be reinforced by our host, who, being perhaps experienced in the art, soon made a hole in the rat with an umbrella, and then flung his stiffened form into the street. The mud near Milwaukie is so deep at some seasons of the year, that the inhabitants are not unfrequently lost in it, which dries around them, and thus transforms them into fossils for the inspection of future generations. Among the specimens of this kind to be disclosed-o after-ages, will be one that will undoubtedly excite great wonder, and tax the ingen. o   163 uity of all the learned men of the period. The manner in' which this specimen first became im- bedded is unknown, for it was not discovered till after the process had been nearly completed. The facts of the- discovery were related to us by a mild, quiet-looking man, who was dressed in black, and wore a white cravat. They were as follows: One summer, after a very wet spring, the mud of which had dried up under the excessive heat, a friend of his was sauntering leisurely along -the road, when he came across a hat, lying quietly in his path. The first impulse, on the first sight of this. object, under such circumstances, is always to give it a kick into the air. This impulse, indeed, is so strong in our nature that we have, ourselves, frequently gone out of our way for the express purpose 9f indulging this irresistible desire. His friend was by no means backward in this respect, but immediately sent it to the other side of the road. The report that followed the kickproduced all those pleasing emotions in his mind that such reports usually produce, and to which effect we ascribe this great and universal passion for kicking hats; when, to his horror, he saw, too late, that he had kicked the hat off a man's head. He, immediately apologized for his rudeness; but the embarrassment he felt in apologizing to nothing but  &#xD;<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC8237-00000082"/> 164 ahead sticking out of the road, only made the matter still more awkward, for the head must evi- dently have seen that it was entirely at his mercy, notwithstanding apologies. He, therefore, asked if he couldn't assist him, when the head surlily answered, "No;" that he bad a strong horse under him, and wished other people. would mind their own business! :This unexpected reply so exasperated his new acquain- tance, that he went after the hat, and replacing it on the owner's head, knocked it over his-eyes and left him. Not long after, he was advertised among the missing, and " supposed to have been lost in the mud, during the late heavy season." These are the facts, as given us by the clerical, benevolent-looking gentleman in the white cravat, and on him, not on us, lies the burden of proof. They say that the Father of Lies has a wiry, forked tail, and cloven foot; but this gentleman, on inspection, was found to possess only very modest coat-tails, and the only fork about him was that which we all possess in common, the one, we mean,' which is formed by the legs branching off. As for the cloven foot, he had on a well-shaped boot, which was the nearest view we could obtain, not daring to ask him to pull it off, for fear he might have some of the Grimshaw tendencies   165 his friend possessed, and knock our hats over our eyes. If ever you should go to Milwaukie, fail not to visit "the Nashotah Mission." It is not far, and is worth your while; for you will there see a picture of life without luxury, yet cheerful and contented. We took the cars to a place called "Forest House," and thence a stage, over a plank road, for about six- teen miles, when, stopping before a white house, the driver opened the door and shouted out "Old Cock of the Walk." We had told him to drop us at "' Ocono- mawoc ;" so we settled ourselves back again into our seats, and wondered "what was that for a name," almost as much as the Frenchman beside us, who seemed also beside himself, half the time. But the driver said he "couldn't wait there all day, and we must go out, or he'd drive on." This only increased our astonishment, afd the driver, now seeing four va- cant saucer eyes staring at him, asked us if we weren't the young men who wanted to be dropped at "Old Cock of the va. alk?" 5We, of course, told him "No,- at Oconomawoc," and asked him if it was much farther on; whereupon, to our great indignation, he burst out into a horse-laugh, and when he had concluded, fur- nished us with the information that there was no such place as "Oconomawoc," imitating our pronunciation,  &#xD;<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC8237-00000083"/>  166  with an affected elegant air, and that "the only place near any such d-d name" (we were awfully shocked :by the d-d '), "was Old Cock of the Walk, and we must get out, or he'd: drive on ;" s. we each put our best foot forward, and got out as rapidly as possible. On inquiring of the host,-for the "white house" now proved to be an inn,---we found that we were very near:Nashotah, and therefore felt quite reconciled to our change.--We had not been long in our new quar- ters (for we determined to dine before going farther), when a light wagon drove up, of the seat of which eight-ninths was occupied by a mammoth, belonging to the class "mammalia,"-we could not say "ox," for he wasn't an ox; neither could we say " man," for "-man," according to Webster, is "opposed to beast;" :but he certainly belonged tothe "Mammalia," so we take refuge in that compromise between the two;- his companion, who occupied thb other ninth of the seat, was lean in proportion. This mammoth was immediately saluted by the host, who was always on the spot, as "Judge." "Judge" entered in the most pompous manner, while the other, evidently his satel- lite, came in proportionably obsequious. Then fol- lowed a talk on politics and nonsense, between the two, that excited the admiration of our host to a most ex- traordinary degree, for he would rub his hands and   167 shake his head, and then look at us in the most pro- found and erudite manner. It was an excellent farce, and we enjoyed it, but we were, nevertheless, glad when the drop-curtain fell, in the shape of a table- cloth. a  The conveyance from Old Cock'of the Walk to Nashotah was an open two-horse wagon, without springs, and over a very rough road, which threatened to jolt the ham and eggs back to where they had gone in.-We found the interior of -Wisconsin much more settled and cultivated than we had expected. The country we now passed through, is a fine woodland one, dotted with lakes, and very romantic. "The Nashotah Mission " is situated on an elevated plain, which rises from the border of one of the Nas- hotah Lakes, and commands a fine view of the sur- rounding country: Four lakes can be seen its imme- diate vicinity, from two of Which, called "the Nas- hotah," it derives its name. These lakes are very similar to each other in size and shape, and communi- cate by a narrow'and shallow stream, which flows from the upper into the lower, whence they are called "the Nashotah," meaning "the twin," lakes. A short distance from the "Mission," is our friend's -house; and he received us with an open heart and hand. Here, in a state of truly enviable celibacy, he /  &#xD;<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC8237-00000084"/> 168. lives among his books, and absorbed in the earnest study of his profession, is fitting himself for the noblest and highest calling on earth. As far as the luxuries of life are concerned, the student at the Mission is truly destitute, but with simple tastes and habits, he is rich in cheerfulness and 6ontent,-the only true conditions of happiness. They number twenty, and live in small white cottages, each having a room about 6 ft. by 8. Necessity obliges them to raise their own vegetables, put up their own fences, do their own car- penter work, and,-start not, ye who wear shirt-collars and bosoms,-even their own washing and ironing. Our friend, himself, was at that time on " the Ironing Committee." He said, with a melancholy air, that they made sad bungling work of it at first, the great difficulty being to get the starch in: but in this they succeeded, at last, and, one morning, all appeared in starched bosoms and collars of most incredible stiffness, and very black to look upon. By perseverance, how- ever, they have cultivated their latent talent for iron- ing, and can now vie with the best washwomen in the country. We took a row on one of the Nashotali lakes, and ran through the woods and frightened pigeons, and started quail, and had a glorious time that afternoon; and then, as the sun was setting, we perched ourselves   on an old rail-fence and cracked jokes, and felt so primitive and innocent that we cannot help mournfully looking back and wishing we were there again, instead of being in this crowded city of New York, so full of all kinds of naughtiness.  We astonished our friend that night with a pair of appetites that spurned all the bounds of decorum and propriety; and shall never forget the evening in "the Study," with all the old theologians on the shelves around us, whom we must also have greatly astonished by the freedom with which we discussed, questions which they had made the study of their lives.  &#xD;<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC8237-00000085"/> CHAPTER XXIV. MLWAUKIE and Chicago seemed tame to us after JNashotah, so we; turned our faces homeward. We "did up"Michigan in a single night; that is. to say, we 'left Chicago one evening in the cars, and reached Detroit the next morning. From the cars to the Lake Erie 3?oat was a rapid transition; we do not mean to nimply that it is necessarily so,-only, that it was so in this instance. The morning after found us in Buf- falo. Here we would stop a moment to warn any ::one reaching that place in the morning with bleared and :unwatehful eyes, against that man who takes your trunks, you unwilling, to a little house near a :teamboat, and gives you tickets to Oswego, swearing ,at the same time, that is the shortest route to Niagara als. He unwilling, you will put your trunks in a baggage car, discard boat-traveling, and rattle it through to the Falls. At the Falls, we pause and deliberate.    , 1i  A sufficient time is supposed to have elapsed for a reasonable amount of deliberation, of which we only record the conclusion, with two reasons: Conclusion. We skip "the Fals." Reasons. 1st. We have read many descriptions of them, but none ever gave us a true idea of the reality. 2d. We felt ourselves unable to improve on, if even to equal, those that have gone before. But we shall not soon forget them, no, nor the little girl at the "Burning Spring," who nearly set us on fire, by plunging the lighted paper too quickly into the gas. We have even now a vague idea of singed eyebrows and smoked faces, and a very vivid one of a pair of bright eyes laughing and dancing about in a bewitching little head. Nor have we yet forgotten that old English soldier at' Lundy Lane Observatory, who told us how "the Americans quietly walked away, leaving the English in possession," and how "the English very coolly staid there three weeks, when, getting tired of waiting for the Americans, they went away themselves." We closely scrutinized that frank, weather-beaten, venerable visage; and how could we help but believe? But, we shall be led, unawares, into giving our description of the Falls, and as that would be violating our own firm convictions, founded on due  &#xD;<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC8237-00000086"/> -  "e      - *  1'2 deliberation, let us here cease all further reminiscences. The more reason this, for we did write- a description to a friend, which we flattered ourselves was an excellent one, and our vanity might tempt us to transcribe it,- but enough of this.  We had looked forward to Saratoga as a place of rest, where we could repose after our wanderings, and regain that strength and flesh which. we had expected to lose. How disappointed, then, were we, on investi- :gating the matter, to find that we were even stronger and fatter than when we had started. Still, we were resolved to spend a week at Saratoga, and as the course of nature hadn't made recruiting necessary, we determined to create a necessity ourselves, so adopted the expedient of leaving Niagara, in the afternoon and traveling through by the "night express," which, in- deed, had the desired effect, for we reached Saratoga in such a sleepy state that, being unable to hold up our heads long enough to eat breakfast, we were fain to re- tire to bed to gain adequate strength for the task. We passed the remainder of the day in the manner and with the degree of comfort usually experienced by persons who haven't slept a wink the night before, but on the day after, finding ourselves as well and fat as ever,.discovered, to our great chagrin, that one day at Saratoga had sufficed to entirely restore us. We now , !         s   173 attempted to delude ourselves into the belief that this extraordinary restoration was merely a mirage, some- thing like the fat appearance of dropsied people, only dropsy moreoclosely resembles that phenomenon, inas- much as mirages frequently have their foundation on water; so, under such distressing circumstances, we continued to remain at Saratoga, sadly bearing about us the appearances of health without its reality. The third day came, but the mirage had not vanished; we were still as hearty as ever; the fourth, fifth, sixth, and seventh days followed in rapid succession, with no change whatever-we were no better than on our arrival; and all for the simple reason, that we couldn't have been better. To attempt a description of Saratoga, as we saw iL, would only be ridiculous, for no one would recognize it. Who ever went to Saratoga in the fore part of June; when we say "who," we of course mean who of the "somebodies," the "nobodies" having no bodies,* can, consequently, have no voice in the mat- ter. But who would believe that Saratoga' is at any * In support of our assertion that they have no bodies, we would refer to a parallel case in Shakespeare's Reports, Merch. of Venice, where a Jew asks, "Hath not-a Jew eyes? hath not a Jew hands, organs, affections, passiona, &amp;c. i" and the case was decided against him.  &#xD;<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC8237-00000087"/> 174 time, a quiet, unobtrusive little village, where the un shines as peacefully, and the leaves of the trees tstle as softlas s in any other little rustic place; that the yellow buttefliyis seen flying about undisturbed; that the chirp of the cricket can be heard there, or the woodman's strokes as he fells the timbea? Nobody, of course, but the few " nobodies " who have dared to go there in June. Still, we both assert that it was the only pleasant time w;e ever spent there. What a comfort, to think, On waking up in the morning with afierce appetite, that one could get something to eat I What a comfort, to sit on ithe piazza, or stroll leisurely about ,as .we pleased, andi enjoy the soft breeze and general quiet, and then, after dinner, to walk out and hear,the, cows lowing in the distance, instead of the chatter, chatter, chatter, and the bustle and the rustle of crowded people, and thrumming of pianos, and dashing off of carriages; and, instead of " somebodies" strutting about in uncomfortable clothes, to see nobody at all, but the swallow, perhaps, in the air, or a stray ehiken or clucking henI But it is useless to say more, for no one will believe it. \ J   CHAPTER XX V. Tnt period is not very far distant when we should have deemed it mere presumption, on our part, to even suppose that there was any one in existence, who didn't know the way to New 'York from Saratoga; but having once taken by mistake the cars to Whitehall, while our trunks went in the opposite and right direc- tion, we now feel that it may not be so very presuming in us to suppose such an ignorance possible. The fact is, that the constant fizzing and rushing in and out of locomotives, and the hurry and bustle always going on at the Saratoga depot, are somewhat adapted to confuse even the mightiest of intellects; and, indeed, for a long time we were positively convinced that t' 4as the right finger post to Albany, while, in fact, , this one was. The right way, then, is to ask some one who knows; but in the absence of that person, or if unacquainted with the individual, a very probable case, by-the-by, the only course left is to arrive at a  &#xD;<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC8237-00000088"/> 176 lV6 proximate result by asking "all hands," from the sun- keneyed conductor to the sweaty and sooty engineer, and then forming your own conclusion from the whole. This was the course we adopted; and, one night, arrived at Albany in time to choose between the cars and steamboat for the remainder of tie route--in other words, to choose between two perilous risks of life. As we considered swimming about in the open air infinitely preferable to being cooped up in the cars under water, in case of accident on the part of either, we chose the steamboat. We deem it irrelevant to make mention of that remarkable instance of charity exhibited by Blue, who, seeing a poor hungry-looking Dutchman prowling near the kitchen of the boat, and snufflng up the savory odors of cookery, could not stifle the desire to let him into the mysteries of grati- fled appetite; or, to make mention of the great mod- esty and humility of Blue, shown in the manner of his charity, who, not desiring the notice of strangers, nor suffering "his right hand to know what his left hand doeth," put the left. into his pocket, and drawing forth what he felt to be a quarter, hastily thrust it into the hand of the Dutchman, and turned aray ; or attempt to paint the disappointed emotions on the donee's face, as, holding out his hand, he asked what he could buy with "that;" or the horror, and blushes of BBue, on   1" seeing that he had made the munificent donation of a-cent; or of the nervous rapidity with which Blue / changed the cent for a quarter; or how, to this day,  Blue protests that the Dutchman first changed the quarter for a cent, and then the cent for quarter No. 2, as he afterwards discovered, on looking into his finan- ces. All this, we consider irrelevant.  We would, however, ask permission to remark, that we have at length reached that goal which the reader has probably looked forward to with as much eager- ness andw impatiehce as the writers themselves; not with more' for we belong, unfortunately, to that class of individuals who consider things in general a great bore, and things in particular, particuiarly so-and "We," dear readers, has been to us a thing in particu- lar. If, however, there should be any one who has not considered "We" as such, we beg leave to tender him our hearty thanks, and congratulate him on the possession of that felicity of, disposition that always looks on the best side of things, and can find some- thing to like even in the unworthy. THE  END.  9                      s  &#xD;<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC8237-00000089"/>  APPENDIX.  A. (CHAP. VIII. p. 47.)5 IN the course of our Washington notes we have had occasion to notice the magnificent silence which John Blue maintained, under trying circumstances, when called upon suddenly and unexpectedly to decide for himself the double-  headed question, whether it were proper, and if so whether it were also expedient, for him to relinquish his "seat on the floor of the Senate" at the request of the janitor. I wish to suggest that this same sort of dignified silence, under certain difficult circumstances, is a sure sign of a great mind within, whose resources, like those of a mighty river, often lie hidden in some invisible recess, so deep that no tempests can ruffle its placidity, no "sea of troubles" surcharge it to the over- flow at the mouth. A few such men I was pleased to see in Washington; some of them occupying the chairs of Senators. This proves my position; for these are "the picked men of the country," and to insinuate aught against their greatness,  would be an infamous libel upon the good sense and dit' crimination of the American public, I do wrong even to hirt at such a monstrous idea. Now, my friend John Blue is just this quiet, taciturn, deep-minded sort of person, and for that reason, I wish, in the most delicate manner possible, to recommend the said John Blue to the State of New York, as a good candidate for the honor of representing her at Washington; and I have even the temerity to explain myself more fully by venturing an opinion that there are so many  &#xD;<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC8237-00000090"/> 180 i'tricate qesetions daily arising in Congre*ss and so much talking and n0ise, that'it would be decidedly to the advantage of the country, were she in future ;to send to Washington a larger proportion of qiet,'practical thinkers, than seem to be there now. Oratorical display seems to be a principal am- bition of too many; the hist for plunder and personal gain or aggrandizement seems to influence too many; while the class of politicians in the country at the present day (including all, from the Presidents down to the torch-light procession men) whose sole ambition is "thieir country" seems small indeed. We have few, very few, of the old-fashioned sort of statesmen left among us now. In conclusion, I would add, that if any further recommend- ation be needed to insure for John Blue an official seat at Washington, we are able to produce certificates from numer- ous personal friends of his, that he, never objects to a good dinner or to good- ines; that he has a keen relish for gen- uine Haivnas; and that, in the world of conviviality and good humor, there is not ajollier soul afloat. B.-  (CAP.. XtV. p. 82.) To all persons who may hereafter visit Louisville, in ignorance as to hotels, we would give this particular notice- that if they stop at the Gait House, and wish to leave at six o'clock in the morning, they will probably be gruffly and heartlessly informed, as we were, that "it is too early an hour to provide anything to eat or drink"We had asked, overnight, whether we could not have a breakfast of some sort, and urged the fact of our setting out the next morning for a long stage-journey; but we were thus positively re- fused our request (was-it an unreasonable one?), although it was at a season of the year when the days are long, and the   181 light comes early. We found the men in the "Office " of this hotel invariably surly and uncivil, and scarce any attention was paid us at table. Having the best and most abundant = authority for it, we would unhesitatingly recommend "the Louisville Hotel," as the best one in that city; unless, indeed, the manaigement of the "Gait House " has changed since the spring of 1862, in which ease, these remarks, of course, would no longer apply to it.  O. (CHAP. XIX. P. 133.) We also saw Jamieson, who was then acting at-this thea- ter (Bates'). He is the same Jamieson who was the intended victim of Forrest, in the notorious conspiracy between that individual and the Honorable John W. Forney, Clerk of the House of Representatives of the United States. Query. What does "Representatives " mean, according to the most modern authorities,-we mean, according to the present authorities at Washington? a  &#xD;<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC8237-00000091"/> E XTRACT-S FROM "ETTERS OF JAMES YELLOW TO A FRIEND IN BOSTON. * \\ ... * *   * You askr me if I have read UNILE ToM's  CABIN yet; and, if so, what I think of it. In answering you, I must throw aside all levity; for the subject which your question suggests, is one very poorly adapted to jeting pur- poses. I have read it, and with much the same kind of shiv- ering sensations as I would read the traitorous correspon- dence of a BENEDICT AuNOtD. I am pleased to learn, by your letter, that you have not read it. If the book presented itself merely as a work of fiction, it might justly claim the merit of being a  very ingeniously devised tale, very well told. But thisis not the case. It pretends to give us a true picture of slavery, as it now exist at the South; and, therefore,-in the outrageous exaggeration of the little truth it contains,-in the 'sweeping-but exceedingly crafty generalization of some few straggling exceptions to an almost universal rule, which it carefully strives to ignre,-.and in its sufficiently evident object, purpose and intent,--I can see nothing deserving a better epithet for the book than that of a most illful and ma- lcious libel. It is a shameful, voluntary, and unprovoked   183 inszlt and wrong to our Southern fellow-countrymen, and, by reflection, to ourselves also of the North. I wish I had an op- portunity to give you a more full and satisfactory exposition of my opinions of "Unicle Tom," and Abolitionism in general, than my present leisure will allow;-and yet, the task would be an unpleasant one, for thesubject is sickening and disgust- ing to me. I must content myself, for the present, by giving you one or two illustrations (taken from our traveling expe- riences) of the mbde of generalizing and exaggerating excep- tions to a general rule, spoken of above. In traveling through Upper Illinois (from Galena to Chicgo), my note-book says that "everything at the inns where we stopped for meals, looked so abominablyfilthy that I had hard work to force food down my throat Our meals were much the same,- breakfast, dinner, and tea,-consisting, in each case, of ham too tough to cut or chew, and apparently much more indai gestible than the pliant leaden instruments with which we were left to operate upon it. This ham, invariably of the saleest kind, was generally musty and covered with that pe- culiar appearance of green mold, which, when it appears upon cheese, I have known to give unbounded delight- to some old men, who had become so intimate with decayas to have-thus fallen in love with it." [Mind you,'this letter is strictly entre nous These, recollect, are extracts from my privatejournal; and if I thought any one, beside yourself was destined to see them, I should have omitted"to copy that last sentence; for many very worthy and estimable mendo, I be. lieve, like moldy cheese,--many, whom I would not offend for the world,-your good old uncle, perhaps, among the number.] "Hot muffins--our; coffee (8o-caled)--made, prob. ably, of burnt pea-nut shells; and (the only thing fit to eat) eggs. At one of these inns they gave us something that they facetiously styled ' brown sugar, for our ' coffee.' It had, how- ever, such a loathsome appearance that I should lave felt unwilling to offer it to a pet brute, if I had one, The color was an indescribable blending of a dirty brownish yellow  &#xD;<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC8237-00000092"/> v184 , dand adirty yellowishTbrown, with occasional grains o f'ablu- :;cish shade, the effect of which, upon my friend J. B., who was befori sufficiently blue himself, can hardly be imagined by thobsejwho had not the luxury of seeing his countenance when f heifirt laid eyes upon this sugar." [Tihere are moments in ones life, of such intense feeling, that one then wants "to be s le won"e, and this appeared to be such an occasion with John B2uoe.: Hee spoke not,- moved notl-but as the expression of ( his face plainly told me, he was undergoing some violent in- -:ternal distresress  espeted the sacredness of his suffering, and did not offer to intrude by any forced attempt at consolation. In fact, a man with an emptystomach, and with only these two alteratives before him-eat filth, or starve-has gener- ally but very little comfort to part with, were he ever so chari- : ably disposed.] ^ "Ants -were crawling through it; and the - Iany hard lumps, of which the greater part consisted, were -Iastened together (some of,them) with coarse red hairs, which - ihad ;eideatly been provided for that purpose by a half-clad seryingwonan, who stood close behind me, and- imparted to -my rostril san offensive odor, which in no way tended to in- cite ,an .appetite for the disgusting viands before me. The feae, neek, hands, and arms of this ill-favored but sturdy wait- ess, exhibited- a great variety of scars, beautifully inlaid with s9lid and liquid ,substances, our conjectures as to the nature :and^causes of which:I will not record; while the 'graceful- 4ess8 (Irish for 'greasefulness') with which thousands of very red hairs floatedin unrestrained license through the air, as :Ashe moved about, showed us that she belonged to that by no means Bmall class of Western people who entertain strong re- ligious: scruples against wasting time at the toilet or the wash- basini and who, whatever other sins they may have to answer for, will surely-never be dalled to accountfor an undue regard to their personal appearance. Now, it was by the hands of this same uncopmbly damsel that the aforesaid sugar was offered to us, in a broken glass tumbler. It looked so perfectly filthy, that I tried to drink my 'coffee' without sugar;-but the  . ,          %   185 'coffee' was very- bad stuff, so I shut my eyes and put in some of the article before mentioned;-but,; phew --augh!-on tasting my sweetened coffee' I almost - but,--(fortunately, I am enabled to avoid an indelicate word)-there happened to be a perfect vacuum' below, at the time, and as 'nothing can come of nothing' the only result was a bootless keeking, causing a somewhat different, but infinitely more painful sensation than that usually attendant upon a good bootedkiek- ing: but the choice of the precise place where, and the exact mode in which one's accounts with misery shall be footed up, is a privilege not generally left to the discretion of the vic- tim; neither are you, when forced to fight with that merci- less Ama7on, even allowed, in every case, to select your own weapons, or your own 'coffee.' Besides, you always enter the field with a perfect understanding that your noblest feats of valor must end in certain defeat, especially when, ashin this case, you are forced, without scarce a chance to strike a blow in your own behalf, to back out from the foetid smell which assails-your nose, In such a contest as the one-in which we have just been engaged, your opponent brandishes before you her formidable weapon -'Famine;' you look tremblingly upon the miserable means of defense provided for you,--take one swallow of your coffee, and then straightway reaH-but before you can find any available weapon, you are down,- (in your stage-seat again)-and the wound, being an internal one, your only relief is silently to weep on, in a state of cor- rosive vacuity, while the coach moves on to the next battle- field. But this is a silly trick,-this punning. It is a vice in which I never indulge, except in extreme eases. I well-know, too, that it- is with me like bad gas, throwing but a dim and sickly light upon the scene I would disclose. However, these gastric matters could not well be introduced otherwise, consistently with the strict rules of analysis." [Thus does my Journal seek to excuse me to myself. Can you forgive me the infliction of those vile puns upon you  Be assured that I am conscious of no injuries or affronts re- 9*  &#xD;<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC8237-00000093"/> 186 quiring so dreadful a retaliation; and that I do not now invent them for your special annoyanee:-but the fact is, I am too lazy'to alter the account, which I am copying verbatim from my notes, made at a time when I was truly desperate, and the most villanous puns; you know, are always excusable on such a pleaj.}/ "To return,-not, alas I to our mutton-but to the ooffee which I had just 'sweetened.' The peanut-shell flavor had now become lost in that of the etract of the castor-bean, which has too positive and well known a taste to be easily mistaken-- In this ease, the oil was very rancid, and who- ever should have had the temerity with which I ventured a glance into the coffee-cups, would have discovered, as I did, many beautiful globules floating on the surface :---o that there could be ho mistake about our 'coffee' being 'sweetened' with castor-oil. The mixture, thusformed, was far worse to take than the professed doses of that vile medicine which used to be 'given me in hot milk or coffee. I afterwards learned that there were three sick men lying in one bed, in an adjoining room :-whence, probably, the castor-oil of the sugar-tumbler I What was the particular name or nature of the maladies with which these men were afflicted, I could not ascertain, although I made many anxious inquiries for that purpose." Now, were I to append to this account a general remark that such is a fair specimen of the meals provided for travel- ers at a majority of the inns on Western stage-routes, I should probably convey to you none other, and no more, than a true general impression of the all-pervading nastiness of- most of said inns, and of the disgusting fare they are wont to place before their unlucky guests. Although you might, indeed, criticise my story, and apply to it such epithets as long-wind- ed," "prosy," "too revolting," &amp;c., &amp;c., you could not call it "false." But I have yet to come to the point. I want now to change the hypothesis, so as to illustrate Mrs. Stowe's or- namental style of portraying truth (orfalsifing it, as it may appear); and, for this purpose, I will turn to my rough jour- nal again for another extract. Traveling through Wisconsin,   187 I happened one day (when I was taking a stroll on foot), about noon, to notice "a log-cabin at the further end of a long, uinelosed field. Two little girls were playing together, and a yellow dog sat on the grass near the door, compla- cently enjoyingthe warm sun which was Bhiningvery pleas- antly upon the scene. I was wondering whether happiness might not probably dwell there, when, suddenly,as I contin- ued admiring the humble picture, a rough, unsightly ogre, in red shirt sleeves, and, in every. respect, altogether unlike any man I ever saw (before or since, out west, or elsewhere), rushed out of the door, followed by two half-grown boys, whom I took to be his sons, and brothers to the little girls. This fiendish apparition took a huge stride towards the dog, who was ap- parently in the act of fixing himself for a quiet snooze, seized him by the throat, and, holding him in mid-air with his left hand, beat him most unmercifully with a big stick; then, fix- ing some cord or rope around his tail, he fastened him to a tree in such a manner that his fore feet rested on the ground, while the hinder part of his body was elevated along the trunk of the tree, at an angle of about forty-five degrees; and then, leaving the poor animal in this uncomfortable position, our ogre strode back again into the house, evidently feeling better than when he came out. What the dog's offense was, I do not know; for I had happened to pass along that way just too late to see the first act of the drama But it mattered not much in this case. No offense, thought I, could warrant so cruel a punishment. But, as we were about determining, (J. B. was with me) to go over and release the poor struggling animal, one of the boys, having taken, perhaps, some of the milk of humanity from his mother's side, took him down, and we passed on." Such is a plain statement of what we saw one day in the interior of Wiseonsin,-no more nor less,-" nothing extenu- ated noraught set down in malice"It mayhb proper, how- ever, to add that there are a great many yellow dogs in some parts of Illnois and Wisconsin, and that, on one other occa-  &#xD;<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC8237-00000094"/> 188 sop, w e saw a Western dog fogged veryseverely to cure him off bad habit, which consisted i frequently gratifying a de praved taste for child's flesh; and that we were also told a story of an Illinois man who once boxed his dog's ears with considerable violence "because he would not mind him, nor come. when he was called." . Now I will endeavor to show you what Mrs. Stowe could make out of these little experiences, on the principle of Un- cle-Tom-ism. Her version might be somewhat as follows:- "The white settlers in our Western country are the most savage, people in the world,-in appearance, actions, and hab- its, more nearly approximatipg than any other to the nature of wild lbeasts. heir customs are far more cruel and inhu-, man than those of their predecessors-the Indians; ;and, chief among these, is the atrociousystem of yellow doggery, the op- eration of whig h I now proceed to explain. "Wherever one goes, in this part of the country, he finds numbers of yellow- dogs; of a form most rare and exquisite, gracefully agile in movement, and altogether the most cun- ning and bewitching of creatures. There is an innocence and purity about these dogs which is very seldom, if ever, to be found in man or woman. No one can look upon them with- 'out a humiliating consciousness of his own inferiority. I, for my par, believe those beings can be nothing less than angels, W;!o look so mildly forth, from beneath the form, color, and smell, of such beautiful yellow dogs ;-so totally different, in all respects, are they from the miserable yellow curs of the Eastern States, which I can by no means endure to have near me, and whose approaches I always instinctively repulse with ho ror.; I wish you -couldsee one of these; They defy de- sgriptionl But for what purpose, think you, do they keep and feed these lovely creatures You could never guess; so I'1 have to tell you.. Shudder not; blush not, at the narra- tivel I4 is of countrymen of ours, whom our constitution and laws recognize as men and fellow-citizens I Well,-they use these dogs in this wise. They have at leant one in every fam-   189 ily. The father issues from his hut each day at noon, and his children,-girls and boys,--stand around him, while he seizes upon the yellow dog and beats him till he tires of the exert cise, or until the poor animal becomes too slippery to Hold any longer, by reason of the clotted blood which accumulates upon him; then he hangs him up, by the throat, to the branch of a tree, to dry, for the next day's use. It is, indeed, wonderful how these dogs can endure such brutal treatment: but the un- happy creatures seem to be-borninto this world for the express purpose of suffering; they have greatpowers of endurance, and their tenacity to life is almost incredible, as many of them seem to survive these injuries for a long time, and, though appa- rently more than half-killed every dau, live often, as I am told, to a very great age. Some profess not to be able to conceive fhe object. of this strange and inhuman custom, in which our Westerncountrymen delight to indulge; but Hean see that it is clearly enough for the sole purposes of gratifying- their naturally savage dispositions; to appease an insatiable thirst for blood; and to transmit like habits of cruelty to their chil- dren. But I will not dwell on the details of horror which make up the history of Western life - They are too sickening to recall."  Now, do you not perceive some slight difference between these two accounts of the same occurrence Compare the first plain statement of facts with the farrago of nonsense 'which follows, founded, in part (a very small part), on those facts, and you may know all about Uncle Tom's Cabin, with' out offending your nostrils by entering into it.  But, should the prevailing malady attack you,-should you resolve to read the book, as thousands have already done, merely for the temporary excitement of the story, believe me now beforehand, when I tell you that you will be very wrong if you fancy the picture of the Southern slave there exhibit- ed, to be anything-like an approach to the truth. If, how- ever, you are in need of some artificial excitement, and take up the book for that purpose, I promise you that you will  &#xD;<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC8237-00000095"/> 190 fiiid,in iti:pages; something-far morehthrilling than the plot of the igenious fictioh itself,--something far-more horrid and revolting than slavery or its tWorst inidents for there you Willbehold an exhibition hitherto unparalleled in our histo-. ry;,-an, American womnan -plotting and acheming for the de- struCtion of her country! IIt is the first spectacle of the kind with 'which we have been cursed:--God- grantit may be the  last!  , *  *    *   *    *   * l But supposing that emancipation in that, way were prac- ticable, do you' suppose these gabbling Abolitionists' would listen to a proposition to raise a direet tax among the North- erii'States, equal to their just proportion of the actual produc-  tfil due that would be lost to the South by the abolition of slavery? =-Would they not fAther be among the first to de- mar? Thdy will preach Anti-Slavery; they will denounce our Southetn brethren; they will snarl, distort, misrepresent, f falifyvilify; curse; it is their nature. r t    '  " v To bark and blte, To growl and-fight."  Itis their foul, diseased ambition, to make a noise in the world at all haards and at any cost, and' they must make it. For the ,4ject, they will seize upon the readiest and easiest which offers; and for the -conseqwees to others, they care not a whit, except that- the more 'damage they can do, the more com- pletely is their ambition gratified.  , .ht, I -ask again, how much are they ready-to sacrifice in orer to purchase, in dollars and cents from their own pockets, what they pretend to be their sole aim-freedom for the slave I No; they prefer the excitement of robbery to the dull method which the laws prescribe for acquiring what belongs to an. 'other. Is the, sacrifice, then, to be wholly on the side of those :who ownthe slave?who feed, clothe, and protect them I and who, seeing-slavery as it ig, cannot discover any   1* - great erime in it, except as, like every other institution, it may in some few exceptional cases be abused Yes, that's the idea. We of the North-it's none of our business, to be  sure; but, then, we choose to make it sueh-we demand of you, our good countrymen of the South, that you sacrifice nothing. ess than your all, to gratify our professed opinions. of philanthropy,. It is nothing to us that were our respective circumstances and institutions transposed, we should be the last to notice such a demand, coming from you, except with utter contempt and defiance. We care not for that. We insist upon our demand, and in default of its complete sa&amp;is- faction, we will not aease to intrigue till we consummate our purpose-our favorite scheme--a grand, whlesale robbery. You know the alternative offered by the highwayman,- deliver up or die; expect nothing different at our hands. In other words, if you will not freely give up your chief property-your slaves-when We tell you it is wrong to hold slaves, we are determined: to go on till .we drown you and yourfamilies, and your slaves and their families, all together in one vast gulf of gore; which shall inundate your growing cities and villages, and, subsiding, shall disclose- in their stead-to the full satiety of our wishes-a silent chaos of decayed greatness, and a boundless deaert of dead men's bones. Such is the stupendous aim of the anti-slavery fanatics. Nothing less than this is the end which, uncontrolled, they would soon compass' Nay, more than this. In its chief object-a dissolution of the confederacy-is necessarily in- volved the desolation and complete undoing of the whole eoutrry,-North, South, East, and West. Every part-every inch that our enterprise and prosperity has now covered, would, by that act, be ruined beyond redemption and beyond hope. How appalling, then, is the thought that this anti-slavery fanaticism is still rampant among us! (and that it is, we are left no room to doubt). How apparent the duty of every  &#xD;<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC8237-00000096"/> 193 loyal citizen, to proclaim and-combat the monster wherever emayappear, and .beneath how fair -oever -an exterior he may And it- convenient to conceal his fangs 1 The venom is *  tiU in our midst. "We have but scotched the snake, not killed it;" and it is madness to ignore its existence, and to le Supinely on our backs,. crying, "peace, peace," while the enemy is as busy at work as ever, . And ye women of America, in particular-ye who do not vote yourselves, but who implant principles,for life, in the 'breasts of your sons, who wuilt hereafter-Heaven grant you 'ia di;'appreciation of the fearful responsibility that rests Nipon you, as mothers, in this regard;. inspire your souls with {the lfty patriotism of those old Roman matrons, whose rnames will be ever prominent on the most glorious pages of hitory; and, above all, protect you from the guilt, and your country from the danger-be it through willfulness, igno- rance, or thoughtlessness-of rearing up a generation of abollition At-vipers I Ye who have read "Uncle Tom's Cabin," and whose sympathies have been warmly enlisted in behalf of the false heroes and heroines of that romance, look well to It :thatye jdoa not allow the impulsive feelings of your ever- susceptible hearts, which have thus been aroused for fictitious claracters, o toontrol your opinions of facts, which require calm investigation and the exercise of cool, reason. :; Frm  aconteplating the wicked machinations of those who make it their business thus to stir' up strife;" and who, in the name and under the garb of philanthropy (that oft- perverted word I) labor day and night to possess themselves of some of the fires of hell, to destroy the mighty structure which our fathers have devised to s, and against which no merely earthly power or cunning could ever prevail; how cheering and  easantt tthe true-hearted American to be -abte to turn hi bat k on these, and behold, on the other side, the bright contrast of true statesmanship; to see before him ie'n whose unwearying efforts are freely given to allay the   193 fury of sectional rife,both 'North and South; who stand ever ready and able successfully to mediate between the impetuous and unreasonable extremes of ultraists and fanatics; to heal the dangerous wounds of the agitators; to stand be- tween the f'ery combatants, and receive the curses and the blows' of 'both sides-aye, even the desertion and revilings of old friends-in the patriotic endeavor to avert an impending calamity, and restore peace and harmony to the whole country; and who thus sacrifice themselves, moreover, with no earthly hope of reward or gain, otherthan the pproval of their own consciences, looking forward to that future world, where' they will one day meet him who has declared, "Blessed are te peacemakers; for they shall be called the children of God." Such men were HENRY CLAYand DANIEL'WEBSTER, On the principles of conservatism, as illustrated in their lives and speeches, rests our only national security. As living repre- sentatives-and upholders of those principles, we have yet with us a FmLMonr and a DIxKINsoN, an EvnRET'an and CAss8 Let us hope, then, that our country may not continue any longer to verify, as it hasemphatically done for some time past, the old saying that "republics are ungrateful." Of late years we have slighted our eminent and deserving statesmen, in a most pointed and shameful manner; crowding honors and emoluments upon the most corrupt and incapable knaves; and, in more cases than -one, we have dragged some petty politician from his proper obscurity, anl insanely hoisted him, of a sudden, into the chief chair of State, no less to his own surprise than to our disgrace. This ingratitude is a'burning shame to ourselves, and seems to evinee a-spirlt of wanton disregard for the best interests of our country. Some say the people are not to blame for all this, and that these things areill in the hands of intriguing politicians, who, manage and control political events pretty much as they please. But this is false Let  &#xD;<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC8237-00000097"/> 194 the people only/fee and peak, and the iatriguers will tremble, and all their craftiest schemes ome to nought, * . -     *. -           *    'NolIustre, it is true, could have been. added to the names of 1eNBR CLAY and 1DAuL WBTERB, by;our having shown a just appreciation of their gigantio powers, long services, and severely-teatedhonestyg in their elevation to the presidency. On the eontraryi ,a ontiuuation of our present degrading standard of availability in presidential elections, will soon establish eunoi. aaetatqof things that future ages (as in some eases they will have nothingelse to judge by) may reasonably infer the decided. iferiority of. a man -from the simple fact Cth the ba: been onearof our modern presidents; and if he happen to be knon to have been a pure and talented man, they will only:wonder by rhat strange fortuity he appears ia list of suoh insignificant names, and will not accord him any additional honor or fame on that account, but rather the pevew *e . - A, :., ,  - ; Cre we notestablishing such a rule Are we not degrading the offle which was once, and should ever remain, the noblest and highest-political honor upon earth Look at. the sad contrast between .past and-present. Take the early periods of- our republican history and there you find honesty and dignity and greatness uniting in the councils of the nation; - for -suh men as Washington and Jefferson are at the head of affairs at home, while representatives of the Franklin sort maintai;nthe honor and dignity of the country abroad. Then look on this picture (what a jump from that!): Here you see the present Sge4-the age of Clay and Webster, and other great- men-and you behol fearless patriotism and true greatness sinking fast, in public esteem, to utter insignifi- cance, and the, first men in the country rudely thrust into the shade, while the White House is the center of attraction for time-serving demagogues and blood-thirsty spoilsmen, and it is the tool who reigns in Washington; it is their president   195 who sits on the seat-of those great, departed statesmen who were presidents of th United State. it is ao longer, as it ws formerly, an independent man, with an independent exist- enee and 'ann indiidual will, 'but a mere, imbecile, soulless automaton in the hands of rapaious'-harpies. On him they keep the attention of the people fixed, while they keep the machinery of government at a standstill; through a system of discordant and mutually-neutralizing schemes (each sepa- rate self has at least a dozen)-gorging themselves, mean- while,t ith the fat of the land, drawn together out of the hard earnings of the citizens' honest toil. Can we look pach other in the faee withoub shame, when a oomparison is insti- tuted between present times and present magistrates, and the times and the men of the past? .Who doubts the truth of the picture If he has eyes and ears,iet him spend but one week in Washington, and we will hot ask him to believe Us in the matter. Have we not cause for bitter self-reproach, as we thinkof our past duties unperformed, and of those great statesmen who devoted all their lives and all their energies to the ser- vice of our country, and who have now gone,-unthanled, to the grave, whence they will never return to us. Those were duties to our country and to ourseles. They can never be performed now; nor can we repay the dead, whom, living, we slighted, by any tribute to their memory. Our country has suffered through our failure to call worthy men to her most honorable and responsible stations. -But though it is too late to retrieve past errors as regards the persons of the illustrious dead, we can repent of past folly; we can act more wisely and patriotically and gratefully in the future. There are some great men still living among us; men emi- nently qualified for, and deserving of, our highest honors. Shall we continue to trample them underourfeet, in mad eon tests for the spoil8? Shall we discourae the growth of the statesmanship, by establishing it as afziedfact, that none but a  &#xD;<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC8237-00000098"/> 196 third arfourth rate politician can ever hereafter be president of the United tates? The United States must decide. May the spirit of wisdom guide them to that decision, and a due sense of their own dignity and power animate the people in its execution!   I ,   &#xD;</p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>