<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC8337">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Victim Bride, or, A Father's Sacrifice </title>
            <author>Wilmer, Lambert A., (1805?-1863)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC8337</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-2761</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The victim bride, or, A father's sacrifice</title>
                  <author>Wilmer, Lambert A., (1805?-1863)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>96 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Barclay</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1875">[1875]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-09-29">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The victim bride, or, A father's sacrifice</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC8337-00000001"/>    THE MODERN 'ROMAN FATHER."  VICTIM\I BRIDE OR, A FATHER'S SACRIFICE. BEING A TRUE AND TOUCHNG RECITAL OF TH MENTAL, MORAL, AND PHYSICAL SUFFERINGS OF THE BEAUTIFUL AND ACCOMPLISTHED KATE RIGBY, DAUGHTER OF THE PHILADELPHA MILLIONAIRE, PHILADELPHA: BARCLAY &amp; CO., PUBLISHERS, No. 21 NORTH SEVENTH STREET.  &#xD;<pb n="0-19" xml:id="VAC8337-00000002"/> Entered rcoording to Act of Congress, in the year 1875, by BARCLAY     &amp; CO., In the Office of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington, D. C.   THE VICTIM BRIDE; OR THE FATHE'R'S SACRIFICE. CHAPTEt I. O  ERMO   THE DOVE'S NEST, t AND TH  BIBDS"WHCH OCCPIED AIB FREQUENTED IT. On the southern extremity of a somewhat famous city called Philadelphia, there was, about fifteen years ago, a small tavern or " hotel," to which the pro- prieter, Major Flipp, had given the name "Dove's Nest," in allusion, we sup- pose, to the tender, gentle and harmonious character and habits of its occupants Po-se, totetnegnl    n  amnoscarcradhbt       fisoccupants and visitors. Major Flipp himself possessed one dove-like peculiarity which could scarcely be overlooked by the most superficial observer; this was a bright crimson circle around each of his eyes, the brilliant effect of which was much improved or relieved by contrast with the dark purple shades which pre omi- nated in his general complexion. In statue he seems not to have attained that elevation which is called the " majestic;" for when he stood behind his counter, in his most erect military position, only his head and the tips of his shoulders were visible to the spectators on the other side. His want of height appears to have originated in some oversight of nature or her journeyman. In neglecting to provide a sufficiency of material for his legs, which were not only unreason. ably short, but manifestly too slender to support the massive rotundity of the Major's person. Nature or her journeyman, as aforesaid, were the more liable to censure, because she had improvidently wasted or misapplied the stuff which should have eked out the Major's lower extremities to a proper length by employing it in a preposterous elongation of his arms. These were so much out of proportion with his other members, that when he happened to drop the cork-screw or lemon-squeezer on the floor, he could reach down and pick it up without stooping. Mrs. Amanda Flipp, the mate of this fascinating turtle, was a lady of pleasing exterior-with some trifling drawhacks, such for instance as very red hair, eyes of an undistinguishable color, and a face which could be called "heavenly" only on account of its resemblence to the starry firmament-every constellation in the celestial hemisphere being numerically represented by the freckles which studded her countenance. Of this lady's figure no definite account can be given, as she always wore a loose flowing night-gown of printed cotton, which made -the outlines of her person indiscernable. - 1  &#xD;<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC8337-00000003"/> 20           TIE VICTIM   BRIDE; At times this matchless pair lavished on each other such a profusion of caresses and endearments, that thlle' name of their habitation-"Dove's Nest"-seemed singularly appropriate; but anon without ally discoverable -cause, the scene would be changed in a twinkling, and a matrimonial tempest would spring up like one of those tiQpcSl t s wih gie'n premoniti   ofheir approach. So much for the regular ob6upanits Of the "Dove's Nte." "The guests who resorted- to the bar room were, for the most part, gentlemen of such bashful and retiring habits, that they were unwilling to have their occupations and modes of  life exposed to the profngraze of the vulgar. The'precise nature of their pur- suits therefore,-wa seldota alluded to in conversation. Sodne,'indeed, called themselves, - sportsmen," but the particular modes in which they disported them- selves, were not obtruded on the notice of the public-or the police department But as these unostentatious gentlemen, in the quiet seclusion of the "Dove's Nest," were often engaged in the performance of various amusing tricks with packs of Crehore cards-rehearsing the most approved methods of turning Jacks, and practising other manceuvres of the gaming profession-it was easy to con- jecture what kind of " sportsmanship" they most delighted in. Be it observed, however, that no'disinterested spectators were permitted to witness these rehearsals. Major Flipp and his lady, and a tall, ghostly young man who did duty as bar-keeper, were in some measure interested in the proceedings; where- fore they were allowed, under certain restrictions, to look on and admire the sacred and sublime mysteries. It was on the night of January 6th, 1868-and a stormy, cold, sleety, and every way disagreeable night it was-that three gentlemen of the class spoken of above, were regaling themselves with hot punch, in the bar-room of the Dove's Nest, and holding a conversation which will be found faithfully reported in the next chapter. One of the three was a tall man, whose face was almost ntirely concealed by a hairy covering of a Hudibrastic orange-tawney color, *wd consisting of three principal divisions, viz, beard, whiskers and eyebrows. Che beard surrounded the mouth, and made that aperture almost invisible by langing over it like matted sea-Weed over the entrance of a rocky cavern. The whiskers grew like a couple of piny forests, and were scarcely separated by a huge Dony nose, which seemed to be placed for a mural barrier between them. 'The eyebrows were of astounding magnitude and density,arid overhung the fiery eyes as the blackened arches of an iron foundry overhang the furnace. The little that was seen of this gentleman's face, suggested nothing to make you regret that the rest was invisible. The dress worn by him was composed of a coarse material, the color of which was a dark brown; coat, vest and pantaloons being all of the same shade. The person here described will be known in this history as Zadoc Hines. He was one of a fanatical congregation called the M'Cubbimites-a name derived from their founder, Anthony M'Cubbin, an es- scissors-grinder, who, having set up a pulpit in an underground apartment which had been occupied as a bottling vault, promised his disciples everlasting felicity on the easy condition that they should believe as he directed, defray the ex- pensep of the subterranean church establishment, furnish their pastor with a moderate allowance of pocket money, and in all other respects, do just as they pleased. It was a favorite doctrine of this sect, that true believers had full pert   OR, I'THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.           21 mission to practice any kind of rascality; and Mr. Zadoc Hines, aswe shall see hereafter unreservedly availed himself of this license. -The three gentlemen we are describing will figure largely in this narrative, and as it is necessary to make the reader well acquainted with their persons and characters, we hope our mode of introducing them will not be considered' too formal and tedious. 'The second individual in the group was a gentleman of medium stature, his earthly tabernacle being 'not particularly well constructed or otherwise, and his manners and general appearance were very similar to those of a daowdyish cabmnan in his Sunday suit. His dress, indeed, if seen in any situation except on the person -of the wearer, might have been called rather genteel; thougE the colors of the vest were too brilliant by half, and the golden ornaments worn by him were more massive and numerous than most gentlemen of good taste might think necessary. The forehead of this gentleman was such an one as Shakspeare calls "villainously low" yet there was a knowing expression in the twinkle of his eyes, and in a peculiar fashio ;! he had of drawing down the criners of his mouth, which showed that his intellectual gifts were of the very kind which his occasions required. The nawe of this prepossessing indi- vidual was Daniel Pritchard. The peculiar traits of his character will be developed as we proceed. With respect to the third and last- individual of this group, it may be ob. served that although we have capriciously given his two companions precedence in our order of arrangement, he, on many accounts, has primary and especial claims to our notice. He was a well-formed young man of about five-and twenty, with a face that had been unusually handsome, and fine black eyes Which once beamed with intellect 'or flashed with honor; but years of dissipation, and the disappointment of all his early hopes, had dimmed the lustre of those eyes and imparted a mingled expression of sadness and recklessness to his whole countenance. His dress was still neat and tasteful, without any appearance of foppery or ostentation, and there was something in his air and manners which showed that he had not always been accustomed to that kind of society in, which we have now found him. This young man is presented to our readers by the name of James Boyd. They who wish to know more of him, are referred to the conversation in the next chapter. CHAPTER IL CONTAINING AN ILLUSTRATIVE DIALOGUE, WHCH THE ReAM R A IM T PEBK t IF BHE WJSFS TO UNDERSTAND WHAT FOLLDOWS. Mr. Daniel Pritchard had been sitting in a reflective attitude, with his legs on the table, his head thrown back, his eyes fixed on the ceiling, a glass of smoking punch in his right hand, while his left fumbled with his golden watch-guard, the links of which were almost stout enough for a chain cable. 'The result of i      "/"  &#xD;<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC8337-00000004"/> 22 -          THE VICTIM   BRIDE; his meditation was at length vocalized, and took the form of the following r speech, which seemed to be addressed to nobody in particular: "Funds must be had. No solid business can be done without capital; but I hope I may be hanged if I see how it is to be got." The only response to this Sensible observation was a groan from Zadoe Hines, the MCubbinite. Thiegentleman, by the way had groans of various intonations to suit all manner of circumstances. He had groans approbative and groans denunciatory; groans of affirmation aid groans of denial; groans, nm short, to express all the emotions and conditions of his mind. In the present instance, the groan was construed by Mr. Daniel Pritchard as acquiescent an interrogatory, as though Mr. Hines had said- "Sure enough; how is the cash to be obtained?" In reply to the meaning of Mr. Hines as he understood it, Mr. Pritchard remarked--  "That is precisely what puzzles me. The philosophy of the thing is, that we must have more money. If I've the ghost of a half-dime left I hope I may be hanged before Christmas." Here Mr. Hines uttered a groan sympathetic, which might have been called forth by the low state of his friend's finances, or by the striking probability of that fate which Mr. Pritchard had made mention of to strengthen his asseve- ration. Pritchard directed a sidelong glance at Boyd, the young man spoken of at the close of the last chapter, whose countenance now began to show some angry excitement. - "I have fifty dollars left," said he-"the last of the five thousand which has been squandered in -your villainous operations." ' Fifty dollars!" repeated Mr. Pritchard. "Ahl, ha! fifty dollars. Too little for faro-but it may do to start again at loo or poker. The philosophy of the thing is, to suit ourselves to circumstances; but I hope I may be hanged, if it does'nt go against a gentleman's grit to come down from faro to all-fours." While Mr. Hines gave a groan of assent to this proposition, the bar-keeper called Mr. Boyd aside to tell him that a young-lady wished to speak with him at the door. On the damp floor of the little piazza in front of the tavern, a female, clothed much too lightly for that inclement season, was standing in an attitude which seemed to betoken great dejection of spirit, when Boyd opened the door, and, by the light which streamed through the window, recognized his sister, whom he little expected to find there at that moment. -An exclama- tion of surprise was uttered by the-young man, as hle gazed on the shivering girl whose insufficient clothing was saturatedl with the freezing rain, and whose countenance expressed a degree of anguish which her corporeal sufferings, severe as they were, could scarcely be supposed to produce. u Good heavens! Elizabeth?"- Yes, brother, it is I," answered the forlorn young woman; "and you may judge nothing but extreme necessity could have brought me here to--night. Our mother is ill, and wants medecine-food-warmth-every thing." "Impossiblel" answered Boyd; "only two weeks ago, I sent her a hundred dollars." "She never received it," said Elizabeth: "but her chief desire not is to see   -O  R, TH E FATHER'S SACRIRICE. ou.  Before I left h  to-nigFt, I promised that I would endeavour to brng you homewith me.  Will you come?" It Elizabeth," answered the young man, with-much emotion, "I have sworn that I will not enter my mother's house until I have retrieved what I have lost. The prosperous business which m y father left -me, and which he intended or the maintenance of my mother and yourself has been stopped as you know too well; but the worst you do not know. The whole -sum produced by the sale of our stock in trade has been expended in a wild speculation. Until I have atoned for this great fault, and am able to restore to my mother and you the means of living which my folly and wickedness have taken from you, I am an outcast and exile from my family and home. This purse contains all that is Ieft of our patrimony. Take it, and before it is exhausted, perhaps some happy shallge may have taken place. Satn, more," he added, with some heat; "my resolution is formed, and I can bear no contradiction. If I am fortunate, you will see me soon; if otherwise, it will be useless to make any inquiries after me, for I will not be found." Without pausing to utter or hear anoter wordBoyd re-entered the tavern 8 and Elizabeth slowly,and apparently in great anguish of mind, proceeded on her walk homeward. When Boyd again took his seat in the bar-room Mr. Pritchard, having re-filled his glass, and lighted a cigar, began to address him as follows: "Concern ing those fifty dollars, Mr. Boyd; the philolsophy of the thing i that we must lay them out to the best advantage; but I hope I lay be hanger if I see, at present, how we shall use such a pitiful seu ih the genteel line o business to which I havTe teen accustomed. I must think of it." "You need not taax your ingenuity," answered Boyd, contemptuously; "th money is already disposed of." "Eh? disposed of? I hope I may be hanged if I can guess at your meaning. a I have given it away." "Oh, I see!- You gave fifty dollars to the young lady dressed in black, wl tusrt left the piazza and went in that direction." As Pritchard spoke these words emphatically and pointed with his fingi to Indicate the route which Elizabeth had taken, he made a furtive signal to wau of very unprelpossessing appearance, who had entered the tavern a minu Defore. This man answered Pritchard's signal with an inteligent lod al imnecliately left the room.- Mr. Pritchard," said Boyd, quite angrily, "I find that you have be watching my movements. Now I would hav e you ol-kerve, that although I E inet so unreasonable as to expect yott to act like a gentleman, I give you ff warning not to make me the object of your impertinence." "The philosophy of the thing is that we ought not to get angry with- friends for trifles, answered Pditchard. "It was by mere accident that saw your gal t hrough the window, and I hope I may be hanged to-morrow-' "You will be banged soon enough, I dare say," remarked Boyd interrupt] slim; " and by the way, sir, will you please to accountfor the hundred doll I entrusted to your care, about twVo weeks ago, withl directions to hand tuwoley to my mother 1"  &#xD;<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC8337-00000005"/> 24           THE VICTIM   BRIDE; "Hundred dollarsl two weeks agol Oh! I begin to have a glimmering recollection of that small affair. But when the figure is under five hundred, or so, I hope I may be hanged ifI can carry it in my mind for four-and-twenty hours together. "But," said Boyd, "now that this trifling affair is re-called to your re- membrance, will you oblige me by saying at once what you did with the note?" "That is precisely whlat I have been trying to remembler," answered Mr. Pritchard, assuming a thoughtful attitude, with his fore-fillger to the side of him head; "and I think I shall be able to give you very satisfactory information on that subject, by to-morrow morning at about half past nine o'clock." "I will hold you to that promise," said Boyd, with stern emphasis. "In the meantime," said Mr. Pritchard, not much disconcerted by the omit nous words and behaviour of the young man, "I think I have hit on a plan for raising a breeze. I saw a jeweler's shop to-day, witl a small side window open- ing into an alley, about six feet from the ground. That might do." "What might do?" said Boyd impatiently. After taking a sip of punch, and a few whiffs of his cigar, Pritchard quietly remarked: "The shutter has no fastening, except a weak bolt The whole job could bBi done with a small chisel. "You are certainly not proposing a robbery to me," said Boyd very. iF- dignantly. I It is the easiest thing in the world, and no risk at all," said Pritchard; "no- body sleeps on the premises. What do you fear?" At this moment, an explosive sound was heard at the other end of the room, where the bar was situated. Pritchard started to his feet and drew a revolver from his bosom evidently expecting an attack. The M'Cubbinite gave a groan expressive of alarm, and Boyd himself seemed to be a little discomposed. Direct- ing their eyes to the bar, the three gentlemen discovered Major Flipp and his lady, in the act of exchanging conjugal endearments, each having an arm around the other's neck; and it then appeared that the noise which had interrupted the con- versation, and surprised the company, was only the report of a tender salute which the Major had administered to the lips of his lady. "D-n it, Flipp," cried Mr. Pritchard, "I wish you would learn to kiss your wife like a christian and a gentleman. The philosophy of the thing is to perform that sort of operation moderately. I wish I may be hanged if I did'nt think it was the police-marshal and all his squad comning down on us." "I am a practical man," said Major Flipp, in answer to this remonstrance, and I always does these jobs like I was in yearnest." tIrs. Flipp somewhat tartly suggested to Mr. Pritchard, that " nobody but a nasty brute and a  gambling vagabond, would think of find fult with a loving husband, for doing what nobody had a better right to do t hhimself." "Oh, I beg your pardon, Madam," cried Pritchard, " the Major is welcome to do all your kissing; and, after all, I don't wonder that it comes off so confounded hard. I rather think it must go against a fellow's grain to do it in any style." The M'Cubbinite gave a groan of approval to this observation, and Mr. Pritchard took his seat, with his eyes fixed on Boyd, as though he expected   &#xD;<pb n="26 (Illustration) -27" xml:id="VAC8337-00000006"/>   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.             27 that gentlemen to resume the discourse which had been broken off by the Major's noisy salutation. "I have been forced by ill-luck," said Boyd, after. a short pause, " to unite with you in some of your scoundrel-like operations, but it is well to let you un- derstand at once, that you can never persuade me to be a thief." "I had the same kind of notions once," cooly observed Mr. Pritchard; "I thought it rather ungenteel to prig, and hung back for a while, till one of them phrenology fellers examined my head, and told me that prigging was on a of my natural propensities. Then I dived right into it at once, for I thought it was O. K. to go according to natur, and no sort of use to kick against the knobs on my own knowledge box."  Mr. IIines, the M'Cubbintte, began to show a growing interest in this part of the conversation. When mere temporal matters were the subject of discourse, he seldom deigned to give any sign of attention, except one of his expressive groans; but when the topic was one which admitted of some doctrinal applica- tiom, according to the peculiar tenets of the church with which he was as- sociated, hle gladly improved the- opportunity to enlighten the understandings of all present. "Prigging," said he, " is of no account, one way or the other, if you only have faith. Faith is everything; works is nothing. Our preacher himself, the great Anthony M'Cubbin, founder of our church, prigged a whole bolt of red flannel to hang around his pulpit; and he did it, as much as for anything else, to show that he did'nt expert to save himself by following up the ten commandlments, or any of them old-time regulations, which were got up ex- pressly for the Hebrews." "Well," observed Mr. Pritcllard, "that's a kind of creed that I can go. It- loolis reasonlable. I always had a taste for religion, when it did'nt go too much against my grit, and it seems to nle that your belief is the very thing that hits my ideas of what's right. I think I'll join your church, one of these days, when I get thrlough with more important business. But about this jeweller's shop." "No more about that, in my presence," exclaimed Boyd, furiously. "Well, well," said Pritchard, with stoical tranquility, "let that slip. The  philosophy of the thing is, for every fellow to go according to the dictates of his own conscience. There's another dodge I've been thinking of; but some people , hlave sulh quer  notions of right and wrong, that I am almost afraid to mention it." Boyd lorkedl at the tempter with a gloomy and somewhat -anxious counter nance. He thought of his mother and sister, in a state of misery and destitution, and remnembered, with bitter self-reproach, that his misconduct was the cause of their wretchedness. Such reflections prepared him for almost any desperate un- dertaking, and his morbidly excited sensibilities suggested to him that he was bound by the sacred obligations of filial and fraternal duty, to hazard reputation, honor, and life itself, to expiate the great wrong he had done to his helpless relatives. Observing the young man's look of intense expectation, Pritchard went on; '4 There is some risk in this affair, I acknowledge " "I care Dot for the risk," said Boyd, sullenly.  &#xD;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC8337-00000007"/> 28           THE VICTIM   BRIDE; "To cut it short," said Pritchard, taking a sip of punch, "what I'm driving at is matrimrony." Mr. Hines here uttered a very deep groan, expressive of horror or dismay.  "Your samtship does not seem to like this proposition," said Boyd to the M'Cubbinite. "There you hit it," answered Mr. Hines. "This marrying will dowell enough for them who expect to save themselves by works. It's a kind of doing penance, allowing yourselves to be clapper-clawed by a woman, in hopes of saving yourself from the claws of Satan." "Oh, bah!" exclaimed Pritchard, "marriage is not such a bad thing after all. I ought to know, for I've had six wives of my own-four of them still living- and I must say from experience, that wedlock is a pretty fair article, under proper restrictions. Well, Mr. Boyd, the plan is, for one of the present com- pany to marry old Righy's daughter; she's a prime piece of stuff, you know, and her figure is about $50,000. Now, the question is, which of us is to attend F6 , this piece of business? Hines is hardly handsome enough to take her eye, and it seems to me that his very beard would frighten her into hysterics, unless he'd agree to shave off about enough of it to stuff a couple of sofas." Mr. Hines uttered a groan of positive denial. As for myself," proceeded Mr. Pritchard, "that idea might do pretty well, but it so happens that I'm just now paying my addresses to another lady. Be- sides I understand that my Alabama wife-no-I'll be -hanged'if 'tisn't the Louisiana one-threatens to come right on and take possession of me; and she's wicked enough to do it. So the philosophy of the thing is that I: must keep pretty dark for the present. But if it was'nifor these obstacles, I'll be hanged if I would'nt marry the Righy gal myself, for she's deucedly pretty." A laugh which had much more of scorn than merriment in it, was the only answer which Mr, Boyd vouchsafed to this speech. "And so," continued Mr. Pritchard, "the track is open for you, Mr. Boyd, if you think the gal is likely to be captivated with a man of your appearance." "I should certainly abandon every hope of that kind," said Bold," if the fas- cinating Mr. Hines or the irresistable Mr. Pritchard were disposed to come into competition for the prize." "As far as I am concerned," said Mr. Prithhard, magnanimously, "you may make yourself quite easy; and I dare say Hines will give the same promise." Mr. Hines expressed his assent by a groan, with a suitable intonation. "But my strong impression is," remarked Boyd, "that Miss Righy would sooner, be hanged, (to use your favorite phrase, than listen- for a moment to the addresses of such a canting vagabond as Mr. Zadde Hines; such an in- famous black-leg as Mr. Daniel Pritchard; or such a miserable outcast and gambler's dupe as Mr. James Boyd." "Never fear" was the calm response of Mr. Pritchard. "Only have faith, and you may move a mountain," muttered Mr. Hines "Ay, or abig pile of old Righy's dollars," suggested Pritchard. "By the way," he added, "I have some reason to suspect that the girl and you have begun to fancy each other already. I have seen you talking together, in her fither's store--"                     r  '/  --         ,  t  ,              , At ."   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIRICE.            29 "You have been cautioned once before, to-night," said Boyd, with a flashing bye, " not to make me the object of your espionage." At this moment, the sound of crashing glass was heard in the bar, and the voices of several persons in angry altercation, succeeded. Once more the three friends started to their feet; and again the disturbancewas found to proceed from Major Flipp and his accomplished lady. The latter had just broken a bottle of porter on the Major's head, and the provoked husband was paying her off with a shower of cuffs, kicks and execrations. "Ah! ha! Flipp, I see you're at it again," cried Mr. Pritchard, rather en- couragingly. "Yes," answered the Major, foaming at once with rage and the porter, which had been spilled on his interesting visage. "I'll 'let the jade know that I'm a practical man; and cus her bones but I'll break every one of'em to show her that I'm in yearnest."                         . "Oh, it's all very well," cried Mr. Pritchard, quoting the words of Mrs. Flipp-" nobody but a tasty brute would think of finding fault with a loving husband, for doing what no one has a better right to do than himself. I've got my lesson to-night, Mrs. Flipp, and I hope I may be hanged if ever I stick my oar in again betwixt man and wife. D--d clear of it!" The M'Cubbinite gave a groan which seemed to approve of this non-inter- ference policy; but Mr. Boyd, being a young man, and therefore more apt to be governed by impulse than prudence, sprang forward and rescued the lady, before'the Major had quite succeeded in stripping her head of its radient tresses and reducing her face to adead level, which, indeed, was no easy matter, as her nose and chin were almost stupendously prominent. This incident of married life broke up the evening party. Boyd and Hines raired to their chambers, and Mr. Pritchard casting a short Spanish cloak ul )und his shoulders, went abroad to- ascertain the result of an enterprise, which h(ihad planned that evening, and which, with a telegraphic signal, as we have rot iated, had directed one of his agents to execute. The purport and success of Mr. Pritchard's enterprise (which threatened the personal safety of Mis Eliza- hi th Boyd,) will be seen Mi the sequel. '  -         ."            * % CH APTER In. A YOUNG LADY'S ADVENTUIRE. When Elizabeth Boyd left the piazza of the tavern, after attempting in vain to detain her brother in a longer cmonversatioin, with the hope of persuading himn to return to his deserted home, she proceeded U ly along the damp and sleety pavemeht, almost unmindful of the wintry shower that saturated her scanty clothing, and the fierce northern blast which met her on her dreary path, with a force and fury that made it almost impossible for her to advance. The deep distress of mind under which she suffered at that moment, not only made her insensible to the "pelting of the pitiless storm," but suppressed the appre- hensions of personal danger, which the circumstances of her present situatrou  &#xD;<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC8337-00000008"/> 30-          THE VICTIM   BRIDE; might be supposed to suggest. The quarter of the town which she had been compelled to visit, was at that time, a place of infamous notoriety on account of the frequent robberies and other outrages that were committed in the neighbor hood. The street through which she passed on her way homeward, contained but few houses, with long intervals of vacant lots, covered, in many cases, with stagnant water, the icy surface of which, reflecting the dim light which gleamed from the window of some distant hovel, formed a scene that was suff-iciently 'gloomy and cheerless. But the mind of Eli beth was otherwise 'occupied than il the contemplation of the melancholy landscape. She thought of her mother's dangerous illness, the ruined fortunes of her family, and her brother's confirmed habits of dissipation. What need had she, (poor girlD of external circum- stances, to cast a shadow over her meditations?! But, before she had walked a furlong from the tavern, even the engrossing sorows of her youth,began to give place to a sense of immediate peril. Without any conception of the particular danger which threatened her, she began to feel; as we have all felt at times, that instinctive dread, which every mind, having the slightest proclivity to super- stition, may interpret as the signal of some impending misfortune. The most rational observer Dwho had seen how, and by whom she was followed, would have admitted that her apprehensions were not all fantasticali or the mere effects of female timidity. A stout man, whose face, had it not been concealed by the mask of night, would lhve revealed his evil designs, came on with stealthy and noiseless footteps, a few paces behind her. Although no sounds were heard; except the roar of the angry northwester, and the rapid pattering of the rain on e icy pavement, Elizabeth looked back again and again, as if some angelie monitor were directing her alarmed observation to the right quarter. But darkness favored its agent. She saw, indeed, the outlines of a human form, but dhe could distinguish no sign which would enable her to discrimrinate between a persecutor and a protector. She increased her speed, and glaneing back again, made the terrifying discovery that her pursuer had likewise quickened his pace. There was no house near; no plaee of refuge; no mean of escape. The force of the wind which-met her on her path, and the slippery condition of the pavement, which menaced her at every step with a fall, made flight impossible. She proceeded, however,-with as much rapidity as circumstances would allow; and a light which now became visible in a house, some few hundreds of yard ahead, flattered her with the prospect of deliverance. But it was too late. A strong hand grasped the scarf which encircled her neck, and before she could utter a shriek, (which, indeed, would have been unheard or unheeded in that locality,) the tightened ligature suppressed respiration, and produced a fainting fit which enabled her captor to take her up in his arms' and bear hex off Leaving the man road, the ruffian, with the itsensible girl in his armod took a narrow path which diverged to the left, and conducted him, after a short walk, to an old ruinous building constructed of rough grey stone, and to all external appearances, uninhabited. The door' was opened, however, islt obedience to a light tap for admission, and Elizabeth was borne into an apartment illuminated 'by a single tallow candle in a tin sconce affixedd to the wall. This room was 80 rit1Zited in the centre of the building, that it had no windows to admit tIS   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.          3. light of day, or to make the faint radiance of the candle which now lighted it, visible to outside spectators, if .there had been any at that moment. Elizabeth recovered her senses, just as the villain who had brought her thither, had seated hAd on the floor. The apartment in which she now found herself, was almost destitute of furniture; an old pine-table, painted red, and a bench which had' once been blue, were the principle articles which answered the purposes of utility or decoration in this saloon. The walls were neither whitewashed nor ornamented with French paper; but in  lieu of both, a number of inartisticil drawings in charcoal, illustrated the four sides, of the room; which pictoria- enmbellishnents, and the moral sentiments interspersed among them, were alto- - getier worthy of the dingy drawing material which the artist had used in pro- ducing them. The room had no fireplace, nor -any better substitute for such a, convenience, than an earthen furnace, filled with burning charcoal, which gave forth a sufficient quantity of carbonic acid gas, to oppress the breathing ap- paratus of any person not accustomed to such an atmosphere. The door had been opened by an old man with tattered clothing and sinister aspect, who followed his yisitors into the room just described, and addressed an eager inquiry to Elizabeth's abductor- "Eh, Bender, what have you got here?' "Fifty dollars," answered Bender; "and now, my girl, hand out the money quietly or you'll find that the worst is yet to come." Elizabeth promptly, but with much fear and trembling, delivered up the - purse, which she had received that evening from her brother, and then, ad- dressing herself to the ill-looking villain called Bender, earnestly besought him to let her go home.  "Not so fast," said Bender, in reply; "I have to account for you to the boss. You must wait till he comes, and if he chooses to let you slip, why it's all the same to me; that's sartin. Now Ogden, (to the old man,) what have you got' here to drink?" The ancient seneschal of the place began to set out some coarse articles of food, and a blue bottle on the table, when Hlizabet;h interrupted these festive - preparations, by throwing herself on her knees, before her stern custodian, and renewing her entreaties for permission to depart, "My mother is dying," said she, " with Lao attendance For heaven's sake, let me go"  Old Ogden, rubbing his palsied hands, moved around the suppliant, and seemed to contemplate her tears and agonies with immeasurable delight ^Eh a" exclaimed the superannuated sinner, U lovely gal-is'nt she, Ben? Fine subject for the doctors I I sold one of just about her size and weight, for thirty-five dollars, last winter, to the young stujent of--College. I'll buy her from the boss, on speculation."  Without exactly comprehending the import of Ogden's speech, Elizabeth continued to repeat, "Oh, let me go-let me go to my mother." "Old woman sick, eh? cried Ogden, still expressing his satisfaction by rub-  bing his hands convulsively; "well, old women of no account. -What's the use of'em, dead or alive?- Doctora won't buy'a1. Too tough, Hal ha I ha I The laugh of the old reprobate sounded like the rattling of cracked crockeriy ware  &#xD;<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC8337-00000009"/> 32         '  THE VICTIM   BRIDDthJ; "Let's put her away at once, and get quit of the bother," said the younger ruffian who answered to the name of Bender; at'the same time he' opened the door of another apartment which was totally dark, and FRlizabeth in spite of all her entreaties, was thrust into this obscure chamber or closet, and there locked up; the crevices of -the door permitting her to see and hear what was going on in the room where Bender and Ogden still remained. Into this room a third person entered, almost at the very moment in which the door of the closet was locked on Elizabeth. The new-comer, fixing his eyes on Bender, uttered the monosyllable--"Well?" in a tone of interrogation. "All right, Mr. Pritchard," said Bender, pointing at the same time to the door of the'room in which Elizabeth was imprisoned. "Lovely gal!" mumbled old Ogden, with his usual gesture of delight. "Lovely, eh?" asked Pritchard, sharply. "Beautiful! pale and thin, but beautiful. So beautiful!" said the vicious looking old dotard, with a grotesque expression of rapture on his withered countenance.  "Beautiful, is she?" said Pritchard, "so much the worse. Where's the money." Bender handed him Elizabeth's purse. Pritchard poured the contents out on the table, carefully counted the coin, then threw a half-eagle to his faithful adjutant, Bender, and requested hitn'in a bland tone of voice, to "go to the d--l." Bender availed himself of this permission to retire; and Mr. Pritchard, having shut and locked the door after him, seated himself on the blue bench by tha side of old Ogden. "So this girl' is rather handsome, eh?" said Pritchard. !Beautiful-most beautiful," answered Ogden. ' Well, the philosophy of the thing--pshaw! 'I forgot myself. Ogden, I thi Ak pyou and. I, understand each other pretty well,---" '-"He, he, he! I think we do," replied old Ogden; with a laugh half senile aI X half sardonic. The beauty- of this girl is an unludky circumstance. Do you see?" ' Unlucky 1 no-I can't say that I do see that^" said Ogden. Yes, unlucky-d-d unlucky. Boyd fancies her, I guess." i Boyd does? Blamed rascal, I'll stab him," muttered Ogden, maliciously. "Stab himI-no, no; we have use for Boyd. He's a California gold mine, for us, as long as he can keep up the supplies. He can't 'keep fromn the cards, and every- dollar that he fobs, is sure to come this way. Now, I want him to marry a rich young lady, and that speculation is as good' as fifty thousand dollars for us; but here this infernal jade, with her cursed beauty, comes right in the way. Do you understand now?" "I think I do., Want- somebody to cut Boyd out, eh? to take this little girl's eye? Wll1, Ill try. ' When she see 'me spruced up, you know--" "That's not exactly the idea," said Pritchard, inwardly chuckling at Ogden's supernatural puppyism; I merely wantl thisgirl kept out of the' way till Boyd forgets her. She must have at pr'ettystrbng hold on him, I guess, for he gave her all the money he had, this very 'eening.' ' "'llitake care of her. I'll keep her Very close," said Ogden. "She sha'nt h moe daylight, for six months; perhaps longer."           '   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.           38 "3But she'll have to come out at last, you know; and then we'll be blowed,"' suggested Pritchard.  'Ah ha! never fear, I'm  awake,I reckon," said the old man, with, a diabolical leer. "Perhaps confinement might not agree with her; she mayt get sick; such things happen sometimes when people are closely shut up," remarked Mr. Pritchard. I  "Oh, yes, she may get sick, sure enough; and-he, he, be!-she might happen to die, about the time the lectures on 'natomy coimmence. That would be lucky; wouldn't it?" "It would be a windfall for you," observed Mr. Pritchard; but if the doctors should happen to suspect that she did not die according., to nature, or science, they might ask questions, you know that would be rather hard to answer. I hlope I may be hanged if I like that idea, altogether." "BahI! you don't know the doctors as well as I do," said Ogden, impatiently.  They are too glad to get 'natomy subjects, to, ask many foolish questions whT r,. you offer to sell them one. Besides, I was in the Burking line, for two yea -n at New York, and larn'd the trade out and out. We used to pick up drunk aisi loafers about the' streets, pack them away in a little room we had fixed up w purpose; fume 'em pretty well with charcoal, all night, and by next morne'll they were generally ready for dissection, and nobody could tell how thy w;all off. We did a famous business, I tell you, under the firm of Smith, Ogden &amp; Ci o, The stujents always bid five dollars extra for one of our subjects, cos they were always fresh and in prime order. The young medical gents with delicate olfac- tories could stand over them." "There was a pretty strong odor of liquor about them, I suppose," said M1r, Pritchard.                 - "e Well, I reckon there was," answered Ogden; "but the stujents are usedA6t that. Most of 'em steam pretty high themselves." This conversation was carried on, for the most part, in low tones; but Elizabeth, whose anxiety made her a listener, heard enough of the discourse to make her sensible of her perilous situation. At one moment, she thought of appealing to the tender mercies of Mr. Pritclard, and making him acquainted with her relationship to Boyd, as she perceived that the mistake under which Pritchard labored, made her position still more dangerous. But there was something in the countenance of Pritchard, even when it was seen through the chink of a door, and by dim candle-light, which did not not invite her to put much faith in his merciful kindness. Besides, as she saw-him take posses- sion of her money, and was thereby satisfied that he was concerned in the robbery, she was aware that by confessing hlerself to be Boyd's sister, she would', 'urnish Pritchard with a very strong motive for keeping-her in confinement, r practising on her life, in order to prevent the outrage which had been cowr- nitted from coming to the knowledge of heo brother. Amid all the agonies of her terror, one most painful thought, unconnected with her present situation, was constantly predominant in her mind; the thought that her dearly beloved orQther was the companion and confederate of these villains, whose desperate character had that night, been so completely unfolded to her observation, 3          *  &#xD;<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC8337-00000010"/> 34    -       TIIE VICTIM  BRIDE; After a reflective pause, Pritchard again addressed himself to his ancient companion in iniquity. "When you were carrying on that pleasant and profitable business in New York, you found a charcoal fire a very nice and comfortable fixture for the room where you put your lodgers to sleep. Didn't you say so, friend Ogden?" "Yes, I did," answered Ogden. "It made them-he, he, he Hit made them sleep well. They never made any complaint, the next morning, of being  plagued with the nightmare." "There is a good deal of philosophy in charcoal," remarked Mr. Pritchard fixing his eyes admiringly on the glowing furnace which warmed the apartmente "Charcoal is a scientific article, if you know how to use it. In a small roolmn like that (pointing to the closet where Elizabeth was imprisoned,) it works well. By the way, COgden, this is a damp and cold night, and a little fire there might not be amiss." Glances were exchanged between the two friends; the old man nodded ant winked, to signify he understood the suggestion, and laughed in his usual un- pleasant way, to show that there was something in his companion's project that was not disagreeable in itself, but for reasons of his own, he desired a postpone- ment of the measure; mumbled something about " outshining Boyd," and malde some reference to his former triumphs "among the gals;" concluding with tilhe observation that "in taking a gal's eye, he couldn't be beat," when he conde- scended to turn his attention to such an object. Pritchard either did not heed these half aside and somewhat egotistical remarks of old Ogden, or he affected not to hear them, but aimed at a further developement of his own views and wfehes. "The philosophy of the thing is," said he, " that there couldn't be a much easier and nicer way of dropping off; it's the very thing especially for a female. I always hated the idea of being hard on the women folks; and I've put up with more of their nonsense than any man living, I guess-as I happen to have an extra allowance of wives, several of them pretty fractious ones, too; but never having heard of this scientific charcoal experiment, I had to bear up, as well as I could under my troubles, not knowing how to put the poor things to sleep without hurting them; which, of course no man who has the right mwt of feelings would like to do." -Finding that this speech, which was, intended to display his humanity and * chivalric tenderness for the female sex, only produced a chuckle from his auditor, Mr. Pritabsrd became indignant.. D I hope I may } b srged, Ogden," he cried, " if I don't take you for an old brute. Now, what is the use of keeping that poor thing,shut up there for days or weeks, pining away and dying by inches, when half a peck of charcoal would make her a happy angel at once? Curse me if I can guess what sort of a heart you must have!" During this dialogue, Elizabeth, standing at the door of the dark chamber into which she had been thrust for safe keeping, not only heard every word-that was said, but saw, through the crevices of the ill-constructed portal, every sinis- ter and villainous gesture of the speakers. The very fact that they showed no apprehension of being overheard, proved that they did not contemplate the   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.            35 possibility of her appearance as a witness against them-and, this of itself wag enough to assure her that escape or deliverence was out of the question In this extremity, her thoughts were directed chiefly to the helplessand desti- tute condition of her sick mother, who might, at that very moment, bN perishing for want of such attendance as her situation required. Not even the prospect of a speedy and violent death could make her unmindful of a mother's suffer- ings; not the least of which, she well knew, was that terrible anxiety of mind which her daughter's absence must produce. For another hour did this unfortu- nate girl listen to the debate between Ogden and Pritchard, the issue of whic was to determine her own fate; Pritchard urging the necessity of her immediat destruction, and Ogden, for reasons which she could scllrcely comprehend, wishing to delay the sacrifice. In this situation we must lease her for a while, as it is impossible to give the reader a clear account of subsequent events, with- out first presenting him with certain brief explanatory details, which, in the end will be found to comprise a very important part of this narrative. CHA PTER IV. 'WHCH SERVES TO INTRODUCE -MR. JOHN RIGBY AND HS FAIR DAUGH"EK. John Righy, the father of Miss Catharine Righy,- the young lady who has been several times mentioned in the foregoing records, was a native of Lanca- shire, England. His father was a country gentleman of respectable family and some property; but having a large number of children, and his eldest son according to the English law of prinmogeniture, inheriting the bulk of the patri- monial estate, John and some eight or ten of his brothers and sisters, found that they hadl come into the world a little too late to enjoy a reasonable share of its blessings. Finding, therefore, that the old world, or the land of his birth, was not likely to afford him that degree of affluence which he so greatly cov. eted, he, resolved to become a pilgrim to some shrine of Mammon where his ardent devotions would be more liberally rewarded. With this darling object in view he found his way to the congenial atmosphere of Philadelphia. But un- propitious circumstances attended his advent.- On the very day of his arrival, his trunk was rifled, and his whole stock of money, except an insignificant sum which he carried in his pocket, was purloined, without any prospect of recovery. But Righy was a man whom   small discouragements could not overpower. Instead of sitting down to weep over his loss, he betook himself to immediate action; and, not being annoyed by that dread of compromising one's dignity, by means of which the devil contrives to cheat so many persons out of that living which the world owes them, Righy soon found means to -secure the necessaries and some of the comforts of life. He opened a small candy shop in the arcade; prospered, extended his business, and, after a lapse of sixteen years, found himself sole proprietor of a large confectionery store in Chestnut street. A Fear or thereabouts after his first settlement in Philadelphia, Mr. Righy married mnd, in process of time, was blessed with a daughter,- who, at the date with which this narrative commences, had reached her seventeenth year. Sparing  &#xD;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC8337-00000011"/> 36           THE VICTIM BRIDE; our readers any rapturous description of this young lady, wee will merely say, in commdn-place phraseology, that she was t very pretty girl. Be it not un- derstood, however, that her beauty was of a commonplace character. On the contrary, it was such as some romance writers, who are less studious of brevity than we are, would deem it a positive slight to describe in less than six or seven duodecimo pages, or with less than sixty or seventy similes and illustrations. Cramped as we are, and emlbarassed by want of time and space, the only com- parison we can afford is, that Miss Catharine was as sweet as the commodities in which her father dealt; and, indeed, it was the common opi:nion among the iunior male customers, that the confectioner's daughter was the most luscious rticle in his shop. As well he might be, Mr. Righy wlas proud of this daughter. She had been liberally educated, and her natural gifts were of no common order. Though she stood behind a counter and sold candies and sugar-plums, Cath arine had an air that would have become a countess; and, truly, her manners and style of conversation were far superior to those of many ladies who. are said to move in the first circles. But some readers may construe this aLs an equivocal com- pliment. In disposition, Miss Catharillne Righy was rather impulsive; and, like many other young ladies who have been educated at boarding schools, and permittedil afterwards to indulge in an unlimited course of novel-reading, she had sonyt dLc'aste for the dull realities of this world. We are compelled to take notice c t' these minute imperfections of her character; for, without such hints or pres. s  nitions, the reader could scarcely be expected to give full credit to some of th(i43 singular events in Miss Righy's history which we have undertaken to recoril. Many circumstances, which may seem to be mysterious or incomprehensible whe ai related in the biography of a particular person, are well interpreted and clearly understood when the character and habits of that person are r. operly explained , John Eighy was not, in all things, like Shylock the Jew; but, in one or two. particulars, there was a striking resemblance between these two characters. The thoughts of Righy, like those of Shylock, dwelt chiefly on " his ducats and his daughter." On these two objects Mr. Righy's hopes, fears, aspirations and resolves were concentrated. - All other matters were of small account in his estimation. One grand purpose of his life-the acquisition of wealth-was already gained; there was one more ardent desire of his heart to be fulfilled; namely, the advantageous marriage of his daughter. A speedy accomplishment of this-desirable object was now in prospect; for a gentleman. of large fortune, an architect of professional eminence, Charles Cuthbert, by name, had been captivated by the charms of Miss Righy, and had made overtures for a matri- monial alliance. Mr. Righy considered the offer in all respects as an eligible one, and Catharine herself had nothing to object-at least she-could give no good reason for a refusal. The age of Mr. Cuthbert was about five-and-twenty! his person and manners unexceptionable. He had many good and amiable qualities, but no dazzling .ones; and, as " maidens like moths are ever caught by glare," and as Miss Righy, more than any other maiden, was unapt to see anything attractive in a plain, unassuming, good-citizen-like person, no decided impression on her fancy or heart was made by Mr. Charles Cuthbert. However.   OR, THE   FATHER'S SACRIFICE.          37 it was impossible for her not to esteem him highly; and she had yielded to the wishes of her parents and consented to become the wife of this gentleman, when an accidental meeting with Mr. James Boyd, and the revival of an old ac- quaintanceship with that person, disposed her to regard her engagement with Mr. Cuthbert as a fatal error, and a compromise of all her happiness on earth. In the prosperous days of the Boyd family, Elizabeth had been a pupil in the same boarding-school where Catharine had received her education. Here a friendship between the two young ladies began, and their intimacy continued after they both returned home, until the death of Elizabeth's father, and the reckless habits of her brother, reduced the family to such a state of indigence, that, urged by some feeling of pride or false shame, they retired to an obscure quater of the city, and endeavoured to conceal their impoverished condition from the observation of their former acquaintance. Previous to this time, Catharine had occasionally met Elizabeth's brother, (the unfortunate young man whom we introduced to the reader in the first chapter of this record), and the effect of these accidental meetings was some degree of mutual admiration, and, perhaps, a certain species of youthful attachment, which seldom results in any thing very serious. But when the Boyds retired from the observation of their friends, as stated above, Catharine could gain no intelligence of her old schoolmate, and for eighteen months or thereabouts, she and Boyd did not meet, the impressson they had made on each other was almost obliterated. In the meantime Mr. Cuthbert became the accepted suitor of Miss Righy, and the wedding day was a?pointed, when Boyd unexpectedly made his appearance again, made frequent visits to Mr. Righy's store, renewed his acquaintance with Catharine, and although the word love was not mentioned in their conversations, we are not 9 aite certain that the idea which that word represents, was not exemplified in 1( minds of both. In the eyes of a romantically disposed young lady, like Catharine, Mr. Boyd v/s well calculated to ioutshine Mr. Cuthbert. -By no effort of the imagination co)uld she invest the latter with the attributes of a Thaddeus, or a Mortimer, or niyJ other model lover; for poor Cuthbert, though a handsome, well-formed man #A ough, was not the material from which a novel hero could be manufactured. He was, indeed, a mere matter-of-fact person,-a gentlemanly, good-citizen like, commonplace individual, with some austerity in his countenance, but a perfect treasury of good and amiable qualities in his heart. Boyd, on the other hand, possessed many shining qualities; his person was more showy than Cuthbert's and his manners more engaging. He knew how to " talk sentiment" on proper occasions, and he could embellish his discourse with a certain kind of dignified humor, which has a fascinating influence on some appreciative young ladies In short, Mr. Boyd came as near as might be to that standard of perfection which Miss Catharine had set up in her own mind; and she was very unapt to discover those imperfections of his character, which have already been exhibited to the observation ot the reader. i           As Mr. BIighy's establishment was quite famous for the Superior quality of the delicate merchandize, dispensed from its counters, the frequent visits of Mr. Boyd could excite neither 3surprise nor suspicion. There was nothing very  &#xD;<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC8337-00000012"/> 38           T1IE VICTIM  BRIDE; particular in his bellaviour to Miss Righy; and it would have required a sharp observer-even such an one as Mr. Daniel Pritchard-to detect the grand secret, that Boyd and Catharine were not quite indifferent to each other. This grand secret Mr. Daniel Pritchard did detect. He happened to be present in the saloon, one day when Boyd and Catharine were engaged in conversation; and as Mr. Pritchard had no'scruples against listening to dialogues intended to be private, he overheard enough to satisfy him that a good speculation might )e made by marrying Boyd to the rich confectioner's daughter; a project which pr reasons of his owia, he'earnestly desired to see accomplished. CHAPTER V. MISS CATHEARINE RIGBY S ADVENTURE. Mr. James Boyd had not appeared at the confectioner's saloon for the space of two months, and this long absence caused some uneasiness in the minind of Miss Righy. The day appointed for the celebration of her marriage with Mr. Cuth- bert drew near. Since the revival of her acquaintance with Boyd, she had formed a resolution to annul her engagement with Cuthbert; but the wanted the courage to declare this purpose to her parents, for she expected, with good reason, that they would be very much grieved, and incensed perhaps, when made acquainted with her fickleness. Believing that her projected union with Cuthbert would make her wretched for life, and fancying that Boyd was the only man in the world who was calculated to make her happy, she determined, at all hazard, to cancel her marriage contract. But how was that to be done? This was the thought which perplexed and distressed her beyond measure; and her affliction, perhaps, was not the less poignant, because it had its origin in an error of judgment, or a species of infatuation. The world laughs at the suffer "gs which it calls fantastic or imaginary; but such are the sufferings, which drive men to madness and self-destruction. Your unimaginative sufferer is scarcely to be pitied. Catharine revolved in her mind many expedients to extricate herself from the embarrassment of her present situation. At-' last, some motive scarcely defined to her owh, perceptions, prompted her to visit her old friend, Elizabeth Boyd, whose residence she had discovered, after many fruitless inquiries, on the very morning which succeeded-that disastrous night, from which the beginning of this narrative takes its date. The present habitation of the widow Boyd was a third story room of a gloomy old house, in Locust street. - When Catharine entered the wretched apartment, she found the widow alone' and in bed, very ill -indeed with inflammatory rheumatism, but almost insensible to the torments of 'that racking disease; for the anguish of her mind on account of her daughter's mysterious absence, and the probable dangers to which Elizabeth was exposed, had almost deprived her of reason, and entirely overcame the sensations of bodily pain. The frequent fainting fits into which she had fallen during the night, had probably been the means of her preservation from absolute frenzy; but, as it was, lshe was scarcely K                        Iv   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.            .9 able to make Catharine acquainted with the circumstances of Eliz:lbeth' departure from her home on the preceding evening, the place to which she went, ind her long and unaccountable absence. As -soon as Catharine gathered these particulars from the wild and incoherent exclamations of the invalid, she administered all the comfort that was in her power, promising the widow that she would immediately go in search of the losi girl, and never abandon the pursuit until she had obtained some tidings con- erning her. Miss Righy then engaged a poor woman, who resided in the same C ouse, to give Mrs. Boyd the needful attendance, and left a sum of money-all he had with her-to provide for the wants of the sick woman, and without pausing to consider what risks she herself might run in the enterprise, she started on her exploring expedition, directing her course, in the first place, to Major Flipp's hotel, the location of which she had learned, with some difficulty, from her friend's half distracted mother. The generous ardor -exhibited by Catharine, in this instance, was strictly in accordance with her general character; but we will not deny that her partiality for the son and birother, may have caused the service, she was about to render itr the mother and sister, to become somewhat more of a pleasure than a duty. So little was she acquainted with the ways of the world she lived in, that sh did not perceive the- disadvantage of being seen in the infamous neighborhood, through whichashe was obliged to pass on her way to the hotel. It was a localit3 with which she was totally unacquainted; a spot frequented by drunken sailors, women of unenviable reputation, thieves and vagabonds of every description. Sho. -was astonished and bewildered by the objects which presented themselves to hate ,notice; and though of an intrepid disposition, she iras not a little alarmed at the rude familiarity, with which some of the passengers accosted her. Two women, with faces painted in the worst possible taste, stood at the open door of a damp and filthy cellar, over whichi the word "REFECTORY' was chalked in uncouth letters, and as Catharine approached one of them exclaimed to her companion- "Bless me, Sal! silks and satins, eh? What sort of a swell is this?" "She? By jingo, it's an old friend of mine," answered the other; "it's Nance Donnelly; and now I remember she owes me a treat." So saying, the frightful woman stepped forward and seized one of Catharine's arms, while her associate took hold of the other, both claiming her as an old acquaintance. Catharine, believing in her innocent simplicity, that they had mistaken her for some other person, endeavoured to make them sensible of their error; but they persisted in identifying her with the imaginary Nance Donnelly and reminded her of certain contracts for brandy and oysters which, on some ormer occasion, she had bound herself to fulfill. Though Catharine had no ecollection of any such engagements, she would gladly have compromised with the claimants, by furnishing them with an equivalent for the required delicacies in ready money; but it was her misfortune to be penniless, having appropriated her purse and its contents to the relief of Mrs. Boyd, about half an hour before. 'The declaration that she had no money, obtained little credit with her trouble- come companions, who perseveringly kept hold of her arms, and insisted on f 4 treat/' enforcing the dmand with an abundance of coarse and abuove laonguaf e  &#xD;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC8337-00000013"/> 40           THIE VICTIM  BRIDE; At this very juncture, Catharine heard an exclamation of surprise, and, on  looking up, discovered Mr. Cuthbert, who, being a very unimaginative person, as we have hinted before, stood aghast, a perfect effigy of the petrified man, now on exhibition in this city, such was the excess of his astonishment and his total inability to account for the scene which now paresented itself to his notice, For some minutes, Catharine's shame and mortification prevented her from giving the explanation, for which Cuthbert was too much confounded to ask. The two women who had taken possession of Catharine's arms, perceived they had made a mistake of some kind, and were almost as much embarrassed as Miss Righy  4d her lover themselves; and so all four stood, staring at each other for fully two minutes, as if wondering at the strange chances which brought them together. Lest the reader should participate in-their perplexity, we will infbrm him at once, that Mr. Cuthbert had been to view a piece of ground which had been selected as the site of a public building, to- furnish a plan for which hav architectural skill had been called into requisition; and he was returning homeward by the nearest route, when the astounding scene of which we have just been speaking, presented itself to his notice. Cuthbert had never been sus- pected by others, nor did he suspect himself, of any aptitude for being deceived by fantastic illusions; but he had heard of very strange cases, in which persons of good sense imagined that they saw things that were not to be seen, and he now began to flatter himself that he had acquired the same faculty. Of course rt ould not be Miss Righy-his beloved Catharine- who appeared to him m whdi a place and with such associates! Though he was indisposed to believe in w-iths, fairies and demons, who could assume the appearance of respectable BriMan beings, rather than acknowledge to himself that the veritable Catharine *0(1 d blushing before him, he began to conjecture that some elf of particularly id taste, had chosen that young lady's figure for masquerading purposes. -While Mr. Cuthbert's mind was occupied with this rational hypothesis, the Ad strange women began to be apprehellsive that they had made a fauxa pas, vm quietly retired, leaving the young lady anrd gelntlerman, to make such j Il-iries and explanations as circumstances seemed to require. Catharine was b together too innocent to have a full understanding of her own unpleasant 1 mtion in this little affair; but she was. very well aware that the women, who hald just quitted her were not the kind of company, which a respectable young lady would wish to be found in by her admirer and affianced husband. Reco- vering her self-possession, however, she calmly made Mr. Cuthbert acquainted v with the particulars of the case; and the gentleman, without making any reply, offered her his arm with the intention of conducting her homeward. This courtesy Miss Righy declined, and informed him that her court lay in th opposite direction. Very much surprised at this piece of intelligence, Cuthber asked permission to accompany her, and Catharine was about to consent, when the thought struck her that the attendance of Mr. Cuthbert on this expedition, would necessarily make him acquainted with the poverty of the Boyds, and she knew that the pride of the family would shrink from such an exposure. She considered herself under an obligation, therefore, to decline the honor of Mr. Cuthbert's company. But that gentleman very promptly informed her, that his fiudety or her safety would not permit him to leave her alone in such a  &#xD;<pb n="42 (Illustration) -43" xml:id="VAC8337-00000014"/>  alibert bravely eneird t e'u h ongldbttemlasla pnhm  thre hi on h rp-ae4 uthtthmut g tper iejtne2mea etntd)te11bte przgn tf b I n rLare ip u i Qtur-ct 7    OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.             43 neighborhood; and, in short, he insisted on either going with her to hler place of destination or conducting her to her home. Catharine was much perplexed and annoyed by Cuthbert's pertinacity, but, perceiving that it was useless to ex- postulate, she compromised matters by consenting to his escort, and requiring him to ask no questions respecting the object of her mission.     . To these conditions Mr. Cuthbert agreed, and they proceeded together towards the "Dove's Nest," which Miss Righy had some difficulty in finding, as she was wholly unacquainted with the localities, and the directions given her by Mrs. J3oyd were, in consequence of that lady's distracted state of mind, very imperfect. But after some travelling around and about, she discovered the sign which swung in front of Major Flipp's hostelrie, and very joyously pointed the spot out to Mr. Cuthbert as the termination of their journey. "Good heavens! you must be mistaken," exclaimed Cuthbert. The place is a notorious gambling house, and it is impossible that you should have any. thing to do with such an infamous den." This is the place for which I have been in search, however," said Catharinie. "I hope, at least, you will allow me to attend to this important affair, what- ever it is," said Cuthbert, with some excitement. "You willI excuse me, if I remark that it does not become a lady to-enter such a house, and I see no necessity for your doing so." "There s such a necessity, Mr. Cuthbert," answered Catharine; "and the affair is of such a nature that I cannot avail myself of your assistance. Y(u will please to remain on the piazza while I speak to the people within." Cuthbert remonstrated, but found her resolute. He was obliged, therefore to yield this point, and Catharine entered -the bar room. Here she found that amiable couple, Major Flipp and his lady, in one of their happiest moods,  sitting on a bench behind the counter, each with an arm entwined around the other's neck, while the unoccupied hand of each -held a glass of some highly colored liquor. It was a scene of domestic felicity- which deserved to be trans. mitted to canvass; ay, a scene which should have been witnessed 'by Lord Erskine before he composed his celebrated apostrophe to "wedded love." Albeit Miss Righy was in general a great admirer of romantic love scenes, at least of such descriptions of them as she found in her favorite books, we must honestly confess, that she did not seem to appreciate the delicacy and tenderness of the scene now before her. On the contrary, it is probable that, had she been in a jocose mood, which indeed she was not, she might have smiled at the picture of conjugal affection, which now presented itself, in the strongest colors, to her observation. But Catharine was not in a humor to smile at anything o, addressing herself to Major Flipp, she very seriously inquired if a young ady had not visited the premises on the preceding evening. Mrs. Flipp was bout to answer the question, when the Major stopped her mouth with a kiss and then very solemnly protested, that no young lady, except the one who sat by him (meaning Mrs. Flipp, of course,) had been seen within a hundred yards of his residence since the preceding Christmas.                "YDU forget the milk girls" suggested Mrs. Flipp. "Ay, sure enough-I did forget the milk girl,/ conceded the Major, bestowinp another kiss on the lips of his " sweet remembrancer."  &#xD;<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC8337-00000015"/> "          THE VICTIM   BRIDE; "A young lady left home, with the intention of coming here, last night," said Catharine.  "I'm very sorry-that she changed her mind," observed the Major; but, re. ceiving a petulant slap on the cheek from Mrs. :., he added, "not that I care about seeing any other specimen of female beauty than the one which is always by my side, but as I'm a practical man-" "Fiddlestick! don't talk such nonsense!" cried Mrs. Flipp, rather sharply. ' Nonnsense!" echoed Major Flipp, starting up and grasping his lady most un- lovingly by the hair and head dress; "nonsense? Do I talk nonsense, you jade? do I?" Mrs. Flipp promptly answered in the affirmative, and as promptly received a blow on the nose from the glass tumbler, which contained a remnant of th reddish liquor the Major had been drinking, and which had the effect of drawing forth another reddish stream from the- nostrils of Mrs. F. These vivacious demonstrations admonished Catharine to withdraw, which she did very hastily, and rejoined Mr. Cuthbert, who had been, not very patiently, waiting for her in the piazza. Perceiving from the sad expression of her countenance, that she had been disappointed in the object of her visit, Cuthbert renewed the offer of his services, and her anxiety for the safety of her friend Elizabeth overcame the scruples of Catharine, and made her determine to entrust Cuthbert with the secret. As briefly as possible, therefore, she gave him an account of Elizabeth's visit to the tavern in search of her brother, and her failure to return. Cuthbert shook his head dubiously, and seemed to think that the aflfair wore a very serious aspect. He assured Catharine, however, that he would use every po- Bil le effort for the recovery of the missing girl; but, before he commenced his in luiries, he demanded, as a sine qua. non,that Catharine should go home im- mlldiately; and having convinced her, with some trouble, that he could pursue theh search much better without her assistance than with it, he succeeded in peasuading her to enter an omnibus which was passing at that moment, and Oich, taking Chestnut street in its route, could set her down at the very door of her residence.  -CHAPTER VI. MB. CU-'HBERT'S STARTLING ADVENTURE. The natural benevolence of Cuthbert's heart, prompted him to engage in the present undertaking with much alacrity. As soon as he foind himself alone, therefore, after Catharine's departure, he entered the bar roon with the hope of discovering some clue, which might guide him in his future inquiries. By this time the domestic storm had blown over, and Major Flipp, with many endearing expressions, was engaged in applying a large lump of ice to the nape of his lady's neck, an approved method of checking the effiusion of blood at the-nose. The quarrels of this amiable couple, though rather violent while they continued, were always of brief duration, the termination of the dispute being often ad unlooked for and as unaccountable as the beginning. Having now recovered   OR, THE FATIIER'S SACRIFICE.            45 51 the native suavity of his temper, Major Flipp answered Cutlhbert's inquiries with great civility, repeating the same statement, which he had made to Catha- rine a few minutes before, to wit, that no lady except his dear Amanda (mean- ing Mrs. Flipp) had appeared in that bar room for the last four weeks. From this account he could not be induced to deviate by all the promises of reward and threats of punishment, which Cuthbert used with the hope of obtaining the informationl he desired. Finding it useless to seek intelligence in this quarter, Cuthbert left the house, for the purpose of engaging the assistance of the police. Before he had proceeded a hundred yards he was accosted by a young man, whose cadaverous aspect had attracted his notice, in the bar of Flipp's hotel, where this ghostly locking person seemed to be employed as bar-keeper.  "You are looking for a certain lady, I believe, sir," said the pallid young mnan to Mr. Cuthllbert. On receiving an affirmative answer, he proceeded to inform Mr. Cuthbert, in a very sentimental way, that he himself had been in love, and was experi- jV  mentally acquainted with "the pangs of absence, the horrors of uncertainty, the agonies'of sudden separation, and all that sort of thing, "and he added that I te was quite prepared to sympathize with any gentleman," in the same sort of fi. " To all this fine discourse Cuthbert made no answer, and the pale bar-keep'r, finding that his auditor was somewhat -dull of comprehension, began to be m (e explicit. "I've seen the time," said he, " when I've been torn by cruel destiny from t k object of my fondest affection, and I would have given-what would I not ha re given? Any reasonable sum, I'm sure, to any individual who could have helped me out of the hobble." Cuthbert stared at the speaker, but made-no answer. "Yes," continued the bar-keeper, "I have suffered some in thatrway, I tell you I was once in precisely the same predicament that you're in at this moment, hunting up a lovely girl that had promised to be mine, but was kidnapped by heartless barbarians, and I beg you to believe that I'd have done any thing desperate in them circumstances. Yes sir-ee!-dI' have given any gentleman ten dollars for any information concerning her whereabouts." "Oh ho," thought Cuthbert, "I begin to see what this fellow is driving at." -Then addressing the pallid bar-keeper, "Well, sir," said he, "though I am not in love with this young lady for whom I am searching, and though I never saw her, as I think, I will give you ten dollars, if you call tell me where to find her." "Ah me," the ghostly young man proceeded," how often have I been carried way by the gushing sensibilities of my heart! Many a time have my tender motions got me into a peck of trouble! By criclkee!-it would be as much as my life is worth, to have it known that I offered to help you in this lrittle piece of business."  - "It shall not be known," said Cuthbert; "you will not be mentioned in connection with the matter." "Your solemn promise." "Don't waste time, sir; I have promised." "Remember that you have a vow recorded in heaven. Now, sir, plank the Specie, and I am yours."  &#xD;<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC8337-00000016"/> "           THE VICTIM   BRIDE; "And remember," said Cuthbert, "that I know where to find you if you attempt todeceive me. There is your money." "Oh, doubt not mine honor. By the holy poker, it never was tarnished by the breath of calumny," said the bar-keeper, as he deposited the golden eagle in aufaded red morocco wallett. "Now, sir, direct your gaze to that distant solitary edifice. What d'ye think of it?" This seemed to be an appeal to Cuthbert's professional judgment, and he gravely replied that he did not see anything in the style of architecture, which deserved particular notice. In fact he pronounced the " edifice" pointed out to him " a villainous old rip." "In those walls," continued the sentimental bar-keeper, "the angelic being vhom you seek is now enclosed like a fly in a molasses jug"  "Pshaw!" exclaimed Cuthbert, either in allusion to the bar-keeper's compa- rison, or in reference to the unworthy castle in which the beauty he sought was incarcerated. But having now obtained the information he desired, and paid for it, he considered himself under no obligation to treat his new acquaintance, with an excess of courtesy; and so, without pausing to take leave, he posted off towards the building in which Elizabeth was supposed to be immured. It was, indeed, a wretched old fabric, whose sunken roof, fallen chimneys and shutterless windows gave no promise of an inhabitant; and truly it was the general belief in the neighborhood, that the house was occupied only by extra-mundane tenants, or, in'other words, that it was haunted. Report says, that shrieks and cries of distress had been heard, in this place at all - hours of the night, and these stories were so well authenticated that, people, who had a taste for the supernatural found no difficult matter to believe them. As appears to be the case with haunted houses generally, the windows of the building were totally demolished, not one entire pane being discoverable from top to bottom; but whether the ghostly inhabitants, themselves, broke the glass for their own convenience, or whether their human neighbors, having heard that such beings - delight in airy locations, did them this service, is only a matter of conjecture. Thle house waa situated fully a quarter of a mile from the road, (or street, as it wts improperly called,) and about the same distance from any other. dwelling place. The only approach was over a marshy piece of ground, which made the walking both unpleasant and laborious. Greatly mystified with the transactions of the day, and with the appearance of the building before him, Cuthbert reached the door, whichl he was about to open without ceremony, but found it securely fastened., Finding it necessary to knock for admittance, he did this dutywith such earnest emlphasis, as a dun commonly uses to notify the debtor inside that the visit, he is about to receive, is not one of idle ceremony. In the case now referred to, the door was opened as promptly as if the visitor had been expected, and the time -f his arrival calculated to a minute;' and such, indeed, was the case, for the approach of Cuthbert had been seen by the watch, which was generally kept up near the tol of the fortress. If there had been more than one visitor, it is highly probable that admittance would halve been denied; but the inmates of the building being well provided, as they thought, for the reception of a single guest, were disposed to favor hint with their hospitality, but in a way peculiar to themselves. Before the door had ceased to vib)l ate aith Cuthbert's hard knocking, it was - I       I/   47 OR, THE FATIER'S S ACRIFICE.             4 thrown open, and old Ogden, making a profound obeisance, invited the getle man to enter. He did, so, and the door closed after him with a bang that - dislaced some of the plaster from the walls of the gloomy entry, the floor of which was almost covered with the same substance. Mr. Cuthbert made his way through the litter, and entered a room Where several men were seated around a table, on which was placed a decanter, three or four drinking glasses and a. pack of cards. "I am very particularly glad to see you here," said one of the convivial party to Mr. Cuthbert, as soon as the latter entered the room, "Perhaps the gentleman would like to take a hand," said another, catchin up the cards, and giving them a scientific shuffle. Or may be he'd rather drink to our better acquaintance," suggested a thirt- as he shoved a bottle towards the visitor. Cuthbert looked around on the company, and mentally congratulated himself on his good-luck, in getting among as scoundrel-like a gang as ever wore the livery of the State prison. The person who first greeted him was Mr. Pritchard, and the others were some of Mr. P's professional brethern and congenial associates. Cuthbert was a brave man, and was, " thrice arme 4" in the conscious- ness of a just cause, but he felt that his position was somewhat perilous, and he - was aware that although that triple armor, of which Shakspeare speaks, may be a very good thing in its place, there are times when a pair of Colt's revolvers' would be more serviceable. He was too much of the good citizen to carry con- cealed weapons on common occasions, and when he left home that morning, he had no expectation of being placed in circumstances of danger efore night, conset. -u ently be was yet pear g hherafmaleoce     n    J J qu entry he was unprovided with any means of defence, except those which nature hd furniloshed him. True his muscular force was considerable, but scarcely suf- fcient to contend with three or four cut-throat rascals, all of whom were probably arTned to'the best dvantag.  ut cUthbert id not take tie to estimate all posed t danau.       u Cuthbert drvl esvrdi i d noltel. ,;ii hadtnah these difficulties of his situation. He proceeded at once to state what purpose hall brought him thither, demanding that the young woman who was said to be detained in that place against her will, should be surrendered to his chargeg IV hile he was yet speaking, he heard a female voice from an adjoining apart. lent calling on him for assistance. He approached the door of the room, from whence t'he voice seemed to proceed when Pritchard and his confederates i'lter- pesed. Cuthbert bravely pe severed in his efforts to release the prisoner, pushing tie villains aside with a vigorousr, and succeeded i placing is hand on the key of the door which remained in the lock, when four of the ruffians simul- tareotsl tt sprang upon him, and with their united strength threw him on the - fo or. They then canvassed his pockets, took possession of his watch and money, pellnel a trap-door in one corner of the apartment, and, after a hard struggle., succeeded in forcing him downv. Falling eight or ten feet on the hard ground below, Cuthbert was so much bruised that for more than half an hour he ha no ability to rise and nlake any ef ort for the recovery of his freedom. He foul himself lying on the nazed earth, and le judged froem this circumstance that the place, into which he had been- thrown was the cellar of blle1 idn.'h  vFault was totatfly-dasrki, and the' air was damlp and oppressive, as it is in subterraw Xa bean apartments thatt have been shut ull for a long timue. After a short interval  &#xD;<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC8337-00000017"/> O I sA *  '  s                                   "b 48            TIIE VICTIIM  B1RIBE; he felt something moving over his face, and applying his ,hand to the spot, he grasped some- kind of insect, which hle judged to jbe a huge centipede. With a slshudder, he now attempted to rise, anld with some diUfficulty succeeded; then, by feeling the wall of his dungeon all ar loluInd, hle ascertained that he was in a rooln or cell about eight feet square, itvhout any opening in the sides whichh could answer the purpose of a door or wincdow. Perhalp]s in this gloomy an. comafortless situationI, Cuthhbert dlidl not regret tie rmauly allnd beneyolent duty ihe had undertaken to peiolrm, buit it is quite probable ;that he blamed himself severely for his iplllxitilrdene a1ld precipitance- in thrusting himlself into such dalngers alone, and without aLNy )prepar ations for ldefenllce. CHAP-lTER VII. IN WHCH IT IS ATLL  UP HLL ANTI) TDOWN DALE"W+IT  h MR. BOYD-HB BECOMES THE fHAPPIEST OF M)1ANrIND,   AND TH1E MOST MSERABLE IFELLOW IN EXISTAN(CGI, 3ALL IN ONE DAY. For several hours, Catharine anxiously expectel soime intelligence fn iv Cuthbert, wlho haLd llpronised to give I the earliest account of his succetr but, as no tidings hadl arriedl at a late hour in the afternoon, she determined It revisit the dweiling of Mrs. 3Boyrd, with the hope that Elizabeth had return -a While making preparations for l;this visit, Boyd hilmself entered the store, and u he appeared to be in possessionI of his usual tranquility of mind, she coiclud I1 very reasonably, that the mystery of Elizabeth's absence from home had bcf t satisfactorily explained. She wras not aware, of course, that Boyd, for seve ^ I  weeks, had seldolm colmmunicated with his own family. There were severai considerations which restricted her inquiries. She knew that the Boyds-w!r, ashamed of. their indigent circumstances, and she was unwilling to make stny allusion to her visit to Mrs. Boyd that morning. She merely asked, with soma embarrassment, therefore, if Mr. Boyd had seen'his sister. He -answered tfh question affirmatively, supposing that Cathlarine referred to' Elizabeth's visit ol the preceding evening; and he was not a little puzzled, confused and annoyedl by the discovery that she was acquainted with that incident. Perceiving that the subject was an unpleasant one, she pursued her inquiries no farther, and the conversation began to flow in another channel. Boyd was in some respects, not a very severe moralist; but he was not quite a villain. He never intended to deceive Catharine by pretending to be what he vas not; and, having now come to the determination to declare his love, he resolved, in the first, place, to make a full confession of his faults. Indeed he began to suspect that a confession was almost unnecessary, for the question which Catharine had asked in relation to his sister, seemed to signify that she hd already become acquainted with the history of his errors. He had heard qo her appointed marriage, and knew that the day drew very near which was to make her the bride of C(uthbert. In these urgent circumstanees, he deemed it expedient to come to an eclaircdssement at once. He therefore spoke of his youthful indiscretions with many expressions of contrition, which were doubtless   OR, THE FTIE    R-'S SACRIFICE.          49 lincere, and made promises of aimeldment which, perhaps, he intended to fulfll. He made a somewhat obscure reference to his plans for'the future; and, without oming to particulars, hinted at some grand enterprise by means of which he expected to make his fortune. He then said that it had been his-design to postpone the declaration he was about to make, until his condition in life had so tar improved that her parents, perhaps, would be disposed to listen to his proposals; -but, finding she would soon be irretrievably lost to him, a-state of mind, bordering on despair, had driven him prematurely to an avowal of that presumptuous love which, under any other circumstances, he would not have dared to confess. To all this, Catharine answered only with tears, and Boyd, not mleeting with the repulse which he had so much reason to expect, spoke so much to. the purpose that he obtained an acknowledgment whch made him, as he thought, the happicst of mankind. Not to dwell on this scene, the lovers came to'a perfect understanlding, and, after reviewing all-the difficulties of their case, they saw n better means of extrication than a speedy and clandestine marriage. ThY measure, Mr. Boyd argued, would be most likely to reconcile Catharine's parents to the match; for, among sensible people (he remarked) whatever is past remed I ceases to be a matter of regret. And thus, with specious arguments, he persuade d Wee artless girl to agree to a new matrimonial arrangement, which was to gii o Boyd possession of her hand on the day preceding that, which was appointed for the celebration of her nuptials with Cuthbert. The reader will rememN:c that Catharine had been, for some time, prepared for this change, and the effeilt of Boyd's solicitations will be the less surprising. Moreover, if it is desirable tu find excuses for the young lady, let it be considered that her engagement wi(h Cuthbert was one which her parents, rather than herself, had been concerned in making, and that the contract had been formed before she was aware of the ob- stacles which might interfere to prevent its fulfilment. We wish to believe that'Boyd really intended to begin a new course of ife, in accordance with the promise given to Catharine. For some time, he had been the unsuspecting dupe of an association of g-lmblers, and he had lost almost everything before he discovered the vile trickery by which he had been victim- ized. When he made this discovery at last, Pritchard, who was a sly member of the confederacy by which Boyd had been ruined, pretended -to sympathize with his wrongs, and proposed, for a certain "consideration," to give him such instructions in the mysteries of the gamester's craft, as would enable him to foil his despoilers at their own game. The fanatic Hines, who was, an adept in the same gentle craft, also volunteered his tutorship, and a triple copartnership was formed between these worthies, the object of whicih, as Boyd "nderstood it, was to break up that nefarious gang of sharpers by whom so many thoughtless young men, including Mr. Boyd himself, had been plundered. It is scarcely necessary to inform the reader, perhaps, that Pritchard and Hines were still the. faithful adherents of this gang, and that their. compact with Boyd was only a part of that grand scheme, by means of which tlis inexperienced young man was to be made instrumental in carrying out the designs of the confederacy. Greatly exhilarated by the success of his love suit, Boyd now resolved to visit his mother and sister, and to make them partakers of his happiness. He hastened 4   &#xD;<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC8337-00000018"/> - o          THE VICTIM   BRIDE; to their dwelling place, and found his miserable parent in charge of the nurse whom Catharine had provided for them. The poor old lady still made frantic ex- clamations, and struggled with'her attendant, declaring that she must rise and go in search of her daughter. "She risked her life for me," cried the wretched widow; - " for my sake, she went to seek her wicked brother-may a mother's curse rest on him!-and she ! has been murdered! They are murdering her now! I must, I will go and die with her!" Boyd heard this speech. For several minutes, he had stood undiscovered at the head of the bed. He thought his mother was raving, and he ascribed her frenzied expressions to the febrile excitement of her disease. With a strong feeling of self-reproach, however, he came to the side of her bed, and, throwing himself on his knees, acknowledged his unworthy conduct, and begged forgive- aess. The invalid stared at him for a minute in silence; then, seizing his hand with tremulous eagerness, she inquired- a Where is she? Have you found her?" "Compose yourself, mother, or I shall become distracted like yourself," an- swered Boyd. "Whom do you ask for? whom should I find?" "Elizabeth! your sister!" screamed the frantic mother. "Do not dare, vil- laii-do not dare to tell me that you have not seen her!" "Certainly! saw her, last night, when she came with a message from you." "Last nightl have you not seen her to-day? Do you know where she is aw?"   - These questions asked with startling eagerness, began to awaken the appre- hensions of Boyd. "For heaven's sake," he cried," if anything has happened, tell me at once. Where is Elizabeth?" A maniacal laugh was the reply to this question. Then, with a sudden change of manner, the sick woman cried- "Do you come here to ask me where she is? Would my child stay away from me, as you have done, if she were not murdered? When you left me to rtonre her labor supported me. She never deserted me-never left me for a moment-till my necessities forced her to come to you. Your vile conduct brought her to that extremity; you are her murderer; and may the just judgment of God fall on you for all the wrongs you have done to her and me," Having uttered this malediction with fearful energy, the invalid sank back on the couch in a state of exhaustion, and appeared to have no longer any conscious- n^ of his presence. For several minutes, Boyd stood like one who finds himself surrounded by the devastations of an earthquake, astonished by the magnitude of the calamity, which he now began to realize. He knew that nothing less than some serious accident or some dreadful outrage 'could have prevented the return of Elizabeth, and he began to reflect, with a feeling of l spneakable horror, on the perils of the route she had taken. Strange as it may seem, this thought had not occurred to him before. Being a man of indom- itable courage, he was unaccustomed to contemplate danger in any case,'and he had never before considered that a path, which he himself could traverse at l hours with a feeling of perfect security, might be a very unsafe walk for a I' ' '-   *      OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.            51 young and beautiful female. But now, when circumstances compelled him to take cognizance of this fact, his remorse for permitting Elizabeth to leave the tavern alone and unprotected, was too keen for endurance. Hle rushed from hi's mother's room, with some desperate purpose scarcely formed in his own mind, but with a resolution to sacrifice his life, and other lives besides, to avenge his sister's wrongs. Of Pritchard and his other associates he had no suspicion; he knew nothing of Ogden's " trap," but supposed that Elizabeth must have been intercepted on her way, in that infamous locality through which she was obliged to pas, and to which reference has been made several times in this narrative. ^    CHAPTER VIII. THE MARVELLOUS ADVENTURE OF MR. BOYD. To that infamous and disorderly locality mentioned at the close of the last  lapter, Boyd now directed his steps with a very good disposition to extermi- nate all the inhabitants of the. neighborhood. His mind was in a terrible state of excitement, which prompted him to seek danger in every shape; and in a district like this, a man engaged in the pursuit of danger, was most likely to be successful. The stormy conditionl of his mind did not permit hiln to make inquiries with prudence and circumspection, and the best mode of conducting his search for Elizabeth which he could think of at that moment, was by questioning the semi-barbarous residents individually, as he found them lounging about their doors. Many of them, when thus interrogated, answered with some degree of civility, that they had seen no such a person as he described; but the usual questions being addressed to two half intoxicated fellows who stood at the entrance of a grog shop, one of them made a discourteous reply, which Boyd, whose excitability was excessive at that juncture, immediately resented by knocking him down. In a moment, he found himself assailed by half a dozen persons, male and female, the aggrieved friends, associates and allies of the prostrate party; for vagabonds, like swine, show a vast amount of sympathy for the injured or distressed ones of their own species; a redeeming trait of character which we may very well afford to give both sorts of animals credit for, as they are net accustomed to receive a very large share of public approbation. Boyd was the fortunate possessor of a vigorous and muscular frame; he had a taste for athletic exercises, and excelled especially in that particular branch of gymnastics which is called, by way of eminence, " the science"-though he was altogether too much of the gentleman to make much use of it. But, besides  these natural gifts and superadded accomplishments, he had that constitutional peculiarity possessed by some people, which produces an indefinite increasf cf strength and agility under the influence of mental excitement. We mention these circumstances lest the reader should find it difficult to believe what follows, On the occasion now under consideration, Boyd was prepared to enact the most prodigious feats of personal prowess. His masculine assailants were disposed of with a facility, that would have astonished intdifferent spectators almost as much as it did the victims themselves. As for Boyd's female antagonists, be it  &#xD;<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC8337-00000019"/> 52           TITHE VICTIAI BRIDE; recorded to his honor that he did not strike any of them; he merely tossed them as gently ae possible into the neighboring cellarLs, which being for the most part tenanted by chifoniers, were filled with old rags, the yielding nature of which prevented any serious damage from being sustained by the Alnazolns who were pitched among them. Boyd's male opponents fared worse; but as fast as they were overthrown, new recruits supplied their places, and soon the whole district seemed to be aroused, the enraged population turning out in a body to repel tile daring aggressor. Truly Boyd had now occupation enough, and was fain to act strictly on the defensive. He was surrounded by enemies of the most blood-thirsty character, many of them having provided themselves with knives and other weapons, well calculated to bring the contest to a speedy and fatal issue. Indeed, Boyd's life, in popular phrase, was " not worth a copper;" and hle, himself, abandoning all hope of victory, began to think only of " gracing his fall, and making his ruin glorious," by means of a magnificent sacrifice of his foes, whenl a cessation/of hostilties was produced in a manner quite unexpected by all palties. An old woman with blear eyes and haggard aspect, and shaking with palsy, appealed between Boyd and the front ranks of-his enemies, every one of whom seemed to be awe-striclken, in her presence. Indeed, she was well known anil much feared by all the .depraved and turbulent denizens of the neighborhood., who reverenced her as an adept in the occult sciences. She was known only t J the name of Mother Bolten, and was believed to be a Scotch woman, and wit lC some probability, for one of her supernatural qualities was a gift resembling tl M "second sight." Among her ignorant and superstitious neighbours, Moths  Bolten's reputation as a witch and fortune-teller, was well established, and thex ( was no doubt that some of her predictions had been surprisingly verified. Boyd, finding himself assailed by persons armed with murderous weaponu caught up an iron bar from the entrance of a "junk shop," and withl his back against the wall of a house, stood prepared for a desperate defence. His antagonists were pressing forward, however, when Mother Bolten, as just related interposed, and, waving her hand, authoritatively commanded the assailants to fall back. "Let him alone," said she, in the querulous tones of old age; " let the young man alone. If you could see as much as I do, you would pity him- too much to do him any harm. And you (she continued, addressing Boyd,) have done this with foolishness. They whom you hate are safe enough; it is your love -St   that must be dangerous to all who become its objects. Come with me." So saying, she took him by the arm and led him through the angry crowd, ' not ok of whom now offered to molest him. The tottering old woman conducted him to a little hut which appeared to be her dwelling-place, and desiring him to be seated in an old chair, which was just half the furniture that the room contained, she sat down opposite to him, in another chair of the same pattern, and gazed at him for s6me time in silence, and with a sad expression of countenance. "Young man," said she at last, "in what dark hour were you born? You are brave; I saw that to-day. Have you courage, think you, to meet all that 'i before you?"   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.             53 "-My good woman," said Boyd, "you have saved my life. I thank you as much for that, as if you had done me a real service." "I could not bear to see you murdered," answered Mother Bolton, "and yet I feel that it would have been better for others-better for yourself, if I had not prevented it. But what is to be, must come to pass.'       beie ' That is very certain," answered Boyd with a melancholy smile. "I believe you claim the power to foretell future events; I[ have no faith in that, but it is probable that you have means of intelligence, which will enable you to do le a greater kindness than you have done to-day. I have no money to ojfer you, but here is my watch; it is a valuable one and it is yours, if you can tell me wherb to find a young lady who is supposed to have passed through this neighborhood last night, and who has not been heard of since." I see," said the old woman, nodding her head with a paralytic motion- "I see standing by You a lovely girl in the dtress of a bride; and now her white satin robe changeo s to a shroud." "Do not waste time in this way, I beg you," cried Boyd, somewhat angrily. "If you can give me the information I ask for, do it quickly. If you cannot, tell me so at once." Mother Bolton continued to gaze at him, with more an appearance of sorrow than anger. "You do not believe me," said she, after a pause, " and I do not blame you for that, for these are things which you have been taught to despise. And yet youa man, when I tell you that I see a parent's curse resting on your head, perhaps you will not think that I am trifling with your misfortunes. "If you can tell me this much," said Boyd, bitterly. "why can you not tell # B where to find my sister?" A nd so I can, perhaps," answered the old woman, "if you can bring me a i4 Love or handkerchief, or any article that has been hers." "God forgive me!" cried Boyd, impatiently arising from his seat; "God , rgive me for idling away these precious moments, by listening to the ravings t f a maniac. I am indebted to you for the preservation of my life, (he added, # arning to Mother Bolton,) and I will prove my gratitude hereafter. At present "n affair of infinitely more consequence than my life or death occupies my attention. Farewell!" Rushing from the hut, Boyd gazed up and down the street, with momentary irresolution, as if doubtful what route he should take next. He began to reflect that Elizabeth must have been intercepted on her return from the " hotel," and that perhaps some impression of her footsteps might still be found in the moist earth to indicate the path she had taken. He therefore determined to make the "Dove's Nest" a starting point, and, if possible, to trace her progress from thence. The result, for a while, seemed to surpass his most sanguine expecta- tions; the delicate footprints of his lost sister were plainly discernible in the piazza of the tavern, where the half-frozen rain had given the impression some degree of permanency; and, with some trouble, he was able to discern the same foot pints, as they were repeated along the slushy pavement. Animated by hope, Boyd followed the-clue he had so fortunately obtained, but at some con- siderable distance from the tavern, this clue suddenly disappeared. There wal  &#xD;<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC8337-00000020"/> 54           THEE VICTIM   BRIDE; no hlollse near the spot, where the foot-prints ceased to be visible, and after some reflection and comparing of circumstances, Boyd felt quite certain that Eliza- beth must have been lifted from the ground at that particular spot; but the most careful investigation could discover no traces of the direction in which she had been carried. Tlhere were many foot-prints of a larger size, showing that numbers of persons had recently passed over the ground, in various dir rections, aid perhaps if Boyd had possessed the sagacity of the North Ameri- can Indian, he might have made further discoveries; but, as it was, his re- searches were completely baffled. While he paused in great perplexity, anxiety and distress of mind, he saw two men approaching over the marshy fields which as we have already informed the reader, (more than once, perhaps,) extended on each side of the road, and as these men drew nearer, he recognised Messrs. Pritchard and Hines; the latter being recognisable much sooner than the other, on account of the " hairy meteor" which concealed, rather than adorned his countenance. -These two gentlemen were en route from "Ogden's Trap," and were deeply engage in conversation on the subject of Mr. Cuthbert's late capture and citar- ceration, which Mr. Pritchard seemed to regard as the most lucky event of his life, except the decease-of one of the five Mrs. Pritchards, at the very time she was about to prosecute him for bigamy. {Don't talk, of luck," said Hines "Whatever comes to pass is so ordered, and you'll fithat everything prospers with us when we have faith." Acquiesdmgin this comfortable doctrine, Mr. Pritchard proceeded to inform his bearded and sanctimonious associate, that Cuthbert was Boyd's rival-the accepted suitor and betrothed husband of the "Righy gal." t I heard this morning," proceeded Mr. P., that the wedding was to have come off within a week, and then we should have been nicely choused out of the fifty thousand; but we are not going to be swindled in that way, if we can help it, of oourse. Boyd must have the gal, and-fire and faggots!-what brought him here?" This exclamation was caused by Mr. Pritchard's discovery of Boyd standing in the road, where we left him a minute ago. To say the truth, Boyd's appear- ance on that- particular spot produced much uneasiness in Pritchard's mind, causing him to approach the young man with some hesitation. "Everything goes on swimmingly," said he after a somewhat ceremonious salutation, " it's all right side up, Mr. Boyd. By the way, 1 have your hundred dollars here; the cash comes just in good time for your outfit, and sparking is a business that requires capital. I forgot to leave the money with the old lady, as you requested, and perhaps, as matters have turned out, it is better that I dal' forget. I hope you found the gallin a pleasant humor this morning." "Don't speak of that now," answered Boyd, gloomily. "My sister-the young lady who came to me last night-is not to be found." Ehl I what is that? your sister " cried Pritchard, thrown entirely off his guard. U Yes, my sister," replied Boyd. "I have traced her to this spot, but from this point I cannot discover whither she went, or was carried." u Hertes a mews," ejaculated Mr. Pritchard, half aloud. "I hope I m*S bn * ' .   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.             55 hanltred if I had any suspicion that the gal was your sister, Mr. Boyd. Why did you not say so?" "What did it concern you to know about the matter?" said'Boyd, ferociously. "Only this much," answered Pritchard, "If I had known that the galwa&amp; your sister, I should have offered my services to see her safe home."  You!" cried Boyd, stamping with rage. "If I were to catch a sister of mine walking with such a blackguard -"- "Well, well, Mr. Boyd," answered Pritchard, coolly, " there's no harm done- -at least not by me. I'm not ambitious to wallk with the sister of any man ' particular. Did'nt you say that you traced her this far, Mr. Boyd?" "Yes; here are her foot-steps, and here they cease to appear. This is what puzzles me," answered Boyd. Pritchard and Hines exchanged glances, unseen by Boyd, who was too much occupied with his own reflections, to observe them. "The philosophy of the thing is-that you must be mistaken," remarked Mfr. Pritchard; " unless she was carried off by an eagle, an angel or some other w i  fowl, her foot-prints couldn't stop off just here, that's very certain. The trulh is, I think she must have gone by the other road." "I have no doubt that she went this way," replied Boyd, who suspected not in the least, however, what reason Mr. Pritchard had for putting him on another track. In fact, Mr. Pritchard's position with respect to Boyd and his sister, hbvlV become extremely embarrassing. Although, since he had discovered her rela- tionlship to Boyd, his original motive for detaining her in custody, no longei existed; yet, knowing that the detection of ]ais conduct towards lizabeth, would cause a hopeless rupture between Boyd and himself, and expose him to many other risks and liabilities, he was more indisposed than ever to be merciful i to his fair prisoner. But, as her brother was now in sight of her place of im- prisonment, Pritchard feared that by some accident Boyd's attention might be directed to the right quarter; and his first object was to withdraw the young -rman from the neighborhood. This, with some trouble and delay, he succeeded in doing, promising that he and Hines would assist in the search; and con- vincing Boyd, by means of much sound reasoning, that no good purpose could be answered by remaining on that particular slpot. By this time, the short winter's afternoon was nearly expended. What a day crowned with events, had just passed over! At noon, Boyd's prospects appeared to be as bright as the meridian sun itself; but now, when the shadows of evening gathered over the sky, the reflections of this ill-starred young man were all dark and comfortless. He could think of nothing then but the agonies of his mother, and the dangers to which his sister was exposed. He charged himself with all the calamities of his family, and meditated an act of expiation; for some fiend, "taking advantage of his weakness and melancholy, to abuse and damn him," suggested that nothing less than the sacrifice of his life could be a sufficient atonement for his misdeeds. When he was about to retire to the room which he occupied as a sleeping apartmeat, in Flipp's tavern, he obtained the loan of a pistol from Mr. Pritchard; and though the wildness of his be- haviour might have admonished Pritchard that some mischief wars intended, Mr P. nWas too anxious to accommodate a friend, to make ony difficulty about  &#xD;<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC8337-00000021"/> 56            TIE VICTIM   BRIDE; -   lending such a small matter as a pistol. It has been remarked, too, as an instance of Mr. Pritchard's virtuous serenity of temper, that when the report of fire-arms was heard about twelve o'clock that night, and the pale bar-keeper, even paler than usual, rushed into Mr. Pritchard's apartment, with the intelli- gence that Boyd had shot himself, Mr. Pritchard answered without the least discomposure, that there was "no great halrm done;" and immediately sank again int a tranquil slumber, proving thereby, either that he was a better man than Macheth, or that his conscience was less delicately excitable than that of the Scottish regicide ',            * '     -  CHAPTER IX.  THE LATEST INTELLIGENCE FROM iOGDEN's TRAP L We think it somewhat probable that if our reader is truly a benevolent one, he will be desirous of some intelligence from "Ogden's Trap." This was the name which Mr. Pritchard and his confederates used to distinguish the old #tone building, where we have been obliged to leave Miss Boyd and Mr. Cuth- bert, in circumstances of some difficulty and danger. On the night of her capture, Elizabeth, as we haverelated, listened to a long debate between Prit- cinrd and Ogden, touching the expediency of trying a certain philosophical und physiological experiment with charcoal; an experiment which Ogden, for vsons which will soon be perceptible, wished to postpone indefinitely. When PGilitchard found that the old man was immovable in his resolution, he left the hS ase, a little incensed at the senior's obstinacy. As soon as he was gone, Ogden, hit ing improved his personal appearance, as he thought, by some change of ap- po rel, opened the door of the prison room, and invited Elizabeth to partake of his slipper, which consisted of bread, cheese and whiskey. .Elizabeth was in too D ich trouble to be tempted to eat, even by such luxurious diet as Mr. Ogden o')ered her, and the old fellow began to address her on another subject. He I 'd her, (what indeed it was unnecessary for him to tell as she had -heard it all,) t) It he had been almost in a quarrel with the bo8ss, about sparing her life, and t, at he was very much afraid that the boss would have his own way at last. There was only one plan, (Mr. Ogden said,) that would be likely to save her- "a very nice plan indeed," and he wondered he did not think of it sooner. This plan was for Elizabeth to become Mrs. Ogden. "Then," said the amorous 1^   old gentleman, "you will be one of us, and we'll not be afraid to trust you. ji  That's a bright idea, is'nt it?" he concluded with his customary laugh. We hope our young female readers will not be incredulous, when we tell them'. that Elizabeth actually shuddered at an offer of marriage, which, as we must freely admit, young ladies are very unapt to do on similar occasions. However improbable the story may be, we are obliged to say that Miss Boyd did not avail herself of this opportunity to improve her condition, although her siitoi endeavoured to impress her with a due sense of her good fortune in receiving such an offer, by telling her he might have had his pick out of a thousand of ^ the nicest gals in Philadelphia; and that some of them, (availing themselves                                          &#xD;<pb n="58 (Illustration) -59" xml:id="VAC8337-00000022"/>   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.             59 of leap-year we suppose,) had even gone so far, as to solicit the honor of his al- liance. As a farther inducement, he represented to her that he was 'doing a first-rate business," and had a very snug establishment there, as she might see for herself He wound up with a   very strong argument, viz: that she must either L " d, Dne thing or another;" meaning perhaps, that her only alternatives were matrimony and suffocation.  Having thus," popped the question," in his own peculiar way, Mr. Ogden advised her to " chaw it over" till the next morning, and, in the meanwhile, furnished henr with -straw mattress, some old rags and a blanket, and then left her to her meditations or slumber. But, Elizabeth, being an enterprising grl, and'the urgency of the moment having called all the energies of her character into requisition, hoped to employ her time better than in dreams of matrimonial bliss, with such a partner as Mr. Ogden, or in waking meditations opn the same subject. In short, she determined to make her escape if possible. Xt was very easy to come to such a resolution, but to carry it out in practice, was proved by actual experiment, to be a more difficult undertaking than she had looked for. The house seemed to have been fitted up expressly forthe purposes to which it was applied. The room in which Elizabeth was imprisoned, had no windows, and no door, except the one which had given her entrance, and which was se- cured by a large and strong lock. Fortunately, perhaps, for the dignity of our narrative, there was no chimney to the apartment; for had there been an opln- ing of that kind, and Miss Boyd had made her escape through the flue, we should have been censured by the critics, for introducing an incident unprecedented in tale or history; for among all the young ladies who have been unjustly detained in captivity, in ancient or modern times, not one is reported to have escaped min this mianner, though many have attempted to liberate themselves by means far more desperate, dangerous and improbable. That side of the room in which the door was placed, was a stout partition of rough boards. The other walls were all of solid masonry, and of course pre eluded all possibility of egress, except for such an ingenious prison-breaker as Mr. Stephen Burroughs, or the renowned Baron Trenck. FlimAbeth's whole attention was directed to the board partition, and when Ogden appeared to have finished his supper and betaken himself to repose, she tried each board in suc- cession, with a faint hope that one of them might be loose enough to be pushed aside, in order to afford a way for her retreat. But alas; the carpenter had done his work better than modern carpenters generally do when they work for honest people. Every board was put on to stay there, and after repeated trials she sank despairingly on her wretched couch, the conflicting emotions of hex mind producing a sort of lethargy, in which she remained until a late hour in tle morning. Mr. Ogden was up at the first peep of daylight, in order to make preparations for his nuptials, which he considered as certain to " come off" as the rising of the sun, or any other event that takes place in the ordinary course of nature, and he resolved to have the affair settled with the utmost expedition. The only regular member of his household was a boy, whose ordinary duty was to keep watch from the garret windows, and to go with messages as occasion might require. This lad was now despatched with a summons for Mr. Hines ana hi  &#xD;<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC8337-00000023"/> th          THE VICTIM1 BRIDE; reverend pastor, Anthony M'Cubbin, whom Mr. Ogden had selected for many good reasons to perform the wedding ceremony; but the best reason of all for this selection, was that the Rev. Anthony MCubbin was willing, on such occa- dions, to dispense with certain legal formalities, which in the present instance would have been troublesome if. not impossible. In less than an hour, Mr. Hines 'and the pastor arrived. The latter was a stout, broad shouldered gentleman, whose round gleaming face was garnished with a beard even more preposterous than that of Mr. Hines himself. By the way, beards were a part of the uniform of the M'Cubbin congregation; and as 'their sect recognized " woman's rights," in all their length and breadth, the female devotees as well as the maleswere permitted to cultivate this facial orna- ment, and some of them bad succeeded in raising a crop, which entitled then;' by the rules of the church, to officiate as deacons or deliver exhortations, wheL the pastor himself was indisposed, or too drunk (as sometimew happened,) to attend to that duty. When it was made known to the reverend Anthony, for what purpose his services were required, he supposed at first that his disciple Hines was to be the bridegroom, and expressed a hope that he had selected a suitable spouse from among the faithful of his own sect. ji "For as it is a part of my duty," said he, "to comfort the wives of my con- gregation, and as it is impossible to comfort any woman who has not faith enough to be- comforted, I don't want to see any outsider married to one of my flock." Mr. Hines hastened to explain that the parties about to be united were both outsiders, and that the bridegroom was Mr. Ogden; but here a new difficulty wrose, for the reverend gentleman had scruples of conscience, in relation to X uniting of two of the unconverted, as the tendency of such an union would it) to increase the army of Satan, and thereby to give permanency to the devil's kingdom on earth, which it was the duty of all good M'Cubbinites to beat down. obstacle to the proposed wedding was so formidable, that the bridegroom cpectant began to look very blank, till at the whispered suggestion of Hines i3 slipped a gold piece into the hand of the conscientious minister, and then lie aspect of affairs was somewhat changed, for the reverend Anthony sud- denly exclaimed; "However, I'll risk it this time!" Aid seeing a decanter and drinking glasses on the table, he helped himself to a " stiff horn," as he called it, of Ogden's whiskey and then notified the com- k pany that if there were anything to be done, they must " drive ahead" with it, as he had " other fish to fry," and he would " see them all scrimmaged," (such was his precise phraseology,) before he would spend half an hour on such a picayune job as the present. Thus urged to be brisk in his preparations, Ogden unlocked the door of Elizabeth's cell The noise aroused her from that lethargic condition into which her grief and terrors had thrown her, and when requested by Ogden to come. forth, she- obeyed without any anticipation of the scene in which she was expected to play a conspicuous part. From the appearance of the apartment, and of the company there assembled, it would iudleed have been hard to conjeeture that a wedding was on the tapis. Imagine   OR, TEE FATIIER'S SACRIFICE.            61 a long dark room with rough walls, well embrowned with smoke, and a floor on which the dust and dirt had accumulated, until the boards were no longer visible. Inmagine three men of uncouth appearance, two with beards of .a size and cut seldom seen in any christianized country, and the third an impish figure, in size too small for a man, but with all the indications of extreme old age, and judge if such a convocation and such a place could suggest the idea of a nuptial celebration to Elizabeth Boyd. It is true that Ogden had not been altogether remiss in his preparations, for at that very moment the room was filled with the odors of the wedding banquet; a huge frying-pan filled with bacon and eggs was hissing and fuming onl the earthen furnace, which was the only cooking and warming apparatus us sed in Mr. Ogden's establishmllent.  It seems that Mr. Ogden had put too much faith in the old saying, "Silence gives consent." When he broached the subject of minatrimony to Elizabeth, on- the preceding evening, she made no reply, because, to say the truth, her mind was so completely occupied with the troubles and perils of her situation, that the old man's discourse was altogethler unheeded. Fer silence was construed by Ogden as a promise of acquiescence; and, as the al renatives offered to the poor girl were matrimony or death, hle doubted not inL tler least that she would choome the former.  Great was Mr. Ogden's rage and disappointment, therefore, when Elizabe(th, being with some difficulty made to understand why she had been summoned to that presence, peremptorily and even indignantly refused to be disposed of i) this summary manner. The foiled bridegroom, with furious gesticulationI, bade her consider herself."just as good as dead and buried,?' and Mr. Hini advised her to provide for her soul's welfare, by embracing the M'Cubbinite faith without a moment's delay. Elizabeth, understanding from some of the discourse, that the Reverend-Anthony was a clergyman, earnestly besought him to deliver her from the villainous hands into which she had fallen, but the reverend gentleman's attention was engaged at that moment with another matter; for Mr. Ogden, finding that the wedding was not likely to " come off,'" was in- sisting on having the nuptial fee returned, inasmuch as the sacred functionary had not earned the money. Mr. M'Cubbin refused to deliver the piece of gold, on the ground that he had lost his time in " fiddling around and fooling about,"  when a certain elect lady, one of the "biggest bugs" in his congregation, was expecting him, in order to make a complaint against her husband for some dere liction of duty. The dispute was referred to Mr,! Hines, who as in duty bound, decided that his pastor was perfectly justified in refusing to make restitution. Whereupon the Reverend Anthony M'Cubbin buttoned up his great coat, - odded very superciliously to Mr. Ogden, and then left the premises, followed by Vis faithful proselyte, Mr. Hines.  Ogden now ordered Elizabeth to return to her cell; and she, perceiving that it would be useless to expostulate or resist, obeyed with a well-grounded as- surance that she would never. come out alive. Soon after, Mr. Pritchard and several other " marvellously ill-favored gentlemen" came in and formed a social party, which had begun to be deeply engaged in " .loo," when they were notified by the boy who kept watch above, that a stranger approa-ched. Mr. Pritchard crept up to the garret window to reconnoitre and recognized in the new-comer,  &#xD;<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC8337-00000024"/> 62           THE VICTIM   BRIDE; our friend Cuthbert, with whose person he was very well acquainted, although it was the misfortune of ,Mr. Cuthbert to know nothing of him. For several reasons which will appear hereafter, the approach of Cuthbert was very satisfactory to Mr. Pritchard, although the purpose for which Mr. C. came could scarcely be guessed at by the sporting gentleman. We have seen that Cuthbert received a cordial welcome from Mr. Pritchard and his friends. Eliza- beth whose anxiety still made her a listener at her prison door, heard with delight inexpressible, the inquiries of Cuthbert, and- flattered herself that deliverance was at hand. But as Cuthbert was wholly unknown to her, she began to fear that she was not the person he sought for; yet as Lis respectable Appearance gave her some assurance that he would be willing to assist her, she endeavoured to make her case known to him by calling for help, as we have related in a preceding chapter. Then followed the struggle in which Cuthbert was overpowered, but the result of that struggle was unknown to Elizabeth, as ter conflicting emotions caused her to relapse into that unconscious state from which Ogden had aroused her a few hours before. When she recovered from her swoon she knew it was night, for the rays of tile lighted candle in thetadjoining apartment streamed through the chinks of the -loor. She also observed a dull ruddy light at the farthest extremity of the cell and perceived that the confined air of her prison was alreacdy loaded with a suffocating vapor. She then remembered the former conversation between Ogden and Pritchard, which she had overheard, and she knew that her doom was. about to be consummated. Already had the deleterious gas begun to do its work. On attempting to rise,.a dizzy sensation in the head and a feeling of languor and weakness compelled her to sink powerless on her hard couch. * She could hear persons in the next room, and remembered the voices of Ogden and Bender. The former was directing the latter to "make haste and dig the grave in the back cellar." "Dig it deep," said the old villain, "and dig it quick. She must be covered over before morning. There's no chance to sell the body just now, and it must not be kept in the house, for that makes all the danger of being pulled for It. Why don't you set to work?"  Bender who appeared to be a little intoxicated objected that such jobs were not in his bargain. He " didn't think they were going to kill the girl, or he wouldn't have had a hand in the matter." But he sulkily added, after a short pause-"Howsomever as you've done it, I s'pose it won't make the thing any worse to bury her." And with this remark, worthy of the philosc(phical Pritchard himself, he left the room, in order to execute the task which Ogden required. CHAPTER X. THE COURSE OF TRUE- LOVE IS SOMEWHAT ROUGH WITH MSS CATHARINE RIGBY After her last interview with Boyd, Catharine's mind was very painfully exercised for many hours. Her conscience accused her of an omission of duty toher parents, and of a great wrong done to Cuthbert; and in spite of all her prepossessions in favor of Boyd the conviction forced itself sn her mind, that   EC OB  E, TH F A'h' I'ER' SACRIFICE . her engagement with him was p recipitate and imprudent, an d uld in all lik- lihood, prove disastrous. She had no reason to expect that her parents w ould ever consent to her marriage with Boyd, whose poverty alone w ould be anion insuperable objection with them. Besides, the thought of a clandestine union ,ith a man whose character was unquestionaby liable to some objectionswa s etremely repugnant to her sense of honor and propriety; and even he r delicacy extremely repugnant t he,91.ity,^ with which she had was shocked when she came to reflect on the apparent facility with which she had broken her engagement with Mr Cuthbert, and given Boyd the promise of her band. A rlecollectionof the uniform kindness and indulgence of her parents thand., A recollection of the umiform ad sJ  n  eeelned now to rise in judgment against the course she had marked out, and an unaccountable foreboding of some impending caamity-t jut penalty of he Z 1 ,.U Cndtl andaitls conducit--veighed heavily on her soul. Aftermuche iUndutiful and fithles ditwI           relieve^ r  her mind and Harassing reflection, she came to a final determination to relieve her mind and conscience by a full confession to lher mother. Mrs. ighy heard the acknowledgment of her daughter's misplaced affections with unspeakable sorrow ; she attempted to reason and remonstrate with the infatuated girl, but it was all in she atteimpted to reason anid remo "   ^   ^  ol  o   the vain. Catharine freely acknowledged Cuthberts merits, and could not deny the defects of Boyd's character when they were pointed out by her mother, but was unwaverirg in her resolution to abide by the promise she had given to the latter. unwavering in. her rsolution to                  hedrb h po^^  Mrs. Righy then informed her that her duty as aife and mother required her to make Mr. Righy acquainted with these facts. To this Catharine acceded, tomerely requesting that the matter might be presented to her father in as gentle termsas possible. This Drs. Righy promised and immediately went to make the astounding disclosure to her husband.  And sure enough, it was an astounding disclosure to Mr. Righy. For some time he was incredulous, but when assured of twee factsh to mhalfe hour in gloomy and silent cogitation. He loved his daughter t oo w ell to make her miserable, and the declaration of Catharine to her mother that the proposed alliance with Guthbert would be a sacrifice of all her earthly happiness, brought ;  aiI 'e with Cuthbert would be a sacrifieol severe pang to I he breast of this affectionate father. He considered himself a, severe pang to ^I h rat ofthis^          anfd having long bound in honor and conscience to adhereto the contract; and having long indulged in the nattering dream that, in all respects, the projected union would indulged in the flattering dre h^     ^   .         n be avantgeous for his child, the present disappointment as almost in be advantageous supportable. But when he came to reflect on the circumstance of his daughter having fixed her affections on Boyd, his grief was changed to indignation, for he knee too much of that young oan's improvident conduct and questionable habits to think of him as a son-in-law, with anv degree of patiece fi    In great perturbation of mind, Mr. Rigy descended to the spitoreits ere at   Catharine sat in an attitude which betokened the deep dejection of her sts. For some minutes he traversed- the roomin slence, but with evident agitation,  as if struggling with his emotions, and endeavouring to acquire a degree of composure before he began to address his daughter on the subject which Is   occupied his thoug:hts Atlength he approached her, and taking herhand in A  his, said in tremulous accents:-      h oA My cchild, what is this I hear? Can it be possible that your mother ha not XI   mistaken you? I cannot believe you ar so greatly in fault till I have two eoltfrssioa from your own lips."  &#xD;<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC8337-00000025"/> "i           THE VICTIM   BRIDE; 'lThe head of Cathalmne sank on her father's arm, as she sobbed out a full eonfirmation of the distressing truth. There was silence for a space, while Righy made a strong effort to preserve his firmness of manner and serenity of temlper. "Antd do you know," said he at last, " do you know this man Boyd! iHave you not heard that he is a paiupelr, a spelndthhrift, a gamllester,a and aL villain?" ( I know," answeredtl Gatrine, " thalt lie i's poor, that lie hlas been imprudent, that lie lias been betlayedl by alse frielndls, ayd ruinei by tlell at the gaming table, and I lknow, likew\Nise, thllt lie is--not a villaill P" "W\lhat better lproof 'would you hav.\,e of his villliny," said Righy, with ompressed lips and a flashin'g eye, "than -Ilis condluct towards your parents, your betrothed hlusbaldll, alld yoursself? HaHs he nlot gained your affiections by stealth, without giving us the leasct hint of his designl ? Did hle not know that you were elgragedl to another, anld didl hle not unscrupulously persuade you to violate that sacred obligation? Hs hel not defirauded you of the wealth and respectabilitv that were writhin your reach, to make you a caretaker of his poverty and his shame? If such deeds as these do not mnak]e a mln a villain, there is nothng ill the worldl that deserves to be called villainy." "I see," answered Catharine with a deep sighl, "that you are prejudicetl against himl;  You misjudre lhim altogethler. 1He did not deceive me in anythinrl. He acknowledged hi s poverty, and confessed the errors of his youth. He knew that my engagement withl Cuthbert was not one of my own making, and that I was ulndler no obligation to -hold it sacred. Heknew also that it was useless \e ask the consent of my parents, for if his poverty lad been the only objectia. against bhim, he was sure to be refusel." Perhlaps Righy felt that there was some appearance of justice and rationalitr in this reply, for he walked to and fro for some minutes, as if in deep reflection, and was probably at a loss for an answer. "MAy dear child," said he again approaching her, " you have never felt that wretchedness which is inseparable from poverty; you know nothing of its wants, its sufferings and its humiliations, or you would know why I wish to preserve you from such a condition in life. But these you will know, I think, if you persist in marrying  that man  Boyd.  I may be mistaken, but yet a deep settled conviction presses on my heart that he loves you, not for yourself alone but principally for the gold that he supposes you-will possess, when Iam  no more. I   hope for your sake it may not be. But let us knowthe worst. Let us test him.   Tell him you are portionless if you marry him, and observe the effect; Will you not do this?"  Catharine not replying to these words, Mr. Righy retired from  the store, leaving her, as it seemed, in a painful study. She thought of what her father had just said, and linked with it the unaccountable absence of her lover, whose recent acceptance should have malde him more observant and grateful; and Catharine was scarcely less offended4 than grieved by this prolonged absence. She little imagined, of course, what weighty reasons excused his want of punctuality.. Under the influence of that feeling of displeasure which the imputed negligence of Boyd produced, the question arose in her mind, "' what if my father should be right?"The test which Mr. Righy proposed then came   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.          6  . to her recollection, and she resolved to applyit at the first opportunity. most likely the reader will believe as did Mr. Righy, that Boyd's lose could not have vithstood the severe trial that Cathrin's father lt suggestedbut that as soon as the lover had been made to understand that lo money could be expected with his bride, he would have treated Catharine as the Duke at Burgundy did the portionless Cordelia, by bidding her a ceremoinous adieu on the spot. Whether Boyd did or did not deserve this suspicion, nust be a matter of uncertainty for the present: and indeed, to judge from the last accounts we ad J I ^^^^^^^^  at the close of, chapter the eig^^ had of this unfortunate lover, at the close of)Chapter the eighth, it is somewhat doubtful whether we shall ever hear from him again, except through a medium CHAPTER XI. STILL LATER INTELLIGENCE FROM THE "TRAP." On that evening when Pritchard and Hines had succeeded in withdrawing Boyd fron the spot to which he had traced his sister's progress, with the promIAe that they would assist him in his search, they continued with him several howle Pwalking about and making inquiries which resulted in nothinghut Boy*t disappointment. Mr. Pritchard pleaded an imperative engagement and left tea exploring party about ten o'clock at night, proceeding with great expedite x to the "Trap." While pretending to assist in the search for Elizabetl, -he had been meditating on the most expedient course to be pursued  reference to that young lady, and having hit on a plan which he thout od be likely to extricate himself from an embarrassing situation, he considered it highly important that his newly devised plan should be reduced to immediat ractice. Posting onwith much rapidity, therefore, he soon reached the " rap, to which he speedily obtained admittance, Ogden informing him at the entrance that " one job was finished."        h  "What job is that?" asked Pritchard hastily as he threw off his cloak. "The gal -she's quite enough now," said Ogden; "won't tell any tales, I reckon, and won't fool me again as she did this morning. Made me ay old preacher two dollars and a half for nothing-curseher? Ha, ha,ha! won t do it again. d!"tcad "Why, you old rascal, what have you done?" cried Pritchard. "Not given the gal her bitters, eh "Ogden; itsalup "Yes I have, just as you told me to do," sulkily replied Ogden; " it's all up with her." Anld a precious mess you've made of it," said Pritchard, pouring out a glass dO liquor; " why, Ogden, it's Boyd's sister!" 'Then I'm confounded glad that she wouldn't consent to be Mrs: Ogden," remarked the senior, "for if she was akin to Boyd she must have had spice of the devil in her, for certain, and I want no spitfires in my ell," he marked  Pritchard, deliberately sipping the wiskey he had just poured out, " the philosophy of the thing is, that what's done can't be helped. The worst of it is, that Boyd'is in sueA a flusterfication about her that I'm afraid he'll never be of any more use to us. Are you sure she's quite gone?" 5  &#xD;<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC8337-00000026"/> "          THE VICTIM   BRIDE; "Pretty sure of it, replied Ogden; "I slipped the furnace into her room, three hours ago. I reckon she could not tell what hurt her by this time, though some women have as many lives as a cat." "I've taken notice of that myself," said Pritchard, as he arose and opened the door of the prison room. Ogden held the candle while his associate lifted the inanimate form of Elizabeth from the mattress, bore it into the adjoining apartment and deposited it on the bench. As the two villains stood and gazed on the pallid and motionless form of their victim, the beautiful image of death seemed to affect even their obstinate natures, with some feeling of compunction. "I hope I may be hanged," said Pritchard, " if I wouldn't give something handsome to save her. Could she be re-what's that word now, I can never think of it-re-suffocated?" "Resuckertated, I guess you mean," said Ogden; "I've often heard the stujents come over it when there was any danger of a subject's coming to. Well, p'raps she might be fetched out of the swoond; but then, d'ye see, Bender's been digging a place for her, and he'll be as mad as fire if he finds he's done all that work for nothing." ' It's not for nothing, you old fool," answered Pritchard. a The philosophy of the thing is, that Bender can cut the hole about a foot longer, and then it will do for that fellow Cuthbert. He'll - have to go the. voyage, and no mistake." "This resuckertating dead bodies," grumbled Ogden, "is not in my line. It's an onnateral sort of thing, and don't seem to be right, for nobody ought to die more than once. Once paying the debt of nater ought to be enough." t'There is a good deal of philosophy in that observation," said Pritchard, "and I know a case that is just in pint. A particular friend of mine had a son that got drowned one day. He staid under water about half an hour, and when he was pulled out, and the people were trying to bring him to, his fatheri who was smoking a pipe in the corner, told them they were giving themselyes a great deal of unnecessary trouble, that he was very well satisfied, for the boy had come to a better end than he expected. But for all that they kept working away with him, and at last, sure enough, they re-'" Suckertated him,"suggested Ogden. "Yes, they did so; and what do you suppose was the upshot of it all?" demanded Mr. Pritchard. Why he got hanged, I guess," answered Mr. Ogden. "Of course he did, four years after, and his father often-sat that it all cam- of not letting him go at the right time." "That shows," observed Ogden, that resuckertating people is not the correct thing. Besides, it don't pay." The last remark was construed by Mr. Pritchard as a delicate hint "Why the fact is, Ogden," said he, "I don't- approve of it as a general thing; but ir 'this case, if you can do anything for the gal I'll give you -a half eagle, and pay for Bender's digging besides." With this encouragement Mr. Ogden undertook the humane but rathei hopeless task of attempting to restore animation'to that form in which the vtta] gpark appeared to be extinguished. The room had no windows, but he admitted   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.             67 the external air by opening a door which communicated with the yard of the building, and plentifully bathed the face of the patient with cold water. After some perseverance in these remedial measures, signs of life appeared, and the unfortunate girl gave utterance to one word-"Mother 1" Soon after, she again opened her eyes on a world in which the virtuous and innocent, when unsustained by the power of wealth, must ever feel that they are exiles and intruders. When Pritchard perceived by the shudder which his presence occasioned, that her consciousness was restored, he addressed her with these words;-                              I "Listen to me, young woman, and remember that your life depends on your obedience to my orders. You were brought here by mistake andwe are sorry for what has happened. We are willing to release you now and restore what has been taken from you; but you must promise and swear that you will never utter a word concerning what has happened here to any human being. We have our spies and agents in every part of the city, and depend upon it, you will be well watched. Any attempt to betray us will be your death-warrant. And take notice besides, that your brother's life depends on your secrecy. i He is one of us, and must suffer with us when the day of reckoning shall come. If you wish to save him from the State's prison or something worse, keep guard on your tongue. One thing in particular I wish you to observe. Your brother is not to know where you have been these two days, or what kept you from home. If he should discover that, it will lead to a quarrel between him and me, and I will be obliged to put him to death in my own defence." Elizatheth, delighted with the prospect of liberty, gave the required promise of secrecy, and Pritchard, without placing a weak reliance on such a promise from a woman, was satisfied that her fears for her own and her brlother's safety would keep her silent. The purse which had been taken from her on the night of her capture was restored, with all its contents; the boy was despatched for a cab, and on its arrival Elizabeth was helped in, and Mr. Pritchard himself accompanied her to the door of her mother's residence, where he discharged the veliele, and took leave of her with a menacing injunction not to forget her promise, or the most terrific vengeance would immediately follow. With a mind somewhat relieved, Mr. Pritchard now repaired to the hostelrie of Major Flipp, where he encountered Boyd, who had been vainly endeavoring to soothe the anguist of his soul by a resort to the cup of inebriation. It was then that the loan of a pistol was demanded, and Pritchard who judged for what purpose it was required, went to his room, on pretence of bringing the weapon thence, though it was all the time in his pocket. This manceuvre afforded him an opportunity to draw the balls, for it was not at all in accordance with Mr. Pritchard's plans to allow Boyd to take an unceremonious leave of the world at that particular juncture. He presented the pistol to Boyd, with a request that the instrument should be carefully handled, a hint which implied that it was dangerously loaded. Boyd was not cool and reflective enough to asspect a tick and after writing a long letter to Catharine, giving her many excellent reasons for blowing out his brains, he put the Inuzzle of the pistol to his right temple, and pulled the tr idger. The concussion stunned him, but as the pistol, like scme of the hanks, issued paper currency only, without anything solid and metalic to back it, Mr. Boyd's skull refused to let it pass. To speak less figuratively, no  &#xD;<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC8337-00000027"/> 68g-      -   THE VICTIM BRIDE; great damjage was done, except burning -a few hyacinthine curls, which, as Boyd had a great profusion of them, could easily be spared. It is a circumstance worthy of note, that when a man makes an attempt on his own life, and does not succeed at the first trial, he never repealts the experi- ment immediately. Human resolution is unequal to an installtaneous repetition of such an attempt. In the case now under notice, there was an insufficiency of physical power to carry out the desperate purpose; for the stimulants which Boyd had used some hours before, for the purpose of soothing. the anguish of his soul, as ale have stated elsewhere, now began to exercise all theiri-power, and he remained in a state of slumberous inactivity until morning. At an early hour he was aroused by Major Flipp, who handed him a note, which, as the Major said, had been left at the bar by a stranger. The billet was anonymous, and informed Boyd, in as few words as possible, that his sister had returned to her home on the preceding evening. CHAPTER XII. BOYD MEETS WITH AN UNEXPECTED OPPONENT. As soon as Boyd was made acquainted with the return of Elizabeth, lie hastened to his mother's dwelling, and found his invalid parent in a calm and pro tracted slumber, into which she lad fallen after the first transpolrts, occasioned bf  her daughter's safe arrival had subsided. It will be remembered thazt Pritcha ri had endeavored to make Elizabeth believe that her brother was associated wi tI him in all his criminal practices; and the conversations of Pritchard and Ogdnt  overheard by Elizabeth, and many other circumstances tended to confirm thift statement. Miss Boyd was an affectionate sister, but she was in. all respects, most rigidly virtuous and honorable; she felt a just and proper abhorrence of the supposed delinquency of her brother, and she now received him as one whose presence occasioned no other emotions than those of shame and sorrow Though her deportment greatly surprised Boyd, he was too anxious to learn the ause of her absence, to postpone his inquiries; in answer to which, however, ahe promptly and decisively refused to give him the information he desired. She then arose and opened a drawer, from which she/ took out the somewhat celebrated purse which Boyd had given her in the piazza of Flipp's tavern, atld which had subsequently been taken from her by Bender and restored by Pritchard. This purse which Pritchard had refilled with the sum it contained at the time of the robbery, she now presented to Boyd; and when, with amaze- ment at the singularity of her behaviour, he refused to receive it, she insisted on his taking it, with somewhat of indignation and resentment of voice and manner. "I have supported my mother," she said " by working for her with my needle. With God's blessing I can do so again; or, if I cannot, I am sure that she and I both would rather want and suffer, than share the spoils of robbery and murder." "Elizabeth, my sister, what can you mean?" exclaimed Boyd, not on.'y distressed but horrified at the awful accusation which her words implied. "Speak lower," said Elizabeth, pointing to the sick woman's couch. "Do not awake her. I would not have her to see you here. Why did you come?" "Merciful God!" cried Boyd; " what a wretch, what a monster I must hawe   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE. , been to deserve such treatment as this! My dear sister I came hither yesterday with the hope of communicating the happiness I then felt, to my mother and yourself I hoped that it rould please you to hear of my approaching marriage with your friend, Catharine Righy." ( Your marriage with Catharine Righy " repeated Elizabeth, with a shudder. "God forbid; While heaven is just and pitiful, such a thing could not come to pass." "It will come to pass" saidjBoyd, " and that before the expiration of a week" "It shall not," answered Elizabeth firmly, " for I will prevent it. She shall 'know what you are. Iwill tell her all." "You cannot tell her more than she has already heard from myself," answered Boyd calmly. "You slander her by saying so," replied Elizabeth. "Would Catharine willingly and knowingly unite herself -to-a-" "WThat?" asked Boycl with sorrowful composure. "What!" repeated Elizabeth excitedly, but in a suppressed tone as if fearful of disturbing her mother's slumbers; "do you ask me what you are? Why, then a candidate for the Penitentiary; the companion of thieves and assassins I Go!" she continued, as she thrust the purse in his hand-" return this money to the rightful owners; abandon your present associates, and earn your bread by the sweat of your brow and not by the sacrifice of every honorable and manly feeling."  "By leaven!" cried Boyd, whose patience was now exhausted," I will hear these unjust reproaches no longer. My faults and errors I am ready to acknowledge; but to be charged- with crimes which no one but you ever sipposed it possible for me to commit-this I cannot and will not endure. Be thre I come to this place again, Elizabeth, I must be assured that you hate i U;covered how much you have wronged me by what you have said to-day." Having spoken thus, Boyd left the room, and Elizabeth sat down and wept long and bitterly; not because she believed that her treatment of her brother was vnjUst or. unduly severe, but because she saw no hope of reclaiming him from *hat downward path which she supposed to be his choice. Besides, she felt that ,-here was a painlful duty for her to perform, and her sisterly affection struggled rith an impulse of humanity, a sense of justice and a feeling of friendship, all of which impelled heFr to warn Catharine against her intended marriage with Boydl. For some time her resolution failed; in was a task from which a sister might naturally shrink; but Elizabeth, having some of the ancient Roman in her composition, finally resolved to act the part, which virtuous integrity and faithful friendship seemed to impose on her.- Calling in the woman who had formerly nursed her mother, she prepared for a visit to Miss Righy; zand promising the nurse that she would return speedily,  she left the house. - On her arrival at Mr. Righy's store, shefound Catharine alone, and having obtained from that-young lady a blushing admission of the truth of Boyd's report, respecting the intended marriage, she protested against it in the most earnest and emphatic manner. But all the persuasive eloquence of Elizabeth was lost on Catharine, who repeated what she had before said to her fatla'^r, viz, that Boyd had made an unreserved confession of his faults and had promised to reform.  &#xD;<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC8337-00000028"/> 70           THE VICTIM   BRIDE; "4re you certain," said Elizabeth to her too confiding friend, "are you certain that he has told you all " Without understanding the full import of this question, Catlarine gave an affirmative answer, and a few minutes of silence followed, during which FElizabeth endeavoured to persuade herself that some reliance might be placed on her brother's promise of reformation. At last she inquired- "And how does the gentleman to whom   you were engaged bear his disappointment?" "You speak of Mr. Cuthbert," answered Catharine. "I have not seen him inee he went in search of you." "In search of me 1" said Elizabeth very much surprised. "Yes" answered Catharine, smiling. "I sent him to hunt you up when you were playing truant a day or two ago." Elizabeth was startled with what appeared to be the beginning of a dreadful discovery. r "Catharine," said she, " do not jest on this subject. I fear it will be found ewritus enough. Did the gentleman you speak of, really go in search of me?" "He did," replied Miss Righy, "and promised to communicate with me as oon as he found you; but I have not heard from him since." "And you have not thought proper to make any inquiries concerning him " 4 I have not, really," said Catharine. "When I heard from your brother that you had returned in safety, I had no motive for concerning myself farther in the matter." "Catharine Righy," said F lizabeth, in a tone of severe reproof, "you have done that for which you deserve to suffer the pains of remorse all the days of your life. This gentleman, who undertook a perilous enterprise at your request has, in all likelihood, been murdered; and you have allowed so much time to elapse without troubling yourself to ask, what may have been his fate!" "Murdered!" repeated Catharine turning very pale. "What reason have, ya for thinking so?" "And this man was to be your husband-my brother's rival, was he not?' aid Elizabeth in a low, solemn tone. "My brother's rival!" she repeated with a singular emphasis. God grant that my suspicions may not all be correct?" - The painful reflections of Miss Righy kept her silent. She thought of Cuthbert's most estimable qualities, and being made aware for the first time, that he had exposed himself to personal danger in the execution of the com- mission she had given him, she charged herself with ingratitude and criminal negligence, for suffering nearly two days to pass over without making those inquiries-which Elizabeth had suggested, and which, to say the truth, Catharine had never imagined to be necessary. After a reflective pause, Elizabeth again spoke.  "As this gentleman endangered his life, and perhaps lost it, while seeking for me, I cannot do less than make some effort for his preservation, if it is not too late. Before I leave you, Catharine, I consider it my duty to tell you, in plain terms, that I have the best of reasons for warning you against this marriage with my brother. God knows-it is very hard for me to sayso; but I have no faith in his promises of amendment; he has so often made the same promises before, to my mother and myself, and yet he has become more profligate, more   OR, TIIE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.           71 reckless and shameless every day. If you knew the charpter of his associates, and of what crimes they are capable, I cannot believe that you would be insane enough to unite your fate with his." While she was yet speaking, Boyd himself entered the store, and probably hoard the conclusion of her speech. Elizabeth was not discomposed in the slightest degree by his arrival, but with the sweet austerity of an angel sent to rebuke the impenitent-sinner, she fixed her eyes on her unhappy relative and id-             v  "I have done what I considered right and necessary for me to do: I have arned Catharine against a marriage which I know must be a miserable and disgraceful one for her. And now, brother, I have a word to say to you, Your rival, Mr Cuthbert, has unaccountably disappeared, and-you know where he is." "Upon my soul I do not," answered Boyd, "and I never heard of his dis- appearance." "Nor have I," said Elizabeth, " but I judge that he has disappeared, from what Catharine tells me, and from some circumstances which have come to my own knowledge. I judge, likewise, that he is in custody of your friends." "My friends " said Boyd; " what friends? who are they." "( Who?" repeated Elizabeth; "Pritchard-Ogden-Bender!" "You are mistaken, Elizabeth; these persons are no friends of mine I have dealings with Pritchard, and I have met with the two others occasionally, but have never spoken to them, except in relation to some matters of business." "Matters of business 1" echoed Elizabeth, with a vivid recollection of her own experience in Mr Ogden's boutique. "I happen to know what kind of business is transacted by these men; and your acknowledgement that you have dealings with them, confirms some of my worst suspicions." "I will say only, that you mistake the whole matter," replied Boyd. "You judge me too harshy; and I cannot perceive upon what grounds you can feel justified in speaking to me as you have done this morning.' "Let me speak with you alone, for a few minutes," Elizabeth said as she drew him towards the door; and when they had reached a point where their conversa- tion could not be overheard by Catharine, she continued-"Will you make it necessary for me to disclose'that, which might lead to your arrest and punish- ment? Can you suppose that my conscience will permit me to be a silent spectator of the villainous wrong you intend to do this girl, whose unsuspicious disposition makes her a defenceless victim to your wicked arts? Can you imagine that, knowing what I do, I would allow you .to become the husband of Catharine Righy? 'No; if you were ten times my brother, I would deliver you up to the law, to the dungeon or the gallows, if nothing else could save this innocent, girl from the fate you intend for her." "Elizabeth," answered Boyd, " if I were not certain that your intentions are virtuous and honorable, I would not bear this language even from you. I confess that some circumstances are well calculated to place my conduct before you in an unfavorable light, and I can easily pardon your errors of judgment. But there is something in your allusions to Pritchard and Ogden which I will not pretend to understand." a Oh lbrother," cried Elizabeth, with a gush of tears, "'if I could only be wnviced that you are less guilty than I have supposed! But do one act of  &#xD;<pb n="72-73 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8337-00000029"/> l:il ;! :8- 7jI   72          TIIE VICTIM   BRIDE;; lustlce and mercy, that may atone for a thousand offences: save this gentleman to whom I gm so, much indebted-Mr. Cuthbert." ;' "Here is mystery on mystery," said Boyd. "You indebted to Mr. Cuthbert  A-re you surethat your mind is not wandering?" "I am indebted to him for his intention to do me a great service," said Elizabeth;, "and if I were not, common hunlmanity should influence you to interest yourself in his behalf."        "I will risk my life to save him, if he is in the danger you suppose," replied Boyd. : (But the first question to be asked is, where shall I find lim?" "Is it possible that you do not know or suspect?" "Aa I hope to live beyond the present moment, I do Jhot." "Then I will showyou," said Elizabeth with generous enthusiasm 6 for at al hazards the life of this man must be saved." CHAPTER XTTT. 1Tff0itls BOLTEN PROVES HERSELF A TRUE PROfi'ia31S. , It yeaa mentioned in a former chapter, that: Elizabeth fell into a swoon at the sry moment when Pritchard and his associates assaulted Mr. Cuthbert, and this will account for. her ignorance of the manner, in which Cuthbert had been diposed oft: Subsequent events of absorbing interest had occupied her thoughts and At was ,not, ulntil she heard from' Ca'tharine, that Mr. Cuthbert had been ergUaged in,seeking her, that she identified him with the gentleman, who had seanle inquiries at the "Trap," and she then began to conjecture that he might ,fifiuibly be detained as a prisoner in that fortress, as she herself had been before. -.jvs suspicion,:ard her gratitude to Cuthbert for his humanne efforts in her behalf, iJAuced her to apply, to her brlther for Cuthbert's liberation: for she believed, on what appeared -to be very'sufficient groullnds, that Boyd was not quite blameless if Cuthbert had really been detained in custody by Ogden and Pritchard. ' But when she beganto reflect that her own capture anmd imprisonment in thle'"Trap" hid certainly been without any co-operation or conlnivance on thel part of her brother, she was induced .to hope that h6 was equally guiltless of any participa- tion in the ill-treatment of his rival, Mr. Guthbert. Boyd having made excuses to Catharine for his ' hasty departure, submitted himself to the guidance of his sister. She-a'dvised him to obtain assistance, as the enterprise was one'which. one man could not safely undertake. Boyd treated this, counsel with some levity, X "'Tell me whither you intend to conduct me," said he, " and I will know wha course will be required. Who are the en'emyy and where are they encamped?" , Oh, I had forgotten," answered Elizabeth in a tone which' was both melan- ohply and slightly sarcastic; "you are not to'meet an enemy, but your friends or associates inbusiness, Pritchard and Ogden I ' ' "If that is all the opposition I: have to fear," replied; Boyd, "I want nor reinforcement. But it perplexes me much, Elizabethto find that you have any knowledge of these people. Are you aware that it is discreditable for you to bi Able to call them by name?"'      -  - Old Ogdn of "Ogde's Trap" atempts tomutder*Misizzie Boy.-Pnge 80 Per' anL-5te gettn,2bnsSle ej,Wi i3eB4ruezobn iie  &#xD;<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC8337-00000030"/> lI    74          THE  VICTIM    BRIDE; "How can that be," said Elizabeth," when they are the intimate acquaintances of my brother?" Boyd sighed deeply, and remained silent for some minutes. Elizabeth herself was little inclined to resume the conversation. Botli were occupied with painful reflections on the past or more paillful anticipations of the future. In this mood they had proceeded to the outskirts of the city, hllen their sombre meditations were interrupted by the approach of an old awoman, who hobbled along with the help of a long staff, the clatter of which on the pavement first attracted the notice of Boyd and Elizabeth. As the ancient dame slowly advanced, she indulged in that eccentric habit which is called " talking to one's self," though it has been insinuated, heretofore, that whenever such mystic dialogues take place, the devil himself is one of the interlocuters. As soon as the parties met, the hobbling old woman paused, laid her hand on Boyd's arm and said- "You are the person I came to meet. And who is this with you? Not the one whose shadowy image I saw yesterday by your side. This is one who has been less favored by fortune than the other; yet she may be much happier in time to come. But beware! This day is unlucky, and you are leading i er into danger.' 6Think you so, Mother Bolton?" answered Boyd. "Well, for once your prophetic spirit deceives you. I am not leading her anywhere; she is lead;,ag me.? "I have been told," said Mother Bolton, "by those who see more than may be seen by mortal eyes, that this is a perilous day for two personz-one of whom, it was said, I should find with you." "And the other?" "The other is myself," answered the old woman. "In spite of your dreams, my good old lady," said Boyd pleasantly, "I am satisfied that you have many happy days to live yet; and although you consider this an unlucky day, I regard. our meeting here as a very fortunate event, since it affords me an opportunity to discharge a small part of the great debt I owe you.'              I As Boyd said this, he attempted to place money in tne old woman's hand; but she rejected it with some appearance of scorn. "What debt do you owe me, James Boyd?" asked Mother Bolton. "I am indebted to you for my life," answered Boyd.. "For your life, young man? Before three days, you will curse mne for having saved it." "Surely," replied Boyd, "you are a most uncomfortable prophetess, Mother Bolton  However, it is not for your soothsaying that I desire to make payment Out for your kind interference in my behalf, yesterday. I beg you to take this as a token of my gratitude. I would pay you more if it were in my power; dtough I estimate the value of my life at a very low rate." "I have an limpression," said Mother Bolton, still refusing the gold which Boyd offered her, "that I shall need no more noney. My earthly wants are provided for. But once mure, James Boyd, I charge you to turn back; or, if you must go on in this path, do not take this dear lamb with you.'} Having spoken thus, Mother Bolton pursued her slow and toilsome wallL Boyd -d  glWi beth stood for some minutes gazing after her-the latter not   OR, THE FA"THER'S SACRIFICE.            75 without some feeling of awe, and a secret apprehension that the warning of the sibyl was not to be despised. Her brother, on the contrary, was disposed to receive the old woman's admonitions with extreme inldifference or ridicule. "You see, Elizabeth," said he, " that this adventure is reserved for me alone. Show me the - haunted forest or enchanted castle to which destiny calls me; and then, having told me what I have to do, you may return in the next omnibus." The sentence was scarcely finished when the sound of a horse's hoofs, indicative of rapid motion, were heard; and, almost at the same instant, a runaway quadruped which had broken away from some vehicle, came sweeping down the pavement. Boyd drew his sister aside as the furious animal passed, yet the creature came in fearful proximity to the young lady, and the iron chain which had fastened him to the carriage, and which was still attached to the harness, distended as it was by the swift motion of the horse, actually touched Elizabeth's bonnet. As the frightened beast dashed on, Boyd followed with his eyes, and saw Mother Bolton still tottering on in the middle of the brick footwalk, seemingly unconscious of the approaching danger. The horse was close behind her, and there was no earthly possibility of saving her, or even apprising her of her peril; but Boyd, acting from the impulse of the moment, rushed towards her. For one moment he saw nothing distinctly; another moment, the horse was far away and the old woman lay motionless on the pavement. The chain had struck her on the back of the neck, and caused instantaneous death. There happened to be a public house at no great distance, and thither Boyd proceeded for assistance. A settee was brought, and Boyd with the help of several men, whom he found in the bar-room, conveyed the body to the tavern, where it was deposited in a private room, and Boyd and Elizabeth sat by it until the arrival of the coroner. In the meanwhile, Boyd had sent for a physician, who on his arrival very speedily declared, what had been strongly suspected before, that life was totally extinct This melancholy incident occasioned a delay of several hours; and when Boyd and Elizabeth were at length released from their attendance on the corpse of Mother Bolton, Miss Boyd seemed to be impressed with a more anxious desire to accomplish the object, which had brought her and her brother into that neighborhood. The dreadful scene they had just witnessed was the subject of a sad and subdued conversation, until they reached a certain spot on the road, -,where Elizabeth paused, and laying her hand impressively on her brother's shoulder, said in an agitated voice "James, do you know this place?" Boyd recognized it in a moment It was the very spot to which he had traced Elbzabeth's footprints, and where they had become invisible. He looked at his sister with an inquiring eye, as he answered- ' I do know the place, Elizabeth; and your positive refusal to explain the mystery connected with this spot, and with your late absence from home, seems to be a most extraordinary instance of female perversity. You can scarcely imagine what trouble your disappearance occasioned, and what might have been the result'" "Concerning the events of the last two dlays," Elizabeth answered, "I myself stand in need of much explanation. But let me ask you, brother, do you know -that house?ts "Oh, ves," replied Boyd, with a very faint smile. "And is it possible that housr  &#xD;<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC8337-00000031"/> ji     76     f     THE VICTIM    BIIDE; i^   can have any connection with the wonderful and unaccountable events you speak of?"       .  C^    aIt has indeed," said Elizabeth, clasping her hands. "And you confess that you know that house? Y ou have been there often, perhaps?" / "I never was nearer to it than I 4m at present; and all I know of it is, that the foolish people in the neighborhood call it the haunted housed' !      "It is indeed haunted," said Elizabeth, "and with the worst kind of spirits i:    But do you not know who lives there?"  Lives there!" repeated Boyd. "Surely no human beirg lives in such a hideous den." "Brother, your sight is good, I believe. Look intently at that window in the third story, and tell me if you can see anything more than the unglazed sash?" Boyd looked at the window as directed, and to his great surprise, saw something like a human being, which was scarcely discernible in the distance. "Some part of the house really appears to be inhabited," said he, ' but what is this to. us?" "We must go to that house," answered Miss Boyd, "and it would be better not to go alone." "If Pritchard and Ogden are there, as you seem to hint, we shall have two allies, at all events," said Boyd. "But one thing I must insist on, Elizabeth; though, I am not apprehensive of any danger, I do not, for several reasons, wish you to accompany me to that place. Before we proceed further, therefore, I must send you homeward in the next coach." "I cannot leave you, brother-l-and will not," said Elizabeth. a Then I cannot go-and will not," answered Boyd. "In that case, I must go by myself," said Elizabeth. "You may, if you please, wait here till I return."  When she had proceeded twenty or thirty yards in, the direction of the old lb :lding, Boyd began to think ;,le twas really in earnest, and following vat'a brisk pacre soon overtook her. He earnestly and even angrily insisted on her retutn, blit all his entreaties and commands could not change her resolution to go firward. At the very acme of the debate, they arrived at the door of the "Trap" sphere Boyd rapped with much vigor, his temper being not a little irritated by his sister's obatinacy.  CHAPTER XIV. +! ,     , ST6nMXGJ THE FOBTRESS. The urgent knocking of Boyd at the portal, met with no response, and not a mound of any kind was heard from the interior. After repeating the summons with increased energy, Boyd applied;his strength and shook the door so violently, that the frame work, being much decayed, seemed evidently about to give way, when the sound of footsteps was heard in the entry, and the door was unlocked at the very moment,- when Ithe operation soft unlocking it seemed to be unnecessary. It was opened no wider, howeverjthah was requsite to afford M:r. Ogden an opportunity to present his face at the opening, and to ask a question which ncrbody could have answert better than himself, viz :-"Who's there l" -   OR  T1E1 FlATi  ER'S SACRlIFICE.       -  " "You know me, I suppose," Boyd replied, " and if you do, perhaps you will get out of the way and let me pass." "At ally other time," replied the ancient janitor, "I shall be very glad to see you, Mr. Boyd, but just now there is a private party of gentlemen-six of them (old Ogden laid a significant emphasis on the number,) and the orders are that no more must be admitted." "Well, I have made up my mind to come in," remarked Boyd coolly, " and I hope you and the six other gentlemen inside, will have sense enough to make no opposition." So saying, he pushed the door open with such force that Ogden, while striving n vain to oppose his ingress, was overthrown amidst the dust and rubbish which strewed the floor of the entry. Without stopping to'apologise for his rudeness, Boyd, closely followed by Elizabeth, passed on to the apartment which with some license of speech, might be called Alr. Ogden's parlor or salon. On his entrance Boyd found that Ogden had correctly reported the niumber of the " party of gentlemen" there assembled. There were really six of them including Pritchard and Hines. All were known to Boyd as votaries oft tortune, whom he had met at the different gamingt establishments of the city. As soon as Boydl made hil appearance and bowed stiffly to the company, Pritchard advanced and began to - apologise for keeping l;im waiting at the door. "I hope I may be hanged," said he, " if I had the least suspiscion that it was you or you should have been admitted at a moment's notice. Miss Boyd, I hope I see you in good health."' Boyd frowned terrifically, as he said- "Mr. Pritchard, my sister will excuse you for any lack of ceremony, and I am really unable to guess what-has given her the honor of your acquaintane.- That is a subject on which I must ask for information after a while. In the first place I wish to have some account of a gentleman named Cuthlbert, who visited these premises yesterday." The stern composure and constrained politeness of Boyd, made Pritchard suspect that there was " a screw loose" somewhere; however, it seemed to be his policy to keep the machinery together as long as possible. In answer to Boyd's inquiry after Cuthllbert, he made a significant gesture, implying thattlhle subject was one which would not bear a public discussion. - He then requested Boyd to step with him into the entry, as " the philosophy of the thing was to talk about such matters as much on the sly as possible." 'What I have to say on the subject, can be said as well here as anywhere lse," answered Boydd. If Mr. Cuthbert is in the house, I wish to see him mmediately." Oh I you wish to see him, Mr. Boyd?" I do, sir; and without any delay?" "Well, the truth is, Mr. Boyd, he is not very well," said Pritchard, with a lurking expression of drollery in his countenance. ",( He has been -verish, I think, and we me obliged to put him on low diet." "Are you trifling with me, sir?" said Boyd very angrily. Here one of the company, whose part it was to play the bully occasionally, for the benefit of the confederacy, advised Pritchard to " pitch the fellow out of doora."  &#xD;<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC8337-00000032"/> 78           THE VICTIM BRIDE; "Perhaps he might require your assistance in that undertaking," suggested Boyd. "I will do it myself in two minutes, if Mr. Pritchard has no objection," said the bully as he arose and approached Boyd. The misfortunes of Boyd had made him a misanthrope, and on various accounts he entertained a particular dislike for the gambling confederacy, of which this bully was a prominent member. It was therefore with a feeling of satisfaction, that he saw him approach with gestures that threatened violence; and as soon as he came within arm's length, Boyd dealt him a blow on the right cheek, which the best christian in the world would not have wished to be repeated on the left. This champion being disabled for a time, another inrdivi. dual of the gang drew a dirk and precipitated himself on Boyd, with an evident design to do serious damage. At this moment Boyd stood near the corner of the table on which a stout blue bottle had been deposited, for the refreshment of the company. Now, among all the anacreontic compliments which have been paid to the bottle, we do not know that any eulogist has taken notice of its utility as a weapon, in cases of emergency. To this purpose, indeed, it has a most happy adaptation; its form allows it to be firmly grasped by the party who uses it, and at the same time, prevents the adversary from obtaining an advan. tageous hold of the other extremity, and thus gaining possession of the weapon; and although like the swords of the Cimnbri, (nlentioned by Plutarch,) it is generally broken at the very commencement of-the contest, a single blow, well directed, is commonly decisive. In addition to all this, the lottle is generally available as a weapon, or within reach at times when it is Inost likely to be required for the uses just spoken of; that is to say, in seasons of baccllanalian excitement. But, whatever may be said by military men and others for or against the bottle as a warlike instrument, it is hoped that the sensible mitajority will excuse Mr. Boyd for resorting to it on the occasion to whchl Ne now refer, as no other sort of arms happened at that time to be withill his reach. HHaving grasped the stout glass bottle by the neck, Boyd pushed aside the arom wshich directed the murderous poignard to his bosom, and aimingz at that part of his alssailant's skull where the left parietal bone was joined to the os frontis, lie permitted his vitreous club to descend with a force whichl produced an irreparable fracture; not of the skull, however, but of the bottle. The hlead ofBoyd's atiltagonIist was, according to Fielding's humerous theory, constructed expressly for warlike encounters; being probably, dike some Afr;ican skulls we have seen) nearly an inch tlick, and it was not likely therefore to sustain any very serious detriment by collision with a glass bottle. But in this case, the very fraragility of the weapon was the cause of its real efficacy;l for if the bottle hadl not been brolken, B1oyd's f1erocious enenly would not have 'been conquleredl. A shharp end or edge of the fractured glass opened a vein or artery in the ruffiatn's temple, and Ogden's surgical skill wa required to stop the flow of blood, which came forth in a torrent that must hav Boon exhausted the fountain of vitality. Pritchard and lHines were nactive and to all appearance, indifferent specta- tors of the'scene; though Hines, near the conclusion of the flay, qtuoted the scriptural precept wrhicll requires brethren to dwell together in unity, and Pritchard remarked that there was "Ino philosophy in SQualubhles between gentle- men in tho Same line of business." Thle two other gamnblers htamd been quite   OR  , THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.           79 lookers-on also, and seemed to wait for sone hint or cue from Pritchard before tney betook themselves to action. Wlien Boyd's last antagonist had been subdued in the manner related, p,;hitrch, who had been quietly sipping a glass of grog at the end of the table, began to speak: tir. Boyd, I suppose you know that I am your friend-e "No sir," promptly answered Boyd, " I now nothing of the kind: and once more I call on you, not as a friend, to let me see Mr. Cuthbert.- mo Certainly, er. Boyd, certaiuy If you wish to see the gentleman you shall be gratified; that is, if Hines has nothing to say against it.'" r. flines siganified by a groan that he was perfectly acquiesent "   do you kow  Who this gentlean is, r. Boyd  " asked Pritchard; "do you know that e isyou wish him to be set at lij)erty i I tine to fulfil his engagement?"i "1 Yol are losing time, Mr. Pritchtard. May I request you to use dispatch" s ro^'MrS   :?^    ^^^^^ifcanttha tewords.*l* sai( 13oyd in a tone which was more significant than the words. ) OM very well," said Pritchard. "The gentleman is i I his private room; I wil illform him that a particzlarfriend wisles to slkakl with him." There was sollletling like fiendish mockery ill Pritcllard's tone and manner; solnetlding that " raised emotions both of rage and fear." He arose, went to one c(r;er of the apartiaent, and tappin t against a trap-door with mock gravity, called out, "Mr. CJuthbert! Mr. Cuthbert ! a gentleian to speak with you, if you are not engaged!" "Ily heaven! you are carrying this joke too far," cried Boyd, as he sprang "rww ld nd catcBiyaeg Pritcarr d by tie collar, shook him violently and then dasledl hirn against the floor with sucll force that he arose with some dificulty, otarfgered to a chair, thd seated himself in a manner which showed that he had 811'C tUillCed sonic corDoreal illjury. eur tamecd sonle corporeal injury.  ,  m"myefiyoraffairs," said '  I this is any rexvarcl, I su'plsose, for interesting myself in your affairs, said the dliscolllfitedl Pritc ard. Y You know it was your concern, and not mine, to ket. r) tiS  -!lo ullr flatclles.' keoIy, tlrallceunlaElizabtlic ho stood near the door, and perceived in her k3oyd (rlancedl at Elizabeth host  ulltellce alln expression of keen anguish. "You detcestale villain," said le to Pritchard, "do you dare to accuse me of hiiill your accmptlice ill thi mnatter? I am sure Mr. Cuthbert himself, will accltit nie of the infamous charge."isoner to So sa) ils, le llnbolted the trap-door, raised it and desired the prisoner to comne torti,. A fiilt voice from the vault ansered "I cannot. dcend. "H1old then and I vill assist you," said Boyd as he prepared to descend. At this lmomlent, Elizalbeth saw Pritchard make a signal to his confederates, xvlie ll 'l tilllx iltimatetl thatlt they should throw down the trap-door, and secure Which, ,ai,]y initimated that they sliould thro^d  t iiaprn it as sin as Bloyd disappeared. Boyd was already half through the apertul of assisting Mr. Cuthbert. Hlines athswercd byr a gro(an of, negation.  &#xD;<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC8337-00000033"/> i  80            TRHE VTICTIM BRIDE; "You hypocritical scoundrel," cried Boyd, " if you do not instantly go down a I command you I will pitch you into the den, head foremost." "What do you wish me to do!" asked the M'Cubbinite, doggedly. "To help Mr. Cuthbert out of this place," answered Boyd; "That is what you might call a work of charity," replied Hines, " and it is against our principles to do anything of the kind. We go by faith alone.' "Then have faith in my intention to break every bone in your body, if you do not obey my orders," shouted Boyd. "Taking that view of the subject," said Hines as he began to comply with Boyd's injunction, "I suppose I will be justified in doing what you bid. But take notice that I claim no merit for this job, as I do it against my own will. "I am quite sure of that," said- Boyd, as he lent his vigorous arm to facilltate the descent of, Mr. Hines into the yawning gulf. While this altercation was in progress, Ogdlen appeared at the door of the room and having picked up the dagger, which had been dropped 'by the man whom Boyd had subdued with the bottle, he heldl up the weapon as he exchanged signals 'with Pritchard. The old villain slyly pointed at Elizabethl with one-hazid, whiNff he displayed the dagger to his colleague with the other. Pritchard gave a n i of assent. Meanwhile, Elizabeth was too deeply interested in-the proceedin a at the other end of the room, to observe what was going on in her iinmedit t( neighborhood. By this time, Hinles with Boyd's assistance, had reached the floor of the va; t, and after groping about in the dark for a few minutes, his hand touched Cuthbeo i, who was seated on the ground with his back against the wall. The dampn, ei and confined air of the dungeon, together with a long fast, had so affected Cuth bert's health that he was unable to move from the spot where Hines found hi 4, It appeared to have been the intention of the villains to starve him, for no lilId o of nourishment, not even water, had been offered him since the beginning of Asia confinement, nearly two days previous. When Hines, by calling to Boyd, had reported the feeble condition of 31r. Cuthbeit, and complained of the difficulty which attended his removal, Boj d haughtily commanded another of the gamblers to go down and give his assistance. The fellow obeyed with visible reluctance, and by the united strength of Hiinll and this worthy coadjutor, Cutlhbert was brought under the trap-door, and raised up, so thlat with Boyd's help from above, he was soon placed on the floor of the superior apartment. Then Boyd promptly and unceremoniously closed the trap door and bolted it, leaving Mr. Hines and the other sporting gentleman below, in quiet possession of the lodging, which Cuthbert had just vacated. By this skilful ct of generalship, Boyd very considerably reduced the strength of Pritchard's party. Two Of the six had previously beeln thrown hors du combat, by Boyd's prowess, and two more being how confilled in the cellar, our champion conceived that he llad none to deal with except Pritchard himself and his single associate. who yet remained in the field of operations. Old Og(den was not taken into the account, for he, in Boyd's estimation, was a cypher ; but alas! Mr. B)oyd was soon tauglt by painful experience, the great moral and arithmetical truth, that even a cypher is not always an insignificant nonentity. While Boyd was engaged in pay- ing the most humane attentions to Cuthbert he was interrupted by an appalling seream from .Elizabeth, and turning around, he saw her prostrate on the floor and Ogden in the act of retreating with a bloody dagger in his hand.   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.              81 CHAPTER XTV. INTERVIEW BDlTWUEEN THE RIVALS-DISCOVERIES. The sight of his sister, prostrate and bleeding, threw Boyd into such a state of distraction, that Cuthbert and every other object except the dreadful spectacle before him was forgotten. He flew to the spot where Elizabeth lay, knelt by her side and supported her in his arms, without having the presence of mind to use such measures as seemed necessary :for her preservation. Taking advantage of Boyd's affliction, Pritchard (who had now recovered the power of locolmotion) and his confederate unbolted the trap-door, and released their comrades. The whole party of gamblers, alarmed no doubt at the prospect of being implicated in the  murder of Elizabeth., made a diligent use of their legs, and escaped from the premises. Ogden had made good his retreat, as soon as he had taken vengeance for Elizabeth's supposed violation of her promise of secrecy. Happily the strength of Ogden's arm was unequal to fl malignancy of Ias heart. His imbecility and decrepitude defeated his revengeful iurpose and tieu wound was merely such an one as a child miight have inflicted with such a dangerous instrument. He hadaiiiexl at Elizabetlh's heart, but his palsied hauld and guilty trepidation had given such an erring direction to the blow, treat although it caused an al arming effusion of blood, the wound was in no degree dangerous. As soon, therefore, as Bloyd recovered. the use of his reflective powers sufficiently to bandage the hurt with his handkerchief, the condition of Elizabeth seemed to be so much improved, that her brother was satisfied that no senrious consequences were to be apprehended. On being introduced to a purer atmosphere, Cuthbert also began to recover rapidly, and was soon able to express his gratitude to Boyd for the timely assist- ance which had. been afforded him. If the reader has any acute sensibilities, he may judge what were Boyd's feelings while he listened to the grateful acknow- ledgments of a man whom he had so greatly injuired. His only reply was- "You are not indebted to me, sir; and there are circumstances which make it impossible for us to be on terms of friendship." After the flight of the gamblers, Boyd fancied that he and his two patients were the sole occupants of the house; but he was slightly mistaken, for Ogden's boy, a ragged vicious looking youth, now descended from the upper story where he was accustomed to keep watch, and peeped cautiously into the room, to discover, perhaps, what changes had been effected by the late commotions, the poise of which he must have overheard. Seeing none but strangers in the apartment, he was about to withdraw, when Boyd recalled him and induced him by the promise of reward, to procure a carriage. The lad soon executed this commission, as he knew the address of a cab. driver, who often had the honor of conveying Mr. Pritchard and his friends to and from the "Trap." This favored individual having arrived with his vehicle, Boyd lifted Elizabeth into the carriage, and having assisted Cuthbert to enter it also, finally got in himself The driver, having received his directions, proceeded at a very slow pace over the soft ground which intervened between the residence of Mr. Ogden and the main road; and vhile the horses were dragging through this toilsome route, Cuthbert again each preqqed a grateful sense of the obligations he owed Boyd and Elizabeth for his  &#xD;<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC8337-00000034"/> 82          THE VICTIM BRIDE; deliverance. However, he did not attempt to conceal the surprise and regret he felt, on account of the exposure of the young lady to the dangers of such a place as that they had recently left. Boyd answered, he had endeavored to dissuade -her from eoning to the place, and it was impossible that either he or she should have any preconception of the risk which attended the visit. Owing to the fright and loss of blood which Elizabeth had lately experienced, she was in too languid a state to take any part in the conversation which now ensued. It was a conversation, however, in which she was deeply interested, and one which comprised matters of infinite surprise to Mr. Boyd. Cuthbert, who by the way was totally ignorant of the names of his companions proceeded' to give an account of his adventure at the "Trap." He related how he went thither in search of a-young lady, who was supposed to have been forcibly conveyed to the place; how he had heard a female voice calling for help, from an inner apartment; and how he himself had been overpowered and imprisoned as soon as he began to make active exertions for the lady's release. Since his ot, deliverance, he had observed that the door of the room from which the call for assistance came, was unlocked, and the boy, in answer to his inquiries had informed him just before they entered the cab, that the young lady had been restored to her friends. "And what was this young lady's name?" asked Boyd, who began to take a lively interest in the narrative. "Her name is Elizabeth Boyd," answered Cuthbert. What!" cried Boyd in a tone which made Cuthbert start; " are you certair that was the name?" "That was the name, as I heard it from the person at whose request I under tok to find 'her." "^And who was the person who requested you to do so?" demanded Boyd. Really," said Cuthbert, "I do not know that I am at liberty to answer tha qaeetion." U It was Catharine," said Elizabeth in a faint voice. The amazement of Boyd kept him silent till Cuthbert again spoke "You appear to have some knowledge of this affair. You are acquainted With Miss Boyd, perhaps?" "She is here to answer for herself," answered Boyd. "For my own art, I giv Pa my wotd that I know nothing of this ' affair' as you are pleased to call it. "That is very extraordinary," remarked Cuthbert, who had heard Elizabet] hi h  brother." it ay be extraordinary," replied Boyd rather haughtily, "but I presum it il a matter which chiefly concerns ourselves." "Excuse me," replied Cuthbert mildly, "I meant not to offend, and I hop Miss Boyd will accept my acknowledgments of the great obligations I owe her. "The obligations seem to be on the other side," said Boyd with formal courtes3 His unfriendly and somewhat austere behaviour greatly surprised Mr. Cuthbei ortho was discourag ed from any farther attempt to carry on the conversation; an indeed, the severe penance he had lately undergone, was enough of itself to mall him yncompanionabJle, even if the reserve of Boytl and the feeble condition o Elizacheth had not, been sufficient to check any disposition to converse. Nothin mlore was said, therefore, till the nab arrived at the door of Btrs. Boyd.'s dwellin   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.             83 whenl Boyd informed Mr. Cuthbert that the driver had been instructed to convey him to his place of residence, and taking a ceremonious leave, lifted his wounded sister from the vehicle, and carried her into the house. While the carriage proceeded to Mr. Cuthbert's place of abode, that gentle- man, being now all alone, perplexed himself with a studious endeavour to account for the inconsistencies of Boyd's conduct. The generous and benevolent zeal which Boyd had exhibited while effecting Cuthbert's deliverance, was unaccount. ably at variance with his subsequent behaviour, which was both morose and re- pulsive. The truth is, Boyd still possessed so much manly sincerity of character that he could not bear to be treated as a friend by Mr. Cuthbert, while he was conscious there was a cause of enmity between them of whicel Cuthbert, as yet was totally ignorant. Boyd's first care was to procure medical attendance for his mother and sister. Thanks to the weakness of the assassin's arm, Elizabeth's-wound proved to be very slight, and the doctor gave Boyd an assurance that within a few days her recovery would be complete. Mrs. Boyd likewise began to be convalescent, but it was a painful discovery for Boyd, that his presence seemed always to be irksome to his mother. Recent events, however, had satisfied Elizabeth that he was less guilty than she had suspected, and with many tears of joy and affection, she acknowledged the injustice of her suspicions. For those suspicions, however, the falsehoods told her by Pritchard, afforded a sufficient excuse. Still she was not reconciled to the projected union of Boyd and Catharine. I'My dear brother," said Elizabeth, "do not take any advantage of her partiality,to induce her to break her engagementwith Mr. Cuthbert. I am satisfied that she would be happier with him than she could be with you. The knowledge I have of your character and disposition convinces me that your marriage with Catharine would be unfortunate. And remember, (continued the rigid but amiable monitress,) remember the inequality of your circumstances If you really love her, do not ask her to sacrifice herself to your advantage." Boyd had never given these considerations the attention they deserved. He could not but acknowledge that Catharine's preference for himself was most injudicious, an err r of youth and inexperience which would probably lead to much unavailing regret and repentance in time to come. He revolved this subject in his mind, until a all powerful love" itself yielded to the suggestions of reason -and honor, and he resolved to prove that he was not altogether unworthy of Catharines affection, by resigning his claims and submitting to the triumph of his rival Cuthbert; thue making his testament, as it were, like another Alexander the GFreat, in fav,* of the most worthy." v j!PYTER XVI. A *JR-DEROUTS ENTERPRISE. Boyd having ormed SPY noble and generous resolution mentioned at the close of chapter the &amp;fteextl, determined to put it in practise forthwith, for he was well aware that virtuous resolutions, when they have to contend for any length of time with passion or inclination, are too apt to be defeated. Without allowing himself any time for deliberation, therefore, he proceeded to Mr.  &#xD;<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC8337-00000035"/> i '  84          THEi-  VICTIM  BPRIDE; Righy's store, feeling very, mucklas Damon or Pythias,(whch was it?) did while going to be hanged as hionor and duty relquired. - At, the sight of Catharine, Boyd's magnanimous resolution ,began to waver.,' She loolked uncommonly beautiful that afternoon, and for some minutes he felt that it was impossible for him to surrender the happiness that was within his reach., .While the unhappy young man stood in pensive silence, and endeavoured to find satisfactory excuses for the non-performance or postponement of the sacrifice on which he had resolved, Catharihe interrupted his meditations by informing him that she had laade her parents acquainted with her new engagement, and that her father had threatened to disinherit her in consequence. Then she anxiously waited to see what effect this announcement would have on her lover. The reply of Boyd seemed to be confirmatory of Mr. Righy's suspicions, concerning Boyd's character and motives. 'He admitted to Catharine that her father's objections to the marriage were perfectly reasonable, and confessed that he was altogether unworthy of such an alliance.  It seemed to be the fate of poor Boyd to be misconstrued by everybody. His apparent willingness to give her up as soon as he was informed that she would be a portionless bride, appeared to be the best proof in then world that his pur- poses were really mercenary, and Catharine reproached himlwith many tears, for the unworthiness of his motives adding that her father had judged him right when he foretold what would be the result of the disclosure which had just been made. "Did he say," asked Boyd, with sad composure, "that want of fortune on your part would make any change of my feelings and intentions in this matter?" Catharine admitted thAt such -was her father's opinion. "And do you likewise, judge me so harshy?" asked Boyd. Catharine wept and was silent. "Remember, now," said Boyd, " that you have pledged yourself to be mine, and while I thought you had perfect confidence in the integrity of my purposes, I was prepared to give you up, because I was unwilling to deprive you of any advantage, which fortune had thrown in your way. But now I claim the fulfil- ment of our contract, and your father and you must both learn that you have wronged me by your unjust suspicions." Mutual explanations and concessions followed, and this singular misunder- standing between the lovers ended, in a complete reconciliation, and a deter- mination on the part of both to consummate their vows, in spite of all obstacles, pains and penalties. At a late hour in the afternoon, as Boyd'was leaving Righy's store, he encountered Mr. Simeon Price, tl pale gentleman who officiated as bar-keeper at Major Flipp's hotel. Boyd was about to pass the gentleman without a word or sign of recognition, when Mr. Price, in his usual gentle ansd insinuating tone requested him to stop, as he had something of the utmost importance to communicate. "Ay, sure enough, "said Boyd, "you can tell me something which I desire to know, and that id, where I may find those rascals, Pritchard and Ogden. Of course they will not be found in any of their former haunts that I am acquainted with." huh," responded Mr. Prie with a sigh, "I have often thought, Mr. Boyd,   is OR, THFE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.            85 that you are the very gentleman whose friendship I should like to cultivate. Friendship, sir, next to love, is mly mbost particular weakness. That's as true as Presbyterian preaching, Mr. Boyd. - Little have you thoughlt,- perhaps, wrhen I've been mixing juleps and cocktails for you at Flipp's, little have you imagined how many sacrifices I have madle on the altars of love and friendship. Yes sir, I have often fretted my gizzard with them sort of things, I tell you; and though I don't like to brag, T may say that I have pined with love, sir, worse than any sick monkey,"                           J Indeed," said Boyd, rather mockingly, "you appear to be a good deal emnaciated, and if love has done it, you must have suffered considerably." "Well, I can't say Mr. Boyd, that it is altogether love which has fetched me down to this pass. The doctor thinks I've got a tape-worm. But, that's neither here nor there, as the saying is; Cupid's dart is not the present theme. It's an affair of friendship that I'm about to agitate." A gesture of impatience made by Boyd admonished Mr. Price to treat the subject of friendship with that brevity, which is sometimes attributed to the duration of friendship itself. "The occurrences of this morning," said Mr. Price; "I mean that little affair at the Trap, made me think that Mr. Cuthbert is a friend of yours. Of course he is, or you wouldn't have taken all that trouble to get him out of that fix, Oh, Mr. Boyd! what a divine thing friendship is! It's nothing shorter; especially when a feller's in a devil of a scrape, or wants to borrow a trifle of money. By the way, Mr. Boyd, I'm rather-hard up, myself, just at this time." "Please to be quick and confine your discourse to one subject," said Boyd. "I thought the topic was to be friendship." "Yes sir-very true-- and that very naturally introduces the subject of money. One follows the other. The fact is, I have a valuable secret which concerns Mr, Cuthbert and yourself, and believing that you like to encourage disinterested firiendship, and all that sort of thing, I walked over here at the risk of losing mly situation, and worse accidents than that, in hopes that you wouldn't think five dollars or something like that figule, too much for my risk and trouble" "I am willing to pay for the secret, if it is worth anything," said Boyd, "provided you will state it in as few words as possible." "I will trust'to your honor anld liberality, my dear sir," said Mr. Price, "as I am sure you would trust to mine, in like circumstances. Well, the matter is this:-Cuthbert's house is to be robbed and Cuthbert's throat is to be cut to-night at a convenient hour. Pritchard thinks that it won't do for Cuthbert to be about and have the use of his tongue and throat, after what has' happened. Pritchard, Hines, Ogdeli and two other gentlemen are to do the job. They will come :n at the back door, in A quiet way you understand, not wishing to disturb the family or give any unnecessary trouble. I heard Pritchard giving the orders to-day. Now sir, if you thinlk the information is worth a V, I'm sure you're welcome to make use of it." - If your information should pro/ve to be true," answered Boyd, " you shall be paid for it, as I have promisled', through it is very much against my disposition to pay one scoundrel for tetralylig another. To-morrow you can apply far payment, for by that time, the truth or falsity. of your information will be known." Mr. Price agreed toi this arrangemlent but objected to the term scoundrel, a  &#xD;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC8337-00000036"/> 86          THE  VICTIM  BRIDE; term which no gentleman, except Mr. Boyd, had ever applied to him before "But," he added, laying his hand on his breast- "All is pure and spotless here. I can afford to be blackguarded and bull- ragged by those who don't know me, satisfied that when they know me better, they will be ready to ask my pardon on their knees. I would remind you, Mr. Boyd, that among men of honor, a private conversation is sacred. No blabbing, I hope, when you visit at Flipp's establishment." "Don't trouble yourself," said Boyd testily "you will nlever see me there again." and with these words, he bade Mr. Price a cold good afternoon, and left him. In the meanwhile, Mr. Cuthbert under the care of an old maiden aunt who kept house for him, had recruited his strength, and pretty well recovered from the effects-of the severe regimen to which he had lately been subjected. He was sitting in his office, about eight o'clock P. M., reflecting on the occurrences of the last two or three days, and dwelling most particularly on the circumstances of his late happy deliverance, without being able to fathom the mysteries which attended that event. Thence his thoughts wandered to Boyd and his sister, who had evidently been instrumental in rescuing him from his critical situation. The behaviour of Boyd himself had not made a very favorable impression on Cuthberfs mind, but he judged truly that the disposition of Elizabeth was far more amiable than that of her brother, and the thought struck him that it was to her mediation, that he was chiefly indebted for his deliverance. This conjeo- ture was rather pleasing to Mr. Cuthbert, for Boyd's haughty and unfriendly deportment was calculated to make the feeling of obligation to him somewhat oppressive; as no man is willing to owe a debt of gratitude to the person he dilikes. Under the influence of this feeling, Cuthbert longed for some oppor- tunity to reciprocate the services which Boyd had rendered him; and his mind was occupied with this very topic when Boyd himself was shown into the room. Cuthbert arose and greeted his visitor with much cordiality, but Boyd, without taking the hand that was offered him, ceremoniously returned Cuthbert's salutation, and seemed in haste to have it understood that his visit was merely in relation to a matter of business. "I owe you much, Mr. Boyd," answered Cuthbert, "and I hope it may be in my power to serve you. But, in the first place, allow me to inquire after the health of Miss Boyd." '; She is doing well, sir," replied Boyd coldly. "I trust we shall be able to bring the villains to punishment,' said Cuthbert, "and I have already taken measures for their detection." "They appear to be willing to save you the trouble of searching after them," remarked Boyd, "for if I am truly informedl they intend to pay you a visit to-night." Cuthbert required an explanation, and Boyd then gave a distinct account of the intended robbery and assassination; adding, however, that the source from which the intelligence was received was not perfectly reliable, And that the truth of the information could be ascertained only by the event. Boyd then volun- teered to assist Mr. Cuthbert in keeping watch on the premises, and Cuthbert thankfully accepted the offer, but remark;ed- *$ T hoped, when you first came hither to-night, that you would give me an          b   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.             87 opportunity to reciprocate some of the favors, you have already conferred on me, but I find that you come only to place me under new obligations." "Mr. Cuthbert," answered Boyd, "let us understand each other better. Your rescue to-day was a matter of duty on my part, as your imprisonment in that vile den was in consequence of your endeavours to release my sister from a similar situation and, in giving you my assistance to-night, I have a purpose of my own. I wish to execute vengeance on those villains for the injuries they lhae done me. Say no more of gratitude or friendship, Mr. Cuthbert; I fear you will soon learn to regard me as an enemy." "That I think is impossible," said Cuthbert with a benevolent smile. But what preparations shall we make for our defence? Shall wewant any more force? A policeman or two-" "uite unnecessary," said Boyd, we two are sufficient. But some arms and nmmunition may be required. Fire-arms if-you have them." "I have a pair of old-fashioned horse pistols, which were used by my grand- father at the battle of Brandywine," said Cuthbert.  "Very valuable and interesting no doubt, as revolutionary relics, but on the present occasion I should prefer a pair of modern revolvers," said Boyd. I thinki" said Cuthbert, "I can obtain the loan of those very articles from a neighbor of mine, a Methodist preacherl He bought them to be used m pre. serving order at camp meetings." If they are Methodist pistols," observed Boyd, " doubtless they will deal out fire and brimstone very promptlyamong the wicked. Therefore it strikes me that nothing could suit our purposes better." Cuthbert sent a servant, with a written application for the loan of the pistols, and was obligingly accommodated by the reverend proprietor. When the weapons arrived Boyd examined them, and found them in " prime order." Gradually, Cuthbert and his visitor became more sociable, as they sat conversing in the office, until a late hour, and when the family (z. e. Cuthbert's aunt and two female servants) had retired to rest, the two gentlemen repaired to the kitchen, where they intended to fix their garrison, as the attack was to be made inm that quarter. The lights were all extinguished, and the allies sat for several hours patiently awaiting the approach of the enemy. A -little after miidnight, Cuthbert and Boyd heard sounds which seemed to be  produced by persons scaling the garden wall, and soon after whispering voices were distinguished. These voices grew more distinct as they came nearer to the The philosophy of the thing is," said one, " that we must bore a hole through this door, and try to get at the fastenings, Nowremember boys," coitinued this voice "that the main thing is to stop the clack of this chap Cuthbert. HEe'll blow us all if we dont put a brake on his gabbing mill. I hope we'll catch the weazel asleep this time, and finish the job which that cursed fool, Boyd, spoiled so confoundedly this morning. Whoever has the fun of cutting his throat will please to finish it-off well." "I would not have believed that Boyd ould have played Us such a scurvy g;ci," said another voice, " he always seemed to be one of the right stripe." s* I hope I may be hanged," said the first speaker," if it isn't a queer affitr To think how Boyd loves the Righy gal, and what a convenient thing it woulH  &#xD;<pb n="88-89 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC8337-00000037"/> 38          THE  VICTILAI BRIDE. have been to get Cuthbert out of the way. I thought Boyd would be the first one to approve of that dodge. But blast him-never mind. I have an account to settle with him, too, when a fair opportunity offers." "I reckon the gal's done for," said another. "Hardly hurt," answered Pritchard, (for he it was,) "I knew by the way that Ogden struck, that the damage wasn't worth mentioning. But that job must be mended; she broke her promise and she's bound to suffer. I'll try my own hand next time." "No more jabber," said a rough voice; " if you wish me to bore, stand back and give me elbow room." The peculiar sound, which is made by that tool called the brace and bit was now heard for a few momnents, when it ceased and the gruff voice exclaimed:- "H-ll and fury! the door is two-inch oak I This d-d bit will break before I get through it." "Only have faith," said a solemn voice which, together with the sentiment it conveyed, evidently came from Mr. Hines.  I "Faith be blowed!" said the gruff voice of the borer. "You miserable sinner," said the voice of Hines, "what success can we expect, wheanwe go a prigging witk such a profane rascal as you?" "I hope I havn't said anytiling to bring bad luck," said the borer, who was plainly infected with something like superstitious awe. Then he cried out, in a more joyous voice, "It's all right, comrades, we're through and I've hit the right plce exactly. Here's the bolt." Bravo%' cried Pritchard; " push in, my lads, and five golden eagles to the man who cut's Cuthbert's throat. All the money found on the premises to be equally divided." CHAPTER XVII. TERMNATION OF THE BATTLE, WtITH A LIST OF THE KILLED, WOUNDED AND MSSINCt. The person who did the boring for Cuthbert's unseasonable visitors, was an avXpt. He had perforated the door and unboltedl it before the two watchers inside were aware of his progress. The first intiintdion they had that the paw was won by the enemy, was the creaking of the binges and the admission of a ray of light through the partly opened portal. The burglars pushed in and closed the door after them, without perceiving whllat preparations had been made for their reception. Boyd's eagle eye had distinguished one of the intruders, by the feeble light which had been admitted ; it was the old reprobate Ogden. All was now total darkness in the kitchen, when Boyd, directed by the asthmatic Breathing of the ancient sinner, reached forth his liand and touched the wretch on the shoulder. Ogden felt the hand, and mistook it for that of one of his companions, he was about to speak, when the grasp of that vengeful hand was fastened on his throat, and the utterance of any vocal sound was impossible. His frame wax convulsed for a few mnoments, and then all was quiet. Boyd was horrified. He knew that a guilty soul had gone to its final reckoning; and although, under the influence of fierce resentment, he had intended, perhaps, to execute fatal vengeance, he felt the keenest pangs of remorse now that the deed    Th Pahr Sciic." I w)1 force by cicmtne to kill myoncid osv e  " '  rfiwe lvo tha deah. Pae   &#xD;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC8337-00000038"/> 90           THE VICTIM   BRIDE; )   was accomplished. The thread of Orden's existence was easily broken, and the manly feelings of Boyd were shocked at the idea of having slain such a weak and defenceless victim. This sacrifice had been effected so noiselessly, that the surviving robbers had no suspicions that any unexpected event had taken place. The first circum- stance which attracted their notice, was the cessation of that peculiarly laborious breathing by which the presence of Ogden might be known. The sudden dis- colltinuance of the sound of that breathing, made Pritchard ask hastily, "Where's Ogdelll?" and receiving no answer, he-gave orders to "Strike a light." Boyd carefully deposited the body of Ogden on the floor, and stood prepared for defence. As scon as, in obedience to Pritchard's orders, a pale, minute, bluish flame appeared in ne corner of the room, showing that a friction match hadl been ignited, Boy raised his revolver and fired in the direction of the light. A groan followed, and Boyd, who had heard many groans from the same source, knew that it originated'with Ilines; though it was a groan of a different sort, or intonation, from any which he had known to proceed from that gentleman before. Cuthbert appeared to be less apt than Boyd in pistol pracetice; but on this occasion, he was not disposed to remain inactive and leave all the work to be done by his ally. The flash of Boyd's pistol showed one of the robbers in close proximity to himself; and Cuthbert embraced the opportunity to embrace the villain, which he did with a pair of arms which had been deprived of some of their usuaf vigor by the recent privations and confinement of their owner, but were still powerful enough to suggest the idea of a bear or a boa constrictor to S    the person they inclosed. The shot fired by Boyd had prevented the burglars from lighting their lamp, but, by the momentary glare which it produced, each party was made aware of the-strength and position of the other. The robbers, on their entrance, had'been five in number; but as Ogden had been killed at the commencement, and Hines was badly wounded, only three remained, il fighting order-and one of those three was imprisoned in the arms of Mr. Cuthbert. By holding his prisoner securely, Cuthbert reducedl the force of his enemy to two; but the same measure reduced the available force of his own party to one. However, Boyd was a host in himself, and to say the truth, he had a relish for fighting which was quite heroic. As soon as Pritchard perceived that his old friend Hines had been hurt, he lost no time in getting the MCubbinite ori his shoulder and carrying him out of the conflict, retreating by the garden gate, and placing hi damaged friend in a dearborn which the thieves had waiting for them in a neighboring alley. "Not much harm done, I hope, old comrade," said Pritchard, as he gently eposited the wounded man in the straw. "I'm done for, friend Pritchard," answered Hines faintly; " but all's well- Im on the right track." "Plenty of faith, I suppose?" said Pritchard. u    "." All right there'" replied Hines. "I've got the regular ticket that will take me clean through." "That's prime!" cried Mr. Pritchard; " but can I do anything for you 1" "I wish you would send for our preacher," answered the'dying man ; " and rll take it as a particular favor if you'll put your knife into Boyd, for I could   ORt, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.           91 swear that this is his work. I had a glimpse of him by the flash of his pistol." "I'll settle with him'," said Pritchard; and then, calling to Ogden's boy, who had been in attendance on the horse, he despatched that hopeful lad after the reverend Anthony, according to-the request of the departing Hines. - Having attended to these duties of friendship, Pritchard hastened back to the scene of action. Boyd's fire which had proved so disastrous to Hines, was instantly returned by one of the robbers. The flash of Boyd's pistol showed his position at the time he fired, but he was cunning enough to change his locality in a moment and, in consequence of this movement, the robber's aim was wide of the mark. Cuthbert, as stated before, had secured a prisoner; but, as he was obliged to use both hands to retain his prize, he was reduced to a state of " masterly inactivity." His position was made still more embarrassing and unpleasant by the discovery, that his prisoner had a very formidable Spanish knife in one hand, and was making strenuous efforts to use it to the detriment of Mr. Cuthbert's person. Every flash of the fire-arms -showed the gleaming instrument of murder and the giant strength of the villain who held it, made Cuthbert aware that it would be totally out of his power to confine the robber's arms five minutes longer. Mean. hile, several shots were exchanged between Boyd and the thief who still remained at liberty, each being armed with "Colt's patent"-a weapon whih may be fired some half a--dozen times without the necessity of re-loading. hen Pritchard returned, he had abandoned all hope of accomplishing both objects of his enterprise, viz, the robbery of the house and the murder of Cuthbrt. He perceived very plainly that the\ reports of so many fire-arms must arouse the neighborhood, and perhaps awaken the watchman, before the lapse of many minutes, and before the robbery could be completed. He came back, therefore,t order a retreat, and to execute what,\n fact, was the main purpose of his undertaking, viz, the slaughter of Cuthbert. He had, besides, given a pledge to the ying Hines which for more reasons than one, he was anxious to fulfil. Late events had convinced him that Boyd could not become useful to the confederacy, n the way that had been expected; and the position which Boyd had lately assumed made it probable, he would become both troublesome and dangerous to the gambling association. His removal, therefore, was a matter of policy; and since Pritchard had given Hines the pledge spoken of above, he considered the assassination of Boyd a matter of- duty. He came back to Cuthbert's kitchen, with a resolution to put both defenders of the premises to death as speedily as possible, and then make good his escape. As won as he opened the door, the light admitted by the aperture fell directly on Boyd, and Pritchard, drawing a dirk from his bosom, advanced to do execution. The robber who had been firing at Boyd ineffectually in the dark, was likewise made aware of his position by the opening of the door, and wishing to make sure of his victim, he approached with the intention of placing the pistol to his breast:before he discharged the last barrel. At the same instant, Pritchard, dirk in hand, rushed to the spot which he supposed Boyd to occupy, and sheathed the weapon to the hilt in the body of a human being. The momentary admission of light when Pritchard entered, showed Boyd the perilous condition oC Flu+\bert, whose utmost vigor was taxed in the endeavor  &#xD;<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC8337-00000039"/> \     THE VICTIM   BRIDE; I'  to confine\ e arms of the robber he had seized. The sturdy rogue had nearly ,;i  succeedled n liberating the hand that held the knife, which he was about to use at the time,  hen the opening of the door had revealed the state of affairs to toyd. By hatening to the assistance of Guthbert, Boyd saved his own life, ;:    his change of poition caused the blow whici Pritchlard intended for him, to be administered to another. The watchman's rattlawas now heard, and Pritchard, calling to his adherents to save themselves, made for the door. No one followed him, and after waiting a few moments, he fled alone to the wagon in which he had left^the wounded Hines, sprang into the vehicle, and ordered the boy to drive to Flipp's taver The Reverend Anthony M'Cubbin had entered the wagon a few minutes before, and"had already administered such ghostly con- solation as was required his dying proselyte. As soon as Pritchard dis- covered the presence of the reverend gentleman, he anxiously inquired if every- thing was "right side up."  "Oh I yes," answered the pastor, with glowing enthusiasm; "the blessed creter is almost gone, and I mus say that a more triumphant departer I never had the luck to behold."   \ "You're quite sure, then, that he ticketed for a seat among the angels?" asked Pritchard.         \ "I'm jest as sure of it," answered the reverend Anthony, "as if I saw the wings sprouting out of his shoulders." \ "Good!" cried Pritchard. "I'll join your church to-morrow; for it's a nice thing to be always ready for these sort of accidents." Here the dying man seemed to be making an effort to speak. Pritchard grasped his hand, and bent over him to catch his last accents. In the intervals of the death rattle, these words were distinguished: 'Did you do that job for Boyd?" ' "I did" replied Pritchard; "I gave him full eight inches of cold iron." "That's enough," murmured Hines; " now I am ready for P1aradise!" In the utterance of this speech, his last breath was expended. During the remainder of the drive, Messrs. M'u2bbin and Pritchard conversed feelingly tin the virtues and saintlike qualities which they attributed to the deceased. In the meantime, the police forces, excited by the din of battle in Cuthbert's kitchen had found their way to the spot. The spectacle which there met their view, was really one which a newspaper reperter might be excused for calling "terrible" or "frightful." Several streams and pools -of blood were found on the floor, and two dead bodies also, one of which was Oglen's, and the other wase the wretch whom Pritchard, in the dark, had mistaken for Boydl. . One of the thieves still lived; he was the one whom Cuthbert had seized, and who had been stunned by a timely blow from Boyd's pistol, at the very moment in which his knife was raised to give Cuthbert his quietus. *       ' .*   ODI, TIIE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.           93 CHAPTER X^VIII. THE CATASTROPHE. About a week after the transactions last related, Mr. Cuthbert, with a pale and woe-begone countenance, entered Mr. Righy's store. He came to communi- cate an astounding piece of intelligence which had just come to his own knowledge. This intelligence related to the clandestine marriage of Boyd and Catharine, which had taken place two days previous. As soon as the dreadful truth was wade known to the unhappy father, he uttered a cry of distress such as Cuthbert had never beforeeard from any human being in extreme agony, and " for many hours afterwards, he appeared to be overwhelmed and stupified by the terrible affliction which had overtaken him. The death of his daughter would have been a far more endurable calamity. It had been the intention of Boyd and Catharine to- keep their marriage concealed for awhile, hoping that some favorable cilrtumstance would transpire to make Mr. Righy more reconcilable to the match. I a the meanwhile, Catharine remained in her father's house, but on the plea of illisposition, absented herself from the store; her mind being too much troubled, in fact, to allow her to give the usual attention to her duties as saleswoman. She felt that she had been too precipitate, and she regretted the step she had taken, now that it was irrevocable. She was sitting in her chamber, weeping and alolle, at a late hour in the afternoon when her father entered. One glance at his countenance convinced her that all was discovered. Yet there was no appearance of angry excitement, nothing resentful or menacing in Righy's face or deportment. His features were pale and rigid; the surface was calm, but there was a terrible commotion in the depths of  his soul. There was something in his very tranquility, which frightened Catha- rine more than any outhurst of rage could have done. She trembled as he ap- proached; but it soon appeared that he came not to reproach or curse her, for he bent over her and wept. "Oh, father!" said Catharine, altogether overcome by this unexpected behaviour, "will you-can you forgive me?"  "My child, my dear child," answered Righy, " you have not offended me. I have nothing to forgive."           .  "Is it possible that you can be so good and kind?" cried Catharine, grasping his hand. "Will you be reconciled to Boyd?" "To Boyd, my daughter? never! I cannot forgive the wrongs he has done to you. But you are innocent. You have been deceived, cheated out of all the happiness of your life, ruined and undone forever. My misery signifies but little; it cannot last long; but you are young and many years of suffering are before you. "Oh, father, do not speak such words of gloom and discouragement, or do not speak them in a voice of kindness. Surely there is no cause for these dreadful forebodings. My husband-" "Catharine 1" cried Righy, " do not use that word again or you will drive me to madness. Call him anything else but that. He is not your husband in the sight of God; heaven never could sanction such an alliance, or the blackest fiend in hell might be wedded to the brightest angel that stands before the throne"  &#xD;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC8337-00000040"/> !   94          THE VICTIM BRIDE; "Oh, father, let me tell you hotw you have misjudged him." i Say nothing of him, my daughter; or say whether you can forgive me if I to  take his worthless life, and thus restore you at once to liberty and honor?" "Father," said Catharine with a quivering lip, " do him no harm, or I shall learn to curse you. If any one must die, letit be myself." "You," repeated Righy, starting back as if a serpent had suddenly sprung up before him; " you! what devil inspired you to say these words? Ah, that thought it was terrible indeed!" "For my own death I could forgive you," said Catharine; i yes, and pray for you with my last breath; but were you to shed his blood, never could I forgive you for that, in time or in eternity." Righy stood for some moments gazing at her in silence and distraction, then turning away he "seemed to find his way without his eyes" and left the apartment. Another morning dawned on a house of sorrow. Righy's store was unopened; his occupation was gone; the affairs of this world had ceased to interest him. The neighbors shook their heads as they observed his closed doors, and some prophesied evil. For several days Boyd, who had been forbidden by Righy to enter the premises, had frequently walked by the house, to be -made as happy as circumstances would permit, by a sight of Catharine at the window; but, on the morning to which our narrative has now arrived, though he passed and repassed again and again, no Catharine appeared. The closed doors and tomb-like still- ness of the place alarmed him; and apprehensions for the safety of Catharine overcoming all other considerations, he rang for admittance, During the whole morning, Mr. and Mrs. Righy had been weeping over their daughter, as the Athenian parents formerly did over their children about to be sacrificed to the Minataur. Cathariie and her-parents mingled their tears together, when a servant entered the room, and informed the mourners that a gentleman at the door wished to speak with Mr. or Mrs. Righy. "Tell the gentleman that we can receive no visitors at this time," was Mr. Righy's prompt answer. The servant having delivered this message, soon returned to announce that the gentleman had sent up his name, Mr. Boyd, and that he requested permission to speak with his vuife. C Tell the villain-" cried Righy, but checking himself when Catharine gave him an Appealing look, he continued in a milder tone, " tell him to come at soire more suitable time." A glance from Catharine to her mother, signified her wish that MErs. Righy herself would speak to the visitor, and she accordingly went down to the door for that purpose. When she had gone but, Righy said to Cathlarine-l "Now, my child, the time has come, when something must be done for your deliverance. There is yet one way to save you; only one way, my beloved daughter. I thought of another, but you yourself have forbidden it. We have trained you in the paths of purity and innocence, and we must -not see you allied to infamy and guilt. Oh, my child, what a task has been imposed on me! But God is merciful, and ; } will give me strength to execute the dreadful duty o which has been confifled : my hands." Cfttharine yokea . him  ; amazement; she feared that his mlind   OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE.            9  6 was wandering and she attempted to soothe him with words of gentleness and affection n. -- "You have heard, my daughter," continued Righy, "of that Roman father, who saved his child from the power of a tyrant, by plunging a dagger into her heart. Was he not justified before God and man, for returning her to her Creator i pure and spotless spirit, such as he had made her?" "Ol, ffll;Aher, what have we to do with these old stories now?" said Cathlarine, ldly.  "Is there not present trouble enough, without disturbing the ashes of the Youll lre right, iny child; let all past troubles be forgotten. Oh, y daughter i  ;4t alny foi)rmer time I have said or done anything to give you pain, let mN ask t;OrfgSiivals now. I had but one wish--but one object-and that wa to SOIeU' e your happiness. I hoped to give you wealth, and a respectable posiion il society; and if at any moment I have seemed harsh and severe it was when your inexperience and child-like simplicity seemed likely to defeat my exertions for your welfare. I could endure all labors, privations and hardships patiently, because it was for you that I endured them." Catharine was too much affected to answer. Mrs. Righy now entered, and drawing near to her husband, informed him in a low tone, that Boyd insisted On seeing hils wif6. "Letn him not come up, or I shall certainly do him mischief," cried Righy, "I wish not to harm him, as I would not give my dear child any unnecessary pain. Tell him that in a few minutes he shall see her." Mrs. Righy again went down, to bear her husband's message to Boyd, who still remained at the door. He appeared to have some impression which made him anxious for the safety of Cathlarine, and it was with extreme difficulty that he mastered his impatience, which urged him to hasten up stairs in despite of Righy's interdiction. Indeed, Mrs. Righy found it necessary to take hold of his arm, as a m ore decided remonstrance againsthis rash intrusion. - While some altercation waiR going on between them, the report of a pistol was heard above, and a faint shriek followed. It was impossible now to restrain Boyd any longer; he broke away from Mrs. Righy and rushed up to the parlor. Righy was supporting his daLghter in his arms; he laid her on a sofa, and kissed her tenderly as Boyd entered. A small stream of blood was trickling from a minute wound in one of her temples. Righy still held the pistol in his hand, and stood confronting Buyd with stern composure. "I told you," said hle, "that you should see her and there she is. Had she not plead for your life, that shot would have sent another fiend to hell, instead of an angel to paradise, but for her sake I have spared you and will spare yoll still." "I despise your mercy and defy your anger," answered Boyd desperately. "If that pistol has a fellow, bhring it forth and let us see if you dare to use it against a man." Then throwing himself on, his knees by her body, he seized her hand, and found that it was already cold and pulseless. Her death pang had been as brief as parental love could have wished it. The scene of confusion which followed is indescribable. Amidst the shrieks and cries of women and the horrid exclamations of many spectators, who now forced their way into the house, the perpetrator of the deed a... remained calm,  &#xD;<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC8337-00000041"/> 9C THE VICTIM   BRIDE; OR, THE FATHER'S SACRIFICE. !      .  \ though he was evidently distressed. ' I am the man who did it"' was his con- stant reply to the inquiries of those who gazed on the dreadful spectacle. Often did he repeat, "I am the miserable father who was forced by circumstances to kill his own clil"l, to save her from'a fate worse than death." At this time and ever after, his behaviour discovered every indlication of, the deepest sorrow, but no repentance, no remorse. He always appeared to regard the, deed he had committed as one of fatal necessity, alnd as ai act of melceifull kindness to his daughter, Righy was slubsequelntl tried on an indictlent t for murder, but the sympathies of the pulblic were with hm, and hle was acquitted, on the ground that the apparent illconsistenc(y of his conduct, in murdering a child whom he enderly loved, was an evidence of insanity. The subsequent history of Boyd is little more than a blank. He never reco- vered from the effects of this terrible visitation, and sank into a state of hopeless melancholy, from -which the friendly offices of Cuthbert were exercised in vain to arouse hiil. Cuthblert himself sustainled, lis affliction with manly fortitude, though he mourned long anid sincerely the sad and untimely fate of his betrothed. When, after the lapse of time, he and Elizabeth were uilited in the bonds of matrimony, this amiable pair dedlicated a costly tonb to the memory of that lovely but unfortunate being, who had once been to each of themn the cholis object of friendship and affectioli. Mr. Pritchard was arrested at-Flipp's hotel, on the morning after his attempt{d robbery, and in due time he found his way to the State's prison, where he did in- voluntary penance for the term of six years. After his release he studied la a, and became a very succesful practitioner and politician in one of the western States. At the last accounts he was an applicant for some office of trust and honor in the public service, and as he was very strongly recommended as a man of inflexible political integrity, it was generally believed that he would obtain the appointment. Major Flipp and his lady continued to kiss and quarrel, till the Major hap- pened to drop off one-night, in a fit of apoplexy; and in due time the pale bar- keeper, Mr. Simeon Price,-became his fortunate successor in business, and in the affections of Mrs. Flipp. The congregation of the Reverend Anthony M'Cubbin continues to increase, and his followers have been enabled to emerge from their subterranean temple, and to occupy a commodious church, very handsomely. finished, and provided with cushions, carpets and all the comforts and elegancies vhich modern christians are apt to require in their places of worship. These are all the particulars concerning the different personages of our story, which we have been enabled to gather from reliable sources; and in conclusion, we beg the reader to observe, that as some of the principal incidents of our story are real historical facts, we are not accountable for anything unpleasant or dis- tressing that may have occurred in the course of the narrative. THE END.     &#xD;</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
